<article title='Dune_Messiah'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg><space/>
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Dune Messiah
</arg><arg name="title_orig"><space/>
</arg><arg name="translator"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Dune Messiah cover.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>First edition dust jacket
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Frank Herbert]]
</arg><arg name="illustrator"><space/>
</arg><arg name="cover_artist"><space/>[[Jack Gaughan]]
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United States
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>[[Dune (franchise)|''Dune'' series]]
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Science fiction novel]]
</arg><arg name="published"><space/>1969
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Putnam Publishing]]
</arg><arg name="media_type"><space/>Print ([[hardcover]] & [[paperback]])
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>256
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>
</arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>32595
</arg><arg name="preceded_by"><space/>[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]
</arg><arg name="followed_by"><space/>[[Children of Dune]]
</arg></template><bold><italics>Dune Messiah</italics></bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>science fiction novel</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Frank Herbert</target></link>, the second in his<space/><link><target>Dune (franchise)</target><part>''Dune'' series</part></link><space/>of six novels. It was originally serialized in<space/><italics><link><target>Galaxy Science Fiction</target><part>Galaxy</part></link></italics><space/>magazine in 1969. The<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>American</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>British</part></link><space/>editions have different prologues summarizing events in the previous novel.<space/><italics>Dune Messiah</italics><space/>and its sequel<space/><italics><link><target>Children of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>were collectively adapted by the<space/><link><target>Syfy</target><part>Sci-Fi Channel</part></link><space/>in 2003 into a miniseries entitled<space/><italics><link><target>Frank Herbert's Children of Dune</target></link></italics>. In 2002, the<space/><link><target>Science Fiction Book Club</target></link><space/>also published the two novels in one volume.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herbert, Frank.<space/><italics>Dune Messiah and Children of Dune</italics>. 1st SFBC Printing edition (2002), 592 pages. ISBN 0-7394-2399-1.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot summary</heading><paragraph>Twelve years after the events described in<space/><italics><link><target>Dune (novel)</target><part>Dune</part></link></italics><space/>(1965),<space/><link><target>Paul Atreides</target><part>Paul &quot;Muad'Dib&quot; Atreides</part></link><space/>rules as Emperor. By accepting the role of<space/><link><target>messiah</target></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>Fremen</target></link>, Paul had unleashed a<space/><link><target>jihad</target></link><space/>which conquered most of the known universe.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Messiah"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Herbert<space/></arg><arg name="first">Frank<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dune Messiah<space/></arg><arg name="year">1969<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="quote">Muad'dib's Qizarate missionaries carried their religious war across space in a Jihad whose major impetus endured only twelve standard years, but in that time, religious colonialism brought all but a fraction of the human universe under one rule.—Excerpts from the Death Cell Interview with Bronso of IX</arg></template></extension><space/>While Paul is the most powerful Emperor ever known, he is powerless to stop the lethal excesses of the religious juggernaut he has created. Although sixty-one billion people have perished, Paul's<space/><link><target>prescience</target><part>prescient</part></link><space/>visions indicate that this is far from the worst possible outcome for humanity. Motivated by this knowledge, Paul hopes to set humanity on a course that will not inevitably lead to stagnation and destruction, while at the same time acting as ruler of the Empire and focal point of the Fremen religion.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Bene Gesserit</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Spacing Guild</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bene Tleilax</target><part>Tleilaxu</part></link><space/>enter into a conspiracy to dethrone Paul, the Bene Gesserit<space/><link><target>Reverend Mother (Dune)</target><part>Reverend Mother</part></link><space/><link><target>Gaius Helen Mohiam</target></link><space/>enlisting Paul's own consort<space/><link><target>Princess Irulan</target></link>, daughter of the deposed<space/><link><target>Padishah Emperor</target></link><space/><link><target>Shaddam IV</target></link>. Paul has refused to father a child with Irulan (or even touch her), but his Fremen<space/><link><target>concubinage</target><part>concubine</part></link><space/><link><target>Chani</target></link><space/>has also failed to produce an heir, causing tension within his monarchy. Desperate both to secure her place in the<space/><link><target>House Atreides</target><part>Atreides</part></link><space/>dynasty and to preserve the Atreides bloodline for the Bene Gesserit<space/><link><target>Bene Gesserit#Breeding program</target><part>breeding program</part></link>, Irulan has secretly been giving<space/><link><target>contraceptive</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to Chani. Paul is aware of this fact, but has foreseen that the birth of his heir will bring Chani's death, and does not want to lose her. He sees this in a terrifying vision of a moon that falls from the sky of Dune. Because of the way oracles interfere with one another's prescience, the<space/><link><target>Guild Navigator</target></link><space/><link><target>Edric (Dune)</target><part>Edric</part></link><space/>is able to shield the conspiracy from Paul's visions of the future. The Tleilaxu<space/><link><target>Face Dancers</target><part>Face Dancer</part></link><space/><link><target>Scytale (Dune)</target><part>Scytale</part></link><space/>gives Paul a gift he cannot resist: a Tleilaxu-grown<space/><link><target>ghola</target></link><space/>of the deceased<space/><link><target>Duncan Idaho</target></link>, Paul's childhood teacher and friend, now called &quot;<link><target>Hayt</target></link>&quot;. The conspirators hope the presence of Hayt will undermine Paul's ability to rule by forcing Paul to question himself and the empire he has created. Furthermore, Paul's acceptance of the gift weakens his support among the Fremen, who see the Tleilaxu and their tools as unclean. Chani, taking matters into her own hands, switches to a traditional Fremen fertility diet, preventing Irulan from being able to tamper with her food, and soon becomes pregnant.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Otheym</target></link>, one of Paul's former<space/><link><target>Fedaykin</target></link><space/>death<space/><link><target>commando</target><trail>s</trail></link>, reveals evidence of a Fremen conspiracy against Paul. Otheym gives Paul his dwarf Tleilaxu servant Bijaz who, like a recording machine, can remember faces, names, and details. Paul accepts reluctantly, seeing the strands of a Tleilaxu plot. As Paul's soldiers attack the conspirators, others set off an<space/><link><target>Atomics (Dune)</target><part>atomic weapon</part></link><space/>called a<space/><link><target>stone burner</target></link>, purchased from the Tleilaxu, that destroys the area and blinds Paul. By tradition, all blind Fremen are abandoned in the desert, but Paul shocks the Fremen and entrenches his godhead by proving he can still see, even without eyes. His oracular powers have become so developed that he can foresee in his mind everything that happens, as though his eyes still function. By moving through his life in lockstep with his visions, he can see even the slightest details of the world around him. The disadvantage of this is his inability to change any part of his destiny, trapping him in a hellish boredom. The unraveling of the Fremen conspiracy reveals that<space/><link><target>Korba (Dune)</target><part>Korba</part></link>, a former Fedaykin and now high priest of Paul's church, is among Paul's enemies.</paragraph><paragraph>Duncan interrogates Bijaz, but the little manactually an agent of the Tleilaxuuses a specific humming intonation that renders Duncan open to implanted commands. Bijaz programs Duncan to offer Paul a bargain when Chani dies: Chani's rebirth as a ghola, and the hope that Duncan Idaho's memories might be reawakened, in return for Paul sacrificing the throne and going into exile. Bijaz also implants a compulsion that will force Duncan to attempt to kill Paul, given the appropriate circumstances. Duncan remains oblivious of the programming. Eventually news is brought that Chani has died giving birth. The grief of his loss is the falling moon that he foresaw in an earlier vision, and Paul stumbles, truly blind now, having removed himself from the prison of his own precise vision. Paul's reaction to his wife's death triggers the compulsions in the mind of Duncan, who attempts to kill Paul. But rather than kill his beloved Paul, Duncan's ghola body reacts against its own programming and recovers Duncan's full consciousness. He remains conscious of the Zen-Sunni and Mentat training given to Duncan by the Tleilaxu, but is no longer bound to their programming.</paragraph><paragraph>Paul and Chani's newborn twins are &quot;<link><target>pre-born</target></link>&quot;, like Paul's sister<space/><link><target>Alia Atreides</target><part>Alia</part></link><space/>had been, and come into the world fully conscious with<space/><link><target>Kwisatz Haderach</target></link>-like access to ancestral memories thanks to a combination of their genes and an<space/><link><target>in utero</target></link><space/>exposure to the quantities of spice in Chani's special pregnancy diet. Scytale offers to revive Chani as a ghola in return for all of Paul's<space/><link><target>CHOAM</target></link><space/>holdings. Paul refuses to submit to the possibility that the Tleilaxu might program Chani in some diabolical way, and Scytale threatens the infants with a knife while he negotiates with Alia. By successfully escaping the oracular trap and setting the universe on a new path, Paul has been rendered completely blind, yet he is able to kill Scytale with an accurately aimed dagger thanks to a vision from his son's perspective.</paragraph><paragraph>Now prophetically as well as physically blind, Paul chooses to embrace the Fremen tradition of a blind man walking alone into the desert, winning the fealty of the Fremen for his children, who will inherit his mantle of Emperor. Paul leaves Alia, now romantically involved with Duncan, as<space/><link><target>regent</target></link><space/>for the twins, whom he has named<space/><link><target>Leto II Atreides</target><part>Leto</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ghanima Atreides</target><part>Ghanima</part></link>. Duncan notes the irony that Paul and Chani's deaths had enabled them to triumph against their enemies, and that Paul has escaped<space/><link><target>Imperial cult</target><part>deification</part></link><space/>by walking into the desert as a man, while guaranteeing Fremen support for the Atreides line.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Characters</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paul Atreides</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; Emperor of the known universe and Messiah of the<space/><link><target>Fremen</target></link>. His formal (public) name is Paul-Muad'Dib, and Fremen sietch (private/secret) name is Usul.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Princess Irulan</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; Princess-consort of Emperor Paul Atreides</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chani</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; of Paul's Fremen tribe, Imperial concubine and chosen mother-to-be</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alia Atreides</target><part>Alia</part></link><space/>&amp;ndash; Paul's sister, born with prescient awareness, a Reverend Mother</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gaius Helen Mohiam</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; a<space/><link><target>Reverend Mother (Dune)</target><part>Reverend Mother</part></link><space/>of the Bene Gesserit and conspirator</listitem><listitem><link><target>Guild Navigator#Edric</target><part>Edric</part></link><space/>&amp;ndash; a prescient Guild Navigator and conspirator</listitem><listitem><link><target>Scytale (Dune)</target><part>Scytale</part></link><space/>&amp;ndash; a<space/><link><target>Bene Tleilax</target><part>Tleilaxu</part></link><space/><link><target>Face Dancer</target></link><space/>and conspirator</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hayt</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; a revived Tleilaxu<space/><link><target>ghola</target></link><space/>of Paul's childhood teacher,<space/><link><target>Duncan Idaho</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stilgar</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; Previous leader of the Fremen, now loyal to Paul Atreides</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Reception</heading><paragraph><link><target>Spider Robinson</target></link><space/>noted that he enjoyed the book, &quot;even as [he] was driving a truck through the holes in its logic, because it had the same majestic rolling grandeur of the previous book.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Galaxy Bookshelf&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Galaxy Science Fiction</target></link></italics>, September 1976, p.110</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>isfdb title</target><arg name="id">2037</arg><arg name="title">Dune Messiah</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Dune franchise</target></template><template><target>Frank Herbert</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:1970 novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels by Frank Herbert</target></link><link><target>Category:Dune novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels first published in serial form</target></link><link><target>Category:Works originally published in Galaxy Science Fiction</target></link></paragraph></article>