<article title='Communist_Party_of_the_Soviet_Union'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>CPSU</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>CPSU (disambiguation)</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>Communist Party of the Soviet Union (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Infobox Political Party</target><arg name="colorcode"><space/>#CE0000
</arg><arg name="slogan"><space/>"[[Workers of the world, unite!]]"
</arg><arg name="anthem"><space/>"[[The Internationale]]"
</arg><arg name="native_name"><space/>Коммунистическая партия Советского Союза (Kommunisticheskaya partiya Sovetskogo Soyuza)
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Communist Party of the<br><space/>Soviet Union
</arg><arg name="party_logo"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>The [[27th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union|27th Party Congress]], held in 1986
</arg><arg name="founded"><space/>1 January 1912
</arg><arg name="dissolved"><space/>29 August 1991
</arg><arg name="founder"><space/>[[Vladimir Lenin]]
</arg><arg name="newspaper">''[[Pravda]]''
</arg><arg name="ideology"><space/>[[Communism]]<br>[[Marxism–Leninism]]
</arg><arg name="position"><space/>[[Far-left]]
</arg><arg name="international"><space/>[[Comintern]] (until 1943), [[Cominform]] (until 1956)
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Russian Social Democratic Labour Party]]
</arg><arg name="youth_wing"><space/>[[Komsomol]]<br>[[Young Pioneer organization of the Soviet Union|Young Pioneers]]
</arg><arg name="colours"><space/>[[Red]]
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>the Soviet Union
</arg><arg name="membership"><space/>19 million (1986)
</arg><arg name="flag"><space/>
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>Коммунистическая партия Советского Союза, КПСС</arg></template>), abbreviated in English as<space/><bold>CPSU</bold>,<template><target>refn</target><arg>Sometimes referred to as the Soviet Communist Party (SCP). Note, the party had four different names during its existence;
* Russian Social Democratic Labour Party (bolsheviks) (1912–1918)
* Russian Communist Party (bolsheviks) (1918–1925)
* All-Union Communist Party (bolsheviks) (1925–1952) (Russian acronym, VKP(b))
* Communist Party of the Soviet Union (1952–1991)</arg><arg name="group">note</arg></template><space/>was the founding and ruling political party of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</part></link><space/>(USSR). The CPSU was the sole governing party of the Soviet Union until 1990 when the<space/><link><target>Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union</target><part>Supreme Soviet</part></link><space/>annulled the law which granted the CPSU a monopoly over the political system. The party was founded in 1912 by the<space/><link><target>Bolsheviks</target></link><space/>(the majority faction of the<space/><link><target>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party</target></link>), a revolutionary group led by<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link><space/>which seized power in the aftermath of the<space/><link><target>October Revolution</target></link><space/>of 1917. The party was dissolved on 29 August 1991 soon after a<space/><link><target>1991 Soviet coup d'tat attempt</target><part>failed coup d'tat</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The CPSU was organized on the basis of<space/><link><target>democratic centralism</target></link>, a principle conceived by Lenin that entails democratic and open discussion of policy issues and the requirement of unity in upholding agreed policies. The highest body within the CPSU was the<space/><link><target>Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>party Congress</part></link>, which convened every five years. When the Congress was not in session, the<space/><link><target>Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Central Committee</part></link><space/>was the highest body. Because the Central Committee met twice a year, most day-to-day duties and responsibilities were vested in the<space/><link><target>Politburo of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Politburo</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Secretariat of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Secretariat</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Orgburo</target></link><space/>(until 1952). The<space/><link><target>List of leaders of the Soviet Union</target><part>party leader</part></link><space/>was the head of government and held the office of either<space/><link><target>General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>General Secretary</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Premier of the Soviet Union</target><part>Premier</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>List of heads of state of the Soviet Union</target><part>head of state</part></link>, or some of the three offices concurrently<template><target>mdash</target></template>but never all three at the same time. The party leader was the de facto chairman of the CPSU Politburo and the chief executive of the USSR.</paragraph><paragraph>The CPSU, according to its party statute, adhered to<space/><link><target>MarxismLeninism</target></link>, an ideology based on the writings of<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link>, and formalized under<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target></link>. The party pursued<space/><link><target>state socialism</target></link>, under which all industries were nationalized and a<space/><link><target>planned economy</target></link><space/>was implemented. Before<space/><link><target>economic planning</target><part>central planning</part></link><space/>was adopted in 1929, Lenin had introduced a<space/><link><target>mixed economy</target></link>, commonly referred to as the<space/><link><target>New Economic Policy</target></link>, in the 1920s. After<space/><link><target>Mikhail Gorbachev</target></link><space/>took power in 1985, rapid steps were taken to transform the economic system in the direction of a<space/><link><target>market economy</target></link>. Gorbachev and some of his allies envisioned the introduction of an economy similar to Lenin's New Economic Policy through a program of<space/><link><target>perestroika</target></link>, or restructuring, but the results of their reforms contributed to the fall of the entire system of government.</paragraph><paragraph>A number of causes contributed to CPSU's loss of control and the dissolution of the Soviet Union. Some historians have written that Gorbachev's policy of liberalization was the root cause, noting that it weakened the party's control over society. Others have blamed the economic stagnation and loss of faith by the general populace in communist ideology.<space/></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>History of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>From Lenin to Stalin (191253)</heading><paragraph>The origin of the CPSU was in the Bolshevik faction of the Russian Social Democratic Party, which left the party in January 1912 to form a new party at the Prague Party Conference, called the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party (bolsheviks) or RSDLP(b).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Russian Socialist Federative Soviet Republic</target></link>, the world's first constitutionally socialist state, was established by the Bolsheviks in the aftermath of the October Revolution.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Suny</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">xvi</arg></template><space/>Immediately after the Revolution, the new, Lenin-led government implemented socialist reforms, including the transfer of estates and imperial lands to workers'<space/><link><target>soviet (council)</target><part>soviets</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Suny</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">xvi</arg></template><space/>In this context, in 1918, RSDLP(b) became (All-)Russian Communist Party (bolsheviks) and remained so until 1925.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Lenin supported<space/><link><target>world revolution</target></link><space/>but first needed to consolidate his power at home. To focus on the civil unrest brewing in Russia, he sought immediate peace with the<space/><link><target>Central Powers</target></link><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Service</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">324–325</arg></template><space/>and agreed to a<space/><link><target>Treaty of Brest-Litovsk</target><part>punitive treaty</part></link><space/>that ceded much of the former Russian Empire to Germany.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Service</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">332–343</arg></template><space/>The treaty was voided after the Allied victory in<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Service</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">332–343</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1921, Lenin proposed the<space/><link><target>New Economic Policy</target></link>, a system of state capitalism that started the process of industrialization and recovery from the<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target><part>Civil War</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Suny</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">22–24</arg></template><space/>On 30 December 1922, the Russian SFSR<space/><link><target>Treaty on the Creation of the USSR</target><part>joined</part></link><space/>former territories of the Russian Empire in the Soviet Union, of which Lenin was elected leader.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Suny</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">xvii</arg></template><space/>On 9 March 1923, Lenin suffered a stroke, which incapacitated him and effectively ended his role in government. He died on 21 January 1924<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Suny</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">xvii</arg></template><space/>and was succeeded by<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1925, the Party's official name was All-Union Communist Party (bolsheviks). In the 1930s, Stalin initiated the<space/><link><target>Great Purge</target></link>, a period of widespread paranoia and repression that culminated in a series of<space/><link><target>Moscow Trials</target><part>show trials</part></link><space/>and the purging of nearly all<space/><link><target>Old Bolshevik</target><part>original Party members</part></link>. With the rise of<space/><link><target>fascism</target></link><space/>in Italy and Germany, the Party actively sought to form &quot;collective security&quot; alliances with western powers. Unable to do so, the USSR signed a<space/><link><target>Molotov-Ribbentrop Pact</target><part>non-aggression pact</part></link><space/>with Germany, which was broken in 1941 when Germany<space/><link><target>Operation Barbarossa</target><part>invaded the Soviet Union</part></link>, beginning the<space/><link><target>Eastern Front (WWII)</target><part>Great Patriotic War</part></link>. After the 1945<space/><link><target>Allies of World War II</target><part>Allied</part></link><space/>victory of<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, the Party held to a doctrine of establishing pro-Stalin governments in the<space/><link><target>Eastern Bloc</target><part>post-war occupied territories</part></link><space/>and of actively seeking to expand their sphere of influence, using<space/><link><target>proxy wars</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>espionage</target></link><space/>and providing training and funding to promote Communist elements abroad.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Post-Stalin years (195385)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Nikita S. Khrushchev.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Khrushchev succeeded Stalin as the Soviet leader. His rule is best known for his liberalization of political and social life, and the end of terror as a means of social control</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>After Stalin's death, Khrushchev rose to the top post by overcoming political adversaries, including<space/><link><target>Lavrentiy Beria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Georgy Malenkov</target></link>, in a power struggle.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">274–275</arg></template><space/>In 1955, Khrushchev achieved the demotion of Malenkov and secured his own position as Soviet leader.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">276</arg></template><space/>Early in his rule and with the support of several members of the Presidium, Khrushchev initiated the<space/><link><target>Khrushchev Thaw</target><part>Thaw</part></link>, which effectively ended the Stalinist mass terror of the prior decades and reduced socio-economic oppression considerably.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">274–276</arg></template><space/>At the<space/><link><target>20th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>20th Congress</part></link><space/>held in 1956, Khrushchev denounced Stalin's crimes, being careful to omit any reference to complicity by any sitting Presidium members.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">268–269</arg></template><space/>His economic policies, while bringing about improvements, were not enough to fix the fundamental problems of the Soviet economy. The standard of living for ordinary citizens did increase; 108 million people moved into new housing between 1956 and 1965.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">278–280</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Khrushchev's foreign policies led to the<space/><link><target>Sino-Soviet split</target></link>, in part a consequence of his public denunciation of Stalin.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">282–284</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev improved relations with<space/><link><target>Josip Broz Tito</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>League of Communists of Yugoslavia</target></link><space/>but failed to establish the close, party-to-party relations that he wanted.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">278–280</arg></template><space/>While the Thaw reduced political oppression at home, it led to unintended consequences abroad, such as the<space/><link><target>Hungarian Revolution of 1956</target></link><space/>and unrest in Poland, where the local citizenry now felt confident enough to rebel against Soviet control.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">284–287</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev also failed to improve Soviet relations with the West, partially because of a hawkish military stance.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">284–287</arg></template><space/>In the aftermath of the<space/><link><target>Cuban Missile Crisis</target></link>, Khrushchev's position within the party was substantially weakened.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">288–289</arg></template><space/>Shortly before his eventual ousting he tried to introduce economic reforms championed by<space/><link><target>Evsei Liberman</target></link>, a Soviet economist, which tried to implement market mechanisms into the planned economy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">289</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Khrushchev was ousted on 14 October 1964 in a Central Committee plenum that officially cited his inability to listen to others, his failure in consulting with the members of the Presidium, his establishment of a cult of personality, his economic mismanagement, and his anti-party reforms as the reasons he was no longer fit to remain as head of the party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Taubman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">289–290</arg></template><space/>He was succeeded in office by<space/><link><target>Leonid Brezhnev</target></link><space/>as First Secretary and<space/><link><target>Alexei Kosygin</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Premier of the Soviet Union</target><part>Chairman</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Council of Ministers (Soviet Union)</target><part>Council of Ministers</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">292</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Brezhnev 1973.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>The Brezhnev era is commonly referred to by historians as the<space/><link><target>Era of Stagnation</target></link>, a term coined by CPSU General Secretary Gorbachev<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">292–296</arg></template></part><part>left</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Brezhnev era began with a rejection of<space/><link><target>Khrushchevism</target></link><space/>in virtually every arena except one; continued opposition to Stalinist methods of terror and political violence.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">296–299</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev's policies were criticized as voluntarism and the Brezhnev period saw the rise of<space/><link><target>neo-Stalinism</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">297– 298</arg></template><space/>While Stalin was never rehabilitated during this period, the most conservative journals in the country were allowed to highlight positive features of his rule.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">297–298</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At the<space/><link><target>23rd Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>23rd Congress</part></link><space/>held in 1966, the names of the office of First Secretary and the body of the Presidium reverted to their original names: General Secretary and Politburo, respectively.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">296–297</arg></template><space/>At the start of his premiership, Kosygin experimented with economic reforms similar to those championed by Malenkov, including prioritizing light industry over heavy industry to increase the production of consumer goods.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">299</arg></template><space/>Similar reforms were introduced in Hungary under the name<space/><link><target>New Economic Mechanism</target></link>; however, with the rise to power of<space/><link><target>Alexander Dubek</target></link><space/>in Czechoslovakia, who called for the establishment of &quot;<link><target>socialism with a human face</target></link>&quot;, all non-conformist reform attempts in the Soviet Union were stopped.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">299–230</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During his rule, Brezhnev supported<space/><italics><link><target>detente</target></link></italics>, a passive weakening of animosity with the West with the goal of improving political and economic relations.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">235–238</arg></template><space/>However, by the<space/><link><target>25th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>25th Congress</part></link><space/>held in 1976, political, economic and social problems within the Soviet Union began to mount and the Brezhnev administration found itself in an increasingly difficult position.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">308</arg></template><space/>The previous year, Brezhnev's health began to deteriorate. He became addicted to painkillers and needed to take increasingly more potent medications to attend official meetings.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">309</arg></template><space/>Because of the &quot;<link><target>trust in cadres</target></link>&quot; policy implemented by his administration, the CPSU leadership evolved into a<space/><link><target>gerontocracy</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">309–310</arg></template><space/>At the end of Brezhnev's rule, problems continued to amount; in 1979 he consented to the<space/><link><target>Soviet war in Afghanistan</target><part>Soviet intervention in Afghanistan</part></link><space/>to save the embattled<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of Afghanistan</target><part>communist regime there</part></link><space/>and supported the oppression of the<space/><link><target>Solidarity</target></link><space/>movement in Poland. As problems grew at home and abroad, Brezhnev was increasingly ineffective in responding to the growing criticism of the Soviet Union by Western leaders, most prominently by US Presidents<space/><link><target>Jimmy Carter</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link>, and UK Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">310–314</arg></template><space/>The CPSU, which had wishfully interpreted the<space/><link><target>197375 recession</target><part>financial crisis of the 1970s</part></link><space/>as the beginning of the end of capitalism, found its country falling far behind the West in its economic development.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">313</arg></template><space/>Brezhnev died on 10 November 1982, and was succeeded by<space/><link><target>Yuri Andropov</target></link><space/>on 12 November.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hanson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">315</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Andropov, a staunch anti-Stalinist, chaired the<space/><link><target>KGB</target></link><space/>during most of Brezhnev's reign.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">316</arg></template><space/>He had appointed several reformers to leading positions in the KGB, many of whom later became leading officials under Gorbachev.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">316</arg></template><space/>Andropov supported increased openness in the press, particularly regarding the challenges facing the Soviet Union.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">317</arg></template><space/>Andropov was in office briefly, but he appointed a number of reformers, including<space/><link><target>Yegor Ligachev</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nikolay Ryzhkov</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mikhail Gorbachev</target></link>, to important positions. He also supported a crackdown on absenteeism and corruption.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">317</arg></template><space/>Andropov had intended to let Gorbachev succeed him in office, but<space/><link><target>Konstantin Chernenko</target></link><space/>and his supporters suppressed the paragraph in the letter which called for Gorbachev's elevation.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">317</arg></template><space/>Andropov died on 9 February 1984 and was succeeded by Chernenko.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">317–318</arg></template><space/>Throughout his short leadership, Chernenko was unable to consolidate power and effective control of the party organization remained in Gorbachev's control.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">317–318</arg></template><space/>Chernenko died on 10 March 1985 and was succeeded in office by Gorbachev on 11 March 1985.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">317–318</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Gorbachev and the CPSU's demise (198591)</heading><paragraph>Gorbachev was elected CPSU General Secretary on 11 March 1985, one day after Chernenko's death.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">319</arg></template><space/>When he acceded, the Soviet Union was stagnating but was stable and may have continued largely unchanged into the 21st century if not for Gorbachev's reforms.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">319–320</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Gorbachev conducted a significant personnel reshuffling of the CPSU leadership, forcing old party conservatives out of office.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">320</arg></template><space/>In 1985 and early 1986, the new party leadership called for<space/><italics><link><target>uskoreniye</target></link></italics><space/>(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>acceleration</arg></template>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">320</arg></template><space/>Gorbachev reinvigorated the party ideology by adding new concepts and updating older ones.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">320</arg></template><space/>A positive consequence of this was the allowance of &quot;<link><target>freedom of thought</target><part>pluralism of thought</part></link>&quot; and a call for the establishment of &quot;<link><target>socialist pluralism</target></link>&quot; (literally, socialist democracy).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">322</arg></template><space/>He introduced a policy of<space/><italics><link><target>glasnost</target></link></italics><space/>(Russian:<space/><italics>openness</italics>,<space/><italics>transparency</italics>) in 1986, which led to a wave of unintended democratization.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">323</arg></template><space/>According to Russian scholar<space/><link><target>Archie Brown</target></link>, the democratization of the Soviet Union brought mixed blessings to Gorbachev; it helped him to weaken his conservative opponents within the party but brought out accumulated grievances which had been oppressed during the previous decades.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">323</arg></template><space/><link><target>File:RIAN archive 359290 Mikhail Gorbachev.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Gorbachev, the last leader of the CPSU and the Soviet Union, as seen in 1986</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In reaction to these changes, a conservative movement gained momentum in 1987 in response to<space/><link><target>Boris Yeltsin</target></link>'s dismissal as First Secretary of the<space/><link><target>Moscow City Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>CPSU Moscow City Committee</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">325</arg></template><space/>On 13 March 1988,<space/><link><target>Nina Andreyeva</target></link>, a university lecturer, wrote an article titled &quot;<link><target>I Cannot Forsake My Principles</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>The publication was planned to occur when both Gorbachev and his protege<space/><link><target>Alexander Yakovlev (Russian politician)</target><part>Alexander Yakovlev</part></link><space/>were visiting foreign countries.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>In their place, Yegor Ligachev led the party organization and told journalists that the article was &quot;a benchmark for what we need in our ideology today&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>Upon Gorbachev's return, the article was discussed at length during a Politburo meeting; it was revealed that nearly half of its members were sympathetic to the letter and opposed further reforms which could weaken the party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>The meeting lasted for two days, but on 5 April, a Politburo resolution responded with a point-by-point rebuttal to Andreyeva's article.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Gorbachev convened the<space/><link><target>19th Conference of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>19th Party Conference</part></link><space/>in June 1988. He criticized leading party conservatives Ligachev,<space/><link><target>Andrei Gromyko</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mikhail Solomentsev</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>In turn, conservative delegates attacked Gorbachev and the reformers.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">327</arg></template><space/>According to Brown, there had not been as much open discussion and dissent at a party meeting since the early 1920s.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">327</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the deep-seated opposition for further reform, the CPSU was still hierarchical; the conservatives acceded to Gorbachev's demands because he was the CPSU General Secretary.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">327</arg></template><space/>The 19th Conference approved the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Congress of People's Deputies of the Soviet Union</target><part>Congress of People's Deputies</part></link><space/>(CPD) and allowed for contested elections between the CPSU and independent candidates. Organized parties were not allowed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">327</arg></template><space/>The CPD was<space/><link><target>Soviet Union legislative election, 1989</target><part>elected in 1989</part></link>; one-third of the seats were appointed by the CPSU and other public organizations to sustain the Soviet<space/><link><target>single-party state</target><part>one-party state</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">327</arg></template><space/>The elections were democratic but most elected CPD members were against any more radical reform.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">327–328</arg></template><space/>The elections marked the highest electoral turnout in Russian history; no election before or since had a higher participation rate.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">328</arg></template><space/>An organized opposition was established within the legislature under the name<space/><link><target>Inter-Regional Group of Deputies</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">328</arg></template><space/>An unintended consequence of these reforms was the increased anti-CPSU pressure; in March 1990 at a session of the<space/><link><target>Supreme Soviet of the Soviet Union</target></link>, the party was forced to relinquish its political monopoly of power, in effect turning the Soviet Union into a<space/><link><target>liberal democracy</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">329</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The CPSU's demise began in March 1990, when party elements were eclipsed in power by state bodies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">329</arg></template><space/>From then until the Soviet Union's disestablishment, Gorbachev ruled the country through the newly created post of<space/><link><target>President of the Soviet Union</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">329</arg></template><space/>Following this, the central party apparatus played little practical role in Soviet affairs.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">329</arg></template><space/>Gorbachev had become independent from the Politburo and faced few constraints from party leaders.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">329</arg></template><space/>In the summer of 1990, the party convened the<space/><link><target>28th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>28th Congress</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">330</arg></template><space/>A new Politburo was elected, previous incumbents except Gorbachev and<space/><link><target>Vladimir Ivashko</target></link>, the CPSU Deputy General Secretary were removed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">330</arg></template><space/>Later that year, the party began work on a new program with a working title, &quot;Towards a Humane, Democratic Socialism&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">330</arg></template><space/>According to Brown, the program reflected Gorbachev's journey from an orthodox communist to a European<space/><link><target>social democracy</target><part>social democrat</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">330</arg></template><space/>The freedoms of thought and organization, which were allowed by Gorbachev, led to a rise in nationalism in the Soviet republics, indirectly weakening the central authorities.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">344–348</arg></template><space/>In response to this, a<space/><link><target>Soviet Union referendum, 1991</target><part>referendum was held in 1991</part></link>, in which most of the union republics<template><target>refn</target><arg>The Soviet Republics of Armenia, Estonia and Georgia all boycotted the 1991 referendum.</arg><arg name="group">note</arg></template><space/>voted to preserve the union in a<space/><link><target>Union of Sovereign States</target><part>different form</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">344–348</arg></template><space/>In reaction to this, conservative elements within the CPSU launched the<space/><link><target>1991 Soviet coup d'tat attempt</target><part>August 1991 coup</part></link>, which overthrew Gorbachev but failed to preserve the Soviet Union.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">344–348</arg></template><space/>When Gorbachev returned after the coup's collapse, he resigned from the CPSU and operations were handed over to Ivashko.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">344–349</arg></template><space/>The CPSU was outlawed on 29 August 1991 and Gorbachev resigned from the presidency on 25 December; the following day the Soviet Union was dissolved.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">349</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Governing style</heading><heading level='3'>Collective leadership</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Collective leadership in the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cult of personality</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Cult of personality</arg><arg>Joseph Stalin's cult of personality</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Democratic centralism and vanguardism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Democratic centralism</arg><arg>Vanguardism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Democratic centralism is an organizational principle conceived by Lenin.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>According to Soviet pronouncements, democratic centralism was distinguished from<space/><link><target>bureaucratic centralism</target></link>, which referred to high-handed formulae without knowledge or discussion.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>In democratic centralism, decisions are taken after discussions but once the general party line has been formed, discussion on the subject must cease.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>No member or organizational institution may dissent on a policy after it has been agreed upon by the party's governing body; to do so would lead to expulsion from the party (formalized at the<space/><link><target>10th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>10th Congress</part></link>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>Because of this stance, Lenin initiated a<space/><link><target>Ban on factions in the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>ban on factions</part></link>, which was approved at the 10th Congress.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">187</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lenin believed that democratic centralism safeguarded both party unity and ideological correctness.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>He conceived of the system after the events of 1917, when several socialist parties &quot;deformed&quot; themselves and actively began supporting nationalist sentiments.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">183–184</arg></template><space/>Lenin intended that the devotion to policy required by centralism would protect the parties from such<space/><link><target>Revisionism (Marxism)</target><part>revisionist</part></link><space/>ills and bourgeois defamation of socialism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">183–184</arg></template><space/>Lenin supported the notion of a highly centralized vanguard party, in which ordinary party members elected the local party committee, the local party committee elected the regional committee, the regional committee elected the Central Committee and the Central Committee elected the Politburo, Orgburo and the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>Lenin believed that the party needed to be ruled from the centre and have at its disposal power to mobilize party members at will.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>This system was later introduced in communist parties abroad through the<space/><link><target>Comintern</target><part>Communist International</part></link><space/>(Comintern).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">187</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A central tenet of Leninism was that of the vanguard party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">179</arg></template><space/>The party was to represent the interests of the working class and all of those who were exploited by capitalism in general; however, it was not to become a part of that class.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">179</arg></template><space/>According to Lenin, the party's sole responsibility was to articulate and plan the long-term interests of the oppressed classes. It was not responsible for the daily grievances of those classes; that was the responsibility of the<space/><link><target>trade union</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">179</arg></template><space/>According to Lenin, the Party and the oppressed classes could never become one because the Party was responsible for leading the oppressed classes to victory.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">181</arg></template><space/>The basic idea was that a small group of organized people could wield power disproportionate to their size with superior organizational skills.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">181</arg></template><space/>Despite this, until the end of his life, Lenin warned of the danger that the party could be taken over by bureaucrats, by a small clique, or by an individual.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">181</arg></template><space/>Toward the end of his life, he criticized the bureaucratic inertia of certain officials and admitted to problems with some of the party's control structures, which were to supervise organizational life.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">181</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Organization</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Organization of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template><template><target>Soviet Union sidebar</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Congress</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Congress, nominally the highest organ of the party, was convened every five years.<space/><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template><space/>Leading up to the October Revolution and until Stalin's consolidation of power, the Congress was the party's main decision-making body.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template><space/>However, after Stalin's ascension the Congresses became largely symbolic.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template><space/>CPSU leaders used Congresses as a propaganda and control tool.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template><space/>The most noteworthy Congress since the 1930s was the 20th Congress, in which Khrushchev denounced Stalin in a speech titled &quot;<link><target>The Personality Cult and its Consequences</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite delegates to Congresses losing their powers to criticize or remove party leadership, the Congresses functioned as a form of<space/><link><target>Mass communications</target><part>elite-mass communication</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template><space/>They were occasions for the party leadership to express the<space/><link><target>party line (politics)</target><part>party line</part></link><space/>over the next five years to ordinary CPSU members and the general public.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template><space/>The information provided was general, ensuring that party leadership retained the ability to make specific policy changes as they saw fit.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Congresses also provided the party leadership with formal legitimacy by providing a mechanism for the election of new members and the retirement of old members who had lost favour.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">3</arg></template><space/>The elections at Congresses were all predetermined and the candidates who stood for seats to the Central Committee and the<space/><link><target>Central Auditing Commission of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Central Auditing Commission</part></link><space/>were approved beforehand by the Politburo and the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">3</arg></template><space/>A Congress could also provide a platform for the announcement of new ideological concepts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zimmerman</arg><arg>1977</arg><arg name="p">3</arg></template><space/>For instance, at the<space/><link><target>22nd Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>22nd Congress</part></link>, Khrushchev announced that the Soviet Union would see &quot;<link><target>Communism in 20 years</target><part>communism in twenty years</part></link>&quot;<template><target>mdash</target></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="pp">62–64</arg></template><space/>a position later retracted.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Conference</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Conference of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template>A party Conference, officially referred to as an All-Union Conference, was convened between Congresses by the Central Committee to discuss party policy and to make personnel changes within the Central Committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="auccpsu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work"><space/>[[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Staff writer]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://bse.sci-lib.com/article007127.html<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">ru:Всесоюзная конференция КПСС<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>All-Union Conference of the CPSU<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>bse.sci-lib.com<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Russian<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>19 conferences were convened during the CPSU's existence.<extension extension_name='ref' name="auccpsu"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>19th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>19th Congress</part></link><space/>held in 1952 removed the clause in the party's statute which stipulated that a party Conference could be convened.<extension extension_name='ref' name="auccpsu"></extension><space/>The clause was reinstated at the 23rd Congress, which was held in 1966.<extension extension_name='ref' name="auccpsu"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Central Committee</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template>The Central Committee was a<space/><link><target>Collectivism</target><part>collective body</part></link><space/>elected at the annual<space/><link><target>Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>party congress</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">455</arg></template><space/>It was mandated to meet at least twice a year to act as the party's supreme governing body.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">455</arg></template><space/>Membership of the Central Committee increased from 71 full members in 1934 to 287 in 1976.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="pp">455–456</arg></template><space/>Central Committee members were elected to the seats because of the offices they held, not on their personal merit.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">458</arg></template><space/>Because of this, the Central Committee was commonly considered an indicator for<space/><link><target>Sovietologist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to study the strength of the different institutions.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">458</arg></template><space/>The Politburo was elected by and reported to the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="pp">25–26</arg></template><space/>Besides the Politburo, the Central Committee also elected the<space/><link><target>Secretariat of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Secretariat</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>General Secretary</part></link><template><target>mdash</target></template>the<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>leader of the Soviet Union.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="pp">25–26</arg></template><space/>In 19191952 the<space/><link><target>Orgburo</target></link><space/>was also elected in the same manner as the Politburo and the Secretariat by the plenums of the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="pp">25–26</arg></template><space/>In between Central Committee plenums, the Politburo and the Secretariat were legally empowered to make decisions on its behalf.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="pp">25–26</arg></template><space/>The Central Committee or the Politburo and/or Secretariat on its behalf could issue nationwide decisions; decisions on behalf of the party were transmitted from the top to the bottom.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">27</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Under Lenin, the Central Committee functioned much like the Politburo did during the post-Stalin era, serving as the party's governing body.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">93</arg></template><space/>However, as the membership in the Central Committee increased, its role was eclipsed by the Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">93</arg></template><space/>Between Congresses, the Central Committee functioned as the Soviet leadership's source of legitimacy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">93</arg></template><space/>The decline in the Central Committee's standing began in the 1920s; it was reduced to a compliant body of the Party leadership during the Great Purge.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">93</arg></template><space/>According to party rules, the Central Committee was to convene at least twice a year to discuss political matters<template><target>mdash</target></template>but not matters relating to military policy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">94</arg></template><space/>The body remained largely symbolic after Stalin's consolidation; leading party officials rarely attended meetings of the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">462</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Central Auditing Commission</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Central Auditing Commission of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template>The Central Auditing Commission (CAC) was elected by the party Congresses and reported only to the party Congress.<extension extension_name='ref' name="caccpsu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work"><space/>[[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Staff writer]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://bse.sci-lib.com/article120553.html<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">ru:Центральная ревизионная комиссия КПСС<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>Central Auditing Commission of the CPSU<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>bse.sci-lib.com<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Russian<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>It had about as many members as the Central Committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="caccpsu"></extension><space/>It was responsible for supervising the expeditious and proper handling of affairs by the central bodies of the Party; it audited the accounts of the Treasury and the enterprises of the Central Committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="caccpsu"></extension><space/>It was also responsible for supervising the Central Committee apparatus, making sure that its directives were implemented and that Central Committee directives complied with the party Statute.<extension extension_name='ref' name="caccpsu"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Statute</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Statute of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Statute, also referred to as the Rules, Charter and Constitution, were the party's by-laws and controlled life within the CPSU.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">393</arg></template><space/>The 1st Statute was adopted at the<space/><link><target>2nd Congress of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party</target></link><template><target>mdash</target></template>the forerunner of the CPSU.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">393</arg></template><space/>How the Statute was to be structured and organized led to a schism within the party, leading to the establishment of two competing factions;<space/><link><target>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>Bolsheviks</part></link><space/>(literally<space/><italics>majority</italics>) and<space/><link><target>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party (Mensheviks)</target><part>Mensheviks</part></link><space/>(literally<space/><italics>minority</italics>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">393</arg></template><space/>The 1st Statute was based upon Lenin's idea of a centralized vanguard party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">393</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>4th Congress of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party</target><part>4th Congress</part></link>, despite a majority of Menshevik delegates, added the concept of<space/><link><target>democratic centralism</target></link><space/>to Article 2 of the Statute.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">394</arg></template><space/>The 1st Statute lasted until 1919, when the<space/><link><target>8th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>8th Congress</part></link><space/>adopted the 2nd Statute.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">396</arg></template><space/>It was nearly five times as long as the 1st Statute and contained 66 articles.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">396</arg></template><space/>It was amended at the<space/><link><target>9th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>9th Congress</part></link>. At the<space/><link><target>11th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>11th Congress</part></link>, the 3rd Statute was adopted with only minor amendments being made.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">398</arg></template><space/>New statutes were approved at the<space/><link><target>17th Congress of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>17th</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>18th Congress of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>18th Congresses</part></link><space/>respectively.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="pp">399–404</arg></template><space/>The last party statute, which existed until the dissolution of the CPSU, was adopted at the 22nd Congress.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Simons</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="pp">404–408</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Central Committee apparatus</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>General Secretary</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>General Secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Politburo</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Politburo of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template><link><target>File:Execute 346 Politburo passes.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>A Politburo resolution to execute 346 &quot;enemies of the CPSU and Soviet Power&quot; who led &quot;counter-revolutionary, right-trotskyite, plotting and spying activities&quot;. Signed by Stalin</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Political Bureau (Politburo), known as the Presidium from 1952 to 1966, was the highest party organ when the Congress and the Central Committee were not in session.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">85</arg></template><space/>Until the 19th Conference in 1988, the Politburo alongside the Secretariat controlled appointments and dismissals nationwide.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">98</arg></template><space/>In the post-Stalin period, the Politburo controlled the Central Committee apparatus through two channels; the<space/><link><target>General Department of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>General Department</part></link><space/>distributed the Politburo's orders to the Central Committee departments and through the personnel overlap which existed within the Politburo and the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">98</arg></template><space/>This personnel overlap gave the CPSU General Secretary a way of strengthening his position within the Politburo through the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">99</arg></template><space/><link><target>Kirill Mazurov</target></link>, Politburo member from 1965 to 1978, accused Brezhnev of turning the Politburo into a &quot;second echelon&quot; of power.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">99</arg></template><space/>He accomplished this by discussing policies before Politburo meetings with<space/><link><target>Mikhail Suslov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andrei Kirilenko (politician)</target><part>Andrei Kirilenko</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Fyodor Kulakov</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dmitriy Ustinov</target></link><space/>among others, who held seats both in the Politburo and the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">99</arg></template><space/>Mazurov's claim was later verified by<space/><link><target>Nikolai Ryzhkov</target></link>, the Chairman of the Council of Ministers under Gorbachev. Ryzhkov said that Politburo meetings lasted only 15 minutes because the people close to Brezhnev had already decided what was to be approved.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">99</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Politburo was abolished and replaced by a Presidium in 1952 at the 19th Congress.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="pp">37–38</arg></template><space/>In the aftermath the 19th Congress and the 1st Plenum of the<space/><link><target>19th Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>19th Central Committee</part></link>, Stalin ordered the creation of the<space/><link><target>Bureau of the Presidium</target></link>, which acted as the standing committee of the Presidium.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">38</arg></template><space/>On 6 March 1953, one day after Stalin's death, a new and smaller Presidium was elected and the Bureau of the Presidium was abolished in a joint session with the<space/><link><target>Presidium of the Supreme Soviet</target></link><space/>and the Council of Ministers.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">45</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Until 1990, the CPSU General Secretary acted as the informal chairman of the Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">101</arg></template><space/>During the first decades of the CPSU's existence, the Politburo was officially chaired by the Chairman of the<space/><link><target>Council of People's Commissars</target></link>; first by Lenin, then by<space/><link><target>Aleksey Rykov</target></link>, Molotov, Stalin and Malenkov.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">101</arg></template><space/>After 1922, when Lenin was incapacitated,<space/><link><target>Lev Kamenev</target></link><space/>as Deputy Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars chaired the Politburo's meetings.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">101</arg></template><space/>This tradition lasted until Khrushchev's consolidation of power.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">101</arg></template><space/>In the first post-Stalin years, when Malenkov chaired Politburo meetings, Khrushchev as First Secretary signed all Central Committee documents into force.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">101</arg></template><space/>From 1954 until 1958, Khrushchev chaired the Politburo as First Secretary but in 1958 he dismissed and succeeded<space/><link><target>Nikolai Bulganin</target></link><space/>as Chairman of the Council of Ministers.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">102</arg></template><space/>During this period, the informal position of Second Secretary<template><target>mdash</target></template>later formalized as Deputy General Secretary<template><target>mdash</target></template>was established.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">102</arg></template><space/>The Second Secretary became responsible for chairing the Secretariat in place of the General Secretary. When the General Secretary could not chair the meetings of the Politburo, the Second Secretary would take his place.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">102</arg></template><space/>This system survived until the dissolution of the CPSU in 1991.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">102</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>To be elected to the Politburo, a member had to serve in the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template><space/>The Central Committee elected the Politburo in the aftermath of a party Congress.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template><space/>Members of the Central Committee were given a predetermined list of candidates for the Politburo having only one candidate for each seat; for this reason the election of the Politburo was usually passed unanimously.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template><space/>The greater the power held by the sitting CPSU General Secretary, the higher the chance that the Politburo membership would be approved.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Secretariat</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Secretariat of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Secretariat headed the CPSU's central apparatus and was solely responsible for the development and implementation of party policies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">26</arg></template><space/>It was legally empowered to take over the duties and functions of the Central Committee when it was not in plenum (did not hold a meeting).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Getty</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">26</arg></template><space/>Many members of the Secretariat concurrently held a seat in the Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">430</arg></template><space/>According to a Soviet textbook on party procedures, the Secretariat's role was that of &quot;leadership of current work, chiefly in the realm of personnel selection and in the organization of the verification of fulfillment [of party-state decisions&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">430</arg></template><space/>&quot;Selections of personnel&quot; (<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>podbor kadrov</arg></template>) in this instance meant the maintenance of general standards and the criteria for selecting various personnel. &quot;Verification of fulfillment&quot; (<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>proverka ispolneniia</arg></template>) of party and state decisions meant that the Secretariat instructed other bodies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">432</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The powers of the Secretariat were weakened under Mikhail Gorbachev; the Central Committee Commissions took over the functions of the Secretariat in 1988.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>Yegor Ligachev, a Secretariat member, said that the changes completely destroyed the Secretariat's hold on power and made the body almost superfluous.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>Because of this, the Secretariat rarely met during the next two years.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brown</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>It was revitalized at the 28th Party Congress in 1990 and the Deputy General Secretary became the official Head of the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harris</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">121</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Orgburo</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Orgburo</arg></template>The Organizational Bureau, or Orgburo, existed from 1919 to 1952 and was one of three leading bodies of the party when the Central Committee was not in session.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">85</arg></template><space/>It was responsible for &quot;organizational questions, the recruitment and allocation of personnel, the coordination of activities of party, government and social organizations (e.g. trade unions and youth organizations), improvement to the party's structure, the distribution of information and reports within the party&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template><space/>The 19th Congress abolished the Orgburo and its duties and responsibilities were taken over by the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lowenhardt</arg><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>Ozinga</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template><space/>At the beginning, the Orgburo held three meetings a week and reported to the Central Committee every second week.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Eaton</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">58</arg></template><space/>Lenin described the relation between the Politburo and the Orgburo as &quot;the Orgburo allocates forces, while the Politburo decides policy&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/>A decision of the Orgburo was implemented by the Secretariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/>However, the Secretariat could make decisions in the Orgburo's name without consulting its members but if one Orgburo member objected to a Secretariat resolution, the resolution would not be implemented.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/>In the 1920s, if the Central Committee could not convene the Politburo and the Orgburo would hold a joint session in its place.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Control Commission</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Control Commission of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template>The Central Control Commission (CCC) functioned as the party's supreme court.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">249</arg></template><space/>The CCC was established at the<space/><link><target>9th All-Russian Conference of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>9th All-Russian Conference</part></link><space/>in September 1920, but rules organizing its procedure were not enacted before the 10th Congress.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template><space/>The 10th Congress formally established the CCC on all party levels and stated that it could only be elected at a party congress or a party conference.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template><space/>The CCC and the CCs were formally independent but had to make decisions through the party committees at their level, which led them in practice to lose their administrative independence.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template><space/>At first, the primary responsibility of the CCs was to respond to party complaints, focusing mostly on party complaints of<space/><link><target>Political faction</target><part>factionalism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bureaucracy</target><part>bureaucratism</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">84</arg></template><space/>At the 11th Congress, the brief of the CCs was expanded; it become responsible for overseeing<space/><link><target>party line (politics)</target><part>party discipline</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">84–85</arg></template><space/>In a bid to further centralize the powers of the CCC, a Presidium of the CCC, which functioned in a similar manner to the Politburo in relation to the Central Committee, was established in 1923.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">167</arg></template><space/>At the 18th Congress, party rules regarding the CCC were changed; it was now elected by the Central Committee and was subordinate to the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Eisen</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">246</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>CCC members could not concurrently be members of the Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">95</arg></template><space/>To create an organizational link between the CCC and other central-level organs, the 9th All-Russian Conference created the joint CCCCC plenums.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">95</arg></template><space/>The CCC was a powerful organ; the 10th Congress allowed it to expel full and candidate Central Committee members and members of their subordinate organs if two thirds of attendants at a CCCCC plenum voted for such.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">95</arg></template><space/>At its first such session in 1921, Lenin tried to persuade the joint plenum to expel<space/><link><target>Alexander Shliapnikov</target></link><space/>from the party; instead of expelling him, Shliapnikov was given a severe reprimand.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gill</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">95</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Departments</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Departments of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template>The leader of a department was usually given the title &quot;head&quot;(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>zaveduiuschchii</arg></template>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="pp">417–418</arg></template><space/>In practice, the Secretariat had a major say in the running of the departments; for example, five of eleven secretaries headed their own departments in 1978.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">418</arg></template><space/>Normally, specific secretaries were given supervising duties over one or more departments.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">418</arg></template><space/>Each department established its own cells<template><target>mdash</target></template>called sctions<template><target>mdash</target></template>which specialized in one or more fields.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">420</arg></template><space/>During the Gorbachev era, a variety of departments made up the Central Committee apparatus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"></extension><space/>The Party Building and Cadre Work Department assigned party personnel in the<space/><link><target>nomenklatura</target></link><space/>system.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"></extension><space/>The State and Legal Department supervised the armed forces, KGB, the Ministry of Internal Affairs, the trade unions, and the Procuracy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"></extension><space/>Before 1989, the Central Committee had several departments but some were abolished that year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"></extension><space/>Among these departments was the Economics Department that was responsible for the economy as a whole, one for machine building, one for the chemical industry, etc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"></extension><space/>The party abolished these departments to remove itself from the day-to-day management of the economy in favour of government bodies and a greater role for the market, as a part of the<space/><link><target>perestroika</target></link><space/>process.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCdepLC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Union: Secretariat<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Library of Congress]]<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+su0195)<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>May 1989<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In their place, Gorbachev called for the creations of commissions with the same responsibilities as departments, but giving more independence from the state apparatus. This change was approved at the 19th Conference, which was held in 1988.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harris</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">53</arg></template><space/>Six commissions were established by late 1988.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harris</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">53</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Pravda</italics></heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Pravda</arg></template><italics><link><target>Pravda</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Truth</italics>) was the leading newspaper in the Soviet Union.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Remington</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">106</arg></template><space/>The Organizational Department of the Central Committee was the only organ empowered to dismiss<space/><italics>Pravda</italics><space/>editors.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lenoe</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">202</arg></template><space/>In 1905,<space/><italics>Pravda</italics><space/>began as a project by members of the<space/><link><target>Ukrainian Social Democratic Labour Party</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Swain</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/><link><target>Leon Trotsky</target></link><space/>was approached about the possibility of running the new paper because of his previous work on Ukrainian newspaper<space/><italics>Kievan Thought</italics>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Swain</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/>The first issue of<space/><italics>Pravda</italics><space/>was published on 3 October 1908<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Swain</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Lviv</target><part>Lvov</part></link>, where it continued until the publication of the sixth issue in November 1909, when the operation was moved to<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Austria-Hungary</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Swain</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">37</arg></template><space/>During the Russian Civil War, sales of<space/><italics>Pravda</italics><space/>were curtailed by<space/><italics><link><target>Izvestia</target></link></italics>, the government run newspaper.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kenez</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">45</arg></template><space/>At the time, the average reading figure for<space/><italics>Pravda</italics><space/>was 130,000.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kenez</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">45</arg></template><space/>This Vienna-based newspaper published its last issue in 1912 and was succeeded the same year by a new newspaper dominated by the Bolsheviks, also called<space/><italics>Pravda</italics>, which was headquartered in<space/><link><target>St. Petersburg</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Swain</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">27</arg></template><space/>The paper's main goal was to promote MarxistLeninist philosophy and expose the lies of the<space/><link><target>bourgeoisie</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GSEPravda"></extension><space/>In 1975, the paper reached a circulation of 10.6 million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GSEPravda"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work"><space/>[[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Staff writer]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://bse.sci-lib.com/article092177.html<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">ru:"Правда" (газета)<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>''Pravda'' (newspaper)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>bse.sci-lib.com<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Russian<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Higher Party School</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Central Committee of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union#Party education system</arg><arg name="l1">Education system under the CPSU Central Committee</arg></template>The Higher Party School (HPS) was the organ responsible for teaching cadres in the Soviet Union.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GSEHPS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work"><space/>[[Great Soviet Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Staff writer]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://bse.sci-lib.com/article055217.html<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">ru:Высшая партийная школа при ЦК КПСС<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>Higher Party School of the CC of the CPSU<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 March 2014<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>bse.sci-lib.com<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Russian<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>It was the successor of the<space/><link><target>Communist Academy</target></link>, which was established in 1918.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GSEHPS"></extension><space/>The HPS was established in 1939 as the Moscow Higher Party School; it offered its students a two-year training course for becoming a Party official.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>It was reorganized in 1956 to that it could offer more specialized ideological training.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>In 1956, the school in Moscow was opened for students from socialist countries outside the USSR.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>The Moscow Higher Party School was the party school with the highest standing.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template><space/>The school itself had eleven faculties until a 1972 Central Committee resolution demanded a reorganization of the curriculum.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>The first regional HPS outside<space/><link><target>Moscow</target></link><space/>was established in 1946;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>by the early 1950s there were 70 Higher Party Schools.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template><space/>During the reorganization drive of 1956, Khrushchev closed 13 of them and reclassified 29 as inter-republican and inter-oblast schools.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>1983</arg><arg name="p">186</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Lower-level organization</heading><heading level='4'>Republican and local organization</heading><paragraph>The lowest organ above the<space/><link><target>primary party organization</target></link><space/>(PPO) was the district level.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>Every two years, the local PPO would elect delegates to the district-level party conference, which was overseen by a secretary from a higher party level. The conference elected a Party Committee and First Secretary, and re-declared the districts commitment to the CPSUs program.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>In between conferences, the &quot;raion&quot; party committee<template><target>mdash</target></template>commonly referred to as &quot;raikom&quot;<template><target>mdash</target></template>was vested with ultimate authority.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>It convened at least six times a year to discuss party directives and to oversee the implementation of party policies in their respective districts, to oversee the implementation of party directives at the PPO-level, and to issue directives to PPOs.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>7580 percent of raikom members were full members, while the remaining 2025 were non-voting, candidate members.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>Raikom members were commonly from the state sector, party sector, Komsomol or the trade unions.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Day-to-day responsibility of the raikom was handed over to a Politburo, which usually composed of 12 members.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>The district-level First Secretary chaired the meetings of the local Politburo and the raikom, and was the direct link between the district and the higher party echelons.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>The First Secretary was responsible for the smooth running of operations.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>The raikom was headed by the local apparat<template><target>mdash</target></template>the local agitation department or industry department.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>A raikom usually had no more than 4 or 5 departments, each of which was responsible for overseeing the work of the state sector but would not interfere in their work.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This system remained identical at all other levels of the CPSU hierarchy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>The other levels were cities, oblasts (regions) and republics.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>The district level elected delegates to a conference held at least held every three years to elect the party committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>The only difference between the oblast and the district level was that the oblast had its own Secretariat and had more departments at its disposal.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>The oblast's party committee in turn elected delegates to the republican-level Congress, which was held every five years.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template><space/>The Congress then elected the Central Committee of the republic, which in turn elected a First Secretary and a Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template><space/>Until 1990, the<space/><link><target>Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic</target></link><space/>was the only republic which did not have its own republican branch, being instead represented by the CPSU Central Committee.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Primary party organizations</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Primary party organization</arg></template>The primary party organization (PPO) was the lowest level in the CPSU hierarchy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>PPOs were organized cells consisting of three or more members.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>A PPO could exist anywhere; for example, in a factory or a student dormitory.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>They functioned as the partys &quot;eyes and ears&quot; at the lowest level and were used to mobilize support for party policies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>All CPSU members had to be a member of a local PPO.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>The size of a PPO varied from three people to several hundreds, depending upon its setting.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>In a large enterprise, a PPO usually had several hundred members.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>In such cases, the PPO was divided into bureaus based upon production-units.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>Each PPO was led by an executive committee and an executive committee secretary.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>Each executive committee is responsible for the PPO executive committee and its secretary.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>In small PPOs, members met periodically to mainly discuss party policies, ideology or practical matters. In such a case, the PPO secretary was responsible for collecting party dues, reporting to higher organs and maintaining the party records.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>A secretary could be elected democratically through a secret ballot, but that was not often the case; in 1979, only 88 out of the over 400,000 PPOs were elected in this fashion.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>The remainder were chosen by a higher party organ and ratified by the general meetings of the PPO.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>The PPO general meeting was responsible for electing delegates to the party conference at either the district- or town-level, depending on where the PPO was located.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Membership</heading><paragraph><link><target>File: .1989.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>CPSU membership card (1989)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Membership of the party was not open. To become a party member, one had to be approved by various committees and one's past was closely scrutinized. As generations grew up having known nothing before the USSR, party membership became something one generally achieved after passing a series of stages. Children would join the<space/><link><target>Young Pioneer organization of the Soviet Union</target><part>Young Pioneers</part></link>, and at the age of 14 might graduate to the<space/><link><target>Komsomol</target></link><space/>(Young Communist League). Ultimately, as an adult, if one had shown the proper adherence to party discipline or had the right connections, one would become a member of the Communist Party itself. Membership of the party carried obligations; the Party expected Komsomol and CPSU members to pay dues and to carry out appropriate assignments and &quot;social tasks&quot; ( ).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1918, Party membership was approximately 200,000. In the late 1920s under Stalin, the Party engaged in an intensive recruitment campaign (the &quot;Lenin Levy&quot;) of new members from both the working class and rural areas. This represented an attempt to &quot;proletarianize&quot; the Party and an attempt by Stalin to strengthen his base by outnumbering the<space/><link><target>Old Bolsheviks</target></link><space/>and reducing their influence in the Party. In 1925, the Party had 1,025,000 members in a Soviet population of 147 million. In 1927, membership had risen to 1,200,000. During the collectivization campaign and industrialization campaigns of the First Five-Year Plan from 1929 to 1933, Party membership grew rapidly to approximately 3.5 million members. However, Party leaders suspected that the mass intake of new members had allowed &quot;social-alien elements&quot; to penetrate the Party's ranks and document verifications of membership ensued in 1933 and 1935, removing supposedly unreliable members. Meanwhile, the Party closed its ranks to new members from 1933 to November 1936. Even after the reopening of Party recruiting, membership fell to 1.9 million by 1939.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2007</arg></template><space/>(Nicholas DeWitt gives 2.307 million members in 1939, including candidate members, compared with 1.535 million in 1929 and 6.3 million in 1947.) In 1986, the CPSU had over 19 million members<template><target>mdash</target></template>approximately 10% of the USSR's adult population. Over 44% of party members were classified as industrial workers and 12% as collective farmers. The CPSU had party organizations in 14 of the USSR's 15 republics. The Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic itself had no separate Communist Party until 1990 because the CPSU controlled affairs there directly.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Komsomol</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Komsomol</arg></template>The All-Union Leninist Communist Youth League, commonly referred to as Komsomol, was the party's youth wing.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">406</arg></template><space/>The Komsomol acted under the direction of the CPSU Central Committee.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">406</arg></template><space/>It was responsible for indoctrinating youths in communist ideology and organizing social events.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">405</arg></template><space/>It was closely modeled on the CPSU; nominally the highest body was the<space/><link><target>Congress of the Komsomol</target><part>Congress</part></link>, followed by the<space/><link><target>Central Committee of the Komsomol</target><part>Central Committee</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Secretariat of the Komsomol</target><part>Secretariat</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Politburo of the Komsomol</target><part>Politburo</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">406</arg></template><space/>The Komsomol participated in nationwide policy-making by appointing members to the collegiums of the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Culture (Soviet Union)</target><part>Ministry of Culture</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Higher and Specialized Secondary Education</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Education (Soviet Union)</target><part>Ministry of Education</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>State Committee for Physical Culture and Sports</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">406</arg></template><space/>The organization's newspaper was the<space/><italics><link><target>Komsomolskaya Pravda</target></link></italics>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">407</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>First Secretary of the Komsomol</target><part>First Secretary</part></link><space/>and the Second Secretary were commonly members of the Central Committee but were never elected to the Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">407</arg></template><space/>However, at the republican level, several Komsomol first secretaries were appointed to the Politburo.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fainsod</arg><arg>Hough</arg><arg>1979</arg><arg name="p">407</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ideology</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Ideology of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>MarxismLeninism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Marxism–Leninism</arg></template>MarxismLeninism was the cornerstone of Soviet ideology.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">206</arg></template><space/>It explained and legitimized the CPSU's right to rule while explaining its role as a vanguard party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">206</arg></template><space/>For instance, the ideology explained that the CPSU's policies, even if they were unpopular, were correct because the party was enlightened.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">206</arg></template><space/>It was represented as the only truth in Soviet society; the Party rejected the notion of multiple truths.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">206</arg></template><space/>MarxismLeninism was used to justify CPSU rule and Soviet policy but it was not used as a means to an end.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">206</arg></template><space/>The relationship between ideology and decision-making was at best ambivalent; most policy decisions were made in the light of the continued, permanent development of MarxismLeninism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">212</arg></template><space/>MarxismLeninism as the only truth could not<template><target>mdash</target></template>by its very nature<template><target>mdash</target></template>become outdated.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sawka</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">212</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite having evolved over the years, MarxismLeninism had several central tenets.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/>The main tenet was the party's status as the sole ruling party.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>1977 Soviet Constitution</target><part>1977 Constitution</part></link><space/>referred to the party as &quot;The leading and guiding force of Soviet society, and the nucleus of its political system, of all state and public organizations, is the Communist Party of the Soviet Union&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">81</arg></template><space/><link><target>State socialism</target></link><space/>was essential and from Stalin until Gorbachev, official discourse considered that private social and economic activity retarding the development of collective consciousness and the economy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Gorbachev supported<space/><link><target>privatization</target></link><space/>to a degree but based his policies on Lenin's and Bukharin's opinions of the New Economic Policy of the 1920s, and supported complete state ownership over the<space/><link><target>commanding heights of the economy</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Unlike<space/><link><target>liberalism</target></link>, MarxismLeninism stressed the role of the individual as a member of a<space/><link><target>collective</target></link><space/>rather than the importance of the individual.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Individuals only had the right to<space/><link><target>freedom of expression</target></link><space/>if it safeguarded the interests of a collective.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>For instance, the 1977 Constitution stated that every person had the right to express his or her opinion, but the opinion could only be expressed if it was in accordance with the &quot;general interests of Soviet society&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>The quantity of rights granted to an individual was decided by the state and the state could remove these rights if it saw fit.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Soviet MarxismLeninism justified<space/><link><target>nationalism</target></link>; the Soviet media portrayed every victory of the state as a victory for the<space/><link><target>communism</target><part>communist movement</part></link><space/>as a whole.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>Largely, Soviet nationalism was based upon ethnic<space/><link><target>Russian nationalism</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>MarxismLeninism stressed the importance of the worldwide conflict between capitalism and socialism; the Soviet press wrote about progressive and reactionary forces while claiming that socialism was on the verge of victory and that the &quot;correlations of forces&quot; were in the Soviet Union's favour.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template><space/>The ideology professed<space/><link><target>state atheism</target></link>; Party members were not allowed to be religious.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>MarxismLeninism believed in the feasibility of a<space/><link><target>pure communism</target><part>communist mode of production</part></link>. All policies were justifiable if it contributed to the Soviet Union's achievement of that stage.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sakwa</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="pp">206–212</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Leninism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Leninism</arg></template>In Marxist philosophy, Leninism is the body of political theory for the democratic organization of a revolutionary vanguard party and the achievement of a<space/><link><target>dictatorship of the proletariat</target></link><space/>as a political prelude to the establishment of the socialist mode of production developed by Lenin.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>Since<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link><space/>barely, if ever wrote about how the socialist mode of production would function, these tasks were left for Lenin to solve.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>Lenin's main contribution to Marxist thought is the concept of the vanguard party of the working class.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>He conceived the vanguard party as a highly-knit, centralized organization which was led by intellectuals rather than by the working class itself.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>The CPSU was open only to a small quantity of workers because the workers in Russia still had not developed<space/><link><target>class consciousness</target></link><space/>and needed to be educated to reach such a state.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>Lenin believed that the vanguard party could initiate policies in the name of the working class even if the working class did not support them. The vanguard party would know what was best for the workers because the party functionaries had attained consciousness.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Leninism was by definition authoritarian.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>Lenin, in light of the<space/><link><target>Marx's theory of the state</target></link><space/>(which views the state as an oppressive organ of the ruling class), had no qualms of forcing change upon the country.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>He viewed the dictatorship of the proletariat, rather than the dictatorship of the bourgeoisie, to be the dictatorship of the majority.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>The repressive powers of the state were to be used to transform the country, and to strip of the former ruling class of their wealth.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>Lenin believed that the transition from the<space/><link><target>capitalist mode of production (Marxist theory)</target><part>capitalist mode of production</part></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>socialist mode of production</target></link><space/>would last for a long period.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">77</arg></template><space/>In contrast to Marx, who believed that the<space/><link><target>socialist revolution</target></link><space/>would comprise and be led by the working class alone, Lenin argued that a socialist revolution did not necessarily need to be led or to comprise the working class alone. Instead, he said that a revolution needed to be led by the oppressed classes of society, which in the case of Russia was the peasant class.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">767</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Stalinism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Stalinism</arg></template><link><target>File:Stalin Image.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Stalinism, while not an ideology ''per se'', refers to the thoughts and policies of Stalin</part></link>Stalinism, while not an ideology<space/><italics>per se</italics>, refers to Stalin's thoughts and policies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>Stalin's introduction of the concept &quot;<link><target>Socialism in One Country</target></link>&quot; in 1924 was an important moment in Soviet ideological discourse.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>According to Stalin, the Soviet Union did not need a socialist world revolution to construct a socialist society.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>Four years later, Stalin initiated his &quot;Second Revolution&quot; with the introduction of state socialism and<space/><link><target>Planned economy</target><part>central planning</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>In the early 1930s, he initiated the<space/><link><target>Collectivization in the Soviet Union</target><part>collectivization</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Agriculture in the Soviet Union</target><part>Soviet agriculture</part></link><space/>by de-privatizing agriculture and creating peasant cooperatives rather than making it the responsibility of the state.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>With the initiation of his &quot;Second Revolution&quot;, Stalin launched the &quot;<link><target>Stalin's cult of personality</target><part>Cult of Lenin</part></link>&quot;<template><target>mdash</target></template>a<space/><link><target>cult of personality</target></link><space/>centered upon himself.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">78</arg></template><space/>The name of the city of Petrograd was changed to<space/><link><target>Leningrad</target></link>, the town of Lenin's birth was renamed Ulyanov (Lenin's birth-name), the<space/><link><target>Order of Lenin</target></link><space/>became the highest state award and portraits of Lenin were hung in public squares, workplaces and elsewhere.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="pp">78–79</arg></template><space/>The increasing bureaucracy which followed the introduction of a state socialist economy was at complete odds with the Marxist notion of &quot;the withering away of the state&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template><space/>Stalin explained the reasoning behind it at the<space/><link><target>16th Congress of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>16th Congress</part></link><space/>held in 1930;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>We stand for the strengthening of the dictatorship of the proletariat, which represents the mightiest and most powerful authority of all forms of State that have ever existed. The highest development of the State power for the withering away of State power this is the Marxian formula. Is this contradictory? Yes, it is contradictory. But this contradiction springs from life itself and reflects completely Marxist dialectic.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the 1939 18th Congress, Stalin abandoned the idea that the state would wither away. In its place, he expressed confidence that the state would exist, even if the Soviet Union reached communism, as long as it was encircled by capitalism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">133</arg></template><space/>Two key concepts were created in the latter half of his rule; the &quot;two camp&quot; theory and the &quot;capitalist encirclement&quot; theory.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template><space/>The threat of capitalism was used to strengthen Stalin's personal powers and<space/><link><target>Soviet propaganda</target></link><space/>began making a direct link with Stalin and stability in society, saying that the country would crumble without the leader.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template><space/>Stalin deviated greatly from<space/><link><target>classical Marxism</target></link><space/>on the subject of &quot;subjective factors&quot;; Stalin said that Party members of all ranks had to profess fanatic adherence to the Party's line and ideology, if not, those policies would fail.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">79</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Concepts</heading><heading level='4'>Dictatorship of the proletariat</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Dictatorship of the proletariat</arg></template><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em</arg><arg name="align">right</arg><arg name="bgcolor">ivory</arg><arg name="quote">"Either the dictatorship of the landowners and capitalists, or the dictatorship of the proletariat ... There is no middle course ... There is no middle course anywhere in the world, nor can there be."</arg><arg name="source">—Lenin, claiming that people had only two choices; between two different, but distinct class dictatorships.{{sfn|Harding|1996|pp</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lenin, supporting Marx's theory of the state, believed democracy to be unattainable anywhere in the world before the proletariat seized power.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">154–155</arg></template><space/>According to Marxist theory, the state is a vehicle for oppression and is headed by a ruling class.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">154–155</arg></template><space/>He believed that by his time, the only viable solution was dictatorship since the war was heading into a final conflict between the &quot;progressive forces of socialism and the degenerate forces of capitalism&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">155</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>Russian Revolution of 1917</target><part>Russian Revolution</part></link><space/>was by 1917, already a failure according to its original aim, which was to act as an inspiration for a world revolution.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">155</arg></template><space/>The initial anti-statist posture and the active campaigning for<space/><link><target>direct democracy</target></link><space/>was replaced because of Russia's level of development with<template><target>mdash</target></template>according to their own assessments<template><target>mdash</target></template><space/>dictatorship.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">155</arg></template><space/>The reasoning was Russia's lack of development, its status as the sole socialist state in the world, its encirclement by imperialist powers and its internal encirclement by the peasantry.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">156</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Marx and Lenin did not care if a bourgeois state was ruled in accordance with a<space/><link><target>republic</target><trail>an</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Parliamentary democracy</target><part>parliamentary</part></link><space/>or a<space/><link><target>Constitutional monarchy</target><part>constitutional monarchical</part></link><space/>system since this did not change the overall situation.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">155–156</arg></template><space/>These systems, even if they were ruled by a small clique or ruled through mass participation, were all dictatorships of the bourgeoisie who implemented policies in defence of capitalism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">157–158</arg></template><space/>However, there was a difference; after<space/><link><target>revolutions of 191723</target><part>the failures of the world revolutions</part></link>, Lenin argued that this did not necessarily have to change under the dictatorship of the proletariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">158</arg></template><space/>The reasoning came from practical considerations; the majority of the country's inhabitants were not communists, neither could the Party reintroduce parliamentary democracy because that was not in synchronization with its ideology and would lead to the Party losing power.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">158</arg></template><space/>He therefore concluded that the form of government has nothing do to with the nature of the dictatorship of the proletariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">158</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Bukharin and Trotsky agreed with Lenin; both said that the revolution had destroyed the old but had failed to create anything new.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">158–159</arg></template><space/>Lenin had now concluded that the dictatorship of the proletariat would not alter the relationship of power between men, but would rather &quot;transform their productive relations so that, in the long run, the realm of necessity could be overcome and, with that, genuine social freedom realized&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template><space/>From 1920 to 1921, Soviet leaders and ideologists began differentiating between socialism and communism; hitherto the two terms had been used interchangeably and used to explain the same things.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template><space/>From then, the two terms had different meanings; Russia was in transition from capitalism to socialism<template><target>mdash</target></template>referred to interchangeably under Lenin as the dictatorship of the proletariat, socialism was the intermediate stage to communism and communism was considered the last stage of social development.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template><space/>By now, the party leaders believed that because of Russia's backward state, universal mass participation and true democracy could only take form in the last stage.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em</arg><arg name="align">left</arg><arg name="bgcolor">ivory</arg><arg name="quote">"[Because] the proletariat is still so divided, so degraded, so corrupted in parts ... that an organization taking in the whole proletariat cannot directly exercise proletarian dictatorship. It can be exercised only by a vanguard that has absorbed the revolutionary energy of the class."</arg><arg name="source">—Lenin, explaining why the regime had become increasingly dictatorial.{{sfn|Harding|1996|p</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In early Bolshevik discourse, the term &quot;dictatorship of the proletariat&quot; was of little significance and the few times it was mentioned it was likened to the form of government which had existed in the<space/><link><target>Paris Commune</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template><space/>However, with the ensuing Russian Civil War and the social and material devastation that followed, its meaning altered from commune-type democracy to rule by iron-discipline.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">160</arg></template><space/>By now, Lenin had concluded that only a proletarian regime as oppressive as its opponents could survive in this world.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">160–161</arg></template><space/>The powers previously bestowed upon the Soviets were now given to the Council of People's Commissars, the central government, which was in turn to be governed by &quot;an army of steeled revolutionary Communists [by Communists he referred to the Party]&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">161</arg></template><space/>In a letter to<space/><link><target>Gavril Myasnikov</target></link><space/>in late 1920, Lenin explained his new interpretation of the term &quot;dictatorship of the proletariat&quot;:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">162</arg></template><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;Dictatorship means nothing more nor less than authority untrammelled by any laws, absolutely unrestricted by any rules whatever, and based directly on force. The term 'dictatorship'<space/><italics>has no other meaning but this</italics>.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">162</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lenin justified these policies by claiming that all states were class states by nature and that these states were maintained through<space/><link><target>class struggle</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">162</arg></template><space/>This meant that the dictatorship of the proletariat in the Soviet Union could only be &quot;won and maintained by the use of violence against the bourgeoisie&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">162</arg></template><space/>The main problem with this analysis is that the Party came to view anyone opposing or holding alternate views of the party as bourgeois.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">162</arg></template><space/>Its worst enemy remained the moderates, which were considered to be &quot;the real agents of the bourgeoisie in the working class movement, the labour lieutenants of the capitalist class&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">162–163</arg></template><space/>The term &quot;bourgeoisie&quot; became synonymous with &quot;opponent&quot; and with people who disagreed with the Party in general.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">163</arg></template><space/>These oppressive measures led to another reinterpretation of the dictatorship of the proletariat and socialism in general; it was now defined as a purely economic system.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">165</arg></template><space/>Slogans and theoretical works about democratic mass participation and collective decision-making were now replaced with texts which supported authoritarian management.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">165</arg></template><space/>Considering the situation, the Party believed it had to use the same powers as the bourgeoisie to transform Russia; there was no alternative.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">165–166</arg></template><space/>Lenin began arguing that the proletariat, like the bourgeoisie, did not have a single preference for a form of government and because of that, dictatorship was acceptable to both the Party and the proletariat.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">166</arg></template><space/>In a meeting with Party officials, Lenin stated<template><target>mdash</target></template>in line with his economist view of socialism<template><target>mdash</target></template>that &quot;Industry is indispensable, democracy is not&quot;, further arguing that &quot;we [the Party] do not promise any democracy or any freedom&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Harding</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">166</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Imperialism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Imperialism</arg></template><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em</arg><arg name="align">right</arg><arg name="bgcolor">ivory</arg><arg name="quote">"Imperialism is capitalism at stage of development at which the dominance of monopolies and finance capital is established; in which the export of capital has acquired pronounced importance; in which the division of the world among the international trusts as begun; in which divisions of all territories of the globe among the biggest capitalist powers has been completed."</arg><arg name="source">—Lenin, citing the main features of capitalism in the age of imperialism in ''Imperialism: the Highest Stage of Capitalism''.{{sfn|McDonough|1995|p</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Marxist theory on imperialism was conceived by Lenin in his book,<space/><italics><link><target>Imperialism: the Highest Stage of Capitalism</target></link></italics><space/>(published in 1917).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">339</arg></template><space/>It was written in response to the theoretical crisis within Marxist thought, which occurred due to capitalism's recovery in the 19th century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">339</arg></template><space/>According to Lenin, imperialism was a specific stage of development of capitalism; a stage he referred to as<space/><link><target>state monopoly capitalism</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">339</arg></template><space/>The Marxist movement was split on how to solve capitalism's resurgence after the great depression of the late 19th century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="pp">344–347</arg></template><space/><link><target>Eduard Bernstein</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Social Democratic Party of Germany</target></link><space/>(SDP) considered capitalism's revitalization as proof that it was evolving into a more humane system, adding that the basic aims of socialists were not to overthrow the state but to take power through elections.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="pp">344–347</arg></template><space/><link><target>Karl Kautsky</target></link>, also from the SDP, held a highly dogmatic view; he said that there was no crisis within Marxist theory.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="pp">344–347</arg></template><space/>Both of them denied or belittled the role of class contradictions in society after the crisis.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="pp">344–347</arg></template><space/>In contrast, Lenin believed that the resurgence was the beginning of a new phase of capitalism; this stage was created because of a strengthening of class contradiction, not because of its reduction.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="pp">344–347</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lenin did not know when the imperialist stage of capitalism began; he said it would be foolish too look for a specific year, however said it began at the beginning of the 20th century (at least in Europe).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">352</arg></template><space/>Lenin believed that the economic crisis of 1900 accelerated and intensified the concentration of industry and banking, which led to the transformation of the finance capital connection to industry into the monopoly of large banks.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">353</arg></template><space/>In<space/><italics>Imperialism: the Highest Stage of Capitalism</italics>, Lenin wrote; &quot;the twentieth century marks the turning point from the old capitalism to the new, from the domination of capital in general to the domination of finance capital&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">353</arg></template><space/>Lenin defines imperialism as the monopoly stage of capitalism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McDonough</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">354</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Peaceful coexistence</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Peaceful coexistence</arg></template><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em</arg><arg name="align">right</arg><arg name="bgcolor">ivory</arg><arg name="quote">"The loss by imperialism of its dominating role in world affairs and the utmost expansion of the sphere in which the laws of socialist foreign policy operate are a distinctive feature of the present stage of social development. The main direction of this development is toward even greater changes in the correlation of forces in the world arena in favour of socialism."</arg><arg name="source">—[[Nikolay Inozemtsev]], a Soviet foreign policy analyst, referring to series of events (which he believed) would lead to the ultimate victory of socialism.{{sfn|Evans|2003|p</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Peaceful coexistence&quot; was an ideological concept introduced under Khrushchev's rule.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template><space/>While the concept has been interpreted by fellow communists as proposing an end to the conflict between the systems of capitalism and socialism, Khrushchev saw it as a continuation of the conflict in every area except in the military field.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="pp">71–72</arg></template><space/>The concept said that the two systems were developed &quot;by way of diametrically opposed laws&quot;, which led to &quot;opposite principles in foreign policy&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Peaceful coexistence was steeped in Leninist and Stalinist thought.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Lenin believed that international politics were dominated by class struggle; in the 1940s Stalin stressed the growing polarization which was occurring in the capitalist and socialist systems.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev's peaceful coexistence was based on practical changes which had occurred; he accused the old &quot;two camp&quot; theory of neglecting the<space/><link><target>non-aligned movement</target></link><space/>and the national<space/><link><target>liberation movement</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev considered these &quot;grey areas&quot;, in which the conflict between capitalism and socialism would be fought.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>He still stressed that the main contradiction in international relations were those of capitalism and socialism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>The Soviet Government under Khrushchev stressed the importance of peaceful coexistence, saying that it had to form the basis of Soviet foreign policy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Failure to do, they believed, would lead to nuclear conflict.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Despite this, Soviet theorists still considered peaceful coexistence to be a continuation of the class struggle between the capitalist and socialist worlds, but not based on armed conflict.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>Khrushchev believed that the conflict, in its current phase, was mainly economical.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The emphasis on peaceful coexistence did not mean that the Soviet Union accepted a static world with clear lines.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>It continued to uphold the creed that socialism was inevitable and they sincerely believed that the world had reached a stage in which the &quot;correlations of forces&quot; were moving towards socialism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>With the establishment of socialist regimes in Eastern Europe and Asia, Soviet foreign policy planners believed that capitalism had lost its dominance as an economic system.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Socialism in One Country</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Socialism in One Country</arg></template><link><target>File:Stalin-Bukharin.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>The concept was developed by Bukharin and Stalin</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The concept of &quot;Socialism in One Country&quot; was conceived by Stalin in his struggle against Leon Trotsky and his concept of<space/><link><target>permanent revolution</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">126</arg></template><space/>In 1924, Trotsky published his pamphlet<space/><italics><link><target>Lessons of October</target></link></italics>, in which he stated that socialism in the Soviet Union would fail because of the backward state of economic development unless a world revolution began.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">126</arg></template><space/>Stalin responded to Trotsky's pamphlet with his article, &quot;<link><target>October and Comrade Trotsky's Theory of Permanent Revolution</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>In it, Stalin stated that he did not believe an inevitable conflict between the working class and the peasants would take place, and that &quot;socialism in one country is completely possible and probable&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>Stalin held the view common among most Bolsheviks at the time; there was a possibility of real success for socialism in the Soviet Union despite the country's backwardness and international isolation.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>While<space/><link><target>Grigoriy Zinoviev</target></link>, Lev Kamenev and<space/><link><target>Nikolai Bukharin</target></link><template><target>mdash</target></template>together with Stalin<template><target>mdash</target></template>opposed Trotsky's theory of permanent revolution, their views on the way socialism could be built diverged.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>According to Bukharin, Zinoviev and Kamenev supported the resolution of the<space/><link><target>14th Conference of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks)</target><part>14th Conference</part></link><space/>held in 1925, which stated that &quot;we cannot complete the building of socialism due to our technological backwardness&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>Despite this cynical attitude, Zinoviev and Kamenev believed that a defective form of socialism could be constructed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>At the 14th Conference, Stalin reiterated his position that socialism in one country was feasible despite the capitalist blockade of the Soviet Union.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">128</arg></template><space/>After the conference, Stalin wrote &quot;<link><target>Concerning the Results of the XIV Conference of the RCP(b)</target></link>&quot;, in which he stated that the peasantry would not turn against the socialist system because they had a self-interest in preserving it.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">128</arg></template><space/>Stalin said the contradictions which arose within the peasantry during the socialist transition could &quot;be overcome by our own efforts&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">128</arg></template><space/>He concluded that the only viable threat to socialism in the Soviet Union was a military intervention.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In late 1925, Stalin received a letter from a Party official which stated that his position of &quot;Socialism in One Country&quot; was in contradiction with<space/><link><target>Friedrich Engels</target></link>' writings on the subject.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template><space/>Stalin countered that Engels' writings reflected &quot;the era of pre-monopoly capitalism, the pre-imperialist era when there were not yet the conditions of an uneven, abrupt development of the capitalist countries&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template><space/>From 1925, Bukharin began writing extensively on the subject and in 1926, Stalin wrote<space/><italics><link><target>On Questions of Leninism</target></link></italics>, which contains his best-known writings on the subject.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template><space/>With the publishing of<space/><italics><link><target>Leninism (book)</target><part>Leninism</part></link></italics>, Trotsky began countering Bukharin's and Stalin's arguments, writing that socialism in one country was only possible only in the short term, and said that without a world revolution it would be impossible to safeguard the Soviet Union from the &quot;restoration of bourgeois relations&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template><space/>Zinoviev disagreed with Trotsky and Bukharin, and Stalin; he maintained Lenin's position from 1917 to 1922 and continued to say that only a defective form of socialism could be constructed in the Soviet Union without a world revolution.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">129–130</arg></template><space/>Bukharin began arguing for the creation of an<space/><link><target>autarkic</target></link><space/>economic model, while Trotsky said that the Soviet Union had to participate in the<space/><link><target>international division of labour</target></link><space/>to develop.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">130</arg></template><space/>In contrast to Trotsky and Bukharin, in 1938, Stalin said that a world revolution was impossible and that Engels was wrong on the matter.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">133</arg></template><space/>At the 18th Congress, Stalin took the theory to its inevitable conclusion, saying that the communist mode of production could be conceived in one country.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">133</arg></template><space/>He rationalized this by saying that the state could exist in a communist society as long as the Soviet Union was encircled by capitalism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">133</arg></template><space/>However, with the establishment of socialist regimes in Eastern Europe, Stalin said that socialism in one country was only possible in a large country like the Soviet Union and that to survive, the other states had to follow the Soviet line.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>van Ree</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">134–135</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reasons for demise</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Dissolution of the Soviet Union</arg><arg>Predictions of the dissolution of the Soviet Union</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Western view</heading><paragraph>There were few, in any, who believed that the Soviet Union was on the verge of collapse by 1985.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.foreignpolicy.com/articles/2011/06/20/everything_you_think_you_know_about_the_collapse_of_the_soviet_union_is_wrong<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Everything You Think You Know About the Collapse of the Soviet Union Is Wrong<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>20 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>4 April 2014<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>[[Foreign Policy]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Aron, Leon</arg></template></extension><space/>The economy was stagnating, but stable enough for the Soviet Union to continue into the 21st century. The political situation was calm because of twenty years of systematic repression against any threat to the country and one-party rule, and the USSR was in its peak of influence in world affairs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP"></extension><space/>The immediate causes for the Soviet Union's dissolution were the policies and thoughts of Mikhail Gorbachev, the CPSU General Secretary.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP"></extension><space/>His policies of<space/><italics>perestroika</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>glasnost</italics><space/>tried to revitalize the Soviet economy and the social and political culture of the country.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP"></extension><space/>Throughout his rule, he put more emphasis on democratizing the Soviet Union because he believed it had the lost its moral legitimacy to rule.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP"></extension><space/>These policies led to the collapse of the communist regimes in Eastern Europe and indirectly destabilized Gorbachev's and the CPSU's control over the Soviet Union.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/coldwar/soviet_end_01.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Reform, Coup and Collapse: The End of the Soviet State<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 February 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>4 April 2014<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[British Broadcasting Corporation]]. [[BBC Online]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Archie Brown|Brown, Archie]]<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Archie Brown said:<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>The expectations of, again most notably, Lithuanians, Estonians and Latvians were enormously enhanced by what they saw happening in the 'outer empire' [Eastern Europe] and they began to believe that they could remove themselves from the 'inner empire'. In truth, a democratised Soviet Union was incompatible with denial of the Baltic states' independence for, to the extent that those Soviet republics became democratic, their opposition to remaining in a political entity whose centre was Moscow would become increasingly evident. Yet, it was not preordained that the entire Soviet Union would break up.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, Brown said that the system did not need to collapse or to do so in the way it did.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension><space/>The democratization from above weakened the Party's control over the country, and put it on the defensive.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension><space/>Brown added that a different leader then Gorbachev would probably have oppressed the opposition and continued with economic reform.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension><space/>Nonetheless, Gorbachev accepted that the people sought a different road and consented to the Soviet Union's dissolution in 1991.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension><space/>He said that because of its peaceful collapse, the fall of Soviet communism is &quot;one of the great success stories of 20th century politics&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"></extension><space/>According to Lars T. Lih, the Soviet Union collapsed because people stopped believing in its ideology. He wrote:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lih</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">731</arg></template><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;When in 1991 the Soviet Union collapsed not with a bang but a whimper, this unexpected outcome was partly the result of the previous disenchantments of the narrative of class leadership. The Soviet Union had always been based on fervent belief in this narrative in its various permutations. When the binding power of the narrative dissolved, the Soviet Union itself dissolved.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lih</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">731</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>According to the Communist Party of China</heading><paragraph>The first research into the collapse of the Soviet Union and the Eastern Bloc were very simple and did not take into account several factors.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">49–51</arg></template><space/>However, these examinations became more advanced by the 1990s and unlike most Western scholarship, which focuses on the role of Gorbachev and his reform efforts, the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of China</target></link><space/>(CPC) examined &quot;core (political) life and death issues&quot; so that it could learn from them and not make the same mistakes.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">51–52</arg></template><space/>Following the CPSU's demise and the Soviet Union's collapse, the CPC's analysis began examining systematic causes.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">60</arg></template><space/>Several leading CPC officials began hailing Khrushchev's rule, saying that he was the first reformer, and that if he had continued after 1964, the Soviet Union would not have witnessed the<space/><link><target>Era of Stagnation</target></link><space/>began under Brezhnev and continued under Yuri Andropov and Konstantin Chernenko.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">60–61</arg></template><space/>The main economic failure was that the political leadership did not pursue any reforms to tackle the economic malaise that had taken hold, dismissing certain techniques as capitalist, and never disentangling the planned economy from socialism.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">64</arg></template><space/><link><target>Xu Zhixin</target></link><space/>from the CASS<space/><link><target>Institute of Eastern Europe, Russia, and Central Asia of the Chinese Academy of Social Science</target><part>Institute of Eastern Europe, Russia, and Central Asia</part></link>, argued that Soviet planners laid too much emphasis on heavy industry, which led to shortages of consumer goods. Unlike his counterparts, Xu argued that the shortages of consumer goods was not an error but &quot;was a consciously planned feature of the system&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">64</arg></template><space/>Other CPSU failures were pursing the policy of state socialism, the high spending on the military-industrial complex, a low tax base and the subsidizing of the economy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">64</arg></template><space/>The CPC argued that when Gorbachev came to power and introduced his economic reforms, they were &quot;to little, too late, and too fast&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">63 & 65</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em</arg><arg name="align">right</arg><arg name="bgcolor">ivory</arg><arg name="quote">"In my opinion, the fundamental cause of the drastic changes in the Soviet Union and East European countries at the end of the 1980s and beginning of the 1990s was the loss of dynamism of the Stalin–Soviet Socialist Model ... The demerits of this model were institutional and fundamental—not a single reform after Stalin's death brought fundamental changes to the Stalin–Soviet Socialist Model. This model, with its problems and contradictions accumulating by day, was finally in crisis, and the people of the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe lost their confidence in it. The [only] way out was to abandon the Stalin–Soviet Socialist Model and seek another road for social development."</arg><arg name="source">—[[Lu Nanqun]], a Sovietologist from CASS''.{{sfn|Shambaugh|2013|p</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While most CPC researchers criticize the CPSU's economic policies, many have criticized what they see as &quot;Soviet totalitarianism&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>They accuse Joseph Stalin of creating a system of mass terror, intimidation, annulling the democracy component of democratic centralism and emphasizing<space/><link><target>centralism</target></link>, which led to the creation of an inner-party dictatorship.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>Other points were Russian nationalism, a lack of separation between the Party and state bureaucracies, suppression of non-Russian ethnicities, distortion of the economy through the introduction of over-centralization and the collectivization of agriculture.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template><space/>According to CPC researcher<space/><link><target>Xiao Guisen</target></link>, Stalin's policies led to &quot;stunted economic growth, tight surveillance of society, a lack of democracy in decision-making, an absence of the rule of law, the burden of bureaucracy, the CPSU's alienation from people's concerns, and an accumulation of ethnic tensions&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">65–66</arg></template><space/>Stalin's effect on ideology was also criticized; several researchers accused his policies of being &quot;leftist&quot;, &quot;dogmatist&quot; and a deviation &quot;from true<space/><link><target>MarxismLeninism</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>He is criticized for initiating the &quot;bastardization of Leninism&quot;, of deviating from true democratic centralism by establishing one-man rule and destroying all inner-party consultation, of misinterpreting Lenin's theory of imperialism and of supporting foreign revolutionary movements only when the Soviet Union could get something out of it.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/><link><target>Yu Sui</target></link>, a CPC theoretician, said that &quot;the collapse of the Soviet Union and CPSU is a punishment for its past wrongs!&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>Similarly, Brezhnev, Mikhail Suslov, Alexei Kosygin and Konstantin Chernenko have been criticized for being &quot;dogmatic, ossified, inflexible, [for having a] bureaucratic ideology and thinking&quot;, while Yuri Andropov is depicted by some of having the potential of becoming a new Khrushchev if he had not died early.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While the CPC concur with Gorbachev's assessment that the CPSU needed internal reform, they do not agree on how it was implemented, criticizing his idea of &quot;humanistic and democratic socialism&quot;, of negating the leading role of the CPSU, of negating Marxism, of negating the analysis of class contradictions and class struggle, and of negating the &quot;ultimate socialist goal of realizing communism&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">67–69</arg></template><space/>Unlike the other Soviet leaders, Gorbachev is criticized for pursuing the wrong reformist policies and for being too flexible and too rightist.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">67–69</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>Organization Department of the Communist Party of China</target><part>CPC Organization Department</part></link><space/>said, &quot;What Gorbachev in fact did was not to transform the CPSU by correct principlesindeed the Soviet Communist Party<space/><italics>needed transformation</italics>but instead he, step-by-step, and ultimately, eroded the ruling party's dominance in ideological, political and organizational aspects&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">67–69</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The CPSU was also criticized for not taking enough care in building the primary party organization and not having inner-party democracy.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template><space/>Others, more radically, concur with<space/><link><target>Milovan ilas</target></link><space/>assessment, saying that a new class was established within the central party leadership of the CPSU and that a &quot;corrupt and privileged class&quot; had developed because of the nomenklatura system.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template><space/>Other criticized the special privileges bestowed on the CPSU elite, the nomenklatura system<template><target>mdash</target></template>which some said had decayed continuously since Stalin's rule<template><target>mdash</target></template>and the relationship between the Soviet military and the CPSU. Unlike in China, the Soviet military was a state institution whereas in China it is a Party institution.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template><space/>The CPC criticizes the CPSU of pursing<space/><link><target>Soviet imperialism</target></link><space/>in its foreign policies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Shambaugh</arg><arg name="pp">74–75</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="group">note</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Articles and journal entries</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">McDonough<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Terrence<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lenin, Imperialism, and the Stages of Capitalist Development<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Science & Society]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">59</arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">339–367<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Guilford Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi"></arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org/stable/40403507<space/></arg><arg name="ref">CITEREFMcDonough1995<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Books</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Archie Brown|Brown, Archie]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Gorbachev Factor<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFBrown1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Oxford University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0192880527</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Archie Brown|Brown, Archie]]<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Gorbachev Era<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[Ronald Grigor Suny|Suny, Ronald Grigor]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cambridge History of Russia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFBrown2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521811449</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Eaton, Katherine Bliss<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Daily Life in the Soviet Union<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFEaton2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Greenwood Publishing Group]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0313316287</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Eisen, Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFFainsodHough1979<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Glasnost Reader<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[University of Michigan]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0453006957<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Evans, Alfred<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFEvans1993<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Marxism–Leninism: The Decline of an Ideology<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[ABC-CLIO]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1993<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0275947637<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Merle Fainsod|Fainsod, Merle]]; [[Jerry F. Hough|Hough, Jerry F.]]<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFFainsodHough1979<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How the Soviet Union is Governed<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Harvard University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0674410300<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1979<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Gill, Graeme<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Origins of the Stalinist Political System<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0674410300<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFGill2002<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Hanson, Stephen<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Brezhnev Era<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[Ronald Grigor Suny|Suny, Ronald Grigor]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cambridge History of Russia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFHanson2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521811449</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Harding, Neil<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Leninism<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFHarding1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Macmillan Publishers]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0333664825</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Harris, Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Subverting the System: Gorbachev's Reform of the Party's Apparat 1986–1991<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFHarris2005<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Rowman & Littlefield]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>074252678X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Kenez, Peter<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Birth of the Propaganda State: Soviet Methods of Mass Mobilization, 1917–1929<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521313988<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFKenez1985<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Lenoe, Matthew Edward<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Closer to the Masses: Stalinist Culture, Social Revolution, and Soviet Newspapers<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Harvard University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0674013190<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFLenoe2004<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Lih, Lars T.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Soviet Union and the road to communism<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[Ronald Grigor Suny|Suny, Ronald Grigor]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cambridge History of Russia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFTaubman2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521811449</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Lowenhardt, John; van Ree, Erik; Ozinga, James<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Rise and Fall of the Soviet Politburo<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFLowenhardtvanReeOzinga1992<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[St Martin's Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0312047843</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Matthews, Marvyn<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Education in the Soviet Union: Policies and Institutions since Stalin<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Routledge]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0043701140<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFMatthews1983<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Richard Sakwa|Sakwa, Richard]]<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSakwa1990<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet politics: an Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Routledge]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>041500506X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Richard Sakwa|Sakwa, Richard]]<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSakwa1998<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet politics in Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Routledge]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0415071534</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[David Shambaugh|Shambaugh, David]]<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFShambaugh2008<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>China's Communist Party: Atrophy and Adaptation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[University of California Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0520254929<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Politics: Continuity and Contradictions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0312007957<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[St. Martin’s Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Smith, Gordon<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSmith1988<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Politics: Continuity and Contradictions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0333535766<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[St. Martin’s Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Smith, Gordon<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSmith1991<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>2nd<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[Ronald Grigor Suny|Suny, Ronald Grigor]]<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Chronology/Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>Suny, Ronald Grigor<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cambridge History of Russia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFBrown2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521811449</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Swain, Geoff<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Trotsky<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Pearson Education]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0582771900<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSwain2006<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Party Statutes of the Communist World<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9024729750<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[BRILL Publishers]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Williams, Simons<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFSimons1984<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>[[William Taubman|Taubman, William]]<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Khrushchev Era<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[Ronald Grigor Suny|Suny, Ronald Grigor]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cambridge History of Russia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFTaubman2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0521811449</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Twenty-fifth Congress of the CPSU: Assessment and Context<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1977<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0817968431<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Stanford University]]. [[Hoover Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Zimmerman, William<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>Dallin, Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>CITEREFZimmerman1977<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>commons category-inline</target><arg>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archontology.org/nations/ussr/cpsu'>Executive Bodies of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (19171991)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.xs4all.nl/~eurodos/docu/cpsu-texts/cpsu86-0.htm'>Program of the CPSU, 27th Party Congress (1986)</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></template><template><target>Soviet Union topics</target></template><template><target>Eastern Bloc parties</target></template><template><target>Leaders of the Ruling Parties of the Eastern Bloc</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Communist Party Of The Soviet Union</target></template><link><target>Category:Political parties disestablished in 1991</target></link><link><target>Category:Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Parties of single-party systems</target></link><link><target>Category:Political parties established in 1912</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet internal politics</target></link><link><target>Category:Eastern Bloc</target></link><link><target>Category:1912 establishments in Russia</target></link><link><target>Category:Communist parties in the Soviet Union</target></link><link><target>Category:Ruling Communist parties</target></link></paragraph></article>