<article title='Ceawlin_of_Wessex'><paragraph><template><target>featured article</target></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="name"><space/>Ceawlin
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Ceawlin name.gif
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Ceawlin's name as it appears in the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', as Ceaulin
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[King of Wessex]]<br/>[[Bretwalda]] of southern Britain
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>560–592
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Cynric of Wessex|Cynric]]
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Ceol of Wessex|Ceol]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>593
</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[House of Wessex]]
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Cynric of Wessex]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>Cutha (possibly)<space/><br><space/>[[Cuthwine]]
</arg></template><bold>Ceawlin</bold><space/>(also spelled<space/><bold>Ceaulin</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>Caelin</bold>, died<space/><italics>ca.</italics><space/>593) was a<space/><link><target>King of Wessex</target></link>. He may have been the son of<space/><link><target>Cynric of Wessex</target></link><space/>and the grandson of<space/><link><target>Cerdic of Wessex</target></link>, whom the<space/><italics><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</target></link></italics><space/>represents as the leader of the first group of<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link><space/>to come to the land which later became<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link>. Ceawlin was active during the last years of the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxons</target><part>Anglo-Saxon</part></link><space/>invasion, with little of southern England remaining in the control of the native<space/><link><target>Britons (historic)</target><part>Britons</part></link><space/>by the time of his death.</paragraph><paragraph>The chronology of Ceawlin's life is highly uncertain. The historical accuracy and dating of many of the events in the later<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>have been called into question, and his reign is variously listed as lasting seven, seventeen, or thirty-two years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stenton, p. 29, accepts the date given for Ceawlin's accession in the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>of 560, but Barbara Yorke in her online DNB article on Ceawlin states that his reign seems to have been deliberately lengthened.</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>records several battles of Ceawlin's between the years 556 and 592, including the first record of a battle between different groups of Anglo-Saxons, and indicates that under Ceawlin Wessex acquired significant territory, some of which was later to be lost to other<space/><link><target>Heptarchy</target><part>Anglo-Saxon kingdoms</part></link>. Ceawlin is also named as one of the eight &quot;<italics><link><target>bretwalda</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics>&quot;, a title given in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>to eight rulers who had overlordship over southern Britain, although the extent of Ceawlin's control is not known.</paragraph><paragraph>Ceawlin died in 593, having been deposed the year before, possibly by his successor,<space/><link><target>Ceol of Wessex</target><part>Ceol</part></link>. He is recorded in various sources as having two sons, Cutha and<space/><link><target>Cuthwine</target></link>, but the genealogies in which this information is found are known to be unreliable.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical context</heading><paragraph>The history of the<space/><link><target>sub-Roman Britain</target><part>sub-Roman period in Britain</part></link><space/>is poorly sourced and the subject of a number of important disagreements among historians. It appears, however, that in the fifth century raids on Britain by continental peoples developed into migrations. The newcomers included<space/><link><target>Angles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Frisii</target><part>Frisians</part></link>. These peoples captured territory in the east and south of England, but at about the end of the fifth century, a British victory at the battle of<space/><link><target>Mons Badonicus</target></link><space/>halted the Anglo-Saxon advance for fifty years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_13">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction to Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 1316.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_23">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 23.</extension><space/>Near the year 550, however, the British began to lose ground once more, and within twenty-five years, it appears that control of almost all of southern England was in the hands of the invaders.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_RBaEE_204">Hunter Blair (<italics>Roman Britain</italics>, p. 204) gives the twenty-five years from 550 to 575 as the dates of the final conquest.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The peace following the battle of Mons Badonicus is attested partly by<space/><link><target>Gildas</target></link>, a monk, who wrote<space/><italics><link><target>De Excidio et Conquestu Britanniae</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics>On the Ruin and Conquest of Britain</italics><space/>during the middle of the sixth century. This essay is a polemic against corruption and Gildas provides little in the way of names and dates. He appears, however, to state that peace had lasted from the year of his birth to the time he was writing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_2">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 27.</extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</target></link></italics><space/>is the other main source that bears on this period, in particular in an entry for the year 827 that records a list of the kings who bore the title &quot;<italics><link><target>bretwalda</target></link></italics>&quot;, or &quot;Britain-ruler&quot;. That list shows a gap in the early sixth century that matches Gildas's version of events.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_60">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 6061</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ceawlin's reign belongs to the period of Anglo-Saxon expansion at the end of the sixth century. Though there are many unanswered questions about the chronology and activities of the early West Saxon rulers, it is clear that Ceawlin was one of the key figures in the final Anglo-Saxon conquest of southern Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_30">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 30.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early West Saxon sources</heading><paragraph>The two main written sources for early West Saxon history are the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>and the West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List. The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>is a set of annals which were compiled near the year 890, during the reign of King<space/><link><target>Alfred the Great</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="KL_41">Keynes and Lapidge,<space/><italics>Alfred the Great</italics>, p. 41.</extension><space/>They record earlier material for the older entries, which were assembled from earlier annals that no longer survive, as well as, from saga material that might have been transmitted orally.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_xix">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, p. xix</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_132">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 132.</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>dates the arrival of the future &quot;West Saxons&quot; in Britain to 495, when<space/><link><target>Cerdic</target></link><space/>and his son,<space/><link><target>Cynric</target></link>, land at<space/><italics>Cerdices ora</italics>, or Cerdic's shore. Almost twenty annals describing Cerdic's campaigns, and those of his descendants appear interspersed through the next hundred years of entries in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_50">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 5051.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 1421</extension><space/>Although these annals provide most of what is known about Ceawlin, the historicity of many of the entries is uncertain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_55">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 55</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List is a list of rulers of Wessex, including the lengths of their reigns. It survives in several forms, including as a preface to the [B] manuscript of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_xxiii">The Regnal List is now separated from the main body of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, and as result the manuscripts are recorded separately in the<space/><link><target>British Library</target></link>, as MS<space/><link><target>Cotton Tiberius</target></link><space/>Aii, f. 178 (for the Regnal List), and MS Cotton Tiberius Avi, ff. 134 (the [B] manuscript of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>). See Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, p. xxii. See also Lapidge,<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 388.</extension><space/>As with<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, the list was compiled during the reign of Alfred the Great, and both the list and the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>are influenced by the desire of their writers to use a single line of descent to trace the lineage of the Kings of Wessex through Cerdic to<space/><link><target>Gewis</target></link>, a descendant of<space/><link><target>Woden</target></link><space/>and the legendary ancestor of the West Saxons. The result served the political purposes of the scribe, but is riddled with contradictions for historians.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_49">D.P. Kirby (<italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 49) refers to the combination of the Chronicle and the Regnal List as a &quot;<link><target>political fiction</target></link>&quot;.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The contradictions may be seen clearly by calculating dates by different methods from the various sources. The first event in West Saxon history, the date of which can be regarded as reasonably certain, is the baptism of<space/><link><target>Cynegils</target></link>, which occurred in the late 630s, perhaps as late as 640. The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>dates Cerdic's arrival to 495, but adding up the lengths of the reigns as given in the West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List, leads to the conclusion that Cerdic's reign might have started in 532, a difference of 37 years. Neither 495 nor 532 may be treated as reliable, however, the latter date relies on the presumption that the Regnal List is correct in presenting the Kings of Wessex as having succeeded one another, with no omitted kings, no<space/><link><target>Joint monarchs</target><part>joint kingship</part><trail>s</trail></link>, and that the durations of the reigns are correct as given. None of these presumptions may be made safely.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_50"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The sources also are inconsistent on the length of Ceawlin's reign. The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>gives it as thirty-two years, from 560 to 592, but the Regnal Lists disagree: different versions give it as seven or seventeen years. A recent detailed study of the Regnal List dates the arrival of the West Saxons in England to 538, and favours seven years as the most likely length of Ceawlin's reign, with dates of 581588 proposed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_50"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_133">D.N. Dumville, &quot;The West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List and the chronology of Wessex&quot;, 1985, cited in Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 133.</extension><space/>The sources do agree that Ceawlin is the son of Cynric and he usually is named as the father of Cuthwine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_GT">See the &quot;Genealogical Tables&quot; in the appendices to Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>.</extension><space/>There is one discrepancy in this case: the entry for 685 in the [A] version of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>assigns Ceawlin a son, Cutha, but in the 855 entry in the same manuscript, Cutha is listed as the son of Cuthwine. Cutha also is named as Ceawlin's brother in the [E] and [F] versions of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, in the 571 and 568 entries, respectively.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_18">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 1819. For tables showing the variations in the Wessex genealogy, see also figures 3 and 4 in Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 223224.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Whether Ceawlin is a descendant of Cerdic is a matter of debate. Subgroupings of different West Saxon lineages give the impression of separate groups, of which Ceawlin's line is one. Some of the problems in the Wessex genealogies may have come about because of efforts to integrate Ceawlin's line with the other lineages: it was very important to the West Saxons to be able to trace their ancestors back to Cerdic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_142">Yorke (<italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 133) gives this argument in some detail.</extension><space/>Another reason for doubting the literal nature of these early genealogies is that the etymology of the names of several early members of the dynasty do not appear to be Germanic, as would be expected in the names of leaders of an apparently Anglo-Saxon dynasty. The name Ceawlin is one of the names that do not have convincing Anglo-Saxon etymologies; it seems more likely to be of native British origin.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Records of the West Saxon dynasties survive in versions which have been subject to later manipulation, which may make it all the more significant that some of the founding 'Saxon' fathers have British names: Cerdic, Ceawlin, Cenwalh.&quot; in: Hills, C.,<space/><italics>Origins of the English,</italics><space/>Duckworth (2003), p. 105. Also &quot;The names Cerdic, Ceawlin and Caedwalla, all in the genealogy of the West Saxon kings, are apparently British.&quot; in: Ward-Perkins, B.,<space/><italics>Why did the Anglo-Saxons not become more British?</italics><space/><italics>The English Historical Review</italics><space/>115.462 (June 2000): p513.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest sources do not use the term &quot;West Saxon&quot;. According to<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Ecclesiastical History of the English People</target></link></italics>, the term is interchangeable with the<space/><link><target>Gewisse</target></link>, meaning the descendants of Gewis. The term &quot;West Saxon&quot; appears only in the late seventh century, after the reign of<space/><link><target>Cdwalla of Wessex</target><part>Cdwalla</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_48">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 48, 223</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>West Saxon expansion</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Ceawlin map.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A map of places mentioned by the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'' in annals relating to Ceawlin; modern versions of the place names are given here, rather than the Anglo-Saxon names used in the chronicle.</part><part>alt=A map showing places in central southern England, including Gloucester, Cirencester, Bath, and Aylesbury</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Ultimately, the kingdom of Wessex occupied the southwest of England, but the initial stages in this expansion are not apparent from the sources.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_49"></extension><space/>Cerdic's landing, whenever it is to be dated, seems to have been near the<space/><link><target>Isle of Wight</target></link>, and the annals record the conquest of the island in 530. In 534, according to the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, Cerdic died and his son Cynric took the throne; the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>adds that &quot;they gave the Isle of Wight to their nephews, Stuf and Wihtgar&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Note that the name &quot;Wight&quot; is derived from the Romano-British &quot;Vectis', not from &quot;Wihtgar&quot;; see Swanton,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, p. 16.</extension><space/>These records are in direct conflict with<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>, who states that the Isle of Wight was settled by Jutes, not Saxons; the<space/><link><target>archaeological record</target></link><space/>is somewhat in favour of Bede on this.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_22">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 2223.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Subsequent entries in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>give details of some of the battles by which the West Saxons won their kingdom. Ceawlin's campaigns are not given as near the coast. They range along the<space/><link><target>Thames Valley</target><part>Thames valley</part></link><space/>and beyond, as far as<space/><link><target>Surrey</target></link><space/>in the east and the mouth of the<space/><link><target>Severn</target></link><space/>in the west. Ceawlin clearly is part of the West Saxon expansion, but the military history of the period is difficult to understand.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_49"></extension><space/>In what follows the dates are as given in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, although as noted above, these are earlier than now thought accurate.</paragraph><heading level='2'>556: Beran byrg</heading><paragraph>The first record of a battle fought by Ceawlin is in 556, when he and his father, Cynric, fought the native Britons at &quot;Beran byrg&quot;, or Bera's Stronghold. This now is identified as<space/><link><target>Barbury Castle</target></link>, an Iron Age hill fort in Wiltshire, near Swindon. Cynric would have been king of Wessex at this time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_26">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 2628.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>568: Wibbandun</heading><paragraph>The first battle Ceawlin fought as king is dated by the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>to 568, when he and Cutha fought with<space/><link><target>thelberht of Kent</target><part>thelberht</part></link>, the king of Kent. The entry says &quot;Here Ceawlin and Cutha fought against Aethelberht and drove him into Kent; and they killed two<space/><link><target>Ealdorman</target><part>ealdormen</part></link>, Oslaf and Cnebba, on Wibbandun.&quot; The location of &quot;Wibbandun&quot;, which can be translated as &quot;Wibba's Mount&quot;, has not been identified definitely; it was at one time thought to be Wimbledon, but this now is known to be incorrect.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Plummer_2_16">Plummer,<space/><italics>Two Saxon Chronicles</italics>, vol. 2 p. 16</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Hodgkins_188">English Place-Name Society (1926), p. xiv, cited in Hodgkins,<space/><italics>A History</italics>, p. 188 n. 2</extension><space/>This battle is notable as the first recorded conflict between the invading peoples: previous battles recorded in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>are between the Anglo-Saxons and the native Britons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are multiple examples of joint kingship in Anglo-Saxon history, and this may be another: it is not clear what Cutha's relationship to Ceawlin is, but it certainly is possible he was also a king. The annal for 577, below, is another possible example.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_143_2">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, pp. 143144.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>571: Bedcanford</heading><paragraph>The annal for 571 reads: &quot;Here Cuthwulf fought against the Britons at Bedcanford, and took four settlements:<space/><link><target>Limbury</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aylesbury</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Benson, Oxfordshire</target><part>Benson</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eynsham</target></link>; and in the same year he passed away.&quot; Cuthwulf's relationship with Ceawlin is unknown, but the alliteration common to Anglo-Saxon royal families suggests Cuthwulf may be part of the West Saxon royal line. The location of the battle itself is unidentified. It has been suggested that it was<space/><link><target>Bedford</target></link>, but what is known of the early history of Bedford's names, does not support this. This battle is of interest because it is surprising that an area so far east should still be in Briton hands this late: there is ample archaeological evidence of early Saxon and Anglian presence in the Midlands, and historians generally have interpreted Gildas's<space/><italics>De Excidio</italics><space/>as implying that the Britons had lost control of this area by the mid-sixth century. One possible explanation is, that this annal records a reconquest of land that was lost to the Britons in the campaigns ending in the battle of Mons Badonicus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_26"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>577: The lower Severn</heading><paragraph>The annal for 577 reads &quot;Here Cuthwine and Ceawlin fought against the Britons, and they killed three kings, Coinmail and Condidan and Farinmail, in the place which is called<space/><link><target>Dyrham</target></link>, and took three cities:<space/><link><target>Gloucester</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cirencester</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bath, Somerset</target><part>Bath</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_18_2">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 1819</extension><space/>This entry is all that is known of these Briton kings; their names are in an archaic form that makes it very likely that this annal derives from a much older written source. The battle itself has long been regarded as a key moment in the Saxon advance, since in reaching the<space/><link><target>Bristol Channel</target></link>, the West Saxons divided the Britons west of the Severn from land communication with those in the peninsula to the south of the Channel.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_29">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 29.</extension><space/>Wessex almost certainly lost this territory to<space/><link><target>Penda of Mercia</target></link><space/>in 628, when the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>records that &quot;Cynegils and Cwichelm fought against Penda at Cirencester and then came to an agreement.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_45">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 45.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_24">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 2425.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is possible that when Ceawlin and Cuthwine took Bath, they found the Roman baths still operating to some extent.<space/><link><target>Nennius</target></link>, a ninth-century historian, mentions a &quot;Hot Lake&quot; in the land of the<space/><link><target>Hwicce</target></link>, which was along the Severn, and adds &quot;It is surrounded by a wall, made of brick and stone, and men may go there to bathe at any time, and every man can have the kind of bath he likes. If he wants, it will be a cold bath; and if he wants a hot bath, it will be hot&quot;. Bede also describes hot baths in the geographical introduction to the<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics><space/>in terms very similar to those of Nennius.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_40">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, pp. 4041.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Wansdyke (earthwork)</target><part>Wansdyke</part></link>, an early medieval defensive linear earthwork, runs from south of<space/><link><target>Bristol</target></link><space/>to near<space/><link><target>Marlborough, Wiltshire</target></link>, passing not far from Bath. It probably was built in the fifth or sixth centuries, perhaps by Ceawlin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fletcher_25">Fletcher,<space/><italics>Who's Who</italics>, pp. 2526.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>584: Fethan leag</heading><paragraph>Ceawlin's last recorded victory is in 584. The entry reads &quot;Here Ceawlin and Cutha fought against the Britons at the place which is named Fethan leag, and Cutha was killed; and Ceawlin took many towns and countless war-loot, and in anger he turned back to his own [territory].&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension><space/>There is a wood named &quot;Fethele&quot; mentioned in a twelfth-century document that relates to<space/><link><target>Stoke Lyne</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>Oxfordshire</target></link>, and it now is thought that the battle of Fethan leag must have been fought in this area.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_29"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The phrase &quot;in anger he turned back to his own&quot; probably indicates that this annal is drawn from saga material, as perhaps are all of the early Wessex annals.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fletcher_25"></extension><space/>It also has been used to argue that perhaps, Ceawlin did not win the battle and that the chronicler chose not to record the outcome fully a king does not usually come home &quot;in anger&quot; after taking &quot;many towns and countless war-loot&quot;. It may be that Ceawlin's overlordship of the southern Britons came to an end with this battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_30"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bretwaldaship</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Entry_for_827_in_the_Anglo-Saxon_Chronicle,_which_lists_the_eight_bretwaldas.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>350px</part><part>The entry for 827 in the [C] manuscript of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle,'' listing the eight ''bretwaldas'', Ceawlin's name can be seen in the fifth line, spelled &quot;Ceaulin&quot;</part><part>alt=Part of a manuscript page showing eleven lines of lettering in an old style, with a Roman numeral in reddish ink at the start of the first line</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>About 731, Bede, a<space/><link><target>Northumbria</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>monk and chronicler, wrote a work called the<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History of the English People</italics>. The work was not primarily a secular history, but Bede provides much information about the history of the Anglo-Saxons, including a list early in the history of seven kings who, he said, held &quot;imperium&quot; over the other kingdoms south of the<space/><link><target>Humber</target></link>. The usual translation for &quot;imperium&quot; is &quot;overlordship&quot;. Bede names Ceawlin as the second on the list, although he spells it &quot;Caelin&quot;, and adds that he was &quot;known in the speech of his own people as Ceaulin&quot;. Bede also makes it clear that Ceawlin was not a ChristianBede mentions a later king, thelberht of Kent, as &quot;the first to enter the kingdom of heaven&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_111">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, II 5, quoted from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 111</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle,</italics><space/>in an entry for the year 827, repeats Bede's list, adds<space/><link><target>Egbert of Wessex</target></link>, and also mentions that they were known as &quot;bretwalda&quot;, or &quot;Britain-ruler&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_60"></extension><space/>A great deal of scholarly attention has been given to the meaning of this word. It has been described as a term &quot;of encomiastic poetry&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_34">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 3435.</extension><space/>but there also is evidence that it implied a definite role of military leadership.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_17">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 17.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bede says that these kings had authority &quot;south of the<space/><link><target>Humber</target></link>&quot;, but the span of control, at least of the earlier bretwaldas, likely was less than this.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_53">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, pp. 5354.</extension><space/>In Ceawlin's case the range of control is hard to determine accurately, but Bede's inclusion of Ceawlin in the list of kings who held<space/><italics>imperium</italics>, and the list of battles he is recorded as having won, indicate an energetic and successful leader who, from a base in the upper Thames valley, dominated much of the surrounding area and held overlordship over the southern Britons for some period.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_55"></extension><space/>Despite Ceawlin's military successes, the northern conquests he made could not always be retained:<space/><link><target>Mercia</target></link><space/>took much of the upper Thames valley, and the north-eastern towns won in 571 were among territory subsequently under the control of Kent and Mercia at different times.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_29"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bede's concept of the power of these overlords also must be regarded as the product of his eighth-century viewpoint. When the<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics><space/>was written,<space/><link><target>thelbald of Mercia</target></link><space/>dominated the English south of the Humber, and Bede's view of the earlier kings was doubtless strongly coloured by the state of England at that time. For the earlier<space/><italics>bretwaldas</italics>, such as lle and Ceawlin, there must be some element of anachronism in Bede's description.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_17"></extension><space/>It also is possible that Bede only meant to refer to power over Anglo-Saxon kingdoms, not the native Britons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_53"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ceawlin is the second king in Bede's list. All the subsequent bretwaldas followed more or less consecutively, but there is a long gap, perhaps fifty years, between<space/><link><target>lle of Sussex</target></link>, the first bretwalda, and Ceawlin. The lack of gaps between the overlordships of the later bretwaldas has been used to make an argument for Ceawlin's dates matching the later entries in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>with reasonable accuracy. According to this analysis, the next bretwalda,<space/><link><target>thelberht of Kent</target></link>, must have been already a dominant king by the time Pope<space/><link><target>Gregory the Great</target></link><space/>wrote to him in 601, since Gregory would have not written to an underking. Ceawlin defeated thelberht in 568 according to the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>. thelberht's dates are a matter of debate, but recent scholarly consensus has his reign starting no earlier than 580. The 568 date for the battle at Wibbandun is thought to be unlikely because of the assertion in various versions of the West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List that Ceawlin's reign lasted either seven or seventeen years. If this battle is placed near the year 590, before thelberht has established himself as a powerful king, then the subsequent annals relating to Ceawlin's defeat and death may be reasonably close to the correct date. In any case, the battle with thelberht is unlikely to have been more than a few years on either side of 590.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_56_2">The argument is made in more detail in Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 56. See also pp. 5051 for a review of the evidence concerning the length of Ceawlin's reign.</extension><space/>The gap between lle and Ceawlin, on the other hand, has been taken as supporting evidence for the story told by Gildas in<space/><italics>De Excidio</italics><space/>of a peace lasting a generation or more following a Briton victory at Mons Badonicus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_19">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 19.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>thelberht of Kent succeeds Ceawlin on the list of bretwaldas, but the reigns may overlap somewhat: recent evaluations give Ceawlin a likely reign of 581588, and place thelberht's accession near to the year 589, but these analyses are no more than scholarly guesses.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_133"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31">Kirby (<italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 3134) provides a very detailed analysis of the chronology of thelberht's reign.</extension><space/>Ceawlin's eclipse in 592, probably by Ceol, may have been the occasion for thelberht to rise to prominence; thelberht very likely was the dominant Anglo-Saxon king by 597.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_56">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 56.</extension><space/>thelberht's rise may have been earlier: the 584 annal, even if it records a victory, is the last victory of Ceawlin's in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, and the period after that may have been one of thelberht's ascent and Ceawlin's decline.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_30"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Wessex at Ceawlin's death</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:England green top.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>right</part><part>The state of Anglo-Saxon England at Ceawlin's death</part><part>alt=A map showing England and Wales, with the locations of Celtic and Anglo-Saxon kingdoms marked, and some towns</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Ceawlin lost the throne of Wessex in 592. The annal for that year reads, in part: &quot;Here there was great slaughter at Woden's Barrow, and Ceawlin was driven out.&quot; Woden's Barrow is a tumulus, now called<space/><link><target>Adam's Grave</target></link>, at<space/><link><target>Alton Priors</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wiltshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension><space/>No details of his opponent are given. The medieval chronicler<space/><link><target>William of Malmesbury</target></link>, writing in about 1120, says that it was &quot;the Angles and the British conspiring together&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Plummer_2_17">Quoted in Plummer,<space/><italics>Two Saxon Chronicles</italics>, vol. 2 p. 17</extension><space/>Alternatively, it may have been Ceol, who is supposed to have been the next king of Wessex, ruling for six years according to the West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_56"></extension><space/>According to the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, Ceawlin died the following year. The relevant part of the annal reads: &quot;Here Ceawlin and Cwichelm and Crida perished.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_14"></extension><space/>Nothing more is known of Cwichelm and Crida, although they may have been members of the Wessex royal house their names fit the alliterative pattern common to royal houses of the time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_30"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_143">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 143</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the Regnal List, Ceol was a son of Cutha, who was a son of Cynric; and Ceolwulf, his brother, reigned for seventeen years after him. It is possible that some fragmentation of control among the West Saxons occurred at Ceawlin's death: Ceol and Ceolwulf may have been based in Wiltshire, as opposed to the upper Thames valley. This split also may have contributed to thelberht's ability to rise to dominance in southern England. The West Saxons remained influential in military terms, however: the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>and Bede record continued military activity against Essex and Sussex within twenty or thirty years of Ceawlin's death.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_17"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>House of Wessex family tree</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Primary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum|Ecclesiastical History of the English People]]</arg><arg name="others"><space/>Translated by Leo Sherley-Price, revised R.E. Latham, ed. D.H. Farmer</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-14-044565-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Swanton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-92129-5</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Secondary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Campbell</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>John</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Eric</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Wormald</arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Patrick</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxons</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Penguin Books]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-014395-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fletcher</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Who's Who in Roman Britain and Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Shepheard-Walwyn</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85683-089-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hodgkins</arg><arg name="first"><space/>H.R.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A History of the Anglo-Saxons</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1952</arg><arg name="origyear">1935</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]</arg><arg name="oclc">59000682<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="title"><space/>An Introduction to Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1960</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]</arg></template><space/>(2003 edition: ISBN 0-521-83085-0)</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Roman Britain and Early England: 55&nbsp;BC – AD&nbsp;871</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1966</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[W. W. Norton & Company]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0-393-00361-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Keynes</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Simon</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Lapidge<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Michael</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alfred the Great: Asser's Life of King Alfred and other contemporary sources</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin Classics</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-044409-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kirby</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.P.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Earliest English Kings</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Routledge]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-09086-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lapidge</arg><arg name="first">Michael</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Blackwell Publishing]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0-631-22492-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Plummer</arg><arg name="first">Charles</arg><arg name="title">Two Saxon Chronicles Parallel</arg><arg name="year">1972</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Clarendon Press]]</arg><arg name="oclc">2697415</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Stenton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Frank M.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Clarendon Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-821716-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Yorke</arg><arg name="first">Barbara</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Seaby</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85264-027-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/4973'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Yorke</arg><arg name="first">Barbara</arg><arg name="title">Ceawlin</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford Online Dictionary of National Biography</arg></template></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-reg</target><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Cynric of Wessex|Cynric]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of monarchs of Wessex|King of Wessex]]</arg><arg name="years">560–592</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Ceol of Wessex|Ceol]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Kings of Wessex</target></template><template><target>Bretwalda</target></template><template><target>authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ceawlin Of Wessex</target></template><link><target>Category:590s deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:West Saxon monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century monarchs in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century English people</target></link><link><target>Category:Year of birth unknown</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Wessex</target></link></paragraph></article>