<article title='Black_and_Tans'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target><arg>Black and tan (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>POV</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox law enforcement agency</target><arg name="doc"><space/>autocat off
</arg><arg name="agencyname"><space/>Royal Irish Constabulary Reserve Force
</arg><arg name="nativename">
</arg><arg name="nativenamea">
</arg><arg name="nativenamer">
</arg><arg name="commonname">Black and Tans
</arg><arg name="abbreviation"><space/>RICRF
</arg><arg name="motto">
</arg><arg name="mottotranslated">
</arg><arg name="mission"><space/>
</arg><arg name="formed"><space/>1919
</arg><arg name="preceding1"><space/>
</arg><arg name="dissolved"><space/>1922
</arg><arg name="superseding"><space/>
</arg><arg name="employees">
</arg><arg name="volunteers">
</arg><arg name="budget">
</arg><arg name="legalpersonality">
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland
</arg><arg name="countryabbr">
</arg><arg name="national"><space/>Yes
</arg><arg name="subdivtype">
</arg><arg name="subdivname">
</arg><arg name="subdivdab">
</arg><arg name="map"><space/>Island of Ireland.svg
</arg><arg name="mapcaption">
</arg><arg name="sizearea"><space/>84,421 km²
</arg><arg name="sizepopulation">
</arg><arg name="badge"><space/>Badge of the Royal Irish Constabulary.svg
</arg><arg name="flag"><space/>
</arg><arg name="police"><space/>Yes
</arg><arg name="local"><space/>Yes
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Black and Tans</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-ga</target><arg>Dúchrónaigh</arg></template>),<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.focal.ie/Search.aspx?term=the+Black+and+Tans&amp;amp;lang=3116649'>Focal.ie Dictionary of Irish Terms</link></extension><space/>officially the<space/><bold>Royal Irish Constabulary Reserve Force</bold>,<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.theguardian.com/news/1921/oct/12/mainsection.fromthearchive</extension><space/>was a force of<space/><link><target>Special Constable</target><part>Temporary Constables</part></link><space/>recruited to assist the<space/><link><target>Royal Irish Constabulary</target></link><space/>(RIC) during the<space/><link><target>Irish War of Independence</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ndic.edu/press/pdf/5463.pdf'>''Improving the law Enforcement-Intelligence Community Relationship''</link>. National Defense Intelligence College, Washington, DC. June 2007. p.120</extension><space/>The force was the brainchild of<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link>, then British<space/><link><target>Secretary of State for War</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Carmel McCaffrey</target><part>McCaffrey, Carmel</part></link>.<space/><italics>In Search of Ireland's Heroes</italics>. 2006.p 233</extension><space/>and was recruited in Great Britain in late 1919 (although it contained Irish members also).<extension extension_name='ref' name="warinpeace"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="editor1">Robert Gerwarth</arg><arg name="editor2">John Horne</arg><arg name="title">War in Peace: Paramilitary Violence in Europe After the Great War</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="page">202</arg><arg name="quote">The Black and Tans were the ex-servicemen recruited as RIC constables throughout Britain in late 1919 and constituted a force of approximately 9,000 men before the war's end. However, 'Black and Tans' also came to refer to the Temporary Cadets of the Auxiliary Division of the RIC, a force of some 2,200 ex-officers, formed in July 1920, and in practice virtually independent of military and policy control. Both forces were made up of veterans from all services. ... Both Auxiliaries and Black and Tans had Irish members.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Padraig Og O Ruairc, Blood on the Banner, The Republican Struggle in Clare, pp. 332333</extension><space/>Thousands, many of them<space/><link><target>British Army</target><part>British</part></link><space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>veterans, answered the British government's call for recruits. Their role was to help the RIC maintain control and fight the<space/><link><target>Irish Republican Army (191722)</target><part>Irish Republican Army</part></link><space/>(IRA), the army of the<space/><link><target>Irish Republic</target></link>. The nickname &quot;Black and Tans&quot; arose from the colours of the improvised uniforms they initially wore, composed of mixed<space/><link><target>khaki</target></link><space/><link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>rifle green</target></link><space/>RIC uniform parts. The Black and Tans became infamous for their attacks on civilians and civilian property.</paragraph><paragraph>The Black and Tans were sometimes confused with the<space/><link><target>Auxiliary Division</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>counter-insurgency</target></link><space/>unit of the RIC made up of former British officers.<extension extension_name='ref'>O'Connell, T.<space/><italics>Interrogation and Treatment of republican suspects by the British Auxiliary Forces, 'Black and Tans', January 1921</italics>, Irish Historical Documents since 1800, edited by Alan O'Day. Gill and MacMillan. p.169.</extension><space/>However, sometimes the term &quot;Black and Tans&quot; is used to cover both of these groups.<extension extension_name='ref' name="warinpeace"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Foundation</heading><paragraph>The late 19th and early 20th centuries in<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link><space/>were dominated by<space/><link><target>Irish nationalism</target><part>Irish nationalists'</part></link><space/>pursuit of<space/><link><target>Irish Home Rule movement</target><part>Home Rule</part></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland</target></link>. The issue of Home Rule was shelved with the outbreak of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, and in 1916<space/><link><target>Irish republicanism</target><part>Irish republicans</part></link><space/>staged the<space/><link><target>Easter Rising</target></link><space/>against British rule in an attempt to establish a republic. Growing support amongst the Irish populace for the republican<space/><link><target>Sinn Fin</target></link><space/>political party saw it win 73 out of 105 seats in the<space/><link><target>Irish general election, 1918</target></link>. In January 1919, Sinn Fin established themselves as the<space/><link><target>First Dil</target></link>, which then declared an independent<space/><link><target>Irish Republic</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.oireachtas.ie/parliament/about/history/</extension><space/>They also declared the<space/><link><target>Irish Republican Army (191722)</target><part>Irish Republican Army</part></link><space/>(IRA) the official army of the state, which in the same month began the<space/><link><target>Irish War of Independence</target></link>. The main targets of the IRA offensive were the Royal Irish Constabulary (RIC) and the British Army in Ireland.</paragraph><paragraph>In September 1919<space/><link><target>David Lloyd George</target></link>, who was British Prime Minister at the time, outlawed the Dil and augmented the British Army presence in Ireland,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>In Search of Ireland's Heroes</italics><space/><link><target>Carmel McCaffrey</target></link>. Ivan R. Dee. p 231</extension><space/>starting work on the next<space/><link><target>Government of Ireland Act 1920</target><part>Home Rule Act</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:A Black and Tan on duty in Dublin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A Black and Tan in Dublin, smoking and carrying a<space/><link><target>Lewis gun</target></link>, February 1921</part></link>In January 1920, the British government started advertising in British cities for men willing to &quot;face a rough and dangerous task&quot;, helping to boost the ranks of the RIC in policing an increasingly anti-British Ireland. There was no shortage of recruits, many of them unemployed First World War army veterans, and by November 1921 about 9,500 men had joined. This sudden influx of men led to a shortage of RIC uniforms, and the new recruits were issued with<space/><link><target>khaki</target></link><space/>army uniforms (usually only trousers) and dark green RIC or blue<space/><link><target>British police</target></link><space/>surplus tunics, caps and belts. These uniforms differentiated them from the British Army and the regular RIC, and gave rise to the force's nickname: Christopher O'Sullivan wrote in the<space/><italics><link><target>Limerick Echo</target></link></italics><space/>on 25 March 1920 that, meeting a group of recruits on a train at<space/><link><target>Limerick Junction</target></link>, the attire of one reminded him of the<space/><link><target>Scarteen</target></link><space/><link><target>fox hunting</target><part>Hunt</part></link>, whose &quot;Black and Tans&quot; nickname derived from the colouration of its<space/><link><target>Kerry Beagle</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Spellissy1998"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Spellissy</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Séan</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The history of Limerick City</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>9 August 2010</arg><arg name="date"><space/>December 1998</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Celtic Bookshop</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-9534683-0-0</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>87–88<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Ennis comedian<space/><link><target>Mike Nono</target></link><space/>elaborated the joke in Limerick's Theatre Royal, and the nickname soon took hold,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Spellissy1998"></extension><space/>persisting even after the men received full RIC uniforms.</paragraph><paragraph>The new recruits received three months' hurried training, and were rapidly posted to RIC barracks, mostly in rural<space/><link><target>County Dublin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Munster</target></link><space/>and eastern<space/><link><target>Connacht</target></link>. The first men arrived on 25 March 1920. The British government also raised another unit, the<space/><link><target>Auxiliary Division</target></link><space/>of the constabulary, known as the Auxiliaries or Auxies, consisting of ex-army officers. The Black and Tans aided the Auxiliaries in the British government's attempts to break both the IRA and the Dil.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Conduct</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Timeline of the Irish War of Independence</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Relief (6492236861).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A group of Black and Tans and Auxiliaries outside the London and North Western Hotel in Dublin following an attack by the IRA, April 1921</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Temporary Constables were paid the relatively good wage of 10<space/><link><target>shilling</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(half a<space/><link><target>Pound stirling#Pre-decimal</target><part>pound</part></link>) a day, plus full board and lodging. With minimal police training, their main role was to increase the strength of police posts, where they functioned as sentries, guards, escorts for government agents, reinforcement to the regular police, and crowd control. They mounted a determined<space/><link><target>counter-insurgency</target></link><space/>campaign. They and the Auxies became known as<space/><italics>Tudor's Toughs</italics><space/>after the police commander, Major-General Sir<space/><link><target>Henry Hugh Tudor</target></link>. They were viewed by republicans as akin to an army of occupation because of these duties. They soon gained a reputation for brutality,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/fromthearchive/story/0,,1920235,00.html'>Don't be too tragic about Ireland</link></italics><space/>The Guardian, 12 October 1921</extension><space/>as the RIC campaign against the IRA and Sinn Fin members was stepped up and police reprisals for IRA attacks were condoned by the government.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/europe/irelands-war-of-independence-the-chilling-story-of-the-black-and-tans-475005.html'>Ireland's War of Independence: The chilling story of the Black and Tans<space/></link></italics><space/>The Independent, 21 April 2006</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexander Will,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.policememorial.org.uk/Forces/IRELAND/RIC_Roll.htm'>RIC Record</link></extension><space/>from<space/><link><target>Forfar</target></link><space/>in Scotland, was the first Temporary Constable to die in the conflict. He was killed during an IRA attack on the RIC barracks in<space/><link><target>Rathmore, County Kerry</target><part>Rathmore</part></link>, County Kerry, on 11 July 1920.</paragraph><paragraph>The Black and Tans were not subject to strict discipline in their first months and as a result, their deaths at the hands of the IRA in 1920 were often repaid with arbitrary reprisals against the civilian population. In the summer of 1920, the Black and Tans burned and sacked many small towns and villages in Ireland, beginning with<space/><link><target>Tuam</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>County Galway</target></link><space/>in July 1920 and also including<space/><link><target>Trim, County Meath</target><part>Trim</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Balbriggan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Knockcroghery</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thurles</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Templemore</target></link><space/>amongst many others. In November 1920, the Tans &quot;besieged&quot;<space/><link><target>Tralee</target></link><space/>in revenge for the IRA abduction and killing of two local RIC men. They closed all the businesses in the town, let no food in for a week and shot dead three local civilians. On 14 November, the Tans were suspected of abducting and murdering a Roman Catholic priest, Father<space/><link><target>Michael Griffin (Irish priest)</target><part>Michael Griffin</part></link>, in<space/><link><target>Galway</target></link>. His body was found in a bog in<space/><link><target>Barna</target></link><space/>a week later. On the night of 11 December 1920, they sacked<space/><link><target>Cork (city)</target><part>Cork</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Burning of Cork</target><part>destroying a large part of the city centre</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In January 1921, the British Labour Commission produced a report on the situation in Ireland which was highly critical of the government's security policy. It said the government, in forming the Black and Tans, had &quot;liberated forces which it is not at present able to dominate&quot;. However, since 29 December 1920, the British government had sanctioned &quot;official reprisals&quot; in Ireland usually meaning burning property of IRA men and their suspected sympathisers. Taken together with an increased emphasis on discipline in the RIC, this helped to curb the random atrocities the Black and Tans committed since March 1920 for the remainder of the war, if only because reprisals were now directed from above rather than being the result of a spontaneous desire for revenge.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of the activities popularly attributed to the Black and Tans may have been committed by the<space/><link><target>Auxiliary Division</target></link>; and some were committed by regular RIC men. For instance,<space/><link><target>Toms Mac Curtain</target></link>, the Mayor of Cork, was assassinated in March 1920 by local RIC men and the shooting dead of 13 civilians at<space/><link><target>Croke Park</target></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Bloody Sunday (1920)</target><part>Bloody Sunday</part></link><space/>was also carried out by the regular RIC, although a small detachment of Auxiliaries were also present. Most Republicans did not make a distinction, and &quot;Black and Tans&quot; was often used as a catch-all term for all police groups.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Government Policy and reaction</heading><paragraph>The actions of the Black and Tans alienated public opinion in both Ireland and Great Britain. Their violent tactics encouraged the Irish public to increase their covert support of the IRA, while the British public pressed for a move towards a peaceful resolution.<space/><link><target>E. F. L. Wood, 1st Earl of Halifax</target><part>Edward Wood</part></link><space/>MP, better known as the future Foreign Secretary Lord Halifax, rejected force and urged the British government to make an offer to the Irish &quot;conceived on the most generous lines&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Frederick Smith, 2nd Earl of Birkenhead</target><part>Lord Birkenhead</part></link>,<space/><italics>Halifax</italics><space/>(Hamish Hamilton, 1965), p. 122.</extension><space/>Sir<space/><link><target>John Simon, 1st Viscount Simon</target><part>John Simon</part></link><space/>MP, another future Foreign Secretary, was also horrified at the tactics being used.<space/><link><target>Lionel Curtis</target></link>, writing in the imperialist journal<space/><italics><link><target>The Round Table Journal</target><part>The Round Table</part></link></italics>, wrote: &quot;If the British Commonwealth can only be preserved by such means, it would become a negation of the principle for which it has stood&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lionel Curtis,<space/><italics>The Round Table</italics>, Vol. XI, No. 43 (June 1921), p. 505.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>George V of the United Kingdom</target><part>King</part></link>, senior Anglican bishops, MPs from the<space/><link><target>Liberal Party (UK)</target><part>Liberal</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Labour Party (UK)</target><part>Labour</part></link><space/>parties,<space/><link><target>Oswald Mosley</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jan Smuts</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Trades Union Congress</target></link><space/>and parts of the press were increasingly critical of the actions of the Black and Tans.<space/><link><target>Mahatma Gandhi</target></link><space/>said of the British peace offer: &quot;It is not fear of losing more lives that has compelled a reluctant offer from England but it is the shame of any further imposition of agony upon a people that loves liberty above everything else&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence James,<space/><italics>The Rise and Fall of the British Empire</italics><space/>(Abacus, 1998), p. 384.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>About 7,000 Black and Tans served in Ireland in 192022. More than one-third of them died or left the service before they were disbanded along with the rest of the RIC in 1922, an extremely high wastage rate, and well over half received government pensions. A total of 404 members of the<space/><link><target>Royal Irish Constabulary</target></link><space/>died in the conflict and more than 600 were wounded but it is not clear how many of these were pre-war RIC men and how many were Black and Tans or Auxiliaries.</paragraph><paragraph>Those who returned to civilian life sometimes had problems re-integrating. At least two former Black and Tans were hanged for murder in Britain and another wanted for murder committed suicide before the police could arrest him.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bennett, Richard<space/><italics>The Black and Tans</italics>(London 1959), Page 222</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph>Due to the ferocity of the Tans' behaviour in Ireland and the numerous<space/><link><target>war crimes</target></link><space/>they committed, feelings continue to run high regarding their actions. &quot;Black and Tan&quot; or &quot;Tan&quot; remains a pejorative term for the British in Ireland<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template>, and the reputation of the Tans is still hated in Ireland. The term can still stir bad reactions because of their remembered brutality.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.irishexaminer.com/ireland/nike-forced-to-run-like-hell-away-over-black-and-tan-trainer-branding-187151.html</extension><space/>One of the best known Irish Republican songs is<space/><link><target>Dominic Behan</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Come out Ye Black and Tans</target></link>&quot;. The<space/><link><target>Irish War of Independence</target></link><space/>is sometimes referred to as the &quot;Tan War&quot; or &quot;Black-and-Tan War.&quot; This term was preferred by those who fought on the anti-Treaty side in the<space/><link><target>Irish Civil War</target></link><space/>and is still used by Republicans today. The &quot;Cogadh na Saoirse&quot; medal, awarded since 1941 by the<space/><link><target>Republic of Ireland</target><part>Irish government</part></link><space/>to IRA veterans of the War of Independence, bears a ribbon with two vertical stripes in black and tan.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.irishmedals.com/1921.html'>1919 1921 War of Independence</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/hi/english/events/northern_ireland/history/newsid_64000/64204.stm'>BBC News Northern Ireland ''191720 The Road to Partition'' posted March 18, 1999</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eprints.qut.edu.au/archive/00000009/01/Ainsworth_Black_conf.PDF'>&quot;The Black &amp; Tans and Auxiliaries in Ireland, 19201921: Their Origins, Roles and Legacy&quot;, by John Ainsworth, 2001</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://homepage.tinet.ie/~abbeydorney/book/burning.html'>Account of the Burning of Abbeydorney, Co. Kerry</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eprints.qut.edu.au/6/1/British_Security_Policy_in_Ireland.pdf'>''British Security Policy in Ireland, 19201921''</link><space/>Ainsworth, John S. (2001) Australian Journal of Irish Studies, 1. pp.&amp;nbsp;176190</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/30112006-BlackandTans/'>Black &amp; Tans in Galway</link><space/>(first hand account and photos)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/16042009_seanbroderick/'>Sean Broderick and the Black &amp; Tans</link><space/>(first hand account and photos from Galway)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.kennys.ie/News/OldGalway/10112005-FatherMichaelGriffin/'>Father Michael Griffin</link><space/>(first hand account and photos from Galway)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Black And Tans</target></template><link><target>Category:Irish War of Independence</target></link><link><target>Category:Royal Irish Constabulary</target></link><link><target>Category:Paramilitary organizations</target></link><link><target>Category:Political repression</target></link></paragraph></article>