<article title='Digital_Equipment_Corporation'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox company</target><arg name="name"><space/>Digital Equipment Corporation
</arg><arg name="logo"><space/>[[File:Digital 556-flattened4.svg|Digital Equipment Corporation Logo|250px]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Honesty and respect for customers and employees.
</arg><arg name="fate"><space/>Acquired by [[Compaq]], after divestiture of major assets.
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Hewlett-Packard]]<br>(2002 – present)<br>[[Compaq]]<br>(1998–2002)
</arg><arg name="foundation"><space/>{{start date and age|1957}}
</arg><arg name="defunct"><space/>1998
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Maynard, Massachusetts]], United States
</arg><arg name="industry"><space/>Computer manufacturing
</arg><arg name="key_people"><space/>[[Ken Olsen]] (founder, president, and chairman)<space/><br /><space/>[[Harlan Anderson]] (co-founder)<space/><br /><space/>[[C. Gordon Bell]] (VP Engineering, 1972-1983)
</arg><arg name="products"><space/>[[Programmed Data Processor|PDP]] minicomputers<space/><br /><space/>[[VAX]] minicomputers<br /><space/>[[DEC Alpha|Alpha]] servers and workstations<br />[[DECnet]]<br />[[VT100]] terminal<br />[[Local Area Transport|LAT]] and [[Terminal server]]<br />[[StrongARM]] microprocessors<br />[[Digital Linear Tape]]
</arg><arg name="num_employees"><space/>over 140,000 (1987)
</arg><arg name="parent">
</arg><arg name="subsid">
</arg></template><bold>Digital Equipment Corporation</bold>, also known as<space/><bold>DEC</bold><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;DEC used by Digital itself:&quot;<space/><italics>PDP11 Processor Handbook</italics><space/>(1973): page 8, &quot;DEC, PDP, UNIBUS are registered trademarks of Digital Equipment Corporation;&quot; page 1-4, &quot;Digital Equipment Corporation (DEC) designs and manufactures many of the peripheral devices offered with<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link>'s. As a designer and manufacturer of peripherals, DEC can offer extremely reliable equipment... The LA30 DECwriter, a totally DEC-designed and built teleprinter, can serve as an alternative to the Teletype.&quot;</extension><space/>and using the trademark<space/><bold>Digital</bold>, was a major American company in the<space/><link><target>computer industry</target></link><space/>from the 1960s to the 1990s. It was a leading vendor of computer systems, including computers, software, and<space/><link><target>computer peripheral</target><part>peripherals</part></link>, and its<space/><link><target>Programmed Data Processor</target><part>PDP</part></link><space/>and successor<space/><link><target>VAX</target></link><space/>products were the most successful of all<space/><link><target>minicomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in terms of sales.</paragraph><paragraph>From 1957 until 1992 its headquarters were located in a former wool mill in<space/><link><target>Maynard, Massachusetts</target></link><space/>(since renamed Clock Tower Place and now home to multiple companies). DEC was acquired in June 1998 by<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link>, which subsequently merged with<space/><link><target>Hewlett-Packard</target></link><space/>in May 2002. Some parts of DEC, notably the compiler business and the<space/><link><target>Hudson, Massachusetts</target></link><space/>facility, were sold to<space/><link><target>Intel</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital Equipment Corporation should not be confused with the unrelated companies<space/><link><target>Digital Research</target><part>Digital Research, Inc</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Western Digital</target></link>, although the latter once manufactured the<space/><link><target>LSI-11</target></link><space/>chipsets used in DEC's low end<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link>/03 computers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview</heading><paragraph>Initially focusing on the small end of the computer market allowed DEC to grow without its potential competitors making serious efforts to compete with them. Their PDP series of machines became popular in the 1960s, especially the<space/><link><target>PDP-8</target></link>, widely considered to be the first successful<space/><link><target>minicomputer</target></link>. Looking to simplify and update their line, DEC replaced most of their smaller machines with the<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link><space/>in 1970, eventually selling over 600,000 units and cementing DECs position in the industry. Originally designed as a follow-on to the PDP-11, DEC's<space/><link><target>VAX</target><part>VAX-11</part></link><space/>series was the first widely used<space/><link><target>32-bit</target></link><space/>minicomputer, sometimes referred to as &quot;<link><target>Superminicomputer</target><part>superminis</part></link>&quot;. These were able to compete in many roles with larger<space/><link><target>mainframe computer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as the<space/><link><target>IBM System/370</target></link>. The VAX was a best-seller, with over 400,000 sold, and its sales through the 1980s propelled the company into the second largest in the industry. At its peak, DEC was the second largest employer in Massachusetts, second only to the state government.</paragraph><paragraph>The rapid rise of the business<space/><link><target>microcomputer</target></link><space/>in the late 1980s, and especially the introduction of powerful 32-bit systems in the 1990s, quickly eroded the value of DEC's systems. DEC's last major attempt to find a space in the rapidly changing market was the<space/><link><target>DEC Alpha</target></link><space/><link><target>64-bit</target></link><space/><link><target>RISC</target></link><space/><link><target>processor architecture</target></link>. DEC initially started work on Alpha as a way to re-implement their VAX series, but also employed it in a range of high-performance<space/><link><target>workstations</target></link>. Although the Alpha processor family met both of these goals, and, for most of its lifetime, was the fastest processor family on the market, extremely high asking prices<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://alasir.com/articles/alpha_history/dec_collapse.shtml'>Alpha: The History in Facts and Comments - The Collapse of DEC</link>. Alasir.com. Retrieved on 2013-07-17.</extension><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template><space/>were outsold by lower priced x86 chips from Intel and clones such as AMD.</paragraph><paragraph>The company was acquired in June 1998 by<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link>, in what was at that time the largest merger in the history of the computer industry. At the time, Compaq was focused on the enterprise market and had recently purchased several other large vendors. DEC was a major player overseas where Compaq had less presence. However, Compaq had little idea what to do with its acquisitions, and soon found itself in financial difficulty of its own. The company subsequently merged with<space/><link><target>Hewlett-Packard</target></link><space/>in May 2002.<space/><template><target>As of</target><arg>2007</arg></template><space/>some of DEC's product lines were still produced under the HP name.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Maynard MA Clock Tower Place.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>DEC was headquartered at a former wool mill in Maynard, Massachusetts, from 1957 until 1992</part></link><link><target>Ken Olsen</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Harlan Anderson</target></link><space/>were two engineers who had been working at<space/><link><target>MIT</target></link><space/><link><target>Lincoln Laboratory</target></link><space/>on the lab's various computer projects. The Lab is best known for their work on what would today be known as &quot;interactivity&quot;, and their machines were among the first where operators had direct control over programs running in real time. These had started in 1944 with the famed<space/><link><target>Whirlwind (computer)</target><part>Whirlwind</part></link><space/>which was originally developed to make a<space/><link><target>flight simulator</target></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>US Navy</target></link>, although this was never completed.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.mitre.org/news/releases/09/whirlwind_07_01_2009.html'>&quot;MITRE's Project Whirlwind Computer Collection Transferred to MIT&quot;</link>, MITRE, 1 July 2009</extension><space/>Instead, this effort evolved into the<space/><link><target>Semi Automatic Ground Environment</target><part>SAGE</part></link><space/>system for the<space/><link><target>US Air Force</target></link>, which used large screens and<space/><link><target>light gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to allow operators to interact with<space/><link><target>radar</target></link><space/>data stored in the computer.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.mitre.org/about/sage.html'>&quot;Semi-Automatic Ground Environment (SAGE)&quot;</link>, MITRE, 25 January 2005</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When the Air Force project wound down, the Lab turned their attention to an effort to build a version of the Whirlwind using<space/><link><target>transistor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in place of<space/><link><target>vacuum tube</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In order to test their new circuitry, they first built a small<space/><link><target>18-bit</target></link><space/>machine known as<space/><link><target>TX-0</target></link><space/>which first ran in 1956.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.computerhistory.org/collections/accession/XD154.75'>&quot;TX-0 Computer&quot;</link>, Computer History Museum</extension><space/>When the TX-0 successfully proved the basic concepts, attention turned to a much larger system, the<space/><link><target>36-bit word length</target><part>36-bit</part></link><space/><link><target>TX-2</target></link><space/>with a then-enormous 64 kWords of<space/><link><target>core memory</target></link>. Core was so expensive that parts of TX-0's memory were stripped for the TX-2, and what remained of the TX-0 was then given to<space/><link><target>MIT</target></link><space/>on permanent loan.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cm"><link type='external' href='http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/TheCompMusRep/TCMR-V08.html'>Highlights from ''The Computer Museum Report'' Volume 8 Spring 1984</link>,<space/><link><target>The Computer Museum, Boston</target><part>The Computer Museum</part></link>, Boston, MA, archived at ed-thelen.org, retrieved 19 February 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At MIT, Olsen and Anderson noticed something odd: students would line up for hours to get a turn to use the stripped-down TX-0, while largely ignoring a faster<space/><link><target>IBM</target></link><space/>machine that was also available. The two decided that the draw of<space/><link><target>interactive computing</target></link><space/>was so strong that they felt there was a market for a small machine dedicated to this role, essentially a commercialized TX-0. They could sell this to users where graphical output or realtime operation would be more important than outright performance. Additionally, as the machine would cost much less than the larger systems then available, it would also be able to serve users that needed a lower-cost solution dedicated to a specific task, where a larger 36-bit machine would not be needed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="companyhistory"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1957 when the pair and Ken's brother Stan went looking for capital, they found that the American business community was hostile to investing in computer companies. Many smaller computer companies had come and gone in the 1950s, wiped out when new technical developments rendered their platforms obsolete, and even large companies like<space/><link><target>RCA</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>General Electric</target></link><space/>were failing to make a profit in the market. The only serious expression of interest came from<space/><link><target>Georges Doriot</target></link><space/>and his<space/><link><target>American Research and Development Corporation</target></link><space/>(AR&amp;D). Worried that a new computer company would find it difficult to arrange further financing, Doriot suggested the fledgling company change its business plan to focus less on computers, and even change their name from &quot;Digital Computer Corporation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="companyhistory"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The pair returned with an updated<space/><link><target>business plan</target></link><space/>that outlined two phases for the company's development. They would start by selling<space/><link><target>computer module</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as stand-alone devices that could be purchased separately and wired together to produce a number of different digital systems for lab use. Then, if these &quot;digital modules&quot; were able to build a self-sustaining business, the company would be free to use them to develop a complete computer in their Phase II.<extension extension_name='ref' name="proposal"><link type='external' href='http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/text/dec/pdp-1/DEC.pdp_1.1957.102664472.pdf'>&quot;A Proposal to American Research and Development Corporation 27 May 1957&quot;</link></extension><space/>The newly christened &quot;Digital<space/><italics>Equipment</italics><space/>Corporation&quot; received $70,000 from AR&amp;D for a 70% share of the company,<extension extension_name='ref' name="companyhistory"></extension><space/>and began operations in a<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target><part>Civil War</part></link><space/>era textile mill in<space/><link><target>Maynard, Massachusetts</target></link>, where plenty of inexpensive manufacturing space was available.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Digital modules</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dec SYSTEM BUILDING BLOCKS 1103.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>System Building Blocks (System Module) 1103 hex-inverter card (both sides)</part></link><link><target>File:PDP-1 System Building Block No. 4106.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>PDP-1 System Building Block #4106, circa 1963 - note that one transistor (yellow) has been replaced</part></link>In early 1958 DEC shipped its first products, the &quot;Digital Laboratory Module&quot; line. The Modules consisted of a number of individual electronic components and<space/><link><target>Bipolar junction transistor#Germanium transistors</target><part>germanium transistors</part></link><space/>mounted to a<space/><link><target>circuit board</target></link>, the actual circuits being based on those from the TX-2.<extension extension_name='ref' name="modules">Richard Best, Russell Doane and John McNamara,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/computer_engineering/00000125.htm'>&quot;Digital Modules, The Basis for Computers&quot;</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://bitsavers.org/pdf/dec/_Books/Bell-ComputerEngineering.pdf'>''Computer Engineering, A DEC view of hardware systems design''</link>, Digital Press, 1978</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Laboratory Modules were packaged in an extruded aluminum housing,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.computerhistory.org/collections/accession/102633142'>&quot;DEC Laboratory Module FLIP-FLOP 201&quot;</link>, Computer History Museum</extension><space/>intended to sit on an engineer's workbench, although a<space/><link><target>19-inch rack</target><part>rack-mount</part></link><space/>bay was sold that held nine laboratory modules.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BuildingBlock1960"><link type='external' href='http://ed-thelen.org/comp-hist/DECbuildingBlockLogic2ndEd.pdf'>DEC Building Block Logic</link>, Second Ed., Digital Equipment Corporation, Nov. 1960; 48 pages.</extension><space/>They were then connected together using<space/><link><target>4 mm plug</target><part>banana plug</part></link><space/><link><target>patch cord</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>inserted at the front of the modules. Three versions were offered, running at 5&amp;nbsp;MHz (1957), 500&amp;nbsp;kHz (1959), or 10&amp;nbsp;MHz (1960).<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1">Richard Best, Russell Doane and John McNamara,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/computer_engineering/00000125.htm'>&quot;Digital Modules, The Basis for Computers&quot;</link>, in ''Computer Engineering, A DEC view of hardware systems design&quot;, Digital Press, 1978</extension><space/>The Modules proved to be in high demand in other computer companies, who used them to build equipment to test their own systems. Despite the recession of the late 1950s, the company sold $94,000 worth of these modules during 1958 alone, turning a profit at the end of its first year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="companyhistory"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The original Laboratory Modules were soon supplemented with the &quot;Digital Systems Module&quot; line, which were identical internally but packaged differently. The Systems Modules were designed with all of the connections at the back of the module using 22-pin<space/><link><target>Amphenol</target></link><space/>connectors, and were attached to each other by plugging them into a backplane that could be mounted in a<space/><link><target>19-inch rack</target></link>. The backplanes allowed 25 modules in a single 5-1/4&amp;nbsp;inch section of rack, and allowed the high densities needed to build a computer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="modules"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The original laboratory and system module lines were offered in 500 kilocycle, 5 megacycle and 10 megacycle versions. In all cases, the supply voltages were -15 and +10 volts, with logic levels of -3 volts (passive pull-down) and 0 volts (active pull-up).<extension extension_name='ref' name="BuildingBlock1960"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>DEC used the Systems Modules to build their &quot;Memory Test&quot; machine for testing core memory systems, selling about 50 of these pre-packaged units over the next eight years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="present3"><italics>Present</italics><space/>1978, pg. 3</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>PDP-1</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>LINC</target></link><space/>computers were also built using Systems Modules (see below).</paragraph><paragraph>Modules were part of DEC's product line into the 1970s, although they went through several evolutions during this time as technology changed. The same circuits were then packaged as the first &quot;R&quot; (red) series &quot;<link><target>Flip Chip (trademark)</target><part>Flip-Chip</part></link>&quot; modules. Later, other module series provided additional speed, much higher logic density, and industrial I/O capabilities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="present10"></extension><space/>Digital published extensive data about the modules in free catalogs that became very popular.</paragraph><heading level='3'>PDP-1 family</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>PDP-1</arg></template><link><target>File:Steve Russell and PDP-1 - Vintage Computer Fair 2006.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>PDP-1</part><part>220px</part><part>right</part><part>A<space/><link><target>PDP-1</target></link><space/>system, with<space/><link><target>Steve Russell</target></link>, developer of<space/><link><target>Spacewar!</target></link><space/>at the console. This is a canonical example of the PDP-1, with the console typewriter on the left, CPU and main control panel in the center, the Type 30 display on the right.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>With the company established and a successful product on the market, DEC turned its attention to the computer market once again as part of its planned &quot;Phase II&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="proposal"></extension><space/>In August 1959, Ben Gurley started design of the company's first computer, the<space/><link><target>PDP-1</target></link>. In keeping with Doriot's instructions, the name was an<space/><link><target>initialism</target></link><space/>for &quot;<link><target>Programmable Data Processor</target></link>&quot;, leaving off the term &quot;computer&quot;. As Gurley put it, &quot;We aren't building computers, we're building 'Programmable Data Processors'.&quot; The prototype was first shown publicly at the Joint Computer Conference in Boston in December 1959.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.computerhistory.org/collections/accession/102634161'>Eastern Joint Computer Conference and Exhibition</link>, official program of 1959 meeting in Boston</extension><space/>The first PDP-1 was delivered to<space/><link><target>Bolt, Beranek and Newman</target></link><space/>in November 1960,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://vt100.net/timeline/1960.html'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1960&quot;</link></extension><space/>and formally accepted the next April.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Computers and Automation</italics>, April 1961, pg. 8B</extension><space/>The PDP-1 sold in basic form for $120,000, or about $900,000 in 2011 US dollars.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bls.gov/data/inflation_calculator.htm'>&quot;Bureau of Labor Statistics Inflation Calculator, 19612011&quot;</link></extension><space/>By the time production ended in 1969, 53 PDP-1s had been delivered.<extension extension_name='ref' name="present3"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;History of Computing&quot;, Lexikon Services, ISBN 0-944601-78-2</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The PDP-1 was supplied standard with 4096 words of<space/><link><target>core memory</target></link>,<space/><link><target>18-bit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per word, and ran at a basic speed of 100,000 operations per second. It was constructed using many System Building Blocks that were packaged into several<space/><link><target>19-inch rack</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The racks were themselves packaged into a single large mainframe case, with a hexagonal control panel containing switches and lights mounted to lay at table-top height at one end of the mainframe. Above the control panel was the system's standard<space/><link><target>input/output</target></link><space/>solution, a<space/><link><target>punch tape</target></link><space/>reader and writer. Most systems were purchased with two<space/><link><target>peripherals</target></link>, the Type 30<space/><link><target>vector graphics</target></link><space/>display, and a<space/><link><target>Soroban Engineering</target></link><space/>modified<space/><link><target>IBM Electric typewriter</target><part>IBM Model B Electric typewriter</part></link><space/>that was used as a<space/><link><target>printer (computing)</target><part>printer</part></link>. The Soroban system was notoriously unreliable, and often replaced with a modified<space/><link><target>Friden Flexowriter</target></link>, which also contained its own punch tape system. A variety of more-expensive add-ons followed, including<space/><link><target>magnetic tape</target></link><space/>systems,<space/><link><target>punched card</target></link><space/>readers and punches, and faster punch tape and printer systems.</paragraph><paragraph>When DEC introduced the PDP-1, they also mentioned larger machines at 24, 30 and 36 bits, based on the same design.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Datamation</italics>, Volume 5 Number 6 (November/December), pg. 24</extension><space/>During construction of the prototype PDP-1, some design work was carried out on a 24-bit PDP-2, and the 36-bit PDP-3. Although the PDP-2 never proceeded beyond the initial design, the PDP-3 found some interest and was designed in full.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/29461'>&quot;Preliminary Specifications: Programmed Data Processor Model Three (PDP-3)&quot;</link>, DEC, October 1960</extension><space/>Only one PDP-3 appears to have been built, in 1960, by the CIA's Scientific Engineering Institute (SEI) in<space/><link><target>Waltham, Massachusetts</target></link>. According to the limited information available, they used it to process radar cross section data for the<space/><link><target>Lockheed A-12</target></link><space/><link><target>reconnaissance aircraft</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Gordon Bell</target></link><space/>remembered that it was being used in<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link><space/>some time later, but could not recall who was using it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Posting in<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.decconnection.org/announcements.htm'>&quot;Announcements from The DEC Connection&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The DEC Connection</italics>, 14 January 2007</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 1962 DEC introduced the $65,000<space/><link><target>PDP-4</target></link>. The PDP-4 was similar to the PDP-1 and used a similar instruction set, but used slower memory and different packaging to lower the price. Like the PDP-1, about 54 PDP-4's were eventually sold, most to a customer base similar to the original PDP-1.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Bell,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/timeline/1962-1.htm'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1962, PDP-4&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1964 DEC introduced its new<space/><link><target>Flip Chip (trademark)</target><part>Flip Chip</part></link><space/>module design, and used it to re-implement the PDP-4 as the<space/><link><target>PDP-7</target></link>. The PDP-7 was introduced in December 1964, and about 120 were eventually produced.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Bell,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/timeline/1964-3.htm'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1964, PDP-7&quot;</link></extension><space/>An upgrade to the Flip Chip led to the R series, which in turn led to the PDP-7A in 1965.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Bell,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/timeline/1964-3.htm'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1965, PDP-7A&quot;</link></extension><space/>The PDP-7 is most famous as the original machine for the<space/><link><target>Unix</target></link><space/>operating system,<extension extension_name='ref'>Eric Steven Raymond,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.faqs.org/docs/artu/ch02s01.html'>&quot;Origins and History of Unix, 19691995&quot;</link>, 19 September 2003</extension><space/>and until the<space/><link><target>Interdata 8/32</target></link><space/>Unix only ran on DEC systems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fiedler198310"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">https://archive.org/stream/byte-magazine-1983-10/1983_10_BYTE_08-10_UNIX#page/n133/mode/2up<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Unix Tutorial / Part 3: Unix in the Microcomputer Marketplace<space/></arg><arg name="work">BYTE<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 1983<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 January 2015<space/></arg><arg name="author">Fiedler, Ryan<space/></arg><arg name="pages">132</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A more dramatic upgrade to the PDP-1 series was introduced in August 1966, the<space/><link><target>PDP-9</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Bell,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/timeline/1966-1.htm'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1965, PDP-9&quot;</link></extension><space/>The PDP-9 was instruction compatible with the PDP-4 and 7, but ran about twice as fast as the 7 and was intended to be used in larger deployments. At only $19,900 in 1968,<extension extension_name='ref'>DEC Advertisement,<space/><italics>Chemical and Engineering News</italics>, Volume 46 (1968), pg. 85</extension><space/>the PDP-9 was a big seller, eventually selling 445 machines, more than all of the earlier models combined.<extension extension_name='ref' name="miller452">Miller 1997, pg. 452</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Even while the PDP-9 was being introduced, its replacement was being designed, and was introduced as 1969's<space/><link><target>PDP-15</target></link>, which re-implemented the PDP-9 using<space/><link><target>integrated circuits</target></link><space/>in place of modules. Much faster than the PDP-9 even in basic form, the PDP-15 also included a<space/><link><target>floating point unit</target></link><space/>and a separate<space/><link><target>input/output</target></link><space/>processor for further performance gains. Over 400 PDP-15's were ordered in the first eight months of production, and production eventually amounted to 790 examples in 12 basic models.<extension extension_name='ref' name="miller452"></extension><space/>However, by this time other machines in DEC's lineup could fill the same niche at even lower price points, and the PDP-15 would be the last of the 18-bit series.</paragraph><heading level='3'>PDP-8 family</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>PDP-8</arg></template><link><target>File:PDP-8.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>A PDP-8 on display at the<space/><link><target>Smithsonian</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>National Museum of American History</target></link><space/>in Washington, D.C.. This example is from the first generation of PDP-8s, built with discrete transistors and later known as the ''Straight 8''.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1962,<space/><link><target>Lincoln Laboratory</target></link><space/>used a selection of System Building Blocks to implement a small 12-bit machine, and attached it to a variety of<space/><link><target>analog-to-digital</target></link><space/>(A to D)<space/><link><target>input/output</target></link><space/>(I/O) devices that made it easy to interface with various analog lab equipment. The<space/><link><target>LINC</target></link><space/>proved to attract intense interest in the scientific community, and has since been referred to as the first real<space/><link><target>minicomputer</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Wesley Clark,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historyofscience.com/G2I/timeline/index.php?id=1006'>&quot;The Linc, Perhaps the First Mini-Computer&quot;</link>, From Cave Paintings to the Internet</extension><space/>a machine that was small and inexpensive enough to be dedicated to a single task even in a small lab.</paragraph><paragraph>Seeing the success of the LINC, in 1963 DEC took the basic logic design but stripped away the extensive A to D systems to produce the<space/><link><target>PDP-5</target></link>. The new machine, the first outside the PDP-1 mould, was introduced at<space/><link><target>WESTCON</target></link><space/>on 11 August 1963. A 1964 ad expressed the main advantage of the PDP-5, &quot;Now you can own the PDP-5 computer for what a core memory alone used to cost: $27,000&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="faqpdp8"><link type='external' href='http://www.faqs.org/faqs/dec-faq/pdp8-models/section-1.html'>&quot;DEC FAQ: What is a PDP-8?&quot;</link></extension><space/>116 PDP-5s were produced until the lines were shut down in early 1967. Like the PDP-1 before it, the PDP-5 inspired a series of newer models based on the same basic design that would go on to be more famous than its parent.</paragraph><paragraph>On 22 March 1965, DEC introduced the<space/><link><target>PDP-8</target></link>, which replaced the PDP-5's modules with the new R-series modules using Flip Chips. The machine was re-packaged into a small tabletop case, which remains distinctive for its use of smoked plastic over the CPU which allowed one to easily see the wire-wrapped internals of the CPU. Sold standard with 4 kWords of 12-bit core memory and a<space/><link><target>Teletype Model 33</target></link><space/>ASR for basic input/output, the machine listed for only $18,000. The PDP-8 is referred to as the first<space/><italics>real</italics><space/><link><target>minicomputer</target></link><space/>because of its sub-$25,000 price.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sciencemuseum.org.uk/objects/computing_and_data_processing/1982-960.aspx'>&quot;DEC PDP-8 minicomputer, 1965&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The Science Museum</italics></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.computerhistory.org/internet_history/'>&quot;Internet History:1965&quot;</link>, Computer History Museum</extension><space/>Sales were, unsurprisingly, very strong, and helped by the fact that several competitors had just entered the market with machines aimed directly at the PDP-5's market space, which the PDP-8 trounced. This gave the company two years of unrestricted leadership,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Present</italics><space/>1978, pg. 7</extension><space/>and eventually 1450 &quot;straight eight&quot; machines were produced before it was replaced by newer implementations of the same basic design.<extension extension_name='ref' name="faqpdp8"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>DEC hit an even lower price-point with the PDP-8/S, the S for &quot;serial&quot;. As the name implies the /S used a serial arithmetic unit, which was much slower but reduced costs so much that the system sold for under $10,000.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Present</italics><space/>1978, pg. 8</extension><space/>DEC then used the new PDP-8 design as the basis for a new LINC, the two-processor<space/><link><target>LINC-8</target></link>. The LINC-8 used one PDP-8 CPU and a separate LINC CPU, and included instructions to switch from one to the other. This allowed customers to run their existing LINC programs, or &quot;upgrade&quot; to the PDP-8, all in software. Although not a huge seller, 142 LINC-8s were sold starting at $38,500.<extension extension_name='ref' name="faqpdp8"></extension><space/>Like the original LINC to PDP-5 evolution, the LINC-8 was then modified into the single-processor<space/><link><target>PDP-12</target></link>, adding another 1000 machines to the 12-bit family.<extension extension_name='ref' name="faqpdp8"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="miller456">Miller 1997, pg. 456</extension><space/>Newer circuitry designs led to the PDP-8/I and PDP-8/L in 1968.<extension extension_name='ref' name="present10"><italics>Present</italics><space/>1978, pg. 10</extension><space/>In 1975, one year after an agreement between Digital and<space/><link><target>Intersil</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Intersil 6100</target></link><space/>chip was launched, effectively a PDP-8 on a chip. This was a way to allow PDP-8 software to be run even after the official end-of-life announcement for the Digital PDP-8 product line.</paragraph><heading level='3'>PDP-10 family</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>PDP-10</arg></template><link><target>File:KA10 mod end.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A &quot;B&quot; (blue) series Flip Chip module containing nine transistors, 1971</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>While the PDP-5 introduced a lower-cost line, 1963's<space/><link><target>PDP-6</target></link><space/>was intended to take DEC into the<space/><link><target>Mainframe computer</target><part>mainframe</part></link><space/>market with a<space/><link><target>36-bit</target></link><space/>machine. However, the PDP-6 proved to be a &quot;hard sell&quot; with customers, as it offered few obvious advantages over similar machines from the better-established vendors like<space/><link><target>IBM</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Honeywell</target></link>, in spite of its low cost around $300,000. Only 23 were sold,<extension extension_name='ref' name="miller457">Miller 1997, pg. 457</extension><space/>or 26 depending on the source,<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Bell,<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/~gbell/Digital/timeline/1964-1.htm'>&quot;DIGITAL Computing Timeline, 1964, PDP-6&quot;</link></extension><space/>and unlike other models the low sales meant the PDP-6 was not improved with successor versions. However, the PDP-6 is historically important as the platform that introduced &quot;Monitor&quot;, an early<space/><link><target>time-sharing</target></link><space/><link><target>operating system</target></link><space/>that would evolve into the widely used<space/><link><target>TOPS-10</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bitsavers.org/pdf/dec/pdp6/PDP-6_TimsharingBroch.pdf'>&quot;PDP-6 Timesharing Software&quot;</link>, DEC Publication F-61B</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When newer Flip Chip packaging allowed the PDP-6 to be re-implemented at a much lower cost, DEC took the opportunity to refine their 36-bit design, introducing the<space/><link><target>PDP-10</target></link><space/>in 1968. The PDP-10 was as much a success as the PDP-6 was a commercial failure; about 700 mainframe PDP-10s were sold before production ended in 1984.<extension extension_name='ref' name="miller457"></extension><space/>The PDP-10 was widely used in university settings, and thus was the basis of many advances in computing and operating system design during the 1970s. DEC later re-branded all of the models in the 36-bit series as the &quot;DECsystem-10&quot;, and PDP-10s are generally referred to by the model of their CPU, starting with the &quot;KA10&quot;, soon upgraded to the &quot;KI10&quot; (I:Integrated circuit); then to &quot;KL10&quot; (L:Large scale integration<space/><link><target>Emitter-coupled logic</target><part>ECL logic</part></link>); also the &quot;KS10&quot; (S: Small<space/><link><target>Computer form factor</target><part>form factor</part></link>). Unified product line upgrades produced the compatible<space/><link><target>DECSYSTEM-20</target></link>, along with a<space/><link><target>TOPS-20</target></link><space/>operating system that included<space/><link><target>virtual memory</target></link><space/>support.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The Jupiter Project was supposed to continue the mainframe product line into the future by using &quot;gate arrays&quot; with an innovative Air Mover Cooling System, coupled with a built-in floating point processing engine called &quot;FBOX&quot;. The design was intended for a top tier scientific computing niche, yet the critical performance measurement was based upon COBOL compilation which did not fully utilize the primary design features of Jupiter technology.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template><space/>When the Jupiter Project was cancelled in 1983, some of the engineers adapted aspects of the 36-bit design into a forthcoming 32-bit design, releasing the high-end VAX8600 in 1985.</paragraph><heading level='3'>DECtape</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>DECtape</arg></template>One of the most unusual peripherals produced for the PDP-10 was the<space/><link><target>DECtape</target></link>. The DECtape was a length of special 3/4-inch wide magnetic tape wound on 5-inch reels. The recording format was a highly-reliable redundant 10-track design using fixed-length numbered data &quot;blocks&quot; organized into a standard file structure, including a directory. Files could be written, read, changed, and deleted on a DECtape as though it were a disk drive. For greater efficiency, the DECtape drive could read and write to a DECtape in both directions.</paragraph><paragraph>In fact, some PDP-10 systems had no disks at all, using DECtapes alone for their primary data storage. The DECtape was also widely used on other PDP models, since it was much easier to use than hand-loading multiple paper tapes. Primitive early time-sharing systems could use DECtapes as system devices and<space/><link><target>swapping device</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Although superior to paper tape, DECtapes were relatively slow, and were supplanted once reliable disk drives became affordable.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Magnetic disk storage</heading><paragraph>DEC was both a manufacturer and a buyer of magnetic disk storage, offering more than 100 different models of<space/><link><target>hard disk drive</target></link><space/>(HDD) and<space/><link><target>floppy disk drive</target></link><space/>(FDD) during its existence.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ultimate.com/phil/pdp10/dec.disks'>DEC disk history</link></extension><space/>In the 1970s, it was the single largest<space/><link><target>OEM</target></link><space/>purchaser of HDDs, procuring from<space/><link><target>Diablo Data Systems</target><part>Diablo</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Control_Data_Corporation#Magnetic_Peripherals_Inc.</target><part>Control Data Corporation</part></link>, Information Storage Systems, and<space/><link><target>Memorex</target></link>, among others.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>DEC's first internally-developed HDD was the RS08, a 256 kWord fixed-head contact-start-stop drive using plated media; it shipped in 1969.</paragraph><paragraph>Beginning in the 1970s, DEC moved first its HDD manufacturing and then its mass storage development labs to<space/><link><target>Colorado Springs</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SaviersOH"><link type='external' href='http://archive.computerhistory.org/resources/access/text/2012/08/102746014-05-01-acc.pdf'>Oral History of Grant Saviers</link>, Computer History Museum, May 17, 2011</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>DEC pioneered a number of HDD technologies, including sampled data servos (RL01, 1977) and serial HDD interfaces (<link><target>Standard Disk Interconnect</target></link>, 1983). The last internally-developed disk drive family (RA9x series) used plated media, departing from the HDD industry trend to carbon overcoated sputtered media. DEC designated a $400 million investment to bring this product line into production.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SaviersOH"></extension><space/>The RA92 (1.5 GB) was introduced in 1992, using a 14-inch platter.</paragraph><paragraph>DEC purchased its FDDs from OEMs such as<space/><link><target>Shugart Associates</target></link>, Toshiba, and Sony.</paragraph><heading level='3'>PDP-11</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>PDP-11</arg></template><link><target>File:Digital PDP11-IMG 1498 cropped.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>PDP-11/20, the first model of PDP-11 on display at<space/><link><target>cole Polytechnique Fdrale de Lausanne</target><part>EPFL</part></link>.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link><space/>16-bit computer was designed in a crash program by Harold McFarland,<space/><link><target>Gordon Bell</target></link>, Roger Cady, and others.<extension extension_name='ref' name="birth">Larry McGowan,<space/><link type='external' href='http://hampage.hu/pdp-11/birth.html'>&quot;How the PDP-11 Was Born (according to Larry McGowan)</link>, 19 August 1998</extension><space/>The project was able to leap forward in design with the arrival of Harold McFarland, who had been researching 16-bit designs at<space/><link><target>Carnegie Mellon University</target></link>. One of his simpler designs became the PDP-11, although when they first viewed the proposal, management was not impressed and almost cancelled it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="birth"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In particular, the new design did not include many of the<space/><link><target>addressing mode</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that were intended to make programs smaller in memory, a technique that was widely used on other DEC machines and<space/><link><target>Complex instruction set computing</target><part>CISC</part></link><space/>designs in general. This would mean the machine would spend more time accessing memory, which would slow it down. However, the machine also extended the idea of multiple &quot;General Purpose Registers&quot; (GPRs), which gave the programmer flexibility to use these high-speed memory caches as they needed, potentially addressing the performance issues.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:PDP-11-34 unibus slots.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>PDP-11/34 top view, showing the<space/><link><target>:en:Unibus</target><part>Unibus</part></link><space/>slots with the CPU,<space/><link><target>:en:RK05</target><part>DK drive controller</part></link><space/>and other options.</part></link>A major advance in the PDP-11 design was Digital's<space/><link><target>Unibus</target></link>, which supported all peripherals through<space/><link><target>Memory-mapped I/O</target><part>memory mapping</part></link>. This allowed a new device to be added easily, generally only requiring plugging a hardware interface board into the backplane and possibly adding a jumper to the<space/><link><target>wire wrap</target><trail>ped</trail></link><space/>backplane, and then installing software that read and wrote to the mapped memory to control it. The relative ease of interfacing spawned a huge market of third party add-ons for the PDP-11, which made the machine even more useful.</paragraph><paragraph>The combination of architectural innovations proved superior to competitors and the &quot;11&quot; architecture was soon the industry leader, propelling DEC back to a strong market position. The design was later expanded to allow<space/><link><target>Paging</target><part>paged physical memory</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>memory protection</target></link><space/>features, useful for<space/><link><target>Computer multitasking</target><part>multitasking</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>time-sharing</target></link>. Some models supported separate instruction and data spaces for an effective virtual address size of 128 kB within a physical address size of up to 4 MB. Smaller PDP-11s, implemented as single-chip CPUs, continued to be produced until 1996, by which time over 600,000 had been sold.<extension extension_name='ref' name="miller452"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:RT-11 help.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>RT-11</target></link><space/>interactive help screen displayed on a<space/><link><target>VT-100</target></link><space/>display terminal.</part></link>The PDP-11 supported several operating systems, including<space/><link><target>Bell Labs</target></link>' new<space/><link><target>Unix</target></link><space/>operating system as well as DEC's<space/><link><target>DOS-11</target></link>,<space/><link><target>RSX-11</target></link>, IAS,<space/><link><target>RT-11</target></link>, DSM-11, and<space/><link><target>RSTS/E</target></link>. Many early PDP-11 applications were developed using standalone paper-tape utilities. DOS-11 was the PDP-11's first disk operating system, but was soon supplanted by more capable systems. RSX provided a general-purpose<space/><link><target>computer multitasking</target><part>multitasking</part></link><space/>environment and supported a wide variety of<space/><link><target>programming language</target><trail>s</trail></link>. IAS was a<space/><link><target>time-sharing</target></link><space/>version of RSX-11D. Both RSTS and Unix were time-sharing systems available to educational institutions at little or no cost, and these PDP-11 systems were destined to be the &quot;sandbox&quot; for a rising generation of engineers and computer scientists. Large numbers of PDP-11/70s were deployed in telecommunications and industrial control applications.<space/><link><target>AT&amp;T Corporation</target></link><space/>became DEC's largest customer.</paragraph><paragraph>RT-11 provided a practical real-time operating system in minimal memory, allowing the PDP-11 to continue Digital's critical role as a computer supplier for<space/><link><target>embedded system</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Historically, RT-11 also served as the inspiration for many microcomputer OS's, as these were generally being written by programmers who cut their teeth on one of the many PDP-11 models. For example,<space/><link><target>CP/M</target></link><space/>used a command syntax similar to RT-11's, and even retained the awkward<space/><link><target>Peripheral Interchange Program</target><part>PIP</part></link><space/>program used to copy data from one computer device to another. As another historical footnote, DEC's use of &quot;/&quot; for &quot;switches&quot; (command-line options) would lead to the adoption of &quot;\&quot; for pathnames in<space/><link><target>MS-DOS</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Microsoft Windows</target></link><space/>as opposed to &quot;/&quot; in<space/><link><target>Unix</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="afu-faq"><link type='external' href='http://www.netwhatever.com/faq/inicio.html#queIII15'>alt.folklore.computers List of Frequently Asked Questions</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The evolution of the PDP-11 followed earlier systems, eventually including a single-user deskside personal computer form, the MicroPDP-11. In total, around 600,000 PDP-11s of all models were sold. and a wide variety of third-party peripheral vendors had also entered the computer product ecosystem.</paragraph><heading level='3'>VAX</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>VAX</arg></template>In 1976, DEC decided to extend the<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link><space/>architecture to<space/><link><target>32 bit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>while adding a complete<space/><link><target>virtual memory</target></link><space/>system to the simple paging and memory protection of the PDP-11. The result was the<space/><link><target>VAX</target></link><space/>architecture, where VAX stands for Virtual Address eXtension (from 16 to 32 bits). The first computer to use a VAX CPU was the<space/><link><target>VAX-11/780</target></link>, which DEC referred to as a<space/><italics><link><target>superminicomputer</target></link></italics>. Although it was not the first 32-bit minicomputer, the VAX-11/780's combination of features, price, and marketing almost immediately propelled it to a leadership position in the market after it was released in 1978. VAX systems were so successful that in 1983, DEC canceled its<space/><link><target>Jupiter project</target></link>, which had been intended to build a successor to the PDP-10 mainframe, and instead focused on promoting the VAX as the single computer architecture for the company.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Electronic Business</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cahners</arg><arg name="page"><space/>76<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Supporting the VAX's success was the<space/><link><target>VT52</target></link>, one of the most successful<space/><link><target>Computer terminal</target><part>smart terminals</part></link>. Building on earlier less successful models (the<space/><link><target>VT05</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>VT50</target></link>), the VT52 was the first terminal that did everything one might want in a single chassis. The VT52 was followed by the even more successful<space/><link><target>VT100</target></link><space/>and its follow-ons, making DEC one of the largest terminal vendors in the industry. With the VT series, DEC could now offer a complete top-to-bottom system from computer to all peripherals, which formerly required collecting the required devices from different suppliers.</paragraph><paragraph>The VAX processor architecture and family of systems evolved and expanded through several generations during the 1980s, culminating in the<space/><link><target>NVAX</target></link><space/><link><target>microprocessor</target></link><space/>implementation and<space/><link><target>VAX 7000/10000</target></link><space/>series in the early 1990s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nvax"><link type='external' href='http://simh.trailing-edge.com/semi/nvax.html'>DEC Microprocessors: NVAX (1991)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early microcomputers</heading><paragraph>When a DEC research group demonstrated two prototype<space/><link><target>microcomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in 1974before the debut of the<space/><link><target>MITS Altair</target></link>Olsen chose to not proceed with the project. The company similarly rejected another personal computer proposal in 1977.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ahl198403"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">https://archive.org/stream/creativecomputing-1984-03/Creative_Computing_v10_n03_1984_Mar#page/n39/mode/2up<space/></arg><arg name="title">Digital<space/></arg><arg name="work">Creative Computing<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 1984<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">6 February 2015<space/></arg><arg name="author">Ahl, David H.<space/></arg><arg name="pages">38–41<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">David H. Ahl</arg></template></extension><space/>At the time these systems were of limited utility, and Olsen famously derided them in 1977, stating &quot;There is no reason for any individual to have a computer in his home.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Olsen later claimed he was referring to home automation, see<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.snopes.com/quotes/kenolsen.asp'>&quot;Ken Olsen&quot;</link></extension><space/>Unsurprisingly, DEC did not put much effort into the microcomputer area in the early days of the market. Interestingly in 1977, the<space/><link><target>Heathkit H11</target></link><space/>was announced; a PDP-11 in kit form. At the beginning of the 1980s, DEC built the<space/><link><target>VT180</target></link><space/>(codenamed &quot;Robin&quot;), which was a<space/><link><target>VT100</target></link><space/>terminal with an added<space/><link><target>Zilog Z80</target><part>Z80</part></link>-based microcomputer running<space/><link><target>CP/M</target></link>, but this product was initially available only to DEC employees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Croxton"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Croxton</arg><arg name="first">Greg</arg><arg name="title">DEC Robin (VT-180) & documentation</arg><arg name="url">http://www.digibarn.com/collections/systems/dec-robin/</arg><arg name="work">DigiBarn Computer Museum</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 March 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It was only after IBM had successfully launched the<space/><link><target>IBM PC</target></link><space/>in 1981 that DEC responded with their own systems. In 1982, Digital introduced not one, but three incompatible machines which were each tied to different<space/><link><target>Proprietary hardware</target><part>proprietary</part></link><space/>architectures. The first, the<space/><link><target>DEC Professional (computer)</target><part>DEC Professional</part></link>, was based on the PDP-11/23 (and later, the 11/73) running the<space/><link><target>RSX-11</target><part>RSX-11M+</part></link><space/>derived, but menu-driven,<space/><link><target>P/OS</target></link><space/>(&quot;Professional Operating System&quot;). This DEC machine easily outperformed the PC, but was more expensive than, and completely incompatible with IBM PC hardware and software, offering far fewer options for customizing a system.</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike CP/M and DOS microcomputers, every copy of every program for the Professional had to be provided with a unique key for the particular machine and CPU for which it was bought. At that time this was mainstream policy, because most computer software was either bought from the company that built the computer or custom-constructed for one client. However, the emerging third-party software industry disregarded the PDP-11/Professional line and concentrated on other microcomputers where distribution was easier. At DEC itself, creating better programs for the Professional was not a priority, perhaps from fear of cannibalizing the PDP-11 line. As a result, the Professional was a superior machine, running inferior software.<extension extension_name='ref'>Katan, M.B., Scholte, B.A., 1984. Application of a Professional 350 in a university department - a consumers report, in: Proceedings Digital Equipment Computer Users Society. Amsterdam, p. 368.</extension><space/>In addition, a new user would have to learn an awkward, slow, and inflexible menu-based user interface which appeared to be radically different from<space/><link><target>PC DOS</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>CP/M</target></link>, which were more commonly used on the 8080 and 8088 based microcomputers of the time. A second offering, the<space/><link><target>DECmate</target><part>DECmate II</part></link><space/>was the latest version of the PDP-8 based word processors, but not really suited to general computing, nor competitive with<space/><link><target>Wang Laboratories</target></link>' popular word processing equipment.</paragraph><paragraph>The most popular early DEC microcomputer was the dual-processor (Z80 and 8088)<space/><link><target>Rainbow 100</target></link>,<template><target>r</target><arg>ahl198403</arg></template><space/>which ran the 8-bit<space/><link><target>CP/M</target></link><space/>operating system on the Z80 and the 16-bit<space/><link><target>CP/M-86</target></link><space/>operating system on the<space/><link><target>Intel 8086</target></link><space/>processor. It could also run a<space/><link><target>UNIX System III</target></link><space/>implementation called<space/><link><target>VENIX</target></link>. Applications from standard CP/M could be re-compiled for the Rainbow, but by this time users were expecting custom-built (pre-compiled binary) applications such as<space/><link><target>Lotus 1-2-3</target></link>, which was eventually ported along with<space/><link><target>MS-DOS</target></link><space/>2.0 and introduced in late 1983. Although the Rainbow generated some press, it was unsuccessful due to its high price and lack of marketing and sales support.<extension extension_name='ref' name="rainbow-faq"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Rainbow 100 Frequently Asked Questions</arg><arg name="url">http://rainbow-100.com/faq/question/1/</arg><arg name="work">Drive W</arg><arg name="publisher">Approximatrix, LLC</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 December 2010</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg></template></extension><space/>By late 1983 IBM was outselling DEC's personal computers by more than ten to one.<template><target>r</target><arg>ahl198403</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The way the DEC standard RX50<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stravers"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Stravers</arg><arg name="first">Kees</arg><arg name="title">The RX50 FAQ</arg><arg name="url">http://users.bart.nl/users/pb0aia/vax/rx50.html</arg><arg name="work">Kees's VAX page</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 March 2011</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>floppy disk drive</target></link><space/>supported DEC's initial offerings seemed to encapsulate their approach to the personal computer market. Although the mechanical drive hardware was nearly identical to other<space/><link><target>5.25&quot; floppy disk</target><part>5&amp;frac14;&quot; floppy disk</part></link><space/>drives available on competing systems,<extension extension_name='ref' name="GeekHist"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">"Geek Historian"</arg><arg name="title">MP01482 RX50 EngrDrws Jul82</arg><arg name="url">http://www.scribd.com/doc/881906/Tech-History-Digital-Equipment-Corporation-MP01482-RX50-EngrDrws-Jul82</arg><arg name="work">Tech History – Digital Equipment Corporation</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 March 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>DEC sought to differentiate their product by using a proprietary disk format for the data written on the disk. The DEC format had a higher capacity for data, but the RX50 drives were incompatible with other PC floppy drives. This required DEC owners to buy higher-priced, specially formatted floppy media, which was harder to obtain through standard distribution channels. DEC attempted to enforce exclusive control over its floppy media sales by<space/><link><target>copyright</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>its proprietary disk format, and requiring a negotiated license agreement and royalty payments from anybody selling compatible media. The proprietary data format meant that RX50 floppies were not interchangeable with other PC floppies, further isolating DEC products from the developing de facto standard PC market. Hardware hackers and DEC enthusiasts eventually reverse-engineered the RX50 format,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stravers"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Wilson</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">PUTR.COM V2.01</arg><arg name="url">http://www.dbit.com/pub/putr/</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 March 2011</arg></template><space/>This relatively recent work is a well-developed example of programs to enhance interchange of data between DEC formatted media and standard PC systems</extension><space/>but the damage had already been done, in terms of market confusion and isolation.</paragraph><paragraph>A further system was introduced in 1986 as the<space/><link><target>VAXmate</target></link>, which included<space/><link><target>Microsoft Windows 1.0</target></link><space/>and used<space/><link><target>VAX/VMS</target></link>-based file and print servers along with integration into DEC's own<space/><link><target>DECnet</target></link>-family, providing LAN/WAN connection from PC to mainframe or supermini. The VAXmate replaced the Rainbow, and in its standard form was the first widely marketed<space/><link><target>diskless workstation</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Networking and clusters</heading><paragraph>In 1984, DEC launched its first 10 Mbit/s<space/><link><target>Ethernet</target></link>. Ethernet allowed scalable networking, and<space/><link><target>VAXcluster</target></link><space/>allowed scalable computing. Combined with<space/><link><target>DECnet</target></link><space/>and Ethernet-based terminal servers (<link><target>Local Area Transport</target><part>LAT</part></link>), DEC had produced a networked storage architecture which allowed them to compete directly with IBM. Ethernet replaced<space/><link><target>token ring</target></link>, and went on to become the dominant networking model in use today.</paragraph><paragraph>In September 1985, DEC became the<space/><link><target>List of the oldest currently registered Internet domain names</target><part>fifth company to register</part></link><space/>a<space/><link><target>.com</target></link><space/><link><target>domain name</target></link><space/>(dec.com).</paragraph><paragraph>Along with the hardware and protocols, DEC also introduced the<space/><link><target>VAXcluster</target></link><space/>concept, which allowed several VAX machines to be tied together into a single larger storage system. VAXclusters allowed a DEC-based company to scale their services by adding new machines to the cluster at any time, as opposed to buying a faster machine and using that to replace a slower one. The flexibility this offered was compelling, and allowed DEC to attack high-end markets formerly out of their reach.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Diversification</heading><paragraph>Although their microcomputer efforts were eventually considered failures, the PDP-11 and VAX lines continued to sell in record numbers. Better yet, DEC was competing very well against the market leader, IBM, taking an estimated $2&amp;nbsp;billion away from them in the mid-80s. In 1986, Digital's profits rose 38% when the rest of the computer industry experienced a downturn, and by 1987 the company was threatening IBM's number one position in the computer industry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="companyhistory"><link type='external' href='http://www.answers.com/topic/digital-equipment-corporation'>&quot;Digital Equipment Corporation&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>International Directory of Company Histories</italics>, Volume 6, St. James Press, 1992</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At its peak, Digital was the second-largest computer company in the world, with over 100,000 employees. It was during this time that the company branched out development into a wide variety of projects that were far from its core business in computer equipment. The company invested heavily in custom software. In the 1970s and earlier most software was custom-written to serve a specific task, but by the 1980s the introduction of<space/><link><target>relational databases</target></link><space/>and similar systems allowed powerful software to be built in a modular fashion, potentially saving enormous amounts of development time. Software companies like<space/><link><target>Oracle Corporation</target><part>Oracle</part></link><space/>became the new darlings of the industry, and DEC started their own efforts in every &quot;hot&quot; niche, in some cases several projects for the same niche. Some of these products competed with DEC's own partners, notably<space/><link><target>Oracle Rdb</target><part>Rdb</part></link><space/>which competed with Oracle's products on the VAX, part of a major partnership only a few years earlier.</paragraph><paragraph>Although many of these products were well designed, most of them were DEC-only or DEC-centric, and customers frequently ignored them and used third-party products instead. This problem was further exacerbated by Olsen's aversion to traditional advertising and his belief that well-engineered products would sell themselves. Hundreds of millions of dollars were spent on these projects, at the same time that workstations using<space/><link><target>RISC</target></link><space/>microprocessors were starting to approach VAX CPUs in performance.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Faltering in the market</heading><paragraph>As microprocessors continued to improve in the 1980s, it soon became clear that the next generation would offer performance and features equal to the best of DECs low-end minicomputer lineup. Worse, the<space/><link><target>Berkeley RISC</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>MIPS architecture</target><part>Stanford MIPS</part></link><space/>designs were aiming to introduce 32-bit designs that would outperform the fastest members of the VAX family, DEC's<space/><link><target>cash cow</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>John L. Hennessy</arg><arg name="author2">David A. Patterson<space/></arg><arg name="author3">David Goldberg<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Computer Architecture: A Quantitative Approach</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Morgan Kaufmann</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-55860-596-1</arg><arg name="page"><space/>152<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Constrained by the huge success of their<space/><link><target>VAX</target></link>/<link><target>OpenVMS</target><part>VMS</part></link><space/>products, which followed the proprietary model, the company was very late to respond to these threats. In the early 1990s, DEC found its sales faltering and its first layoffs followed. The company that created the minicomputer, a dominant networking technology, and arguably the first computers for personal use, had abandoned the &quot;low end&quot; market, whose dominance with the PDP-8 had built the company in a previous generation. Decisions about what to do about this threat led to infighting within the company that seriously delayed their responses.</paragraph><paragraph>One group suggested that every possible development in the industry be poured into the construction of a new VAX family that would leapfrog the performance of the existing machines. This would limit the market erosion in the top-end segment, where<space/><link><target>profit margin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were maximized and DEC could continue to survive as a minicomputer vendor. This line of thought led, eventually, to the<space/><link><target>VAX 9000</target></link><space/>series, which were plagued with problems when they were first introduced in October 1989, already two years late.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Markoff, &quot;Market Place; Digital Finally Follows a Trend&quot;,<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, 16 July 1990</extension><space/>The problems took so long to work out, and the prices of the systems were so high, that DEC was never able to make the line the success they hoped.</paragraph><paragraph>Others within the company felt that the proper response was to introduce their own RISC designs and use those to build new machines. However, there was little official support for these efforts, and no less than four separate small projects ran in parallel at various labs around the US. Eventually these were gathered into the<space/><link><target>DEC PRISM</target></link><space/>project, which delivered a credible 32-bit design with some unique features allowing it to serve as the basis of a new VAX implementation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dileep Bhandarkar et al.,<space/><link type='external' href='http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber=63667'>&quot;High performance issue oriented architecture&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Proceedings of Compcon Spring '90</italics>, pg. 153160</extension><space/>Infighting with teams dedicated to DEC's big iron made funding difficult, and the design was not finalized until April 1988, and then cancelled shortly thereafter.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mark Smotherman,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cs.clemson.edu/~mark/prism.html'>&quot;PRISM (Parallel Reduced Instruction Set Machine)&quot;</link>, Clemson University School of Computing, October 2009</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another group concluded that new<space/><link><target>workstation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>like those from<space/><link><target>Sun Microsystems</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Silicon Graphics</target></link><space/>would take away a large part of DEC's existing customer base before the new VAX systems could address the issues, and that the company needed its own Unix workstation as soon as possible. Fed up with slow progress on both the RISC and VAX fronts, a group in<space/><link><target>Palo Alto, California</target><part>Palo Alto</part></link><space/>started a<space/><link><target>skunkworks project</target></link><space/>to introduce their own systems. Selecting the MIPS processor, which was widely available, introducing the new<space/><link><target>DECstation</target></link><space/>series with the model 3100 on 11 January 1989.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas Furlong et al.,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dtjcd.vmsresource.org.uk/pdfs/dtj_v02-02_1990.pdf'>&quot;Development of the DECstation 3100&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Digital Technical Journal</italics>, Volume 2 Number 2 (Spring 1990), pg. 8488</extension><space/>These systems would see some success in the market, but were later displaced by similar models running the Alpha.</paragraph><heading level='3'>32-bit MIPS and 64-bit Alpha systems</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:AlphaServer-2100-guts.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Inside view of AlphaServer 2100.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Eventually, in 1992, DEC launched the<space/><link><target>Alpha 21064</target><part>DECchip 21064</part></link><space/>processor, the first implementation of their<space/><link><target>DEC Alpha</target><part>Alpha</part></link><space/><link><target>instruction set architecture</target></link>, initially named Alpha&amp;nbsp;AXP (the &quot;AXP&quot; was a &quot;non-acronym&quot; and was later dropped). This was a<space/><link><target>64-bit</target></link><space/><link><target>RISC</target></link><space/>architecture (as opposed to the 32-bit<space/><link><target>Complex instruction set computer</target><part>CISC</part></link><space/>architecture used in the VAX) and one of the first &quot;pure&quot; (not an extension of an earlier 32-bit architecture) 64-bit<space/><link><target>microprocessor</target></link><space/>architectures and implementations. The Alpha offered class-leading performance at its launch, and subsequent variants continued to do so into the 2000s. An AlphaServer SC45 supercomputer was still ranked No.&amp;nbsp;6 in the world in November 2004.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.top500.org/lists/2004/11'>www.top500.org Top 10 Supercomputing Sites, November 2004</link></extension><space/>Alpha-based computers (the DEC AXP series, later the<space/><link><target>AlphaStation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>AlphaServer</target></link><space/>series) superseded both the VAX and MIPS architecture in DEC's product lines, and could run<space/><link><target>OpenVMS</target></link>, DEC<space/><link><target>OSF/1</target></link><space/>AXP (later, Digital Unix or Tru64 UNIX) and Microsoft's then-new operating system,<space/><link><target>Windows NT</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1998, following the takeover by Compaq Computers, a decision was made that Microsoft would no longer support and develop Windows NT for the Alpha series computers, a decision that was seen as the beginning of the end for the Alpha series computers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>StrongARM</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>StrongARM</arg></template>In the mid-1990s, Digital Semiconductor collaborated with<space/><link><target>ARM Limited</target></link><space/>to produce the<space/><link><target>StrongARM</target></link><space/>microprocessor. This was based in part on ARM7 and in part on DEC technologies like Alpha, and was targeted at<space/><link><target>embedded system</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and portable devices. It was highly compatible with the ARMv4 architecture and was very successful, competing effectively against rivals such as the<space/><link><target>SuperH</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>MIPS architecture</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>portable digital assistant</target></link><space/>market.<space/><link><target>Microsoft</target></link><space/>subsequently dropped support for these other architectures in their<space/><link><target>Pocket PC</target></link><space/>platform. In 1997, as part of a lawsuit settlement, the<space/><link><target>StrongARM</target></link><space/>intellectual property was sold to<space/><link><target>Intel</target></link>. They continued to produce<space/><link><target>StrongARM</target></link>, as well as developing it into the<space/><link><target>XScale</target></link><space/>architecture. Intel subsequently sold this business to<space/><link><target>Marvell Technology Group</target></link><space/>in 2006.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Video and Interactive Information Server</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Video-on-Demand</target></link><space/>project at DEC started in 1992, following<space/><link><target>Ken Olsen</target></link>s retirement. At the time the company was rapidly downsizing under<space/><link><target>Robert Palmer (computer businessman)</target><part>Robert Palmer</part></link>, and it was difficult to gain funding for any new project. DECs Interactive Video Information Server architecture gained traction and excelled over those of other companies, in that it was highly scalable, using a gateway to set up interactive video delivery sessions on large numbers of video and information servers. Initially high-end VAXes were used, then Alphas.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Free Library, Digital Equipment Corporation enters Video-on-demand market. October 19, 1993.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>IGI Consulting, Inc, Video Dialtone &amp; Video-on-Demand, Market &amp; Technology Assessment Study, 1994.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The scalability feature allowed it to win contracts for many of the video-on-demand trials in the 1993-1995 timeframe, since the system could theoretically accommodate unlimited interactive video streams and other non-video content.<extension extension_name='ref'>Daniel Minoli, Video Dialtone Technology : Digital Video over ADSL, HFC, FTTC, and ATM, Mcgraw Hill, Inc., 1995.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The design was proposed and incorporated into the<space/><link><target>MPEG2</target></link><space/>international standard.<extension extension_name='ref'>ISO/IEC 13818-1, part 6,<space/><link><target>DSM-CC</target></link><space/>TC1/SC29/WG11, Digital Storage Media Command &amp; Control, November 1994.</extension><space/>Its<space/><link><target>object-oriented</target></link><space/>interface became the mandatory user-to user core interface in DSM-CC, widely used in video stream and file delivery for MPEG-2 compliant systems.</paragraph><paragraph>Commercially, DECs Digital and Interactive Information System was used by Adlink to distribute advertising to over 2 million subscribers.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Free Library, Adlink selects Digital to implement new video ad insertion system, January 11, 1995.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Borko Furht, Multimedia Technologies and Applications for the 21st Century: Visions of World Experts, Springer Science &amp; Business Media, Nov 30, 1997.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Designing solutions</heading><paragraph>Beyond DECsystem-10/20, PDP, VAX and Alpha, Digital was well respected for its communication subsystem designs, such as Ethernet, DNA (<link><target>DIGITAL Network Architecture</target></link><space/>predominantly DECnet products), DSA (Digital Storage Architecture disks/tapes/controllers), and its &quot;dumb terminal&quot; subsystems including VT100 and DECserver products.<extension extension_name='ref'>For in-depth articles regarding Digital technologies, refer to the archived<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hpl.hp.com/hpjournal/dtj/past.htm'>Digital Technical Journal</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Final years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Digital Equipment Corporation 1993 logo.png</target><part>New 1993 corporate logo</part><part>thumb</part></link>At its peak in the late 1980s, Digital had $14 billion in sales and ranked among the most profitable companies in the US. With its strong staff of engineers, Digital was expected to usher in the age of personal computers, but the autocratic and trend-resistant Mr. Olsen was openly skeptical of the desktop machines, saying the personal computer will fall flat on its face in business, and regarding them as toys used for playing video games. Digital's fortunes declined after missing out on some critical market shifts, particularly toward the personal computer. The board forced Olsen to resign as president in July 1992.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2011/02/08/technology/business-computing/08olsen.html?_r=0'></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In June 1992,<space/><link><target>Ken Olsen</target></link><space/>was replaced by<space/><link><target>Robert Palmer (computer businessman)</target><part>Robert Palmer</part></link><space/>as the company's president. Digital's board of directors also granted Palmer the title of chief executive officer (&quot;CEO&quot;), a title that had never been used during Digital's 35-year existence. Palmer had joined DEC in 1985 to run Semiconductor Engineering and Manufacturing. His relentless campaign to be CEO, and success with the Alpha microprocessor family, made him a candidate to succeed Olsen. At the same time a more modern logo was designed<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Ned Batchelder</target></link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://vt100.net/dec/logo'>Vt100.net</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Palmer restructured Digital into nine business units that reported directly to him. Nonetheless, Digital continued to suffer record losses in recent quarters, including a loss of $260.5 million for the quarter that ended on September 30, 1992. It reported $2.8 billion in losses for its fiscal year 1992. January 5, 1993 saw the retirement of John F. Smith as senior vice president of operations, the second in command at Digital, and his position was not filled. A 35-year company veteran, he had joined Digital in 1958 as the company's 12th employee, passing up a chance to work for Bell Laboratories in New Jersey to work for Digital, then a tiny start-up company in the mill town of<space/><link><target>Maynard, Massachusetts</target></link>. Smith rose to become one of the three senior vice presidents in 1987 and was widely considered among the potential successors to Ken Olsen, especially when Smith was appointed chief operating officer in 1991. Smith became a corporate spokesman on financial issues, and had filled in at trouble spots for which Olsen ordered more attention. However Smith was passed over in favor of Palmer when Olsen was forced to resign in July 1992, though Smith stayed on for a time to help turn around the struggling company.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/1993/01/06/business/company-news-no-2-officer-retires-at-digital-equipment.html'>COMPANY NEWS; No. 2 Officer Retires at Digital Equipment - New York Times</link>. Nytimes.com (1993-01-06). Retrieved on 2014-04-12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In June 1993, Palmer and several of his top lieutenants presented their reorganization plans to applause from the board of directors, and several weeks later Digital reported its first profitable quarter in several years. However, on April 15, 1994, Digital reported a loss of $183 millionthree to four times higher than the loss many people on Wall Street had predicted (compared with a loss of $30 million in the comparable period a year earlier), causing the stock price on the NYSE to plunge $5.875 to $23, a 20% drop. The losses at that point totaled $339 million for the current fiscal year. Sales of the VAX, long the company's biggest moneymaker, continued to decline, which in turn also hurt Digital's lucrative service and maintenance business (this made up more than a third of Digital Equipment's revenue of $14 billion in the 1993 fiscal year), which declined 11% year over year to $1.5 billion in the most recent quarter.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Market acceptance of Digital Alpha computers and chips had been slower than the company had hoped, even though Alpha's sales for the quarter estimated at $275 million were up significantly from $165 million in the December quarter. Digital had also made a strong push into personal computers and workstations, which had even lower margins than Alpha computers and chips. Also, Digital was playing catchup with its own Unix offerings for client-server networks, as it long emphasized its own VMS software, while corporate computer users based their client-server networks on the industry-standard Unix software (of which Hewlett Packard was one of the market leaders). Digital's problems were similar to that of larger rival IBM, due to the fundamental shift in the computer industry that made it unlikely that Digital could ever again operate profitably at its former size of 120,000 employees, and while its workforce had been reduced to 92,000 people many analysts expected that they would have to cut another 20,000.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/1994/04/16/business/company-reports-a-deepening-of-losses-at-digital-equipment.html'>COMPANY REPORTS; A Deepening of Losses at Digital Equipment - New York Times</link>. Nytimes.com. Retrieved on 2014-04-12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the profitable years up until the early 1990s, DEC was a company that boasted that it never had a general layoff.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schein,<space/><italics>et al</italics>, pp. 67, 109.</extension><space/>Following the<space/><link><target>Early 1990s recession</target><part>1992 economic downturn</part></link>, layoffs became regular events as the company continually downsized to try to stay afloat.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schein,<space/><italics>et al</italics>, p. 233.</extension><space/>Palmer was tasked with the goal of bringing DEC back to profitability, which he attempted to do by changing the established DEC business culture, hiring new executives from outside the company, and selling off various non-core business units:<extension extension_name='ref'>Schein,<space/><italics>et al</italics>, pp. 128, 144, 234.</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Worldwide training was spun off to form an independent/new company called Global Knowledge Network.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Oracle Rdb</target><part>Rdb</part></link>, DEC's database product, was sold to<space/><link><target>Oracle Corporation</target><part>Oracle</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>Rights to the<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link><space/>line and several PDP-11 operating systems were sold to Mentec in 1994, though DEC continued to produce some PDP-11 hardware for a few years.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://replay.waybackmachine.org/20060813131029/http://www.mentec-inc.com/'>PDP-11 RSX RT RSTS Emulator Osprey Charon</link></extension></listitem><listitem>Disk and<space/><link><target>Digital Linear Tape</target><part>DLT</part></link><space/>technologies was sold to<space/><link><target>Quantum Corporation</target></link><space/>in 1994.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Text terminal</target></link><space/>business (<link><target>VT100</target></link><space/>and its successors) was sold in August 1995 to<space/><link><target>Boundless Technologies</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>CORBA</target></link>-based product, ObjectBroker, and its messaging software, MessageQ, were sold to<space/><link><target>BEA Systems</target><part>BEA Systems, Inc</part></link><space/>in March 1997.</listitem><listitem>In May 1997, DEC sued<space/><link><target>Intel</target></link><space/>for allegedly infringing on its Alpha patents in designing the<space/><link><target>Original Intel Pentium (P5 microarchitecture)</target><part>original Pentium</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Pentium Pro</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Pentium II</target></link><space/>chips.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;DEC, Cyrix sue Intel&quot;, by Gale Bradley and Jim Detar,<space/><italics>Electronic News</italics><space/><bold>43</bold>, #2168 (19 May 1997), ISSN 1061-6624.</extension><space/>As part of a settlement, much of DEC's chip design and fabrication business was sold to Intel. This included DEC's<space/><link><target>StrongARM</target></link><space/>implementation of the<space/><link><target>ARM architecture</target><part>ARM computer architecture</part></link>, which Intel marketed as the<space/><link><target>Intel XScale</target><part>XScale</part></link><space/>processors commonly used in<space/><link><target>Pocket PC</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The core of Digital Semiconductor, the Alpha microprocessor group, remained with DEC, while the associated office buildings went to Intel as part of the Hudson, Mass. fabrication site.</listitem><listitem>Printer business was sold in 1997 to<space/><link><target>GENICOM</target></link><space/>(now TallyGenicom), which then produced models bearing the Digital logo.</listitem><listitem>Networking business was sold c.1997 to<space/><link><target>Cabletron Systems</target></link>, and subsequently spun off as<space/><link><target>Digital Network Products Group</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>DECtalk</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>DECvoice</target></link><space/>voice products were spun off, and eventually arrived at<space/><link><target>Fonix Speech Group</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>By 1997, Digital had subsidiary companies in more than two dozen countries including Austria, Australia, Belgium, Brazil, Canada, China (People's Republic), Colombia, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Denmark, Finland, France, Germany, Ireland, Israel, Japan, Jersey States, New Zealand, Netherlands, Norway, Russia, Singapore, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland, Taiwan, and the United Kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.secinfo.com/dsvRx.83Pe.7.htm'>SEC Web site</link><space/>retrieved 22 January 2008</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Eventually, on 26 January 1998, what remained of the company (including Digital's multivendor global services organization and customer support centers) was sold to PC manufacturer<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link><space/>in what was the largest merger up to that time in the computer industry. Several years earlier, Compaq had considered a bid for Digital but became seriously interested only after Digital's major divestments and refocusing on the Internet in 1997. At the time of Compaq's acquisition announcement, Digital had a total of 53,500 employees, down from a peak of 130,000 in the 1980s, but it still employed about 65% more people than Compaq to produce about half the volume of sales revenues. After the merger closed, Compaq moved aggressively to reduce Digitals high selling, general, and administrative (SG&amp;A) costs (equal to 24% of total 1997 revenues) and bring them more in line with Compaqs SG&amp;A expense ratio of 12% of revenues.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mhhe.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.mhhe.com/business/management/updates/thompson12e/case/dell10.html'>Dell Computer Corporation Online Case</link>. Mhhe.com. Retrieved on 2014-04-12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Compaq used the acquisition to move into enterprise services and compete with IBM, and by 2001 services made up over 20% of Compaq's revenues, largely due to the Digital employees inherited from the merger.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ecommerce.hostip.info/pages/323/Digital-Equipment-Corp-TAKEOVER-BY-COMPAQ-COMPUTER-CORP.html'>Digital Equipment Corp - Takeover By Compaq Computer Corp. - Intel, Service, Services, and Personal</link>. Ecommerce.hostip.info. Retrieved on 2013-07-17.</extension><space/>Digital's own PC manufacturing was discontinued after the merger closed. As Compaq did not wish to compete with one of its key partner suppliers, the remainder of Digital Semiconductor (the Alpha microprocessor group) was sold to Intel, which placed those employees back in their Hudson (Massachusetts) office, which they had vacated when the site was sold to Intel in 1997.</paragraph><paragraph>Compaq struggled as a result of the merger with Digital,<extension extension_name='ref' name="mhhe.com"></extension><space/>and was acquired by<space/><link><target>Hewlett-Packard</target></link><space/>in 2002. Compaq, and later HP, continued to sell many of the former Digital products but re-branded with their own logos. For example, HP now sells what were formerly Digital's StorageWorks disk/tape products,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://h18006.www1.hp.com/storage/'>HP StorageWorks Data and Network Storage Products and Solutions</link></extension><space/>as a result of the Compaq acquisition.</paragraph><paragraph>The Digital logo survived for a while after the company ceased to exist, as the logo of Digital GlobalSoft, an IT services company in India (which was a 51% subsidiary of Compaq). Digital GlobalSoft was later renamed &quot;HP GlobalSoft&quot; (also known as the &quot;HP Global Delivery India Center&quot; or HP GDIC), and no longer uses the Digital logo.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital once held the<space/><link><target>Classful network</target><part>Class A</part></link><space/><link><target>IP address</target></link><space/>block 16.0.0.0/8.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>List of assigned /8 IPv4 address blocks</target></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Digital Federal Credit Union</target></link><space/>(DCU, now DFCU), which was chartered in 1979 for employees of DEC, is now open to essentially everyone. DFCU has over 700 different sponsors, including the companies that acquired pieces of DEC.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Research</heading><paragraph>DEC's Research Laboratories (or Research Labs, as they were commonly known) conducted Digital's corporate research. Some of them were operated by<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link><space/>and are still operated by<space/><link><target>Hewlett-Packard</target></link>. The laboratories were:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Western Research Laboratory</target></link><space/>(WRL) in<space/><link><target>Palo Alto, California</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>DEC Systems Research Center</target><part>Systems Research Center</part></link><space/>(SRC) in<space/><link><target>Palo Alto, California</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>Network Systems Laboratory</target></link><space/>(NSL) in<space/><link><target>Palo Alto, California</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cambridge Research Laboratory</target></link><space/>(CRL) in<space/><link><target>Cambridge, Massachusetts</target></link>, US</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paris Research Laboratory</target></link><space/>(PRL) in<space/><link><target>Paris, France</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>MetroWest Technology Campus</target></link><space/>(MTC) in<space/><link><target>Maynard, Massachusetts</target></link>, US</listitem></list><paragraph>Some of the former employees of Digital's Research Labs or Digital's R&amp;D in general include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Gordon Bell</target></link><space/>technical visionary, VP Engineering 1972-1983;<space/><link><target>Microsoft Research</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Leonard Bosack</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Henry Burkhardt III</target></link><space/>co-founder of<space/><link><target>Data General</target><part>Data General Corporation</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kendall Square Research</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Michael Burrows</target><part>Mike Burrows</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Luca Cardelli</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dave Cutler</target></link><space/>led<space/><link><target>RSX-11M</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>VAX/VMS</target></link><space/><link><target>operating systems</target></link><space/>development; then led<space/><link><target>Windows NT</target></link><space/>development at<space/><link><target>Microsoft</target></link><template><target>discuss</target><arg>unsourced/exaggerated synopses of notable people</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Edson deCastro</target><part>Ed deCastro</part></link><space/>co-founder of<space/><link><target>Data General</target><part>Data General Corporation</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jim Gettys</target></link><space/>early developer of<space/><link><target>X Window System</target></link><template><target>discuss</target><arg>unsourced/exaggerated synopses of notable people</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Henri Gouraud (computer scientist)</target><part>Henri Gouraud</part></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jim Gray (computer scientist)</target><part>Jim Gray</part></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Alan Kotok</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Leslie Lamport</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Butler Lampson</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Louis Monier</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Isaac Nassi</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Radia Perlman</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Marcus J. Ranum</target><part>Marcus Ranum</part></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brian Reid (computer scientist)</target><part>Brian Reid</part></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Vixie</target></link><space/></listitem></list><paragraph>Some of the former employees of Digital Equipment Corp who were responsible for developing Alpha and StrongARM</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Daniel W. Dobberpuhl</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jill Keller</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rich Witek</target></link><space/></listitem></list><paragraph>Some of the work of the Research Labs was published in the<space/><italics>Digital Technical Journal</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.hpl.hp.com/hpjournal/dtj/past.htm'>Digital Technical Journal Online Issues</link></extension><space/>which was in published from 1985 until 1998.<extension extension_name='ref'>At least some of the research reports are available online at<space/><link type='external' href='ftp://ftp.digital.com/pub/DEC/'>ftp.digital.com</link>, in the subdirectories WRL, SRC, NSL, CRL, PRL (see<space/><link><target>Digital Equipment Corporation#Research</target><part>Research</part></link><space/>section). Verified July 2006</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Accomplishments</heading><paragraph>Digital supported the<space/><link><target>American National Standards Institute</target><part>ANSI</part></link><space/>standards, especially the<space/><link><target>ASCII</target></link><space/>character set, which survives in<space/><link><target>Unicode</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>ISO 8859</target></link><space/>character set family. Digital's own<space/><link><target>Multinational Character Set</target></link><space/>also had a large influence on<space/><link><target>ISO 8859-1</target></link><space/>(Latin-1) and, by extension, Unicode .</paragraph><paragraph>The first versions of the<space/><link><target>C (programming language)</target><part>C</part></link><space/>language and the<space/><link><target>Unix</target></link><space/>operating system ran on Digital's<space/><link><target>Programmed Data Processor</target><part>PDP</part></link><space/>series of computers (first on a PDP-7, then the<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link>'s), which were among the first commercially viable<space/><link><target>minicomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, although for several years Digital itself did not encourage the use of Unix.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital produced widely used and influential interactive operating systems, including<space/><link><target>OS/8</target><part>OS-8</part></link>,<space/><link><target>TOPS-10</target></link>,<space/><link><target>TOPS-20</target></link>,<space/><link><target>RSTS/E</target></link>,<space/><link><target>RSX-11</target></link>,<space/><link><target>RT-11</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>OpenVMS</target></link>. PDP computers, in particular the<space/><link><target>PDP-11</target></link><space/>model, inspired a generation of programmers and software developers. Some PDP-11 systems more than 25 years old (software and hardware) are still being used to control and monitor factories, transportation systems and nuclear plants. Digital was an early champion of<space/><link><target>time-sharing</target></link><space/>systems.</paragraph><paragraph>The command-line interfaces found in Digital's systems, eventually codified as<space/><link><target>DIGITAL Command Language</target><part>DCL</part></link>, would look familiar to any user of modern microcomputer CLIs; those used in earlier systems, such as<space/><link><target>Compatible Time-Sharing System</target><part>CTSS</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IBM</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Job Control Language</target><part>JCL</part></link>, or<space/><link><target>Univac</target></link>'s time-sharing systems, would look utterly alien. Many features of the CP/M and MS-DOS CLI show a recognizable family resemblance to Digital's OSes, including command names such as DIR and HELP and the &quot;name-dot-extension&quot; file naming conventions.</paragraph><paragraph>VAX and<space/><link><target>MicroVAX</target></link><space/>computers (very widespread in the 1980s) running<space/><link><target>Virtual Memory System</target><part>VMS</part></link><space/>formed one of the most important proprietary networks,<space/><link><target>DECnet</target></link>, which linked business and research facilities. The<space/><link><target>DECnet</target></link><space/>protocols formed one of the first peer-to-peer networking standards, with DECnet phase I being released in the mid-1970s. Email, file sharing, and distributed collaborative projects existed within the company long before their value was recognized in the market.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital,<space/><link><target>Intel</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Xerox</target></link><space/>through their collaboration to create the DIX standard, were champions of<space/><link><target>Ethernet</target></link>, but Digital is the company that made Ethernet commercially successful. Initially, Ethernet-based DECnet and<space/><link><target>Local Area Transport</target><part>LAT</part></link><space/>protocols interconnected VAXes with<space/><link><target>DECserver</target></link><space/><link><target>terminal server</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Starting with the<space/><link><target>Unibus</target></link><space/>to Ethernet adapter, multiple generations of Ethernet hardware from Digital were the de facto standard. The CI &quot;computer interconnect&quot; adapter was the industry's first network interface controller to use separate transmit and receive &quot;rings&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital also invented<space/><link><target>Computer cluster</target><part>clustering</part></link>, an operating system technology that treated multiple machines as one logical entity. Clustering permitted sharing of pooled disk and tape storage via the HSC50/70/90 and later series of Hierarchical Storage Controllers (HSC). The HSCs delivered the first hardware<space/><link><target>RAID 0</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>RAID 1</target></link><space/>capabilities and the first serial interconnects of multiple storage technologies. This technology was the forerunner to architectures such as<space/><link><target>Network of Workstations</target></link><space/>which are used for massively cooperative tasks such as web-searches and drug research.</paragraph><paragraph>The LA36 and LA120<space/><link><target>dot matrix printer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>became industry standards and may have hastened the demise of the<space/><link><target>Teletype Corporation</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>VT100</target></link><space/><link><target>computer terminal</target></link><space/>became the industry standard, implementing a useful subset of the<space/><link><target>ANSI X3.64</target></link><space/>standard, and even today terminal emulators such as<space/><link><target>HyperACCESS</target><part>HyperTerminal</part></link>,<space/><link><target>PuTTY</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Xterm</target></link><space/>still emulate a VT100 (or its more capable successor, the<space/><link><target>VT220</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>X Window System</target></link>, the network transparent window system used on<space/><link><target>UNIX</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Linux</target></link>, and also available on other operating systems, was developed at<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</target><part>MIT</part></link><space/>jointly between<space/><link><target>Project Athena</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Laboratory for Computer Science</target></link>. Digital was the primary sponsor for this project, which was a contemporary of the<space/><link><target>GNU Project</target></link><space/>but not associated with it.</paragraph><paragraph><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>Disputed-inline</target><arg>Linux_not_DEC-accomplishment</arg><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><space/>In the period 1994-1999<space/><link><target>Linus Torvalds</target></link><space/>developed versions of Linux on early<space/><link><target>AlphaServer</target></link><space/>systems made available to him by the engineering department. Compaq software engineers developed special Linux kernel modules.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.informatica.co.cr/linux/research/1999/0302-a.htm'>Compaq was actively participating during the period 1994-1999 into the Linux development</link>, verified July 2014</extension><space/>A well-known<space/><link><target>Linux distribution</target></link><space/>that ran on AlphaServer systems was<space/><link><target>Red Hat</target></link><space/>7.2.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.informatica.co.cr/linux/research/2002/0108.htm'>Red Hat and Compaq Announce Port of Red Hat Linux 7.2 to Compaq's Alpha Processors (January 8, 2002)</link>, verified July 2014</extension><space/>Another distribution that ran on Alpha was<space/><link><target>Gentoo Linux</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Microsoft was not exclusively bound to the Alpha chip so it pursued other processor makers such as IBM with the<space/><link><target>PowerPC</target></link><space/>architecture and eventually capitalized on the emerging strength of the Intel x86 based processors.</paragraph><paragraph>Notes-11 and its follow-on product,<space/><template><target>anchor</target><arg>VAX_Notes</arg></template>VAX Notes, were two of the first examples of online collaboration software, a category that has become to be known as<space/><link><target>Collaborative software</target><part>groupware</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Len Kawell</target></link>, one of the original Notes-11 developers later joined<space/><link><target>Lotus Development Corporation</target></link><space/>and contributed to their<space/><link><target>Lotus Notes</target></link><space/>product.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital was one of the first businesses connected to the Internet, with<space/><italics>dec.com</italics>, registered in 1985,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/Users/gbell/Digital/timeline/1985-6.htm'>dec.com</link></extension><space/>being one of the first of the now ubiquitous<space/><italics>.com</italics><space/>domains. DEC's<space/><italics>gatekeeper.dec.com</italics><space/>was a well-known<space/><link><target>software repository</target></link><space/>during the pre-<link><target>WWW</target><part>World Wide Web</part></link><space/>days, and Digital was also the first computer vendor to open a public website, on 1 October 1993.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://listserv.acsu.buffalo.edu/cgi-bin/wa?A2=ind9402&amp;amp;L=dectei-l&amp;amp;T=0&amp;amp;P=200'>DECTEI-L Archives February 1994 (#2)</link></extension><space/>The popular<space/><link><target>AltaVista</target></link>, created by Digital, was one of the first comprehensive Internet<space/><link><target>Search engine (computing)</target><part>search engines</part></link>. (Although<space/><link><target>Lycos</target></link><space/>was earlier, it was much more limited.)</paragraph><paragraph>DEC invented<space/><link><target>Digital Linear Tape</target></link><space/>(DLT), formerly known as CompacTape, which began as a compact backup medium for MicroVAX systems, and later grew to capacities of 800 gigabytes.</paragraph><paragraph>Work on the first hard-disk-based MP3-player, the<space/><link><target>Personal Jukebox</target></link>, started at the<space/><link><target>DEC Systems Research Center</target></link>. (The project was started about a month before the merger into<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link><space/>was completed.)</paragraph><paragraph>DEC's Western Research Lab created the<space/><link><target>Itsy Pocket Computer</target></link>. This was developed into the Compaq<space/><link><target>iPaq</target></link><space/>line of<space/><link><target>Personal digital assistant</target><part>PDAs</part></link>, which replaced the<space/><link><target>Compaq Aero</target></link><space/>PDA.</paragraph><heading level='2'>User organizations</heading><paragraph>Originally the<space/><link><target>users' group</target></link><space/>was called<space/><link><target>DECUS</target></link><space/>(Digital Equipment Computer User Society) during the 1960s to 1990s. When<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link><space/>acquired Digital in 1998, the users group was renamed CUO, the Compaq Users' Organisation. When<space/><link><target>Hewlett-Packard</target><part>HP</part></link><space/>acquired<space/><link><target>Compaq</target></link><space/>in 2002, CUO became<space/><link><target>HP-Interex</target></link>, although there are still DECUS groups in several countries. In the United States, the organization is represented by the<space/><link><target>Encompass</target></link><space/>organization; currently<space/><link><target>Connect (users group)</target><part>Connect</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>(<italics>Present</italics>),<space/><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/en-us/um/people/gbell/digital/DEC%201957%20to%20Present%201978.pdf'>&quot;Digital Equipment Corporation: Nineteen Fifty-Seven to the Present&quot;</link>, DEC Press, 1978</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>David Donald Miller</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Open Vms Operating System Concepts</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Elsevier</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-55558-157-2<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alan R. Earls</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Digital Equipment Corporation</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2004-06-30</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Arcadia Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7385-3587-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Paul J</arg><arg name="author2">Edgar H<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Peter S<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Michael M<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>DEC is dead, long live DEC</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2003-07-01</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Berrett-Koehler Pub</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-57675-225-8<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Jamie Parker Pearson</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Digital at work: snapshots from the first thirty-five years</arg><arg name="date"><space/>September 1992</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Digital Press</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-55558-092-0<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Glenn & George Harrar Rifkin</arg><arg name="author2">George Harrar</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Ultimate Entrepreneur: The Story of Ken Olsen and Digital Equipment Corporation</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGraw-Hill/Contemporary</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8092-4559-8<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>C. Gordon Bell</arg><arg name="author2">J. Craig Mudge<space/></arg><arg name="author3">John E. McNamara<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Digital Equipment Corporation<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Computer engineering: A DEC view of hardware systems design</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1978</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-932376-00-2<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://research.microsoft.com/users/gbell/Digital/DECMuseum.htm'>GBell's CyberMuseum for Digital Equipment Corp (DEC)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://technikum29.de/en/devices/dec-history.shtm'>Rise and Fall of Digital (Equipment Corporation)</link>, a company chronicle at a German computer museum</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.economicadventure.org/decision/olsen.pdf'>Ken Olsen</link>, New England Economic Adventure</listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Digital+Equipment+Corporation<space/></arg><arg name="name">Digital Equipment Corporation</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Digital Equipment Corporation<space/></arg><arg name="sopt">t</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEC hardware</target></template><template><target>DEC video terminals</target></template><template><target>Hard disk drive manufacturers</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Digital Equipment Corporation</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Defunct computer companies based in Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:Defunct computer hardware companies</target></link><link><target>Category:Manufacturing companies based in Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:Hewlett-Packard</target></link><link><target>Category:UML Partners</target></link><link><target>Category:Companies based in Middlesex County, Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:Manufacturing companies established in 1957</target></link><link><target>Category:Manufacturing companies disestablished in 1998</target></link></paragraph></article>