<article title='Transport_in_Antarctica'><paragraph><bold>Transport in Antarctica</bold><space/>has transformed from explorers crossing the isolated remote area of<space/><link><target>Antarctica</target></link><space/><link><target>walking</target><part>by foot</part></link><space/>to a more open area due to human technologies enabling more convenient and faster transport, predominantly by air and water, as well as land. Transportation technologies on a remote area like Antarctica need to be able to deal with extremely low<space/><link><target>temperature</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and continuous<space/><link><target>wind</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to ensure the travelers' safety. Due to the fragility of the Antarctic environment, only a limited amount of transport movements can take place and sustainable transportation technologies have to be used to reduce the<space/><link><target>ecological footprint</target></link>.The<space/><link><target>infrastructure</target></link><space/>of land, water and air transport needs to be safe and sustainable. Currently thousands of tourists and hundreds of scientists a year rely on the Antarctic transportation system.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Land transport</heading><paragraph><link><target>Mawson Station</target></link><space/>started using classic<space/><link><target>Volkswagen Beetle</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the first production cars to be used in Antarctica. The first of these was named 'Antarctica 1'. However, the scarcity and poor quality of<space/><link><target>road</target></link><space/>infrastructure limits land transportation by conventional vehicles. Winds continuously blow snow on the roads. The<space/><link><target>South Pole Traverse</target></link><space/>(also called McMurdo South Pole Highway) is a 900-mile (1450&amp;nbsp;km) road in Antarctica linking the United States<space/><link><target>McMurdo Station</target></link><space/>on the coast to the<space/><link><target>AmundsenScott South Pole Station</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2006 a team of six people took part in the<space/><link><target>Ice Challenger Expedition</target></link>. Travelling in a specially designed six wheel drive vehicle, the team completed the journey from the<space/><link><target>Antarctic</target></link><space/>coast at Patriot Hills to the geographic<space/><link><target>South Pole</target></link><space/>in 69 hours. In doing so they easily beat the previous record of 24 days. They arrived at the South Pole on the 12th of December 2005.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.icechallenger.co.uk/'>Ice Challenger 2005<space/></link><space/>Retrieved on 2008-10-14</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The team members on that expedition were<space/><link><target>Andrew Regan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jason De Carteret</target></link>, Andrew Moon, Richard Griffiths, Gunnar Egilsson and Andrew Miles. The expedition successfully showed that wheeled transport on the continent is not only possible but also often more practical. The expedition also hoped to raise awareness about global warming and climate change.</paragraph><paragraph>A second expedition led by Andrew Regan and Andrew Moon departed in November 2010. The Moon-Regan Trans Antarctic Expedition this time traversed the entire continent twice, using two six-wheel-drive vehicles and a Concept Ice Vehicle designed by Lotus.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.transantarcticexpedition.com/'>Trans Antarctic Expedition<space/></link><space/>Retrieved on 2011-02-20</extension><space/>This time the team used the expedition to raise awareness about the global environmental importance of the Antarctic region and to show that<space/><link><target>biofuel</target></link><space/>can be a viable and environmentally friendly option.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Water transport</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:National Geographic Explorer in fast ice, Antarctica - edit 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A tour boat in fast ice near the coast</part></link>Antarctica's only harbour is at<space/><link><target>McMurdo Station</target></link>. Most coastal stations have offshore anchorages, and supplies are transferred from ship to shore by small boats, barges, and helicopters. A few stations have a basic wharf facility. All ships at port are subject to inspection in accordance with Article 7,<space/><link><target>Antarctic Treaty</target></link>. Offshore anchorage is sparse and intermittent, but poses no problem to sailboats designed for the ice, typically with lifting keels and long shorelines.<link><target>McMurdo Station</target></link><space/>(<template><target>coord</target><arg>77</arg><arg>51</arg><arg>S</arg><arg>166</arg><arg>40</arg><arg>E</arg><arg></arg></template>),<space/><link><target>Palmer Station</target></link><space/>(<template><target>coord</target><arg>64</arg><arg>43</arg><arg>S</arg><arg>64</arg><arg>03</arg><arg>W</arg><arg></arg></template>); government use only except by permit (see Permit Office under &quot;Legal System&quot;). A number of tour boats, ranging from large motorized vessels to small sailing yachts, visit the Antarctic Peninsula during the summer months (JanuaryMarch). Most are based in<space/><link><target>Ushuaia</target></link>, Argentina.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Air transport</heading><paragraph>Transport in Antarctica takes place by air, using<space/><link><target>aeroplane</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>helicopter</target><trail>s</trail></link>.Aeroplane runways and helicopter pads have to be kept snow free to ensure safe take off and landing conditions.</paragraph><paragraph>Antarctica has<space/><link><target>List of airports in Antarctica</target><part>20 airports</part></link>, but there are no developed public-access airports or landing facilities. Thirty stations, operated by 16 national governments party to the<space/><link><target>Antarctic Treaty</target></link>, have landing facilities for either<space/><link><target>helicopter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and/or<space/><link><target>fixed-wing aircraft</target></link>; commercial enterprises operate two additional air facilities.</paragraph><paragraph>Helicopter pads are available at 27 stations; runways at 15 locations are gravel, sea-ice, blue-ice, or compacted snow suitable for landing wheeled, fixed-wing aircraft; of these, 1 is greater than 3&amp;nbsp;km in length, 6 are between 2&amp;nbsp;km and 3&amp;nbsp;km in length, 3 are between 1&amp;nbsp;km and 2&amp;nbsp;km in length, 3 are less than 1&amp;nbsp;km in length, and 2 are of unknown length; snow surface skiways, limited to use by<space/><link><target>ski</target></link>-equipped, fixed-wing aircraft, are available at another 15 locations; of these, 4 are greater than 3&amp;nbsp;km in length, 3 are between 2&amp;nbsp;km and 3&amp;nbsp;km in length, 2 are between 1&amp;nbsp;km and 2&amp;nbsp;km in length, 2 are less than 1&amp;nbsp;km in length, and data is unavailable for the remaining 4.</paragraph><paragraph>Antarctic airports are subject to severe restrictions and limitations resulting from extreme seasonal and geographic conditions; they do not meet<space/><link><target>ICAO</target></link><space/>standards, and advance approval from the respective governmental or nongovernmental operating organization is required for landing (1999 est.) Flights to the continent in the permanent darkness of the winter are normally only undertaken in an emergency, with burning barrels of fuel to outline a runway. On September 11, 2008, a United States Air Force<space/><link><target>C-17 Globemaster III</target></link><space/>successfully completed the first landing in Antarctica using<space/><link><target>night-vision goggles</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Pegasus Field</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://antarcticsun.usap.gov/features/contenthandler.cfm?id</arg><arg name="title">Air Force successfully tests new capability to fly any time of year to McMurdo</arg><arg name="work">Antarctic Sun</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="last">Rejcek</arg><arg name="date">September 26, 2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In April 2001 an emergency evacuation of Dr. Ronald Shemenski was needed from<space/><link><target>AmundsenScott South Pole Station</target></link><space/>when he contracted<space/><link><target>pancreatitis</target></link>. Three<space/><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target><part>C-130 Hercules</part></link><space/>were called back before their final leg because of weather. Organizers then called on<space/><link><target>Kenn Borek Air</target></link><space/>based in<space/><link><target>Calgary</target></link>. Two<space/><link><target>de Havilland Canada DHC-6 Twin Otter</target><part>de Havilland Twin Otters</part></link><space/>were dispatched out of Calgary with one being back-up. Twin Otters are specifically designed for the Canadian north and Kenn Borek Air's motto is &quot;Anywhere, Anytime, World-Wide&quot;. The mission was a success but not without difficulties and drawbacks. Ground crews needed to create a 2&amp;nbsp;km runway with tracked equipment not designed to operate in the low temperatures at that time of year, the aircraft controls had to be &quot;jerry-rigged&quot; when the flaps were frozen in position after landing, and instruments were not reliable because of the cold. When they saw a &quot;faint pink line on the horizon&quot; they knew they were going in the right direction. This was the first rescue from the South Pole during polar winter.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CNNtranscript-2001-04-26"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://edition.cnn.com/TRANSCRIPTS/0104/26/bn.02.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Plane With Dr. Shemenski Arrives in Chile<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>26 April 2001<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>23 January 2013<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Transcript<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>CNN<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Canada honoured the Otter crew for bravery.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id</arg><arg name="title">Polar Doc Rescuers Battle Time, Weather - ABC News<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abcnews.go.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-11-11</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ctvnews.ca/w5/canadians-pulled-off-daring-2001-south-pole-rescue-1.1127682<space/></arg><arg name="title">Canadians pulled off daring 2001 South Pole rescue<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Ctvnews.ca<space/></arg><arg name="date">2013-01-24<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-11-11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Tourism in Antarctica</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of airports in Antarctica</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.polar.se/en/research/logistics'>Webpage of the Swedish Polar Research Secretariat on logistics</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Antarctica</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Transport in Antarctica</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>