<article title='Dwight_L._Moody'><paragraph><template><target>Lead too short</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template></paragraph><table align="right"><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="name"><space/>Dwight Lyman Moody
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Dwight Lyman Moody c.1900.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Preacher, evangelist and publisher
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1837|2|5}} 
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Northfield, Massachusetts]], USA
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1899|12|22|1837|2|5}} 
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Northfield, Massachusetts]], USA
</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph><bold>Dwight Lyman Moody</bold><space/>(February 5, 1837 December 22, 1899), also known as<space/><bold>D.L. Moody</bold>, was an<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>American</part></link><space/><link><target>Evangelism</target><part>evangelist</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>publisher</target></link>, who founded the<space/><link><target>Moody Church</target></link>, Northfield School and Mount Hermon School in Massachusetts (now<space/><link><target>Northfield Mount Hermon School</target></link>), the<space/><link><target>Moody Bible Institute</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Moody Publishers</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life</heading><paragraph>Dwight Moody was born in<space/><link><target>Northfield, Massachusetts</target></link>, to a large family. His father, Edwin J. Moody (18001841), a small farmer and stonemason, died at the age of 41, when Dwight was only four years old; his mother was Betsey Moody (ne Holton; 18051896). They had five sons and a daughter before Dwight's birth, with twins, a boy and a girl, born one month after Edwin's death. His mother struggled to support the family, but even with her best effort, some of her children had to be sent off to work for their room and board. Dwight too was sent off, where he received cornmeal, porridge, and milk three times a day.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Johnson</arg><arg name="first">George</arg><arg name="title">What Will A Man Give In Exchange For His Soul?</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Xlibris Corporation</arg><arg name="isbn">1465380981</arg><arg name="pages">113–115</arg></template></extension><space/>He complained to his mother, but when she found out that he got all that he wanted to eat, she sent him back. Even during that time she continued to send them to church. Together with his eight siblings he was raised in the<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarian church</part></link>. His oldest brother ran away and was not heard from by the family until many years later.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template><link><target>File:Plaque on Site of the conversion of Dwight Moody in Boston Massachusetts MA USA on Court Street.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Plaque commemorating the spot on Court Street in Boston where Dwight Moody was converted in 1855</part></link>When Moody turned 17, he moved to<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link><space/>to work (after many job rejections) in an uncle's shoe store. One of the uncle's requirements was that Moody attend the<space/><link><target>Mount Vernon Church, Boston</target><part>Congregational Church of Mount Vernon</part></link><space/>where<space/><link><target>Edward Norris Kirk</target><part>Dr. Edward Norris Kirk</part></link><space/>served as the<space/><link><target>pastor</target></link>. In April 1855 Moody was then converted to evangelical Christianity when his Sunday school teacher, Edward Kimball, talked to him about how much God loved him. His conversion sparked the start of his career as an evangelist. However, his first application for church membership, in May 1855, was rejected. He was not received as a church member until May 4, 1856. As his teacher, Edward Kimball, stated:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>"I can truly say, and in saying it I magnify the infinite grace of God as bestowed upon him, that I have seen few persons whose minds were spiritually darker than was his when he came into my [[Sunday School]] class; and I think that the committee of the Mount Vernon Church seldom met an applicant for membership more unlikely ever to become a Christian of clear and decided views of Gospel truth, still less to fill any extended sphere of public usefulness."<ref>Moody (1900), 21</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>The Civil War</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>"The first meeting I ever saw him at was in a little old shanty that had been abandoned by a saloon-keeper. Mr. Moody had got the place to hold the meetings in at night. I went there a little late; and the first thing I saw was a man standing up with a few tallow candles around him, holding a negro boy, and trying to read to him the story of the Prodigal Son and a great many words he could not read out, and had to skip. I thought, 'If the Lord can ever use such an instrument as that for His honor and glory, it will astonish me. As a result of his tireless labor, within a year the average attendance at his school was 650, while 60 volunteers from various churches served as teachers. It became so well known that the just-elected [[Abraham Lincoln|President Lincoln]] visited and spoke at a Sunday School meeting on November 25, 1860."</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>D. L. Moody &quot;could not conscientiously enlist&quot; in the Union Army during the Civil War, later describing himself as &quot;a Quaker&quot; in this respect.<extension extension_name='ref'>Donald W. Dayton,<space/><italics>Discovering an Evangelical Heritage</italics><space/>(New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1976), 134.</extension><space/>After the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target><part>Civil War</part></link><space/>started, he became involved with the<space/><link><target>United States Christian Commission</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>YMCA</target></link>, and paid nine visits to the battlefront, being present among the Union soldiers after the<space/><link><target>Battle of Shiloh</target></link><space/>(a.k.a.<space/><link><target>Pittsburg Landing</target></link>) and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Stones River</target></link>; he also entered<space/><link><target>Richmond, Virginia</target></link>, with the troops of<space/><link><target>Ulysses S. Grant</target><part>General Grant</part></link>. On August 28, 1862, he married Emma C. Revell, with whom he had a daughter, Emma Reynolds Moody, and two sons, William Revell Moody and<space/><link><target>Paul Dwight Moody</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Chicago and the post-Civil War years</heading><paragraph>The growing Sunday School congregation needed a permanent home, so Moody started a church in Chicago, the Illinois Street Church.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In June 1871 at an International Sunday School Convention in Indianapolis, Dwight Moody met<space/><link><target>Ira D. Sankey</target></link>, up to then a single-gospel-singer, with whom he soon began to cooperate and collaborate.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template>Four months later in October 1871 the<space/><link><target>Great Chicago Fire</target></link><space/>destroyed Dwight's church building, as well as his family dwelling and the homes of most of his churchmembers. Many had to flee the flames, saving only their lives, and ending up completely destitute. Moody, reporting on the disaster, said about his own situation that: &quot;...he saved nothing but his reputation and his Bible.&quot;<template><target>citequote</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template><space/>Moody's chapel was rebuilt within three months as the Chicago Avenue Church.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the years after the fire, Moody's wealthy Chicago supporter<space/><link><target>John V. Farwell</target></link><space/>tried to persuade him to make his permanent home in Chicago, offering to build a new house for Moody and his family. But the newly famous Moody, also sought by supporters in New York, Philadelphia, and elsewhere, chose the tranquil farm he had purchased next door to his birthplace in Northfield, Massachusetts. He felt he could better recover from his lengthy and exhausting preaching trips in a rural setting.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson"></extension><space/>Northfield became an important location in evangelical Christian history in the late 19th century as Moody organized summer conferences which were led and attended by prominent Christian preachers and evangelists from around the world. It was also in Northfield where Moody founded two schools (Northfield School for Girls, founded in 1879, and the Mount Hermon School for Boys, founded in 1881) which later merged into today's co-educational, nondenominational<space/><link><target>Northfield Mount Hermon</target></link><space/>School.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template><space/>The Franklin County area has had a rich connection to evangelical Christianity including Jonathan Edwards preaching in Northampton and C.I. Scofield's preaching in Northfield. A protg of Moody founded Moores Corner Church in Leverett Massachusetts which remains Evangelical to this day.</paragraph><heading level='3'>England</heading><paragraph>During a trip to<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>in the spring of 1872, he became well known as an evangelist. Literary works published by the Moody Bible Institute have claimed that he was the greatest evangelist of the 19th century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bailey"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bailey</arg><arg name="first">Faith</arg><arg name="title">D. L Moody</arg><arg name="origyear">1959</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="publisher">The Moody Bible Institute of Chicago</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8024-0039-6</arg><arg name="page">Cover</arg></template></extension><space/>He preached almost a hundred times and came into communion with the<space/><link><target>Plymouth Brethren</target></link>. On several occasions he filled stadia of a capacity of 2,000 to 4,000. In the Botanic Gardens Palace a meeting had an audience between 15,000 and 30,000.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>That turnout continued throughout 1874 and 1875, with crowds of thousands at all of his meetings. During his visit to Scotland he was helped and encouraged by<space/><link><target>Andrew A. Bonar</target></link>. The famous London Baptist preacher,<space/><link><target>Charles Spurgeon</target></link>, invited him to speak, and he promoted him as well. When he returned to the US, crowds of 12,000 to 20,000 were as common as they had been in England.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><space/>President<space/><link><target>Ulysses S. Grant</target><part>Grant</part></link><space/>and some of his cabinet officials attended a meeting on January 19, 1876. His evangelistic meetings took place from Boston to New York, throughout New England, and as far as San Francisco, along with other West Coast towns from Vancouver to San Diego.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Moody aided in the work of cross-cultural evangelism by promoting &quot;<link><target>The Wordless Book</target></link>,&quot; a teaching tool that had been invented by<space/><link><target>Charles Spurgeon</target></link><space/>in 1866. In 1875 he added a fourth color to the design of the three-color evangelistic device: goldto &quot;represent heaven.&quot; This &quot;book&quot; has been and is still used to teach uncounted thousands of illiterate people, young and old, around the globe about the<space/><link><target>gospel</target></link><space/>message.<extension extension_name='ref'>Austin (2007), 1-10</extension><link><target>File:Open Air Preaching WB.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Missionary preaching in<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>using Moody's version of<space/><link><target>The Wordless Book</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Dwight L. Moody visited Britain with<space/><link><target>Ira D. Sankey</target></link>, with Moody preaching and Sankey singing. Together they published books of Christian<space/><link><target>hymns</target></link>. In 1883 they visited<space/><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link><space/>and raised 10,000 for the building of a new home for the<space/><link><target>Carrubbers Close Mission</target></link>. Moody later preached at the laying of the foundation stone for what is one of the few buildings on the<space/><link><target>Royal Mile</target></link><space/>which continues to be used for its original purpose and is now called the<space/><link><target>Carrubbers Christian Centre</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Moody greatly influenced the cause of cross-cultural<space/><link><target>Christian missions</target></link><space/>after he met<space/><link><target>Hudson Taylor</target></link>, a pioneer missionary to China. He actively supported the<space/><link><target>China Inland Mission</target></link><space/>and encouraged many of his congregation to volunteer for service overseas.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>International acclaim</heading><paragraph>His influence was felt among Swedes despite that he was of English heritage, that he never visited Sweden or any other Scandinavian country, and that he never spoke a word of Swedish. Nonetheless he became a hero revivalist among Swedish Mission Friends in Sweden and America.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gustafson (2008)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>News of Moodys large revival campaigns in Great Britain from 1873 through 1875 traveled quickly to Sweden, making &quot;Mr. Moody&quot; a household name in homes of many Mission Friends. Moodys sermons published in Sweden were distributed in books, newspapers, and colporteur tracts, and they led to the spread of Swedens &quot;Moody fever&quot; from 1875 through 1880.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He preached his last sermon on November 16, 1899, in<space/><link><target>Kansas City, Missouri</target></link>. Becoming ill, he returned home by train to Northfield. During the preceding several months, friends had observed he had added some<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>30</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>to his already ample frame. Although his illness was never diagnosed, it has been speculated that he suffered from congestive heart failure. He died on December 22, 1899, surrounded by his family. Already installed as the leader of his Chicago Bible Institute,<space/><link><target>Reuben Archer Torrey</target><part>R. A. Torrey</part></link><space/>succeeded Moody as its president. Ten years after Moody's death the Chicago Avenue Church was renamed the<space/><link><target>Moody Church</target></link><space/>in his honor, and the Chicago Bible Institute was likewise renamed the<space/><link><target>Moody Bible Institute</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Heaven</italics><space/>Diggory Press ISBN 978-1-84685-812-3</listitem><listitem><italics>Prevailing PrayerWhat Hinders it?</italics><space/>Diggory Press ISBN 978-1-84685-803-1</listitem><listitem><italics>Secret Power</italics><space/>Diggory Press ISBN 978-1-84685-802-4</listitem><listitem><italics>The Ten Commandments</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fbinstitute.com/moody/The_TenCommandments_Text.html'>The Ten Commandments</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Biography</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Horatio Spafford</target></link>, a friend of Moody who wrote the words to the hymn<space/><italics>It Is Well With My Soul</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Northfield Mount Hermon School</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.christianitytoday.com/ch/131christians/evangelistsandapologists/moody.html'>&quot;Dwight Moody: evangelist with a common touch&quot;</link><space/><italics>Christianity Today</italics>, 8 August 2008.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wholesomewords.org/biography/biomoody.html'>Christian Biography Resources</link></listitem><listitem>Austin, Alvyn.<space/><italics>Chinas Millions: The China Inland Mission and Late Qing Society.</italics><space/>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Company (March 5, 2007) ISBN 978-0-8028-2975-7</listitem><listitem>Beadenkopf, T. M.; Stricklen, W.R.<space/><italics>Moody in Baltimore</italics>, &quot;Students of Johns Hopkins&quot;, Baltimore, 1879, 2nd ed.</listitem><listitem>Dorsett, L. W.<space/><italics>A Passion for Souls: The Life of D. L. Moody.</italics><space/>1997</listitem><listitem>Findlay, J. F. Jr.<space/><italics>Dwight L. Moody: American Evangelist 18371899.</italics><space/>1969</listitem><listitem>Gundry, S. N.<space/><italics>Love them in: The Proclamation Theology of D. L. Moody.</italics><space/>1976</listitem><listitem>Evensen, B. J.<space/><italics>God's Man for Gilded Age: D. L. Moody and the Rise of Mass Evangelism.</italics><space/>2003</listitem><listitem>Gustafson, D. M.<space/><italics>D. L. Moody and Swedes: Shaping Evangelical Identity among Swedish Missions Friends 18671899.</italics><space/>(Linkping Studies in Arts and Sciences 419. / Linkping Studies in Identity and Pluralism 7.) 2008.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ep.liu.se/theses/abstract.xsql?dbid=11087'>Ph.D. Dissertation</link></listitem><listitem>Moody, Paul Dwight.<space/><italics>The Shorter Life of D. L. Moody.</italics><space/>1900</listitem><listitem>Schlachter, Franz Eugen.<space/><italics>D. L. Moody, ein Lebensbild</italics><space/>(1894)</listitem><listitem>Simons, M. Laird.<space/><italics>Holding the Fort: comprising sermons and addresses at the Great Revival meetings conducted by Moody and Sankey, with the lives and labors of Dwight L. Moody, Ira D. Sankey, and P. P. Bliss</italics>, Norwich, Connecticut: Henry Bill Publishing Co., 1877.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Dwight Lyman Moody</arg></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>NSRW Poster</target><arg>Moody, Dwight Lyman</arg><arg>Dwight L. Moody</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.moodyqc.org/d-l-moody-reads-the-beatitudes/'>Recording of Moody reading the Beatitudes</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sermondepository.com/DLMoody.htm'>Sample sermons by D. L. Moody</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.anabaptists.org/tracts/moodywar.html'>&quot;Shall I enter the Army?&quot; Moody said, &quot;No.&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.apibs.org/class.htm#moody'>Sermons by D. L. Moody</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Moody,+Dwight+Lyman</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Dwight Lyman Moody</arg></template><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/gladtidingscomp00moodgoog'>Glad Tidings, sermons by D. L. Moody</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/gospelawakening01remlgoog'>The Gospel Awakening, sermons by D. L. Moody</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://fundamentalbaptistsermons.net/Site6/EBOOKS/reading.htm'>books by D. L. Moody</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME">Moody, Dwight L.
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION">[[United States|American]] [[Evangelism|evangelist]] and [[publisher]] who founded the [[Moody Church]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH">February 5, 1837
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH">[[Northfield, Massachusetts]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH">December 22, 1899
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Northfield, Massachusetts]]
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Moody, Dwight L.</target></template><link><target>Category:1837 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1899 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:American Christian pacifists</target></link><link><target>Category:American evangelicals</target></link><link><target>Category:American evangelists</target></link><link><target>Category:American hymnwriters</target></link><link><target>Category:American sermon writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Evangelicalism</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian revivalists</target></link><link><target>Category:Founders of schools in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Moody Bible Institute people</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Franklin County, Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:YMCA leaders</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century American writers</target></link></paragraph></article>