<article title='Blind_Lemon_Jefferson'><paragraph><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox musical artist</target><arg name="name"><space/>Blind Lemon Jefferson
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Blindlemonjeffersoncirca1926.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>
</arg><arg name="landscape"><space/>
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Only known photograph of Jefferson, ca. 1926.
</arg><arg name="background"><space/>solo_singer
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Lemon Henry Jefferson
</arg><arg name="native_name"><space/>
</arg><arg name="native_name_lang"><space/>
</arg><arg name="alias"><space/>Deacon L. J. Bates
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1893|09|24}}<ref>Some sources indicate Jefferson was born on October 26, 1894.</ref>
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Coutchman, Texas]], U.S.
</arg><arg name="origin"><space/>Texas
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1929|12|19|1893|09|24}}
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Chicago]], [[Illinois]], U.S.
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Blues]], [[gospel blues]]
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Singer-songwriter, musician
</arg><arg name="instrument"><space/>Guitar
</arg><arg name="years_active"><space/>1900s–1929
</arg><arg name="label"><space/>{{unbulleted list|[[Paramount Records]]|[[Okeh Records]]}}
</arg><arg name="associated_acts"><space/>
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>
</arg><arg name="notable_instruments"><space/>Acoustic Guitar
</arg></template><bold>&quot;Blind&quot; Lemon Jefferson</bold><space/>(born<space/><bold>Lemon Henry Jefferson</bold>; September 24, 1893 December 19, 1929) was an<space/><link><target>American people</target><part>American</part></link><space/><link><target>blues</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gospel</target></link><space/>singer, guitarist, and songwriter from<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link>. He was one of the most popular blues singers of the 1920s, and has been called &quot;Father of the<space/><link><target>Texas Blues</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire">Dicaire, David.<space/><italics>Blues Singers: Biographies of 50 Legendary Artists of the Early 20th Century</italics>. Jefferson, North Carolina: McFarland and Company, Inc., 1999; ISBN 0-7864-0606-2, pp 14044.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson's performances were distinctive as a result of his high-pitched voice and the originality on his guitar playing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension><space/>Although his recordings sold well, he was not so influential on some younger blues singers of his generation, who could not imitate him as easily as they could other commercially successful artists.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Charters"><link><target>Samuel Charters</target><part>Charters, Samuel</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Blues Makers</italics>. New York: Da Capo Press, 1977; ISBN 0-306-80438-7.</extension><space/>Later blues and<space/><link><target>rock and roll</target></link><space/>musicians, however, did attempt to imitate both his songs and his musical style.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Early life</heading><paragraph>Jefferson was born<space/><link><target>Blindness</target><part>blind</part></link>, near Coutchman in<space/><link><target>Freestone County</target></link>, near present-day<space/><link><target>Wortham, Texas</target></link>. He was the youngest of seven<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/302253/Blind-Lemon-Jefferson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Blind Lemon Jefferson &#124; biography - American musician<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Britannica.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-08-30</arg></template></extension><space/>(or possibly eight) children born to<space/><link><target>Sharecropping</target><part>sharecroppers</part></link><space/>Alex and Clarissa Jefferson.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension><space/>Disputes regarding his exact birth date derive from contradictory census records and draft registration records. By 1900, the family was farming southeast of<space/><link><target>Streetman, Texas</target></link>, and Lemon Jefferson's birth date is indicated as September 1893 in the<space/><link><target>1900 census</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>1900 US Census; Census Place: Justice Precinct 5, Freestone, Texas; Roll: T623 1636; Page: 3A; Enumeration District: 37.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>1910 United States Census</target><part>1910 census</part></link>, taken in May before his birthday, further confirms his year of birth as 1893, and indicated the family was farming northwest of Wortham, near Lemon Jefferson's birthplace.<extension extension_name='ref'>1910 US Census; Census Place: Justice Precinct 6, Navarro, Texas; Roll: T624_1580; Page: 17B; Enumeration District: 98; Image: 982.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In his 1917<space/><link><target>Conscription in the United States</target><part>draft registration</part></link>, Jefferson gave his birth date as October 26, 1894, further stating that he then lived in<space/><link><target>Dallas, Texas</target></link><space/>and had been blind since birth.<extension extension_name='ref'>World War I Draft Registration records; Dallas County, Texas; Roll: 1952850; Draft Board: 2</extension><space/>In the<space/><link><target>1920 United States Census</target><part>1920 Census</part></link>, he is recorded as having returned to Freestone County and was living with his half-brother, Kit Banks, on a farm between Wortham and Streetman.<extension extension_name='ref'>1920 US Census;Census Place: Kirvin, Freestone, Texas; Roll: T625_1805; Page: 3A; Enumeration District: 24; Image: 231.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson began playing the guitar in his early teens, and soon after he began performing at<space/><link><target>picnic</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and parties. He became a<space/><link><target>busking</target><part>street musician</part></link>, playing in<space/><link><target>East Texas</target></link><space/>towns, in front of<space/><link><target>barber</target><trail>shops</trail></link><space/>and on streetcorners.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension><space/>According to his cousin, Alec Jefferson, quoted in the notes for<space/><italics>Blind Lemon Jefferson, Classic Sides</italics>:<space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>They were rough. Men were [[prostitution|hustling women]] and selling [[bootleg liquor|bootleg]] and Lemon was singing for them all night... he'd start singing about eight and go on until four in the morning... mostly it would be just him sitting there and playing and singing all night.''</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the early 1910s, Jefferson began traveling frequently to Dallas, where he met and played with fellow blues musician<space/><link><target>Lead Belly</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension><space/>In Dallas, Jefferson was one of the earliest and most prominent figures in the blues movement developing in the<space/><link><target>Deep Ellum</target></link><space/>section of Dallas. Jefferson likely moved to Deep Ellum in a more permanent fashion by 1917, where he met Aaron Thibeaux Walker, also known as<space/><link><target>T-Bone Walker</target></link>. Jefferson taught Walker the basics of blues guitar in exchange for Walker's occasional services as a guide. By the early 1920s, Jefferson was earning enough money for his musical performances to support a wife, and possibly a child.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dicaire"></extension><space/>However, firm evidence for both his marriage and any offspring is unavailable.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Beginning of recording career</heading><paragraph>Prior to Jefferson, very few artists had recorded solo voice and blues guitar, the first of which was vocalist<space/><link><target>Sara Martin</target></link><space/>and guitarist Sylvester Weaver, with &quot;Longing for Daddy Blues&quot; probably recorded October 24, 1923.<extension extension_name='ref'><preblock><preline>Craig Martin Gibbs (2012) Black Recording Artists, 1877-1926: An Annotated Discography Page 175<space/><link><target>McFarland &amp; Company</target></link></preline></preblock></extension><space/>The first self accompanied solo performer of a self composed blues song was<space/><link><target>Lee Morse</target></link>'s &quot;Mail Man Blues&quot; recorded October 7. 1924.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.washingtonhistory.org/files/library/LeeMorse.pdf retrieved 9/27/2015</extension><space/>Jefferson's music is uninhibited and represented the classic sounds of everyday life from a<space/><link><target>honky-tonk</target></link><space/>to a country picnic to street corner blues to work in the burgeoning oil fields, a further reflection of his interest in mechanical objects and processes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joe W. Specht,<space/><link><target>McMurry University</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Abilene, Texas</target><part>Abilene</part></link>, Texas, &quot;Oil Well Blues: African-American Oil Patch Songs&quot;, joint meeting of<space/><link><target>East Texas Historical Association</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>West Texas Historical Association</target></link>, annual meeting in<space/><link><target>Fort Worth, Texas</target><part>Fort Worth</part></link>, February 27, 2010.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson did what very few had ever done he became a successful solo guitarist and male vocalist in the commercial recording world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Evans 2000 83116"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Music Innovation in the Blues of Blind Lemon Jefferson</arg><arg name="journal">Black Music Research Journal<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="last">Evans</arg><arg name="volume">20</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">83–116</arg><arg name="jstor">779317</arg></template></extension><space/>Unlike many artists who were &quot;discovered&quot; and recorded in their normal venues, in December 1925 or January 1926, he was taken to<space/><link><target>Chicago</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Illinois</target></link>, to record his first tracks. Uncharacteristically, Jefferson's first two recordings from this session were<space/><link><target>Gospel music</target><part>gospel</part></link><space/>songs (&quot;I Want to be like Jesus in my Heart&quot; and &quot;All I Want is that Pure Religion&quot;), released under the name<space/><bold>Deacon L. J. Bates</bold>. This led to a second recording session in March 1926.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Russell"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Tony</arg><arg name="last">Russell</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="title">The Blues: From Robert Johnson to Robert Cray</arg><arg name="publisher">Carlton Books Limited</arg><arg name="location">Dubai</arg><arg name="page">12</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85868-255-X</arg></template></extension><space/>His first releases under his own name, &quot;Booster Blues&quot; and &quot;Dry Southern Blues&quot;, were hits; this led to the release of the other two songs from that session, &quot;Got the Blues&quot; and &quot;Long Lonesome Blues,&quot; which became a runaway success, with sales in six figures. He recorded about 100 tracks between 1926 and 1929; 43<space/><link><target>gramophone record</target><part>records</part></link><space/>were issued, all but one for<space/><link><target>Paramount Records</target></link>. Unfortunately, Paramount Records' studio techniques and quality were poor, and the resulting recordings were released with poor sound quality. In fact, in May 1926, Paramount had Jefferson re-record his hits &quot;Got the Blues&quot; and &quot;Long Lonesome Blues&quot; in the superior facilities at<space/><link><target>Autograph Records</target><part>Marsh Laboratories</part></link>, and subsequent releases used those versions. Both versions appear on compilation albums and may be compared.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Success with Paramount records</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:ParamountLabelBLJefferson.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Label of a Blind Lemon Jefferson Paramount record from 1926</part></link>Largely due to the popularity of artists such as Blind Lemon Jefferson and contemporaries such as<space/><link><target>Blind Blake</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ma Rainey</target></link>, Paramount became the leading recording company for the blues in the 1920s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dixon, R.M.W. &amp; J. Godrich (1970)<space/><italics>Recording the Blues</italics>. Reprinted in Oliver, Paul, Tony Russell, Robert M.W. Dixon, John Godrich &amp; Howard Rye (2001)<space/><italics>Yonder Come the Blues</italics>. Cambridge; ISBN 0-521-78777-7. p. 288.</extension><space/>Jefferson's earnings reputedly enabled him to buy a car and employ chauffeurs (although there is debate over the reliability of this as well); he was given a Ford car &quot;worth over $700&quot; by<space/><link><target>Mayo Williams</target></link>, Paramount's connection with the black community. This was a frequently-seen compensation for recording rights in that market. Jefferson is known to have done an unusual amount of traveling for the time in the American South, which is reflected in the difficulty of pigeonholing his music into one regional category.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson's &quot;old-fashioned&quot; sound and confident musicianship made him easy to market. His skillful guitar playing and impressive vocal ranges opened the door for a new generation of male solo blues performers such as Furry Lewis, Charlie Patton, and Barbecue Bob.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Evans 2000 83116"></extension><space/>He sticks to no musical conventions, varying his<space/><link><target>riff</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and rhythm and singing complex and expressive lyrics in a manner exceptional at the time for a &quot;simple country blues singer.&quot; According to North Carolina musician Walter Davis, Jefferson played on the streets in<space/><link><target>Johnson City, Tennessee</target></link>, during the early 1920s at which time Davis and fellow entertainer Clarence Greene learned the art of blues guitar.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Walter Davis: Fist and Skull Banjo</italics>, by Wayne Erbsen, Bluegrass Unlimited: March 1981, pp 2226</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson was reputedly unhappy with his royalties (although Williams said that Jefferson had a bank account containing as much as $1500). In 1927, when Williams moved to<space/><link><target>OKeh Records</target></link>, he took Jefferson with him, and OKeh quickly recorded and released Jefferson's &quot;Matchbox Blues&quot; backed with &quot;Black Snake Moan.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Russell"></extension><space/>It was his only OKeh recording, probably because of contractual obligations with Paramount. Jefferson's two songs released on Okeh have considerably better sound quality than on his Paramount records at the time. When he had returned to Paramount a few months later, &quot;Matchbox Blues&quot; had already become such a hit that Paramount re-recorded and released two new versions, under producer<space/><link><target>Arthur Laibly</target></link>. In 1927, Jefferson recorded another of his now classic songs, the haunting &quot;<link><target>See That My Grave Is Kept Clean</target></link>&quot; (once again using the pseudonym Deacon L. J. Bates) along with two other uncharacteristically spiritual songs, &quot;He Arose from the Dead&quot; and &quot;Where Shall I Be&quot;. Of the three, &quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; was so successful that it was re-recorded and re-released in 1928.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Death and grave</heading><paragraph>Jefferson died in Chicago at 10:00 am on December 19, 1929, of what his death certificate called &quot;probably acute<space/><link><target>myocarditis</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Frog Blues & Jazz Annual No. 1: The Musicians, the Records & the Music of the 78 Era<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Frog Records]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0956471706</arg></template></extension><space/>For many years, apocryphal rumors circulated that a jealous lover had poisoned his coffee, but a more likely scenario is that he died of a heart attack after becoming disoriented during a snowstorm. Some have said that Jefferson died from a heart attack after being attacked by a dog in the middle of the night. More recently, the book,<space/><italics>Tolbert's Texas,</italics><space/>claimed that he was killed while being robbed of a large royalty payment by a guide escorting him to Union Station to catch a train home to Texas. Paramount Records paid for the return of his body to Texas by train, accompanied by pianist<space/><link><target>William Ezell</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Jefferson was buried at Wortham Negro Cemetery (later Wortham Black Cemetery). Far from<space/><link><target>See That My Grave Is Kept Clean</target><part>his grave being kept clean</part></link>, it was unmarked until 1967, when a Texas Historical Marker was erected in the general area of his plot, the precise location being unknown. By 1996, the cemetery and marker were in poor condition, but a new granite headstone was erected in 1997. In 2007, the cemetery's name was changed to Blind Lemon Memorial Cemetery and his gravesite is kept clean by a cemetery committee in Wortham, Texas.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tshaonline.org/handbook/online/articles/view/JJ/fje1.html'>&quot;Jefferson, Blind Lemon&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Handbook of Texas Online</italics>,<space/><link><target>Texas State Historical Association</target></link>, May 30, 2010. Published by the Texas State Historical Association and distributed in partnership with the<space/><link><target>University of North Texas</target></link>. &quot;In 2007 the name of the cemetery was changed to Blind Lemon Memorial Cemetery.&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Discography and awards</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Blind Lemon Jefferson discography</arg></template>Jefferson had an intricate and fast style of guitar playing and a particularly high-pitched voice. He was a founder of the<space/><link><target>Texas blues</target></link><space/>sound and an important influence on other blues singers and guitarists, including<space/><link><target>Lead Belly</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lightnin' Hopkins</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>He was the author of many tunes covered by later musicians, including the classic &quot;<link><target>See That My Grave Is Kept Clean</target></link>&quot;. Another of his tunes, &quot;<link><target>Matchbox (song)</target><part>Matchbox Blues</part></link>&quot;, was recorded more than 30 years later by<space/><link><target>The Beatles</target></link>, albeit in a<space/><link><target>rockabilly</target></link><space/>version credited to<space/><link><target>Carl Perkins</target></link>, who himself did not credit Jefferson on his 1955 recording.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Rock and Roll Hall of Fame</target></link><space/>listed Jefferson's 1927 recording &quot;<link><target>Matchbox (song)</target><part>Matchbox Blues</part></link>&quot; one of the 500 songs that shaped rock and roll.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.infoplease.com/ipea/A0150472.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">500 Songs That Shaped Rock<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Infoplease.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-08-30</arg></template></extension><space/>Jefferson was among the inaugural class of blues musicians inducted into the<space/><link><target>Blues Hall of Fame</target></link><space/>in 1980.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cover versions</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bukka White</target></link><space/>- &quot;Jack O'diamonds&quot; on Bukka White - 1963 Isn't 1962 released in the 1990s</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bob Dylan</target></link><space/>&quot;<link><target>See That My Grave Is Kept Clean</target></link>&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>Bob Dylan (album)</target><part>Bob Dylan</part></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Grateful Dead</target></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; as &quot;One Kind Favor&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>Birth of the Dead</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Merl Saunders</target></link>/<link><target>Jerry Garcia</target></link>/<link><target>John Kahn</target></link>/Bil Vitt &quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; as &quot;One Kind Favor&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>Keystone Encores</target><part>Keystone Encores Volume I</part></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>John P. Hammond</target><part>John Hammond</part></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; as &quot;One Kind Favor&quot; on<space/><italics>John Hammond Live</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>B.B. King</target></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>One Kind Favor</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter, Paul &amp; Mary</target></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave is Kept Clean,&quot; reworked as &quot;One Kind Favor&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>In Concert (Peter, Paul and Mary album)</target><part>In Concert</part></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kelly Joe Phelps</target></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>Roll Away the Stone (Kelly Joe Phelps album)</target><part>Roll Away The Stone</part></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Counting Crows</target></link><space/>&quot;Mean Jumper Blues&quot;. Counting Crows lead singer<space/><link><target>Adam Duritz</target></link><space/>accidentally claimed credit for &quot;Mean Jumper Blues&quot; in the liner notes of the Deluxe Edition reissue of the album<space/><italics><link><target>August And Everything After</target></link></italics>. The cover was featured as part of a selection of early demo tracks. Immediately after the error was brought to his attention, Duritz apologized in his personal blog.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.countingcrows.com/news/journal.php?uid=2426'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.countingcrows.com/news/journal.php?uid</arg><arg name="date">20071106070327<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Laibach (band)</target><part>Laibach</part></link><space/>&quot;See That My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; on<space/><italics><link><target>Spectre (Laibach album)</target><part>SPECTRE</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://spectre.laibach.org/more-info/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Laibach Spectre<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Spectre.laibach.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-08-30</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pat Donohue</target></link><space/>&quot;See that My Grave Is Kept Clean&quot; as<space/><italics><link><target>One Kind Favor</target></link></italics><space/>(live on<space/><link><target>Garrison Keillor</target></link>'s &quot;A Prairie Home Companion&quot;) and later released on the CD<space/><italics>Radio Blues</italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Corey Harris</target></link><space/>- &quot;Jack O'diamonds&quot; on Fish Ain't Bitin' released 1997</listitem></list><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 2009, Grammy nominated R&amp;B act<space/><link><target>Yarbrough and Peoples</target></link><space/>were co-produced and were featured in the Off-Broadway production<space/><italics>Blind Lemon Blues</italics>.</listitem><listitem>A tribute song, &quot;My Buddy Blind Papa Lemon&quot;, was recorded for<space/><link><target>Paramount Records</target></link><space/>in 1932 by<space/><link><target>King Solomon Hill</target></link>. The record was long considered lost, but one copy was located by John Tefteller in 2002.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Geoff Muldaur</target></link><space/>refers to Jefferson with the song &quot;Got To Find Blind Lemon&quot; on the album<space/><italics><link><target>The Secret Handshake</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Art Evans</target></link><space/>portrays Blind Lemon in the 1976 film<space/><italics><link><target>Leadbelly (film)</target><part>Leadbelly</part></link></italics><space/>directed by<space/><link><target>Gordon Parks</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Nick Cave and the Bad Seeds</target></link><space/>recorded the song &quot;Blind Lemon Jefferson&quot; on the album<space/><italics><link><target>The Firstborn Is Dead</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem>The 2010 video game<space/><italics><link><target>Fallout: New Vegas</target></link></italics>, in one of its many downloadable add-ons ('Old World Blues'), features an<space/><link><target>AI</target></link><space/>juke-box by the name of 'Blind Diode Jefferson'.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.falloutwiki.com/Blind_Diode_Jefferson</arg><arg name="title">Blind Diode Jefferson</arg><arg name="publisher">Falloutwiki.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 10, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The AI claims to have once been a 'blues musician' before his music hard-drives were stripped from him. Voicing of the AI can be characterized as a Southern drawl homage to Blind Lemon Jefferson.</listitem><listitem>In the 2003 movie<space/><italics><link><target>Masked and Anonymous</target></link></italics>, Bobby Cupid (Luke Wilson) gives his friend Jack Fate (Bob Dylan) Blind Lemon's original guitar, on which he claims &quot;Matchbox Blues&quot; was first recorded.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cheech and Chong</target></link><space/>parodied Jefferson as &quot;Blind Melon Chitlin'&quot; on their self-titled 1971 album<space/><italics><link><target>Cheech and Chong (album)</target><part>Cheech and Chong</part></link></italics>, on their 1985 album<space/><italics><link><target>Get Out of My Room</target></link></italics>, and in a stage routine that can be seen in their 1983 film<space/><italics><link><target>Still Smokin (film)</target><part>Still Smokin'</part></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chet Atkins</target></link><space/>calls Jefferson &quot;one of my first finger-picking influences&quot; in the song &quot;Nine Pound Hammer&quot;, on the album<space/><italics><link><target>The Atkins - Travis Traveling Show</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem>A practical joke played on<space/><italics>Down Beat</italics><space/>magazine editor Gene Lees in the late 1950s took on a life of its own and became a long-running hoax when one of his correspondents included a reference to blues legend &quot;Blind Orange Adams&quot; in an article and it was inadvertently published in the magazine. &quot;Blind Orange Adams&quot; is obviously a parody on the name &quot;Blind Lemon Jefferson&quot;. References to the non-existent Adams appeared in numerous articles in<space/><italics>Down Beat</italics><space/>over the next few years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bill Crow,<space/><italics>Jazz Anecdotes</italics>,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>, (1990), pp 175176, ISBN 9780195071337.</extension></listitem><listitem>American drama film<space/><italics><link><target>Black Snake Moan (film)</target><part>Black Snake Moan</part></link></italics><space/>was named after one of his only songs recorded with OKeh Records.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Biography</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of nicknames of blues musicians</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Govenar, Alan/Brakefield, Jay F.<space/><italics>Deep Ellum and Central Track: Where the Black and White Worlds of Dallas Converged.</italics><space/>Denton, Texas:<space/><link><target>University of North Texas Press</target></link>, 1998; ISBN 1-57441-051-2.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Evans, David,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/779317'>&quot;Musical Innovation in the Blues of Blind Lemon Jefferson&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Black Music Research Journal</italics>, Vol. 20, No. 1, Blind Lemon Jefferson (Spring, 2000), pp.&amp;nbsp;83116 Published by: Center for Black Music Research Columbia College Chicago and University of Illinois Press</listitem><listitem>Monge, Luigi; Evansy, David,<space/><link type='external' href='http://ecommons.txstate.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1036&amp;amp;context=jtmh'>&quot;New Songs of Blind Lemon Jefferson&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Journal of Texas Music History</italics>, Volume 3, Issue 2, 2003 (Fall 2003)</listitem><listitem>Monge, Luigi,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/779316'>&quot;The Language of Blind Lemon Jefferson: The Covert Theme of Blindness&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Black Music Research Journal</italics>, Vol. 20, No. 1, Blind Lemon Jefferson (Spring, 2000), pp.&amp;nbsp;3581 Published by: Center for Black Music Research Columbia College Chicago and University of Illinois Press</listitem><listitem>Uzzel, Robert L.,<space/><italics>Blind Lemon Jefferson: his life, his death, and his legacy</italics>, Austin, Tex. : Eakin Press, 2002. ISBN 9781571686565</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.blues.org/awards-search/hall-of-fame-inductees/hall-of-fame-inductees-winners/?y=25'>Blues Foundation Hall of Fame induction</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Allmusic</target><arg name="class">artist</arg><arg name="id">p390</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IMDb name</target><arg>4635781</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wirz.de/music/jefferso.htm'>Illustrated Blind Lemon Jefferson discography</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wkarrer.webs.com/blindlemonjefferson.htm'>The lyrics of his songs</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>findagrave</target><arg>6142078</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Blues</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Jefferson, Blind Lemon
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Jefferson, Lemon Henry (birth name); Bates, Deacon L. J. (pseudonym)
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>American blues singer and guitarist
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>September 24, 1893
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Coutchman, Texas
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>December 19, 1929
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Chicago, Illinois
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Jefferson, Blind Lemon</target></template><link><target>Category:1893 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1929 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:African-American musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:American blues guitarists</target></link><link><target>Category:American blues musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:American blues singers</target></link><link><target>Category:American blues singer-songwriters</target></link><link><target>Category:American buskers</target></link><link><target>Category:American male singers</target></link><link><target>Category:Blind musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:Blues Hall of Fame inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:Gospel blues musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Freestone County, Texas</target></link><link><target>Category:Musicians from Dallas, Texas</target></link><link><target>Category:Gennett Records artists</target></link><link><target>Category:Okeh Records artists</target></link><link><target>Category:Texas blues musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:Paramount Records artists</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century American singers</target></link></paragraph></article>