<article title='HM_Prison_Dartmoor'><paragraph><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox prison</target><arg name="prison_name"><space/>HMP Dartmoor
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:Dartmoor Prison and North Hessary.jpg|frameless]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Princetown, England|Princetown]], Devon
</arg><arg name="coordinates"><space/>
</arg><arg name="status"><space/>
</arg><arg name="classification"><space/>[[Prisoner security categories in the United Kingdom|Adult Male/Category C]]
</arg><arg name="capacity"><space/>
</arg><arg name="population"><space/>641
</arg><arg name="populationdate"><space/>June 2015
</arg><arg name="opened"><space/>1809
</arg><arg name="closed"><space/>
</arg><arg name="former_name">
</arg><arg name="managed_by"><space/>[[Her Majesty's Prison Service|HM Prison Services]]
</arg><arg name="governor"><space/>Bridie Oakes-Richards
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>{{HM prison|dartmoor|Dartmoor}}
</arg></template><bold>HM Prison Dartmoor</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Prison security categories in the United Kingdom</target><part>Category C</part></link><space/>men's prison, located in<space/><link><target>Princetown, England</target><part>Princetown</part></link>, high on<space/><link><target>Dartmoor</target></link><space/>in the English county of<space/><link><target>Devon</target></link>. Its high<space/><link><target>granite</target></link><space/>walls dominate this area of the<space/><link><target>moorland</target><part>moor</part></link>. The prison is owned by the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Cornwall</target></link>, and is operated by<space/><link><target>Her Majesty's Prison Service</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>In 1805, Great Britain was at<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target><part>war with Napoleonic France</part></link>; a conflict during which thousands of prisoners were taken and confined in prison &quot;hulks&quot; or derelict ships. This was considered unsafe, partially due to the proximity of the Royal Naval dockyard at<space/><link><target>Devonport, Devon</target><part>Devonport</part></link><space/>(then called Plymouth Dock), and as living conditions were appalling in the extreme, a prisoner of war depot was planned in the remote isolation of Dartmoor. Construction started in 1806, taking three years to complete. In 1809 the first French prisoners arrived, and were joined by American POWs taken in the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link>. At one time the prison population numbered almost 6,000. Many prisoners died and were buried on the moor. Both French and American wars were concluded in 1815, and repatriations began. The prison then lay empty until 1850, when it was largely rebuilt and commissioned as a convict gaol. With the establishment of the prison farm in about 1852, all the prisoners' remains were exhumed and re-interred in two cemeteries behind the prison.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early history</heading><paragraph>Designed by<space/><link><target>Daniel Asher Alexander</target></link><space/>and constructed originally between 1806 and 1809 by local labour, to hold prisoners of the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>, it was also used to hold American prisoners from the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link>. Although the war ended with the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Ghent</target></link><space/>in December 1814, many American<space/><link><target>prisoners of war</target></link><space/>still remained in Dartmoor.</paragraph><paragraph>From the spring of 1813 until March 1815 about 6,500 American sailors were imprisoned at Dartmoor. These were naval prisoners, and impressed American seamen discharged from British vessels. Whilst the British were in charge of the prison, the prisoners created their own governance and culture. They had courts which meted out punishments, there was an in-prison market, a theatre and a gambling room. About 1,000 of the prisoners were black Americans.<extension extension_name='ref'>1812: War with America, Jon Latimer, Harvard University Press, 2007 p. 239</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ea"><template><target>Americana</target><arg name="wstitle">Dartmoor Massacre, The</arg><arg name="inline">1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the prisoners heard of the Peace of Ghent, they expected immediate release, but the British government refused to let them go on parole or take any steps until the treaty was ratified by the<space/><link><target>United States Senate</target></link>, 17 February 1815. It took several weeks for the American agent to secure ships for their transportation home, and the men grew very impatient. On 4 April, a food contractor attempted to work off some damaged hardtack on them in place of soft bread and was forced to yield by their insurrection. The commandant, Captain T. G. Shortland, suspected them of a design to break out of the gaol. This was the reverse of the truth in general, as they would lose their chance of going on the ships, but a few had made threats of the sort, and the commandant was very uneasy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ea"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>About 6:00 pm of the 6th, Shortland discovered a hole from one of the five prisons to the barrack yard near the gun racks. Some prisoners were outside the fence, noisily pelting each other with turf, and many more were near the breach (and the gambling tables), though the signal for return to prisons had sounded. Shortland was convinced of a plot, and rang the alarm bell to collect the officers and have the men ready. This precaution brought back a crowd just going to quarters. Just then a prisoner broke a gate chain with an iron bar and a number of the prisoners pressed through to the prison market square. After attempts at persuasion, Shortland ordered a charge which drove some of the prisoners in. Those near the gate, however, hooted at and taunted the soldiery, who fired a volley over their heads. The crowd yelled louder and threw stones, and the soldiers, probably without orders, fired a direct volley which killed and wounded a large number. Then they continued firing at the prisoners, many of whom were now struggling to get back inside the blocks.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ea"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Finally the captain, a lieutenant and the hospital surgeon (the other officers being at dinner) succeeded in stopping the shooting and caring for the wounded about 60, 30 seriously, besides seven killed outright. The affair was examined by a joint commission, Charles King for the United States and F. S. Larpent for Great Britain, which exonerated Shortland, justified the initial shooting and blamed the subsequent deaths on unknown culprits. The British government provided for the families of the killed, pensioned the disabled and promoted Shortland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ea"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A memorial has been erected to the 271<space/><link><target>POW</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(mostly<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target><part>seamen</part></link>) who are buried in the prison grounds.</paragraph><paragraph>Dartmoor was reopened in 1851 as a civilian prison, but was closed again in 1917, when it was converted into a Home Office Work Centre for certain<space/><link><target>conscientious objectors</target></link><space/>granted release from prison; cells were unlocked, inmates wore their own clothes, and could visit the village in their off-duty time. It was reopened as a prison in 1920, and then contained some of Britain's most serious offenders.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Dartmoor mutiny</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dartmoor Prison entrance.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Main gates of Dartmoor Prison</part></link>On 24 January 1932, there was a major disturbance at the prison. The cause of the riots is generally attributed to the food, not generally but just on specific days when it was suspected it had been tampered with prior to the disturbance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fitzgerald, M. (1977)<space/><italics>Prisoners in Revolt</italics>, Harmondsworth: Penguin pg.123</extension><space/>There had also been other instances of disobedience prior to this, according to the official Du Parcq report into the incident such as a model prisoner attacking a popular guard with a razor blade and rough treatment of a prisoner being removed to solitary.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fitzgerald, M. (1977)<space/><italics>Prisoners In Revolt</italics>, Harmondsworth: Penguin pg.124</extension><space/>At the parade later that day, 50 prisoners refused orders, and the rest were marched back to their cells but refused to enter. At this point, the prison governor and his staff fled to an unused part of the prison and secured themselves in there. The prisoners then released those held in solitary. There was extensive damage to property and a prisoner was shot by one of the staff but no prison staff were injured.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fitzgerald, M. (1977)<space/><italics>Prisoners In Revolt</italics>, Harmondsworth: Penguin pg.124-5</extension><space/>According to Fitzgerald (1977) &quot;Reinforcements arrived, and within fifteen minutes these 'vicious brutes', who for some two hours had terrorized well-armed prison staff, and effectively controlled the prison, had surrendered and been locked up again&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fitzgerald, M. (1977)<space/><italics>Prisoners In Revolt</italics>, Harmondsworth: Penguin pg.126</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Post 2000 history</heading><paragraph>In 2001 a<space/><link><target>Board of Visitors</target></link><space/>report condemned sanitation at Dartmoor as well as highlighting a list of urgent repairs needed at the prison.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/1656099.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dartmoor prison sanitation 'unacceptable'<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 November 2001</arg></template></extension><space/>A year later Dartmoor was converted to a Category C prison for less violent offenders.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>In 2002 the<space/><link><target>Prison Reform Trust</target></link><space/>warned that Dartmoor Prison may be breaching the<space/><link><target>Human Rights Act 1998</target></link><space/>due to severe overcrowding at the jail.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2266627.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dartmoor breaches Human Rights<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 September 2002</arg></template></extension><space/>A year later, however, the Chief Inspector of Prisons declared that Dartmoor had made substantial improvements to its management and regime.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/devon/3066953.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Prison praised for progress<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 July 2003</arg></template></extension><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>In March 2008 staff at the prison passed a<space/><link><target>vote of no confidence</target></link><space/>in the governor Serena Watts, claiming they felt bullied by managers and unsafe.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/devon/7305479.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dartmoor prison staff 'bullied'<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 March 2008</arg></template></extension><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Previous governor Tony Corcoran is now governor of<space/><link><target>HM Prison Haverigg</target><part>HMP Haverigg</part></link>, taking up the post in early 2013.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The prison today</heading><paragraph>Dartmoor still has a misplaced reputation for being a high-security prison that is escape-proof. Now a Category C prison, Dartmoor houses mainly non-violent offenders and<space/><link><target>White-collar crime</target><part>white-collar</part></link><space/>criminals. It also holds sex offenders and offers sex offender treatment programmes intended to make the offender realise their behaviour is unacceptable.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Decca"></extension><space/>Some subsequently volunteer for behaviour changing treatment with medication under a scheme being piloted at<space/><link><target>HMP Whatton</target></link><space/>which has had encouraging results.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Decca"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/society/2013/jan/18/chemical-castration-soft-option-sex-offenders</arg><arg name="title">Chemical castration: the soft option?</arg><arg name="author">Decca Aitkenhead</arg><arg name="work">Guardian Newspapers</arg><arg name="date">18 January 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 January 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Dartmoor offers cellular accommodation on 6 wings. Education is available at the prison (full and part-time), and ranges from basic educational skills to<space/><link><target>Open University</target></link><space/>courses. Vocational training includes<space/><link><target>electronics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>brickwork</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>carpentry</target></link><space/>courses up to<space/><link><target>City &amp; Guilds</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>NVQ</target></link><space/>level,<space/><link><target>Painting and Decorating</target></link><space/>courses,<space/><link><target>janitor</target><part>industrial cleaning</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>desktop publishing</target></link>. Full-time employment is also available in catering, farming, gardening, laundry, textiles,<space/><link><target>Braille</target></link>, contract services, furniture manufacturing and<space/><link><target>polishing</target></link>. Employment is supported with NVQ or City &amp; Guilds vocational qualifications. All courses and qualifications at Dartmoor are operated by<space/><link><target>South Gloucestershire and Stroud College</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cornwall College</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The 'Dartmoor Jailbreak' is a yearly event, in which members of the public 'escape' from the prison and must travel as far as possible in 4 days, without directly paying for transport, raising money for charity.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://vranchhouse.org/about-vranch-house/fundraising/dartmoor-jailbreak/'>Dartmoor Jailbreak</link>.<space/><italics>Vranch House</italics>. Retrieved 15 January 2014</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Future</heading><paragraph>In September 2013 it was announced that discussions would commence with the Duchy of Cornwall about the long-term future of HMP Dartmoor.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thetimes.co.uk/tto/news/politics/article3860342.ece</arg><arg name="title">Dartmoor Prison set to close in latest jail shake-up</arg></template></extension><space/>In January 2014 it was stated on the BBC news website that the notice period with the Duchy for closing is 10 years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-devon-25613528</arg><arg name="title">Drug use and cell sharing 'still issues at Dartmoor Prison'
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Dartmoor Prison Museum</heading><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Dartmoor Prison Museum</bold>, located in the old dairy buildings, focuses on the history of HMP Dartmoor. Exhibits include the prison's role in housing<space/><link><target>prisoners of war</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link><space/>and the War of 1812,<space/><link><target>manacles</target></link><space/>and weapons, memorabilia, clothing and uniforms, famous prisoners, and the changed focus of the prison. It also sells (2015) garden ornaments and other items made in the prison concrete and carpentry shops by prisoners engaged in educational courses.</paragraph><paragraph>There are also displays and information on less well known aspects of the prison such as the incarceration of conscientious objectors during world war one.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notable former inmates</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Eamon de Valera c 1922-30.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>amon de Valera (1920s)</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Michael Davitt</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hammond, Louisiana#History</target><part>Peter Hammond</part></link>, founder of Hammond, Louisiana, USA</listitem><listitem><link><target>Fred Longden</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>John Rodker</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Moondyne Joe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas William Jones, Baron Maelor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Arthur Owens</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>amon de Valera</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>F. Digby Hardy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>John Williams (convict)</target><part>John Williams</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Frank Mitchell (prisoner)</target><part>Frank Mitchell</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Reginald Horace Blyth</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Darkie Hutton</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>John George Haigh</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>The adventure story<space/><italics>A Rogue by Compulsion. An Affair of the Secret Service</italics><space/>(1915) by<space/><link><target>Victor Bridges</target></link><space/>begins with a dramatic escape from Dartmoor.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/10511/pg10511.txt'>Retrieved 27 December 2012.</link></extension></listitem><listitem>In the John Galsworthy play,<space/><link><target>Escape (play)</target><part>Escape</part></link>, Dartmoor is the prison whence the hero, Captain Denman escapes. The stage production in 1927 starred Leslie Howard and the 1930 film version starred Sir Gerald du Maurier.</listitem><listitem>An escaped convict from Dartmoor figures in<space/><link><target>Nevil Shute</target></link>'s first novel<space/><italics><link><target>Marazan</target></link></italics>, published in 1926.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Decline and Fall</target></link></italics>, a novel by<space/><link><target>Evelyn Waugh</target></link>, first published in 1928 makes thinly disguised references to Dartmoor Prison.</listitem><listitem>Dartmoor Prison is mentioned in<space/><italics><link><target>The Thirteen Problems</target></link></italics>, a short story collection written by<space/><link><target>Agatha Christie</target></link>, and first published in 1932. Christie's<space/><italics>The Sittaford Mystery</italics><space/>(1931) is set on Dartmoor and features an escaped prisoner.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link><space/>made reference to 'Princetown Prison' in four stories that he wrote between 1890 and 1903. In<space/><italics>The Hound of the Baskervilles</italics><space/>(1902), an escaped prisoner from Princetown serves as a red herring for Holmes and Watson.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Dressed to Kill (1946 film)</target><part>Dressed to Kill</part></link></italics>, A 1946<space/><link><target>Sherlock Holmes</target></link><space/>film uses Dartmoor Prison in the plot as the supposed location where three music boxes were made that contain a secret code for a criminal gang.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Weaver</arg><arg name="first">Tom</arg><arg name="title">Universal horrors: the studio's classic films, 1931–1946</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">McFarland</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Referenced in Bob Miller's song,<space/><italics>Twenty-One Years</italics>.</listitem><listitem>In the<space/><italics>Tales of Old Dartmoor</italics><space/>episode (recorded in 1956) of<space/><link><target>Goons</target><part>The Goons</part></link><space/>radio comedy series,<space/><link><target>Hercules Grytpype-Thynne</target><part>Grytpype-Thynne</part></link><space/>arranges for the prison to put to sea to visit the<space/><link><target>Chteau d'If</target></link><space/>in France as part of a plan to find the treasure of the Count of Monte Cristo hid there. A cardboard replica is left in its place, which is left standing after the original Dartmoor Prison sinks with all hands at the end of the episode.</listitem><listitem>In an episode of<space/><italics><link><target>The Saint (TV series)</target><part>The Saint</part></link></italics><space/>television series entitled 'Escape Route' (1966),<space/><link><target>Simon Templar</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Roger Moore</target></link>) is sent to Dartmoor to uncover a planned escape.</listitem><listitem>Comedy Band<space/><link><target>The Barron Knights</target></link>' 1978 UK No. 3 hit single<space/><italics>A Taste of Aggro</italics>, a<space/><link><target>medley (music)</target><part>medley</part></link><space/>of parodies, included a version of<space/><italics>The Smurf Song</italics><space/>featuring, in place of the<space/><link><target>Smurfs</target></link>, a group of bank robbers from<space/><link><target>Catford</target></link><space/>who have escaped from Dartmoor Prison.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.lyricsondemand.com/b/barronknightslyrics/atasteofaggrolyrics.html'>Barron Knights Lyrics: A Taste Of Aggro Lyrics</link>.<space/><italics>Lyrics on Demand</italics>. Retrieved 15 January 2014</extension></listitem><listitem>In 1988, the prison played host to a storyline in<space/><italics><link><target>EastEnders</target></link></italics>, where<space/><link><target>Den Watts</target></link><space/>(played by<space/><link><target>Leslie Grantham</target></link>) was being held on remand for arson. He was also joined for some of the storyline by<space/><link><target>Nick Cotton</target></link><space/>(played by<space/><link><target>John Altman (actor)</target><part>John Altman</part></link>), who was imprisoned for a different offence. The prison was called<space/><link><target>Dickens Hill</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Dartmoor is frequently mentioned in the<space/><italics><link><target>Agent Z</target></link></italics><space/>series of comical children's books written by<space/><link><target>Mark Haddon</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Dartmoor prison is implicated in the local Dartmoor '<link><target>Hairy hands</target></link>'<space/><link><target>ghost story</target></link>/<link><target>legend</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Dartmoor prison plays a central role in<space/><italics>The Lively Lady</italics>, American author<space/><link><target>Kenneth Roberts (author)</target><part>Kenneth Roberts</part></link>' 1931 historical novel taking place during The<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link></listitem><listitem>In the first episode of the second series of<space/><italics><link><target>James May's Man Lab</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>James May</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oz Clarke</target></link><space/>were demonstrating map-reading skills by pretending to escape from Dartmoor prison and cross<space/><link><target>Dartmoor</target></link><space/>to their escape car<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">BBC Two – James May's Man Lab, Series 2, Episode 1</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b016mz66</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 October 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>(although they had to start their escape from outside the prison grounds as they were not allowed permission inside the prison).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>33em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.justice.gov.uk/global/contacts/noms/prison-finder/dartmoor/'>Ministry of Justice pages on Dartmoor</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor-prison.co.uk/'>Dartmoor Prison Museum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.justiceinspectorates.gov.uk/hmiprisons/inspections/?s&amp;amp;location=dartmoor'>HMP Dartmoor - HM Inspectorate of Prisons Reports</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Coord</target><arg>50</arg><arg>32</arg><arg>59</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>3</arg><arg>59</arg><arg>46</arg><arg>W</arg><arg name="display">title</arg><arg>type:landmark_region:GB</arg></template><template><target>Prisons in South West England</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Dartmoor (Hm Prison)</target></template><link><target>Category:Category C prisons in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Dartmoor</target></link><link><target>Category:Prisons in Devon</target></link><link><target>Category:1809 establishments in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Museums in Devon</target></link><link><target>Category:Prison museums in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link><link><target>Category:Men's prisons</target></link></paragraph></article>