<article title='Celestines'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target><arg>Celestine (disambiguation)</arg></template><link><target>File:Religieux clestin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>right</part><part>Religious habit of the Celestine Order (18th century image).</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Celestines</bold><space/>were a<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/><link><target>monasticism</target><part>monastic</part></link><space/><link><target>Order (religious)</target><part>order</part></link>, a branch of the<space/><link><target>Benedictine</target><trail>s</trail></link>, founded in 1244.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Between Church and State: The Lives of Four French Prelates in the Late Middle Ages</arg><arg name="first1">Bernard</arg><arg name="first2">Arthur<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Goldhammer</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Chicago Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="isbn">0-226-31032-9</arg></template></extension><space/>At the foundation of the new rule, they were called<space/><link><target>Hermit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of St Damiano, or Moronites (or Murronites), and did not assume the appellation of Celestines until after the election of their founder, Peter of Morone (Pietro Murrone), to the<space/><link><target>Papacy</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Pope Celestine V</target><part>Celestine V</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>CathEncy</target><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/16019a.htm</arg><arg name="title">Celestine Order</arg></template></extension><space/>The fame of the holy life and the austerities practised by the hermit in his solitude on the Mountain of Majella, near<space/><link><target>Sulmona</target></link>, attracted many visitors, several of whom were moved to remain and share his mode of life. They built a small<space/><link><target>convent</target></link><space/>on the spot inhabited by the holy hermit, which became too small for the accommodation of those who came to share their life of privations. Peter of Morone (later Pope Celestine V), their founder, built a number of other small<space/><link><target>Oratory (worship)</target><part>oratories</part></link><space/>in that neighborhood.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Founding</heading><paragraph>About the year 1254, Peter of Morone gave the order a rule formulated in accordance with his own practices. In 1264 the new institution was approved by<space/><link><target>Pope Urban IV</target><part>Urban IV</part></link>; however, the next pope<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory X</target></link><space/>had commanded that all orders founded since the prior<space/><link><target>Lateran Council</target></link><space/>should not be further multiplied, and was rumored to be planning to suppress. This prompted even the reclusive Peter to travel to<space/><link><target>Lyon</target></link>, where the Pope was holding a council. There he persuading Gregory to approve his new order, making it a branch of the Benedictines and following the<space/><link><target>Rule of St Benedict</target><part>rule of Saint Benedict</part></link>, but adding to it additional severities and privations. Gregory took it under the Papal protection, assured to it the possession of all property it might acquire, and endowed it with exemption from the authority of the ordinary. Nothing more was needed to ensure the rapid spread of the new association and Peter the hermit of Morone lived to see himself &quot;Superior-General&quot; to thirty-six<space/><link><target>monastery</target><part>monasteries</part></link><space/>and more than six hundred<space/><link><target>monk</target><trail>s</trail></link>. However, even as a monastic superior, Peter cannot be accused of ambition or the lust of power, since he insisted on divesting himself of the Papacy, to which he was subsequently raised.<space/><link><target>File:Couvent des Clestins d'Avignon - cloitre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>270px</part><part>Celestine cloister. Avignon, France.</part></link>As soon as he had seen his new order thus consolidated he gave up the government of it to a certain Robert, and retired once again to an even more remote site to devote himself to solitary penance and prayer. Shortly afterwards, in a chapter of the order held in 1293, the original monastery of Majella being judged to be too desolate and exposed to too rigorous a climate, it was decided that the<space/><link><target>Abbey of the Holy Spirit at Monte Morrone, Sulmona</target><part>Abbey of the Holy Spirit at Monte Morrone</part></link>, located in Sulmona, should be the headquarters of the order and the residence of the General-Superior, where it continued for centuries. The next year Peter of Morrone, despite his reluctance, was elected Pope by the name of Celestine V. From there on, the order he had founded took the name of Celestines. During his short reign as Pope, the former hermit confirme the rule of the order, which he had himself composed, and to confer on the society a variety of special graces and privileges. In the only creation of<space/><link><target>Cardinal (Catholicism)</target><part>cardinal</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>promoted by him, among the twelve raised to the purple, there were two monks of his order. He also visited personally the Benedictine monastery on<space/><link><target>Monte Cassino</target></link>, where he persuaded the monks to accept his more rigorous rule. He sent fifty monks of his order to introduce it, who remained there, however, for only a few months.</paragraph><paragraph>After the death of the founder the order was favoured and privileged by<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XI</target><part>Benedict XI</part></link>, and rapidly spread through<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Flanders</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, where they were received by<space/><link><target>Philip IV of France</target><part>Philip the Fair</part></link><space/>in 1300. Subsequently the French Celestines, with the consent of the Italian superiors of the order, and of<space/><link><target>Pope Martin V</target></link><space/>in 1427, obtained the privilege of making new constitutions for themselves, which they did in the 17th century in a series of regulations accepted by the provincial chapter in 1667. At that time the French congregation of the order was composed of twenty-one monasteries, the head of which was that of<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>, and was governed by a Provincial with the authority of General.<space/><link><target>Pope Paul V</target><part>Paul V</part></link><space/>was a notable benefactor of the order. But in consequence of later political changes and events the order has been dissolved.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Description of order</heading><paragraph>According to their special constitutions the Celestines were bound to say<space/><link><target>matins</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>choir</target></link><space/>at two o'clock in the morning, and always to abstain from eating meat, save in illness. The distinct rules of their order with regard to<space/><link><target>fasting</target></link><space/>are numerous, but not more severe than those of similar congregations, though much more so than is required by the old Benedictine rule. In reading their minute directions for divers degrees of abstinence on various days, it is impossible to avoid being struck by the conviction that the great object of the framers of these rules was the general purpose of ensuring an<space/><link><target>asceticism</target><part>ascetic</part></link><space/>mode of life.</paragraph><paragraph>The Celestines wore a white<space/><link><target>wool</target><trail>len</trail></link><space/><link><target>cassock</target></link><space/>bound with a<space/><link><target>linen</target></link><space/>band, and a<space/><link><target>leather</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>girdle</target></link><space/>of the same colour, with a<space/><link><target>scapular</target></link><space/>unattached to the body of the dress, and a black<space/><link><target>hood (headgear)</target><part>hood</part></link>. It was not permitted to them to wear any shirt save of<space/><link><target>serge (fabric)</target><part>serge</part></link>. Their dress in short was very like that of the<space/><link><target>Cistercians</target></link>. But it is a tradition in the order that in the time of the founder they wore a coarse brown cloth. The church and monastery of<space/><link><target>San Pietro in Montorio</target></link><space/>originally belonged to the Celestines in<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link>; but they were turned out of it by<space/><link><target>Pope Sixtus IV</target><part>Sixtus IV</part></link><space/>to make way for<space/><link><target>Franciscan</target><trail>s</trail></link>, receiving from the Pope in exchange the Church of<space/><link><target>St Eusebius of Vercelli</target></link><space/>with the adjacent mansion for a monastery.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>commons</target><arg>Category:Celestine order</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Celestine Order</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1244 establishments</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Catholic orders and societies</target></link><link><target>Category:Religious organizations established in the 1240s</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian religious orders established in the 13th century</target></link></paragraph></article>