<article title='Category_of_being'><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>metaphysics</target></link><space/>(in particular,<space/><link><target>ontology</target></link>)<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template>, the different kinds or ways of<space/><link><target>being</target></link><space/>are called<space/><bold>categories of being</bold><space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template><space/>or simply<space/><bold>categories.</bold><space/>To investigate the categories of being is to determine the most fundamental and the broadest<space/><link><target>class (philosophy)</target><part>class</part><trail>es</trail></link><space/>of entities. A distinction between such categories, in making the categories or applying them, is called an<space/><bold>ontological distinction</bold>.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Introduction</heading><paragraph>The categories of being, or simply the categories, are defined as the highest classes under which all elements of being whether material or conceptual can be classified. These categories belong to the realm of philosophy and the difference between categories and classes was described by the philosopher<space/><link><target>Clarence Irving Lewis</target><part>C.I. Lewis</part></link><space/>as that of a hierarchical<space/><link><target>Porphyrian tree</target><part>tree</part></link><space/>or pyramid where the most general categories such as those of logic are to be found at the top and the least general classes such as species of animal at the bottom.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis C.I.<space/><italics>Mind and the World Order</italics><space/>1929, pp.233-234</extension><space/>There are therefore two main areas of interest (i) at the top of the tree - how being first divides into discrete or overlapping subentities, and (ii) at the bottom of the tree - how the different elements can be correlated into higher classes. The structure may consist of a simple list such as the one produced by<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle<space/><italics>Categories</italics><space/>in<space/><italics>Aristotles Categories and De Interpretatione</italics><space/>(tr. Ackrill J.L. Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1963) Ch.4</extension><space/>or it may be composed of headings and subheadings such as the tables produced by<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kant I.<space/><italics>Critique of Pure Reason</italics><space/>1781 (tr. Smith N.K., Macmillan, London, 1968)</extension><space/>The elements of being are commonly seen as things, whether objects or concepts, but most systems will also include as elements the<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>relations</part></link><space/>between the objects and concepts. The distinction is also made between the elements themselves and the words used to denote such elements. The word category itself is derived from the Greek<space/><italics>kategorien</italics><space/>meaning to predicate, and therefore the categories may also be thought of as kinds of predicate which may be applied to any particular subject or element, and by extension to the concept of being itself.</paragraph><paragraph>If we take any subject and with it form a sentence the subject is then in a valid system of categorisation all the different things we can say about the subject should be classifiable under one of the categories within the system. Aristotle listed<space/><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>ten categories</part></link><space/>amongst which we find, for example, the three categories of<space/><link><target>Substance theory</target><part>Substance</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Quantity</target></link>. In<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target><part>Heidegger</part></link>s example This is a house. It is both red and tall the word house can be classified under Substance, red under Quality and tall under Quantity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heidegger M.<space/><italics>What is a Thing</italics><space/>1935 (tr. Barton W. &amp; Deutsch V. Henry Regnery, Chicago, 1967) pp.62,187</extension><space/>The subject, the house, gathers around it what was called in the 19th century a colligation of concepts<extension extension_name='ref'>Peirce C.S.<space/><italics>Collected Papers of Charles Sanders Peirce</italics><space/>(Hartshorne C. &amp; Weiss P. (eds) Harvard University Press, 1931) Vol.2, p.267</extension><space/>or in the 20th century a<space/><link><target>Bundle theory</target><part>bundle of properties</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>cf Locke J.<space/><italics>Essay concerning Human Understanding</italics><space/>(J.F.Dove, London, 1828) p.371 on coexistence of qualities</extension><space/>all of which serve to define the house. By extension we can say that all being consists of nothing but Substance, Quality, Quantity and the rest because nothing else can be said of the subject. Categorisation has raised many problems throughout the history of philosophy, including those of the number and types of category, how the categories interrelate with one another and whether they are real in some way or just mental constructs, and to introduce the many different solutions that have arisen it is worth considering the history of the categories in brief outline.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early Development</heading><paragraph>The process of abstraction required to discover the number and names of the categories has been undertaken by many philosophers since<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>and involves the careful inspection of each concept to ensure that there is no higher category or categories under which that concept could be subsumed. The<space/><link><target>Scholasticism</target><part>scholars</part></link><space/>of the twelfth and thirteenth centuries developed Aristotles ideas, firstly, for example by<space/><link><target>Gilbert de la Porre</target><part>Gilbert of Poitiers</part></link>, dividing Aristotle's ten categories into two sets, primary and secondary, according to whether they inhere in the subject or not:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Primary categories: Substance, Relation, Quantity and Quality</listitem><listitem>Secondary categories: Place, Time, Situation, Condition, Action, Passion<extension extension_name='ref'>Reese W.L.<space/><italics>Dictionary of Philosophy and Religion</italics><space/>(Harvester Press, 1980)</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Secondly, following<space/><link><target>Porphyry (philosopher)</target><part>Porphyry</part></link>s likening of the classificatory hierarchy to a<space/><link><target>Porphyrian tree</target><part>tree</part></link>, they concluded that the major classes could be subdivided to form subclasses, for example,<space/><link><target>Substance theory</target><part>Substance</part></link><space/>could be divided into<space/><link><target>Genus</target></link><space/>and Species, and<space/><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link><space/>could be subdivided into<space/><link><target>Property (philosophy)</target><part>Property</part></link><space/>and Accident, depending on whether the property was necessary or contingent.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid</italics>. cf Evangelou C.<space/><italics>Aristotles Categories and Porphyry</italics><space/>(E.J.Brill, Leiden, 1988)</extension><space/>An alternative line of development was taken by<space/><link><target>Plotinus</target></link><space/>in the second century who by a process of abstraction reduced Aristotles list of ten categories to five: Substance, Relation, Quantity, Motion and Quality.<extension extension_name='ref'>Plotinus<space/><italics>Enneads</italics><space/>(tr. Mackenna S. &amp; Page B.S., The Medici Society, London, 1930) VI.3.3</extension><space/>Plotinus further suggested that the latter three categories of his list, namely Quantity, Motion and Quality correspond to three different<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>kinds of relation</part></link><space/>and that these three categories could therefore be subsumed under the category of Relation.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid</italics>. VI.3.21</extension><space/>This was to lead to the supposition that there were only two categories at the top of the hierarchical tree, namely Substance and Relation, and if relations only exist in the mind as many supposed, to the two highest categories, Mind and Matter, reflected most clearly in the dualism of<space/><link><target>Ren Descartes</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Descartes R.<space/><italics>The Philosophical Works of Descartes</italics><space/>(tr. Haldane E. &amp; Ross G., Dover, New York, 1911) Vol.1</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern Development</heading><paragraph>An alternative conclusion however began to be formulated in the eighteenth century by<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link><space/>who realised that we can say nothing about<space/><link><target>Substance theory</target><part>Substance</part></link><space/>except through the relation of the subject to other things.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.3</italics><space/>p.87</extension><space/>In the sentence This is a house the substantive subject house only gains meaning in relation to human use patterns or to other similar houses. The category of Substance disappears from<space/><link><target>Category (Kant)</target><part>Kants tables</part></link>, and under the heading of Relation, Kant lists<space/><italics>inter alia</italics><space/>the three relationship types of<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>Disjunction, Causality and Inherence</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>pp.107,113</extension><space/>The three older concepts of Quantity, Motion and Quality, as<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target><part>Peirce</part></link><space/>discovered, could be subsumed under these three broader headings in that<space/><link><target>Quantity</target></link><space/>relates to the subject through the relation of<space/><link><target>Logical disjunction</target><part>Disjunction</part></link>; Motion relates to the subject through the relation of<space/><link><target>Causality</target></link>; and<space/><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link><space/>relates to the subject through the relation of<space/><link><target>Inherence</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.5</italics><space/>pp.148-179</extension><space/>Sets of three continued to play an important part in the nineteenth century development of the categories, most notably in<space/><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target><part>G.W.F.Hegels</part></link><space/>extensive tabulation of categories,<extension extension_name='ref'>Stace W.T.<space/><italics>The Philosophy of Hegel</italics><space/>(Macmillan &amp; Co, London, 1924)</extension><space/>and in<space/><link><target>Categories (Peirce)</target><part>C.S.Peirces categories</part></link><space/>set out in his work on the logic of relations. One of Peirces contributions was to call the three primary categories Firstness, Secondness and Thirdness<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.5</italics><space/>pp.148-179</extension><space/>which both emphasises their general nature, and avoids the confusion of having the same name for both the category itself and for a concept within that category.</paragraph><paragraph>In a separate development, and building on the notion of primary and secondary categories introduced by the Scholastics,<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link><space/>introduced the idea that secondary or derivative categories could be derived from the primary categories through the combination of one primary category with another.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.3</italics><space/>p.116</extension><space/>This would result in the formation of three secondary categories: the first, Community was an example that Kant gave of such a derivative category; the second,<space/><link><target>Linguistic modality</target><part>Modality</part></link>, introduced by Kant, was a term which Hegel, in developing Kants dialectical method, showed could also be seen as a derivative category;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hegel G.W.F.<space/><italics>Logic</italics><space/>(tr. Wallace W., Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1975) pp.124ff</extension><space/>and the third, Spirit or Will were terms that<space/><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target><part>Hegel</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.15</italics></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target><part>Schopenhauer</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Schopenhauer A.<space/><italics>On the Four-Fold Root of the Principle of Sufficient Reason</italics><space/>1813 (tr. Payne E., La Salle, Illinois, 1974)</extension><space/>were developing separately for use in their own systems.<space/><link><target>Karl Jaspers</target></link><space/>in the twentieth century, in his development of existential categories, brought the three together, allowing for differences in terminology, as Substantiality, Communication and Will.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jaspers K.<space/><italics>Philosophy</italics><space/>1932 (tr. Ashton E.B., University of Chicago Press, 1970) pp.117ff</extension><space/>This pattern of three primary and three secondary categories was used most notably in the nineteenth century by<space/><link><target>Peter Mark Roget</target></link><space/>to form the six headings of his<space/><link><target>Roget's Thesaurus</target><part>Thesaurus</part></link><space/>of English Words and Phrases. The headings used were the three objective categories of Abstract Relation, Space (including Motion) and Matter and the three subjective categories of Intellect, Feeling and Volition, and he found that under these six headings all the words of the English language, and hence any possible predicate, could be assembled.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roget P.M.<space/><italics>Rogets Thesaurus: The Everyman Edition</italics><space/>1952 (Pan Books, London, 1972)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Twentieth Century Development</heading><paragraph>In the twentieth century the primacy of the division between the subjective and the objective, or between mind and matter, was disputed by, among others,<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Russell B.<space/><italics>The Analysis of Mind</italics><space/>(George Allen &amp; Unwin, London, 1921) pp.10,23</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Gilbert Ryle</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ryle G.<space/><italics>The Concept of Mind</italics><space/>(Penguin, Harmondsworth, 1949) pp.17ff</extension><space/>Philosophy began to move away from the metaphysics of categorisation towards the linguistic problem of trying to differentiate between, and define, the words being used.<space/><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target></link>s conclusion was that there were no clear definitions which we can give to words and categories but only a halo or corona<extension extension_name='ref'>Wittgenstein L.<space/><italics>Philosophical Investigations</italics><space/>1953 (tr. Anscombe G., Blackwell, Oxford, 1978) pp.14,181</extension><space/>of related meanings radiating around each term. Gilbert Ryle thought the problem could be seen in terms of dealing with a galaxy of ideas rather than a single idea, and suggested that<space/><link><target>category mistake</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are made when a concept (e.g. university), understood as falling under one category (e.g. abstract idea), is used as though it falls under another (e.g. physical object).<extension extension_name='ref'>Ryle G.<space/><italics>Collected Papers</italics><space/>(Hutchinson, London, 1971) Vol.II:<space/><italics>Philosophical Arguments</italics><space/>1945, pp.201,202</extension><space/>With regard to the visual analogies being used,<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target><part>Peirce</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Clarence Irving Lewis</target><part>Lewis</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.1</italics><space/>pp.52,82,106</extension><space/>just like<space/><link><target>Plotinus</target></link><space/>earlier,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.9</italics><space/>VI.5.5</extension><space/>likened the terms of propositions to points, and the relations between the terms to lines. Peirce, taking this further, talked of univalent, bivalent and trivalent relations linking predicates to their subject and it is just the number and<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>types of relation</part></link><space/>linking subject and predicate that determine the category into which a predicate might fall.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.5</italics><space/>Vol I pp.159,176</extension><space/>Primary categories contain concepts where there is one dominant kind of relation to the subject. Secondary categories contain concepts where there are two dominant kinds of relation. Examples of the latter were given by<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target><part>Heidegger</part></link><space/>in his two propositions the house is on the creek where the two dominant relations are spatial location (Disjunction) and cultural association (Inherence), and the house is eighteenth century where the two relations are temporal location (Causality) and cultural quality (Inherence).<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.4</italics><space/>pp.62,187</extension><space/>A third example may be inferred from Kant in the proposition the house is impressive or<space/><link><target>Sublime (philosophy)</target><part>sublime</part></link><space/>where the two relations are spatial or mathematical disposition (Disjunction) and dynamic or motive power (Causality).<extension extension_name='ref'>Kant I.<space/><italics>Critique of Judgement</italics><space/>1790 (tr. Meredith J.C., Clarendon Press, Oxford 1952) p.94ff</extension><space/>Both<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target><part>Peirce</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target><part>Wittgenstein</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.25</italics><space/>pp.36,152</extension><space/>introduced the analogy of<space/><link><target>colour theory</target></link><space/>in order to illustrate the shades of meanings of words. Primary categories, like primary colours, are analytical representing the furthest we can go in terms of analysis and abstraction and include Quantity, Motion and Quality. Secondary categories, like secondary colours, are synthetic and include concepts such as Substance, Community and Spirit.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Categorical distinctions</heading><paragraph>The common or dominant ways to view categories as of the end of the 20th century.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>via<space/><link><target>bundle theory</target></link><space/>as bundles of properties categories reflect differences in these</listitem><listitem>via peer-to-peer comparisons or<space/><link><target>dialectic</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>categories are formed by conflict/debate</listitem><listitem>via<space/><link><target>value theory</target></link><space/>as leading to specific ends categories are formed by choosing ends</listitem><listitem>via<space/><link><target>conceptual metaphor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as arising from characteristics of human<space/><link><target>cognition</target></link><space/>itself categories are found via<space/><link><target>cognitive science</target></link><space/>and other study of that biological system</listitem></list><paragraph>Any of these ways can be criticized for...</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>for seeking to make distinctions that aren't as universal as claimed (<link><target>greedy reductionism</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>for serious<space/><link><target>bias</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>perspective (cognitive)</target><part>point of view</part></link><space/>(<link><target>subject-object problem</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>God's eye view</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>for relying on theological or spiritual claims<space/><link><target>A priori and a posteriori</target><part>a priori</part></link>, for relying too much on surface conflict or current investigative priorities to point out differences</listitem><listitem>for ignoring<space/><link><target>action (philosophy)</target><part>action</part></link></listitem><listitem>for ignoring<space/><link><target>environmentalism (psychology)</target><part>the perceived</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Gaia philosophy</target><part>biospheric</part></link><space/>context, or<space/><link><target>embodied philosophy</target><part>the cognitive mechanisms that perceive and invent categories</part></link></listitem><listitem>or for relying on a complex empirical process of investigation that is poorly understood and only recently embarked upon.</listitem></list><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>process philosophy</target></link>, this last is the only possibility, but historically philosophers have been loath to conclude that nothing exists but process.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Categorization of existence</heading><heading level='3'>As bundles of properties</heading><paragraph><link><target>Bundle theory</target></link><space/>is an ontological theory about objecthood proposed by the 18th century Scottish philosopher<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link>, which states that objects only subsist as a collection (bundle) of properties, relations or tropes. In an<space/><italics>epistemological</italics><space/>sense, bundle theory says that all that can be known about objects are the properties which they are composed of, and that these properties are all that can be truly said to exist.</paragraph><paragraph>For example, if we take the concept of a black square, bundle theory would suggest that all that can be said to exist are the properties of a black square.</paragraph><paragraph>The properties of a black square are:<space/><bold>Black,</bold><space/><bold>Regular</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>Quadrilateral.<space/></bold></paragraph><paragraph>However, from these properties alone, we cannot deduce any kind of underlying essence of a &quot;black square&quot;, or some object called a &quot;black square&quot;, except as a bundle of properties which constitute the object that we then go on to label as a<space/><italics>&quot;black square&quot;</italics>, but the object<space/><italics>itself</italics><space/>is really nothing more than a system of relations (or bundle) of properties. To defend this, Hume asks us to imagine an object without properties, if we strip the black square of its properties (being black, regular and quadrilateral) we end up reducing the object to non-existence.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template><template><target>Empty section</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>As formed by debate</heading><paragraph><template><target>Empty section</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Intuition as evasion</heading><paragraph>A seemingly simpler way to view categories is as arising only from intuition. Philosophers argue this evades the issue. What it means to take the category<space/><link><target>physical object</target></link><space/>seriously as a category of being is to assert that the concept of physical objecthood cannot be reduced to or explicated in any other terms not, for example, in terms of<space/><link><target>bundle theory</target><part>bundles of properties</part></link><space/>but only in terms of other items in that category.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In this way, many ontological controversies can be understood as controversies about exactly which categories should be seen as fundamental, irreducible, or primitive. To refer to intuition as the source of distinctions and thus categories doesn't resolve this.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Ideology, dogma, theory</heading><paragraph>Modern theories give weight to intuition, perceptually observed properties, comparisons of categories among persons, and the direction of investigation towards known specified ends, to determine what<space/><link><target>human</target><trail>ity</trail></link><space/>in its present state of being needs to consider irreducible. They seek to explain why certain beliefs about categories would appear in<space/><link><target>political science</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>ideology</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>religion</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>dogma</target></link>, or in<space/><link><target>science</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>theory</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>As metaphors</heading><paragraph>A set of ontological distinctions related by a single<space/><link><target>conceptual metaphor</target></link><space/>was called an<space/><link><target>ontological metaphor</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>George Lakoff</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mark Johnson (professor)</target><part>Mark Johnson</part></link>, who claimed that such metaphors arising from<space/><link><target>experience</target></link><space/>were more basic than any properties or symbol-based comparisons. Their<space/><link><target>cognitive science of mathematics</target></link><space/>was a study of the embodiment of basic symbols and properties including those studied in the<space/><link><target>philosophy of mathematics</target></link>, via<space/><link><target>embodied philosophy</target></link>, using<space/><link><target>cognitive science</target></link>. This theory comes after several thousand years of inquiry into patterns and<space/><link><target>cognitive bias</target></link><space/>of humanity.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Categories of being</heading><paragraph>Philosophers have many differing views on what the fundamental categories of being are. In no particular order, here are at least<space/><italics>some</italics><space/>items that have been regarded as categories of being by someone or other:<template><target>who</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Physical objects</heading><paragraph><link><target>Physical object</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are beings; certainly they are said to<space/><italics>be</italics><space/>in the simple sense that they<space/><italics>exist</italics><space/>all around us. So a house is a being, a person's body is a being, a tree is a being, a cloud is a being, and so on. They are beings because, and in the sense that, they are physical objects. One might also call them<space/><link><target>Physical body</target><part>bodies</part></link>, or physical<space/><link><target>particular</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or<space/><link><target>concrete</target></link><space/>things, or<space/><link><target>matter</target></link>, or maybe<space/><link><target>Substance theory</target><part>substance</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(but bear in mind the word 'substance' has some special philosophical meanings).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Minds</heading><paragraph><link><target>Mind</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>those &quot;parts&quot; of us that think and perceiveare considered beings by some philosophers. Each of us, according to<space/><link><target>common sense</target></link><space/>anyway, &quot;has&quot; a mind. Of course, philosophers rarely just assume that minds occupy a different category of beings from physical objects. Some, like<space/><link><target>Ren Descartes</target></link>, have thought that this is so (this view is known as<space/><link><target>dualism</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Functionalism (philosophy of mind)</target><part>functionalism</part></link><space/>also considers the mind as distinct from the body), while others have thought that concepts of the mental can be<space/><link><target>Reduction (philosophy)</target><part>reduced</part></link><space/>to physical concepts (this is the view of<space/><link><target>physicalism</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>materialism</target></link>). Still others maintain though &quot;mind&quot; is a noun, it is not necessarily the &quot;name of a thing&quot; distinct within the whole person. In this view the relationship between mental properties and physical properties is one of<space/><link><target>supervenience</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; similar to how &quot;banks&quot; supervene upon certain buildings.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Classes</heading><paragraph>We can talk about all human beings, and the planets, and all engines as belonging to<space/><link><target>class (philosophy)</target><part>class</part><trail>es</trail></link>. Within the class of human beings are all of the human beings, or the<space/><link><target>extension (semantics)</target><part>extension</part></link><space/>of the term 'human being'. In the class of<space/><link><target>planet</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>would be Mercury, Venus, the Earth, and all the other planets that there might be in the universe. Classes, in addition to each of their members, are often taken to be beings. Surely we can say that in some sense, the class of planets<space/><italics>is</italics>, or has being. Classes are usually taken to be<space/><link><target>abstract objects</target></link>, like sets; 'class' is often regarded as equivalent, or nearly equivalent, in meaning to '<link><target>Set (mathematics)</target><part>set</part></link>'. Denying that classes and sets exist is the contemporary meaning of<space/><link><target>nominalism</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Properties</heading><paragraph>The redness of a red apple, or more to the point, the redness all red things share, is a<space/><italics><link><target>property (philosophy)</target><part>property</part></link></italics>. One could also call it an<space/><italics>attribute</italics><space/>of the apple. Very roughly put, a property is just a quality that describes an object. This will not do as a definition of the word 'property' because, like 'attribute', 'quality' is a near-synonym of 'property'. But these synonyms can at least help us to get a fix on the concept we are talking about. Whenever one talks about the size, color, weight, composition, and so forth, of an object, one is talking about the properties of that object. Somethough this is a point of severe contention in the<space/><link><target>problem of universals</target></link><space/>believe that properties are beings; the redness of all apples is something that<space/><italics>is.</italics><space/>To deny that universals exist is the<space/><link><target>Scholastic philosophy</target><part>scholastic</part></link><space/>variant of<space/><link><target>nominalism</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Note that the color red is an objective property of an object. The intrinsic property is that it reflects radiation (including light) in a certain way. A human perceives that as the color red in his or her brain. An object thus has two types of properties, intrinsic (physical) and objective (observer specific).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Relations</heading><paragraph>An apple sitting on a table is in a<space/><link><target>logic of relatives</target><part>relation</part></link><space/>to the table it sits on. So we can say that there is a relation between the apple and the table: namely, the relation of sitting-on. So, some say, we can say that that relation has being. For another example, the<space/><link><target>Washington Monument</target></link><space/>is taller than the<space/><link><target>White House</target></link>. Being-taller-than is a relation between the two structures. We can say that<space/><italics>that</italics><space/>relation has being as well. This, too, is a point of contention in the<space/><link><target>problem of universals</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Space and time</heading><paragraph>Space and time are what physical objects are extended into. There is debate as to whether time exists<space/><link><target>presentism (philosophy of time)</target><part>only in the present</part></link><space/>or whether far away times are<space/><link><target>eternalism (philosophy of time)</target><part>just as real as far away spaces</part></link>, and there is debate (among who?) as to whether<space/><link><target>Curved space</target><part>space is curved</part></link>. Many (nearly all?) contemporary thinkers actually suggest that<space/><link><target>spacetime</target><part>time is the fourth dimension</part></link>, thus reducing space and time to one distinct ontological entity, the<space/><link><target>spacetime</target><part>space-time continuum</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Propositions</heading><paragraph><link><target>Proposition (philosophy)</target><part>Proposition</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are units of meaning. They should not be confused with<space/><link><target>declarative sentence</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are just sets of words in languages that refer to propositions. Declarative sentences, ontologically speaking, are thus ideas, a property of substances (minds), rather than a distinct ontological category. For instance, the English declarative sentence &quot;snow is white&quot; refers to the same proposition as the equivalent French declarative sentence &quot;la neige est blanche&quot;; two sentences, one proposition. Similarly, one declarative sentence can refer to many propositions; for instance, &quot;I am hungry&quot; changes meaning (i.e. refers to different propositions) depending on the person uttering it.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Events</heading><paragraph>Events are that which can be said to occur. To illustrate, consider the claim &quot;John went to a ballgame&quot;; if true, then we must ontologically account for every entity in the sentence. &quot;John&quot; refers to a substance. But what does &quot;went to a ballgame&quot; refer to? It seems wrong to say that &quot;went to a ballgame&quot; is a property that instantiates John, because &quot;went to a ballgame&quot; does not seem to be the same ontological kind of thing as, for instance, redness. Thus, events arguably deserve their own ontological category.</paragraph><paragraph>Properties, relations, and classes are supposed to be<space/><italics><link><target>Abstraction</target><part>abstract</part></link>,</italics><space/>rather than<space/><italics><link><target>Concrete (philosophy)</target><part>concrete</part></link>.</italics><space/>Many philosophers say that properties and relations have an abstract existence, and that physical objects have a concrete existence. That, perhaps, is the<space/><link><target>paradigm case</target></link><space/>of a difference in ways in which items can be said to<space/><italics>be,</italics><space/>or to have being.</paragraph><paragraph>Many philosophers have attempted to reduce the number of distinct ontological categories. For instance,<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>famously regarded Space and Time as nothing more than psychological facts about human beings, which would effectively reduce Space and Time to ideas, which are properties of humans (substances).<space/><link><target>Nominalists</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Philosophical realism</target><part>realists</part></link><space/>argue over the existence of properties and relations. Finally, events and propositions have been argued to be reducible to sets (classes) of substances and other such categories.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Aristotle</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Categories (Aristotle)</arg></template>One of<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>s early interests lay in the classification of the natural world, how for example the genus animal could be first divided into two-footed animal and then into wingless, two-footed animal.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle<space/><italics>Metaphysics</italics><space/>1075a</extension><space/>He realised that the distinctions were being made according to the qualities the animal possesses, the quantity of its parts and the kind of motion that it exhibits. To fully complete the proposition this animal is Aristotle stated in his work on the<space/><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>Categories</part></link><space/>that there were ten kinds of predicate where...</paragraph><paragraph>	each signifies either substance or quantity or quality or relation or where or when or being-in-a-position or having or acting or being acted upon.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.2</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>	He realised that predicates could be simple or complex. The simple kinds consist of a subject and a predicate linked together by the categorical or inherent type of relation. For Aristotle the more complex kinds were limited to propositions where the predicate is compounded of two of the above categories for example this is a horse running. More complex kinds of proposition were only discovered after Aristotle by the Stoic,<space/><link><target>Chrysippus</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Long A. &amp; Sedley D.<space/><italics>The Hellenistic Philosophers</italics><space/>(Cambridge University Press, 1987) p.206</extension><space/>who developed the hypothetical and disjunctive types of<space/><link><target>syllogism</target></link><space/>and these were terms which were to be developed through the<space/><link><target>Scholasticism</target><part>Middle Ages</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Peter of Spain (<italics>alias</italics><space/>John XXI)<space/><italics>Summulae Logicales</italics></extension><space/>and were to reappear in<space/><link><target>Category (Kant)</target><part>Kants system of categories</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Category</italics><space/>came into use with<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>'s essay<space/><italics><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>Categories</part></link></italics>, in which he discussed univocal and<space/><link><target>equivocal</target></link><space/>terms, predication, and ten categories:<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/files/2412/2412-h/2412-h.htm'>Categories</link></italics>, translated by<space/><link><target>Ella Mary Edghill</target><part>E. M. Edghill</part></link>. For the Greek terms, see<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://meta.montclair.edu/ancient/greek/aristotle_greek/'>The Complete Works of Aristotle in Greek</link></italics><space/>(requires DjVu), Book 1 (<italics>Organon</italics>),<space/><italics>Categories</italics><space/>Section 4 (DjVu file's page 6).<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/2412/2412-h/2412-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20131102084057<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Substance theory</target><part>Substance</part></link></bold>, essence (<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc"><link><target>ousia</target></link></xhtml:span></italics>) examples of primary substance: this man, this horse; secondary substance (species, genera): man, horse</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Quantity</target></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">poson</xhtml:span></italics>, how much), discrete or continuous examples: two cubits long, number, space, (length of) time.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">poion</xhtml:span></italics>, of what kind or description) examples: white, black, grammatical, hot, sweet, curved, straight.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Finitary relation</target><part>Relation</part></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">pros ti</xhtml:span></italics>, toward something) examples: double, half, large, master, knowledge.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Place (mathematics)</target><part>Place</part></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">pou</xhtml:span></italics>, where) examples: in a marketplace, in the Lyceum</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Time</target></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">pote</xhtml:span></italics>, when) examples: yesterday, last year</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Human position</target><part>Position</part></link></bold>, posture, attitude (<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">keisthai</xhtml:span></italics>, to lie) examples: sitting, lying, standing</listitem><listitem><bold>State</bold>, condition (<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">echein</xhtml:span></italics>, to have or be) examples: shod, armed</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Action (philosophy)</target><part>Action</part></link></bold><space/>(<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">poiein</xhtml:span></italics>, to make or do) examples: to lance, to heat, to cool (something)</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Affection (philosophy)</target><part>Affection</part></link></bold>, passion (<italics><xhtml:span lang="grc">paschein</xhtml:span></italics>, to suffer or undergo) examples: to be lanced, to be heated, to be cooled</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Plotinus</heading><paragraph><link><target>Plotinus</target></link><space/>in writing his<space/><italics><link><target>Enneads</target></link></italics><space/>around AD 250 recorded that philosophy at a very early age investigated the number and character of the existents some found ten, others less. to some the genera were the first principles, to others only a generic classification of existents.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.9</italics><space/>VI.1.1</extension><space/>He realised that some categories were reducible to others saying why are not Beauty, Goodness and the virtues, Knowledge and Intelligence included among the primary genera?<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>VI.2.17</extension><space/>He concluded that such<space/><link><target>Transcendentals</target><part>transcendental categories</part></link><space/>and even the<space/><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>categories of Aristotle</part></link><space/>were in some way posterior to the three<space/><link><target>Eleatics</target><part>Eleatic</part></link><space/>categories first recorded in Plato's dialogue<space/><italics><link><target>Parmenides (dialogue)</target><part>Parmenides</part></link></italics><space/>and which comprised the following three coupled terms:<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Unity/Plurality</listitem><listitem>Motion/Stability</listitem><listitem>Identity/Difference<extension extension_name='ref'>Plato<space/><italics>Parmenides</italics><space/>(tr. Jowett B.,<space/><italics>The Dialogues of Plato</italics>, Clarendon Press, Oxford, 1875) p.162</extension><space/></listitem></list><paragraph>	<link><target>Plotinus</target></link><space/>called these the hearth of reality<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.9</italics><space/>Op.cit.1.4</extension><space/>deriving from them not only the three categories of Quantity, Motion and Quality but also what came to be known as the three moments of the<space/><link><target>Neoplatonism</target><part>Neoplatonic world process</part></link>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>First, there existed the One, and his view that the origin of things is a contemplation</listitem><listitem>The Second is certainly an activity a secondary phase life streaming from life energy running through the universe</listitem><listitem>The Third is some kind of Intelligence concerning which he wrote Activity is prior to Intellection and self knowledge<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>III.8.5</extension><space/></listitem></list><paragraph>	Plotinus likened the three to the centre, the radii and the circumference of a circle, and clearly thought that the principles underlying the categories were the first principles of creation. From a single root all being multiplies. Similar ideas were to be introduced into Early Christian thought by, for example,<space/><link><target>Gregory of Nazianzus</target></link><space/>who summed it up saying Therefore Unity, having from all eternity arrived by motion at duality, came to rest in<space/><link><target>trinity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rawlinson A.E. (ed.)<space/><italics>Essays on the Trinity and the Incarnation</italics><space/>(Longmans, London, 1928) pp.241-244</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Kant</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><italics><link><target>Critique of Pure Reason</target></link></italics><space/>(1781)<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link><space/>argued that the<space/><link><target>Category (Kant)</target><part>categories</part></link><space/>are part of our own mental structure and consist of a set of<space/><italics>a priori</italics><space/>concepts through which we interpret the world around us.<extension extension_name='ref'>	<italics>Op.cit.3</italics><space/>p.87</extension><space/>These concepts correspond to twelve logical functions of the understanding which we use to make judgements and there are therefore two tables given in the<space/><italics>Critique</italics>, one of the Judgements and a corresponding one for the<space/><link><target>Category (Kant)</target><part>Categories</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>pp.107,113</extension><space/>To give an example, the logical function behind our reasoning from ground to consequence (based on the<space/><link><target>Hypothetical syllogism</target><part>Hypothetical relation</part></link>) underlies our understanding of the world in terms of cause and effect (the<space/><link><target>Causality</target><part>Causal relation</part></link>). In each table the number twelve arises from, firstly, an initial division into two: the Mathematical and the Dynamical; a second division of each of these headings into a further two: Quantity and Quality, and Relation and Modality respectively; and, thirdly, each of these then divides into a further three subheadings as follows.<template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-break</target></template>Table of Judgements</paragraph><paragraph>Mathematical</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Quantity<list type='bullet'><listitem>Universal</listitem><listitem>Particular</listitem><listitem>Singular</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Quality<list type='bullet'><listitem>Affirmative</listitem><listitem>Negative</listitem><listitem>Infinite</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Dynamical</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Relation<list type='bullet'><listitem>Categorical</listitem><listitem>Hypothetical</listitem><listitem>Disjunctive</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Modality<list type='bullet'><listitem>Problematic</listitem><listitem>Assertoric</listitem><listitem>Apodictic</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-break</target></template>Table of Categories</paragraph><paragraph>Mathematical</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Quantity</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem>Unity</listitem><listitem>Plurality</listitem><listitem><link><target>Absolute (philosophy)</target><part>Totality</part></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Reality</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Negation</target></link></listitem><listitem>Limitation</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Dynamical</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Relation of Ideas</target><part>Relation</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Inherence</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Subsistence</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Substance theory</target><part>substance</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>accident</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Causality</target></link><space/>and Dependence (<link><target>cause</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Result</target><part>effect</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>Community (reciprocity)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Modal logic</target><part>Modality</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Logical possibility</target><part>Possibility</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Existence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Necessity</target></link></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template><link><target>Critique of the Kantian philosophy</target><part>Criticism of Kants system</part></link><space/>followed, firstly, by<space/><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target></link>, who amongst other things was unhappy with the term Community, and declared that the tables do open violence to truth, treating it as nature was treated by old-fashioned gardeners,<extension extension_name='ref'>Schopenhauer A.<space/><italics>The World as Will and Representation</italics><space/>(tr. Payne A., Dover Publications, London, New York, 1966) p.430</extension><space/>and secondly, by<space/><link><target>Walter Terence Stace</target><part>W.T.Stace</part></link><space/>who in his book<space/><italics>The Philosophy of Hegel</italics><space/>suggested that in order to make Kants structure completely symmetrical a third category would need to be added to the Mathematical and the Dynamical.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.15</italics><space/>p.222</extension><space/>This, he said, Hegel was to do with his category of Notion.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hegel</heading><paragraph><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target><part>G.W.F.Hegel</part></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Science of Logic</target></link></italics><space/>(1812) attempted to provide a more comprehensive system of categories than Kant and developed a structure that was almost entirely triadic.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics></extension><space/>So important were the categories to Hegel that he claimed the first principle of the world, the Absolute, is a system of categories the categories must be the reason of which the world is a consequent.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>pp.63,65</extension>	Using his own logical method of combination, later to be called the<space/><link><target>Dialectic</target><part>Hegelian dialectic</part></link>, of arguing from thesis through antithesis to synthesis, he arrived, as shown in W.T.Stace's work cited, at a hierarchy of some 270 categories. The three very highest categories were Logic, Nature and Spirit. The three highest categories of Logic, however, he called Being, Essence and Notion which he explained as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Parmenides (dialogue)</target><part>Being</part></link><space/>was differentiated from Nothing by containing with it the concept of the Other, an initial internal division that can be compared with Kants category of Disjunction. Stace called the category of Being the sphere of common sense containing concepts such as consciousness, sensation, quantity, quality and measure.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Essence</target></link>. The Other separates itself from the One by a kind of motion, reflected in Hegels first synthesis of<space/><link><target>Becoming (philosophy)</target><part>Becoming</part></link>. For Stace this category represented the sphere of science containing within it firstly, the thing, its form and properties; secondly, cause, effect and reciprocity, and thirdly, the principles of classification, identity and difference.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Notion (philosophy)</target><part>Notion</part></link>. Having passed over into the Other there is an almost<space/><link><target>Neoplatonism</target><part>Neoplatonic return</part></link><space/>into a higher unity that in embracing the One and the Other enables them to be considered together through their inherent qualities. This according to<space/><link><target>Walter Terence Stace</target><part>Stace</part></link><space/>is the sphere of philosophy proper where we find not only the three types of logical proposition:<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>Disjunctive, Hypothetical and Categorical</part></link><space/>but also the three transcendental concepts of<space/><link><target>Transcendentals</target><part>Beauty, Goodness and Truth</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.18</italics><space/>pp.124ff</extension></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target><part>Schopenhauers</part></link><space/>category that corresponded with Notion was that of Idea, which in his<space/><italics>Four-Fold Root of Sufficient Reason</italics><space/>he complemented with the category of the Will.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.20</italics></extension><space/>The title of his major work was<space/><link><target>The World as Will and Representation</target><part>The World as Will and Idea</part></link>. The two other complementary categories, reflecting one of Hegels initial divisions, were those of Being and Becoming. Interestingly, at around the same time,<space/><link><target>Johann Wolfgang von Goethe</target><part>Goethe</part></link><space/>was developing his colour theories in the<space/><italics><link><target>Theory of Colours</target><part>Farbenlehre</part></link></italics><space/>of 1810, and introduced similar principles of combination and complementation, symbolising, for Goethe, the primordial relations which belong both to nature and vision.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goethe J.W. von,<space/><italics>The Theory of Colours</italics><space/>(tr. Eastlake C.L., MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass., 1970) p.350</extension><space/><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target><part>Hegel</part></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Science of Logic</target></link></italics><space/>accordingly asks us to see his system not as a tree but as a circle.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Peirce</heading><paragraph><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target></link>, who had read Kant and Hegel closely, and who also had some knowledge of Aristotle, proposed a system of merely three phenomenological categories:<space/><link><target>Categories (Peirce)</target><part>Firstness, Secondness, and Thirdness</part></link>, which he repeatedly invoked in his subsequent writings. Like Hegel, C.S.Peirce attempted to develop a system of categories from a single indisputable principle, in Peirces case the notion that in the first instance he could only be aware of his own ideas. 	It seems that the true categories of consciousness are first, feeling second, a sense of resistance and third, synthetic consciousness, or thought.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Op.cit.5</italics><space/>p.200, cf Locke</extension>	Elsewhere he called the three primary categories:<space/><link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link>, Reaction and<space/><link><target>Meaning (semiotics)</target><part>Meaning</part></link>, and even<space/><link><target>Categories (Peirce)</target><part>Firstness, Secondness and Thirdness</part></link>, saying, perhaps it is not right to call these categories conceptions, they are so intangible that they are rather tones or tints upon conceptions:<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>p.179</extension><space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Firstness (<link><target>Quality (philosophy)</target><part>Quality</part></link>): The first is predominant in feeling we must think of a quality without parts, e.g. the colour of magenta When I say it is a quality I do not mean that it inheres in a subject The whole content of consciousness is made up of qualities of feeling, as truly as the whole of space is made up of points, or the whole of time by instants.</listitem><listitem>Secondness (Reaction): This is present even in such a rudimentary fragment of experience as a simple feeling an action and reaction between our soul and the stimulus The idea of second is predominant in the ideas of causation and of statical force the real is active; we acknowledge it by calling it the actual.</listitem><listitem>Thirdness (<link><target>Meaning (semiotics)</target><part>Meaning</part></link>): Thirdness is essentially of a general nature ideas in which thirdness predominate [include] the idea of a sign or representation Every genuine triadic relation involves meaning the idea of meaning is irreducible to those of quality and reaction synthetical consciousness is the consciousness of a third or medium.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>pp.148-179</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>	Although Peirces three categories correspond to the<space/><link><target>Relation (history of concept)</target><part>three concepts of relation</part></link><space/>given in Kants tables, the sequence is now reversed and follows that given by<space/><link><target>Science of Logic</target><part>Hegel</part></link>, and indeed before Hegel of the three moments of the world-process given by<space/><link><target>Neoplatonism</target><part>Plotinus</part></link>. Later, Peirce gave a mathematical reason for there being three categories in that although monadic, dyadic and triadic nodes are irreducible, every node of a higher valency is reducible to a compound of triadic relations.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ibid.</italics><space/>p.176</extension><space/><link><target>Ferdinand de Saussure</target></link>, who was developing semiology in France just as Peirce was developing semiotics in the USA, likened each term of a proposition to the centre of a constellation, the point where other coordinate terms, the sum of which is indefinite, converge.<extension extension_name='ref'>Saussure F. de,<italics>Course in General Linguistics</italics><space/>1916 (tr. Harris R., Duckworth, London, 1983) p.124</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Others</heading><paragraph><link><target>Edmund Husserl</target></link><space/>(1962, 2000) wrote extensively about categorial systems as part of his<space/><link><target>Phenomenology (philosophy)</target><part>phenomenology</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>Gilbert Ryle</target></link><space/>(1949), a category (in particular a &quot;<link><target>category mistake</target></link>&quot;) is an important semantic concept, but one having only loose affinities to an ontological category.</paragraph><paragraph>Contemporary systems of categories have been proposed by<space/><link><target>John G. Bennett</target></link><space/>(The Dramatic Universe, 4 vols., 195665),<space/><link><target>Wilfrid Sellars</target></link><space/>(1974),<space/><link><target>Reinhardt Grossmann</target></link><space/>(1983, 1992), Johansson (1989), Hoffman and Rosenkrantz (1994),<space/><link><target>Roderick Chisholm</target></link><space/>(1996),<space/><link><target>Barry Smith (ontologist)</target></link><space/>(2003), and<space/><link><target>Jonathan Lowe</target></link><space/>(2006).</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-break</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Category (mathematics)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Categories (Peirce)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Categories (Stoic)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Category (Kant)</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-break</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Metaphysics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Modal logic</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ontology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Schema (Kant)</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>More footnotes</target><arg name="date">February 2008</arg></template><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Selected bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>, 1953.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/a/aristotle/metaphysics/'>Metaphysics</link></italics>. Ross, W. D., trans. Oxford University Press.</listitem><listitem>--------, 2004.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/a/a8/categori.html'>Categories</link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Ella Mary Edghill</target><part>Edghill, E. M.</part></link>, trans. Uni. of Adelaide library.</listitem><listitem><link><target>John G. Bennett</target></link>, 19561965.<space/><italics>The Dramatic Universe</italics>. London, Hodder &amp; Stoughton.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gustav Bergmann</target></link>, 1992.<space/><italics>New Foundations of Ontology</italics>. Madison: Uni. of Wisconsin Press.</listitem><listitem>Browning, Douglas, 1990.<space/><italics>Ontology and the Practical Arena</italics>. Pennsylvania State Uni.</listitem><listitem>Butchvarov, Panayot, 1979.<space/><italics>Being qua Being: A Theory of Identity, Existence, and Predication</italics>. Indiana Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Roderick Chisholm</target></link>, 1996.<space/><italics>A Realistic Theory of Categories</italics>. Cambridge Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem>Feibleman, James Kern, 1951.<space/><italics>Ontology</italics>. The Johns Hopkins Press (reprinted 1968, Greenwood Press, Publishers, New York).</listitem><listitem>Grossmann, Reinhardt, 1983.<space/><italics>The Categorial Structure of the World</italics>. Indiana Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem>Grossmann, Reinhardt, 1992.<space/><italics>The Existence of the World: An Introduction to Ontology</italics>. Routledge.</listitem><listitem>Haaparanta, Leila and Koskinen, Heikki J., 2012.<space/><italics>Categories of Being: Essays on Metaphysics and Logic</italics>. New York: Oxford University Press.</listitem><listitem>Hoffman, J., and Rosenkrantz, G. S.,1994.<space/><italics>Substance among other Categories</italics>. Cambridge Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Edmund Husserl</target></link>, 1962.<space/><italics>Ideas: General Introduction to Pure Phenomenology</italics>. Boyce Gibson, W. R., trans. Collier.</listitem><listitem>------, 2000.<space/><italics>Logical Investigations</italics>, 2nd ed. Findlay, J. N., trans. Routledge.</listitem><listitem>Johansson, Ingvar, 1989.<space/><italics>Ontological Investigations</italics>. Routledge, 2nd ed. Ontos Verlag 2004.</listitem><listitem>Kahn, Charles H., 2009.<space/><italics>Essays on Being</italics>, Oxford University Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, 1998.<space/><italics>Critique of Pure Reason</italics>. Guyer, Paul, and Wood, A. W., trans. Cambridge Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target></link>, 1992, 1998.<space/><italics><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce bibliography#EP</target><part>The Essential Peirce</part></link></italics>, vols. 1,2. Houser, Nathan et al., eds. Indiana Uni. Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gilbert Ryle</target></link>, 1949.<space/><italics>The Concept of Mind</italics>. Uni. of Chicago Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wilfrid Sellars</target></link>, 1974, &quot;Toward a Theory of the Categories&quot; in<space/><italics>Essays in Philosophy and Its History</italics>. Reidel.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Barry Smith (ontologist)</target><part>Barry Smith</part></link>, 2003. &quot;Ontology&quot; in<space/><italics>Blackwell Guide to the Philosophy of Computing and Information</italics>. Blackwell.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Aristotle's<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://classics.mit.edu/Aristotle/categories.html'>Categories</link></italics><space/>at MIT.</listitem><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>categories</arg><arg>Categories</arg><arg>[[Amie Thomasson]]</arg></template></listitem><listitem>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://ejap.louisiana.edu/EJAP/1997.spring/thomasson976.html'>Ontological Categories and How to Use Them</link>&quot; Amie Thomasson.</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.cs.vassar.edu/~weltyc/fois/fois-2001/keynote/'>Recent Advances in Metaphysics</link>&quot; E. J. Lowe.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ontology.co/'>Theory and History of Ontology</link><space/>Raul Corazzon.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>metaphysics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Ontology</target></link><link><target>Category:Concepts in metaphysics</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophical categories</target></link><link><target>Category:Concepts</target></link></paragraph></article>