<article title='Continuity_%28fiction%29'><paragraph><template><target>Multiple issues</target><arg name="{{Refimprove|date">December 2008}}
{{Original research|date</arg></template>In fiction,<space/><bold>continuity</bold><space/>(also called<space/><bold>time-scheme</bold>) is consistency of the characteristics of people, plot, objects, and places seen by the reader or viewer over some period of time. It is relevant to several media.</paragraph><paragraph>Continuity is particularly a concern in the production of film and television due to the difficulty of rectifying an error in continuity after shooting has wrapped up. It also applies to other art forms, including novels, comics, and<space/><link><target>video games</target></link>, though usually on a smaller scale.</paragraph><paragraph>Most productions have a<space/><link><target>script supervisor</target></link><space/>on hand whose job is to pay attention to and attempt to maintain continuity across the chaotic and typically non-linear production shoot. This takes the form of a large amount of paperwork, photographs, and attention to and memory of large quantities of detail, some of which is sometimes assembled into the<space/><link><target>Bible (writing)</target><part>story bible</part></link><space/>for the production. It usually regards factors both with-in the scene and often even technical details including meticulous records of camera positioning and equipment settings. The use of a<space/><link><target>Polaroid camera</target></link><space/>was standard but has since been replaced by the advent of<space/><link><target>digital camera</target><trail>s</trail></link>. All of this is done so that ideally all related shots can match, despite perhaps parts being shot thousands of miles and several months apart. It is a less conspicuous job, though, because if done perfectly, no one will ever notice.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>In comic books, continuity has also come to mean a set of contiguous events, sometimes said to be &quot;set in the same universe&quot; (see<space/><link><target>fictional crossover</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fictional universe</target></link>) or &quot;separate universes&quot; (see<space/><link><target>intercompany crossover</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Continuity errors</heading><paragraph>Whilst most continuity errors are subtle, such as changes in the level of drink in a character's glass or the length of a cigarette, others can be more noticeable, such as sudden drastic changes in appearance of a character. Such errors in continuity can ruin the illusion of realism and affect<space/><link><target>suspension of disbelief</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In cinema, special attention must be paid to continuity because films are rarely shot in the order in which they are presented. The shooting schedule is often dictated by location permit issues. A character may return to<space/><link><target>Times Square</target></link><space/>in New York City several times throughout a movie, but as it is extraordinarily expensive to close off Times Square, those scenes will likely be filmed all at once to reduce permit costs. Weather, the ambience of natural light, cast and crew availability, or any number of other circumstances can also influence a shooting schedule.</paragraph><heading level='3'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Attempts to prevent continuity errors in film</arg></template><space/>Measures against continuity errors in film</heading><paragraph>Film production companies use various techniques to prevent continuity errors. First would be to film all the shots for a particular scene together, and all shots of consecutive scenes together (if the scenes take place together, with no break between them in the film's timeline). This allows actors to remain in costume, in character, and in the same location (and with the same weather, if shooting on location).</paragraph><paragraph>The second major technique is for costume designers, production designers, prop masters, and make-up artists to take instant photographs of actors and sets at the beginning and end of each day's shooting (once made possible by<space/><link><target>Polaroid Corporation</target><part>Polaroid</part></link><space/>cameras, now done with digital cameras and cell phones as well). This allows the various workers to check each day's clothing, set, props, and make-up against a previous day's.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The third is to avoid shooting on location entirely, but instead film everything on a studio set. This allows weather and lighting to be controlled (as the shooting is indoors), and for all clothing and sets to be stored in one place to be hauled out the next day from a secure location.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Editing errors</heading><paragraph>Editing errors can occur when a character in a scene references a scene or incident that has not occurred yet, or of which they should not yet be aware.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An example of an editing error can be seen in the film<space/><italics><link><target>It's a Mad, Mad, Mad, Mad World</target></link></italics><space/>(1963), where a scene of people climbing a slope at the start is seen from below and then replayed from above.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Visual errors</heading><paragraph>Visual errors are instant<space/><italics>discontinuities</italics><space/>occurring in visual media such as film and television. Items of clothing change colors, shadows get longer or shorter, items within a scene change place or disappear, etc.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the earliest examples of a<space/><italics>visual error</italics><space/>appears in<space/><link><target>Charlie Chaplin</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>1914 in film</target><part>1914</part></link><space/>movie<space/><italics><link><target>The Property Man</target></link></italics>. Here, in a supposedly smooth step from one room to another,<space/><link><target>the Tramp</target></link><space/>loses his hat in one room, but it is instantly back on his head as he enters the next room. Rather &quot;loose&quot; plots and a lack of<space/><link><target>continuity editing</target></link><space/>made most early films rife with such errors.</paragraph><paragraph>Another example occurs in the<space/><link><target>1998 in film</target><part>1998</part></link><space/>film<space/><italics><link><target>Waking Ned</target></link></italics>, when two of the film's characters, Jackie and Michael, are walking through a storm towards Ned's house. The umbrella they are under is black during their conversation as they walk towards the house (filmed from slightly above and to the front), yet after cutting to a lower shot (filmed from behind Jackie), Michael walks onscreen from the right holding an<space/><link><target>umbrella</target></link><space/>that is not black but beige, with a brown band at the rim.</paragraph><paragraph>Yet another glaring example of poor continuity occurs in the Disney film<space/><italics><link><target>Petes Dragon</target></link></italics><space/>(filmed in 1976). During the song &quot;Brazzle Dazzle Day&quot; when Lampie (Mickey Rooney), Pete (Sean Marshall), and Nora (Helen Reddy) climb the stairs to the top of the lighthouse, Pete's shirt beneath his overalls is orange. But after descending to the bottom again and coming out of the lighthouse door, his shirt is now grey.</paragraph><paragraph>Though visual continuity errors are logically confined to visual media, parallel mistakes can occur in text. In &quot;<link><target>The Miller's Prologue and Tale</target><part>The Miller's Tale</part></link>&quot; in<space/><link><target>Chaucer</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Canterbury Tales</target></link></italics>, a door is ripped off its hinges only to be slowly closed again in the next scene.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Plot errors</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Plot hole</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A plot error, or a plot hole as it's commonly known, reflects a failure in the consistency of the created fictional world. A character might state he was an only child, yet later mention a sibling. In the TV show<space/><italics><link><target>Cheers</target></link></italics>, Frasier Crane's wife Lilith mentions Frasier's parents are both dead. When the character was spun off into<space/><italics><link><target>Frasier</target></link></italics>, his father became a central character with, in a case of<space/><link><target>retroactive continuity</target></link>, the explanation that Frasier was embarrassed about his father's lowbrow attitudes and thus claimed his death. This is a frequent occurrence in sitcoms, where networks may agree to continue a show, but only if a certain character is emphasized, leading other minor characters to become victims of Chuck Cunningham Syndrome (i.e. written out of the show with no further mention of the character's fate or even its existence, as was the case with Chuck Cunningham on<space/><italics><link><target>Happy Days</target></link></italics>), while the emphasized character (usually a<space/><link><target>breakout character</target></link>) (as in the case of<space/><link><target>Frasier Crane</target></link>) develops a more complete back story that ignores previous, more simplified back stories.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Homeric Nod</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>Homer nods</arg></template>A<space/><bold>Homeric nod</bold><space/>(sometimes heard as 'Even Homer nods') is a continuity error. It has its origins in<space/><link><target>Homer</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/><link><target>epic poetry</target><part>epic</part></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>proverbial phrase</target></link><space/>for it was coined by the<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>poet<space/><link><target>Horace</target></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Ars poetica</target></link></italics>:<extension extension_name='ref'>Lines 358-359.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><italics>... et idem</italics><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>indignor quandoque bonus dormitat Homerus</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>... and yet I also become annoyed whenever the great Homer<space/><link><target>wikt:nod</target><part>nod</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>off.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are numerous continuity errors in Homer that resemble &quot;nods&quot;, as for example:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>Iliad</target></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Book V Lines 576-579</extension><space/><link><target>Menelaos</target></link><space/>kills a minor character, Pylaimenes, in combat; who is later<extension extension_name='ref'>Book XIII Lines 643-659</extension><space/>still alive to witness the death of his son.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>In<space/><italics>Iliad</italics><space/>9.165-93 three characters,<space/><link><target>Phoenix (son of Amyntor)</target><part>Phoinix</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Odysseus</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Telamonian Aias</target><part>Aias</part></link><space/>set out on an embassy to<space/><link><target>Achilleus</target></link>; however, at line 182 the poet uses a verb in the<space/><link><target>Dual (grammatical number)</target><part>dual</part></link><space/>form to indicate that there are only two people going; at lines 185ff. verbs in the<space/><link><target>plural</target></link><space/>form are used, indicating more than two; but another dual verb appears at line 192 (&quot;the two of them came forward&quot;).</listitem></list><paragraph>In modern<space/><link><target>Homeric scholarship</target></link><space/>many of Homer's &quot;nods&quot; are explicable as the consequences of the poem being retold and improvised by generations of oral poets. So in the second case cited above, it is likely that two different versions are being conflated: one version with an embassy of three people, another with just two people.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Alexander Pope</target></link><space/>was inclined to give Homeric nods the benefit of the doubt:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Those oft are Stratagems which Errors seem,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Nor is it Homer Nods, but We that Dream. -<space/><italics><link><target>Essay on Criticism</target></link></italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Modern usage</heading><paragraph>In his online column,<space/><italics>Best of The Web Today</italics>,<space/><link><target>James Taranto</target></link><space/>of<space/><italics><link><target>The Wall Street Journal</target></link></italics><space/>often uses the phrase &quot;Homer Nods&quot; as the title of a retraction or correction.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aging discrepancies</heading><paragraph>The practice of accelerating the age of a television character (usually a child or teenager) in conflict with the timeline of a series and/or the real-world progression of time is popularly known as<space/><link><target>Soap Opera Rapid Aging Syndrome</target></link>, or SORAS.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rising Stars"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://tonight.co.za/index.php?fArticleId</arg><arg name="title">Soaps' rising stars<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kim<space/></arg><arg name="last">Clayton-Millar<space/></arg><arg name="date">April 24, 2006<space/></arg><arg name="work">Tonight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Independent News & Media<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">December 17, 2009–12<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Children unseen on screen for a time might reappear portrayed by an actor several years older than the original.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Bird<space/></arg><arg name="first1">S. Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Audience in Everyday Life: Living in a Media World<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 12, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-94259-4<space/></arg><arg name="page">135<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Usually coinciding with a recast, this rapid aging is typically done to open up the character to a wider range of storylines, and to attract younger viewers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rising Stars"></extension><space/>A recent example of this occurring is in the BBC's<space/><italics><link><target>Merlin (TV series)</target><part>Merlin</part></link></italics><space/>series, in which Mordred is initially played by a young child in Season 4, yet suddenly grows up into his late teens in time for the start of Season 5, with the rest of the characters aging by only three years.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Deliberate continuity errors</heading><paragraph>Sometimes a work of fiction may deliberately employ continuity errors, usually for comedy. For example, the<space/><link><target>Marx Brothers</target></link>' classic film<space/><italics><link><target>Duck Soup (1933 film)</target><part>Duck Soup</part></link></italics>, at the climax of the film, the camera shows a<space/><link><target>shot (filmmaking)</target><part>shot</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Groucho Marx</target></link><space/>speaking a line, followed by a shot of something else happening, followed by another shot of Groucho. Each time, Groucho's hat changes, usually to something more outrageous than before (a<space/><link><target>Napoleon</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>hat, a<space/><link><target>Prussia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>hat, etc.).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dealing with errors</heading><paragraph>When continuity mistakes have been made, explanations are often proposed by either writers or fans to smooth over discrepancies. Fans sometimes make up explanations for such errors that may or may not be integrated into<space/><link><target>canon (fiction)</target><part>canon</part></link>; this has come to be colloquially known as<space/><italics>fanwanking</italics><space/>(a term originally coined by the author<space/><link><target>Craig Hinton</target></link><space/>to describe excessive use of continuity).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">AHistory: An Unauthorized History of the ''Doctor Who'' universe<space/></arg><arg name="last">Parkin<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lance<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Lance Parkin<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Mad Norwegian Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Des Moines, Iowa<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-9759446-6-0<space/></arg><arg name="page">13</arg></template></extension><space/>Often when fans do not agree with one of the events in a story (such as the death of a favorite character), they will choose to ignore the event in question so that their enjoyment of the franchise is not diminished. When the holder of the intellectual property discards all existing continuity and starts from scratch it is known as<space/><link><target>Reboot (fiction)</target><part>rebooting</part></link>. Fans call a less extreme literary technique that erases one episode the<space/><link><target>reset button technique</target><part>reset button</part></link>. See also<space/><link><target>Canon (fiction)#Fanon</target><part>fanon</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Discrepancies in past continuity are sometimes made deliberately; this is known as<space/><link><target>Retroactive continuity</target><part>retcon</part><trail>ning</trail></link>. Retcons are also sometimes used to either correct or cover up a perceived error. These changes may be made either by the same writer who made it, or more commonly by an author that has taken over the creative lead of a corporate owned show or publication.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2008</arg></template><space/>Not to be confused with the continuance of a reality (continuality).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Real time programs vs traditional films</heading><paragraph>Television programs like<space/><italics><link><target>24 (television)</target><part>24</part></link></italics>, in which actors have to appear as if it is the same day for 24 consecutive episodes, have raised public recognition of continuity. However, traditional films have frequently had much of the same sort of the issues to deal with; film shoots may last several months and as scenes are frequently shot out of story sequence, footage shot weeks apart may be edited together as part of the same day's action in the completed film. In some ways,<space/><italics>24</italics><space/>presents a simpler situation, as costumes and hairstyles generally should<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>change very frequently; in many feature films a range of different hairstyles and costumes must be created, changed, and then recreated exactly, as various scenes are shot.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Script Supervising and Film Continuity, Third Edition<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pat<space/></arg><arg name="last">Miller<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-240-80294-2<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Focal Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 1998</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2008/nov/10/james-bond-quantum-solace-mistakes<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''[[The Guardian]]''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-21<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-11-10<space/></arg><arg name="title">An Aston Martini, stirred not shaken, please Pennymoney / Site lists 007 continuity gaffes in new Bond film / Odd Corsas, corpses and capitals spotted in movie<space/></arg><arg name="first">Audrey<space/></arg><arg name="last">Gillan<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">When Continuity Counts, Call a Script Girl — Er, Guy<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/templates/story/story.php?storyId</arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Public Radio]]<space/></arg><arg name="first">Susan<space/></arg><arg name="last">Stamberg<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-02-21<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-21<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.latimes.com/classified/jobs/counselor/la-counselor-080505,0,5204004.htmlstory<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''[[Los Angeles Times]]''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-21<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005-08-05<space/></arg><arg name="first">Susan W.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Miller<space/></arg><arg name="title">Career Counselor: Script Supervisor<space/></arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">October 2010</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Continuity (Fiction)</target></template><link><target>Category:Style (fiction)</target></link><link><target>Category:Narratology</target></link><link><target>Category:Continuity (fiction)</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Phrases</target></link><link><target>Category:Homeric style</target></link></paragraph></article>