<article title='B%C3%A9la_Bart%C3%B3k'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Bartok</arg></template><template><target>pp-move-vandalism</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><template><target>eastern name order</target><arg>Bartók Béla Viktor János</arg></template><link><target>File:Bartk Bla 1927.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bla Bartk in 1927</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bla Viktor Jnos Bartk</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>ɑr</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>k</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>IPA-hu</target><arg>ˈbeːlɒ ˈbɒrtoːk</arg></template>; March 25, 1881 September 26, 1945) was a<space/><link><target>Hungarian people</target><part>Hungarian</part></link><space/>composer and pianist. He is considered one of the most important composers of the 20th century; he and<space/><link><target>Franz Liszt</target><part>Liszt</part></link><space/>are regarded as Hungary's greatest composers<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies<space/></arg><arg>2001</arg></template>. Through his collection and analytical study of<space/><link><target>folk music</target></link>, he was one of the founders of comparative musicology, which later became<space/><link><target>ethnomusicology</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Childhood and early years (188198)</heading><paragraph>Bla Bartk was born in the small<space/><link><target>Banat</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>town of Nagyszentmikls in the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Hungary</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Austria-Hungary</target></link><space/>(since 1920<space/><link><target>Snnicolau Mare</target></link>, Romania) on March 25, 1881. Bartk had a diverse ancestry. On his father's side, the Bartk family was a Hungarian lower noble family, originating from<space/><link><target>Borsodszirk</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Borsod county</target></link><space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Móser</arg><arg>2006a</arg><arg name="loc">44</arg></template>. Although, his father's mother was of a<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/>Serbian family<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Bayley</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="loc">16</arg></template>. Bla Bartk's mother, Paula (born Paula Voit), was an ethnic German, though she spoke<space/><link><target>Hungarian language</target><part>Hungarian</part></link><space/>fluently<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Bayley</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="loc">16</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Bla displayed notable musical talent very early in life: according to his mother, he could distinguish between different dance rhythms that she played on the piano before he learned to speak in complete sentences<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="loc">6</arg></template>. By the age of four he was able to play 40 pieces on the piano and his mother began formally teaching him the next year.</paragraph><paragraph>Bla was a small and sickly child and suffered from severe eczema until the age of 5<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="loc">5</arg></template>. In 1888, when he was seven, his father (the director of an agricultural school) died suddenly. Bla's mother then took him and his sister, Erzsbet, to live in<space/><link><target>Nagyszls</target></link><space/>(today<space/><link><target>Vinogradiv</target></link>, Ukraine) and then to<space/><link><target>Pozsony</target></link><space/>(German: Pressburg, today<space/><link><target>Bratislava</target></link>, Slovakia). In Pozsony, Bla gave his first public recital at age 11 to a warm critical reception. Among the pieces he played was his own first composition, written two years previously: a short piece called &quot;The Course of the Danube&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>de Toth</arg><arg>1999</arg></template>. Shortly thereafter Lszl Erkel accepted him as a pupil.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early musical career (18991908)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bartok tablo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Bartk's signature on his high-school-graduation photograph, dated September 9, 1899</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>From 1899 to 1903, Bartk studied piano under<space/><link><target>Istvn Thomn</target></link>, a former student of<space/><link><target>Franz Liszt</target></link>, and composition under<space/><link><target>Jnos Koessler</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Franz Liszt Academy of Music</target><part>Royal Academy of Music in Budapest</part></link>. There he met<space/><link><target>Zoltn Kodly</target></link>, who influenced him greatly and became his lifelong friend and colleague. In 1903, Bartk wrote his first major orchestral work,<space/><italics><link><target>Kossuth (Bartk)</target><part>Kossuth</part></link></italics>, a<space/><link><target>symphonic poem</target></link><space/>which honored<space/><link><target>Lajos Kossuth</target></link>, hero of the<space/><link><target>Hungarian Revolution of 1848</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The music of<space/><link><target>Richard Strauss</target></link>, whom he met in 1902 at the<space/><link><target>Budapest</target></link><space/>premiere of<space/><italics><link><target>Also sprach Zarathustra (Strauss)</target><part>Also sprach Zarathustra</part></link>,</italics><space/>strongly influenced his early work. When visiting a holiday resort in the summer of 1904, Bartk overheard a young nanny, Lidi Dsa from<space/><link><target>Kibd</target></link><space/>in Transylvania, sing folk songs to the children in her care. This sparked his lifelong dedication to folk music.</paragraph><paragraph>From 1907, he also began to be influenced by the French composer<space/><link><target>Claude Debussy</target></link>, whose compositions Kodly had brought back from Paris. Bartk's large-scale orchestral works were still in the style of<space/><link><target>Johannes Brahms</target></link><space/>and Richard Strauss, but he wrote a number of small piano pieces which showed his growing interest in folk music. The first piece to show clear signs of this new interest is the<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 1 (Bartk)</target><part>String Quartet No. 1</part></link><space/>in A minor (1908), which contains folk-like elements.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1907, Bartk began teaching as a piano professor at the Royal Academy. This position freed him from touring Europe as a pianist and enabled him to work in Hungary. Among his notable students were<space/><link><target>Fritz Reiner</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sir Georg Solti</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gyrgy Sndor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ern Balogh</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lili Kraus</target></link>. After Bartk moved to the United States, he taught<space/><link><target>Jack Beeson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Violet Archer</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1908, he and Kodly traveled into the countryside to collect and research old<space/><link><target>Hungarian people</target><part>Magyar</part></link><space/>folk melodies. Their growing interest in folk music coincided with a contemporary social interest in traditional national culture. They made some surprising discoveries. Magyar folk music had previously been categorised as<space/><link><target>Romani people</target><part>Gypsy</part></link><space/>music. The classic example is<space/><link><target>Franz Liszt</target></link>'s famous<space/><italics><link><target>Hungarian Rhapsodies</target></link></italics><space/>for piano, which he based on popular art songs performed by<space/><link><target>Romani people</target><part>Romani</part></link><space/>bands of the time. In contrast, Bartk and Kodly discovered that the old Magyar folk melodies were based on<space/><link><target>pentatonic</target></link><space/>scales, similar to those in Asian folk traditions, such as those of Central Asia,<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Siberia</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Bartk and Kodly quickly set about incorporating elements of such Magyar peasant music into their compositions. They both frequently quoted folk song melodies<space/><italics>verbatim</italics><space/>and wrote pieces derived entirely from authentic songs. An example is his two volumes entitled<space/><italics>For Children</italics><space/>for solo piano, containing 80 folk tunes to which he wrote accompaniment. Bartk's style in his art music compositions was a synthesis of folk music, classicism, and modernism. His melodic and harmonic sense was profoundly influenced by the folk music of Hungary, Romania, and other nations. He was especially fond of the asymmetrical dance rhythms and pungent harmonies found in<space/><link><target>Bulgarian music</target></link>. Most of his early compositions offer a blend of nationalist and late Romanticism elements.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Middle years and career (190939)</heading><heading level='4'>Personal life</heading><paragraph>In 1909 at the age of 28, Bartk married Mrta Ziegler (18931967), aged 16. Their son, Bla III, was born on August 22, 1910. After nearly 15 years together, Bartk divorced Mrta in June 1923.</paragraph><paragraph>Two months after his divorce, he married<space/><link><target>Ditta Psztory-Bartk</target><part>Ditta Psztory</part></link><space/>(19031982), a piano student, ten days after proposing to her. She was aged 19, he 42. Their son, Pter, was born in 1924.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Opera</heading><paragraph>In 1911, Bartk wrote what was to be his only opera,<space/><italics><link><target>Bluebeard's Castle</target></link></italics>, dedicated to Mrta. He entered it for a prize by the Hungarian Fine Arts Commission, but they rejected his work as not fit for the stage<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">93</arg></template>. In 1917 Bartk revised the score for the 1918 premire, and rewrote the ending. Following the<space/><link><target>Hungarian Soviet Republic</target><part>1919 revolution</part></link>, he was pressured by the new Soviet government to remove the name of the librettist<space/><link><target>Bla Balzs</target></link><space/>from the opera<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">123</arg></template>, as he was blacklisted and had left the country for Vienna.<space/><italics>Bluebeard's Castle</italics><space/>received only one revival, in 1936, before Bartk emigrated. For the remainder of his life, although he was passionately devoted to Hungary, its people and its culture, he never felt much loyalty to the government or its official establishments.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Folk music and composition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bartok recording folk music.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bla Bartk using a<space/><link><target>Phonograph</target><part>gramophone</part></link><space/>to record folk songs sung by peasants in what is now<space/><link><target>Slovakia</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>After his disappointment over the Fine Arts Commission competition, Bartk wrote little for two or three years, preferring to concentrate on collecting and arranging folk music. He collected first in the<space/><link><target>Carpathian Basin</target></link><space/>(then the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Hungary in the 18th and 19th century</target><part>Kingdom of Hungary</part></link>), where he notated<space/><link><target>Hungarian folk music</target><part>Hungarian</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Music of Slovakia</target><part>Slovakian</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Music of Romania</target><part>Romanian</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Music of Bulgaria</target><part>Bulgarian</part></link><space/>folk music. He also collected in<space/><link><target>Moldavia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wallachia</target></link>, and (in 1913)<space/><link><target>Algeria</target></link>. The outbreak of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>forced him to stop the expeditions; and he returned to composing, writing the ballet<space/><italics><link><target>The Wooden Prince</target></link></italics><space/>(191416) and the<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 2 (Bartk)</target><part>String Quartet No. 2</part></link><space/>in (191517), both influenced by<space/><link><target>Debussy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Raised as a<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link>, by his early adulthood Bartk had become an<space/><link><target>atheist</target></link>. He believed that the existence of God could not be determined and was unnecessary. He later became attracted to<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target></link><space/>and publicly converted to the<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarian</part></link><space/>faith in 1916. As an adult, his son later became president of the Hungarian Unitarian Church<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Hughes</arg><arg>1999–2007</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Bartk wrote another ballet,<space/><italics><link><target>The Miraculous Mandarin</target></link></italics><space/>influenced by<space/><link><target>Igor Stravinsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arnold Schoenberg</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>Richard Strauss</target></link>. A modern story of prostitution, robbery, and murder, it was started in 1918, but not performed until 1926 because of its<space/><link><target>Human sexuality</target><part>sexual</part></link><space/>content. He next wrote his two<space/><link><target>violin sonata</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(written in 1921 and 1922 respectively), which are harmonically and structurally some of his most complex pieces.</paragraph><paragraph>In 192728, Bartk wrote his<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 3 (Bartk)</target><part>Third</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 4 (Bartk)</target><part>Fourth String Quartets</part></link>, after which his compositions demonstrated his mature style. Notable examples of this period are<space/><italics><link><target>Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta</target></link></italics><space/>(1936) and<space/><italics><link><target>Divertimento for String Orchestra BB 118</target></link></italics><space/>(1939). The<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 5 (Bartk)</target><part>Fifth String Quartet</part></link><space/>was composed in 1934, and the<space/><link><target>String Quartet No. 6 (Bartk)</target><part>Sixth String Quartet</part></link><space/>(his last) in 1939.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1936 he travelled to<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>to collect and study folk music. He worked in collaboration with Turkish composer<space/><link><target>Ahmet Adnan Saygun</target></link><space/>mostly around<space/><link><target>Adana</target></link><space/>(<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Özgentürk</arg><arg>2008</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Sipos</arg><arg>2000</arg></template>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>World War II and last years in America (194045)</heading><paragraph>In 1940, as the European political situation worsened after the outbreak of World War II, Bartk was increasingly tempted to flee Hungary. He was strongly opposed to the<space/><link><target>Nazis</target></link><space/>and Hungary's siding with Germany. After the Nazis came to power in the early 1930s, Bartk refused to give concerts in Germany and broke away from his publisher there. His anti-fascist political views caused him a great deal of trouble with the establishment in Hungary. Having first sent his manuscripts out of the country, Bartk reluctantly emigrated to the U.S. with his wife<space/><link><target>Ditta Psztory-Bartk</target><part>Ditta</part></link><space/>in October that year. They settled in New York City. After joining them in 1942, their son, Pter Bartk, enlisted in the<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target></link><space/>where he served in the Pacific during the remainder of the war and later settled in Florida where he became a recording and sound engineer. His oldest son, Bla Bartk III, remained in Hungary where he survived the war and later worked as a railroad official until his retirement in the early 1980s.</paragraph><paragraph>Although he became an American citizen in 1945, shortly before his death<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gagné</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="loc">28</arg></template>, Bartk never became fully at home in the USA. He initially found it difficult to compose. Although well known in America as a pianist, ethnomusicologist and teacher, he was not well known as a composer. There was little American interest in his music during his final years. He and his wife Ditta gave some concerts, although demand for them was low.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template><space/>Bartk, who had made some recordings in Hungary, also recorded for<space/><link><target>Columbia Records</target></link><space/>after he came to the US; many of these recordings (some with Bartk's own spoken introductions) were later issued on LP and CD<space/><template><target>harvard citations</target><arg name="last">Bartók</arg><arg name="year">1994<space/></arg><arg name="year2">1995a<space/></arg><arg name="year3">1995b<space/></arg><arg name="year4">2003<space/></arg><arg name="year5">2007<space/></arg><arg name="year6">2008</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Supported by a research fellowship from<space/><link><target>Columbia University</target></link>, for several years, Bartk and Ditta worked on a large collection of<space/><link><target>Serbian language</target><part>Serbian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Croatian language</target><part>Croatian</part></link><space/>folk songs in Columbia's libraries. Bartk's economic difficulties during his first years in America were mitigated by publication royalties, teaching and performance tours. While his finances were always precarious, he did not live and die in poverty as was the common myth. He had enough friends and supporters to ensure that there was sufficient money and work available for him to live on. Bartk was a proud man and did not easily accept charity. Despite being short on cash at times, he often refused money that his friends offered him out of their own pockets. Although he was not a member of the<space/><link><target>ASCAP</target></link>, the society paid for any medical care he needed during his last two years. Bartk reluctantly accepted this<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">196–203</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>The first symptoms of his health problems began late in 1940, when his right shoulder began to show signs of stiffening. In 1942, symptoms increased and he started having bouts of fever, but no underlying disease was diagnosed, in spite of medical examinations. Finally, in April 1944,<space/><link><target>leukemia</target></link><space/>was diagnosed, but by this time, little could be done<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">202–207</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>As his body slowly failed, Bartk found more creative energy, and he produced a final set of masterpieces, partly thanks to the violinist<space/><link><target>Joseph Szigeti</target></link><space/>and the conductor<space/><link><target>Fritz Reiner</target></link><space/>(Reiner had been Bartk's friend and champion since his days as Bartk's student at the Royal Academy). Bartk's last work might well have been the String Quartet No. 6 but for<space/><link><target>Serge Koussevitzky</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>commission (art)</target><part>commission</part></link><space/>for the<space/><link><target>Concerto for Orchestra (Bartk)</target><part>Concerto for Orchestra</part></link>. Koussevitsky's<space/><link><target>Boston Symphony Orchestra</target></link><space/>premired the work in December 1944 to highly positive reviews. The Concerto for Orchestra quickly became Bartk's most popular work, although he did not live to see its full impact. In 1944, he was also commissioned by<space/><link><target>Yehudi Menuhin</target></link><space/>to write a<space/><link><target>Sonata for Solo Violin (Bartk)</target><part>Sonata for Solo Violin</part></link>. In 1945, Bartk composed his<space/><link><target>Piano Concerto No. 3 (Bartk)</target><part>Piano Concerto No. 3</part></link>, a graceful and almost neo-classical work, as a surprise 42nd birthday present for Ditta, but he died just over a month before her birthday, with the scoring not quite finished. He had sketched his<space/><link><target>Viola Concerto (Bartk)</target><part>Viola Concerto</part></link>, but had barely started the scoring at his death.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:HUF 1000 1983 obverse.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bla Bartk's portrait on 1,000<space/><link><target>Hungarian forint</target></link><space/>banknote (printed between 1983 and 1992; no longer in circulation)</part></link>Bla Bartk died at age 64 in a hospital in New York City from complications of<space/><link><target>leukemia</target></link><space/>(specifically, of secondary<space/><link><target>polycythemia</target></link>) on September 26, 1945. His funeral was attended by only ten people. Among them were his wife Ditta, their son Pter, and his pianist friend<space/><link><target>Gyrgy Sndor</target></link><space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Anon.</arg><arg>2006</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Bartk's body was initially interred in<space/><link><target>Ferncliff Cemetery</target></link><space/>in Hartsdale, New York. During the final year of communist Hungary in the late 1980s, the Hungarian government, along with his two sons, Bla III and Pter, requested that his remains be exhumed and transferred back to<space/><link><target>Budapest</target></link><space/>for burial, where Hungary arranged a<space/><link><target>state funeral</target></link><space/>for him on July 7, 1988. He was reinterred at Budapest's<space/><link><target>Farkasrti Cemetery</target></link>, next to the remains of Ditta, who died in 1982, the year after his centenary<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers<space/></arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">214</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Third Piano Concerto was nearly finished at his death. For his Viola Concerto, Bartk had completed only the viola part and sketches of the orchestral part. Both works were later completed by his pupil<space/><link><target>Tibor Serly</target></link>. Gyrgy Sndor was the soloist in the first performance of the Third Piano Concerto on February&amp;nbsp;8, 1946. Ditta Psztory-Bartk later played and recorded it. The Viola Concerto was revised and published in the 1990s by Bartk's son, Peter; this version may be closer to what Bartk intended<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Chalmers</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="loc">210</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Concurrently, Peter Bartk, in association with Argentinian musician<space/><link><target>Nelson Dellamaggiore</target></link>, worked to reprint and revise past editions of the Third Piano Concerto<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Somfai</arg><arg>1996</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Statues</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Statue of Bla Bartk.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>Statue of Bartk in<space/><link><target>Mak</target></link>, Hungary</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A statue of Bartk stands in<space/><link><target>Brussels</target></link>, Belgium near the central train station in a public square,<space/><italics>Spanjeplein-Place d'Espagne</italics><space/>(<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon.</arg><arg>2014</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Dicaire</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="loc">145</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem>A statue stands outside Malvern Court, south of<space/><link><target>South Kensington</target></link><space/><link><target>London Underground</target><part>Underground Station</part></link>, and just north of 7 Sydney Place, where he stayed when performing in London. An<space/><link><target>English Heritage</target></link><space/><link><target>blue plaque</target></link>, unveiled in 1997, now commemorates Bartk at 7 Sydney Place (<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon.</arg><arg>n.d.(a)</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2012</arg></template>).</listitem><listitem>A statue of him was installed in front of the house in which Bartk spent his last eight years in Hungary, at Csaln t 29, in the hills above Budapest. It is now operated as the Bla Bartk Memorial House (Bartk Bla Emlkhz)<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Tudzin</arg><arg>2010</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>A bust and plaque located at his last residence, in New York City at 309 W. 57th Street, inscribed: &quot;The Great Hungarian Composer / Bla Bartk / (18811945) / Made His Home In This House / During the Last Year of His Life&quot;.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem>A bust of him is located in the front yard of<space/><link><target>Ankara State Conservatory</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ankara</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>right next to the bust of<space/><link><target>Ahmet Adnan Saygun</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem>A bronze statue of Bartk, sculpted by Imre Varga in 2005, stands in the front lobby of the Royal Conservatory of Music, 273 Bloor Street West, Toronto, Ontario, Canada.</listitem><listitem>A statue of Bartk, sculpted by Imre Varga, stands near the<space/><link><target>River Seine</target></link><space/>in the public park at Square Bela Bartok, 26 Place de Brazzaville, in<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>, France<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Anon.</arg><arg>n.d.(b)</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Also to be noted, in the same park, a sculptural transcription of the composer's research on tonal harmony, the fountain/sculpture<space/><italics>Cristaux</italics><space/>designed by<space/><link><target>Jean-Yves Lechevallier</target></link><space/>in 1980.</listitem><listitem>An expressionist sculpture by Hungarian sculptor<space/><link><target>Andrs Beck</target></link><space/>in Square Henri-Collet, Paris<space/><link><target>16th arrondissement of Paris</target><part>16th</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>A statue of him also stands in<space/><link><target>Targu Mures</target></link><space/>city centre.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Compositions</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>List of compositions by Béla Bartók</arg><arg>List of solo piano compositions by Béla Bartók</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Bartk's music reflects two trends that dramatically changed the sound of music in the 20th century: the breakdown of the<space/><link><target>diatonic</target></link><space/>system of harmony that had served composers for the previous two hundred years<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Griffiths</arg><arg>1978</arg><arg name="loc">7</arg></template>; and the revival of nationalism as a source for musical inspiration, a trend that began with<space/><link><target>Mikhail Glinka</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Antonn Dvok</target></link><space/>in the last half of the 19th century<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Einstein</arg><arg>1947</arg><arg name="loc">332</arg></template>. In his search for new forms of tonality, Bartk turned to Hungarian folk music, as well as to other folk music of the<space/><link><target>Carpathian Basin</target></link><space/>and even of Algeria and Turkey; in so doing he became influential in that stream of modernism which exploited indigenous music and techniques<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Botstein</arg><arg>[n.d.]</arg><arg name="loc">§6</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>One characteristic style of music is his<space/><link><target>Night music (Bartk)</target><part>Night music</part></link>, which he used mostly in slow movements of multi-movement ensemble or orchestral compositions in his mature period. It is characterised by &quot;eerie dissonances providing a backdrop to sounds of nature and lonely melodies&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Schneider</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="loc">84</arg></template>. An example is the third movement (Adagio) of his<space/><italics>Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>His music can be grouped roughly in accordance with the different periods in his life.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Youth: Late-Romanticism (18901902)</heading><paragraph>The works of his youth are of a late-Romantic style. Between 1890 and 1894 (nine to 13 years of age) he wrote 31 pieces with corresponding opus numbers. He started numbering his works anew with &quot;opus 1&quot; in 1894 with his first large scale work, a piano sonata. Up to 1902, Bartk wrote in total 74 works which can be considered in Romantic style. Most of these early compositions are either scored for piano solo or include a piano. Additionally, there is some chamber music for strings.</paragraph><heading level='3'>New influences (190311)</heading><paragraph>Under the influence of<space/><link><target>Richard Strauss</target></link>among other works<space/><italics><link><target>Also sprach Zarathustra (Strauss)</target><part>Also sprach Zarathustra</part></link></italics><space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Stevens</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">15–17</arg></template>, Bartk composed in 1903<space/><italics><link><target>Kossuth (Bartk)</target><part>Kossuth</part></link></italics>, a symphonic poem in ten tableaux. In 1904 followed his<space/><italics>Rhapsody for piano and orchestra</italics><space/>which he numbered opus 1 again, marking it himself as the start of a new era in his music. An even more important occurrence of this year was his overhearing the eighteen-year-old nanny Lidi Dsa from<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link><space/>sing folk songs, sparking Bartk's lifelong dedication to folk music<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Stevens</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">22</arg></template>. When criticised for not composing his own melodies<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2010</arg></template><space/>Bartk pointed out that<space/><link><target>Molire</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Shakespeare</target></link><space/>mostly based their plays on well-known stories too. Regarding the incorporation of folk music into art music he said:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>The question is, what are the ways in which peasant music is taken over and becomes transmuted into modern music? We may, for instance, take over a peasant melody unchanged or only slightly varied, write an accompaniment to it and possibly some opening and concluding phrases. This kind of work would show a certain analogy with Bach's treatment of chorales.&amp;nbsp;... Another method&amp;nbsp;... is the following: the composer does not make use of a real peasant melody but invents his own imitation of such melodies. There is no true difference between this method and the one described above.&amp;nbsp;... There is yet a third way&amp;nbsp;... Neither peasant melodies nor imitations of peasant melodies can be found in his music, but it is pervaded by the atmosphere of peasant music. In this case we may say, he has completely absorbed the idiom of peasant music which has become his musical mother tongue.<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Bartók</arg><arg>1931/1976</arg><arg name="loc">341–44</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bartk became first acquainted with Debussy's music in 1907 and regarded his music highly. In an interview in 1939 Bartk said<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Debussy's great service to music was to reawaken among all musicians an awareness of harmony and its possibilities. In that, he was just as important as Beethoven, who revealed to us the possibilities of progressive form, or as Bach, who showed us the transcendent significance of counterpoint. Now, what I am always asking myself is this: is it possible to make a synthesis of these three great masters, a living synthesis that will be valid for our time?<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Moreux</arg><arg>1953</arg><arg name="loc">92</arg></template></extension><space/>Debussy's influence is present in the Fourteen Bagatelles (1908). These made<space/><link><target>Ferruccio Busoni</target></link><space/>exclaim 'At last something truly new!'<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Bartók</arg><arg>1948</arg><arg name="loc">2:83</arg></template>. Until 1911, Bartk composed widely differing works which ranged from adherence to romantic-style, to folk song arrangements and to his modernist opera<space/><italics>Bluebeard's Castle</italics>. The negative reception of his work led him to focus on folk music research after 1911 and abandon composition with the exception of folk music arrangements (<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">404</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Stevens</arg><arg>1964</arg><arg name="loc">47–49</arg></template>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>New inspiration and experimentation (191621)</heading><paragraph>His pessimistic attitude towards composing was lifted by the stormy and inspiring contact with Klra Gombossy in the summer of 1915<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">405</arg></template>. This interesting episode in Bartk's life remained hidden until it was researched by Denijs Dille between 1979 and 1989<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Dille</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="loc">257–77</arg></template>. Bartk started composing again, including the Suite for piano opus 14 (1916), and<space/><italics><link><target>The Miraculous Mandarin</target></link></italics><space/>(1918) and he completed<space/><italics>The Wooden Prince</italics><space/>(1917).</paragraph><paragraph>Bartk felt the result of World War I as a personal tragedy<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Stevens</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">3</arg></template>. Many regions he loved were severed from<space/><link><target>Hungary</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Banat</target></link><space/>where he was born, and<space/><link><target>Pozsony</target></link><space/>where his mother lived. Additionally, the political relations between Hungary and the other successor states to the<space/><link><target>Austro-Hungarian empire</target></link><space/>prohibited his folk music research outside of Hungary<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Somfai</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="loc">18</arg></template>. Bartk also wrote the noteworthy<space/><italics><link><target>Eight Improvisations on Hungarian Peasant Songs</target></link></italics><space/>in 1920, and the sunny<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Suite (Bartk)</target><part>Dance Suite</part></link></italics><space/>in 1923, the year of his second marriage.</paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Synthesis of East and West&quot; (192645)</heading><paragraph>In 1926, Bartk needed a significant piece for piano and orchestra with which he could tour in Europe and America. In the preparation for writing his<space/><link><target>Piano Concerto No. 1 (Bartk)</target><part>First Piano Concerto</part></link>, he wrote his Sonata,<space/><italics><link><target>Out of Doors (Bartk)</target><part>Out of Doors</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics>Nine Little Pieces</italics>, all for solo piano<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">173</arg></template>. He increasingly found his own voice in his maturity. The style of his last periodnamed &quot;Synthesis of East and West&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="loc">189</arg></template>is hard to define let alone to put under one term. In his mature period, Bartk wrote relatively few works but most of them are large-scale compositions for large settings. Only his voice works have programmatic titles and his late works often adhere to classical forms.</paragraph><paragraph>Among his masterworks are all the six<space/><link><target>List of string quartets by Bla Bartk</target><part>string quartets</part></link><space/>(1908, 1917, 1927, 1928, 1934, and 1939), the<space/><italics><link><target>Cantata Profana</target></link></italics><space/>(1930, Bartk declared that this was the work he felt and professed to be his most personal &quot;credo&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Szabolcsi</arg><arg>1974</arg><arg name="loc">186</arg></template>, the<space/><italics>Music for Strings, Percussion and Celesta</italics><space/>(1936), the Concerto for Orchestra (1943) and the Third Piano Concerto (1945).</paragraph><paragraph>Bartk also made a lasting contribution to the literature for younger students: for his son Pter's music lessons, he composed<space/><italics><link><target>Mikrokosmos (Bartk)</target><part>Mikrokosmos</part></link></italics>, a six-volume collection of graded piano pieces.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Musical analysis</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bartok Bela Baja.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Bla Bartk memorial plaque in<space/><link><target>Baja, Hungary</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Paul Wilson (music theorist)</target><part>Paul Wilson</part></link><space/>lists as the most prominent characteristics of Bartk's music from late 1920s onwards the influence of the<space/><link><target>Carpathian basin</target></link><space/>and European art music, and his changing attitude toward (and use of) tonality, but without the use of the traditional<space/><link><target>Diatonic functionality</target><part>harmonic functions</part></link><space/>associated with major and minor scales<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Wilson</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">2–4</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Although Bartk claimed in his writings that his music was always tonal, he rarely uses the chords or scales of tonality, and so the descriptive resources of tonal theory are of limited use.<space/><link><target>George Perle</target><part>George</part></link><space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Perle</arg><arg>1955</arg></template><space/>and Elliott<space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Antokoletz</arg><arg>1984</arg></template><space/>focus on alternative methods of signaling tonal centers, via axes of inversional symmetry. Others view Bartk's axes of symmetry in terms of atonal analytic protocols.<space/><link><target>Richard Cohn</target><part>Richard</part></link><space/><template><target>harvtxt</target><arg>Cohn</arg><arg>1988</arg></template><space/>argues that<space/><link><target>Inversion (music)#Inversional equivalency</target><part>inversional symmetry</part></link><space/>is often a byproduct of another atonal procedure, the formation of chords from transpositionally related dyads. Atonal pitch-class theory also furnishes the resources for exploring<space/><link><target>polymodal chromaticism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>projected set</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>privileged pattern</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and large set types used as source sets such as the equal tempered twelve tone<space/><link><target>tone row#total chromatic</target><part>aggregate</part></link>,<space/><link><target>octatonic scale</target></link><space/>(and<space/><link><target>alpha chord</target></link>), the diatonic and<space/><italics>heptatonia secunda</italics><space/>seven-note scales, and less often the whole tone scale and the primary pentatonic collection<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Wilson</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">24–29</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>He rarely used the simple aggregate actively to shape musical structure, though there are notable examples such as the second theme from the first movement of his Second Violin Concerto, commenting that he &quot;wanted to show<space/><link><target>Arnold Schoenberg</target><part>Schoenberg</part></link><space/>that one can use all twelve tones and still remain tonal&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Gillies</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="loc">185</arg></template>. More thoroughly, in the first eight measures of the last movement of his Second Quartet, all notes gradually gather with the twelfth (G) sounding for the first time on the last beat of measure 8, marking the end of the first section. The aggregate is partitioned in the opening of the Third String Quartet with CDDE in the accompaniment (strings) while the remaining pitch classes are used in the melody (violin 1) and more often as 735 (diatonic or &quot;white-key&quot; collection) and 535 (pentatonic or &quot;black-key&quot; collection) such as in no. 6 of the<space/><italics>Eight Improvisations</italics>. There, the primary theme is on the black keys in the left hand, while the right accompanies with triads from the white keys. In measures 5051 in the third movement of the Fourth Quartet, the first violin and cello play black-key chords, while the second violin and viola play stepwise diatonic lines<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Wilson</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">25</arg></template>. On the other hand, from as early as the Suite for piano, Op. 14 (1914), he occasionally employed a form of<space/><link><target>serialism</target></link><space/>based on compound interval cycles, some of which are maximally distributed, multi-aggregate cycles (<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Martins</arg><arg>2004</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Gollin</arg><arg>2007</arg></template>).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Bartok - Sonata for two pianos and percussion, 3rd mov. fibonacci.png</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Fibonacci number</target><part>Fibonacci</part></link><space/>intervals (counting in semitones) in Bartk's<space/><link><target>Sonata for Two Pianos and Percussion</target></link>, 3rd mov. (1937) (<template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Maconie</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">26, 28</arg></template>, citing<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Lendvai</arg><arg>1972</arg></template>)<space/><template><target>audio</target><arg>Bartok - Sonata for two pianos and percussion, 3rd mov. fibonacci.mid</arg><arg>Play</arg></template></part></link><link><target>Ern Lendvai</target></link><space/>(1971) analyses Bartk's works as being based on two opposing tonal systems, that of the<space/><link><target>acoustic scale</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>axis system</target></link>, as well as using the<space/><link><target>golden ratio</target><part>golden section</part></link><space/>as a structural principle.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Milton Babbitt</target></link>, in his 1949 critique of Bartk's string quartets, criticized Bartk for using tonality and non tonal methods unique to each piece. Babbitt noted that &quot;Bartk's solution was a specific one, it cannot be duplicated&quot;<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Babbitt</arg><arg>1949</arg><arg name="loc">385</arg></template>. Bartk's use of &quot;two organizational principles&quot;tonality for large scale relationships and the piece-specific method for moment to moment thematic elementswas a problem for Babbitt, who worried that the &quot;highly attenuated tonality&quot; requires extreme non-harmonic methods to create a feeling of closure<space/><template><target>harv</target><arg>Babbitt</arg><arg>1949</arg><arg name="loc">377–78</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Catalogues and opus numbers</heading><paragraph>The cataloguing of Bartk's works is somewhat complex. Bartk assigned opus numbers to his works three times, the last of these series ending with the Sonata for Violin and Piano No. 1, Op. 21 in 1921. He ended this practice because of the difficulty of distinguishing between original works and ethnographic arrangements, and between major and minor works. Since his death, three attemptstwo full and one partialhave been made at cataloguing. The first, and still most widely used, is<space/><link><target>Andrs Szllsy</target></link>'s chronological Sz. numbers, from 1 to 121.<space/><link><target>Denijs Dille</target></link><space/>subsequently reorganised the juvenilia (Sz. 125) thematically, as DD numbers 1 to 77. The most recent catalogue is that of<space/><link><target>Lszl Somfai</target></link>; this is a chronological index with works identified by BB numbers 1 to 129, incorporating corrections based on the Bla Bartk Thematic Catalogue.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2007</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Discography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 1994.<space/><italics>Bartk at the Piano</italics>. Hungaroton 12326. 6-CD set.</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 1995a.<space/><italics>Bartok Plays Bartok Bartok at the Piano 192941</italics>. Pearl 9166. CD recording.</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 1995b.<space/><italics>Bartk Recordings from Private Collections</italics>. Hungaroton 12334. CD recording.</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 2003.<space/><italics>Bartk Plays Bartk</italics>. Pearl 179. CD recording.</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 2007.<space/><italics>Bartk: Contrasts, Mikrokosmos</italics>. Membran/Documents 223546. CD recording.</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 2008.<space/><italics>Bartok Plays Bartok</italics>. Urania 340. CD recording.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Media</heading><paragraph><template><target>multi-listen start</target></template><template><target>multi-listen item</target><arg><space/></arg><arg name="filename"><space/>Bartók - Sonata for two pianos and percussion - Assai lento - Allegro molto (clip).ogg<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sonata for two pianos and percussion, first movement (excerpt)<space/></arg><arg name="description"><space/>This segment of Bartók's Sonata for two pianos and percussion features pedal glissandos during a timpani roll.</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>multi-listen item</target><arg name="filename"><space/>Bartók - Concerto for Orchestra (clip).ogg</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concerto for Orchestra (excerpt)<space/></arg><arg name="description"><space/>In this passage from the ''Intermezzo interrotto'' movement of Bartók's [[Concerto for Orchestra (Bartók)|Concerto for Orchestra]], the timpanist plays a chromatic bass line, which requires using the pedal to change pitches.</arg></template><template><target>multi-listen item</target><arg name="filename">Bartok - Romanian Folk Dances.ogg</arg><arg name="title">Romanian Folk Dances Nos. 2, 5 and 6</arg><arg name="description">Performed by the Advent Chamber Orchestra</arg><arg name="format">[[ogg]]</arg></template><template><target>multi-listen item</target><arg name="filename">Bartok_Op._17,_Second_Movement.OGG</arg><arg name="title">String quartet number 2, second movement</arg><arg name="description">played by the [http://www.carmelquartet.com Carmel Quartet].</arg></template><template><target>multi-listen item</target><arg name="filename">Bartok - Sonatina.ogg</arg><arg name="title">Sonatina for solo piano</arg><arg name="description">Performed March 2009</arg></template><template><target>multi-listen end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Biography</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>30em</arg><arg name="normalfont">yes</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Anon.|n.d.(a)}}</arg><arg name="reference">Anon. n.d.(a) "[http://www.english-heritage.org.uk/discover/blue-plaques/search/bartok-bela-1881-1945 Bartók, Béla (1881–1945) Plaque erected in 1997 by English Heritage at 7 Sydney Place, South Kensington, London SW7 3NL, Royal Borough of Kensington and Chelsea]". English Heritage website (Accessed 19 October 2012).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Anon.|n.d.(b)}}</arg><arg name="reference">Anon. n.d.(b). "[http://www.eutouring.com/square_bela_bartok.html Square Béla Bartók in Paris]" Eutouring.com website (2 August) (accessed 4 July 2014).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Anon.|2006}}</arg><arg name="reference">Anon. 2006. "[http://www.juilliard.edu/update/journal/j_articles785.html Gyorgy Sandor, Pianist and Bartok Authority, Dies at 93]". ''The Juilliard Journal Online'' 21, no. 5 (February) (accessed September 15, 2010).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Anon.|2014}}</arg><arg name="reference">Anon. 2014. [http://www.brusselsremembers.com/ Location Map]. Brussels Remembers: Memorials of Brussels (accessed 17 June 2014).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Antokoletz|1984}}</arg><arg name="reference">Antokoletz, Elliott. 1984. ''The Music of Béla Bartók: A Study of Tonality and Progression in Twentieth-Century Music''. Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press. ISBN 0-520-04604-8.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Babbitt|1949}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Milton Babbitt|Babbitt, Milton]]. 1949. "The String Quartets of Bartók". ''Musical Quarterly'' 35 (July): 377–85. Reprinted in ''The Collected Essays of Milton Babbitt'', edited by Stephen Peles, with Stephen Dembski, Andrew Mead, and Joseph N. Straus, [http://press.princeton.edu/chapters/s7616.pdf {{page needed|date</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Bartók|1981}}</arg><arg name="reference">Bartók, Béla. 1981. ''[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Bayley|2001}}</arg><arg name="reference">Bayley, Amanda. 2001. ''[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Botstein|[n.d.]}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Leon Botstein|Botstein, Leon]]. [n.d.] "Modernism", ''Grove Music Online'', ed. L. Macy (Accessed April 29, 2008), [http://www.grovemusic.com (subscription access)].</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Chalmers|1995}}</arg><arg name="reference">Chalmers, Kenneth. 1995. ''Béla Bartók''. 20th-Century Composers. London: Phaidon Press. ISBN 0-7148-3164-6 (pbk).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Cohn|1988}}</arg><arg name="reference">Cohn, Richard, 1988. "Inversional Symmetry and Transpositional Combination in Bartok." ''Music Theory Spectrum'' 10:19–42.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|de Toth|1999}}</arg><arg name="reference">de Toth, June. 1999. "Béla Bartók: A Biography". [http://www.bartokcds.com/bio.html Bela Bartok Biography Liner notes to ''Béla Bartók: Complete Piano Works''] 7-CD set, Eroica Classical Recordings{{Full|date</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Dicaire|2010}}</arg><arg name="reference">Dicaire, David. 2010. ''The Early Years of Folk Music: Fifty Founders of the Tradition'', p.145. McFarland. ISBN 9780786457373.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Dille|1990}}</arg><arg name="reference">Dille, Denijs. 1990. Béla Bartók: Regard sur le Passé. (French, no English version available). Namur: Presses universitaires de Namur. ISBN 2-87037-168-3 ISBN 978-2-87037-168-8.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Einstein|1947}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Alfred Einstein|Einstein, Alfred]]. 1947. ''Music in the Romantic Era''. New York: W. W. Norton.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Gagné|2012}}</arg><arg name="reference">Gagné, Nicole V. 2012. ''Historical Dictionary of Modern and Contemporary Classical Music''. Historical Dictionaries of Literature and the Arts. Lanham, Maryland: Scarecrow Press. ISBN 978-0-8108-6765-9.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Gillies|1990}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Malcolm Gillies|Gillies, Malcolm]] (ed.). 1990. ''Bartók Remembered''. London: Faber. ISBN 0-571-14243-5 (cased) ISBN 0-571-14244-3 (pbk).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Gillies|1993}}</arg><arg name="reference">Gillies, Malcolm (ed.). 1993. ''The Bartók Companion''. London: Faber. ISBN 0-571-15330-5 (cloth), ISBN 0-571-15331-3 (pbk); New York: Hal Leonard. ISBN 0-931340-74-8.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Gillies|2001}}</arg><arg name="reference">Gillies, Malcolm. 2001. "Béla Bartók". ''The New Grove Dictionary of Music and Musicians'', second edition, edited by [[Stanley Sadie]] and [[John Tyrrell (professor of music)|John Tyrrell]]. London: Macmillan Publishers. Also in ''Grove Music Online'', ed. L. Macy (Accessed May 23, 2006), [http://www.grovemusic.com (subscription access)].</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Gollin|2007}}</arg><arg name="reference">Gollin, Edward. 2007. "Multi-Aggregate Cycles and Multi-Aggregate Serial Techniques in the Music of Béla Bartók". ''Music Theory Spectrum'' 29, no. 2 (Fall): 143–76.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Griffiths|1978}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Paul Griffiths (writer)|Griffiths, Paul]]. 1978. ''A Concise History of Modern Music''. London: Thames and Hudson. ISBN 0-500-20164-1.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Hughes|1999–2007}}</arg><arg name="reference">Hughes, Peter. 1999–2007. "[http://www25.uua.org/uuhs/duub/articles/belabartok.html Béla Bartók]" in ''Dictionary of Unitarian and Universalist Biography''. [n.p.]: Unitarian Universalist Historical Society.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Jones|2012}}</arg><arg name="reference">Jones, Tom. 2012. "[http://www.tiredoflondontiredoflife.com/2012/10/see-bela-bartok.html See Béla Bartók]". Tired of London, Tired of Life blog site (8 October) (accessed 4 July 2014).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Lendvai|1971}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Ernő Lendvai|Lendvai, Ernő]]. 1971. ''Béla Bartók: An Analysis of His Music'', introduced by [[Alan Bush]]. London: Kahn & Averill. ISBN 0-900707-04-6 {{oclc|240301}}.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Lendvai|1972}}</arg><arg name="reference">Lendvai, Ernő. 1972. "Einführung in die Formen- und Harmoniewelt Bartóks" (1953). In his ''Béla Bartók: Weg und Werk'', edited by [[Bence Szabolcsi]], 105–49. Kassel: Bärenreiter.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Maconie|2005}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[Robin Maconie|Maconie, Robin]]. 2005. ''Other Planets: The Music of Karlheinz Stockhausen''. Lanham, MD, Toronto, Oxford: The Scarecrow Press, Inc. ISBN 978-0-8108-5356-0.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Moreux|1953}}</arg><arg name="reference">Moreux, Serge. 1953. ''Béla Bartók'', translated [[G. S. Fraser]] and [[Erik de Mauny]]. London: The Harvill Press.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Móser|2006a}}</arg><arg name="reference">Móser, Zoltán. 2006a. "[http://epa.oszk.hu/00700/00713/00175/pdf/2006_03.pdf Szavak, feliratok, kivonatok]". ''Tiszatáj'' 60, no. 3 (March): 41–45.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Özgentürk|2008}}</arg><arg name="reference">Özgentürk, Nebil. 2008. ''Türkiye'nin Hatıra Defteri'', episode 3. Istanbul: Bir Yudum İnsan Prodüksiyon LTD. ȘTİ. Turkish CNN television documentary series.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Perle|1955}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[George Perle|Perle, George]]. 1955. "Symmetrical Formations in the String Quartets of Béla Bartók". ''Music Review'' 16, no. 4 (November 1955). Reprinted in ''The Right Notes: Twenty-Three Selected Essays by George Perle on Twentieth-Century Music'', foreword by Oliver Knussen, introduction by David Headlam, 189–205. Monographs in Musicology. Stuyvesant, NY: Pendragon Press. ISBN 0-945193-37-8.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Schneider|2006}}</arg><arg name="reference">Schneider, David E. 2006. ''Bartók, Hungary, and the Renewal of Tradition: Case Studies in the Intersection of Modernity and Nationality''. California Studies in 20th-Century Music 5. Berkeley: University of California Press. ISBN 978-0-520-24503-7.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Sipos|2000}}</arg><arg name="reference">Sipos, János (ed.). 2000. ''In the Wake of Bartók in Anatolia 1: Collection Near Adana''. Budapest: Ethnofon Records.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Smith|1965}}</arg><arg name="reference"><space/>Smith, Erik. 1965. ''A discussion between [[István Kertész (conductor)|István Kertész]] and the producer''. DECCA Records (liner notes for ''[[Bluebeard's Castle]]'')</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Somfai|1996}}</arg><arg name="reference">[[László Somfai|Somfai, László]]. 1996. ''Béla Bartók: Composition, Concepts, and Autograph Sources''. Ernest Bloch Lectures in Music 9. Berkeley : University of California Press. ISBN 978-0-520-08485-8.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Statue:Bela Bartok|n.d.}}</arg><arg name="reference">"[http://www.brusselsremembers.com/memorials/bela-bartok Statue: Bela Bartok]", ''BrusselsRemembers.com''.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Stevens|1964}}</arg><arg name="reference">Stevens, Halsey. 1964. ''The Life and Music of Béla Bartók'', second edition. New York: Oxford University Press. ASIN: B000NZ54ZS (Third edition, prepared by Malcolm Gillies, 1993, ISBN 978-0-19-816349-7).</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Szabolcsi|1974}}</arg><arg name="reference">Szabolcsi, Bence. 1974. "Bartók Béla: Cantata profana". In "Miért szép századunk zenéje?" (Why is the music of the Twentieth century so beautiful), ed. György Kroó. Budapest.{{Full|date</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Tudzin|2010}}</arg><arg name="reference">Tudzin, Jessica Taylor. 2010. "[http://www.bohemianink.net/?p</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Wilson|1992}}</arg><arg name="reference">Wilson, Paul. 1992. ''The Music of Béla Bartók''. New Haven: Yale University Press. ISBN 0-300-05111-5.</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Anon. 2003. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.websophia.com/faces/bartok.html'>Bla Bartk 18811945</link>&quot;.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.websophia.com/'>Websophia.com</link></italics>. (Accessed March 25, 2009)</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 1948.<space/><italics>Levelek, fnykpek, kziratok, kottk.</italics><space/>(&quot;Letters, photographs, manuscripts, scores&quot;), ed. Jnos Demny, 2 vols. A Muvszeti Tancs knyvei, 1.2. sz. Budapest: Magyar Muvszeti Tancs. English edition, as<space/><italics>Bla Bartk: Letters</italics>, translated by Pter Balabn and Istvn Farkas; translation revised by Elisabeth West and Colin Mason (London: Faber and Faber Ltd.; New York: St. Martin's Press, 1971). ISBN 978-0-571-09638-1</listitem><listitem>Bartk, Bla. 1976. &quot;The Influence of Peasant Music on Modern Music (1931)&quot;. In<space/><italics>Bla Bartk Essays</italics>, edited by Benjamin Suchoff, 34044. London:<space/><link><target>Faber &amp; Faber</target></link>. ISBN 0-571-10120-8<space/><template><target>oclc</target><arg>60900461</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Bartk, Peter. 2002. &quot;My Father&quot;. Homosassa, Florida, Bartk Records (ISBN 0-9641961-2-3).</listitem><listitem>Bnis, Ferenc. 2006.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=W7-iAQAACAAJ&amp;amp;dq=%C3%89LET-K%C3%89PEK:+BART%C3%93K+B%C3%89LA'>let-kpek: Bartk Bla</link></italics>. Budapest: Balassi Kiad: Vvi Kft., Alfldi Nyomda Zrt. ISBN 963-506-649-X.</listitem><listitem>Boys, Henry. 1945. &quot;Bla Bartk 18811945&quot;.<space/><italics>Musical Times</italics><space/>86, no. 1233 (November): 32931.</listitem><listitem>Cohn, Richard, 1992. &quot;Bartok's Octatonic Strategies: A Motivic Approach.&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of the American Musicological Society</italics><space/>44</listitem><listitem>Czeizel, Endre. 1992.<space/><italics>Csaldfa: honnan jvnk, mik vagyunk, hov megynk?</italics><space/>[Budapest]: Kossuth Knyvkiad. ISBN 963-09-3569-4</listitem><listitem>Jyrkiinen, Reijo. 2012. &quot;Form, Monothematicism, Variation and Symmetry in Bla Bartk's String Quartets&quot;. Ph.D. diss. Helsinki: University of Helsinki. ISBN 978-952-10-8040-1 (<link type='external' href='https://helda.helsinki.fi/handle/10138/33683'>Abstract</link>).</listitem><listitem>Krpti, Jnos. 1975.<space/><italics>Bartk's String Quartets</italics>, translated by Fred MacNicol. Budapest: Corvina Press.</listitem><listitem>Kasparov, Andrey. 2000. &quot;Third Piano Concerto in the Revised 1994 Edition: Newly Discovered Corrections by the Composer&quot;.<space/><italics>Hungarian Music Quarterly</italics><space/>11, nos. 34:211.</listitem><listitem>Leafstedt, Carl S. 1999.<space/><italics>Inside Bluebeard's Castle</italics>. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 0-19-510999-6</listitem><listitem>Loxdale, Hugh D., and Adalbert Balog. 2009. &quot;Bela Bartok: Musician, Musicologist, Composer, and Entomologist!.&quot;<space/><italics>Antenna</italics><space/>Bulletin of the<space/><link><target>Royal Entomological Society of London</target></link><space/>33, no. 4:17582.</listitem><listitem>Mser, Zoltn. 2006b. &quot;Bartk-sk Gmrben&quot;.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hnm.hu/honismeret/folyoirat/2006-2-honismeret1.pdf'>''Honismeret: A Honismereti Szvetsg folyirata''<space/></link><space/>34, no. 2 (April): 911.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.cedarville.edu/musicalofferings/vol3/iss2/2'>Nelson, David Taylor (2012). &quot;Bla Bartk: The Father of Ethnomusicology&quot;, Musical Offerings: Vol. 3: No. 2, Article 2.</link></listitem><listitem>Sluder, Claude K. 1994. &quot;Revised Bartok Composition Highlights Pro Musica Concert&quot;.<space/><italics><link><target>The Republic (Columbus)</target><part>The Republic</part></link></italics><space/>(16 February).</listitem><listitem>Somfai, Lszl. 1981.<space/><italics>Tizennyolc Bartk-tanulmny</italics><space/>[Eighteen Bartk Studies]. Budapest: Zenemkiad. ISBN 963-330-370-2.</listitem><listitem>Wells, John C. 1990. &quot;Bartk&quot;, in<space/><italics>Longman Pronunciation Dictionary</italics>, 63. Harlow, England: Longman. ISBN 0-582-05383-8.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lieder.net/lieder/b/bartok.html'>The Lied and Art Song Texts Page</link><space/>Original texts of the songs of Bartk with translations in various languages.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bartokmuseum.hu'>Bartk Bla Memorial House, Budapest</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bartok.kbr.be'>The Belgian Bartk Archives, housed in the Brussels Royal Library and founded by Denijs Dille</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>BBC composer page</target><arg>bartok</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gallery-diabolus.com/gallery/artist.php?language=english&amp;amp;id=utisz&amp;amp;page=205/'>Gallery of Bartk portraits</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.zti.hu/bartok/exhibition/main.htm'>Virtual Exhibition on Bartk</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>ContemporaryMusicOnline</target><arg>Bartok</arg><arg>works</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>IMSLP</target><arg>Bartók, Béla</arg></template></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline><preline><template><target>Bla Bartk</target></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Modernist composers</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Bartók, Béla Viktor János
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION">[[Hungary|Hungarian]] composer, pianist, and collector of Eastern European and Middle Eastern [[folk music]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>March 25, 1881
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH">[[Nagyszentmiklós]], Kingdom of Hungary (now [[Sânnicolau Mare]], Romania)
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>September 26, 1945
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">New York City
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Bartok, Bela</target></template><link><target>Category:1881 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1945 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Snnicolau Mare</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Franz Liszt Academy of Music alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Anton Rubinstein Competition prize-winners</target></link><link><target>Category:Ballet composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Ferncliff Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Farkasrti Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in New York</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from leukemia</target></link><link><target>Category:Ethnomusicologists</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian atheists</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian Unitarians</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian classical pianists</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian people of German descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Male classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian educators</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian music educators</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian entomologists</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian folk-song collectors</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian emigrants to the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian song collectors</target></link><link><target>Category:Modernist composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Opera composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Danube-Swabian people</target></link><link><target>Category:Pupils of Istvn Thomn</target></link><link><target>Category:Pupils of Hans von Koessler</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungarian refugees</target></link><link><target>Category:Members of the Hungarian Academy of Sciences</target></link><link><target>Category:Members of the Romanian Academy elected post-mortem</target></link><link><target>Category:Composers for piano</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Saranac Lake, New York</target></link></paragraph></article>