<article title='Cottingley_Fairies'><paragraph><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:Cottingley Fairies 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=photo</part><part>The first of the five photographs, taken by Elsie Wright in 1917, shows Frances Griffiths with the alleged fairies.</part></link>The<space/><bold>Cottingley Fairies</bold><space/>appear in a series of five photographs taken by Elsie Wright (190088) and Frances Griffiths (190786), two young cousins who lived in<space/><link><target>Cottingley, Bradford</target><part>Cottingley</part></link>, near<space/><link><target>Bradford</target></link><space/>in England. In 1917, when the first two photographs were taken, Elsie was 16 years old and Frances was 9. The pictures came to the attention of writer Sir<space/><link><target>Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link>, who used them to illustrate an article on<space/><link><target>fairy</target><part>fairies</part></link><space/>he had been commissioned to write for the Christmas 1920 edition of<space/><italics><link><target>Strand Magazine</target><part>The Strand Magazine</part></link></italics>. Doyle, as a<space/><link><target>Spiritualism (religious movement)</target><part>spiritualist</part></link>, was enthusiastic about the photographs, and interpreted them as clear and visible evidence of<space/><link><target>psychic</target></link><space/>phenomena. Public reaction was mixed; some accepted the images as genuine, but others believed they had been faked.</paragraph><paragraph>Interest in the Cottingley Fairies gradually declined after 1921. Both girls married and lived abroad for a time after they grew up, yet the photographs continued to hold the public imagination. In 1966 a reporter from the<space/><italics><link><target>Daily Express</target></link></italics><space/>newspaper traced Elsie, who had by then returned to the UK. Elsie left open the possibility that she believed she had photographed her thoughts, and the media once again became interested in the story.</paragraph><paragraph>In the early 1980s Elsie and Frances admitted that the photographs were faked, using cardboard cutouts of fairies copied from a popular children's book of the time, but Frances maintained that the fifth and final photograph was genuine. The photographs and two of the cameras used are on display in the<space/><link><target>National Media Museum</target></link><space/>in Bradford.</paragraph><heading level='2'>1917 photographs</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CottingleyBeck.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>alt=Photo</part><part>Cottingley Beck, where Frances and Elsie claimed to have seen the fairies</part></link>In mid-1917 nine-year-old Frances Griffiths and her motherboth newly arrived in the UK from South Africawere staying with Frances' aunt, Elsie Wright's mother, in the village of<space/><link><target>Cottingley, Bradford</target><part>Cottingley</part></link><space/>in West Yorkshire; Elsie was then 16 years old. The two girls often played together beside the beck (stream) at the bottom of the garden, much to their mothers' annoyance, because they frequently came back with wet feet and clothes. Frances and Elsie said they only went to the beck to see the fairies, and to prove it, Elsie borrowed her father's camera, a Midg<space/><link><target>Film format#Still photography film formats</target><part>quarter-plate</part></link>. The girls returned about 30&amp;nbsp;minutes later, &quot;triumphant&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">97–98</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Elsie's father, Arthur, was a keen amateur photographer, and had set up his own darkroom. The picture on the<space/><link><target>photographic plate</target></link><space/>he developed showed Frances behind a bush in the foreground, on which four fairies appeared to be dancing. Knowing his daughter's artistic ability, and that she had spent some time working in a photographer's studio, he dismissed the figures as cardboard cutouts. Two months later the girls borrowed his camera again, and this time returned with a photograph of Elsie sitting on the lawn holding out her hand to a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg><arg name="disp">x</arg><arg>-tall (</arg><arg>)</arg></template><space/>gnome. Exasperated by what he believed to be &quot;nothing but a prank&quot;,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">97</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>and convinced that the girls must have tampered with his camera in some way, Arthur Wright refused to lend it to them again.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Prashad</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">42</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>His wife Polly, however, believed the photographs to be authentic.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">97</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width">25em<space/></arg><arg name="align">right<space/></arg><arg name="quoted">true<space/></arg><arg name="bgcolor">#FFFFF0<space/></arg><arg name="salign">left<space/></arg><arg name="quote">I am learning French, Geometry, Cookery and Algebra at school now. Dad came home from France the other week after being there ten months, and we all think the war will be over in a few days&nbsp;... I am sending two photos, both of me, one of me in a bathing costume in our back yard, while the other is me with some fairies. Elsie took that one.</arg><arg name="source">Letter from Frances Griffiths to a friend in South Africa{{sfnp|Prashad|2008|p</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Towards the end of 1918, Frances sent a letter to Johanna Parvin, a friend in<space/><link><target>Cape Town</target></link>, South Africa, where Frances had lived for most of her life, enclosing the photograph of herself with the fairies. On the back she wrote &quot;It is funny, I never used to see them in Africa. It must be too hot for them there.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Prashad</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">40</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The photographs became public in mid-1919, after Elsie's mother attended a meeting of the<space/><link><target>Theosophical Society</target></link><space/>in Bradford. The lecture that evening was on &quot;fairy life&quot;, and at the end of the meeting Polly Wright showed the two fairy photographs taken by her daughter and niece to the speaker. As a result, the photographs were displayed at the society's annual conference in<space/><link><target>Harrogate</target></link>, held a few months later. There they came to the attention of a leading member of the society, Edward Gardner.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">98–99</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>One of the central beliefs of theosophy is that humanity is undergoing a cycle of evolution, towards increasing &quot;perfection&quot;, and Gardner recognised the potential significance of the photographs for the movement:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="... the fact that two young girls had not only been able to see fairies, which others had done, but had actually for the first time ever been able to materialise them at a density sufficient for their images to be recorded on a photographic plate, meant that it was possible that the next cycle of evolution was underway.{{sfnp|Smith|1997|p">382|ps</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Initial examinations</heading><paragraph>Gardner sent the prints along with the original glass-plate negatives to Harold Snelling, a photography expert. Snelling's opinion was that &quot;the two negatives are entirely genuine, unfaked photographs&amp;nbsp;... [with] no trace whatsoever of studio work involving card or paper models&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">99</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>He did not go so far as to say that the photographs showed fairies, stating only that &quot;these are straight forward photographs of whatever was in front of the camera at the time&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">389</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Gardner had the prints &quot;clarified&quot; by Snelling, and new negatives produced, &quot;more conducive to printing&quot;,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">98–99</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">382</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>for use in the illustrated lectures he gave around the UK.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">382</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Snelling supplied the photographic prints which were available for sale at Gardner's lectures.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">401</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="crawley"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CottingleyFairies2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>alt=Photo</part><part>The second of the five photographs, showing Elsie with a winged gnome</part></link>Author and prominent<space/><link><target>Spiritualism (religious movement)</target><part>spiritualist</part></link><space/><link><target>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link><space/>learned of the photographs from the editor of the spiritualist publication<space/><italics>Light</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">383</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Doyle had been commissioned by<space/><italics><link><target>The Strand Magazine</target></link></italics><space/>to write an article on fairies for their Christmas issue, and the fairy photographs &quot;must have seemed like a godsend&quot; according to broadcaster and historian<space/><link><target>Magnus Magnusson</target></link>. Doyle contacted Gardner in June 1920 to determine the background to the photographs, and wrote to Elsie and her father to request permission from the latter to use the prints in his article. Arthur Wright was &quot;obviously impressed&quot; that Doyle was involved, and gave his permission for publication, but he refused payment on the grounds that, if genuine, the images should not be &quot;soiled&quot; by money.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">99–100</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Gardner and Doyle sought a second expert opinion from the photographic company<space/><link><target>Eastman Kodak</target><part>Kodak</part></link>. Several of the company's technicians examined the enhanced prints, and although they agreed with Snelling that the pictures &quot;showed no signs of being faked&quot;, they concluded that &quot;this could not be taken as conclusive evidence&amp;nbsp;... that they were authentic photographs of fairies&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">384</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Kodak declined to issue a certificate of authenticity.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">101</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Gardner believed that the Kodak technicians might not have examined the photographs entirely objectively, observing that one had commented &quot;after all, as fairies couldn't be true, the photographs must have been faked somehow&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">385</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>The prints were also examined by another photographic company,<space/><link><target>Ilford Photo</target><part>Ilford</part></link>, who reported unequivocally that there was &quot;some evidence of faking&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">385</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Gardner and Doyle, perhaps rather optimistically, interpreted the results of the three expert evaluations as two in favour of the photographs' authenticity and one against.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">385</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Doyle also showed the photographs to the<space/><link><target>physicist</target></link><space/>and pioneering<space/><link><target>parapsychology</target><part>psychical researcher</part></link><space/><link><target>Sir Oliver Lodge</target></link>, who believed the photographs to be fake. He suggested that a troupe of dancers had masqueraded as fairies, and expressed doubt as to their &quot;distinctly 'Parisienne<template><target>'&quot;</target></template><space/>hairstyles.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">101</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>1920 photographs</heading><paragraph>Doyle was preoccupied with organising an imminent lecture tour of Australia, and in July 1920, sent Gardner to meet the Wright family. Frances was by then living with her parents in<space/><link><target>Scarborough, North Yorkshire</target><part>Scarborough</part></link>,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">385</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>but Elsie's father told Gardner that he had been so certain the photographs were fakes that while the girls were away he searched their bedroom and the area around the beck (stream), looking for scraps of pictures or cutouts, but found nothing &quot;incriminating&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">102</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CottingleyFairies3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>alt=Photo</part><part>''Frances and the Leaping Fairy'', the third photograph</part></link>Gardner believed the Wright family to be honest and respectable. To place the matter of the photographs' authenticity beyond doubt, he returned to Cottingley at the end of July with two Kodak Cameo cameras and 24&amp;nbsp;secretly marked photographic plates. Frances was invited to stay with the Wright family during the school summer holiday so that she and Elsie could take more pictures of the fairies.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">102</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Gardner described his briefing in his 1945<space/><italics>Fairies: A Book of Real Fairies</italics>:<template><target>quote/to right of image</target><arg name="I went off, to Cottingley again, taking the two cameras and plates from London, and met the family and explained to the two girls the simple working of the cameras, giving one each to keep. The cameras were loaded, and my final advice was that they need go up to the glen only on fine days as they had been accustomed to do before and ''tice'' the fairies, as they called their way of attracting them, and see what they could get. I suggested only the most obvious and easy precautions about lighting and distance, for I knew it was essential they should feel free and unhampered and have no burden of responsibility. If nothing came of it all, I told them, they were not to mind a bit.<ref name">Cooper/></arg></template>Until 19 August the weather was unsuitable for photography. Because Frances and Elsie insisted that the fairies would not show themselves if others were watching, Elsie's mother was persuaded to visit her sister's for tea, leaving the girls alone. In her absence the girls took several photographs, two of which appeared to show fairies. In the first,<space/><italics>Frances and the Leaping Fairy</italics>, Frances is shown in profile with a winged fairy close by her nose. The second,<space/><italics>Fairy offering Posy of<space/><link><target>Campanula rotundifolia</target><part>Harebells</part></link><space/>to Elsie</italics>, shows a fairy either hovering or tiptoeing on a branch, and offering Elsie a flower. Two days later the girls took the last picture,<space/><italics>Fairies and Their Sun-Bath</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">102–3</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The plates were packed in cotton wool and returned to Gardner in London, who sent an &quot;ecstatic&quot; telegram to Doyle, by then in<space/><link><target>Melbourne</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">103</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Doyle wrote back:<template><target>quote/to right of image</target><arg name="My heart was gladdened when out here in far Australia I had your note and the three wonderful pictures which are confirmatory of our published results. When our fairies are admitted other psychic phenomena will find a more ready acceptance&nbsp;... We have had continued messages at seances for some time that a visible sign was coming through.{{sfnp|Magnusson|2006|p">103|ps</arg></template><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Publication and reaction</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CottingleyFairies4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>alt=Photo</part><part>The fourth photograph, ''Fairy Offering Posy of Harebells to Elsie''</part></link>Doyle's article in the December 1920 issue of<space/><italics>The Strand</italics><space/>contained two higher-resolution prints of the 1917 photographs, and sold out within days of publication. To protect the girls' anonymity, Frances and Elsie were called Alice and Iris respectively, and the Wright family was referred to as the &quot;Carpenters&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">388</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>An enthusiastic and committed spiritualist, Doyle hoped that if the photographs convinced the public of the existence of fairies then they might more readily accept other psychic phenomena.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Roden"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Roden<space/></arg><arg name="first">Barbara<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Coming of the Fairies: An Alternative View of the Episode of the Cottingley Fairies<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ash-tree.bc.ca/acdsfairies.htm<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Arthur Conan Doyle Society<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">25 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>He ended his article with the words:<template><target>quote/to right of image</target><arg name="The recognition of their existence will jolt the material twentieth century mind out of its heavy ruts in the mud, and will make it admit that there is a glamour and mystery to life. Having discovered this, the world will not find it so difficult to accept that spiritual message supported by physical facts which has already been put before it.<ref name">Roden/></arg></template>Early press coverage was &quot;mixed&quot;,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">390</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>generally a combination of &quot;embarrassment and puzzlement&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">391</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>The historical novelist and poet<space/><link><target>Maurice Hewlett</target></link><space/>published a series of articles in the literary journal<space/><italics>John O' London's Weekly</italics>, in which he concluded: &quot;And knowing children, and knowing that Sir Arthur Conan Doyle has legs, I decide that the Miss Carpenters have pulled one of them.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">390</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>The Sydney newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Truth (Sydney newspaper)</target><part>Truth</part></link></italics><space/>on 5 January 1921 expressed a similar view; &quot;For the true explanation of these fairy photographs what is wanted is not a knowledge of occult phenomena but a knowledge of children.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cooper"></extension><space/>Some public figures were more sympathetic.<space/><link><target>Margaret McMillan</target></link>, the educational and social reformer, wrote: &quot;How wonderful that to these dear children such a wonderful gift has been vouchsafed.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">390</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>The novelist<space/><link><target>Henry De Vere Stacpoole</target></link><space/>decided to take the fairy photographs and the girls at face value.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cooper"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Cooper<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joe</arg><arg name="title">Cottingley: At Last the Truth<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The Unexplained<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="issue">117<space/></arg><arg name="pages">2, 338–40<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In a letter to Gardner he wrote: &quot;Look at Alice's [Frances'] face. Look at Iris's [Elsie's] face. There is an extraordinary thing called Truth which has 10&amp;nbsp;million faces and forms&amp;nbsp; it is God's currency and the cleverest coiner or forger can't imitate it.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>John Hall-Edwards</target><part>Major John Hall-Edwards</part></link>, a keen photographer and pioneer of<space/><link><target>X-ray#Medical uses</target><part>medical X-ray treatments</part></link><space/>in Britain, was a particularly vigorous critic:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Major John Hall-Edwards<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.birmingham.gov.uk/xray<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Birmingham City Council<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg name="On the evidence I have no hesitation in saying that these photographs could have been "faked". I criticize the attitude of those who declared there is something supernatural in the circumstances attending to the taking of these pictures because, as a medical man, I believe that the inculcation of such absurd ideas into the minds of children will result in later life in manifestations and nervous disorder and mental disturbances.<ref name">Cooper/></arg></template>Doyle used the later photographs in 1921 to illustrate a second article in<space/><italics>The Strand</italics>, in which he described other accounts of fairy sightings. The article formed the foundation for his 1922 book<space/><italics>The Coming of the Fairies</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">389</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>As before, the photographs were received with mixed credulity. Sceptics noted that the fairies &quot;looked suspiciously like the traditional fairies of nursery tales&quot; and that they had &quot;very fashionable hairstyles&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cooper"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Gardner's final visit</heading><paragraph>Gardner made a final visit to Cottingley in August 1921. He again brought cameras and photographic plates for Frances and Elsie, but was accompanied by the clairvoyant<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Hodson</target></link>. Although neither of the girls claimed to see any fairies, and there were no more photographs, &quot;on the contrary, he [Hodson] saw them [fairies] everywhere&quot; and wrote voluminous notes on his observations.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">390</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By now Elsie and Frances were tired of the whole fairy business. Years later Elsie looked at a photograph of herself and Frances taken with Hodson and said: &quot;Look at that, fed up with fairies.&quot; Both Elsie and Frances later admitted that they &quot;played along&quot; with Hodson &quot;out of mischief&quot;,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">105</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>and that they considered him &quot;a fake&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">390</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Later investigations</heading><paragraph>Public interest in the Cottingley Fairies gradually subsided after 1921. Elsie and Frances eventually married and lived abroad for many years.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">393</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>In 1966, a reporter from the<space/><italics>Daily Express</italics><space/>newspaper traced Elsie, who was by then back in England. She admitted in an interview given that year that the fairies might have been &quot;figments of my imagination&quot;, but left open the possibility she believed that she had somehow managed to photograph her thoughts.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">104</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>The media subsequently became interested in Frances and Elsie's photographs once again.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cooper"></extension><space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>television's<space/><italics><link><target>Nationwide (TV series)</target><part>Nationwide</part></link></italics><space/>programme investigated the case in 1971, but Elsie stuck to her story: &quot;I've told you that they're photographs of figments of our imagination, and that's what I'm sticking to&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">104</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Elsie and Frances were interviewed by journalist<space/><link><target>Austin Mitchell</target></link><space/>in September 1976, for a programme broadcast on<space/><link><target>Yorkshire Television</target></link>. When pressed, both women agreed that &quot;a rational person doesn't see fairies&quot;, but they denied having fabricated the photographs.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">105</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>In 1978 the magician and<space/><link><target>scientific skepticism</target><part>scientific sceptic</part></link><space/><link><target>James Randi</target></link><space/>and a team from the<space/><link><target>Committee for the Scientific Investigation of Claims of the Paranormal</target></link><space/>examined the photographs, using a &quot;computer enhancement process&quot;. They concluded that the photographs were fakes, and that strings could be seen supporting the fairies.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="pp">394–5</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/><link><target>Geoffrey Crawley</target></link>, editor of the<space/><italics><link><target>British Journal of Photography</target></link></italics>, undertook a &quot;major scientific investigation of the photographs and the events surrounding them&quot;, published between 1982 and 1983, &quot;the first major postwar analysis of the affair&quot;. He also concluded that the pictures were fakes.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">395</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Confession</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Cottingley fairies illustration.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>alt=Three dancing figures</part><part>One of Claude Arthur Shepperson's illustrations of dancing girls, from ''Princess Mary's Gift Book''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1983, the cousins admitted in an article published in the magazine<space/><italics><link><target>The Unexplained (magazine)</target><part>The Unexplained</part></link></italics><space/>that the photographs had been faked, although both maintained that they really had seen fairies. Elsie had copied illustrations of dancing girls from a popular children's book of the time,<space/><italics>Princess Mary's Gift Book</italics>, published in 1914, and drew wings on them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="World of Strange Powers">[&quot;Fairies, Phantoms, and Fantastic Photographs&quot;. Presenter:<space/><link><target>Arthur C. Clarke</target></link>. Narrator:<space/><link><target>Anna Ford</target></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Arthur C. Clarke's World of Strange Powers</target></link></italics>.<space/><link><target>ITV (TV network)</target><part>ITV</part></link>. 22 May 1985. No. 6, season 1]</extension><space/>They said they had then cut out the cardboard figures and supported them with<space/><link><target>hatpin</target><trail>s</trail></link>, disposing of their props in the beck once the photograph had been taken.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">105</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>But the cousins disagreed about the fifth and final photograph, which Doyle in his<space/><italics>The Coming of the Fairies</italics><space/>described in this way:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="Seated on the upper left hand edge with wing well displayed is an undraped fairy apparently considering whether it is time to get up. An earlier riser of more mature age is seen on the right possessing abundant hair and wonderful wings. Her slightly denser body can be glimpsed within her fairy dress.{{sfnp|Doyle|2006|p">103|ps</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Cottingley-sunbath.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Photograph</part><part>''Fairies and Their Sun-Bath'', the fifth and last photograph of the Cottingley Fairies</part></link><link><target>File:CottingleyFairies-PrincessMary2 gobeirne.png</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Comparison of Cottingley Fairies and illustrations from ''Princess Mary's Gift Book''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Elsie maintained it was a fake, just like all the others, but Frances insisted that it was genuine. In an interview given in the early 1980s Frances said:<template><target>quote/to right of image</target><arg name="It was a wet Saturday afternoon and we were just mooching about with our cameras and Elsie had nothing prepared. I saw these fairies building up in the grasses and just aimed the camera and took a photograph.<ref name">Cooper/></arg></template>Both Frances and Elsie claimed to have taken the fifth photograph.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Hewson<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="title">Secrets of Two Famous Hoaxers<space/></arg><arg name="date">4 April 1983<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">The Times<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://archive.timesonline.co.uk/tol/viewArticle.arc?articleId</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In a letter published in<space/><italics><link><target>The Times</target></link></italics><space/>newspaper on 9 April 1983, Geoffrey Crawley explained the discrepancy by suggesting that the photograph was &quot;an unintended double exposure of fairy cutouts in the grass&quot;, and thus &quot;both ladies can be quite sincere in believing that they each took it&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crawley"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Crawley<space/></arg><arg name="first">Geoffrey<space/></arg><arg name="title">More to Discover about Fairies<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://infotrac.galegroup.com/itw/infomark/643/561/106140179w16/purl</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template><space/><template><target>subscription required</target></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a 1985 interview on<space/><link><target>Yorkshire Television</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Arthur C. Clarke's World of Strange Powers</target></link></italics>, Elsie said that she and Frances were too embarrassed to admit the truth after fooling Doyle, the author of<space/><link><target>Sherlock Holmes</target></link>: &quot;Two village kids and a brilliant man like Conan Doyle&amp;nbsp; well, we could only keep quiet.&quot; In the same interview Frances said: &quot;I never even thought of it as being a fraud&amp;nbsp; it was just Elsie and I having a bit of fun and I can't understand to this day why they were taken in&amp;nbsp; they wanted to be taken in.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="World of Strange Powers"></extension><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Subsequent history</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:FrancesGriffithsandElsieWright.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright=0.5</part><part>Frances Griffiths and Elsie Wright, June 1917</part></link>Frances died in 1986, and Elsie in 1988.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Magnusson</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">105</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template><space/>Prints of their photographs of the fairies, along with a few other items including a first edition of Doyle's book<space/><italics>The Coming of the Fairies</italics>, were sold at auction in London for 21,620 in 1998.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">'Fairy' fakes sell for fortune<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 July 1998<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/134243.stm<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 May 2007<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>That same year, Geoffrey Crawley sold his Cottingley Fairy material to the National Museum of Film, Photography and Television in Bradford (now the<space/><link><target>National Media Museum</target></link>), where it is on display. The collection included prints of the photographs, two of the cameras used by the girls, watercolours of fairies painted by Elsie, and a nine-page letter from Elsie admitting to the hoax.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Sorry, Mel – they're ours!<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Bradford Telegraph & Argus<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 April 1998<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.thetelegraphandargus.co.uk/archive/1998/04/16/Bradford+District+Archive/8078013.Sorry__Mel___they_re_ours_/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">25 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension>The glass photographic plates were bought for 6,000 by an unnamed buyer at a London auction held in 2001.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">'Fairy' pictures fetch £6,000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 March 2001<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/entertainment/1218778.stm<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 May 2007<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Frances' daughter, Christine Lynch, appeared in an episode of the television programme<space/><italics><link><target>Antiques Roadshow</target></link></italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Belfast</target></link>, broadcast on<space/><link><target>BBC One</target></link><space/>in January 2009, with the photographs and one of the cameras given to the girls by Doyle. Christine told the expert,<space/><link><target>Paul Atterbury</target></link>, that she believed, as her mother had done, that the fairies in the fifth photograph were genuine. Atterbury estimated the value of the items at between 25,000 and 30,000.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Antiques Roadshow</target></link></italics>. Presenter:<space/><link><target>Fiona Bruce</target></link>.<space/><link><target>BBC One</target></link>. 4 January 2009. No. 17, series 31</extension><space/>The first edition of Frances' memoirs was published a few months later, under the title<space/><italics>Reflections on the Cottingley Fairies</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Cursed by the Fairies<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.dailyexpress.co.uk/posts/view/100031<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 May 2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">express.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="mode">cs2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The book contains correspondence, sometimes &quot;bitter&quot;, between Elsie and Frances. In one letter, dated 1983, Frances wrote:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="I hated those photographs from the age of 16 when Mr Gardner presented me with a bunch of flowers and wanted me to sit on the platform [at a Theosophical Society meeting] with him. I realised what I was in for if I did not keep myself hidden.<ref>{{cite news |last">Clayton |first</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The 1997 films<space/><italics><link><target>FairyTale: A True Story</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Photographing Fairies</target></link></italics><space/>were inspired by the events surrounding the Cottingley Fairies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Klein<space/></arg><arg name="first">Andy<space/></arg><arg name="title">Fairy, Fairy, Quite Contrary<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Phoenix New Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 October 1997<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.phoenixnewtimes.com/1997-10-23/film/fairy-fairy-quite-contrary/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 April 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>The photographs were parodied in a 1994 book written by<space/><link><target>Terry Jones</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Brian Froud</target></link>,<space/><italics>Lady Cottington's Pressed Fairy Book</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Ansley</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">174</arg><arg name="ps"></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><bold>Notes</bold><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template><bold>Bibliography</bold><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Ansley<space/></arg><arg name="first">William H.<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">Little, Big Girl: The Influence of the Alice Books and Other Works of Lewis Carroll on John Crowley's Novel ''Little Big, or The Fairies' Parliament''<space/></arg><arg name="title">Snakes-Hands: The Fiction of John Crowley<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Turner<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Alice K.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Andre-Druissi<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cosmos Books<space/></arg><arg name="pages">165–203<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59224-051-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Doyle<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arthur Conan<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Coming of the Fairies<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1922<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Nebraska Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8032-6655-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Magnusson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Magnus<space/></arg><arg name="title">Fakers, Forgers & Phoneys<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Mainstream Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-84596-190-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Prashad<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sukhadev<space/></arg><arg name="title">World Famous Supernatural Mysteries<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pustak Mahal<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-81-223-0559-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Smith<space/></arg><arg name="first">Paul<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">The Cottingley Fairies: The End of a Legend<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Narváez<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Good People: New Fairylore Essays<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="pages">371–405<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The University Press of Kentucky<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8131-0939-8</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Losure<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Mary<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Fairy Ring or Elsie and Frances Fool the World<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Candlewick<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7636-5670-6<space/></arg><arg name="ref">none</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Griffiths<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Frances Mary<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Lynch<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Christine<space/></arg><arg name="title">Reflections on the Cottingley Fairies<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">JMJ Publications<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-899228-06-5<space/></arg><arg name="ref">none</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Cottingley fairies</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>The Coming of the Fairies</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/comingoffairies00doylrich'>''The Coming of the Fairies''</link>&amp;nbsp; scans of the original version of Sir Arthur Conan Doyle's book (1922)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.randi.org/uploads/3/7/3/7/37377621/jref13edmod_fairies_teacher_print.pdf'>The Case of the Cottingley Fairies</link><space/>at The James Randi Educational Foundation</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cottingley.net/fairies.shtml'>Cottingley Fairies</link><space/>at Cottingley.Net&amp;nbsp; The Cottingley Network</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cottingleyconnect.org.uk/fairies.htm'>Cottingley Fairies</link><space/>at Cottingley Connect</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Fairies</target></template><template><target>featured article</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cottingley Fairies</target></template><link><target>Category:Bradford</target></link><link><target>Category:Fairies</target></link><link><target>Category:Paranormal hoaxes</target></link><link><target>Category:Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link><link><target>Category:Forteana</target></link><link><target>Category:Hoaxes in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Black-and-white photographs</target></link><link><target>Category:Photography in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Works originally published in The Strand Magazine</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century hoaxes</target></link></paragraph></article>