<article title='Existence'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>other uses</target><arg>Exist (disambiguation){{!}}Exist</arg></template><template><target>Multiple issues</target><arg name="{{Inadequate lead|date">March 2012}}{{Refimprove|date</arg></template><template><target>Philosophy sidebar</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Existence</bold><space/>is commonly held to be that which objectively persists independent of one's presence.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Ontology</target></link><space/>is the philosophical study of the nature of<space/><link><target>being</target></link>, existence or<space/><link><target>reality</target></link><space/>in general, as well as of the basic<space/><link><target>category of being</target><part>categories of being</part></link><space/>and their relations. Traditionally listed as a part of the major branch of philosophy known as<space/><link><target>metaphysics</target></link>, ontology deals with questions concerning what<space/><link><target>Entity</target><part>entities</part></link><space/>exist or can be said to exist, (for instance:<space/><italics>&quot;Does the stellar structure<space/><link><target>UDFj-39546284</target></link><space/>exist?&quot;</italics>), and how such entities can be grouped, related within a<space/><link><target>hierarchy</target></link>, and subdivided according to similarities and differences. A lively debate continues about the<space/><link><target>existence of God</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Epistemology</target></link><space/>studies<space/><link><target>criteria of truth</target></link>, defining &quot;primary truths&quot; inherently accepted in the investigation of knowledge. The first is existence. It is inherent in every analysis. It is<space/><link><target>self-evidence</target><part>self-evident</part></link>,<space/><link><target>A priori and a posteriori</target><part>a priori</part></link><space/>nature cannot be consistently doubted, since a person objecting to existence according to some standard of proof must implicitly accept the standard's existence as a premise.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dolhenty"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://web.archive.org/web/20080316075408/http://www.radicalacademy.com/epistom.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Part Thirteen: The Criterion of Truth<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-10-31<space/></arg><arg name="last">Dolhenty<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>The Problem of Knowledge: A brief introduction to epistemology</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Materialism</target></link><space/>holds that the only thing that exists is<space/><link><target>matter</target></link>, that all things are composed of material, and all phenomena (including<space/><link><target>consciousness</target></link>) are the result of material interactions.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Life</target></link><space/>is a characteristic that distinguishes<space/><link><target>Object (philosophy)</target><part>object</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that have self-sustaining<space/><link><target>biological process</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>from those that do not<extension extension_name='ref' name="Koshland"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Seven Pillars of Life</arg><arg name="journal">Science</arg><arg name="date">2002</arg><arg name="first">Daniel E.</arg><arg name="last">Koshland Jr</arg><arg name="pmid">11910092</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>295</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5563</arg><arg name="pages">2215–2216</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1126/science.1068489</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="AHDLife"><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>American Heritage Dictionary</target></link><space/>of the English Language, 4th edition, published by Houghton Mifflin Company, via<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.answers.com/topic/life'>Answers.com</link>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;The property or quality that distinguishes living organisms from dead organisms and inanimate matter, manifested in functions such as metabolism, growth, reproduction, and response to stimuli or adaptation to the<space/><link><target>Environment (biophysical)</target><part>environment</part></link><space/>originating from within the organism.&quot;</listitem><listitem>&quot;The characteristic state or condition of a living organism.&quot;</listitem></list></extension>either because such functions have ceased (<link><target>death</target></link>), or else because they lack such functions and are classified as &quot;<link><target>wiktionary:inanimate</target><part>inanimate</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://wordnetweb.princeton.edu/perl/webwn?s=inanimate'>Definition of ''inanimate''.</link><space/>WordNet Search by Princeton University.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The word &quot;existence&quot; comes from the<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>word<space/><italics>exsistere</italics><space/>meaning &quot;to appear&quot;, &quot;to arise&quot;, &quot;to become&quot;, or &quot;to be&quot;, but literally, it means &quot;to stand out&quot; (<italics>ex-</italics><space/>being the Latin prefix for &quot;out&quot; added to the causative of the verb<space/><italics>stare</italics>, meaning &quot;to stand&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>OEtymD</target><arg>existence</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical conceptions</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Avicennism</arg><arg>Scholasticism</arg></template>In the<space/><link><target>Western world</target><part>Western</part></link><space/>tradition of philosophy, the earliest known comprehensive treatments of the subject are from<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Phaedo</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Republic (Plato)</target><part>Republic</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Statesman (dialogue)</target><part>Statesman</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Metaphysics (Aristotle)</target><part>Metaphysics</part></link></italics>, though earlier fragmentary writing exists. Aristotle developed a comprehensive theory of being, according to which only individual things, called substances, fully have being, but other things such as relations, quantity, time, and place (called the<space/><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>categories</part></link>) have a derivative kind of being, dependent on individual things. In Aristotle's<space/><italics>Metaphysics</italics>, there are<space/><link><target>four causes</target></link><space/>of existence or change in nature: the material cause, the formal cause, the efficient cause, and the final cause.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Neo-Platonist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and some early<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/>philosophers argued about whether existence had any reality except in the mind of God. Some taught that existence was a snare and a delusion, that the world, the flesh, and the devil existed only to tempt weak humankind away from God.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Medieval philosophy</target><part>medieval philosopher</part></link><space/><link><target>Thomas Aquinas</target></link><space/>argued that God is pure being, and that in God<space/><link><target>essence</target></link><space/>and existence are the same.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Marenbon</arg><arg name="first"><space/>John</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Medieval Philosophy: An Historical and Philosophical Introduction</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="series"><space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006</arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>239</arg><arg name="language"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781134461837</arg><arg name="mr"><space/></arg><arg name="zbl"><space/></arg><arg name="jfm"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>At about the same time, the<space/><link><target>nominalist</target></link><space/>philosopher<space/><link><target>William of Ockham</target></link><space/>argued, in Book I of his<space/><italics><link><target>Sum of Logic</target><part>Summa Totius Logicae</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>Treatise on all Logic</italics>, written some time before 1327), that Categories are not a form of Being in their own right, but derivative on the existence of individuals.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early modern philosophy</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Early modern Europe</target><part>early modern</part></link><space/>treatment of the subject derives from<space/><link><target>Antoine Arnauld</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pierre Nicole</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Logic</italics>, or<space/><italics>The Art of Thinking</italics>, better known as the<space/><italics><link><target>Port-Royal Logic</target></link></italics>, first published in 1662. Arnauld thought that a<space/><link><target>proposition</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Decision making</target><part>judgment</part></link><space/>consists of taking two different ideas and either putting them together or rejecting them:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">After conceiving things by our ideas, we compare these ideas and, finding that some belong together and others do not, we unite or separate them. This is called affirming or denying, and in general judging.

This judgment is also called a proposition, and it is easy to see that it must have two terms. One term, of which one affirms or denies something, is called the [[subject (philosophy)|subject]]; the other term, which is affirmed or denied, is called the attribute or [[predicate (logic)|Praedicatum]].</arg><arg name="sign">Antoine Arnauld</arg><arg name="source">''The Art of Thinking'' (''[[Port-Royal Logic]]''),(1662) (translated J. Buroker 1996), Logic, II.3, page 82</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The two terms are joined by the verb &quot;is&quot; (or &quot;is not&quot;, if the predicate is denied of the subject). Thus every proposition has three components: the two terms, and the &quot;<link><target>Copula (linguistics)</target><part>copula</part></link>&quot; that connects or separates them. Even when the proposition has only two words, the three terms are still there. For example, &quot;God loves humanity&quot;, really means &quot;God is a lover of humanity&quot;, &quot;God exists&quot; means &quot;God is a thing&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>This theory of judgment dominated logic for centuries, but it has some obvious difficulties: it only considers proposition of the form &quot;All A are B.&quot;, a form logicians call<space/><link><target>universal quantifier</target><part>universal</part></link>. It does not allow propositions of the form &quot;Some A are B&quot;, a form logicians call<space/><link><target>existential quantifier</target><part>existential</part></link>. If neither A nor B includes the idea of existence, then &quot;some A are B&quot; simply adjoins A to B. Conversely, if A or B do include the idea of existence in the way that &quot;triangle&quot; contains the idea &quot;three angles equal to two right angles&quot;, then &quot;A exists&quot; is automatically true, and we have an<space/><link><target>ontological proof</target></link><space/>of A's existence. (Indeed, Arnauld's contemporary<space/><link><target>Descartes</target></link><space/>famously argued so, regarding the concept &quot;God&quot; (discourse 4, Meditation 5)). Arnauld's theory was current until the middle of the nineteenth century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>argued that the claim that a thing exists, when added to our notion of a thing, does not add anything to the concept. For example, if we form a complete notion of Moses, and superadd to that notion the claim that Moses existed, we are not adding anything to the notion of Moses.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link><space/>also argued that existence is not a &quot;real&quot; predicate, but gave no explanation of how this is possible. Indeed, his famous discussion of the subject is merely a restatement of Arnauld's doctrine that in the proposition &quot;God is omnipotent&quot;, the verb &quot;is&quot; signifies the joining or separating of two concepts such as &quot;God&quot; and &quot;omnipotence&quot;.<template><target>Or</target><arg name="date">January 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target><part>Schopenhauer</part></link><space/>claimed that everything that exists for knowledge, and hence the whole of this world, is only object in relation to the subject, perception of the perceiver, in a word, representation.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The World as Will and Representation</italics>, vol. I, 1</extension><space/>According to him there can be &quot;No object without subject&quot; because &quot;everything objective is already conditioned as such in manifold ways by the knowing subject with the forms of its knowing, and presupposes these forms&amp;hellip;&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"><italics>The World as Will and Representation</italics>, vol. I, 7</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Predicative nature</heading><paragraph><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target></link><space/>(and also Kant's pupil<space/><link><target>Johann Friedrich Herbart</target><part>Herbart</part></link>) argued that the predicative nature of existence was proved by sentences like &quot;A centaur is a poetic fiction&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>A System of Logic</target></link></italics>, 1843 I. iv. 1.page 124</extension><space/>or &quot;A greatest number is impossible&quot; (Herbart).<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Uberweg</italics><space/>(System of Logic) 68</extension><space/><link><target>Franz Brentano</target></link><space/>challenged this; so also (as is better known) did<space/><link><target>Gottlob Frege</target><part>Frege</part></link>. Brentano argued that we can join the concept represented by a noun phrase &quot;an A&quot; to the concept represented by an adjective &quot;B&quot; to give the concept represented by the noun phrase &quot;a B-A&quot;. For example, we can join &quot;a man&quot; to &quot;wise&quot; to give &quot;a wise man&quot;. But the noun phrase &quot;a wise man&quot; is not a sentence, whereas &quot;some man is wise&quot; is a sentence. Hence the copula must do more than merely join or separate concepts. Furthermore, adding &quot;exists&quot; to &quot;a wise man&quot;, to give the complete sentence &quot;a wise man exists&quot; has the same effect as joining &quot;some man&quot; to &quot;wise&quot; using the copula. So the copula has the same effect as &quot;exists&quot;. Brentano argued that every categorical proposition can be translated into an existential one without change in meaning and that the &quot;exists&quot; and &quot;does not exist&quot; of the existential proposition take the place of the copula. He showed this by the following examples:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The categorical proposition &quot;Some man is sick&quot; has the same meaning as the existential proposition &quot;A sick man exists&quot; or &quot;There is a sick man&quot;.</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>The categorical proposition &quot;No stone is living&quot; has the same meaning as the existential proposition &quot;A living stone does not exist&quot; or &quot;there is no living stone&quot;.</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>The categorical proposition &quot;All men are mortal&quot; has the same meaning as the existential proposition &quot;An immortal man does not exist&quot; or &quot;there is no immortal man&quot;.</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>The categorical proposition &quot;Some man is not learned&quot; has the same meaning as the existential proposition &quot;A non-learned man exists&quot; or &quot;there is a non-learned man&quot;.</listitem></list><paragraph>Frege developed a similar view (though later) in his great work<space/><italics><link><target>The Foundations of Arithmetic</target></link></italics>, as did<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target></link><space/>(but Peirce held that<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce#Philosophy: metaphysics</target><part>the possible and the real are not limited to the actually, individually existent</part></link>). The Frege-Brentano view is the basis of the dominant position in<space/><link><target>Analytic philosophy</target><part>modern Anglo-American philosophy</part></link>: that existence is asserted by the existential quantifier (as expressed by<space/><link><target>Willard Van Orman Quine</target><part>Quine</part></link>'s slogan &quot;To be is to be the value of a variable.&quot;<space/><italics>On What There Is</italics>, 1948).<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>On What There Is</italics><space/>in Review of Metaphysics (1948). Reprinted in<space/><link><target>Willard Van Orman Quine</target><part>W.V.O. Quine</part></link>,<space/><italics>From a Logical Point of View</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press, 1953)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Semantics</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>mathematical logic</target></link>, there are two quantifiers, &quot;some&quot; and &quot;all&quot;, though as<space/><link><target>Franz Brentano</target><part>Brentano</part></link><space/>(18381917) pointed out, we can make do with just one quantifier and negation. The first of these quantifiers, &quot;some&quot;, is also expressed as &quot;there exists&quot;. Thus, in the sentence &quot;There exists a man&quot;, the term &quot;man&quot; is asserted to be part of existence. But we can also assert, &quot;There exists a triangle.&quot; Is a &quot;triangle&quot; an abstract idea part of existence in the same way that a &quot;man&quot; a physical body is part of existence? Do abstractions such as goodness, blindness, and virtue exist in the same sense that chairs, tables, and houses exist? What<space/><link><target>Categories (Aristotle)</target><part>categories</part></link>, or kinds of thing, can be the subject or the predicate of a proposition?</paragraph><paragraph>Worse, does &quot;existence&quot; exist?<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>To exist is to have a specific relation to existence a relation, by the way, which existence itself does not have</italics>.<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link><space/><italics>The Principles of Mathematics</italics><space/>New York, W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1903, second edition 1937 pages 449450.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In some statements, existence is implied without being mentioned. The statement &quot;A bridge crosses the Thames at Hammersmith&quot; cannot just be about a bridge, the Thames, and Hammersmith. It must be about &quot;existence&quot; as well. On the other hand, the statement &quot;A bridge crosses the Styx at Limbo&quot; has the same form, but while in the first case we understand a real bridge in the real world made of stone or brick, what &quot;existence&quot; would mean in the second case is less clear.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>nominalist</target></link><space/>approach is to argue that certain noun phrases can be &quot;eliminated&quot; by rewriting a sentence in a form that has the same meaning, but does not contain the noun phrase. Thus<space/><link><target>William of Ockham</target><part>Ockham</part></link><space/>argued that &quot;Socrates has wisdom&quot;, which apparently asserts the existence of a reference for &quot;wisdom&quot;, can be rewritten as &quot;Socrates is wise&quot;, which contains only the referring phrase &quot;Socrates&quot;. This method became widely accepted in the twentieth century by the<space/><link><target>Analytic philosophy</target><part>analytic school</part></link><space/>of philosophy.</paragraph><paragraph>However, this argument may be inverted by<space/><link><target>Philosophical realism</target><part>realists</part></link><space/>in arguing that since the sentence &quot;Socrates is wise&quot; can be rewritten as &quot;Socrates has wisdom&quot;, this proves the existence of a hidden referent for &quot;wise&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>A further problem is that human beings seem to process information about<space/><link><target>Character (arts)</target><part>fictional characters</part></link><space/>in much the same way that they process information about real people. For example, in the 2008 United States presidential election, a politician and actor named<space/><link><target>Fred Thompson</target></link><space/>ran for the<space/><link><target>Republican Party (United States)</target><part>Republican Party</part></link><space/>nomination. In polls, potential voters identified Fred Thompson as a &quot;law and order&quot; candidate. Thompson plays a fictional character on the television series<space/><italics><link><target>Law &amp; Order franchise</target><part>Law and Order</part></link></italics>. Doubtless the people who make the comment are aware that<space/><italics>Law and Order</italics><space/>is fiction, but at some level, they process fiction as if it were fact.<template><target>Dubious</target><arg name="date">August 2009</arg></template><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2009</arg></template><space/>Another example of this is the common experience of actresses who play the villain in a soap opera being accosted in public as if they are to blame for the actions of the characters they play.</paragraph><paragraph>A scientist might make a clear distinction about objects that exist, and assert that all objects that exist are made up of either matter or energy. But in the layperson's<space/><link><target>worldview</target></link>, existence includes real, fictional, and even contradictory objects. Thus if we reason from the statement &quot;<link><target>Pegasus</target></link><space/>flies&quot; to the statement &quot;Pegasus exists&quot;, we are not asserting that Pegasus is made up of atoms, but rather that Pegasus exists in a particular worldview, the worldview of classical myth. When a mathematician reasons from the statement &quot;ABC is a triangle&quot; to the statement &quot;triangles exist&quot;, she is not asserting that triangles are made up of atoms but rather that triangles exist within a particular<space/><link><target>mathematical model</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern approaches</heading><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Theory of Descriptions</target></link>, the negation operator in a singular sentence can take either wide or narrow scope: we distinguish between &quot;some S is not P&quot; (where negation takes &quot;narrow scope&quot;) and &quot;it is not the case that 'some S is P'&quot; (where negation takes &quot;wide scope&quot;). The problem with this view is that there appears to be no such scope distinction in the case of proper names. The sentences &quot;Socrates is not bald&quot; and &quot;it is not the case that Socrates is bald&quot; both appear to have the same meaning, and they both appear to assert or presuppose the existence of someone (Socrates) who is not bald, so that negation takes narrow scope. However, Russell's theory analyses proper names into a logical structure which makes sense of this problem. According to Russell, Socrates can be analysed into the form 'The Philosopher of Greece.' In the wide scope this would then read: It is not the case that there existed a philosopher of Greece who was bald. In the narrow scope it would read the Philosopher of Greece was not bald.</paragraph><paragraph>According to the<space/><link><target>Direct reference</target><part>direct-reference</part></link><space/>view, an early version of which was originally proposed by<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link>, and perhaps earlier by<space/><link><target>Gottlob Frege</target></link>, a proper name strictly has no meaning when there is no object to which it refers. This view relies on the argument that the semantic function of a proper name is to tell us<space/><italics>which</italics><space/>object bears the name, and thus to identify some object. But no object can be identified if none exists. Thus, a proper name must have a bearer if it is to be meaningful.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Existence in the wide and narrow senses</heading><paragraph>According to the &quot;two sense&quot; view of existence, which derives from<space/><link><target>Alexius Meinong</target></link>, existential statements fall into two classes.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Those asserting existence in a<space/><italics>wide</italics><space/>sense. These are typically of the form &quot;N is P&quot; for singular N, or &quot;some S is P&quot;.</listitem><listitem>Those asserting existence in a<space/><italics>narrow</italics><space/>sense. These are typically of the form &quot;N exists&quot; or &quot;Ss exist&quot;.</listitem></list><paragraph>The problem is then evaded as follows. &quot;Pegasus flies&quot; implies existence in the wide sense, for it implies that<space/><italics>something</italics><space/>flies. But it does not imply existence in the narrow sense, for we deny existence in this sense by saying that Pegasus does not exist. In effect, the world of all things divides, on this view, into those (like<space/><link><target>Socrates</target></link>, the planet<space/><link><target>Venus</target></link>, and New York City) that have existence in the narrow sense, and those (like<space/><link><target>Sherlock Holmes</target></link>, the goddess<space/><link><target>Venus (mythology)</target><part>Venus</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Minas Tirith</target></link>) that do not.</paragraph><paragraph>However, common sense suggests the non-existence of such things as<space/><link><target>Character (arts)</target><part>fictional characters</part></link><space/>or places.</paragraph><heading level='3'>European views</heading><paragraph>Influenced by the views of Brentano's pupil<space/><link><target>Alexius Meinong</target></link>, and by<space/><link><target>Edmund Husserl</target></link>, Germanophone and Francophone philosophy took a different direction regarding the question of existence.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Anti-realist arguments</heading><paragraph><link><target>Anti-realism</target></link><space/>is the view of idealists who are skeptics about the physical world, maintaining either: 1) that nothing exists outside the<space/><link><target>mind</target></link>, or 2) that we would have no access to a mind-independent reality even if it may exist. Realists, in contrast, hold that perceptions or<space/><link><target>sense data</target></link><space/>are caused by mind-independent objects. An &quot;anti-realist&quot; who denies that other minds exist (i. e., a<space/><link><target>solipsist</target></link>) is different from an &quot;anti-realist&quot; who claims that there is no fact of the matter as to whether or not there are unobservable other minds (i. e., a logical<space/><link><target>behaviorist</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dharmic &quot;middle way&quot; view</heading><paragraph>The Indian philosopher<space/><link><target>Nagarjuna#Philosophy</target><part>Nagarjuna</part></link><space/>(c. 150 250 CE) largely advanced existence concepts and founded the<space/><link><target>Madhyamaka</target></link><space/>school of<space/><link><target>Mahyna</target></link><space/>Buddhism.</paragraph><paragraph>In eastern philosophy,<space/><link><target>Anicca</target></link><space/>(Sanskrit<space/><italics>anitya</italics>) or &quot;<link><target>impermanence</target></link>&quot; describes existence. It refers to the fact that all conditioned things (<link><target>sankhara</target></link>) are in a constant state of flux. In reality there is no thing that ultimately ceases to exist; only the appearance of a thing ceases as it changes from one form to another. Imagine a leaf that falls to the ground and decomposes. While the appearance and relative existence of the leaf ceases, the components that formed the leaf become particulate material that goes on to form new plants. Buddhism teaches a middle way, avoiding the extreme views of<space/><link><target>eternalism (philosophy of time)</target><part>eternalism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>nihilism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.accesstoinsight.org/lib/authors/various/wheel186.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Three Basic Facts of Existence<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-07-14</arg><arg name="last">The Buddhist Publication Society<space/></arg><arg name="quote">(ref.1) Change or impermanence is the essential characteristic of all phenomenal existence. We cannot say of anything, animate or inanimate, organic or inorganic, "this is lasting"; for even while we are saying this, it would be undergoing change. All is fleeting; the beauty of flowers, the bird's melody, the bee's hum, and a sunset's glory.</arg></template></extension><space/>The middle way recognizes there are vast differences between the way things are perceived to exist and the way things really exist. The differences are reconciled in the concept of<space/><link><target>Shunyata</target></link><space/>by addressing the existing object's served purpose for the subject's identity in being. What exists is in non-existence, because the subject changes.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Trailokya</target></link><space/>elaborates on three kinds of existence, those of desire, form, and formlessness in which there are karmic rebirths. Taken further to the<space/><link><target>Trikaya</target></link><space/>doctrine, it describes how the Buddha exists. In this philosophy, it is accepted that the Buddha exists in more than one absolute way.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Being</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Cogito ergo sum</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conservation law (physics)</target><part>Conservation law</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cosmogony</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cosmological argument</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Existence precedes essence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Existence theorem</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Existentialism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Existential operator</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gdel's ontological proof</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gaunilo of Marmoutiers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Identity and change</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Meaning of life (philosophy)</target><part>Meaning of life</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Performative contradiction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Right to exist</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Solipsism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Three marks of existence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Personal experience</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Antoine Arnauld</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pierre Nicole</target></link><space/><italics>Logic, or the Art of Thinking</italics>, (known as the<space/><italics><link><target>Port-Royal Logic</target></link></italics>), translated J. Buroker, Cambridge 1996</listitem><listitem><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target><part>Mill, J.S.</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>A System of Logic</target></link></italics>, 8th edition 1908</listitem><listitem>Loux, M.,<space/><italics>Ockham's Theory Of Terms</italics><space/>(translation of book I of the<space/><italics>Summa Logicae</italics><space/>c-1327).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Plato</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Republic</italics>, translated by Desmond Lee, Penguin Classics, 2003, ISBN 0-14-044914-0, ISBN 978-0-14-044914-3</listitem><listitem><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Metaphysics</italics>, translated by Hugh Lawson-Tancred, Penguin Classics, 1999, ISBN 0-14-044619-2, ISBN 978-0-14-044619-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Heraclitus</target></link>,<space/><italics>Fragments</italics>, James Hilton, forward, Brooks Hexton, translator, Penguin Classics, 2003, ISBN 0-14-243765-4, ISBN 978-0-14-243765-0.</listitem><listitem>Thalheimer, Alvin.,<space/><italics>The Meaning of the Terms: Existence and Reality.</italics><space/>Princeton University Press, 1920.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Meaning of Life</italics>,<space/><link><target>Terry Eagleton</target></link>, Oxford University Press, 2007, ISBN 0-19-921070-5 ISBN 978-0-19-921070-1</listitem><listitem><italics>The Story of Philosophy</italics>,<space/><link><target>Bryan Magee</target></link>, Dorling Kindersley Lond. 1998, ISBN 0-7513-0590-1</listitem><listitem><italics>What is Existence?</italics>, C.J.F. Williams, Oxford University Press, 1981</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>existence</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>existence</arg><arg>Existence</arg><arg>Michael Nelson</arg><arg>2012-10-11</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ontology.co/existence.htm'>The Concept of Existence: History and Definitions from Leading Philosophers</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wdl.org/en/item/2983'>&quot;A Treatise on Book Titles&quot;</link><space/>is a work by<space/><link><target>Sayf al-Din al-Amidi</target></link>, in Arabic, about &quot;original&quot; and &quot;mental existence&quot;. It dates from 1805.</listitem></list><paragraph><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template><template><target>metaphysics</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>Category:Ontology</target></link></preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>Category:Concepts in metaphysics</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of life</target></link><link><target>Category:Reality</target></link></paragraph></article>