<article title='Congregationalist_polity'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the form of church organization in which each congregation governs itself</arg><arg>the family of Protestant churches characterized by and named for this form of governance</arg><arg>Congregational church</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Congregationalism (disambiguation)</arg></template><bold>Congregationalist polity</bold>, often known as<space/><bold>congregationalism,</bold><space/>is a system of<space/><link><target>Ecclesiastical polity</target><part>church governance</part></link><space/>in which every<space/><link><target>local church</target></link><space/>congregation is independent,<space/><link><target>Ecclesiastical polity</target><part>ecclesiastically</part></link><space/><link><target>Sovereignty</target><part>sovereign</part></link>, or &quot;<link><target>autonomy</target><part>autonomous</part></link>&quot;. Among those major<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target><part>Protestant</part></link><space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/>traditions that employ congregationalism are those<space/><link><target>Congregational Churches</target></link><space/>known by the &quot;Congregationalist&quot; name that descended from the<space/><link><target>Independent (religion)</target><part>Independent</part></link><space/>wing of the Anglo-American<space/><link><target>Puritan</target></link><space/>movement of the 17th century,<space/><link><target>Quakerism</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Baptists</target><part>Baptist</part></link><space/>churches, and most of the groups brought about by the<space/><link><target>Anabaptist</target></link><space/>movement in<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>that migrated to the U.S. in the late 18th century. More recent generations have witnessed also a growing number of<space/><link><target>Non-denominational Christianity</target><part>non-denominational</part></link><space/>churches, which are most often congregationalist in their governance. In<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>, congregationalism is distinguished most clearly from<space/><link><target>episcopal polity</target></link>, which is governance by a hierarchy of<space/><link><target>bishop</target><trail>s</trail></link>. But it is also distinct from<space/><link><target>presbyterian polity</target></link>, in which higher assemblies of congregational representatives can exercise considerable authority over individual congregations.</paragraph><paragraph>Congregationalism is not limited only to organization of Christian congregations; the principles of congregationalism have been inherited by the<space/><link><target>Unitarian Universalist Association</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Canadian Unitarian Council</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Jewish</target></link><space/><link><target>synagogue</target><trail>s</trail></link>, many<space/><link><target>Sikh</target></link><space/><link><target>Gurdwaras</target></link><space/>and most<space/><link><target>Islam</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/><link><target>mosque</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the U.S. operate under congregational government, with no hierarchies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Basic form</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;congregationalist polity&quot; describes a form of church governance that is based on the local congregation. Each local congregation is independent and self-supporting, governed by its own members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide">Carmen Renee Berry,<space/><italics>The Unauthorized Guide to Choosing a Church</italics>, Brazos Press, 2003, ISBN 1-58743-036-3</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>Some band into loose voluntary associations with other congregations that share similar beliefs (e.g., the<space/><link><target>Willow Creek Association</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>Others join &quot;conventions&quot;, such as the<space/><link><target>Southern Baptist Convention</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.</target><part>National Baptist Convention</part></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>American Baptist Churches USA</target></link><space/>(formerly the Northern Baptist Convention).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>In Quaker Congregationalism,<space/><link><target>monthly meetings</target></link>, which are the most basic unit of administration, may be organized into larger Quarterly meetings or<space/><link><target>Yearly Meetings</target></link>. Monthly, quarterly, or yearly meetings may also be associated with large &quot;umbrella&quot; associations such as<space/><link><target>Friends General Conference</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Friends United Meeting</target></link>. These conventions generally provide stronger ties between congregations, including some doctrinal direction and pooling of financial resources.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>Congregations that belong to associations and conventions are still independently governed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>Most<space/><link><target>Non-denominational Christianity</target><part>non-denominational churches</part></link><space/>are organized along congregationalist lines.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>Many do not see these voluntary associations as &quot;<link><target>Christian denomination</target><part>denominations</part></link>&quot;, because they &quot;believe that there is no church other than the local church, and denominations are in variance to Scripture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unauthorized Guide"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Congregational church</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Congregational church</arg></template><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template>The earmarks of Congregationalism can be traced back to the Pilgrim societies of the United States in the early 17th century. Congregationalism expressed the viewpoint that (1) every local church is a full realization in miniature of the<space/><link><target>One, Holy, Catholic, and Apostolic Church</target><part>entire Church</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Jesus Christ</target></link>; and (2) the Church, while on earth, besides the local church, can<space/><bold>only</bold><space/>be invisible and ideal. While other theories may insist on the truth of the former, the latter precept of congregationalism gives the entire theory a unique character among plans of church government. There is no other reference than the local congregation for the &quot;visible church&quot; in Congregationalism. And yet, the connection of all Christians is also asserted, albeit in a way that defenders of this view usually decline, often intentionally, to elaborate more clearly or consistently. This first, foundational principle by which congregationalism is guided results in confining it to operate with the consent of each gathering of believers.</paragraph><paragraph>Although &quot;congregational rule&quot; may seem to suggest that<space/><link><target>direct democracy</target><part>pure democracy</part></link><space/>reigns in congregational churches, this is seldom the case. It is granted, with few exceptions (namely in some Anabaptist churches), that<space/><link><target>God</target></link><space/>has given the government of the Church into the hands of an<space/><link><target>ordination</target><part>ordained</part></link><space/>ministry. What makes congregationalism unique is its system of checks and balances, which constrains the authority of the minister, the lay officers, and the members.</paragraph><paragraph>Most importantly, the boundaries of the powers of the ministers and church officers are set by clear and constant reminders of the freedoms guaranteed by the<space/><link><target>Gospel</target></link><space/>to the laity, collectively and individually. With that freedom comes the responsibility upon each member to govern himself or herself under Christ. This requires lay people to exercise great charity and patience in debating issues with one another and to seek the glory and service of God as the foremost consideration in all of their decisions.</paragraph><paragraph>The authority of all of the people, including the officers, is limited in the local congregation by a definition of union, or a covenant, by which the terms of their cooperation together are spelled out and agreed to. This might be something as minimal as a charter specifying a handful of<space/><link><target>doctrine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and behavioral expectations, or even a statement only guaranteeing specific freedoms. Or, it may be a<space/><link><target>constitution</target></link><space/>describing a comprehensive doctrinal system and specifying terms under which the local church is connected to other local churches, to which participating congregations give their assent. In congregationalism, rather uniquely, the church is understood to be a truly voluntary association.</paragraph><paragraph>Finally, the congregational theory strictly forbids ministers from ruling their local churches by themselves. Not only does the minister serve by the approval of the congregation, but committees further constrain the pastor from exercising power without consent by either the particular committee, or the entire congregation. It is a contradiction of the congregational principle if a minister makes decisions concerning the congregation without the vote of these other officers.</paragraph><paragraph>The other officers may be called &quot;deacons&quot;, &quot;elders&quot; or &quot;session&quot; (borrowing<space/><link><target>Presbyterianism</target><part>Presbyterian</part></link><space/>terminology), or even &quot;<link><target>vestry</target></link>&quot; (borrowing the<space/><link><target>Anglicanism</target><part>Anglican</part></link><space/>term) &amp;mdash; it is not their label that is important to the theory, but rather their lay status and their equal vote, together with the pastor, in deciding the issues of the church. While other forms of church government are more likely to define &quot;tyranny&quot; as &quot;the imposition of unjust rule&quot;, a congregationally governed church would more likely define tyranny as &quot;transgression of liberty&quot; or equivalently, &quot;rule by one man&quot;. To a congregationalist; no abuse of authority is worse than the concentration of all decisive power in the hands of one ruling body, or one person.</paragraph><paragraph>Following this sentiment, congregationalism has evolved over time to include even more participation of the congregation, more kinds of lay committees to whom various tasks are apportioned, and more decisions subject to the vote of the entire membership.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the most notable characteristics of New England (or British)-heritage Congregationalism has been its consistent leadership role in the formation of &quot;unions&quot; with other churches. Such sentiments especially grew strong in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, when ecumenism evolved out of a liberal, non-sectarian perspective on relations to other Christian groups that accompanied the relaxation of<space/><link><target>Calvinist</target></link><space/>stringencies held by earlier generations. The congregationalist theory of independence within a union has been a cornerstone of most ecumenical movements since the 18th century.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Baptist churches</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Baptists</arg></template><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">February 2010</arg></template>Most Baptists hold that no church or ecclesiastical organization has inherent authority over a Baptist church. Churches can properly relate to each other under this polity only through voluntary cooperation, never by any sort of coercion. Furthermore, this Baptist polity calls for freedom from governmental control.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Pinson, William M., Jr.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Trends in Baptist Polity<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Baptist History and Heritage Society<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.baptisthistory.org/contissues/pinson.htm</arg></template></extension>Exceptions to this local form of local governance include a few churches that submit to the leadership of a body of<space/><link><target>Elder (Christianity)#Baptists</target><part>elders</part></link>, as well as the<space/><link><target>Episcopal Baptist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that have an<space/><link><target>Episcopal polity</target><part>Episcopal system</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Independent Baptist</target></link><space/>churches have no formal organizational structure above the level of the local congregation. More generally among<space/><link><target>Baptists</target></link>, a variety of parachurch agencies and evangelical educational institutions may be supported generously or not at all, depending entirely upon the local congregation's customs and predilections. Usually doctrinal conformity is held as a first consideration when a church makes a decision to grant or decline financial contributions to such agencies, which are legally external and separate from the congregations they serve. These practices also find currency among non-denominational fundamentalist or<space/><link><target>Charismatic (Christians)</target><part>charismatic</part></link><space/>fellowships, many of which derive from Baptist origins, culturally if not theologically.</paragraph><paragraph>Most<space/><link><target>Southern Baptist Convention</target><part>Southern Baptist</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>National Baptist Convention, USA, Inc.</target><part>National Baptist</part></link><space/>congregations, by contrast, generally relate more closely to external groups such as mission agencies and educational institutions than do those of independent persuasion. However, they adhere to a very similar ecclesiology, refusing to permit outside control or oversight of local affairs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Churches of Christ</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Churches of Christ</arg></template>Church government is congregational rather than denominational. Churches of Christ purposefully have no central headquarters, councils, or other organizational structure above the local church level.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of Religion in the South">Samuel S. Hill, Charles H. Lippy, Charles Reagan Wilson,<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of Religion in the South</italics>,Mercer University Press, 2005, (ISBN 0-86554-758-0, ISBN 978-0-86554-758-2) 854 pages</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>214</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Perfect Stranger">Stuart M. Matlins, Arthur J. Magida, J. Magida,<space/><italics>How to Be a Perfect Stranger: A Guide to Etiquette in Other People's Religious Ceremonies</italics>, Wood Lake Publishing Inc., 1999, ISBN 1-896836-28-3, ISBN 978-1-896836-28-7, 426 pages, Chapter 6 - Churches of Christ</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>103</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Rhodes 2005">Ron Rhodes,<space/><italics>The Complete Guide to Christian Denominations</italics>, Harvest House Publishers, 2005, ISBN 0-7369-1289-4</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>124</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Churches of Christ from the beginning have maintained no formal organization structures larger than the local congregations and no official journals or vehicles declaring sanctioned positions. Consensus views do, however, often emerge through the influence of opinion leaders who express themselves in journals, at lectureships, or at area preacher meetings and other gatherings&quot; page 213, Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant,<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ</italics>,<space/><link><target>William B. Eerdmans Publishing Co.</target></link>, 2004, ISBN 0-8028-3898-7, ISBN 978-0-8028-3898-8, 854 pages</extension><space/>Rather, the independent congregations are a network with each congregation participating at its own discretion in various means of service and fellowship with other congregations (see<space/><link><target>Sponsoring church (Churches of Christ)</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rhodes 2005"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>124</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Who Are the churches of Christ"><link><target>Batsell Barrett Baxter</target></link>,<space/><italics>Who are the churches of Christ and what do they believe in?</italics><space/>Available on-line in an<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://woodsonchapel.com/coc.cfm</arg><arg name="date">20060616071601</arg></template>, and<space/><link type='external' href='http://church-of-christ.org/who.html'>here</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cris.com/~mmcoc/coc.html'>here</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.scripturessay.com/article.php?cat=&amp;amp;id=6'>here</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Churches of Christ adhere to a strict congregationalism that cooperates in various projects overseen by one congregation or organized as parachurch enterprises, but many congregations hold themselves apart from such cooperative projects.&quot; Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant,<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ</italics>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2004, page 206, entry on<space/><italics>Church, Doctrine of the</italics></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;It is nothing less than phenomenal that the Churches of Christ get so much done without any centralized planning or structure. Everything is<space/><italics>ad hoc</italics>. Most programs emerge from the inspiration and commitment of a single congregation or even a single person. Worthwhile projects survive and prosper by the voluntary cooperation of other individuals and congregations.&quot; Page 449, Leroy Garrett,<space/><italics>The Stone-Campbell Movement: The Story of the American Restoration Movement</italics>, College Press, 2002, ISBN 0-89900-909-3, ISBN 978-0-89900-909-4, 573 pages</extension><space/>Churches of Christ are linked by their shared commitment to restoration principles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Perfect Stranger"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>106</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Who Are the churches of Christ"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Congregations are generally overseen by a<space/><link><target>Plurality (church governance)</target><part>plurality</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Elder (religious)</target><part>elder</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(also known in some congregations as shepherds, bishops, or pastors) who are sometimes assisted in the administration of various works by<space/><link><target>deacon</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rhodes 2005"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>124</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Who Are the churches of Christ"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Howard 1971">V. E. Howard,<space/><italics>What Is the Church of Christ?</italics><space/>4th Edition (Revised) Central Printers &amp; Publishers, West Monroe, Louisiana, 1971</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>47,54–55</arg></template><space/>Elders are generally seen as responsible for the spiritual welfare of the congregation, while deacons are seen as responsible for the non-spiritual needs of the church.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Ministry"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>531</arg></template><space/>Deacons serve under the supervision of the elders, and are often assigned to direct specific ministries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Ministry"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>531</arg></template><space/>Successful service as a deacon is often seen as preparation for the eldership.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Ministry"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>531</arg></template><space/>Elders and deacons are chosen by the congregation based on the qualifications found in<space/><template><target>Bibleref</target><arg>1Timothy</arg><arg>3</arg><arg>I Timothy 3</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>Bibleref</target><arg>Titus</arg><arg>1</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Howard 1971"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>53,48–52</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferguson 1975"><link><target>Everett Ferguson</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.acu.edu/sponsored/restoration_quarterly/archives/1970s/vol_18_no_3_contents/Ferguson.html'>&quot;Authority and Tenure of Elders&quot;,</link><space/><italics><link><target>Restoration Quarterly</target></link></italics>, Vol. 18 No. 3 (1975): 142-150</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferguson 1996"><link><target>Everett Ferguson</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Church of Christ: A Biblical Ecclesiology for Today</italics>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 1996, ISBN 0-8028-4189-9, ISBN 978-0-8028-4189-6, 443 pages</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>323,335</arg></template><space/>Congregations look for elders who have a mature enough understanding of scripture to enable them to supervise the minister and to teach, as well as to perform &quot;governance&quot; functions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Elders">Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant,<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ</italics>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2004, ISBN 0-8028-3898-7, ISBN 978-0-8028-3898-8, 854 pages, entry on<space/><italics>Elders, Eldership</italics></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>298</arg></template><space/>In lieu of willing men who meet these qualifications, congregations are sometimes overseen by the congregation's men in general.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Where elderships do not exist, most congregations function through a 'business meeting' system that may include any member of the congregation or, in other cases, the men of the church.&quot; Page 531, Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant,<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ</italics>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2004, ISBN 0-8028-3898-7, ISBN 978-0-8028-3898-8, 854 pages, entry on<space/><italics>Ministry</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the early<space/><link><target>Restoration Movement</target></link><space/>had a tradition of itinerant<space/><link><target>preacher</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>rather than &quot;located Preachers&quot;, during the 20th century a long-term, formally trained congregational<space/><link><target>Minister (Christianity)</target><part>minister</part></link><space/>became the norm among Churches of Christ.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Ministry">Douglas Allen Foster and Anthony L. Dunnavant,<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Christian Church (Disciples of Christ), Christian Churches/Churches of Christ, Churches of Christ</italics>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, 2004, ISBN 0-8028-3898-7, ISBN 978-0-8028-3898-8, 854 pages, entry on<space/><italics>Ministry</italics></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>532</arg></template><space/>Ministers are understood to serve under the oversight of the elders.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Elders"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>298</arg></template><space/>While the presence of a long-term professional minister has sometimes created &quot;significant<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>ministerial authority&quot; and led to conflict between the minister and the elders, the eldership has remained the &quot;ultimate locus of authority in the congregation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement: Ministry"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>531</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Churches of Christ hold to the<space/><link><target>priesthood of all believers</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Roberts<space/></arg><arg name="first">Price<space/></arg><arg name="title">Studies for New Converts<space/></arg><arg name="place">Cincinnati<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Standard Publishing Company<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="pages">53–56</arg></template></extension><space/>No special titles are used for preachers or ministers that would identify them as &quot;<link><target>clergy</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Perfect Stranger"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>106</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wharton 1997">Edward C. Wharton,<space/><italics>The Church of Christ: The Distinctive Nature of the New Testament Church</italics>,<space/><link><target>Gospel Advocate</target></link><space/>Co., 1997, ISBN 0-89225-464-5</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>112–113</arg></template><space/>Churches of Christ emphasize that there is no distinction between &quot;clergy&quot; and &quot;<link><target>laity</target></link>&quot; and that every member has a gift and a role to play in accomplishing the work of the church.<extension extension_name='ref'>R. B. Sweet,<space/><italics>Now That I'm a Christian</italics>, Sweet Publishing, 1948 (revised 2003), ISBN 0-8344-0129-0</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>38–40</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Christianity</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United and uniting churches</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Wayne Grudem,<space/><italics>Electronic Systematic Theology: An Introduction to Biblical Doctrine</italics><space/>(Whitefish, MT: Bits &amp; Bytes Computer Resources, 2000)</listitem><listitem>Stanley M. Horton, ed.,<space/><italics>Systematic Theology, A Pentecostal Perspective</italics><space/>(rev. edn, Springfield, MO: Logion Press, 1994)</listitem><listitem>Byron D. Klaus,<space/><italics>Systematic Theology</italics>, ed. Stanley M. Horton (Springfield, MI: Logion P, 2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;56796</listitem><listitem>Michael L. Dusing,<space/><italics>Systematic Theology</italics>, ed. Stanley M. Horton (Springfield, MI: Logion P, 2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;52566</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Fiddes</target></link>,<space/><italics>A leading question: the structure and authority of leadership in the local church</italics><space/>(London: Baptist Publications, 1986)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul Fiddes</target></link>,<space/><italics>Tracks and traces: Baptist identity in church and theology</italics><space/>(Carlisle: Paternoster, 2003)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Church-polity</target></template><template><target>Unitarian, Universalist, and Unitarian Universalist topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Congregationalist Polity</target></template><link><target>Category:Congregationalism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:United Church of Christ</target></link><link><target>Category:Ecclesiology</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Unitarian Universalism</target></link></paragraph></article>