<article title='Abd-ar-Rahman_III'><paragraph><template><target>Other people2</target><arg>Abd-ar-Rahman (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="type"><space/>monarch
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Abd-ar-Rahman III
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Amir al-Mu'minin]]<ref name</arg><arg name="image"><space/>La civilització del califat de Còrdova en temps d'Abd-al-Rahman III.jpg
</arg><arg name="alt">
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Abd-ar-Rahman III and his court in [[Medina Azahara]], by [[Dionisio Baixeras Verdaguer]].
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>8th [[Emir]] of [[Caliphate of Córdoba|Córdoba]]
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>16 October 912 – 16 January 929
</arg><arg name="coronation"><space/>17 October 912 (aged {{age|891|01|07|912|10|17}})<ref>{{cite book |last</arg><arg name="cor-type"><space/>[[Bay'ah]]
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Abdullah ibn Muhammad al-Umawi|Abdullah]]
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>Himself as caliph
</arg><arg name="succession1"><space/>15th [[Caliph]] of [[Umayyad Dynasty]]<space/><br /><space/>1st [[Caliph]] of [[Caliphate of Córdoba|Córdoba]]
</arg><arg name="reign1"><space/>16 January 929 – 15 October 961
</arg><arg name="coronation1"><space/>16 January 929 (aged {{age|891|01|07|929|01|16}})<ref name</arg><arg name="cor-type1"><space/>[[#Assumption of the Caliphate|Proclamation]]
</arg><arg name="predecessor1"><space/>Himself as emir
</arg><arg name="successor1"><space/>[[Al-Hakam II]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>6,300 women<ref>{{cite book |last</arg><arg name="spouse-type"><space/>[[Harem]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>Sons in order of birth according to [[Ibn Hazm]]:<ref name</arg><arg name="full name"><space/>'''[[Kunya (Arabic)|Kunya:]]''' Abu al-Mutarrif<ref name</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[Umayyad Caliphate|Umayyad]] (Spanish branch)<br>[[List of Navarrese monarchs|House of Íñiguez]]
</arg><arg name="house-type"><space/>Dynasty
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>Muhammad ibn [[Abdullah ibn Muhammad al-Umawi|Abdullah]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>Muzna (originally Maria?)<ref name</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|891|01|07|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]]<ref>{{cite encyclopedia |editor-last</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|961|10|15|891|01|07|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Córdoba, Spain|Córdoba]]<ref name</arg><arg name="place of burial"><space/>[[Alcázar de los Reyes Cristianos|Alcázar of Córdoba]]<ref>{{cite book |last</arg><arg name="signature">
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Sunni Islam]] ([[Maliki]] [[Madh'hab|school]])<ref>{{cite book |last</arg></template><bold>Abd-ar-Rahman III</bold><space/>(<bold>Abd ar-Rahmn ibn Muhammad ibn Abd Allh ibn Muhammad ibn abd ar-Rahman ibn al-Hakam ar-Rabdi ibn Hisham ibn abd ar-Rahman ad-Dakhil</bold>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last"><space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/></arg><arg name="editor-link"><space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="title">'Abd ar-Rahman III<space/></arg><arg name="edition">15th<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.</arg><arg name="volume">I: A-Ak - Bayes</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Chicago, IL</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59339-837-8</arg><arg name="pages">17–18</arg></template></extension><space/><template><target>lang-ar</target><arg><big>عبد الرحمن الثالث</big></arg></template>; 11 January 889/91<extension extension_name='ref'>His date of birth is given as 891 in<space/><link><target>Chambers Biographical Dictionary</target></link>, ISBN 0-550-18022-2, page 2</extension><space/>15 October 961) was the<space/><link><target>Emir of Crdoba</target><part>Emir</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Caliph of Crdoba</target></link><space/>(912961) of the<space/><link><target>Ummayads</target><part>Ummayad</part></link><space/>dynasty in<space/><link><target>al-Andalus</target></link>. Called<space/><italics>al-Nasir li-Din Allah</italics><space/>(&quot;the Defender of God's Faith&quot;), he ascended the throne in his early 20s, and reigned for half a century as the most powerful prince of Iberia.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.saudiaramcoworld.com/issue/197605/the.golden.caliphate.htm'>The Golden Caliphate</link></extension><space/>Although people of all creeds enjoyed tolerance and<space/><link><target>freedom of religion</target></link><space/>under his rule, he repelled the<space/><link><target>Fatimid</target><trail>s</trail></link>, partly by supporting their<space/><link><target>Maghrawa</target></link><space/>enemies in<space/><link><target>North Africa</target></link>, and partly by claiming the title<space/><link><target>Caliph</target></link><space/>(ruler of the<space/><link><target>Muslim world</target><part>Islamic world</part></link>) for himself.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Life</heading><heading level='3'>Early years</heading><paragraph>Abd ar-Rahman was born in<space/><link><target>Crdoba, Spain</target><part>Crdoba</part></link>, the grandson of<space/><link><target>Abdallah ibn Muhammad</target><part>Abdullah</part></link>, seventh independent<space/><link><target>Umayyad</target></link><space/>emir of<space/><link><target>Al-Andalus</target></link>. His parents were Abdullah's son Muhammad and Muzna (or Muzayna), a Christian concubine.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bookrags.com/biography/abd-al-rahman-iii/'>Abd al-Rahman, III Biography</link></extension><space/>His paternal grandmother was also a Christian, the royal infanta<space/><link><target>Onneca Fortnez</target></link>, daughter of the captive king<space/><link><target>Fortn Garcs of Pamplona</target></link>. Abd ar-Rahman was thus nephew in the half-blood of queen<space/><link><target>Toda of Navarre</target></link>. He is described as having:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">.. white skin, blue eyes and attractive face; good looking, although somewhat sturdy and stout. His legs were short, to the point that the stirrups of his saddle were mounted just one palm under it. When mounted, he looked tall, but on his feet he was quite short. He dyed his beard black.<ref>[[Ibn Idhari]], ''Kitab al-Bayan''</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Muhammad was assassinated by his brother Al-Mutarrif, who had allegedly grown jealous of the favour Muhammad had gained in the eyes of their father Abdallah. Al-Mutarrif had accused Muhammad of plotting with the rebel<space/><link><target>Umar ibn Hafsun</target></link>, and Muhammad had been imprisoned. According to some sources, the emir himself was behind Muhammad's fall, as well as Al-Mutarrif's death in 895. Abd ar-Rahman spent his youth in his mother's harem. Al-Mutarrif's sister, known as<space/><italics>al-Sayyida</italics><space/>(&quot;the Lady&quot;), was entrusted with his education. She made sure that Abd ar-Rahman's education was conducted with some rigor.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Ibn Hazm</target></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Accession to throne</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template>Emir Abdallah died at the age of 72. Despite the fact that four of his sons (Aban, Abd al Rahman, Muhammad and Ahmad) were alive at the time of his death, all of them were passed over for succession. Abdallah instead chose as his successor his grandson, Abd al-Rahman III (the son of his first son). This came as no surprise, since Abdallah had already demonstrated his affection for his grandson in many ways, namely by allowing him to live in his own tower (something he did not allow for any of his sons), and allowing him to sit on the throne on some festive occasions. Most importantly Abdallah gave Abd al-Rahman his ring, the symbol of power, when Abdallah fell ill prior to his death. Abd al-Rahman succeeded Abdallah the day after his death, 16 October 912.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>Historiographers of the time, such as al-Bayan l'Mogrib and the<space/><italics>Cronica anonima de Abd-ar-Rahman III</italics>, state that his succession was &quot;without incident&quot;. At the time, Abd al-Rahman was about 21 or 22 years old. He inherited an emirate on the verge of dissolution, his power extending not far beyond the vicinity of Crdoba.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>To the north, the Christian<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Asturias</target></link><space/>was continuing its program of<space/><italics><link><target>Reconquista</target></link></italics><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Duero</target></link><space/>valley. To the south in Ifriqiya, the Fatimids had created an independent caliphate that threatened to attract the allegiance of the Muslim population, who had suffered under the harsh rule of Abdullah. On the internal front the discontented<space/><link><target>Muladi</target></link><space/>families (Muslims of Iberian origin) represented a constant danger for the Crdoban emir. The most powerful of the latter was Umar ibn Hafsun, who, from his impregnable fortress of<space/><link><target>Bobastro</target></link>, controlled much of eastern Al-Andalus.</paragraph><paragraph>From the very early stages of his reign, Abd ar-Rahman showed a firm resolve to quash the rebels of Al-Andalus, consolidate centralized power, and reestablish internal order within the emirate. Within 10 days of taking the throne, he exhibited the head of a rebel leader in Cordoba.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>From this point on he led annual expeditions against the northern and southern tribes to maintain control over them. To accomplish his aims he introduced into the court the<space/><italics><link><target>saqaliba</target><trail>h</trail></link></italics>, slaves of East European origin. The<space/><italics><link><target>saqaliba</target><trail>h</trail></link></italics><space/>represented a third ethnic group that could neutralize the endless strife between his subjects of Muslim<space/><link><target>Arab people</target><part>Arab</part></link><space/>heritage, and those of Muslim<space/><link><target>Berber people</target><part>Berber</part></link><space/>heritage.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early rule</heading><paragraph>During the first 20 years of his rule, Abd ar-Rahman avoided military action against the northern Christian kingdoms, Asturias and<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Navarre</target><part>Navarre</part></link>. The Muladi rebels were the first problem he confronted. Those powerful families were supported by Iberians who were openly or secretly Christians and had acted with the rebels. These elements, which formed the bulk of the population, were not averse to supporting a strong ruler who would protect them against the Arab aristocracy. Abd ar-Rahman moved to subdue them by means of a mercenary army that included Christians.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Mosque of Cordoba Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Great Mosque of Crdoba</target></link>.</part></link>He first had to suppress the rebel Umar ibn Hafsun. On 1 January 913 an army, led by the eunuch Badr, conquered the fortress of<space/><link><target>cija</target></link>, at some 50&amp;nbsp;km from the capital. All the city's fortifications were destroyed, aside from the citadel, which was left as residence of the governor and a garrison for the emiral troops. In the following spring, after sixty-five days of meticulous preparations, Abd ar-Rahman personally led an expedition to the south of his realm. His troops were able to recover the<space/><italics>coras</italics><space/>(provinces) of<space/><link><target>Jan (Spanish province)</target><part>Jan</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Granada</target><part>Elvira</part></link>, while a cavalry detachment was sent to free<space/><link><target>Mlaga</target></link><space/>from ibn Hafsun's siege. He also obtained the capitulation of<space/><link><target>Fiana</target></link><space/>(in the modern<space/><link><target>province of Almera</target></link>), after setting fire to its suburbs. Subsequently he moved against the castle of<space/><link><target>Juviles</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Alpujarras</target></link>. After devastating its countryside to deprive it of any resource, he encircled it. Finding it difficult to bombard with catapults, he ordered the construction of a platform where his<space/><link><target>siege weapon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>could be mounted to greater effect, and cut the water supply. The Muladi defenders surrendered after a few days: their lives, apart from fifty-five die-hards who were beheaded, were spared in exchange of their allegiance to the emir. The campaign continued in a similar vein, lasting for a total of ninety days. Abd ar-Rahman forced the defeated Muladi to send hostages and treasures to Crdoba, in order to secure their continued submission.</paragraph><paragraph>In the first year of his reign, Abd ar-Rahman took advantage of the rivalries between the<space/><link><target>Banu Hayyay</target></link><space/>lords of<space/><link><target>Seville</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carmona, Spain</target><part>Carmona</part></link><space/>to force them to submit. He initially sent a special corps (<italics>hasam</italics>) under Ahmad ibn Muhammad ibn Hudayr, governor of cija, to Seville, to obtain their submission. This attempt failed, but gained him the support of Muhammad ibn Ibrahim ibn Hayyay, lord of Carmona, and a cousin of the Sevillan lord, Ahmad ibn Maslama. When the latter was surrounded by Umayyad troops, he sued for help to Ibn Hafsun, but the latter was defeated by the besiegers and returned to Bobastro. He next went after the forts in the provinces of<space/><link><target>Granada (province)</target><part>Elvira</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Granada (province)</target><part>Granada</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Province of Jan (Spain)</target><part>Jaen</part></link>, all of which were either directly or indirectly controlled by Hafsun.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>Seville finally capitulated on 20 December 913. Ibn al-Mundir al-Qurays, a member of the royal family, was named governor of the city, while the Lord of Carmona obtained the title of<space/><link><target>vizier</target></link>. Muhammad ibn Ibrahim enjoyed his office for only a single day, for Abd ar-Rahman soon discovered his collusion with the rebel governor of Carmona. Muhammad was sent to prison, where he later met his death.</paragraph><paragraph>The region of<space/><link><target>Valencia</target></link><space/>submitted peacefully in 915.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ibn Hafsun and other rebels</heading><paragraph>Abd ar-Rahman's next objective was to quash the longstanding rebellion of<space/><link><target>Umar ibn Hafsun</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>His troops left Crdoba on 7 May 914 and, after a few days, encamped before the walls of Balda (identified with today's<space/><link><target>Cuevas de San Marcos</target></link>). His cavalry ravaged the nearby woods and the countryside, while the rest of the troopes moved to Turrus, a castle located in the present municipality of<space/><link><target>Algarinejo, Granada</target><part>Algarinejo</part></link>, which was surrounded within five days, while its environs were also devastated.</paragraph><paragraph>The Umayyad army then moved to Bobastro, while the cavalry was sent to the castle of Sant Batir, which was abandoned by the defenders, allowing Abd ar-Rahman's troops to secure a large booty. Then it was the turn of the castles of Olas and Reina. The latter fell after a violent fight, leaving the road open to the major city and provincial capital of Mlaga, which he captured after one day. Abd ar-Rahman then turned and followed the coast by Montemayor, near<space/><link><target>Benahavs</target></link>, Suhayl (<link><target>Fuengirola</target></link>) and another castle called<space/><italics>Turrus<space/></italics>or<space/><italics>Turrus Jusayn</italics><space/>(identified by<space/><link><target>variste Lvi-Provenal</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Ojn</target></link>). He finally arrived at<space/><link><target>Algeciras</target></link><space/>on 1 June 914. He ordered a patrol of the coast to destroy the boats that supplied<space/><link><target>Umar ibn Hafsun</target></link><space/>from North Africa. Many of them were captured and set afire in front of the emir. The rebellious castles near Algeciras surrendered as soon as the Cordoban army manifested itself.</paragraph><paragraph>Abd ar-Rahman launched three different campaigns against Ibn Hafsun (who died in 917) and his sons. Among them, Jafar ibn Hafsun held the stronghold of Toledo. Abd ar-Rahman ordered ravaged the city's countryside. Jafar, after two years of siege, escaped the city to ask for help in the northern Christian kingdoms. In the meantime Abd ar-Rahman obtained the surrender of the city from its population, after promising them immunity, although 4,000 rebel men escaped in a night sally. The city surrendered on 2 August 932, after a siege of two years.</paragraph><paragraph>In 921 the Banu Muhallab of<space/><link><target>Guadix</target></link><space/>submitted, followed by those of<space/><link><target>Jerez de la Frontera</target><part>Jerez</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cdiz</target></link>, as well as the trading republic of<space/><link><target>Pechina</target></link><space/>(922). In 927, Abd-ar-Rahman also launched a campaign against the rebel<space/><link><target>Banu Qasi</target></link><space/>clan, but was forced to break it off by the intervention of King<space/><link><target>Jimeno Garcs of Pamplona</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The last of Ibn Hafsun to fall was Hafs, who commanded his powerful fortress of Bobastro. Surrounded by Abd ar-Rahman's vizier Said ibn al-Mundhir who had ordered the construction of bastions around the city, he resisted the siege for six months,<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>until he surrendered in 928 and had his life spared.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Hermann<space/></arg><arg name="last">Schreiber</arg><arg name="title">Gli Arabi in Spagna</arg><arg name="page">142</arg><arg name="publisher">Garzanti</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Levente and Algarve rebels</heading><paragraph>The continued expeditions against the Hafsunids did not distract Abd ad-Rahman III from the situation of other regions in al-Andalus, which recognized him only nominally, if not being in open revolt. Most of the loyal governors of the cities were in a weak position, such as the governor of<space/><link><target>vora</target></link>, who could not prevent the attack of the king of Galicia (future king of Len),<space/><link><target>Ordoo II of Len</target><part>Ordoo II</part></link>, who captured the city in the summer of 913, taking back a sizable booty and 4,000 prisoners and massacring many Muslims.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In much of the eastern and western province, Abd ar-Rahman's authority was completely unrecognized. The lord of Badajoz, Abd Allah ibn Muhammad, grandson of Abd-ar-Rahman ibn Marwan al-Yilliqi, not only fortified his city against a possible attack from Ordoo, but also acted in complete independence from Crdoba. To avoid the fall of vora into the hands of the Berber groups of the region, he ordered the destruction of its defensive towers and lowered the walls, though a year later he decided to reconstruct it, giving its control to his ally Masud ibn Sa' dun al-Surunbaqi. The Algarve was dominated completely by a mulad coalition led by Sa'id ibn Mal, who had expelled the Arabs from<space/><link><target>Beja (Portugal)</target><part>Beja</part></link>, and the lords of<space/><link><target>Faro, Portugal</target><part>Ocsnoba</part></link>, Yahya ibn Bakr, and of<space/><link><target>Taifa of Niebla</target><part>Niebla</part></link>, Ibn Ufayr.</paragraph><paragraph>The absence of royal authority enabled Ordoo II to easily campaign in this area, his main objective being the city of<space/><link><target>Mrida, Spain</target><part>Mrida</part></link>, in the summer of 915. Abd ar-Rahman III did not send an army and only several local Berber<space/><italics>jefes</italics><space/>offered some resistance which was ineffective.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Assumption of the Caliphate</heading><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="title"><space/>Letter proclaiming Abd-ar-Rahman III's assumption of the Caliph title
<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/>We are the most worthy to fulfil our right, and the most entitled to complete our good fortune, and to put on the clothing granted by the nobility of God, because of the favour which He has shown us, and the renown which He has given us, and the power to which He has raised us, because of what He has enabled us to acquire, and because of what He has made easy for us and for our state [? dynasty; {{Lang-ar|''[[wiktionary:دولة|dawla]]''}}] to achieve; He has made our name and the greatness of our power celebrated everywhere; and He has made the hopes of the worlds depend on us<space/><nowiki>[</nowiki>{{Lang-ar|''[[wiktionary:علق|a‘laqa]]''}}<nowiki>]</nowiki>, and made their errings turn again to us and their rejoicing at good news be (rejoicing at good news) about our dynasty<space/><nowiki>[</nowiki>{{Lang-ar|''[[wiktionary:دولة|dawla]]''}}<nowiki>]</nowiki>. And praise be to God, possessed of grace and kindness, for the grace which He has shown, [God] most worthy of superiority for the superiority which He has granted us. We have decided that the ''[[Dawah|da‘wa]]'' should be to us as [[Amir al-Mu'minin|Commander of the Faithful]] and that letters emanating from us or coming to us should be [headed] in the same manner. Everyone who calls himself by this name apart from ourselves is arrogating it to himself [unlawfully] and trespassing upon it and is branded with something to which he has no right. We know that if we were to continue [allowing] the neglect of this duty which is owed to us in this matter then we should be forfeiting our right and neglecting our title, which is certain. So order the ''[[Khatib|khaṭīb]]'' in your place to pronounce [the ''[[Khutbah|khuṭba]]''] using [this title] and address your communications to us accordingly, if God will. Written on Thursday, 2 [[Dhu al-Hijjah|Dhū al-Ḥijja]] 316 [16 January 929].
<space/></arg><arg name="source"><space/>Translated by David Wasserstein<ref name</arg><arg name="width"><space/>45%</arg></template>In the next year, despite having defeated only some of the rebels, Abd ar-Rahman III considered himself powerful enough to declare himself<space/><link><target>Caliph of Crdoba</target></link><space/>(16 January 929), effectively breaking his allegiance to, and ties with, the<space/><link><target>Fatimid</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Abbasid</target></link><space/>caliphs.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.allaboutphilosophy.org/abd-ar-rahman-iii.htm'>Abd-ar-Rahman III</link></extension><space/>The caliphate was thought only to belong to the Emperor who ruled over the sacred cities of<space/><link><target>Mecca</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Medina</target></link>, and his ancestors had until then been content with the title of emir. But the force of this tradition had weakened over time; and the title increased Abd-ar-Rahman's prestige with his subjects, both in Iberia and Africa. He based his claim to the caliphate on his Umayyad ancestors who had held undisputed control of the caliphate until they were overthrown by the Abbasids.</paragraph><paragraph>Abd ar-Rahman's move made him both the political and the religious leader of all the Muslims in al-Andalus, as well as the protector of his Christian and Jewish subjects. The symbols of his new caliphate power were a scepter (<italics>jayzuran</italics>) and the throne (<italics>sarir</italics>). In the mint he had founded in November 928, Abd ar-Rahman started to coin golden dinars<extension extension_name='ref'>No golden Islamic coins had been found in Spain preceding Abd ar-Rahman III's reign. See Schreiber,<space/><italics>Gli Arabi in Spagna</italics>, p. 143.</extension><space/>and silver dirhams, replacing the &quot;al-Andalus&quot; title with his name.</paragraph><paragraph>In his new role of caliph, he achieved the surrender of<space/><link><target>Ibn Marwan</target></link><space/>of Badajoz in 930. On the southern front, to counter the increasing Fatimid power in North Africa, abd ar-Rahmad ordered the construction of a fleet based in<space/><link><target>Almeria</target></link>. The caliph helped the<space/><link><target>Maghrawa</target></link><space/>Berbers conquer<space/><link><target>Melilla</target></link><space/>(927),<space/><link><target>Ceuta</target></link><space/>(931)<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Tangiers</target></link><space/>(951), which accepted his suzerainty. However, he was unable to defeat<space/><link><target>Jawhar al-Siqilli</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Fatamid</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>In 951 he signed a peace with the new king of Len,<space/><link><target>Ordoo III of Len</target><part>Ordoo III</part></link>, in order to have a free hand against the Fatimids whose ships were harassing the caliphate ones in the Mediterranean and had even launched an assault against Almeria. Abd ar-Rahman's force, led by prime minister Ahmad ibn Said, besieged the Fatimid port of Tunis, which bought its safety through paying a huge sum.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schreiber,<space/><italics>Gli Arabi in Spagna</italics>, p. 154</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the end he was able to create a protectorate covering the northern and central Maghreb, supporting the<space/><link><target>Idrisid</target></link><space/>dynasty; the caliphate influence in the area disappeared after a Fatimid offensive in 958, after which abd ar-Rahman kept only the strongholds of Ceuta and Tangiers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>War with the Christian kingdoms of the north</heading><paragraph>Even before al-Andalus was firmly under his rule, he had restarted the war against King<space/><link><target>Ordoo II of Len</target></link>, who had taken advantage of the previous troublesome situation to capture some boundary areas and menace the Umayyad territory. In 917 the then emir had sent a large army under his general Ahmad ibn Abi Abda against Len, but this force was destroyed at the<space/><link><target>Battle of San Esteban de Gormaz (917)</target><part>Battle of San Esteban de Gormaz</part></link><space/>in September of that year.</paragraph><paragraph>Recognizing he had underestimated the power of Ordoo II, in 920 Abd ar-Rahman mustered another powerful army to reclaim the territories lost after the previous campaign. He captured the forts of<space/><link><target>Osma</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>San Esteban de Gormaz</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>After defeating king<space/><link><target>Sancho Garcs I of Navarre</target></link><space/>and the king of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Len</target><part>Leon</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Battle of Valdejunquera</target><part>Valdejunquera</part></link><space/>on 26 July,<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>he penetrated into Navarre, overcoming Aragon by the classic route of the invasions from the south. Abd ar-Rahman reached the Basque city of<space/><link><target>Pamplona</target></link>, which was sacked and its cathedral church demolished.</paragraph><paragraph>In 924 Abd-ar-Rahman felt obliged to avenge the massacre of Viguera castle perpetrated by king Sancho Ordez of Navarre one year earlier. he launched counter offensive against Sancho in which Abd-ar-Rahman devastated large numbers of Basque area<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com.au/books?id=qVYT4Kraym0C&amp;amp;pg=PA435&amp;amp;dq=Abd-ar-Rahman++III+zaragoza&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=aNLLVJW5O82qaaaZgbAB&amp;amp;ved=0CCYQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Abd-ar-Rahman%20%20III%20zaragoza&amp;amp;f=false'>Al Maqqari, Nafh at-Tih, I, page 363</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The succession crisis which struck Len after Ordoo II's death in the same year caused hostilities to cease until<space/><link><target>Ramiro II of Len</target><part>Ramiro II</part></link><space/>obtained the throne in 932; a first attempt by him to assist the besieged rebels in Toledo was repelled in 932, despite the Christian king capturing<space/><link><target>Madrid</target></link><space/>and scoring a victory at<space/><link><target>Osma</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 934, after reasserting supremacy over Pamplona and<space/><link><target>lava</target></link>, abd ar-Rahmad forced Ramiro to retreat to<space/><link><target>Burgos</target></link>, and forced the Navarrese queen<space/><link><target>Toda of Navarre</target><part>Toda</part></link>, his aunt, to submit to him as a vassal and withdraw from direct rule as regent for her son<space/><link><target>Garca Snchez I of Pamplona</target><part>Garca Snchez I</part></link>. In 937 he conquered some thirty castles in Len. Next he turned to Muhammad ibn Hashim at-Tugib, governor of<space/><link><target>Zaragoza</target></link>, who had allied with Ramiro but was pardoned after the capture of his city.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite early defeats, Ramiro and Garca were able to crush the caliphate army in 939 at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Simancas</target></link>, and almost kill Abd-ar-Rahman III,<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>in part, most likely, due to treason from Arab elements in the caliph's army. After this defeat, Abd-ar-Rahman stopped taking personal command of his military campaigns. His cause was helped, however, by<space/><link><target>Fernn Gonzlez of Castile</target></link>, one of the Christian leaders at Simancas, who subsequently launched a sustained rebellion against Ramiro. The victory of Simancas enabled the Christian kingdom to maintain the military initiative in the peninsula until the defeat of Ramiro's successor,<space/><link><target>Ordoo III of Len</target></link>, in 956. However they did not press this advantage as civil war broke out in the Christian territories.</paragraph><paragraph>In 950 Abd ar-Rahman received in Crdoba an embassy from count<space/><link><target>Borrell II of Barcelona</target></link>, by which the northern county recognized caliphate supremacy in exchange for peace and mutual support. In 958,<space/><link><target>Sancho I of Len</target><part>Sancho</part></link>, the exiled king of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Len</target><part>Leon</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Garca Snchez I</target><part>Garcia Sanchez</part></link>, King of<space/><link><target>Navarre</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Toda of Navarre</target><part>Queen Toda</part></link><space/>all paid homage to abd ar-Rahmad in<space/><link><target>Caliphate of Crdoba</target><part>Cordoba</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Until 961, the caliphate played an active role in the dynastic strife characterizing the Christian kingdom during the period. Ordoo III's half-brother and successor,<space/><link><target>Sancho I of Len</target><part>Sancho the Fat</part></link>, had been deposed by his cousin<space/><link><target>Ordoo IV of Len</target><part>Ordoo IV</part></link>. Together with his grandmother Toda of Navarre, Sancho sought an alliance with Crdoba. In exchange for some castles, Abd-ar-Rahman helped them to take back<space/><link><target>Zamora, Spain</target><part>Zamora</part></link><space/>(959) and<space/><link><target>Oviedo</target></link><space/>(960) and to overthrow Ordoo IV.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Later years</heading><paragraph>Abd-ar-Rahman was accused of having sunk in his later years into the self-indulgent habits of the<space/><link><target>harem</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wikisource"><link><target>s:1911 Encyclopdia Britannica/Abd-ar-Rahman</target><part>Article on WikiSource</part></link></extension><space/>He is known to have openly kept a male as well as a female harem.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Encyclopedia of Medieval Iberia</italics>, ed. Michael Gerli (New York: Routledge, 2003), 398399.</extension><space/>This likely influenced the polemical story of his falling in love with a 13-year-old boy (later enshrined as a Christian martyr and canonised as<space/><link><target>Pelagius of Cordova</target><part>Saint Pelagius of Crdoba</part></link>) who refused the Caliph's advances. The love story may have been a construct on top of an original tale, however, in which he ordered the boy-slave to convert to Islam. Either way, enraged, he had the boy tortured and dismembered, thus serving the Christian polemic demonizing Muslims.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walter Andrews and Mehmet Kalpakl,<space/><italics>The Age of Beloveds</italics>, Duke University Press, 2005; p.2</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Mark D. Jordan,<space/><italics>The Invention of Sodomy in Christian Theology</italics>, Chicago, 1997; pp.1028</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Abd-ar-Rahman spent the rest of his years in his new palace outside Crdoba. He died in October 961 and was succeeded by his son<space/><link><target>al-Hakam II</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph>Abd-ar-Rahman was a patron of arts, especially architecture. A third of his revenue sufficed for the ordinary expenses of government, a third was hoarded, and a third was spent on buildings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wikisource"></extension><space/>After declaring the caliphate, he had a massive palace complex, known as the<space/><link><target>Medina Azahara</target></link>, built some five kilometers north of Crdoba. The Medina Azahara was modeled after the old Umayyad palace in<space/><link><target>Damascus</target></link><space/>and served as a symbolic tie between the new caliph and his ancestors. It was said that Cordoba contained 3000 mosques and 100,000 shops and homes during his reign.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Under his reign, Crdoba became the most important intellectual centre of Western Europe. He expanded the city's library, which would be further enriched by his successors.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">I have now reigned above fifty years in victory or peace; beloved by my subjects, dreaded by my enemies, and respected by my allies. Riches and honours, power and pleasure, have waited on my call, nor does any earthly blessing appear to have been wanting to my felicity. In this situation, I have diligently numbered the days of pure and genuine happiness which have fallen to my lot: they amount to Fourteen: - O man! place not thy confidence in this present world!</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He also reinforced the Iberian fleet, which became the most powerful in<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Europe</target></link>. Iberian raiders moved up to<space/><link><target>Galicia (Spain)</target><part>Galicia</part></link>, Asturias, and North Africa. The colonizers of<space/><link><target>Fraxinetum</target></link><space/>came from al-Andalus as well.</paragraph><paragraph>Due to his consolidation of power, Muslim Iberia became a power for a few centuries. It also brought prosperity, and with this he created mints where pure gold and silver coins were created. He renovated and added to the<space/><link><target>MosqueCathedral of Crdoba</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He was very wary of losing control and kept tight reins in his family. In 949, he executed one of his sons for conspiring against him. He was tolerant of non-Muslims, Jews and Christians who were treated fairly. European nations sent emissaries such as from<space/><link><target>Otto I</target></link><space/>of Germany, and the<space/><link><target>Byzantine</target></link><space/>emperor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ancestry</heading><paragraph>Abd-ar-Rahman III's mother Muzna was a Christian captive, possibly from the<space/><link><target>Pyrenees</target><part>Pyrenean</part></link><space/>region. His paternal grandmother<space/><link><target>Onneca Fortnez</target></link><space/>was a Christian princess from the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Navarre</target><part>Kingdom of Pamplona</part></link>. In his immediate ancestry, Abd-ar-Rahman III was Hispano<link><target>Basque people</target><part>Basque</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arab people</target><part>Arab</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fletcher"></extension><template><target>ahnentafel top</target><arg name="width">100%</arg></template><template><target>ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Abd-ar-Rahman III, Caliph of Córdoba'''
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. Muhammad<ref name</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. Muzna (originally Maria?)<ref name</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[Abdullah ibn Muhammad al-Umawi|Abdullah, Emir of Córdoba]]<ref name</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. [[Onneca Fortúnez|Onneca Fortúnez (Durr)]]<ref name</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3">
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4">
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[Muhammad I of Córdoba|Muhammad I, Emir of Córdoba]]<ref name</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. Baher<ref>[[#Ibn|Ibn Idhari]], [http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[Fortún Garcés of Pamplona|Fortún Garcés, King of Pamplona]]<ref name</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. Oria<ref name</arg><arg name="4">
</arg><arg name="5">
</arg><arg name="6">
</arg><arg name="7">
</arg><arg name="8"><space/>16. [[Abd ar-Rahman II|Abd ar-Rahman II, Emir of Córdoba]]<ref name</arg><arg name="9"><space/>17. Buheyr<ref>[[#Ibn|Ibn Idhari]], [http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="10">
</arg><arg name="11">
</arg><arg name="12"><space/>20. [[García Íñiguez of Pamplona|García Íñiguez, King of Pamplona]]<ref name</arg><arg name="13">
</arg><arg name="14">
</arg><arg name="15">
</arg><arg name="16">
</arg><arg name="17">
</arg><arg name="18">
</arg><arg name="19">
</arg><arg name="20">
</arg><arg name="21">
</arg><arg name="22">
</arg><arg name="23">
</arg><arg name="24">
</arg><arg name="25">
</arg><arg name="26">
</arg><arg name="27">
</arg><arg name="28">
</arg><arg name="29">
</arg><arg name="30">
</arg><arg name="31">
</arg></template>&lt;/center&gt;<template><target>ahnentafel bottom</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Jessica<space/></arg><arg name="last">Coope</arg><arg name="title">Martyrs of Córdoba: Community and Family Conflict in an Age of Mass Conversion</arg><arg name="location">Lincoln</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8032-1471-5</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Nebraska Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Maribel<space/></arg><arg name="last">Fierro</arg><arg name="title">Abd-al-Rahman III of Córdoba</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">Oneworld Publications</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-85168-384-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Ibn Idhari]]<space/></arg><arg name="others">trans. Francisco Fernández y González<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[Al-Bayan al-Mughrib]]<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">[http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="volume">Volume 1<space/></arg><arg name="year">1860<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">Composed c. 1312<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Francisco Ventura y Sabatel<space/></arg><arg name="location">Granada<space/></arg><arg name="language">Spanish<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">557028856<space/></arg><arg name="ref">Ibn</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lane-Poole<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Stanley<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Stanley Lane-Poole<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Mohammedan Dynasties: Chronological and Genealogical Tables with Historical Introductions<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.archive.org/details/mohammedandynas00lanegoog<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1894<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Archibald Constable and Company<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Westminster<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>1199708<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Lan94</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor1-first">Évariste</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Lévi-Provençal</arg><arg name="editor1-link">Évariste Lévi-Provençal</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Emilio</arg><arg name="editor2-last">García Gómez</arg><arg name="editor2-link">Emilio García Gómez</arg><arg name="title">Una crónica anónima de 'Abd al-Rahman III al-Nasir</arg><arg name="language">Spanish</arg><arg name="publisher">Instituto Miguel Asin</arg><arg name="location">Madrid-Granada</arg><arg name="year">1950</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last">Scales</arg><arg name="title">Fall of the Caliphate of Córdoba</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">EJ Brill</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>90-04-09868-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Kenneth<space/></arg><arg name="last">Wolf</arg><arg name="title">Christian Martyrs in Muslim Spain</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Cambridge|Cambridge University]] Press</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-34416-6</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Wikisource-inline</target><arg name="list">
**{{Cite EB1911|wstitle</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg>[[Umayyad|Banu Umayyah]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg>[[Quraysh (tribe)|Banu Quraish]]</arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Abdallah ibn Muhammad]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Emir of Córdoba]]</arg><arg name="years">912–929</arg></template><template><target>S-non</target><arg name="reason">Became caliph</arg></template>|-<template><target>S-new</target><arg name="reason">[[Caliphate of Córdoba]]<br />created</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Caliph of Córdoba]]</arg><arg name="years">929–961</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Al-Hakam II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Umayyads</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Abd-Ar-Rahman Iii</target></template><link><target>Category:889 births</target></link><link><target>Category:961 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Crdoba, Andalusia</target></link><link><target>Category:Umayyad caliphs of Crdoba</target></link><link><target>Category:10th-century caliphs of Crdoba</target></link><link><target>Category:Pardon recipients</target></link><link><target>Category:LGBT history prior to the 19th century</target></link><link><target>Category:Emirs of Crdoba</target></link></paragraph></article>