<article title='Concorde'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2010</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><table><tablerow><tablecell>name= Concorde</tablecell><tablecell>image= File:British Airways Concorde G-BOAC 03.jpg</tablecell><tablecell>caption= British Airways Concorde in 1986</tablecell><tablecell>alt=}}<template><target>Infobox aircraft type</target><arg name="type"><space/>Supersonic airliner
<space/></arg><arg name="manufacturer"><space/>[[British Aircraft Corporation|BAC]] (later [[British Aerospace|BAe]] and [[BAE Systems]])<br/>[[Sud Aviation]] (later [[Aérospatiale]] and [[EADS]])
<space/></arg><arg name="designer">
<space/></arg><arg name="first flight"><space/>2 March 1969
<space/></arg><arg name="introduction"><space/>21 January 1976
<space/></arg><arg name="national origin"><space/>United Kingdom and France
<space/></arg><arg name="retired"><space/>26 November 2003
<space/></arg><arg name="status"><space/>Retired from service
<space/></arg><arg name="primary user"><space/>[[British Airways]] 
<space/></arg><arg name="more users"><space/>[[Air France]]<space/><br>See ''[[#Operators|Operators]]'' below for others 
<space/></arg><arg name="produced"><space/>1965–1979
<space/></arg><arg name="number built"><space/>20 (including 6 non-airline aircraft)<ref>Towey 2007, p. 359.</ref><ref>{{cite news |url</arg><arg name="unit cost"><space/>[[Pound sterling|£]] {{formatprice|23000000}} in 1977 ([[Pound sterling|£]] {{formatprice|{{Inflation|UK|23000000|1977}}}} in {{CURRENTYEAR}} [[Pound sterling|pounds]]{{inflation-fn|UK}})
<space/></arg><arg name="program cost">[[Pound sterling|£]] 1.3 billion<ref name</arg><arg name="variants with their own articles">
</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><bold>Arospatiale-BAC Concorde</bold><space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>ŋ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɔr</arg><arg>d</arg></template><space/>is a<space/><link><target>turbojet</target></link>-powered<space/><link><target>supersonic aircraft</target><part>supersonic</part></link><space/>passenger<space/><link><target>jet airliner</target></link>. It featured a maximum speed over twice the speed of sound at<space/><link><target>Mach number</target><part>Mach</part></link><space/>2.04, with seating for 92 to 128 passengers. First flown in 1969, Concorde entered service in 1976 and continued commercial flights for 27 years until 2003. It is one of only two<space/><link><target>supersonic transport</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to have entered commercial service; the other was the<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-144</target></link>.</preline></preblock><paragraph>Concorde was jointly developed and produced by<space/><link><target>Arospatiale</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>British Aircraft Corporation</target></link><space/>(BAC) under an Anglo-French treaty. Concorde's name reflects the development agreement between the United Kingdom and France. In the UK, any or all of the typeunusually for an aircraftare known simply as &quot;Concorde&quot;, without an article. A total of 20 aircraft were built in France and the United Kingdom; six of these were prototypes and development aircraft. Seven each were delivered to<space/><link><target>Air France</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>British Airways</target></link>. With only 20 aircraft built, the development of Concorde was a substantial economic loss; Air France and British Airways received considerable government subsidies to purchase them.</paragraph><paragraph>Among other<space/><link><target>#Scheduled flights</target><part>destinations</part></link>, Concorde flew regular<space/><link><target>transatlantic flight</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>London Heathrow Airport</target><part>London Heathrow</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Charles de Gaulle Airport</target><part>Paris Charles de Gaulle Airport</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>John F. Kennedy International Airport</target><part>New York-JFK</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Washington Dulles International Airport</target><part>Washington Dulles</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Grantley Adams International Airport</target><part>Barbados</part></link>; it flew these routes in less than half the time of other airliners. Over time the aircraft became profitable when it found a customer base willing to pay for flights on what was for most of its career the fastest commercial aircraft in the world. The aircraft is regarded by many people as an aviation icon and an engineering marvel.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde beats"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde was retired in 2003 due to a general downturn in the aviation industry after the type's<space/><link><target>Air France Flight 4590</target><part>only crash in 2000</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>September 11 attacks</target><part>11&amp;nbsp;September terrorist attacks</part></link><space/>in 2001, and a decision by<space/><link><target>Airbus</target></link>, the successor firm of Arospatiale and BAC, to discontinue maintenance support.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC Concorde Grounded"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/2934257.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">UK &#124; Concorde grounded for good<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">2003-04-10<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Development</heading><heading level='3'>Early studies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Jeton l'effigie du Concorde Supersonique.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Commemorative gold medallion by Albert de Jaeger, of the intention to build Concorde</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The origins of the Concorde project date to the early 1950s, when<space/><link><target>Arnold Hall</target></link>, director of the<space/><link><target>Royal Aircraft Establishment</target></link><space/>(RAE) asked<space/><link><target>Morien Morgan</target></link><space/>to form a committee to study the supersonic transport (SST) concept. The group met for the first time in February 1954 and delivered their first report in April 1955.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At the time it was known that the drag at supersonic speeds was strongly related to the span of the wing.<extension extension_name='ref' group="N">In particular, R. T. Jones' work at NACA demonstrated this in depth.</extension><space/>This led to the use of very short-span, very thin rectangular wings such as those seen on the control surfaces of many missiles, or in aircraft like the<space/><link><target>Lockheed F-104 Starfighter</target></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>Avro 730</target></link><space/>that the team studied. The team outlined a baseline configuration that looked like an enlarged Avro 730.</paragraph><paragraph>This same short span produced very little lift at low speed, which resulted in extremely long takeoff runs and frighteningly high landing speeds.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jan Meyer,<space/><link type='external' href='http://starfighter.no/web/hi-alt.html'>&quot;High altitude flying with F-104&quot;</link>, Starfighterens veneer Norge</extension><space/>In an SST design, this would have required enormous engine power to lift off from existing runways, and to provide the fuel needed, &quot;some horribly large aeroplanes&quot; resulted.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template><space/>Based on this, the group considered the concept of an SST unfeasible, and instead suggested continued low-level studies into supersonic aerodynamics.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Slender deltas</heading><paragraph>Soon after,<space/><link><target>Johanna Weber</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dietrich Kchemann</target></link><space/>at the RAE published a series of reports on a new wing planform, known in the UK as the &quot;slender delta&quot; concept.<extension extension_name='ref' name='deltawing'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title">The development of the slender delta concept<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering<space/></arg><arg name="author">Maltby, R.L.<space/></arg><arg name="volume">40, 1968<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20130928074301/http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="archivedate">28 September 2013<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="aerosoc"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://aerosociety.com/News/Society-News/2742/OBITUARY-DR-JOHANNA-WEBER</arg><arg name="title">Obituary: Dr Johanna Weber</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Royal Aeronautical Society]]</arg><arg name="date">January 12, 2015</arg><arg name="last">Green</arg><arg name="first">John</arg></template></extension><space/>The team, including Eric Maskell, worked with the fact that delta wings can produce strong<space/><link><target>vortex</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>on their upper surfaces at high<space/><link><target>angle of attack</target><part>angles of attack</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template><space/>The vortex will lower the air pressure and cause lift to be greatly increased. This effect had been noticed earlier, notably by<space/><link><target>Chuck Yeager</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Convair XF-92</target></link>, but its qualities had not been fully appreciated. Weber suggested that this was no mere curiosity, and the effect could be deliberately used to improve low speed performance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="aerosoc"></extension><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Kchemann's and Weber's papers changed the entire nature of supersonic design almost overnight. Although the delta had already been used on aircraft prior to this point, these designs used planforms that were not much different from a<space/><link><target>swept wing</target></link><space/>of the same span.<extension extension_name='ref' group="N">Consider especially the<space/><link><target>English Electric Lightning</target></link>, whose wing can be considered either a highly swept rectangle, or a delta with a notch cut out of the root.</extension><space/>Weber noted that the lift from the vortex was increased by the length of the wing it had to operate over, which suggested that the effect would be maximized by extending the wing along the fuselage as far as possible. Such a layout would still have good supersonic performance inherent to the short span, while also offering reasonable takeoff and landing speeds using vortex generation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="aerosoc"></extension><space/>The only downside to such a design is that the aircraft would have to take off and land very &quot;nose high&quot; to generate the required vortex lift, which led to questions about the low speed handling qualities of such a design.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brown"></extension><space/>It would also need to have long<space/><link><target>landing gear</target></link><space/>to produce the required angles while still on the runway.</paragraph><paragraph>Kchemann presented the idea at a meeting where Morgan was also present. Test pilot<space/><link><target>Eric Brown (pilot)</target><part>Eric Brown</part></link><space/>recalls Morgan's reaction to the presentation, saying that he immediately seized on it as the solution to the SST problem. Brown considers this moment as being the true birth of the Concorde project.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brown">Eric Brown,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.ca/books?id=MMEK1jwD03AC&amp;amp;pg=PT121'>&quot;Wings On My Sleeve&quot;</link>, Hachette UK, 2008, end of Chapter 12</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Supersonic Transport Advisory Committee</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:HP.115.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The HP.115 tested the low-speed performance of the slender delta layout.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On 1 October 1956 the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Supply</target></link><space/>asked Morgan to form a new study group, the<space/><italics>Supersonic Transport Advisory Committee</italics><space/>(<italics>STAC</italics>),<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">39</arg></template><space/>with the explicit goal of developing a practical SST design and finding industry partners to build it. At the very first meeting, on 5 November 1956, the decision was made to fund the development of a testbed aircraft to examine the low speed performance of the slender delta, a contract that eventually produced the<space/><link><target>Handley Page HP.115</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brown"></extension><space/>This aircraft would ultimately demonstrate safe control at speeds as low as 69&amp;nbsp;mph, about that of the Starfighter.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jim Winchester, &quot;Handley Page HP.115 (1961)&quot;, in &quot;X-Planes and Prototypes&quot;, Amber Books, 2005, p. 134.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>STAC stated that an SST would have economic performance similar to existing subsonic types.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template><space/>Although they would burn more fuel in cruise, they would be able to fly more<space/><link><target>sorties</target></link><space/>in a given period of time, so fewer aircraft would be needed to service a particular route. This would remain economically advantageous as long as fuel represented a small percentage of operational costs, as it did at the time. STAC suggested that two designs naturally fell out of their work, a transatlantic model flying at about Mach 2, and a shorter-range version flying at perhaps Mach 1.2. Morgan suggested that a 150 passenger transatlantic SST would cost about 75 to 90 million to develop to production, and be in service in 1970. The smaller 100 passenger short-range version would cost perhaps 50 to 80 million, and be ready for service in 1968. To meet this schedule, development would need to begin in 1960, with production contracts let in 1962.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template><space/>Morgan strongly suggested that the US was already involved in a similar project, and that if the UK failed to respond it would be locked out of an airliner market that he believed would be dominated by SST aircraft.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1959, a study contract was awarded to<space/><link><target>Hawker Siddeley</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bristol Aeroplane Company</target><part>Bristol</part></link><space/>for preliminary designs based on the slender delta concept,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template><space/>which developed as the<space/><link><target>Hawker Siddeley HSA.1000</target><part>HSA.1000</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bristol 223</target><part>Bristol 198</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Armstrong Whitworth</target></link><space/>also responded with an internal design, the<space/><italics>M-Wing</italics>, for the lower-speed shorter-range category. Even at this early time, both the STAC group and the government were looking for partners to develop the designs. In September 1959 Hawker approached<space/><link><target>Lockheed Corporation</target><part>Lockheed</part></link>, and after the creation of<space/><link><target>British Aircraft Corporation</target></link><space/>in 1960, the former Bristol team immediately started talks with<space/><link><target>Boeing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>General Dynamics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Douglas Aircraft</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sud Aviation</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ogee planform selected</heading><paragraph>Kchemann and others at the RAE continued their work on the slender delta throughout, considering three basic shapes; the classic straight-edge delta, the &quot;gothic delta&quot; that was rounded outwards to appear like a<space/><link><target>Gothic architecture#Equilateral arch</target><part>gothic arch</part></link>, and the &quot;ogival wing&quot; that was compound-rounded into the shape of an<space/><link><target>ogee</target></link>. Each of these planforms had their own advantages and disadvantages in terms of aerodynamics. As they worked with these shapes, a practical concern grew to become so important that it forced selection of one of these designs.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">40</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Generally one wants to have the wing's<space/><link><target>Center of pressure (fluid mechanics)</target><part>centre of pressure</part></link><space/>(CoP, or &quot;lift point&quot;) close to the aircraft's<space/><link><target>centre of gravity</target></link><space/>(CoG, or &quot;balance point&quot;) to reduce the amount of control force required to<space/><link><target>Pitch axis (kinematics)</target><part>pitch</part></link><space/>the aircraft. As the aircraft layout changes during the design phase, it is common for the CoG to move fore or aft. With a normal wing design this can be addressed by moving the wing slightly fore or aft to account for this.<extension extension_name='ref' group="N">Or, more rarely, &quot;bent&quot; back into position. Examples include the<space/><link><target>Douglas DC-3</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Messerschmitt Me 262</target></link>.</extension><space/>With a delta wing running most of the length of the fuselage, this was no longer easy; moving the wing would leave it in front of the nose or behind the tail. Studying the various layouts in terms of CoG changes, both during design and changes due to fuel use during flight, the ogee planform immediately came to the fore.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">40</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While the wing planform was evolving, so was the basic SST concept. Bristol's original Type 198 was a small design with an almost pure slender delta wing,<extension extension_name='ref'>J. S. Thompson and R. A. Fail,<space/><link type='external' href='http://naca.central.cranfield.ac.uk/reports/arc/cp/0815.pdf'>&quot;Measurements of Oscillatory Derivatives at Mach Numbers up to 2.6 on a Model of a Supersonic Transport Design Study (Bristol Type 198)&quot;</link>, RAE Bedford, 1964.</extension><space/>but evolved into the larger<space/><link><target>Bristol Type 223</target><part>Type 223</part></link><space/>with an ogival wing and<space/><link><target>Canard (aeronautics)</target><part>canard</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as well.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Partnership with Sud</heading><paragraph>By this time similar political and economic concerns in<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>had led to their own SST plans. In the late 1950s the government requested designs from both the government-owned Sud and<space/><link><target>Nord Aviation</target><part>Nord</part></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>Dassault</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' group="N">This apparently took place some time in 1957, according to Conway's unclear statement about &quot;the following year&quot; which apparently references the first STAC meeting in late 1956.</extension><space/>All three returned designs based on Kchemann and Weber's slender delta; Nord suggested a<space/><link><target>ramjet</target></link><space/>powered design flying at Mach 3, the other two were jet powered Mach 2 designs that were similar to each other. Of the three, the<space/><link><target>Sud Aviation Super-Caravelle</target></link><space/>won the design contest with a medium-range design deliberately sized to avoid competition with transatlantic US designs they assumed were already on the drawing board.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As soon as the design was complete, in April 1960, Pierre Satre, the company's technical director, was sent to Bristol to discuss a partnership. Bristol was surprised to find that the Sud team had designed a very similar aircraft after considering the SST problem and coming to the very same conclusions as the Bristol and STAC teams in terms of economics. It was later revealed that the original STAC report, marked &quot;For UK Eyes Only&quot;, had secretly been passed to the French to win political favour. Sud made minor changes to the paper, and presented it as their own work.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">49</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Unsurprisingly, the two teams found much to agree on. The French had no modern large jet engines, and had already concluded they would buy a British design anyway (as they had on the earlier subsonic<space/><link><target>Sud Aviation Caravelle</target><part>Caravelle</part></link>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">47</arg></template><space/>As neither company had experience in the use of high-heat metals for airframes, a maximum speed of around Mach 2 was selected so aluminium could be used&amp;nbsp; above this speed the friction with the air warms the metal so much that aluminium begins to soften. This lower speed would also speed development and allow their design to fly before the Americans. Finally, everyone involved agreed that Kchemann's<space/><link><target>ogee</target></link><space/>shaped wing was the right one.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The only disagreements were over the size and range. The UK team was still focused on a 150 passenger design serving transatlantic routes, while the French were deliberately avoiding these. However, this proved not to be the barrier it might seem; common components could be used in both designs, with the shorter range version using a clipped fuselage and four engines, the longer one with a stretched fuselage and six engines, leaving only the wing to be extensively re-designed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">41</arg></template><space/>The teams continued to meet through 1961, and by this time it was clear that the two aircraft would be considerably more similar in spite of different range and seating arrangements. A single design emerged that differed primarily in fuel load. More powerful<space/><link><target>Rolls-Royce Olympus</target><part>Bristol Siddeley Olympus</part></link><space/>engines, being developed for the<space/><link><target>TSR-2</target></link>, allowed either design to be powered by only four engines.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Owen</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">50</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cabinet response, treaty</heading><paragraph>While the development teams met, French Minister of Public Works and Transport<space/><link><target>Robert Buron</target></link><space/>was meeting with the UK Minister of Aviation<space/><link><target>Peter Thorneycroft</target></link>, and Thorneycroft soon revealed to the cabinet that the French were much more serious about a partnership than any of the US companies.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template><space/>The various US companies had proved uninterested in such a venture, likely due to the belief that the government would be funding development and would frown on any partnership with a European company, and the risk of &quot;giving away&quot; US technological leadership to a European partner.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">69</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When the STAC plans were presented to the UK cabinet, a very negative reaction resulted. The economic considerations were considered highly questionable, especially as these were based on development costs, now estimated to be 150 million, which were repeatedly overrun in the industry. The Treasury Ministry in particular presented a very negative view, suggesting that there was no way the project would have any positive financial returns for the government, especially in light that &quot;the industry's past record of over-optimistic estimating (including the recent history of the TSR.2) suggests that it would be prudent to consider the 150 million [cost] to turn out much too low.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This concern led to an independent review of the project by the Committee on Civil Scientific Research and Development, which met on topic between July and September 1962. The Committee ultimately rejected the economic arguments, including considerations of supporting the industry made by Thorneycroft. Their report in October stated that it was unlikely there would be any direct positive economic outcome, but that the project should still be considered for the simple reason that everyone else was going supersonic, and they were concerned they would be locked out of future markets. Conversely, it appeared the project would not be likely to significantly impact other, more important, research efforts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">71</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>After considerable argument, the decision to proceed ultimately fell to an unlikely political expediency. At the time, the UK was pressing for admission to the<space/><link><target>European Common Market</target></link>, which was being controlled by<space/><link><target>Charles de Gaulle</target></link><space/>who felt the UK's<space/><link><target>Special Relationship</target></link><space/>with the US made them unacceptable in a pan-European group. Cabinet felt that signing a deal with Sud would pave the way for Common Market entry, and this became the main deciding reason for moving ahead with the deal.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template><space/>It was this belief that had led the original STAC documents being leaked to the French. However, De Gaulle spoke of the European origin of the design, and continued to block the UK's entry into the Common Market.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Conway</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">66</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The development project was negotiated as an international<space/><link><target>treaty</target></link><space/>between the two countries rather than a commercial agreement between companies and included a clause, originally asked for by the UK, imposing heavy penalties for cancellation. A draft treaty was signed on 29 November 1962.<extension extension_name='ref' name="earlyhist"><link type='external' href='http://www.concordesst.com/history/eh1.html#a'>&quot;Early History.&quot;</link><space/><italics>concordesst.com</italics>. Retrieved 8 September 2007.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Naming</heading><paragraph>Reflecting the treaty between the British and French governments that led to Concorde's construction, the name<space/><italics>Concorde</italics><space/>is from the French word<space/><italics><link><target>wikt:concorde#French</target><part>concorde</part></link></italics><space/>(<template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>kɔ̃kɔʁd</arg><arg>IPA</arg></template>), which has an English equivalent,<space/><italics><link><target>wikt:concord#English</target><part>concord</part></link></italics>. Both words mean<space/><italics>agreement</italics>,<space/><italics>harmony</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>union</italics>. The name was officially changed to<space/><italics>Concord</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Harold Macmillan</target></link><space/>in response to a perceived slight by<space/><link><target>Charles de Gaulle</target></link>. At the French roll-out in<space/><link><target>Toulouse</target></link><space/>in late 1967,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ssccunv"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">https://news.google.com/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="newspaper">Milwaukee Sentinel<space/></arg><arg name="agency">Associated Press<space/></arg><arg name="title">Supersonic Concorde unveiled<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 12, 1967<space/></arg><arg name="page">3, part 1<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>the British Government<space/><link><target>Minister for Technology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tony Benn</target></link>, announced that he would change the spelling back to<space/><italics>Concorde</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benn"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.guardian.co.uk/g2/story/0,3604,1064752,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sonic booms and that 'e' on the end: Tony Benn remembers his role in getting Concorde off the ground<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tony<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Benn<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Guardian,'' 17 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 October 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>This created a nationalist uproar that died down when Benn stated that the suffixed 'e' represented &quot;Excellence, England, Europe and<space/><link><target>Entente Cordiale</target><part>Entente (Cordiale)</part></link>.&quot; In his memoirs, he recounts a tale of a letter from an irate Scotsman claiming: &quot;[Y]ou talk about 'E' for England, but part of it is made in Scotland.&quot; Given Scotlands contribution of providing the nose cone for the aircraft, Benn replied, &quot;[I]t was also 'E' for '<link><target>wikt:cosse#French</target><part>cosse</part></link>' (the French name for Scotland) &amp;nbsp; and I might have added 'e' for extravagance and 'e' for escalation as well!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>McIntyre 1992, p. 20.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde also acquired an unusual<space/><link><target>nomenclature</target></link><space/>for an aircraft. In common usage in the United Kingdom, the type is known as<space/><italics>Concorde</italics><space/>without an<space/><link><target>article (grammar)</target><part>article</part></link>, rather than<space/><bold><italics>the</italics>' Concorde<italics><space/>or<space/></italics></bold>a<italics>' Concorde</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Note this British convention is used throughout this article:<space/><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_depth/uk/2003/concorde_retirement/default.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>In depth: Farewell to Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 15 August 2007<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 August 2007</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/concorde/aboutconcorde.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>About Concorde&nbsp;– main page<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''British Airways''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 January 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sales efforts</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:British Concorde.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright=1.15</part><part><link><target>British Airways</target></link><space/>Concorde in early BA livery at<space/><link><target>London-Heathrow Airport</target></link>, in the 1980s</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>At first the new consortium intended to produce one long-range and one short-range version. However, prospective customers showed no interest in the short-range version and it was dropped.<extension extension_name='ref' name="earlyhist"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An advertisement covering two full pages, promoting Concorde, ran in the 29 May 1967 issue of<space/><italics>Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology</italics>. The advertisement predicted a market for 350 aircraft by 1980 and boasted of Concorde's head start over the United States' SST project.<extension extension_name='ref'>48 years ago in AW&amp;ST, Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology, May 25-June 7, 2015, p.14</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The consortium secured orders (i.e., non-binding options) for over 100 of the long-range version from the major airlines of the day:<space/><link><target>Pan American World Airways</target><part>Pan Am</part></link>,<space/><link><target>British Overseas Airways Corporation</target><part>BOAC</part></link>, and Air France were the launch customers, with six Concordes each. Other airlines in the order book included<space/><link><target>Panair do Brasil</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Continental Airlines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Japan Airlines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lufthansa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>American Airlines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Airlines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Air India</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Air Canada</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Braniff International Airways</target><part>Braniff</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Singapore Airlines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Iran Air</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Olympic Airways</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Qantas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Civil Aviation Administration of China</target><part>CAAC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Middle East Airlines</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Trans World Airlines</target><part>TWA</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="earlyhist"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,903850,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Aerospace: Pan Am's Concorde Retreat<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Time'', 12 February 1973<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>12 February 1973</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Vertrag mit Luken</arg><arg name="url">http://www.spiegel.de/spiegel/print/d-46437753.html</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Der Spiegel]]</arg><arg name="date">13 March 1967</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 November 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>At the time of the first flight the options list contained 74 options from 16 airlines:</paragraph><table class="wikitable sortable"><tablerow><tablehead>Airline</tablehead><tablehead>Number</tablehead><tablehead>Reserved</tablehead><tablehead>Cancelled</tablehead><tablehead>Remarks</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Panair do Brasil</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>Oct 1961</tablecell><tablecell>10 Feb 1965</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Pan Am</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>3 Jun 1963</tablecell><tablecell>31 Jan 1973</tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options in 1964</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Air France</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>3 Jun 1963</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options in 1964</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>BOAC</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>3 Jun 1963</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options in 1964</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Continental Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>24 Jul 1963</tablecell><tablecell>Mar 1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>American Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>7 Oct 1963</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1973</tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options in 1965</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>TWA</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>16 Oct 1963</tablecell><tablecell>31 Jan 1973</tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options in 1965</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Middle East Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>4 Dec 1963</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Qantas</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>19 Mar 1964</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>2 cancelled in May 1966</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Air India</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>15 Jul 1964</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1975</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Japan Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>30 Sep 1965</tablecell><tablecell>1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Sabena</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>1 Dec 1965</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Eastern Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>28 Jun 1966</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1973</tablecell><tablecell>2 extra options on 15 Aug 1966<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>2 other extra options on 28 Apr 1967</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>United Airlines</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>29 Jun 1966</tablecell><tablecell>26 Oct 1972</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Braniff</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>1 Sep 1966</tablecell><tablecell>Feb 1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Lufthansa</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>16 Feb 1967</tablecell><tablecell>Apr 1973</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Air Canada</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>1 Mar 1967</tablecell><tablecell>6 Jun 1972<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Pigott:<space/><italics>Air Canada, the History</italics>. 2014 ISBN 978-1-4597-1952-1. page 104</extension></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Testing</heading><paragraph>The design work was supported by a preceding research programme studying the flight characteristics of low ratio<space/><link><target>delta wing</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The supersonic<space/><link><target>Fairey Delta 2</target><part>BAC 221</part></link><space/>was modified for flight tests of the high speed flight envelope,<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor 1965, p. 130.</extension><space/>the<space/><link><target>Handley Page HP.115</target></link><space/>also provided valuable information on low speed performance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Winchester 2005, p. 134.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Construction of two prototypes began in February 1965: 001, built by Aerospatiale at Toulouse, and 002, by BAC at<space/><link><target>Filton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bristol</target></link>. Concorde 001 made its first test flight from Toulouse on 2 March 1969, piloted by<space/><link><target>Andr Turcat</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pilot Says Concorde Flight "Perfect"<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Montreal Gazette,''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 March 1969<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and first went supersonic on 1 October.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Tops Speed of Sound for 9 Minutes on a Test Flight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 2 October 1969<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2 October 1969</arg></template></extension><space/>The first UK-built Concorde flew from Filton to<space/><link><target>RAF Fairford</target></link><space/>on 9 April 1969, piloted by<space/><link><target>Brian Trubshaw</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/march/2/newsid_2514000/2514535.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>1969: Concorde flies for the first time<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 2 March 1969<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 July 2007<space/></arg><arg name="date">2 March 1969</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/584606362.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde 002 Makes 1st Flight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Chicago Tribune,'' 10 April 1969<space/></arg><arg name="first">Edward<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rohrbach<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 April 1969</arg></template></extension><space/>Both prototypes were presented to the public for the first time on 78 June 1969 at the<space/><link><target>Paris Air Show</target></link>. As the flight programme progressed, 001 embarked on a sales and demonstration tour on 4 September 1971, which was also the first transatlantic crossing of Concorde.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/597531692.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde 001 Makes Its First Atlantic Crossing<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Chicago Tribune,'' 5 September 1971<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 September 1971</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-French Concorde Lands in Brazil to begin Week of Demonstration Flights<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bangor Daily News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>7 September 1971</arg></template></extension><space/>Concorde 002 followed suit on 2 June 1972 with a tour of the Middle and Far East.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Prototype Begins 10-Nation Tour; Britain Shows Optimism For Supersonic Aircraft<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">'' The New York Times,'' 3 June 1972<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="last">Stern<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 June 1972</arg></template></extension><space/>Concorde 002 made the first visit to the United States in 1973, landing at the new<space/><link><target>Dallas/Fort Worth International Airport</target><part>Dallas/Fort Worth Regional Airport</part></link><space/>to mark that airports opening.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Supersonic Concorde Lands in Texas<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 21 September 1973<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="last">Witkin<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">21 September 1973</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde first visit Heathrow Fitzgerald.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Concorde's first visit to Heathrow Airport on 1 July 1972</part></link>While Concorde had initially held a great deal of customer interest, the project was hit by a large number of order cancellations. The<space/><link><target>1973 Paris Air Show crash</target><part>Paris Le Bourget air show crash</part></link><space/>of the competing Soviet<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-144</target></link><space/>had shocked potential buyers, and public concern over the environmental issues presented by a supersonic aircraft&amp;nbsp; the<space/><link><target>sonic boom</target></link>,<space/><link><target>takeoff</target></link>-noise and pollution&amp;nbsp; had produced a shift in public opinion of SSTs. By 1976 four nations remained as prospective buyers: Britain, France, China, and Iran.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Concordes limited to 16<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Virgin Islands Daily News,'' 5 June 1976</arg></template></extension><space/>Only Air France and British Airways (the successor to BOAC) took up their orders, with the two governments taking a cut of any profits made.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/concorde/faq.html#6<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Payments for Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''British Airways''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2 December 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The United States cancelled the<space/><link><target>Boeing 2707</target></link>, its rival supersonic transport programme, in 1971. Observers have suggested that opposition to Concorde on grounds of noise pollution had been encouraged by the<space/><link><target>United States Government</target></link>, as it lacked its own competitor.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Britain and France have wasted billions on the Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 12 February 1973<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Anthony<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lewis<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>12 February 1973</arg></template></extension><space/>The US, India, and Malaysia all ruled out Concorde supersonic flights over the noise concern, although some of these restrictions were later relaxed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Malaysia lifting ban on the use Of its Airspace by the Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">'' The New York Times,'' 17 December 1978<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 December 1978</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>News from around the world<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Herald-Journal,'' 13 January 1978<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Professor Douglas Ross characterised restrictions placed upon Concorde operations by President<space/><link><target>Jimmy Carter</target></link>'s administration as having been an act of<space/><link><target>protectionism</target></link><space/>of American aircraft manufacturers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ross 1978, p. 46.</extension><space/>Concorde flew to an altitude of 68,000&amp;nbsp;ft (20,700 m) during a test flight in June 1973.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concordesst.com/01.html</arg><arg name="title">CONCORDE SST : DEVELOPMENT FLEET : 01</arg><arg name="work">concordesst.com</arg></template></extension><template><target>specify</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde had other considerable difficulties that led to its dismal sales performance. Costs had spiralled during development to more than six times the original projections, arriving at a unit cost of 23&amp;nbsp;million in 1977.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1352927/Is-this-the-end-of-the-Concorde-dream.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Is this the end of the Concorde dream?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daily Telegraph,'' 16 August 2000<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Marston<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>16 August 2000<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>World events had also dampened Concorde sales prospects, the<space/><link><target>1973 oil crisis</target></link><space/>made many airlines think twice about aircraft with high fuel consumption rates; and new<space/><link><target>wide-body aircraft</target></link>, such as the<space/><link><target>Boeing 747</target></link>, had recently made subsonic aircraft significantly more efficient and presented a low-risk option for airlines.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ross 1978, pp. 4749.</extension><space/>While carrying a full load, Concorde achieved 15.8<space/><link><target>passenger miles</target></link><space/>per gallon of fuel, while the<space/><link><target>Boeing 707</target></link><space/>reached 33.3 pm/g, the Boeing 747 46.4 pm/g, and the<space/><link><target>McDonnell Douglas DC-10</target></link><space/>53.6 pm/g.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ross 1978, p. 49.</extension><space/>An emerging trend in the industry in favour of cheaper airline tickets had also caused airlines such as Qantas to question Concorde's market suitability.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gunn 2010, p. 45.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Design</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:ConcordeCockpitSinsheim.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Concorde flight deck layout</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>General features</heading><paragraph>Concorde is an<space/><link><target>ogival delta</target></link><space/>winged aircraft with four<space/><link><target>Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593</target><part>Olympus</part></link><space/>engines based on those employed in the RAF's<space/><link><target>Avro Vulcan</target></link><space/><link><target>strategic bomber</target></link>. It is one of the few commercial aircraft to employ a<space/><link><target>tailless aircraft</target><part>tailless design</part></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-144</target></link><space/>being another). Concorde was the first airliner to have a (in this case, analogue)<space/><link><target>fly-by-wire</target></link><space/>flight-control system; the<space/><link><target>avionics</target></link><space/>system the Concorde used was unique because it was the first commercial aircraft to employ<space/><link><target>Hybrid integrated circuit</target><part>hybrid circuits</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name='elecflybywire'></extension><space/>The principal designer for the project was Pierre Satre, with<space/><link><target>Archibald Russell</target><part>Sir Archibald Russell</part></link><space/>as his deputy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first"><space/>Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Masefield<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Obituary: Sir Archibald Russell<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Independent,'' 1 July 1995<space/></arg><arg name="location">UK<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde pioneered the following technologies:</paragraph><paragraph>For high speed and optimisation of flight:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Double delta</target></link><space/>(<link><target>ogee</target></link>/ogival) shaped wings<extension extension_name='ref' name='deltawing'></extension></listitem><listitem>Variable engine air<space/><link><target>intake ramp</target></link><space/>system controlled by<space/><link><target>digital computer</target><trail>s</trail></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Supercruise</target></link><space/>capability<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.janes.com/transport/news/jae/jae000725_1_n.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rolls-Royce Snecma Olympus<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Janes<space/></arg><arg name="date">25 July 2000<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20131023060458/http://www.janes.com/transport/news/jae/jae000725_1_n.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">23 October 2013<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Thrust-by-wire engines, predecessor of todays<space/><link><target>FADEC</target></link>-controlled engines<extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Droop-nose</target></link><space/>section for better landing visibility</listitem></list><paragraph>For weight-saving and enhanced performance:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mach number</target><part>Mach</part></link><space/>2.04 (~<template><target>convert</target><arg>2179</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg name="disp">or</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>) cruising speed<extension extension_name='ref' name="Frawley_civil"></extension><space/>for optimum fuel consumption (supersonic drag minimum although turbojet engines are more efficient at higher speed<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://ocw.mit.edu/ans7870/16/16.unified/propulsionS04/UnifiedPropulsion8/UnifiedPropulsion8.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Unified propulsion 8<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MIT<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 December 2010</arg></template></extension>) Fuel consumption at Mach 2.0 and at altitude of 60,000 feet (18,000 m) was 4,800 gallons per hour (22,000 L/h).<extension extension_name='ref'>Allen, Roy, Concorde The Magnificent, Airliner Classics, July 2012, p.65</extension></listitem><listitem>Mainly aluminium construction for low weight and conventional manufacture (higher speeds would have ruled out aluminium)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title"><space/>''Concorde''&nbsp;– Choice of a light alloy for the construction of the first supersonic commercial aircraft<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Revue De L'Aluminium<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>316, March 1964<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>111–119<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Full-regime<space/><link><target>autopilot</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>autothrottle</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.emeraldinsight.com/journals.htm?articleid</arg><arg name="title">The Concorde Automatic Flight Control System: A description of the automatic flight control system for the Anglo/French SST and its development to date<space/></arg><arg name="first">B.S.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Wolfe<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1967<space/></arg><arg name="volume">39<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5, 1967<space/></arg><arg name="page">40<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB UP<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1108/eb034268</arg></template></extension><space/>allowing &quot;hands off&quot; control of the aircraft from climb out to landing</listitem><listitem>Fully electrically controlled analogue<space/><link><target>Aircraft flight control systems#Fly-by-wire control systems</target><part>fly-by-wire</part></link><space/>flight controls systems<extension extension_name='ref' name='elecflybywire'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Advances in aircraft flight control<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>Mark B. Tischler<space/></arg><arg name="author">Favre, C.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7484-0479-1<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>219<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CRC Press<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>High-pressure hydraulic system of 28 MPa (4,000&amp;nbsp;lbf/in) for lighter hydraulic components,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde has designed-in reliability<space/></arg><arg name="author">Schefer, L.J.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Hydraulics and Pneumatics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>29, 1976<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>51–55</arg></template></extension><space/>tripled independent systems (&quot;Blue&quot;, &quot;Green&quot;, and &quot;Yellow&quot;) for redundancy, with an emergency<space/><link><target>ram air turbine</target></link><space/>(RAT) stored in the port-inner elevon jack fairing supplying &quot;Green&quot; and &quot;Yellow&quot; as backup.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.svfw.ch/Archiv/ConcordeDev.pdf</extension></listitem><listitem>Complex<space/><link><target>Air data computer</target></link><space/>(ADC) for the automated monitoring and transmission of aerodynamic measurements (total pressure,<space/><link><target>static pressure</target></link>,<space/><link><target>angle of attack</target></link>, side-slip).<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 101.</extension></listitem><listitem>Fully electrically controlled analogue<space/><link><target>brake-by-wire</target></link><space/>system<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035278<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Aircraft Stopping Systems<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1975<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>47<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>10, 1975<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>18<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB UP</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Pitch trim by shifting fuel around the fuselage for<space/><link><target>Center of mass#Center of gravity</target><part>centre-of-gravity</part></link><space/>(CofG) control at the approach to Mach 1 and above with no drag penalty.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb034738<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Fuel Management for Concorde: A brief account of the fuel system and the fuel pumps developed for the aircraft<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>H.G.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Turner<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB Ltd<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>43<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3, 1971<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>36–39</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Parts made using &quot;<link><target>Milling machine</target><part>sculpture milling</part></link>&quot;, reducing the part count while saving weight and adding strength.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb033911<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>British Contribution to Concord Production in France<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1964<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>36<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>8, 1964<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>232–237<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB Ltd</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>No<space/><link><target>auxiliary power unit</target></link>, as Concorde would only visit large airports where<space/><link><target>Ground support equipment#Air Start Unit (ASU)</target><part>ground air start carts</part></link><space/>are available.<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 206.</extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Powerplant</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>220
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>2001concordewingduxfordJM.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>Close up of engine nozzles of pre-production Concorde G-AXDN. The nozzle/thrust reverser design was altered on production aircraft.
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Concordeintake.gif
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>Concorde's [[intake ramp]] system schematics
<space/></arg><arg name="image3"><space/>Concorde Ramp.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption3"><space/>Concorde's intake ramp system
<space/></arg></template><template><target>Main</target><arg>Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde needed to fly long distances to be economically viable; this required high efficiency.<space/><link><target>Turbofan</target></link><space/>engines were rejected due to their larger cross-section producing excessive drag.<space/><link><target>Turbojet</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were found to be the best choice of engines.<extension extension_name='ref'>Birtles, Philip.<space/><italics>Concorde</italics>, pp. 6263. Vergennes, Vermont: Plymouth Press, 2000. ISBN 1-882663-44-6.</extension><space/>The engine used was the twin spool<space/><link><target>Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593</target></link>, a development of the Bristol engine first used for the<space/><link><target>Avro Vulcan</target></link><space/>bomber, and developed into an afterburning supersonic variant for the<space/><link><target>BAC TSR-2</target></link><space/>strike bomber.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wingweb"><link type='external' href='http://www.wingweb.co.uk/engines/Olympus593_MK610.html'>&quot;Rolls Royce Olympus history.&quot;</link><space/><italics>wingweb.co.uk</italics>. Retrieved 15 January 2010.</extension><space/>Rolls-Royce's own engine proposed for the aircraft at the time of Concorde's initial design was the RB.169.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="journal">Flight International<space/></arg><arg name="date">28 June 1962<space/></arg><arg name="page">1018<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1962/1962%20-%201020.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Aero Engines 1962<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The aircraft used reheat (<link><target>afterburner</target><trail>s</trail></link>) at takeoff and to pass through the upper<space/><link><target>transonic</target></link><space/>regime and to supersonic speeds, between Mach 0.95 and Mach 1.7. The afterburners were switched off at all other times.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Rolls Royce/SNECMA Olympus 593 engine operational experience and the lessons learned<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''European Symposium on the Future of High Speed Air Transport''<space/></arg><arg name="author">Ganley, G.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">G. Laviec<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>73–80<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Due to jet engines being<space/><link><target>propulsive efficiency</target><part>highly inefficient at low speeds</part></link>, Concorde burned two tonnes of fuel (almost 2% of the maximum fuel load) taxiing to the runway.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/5195964.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Are the skies turning green?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joe<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lynam<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>19 July 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>Fuel used is<space/><link><target>Jet fuel</target><part>Jet A-1</part></link>. Due to the high thrust produced even with the engines at idle, only the two outer engines were run after landing for easier taxiing.</paragraph><paragraph>The intake design for Concordes engines was especially critical.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://www.sae.org/technical/papers/912180<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Propulsion—Did we get it right? The Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593 Engine reviewed<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SAE International<space/></arg><arg name="author">Ganley, G. A.<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>September 1991</arg></template></extension><space/>The intakes had to provide low distortion levels (to prevent engine surge) and high efficiency for all likely ambient temperatures to be met in cruise. They had to provide adequate subsonic performance for diversion cruise and low engine-face distortion at take-off. They also had to provide an alternate path for excess intake air during engine throttling or shutdown.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Design and Development of an Air Intake for a Supersonic Transport Aircraft&quot; Rettie and Lewis, Journal of Aircraft, Volume 5, Number 6, NovemberDecember 1968</extension><space/>The variable intake features required to meet all these requirements consisted of front and rear ramps, a dump door, an auxiliary inlet and a ramp bleed to the exhaust nozzle.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Concorde A Designer's Life&quot; Talbot, ISBN 978 0 7524 8928 5, plate 4</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As well as supplying air to the engine the intake also supplied air through the ramp bleed to the propelling nozzle. The nozzle ejector (or aerodynamic) design, with variable exit area and secondary flow from the intake, contributed to good expansion efficiency from take-off to cruise.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;An experiment on aerodynamic nozzles at M=2&quot; Reid, Ministry of Aviation, R. &amp; M. No. 3382, p.4</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Engine failure causes problems on conventional<space/><link><target>subsonic aircraft</target></link>; not only does the aircraft lose thrust on that side but the engine creates drag, causing the aircraft to yaw and bank in the direction of the failed engine. If this had happened to Concorde at supersonic speeds, it theoretically could have caused a catastrophic failure of the airframe. Although computer simulations predicted considerable problems, in practice Concorde could shut down both engines on the same side of the aircraft at Mach 2 without the predicted difficulties.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2003/10/21/172657/concorde-special-the-test-pilot-john-cochrane.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Special&nbsp;– The test pilot&nbsp;– John Cochrane<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Flight International]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>21 October 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>During an engine failure the required air intake is virtually zero so, on Concorde, engine failure was countered by the opening of the auxiliary spill door and the full extension of the ramps, which deflected the air downwards past the engine, gaining lift and minimising drag. Concorde pilots were routinely trained to handle double engine failure.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-63710463.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How a Concorde pilot would handle a nightmare failure<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Birmingham Post<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Woodman<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>27 July 2000</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde's Air Intake Control Units (AICUs) made use of a digital processor to provide the necessary accuracy for intake control. It was the world's first use of a digital processor to be given full authority control of an essential system in a passenger aircraft. It was developed by the Electronics and Space Systems (ESS) division of the British Aircraft Corporation after it became clear that the analogue AICUs fitted to the prototype aircraft and developed by<space/><link><target>Ultra Electronics</target></link><space/>were found to be insufficiently accurate for the tasks in hand.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde's thrust-by-wire engine control system was developed by<space/><link><target>Ultra Electronics</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1976/1976%20-%201835.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">1976 &#124; 1835 &#124; Flight Archive<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Flightglobal.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">1976-09-04<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Heating issues</heading><paragraph>Air compression on the outer surfaces caused the cabin to heat up during flight. Every surface, such as windows and panels, was warm to the touch by the end of the flight.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dalton, Alastair.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.scotsman.com/news/transport/supersonic-the-enduring-allure-of-concorde-1-2415088'>&quot;Supersonic: The enduring allure of Concorde&quot;</link>. Scotsman.com, 17 July 2012.</extension><space/>Besides engines, the hottest part of the structure of any supersonic aircraft, due to<space/><link><target>aerodynamic heating</target></link>, is the<space/><link><target>nose cone</target><part>nose</part></link>. The engineers used<space/><link><target>Hiduminium</target><part>Hiduminium R.R. 58</part></link>, an aluminium alloy, throughout the aircraft due to its familiarity, cost and ease of construction. The highest temperature that aluminium could sustain over the life of the aircraft was<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>127</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>°F</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, which limited the top speed to Mach 2.02.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/3951418<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>When the SST Is Too Slow..<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Society for Science & the Public<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Science News<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Eberhart<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>91<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>22, 3 June 1967<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>528–529<space/></arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>3951418</arg></template></extension><space/>Concorde went through two cycles of heating and cooling during a flight, first cooling down as it gained altitude, then heating up after going supersonic. The reverse happened when descending and slowing down. This had to be factored into the metallurgical and<space/><link><target>fatigue (material)</target><part>fatigue</part></link><space/>modelling. A test rig was built that repeatedly heated up a full-size section of the wing, and then cooled it, and periodically samples of metal were taken for testing.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb034143<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concorde takes shape : Test programme and construction proceeding according to schedule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB UP<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>38<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1966<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>38<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4, 1966<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1972NASSP.309..631N<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>309<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Fatigue Tests on Big Structure Assemblies of Concorde Aircraft<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>631<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">NASA<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1972<space/></arg><arg name="author">N'guyen, V.P.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">J.P. Perrais<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Advanced Approaches to Fatigue Evaluation. NASA SP-309</arg></template></extension><space/>The Concorde airframe was designed for a life of 45,000 flying hours.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1967/1967%20-%202250.html</arg><arg name="title">concorde - 1967 - 2250 - Flight Archive</arg><arg name="work">flightglobal.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Owing to<space/><link><target>ram pressure</target><part>air compression</part></link><space/>in front of the plane as it travelled at<space/><link><target>supersonic speed</target></link>, the fuselage heated up and<space/><link><target>Thermal expansion</target><part>expanded</part></link><space/>by as much as 300&amp;nbsp;mm (almost 1&amp;nbsp;ft). The most obvious manifestation of this was a gap that opened up on the flight deck between the<space/><link><target>flight engineer</target></link>'s console and the bulkhead. On some aircraft that conducted a retiring supersonic flight, the flight engineers placed their caps in this expanded gap, wedging the cap when it shrank again.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.seattlepi.com/business/147276_pilot07.html<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Wallace<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Those who flew the Concorde will miss it<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Seattle Post<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>7 November 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>To keep the cabin cool, Concorde used the fuel as a<space/><link><target>heat sink</target></link><space/>for the heat from the air conditioning.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Introduction to Concorde: A brief review of the Concorde and its prospects<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Emerald Group Publishing Limited<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="author">Gedge, G.T.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">M.I. Prod<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>40<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3, 1993</arg></template></extension><space/>The same method also cooled the hydraulics. During supersonic flight the surfaces forward from the cockpit became heated, and a visor was used to deflect much of this heat from directly reaching the cockpit.<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 14.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Air France Concorde (F-BTSD) short-lived Pepsi logojet.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Air France Concorde (F-BTSD) short-lived promotional Pepsi livery (April 1996)</part></link>Concorde had<space/><link><target>aircraft livery</target><part>livery</part></link><space/>restrictions; the majority of the surface had to be covered with a<space/><link><target>Anti-flash white</target><part>highly reflective white</part></link><space/>paint to avoid overheating the aluminium structure due to heating effects from supersonic flight at Mach 2. The white finish reduced the skin temperature by 6 to 11 degrees Celsius.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1967/1967%20-%200821.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">1967 &#124; 0821 &#124; Flight Archive<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Flightglobal.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-15</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1996, Air France briefly painted F-BTSD in a predominantly blue livery, with the exception of the wings, in a promotional deal with<space/><link><target>Pepsi</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4794332.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Is this the colour of the new millennium?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Independent,'' 3 April 1996<space/></arg><arg name="location">UK<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20130516143325/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4794332.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">16 May 2013<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In this paint scheme, Air France were advised to remain at Mach 2 for no more than 20 minutes at a time, but there was no restriction at speeds under Mach 1.7. F-BTSD was used because it was not scheduled for any long flights that required extended Mach 2 operations.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Azul contra rojo<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''El Mundo,'' 5 April 1996<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cristina<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Frade<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Structural issues</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde fuel trim.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Fuel pitch trim</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Due to its high speeds, large forces were applied to the aircraft during banks and turns, and caused twisting and distortion of the aircraft's structure. In addition there were concerns over maintaining precise control at supersonic speeds. Both of these issues were resolved by active ratio changes between the inboard and outboard<space/><link><target>elevon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, varying at differing speeds including supersonic. Only the innermost elevons, which are attached to the stiffest area of the wings, were active at high speed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 78.</extension><space/>Additionally, the narrow fuselage meant that the aircraft flexed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"></extension><space/>This was visible from the rear passengers viewpoints.<extension extension_name='ref' name="popular">Kocivar, Ben.<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=lpiMSzja6W4C&amp;amp;lpg=PA142&amp;amp;dq=concorde%20flexing&amp;amp;pg=PA118#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=concorde%20flexing&amp;amp;f=false'>&quot;Aboard the Concorde SST.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Popular Science,</italics><space/>October 1973, p. 117.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When any aircraft passes the<space/><link><target>critical mach</target></link><space/>of that particular airframe, the<space/><link><target>Center of pressure (fluid mechanics)</target><part>centre of pressure</part></link><space/>shifts rearwards. This causes a pitch down force on the aircraft if the centre of mass remains where it was. The engineers designed the wings in a specific manner to reduce this shift, but there was still a shift of about 2&amp;nbsp;metres. This could have been countered by the use of<space/><link><target>Trim tab</target><part>trim controls</part></link>, but at such high speeds this would have dramatically increased drag. Instead, the distribution of fuel along the aircraft was shifted during acceleration and deceleration to move the centre of mass, effectively acting as an auxiliary trim control.<extension extension_name='ref' name='fueltrim'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035344<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Flight Refuelling Limited and Concorde: The fuel system aboard is largely their work<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB UP<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>48<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>9, September 1976<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>20–21</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Range</heading><paragraph>To fly non-stop across the Atlantic Ocean, Concorde required the greatest supersonic<space/><link><target>Range (aeronautics)</target><part>range</part></link><space/>of any aircraft. This was achieved by a combination of engines which were highly efficient at supersonic speeds,<template><target>refn</target><arg name=""It is the world's most efficient jet engine." -Ricky Bastin, Concorde Engineer<ref name">nova/></arg><arg name="group">N</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"></extension><space/>a slender fuselage with high<space/><link><target>fineness ratio</target></link>, and a complex wing shape for a high<space/><link><target>lift-to-drag ratio</target></link>. This also required carrying only a modest payload and a high fuel capacity, and the aircraft was trimmed with precision to avoid unnecessary drag.<extension extension_name='ref' name='deltawing'></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name='fueltrim'></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, soon after Concorde began flying, a Concorde &quot;B&quot; model was designed with slightly larger fuel capacity and slightly larger wings with<space/><link><target>leading edge slats</target></link><space/>to improve aerodynamic performance at all speeds, with the objective of expanding the range to reach markets in new regions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concordesst.com/concordeb.html</arg><arg name="title">CONCORDE SST : CONCORDE B</arg><arg name="work">concordesst.com</arg></template></extension><space/>It featured more powerful engines with sound deadening and without the fuel-hungry and noisy<space/><link><target>afterburner</target></link>. It was speculated that it was reasonably possible to create an engine with up to 25% gain in efficiency over the Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Propulsion challenges and opportunities for high-speed transport aircraft<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Aeropropulsion,'' 1987<space/></arg><arg name="author">Strack, William<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>437–452<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>This would have given<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>additional range and a greater payload, making new commercial routes possible. This was cancelled due in part to poor sales of Concorde, but also to the rising cost of aviation fuel in the 1970s.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Fuel costs kill Second Generation of Concordes<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alison<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Smale<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Sarasota Herald-Tribune,'' 22 September 1979<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Radiation concerns</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>220
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>ConcordeFuselageSinsheim.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>External view of Concorde's [[fuselage]]
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Concorde passenger cabin.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>[[British Airways]] Concorde interior. The narrow fuselage permitted only a 4-abreast seating with limited headroom
<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde's high cruising altitude meant passengers received almost twice the<space/><link><target>flux</target></link><space/>of extraterrestrial<space/><link><target>ionising radiation</target></link><space/>as those travelling on a conventional long-haul flight.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/travel/healthcosmic/public/en_gb#4<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How much radiation might I be exposed to?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">British Airways<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 January 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name='concradi'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035011<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do;jsessionid</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Electronic safety test replaces radioactive test source<space/></arg><arg name="author">Guerin, D.W.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1973<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>45<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4, 1973<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>10<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''MCB'' UP</arg></template></extension><space/>Upon Concorde's introduction, it was speculated that this exposure during supersonic travels would increase the likelihood of skin cancer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Skin cancer danger linked to stratospheric jet planes<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">St. Petersburg Times<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1 April 1975</arg></template></extension><space/>Due to the proportionally reduced flight time, the overall<space/><link><target>equivalent dose</target></link><space/>would normally be less than a conventional flight over the same distance.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/travel/healthcosmic/public/en_gb<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cosmic radiation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">British Airways<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 January 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Unusual<space/><link><target>Solar variation</target><part>solar activity</part></link><space/>might lead to an increase in incident radiation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Arctowski<space/></arg><arg name="first">Henryk<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1940<space/></arg><arg name="title">On Solar Faculae and Solar Constant Variations<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.'', 1940<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">16588370<space/></arg><arg name="volume">26<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="pmc">1078196<space/></arg><arg name="pages">406–411<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1073/pnas.26.6.406<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.pnas.org/cgi/reprint/26/6/406.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1940PNAS...26..406A<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>To prevent incidents of excessive radiation exposure, the flight deck had a radiometer and an instrument to measure the rate of decrease of radiation.<extension extension_name='ref' name='concradi'></extension><space/>If the radiation level became too high, Concorde would descend below<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>47000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cabin pressurisation</heading><paragraph>Airliner cabins were usually maintained at a pressure equivalent to 6,0008,000&amp;nbsp;feet (1,8002,400 m) elevation. Concordes pressurisation was set to an altitude at the lower end of this range,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/occmed/17.2.47<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://occmed.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/17/2/47.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Human Factors in the Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Occupational Medicine<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Hepburn<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>A.N.<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>17<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2, 1967<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1967<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>47–51</arg></template></extension><space/>Concordes maximum cruising altitude was<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>; subsonic airliners typically cruise below<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>A sudden reduction in cabin pressure is hazardous to all passengers and crew.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Flight Training Handbook<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1980<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 July 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">U.S. Dept. of Transportation, [[Federal Aviation Administration]], Flight Standards Service, 1980<space/></arg><arg name="page">250</arg></template></extension><space/>Above<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template>, a sudden cabin depressurisation would leave a &quot;<link><target>time of useful consciousness</target></link>&quot; up to 1015 seconds for a conditioned athlete.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.theairlinepilots.com/medical/decompressionandhypoxia.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cabin Decompression and Hypoxia<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Wolff<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''PIA Air Safety Publication,''6 January 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>At Concordes altitude, the air density is very low; a breach of cabin integrity would result in a loss of pressure severe enough so that the plastic emergency oxygen masks installed on other passenger jets would not be effective and passengers would quickly suffer from<space/><link><target>Hypoxia (medical)</target><part>hypoxia</part></link><space/>despite quickly donning them. Concorde was equipped with smaller windows to reduce the rate of loss in the event of a breach,<extension extension_name='ref' name='nunn'>Nunn 1993, p. 341.</extension><space/>a reserve air supply system to augment cabin air pressure, and a rapid descent procedure to bring the aircraft to a safe altitude. The FAA enforces minimum emergency descent rates for aircraft and noting Concordes higher operating altitude, concluded that the best response to pressure loss would be a rapid descent.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://rgl.faa.gov/Regulatory_and_Guidance_Library%5CrgPolicy.nsf/0/90AA20C2F35901D98625713F0056B1B8?OpenDocument<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Interim Policy on High Altitude Cabin Decompression&nbsp;– Relevant Past Practice<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Steve<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Happenny<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Federal Aviation Administration,'' 24 March 2006</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Continuous positive airway pressure</target></link><space/>would have delivered pressurised oxygen directly to the pilots through masks.<extension extension_name='ref' name='nunn'></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Flight characteristics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde at Baginton - geograph.org.uk - 156846.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Concorde performing a low-level flypast at an air show in August 1981</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>While subsonic commercial jets took eight hours to fly from New York to Paris, the average supersonic flight time on the transatlantic routes was just under 3.5 hours. Concorde had a maximum cruise altitude of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18,300</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>and an average cruise speed of Mach 2.02, about 1155<space/><link><target>Knot (unit)</target><part>knots</part></link><space/>(2140&amp;nbsp;km/h or 1334&amp;nbsp;mph), more than twice the speed of conventional aircraft.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schrader 1989, p. 64.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>With no other civil traffic operating at its cruising altitude of about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>56000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, dedicated<space/><link><target>North Atlantic Tracks</target><part>oceanic airways</part></link><space/>or &quot;tracks&quot; were used by Concorde to cross the Atlantic. Due to the nature of high altitude winds, these SST tracks were fixed in terms of their co-ordinates, unlike the<space/><link><target>North Atlantic Tracks</target></link><space/>at lower altitudes whose co-ordinates alter daily according to forecast weather patterns (<link><target>jetstream</target><trail>s</trail></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Orlebar p. 84">Orlebar 2002, p. 84.</extension><space/>Concorde would also be cleared in a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>block, allowing for a slow climb from 45,000 to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>during the oceanic crossing as the fuel load gradually decreased.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Shanwick Oceanic Control</target><part>Prestwick Oceanic Area Control Centre</part></link>: Manual of Air Traffic Services (Part 2).<space/><link><target>National Air Traffic Services</target><part>NATS</part></link></extension><space/>In regular service, Concorde employed an efficient<space/><italics>cruise-climb</italics><space/>flight profile following take-off.<extension extension_name='ref'>Orlebar 2002, p. 92.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The delta-shaped wings required Concorde to adopt a higher<space/><link><target>angle of attack</target></link><space/>at low speeds than conventional aircraft, but it allowed the formation of large low pressure vortices over the entire upper wing surface, maintaining lift.<extension extension_name='ref'>Orlebar 2002, p. 44.</extension><space/>The normal landing speed was<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>170</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>0</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schrader 1989, p. 84.</extension><space/>Because of this high angle, during a landing approach Concorde was on the &quot;back side&quot; of the<space/><link><target>Parasitic drag</target><part>drag force</part></link><space/>curve, where raising the nose would increase the rate of descent; the aircraft was thus largely flown on the throttle and was fitted with an autothrottle to reduce the pilot's workload.<extension extension_name='ref'>Orlebar 2002, p. 110.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">"The only thing that tells you that you're moving is that occasionally when you're flying over the subsonic aeroplanes you can see all these 747s 20,000 feet below you almost appearing to go backwards, I mean you are going 800 miles an hour or thereabouts faster than they are. The aeroplane was an absolute delight to fly, it handled beautifully. And remember we are talking about an aeroplane that was being designed in the late 1950s&nbsp;– mid 1960s. I think it's absolutely amazing and here we are, now in the 21st century, and it remains unique."</arg><arg name="sign">John Hutchinson, Concorde Captain</arg><arg name="source">"The World's Greatest Airliner" (2003)<ref>{{cite av media|url</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Brakes and undercarriage</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>200
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>Train d'atterrissage Concorde Musee du Bourget P1020039.JPG
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>Concorde rear undercarriage
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Concorde tail gear.JPG
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>Tail bumper of Concorde G-BOAG at the [[Museum of Flight]] in Seattle
<space/></arg></template>Because of the way Concorde's delta-wing generated lift, the undercarriage had to be unusually strong. At<space/><link><target>Rotation (aviation)</target><part>rotation</part></link>, Concorde would rise to a high angle of attack, about 18 degrees. Prior to rotation the wing generated almost no lift, unlike typical aircraft wings. Combined with the high airspeed at rotation (199 knots<space/><link><target>indicated airspeed</target></link>), this increased the stresses on the rear undercarriage in a way that was initially unexpected during the development and required a major redesign.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.iasa.com.au/folders/Safety_Issues/others/concordespacer.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The real story of Flight 4590: Special Investigation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''iasa.com.au,'' 13 May 2001<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Rose<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Due to the high angle needed at rotation, a small set of wheels were added aft to prevent<space/><link><target>tailstrike</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The rear main undercarriage units swing towards each other to be stowed but due to their great height also need to retract telescopically before swinging to clear each other when stowed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooklands Museum</extension><space/>The four main wheel tyres on each<space/><link><target>bogie</target></link><space/>unit are inflated to 232&amp;nbsp;lb/sq in. The twin-wheel nose undercarriage retracts forwards and its tyres are inflated to a pressure of 191&amp;nbsp;lb/sq in, and the wheel assembly carries a spray deflector to prevent standing water being thrown up into the engine intakes. The tyres are rated to 250&amp;nbsp;mph. The starboard nose wheel carries a single disc brake to halt wheel rotation during retraction of the undercarriage. The port nose wheel carries speed generators for the anti-skid braking system which prevents brake activation until nose and main wheels rotate at the same rate.</paragraph><paragraph>Additionally, due to the high average takeoff speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>250</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg>km/h</arg></template>, Concorde needed upgraded brakes. Like most airliners, Concorde has<space/><link><target>anti-lock braking system</target><part>anti-skid braking</part></link>&amp;nbsp; a system which prevents the tyres from losing traction when the brakes are applied for greater control during roll-out. The brakes, developed by<space/><link><target>Dunlop Rubber</target><part>Dunlop</part></link>, were the first carbon-based brakes used on an airliner.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Design and Engineering of Carbon Brakes<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Royal Society<space/></arg><arg name="author">Stimson, I.L.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">R. Fisher<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>294<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1411, January 1980<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>583–590<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">36383<space/></arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1980RSPTA.294..583S<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1098/rsta.1980.0068</arg></template></extension><space/>The use of carbon over equivalent steel brakes provided a weight-saving of<space/><template><target>Unit weight</target><arg>lb</arg><arg>12000</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 118.</extension><space/>Each wheel has multiple discs which are cooled by electric fans. Wheel sensors include brake overload, brake temperature, and tyre deflation. After a typical landing at Heathrow, brake temperatures were around 300-400&amp;nbsp;C (572-752&amp;nbsp;F).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Droop nose</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Droop-nose</arg></template>Concordes drooping nose, developed by<space/><link><target>Marshall Aerospace</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde nose"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1971/1971%20-%201503.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Droop nose<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Flight International<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>12 August 1971<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>257–258</arg></template></extension><space/>enabled the aircraft to switch between being streamlined to reduce drag and achieve optimum aerodynamic efficiency, and not obstructing the pilot's view during taxi, takeoff, and landing operations. Due to the high angle of attack, the long pointed nose obstructed the view and necessitated the capability to droop. The droop nose was accompanied by a moving visor that retracted into the nose prior to being lowered. When the nose was raised to horizontal, the visor would rise in front of the cockpit windscreen for aerodynamic streamlining.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde nose"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde landing Farnborough Fitzgerald.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Concorde landing at<space/><link><target>Farnborough Aerodrome</target><part>Farnborough</part></link><space/>in September 1974</part></link>A controller in the cockpit allowed the visor to be retracted and the nose to be lowered to 5 below the standard horizontal position for taxiing and takeoff. Following takeoff and after clearing the airport, the nose and visor were raised. Prior to landing, the visor was again retracted and the nose lowered to 12.5 below horizontal for maximum visibility. Upon landing the nose was raised to the five-degree position to avoid the possibility of damage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde nose"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Federal Aviation Administration</target></link><space/>had objected to the restrictive visibility of the visor used on the first two prototype Concordes and thus requiring alteration before the FAA would permit Concorde to serve US airports; this led to the redesigned visor used on the production and the four pre-production aircraft (101, 102, 201, and 202).<extension extension_name='ref'>Owen 2001, p. 84.</extension><space/>The nose window and visor glass needed to endure temperatures in excess of 100&amp;nbsp;C (212&amp;nbsp;F) at supersonic flight were developed by<space/><link><target>Pilkington</target><part>Triplex</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1968/1968%20-%202105.html'>&quot;Triplex in Concorde: The story behind the film.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Flightglobal.com,</italics><space/>1968. Retrieved 7 June 2011.</extension><template><target>clear left</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Operational history</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Concorde aircraft histories</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Scheduled flights</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:British Airways Concorde official handover ceremony Fitzgerald.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The official handover ceremony to British Airways of its first Concorde occurred on 15 January 1976 at Heathrow Airport</part></link><link><target>File:Singapore Airlines Concorde Fitzgerald-1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Concorde in<space/><link><target>Singapore Airlines</target></link><space/>livery at<space/><link><target>Heathrow</target></link><space/>in 1979</part></link><link><target>File:Air France Aerospatiale BAe Concorde 101; F-BVFB@ZRH;23.08.1998 (5888389391).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Concorde in<space/><link><target>Zrich Airport</target></link><space/>in 1998</part></link><link><target>File:Aerospatiale-British Aircraft Corporation Concorde, Air France JP71122.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Air France Concorde at<space/><link><target>JFK Airport</target></link><space/>in 2003</part></link><link><target>File:Air France Concorde Jonsson.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Air France Concorde at<space/><link><target>Charles de Gaulle Airport</target><part>CDG Airport</part></link><space/>in 2003</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Scheduled flights began on 21 January 1976 on the London<link><target>Bahrain</target></link><space/>and Paris<link><target>Rio de Janeiro</target><part>Rio</part></link><space/>(via<space/><link><target>Dakar</target></link>) routes,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035500<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do;jsessionid</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde in Service<space/></arg><arg name="author">Strang, Dr. W.J<space/></arg><arg name="author2">R. McKinley<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>50<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>12, 1978<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MCB UP</arg></template></extension><space/>with BA flights using the &quot;<italics><link><target>Speedbird</target></link><space/>Concorde</italics>&quot; call sign to notify air traffic control of the aircrafts unique abilities and restrictions, but the French using their normal call signs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid</arg><arg name="title">BA Tribute to Concorde. The takeoff scene at the end of the video contains a clip of the ATC communication with the "Speedbird Concorde"<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">British Airways<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 January 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20100531215441/http://video.google.com/videoplay?docid</arg><arg name="archivedate">31 May 2010<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The Paris-<link><target>Caracas</target></link><space/>route (via<space/><link><target>Azores</target></link>) began on 10 April. The<space/><link><target>Congress of the United States</target><part>US Congress</part></link><space/>had just banned Concorde landings in the US, mainly due to citizen protest over<space/><link><target>sonic booms</target></link>, preventing launch on the coveted<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target><part>North Atlantic</part></link><space/>routes. The<space/><link><target>US Secretary of Transportation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Thaddeus Coleman, Jr.</target><part>William Coleman</part></link>, gave permission for Concorde service to<space/><link><target>Washington Dulles International Airport</target></link>, and Air France and British Airways simultaneously began service to Dulles on 24 May 1976.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Safety Regulation of the Concorde Supersonic Transport: Realistic Confinement of the National Environmental Policy Act<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert B<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Donin<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''HeinOnline,'' 1976<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When the US ban on JFK Concorde operations was lifted in February 1977, New York banned Concorde locally. The ban came to an end on 17 October 1977 when the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target></link><space/>declined to overturn a lower courts ruling rejecting efforts by the<space/><link><target>Port Authority of New York and New Jersey</target><part>Port Authority</part></link><space/>and a grass-roots campaign led by<space/><link><target>Carol Berman</target></link><space/>to continue the ban.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>O'Grady<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jim<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Neighborhood Report: The Rockaways; Ears Ringing? It's Cheering Over the Demise Of the Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 27 April 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 April 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>In spite of complaints about noise, the noise report noted that<space/><link><target>Air Force One</target></link>, at the time a<space/><link><target>Boeing C-137 Stratoliner</target><part>Boeing VC-137</part></link>, was louder than Concorde at subsonic speeds and during takeoff and landing.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,915764,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Nation: Smooth Landing for the Birds<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Time,'' 5 December 1977<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 December 1977</arg></template></extension><space/>Scheduled service from Paris and London to New Yorks<space/><link><target>JFK International Airport</target><part>John F. Kennedy Airport</part></link><space/>began on 22 November 1977.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/concorde/aboutconcorde.html#facts_figures<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde facts and figures<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''British Airways''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 January 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1977, British Airways and<space/><link><target>Singapore Airlines</target></link><space/>shared a Concorde for flights between London and<space/><link><target>Singapore International Airport</target></link><space/>at Paya Lebar via Bahrain. The aircraft, BAs Concorde G-BOAD, was painted in Singapore Airlines livery on the port side and British Airways livery on the<space/><link><target>starboard</target></link><space/>side.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde by June: Offer to Qantas<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ross<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Warneke<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Age,'' 25 October 1977<space/></arg><arg name="location">Australia<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name='singaconc'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Singapore Concorde flights<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 14 October 1977<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 October 1977</arg></template></extension><space/>The service was discontinued after three return flights because of noise complaints from the<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>government;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>London and Singapore halt Concorde service<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 17 December 1977<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 December 1977</arg></template></extension><space/>it could only be reinstated on a new route bypassing Malaysian airspace in 1979. A dispute with India prevented Concorde from reaching supersonic speeds in Indian airspace, so the route was eventually declared not viable and discontinued in 1980.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde route cut<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Montreal Gazette,'' 16 September 1980<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Mexican oil boom</target></link>, Air France flew Concorde twice weekly to Mexico Citys<space/><link><target>Benito Jurez International Airport</target></link><space/>via Washington, DC, or New York City, from September 1978 to November 1982.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>French Concorde to Mexico City<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daytona Beach Morning Journal,'' 11 August 1978<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Supersonic Jet flights suspended<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daytona Beach Morning Journal,'' 27 September 1982<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The worldwide economic crisis during that period resulted in this routes cancellation; the last flights were almost empty. The routing between Washington or New York and Mexico City included a deceleration, from Mach 2.02 to Mach 0.95, to cross Florida subsonically and avoid creating a sonic boom over the state; Concorde then re-accelerated back to high speed while crossing the Gulf of Mexico. On 1 April 1989, on an around-the-world luxury tour charter, British Airways implemented changes to this routing that allowed G-BOAF to maintain Mach 2.02 by passing around Florida to the east and south. Periodically Concorde visited the region on similar chartered flights to Mexico City and Acapulco.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-5212185.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Air France offering 'New Year's Eve in Paris.'<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''PR Newswire,'' 2 October 1987<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20121104070406/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-5212185.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">4 November 2012<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>From 1978 to 1980,<space/><link><target>Braniff International Airways</target></link><space/>leased 10 Concordes, five each from Air France and British Airways.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/646052352.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Braniff seeks deal to fly Concorde in U.S<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Los Angeles Times,'' 10 February 1977<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Getze<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>10 February 1977</arg></template></extension><space/>These were used on subsonic flights between<space/><link><target>Dallas-Fort Worth International Airport</target><part>Dallas-Fort Worth</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Washington Dulles International Airport</target></link>, flown by Braniff flight crews.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/647634162.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde flights to Texas Ok'd<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Los Angeles Times,'' 22 June 1978<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">22 June 1978</arg></template></extension><space/>Air France and British Airways crews then took over for the continuing supersonic flights to London and Paris.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde now reaping profits on N.Y. route<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Spokesman-Review,'' 23 November 1979<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The aircraft were registered in both the United States and their home countries; the European registration was covered while being operated by Braniff, retaining full AF/BA liveries. The flights were not profitable and typically less than 50% booked, forcing Braniff to end its tenure as the only US Concorde operator in May 1980.<extension extension_name='ref' name='braniconc'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Braniff to halt US Concorde flights<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Milwaukee Journal,'' 16 April 1980<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde flights between Texas and Europe end; Big Dreams at the start, $1,447 for flight to Paris<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>''The New York Times,'' 1 June 1980<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 June 1980</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In its early years, the British Airways Concorde service had a greater number of &quot;no shows&quot; (passengers who booked a flight and then failed to appear at the gate for boarding) than any other aircraft in the fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Allen, Roy, Concorde The Magnificent, Airliner Classics, July 2012, p.63</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British Caledonian interest</heading><paragraph>Following the launch of British Airways' Concorde services, Britain's other major airline,<space/><link><target>British Caledonian</target></link><space/>(BCal), set up a task force headed by Gordon Davidson, BA's former Concorde director, to investigate the possibility of their own Concorde operations.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%200919.html'>''B.CAL appoints Concorde consultant''.</link><space/>Flight International, 24 March 1979, p. 881.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%201617.html'>''Caledonian reports best results''.</link><space/>Flight International, 12 May 1979, p. 1547.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%202664.html'>''New job for B.CAL Concorde man''.</link><space/>Flight International, 21 July 1979, p. 158.</extension><space/>This was seen as particularly viable for the airline's long-haul network as there were two unsold aircraft then available for purchase.<extension extension_name='ref' name="whitetails"><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%200541.html'>''B.CAL to lease unsold Concorde?''.</link><space/>Flight International, 24 February 1979, p. 517.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde_details"><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%201182.html'>''Tories support B.CAL's Concorde plan''.</link><space/>Flight International, 14 April 1979, p. 1132.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="final_SST"><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%201348.html'>World News.</link><space/>Flight International, 28 April 1979, p. 1286.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One important reason for BCal's interest in Concorde was that the<space/><link><target>British Caledonian in the 1970s#Spheres of influence</target><part>British Government's 1976 aviation policy review</part></link><space/>had opened the possibility of BA setting up supersonic services in competition with BCal's established sphere of influence. To counteract this potential threat, BCal considered their own independent Concorde plans, as well as a partnership with BA.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>High Risk: The Politics of the Air</italics>, Thomson, A., Sidgwick and Jackson, London, 1990, pp. 316317.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cancel_Concorde"><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%202433.html'>''B.CAL drops Concorde plans but asks for Hong Kong licence''.</link><space/>Flight International, 30 June 1979, p. 2331.</extension><space/>BCal were considered most likely to have set up a Concorde service on the GatwickLagos route, a major source of revenue and profits within BCal's scheduled route network;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1971/1971%20-%202766.html'>''BCAL's African Profit ...''.</link><space/>World News, Flight International, 23 December 1971, p. 994.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Caledonian punchbag</italics>, Flight International, 21 March 1987, p. 33.</extension><space/>BCal's Concorde task force did assess the viability of a daily supersonic service complementing the existing subsonic widebody service on this route.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde_details"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cancel_Concorde"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BCAL_Concorde"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%201007.html</arg><arg name="title">1979 - 1007 - Flight Archive</arg><arg name="work">flightglobal.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>BCal entered into a bid to acquire at least one Concorde.<extension extension_name='ref' name="whitetails"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="final_SST"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BCAL_Concorde"></extension><space/>However, BCal eventually arranged for two aircraft to be leased from BA and<space/><link><target>Arospatiale</target></link><space/>respectively, to be maintained by either BA or Air France. BCal's envisaged two-Concorde fleet would have required a high level of<space/><link><target>Airline cost glossary#Aircraft Utilization</target><part>aircraft utilisation</part></link><space/>to be cost-effective; therefore, BCal had decided to operate the second aircraft on a supersonic service between Gatwick and Atlanta, with a stopover at either Gander or Halifax.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde_details"></extension><space/>Consideration was given to services to Houston and various points on its South American network at a later stage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BCAL_Concorde"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BCal_Package"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1979/1979%20-%201711.html</arg><arg name="title">1979 - 1711 - Flight Archive</arg><arg name="work">flightglobal.com</arg></template></extension><space/>Both supersonic services were to be launched at some point during 1980; however, steeply rising oil prices caused by the<space/><link><target>1979 energy crisis</target></link><space/>led to BCal shelving their supersonic ambitions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cancel_Concorde"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British Airways buys its Concordes outright</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde at JFK.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>An Air France Concorde at John F. Kennedy International Airport in 1987</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By around 1981 in the UK, the future for Concorde looked bleak. The British government had lost money operating Concorde every year, and moves were afoot to cancel the service entirely. A cost projection came back with greatly reduced metallurgical testing costs because the test rig for the wings had built up enough data to last for 30 years and could be shut down. Despite this, the government was not keen to continue. In 1983, BA's managing director,<space/><link><target>John King, Baron King of Wartnaby</target><part>Sir John King</part></link>, convinced the government to sell the aircraft outright to British Airways for 16.5&amp;nbsp;million plus the first years profits.<extension extension_name='ref'>Backroom boys&amp;nbsp; Francis Spufford</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name='concewhitele'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/632500842.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The plane fact is, Concorde has broken the profit barrier for the first time<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Chicago Tribune,'' 1 April 1984<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Greenberg<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 April 1984</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>King recognised that, in Concorde, BA had a premier product that was underpriced. Market research had revealed that many customers thought Concorde was more expensive than it actually was; thus ticket prices were progressively raised to match these perceptions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/transcripts/3203_concorde.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>NOVA transcript: Supersonic Dream<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''PBS,'' 18 January 2005</arg></template></extension><space/>It is reported that British Airways then ran Concorde at a profit, unlike their French counterpart.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="title">The Concorde belies those who foresaw its extinction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Philadelphia Inquirer,'' 26 January 1986<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 January 1986</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/2935337.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Why economists don't fly Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Arnold<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 10 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 October 2003</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Between 1984 and 1991, British Airways flew a thrice-weekly Concorde service between London and Miami, stopping at Washington Dulles International Airport.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde to fly Miami-London route<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Miami Herald,'' 24 January 1984<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 January 1984</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cuts ground Concorde from Miami to London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Miami Herald''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 January 1991</arg></template></extension><space/>Until 2003, Air France and British Airways continued to operate the New York services daily. Concorde routinely flew to<space/><link><target>Grantley Adams International Airport</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Barbados</target></link>, during the winter holiday season.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.com/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>After eight years, the Concorde flies to supersonic profit<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Reading Eagle,'' 27 March 1984<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Gregory<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Jensen<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the Air France Paris crash, several UK and French tour operators operated charter flights to European destinations on a regular basis;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/64470984.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Flying via charter off to New Bustle<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Los Angeles Times,'' 23 June 1985<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter S.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Greenberg<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 June 1985</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/474815901.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Supersonic Concorde 10 years in service and still confounding critics<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Toronto Star,'' 18 January 1986<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jay<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Clark<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 January 1986</arg></template></extension><space/>the charter business was viewed as lucrative by British Airways and Air France.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1986/1986%20-%200201.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde money is in charters<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Flight International,'' 25 January 1986<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1997, British Airways held a promotional contest to mark the 10th anniversary of the airline's move into the private sector. The promotion was a lottery to fly to New York held for 190 tickets valued at 5,400 each, to be offered at 10. Contestants had to call a special hotline to compete with up to 20 million people.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.thefreelibrary.com/I+BEAT+20m+TO+LAND+LAST+pounds+10+SEATS+ON+CONCORDE%3B+Joe+grabs...-a061046466'>&quot;I beat 20m to land last pounds 10 seats on Concorde; Joe grabs bargain of a lifetime.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Scottish Daily Record &amp; Sunday (Glasgow, Scotland)</italics>, 13 February 1997. Retrieved: 13 November 2012.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Concorde Flight 4590 crash</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Air France Flight 4590</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On 25 July 2000, Air France Flight 4590, registration F-BTSC, crashed in<space/><link><target>Gonesse</target></link>, France after departing from<space/><link><target>Paris-Charles de Gaulle</target></link><space/>en route to<space/><link><target>John F. Kennedy International Airport</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link>, killing all 100 passengers and nine crew members on board the flight, and four people on the ground. It was the only fatal accident involving Concorde.</paragraph><paragraph>According to the official investigation conducted by the<space/><italics><link><target>Bureau d'Enqutes et d'Analyses pour la Scurit de l'Aviation Civile</target></link></italics><space/>(BEA), the crash was caused by a metallic strip that fell from a<space/><link><target>Continental Airlines</target></link><space/><link><target>McDonnell Douglas DC-10</target><part>DC-10</part></link><space/>that had taken off minutes earlier. This fragment punctured a tyre on Concorde's left main wheel bogie during takeoff. The tyre exploded, and a piece of rubber hit the fuel tank, which caused a fuel leak and led to a fire. The crew shut down engine number 2 in response to a fire warning, and with engine number 1 surging and producing little power, the aircraft was unable to gain altitude or speed. The aircraft entered a rapid pitch-up then a violent descent, rolling left and crashing tail-low into the Htelissimo Les Relais Bleus Hotel in Gonesse.<extension extension_name='ref'>Endres 2001, pp. 110113.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 6 December 2010, Continental Airlines and John Taylor, one of their mechanics, were found guilty of involuntary manslaughter,<extension extension_name='ref'>Cody, E.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/12/06/AR2010120601740.html'>&quot;French court holds Continental Airlines responsible for 2000 Concorde crash&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Washington Post</italics>, 6 December 2010.</extension><space/>but on 30 November 2012 a French court overturned the conviction, saying mistakes by Continental and Taylor did not make them criminally responsible.<extension extension_name='ref' name="conviction_overturned"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nzherald.co.nz/world/news/article.cfm?c_id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>French court overturns Concorde crash conviction<space/></arg><arg name="agency"><space/>Associated Press<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New Zealand Herald<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>30 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>30 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg><arg name="bot">RjwilmsiBot</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the accident, Concorde had been arguably the safest operational passenger airliner in the world in passenger deaths-per-kilometres travelled with zero, but had a rate of tyre damage some 30 times higher than subsonic airliners from 1995 to 2000.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-82753359.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Human Factor Issues Emerge from Concorde Crash Investigation<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Air Safety Week, 11 February 2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 June 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bea.aero/docspa/2000/f-sc000725a/pdf/f-sc000725a.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Accident on 25 July 2000 at La Patte d’Oie in Gonesse (95) to the Concorde registered F-BTSC operated by Air France<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">French Bureau Enquêtes-Accidents (BEA), January 2002<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>145–147<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Safety improvements were made in the wake of the crash, including more secure electrical controls,<space/><link><target>Kevlar</target></link><space/>lining on the fuel tanks and specially developed burst-resistant tyres.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/1442061.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde's safety modifications<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 17 July 2001<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 July 2001</arg></template></extension><space/>The first flight with the modifications departed from<space/><link><target>London Heathrow airport</target><part>London Heathrow</part></link><space/>on 17 July 2001, piloted by BA Chief Concorde Pilot<space/><link><target>Mike Bannister</target></link>. During the 3-hour 20-minute flight over the mid-Atlantic towards Iceland, Bannister attained Mach 2.02 and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>before returning to<space/><link><target>RAF Brize Norton</target></link>. The test flight, intended to resemble the LondonNew York route, was declared a success and was watched on live TV, and by crowds on the ground at both locations.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,29732,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Completes Successful Test Flight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Fox News,'' 17 July 2001<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 July 2001</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first flight with passengers after the accident took place on 11 September 2001, landing shortly before the<space/><link><target>September 11 attacks</target><part>World Trade Center attacks</part></link><space/>in the United States. This was not a revenue flight, as all the passengers were BA employees.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-78118409.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Concorde, 100 BA staff fly over Atlantic<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''United Press International,'' 11 September 2001<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20130516144849/http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-78118409.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">16 May 2013<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Normal commercial operations resumed on 7 November 2001 by BA and AF (aircraft G-BOAE and F-BTSD), with service to New York JFK, where passengers were welcomed by then mayor<space/><link><target>Rudy Giuliani</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde returns<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Ocala Star-Banner,'' 7 November 2001<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Timothy<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Williams<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/1641466.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde 'back where she belongs'<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 6 November 2001<space/></arg><arg name="date">6 November 2001</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Retirement</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Concorde on Bristol.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Concorde's final flight: G-BOAF from Heathrow to Bristol, on 26 November 2003. The extremely high<space/><link><target>fineness ratio</target></link><space/>of the fuselage is evident.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On 10 April 2003, Air France and British Airways simultaneously announced that they would retire Concorde later that year.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/2934257.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde grounded for good<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 10 April 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 April 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>They cited low passenger numbers following the 25&amp;nbsp;July 2000 crash, the<space/><link><target>Economic effects arising from the September 11 attacks</target><part>slump in air travel</part></link><space/>following the<space/><link><target>September 11, 2001 attacks</target></link>, and rising maintenance costs. Although Concorde was technologically advanced when introduced in the 1970s, 30&amp;nbsp;years later, its analogue cockpit was dated. There had been little commercial pressure to upgrade Concorde due to a lack of competing aircraft, unlike other airliners of the same era such as the<space/><link><target>Boeing&amp;nbsp;747</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035646<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do;jsessionid</arg><arg name="title"><space/>New Aircraft: Where are we heading in the 1980s and 1990s<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''MCB UP,''<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ian S.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Macdonald<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>52<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>7, 1980<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0002-2667<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>23–17<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1980<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>By its retirement, it was the last aircraft in British Airways' fleet that had a<space/><link><target>flight engineer</target></link>; other aircraft, such as the modernised<space/><link><target>747-400</target></link>, had eliminated the role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fliengi"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://online.wsj.com/article/SB106504293992222300.html?mod</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Final Boarding Call: As Concorde Departs, so do 3-Man Crews: In New Cockpits, Engineers are seen as Extra Baggage<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Wall Street Journal,'' 2 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Danial<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Michaels<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2 October 2003</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 11 April 2003,<space/><link><target>Virgin Atlantic</target></link><space/>founder Sir<space/><link><target>Richard Branson</target></link><space/>announced that the company was interested in purchasing British Airways Concorde fleet for their nominal original price of 1 (US$1.57 in April 2003) each.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/europe/04/11/biz.trav.concorde/</arg><arg name="title">Concorde not for sale, says BA</arg><arg name="publisher">''CNN,'' 11 April 2003</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 June 2013</arg><arg name="date">11 April 2003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.sfgate.com/business/article/Fabled-Concorde-to-fly-off-into-sunset-British-2622958.php</arg><arg name="title">Fabled Concorde to fly off into sunset / British, French airlines to retire supersonic jet<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''San Francisco Chronicle,'' 11 April 2003</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 June 2013</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="last">Armstrong</arg><arg name="date">11 April 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>British Airways dismissed the idea, prompting Virgin to increase their offer to 1 million each.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.spacedaily.com/news/concord-03a.html</arg><arg name="title">Virgin Increases Concorde Bid<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Space Daily (from AFP article)</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/1433748/Branson-increases-offer-for-Concorde.html</arg><arg name="title">Branson increases offer for Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Daily Telegraph,'' 22 June 2003</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 June 2013</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="date">22 June 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>Branson claimed that when BA was privatised, a clause in the agreement required them to allow another British airline to operate Concorde if BA ceased to do so, but the Government denied the existence of such a clause.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/3005705.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Branson's Concorde bid rejected<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 6 May 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Simon<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Montague<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>6 May 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>In October 2003, Branson wrote in<space/><italics><link><target>The Economist</target></link></italics><space/>that his final offer was &quot;over 5 million&quot; and that he had intended to operate the fleet &quot;for many years to come&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-109201077.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Branson accuses 'sad' Government of washing its hands of Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Western Mail'', 24 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The chances for keeping Concorde in service were stifled by Airbus's lack of support for continued maintenance.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://edition.cnn.com/2003/WORLD/europe/10/30/concorde.nofly.reut/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde not to fly at air shows<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''CNN,'' 30 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 October 2003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.telegraph.co.uk/finance/2855044/Buffett-vehicle-to-follow-in-Concordes-slipstream.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Buffett vehicle to follow in Concorde's slipstream<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Daily Telegraph,'' 15 June 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Edward<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Simpkins<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>15 June 2003<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><template><target>refn</target><arg>Quote: "Airbus, the manufacturer of Concorde, has said it is becoming uneconomic to maintain the ageing craft and that it will no longer provide spare parts for it."</arg><arg name="group">N</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It has been suggested that Concorde was not withdrawn for the reasons usually given but that it became apparent during the grounding of Concorde that the airlines could make more profit carrying first class passengers subsonically.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.thetravelinsider.info/2003/0411.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde: An Untimely and Unnecessary Demise<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Travel Insider,'' 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 January 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>A lack of commitment to Concorde from Director of Engineering Alan MacDonald was cited as having undermined BAs resolve to continue operating Concorde.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.concorde-spirit-tours.com/concorde.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Betrayal of Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Donald L.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Pevsner<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Concorde Spirit Tours''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 January 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Air France</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>220
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>ConcordeCDG.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>Air France Concorde at [[Paris-Charles de Gaulle Airport]]
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Aerospatial Concorde (6018513515).jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>Air France Concorde in [[Sinsheim Auto & Technik Museum|Auto & Technik Museum Sinsheim]]
<space/></arg></template>Air France made its final commercial Concorde landing in the United States in New York City from Paris on 30 May 2003.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde makes Final Flight from Paris to New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Associated Press,'' 30 May 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Laurent<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lemel<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/2952594.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>French Concorde bids adieu<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 31 May 2003<space/></arg><arg name="date">31 May 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>Air France's final Concorde flight took place on 27 June 2003 when F-BVFC retired to Toulouse.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-104484558.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Jetting off<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daily Mirror,'' 28 June 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><link><target>auction</target></link><space/>of Concorde parts and memorabilia for Air France was held at<space/><link><target>Christie's</target></link><space/>in Paris on 15 November 2003; 1,300 people attended, and several lots exceeded their predicted values.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3246326.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>3,500 due at UK Concorde auction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 30 November 2003<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 November 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>French Concorde F-BVFC was retired to Toulouse and kept functional for a short time after the end of service, in case taxi runs were required in support of the French judicial enquiry into the 2000 crash.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.alacrastore.com/storecontent/Business-and-Industry/105669362<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Miscellaneous brief articles&nbsp;– Business & Industry<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Flight International.'' 15 July 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The aircraft is now fully retired and no longer functional.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.tourmag.com/Pourquoi-n-a-t-on-pas-sauve-le-Concorde_a7.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pourquoi n'a-t-on pas sauvé le Concorde?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''TourMag.com,'' 24 March 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>French Concorde F-BTSD has been retired to the &quot;<link><target>Muse de l'Air</target></link>&quot; at<space/><link><target>ParisLe Bourget Airport</target></link><space/>near Paris, unlike the other museum Concordes, a few of the systems are being kept functional. For instance, the famous &quot;droop nose&quot; can still be lowered and raised. This led to rumours that they could be prepared for future flights for special occasions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vafhtk"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>This is not a flight of fancy: Volunteers say Concorde can realise an Olympic dream if BA will help<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Times,'' 31 May 2006<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ben<space/></arg><arg name="last">Webster</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>French Concorde F-BVFB currently rests at the<space/><link><target>Sinsheim Auto &amp; Technik Museum</target><part>Auto &amp; Technik Museum Sinsheim</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Sinsheim</target></link>, Germany, after its last flight from Paris to Baden-Baden, followed by a spectacular transport to<space/><link><target>Sinsheim</target></link><space/>via barge and road. The museum also has a<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-144</target></link><space/>on display&amp;nbsp; this is the only place where both supersonic airliners can be seen together.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://sinsheim.technik-museum.de/concorde-f-bvfb/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Museum Sinsheim<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Museum Sinsheim''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 June 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20100512045534/http://sinsheim.technik-museum.de:80/concorde-f-bvfb<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">12 May 2010<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1989, Air France signed a letter of agreement to donate a Concorde to the<space/><link><target>National Air and Space Museum</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Washington D.C.</target></link><space/>upon the aircraft's retirement. On 12 June 2003, Air France honoured that agreement, donating Concorde F-BVFA (serial 205) to the Museum upon the completion of its last flight. This aircraft was the first Air France Concorde to open service to Rio de Janeiro, Washington, D.C., and New York and had flown 17,824 hours. It is on display at the Smithsonian's<space/><link><target>Steven F. Udvar-Hazy</target></link><space/>Center at<space/><link><target>Dulles Airport</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">Tag for entire paragraph, mainly agreement and other specifics.</arg><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>British Airways</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>220
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>G-BOAB in new home (8472694454).jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>BA Concorde G-BOAB in storage at [[London Heathrow Airport]]. This aircraft flew for 22,296 hours between its first flight in 1976 and its final flight in 2000.
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Concorde at Manchester Viewing Park.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2">BA Concorde G-BOAC in its hangar at [[Manchester Airport]] Aviation Viewing Park
<space/></arg></template>British Airways conducted a North American farewell tour in October 2003. G-BOAG visited<space/><link><target>Toronto Pearson International Airport</target></link><space/>on 1 October, after which it flew to New Yorks John F. Kennedy International Airport.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/thestar/access/417072421.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde's supersonic swan song; Star writer aboard for jet's farewell trip to Toronto Transatlantic sound-breaker a vision of grace<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Toronto Star,'' 2 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Marc<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Atchison<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2 October 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>G-BOAD visited<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link>s<space/><link><target>Logan International Airport</target></link><space/>on 8 October, and G-BOAG visited<space/><link><target>Washington Dulles International Airport</target></link><space/>on 14 October.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-3250817/Final-flight-British-Airways-Concorde.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Final flight: British Airways Concorde lands locally for last time<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Washington Post,'' 15 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first">Tom<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ramstack<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20150510192947/http://goliath.ecnext.com/coms2/gi_0199-3250817/Final-flight-British-Airways-Concorde.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">10 May 2015<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>It has been claimed that G-BOADs flight from<space/><link><target>London Heathrow Airport</target><part>London Heathrow</part></link><space/>to Boston set a transatlantic flight record of 3 hours, 5 minutes, 34 seconds.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-24654137_ITM<space/></arg><arg name="title">Concorde establishes London-to-U.S. record<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''America's Intelligence Wire,'' 9 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20120127041801/http://www.accessmylibrary.com/coms2/summary_0286-24654137_ITM<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">27 January 2012<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>However the fastest transatlantic flight was from<space/><link><target>New York</target></link><space/>JFK airport to Heathrow on 7 February 1996, taking 2 hours, 52 minutes, 59 seconds; 90 seconds less than a record set in April 1990.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FlightSupersonicRecord"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1996/1996%20-%200341.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Supersonic record</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="work">Flight International<space/></arg><arg name="date">14–20 February 1996<space/></arg><arg name="page">5</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="intrepid"><link type='external' href='http://www.intrepidmuseum.org/The-Intrepid-Experience/Exhibits/Concorde.aspx'>&quot;Exhibits: Concorde&quot;.</link><space/><italics>Intrepidmuseum.org.</italics><space/>Retrieved 6 March 2011.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a week of farewell flights around the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>, Concorde visited<space/><link><target>Birmingham</target></link><space/>on 20 October,<space/><link><target>Belfast</target></link><space/>on 21 October,<space/><link><target>Manchester</target></link><space/>on 22 October,<space/><link><target>Cardiff</target></link><space/>on 23 October, and<space/><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link><space/>on 24 October. Each day the aircraft made a return flight out and back into<space/><link><target>Heathrow</target></link><space/>to the cities, often overflying them at low altitude.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/england/bristol/somerset/3238674.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Last Concorde lands<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 November 2003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/3205915.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde enjoys Cardiff farewell<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News.'' 23 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 October 2003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.amazon.co.uk/dp/B0001DI57G<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde&nbsp;– The Farewell&nbsp;– A collection of the final flights of the last days of Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Simply Media,'' 19 April 2004<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>On 22 October, both Concorde flight BA9021C, a special from<space/><link><target>Manchester</target></link>, and BA002 from<space/><link><target>New York</target></link><space/>landed simultaneously on both of Heathrow's runways. On 23 October 2003,<space/><link><target>Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom</target><part>the Queen</part></link><space/>consented to the illumination of<space/><link><target>Windsor Castle</target></link>, an honour reserved for state events and visiting dignitaries, as Concorde's last west-bound commercial flight departed London.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.rockawave.com/news/2003-10-31/Front_Page/028.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concorde Makes A Comeback<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Brian<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Magoolaghan<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Wave of Long Island,'' 31 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>British Airways</target></link><space/>retired its Concorde fleet on 24 October 2003.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jlfin"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A11477-2003Oct24.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Final Concorde flight lands at Heathrow<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jill<space/></arg><arg name="last">Lawless<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Associated Press,'' 26 October 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>G-BOAG left New York to a fanfare similar to that given for Air Frances F-BTSD, while two more made round trips, G-BOAF over the<space/><link><target>Bay of Biscay</target></link>, carrying VIP guests including former Concorde pilots, and G-BOAE to Edinburgh. The three aircraft then circled over London, having received special permission to fly at low altitude, before landing in sequence at Heathrow. The captain of the New York to London flight was Mike Bannister.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/3211053.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>End of an era for Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News''<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 October 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>The final flight of a Concorde in the US occurred on 5 November 2003 when G-BOAG flew from New York's<space/><link><target>John F. Kennedy International Airport</target><part>Kennedy Airport</part></link><space/>to Seattle's<space/><link><target>Boeing Field</target></link><space/>to join the<space/><link><target>Museum of Flight</target></link>'s permanent collection. The plane was piloted by Mike Bannister and Les Broadie who claimed a flight time of three hours, 55 minutes and 12 seconds, a record between the two cities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.seattlepi.com/local/article/Thousands-welcome-Concorde-to-Seattle-1128999.php</arg><arg name="title">Thousands welcome Concorde to Seattle</arg><arg name="work">seattlepi.com</arg></template></extension><space/>The museum had been pursuing a Concorde for their collection since 1984.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://rbogash.com/Concorde.html</arg><arg name="title">Concorde</arg><arg name="author">Robert Bogash</arg><arg name="work">rbogash.com</arg></template></extension><space/>The final flight of a Concorde world-wide took place on 26 November 2003 with a landing at Filton, Bristol, UK.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/bristol/3238674.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>BBC News: Last Concorde lands<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,''<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 November 2003</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>All of BA's Concorde fleet have been grounded, drained of hydraulic fluid and their airworthiness certificates withdrawn. Jock Lowe, ex-chief Concorde pilot and manager of the fleet estimated in 2004 that it would cost 1015&amp;nbsp;million to make G-BOAF airworthy again.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vafhtk"></extension><space/>BA maintain ownership and have stated that they will not fly again due to a lack of support from Airbus.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/concorde/faq.html#17<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Will Concorde ever come out of retirement&nbsp;– e.g. for a Coronation flypast or airshows?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''British Airways''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 January 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>On 1 December 2003,<space/><link><target>Bonhams</target></link><space/>held an auction of British Airways Concorde artifacts, including a nose cone, at<space/><link><target>Olympia Exhibition Centre</target><part>Kensington Olympia</part></link><space/>in London.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.usatoday.com/travel/news/2003-12-02-concorde_x.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Concorde nose cone sells for half-million at auction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''USA Today,'' 12 December 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">2 December 2003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-87889450.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Concorde Memorabilia Auction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Getty Images,'' 1 December 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Proceeds of around 750,000 were raised, with the majority going to charity. G-BOAD is currently on display at the<space/><link><target>Intrepid Sea, Air &amp; Space Museum</target></link><space/>in New York.<extension extension_name='ref' name="intrepid"></extension><space/>In 2007, BA announced that the advertising spot at Heathrow where a 40% scale model of Concorde was located would not be retained; the model is now on display at the<space/><link><target>Brooklands Museum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/6509667.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heathrow Concorde model removed<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News''<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 March 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Restoration</heading><paragraph>Although only used for spares after being retired from test flying and trials work in 1981, Concorde G-BBDG was dismantled and transported by road from<space/><link><target>Filton</target></link><space/>then restored from essentially a shell at the<space/><link><target>Brooklands Museum</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Surrey</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.concordeproject.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Brooklands Concorde Project<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Brooklands Museum''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 January 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of the youngest Concordes (F-BTSD) is on display at<space/><link><target>Muse de l'Air</target><part>Le Bourget Air and Space Museum</part></link><space/>in Paris. In February 2010, it was announced that the museum and a group of volunteer Air France technicians intend to restore F-BTSD so it can taxi under its own power.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.flightglobal.com/articles/2010/02/05/338114/air-france-concorde-to-taxi-again-under-own-power.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Air France Concorde to taxi again under own power<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Flightglobal,'' 5 February 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 February 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>In May 2010, it was reported that the British Save Concorde Group and French Olympus 593 groups had begun inspecting the engines of a Concorde at the French museum; their intent is to restore the airliner to a condition where it can fly in demonstrations.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/8712806.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Work starts in £15m plan to get Concorde Flying<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>''BBC News''<space/></arg><arg name="date">29 May 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 May 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Save Concorde Group hoped to get F-BTSD flying for the 2012 London Olympics, but this never happened. The work for restoring F-BTSD to operating condition as of September 2015 is currently not very well known, and it is still being housed in Le Bourget as a museum exhibit. In 2015 the organisation Club Concorde announced that it had raised funds of 120 million for a static display<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.avweb.com/avwebflash/news/Group-Plans-To-Fly-Concorde-By-2019-224879-1.html</arg><arg name="title">Group Plans To Fly Concorde By 2019</arg><arg name="work">avweb.com</arg></template></extension><space/>and to buy the Concorde at Le Bourget, restore it and return it to service as a heritage aircraft for air displays and charter hire by 2019, to coincide with the 50th anniversary of Concorde's first flight.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/sep/18/supersonic-breakthrough-concorde-could-fly-again-within-four-years<space/></arg><arg name="title">Supersonic breakthrough: Concorde could fly again within four years<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Coldwell<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Will</arg><arg name="date">18 September 2015<space/></arg><arg name="website">[[theguardian.com]]</arg><arg name="access-date">18 September 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July 2015 it was reported that planning permission had been granted for the construction of the museum at<space/><link><target>Bristol Filton Airport</target></link><space/>to house G-BOAF the last Concorde where it is intended to form a key exhibit of the new<space/><link><target>Bristol Aviation Heritage Museum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Concorde museum wins planning permission</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bristolpost.co.uk/Concorde-museum-wins-planning-permission/story-27449949-detail/story.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 July 2015</arg><arg name="work">Bristol Post</arg><arg name="date">20 July 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Return to service plan</heading><paragraph>In September 2015 it was publicly revealed<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.telegraph.co.uk/luxury/travel/83904/concorde-flights-planned-to-resume-and-aircraft-proposed-for-display-in-london.html</extension><space/>that the Concorde Club had secured over 160&amp;nbsp;million to return an aircraft to service.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.dailymail.co.uk/travel/travel_news/article-3239952/Concorde-set-return-skies-Supersonic-jet-used-charter-flights-2019.html</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde Club president Paul James said: The main obstacle to any Concorde project to date has been Wheres the money? a question we heard ad nauseam, until we found an investor. Now that money is no longer the problem its over to those who can help us make it happen.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.clubconcorde.co.uk/potential-return-to-flight-2015.php</extension><space/>The organisation aims to buy the Concorde currently on display at Le Bourget airport. A tentative date of 2019 has been put forward for the first flight - 50 years after its maiden journey.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/sep/18/supersonic-breakthrough-concorde-could-fly-again-within-four-years</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Operators</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Air France</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>British Airways</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Braniff International Airways</target></link><space/>(1 on short term lease)<extension extension_name='ref' name='braniconc'></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Singapore Airlines</target></link><space/>(1 on short term<space/><link><target>wet lease</target></link>)<extension extension_name='ref' name='singaconc'></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Aircraft on display</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Concorde aircraft histories</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Comparable aircraft</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Russian Tu-144LL SST Flying Laboratory Takeoff at Zhukovsky Air Development Center.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Tu-144FL as a research aircraft for<space/><link><target>NASA</target></link><space/>in 1997</part></link><link><target>File:Sinsheim Auto &amp; Technik Museum.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Tu-144 and Concorde in<space/><link><target>Sinsheim Auto &amp; Technik Museum</target><part>Auto &amp; Technik Museum Sinsheim</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The only supersonic airliner in direct competition with Concorde was the Soviet<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-144</target></link>, nicknamed &quot;Concordski&quot; by Western European journalists for its outward similarity to Concorde.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,912014,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Union: Christening the Concordski<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Time,'' 14 November 1977<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 November 1977</arg></template></extension><space/>It had been alleged that Soviet<space/><link><target>espionage</target></link><space/>efforts had resulted in the theft of Concorde blueprints, ostensibly to assist in the design of the Tu-144.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon, Yefim.<space/><italics>Tupolev Tu-144</italics>. London: Midland, 2006. ISBN 1-85780-216-0.</extension><space/>As a result of a rushed development programme, the first Tu-144 prototype was substantially different from the preproduction machines, but both were cruder than Concorde. The Tu-144<italics>S</italics><space/>had a significantly shorter range than Concorde, due to its low-bypass turbofan engines.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/1328132.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>'Concordski' designer dies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 13 May 2001<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 May 2001</arg></template></extension><space/>The aircraft had poor control at low speeds because of a simpler supersonic wing design; in addition the Tu-144 required<space/><link><target>drogue parachute</target><part>braking parachutes</part></link><space/>to land while Concorde used anti-lock brakes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet SST, in Its First Flight to the West, Arrives in Paris for Air Show<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John L<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Hess<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 26 May 1971<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 May 1971</arg></template></extension><space/>The Tu-144 had two crashes, one at the<space/><link><target>1973 Paris Air Show crash</target><part>1973 Paris Air Show</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet SST stalls, dives into towns<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>George<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Deruaz<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''St. Petersburg Times,'' 4 June 1973<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.google.co.uk/newspapers?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pride of Soviet air fleet explodes during exhibition<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Sarasota Journal,'' 4 June 1973<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>and another during a pre-delivery test flight in May 1978.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/latimes/access/659730132.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Russia confirms crash of Supersonic Airliner in test: Latest failure of Trouble-plagued TU-144 seen as blow to Soviet hopes of expanding industry<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Los Angeles Times,'' 27 October 1978<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Fisher<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>27 October 1978</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://aviation-safety.net/database/record.php?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>ASN Aircraft accident Tupolev 144D CCCP-77111 Yegoryevsk<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Flight Safety Foundation<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 July 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Later production Tu-144 versions were more refined and competitive. They had retractable<space/><link><target>canards</target></link><space/>for better low-speed control, turbojet engines providing nearly the fuel efficiency and range of Concorde<extension extension_name='ref' name='rus144'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://en.rian.ru/analysis/20080603/109170103.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Tu-144: the future that never was<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''RIA Novosti,'' 3 January 2008<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>and a top speed of Mach 2.35. Passenger service commenced in November 1977, but after the 1978 crash the aircraft was taken out of service. The aircraft had an inherently unsafe structural design as a consequence of an automated production method chosen to simplify and speed up manufacturing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fridlyander">Fridlyander, Iosif. &quot;Sad Epic of the Tu-144.&quot;<space/><italics>Messenger of Russian Academy of Sciences</italics>, 1, 2002 (in Russian: .. ,<space/><link type='external' href='http://vivovoco.rsl.ru/VV/JOURNAL/VRAN/02_01/FRID.HTM'>&quot; -144&quot;</link>, , 1, 2002.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The American designs, the<space/><link><target>Boeing 2707</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lockheed L-2000</target></link>, were to have been larger, with seating for up to 300 people.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.flightglobal.com/pdfarchive/view/1964/1964%20-%200377.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The United States SST Contenders<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Flight International,'' 13 February 1964<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>234–235<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Winchester 2005, p. 84.</extension><space/>Running a few years behind Concorde, the Boeing 2707 was redesigned to a cropped delta layout; the extra cost of these changes helped to kill the project.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Russians Lead With the SST...<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard D<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lyons<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The New York Times,'' 5 January 1969<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 January 1969</arg></template></extension><space/>The operation of US military aircraft such as the<space/><link><target>XB-70 Valkyrie</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>B-58 Hustler</target></link><space/>had shown that sonic booms were quite capable of reaching the ground,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pqasb.pqarchiver.com/chicagotribune/access/574189232.html?dids</arg><arg name="title"><space/>B-58's Sonic Boom Rattles Kentuckians<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Chicago Daily Tribune,'' 19 December 1961<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 December 1961</arg></template></extension><space/>and the experience from the<space/><link><target>Oklahoma City sonic boom tests</target></link><space/>led to the same environmental concerns that hindered the commercial success of Concorde. The American government cancelled the project in 1971, after having spent more than $1&amp;nbsp;billion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,944291,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Nation: Showdown on the SST<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Time,'' 29 May 1971<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">29 March 1971</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The only other large supersonic aircraft comparable to Concorde are<space/><link><target>strategic bomber</target><trail>s</trail></link>, principally the Russian<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-22</target><part>Tu-22</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-22M</target><part>Tu-22M</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Myasishchev M-50</target><part>M-50</part></link><space/>(experimental),<space/><link><target>Sukhoi T-4</target><part>T-4</part></link><space/>(experimental),<space/><link><target>Tupolev Tu-160</target><part>Tu-160</part></link><space/>and the American<space/><link><target>North American XB-70 Valkyrie</target><part>XB-70</part></link><space/>(experimental),<space/><link><target>Rockwell B-1 Lancer</target><part>B-1</part></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Supersonic transport</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Impact</heading><heading level='3'>Environmental</heading><paragraph>Before Concordes flight trials, developments in the civil aviation industry were largely accepted by governments and their respective electorates. Opposition to Concordes noise, particularly on the east coast of the United States,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,918012,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Here Comes the Concorde, Maybe<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Time,'' 16 February 1976<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 February 1976</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Legal and Environmental ramifications of the Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert M.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Allen<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">J. Air L. & Com., 1976<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>forged a new political agenda on both sides of the Atlantic, with scientists and technology experts across a multitude of industries beginning to take the environmental and social impact more seriously.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://md1.csa.com/partners/viewrecord.php?requester</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Recent studies into Concorde noise reduction<space/></arg><arg name="author">Hock, R.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">R. Hawkins<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''AGARD Noise Mech,'' 1974<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>14<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Aircraft Noise: Federal pre-emption of Local Control, Concorde and other recent cases<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joshua A.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Muss<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''J. Air L. & Com,'' 1977<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Although Concorde led directly to the introduction of a general noise abatement programme for aircraft flying out of John F. Kennedy Airport, many found that Concorde was quieter than expected,<extension extension_name='ref' name="nova"></extension><space/>partly due to the pilots temporarily throttling back their engines to reduce noise during overflight of residential areas.<extension extension_name='ref'>Endres 2001, p 90.</extension><space/>Even before revenue flights started it had been claimed that Concorde was quieter than several aircraft then in service.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1108/eb035013<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.emeraldinsight.com/Insight/viewContentItem.do?contentType</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Reducing noise with type 28 nozzle<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Aircraft Engineering and Aerospace Technology<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1973<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>45<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4, 1973<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>14<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''MCB UP''</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1971 BAC's technical director was quoted &quot;It is certain on present evidence and calculations that in the airport context, production Concordes will be no worse than aircraft now in service and will in fact be better than many of them.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Aviation Daily</italics><space/>18 Feb 1971 p263</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde produced nitrogen oxides in its exhaust, which, despite complicated interactions with other ozone-depleting chemicals, are understood to result in degradation to the<space/><link><target>ozone layer</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>stratosphere</target><part>stratospheric</part></link><space/>altitudes it cruised.<extension extension_name='ref' name='emissions'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1126/science.270.5233.70<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/abstract/sci;270/5233/70<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Emission Measurements of the Concorde Supersonic Aircraft in the Lower Stratosphere<space/></arg><arg name="author">Fahey, D. W.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Science<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>270<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>70<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5233<space/></arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1995Sci...270...70F<space/></arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><space/>It has been pointed out that other, lower-flying, airliners produce ozone during their flights in the troposphere, but vertical transit of gases between the layers is restricted. The small fleet meant overall ozone-layer degradation caused by Concorde was negligible.<extension extension_name='ref' name='emissions'></extension>David W. Fahey, of the<space/><link><target>National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</target></link>, found that to produce a drop in stratospheric ozone of 1 to 2% would require a fleet of 500 supersonic aircraft to be operated. Dr. Fahey stated that this would not be a limiting factor for further<space/><link><target>supersonic transport</target></link><space/>development.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://articles.baltimoresun.com/1995-10-08/news/1995281022_1_ozone-sulfur-exhaust-particles'>&quot;Increase in supersonic jets could be threat to ozone U-2 plane trails Concorde, studies exhaust particles.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Baltimore Sun,</italics><space/>October 8, 1995.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concordes technical leap forward boosted the publics understanding of conflicts between technology and the environment as well as awareness of the complex decision analysis processes that surround such conflicts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://heinonline.org/HOL/LandingPage?collection</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Decision Analysis in Environmental Decisionmaking: Improving the Concorde Balance<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jon<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Anderson<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''HeinOnline,'' 1978<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>In France, the use of<space/><link><target>noise barrier</target><part>acoustic fencing</part></link><space/>alongside<space/><link><target>TGV</target></link><space/>tracks might not have been achieved without the 1970s controversy over aircraft noise.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="publisher">''Environmental Science and Engineering,'' November 2001<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.esemag.com/1101/1101ed.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Train à grande vitesse causes distress<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20100116124028/http://www.esemag.com:80/1101/1101ed.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">16 January 2010<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In the UK, the<space/><link><target>Campaign to Protect Rural England</target><part>CPRE</part></link><space/>has issued<space/><link><target>Tranquillity#Mapping tranquillity</target><part>tranquillity maps</part></link><space/>since 1990.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cpre.org.uk/campaigns/landscape/tranquillity/national-and-regional-tranquillity-maps<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>National and regional tranquillity maps<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Campaign to Protect Rural England''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">25 April 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some sources say Concorde typically flew<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>17</arg><arg>mpgu.s.</arg></template><space/>per passenger (100 passengers were maximum capacity).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concordesst.com/powerplant.html</arg><arg name="title">CONCORDE SST : Powerplant</arg><arg name="work">concordesst.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Public perception</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:ConcordeBG.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Parade flight at Queens<space/><link><target>Golden Jubilee of Elizabeth II</target><part>Golden Jubilee</part></link><space/>in June 2002</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde was normally perceived as a privilege of the rich, but special circular or one-way (with return by other flight or ship) charter flights were arranged to bring a trip within the means of moderately well-off enthusiasts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.alacrastore.com/storecontent/Business-and-Industry/24962872<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>British Airways Concorde is expected to begin flying passengers again in next 6 weeks<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Dallas Morning News,'' 23 August 2001<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The aircraft was usually referred to by the British as simply &quot;Concorde&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_depth/uk/2003/concorde_retirement/default.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Farewell to Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''BBC News,'' 15 August 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 January 2010<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 August 2007</arg></template></extension><space/>In France it was known as &quot;le Concorde&quot; due to &quot;le&quot;, the definite article,<extension extension_name='ref' name="OxLangFrGlos"><link type='external' href='http://www.oxfordlanguagedictionaries.com/Public/PublicResources.html?direction=b-fr-en&amp;amp;sp=S/oldo/resources/fr/French-supp-05.xml'>Oxford Language Dictionaries Online&amp;nbsp; French Resources</link>: Glossary of Grammatical Terms</extension><space/>used in<space/><link><target>French grammar</target></link><space/>to introduce the name of a ship or aircraft,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cnrtl.fr/lexicographie/academie9/le'>Centre National de Ressources Textuelles et Lexicales</link>&amp;nbsp; Dfinition de LE, LA: article dfini, II.3</extension><space/>and the capital being used to distinguish a<space/><link><target>proper name</target></link><space/>from a<space/><link><target>common noun</target></link><space/>of the same spelling.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OxLangFrGlos"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://grammaire.reverso.net/5_2_01_la_majuscule_dans_les_noms_propres.shtml'>Reverso Dictionnaire: La majuscule dans les noms propres</link><space/>(&quot;Capital letters within proper names&quot;)</extension><space/>In French, the common noun<space/><italics>concorde</italics><space/>means &quot;agreement, harmony, or peace&quot;.<space/><template><target>refn</target><arg>'''concorde''' ''s.f.'' concord, unity, harmony, peace.<ref>Ferrar 1980, p. 114.</ref><space/></arg><arg name="group">N</arg></template><space/>Concordes pilots and British Airways in official publications often refer to Concorde both in the singular and plural as &quot;she&quot; or &quot;her&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.britishairways.com/travel/concvidhome/public/en_gb<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Celebrate Concorde: videos<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''British Airways''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 January 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Documentary of British Airways Concorde introduction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''youtube.com''<space/></arg></template></extension><template><target>refn</target><arg>Quote: [[Raymond Baxter]] commentating as Concorde flies for first time: "She rolls ... She flies!"<space/></arg><arg name="group">N</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As a symbol of national pride, an example from the BA fleet made occasional<space/><link><target>flypast</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>at selected Royal events, major air shows and other special occasions, sometimes in formation with the<space/><link><target>Red Arrows</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-62676656.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Red Arrows fly into Scotland<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daily Record,'' 12 June 2000<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.telegraph.co.uk/education/3297816/Million-turn-out-to-crown-Queens-Jubilee.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Million turn out to crown Queen's Jubilee<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daily Telegraph,'' 4 June 2002<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="date">4 June 2002</arg></template></extension><space/>On the final day of commercial service, public interest was so great that grandstands were erected at Heathrow Airport. Significant numbers of people attended the final landings; the event received widespread media coverage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1444939/Chaos-fear-at-Concorde-farewell.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Chaos fear at Concorde farewell<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Daily Telegraph,'' 24 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Sandra<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Laville<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>24 October 2003<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2006, 37 years after its first test flight, Concorde was announced the winner of the Great British Design Quest organised by the BBC and the<space/><link><target>Design Museum</target></link>. A total of 212,000 votes were cast with Concorde beating design icons such as the<space/><link><target>Mini</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mini skirt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jaguar E-type</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tube map</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Supermarine Spitfire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Concorde beats"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.independent.co.uk/uk/this_britain/article351851.ece<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde beats Tube map to become Britain's favourite design<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Louise<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Jury<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''The Independent,'' 17 March 2006<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 March 2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Special missions</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction"><space/>vertical
<space/></arg><arg name="width"><space/>220
<space/></arg><arg name="image1"><space/>Queen Elizabeth II and Prince Philip disembark from a British Airways Concorde.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>[[Elizabeth II|The Queen]] and [[Prince Philip, Duke of Edinburgh|The Duke of Edinburgh]] disembark Concorde in 1991.
<space/></arg><arg name="image2"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>
<space/></arg></template>Heads of France and the United Kingdom flew Concorde many times.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aparchive.com/metadata/Concorde-Clipreel-Part-9/7ece56f04f3cf534e71bd4b4454b8d9e?searchfilter</arg><arg name="title">Concorde Clipreel: Part 9 - AP Archive</arg><arg name="work">aparchive.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://heritageconcorde.com/passenger-experience-2/famous-concorde-passengers-2</arg><arg name="title">Heritage Concorde</arg><arg name="work">Heritage Concorde</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aviation-news.co.uk/archive/concordeChronology.html</arg><arg name="title">Aviation News Magazine - Concorde chronology</arg><arg name="work">aviation-news.co.uk</arg></template></extension><space/>Presidents<space/><link><target>Georges Pompidou</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aparchive.com/metadata/Concorde-Clipreel-Part-8/3e56c7b758bb1e049f6763222b9e93c2?searchfilter</arg><arg name="title">Concorde Clipreel: Part 8 - AP Archive</arg><arg name="work">aparchive.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gettyimages.co.uk/detail/news-photo/french-president-georges-pompidou-at-the-microphone-in-the-news-photo/3375737</arg><arg name="title">French President Georges Pompidou at the microphone in the cockpit of...</arg><arg name="author">Keystone</arg><arg name="work">Getty Images</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Valry Giscard d'Estaing</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.newspapers.com/newspage/29590760/</arg><arg name="title">The Amarillo Globe-Times from Amarillo, Texas · Page 31</arg><arg name="work">Newspapers.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.newspapers.com/newspage/49473870/</arg><arg name="title">The Ottawa Journal from Ottawa, · Page 29</arg><arg name="work">Newspapers.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=9407E6D61F3CE334BC4052DFB366838D669EDE&amp;amp;n=Top%2fReference%2fTimes%20Topics%2fOrganizations%2fC%2fCongress%20'>The New York Times. Giscard Arrives for Talks With Ford</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords/1976/may/27/the-queens-visit-to-north-america</arg><arg name="title">THE QUEEN'S VISIT TO NORTH AMERICA</arg><arg name="work">millbanksystems.com</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Franois Mitterrand</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/7733286/Francois-Mitterrand.html</arg><arg name="title">François Mitterrand</arg><arg name="date">9 January 1996</arg><arg name="work">Telegraph.co.uk</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/1988-11-27/news/mn-1081_1_soviet-space</arg><arg name="title">French Cosmonaut Aboard : Mitterrand Sees a Soviet Space Launch</arg><arg name="work">latimes</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://newspaperarchive.com/kingston-gleaner/1985-09-12/page-9'>Reuter. President Francois Mitterrand prepared today to fly by Concorde</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/1986/07/13/weekinreview/mitterrand-s-travels-are-well-received-back-home.html'>The New York Times. Miitterrand's travels are well received back home</link></extension><space/>regularly used Concorde as French flagman aircraft in foreign visits. Queen<space/><link><target>Elizabeth II</target></link><space/>and Prime Ministers<space/><link><target>Edward Heath</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jim Callaghan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Major</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tony Blair</target></link><space/>took Concorde in some charter flights such as the Queen's trips to Barbados on her Silver Jubilee in 1977, in 1987 and in 2003, to Middle East in 1984, to the United States in 1991, etc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="burleigh2008"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.burleighphoto.com/pages/stk-qe77/qe2.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Queen Elizabeth II Silver Jubilee in Barbados ends with her first flight on Concorde on a record setting flight back to London Heathrow.<space/></arg><arg name="first">Craig<space/></arg><arg name="last">Burleigh<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="at"><space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 January 2010<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="burleigh2008"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Queen Elizabeth II 2010"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.royal.gov.uk/MonarchAndCommonwealth/TheQueenandBarbados/Royalvisits.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">Queen and Barbados: Royal visits<space/></arg><arg name="author">Queen Elizabeth II<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2010<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="at"><space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 January 2010<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concordesst.com/history/00s.html</arg><arg name="title">CONCORDE SST : TIMELINE -90's</arg><arg name="work">concordesst.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.barbadosconcorde.com/'>Barbados Concorde Experience</link>, museum</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link><space/>flew Concorde in May 1989.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.concorde-art-world.com/html/f-btsc.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde F-BTSC - French Production Test Aircraft</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>11 May 2014</arg><arg name="website"><space/>Concorde Art World</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The British Prime Minister flew in a British Airways Concorde (G-BOAC) to<space/><link><target>San Juan, Puerto Rico</target><part>San Juan</part></link><space/>for the second G-6 Economic Summit, held in the United States and hosted by<space/><link><target>President</target></link><space/><link><target>Gerald Ford</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Dorado Beach Hotel</target></link><space/>in Dorado, Puerto Rico on June 2728, 1976.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde sometimes made special flights for its demonstration, for exhibit on airshows (<link><target>Farnborough Airshow</target><part>Farnborough</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Paris Air Show</target><part>Paris-LeBourget</part></link>,<space/><link><target>MAKS (air show)</target><part>MAKS</part></link>, etc.) and other expositions, for taking part in parades and celebrations (as ex., of Zrich airport anniversary in 1998), for private charters (as ex., many times by President of<space/><link><target>Zaire</target></link><space/><link><target>Mobutu Sese Seko</target></link>), for promo-advertising of companies (<link><target>Oki Electric Industry</target><part>OKI</part></link>, etc.), for Olympic torch relays (<link><target>1992 Winter Olympics</target><part>1992 Winter Olympics in Albertville</part></link>), for observing of<space/><link><target>solar eclipse</target></link>, etc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="time.com"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Tharoor</arg><arg name="first">Ishaan</arg><arg name="title">Mobutu Sese Seko</arg><arg name="url">http://www.time.com/time/specials/packages/article/0,28804,2097426_2097427_2097458,00.html</arg><arg name="work">Top 15 Toppled Dictators</arg><arg name="publisher">Time Magazine</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 April 2013</arg><arg name="date">20 October 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shaw<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Karl<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Power Mad!<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>Šílenství mocných<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Metafora<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Praha<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Czech<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>80-7359-002-6<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>47., 58.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concorde-jet.com/e_photos.php?ref</arg><arg name="title">Finding the Right Arizona Insurance</arg><arg name="work">Concorde Insurance</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aparchive.com/metadata/Concorde-Clipreel-Part-14/a1e5b8386694bfb4b427492aaafb6e0e?searchfilter</arg><arg name="title">Concorde Clipreel: Part 14 - AP Archive</arg><arg name="work">aparchive.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="spirit"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concorde-spirit-tours.com/</arg><arg name="title">Concorde Spirit Tours</arg><arg name="work">concorde-spirit-tours.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Records</heading><paragraph>The fastest transatlantic airliner flight was from<space/><link><target>John F. Kennedy International Airport</target><part>New York JFK</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>London Heathrow</target></link><space/>on 7 February 1996 by British Airways' G-BOAD in 2 hours, 52 minutes, 59 seconds from takeoff to touchdown aided by a 175&amp;nbsp;mph (282&amp;nbsp;km/h) tailwind.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SST makes record flight"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="last">Reuters News Service<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>SST makes record flight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''St Louis Post,'' 9 February 1996<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 February 1996</arg></template></extension><space/>On 13 February 1985, a Concorde charter flight flew from London Heathrow to<space/><link><target>Sydney Airport</target><part>Sydney</part></link>on the opposite side of the worldin a time of 17 hours, 3 minutes and 45 seconds, including refuelling stops.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.concorde-art-world.com/html/record_breaker.html</arg><arg name="title">Concorde Supersonic Airliner - Record Breaker</arg><arg name="work">concorde-art-world.com</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://concordesst.yuku.com/topic/4886/List-of-Concorde-Records</arg><arg name="title">List of Concorde Records in Main Discussion area Forum</arg><arg name="work">Yuku</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://news.google.com/newspapers?nid</arg><arg name="title">The Sydney Morning Herald - Google News Archive Search</arg><arg name="work">google.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Concorde also set other records, including the official<space/><link><target>Fdration Aronautique Internationale</target><part>FAI</part></link><space/>&quot;Westbound Around the World&quot; and &quot;Eastbound Around the World&quot; world air speed records.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.allbusiness.com/transportation/air-transportation-airports/7142582-1.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Air France Concorde sets round-the-world speed record<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Business Wire,'' 16 August 1995<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2011</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></extension><space/>On 1213 October 1992, in commemoration of the 500th anniversary of Columbus first New World landing, Concorde Spirit Tours (USA) chartered Air France Concorde F-BTSD and circumnavigated the world in 32 hours 49 minutes and 3 seconds, from Lisbon, Portugal, including six refuelling stops at<space/><link><target>Santo Domingo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Acapulco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Honolulu</target></link>, Guam,<space/><link><target>Bangkok</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Bahrain</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>French Concorde to attempt round-the-world record<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Anchorage Daily News,'' 12 October 1992</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The eastbound record was set by the same Air France Concorde (F-BTSD) under charter to Concorde Spirit Tours<extension extension_name='ref' name="spirit"></extension><space/>in the USA on 1516 August 1995. This promotional flight circumnavigated the world from New York/JFK International Airport in 31 hours 27 minutes 49 seconds, including six refuelling stops at<space/><link><target>Toulouse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dubai</target></link>, Bangkok, Andersen AFB in<space/><link><target>Guam</target></link>, Honolulu, and<space/><link><target>Acapulco</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde jets occupants on record ride<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Deseret News''<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 August 1995</arg></template></extension><space/>By its 30th flight anniversary on 2 March 1999 Concorde had clocked up 920,000 flight hours, with more than 600,000 supersonic, many more than all of the other supersonic aircraft in the Western world combined.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Rolls-Royce SNECMA Olympus<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Janes,'' 25 July 2000</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On its way to the Museum of Flight in November 2003, G-BOAG set a New York City-to-Seattle speed record of 3 hours, 55 minutes, and 12 seconds.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.museumofflight.org/aircraft/concorde<space/></arg><arg name="title">Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Museum of Flight<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 August 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Specifications</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Concordev1.0.png</target><part>right</part><part>400px</part><part>Other line drawings of Concorde</part></link><link><target>File:Concorde G-BOAC.png</target><part>right</part><part>400px</part><part>Concorde G-BOAC</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>aircraft specifications</target><arg name="plane or copter?"><space/>plane
<space/></arg><arg name="jet or prop?"><space/>jet
<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>''Wall Street Journal'',<ref name</arg><arg name="crew"><space/>3 (2 [[Aviator|pilots]] and 1 [[flight engineer]])
<space/></arg><arg name="capacity"><space/>92–120 passengers<space/><br>(128 in high-density layout){{refn|BA and Air France Concordes originally had 100 seats. Due to weight considerations Air France removed 8 seats after the safety modifications of CY2000–2001.|group</arg><arg name="length main"><space/>202 ft 4 in
<space/></arg><arg name="length alt"><space/>61.66 m
<space/></arg><arg name="span main"><space/>84 ft 0 in
<space/></arg><arg name="span alt"><space/>25.6 m
<space/></arg><arg name="height main"><space/>40 ft 0 in
<space/></arg><arg name="height alt"><space/>12.2 m)
* '''Fuselage internal length:''' {{convert|129|ft|0|in|m|abbr</arg><arg name="area main"><space/>3,856&nbsp;ft<sup>2</sup>
<space/></arg><arg name="area alt"><space/>358.25&nbsp;m<sup>2</sup>
<space/></arg><arg name="empty weight main"><space/>173,500 lb
<space/></arg><arg name="empty weight alt"><space/>78,700 kg
<space/></arg><arg name="max take-off weight main"><space/>408,000 lb
<space/></arg><arg name="max take-off weight alt"><space/>185,070 kg
<space/></arg><arg name="useful load main"><space/>245,000 lb
<space/></arg><arg name="useful load alt"><space/>111,130 kg
<space/></arg><arg name="more general"><space/>'''Maximum fuel load:''' {{convert|210940|lb|kg|abbr</arg><arg name="engine (jet)">[[Rolls-Royce/Snecma Olympus 593|Rolls-Royce/SNECMA Olympus 593]] Mk 610
<space/></arg><arg name="type of jet"><space/>Afterburning [[turbojet]]s
<space/></arg><arg name="number of jets"><space/>4
<space/></arg><arg name="thrust main"><space/>32,000 [[pound-force|lbf]]
<space/></arg><arg name="thrust alt"><space/>140 kN
<space/></arg><arg name="afterburning thrust main"><space/>38,050 lbf
<space/></arg><arg name="afterburning thrust alt"><space/>169 kN
<space/></arg><arg name="max speed main"><space/>[[Mach number|Mach]] 2.04
<space/></arg><arg name="max speed alt"><space/>≈1,354 mph, 2,179 km/h, 1,176 knots
<space/></arg><arg name="max speed more"><space/>at cruise altitude
<space/></arg><arg name="cruise speed main"><space/>Mach 2.02
<space/></arg><arg name="cruise speed alt"><space/>≈1,340 mph, 2,158 km/h, 1,164 knots
<space/></arg><arg name="cruise speed more"><space/>at cruise altitude
<space/></arg><arg name="ceiling main"><space/>60,000 ft
<space/></arg><arg name="ceiling alt"><space/>18,300 m
<space/></arg><arg name="climb rate main"><space/>5,000 ft/min
<space/></arg><arg name="climb rate alt"><space/>25.41 m/s
<space/></arg><arg name="range main"><space/>3,900 nmi
<space/></arg><arg name="range alt"><space/>4,488.04 mi, 7,222.8 km
<space/></arg><arg name="loading main">
<space/></arg><arg name="loading alt">
<space/></arg><arg name="thrust/weight"><space/>0.373
<space/></arg><arg name="lift to drag"><space/>''Low speed–'' 3.94, ''Approach–'' 4.35, ''250 kn, 10,000 ft–'' 9.27, ''Mach 0.94–'' 11.47, ''Mach 2.04–'' 7.14
<space/></arg><arg name="fuel consumption"><space/>46.85 lb/mi (13.2 kg/km) operating for maximum range
<space/></arg><arg name="more performance">
* '''Maximum [[Heat shield|nose tip temperature]]:''' {{convert|260|°F|°C|abbr</arg><arg name="avionics">* [[EKCO]] E390/564 weather radar<ref>{{cite web|url</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notable appearances in media</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>Aircraft in fiction#Concorde</arg></template></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>France</arg><arg>United Kingdom</arg><arg>Aviation</arg></template><template><target>aircontent</target><arg name="see also"><space/>
*[[Fairey Delta 2#BAC 221|BAC 221]]
*[[Barbara Harmer]], the first qualified female Concorde pilot.
*[[North American XB-70 Valkyrie]]
*[[Anti-Concorde Project]], Anti-Concorde campaign
</arg><arg name="related"><space/>
* [[Bristol Type 223]]
* [[Sud Aviation Super-Caravelle]]
* [[Fairey Delta 2]]
</arg><arg name="lists"><space/>
* [[List of jet airliners]]
* [[List of civil aircraft]]
<space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Notes</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="group">N</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Citations</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Bibliography</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Conway<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eric<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>High-Speed Dreams: NASA and the Technopolitics of Supersonic Transportation, 1945–1999<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">JHU Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>080188067X<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Beniada<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Frederic<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Minneapolis, Minnesota<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Zenith Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7603-2703-3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Calvert<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Brian<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Flying Concorde: The Full Story<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Crowood Press, 2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84037-352-0<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Deregel<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Xavier<space/></arg><arg name="coauthor"><space/>Jean-Philippe Lemaire<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde Passion<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">LBM, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>2-915347-73-5<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Endres<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Günter<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>St Paul, Minnesota<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MBI Publishing Company, 2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7603-1195-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ferrar<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Henry (ed.)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concise Oxford French-English Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press, 1980<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-19-864157-5<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Frawley<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Gerald<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The International Directory of Civil Aircraft, 2003/2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Aerospace Publications<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-875671-58-7<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gunn<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Crowded Skies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Turnkey Productions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-646-54973-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kelly<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Neil<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concorde Story: 34 Years of Supersonic Air Travel<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Surrey, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Merchant Book Company Ltd, 2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-904779-05-0<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Knight<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Geoffrey<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde: The Inside Story<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Weidenfeld and Nicolson, 1976<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-297-77114-0<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lewis<space/></arg><arg name="first">Rob<space/></arg><arg name="coauthors">Lewis, Edwin<space/></arg><arg name="title">Supersonic secrets : the unauthorised biography of Concorde<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Exposé<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-9546617-0-2<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.co.uk/Supersonic-Secrets-Unofficial-Biography-Concorde/dp/0954661702<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>McIntyre<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ian<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dogfight: The Transatlantic Battle over Airbus<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Westport, Connecticut<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Praeger Publishers, 1992<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-275-94278-3<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Nunn's Applied Respiratory Physiology<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John Francis<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Nunn<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Burlington, Maryland<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Butterworth-Heineman, 1993<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7506-1336-X<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde: Story of a Supersonic Pioneer<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Science Museum, 2001<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kenneth<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Owen<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-900747-42-4<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Christopher Orlebar|Orlebar, Christopher]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concorde Story<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey Publishing, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-85532-667-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ross<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Douglas<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Concorde Compromise: The Politics of Decision-making<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>March 1978<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>46–53<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Schrader<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard K<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Concorde: The Full Story of the Anglo-French SST<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Kent, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pictorial Histories Pub. Co., 1989<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-929521-16-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Taylor<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John W. R.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Jane's All The World's Aircraft 1965–66<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Marston<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1965</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Towey<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Barrie (ed.)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Jet Airliners of the World 1949–2007<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Tunbridge Wells, Kent, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Air-Britain (Historians) Ltd, 2007<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-85130-348-X<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Winchester<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jim<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The World's Worst Aircraft: From Pioneering Failures to Multimillion Dollar Disasters<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Amber Books Ltd, 2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-904687-34-2<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Winchester<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jim<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>X-Planes and Prototypes: From Nazi Secret Weapons to the Warplanes of the Future<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Amber Books Ltd<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84013-815-7<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.britishairways.com/concorde/index.html'>British Airways Concorde page</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.designmuseum.org/design/concorde'>Design Museum (UK) Concorde page</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://heritageconcorde.com/'>Heritage Concorde preservation group site</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.concordelegacy.org.uk/'>Concorde Legacy site</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://aviationweek.com/site-files/aviationweek.com/files/uploads/2015/02/1969-%20First%20Concorde%20Flight%20%281%20of%202%29.pdf'>First Concorde Supersonic Transport Flies</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://aviationweek.com/site-files/aviationweek.com/files/uploads/2015/02/1969-%20First%20Concorde%20Flight%20%282%20of%202%29.pdf'>Concorde Enters Flight Test Phase</link><space/>by Donald Fink,<space/><link><target>Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://aviationweek.com/blog/2003-concorde-end-era'>End of an Era</link><space/>by Dave North, Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Pn0PJc-v510&amp;amp;list=PLNxwX7r4A557deayljDNLqVA7Pl9Y8K9Z&amp;amp;index=14'>Video: Roll-out</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>British Aircraft Corporation aircraft</target></template><template><target>BAE aircraft</target></template><template><target>Sud/Arospatiale aircraft</target></template><template><target>Supersonic transport</target></template><template><target>Good article</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Air FranceKLM</target></link><link><target>Category:British Airways</target></link><link><target>Category:British Aircraft Corporation aircraft</target></link><link><target>Category:Delta-wing aircraft</target></link><link><target>Category:FranceUnited Kingdom relations</target></link><link><target>Category:International airliners 19601969</target></link><link><target>Category:Quadjets</target></link><link><target>Category:Supersonic transports</target></link><link><target>Category:Tailless aircraft</target></link></paragraph></article>