<article title='Archduke_Charles%2C_Duke_of_Teschen'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Archduke Charles of Austria</arg></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="name">Archduke Charles
</arg><arg name="image">Archdukecharles1.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption">
</arg><arg name="full name">Karl Ludwig Johann Josef Lorenz
</arg><arg name="succession">[[Duke of Teschen]]
</arg><arg name="reign">1822–1847
</arg><arg name="reign-type">Tenure
</arg><arg name="predecessor">[[Prince Albert of Saxony, Duke of Teschen|Albert Casimir]]
</arg><arg name="successor">[[Archduke Albert, Duke of Teschen|Albert]]
</arg><arg name="spouse">[[Princess Henrietta of Nassau-Weilburg]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>[[Maria Theresa of Austria (1816–1867)|Maria Theresa, Queen of the Two Sicilies]]<space/><br><space/>[[Archduke Albert, Duke of Teschen]]<space/><br><space/>[[Archduke Karl Ferdinand of Austria|Archduke Karl Ferdinand]]<space/><br><space/>[[Archduke Frederick Ferdinand of Austria|Archduke Frederick Ferdinand]]<space/><br>Archduke Rudolph<br />Archduchess Maria Karoline<br /><space/>[[Archduke Wilhelm Franz of Austria|Archduke Wilhelm Franz]]
</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[House of Habsburg-Lorraine]]
</arg><arg name="father">[[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="mother">[[Infanta Maria Luisa of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date">5 September 1771
</arg><arg name="birth_place">[[Florence]], [[Grand Duchy of Tuscany]]
</arg><arg name="death_date">{{Death date and age|1847|4|30|1771|9|5|df</arg><arg name="death_place">[[Vienna]], [[Austrian Empire]]
</arg><arg name="date of burial">
</arg><arg name="place of burial">
</arg><arg></arg></template><link><target>File:Ernst Ludwig Posselt - Staatsgeschichte Europas - 1805 - Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen - PPL-9046.tif</target><part>thumb</part><part>Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Archduke Charles of Austria, Duke of Teschen</bold><space/>(Karl Ludwig Johann Josef Lorenz of Austria; 5 September 1771 30 April 1847) was an<space/><link><target>Austrian Empire</target><part>Austria</part><trail>n</trail></link><space/>field-marshal, the third son of emperor<space/><link><target>Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Leopold II</part></link><space/>and his wife<space/><link><target>Infanta Maria Luisa of Spain</target></link>. He was also the younger brother of<space/><link><target>Francis II, Holy Roman Emperor</target></link>. Despite being<space/><link><target>epilepsy</target><part>epileptic</part></link>, Charles achieved respect both as a commander and as a reformer of the Austrian army. He was considered one of<space/><link><target>Napoleon I</target><part>Napoleon's</part></link><space/>most formidable opponents.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Eugene Tarle</target></link>, Napoleon.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>He began his career fighting the revolutionary armies of France. Early in the wars of the<space/><link><target>First Coalition</target></link>, he saw victory at<space/><link><target>Battle of Neerwinden (1793)</target><part>Neerwinden</part></link><space/>in 1793, before tasting defeat at<space/><link><target>Battle of Wattignies</target><part>Wattignies</part></link><space/>1793 and<space/><link><target>Battle of Fleurus (1794)</target><part>Fleurus</part></link><space/>1794. In 1796, as chief of all Austrian forces on the<space/><link><target>Rhine</target></link>, Charles out-generaled<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Jourdan</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Battle of Amberg</target><part>Amberg</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Wrzburg</target><part>Wrzburg</part></link>, and forced<space/><link><target>Jean Victor Marie Moreau</target></link><space/>to withdraw across the Rhine, and followed these victories with others at<space/><link><target>First Battle of Zrich</target><part>Zrich</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Ostrach</target><part>Ostrach</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Stockach (1799)</target><part>Stockach</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Battle of Messkirch</target><part>Messkirch</part></link><space/>in 1799. He reformed Austria's armies to adopt the nation at arms principle; in 1809, he went into the<space/><link><target>War of the Fifth Coalition</target></link><space/>with confidence and inflicted Napoleon's first major setback at<space/><link><target>Battle of Aspern-Essling</target><part>Aspern-Essling</part></link>, before suffering a defeat at the bloody<space/><link><target>Battle of Wagram</target></link>. Following Wagram, Charles saw no more significant action in the Napoleonic Wars.</paragraph><paragraph>As a military strategist, historians compare him to<space/><link><target>Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington</target></link>, conservative, cautious, and competent. Charles was a study in contrasts. As a practitioner, he was flawless in executing complex and risky maneuvers of troops in the heat of battle, achieving brilliant victories in the face of almost certain defeat. Yet, as a theoretician, his devotion to ground and caution led his contemporary,<space/><link><target>Carl von Clausewitz</target></link>, to criticize his rigidity and adherence to geographic strategy. Regardless, he remains among Austria's pantheon of heroes of the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic wars.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Youth and early career</heading><paragraph>Charles was born in<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Grand Duchy of Tuscany</target><part>Tuscany</part></link>. His father, then Grand Duke of Tuscany, generously permitted Charles's childless aunt<space/><link><target>Archduchess Maria Christina, Duchess of Teschen</target><part>Archduchess Marie Christine of Austria</part></link><space/>and her husband<space/><link><target>Albert of Saxe-Teschen</target></link><space/>to adopt and raise the boy in Vienna. Charles spent his youth in<space/><link><target>Tuscany</target></link>, at<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link><space/>and in the Austrian Netherlands, where he began his career of military service in the<space/><link><target>French Revolutionary Wars</target><part>wars of the French Revolution</part></link>. He commanded a brigade at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jemappes</target></link><space/>(1792), and in the campaign of 1793 distinguished himself at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Aldenhoven (1794)</target><part>Action of Aldenhoven</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Neerwinden (1793)</target><part>Battle of Neerwinden</part></link>. In this year he became<space/><link><target>List of governors of the Habsburg Netherlands</target><part>Governor of the Habsburg Netherlands</part></link>, an office he lost with the occupation of the Low Countries by the French revolutionaries in 1794. The year he became Governor he also received the army rank of<space/><link><target>Lieutenant Field Marshal</target></link>. Shortly thereafter another promotion saw him made<space/><italics><link><target>Feldzeugmeister</target></link></italics><space/>(equivalent of Lieutenant General). In the remainder of the war in the<space/><link><target>Low Countries</target></link><space/>he held high commands, and was present at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Fleurus (1794)</target><part>Battle of Fleurus</part></link><space/>(1794).</paragraph><paragraph>In 1795 he served on the Rhine, and in the following year was entrusted with chief control of all the Austrian forces on that river. His conduct of the operations against<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Jourdan</target><part>Jourdan</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jean Victor Marie Moreau</target><part>Moreau</part></link><space/>in 1796 marked him out at once as one of the greatest generals in Europe. At first falling back carefully and avoiding a decision, he finally marched away, leaving a mere screen in front of Moreau. Falling upon Jourdan, he beat him in the battles of<space/><link><target>Battle of Amberg</target><part>Amberg</part></link><space/>(August) and<space/><link><target>Battle of Wrzburg</target><part>Wrzburg</part></link><space/>(September), and drove him over the Rhine with great loss. He then turned upon Moreau's army, which he defeated and forced out of Germany (<link><target>Battle of Emmendingen</target></link>, October).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Napoleonic Wars</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Johann Peter Krafft 003.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>Victorious Archduke Charles of Austria during the<space/><link><target>Battle of Aspern-Essling</target></link><space/>(2122 May 1809).</part></link><template><target>See also</target><arg>Imperial and Royal Army during the Napoleonic Wars</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1797 he was sent to arrest the victorious march of<space/><link><target>Napoleon</target><part>General Bonaparte</part></link><space/>in Italy, and he conducted the retreat of the over-matched Austrians with the highest skill. In the campaign of 1799 he once more opposed<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Jourdan</target><part>Jourdan</part></link>, whom he defeated in the battles of<space/><link><target>Battle of Ostrach</target><part>Ostrach</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Stockach (1799)</target><part>Stockach</part></link>, following up his success by invading<space/><link><target>Helvetic Republic</target><part>Switzerland</part></link><space/>and defeating<space/><link><target>Andr Massna</target><part>Massna</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>First Battle of Zurich</target></link>, after which he re-entered Germany and drove the French once more over the Rhine.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="authorlink">Gunther E. Rothenberg<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gunther E.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rothenberg
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Napoleon’s Great Adversaries: Archduke Charles and the Austrian Army 1792–1914
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Spellmount, Stroud<space/></arg><arg name="location">Gloucester<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ill-health, however, forced him to retire to<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Bohemia</target><part>Bohemia</part></link>, but he was soon recalled to undertake the task of checking Moreau's advance on Vienna. The result of the<space/><link><target>Battle of Hohenlinden</target></link><space/>had, however, foredoomed the attempt, and the archduke had to make the armistice of<space/><link><target>Steyr</target></link>. His popularity was now such that the<space/><link><target>Perpetual Diet of Regensburg</target></link>, which met in 1802, resolved to erect a statue in his honor and to give him the title of savior of his country, but Charles refused both distinctions.</paragraph><paragraph>In the short and disastrous war of 1805 Archduke Charles commanded what was intended to be the main army in Italy, but events made Germany the decisive theatre of operations; Austria sustained defeat on the<space/><link><target>Danube</target></link>, and the archduke was defeated by Massena in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Caldiero (1805)</target><part>Battle of Caldiero</part></link>. With the conclusion of peace he began his active work of army reorganization, which was first tested on the field in 1809.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1806 Francis II (now Francis I of Austria) named the Archduke Charles, already a<space/><link><target>Field Marshal (Germany)</target><part>field marshal</part></link>, as Commander in Chief of the Austrian army and Head of the<space/><link><target>Council of War (Austria)</target><part>Council of War</part></link>. Supported by the prestige of being the only general who had proved capable of defeating the French, he promptly initiated a far-reaching scheme of reform, which replaced the obsolete methods of the 18th century. The chief characteristics of the new order were the adoption of the nation in arms principle and the adoption of French war organization and tactics. The army reforms were not yet completed by the war of 1809, in which Charles acted as commander in chief, yet even so it proved a far more formidable opponent than the old and was only defeated after a desperate struggle involving Austrian victories and large loss of life on both sides.</paragraph><paragraph>Its initial successes were neutralized by the reverses of<space/><link><target>Battle of Abensberg</target><part>Abensberg</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Landshut (1809)</target><part>Landshut</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Eckmhl</target><part>Eckmhl</part></link><space/>but, after the evacuation of Vienna, the archduke won a strong victory at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Aspern-Essling</target></link><space/>but soon afterwards lost at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Wagram</target></link>. At the end of the campaign the archduke gave up all his military offices.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later life</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Karl AustriaTeschen Henriette NassauWeilburg.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Archduke Charles with family.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>When Austria joined the ranks of the allies during the<space/><link><target>War of the Sixth Coalition</target></link>, Charles was not given a command and the post of commander-in-chief of the allied Grand Army of Bohemia went to the<space/><link><target>Karl Philipp, Prince of Schwarzenberg</target><part>Prince of Schwarzenberg</part></link>. Charles spent the rest of his life in retirement, except for a short time in 1815 when he was military governor of the<space/><link><target>Fortress Mainz</target></link>. In 1822 he succeeded to the duchy of Saxe-Teschen.</paragraph><paragraph>On 15 September/17 September 1815 in<space/><link><target>Weilburg</target></link>, Charles married Princess<space/><link><target>Henrietta of Nassau-Weilburg</target></link><space/>(17971829). She was a daughter of<space/><link><target>Frederick William of Nassau-Weilburg</target></link><space/>(17681816) and his wife<space/><link><target>Burgravine Louise Isabelle of Kirchberg</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Frederick William was the eldest surviving son of<space/><link><target>Karl Christian of Nassau-Weilburg</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Princess Wilhelmine Carolina of Orange-Nassau</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Wilhelmine Carolina was a daughter of<space/><link><target>William IV, Prince of Orange</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Anne, Princess Royal and Princess of Orange</target></link>. Anne was in turn the eldest daughter of<space/><link><target>George II of Great Britain</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Caroline of Ansbach</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Charles died at<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link><space/>on 30 April 1847. He is buried in tomb 122 in the<space/><link><target>Imperial Crypt Vaults#The New Vault</target><part>New Vault</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Imperial Crypt</target></link><space/>in Vienna.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.napoleon-empire.com/personalities/archiduc_charles.php'>Archduke Charles' short biography</link><space/>in Napoleon &amp; Empire website, displaying a photograph of his tomb in Vienna</extension><space/>An equestrian statue was erected to his memory on the<space/><link><target>Heldenplatz</target></link><space/>in Vienna in 1860.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Assessment of his achievements</heading><paragraph>The caution which the<space/><link><target>archduke</target></link><space/>preached so earnestly in his strategic works, he displayed in practice only when the situation seemed to demand it, though his education certainly prejudiced him in favor of the defensive at all costs. He was at the same time capable of forming and executing the most daring offensive strategy, and his tactical skill in the handling of troops, whether in wide turning movements, as at Wrzburg and Zrich, or in masses, as at Aspern and Wagram, was certainly equal to that of any leader of his time, with only a few exceptions.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Archduke Charles at Battle of Ostrach.JPG</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>230px</part><part>Archduke Charles at the Battle of Ostrach</part></link>His<space/><link><target>military campaign</target><part>campaign</part></link><space/>of 1796 is considered almost faultless. That he sustained defeat in 1809 was due in part to the great numerical superiority of the French and their allies, and in part to the condition of his newly reorganized troops. His six weeks' inaction after the victory of Aspern is, however, open to unfavorable criticism. As a military writer, his position in the evolution of the art of war is very important, and his doctrines had naturally the greatest weight. Nevertheless they cannot but be considered antiquated even in 1806. Caution and the importance of strategic points are the chief features of his system. The rigidity of his geographical strategy may be gathered from the prescription that this principle is never to be departed from.</paragraph><paragraph>Again and again he repeats the advice that nothing should be hazarded unless one's army is completely secure, a rule which he himself neglected with such brilliant results in 1796. Strategic points, he says, not the defeat of the enemy's army, decide the fate of one's own country, and must constantly remain the general's main concern, a<space/><link><target>Maxim (philosophy)</target><part>maxim</part></link><space/>which was never more remarkably disproved than in the war of 1809. The editor of the archduke's work is able to make but a feeble defense against<space/><link><target>Carl von Clausewitz</target><part>Clausewitz</part></link>'s reproach that Charles attached more value to ground than to the annihilation of the foe. In his tactical writings the same spirit is conspicuous. His reserve in battle is designed to cover a retreat.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Archduke Charles Statue.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part>right</part><part>Statue of Archduke Charles on the<space/><link><target>Heldenplatz</target></link><space/>in Vienna</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The baneful influence of these antiquated principles was clearly shown in the maintenance of<space/><link><target>Battle of Kniggrtz</target><part>Kniggrtz-Josefstadt</part></link><space/>in 1866 as a strategic point, which was preferred to the defeat of the separated Prussian armies, and in the strange plans produced in Vienna for the campaign of 1859, and in the almost unintelligible<space/><link><target>Battle of Montebello (1859)</target><part>Battle of Montebello</part></link><space/>in the same year. The theory and the practice of Archduke Charles form one of the most curious contrasts in military history. In the one he is unreal, in the other he displayed, along with the greatest skill, a vivid activity which made him for long the most formidable opponent of Napoleon.</paragraph><paragraph>On the battlefield, it is probably fair to say, Charles was comparable in skill and style to Sir<space/><link><target>Arthur Wellesley, 1st Duke of Wellington</target></link><space/>- quite conservative and yet exceedingly competent. Wellington is better-known to posterity, because he led one of the two Allied armies at the final decisive victory of the Napoleonic Wars (the battle of Waterloo in 1815), although Wellington's superior reputation is perhaps also because he only once faced Napoleon, whereas Charles was confronted by Napoleon in battle more times than any other commander. On these occasions the reliable and yet unimaginative tactics Charles was fond of were not sufficient, except on one occasion at Aspern-Essling, to defeat the unpredictable<space/><link><target>Corsica</target><trail>n</trail></link>. Nonetheless Charles is a member of a<space/><link><target>pantheon (gods)</target><part>pantheon</part></link><space/>of famous Napoleonic figures that includes the Emperor himself,<space/><link><target>Louis-Nicolas Davout</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andr Massna</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Karl Philipp, Prince of Schwarzenberg</target><part>Karl von Schwarzenberg</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Mikhail Kutuzov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gebhard Leberecht von Blcher</target></link><space/>and the aforementioned Duke of Wellington.</paragraph><paragraph>He was the 831st<space/><link><target>Knight</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Order of the Golden Fleece</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Austrian Empire</target><part>Austria</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Issue</heading><table class="wikitable sortable"><tablerow><tablehead width="250">Name</tablehead><tablehead width="125">Birth</tablehead><tablehead width="125">Death</tablehead><tablehead class="unsortable">Notes</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Maria Theresa of Austria (1816-1867)</target><part>Archduchess Maria Theresa of Austria</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>31 July 1816</tablecell><tablecell>8 August 1867</tablecell><tablecell>Married<space/><link><target>Ferdinand II of the Two Sicilies</target></link>, had issue.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Archduke Albert, Duke of Teschen</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>3 August 1817</tablecell><tablecell>2 February 1895</tablecell><tablecell>Married<space/><link><target>Princess Hildegard of Bavaria</target></link>, had issue.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Karl Ferdinand, Archduke of Austria</target><part>Archduke Karl Ferdinand</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>29 July 1818</tablecell><tablecell>20 November 1874</tablecell><tablecell>Married<space/><link><target>Archduchess Elisabeth Franziska of Austria</target></link>, had issue.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Archduke Frederick Ferdinand of Austria</target><part>Archduke Frederick Ferdinand</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>14 May 1821</tablecell><tablecell>5 October 1847</tablecell><tablecell>Died unmarried.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Archduke Rudolph of Austria</tablecell><tablecell>25 September 1822</tablecell><tablecell>11 October 1822</tablecell><tablecell>Died in childhood.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Archduchess Maria Karoline of Austria (1825-1915)</target><part>Archduchess Maria Karoline of Austria</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>10 September 1825</tablecell><tablecell>17 July 1915</tablecell><tablecell>Married her first cousin<space/><link><target>Archduke Rainer Ferdinand of Austria</target><part>Archduke Rainer of Austria</part></link>, third son of<space/><link><target>Archduke Rainer Joseph of Austria</target><part>Archduke Rainer of Austria</part></link><space/>and Princess Elisabeth of Savoy-Carignano.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Archduke Wilhelm Franz of Austria (1827-1894)</target><part>Archduke Wilhelm of Austria</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>21 April 1827</tablecell><tablecell>29 July 1894</tablecell><tablecell>Died unmarried.</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Ancestry</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">July 2015<space/></arg></template><template><target>ahnentafel top</target><arg name="width">100%</arg></template><xhtml:center><template><target>ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen'''
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. [[Leopold II, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. [[Infanta Maria Luisa of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[Francis I, Holy Roman Emperor]]<br>Francis III Stephen, Duke of Lorraine
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. [[Maria Theresa of Austria|Maria Theresa of Austria<br>Queen of Hungary & Bohemia]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3"><space/>6. [[Charles III of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4"><space/>7. [[Maria Amalia of Saxony]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[Leopold, Duke of Lorraine]]
</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. [[Élisabeth Charlotte of Orléans|Princess Élisabeth Charlotte of Orléans]]
</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. [[Elisabeth Christine of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel]]
</arg><arg name="4"><space/>12. [[Philip V of Spain]]
</arg><arg name="5"><space/>13. [[Elisabeth of Parma]]
</arg><arg name="6"><space/>14. [[Augustus III of Poland]]<br>Elector of Saxony
</arg><arg name="7"><space/>15. [[Maria Josepha of Austria]]
</arg><arg name="8"><space/>16. [[Charles V, Duke of Lorraine]]
</arg><arg name="9"><space/>17. [[Eleonora Maria Josefa of Austria]]<br>Queen Dowager of Poland-Lithuania
</arg><arg name="10"><space/>18. [[Philippe I, Duke of Orléans]]
</arg><arg name="11"><space/>19. [[Elizabeth Charlotte, Princess Palatine|Countess Palatine Elizabeth Charlotte of Simmern]]
</arg><arg name="12"><space/>20. [[Leopold I, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="13"><space/>21. [[Eleonore-Magdalena of Neuburg]]
</arg><arg name="14"><space/>22. [[Louis Rudolph, Duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg|Louis Rudolph, Duke of Brunswick-Wolfenbüttel]]
</arg><arg name="15"><space/>23. [[Princess Christine Louise of Oettingen-Oettingen]]
</arg><arg name="16"><space/>24. [[Louis, Dauphin of France (1661-1711)|Louis, Dauphin of France]]
</arg><arg name="17"><space/>25. [[Maria Anna of Bavaria (1660-1690)|Duchess Maria Anna of Bavaria]]
</arg><arg name="18"><space/>26. [[Odoardo II Farnese|Edward II Farnese, Duke of Parma]]
</arg><arg name="19"><space/>27. [[Dorothea Sophie of Neuburg|Countess Palatine Dorothea Sophie of Neuburg]]
</arg><arg name="20"><space/>28. [[Augustus II of Poland]]<br>Elector of Saxony
</arg><arg name="21"><space/>29. [[Christiane Eberhardine of Brandenburg-Bayreuth]]
</arg><arg name="22"><space/>30. [[Joseph I, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="23"><space/>31. [[Wilhelmina Amalia of Brunswick|Wilhelmina Amalia of Brunswick-Calenberg]]
</arg><arg name="24"><space/>24. [[Louis, Dauphin of France (1661-1711)|Louis, Dauphin of France]]
</arg><arg name="25"><space/>25. [[Maria Anna of Bavaria (1660-1690)|Duchess Maria Anna of Bavaria]]
</arg><arg name="26"><space/>26. [[Odoardo II Farnese|Edward II Farnese, Duke of Parma]]
</arg><arg name="27"><space/>27. [[Dorothea Sophie of Neuburg|Countess Palatine Dorothea Sophie of Neuburg]]
</arg><arg name="28"><space/>28. [[Augustus II of Poland]]<br>Elector of Saxony
</arg><arg name="29"><space/>29. [[Christiane Eberhardine of Brandenburg-Bayreuth]]
</arg><arg name="30"><space/>30. [[Joseph I, Holy Roman Emperor]]
</arg><arg name="31"><space/>31. [[Wilhelmina Amalia of Brunswick|Wilhelmina Amalia of Brunswick-Calenberg]]
</arg></template><template><target>ahnentafel bottom</target></template></xhtml:center></paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Grundstze der Kriegskunst fr die Generale</italics><space/>(1806)</listitem><listitem><italics>Grundstze der Strategie erlutert durch die Darstellung des Feldzugs 1796</italics><space/>(1814)</listitem><listitem><italics>Geschichte des Feldzugs von 1799 in Deutschland und in der Schweiz</italics><space/>(1819)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="title">Charles (Archduke of Austria)</arg><arg name="display">Charles, archduke of Austria and duke of Teschen</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Archduke Charles, Duke of Teschen</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite AmCyc</target><arg name="wstitle">Charles (Archduke)</arg><arg name="display">Charles, archduke of Austria<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></template><template><target>French Revolution navbox</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[House of Habsburg|House of Habsburg-Lorraine]]</arg><arg>5 September</arg><arg>1771</arg><arg>30 April</arg><arg>1847</arg><arg>[[House of Lorraine]]</arg></template><template><target>S-reg</target></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Prince Albert of Saxony, Duke of Teschen|Albert Casimir]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Duke of Teschen]]</arg><arg name="years">1822–1847</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Archduke Albrecht, Duke of Teschen|Albert]]</arg></template><template><target>s-gov</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Maria Christina, Duchess of Teschen|Archduchess Maria Christina of Austria]]<br>and [[Albert Casimir, Duke of Teschen]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Governors of the Habsburg Netherlands|Governor of the Austrian Netherlands]]<space/></arg><arg name="years">1793–1794<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-non</target><arg name="reason">Office abolished<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-hon</target></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Archduke Maximilian Franz of Austria]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Teutonic Knights#Hochmeister|Grand Master]] of the [[Teutonic Knights|Teutonic Order]]</arg><arg name="years">1801–1804</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Archduke Anton Victor of Austria]]</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template><template><target>Austrian archdukes</target></template><template><target>Tuscan princes</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Charles Of Austria, Archduke
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Archduke of Austria
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>5 September 1771
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Florence]], [[Italy]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>30 April 1847
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Vienna]], [[Austrian Empire]]
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Charles Of Austria, Archduke</target></template><link><target>Category:Field marshals of Austria</target></link><link><target>Category:Governors of the Habsburg Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Habsburg-Lorraine</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Golden Fleece</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Florence</target></link><link><target>Category:Dukes of Teschen</target></link><link><target>Category:1771 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1847 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of Saint Ferdinand and of Merit</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Order of Saint Januarius</target></link><link><target>Category:Austrian generals</target></link><link><target>Category:Austrian soldiers</target></link><link><target>Category:Austrian Empire military leaders of the French Revolutionary Wars</target></link><link><target>Category:Military leaders of the French Revolutionary Wars</target></link><link><target>Category:Austrian Empire commanders of the Napoleonic Wars</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights of the Order of Saint Hubert</target></link><link><target>Category:Knights Grand Cross of the Order of Saint Joseph</target></link><link><target>Category:Military writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Imperial generals of the Holy Roman Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:People with epilepsy</target></link><link><target>Category:Royalty and nobility with disabilities</target></link><link><target>Category:Austrian princes</target></link></paragraph></article>