<article title='A_cappella'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox music genre</target><arg name="Name"><space/>a capella
</arg><arg name="color"><space/>black
</arg><arg name="bgcolor"><space/>#FFC0CB
</arg><arg name="stylistic_origins"><space/>[[Church music]], [[Gregorian chant]], [[Madrigal]]
</arg><arg name="cultural_origins"><space/>Jewish and Christian worship
</arg><arg name="instruments"><space/>[[Vocals]], [[Vocal percussion]], [[Beatboxing]], [[Live looping]], instrument mimicry
</arg><arg name="derivatives">
</arg><arg name="subgenrelist">
</arg><arg name="subgenres"><space/>{{plainlist|
* [[Barbershop music|barbershop]]
* [[Collegiate a cappella|collegiate]]
* [[Puirt à beul|mouth music]]}}
</arg><arg name="other_topics">
</arg><arg name="current_year"><space/>no
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>A cappella</bold><space/><template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>a kkapˈpɛlla</arg><arg></arg></template><space/>(Italian for &quot;in the manner of the chapel&quot;)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holmes"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Holmes</arg><arg>2007</arg></template></extension><space/>music is specifically group or solo singing without<space/><link><target>Musical instrument</target><part>instrumental</part></link><space/>accompaniment, or a piece intended to be performed in this way. It contrasts with<space/><link><target>cantata</target></link>, which is accompanied singing. The term &quot;a cappella&quot; was originally intended to differentiate between<space/><link><target>Renaissance music</target><part>Renaissance</part></link><space/><link><target>polyphony</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Baroque (music)</target><part>Baroque</part></link><space/><link><target>concertato</target></link><space/>style. In the 19th century a renewed interest in Renaissance polyphony coupled with an ignorance of the fact that vocal parts were often doubled by instrumentalists led to the term coming to mean unaccompanied vocal music.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holmes"></extension><space/>The term is also used, albeit rarely, as a synonym for<space/><link><target>alla breve</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Arnold</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">314</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Religious origins</heading><paragraph>A cappella music was originally used in religious music, especially<space/><link><target>church music</target></link><space/>as well as<space/><link><target>anasheed</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>zemirot</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Gregorian chant</target></link><space/>is an example of a cappella singing, as is the majority of secular vocal music from the<space/><link><target>Renaissance music</target><part>Renaissance</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Madrigal (music)</target><part>madrigal</part></link>, up until its development in the early<space/><link><target>Baroque music</target><part>Baroque</part></link><space/>into an instrumentally-accompanied form, is also usually in a cappella form. Jewish and Christian music were originally a cappella,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">This claim needs a reliable source; many Old Testament passages make reference to multiple instruments being used. [By definition, Christianity began with the New Testament.]</arg><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template><space/>and this practice has continued in both of these religions as well as in Islam.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Christian</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>polyphony</target></link><space/>of Christian a cappella music began to develop in Europe around the late 15th century, with compositions by<space/><link><target>Josquin des Prez</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Hoiberg</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template></extension><space/>The early a cappella polyphonies may have had an accompanying instrument, although this instrument would merely double the singers' parts and was not independent. By the 16th century, a cappella<space/><link><target>polyphony</target></link><space/>had further developed, but gradually, the<space/><link><target>cantata</target></link><space/>began to take the place of a cappella forms.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>16th century a cappella polyphony, nonetheless, continued to influence church composers throughout this period and to the present day. Recent evidence has shown that some of the early pieces by Palestrina, such as what was written for the Sistine Chapel was intended to be accompanied by an organ &quot;doubling&quot; some or all of the voices.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB"></extension><space/>Such is seen in the life of<space/><link><target>Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina</target><part>Palestrina</part></link><space/>becoming a major influence on<space/><link><target>Johann Sebastian Bach</target><part>Bach</part></link>, most notably in the aforementioned<space/><italics><link><target>Mass in B Minor</target></link></italics>. Other composers that utilized the a cappella style, if only for the occasional piece, were<space/><link><target>Claudio Monteverdi</target></link><space/>and his masterpiece,<space/><italics>Lagrime d'amante al sepolcro dell'amata</italics><space/>(A lover's tears at his beloved's grave), which was composed in 1610,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>2005a</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Andrea Gabrieli</target></link><space/>when upon his death it was discovered many choral pieces, one of which was in the unaccompanied style.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">780</arg></template></extension><space/>Learning from the preceding two composeres,<space/><link><target>Heinrich Schtz</target></link><space/>utilized the a cappella style in numerous pieces, chief among these were the pieces in the<space/><link><target>oratorio</target></link><space/>style, which were traditionally performed during the Easter week and dealt with the religious subject matter of that week, such as Christ's suffering and<space/><link><target>Passion (Christianity)</target><part>the Passion</part></link>. Five of Schutz's<space/><italics>Historien</italics><space/>were Easter pieces, and of these the latter three, which dealt with the passion from three different viewpoints, those of<space/><link><target>Matthew the Apostle</target><part>Matthew</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Luke the Evangelist</target><part>Luke</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John the Evangelist</target><part>John</part></link>, were all done a cappella style. This was a near requirement for this type of piece, and the parts of the crowd were sung while the solo parts which were the quoted parts from either Christ or the authors were performed in a<space/><link><target>plainchant</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>2005a</arg><arg name="p">73</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Byzantine Rite</heading><paragraph>In the Byzantine Rite of the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Eastern Catholic Churches</target></link>, the music performed in the liturgies is exclusively sung without instrumental accompaniment. Bishop Kallistos Ware says, &quot;The service is sung, even though there may be no choir... In the Orthodox Church today, as in the early Church, singing is unaccompanied and instrumental music is not found.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ware"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Ware</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">268</arg></template></extension><space/>This<space/><italics>a cappella</italics><space/>behavior arises from strict interpretation of Psalms 150, which states,<space/><italics>Let every thing that hath breath praise the Lord. Praise ye the Lord.</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Pslams</arg><arg>150:6</arg></template></extension><space/>In keeping with this philosophy, early Russian<space/><italics>musika</italics><space/>which started appearing in the late 17th century, in what was known as<space/><italics>khorovye kontsert</italics><space/>(choral concertos) made a cappella adaptations of Venetian-styled pieces, such as the treatise,<space/><italics>Grammatika musikiyskaya</italics><space/>(1675), by<space/><link><target>Nikolai Diletsky</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>2005b</arg><arg name="p">234</arg></template></extension><space/>Divine Liturgies and Western Rite masses composed by famous composers such as<space/><link><target>Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom (Tchaikovsky)</target><part>Peter Tchaikovsky</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom (Rachmaninoff)</target><part>Sergei Rachmaninoff</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Alexander Arkhangelsky (composer)</target><part>Alexander Arkhangelsky</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Liturgy of St. John Chrysostom (Leontovych)</target><part>Mykola Leontovych</part></link><space/>are fine examples of this.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Opposition to instruments in worship</heading><paragraph>Present-day Christian religious bodies known for conducting their worship services without musical accompaniment include some<space/><link><target>Presbyterian</target></link><space/>churches devoted to the<space/><link><target>regulative principle of worship</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Old Regular Baptist</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Primitive Baptist</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Plymouth Brethren</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Churches of Christ</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Old German Baptist Brethren</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Rite</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Amish</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Old Order Mennonites</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Conservative Mennonites</target></link>. Certain<space/><link><target>high church</target></link><space/>services and other musical events in liturgical churches (such as the Roman Catholic<space/><link><target>Mass (liturgy)</target><part>Mass</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target><part>Lutheran</part></link><space/><link><target>Divine Service (Lutheran)</target><part>Divine Service</part></link>) may be a cappella, a practice remaining from apostolic times. Many<space/><link><target>Mennonite</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>also conduct some or all of their services without instruments.<space/><link><target>Sacred Harp</target></link>, a type of<space/><link><target>folk music</target></link>, is an a cappella style of religious singing with<space/><link><target>shape notes</target></link>, usually sung at singing conventions.</paragraph><paragraph>Opponents of<space/><link><target>musical instruments in the Christian worship</target></link><space/>believe that such opposition is supported by the Christian scriptures and Church history. The scriptures typically referenced are<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Matthew%2026:30;%20Acts%2016:25;%20Romans%2015:9;%201%20Corinthians%2014:15;%20Ephesians%205:19;%20Colossians%203:16;%20Hebrews%202:12,%2013:15;%20James%205:13;&amp;amp;version=49;'>Matthew 26:30; Acts 16:25; Romans 15:9; 1 Corinthians 14:15; Ephesians 5:19; Colossians 3:16; Hebrews 2:12, 13:15; James 5:13</link>, which show examples and exhortations for Christians to sing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kurfees"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Kurfees</arg><arg>1911</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There is no reference to instrumental music in early church worship in the New Testament, or in the worship of churches for the first six centuries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McKinnon"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>McKinnon</arg><arg>1965</arg><arg name="pp">263, 265</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Bales"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Bales</arg><arg>1973</arg><arg name="p">351</arg></template></extension><space/>Several reasons have been posited throughout church history for the absence of instrumental music in church worship.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">"nb"</arg><arg>The absence of instrumental music is rooted in various hermeneutic principles (ways of interpreting the Bible) which determine what is appropriate for worship. Among such principles are the [[regulative principle of worship]] (Ulrich Zwingli), [[Sola scriptura]] (Martin Luther and Ulrich Zwingli), and the history of [[hymn]] in "Christianity". Dispensationalism emphasizes the differences between the old (Law of Moses) and the new (Jesus and the Apostles) covenants, emphasizing that the majority of the practices from the Law of Moses were replaced by the teachings of Jesus and the Apostles. The absence of instrumental music in early church worship is significant given the abundance of Hebrew Bible references and commands to worship God with harp, lyre and cymbal. After several hundred years of Tabernacle worship without references to instrumental music, King David (ca 1500 BCE) introduced musical instruments into Temple worship reportedly because of a commandment from God, complete with who was to sing, who was to play, and what instruments were to be used.<ref>{{bibleverse|2|Chronicles|29:25-29}}</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Christians who believe in a cappella music today believe that in the Israelite worship assembly during Temple worship only the Priests of Levi sang, played, and offered animal sacrifices, whereas in the church era, all Christians are commanded to sing praises to God. They believe that if God wanted instrumental music in New Testament worship, He would have commanded not just singing, but singing and playing like he did in the Hebrew scriptures.</paragraph><paragraph>The first recorded example of a musical instrument in Roman Catholic worship was a<space/><link><target>pipe organ</target></link><space/>introduced by<space/><link><target>Pope Vitalian</target></link><space/>into a cathedral in Rome around 670.<extension extension_name='ref'>American Encyclopedia, Volume 12, p. 688<template><target>title missing</target></template></extension><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">"nb"</arg><arg name="McKinnon maintained that the organ was the first instrument to be introduced into worship and the next was the trumpet. He noted accounts of an organ being sent from Byzantium to Pippin in 757, and another to Charlemagne in 812.<ref>{{harvnb|McKinnon|1965|p">265}}</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Instruments have divided Christendom since their introduction into worship. They were considered a Catholic innovation, not widely practiced until the 18th century, and were opposed vigorously in worship by a number of<space/><link><target>Protestant Reformers</target></link>, including<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link><space/>(14831546),<extension extension_name='ref' name="M&amp;S"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>M'Clintock</arg><arg>Strong</arg><arg>1894</arg><arg name="p">762</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Ulrich Zwingli</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Calvin</target></link><space/>(15091564)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Calvin"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Calvin</arg><arg>2009</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Wesley</target></link><space/>(17031791).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Clarke"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Clarke</arg><arg>1844</arg><arg name="p">684</arg></template></extension><space/>Alexander Campbell referred to the use of an instrument in worship as &quot;a cow bell in a concert&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ferg"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Ferguson</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">414</arg></template></extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Walter Scott</target><part>Sir Walter Scott</part></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Heart of Midlothian</target></link></italics>, the heroine,<space/><link><target>Jeanie Deans</target></link>, a Scottish Presbyterian, writes to her father about the church situation she has found in England (bold added):</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The folk here are civil, and, like the barbarians unto the holy apostle, have shown me much kindness; and there are a sort of chosen people in the land, for they have some<space/><bold><link><target>kirk</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>without organs that are like ours</bold>, and are called meeting-houses, where the minister preaches without a gown.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Scott"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Scott</arg><arg>1818</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Acceptance of instruments in worship</heading><paragraph>Those who do not adhere to the<space/><link><target>regulative principle</target></link><space/>of interpreting Christian scripture, believe that limiting praise to the unaccompanied chant of the early church is not commanded in scripture, and that churches in any age are free to offer their songs with or without musical instruments.</paragraph><paragraph>Those who subscribe to this interpretation believe that since the Christian scriptures never counter instrumental language with any negative judgment on instruments, opposition to instruments instead comes from an interpretation of history. There is no written opposition to musical instruments in any setting in the first century and a half of Christian churches (33 AD to 180AD).<extension extension_name='ref' name="McKinnon2"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>McKinnon</arg><arg>1989</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template></extension><space/>The use of instruments for Christian worship during this period is also undocumented. Toward the end of the 2nd century, Christians began condemning the instruments themselves.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McKinnon3"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>McKinnon</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">72</arg></template></extension><space/>Those who oppose instruments today believe these Church Fathers had a better understanding of God's desire for the church,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><space/>but there are significant differences between the teachings of these Church Fathers and Christian opposition to instruments today.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Modern Christians typically believe it is acceptable to play instruments or to attend weddings, funerals, banquets, etc., where instruments are heard playing religious music. The Church Fathers made no exceptions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McKinnon3"></extension><space/>Since the New Testament never condemns instruments themselves, much less in any of these settings, it is believed<template><target>by whom</target><arg name="date">September 2014</arg></template><space/>that &quot;the church Fathers go beyond the New Testament in pronouncing a negative judgment on musical instruments.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Ferguson</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">74</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Written opposition to instruments in worship began near the turn of the 5th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Ferguson</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="pp">52, 53</arg></template></extension><space/>Modern opponents of instruments typically do not make the same assessment of instruments as these writers,<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">"nb"</arg><arg name="Rather than calling the use of instruments "evil", modern opposition typically uses terms like "unspiritual"<ref>{{harvnb|Ferguson|1972|p">88}}</ref><space/>or an Old Testament "shadow".<ref>{{harvnb|Ferguson|Lewis|West|1984|p</arg></template><space/>who argued that God had allowed David the &quot;evil&quot; of using musical instruments in praise.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>McKinnon</arg><arg>1989</arg><arg name="p">7</arg></template></extension><space/>While the Old Testament teaches that God specifically asked for musical instruments,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Chronicles</arg><arg>29:25</arg></template></extension><space/>modern concern is for worship based on the New Testament.</listitem></list><paragraph>Since &quot;a cappella&quot; singing brought a new polyphony (more than one note at a time) with instrumental accompaniment, it is not surprising that Protestant reformers who opposed the instruments (such as Calvin and Zwingli) also opposed the polyphony.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Weiss</arg><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">107</arg></template></extension><space/>While Zwingli was burning organs in Switzerland&amp;nbsp; Luther called him a fanatic&amp;nbsp; the Church of England was burning books of polyphony.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Weiss</arg><arg>Taruskin</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">109</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some<space/><link><target>Holiness Churches</target></link><space/>such as the<space/><link><target>Free Methodist Church</target></link><space/>opposed the use of musical instruments in church worship until the mid-20th century. The Free Methodist Church allowed for local church decision on the use of either an organ or piano in the 1943 Conference before lifting the ban entirely in 1955.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Jewish</heading><paragraph>While worship in the<space/><link><target>Temple in Jerusalem</target></link><space/>included musical instruments (<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Chronicles</arg><arg>29:25–27</arg></template>), traditional Jewish religious services in the Synagogue, both before and after the last destruction of the Temple, did not include musical instruments<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Price</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template></extension><space/>given the practice of scriptural<space/><link><target>cantillation</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>McKinnon</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">85</arg></template></extension><space/>The use of musical instruments is traditionally forbidden on the Sabbath out of concern that players would be tempted to repair (or tune) their instruments, which is forbidden on those days. (This prohibition has been relaxed in many Reform and some Conservative congregations.) Similarly, when Jewish families and larger groups sing traditional Sabbath songs known as<space/><link><target>zemirot</target></link><space/>outside the context of formal religious services, they usually do so a cappella, and Bar and Bat Mitzvah celebrations on the Sabbath sometimes feature entertainment by a cappella ensembles. During<space/><link><target>the Three Weeks</target></link><space/>musical instruments are prohibited. Many Jews consider a portion of the 49-day period of the<space/><link><target>Counting of the Omer</target><part>counting of the omer</part></link><space/>between Passover and Shavuot to be a time of semi-mourning and instrumental music is not allowed during that time.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Melamed</arg><arg>2013</arg></template></extension><space/>This has led to a tradition of a cappella singing sometimes known as<space/><italics>sefirah</italics><space/>music.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Shircago"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Shircago</arg><arg>2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The popularization of the Jewish chant may be found in the writings of the Jewish philosopher<space/><link><target>Philo</target></link>, born 20 BCE. Weaving together Jewish and Greek thought, Philo promoted praise without instruments, and taught that &quot;silent singing&quot; (without even vocal chords) was better still.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Ferguson</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="pp">39–41</arg></template></extension><space/>This view parted with the Jewish scriptures, where Israel offered praise with instruments by God's own command (<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Chronicles</arg><arg>29:25</arg></template>). The<space/><link><target>shofar</target></link><space/>is the only temple instrument still being used today in the synagogue,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Olson</arg><arg>1967</arg><arg name="p">562</arg></template></extension><space/>and it is only used from<space/><link><target>Rosh Chodesh</target></link><space/><link><target>Elul</target></link><space/>through the end of<space/><link><target>Yom Kippur</target></link>. The shofar is used by itself, without any vocal accompaniment, and is limited to a very strictly defined set of sounds and specific places in the synagogue service.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Alleman</arg><arg>2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In the United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><link><target>File:The Hullabahoos.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Hullabahoos, a popular a cappella group at the<space/><link><target>University of Virginia</target></link>, were featured in the movie ''<link><target>Pitch Perfect</target></link>''</part></link>Peter Christian Lutkin, dean of the<space/><link><target>Bienen School of Music</target><part>Northwestern University School of Music</part></link>, helped popularize a cappella music in the United States by founding the Northwestern A Cappella Choir in 1906. The A Cappella Choir was &quot;the first permanent organization of its kind in America.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Wittman</arg><arg>1978</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>van Camp</arg><arg>1965</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A strong and prominent a cappella tradition was begun in the midwest part of the United States in 1911 by<space/><link><target>F. Melius Christiansen</target></link>, a music faculty member at<space/><link><target>St. Olaf College</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Northfield, Minnesota</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>St. Olaf Choir</target><part>St. Olaf College Choir</part></link><space/>was established as an outgrowth of the local<space/><link><target>St. John's Lutheran Church (Northfield, Minnesota)</target><part>St. John's Lutheran Church</part></link>, where Christiansen was organist and the choir was composed, at least partially, of students from the nearby St. Olaf campus. The success of the ensemble was emulated by other regional conductors, and a rich tradition of a cappella choral music was born in the region at colleges like<space/><link><target>Concordia College, Moorhead</target><part>Concordia College</part></link><space/>(Moorhead, Minnesota),<space/><link><target>Augustana College (Illinois)</target><part>Augustana College</part></link><space/>(Rock Island, Illinois),<space/><link><target>Wartburg College</target></link><space/>(Waverly, Iowa),<space/><link><target>Luther College (Iowa)</target><part>Luther College</part></link><space/>(Decorah, Iowa),<space/><link><target>Gustavus Adolphus College</target></link><space/>(St. Peter, Minnesota),<space/><link><target>Augustana College (South Dakota)</target><part>Augustana College</part></link><space/>(Sioux Falls, South Dakota), and<space/><link><target>Augsburg College</target></link><space/>(Minneapolis, Minnesota). The choirs typically range from 40 to 80 singers and are recognized for their efforts to perfect blend, intonation, phrasing and pitch in a large choral setting.</paragraph><paragraph>Major movements in modern a cappella over the past century include<space/><link><target>Barbershop music</target><part>Barbershop</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>doo wop</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Barbershop Harmony Society</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sweet Adelines International</target></link>, and Harmony Inc. host educational events including Harmony University, Directors University, and the International Educational Symposium, and international contests and conventions, recognizing international champion<space/><link><target>List of chorus champions by year</target><part>choruses</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>List of quartet champions by year</target><part>quartets</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>These days, many a cappella groups can be found in high schools and colleges. There are amateur<space/><link><target>Barbershop Harmony Society</target></link><space/>and professional groups that sing a cappella exclusively. Although a cappella is technically defined as singing without instrumental accompaniment, some groups use their voices to emulate instruments; others are more traditional and focus on harmonizing. A cappella styles range from gospel music to contemporary to barbershop quartets and choruses.</paragraph><paragraph>A cappella music was popularized in the late 2000s and early 2010s with media hits such as the 20092014 TV show<space/><italics><link><target>The Sing-Off</target></link></italics>, the<space/><link><target>Musical theatre</target><part>musical</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Perfect Harmony (musical)</target><part>Perfect Harmony</part></link></italics>, and the musical comedy film series<space/><italics><link><target>Pitch Perfect</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Recording artists</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template>In<space/><link><target>Number-one hits of 1943 (United States)</target><part>July 1943</part></link>, as a result of the<space/><link><target>American Federation of Musicians</target></link><space/>boycott of US recording studios, the a cappella vocal group<space/><italics>The Song Spinners</italics><space/>had a best-seller with &quot;Comin' In On A Wing And A Prayer&quot;. In the 1950s several recording groups, notably<space/><link><target>The Hi-Los</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Four Freshmen</target></link>, introduced complex jazz harmonies to a cappella performances. The<space/><link><target>King's Singers</target></link><space/>are credited with promoting interest in small-group a cappella performances in the 1960s. In 1983 an a cappella group known as<space/><link><target>The Flying Pickets</target></link><space/>had a Christmas 'number one' in the UK with a cover of<space/><link><target>Yazoo (band)</target><part>Yazoo</part></link>'s (known in the US as<space/><link><target>Yazoo (band)</target><part>Yaz</part></link>) &quot;<link><target>Only You (Yazoo song)</target><part>Only You</part></link>&quot;. A cappella music attained renewed prominence from the late 1980s onward, spurred by the success of Top 40 recordings by artists such as<space/><link><target>The Manhattan Transfer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bobby McFerrin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Huey Lewis and the News</target></link>,<space/><link><target>All-4-One</target></link>,<space/><link><target>The Nylons</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Backstreet Boys</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Boyz II Men</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Contemporary a cappella includes many vocal groups and bands who add<space/><link><target>vocal percussion</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>beatboxing</target></link><space/>to create a pop/rock/gospel sound, in some cases very similar to bands with instruments. Examples of such professional groups include<space/><link><target>Straight No Chaser (group)</target><part>Straight No Chaser</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Pentatonix</target></link>,<space/><link><target>The House Jacks</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rockapella</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mosaic (vocal band)</target><part>Mosaic</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>M-pact</target></link>. There also remains a strong a cappella presence within Christian music, as some denominations purposefully do not use instruments during worship. Examples of such groups are<space/><link><target>Take 6</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Glad (band)</target><part>Glad</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Acappella (group)</target><part>Acappella</part></link>. Arrangements of popular music for small a cappella ensembles typically include one voice singing the lead melody, one singing a rhythmic bass line, and the remaining voices contributing chordal or<space/><link><target>Polyphony</target><part>polyphonic</part></link><space/>accompaniment.</paragraph><paragraph>A cappella can also describe the isolated vocal track(s) from a<space/><link><target>multitrack recording</target></link><space/>that originally included instrumentation.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><space/>These vocal tracks may be<space/><link><target>remix</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>or put onto vinyl records for DJs, or released to the public so that fans can remix them. One such example is the a cappella release of<space/><link><target>Jay-Z</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Black Album (Jay-Z album)</target><part>Black Album</part></link></italics>, which<space/><link><target>Danger Mouse (artist)</target><part>Danger Mouse</part></link><space/>mixed with<space/><link><target>The Beatles</target></link>'<space/><italics><link><target>The Beatles (album)</target><part>White Album</part></link></italics><space/>to create<space/><italics><link><target>The Grey Album</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>A cappella's growth is not limited to live performance, with hundreds of recorded a cappella albums produced over the past decade. As of December 2006, the Recorded A Cappella Review Board (RARB) had reviewed over 660 a cappella albums since 1994, and its popular discussion forum had over 900 users and 19,000 articles.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Recording artist<space/><link><target>Brandy Norwood</target></link><space/>included a song on her 2008 album<space/><italics><link><target>Human (Brandy Norwood album)</target><part>Human</part></link></italics><space/>titled &quot;A Capella (Something's Missing)&quot;. Brandy uses her voice for background music in this song, showing her capabilities of using her voice as an instrument.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Macpherson</arg><arg>2008</arg></template></extension><space/>No other instruments are used, except for an electric guitar.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Pareles</arg><arg>2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2010, American dance recording artist<space/><link><target>Kelis</target></link><space/>released a song called<space/><link><target>Acapella (Kelis song)</target><part>&quot;Acapella&quot;</part></link><space/>as the first single from her album<space/><italics><link><target>Flesh Tone</target></link></italics>. The song is not actually performed a cappella, but rather explains that before her son was born, her life was without music.<extension extension_name='ref' name="digispyrev"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Levin</arg><arg>2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2013, an artist by the name<space/><link><target>Smooth McGroove</target></link><space/>rose to prominence with his style of a cappella music.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Futter</arg><arg>2013</arg></template></extension><space/>He is best known for his a cappella covers of<space/><link><target>video game</target></link><space/>music tracks on<space/><link><target>YouTube</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Hilliard</arg><arg>2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Musical theater</heading><paragraph>A cappella has been used as the sole orchestration for original works of<space/><link><target>musical theater</target></link><space/>that have had commercial runs<space/><link><target>Off-Broadway</target></link><space/>(theaters in New York City with 99 to 500 seats) only four times. The first was Avenue X which opened on 28 January 1994 and ran for 77 performances. It was produced by<space/><link><target>Playwrights Horizons</target></link><space/>with book by John Jiler, music and lyrics by Ray Leslee. The musical style of the show's score was primarily<space/><link><target>Doo-Wop</target></link><space/>as the plot revolved around Doo-Wop group singers of the 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>2002</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>1993</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2001,<space/><link><target>The Kinsey Sicks</target></link>, produced and starred in the critically acclaimed<space/><link><target>off-Broadway</target></link><space/>hit, &quot;DRAGAPELLA! Starring the Kinsey Sicks&quot; at New York's legendary<space/><link><target>Studio 54</target></link>. That production received a nomination for a<space/><link><target>Lucille Lortel</target></link><space/>award as Best Musical and a Drama Desk nomination for Best Lyrics. It was directed by Glenn Casale with original music and lyrics by Ben Schatz.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The a cappella musical<space/><link><target>Perfect Harmony (musical)</target><part>Perfect Harmony</part></link>, a comedy about two high school a cappella groups vying to win the National championship, made its Off Broadway debut at Theatre Rows Acorn Theatre on 42nd Street in New York City in October, 2010 after a successful out-of-town run at the Stoneham Theatre, in Stoneham, Massachusetts. Perfect Harmony features the hit music of The Jackson 5, Pat Benatar, Billy Idol, Marvin Gaye, Scandal, Tiffany, The Romantics, The Pretenders, The Temptations, The Contours, The Commodores, Tommy James &amp; the Shondells and The Partridge Family, and has been compared to a cross between<space/><link><target>Altar Boyz</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>The 25th Annual Putnam County Spelling Bee</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Finkle</arg><arg>Bacalzo</arg><arg>2006</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Jacobs</arg><arg>2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The fourth a cappella musical to appear Off-Broadway, In Transit, premiered 5 October 2010 and was produced by<space/><link><target>Primary Stages</target></link><space/>with book, music, and lyrics by Kristen Anderson-Lopez, James-Allen Ford, Russ Kaplan, and Sara Wordsworth. Set primarily in the New York City subway system its score features an eclectic mix of musical genres (including jazz, hip hop, Latin, rock, and country). In Transit incorporates vocal beat boxing into its contemporary a cappella arrangements through the use of a subway beat boxer character. Beat boxer and actor<space/><link><target>Chesney Snow</target></link><space/>performed this role for the 2010 Primary Stages production.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>2010a</arg></template></extension><space/>According to the show's website, it is scheduled to reopen for an open-ended commercial run in the Fall of 2011. In 2011 the production received four Lucille Lortel Award nominations including Outstanding Musical, Outer Critics Circle and Drama League nominations, as well as five Drama Desk nominations including Outstanding Musical and won for Outstanding Ensemble Performance.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>As of</target><arg>2013</arg><arg>04</arg></template>, no show with a cappella orchestrations has ever run on Broadway.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Barbershop style</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Barbershop music</arg></template><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template><link><target>Barbershop music</target></link><space/>is one of several uniquely American art forms. The earliest reports of this style of a cappella music involved African Americans. The earliest documented quartets all began in barbershops. In 1938, the first formal men's barbershop organization was formed, known as the Society for the Preservation and Encouragement of Barber Shop Quartet Singing in America (S.P.E.B.S.Q.S.A), and in 2004 rebranded itself and officially changed its public name to the<space/><link><target>Barbershop Harmony Society</target></link><space/>(BHS). Today the BHS has over 22,000 members in approximately 800 chapters across the United States, and the barbershop style has spread around the world with organizations in many other countries. The Barbershop Harmony Society provides a highly organized competition structure for a cappella quartets and choruses singing in the barbershop style.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1945, the first formal women's barbershop organization, Sweet Adelines, was formed. In 1953 Sweet Adelines became an international organization, although it didn't change its name to<space/><link><target>Sweet Adelines International</target></link><space/>until 1991. The membership of nearly 25,000 women, all singing in English, includes choruses in most of the fifty United States as well as in Australia, Canada, England, Finland, Germany, Ireland, Japan, New Zealand, Scotland, Sweden, Wales and the Netherlands. Headquartered in Tulsa, Oklahoma, the organization encompasses more than 1,200 registered quartets and 600 choruses.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1959, a second women's barbershop organization started as a break off from Sweet Adelines due to ideological differences. Based on democratic principles which continue to this day,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.harmonyinc.org'>Harmony, Inc.</link><space/>is smaller than its counterpart, but has an atmosphere of friendship and competition. With about 2,500 members in the United States and Canada, Harmony, Inc. uses the same rules in contest that the Barbershop Harmony Society uses. Harmony, Inc. is registered in Providence, Rhode Island.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In other countries</heading><paragraph><template><target>expand section</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sri Lanka</heading><paragraph>Composer<space/><link><target>Dinesh Subasinghe</target></link><space/>became the first<space/><link><target>Sri Lanka</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>to write a cappella pieces for<space/><link><target>SATB</target></link><space/>choirs. He wrote &quot;The Princes of the Lost Tribe&quot; and &quot;Ancient Queen of Somawathee&quot; for Menaka De Shabandu and Bridget Halpe's choirs, respectively, based on historical incidents in ancient Sri Lanka.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>2010b</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Chanmugam</arg><arg>2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Perera</arg><arg>2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sweden</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template>The European a cappella tradition is especially strong in the countries around the Baltic and perhaps most so in Sweden as described by<space/><link><target>Richard Sparks</target></link><space/>in his doctoral thesis<space/><italics>The Swedish Choral Miracle</italics><space/>in 2000.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SCM"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Sparks</arg><arg>2000</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Swedish a cappella choirs have over the last 25 years won around 25% of the annual prestigious<space/><link><target>European Grand Prix for Choral Singing</target><part>European Grand Prix for Choral Singing (EGP)</part></link><space/>that despite its name is open to choirs from all over the world (see list of laureates in the Wikipedia article on the EGP competition).</paragraph><paragraph>The reasons for the strong Swedish dominance are as explained by Richard Sparks manifold; suffice to say here that there is a long-standing tradition, an unsusually large proportion of the populations (5% is often cited) regularly sing in choirs, the Swedish choral director<space/><link><target>Eric Ericson</target></link><space/>had an enormous impact on a cappella choral development not only in Sweden but around the world, and finally there are a large number of very popular junior och senior high schools (<italics>music schools</italics>) with high admission standards based on auditions that combine a rigid academic regimen with high level choral singing on every school day, a system that started with<space/><link><target>Adolf Fredrik's Music School</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>in 1939 but has spread over the country.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Oxfordalternotives.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>The Oxford Alternotives</target></link>, the oldest a cappella group at the University of Oxford in the UK</part></link><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:University of Exeter's Sweet Nothings.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Sweet Nothings are one of the University of Exeter's eight A Capella groups. They are one of the oldest and most successful girl groups in the UK</part></link>A cappella has gained attention in the UK in recent years, with many groups forming at British universities by students seeking an alternative singing pursuit to traditional choral and chapel singing. This movement has been bolstered by organisations such as<space/><link><target>The Voice Festival UK</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Collegiate</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Collegiate a cappella</arg><arg>List of collegiate a cappella groups</arg><arg>List of collegiate a cappella groups in the UK</arg></template><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template><link><target>Image:MadHatters Fall 2013.jpg</target><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>UW MadHatters</target><part>The MadHatters</part></link><space/>are a collegiate a cappella group from the University of Wisconsin-Madison</part></link>It is not clear exactly where collegiate a cappella began. The Rensselyrics of<space/><link><target>Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute</target></link><space/>(formerly known as the RPI Glee Club), established in 1873 is perhaps the oldest known collegiate a cappella group.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template><space/>However the longest continuously-singing group is probably<space/><link><target>The Whiffenpoofs</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Yale University</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yale"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>1999</arg></template></extension><space/>which was formed in 1909 and once included<space/><link><target>Cole Porter</target></link><space/>as a member.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yale"></extension><space/>Collegiate a cappella groups grew throughout the 20th century. Some notable historical groups formed along the way include<space/><link><target>Princeton University</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Princeton Tigertones</target><part>Tigertones</part></link><space/>(1946),<space/><link><target>Colgate University</target></link>'s The Colgate 13 (1942),<space/><link><target>Dartmouth College</target></link>'s Aires (1946),<space/><link><target>Cornell University</target></link>'s Cayuga's Waiters (1949) and The Hangovers (1968), the<space/><link><target>University of Maine</target></link><space/>Maine Steiners (1958), the<space/><link><target>Columbia University</target></link><space/>Kingsmen (1949), the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jabberwocks.com'>Jabberwocks</link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Brown University</target></link><space/>(1949), and the<space/><link><target>University of Rochester</target></link><space/>YellowJackets (1956). All-women a cappella groups followed shortly, frequently as a<space/><link><target>parody</target></link><space/>of the men's groups: the<space/><link><target>Smiffenpoofs</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Smith College</target></link><space/>(1936), The Shwiffs of Connecticut College (The She-Whiffenpoofs, 1944), and<space/><link><target>The Chattertocks of Brown University</target></link><space/>(1951). A cappella groups exploded in popularity beginning in the 1990s, fueled in part by a change in style popularized by the<space/><link><target>Beelzebubs</target><part>Tufts University Beelzebubs</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Dear Abbeys</target><part>Boston University Dear Abbeys</part></link>. The new style used voices to emulate modern rock instruments, including<space/><link><target>vocal percussion</target></link>/&quot;<link><target>beatboxing</target></link>&quot;. Some larger universities now have multiple groups. Groups often join one another in on-campus concerts, such as<space/><link><target>the Georgetown Chimes</target></link>' Cherry Tree Massacre, a 3-weekend a cappella festival held each February since 1975, where over a hundred collegiate groups have appeared, as well as<space/><link><target>List of quartet champions by year</target><part>International Quartet Champions</part></link><space/><link><target>Boston Common (quartet)</target><part>The Boston Common</part></link><space/>and the contemporary commercial a cappella group<space/><link><target>Rockapella</target></link>. Co-ed groups have produced many up-and-coming and major artists, including<space/><link><target>John Legend</target></link>, an alumnus of the Counterparts at the<space/><link><target>University of Pennsylvania</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Sara Bareilles</target></link>, an alumna of Awaken A Cappella at<space/><link><target>University of California, Los Angeles</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Mira Sorvino</target></link><space/>is an alumna of<space/><link><target>the Harvard-Radcliffe Veritones</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Harvard College</target></link><space/>where she had the solo on<space/><link><target>Only You (Yazoo song)</target><part>Only You</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Yazoo (band)</target><part>Yaz</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A cappella is gaining popularity among South Asians with the emergence of primarily Hindi-English College groups. The first South Asian a cappella group was<space/><link><target>Penn Masala</target></link>, founded in 1996 at the University of Pennsylvania. Other groups include:<space/><link><target>The University of Texas at Austin</target></link>'s Hum A Cappella,<space/><link><target>Case Western Reserve University</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Dhamakapella</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carnegie Mellon University</target></link>'s Deewane,<space/><link><target>Northwestern University</target></link>'s Brown Sugar,<space/><link><target>Chai-Town</target></link><space/>from the University of Illinois, Raagapella from<space/><link><target>Stanford University</target></link>, Andaaz from the<space/><link><target>University of California, Irvine</target></link>, and Maize Mirchi from<space/><link><target>University of Michigan</target></link>. Co-ed South Asian a cappella groups are also gaining in popularity. The first co-ed south Asian a cappella was Anokha, from the<space/><link><target>University of Maryland</target></link>, formed in 2001. Also, Dil se, another co-ed a cappella from UC Berkeley, hosts the &quot;Anahat&quot; competition at the University of California, Berkeley annually. Maize Mirchi, the co-ed a cappella group from the<space/><link><target>University of Michigan</target></link><space/>hosts &quot;Sa Re Ga Ma Pella&quot;, an annual South Asian a cappella invitational with various groups from the Midwest. Other co-ed groups include Asli Baat, from<space/><link><target>University of Southern California</target></link>, Sitaare from<space/><link><target>University of California, San Diego</target></link>, Jhankaar from<space/><link><target>University of California, Davis</target></link>, Taal Tadka from<space/><link><target>Georgia Institute of Technology</target></link>, Swaram A Cappella from<space/><link><target>Texas A&amp;M University</target></link>, RAAG (Rutgers Asian A cappella Group) from<space/><link><target>Rutgers University</target></link>, Sur et Veritaal from<space/><link><target>Yale University</target></link>, Naya Zamaana from<space/><link><target>UCLA</target></link>, UW Awaaz from the<space/><link><target>University of Washington</target></link>, BU Suno from<space/><link><target>Boston University</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>MIT</target></link><space/>Ohms, Kranti from<space/><link><target>Johns Hopkins University</target></link>, and Samaa from<space/><link><target>The University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Jewish-interest groups such as<space/><link><target>Tufts University</target></link>'s Shir Appeal,<space/><link><target>University of Chicago</target></link>'s Rhythm and Jews,<space/><link><target>Ohio State University</target></link>'s Meshuganotes,<space/><link><target>Rutgers University</target></link>'s Kol Halayla,<space/><link><target>New York University</target></link>'s Ani V'Ata and<space/><link><target>Yale University</target></link>'s Magevet are also gaining popularity across the U.S.</paragraph><paragraph>Increased interest in modern a cappella (particularly collegiate a cappella) can be seen in the growth of awards such as the Contemporary A Cappella Recording Awards (overseen by the<space/><link><target>Contemporary A Cappella Society</target></link>) and competitions such as the<space/><link><target>International Championship of Collegiate A Cappella</target></link><space/>for college groups and the<space/><link><target>Harmony Sweepstakes</target></link><space/>for all groups. In December 2009, a new television competition series called<space/><italics><link><target>The Sing-Off</target></link></italics><space/>aired on<space/><link><target>NBC</target></link>. The show featured eight a cappella groups from the United States and Puerto Rico vying for the prize of $100,000 and a recording contract with<space/><link><target>Epic Records</target></link>/<link><target>Sony Music</target></link>. The show was judged by<space/><link><target>Ben Folds</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Shawn Stockman</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Nicole Scherzinger</target></link><space/>and was won by an all-male group from Puerto Rico called<space/><link><target>Nota (group)</target><part>Nota</part></link>. The show returned for a second and third season, won by<space/><link><target>Committed (group)</target><part>Committed</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pentatonix</target></link>, respectively.</paragraph><paragraph>Each year, hundreds of Collegiate a cappella groups submit their strongest songs in a competition to be on The Best of College A Cappella (BOCA), an album compilation of tracks from the best college a cappella groups around the world. The album is produced by Varsity Vocals&amp;nbsp; which also produces the International Championship of Collegiate A Cappella&amp;nbsp; and<space/><link><target>Deke Sharon</target></link>. A group chosen to be on the BOCA album earns much credibility among the a cappella community.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Along with BOCA, Collegiate a cappella groups may submit their tracks to Voices Only, a two-disc series released at the beginning of each school year. This album is known internationally for its award winning sound and prestigious title. Some featured groups on the album series include the USC<space/><link><target>SoCal VoCals</target></link>, Tufts<space/><link><target>Beelzebubs</target></link>, BYU<space/><link><target>Noteworthy (vocal group)</target><part>Noteworthy</part></link>, and the University of Michigan G-Men. A Voices Only album has been released every year since 2005.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Anon</arg><arg>2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another successful a cappella group is<space/><link><target>Straight No Chaser (group)</target><part>Straight No Chaser</part></link><space/>(SNC), which was formed as a collegiate a cappella group in 1996 at Indiana University in Bloomington, IN. In 2007, their arrangement of 12 Days of Christmas went viral on YouTube, catching the attention of Atlantic Records Chairman and CEO, Craig Kallman. The group signed to a 5-record deal with Atlantic in March 2008, and has released four traditional albums to date, along with three extended play albums.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Emulating instruments</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template>In addition to singing words, some a cappella singers also emulate instrumentation by reproducing instrumental sounds with their<space/><link><target>vocal cords</target></link><space/>and mouth. One of the earliest 20th century practitioners of this method were<space/><link><target>The Mills Brothers</target></link><space/>whose early recordings of the 1930s clearly stated on the label that all instrumentation were done vocally. More recently, &quot;<link><target>Twilight Zone (dance song)</target><part>Twilight Zone</part></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>2 Unlimited</target></link><space/>was sung a cappella to the instrumentation on the comedy television series<space/><italics>Tompkins Square</italics>. Another famous example of emulating instrumentation instead of singing the words is the theme song for<space/><italics><link><target>The New Addams Family</target></link></italics><space/>series on<space/><link><target>Fox Family Channel</target></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>ABC Family</target></link>). Groups such as<space/><link><target>Vocal Sampling</target></link><space/>and Undivided emulate Latin rhythms a cappella. In the 1960s, the Swingle Singers used their voices to emulate musical instruments to Baroque and Classical music. Vocal artist<space/><link><target>Bobby McFerrin</target></link><space/>is famous for his instrumental emulation. A cappella group<space/><link><target>Naturally Seven</target></link><space/>recreates entire songs using vocal tones for every instrument.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Swingle Singers</target></link><space/>used nonsense words to sound like instruments, but have been known to produce non-verbal versions of musical instruments. Like the other groups, examples of their music can be found on YouTube.<space/><link><target>Beatboxing</target></link>, more accurately known as vocal percussion, is a technique used in a cappella music popularized by the<space/><link><target>hip-hop</target></link><space/>community, where<space/><link><target>Rapping</target><part>rap</part></link><space/>is often performed a cappella also. The advent of vocal percussion added new dimensions to the a cappella genre and has become very prevalent in modern arrangements.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Pauley</arg><arg>2012</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Petra Haden</target></link><space/>used a four-track recorder to produce an a cappella version of<space/><italics><link><target>The Who Sell Out</target></link></italics><space/>including the instruments and fake advertisements on her album<space/><italics><link><target>Petra Haden Sings: The Who Sell Out</target></link></italics><space/>in 2005. Haden has also released a cappella versions of<space/><link><target>Journey (band)</target><part>Journey</part></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Don't Stop Believin'</target></link>&quot;,<space/><link><target>The Beach Boys</target></link>' &quot;<link><target>God Only Knows</target></link>&quot; and<space/><link><target>Michael Jackson</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Thriller (song)</target><part>Thriller</part></link>&quot;. In 2009,<space/><link><target>Toyota</target></link><space/>commissioned Haden to perform three songs for television commercials for the third-generation<space/><link><target>Toyota Prius</target></link>, including an a cappella version of<space/><link><target>The Bellamy Brothers</target></link>' 1970s song &quot;<link><target>Let Your Love Flow</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Christian rock group<space/><link><target>Relient K</target></link><space/>recorded the song &quot;Plead the Fifth&quot; a cappella on its album<space/><italics><link><target>Five Score and Seven Years Ago</target></link></italics>. The group recorded lead singer<space/><link><target>Matt Thiessen</target></link><space/>making drum noises and played them with an electronic drum machine to record the song.</paragraph><paragraph>The German<space/><link><target>Heavy Metal Music</target><part>metal</part></link><space/>band<space/><link><target>van Canto</target></link><space/>uses vocal noises to imitate guitars on covers of well-known rock and metal songs (such as &quot;<link><target>Master of Puppets (song)</target><part>Master of Puppets</part></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>Metallica</target></link>) as well as original compositions. Although they are generally classified as a cappella metal, the band also includes a drummer, and uses amplifiers on some songs to distort the voice to sound more like an electric guitar.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Pentatonix</target></link><space/>quintet, winners of NBC's Sing-Off Season 3 and Grammy-winning a cappella group</listitem><listitem><link><target>Home Free (group)</target><part>Home Free</part></link><space/>quintet, winners of NBC's Sing-Off Season 4</listitem><listitem><link><target>Barbershop music</target></link><space/>four-part a cappella (in close harmony)</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Contemporary A Cappella Society</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Collegiate a cappella</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Klapa</target></link><space/>a cappella style found in Dalmatia, Croatia</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of collegiate a cappella groups</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of collegiate a cappella groups in the UK</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of professional a cappella groups</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sweet Adelines International</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Pitch Perfect</target></link></italics><space/>a<space/><link><target>2012 in film</target><part>2012</part></link><space/>film widely focusing on an a cappella talent competition</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Perfect Harmony (musical)</target><part>Perfect Harmony</part></link></italics><space/>an a cappella musical comedy</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references' group="nb"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>25em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Alleman</arg><arg name="first">Annie</arg><arg name="url">http://heraldnews.suntimes.com/entertainment/8071132-421/chicago-a-cappella-sings-music-of-high-holidays.html</arg><arg name="title">Chicago a cappella sings music of high holidays</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 November 2013</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="website">Herald-News</arg><arg name="publisher">Chicago Sun times</arg><arg name="location">Chicago, IL</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1993/06/11/theater/last-chance.html?scp</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="title">Last Chance</arg><arg name="date">11 June 1993</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://www.singers.com/collegiate/whiffenpoofs.html</arg><arg name="title">The Yale Whiffenpoofs</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2007</arg><arg name="publisher">United Singers International</arg><arg name="website">United Singers International</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://www.lortel.org/lla_archive/index.cfm?search_by</arg><arg name="title">Avenue X</arg><arg name="publisher">Lortel.org</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 May 2011</arg><arg name="series">Lortel Archives-The Internet Off-Broadway Database</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://www.kinseysicks.com/about</arg><arg name="title">Who are the Kinsey Sicks?</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 May 2013</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://www.take40.com/news/20335/2010-ARIA-Nominations-Announced---Full-List-Here!</arg><arg name="title">2010 ARIA Nominations Announced&nbsp;– Full List Here!</arg><arg name="publisher">Take 40</arg><arg name="date">28 September 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 May 2011</arg><arg name="website">MCM Entertainment</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">www.cgiscript.net, LLC.</arg><arg name="url">http://www.lortel.org/lla_archive/index.cfm?search_by</arg><arg name="title">In Transit</arg><arg name="publisher">Lortel.org</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 May 2011</arg><arg name="year">2010a</arg><arg name="series">Lortel Archives-The Internet Off-Broadway Database</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="url">http://sundaytimes.lk/100822/Plus/plus_22.html</arg><arg name="title">Manaka Singers on song</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Sunday Times</arg><arg name="location">Colombo, Sri Lanka</arg><arg name="year">2010b</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 April 2012</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Anon</arg><arg name="title">Voices Only A Cappella</arg><arg name="url">http://www.voicesonlyacappella.com/VO/</arg><arg name="accessdate">31 July 2014</arg><arg name="year">2014</arg><arg name="website">http://www.voicesonlyacappella.com/<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="editor-last">Arnold</arg><arg name="editor-first">Denis</arg><arg name="title">Cappella</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The New Oxford Companion to Music</arg><arg name="volume">I: A-J</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-311316-3</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bales</arg><arg name="first">James D.</arg><arg name="title">Instrumental Music and New Testament Worship</arg><arg name="location">Searcy, AR</arg><arg name="publisher">Truth for Today World Mision School</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="asin">B0006CBMTU</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Calvin</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Calvin's Commentaries</arg><arg name="volume">8</arg><arg name="chapter">Psalms 33:2</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="origyear">16th century</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0801013317</arg><arg name="author1-link">John Calvin</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Chanmugam</arg><arg name="first">Mano</arg><arg name="url">http://www.island.lk/index.php?page_cat</arg><arg name="title">Menaka singers - ‘September Song’ - Satisfies!</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Island</arg><arg name="location">Colombo, Sri Lanka</arg><arg name="date">25 September 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 April 2012</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Clarke</arg><arg name="first">Adam</arg><arg name="title">The New Testament of Our Lord and Saviour Jesus Christ, the Text Carefully Printed From the Most Correct Copies of the Present Authorized Version Including the Marginal Readings and Parallel Texts with a Commentary and Critical Notes With a Commentary and Critical Notes Designed As a Help to a Better Understanding of the Sacred Writings (Clarke's Commentary)</arg><arg name="volume">VI</arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon Press, n.d.</arg><arg name="location">Nashville, TN</arg><arg name="author1-link">Adam Clarke</arg><arg name="year">1844</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ferguson</arg><arg name="first">Everett</arg><arg name="title">A Cappella Music in the Public Worship of the Church</arg><arg name="series">The Way of Life Series</arg><arg name="location">Abilene, TX</arg><arg name="publisher">Biblical Research Press</arg><arg name="year">1972</arg><arg name="asin">B001D08SDM</arg><arg name="issue">125</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">Ferguson</arg><arg name="first">Everett</arg><arg name="title">Instrumental Music</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The Encyclopedia of the Stone-Campbell Movement</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Douglas A.</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Foster</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Paul M.</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Blowers</arg><arg name="editor3-first">Anthony L.</arg><arg name="editor3-last">Dunnavant</arg><arg name="editor4-first">D. Newell</arg><arg name="editor4-last">Williams</arg><arg name="displayeditors">4</arg><arg name="location">Grand Rapids, MI</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8028-3898-7</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Ferguson</arg><arg name="first1">Everett</arg><arg name="last2">Lewis</arg><arg name="first2">Jack P.</arg><arg name="last3">West</arg><arg name="first3">Earl</arg><arg name="title">The Instrumental Music Issue</arg><arg name="publisher">Gospel Advocate Co.</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0892252954</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Finkle</arg><arg name="first1">David</arg><arg name="last2">Bacalzo</arg><arg name="first2">Dan</arg><arg name="url">http://www.theatermania.com/new-york-city-theater/reviews/08-2006/fringenyc-2006-roundup-3_8876.html</arg><arg name="title">FringeNYC 2006 Roundup 3: Reports on Perfect Harmony, t.l.c., The Infliction of Cruelty, and Don't Ask.</arg><arg name="publisher">TheaterMania</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 January 2013</arg><arg name="date">22 August 2006</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Futter</arg><arg name="first">Mike</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gameinformer.com/b/news/archive/2013/10/21/smooth-mcgroove-leads-us-to-final-fantasy-7-victory.aspx</arg><arg name="title">Smooth McGroove Leads Us To Final Fantasy VII Victory</arg><arg name="website">[[Game Informer]]</arg><arg name="date">21 October 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 February 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">gamestop</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Hilliard</arg><arg name="first">Kyle</arg><arg name="title">How Smooth Got His McGroove – The Introverted Acapella YouTube Artist</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gameinformer.com/b/features/archive/2013/09/09/how-smooth-got-his-mcgroove-the-introverted-acapella-youtube-artist.aspx</arg><arg name="website">[[Game Informer]]</arg><arg name="date">9 September 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 February 2014</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="editor-last">Hoiberg</arg><arg name="editor-first">Dale H.</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="title">A Cappella</arg><arg name="edition">15th</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopædia Britannica, Inc.</arg><arg name="volume">I: A–Ak&nbsp;– Bayes</arg><arg name="location">Chicago, IL</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59339-837-8</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Holmes</arg><arg name="first">William C.</arg><arg name="title">A cappella</arg><arg name="publisher">Grove Music Online. Oxford Music Online</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 September 2008</arg><arg name="url">http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/00091</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Jacobs</arg><arg name="first">Leonard</arg><arg name="url">http://www.backstage.com/review/ny-theater/perfect-harmony_2/</arg><arg name="title">Perfect Harmony</arg><arg name="publisher">Backstage</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2013</arg><arg name="date">24 August 2006</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kurfees</arg><arg name="first">Marshall C.</arg><arg name="title">Instrumental music in the worship or the Greek verb psallo philologically and historically examined together with a full discussion of kindred matters relating to music in Christian worship</arg><arg name="location">Nashville</arg><arg name="publisher">McQuiddy Print Co.</arg><arg name="year">1911</arg><arg name="asin">B00088QFHQ</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Levin</arg><arg name="first">Nick</arg><arg name="url">http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/music/singlesreviews/a214731/kelis-acapella.html</arg><arg name="title">Music Reviews: Kelis Acapella</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Digital Spy]]</arg><arg name="date">16 April 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2010</arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20100418203740/http://www.digitalspy.co.uk/music/singlesreviews/a214731/kelis-acapella.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">18 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Macpherson</arg><arg name="first">Alex</arg><arg name="title">Brandy: ''Human''</arg><arg name="date">5 December 2008</arg><arg name="work">[[The Guardian]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/music/2008/dec/05/urban-brandy-norwood-human/</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 February 2009</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McKinnon</arg><arg name="first">James William</arg><arg name="title">The Church Fathers and Musical Instruments</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia University</arg><arg name="series">Columbia University Dissertations</arg><arg name="asin">B001F2LQJ6</arg><arg name="year">1965</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McKinnon</arg><arg name="first">James</arg><arg name="title">Music in Early Christian Literature</arg><arg name="year">1989</arg><arg name="origyear">1987</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-37624-6</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McKinnon</arg><arg name="first">James</arg><arg name="title">The Temple, the Church Fathers, and Early Western Chant</arg><arg name="location">Aldershot</arg><arg name="publisher">Ashgate Publishing Limited</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0860786887</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="editor1-last">M'Clintock</arg><arg name="editor1-first">John</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Strong</arg><arg name="editor2-first">James</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Cyclopaedia of Biblical, Theological, and Ecclesiastical Literature</arg><arg name="volume">VI: Me-Nev</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper and Brothers Publishers</arg><arg name="location">New York, NY</arg><arg name="year">1894</arg><arg name="title">Music</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Melamed</arg><arg name="first">Rabbi Eliezer</arg><arg name="url">http://www.yeshiva.org.il/midrash/Shiur.asp?id</arg><arg name="title">Mourning Customs During the Omer</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 January 2009</arg><arg name="work">yeshiva.org.il</arg><arg name="publisher">Bet El Yeshiva Center</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">Olson</arg><arg name="first">Lee G.</arg><arg name="title">Music and Musical Instruments of the Bible</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Zondervan Pictoral Bible Dictionary</arg><arg name="editorlink">Merrill C. Tenney</arg><arg name="editor-first">Merrill C.</arg><arg name="editor-last">Tenney</arg><arg name="location">Grand Rapids, MI</arg><arg name="publisher">Zondervan Publishing House</arg><arg name="year">1967</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0310331605</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Pareles</arg><arg name="first">Jon</arg><arg name="title">Critic's Choice&nbsp;– Brandy (''Human'')</arg><arg name="publisher">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2008/12/29/arts/music/29choi.html?_r</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 January 2010</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Pauley</arg><arg name="first">Jared</arg><arg name="title">Freestyle rap [Freestyling]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/A2224354?q</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 October 2014</arg><arg name="website">oxfordmusiconline</arg><arg name="date">10 July 2012</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6TWK0wE3K</arg><arg name="archivedate">22 October 2014</arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Perera</arg><arg name="first">Mahes</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sundayobserver.lk/2010/08/29/mon50.asp</arg><arg name="title">September Song</arg><arg name="newspaper">Sunday Observer</arg><arg name="location">Colombo, Sri Lanka</arg><arg name="date">29 August 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 April 2012</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Price</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Old Light on New Worship: Musical Instruments and The Worship of God, A Theological, Historical, and Psychological Study</arg><arg name="location">Avinger, TX</arg><arg name="publisher">Simpson Publishing Company</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1881095019</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Scott</arg><arg name="first">Walter</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/6944/6944.txt</arg><arg name="title">The Heart of Mid-Lothian</arg><arg name="authorlink">Walter Scott</arg><arg name="year">1818</arg><arg name="publisher">Archibald Constable and Company</arg><arg name="location">Edinburgh, Scotland</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Shircago</arg><arg name="url">http://www.shircago.com/jewish-a-cappella-omer.php</arg><arg name="publisher">Shircago</arg><arg name="title">Jewish A Cappella and Sefirat Omer</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 May 2013</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Sparks</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="authorlink">Richard Sparks</arg><arg name="title">The Swedish Choral Miracle: Swedish A Capella Music Since 1945</arg><arg name="publisher">Walton Music</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="location">Chapel Hill, NC</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-9703134-0-9</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Taruskin</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford History of Western Music</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York, NY</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-522270-9</arg><arg name="volume">1</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Taruskin</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford History of Western Music</arg><arg name="year">2005a</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York, NY</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-522271-7</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Taruskin</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford History of Western Music</arg><arg name="year">2005b</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York, NY</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-522272-5</arg><arg name="volume">3</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">van Camp</arg><arg name="first">Leonard</arg><arg name="title">The Formation of A Cappella Choirs at Northwestern University, St. Olaf College, and Westminster College</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Research in Music Education</arg><arg name="volume">13</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="year">1965</arg><arg name="pages">227–238</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3344375</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ware</arg><arg name="first">Timothy</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="title">The Orthodox Church: New Edition</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0140146561</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Weiss</arg><arg name="first1">Piero</arg><arg name="last2">Taruskin</arg><arg name="first2">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Music in the Western World</arg><arg name="location">New York, NY</arg><arg name="publisher">Shirmer Books</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0028729008</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Wittman</arg><arg name="first">Elisabeth</arg><arg name="contribution-url"></arg><arg name="series">Peter Christian Lutkin Papers</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="place">Evanston, IL</arg><arg name="publisher">Northwestern University</arg><arg name="url">http://files.library.northwestern.edu/findingaids/lutkin_papers.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Biography of Peter Christian Lutkin</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>a cappella</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.casa.org'>Contemporary A Cappella Society of America (CASA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.harmony-sweepstakes.com'>Harmony Sweepstakes A Cappella Festival</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.acappellanews.com'>A Cappella News</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.singers.com'>Primarily A Cappella</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rarb.org'>The Recorded A Cappella Review Board (RARB)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.intransitthemusical.com'>In Transit the Musical</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://vocalaustralia.com/blog/2011/12/15/get-vocal-2012-melbourne-a-cappella-festival/'>Melbourne A Cappella Festival</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://singacappella.org'>British Contemporary A Cappella Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://barbershop.org/history.html'>History of Barbershop</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:A Cappella</target></template><link><target>Category:A cappella</target></link><link><target>Category:Singing</target></link><link><target>Category:Vocal music</target></link><link><target>Category:Musical terminology</target></link></paragraph></article>