<article title='Blue_law'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>laws created to enforce strict moral standards</arg><arg>early Colony of Connecticut laws</arg><arg>Blue Laws (Connecticut)</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template><template><target>more footnotes</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Blue laws</bold><space/>known also as Sunday lawsare laws designed to restrict or ban some or all Sunday activities for religious reasons, particularly to promote the observance of a day of worship or rest. Blue laws may also restrict shopping or ban sale of certain items on specific days, most often on Sundays in the western world. Some Islamic nations may ban on Fridays. Blue laws are enforced in parts of the United States as well as some European countries, particularly in Austria, Germany, Switzerland, and Norway keeping most stores closed on Sundays.</paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, the U.S. Supreme Court have held blue laws as constitutional numerous times due to secular rationales, even though the origin of the blue laws were for religious purposes. Most blue laws have been repealed in the United States, although many states still ban the sale of<space/><link><target>alcoholic beverages</target></link><space/>or cars on Sundays.<space/><link><target>Bergen County, New Jersey</target></link><space/>is notable for their blue laws banning the sale of clothing, shoes, furniture, home supplies and appliances on Sundays kept through county-wide referendum.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.neh.gov/humanities/2015/julyaugust/feature/fighting-the-right-party-sundays'>Kyle G. Volk, &quot;Fighting for the Right to Party on Sundays: How the struggle over blue laws changed American politics,&quot; Humanities (July/August 2015)</link></extension><space/><link><target>Paramus, New Jersey</target></link><space/>has<space/><link><target>Paramus, New Jersey#Blue laws</target><part>its own blue laws</part></link><space/>even more strict than the county itself, banning any type of secular employment on Sundays except necessity items such as food and gasoline.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The first occurrence of the phrase<space/><italics>blue law</italics><space/>so far found is in the<space/><italics>New-York Mercury</italics><space/>of March 3, 1755, where the writer imagines a future newspaper praising the revival of &quot;our<space/><link><target>Connecticut</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Blue Laws (Connecticut)</target><part>old Blue Laws</part></link>&quot;. In his 1781 book<space/><italics>General History of Connecticut</italics>, the Reverend<space/><link><target>Samuel Peters</target></link><space/>(17351826) used it to describe various laws first enacted by<space/><link><target>Puritan</target></link><space/>colonies in the 17th century that prohibited various activities, recreational as well as commercial, on Sunday (Saturday evening through Sunday night). Sometimes the sale of certain types of merchandise was prohibited, and in some cases all retail and business activity.</paragraph><paragraph>Contrary to popular belief, there is no evidence that blue laws were originally printed on blue paper. Rather, the word<space/><italics>blue</italics><space/>was used in the 17th century as a disparaging reference to rigid moral codes and those who observed them, particularly in<space/><italics>blue-stocking</italics>, a reference to<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link>'s supporters in the parliament of 1653.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Oxford English Dictionary</italics>.</extension><space/>Moreover, although Reverend Peters claimed that the term<space/><italics>blue law</italics><space/>was originally used by Puritan colonists, his work has since been found to be unreliable.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.snopes.com/language/colors/bluelaws.htm'>Snopes.com: American &quot;blue laws&quot; were so named because they were originally printed on blue paper.</link>. Retrieved July 12, 2006.</extension><space/>In any event, Peters never asserted that the blue laws were originally printed on blue paper, and this has come to be regarded as an example of<space/><link><target>false etymology</target></link>, another version of which is that the laws were first bound in books with blue covers.</paragraph><paragraph>As Protestant moral reformers organized the Sabbath reform in nineteenth-century America, calls for the enactment and/or enforcement of stricter Sunday laws developed. Numerous Americans were arrested for working, keeping an open shop, drinking alcohol, traveling, and recreating on Sundays. Beginning in the 1840s, Catholic immigrants, workingmen, Jews, Seventh Day Baptists, free-thinkers, and other groups began to organize opposition. Throughout the century, Sunday laws served as a major source of church-state controversy and as an issue that drove the emergence of modern American minority-rights politics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kyle G. Volk (2014),<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/Moral-Minorities-Making-American-Democracy/dp/0199371911/'>Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy</link></italics>. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 019937192X.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many European countries<template><target>which</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><space/>still place strong restrictions on store opening hours on Sundays, an example being Germany's<space/><link><target>Ladenschlussgesetz</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In Texas, for example, blue laws prohibited selling housewares such as pots, pans, and washing machines on Sunday until 1985. In<space/><link><target>Colorado</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Illinois</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Indiana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Iowa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Louisiana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Maine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Minnesota</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Missouri</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Oklahoma</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Jersey</target></link>,<space/><link><target>North Dakota</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Wisconsin</target></link>, car dealerships continue to operate under blue-law prohibitions in which an automobile may not be purchased or traded on a Sunday.<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link><space/>permits Sunday automobile sales only in the counties of<space/><link><target>Charles County, Maryland</target><part>Charles</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Prince George's County, Maryland</target><part>Prince George's</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Montgomery County, Maryland</target><part>Montgomery</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Howard County, Maryland</target><part>Howard</part></link>; similarly,<space/><link><target>Michigan</target></link><space/>restricts Sunday sales to only those counties with a population of less than 130,000. Texas and<space/><link><target>Utah</target></link><space/>prohibit car dealerships from operating over consecutive weekend days. In some cases these laws were created or retained with the support of those whom they affected, to allow them a day off each week without fear of their competitors still being open.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://wcco.com/consumer/local_story_324235359.html'>Good Question: Why Can't We Buy Alcohol On Sunday?</link>,<space/><link><target>WCCO-TV</target></link>, November 20, 2006<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://wcco.com/consumer/local_story_324235359.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20131102162144<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Canada</heading><paragraph>The Lord's Day Act, which since 1906 had prohibited business transactions from taking place on Sundays, was declared unconstitutional in the 1985 case<space/><italics><link><target>R. v. Big M Drug Mart Ltd.</target></link></italics><space/>Calgary police officers witnessed several transactions at the Big M Drug Mart, all of which occurred on a Sunday. Big M was charged with a violation of the Lord's Day Act. A provincial court ruled that the Lord's Day Act was unconstitutional, but the Crown proceeded to appeal all the way to the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Canada</target></link>. In a unanimous 60 decision, the Lord's Day Act was ruled an infringement of the freedom of conscience and religion defined in section 2(a) of the<space/><link><target>Charter of Rights and Freedoms</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://canlii.org/en/ca/scc/doc/1985/1985canlii69/1985canlii69.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">CanLII – 1985 CanLII 69 (S.C.C.)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Canadian Legal Information Institute (CanLII.org)<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 3, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-09-24</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A Toronto referendum in 1950 allowed only team sports to be played professionally on Sunday. Theatre performances, movie screenings, and horse racing were not permitted until the 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://fullcomment.nationalpost.com/2014/10/01/allan-levine-never-mind-ford-nation-hogtown-has-a-long-history-of-drunks-tyrants-and-loudmouths-running-city-hall/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Supreme Court later concluded, in<space/><link><target>R. v. Edwards Books and Art Ltd.</target></link>, [1986] (2 S.C.R. 713) that Ontario's Retail Business Holiday Act, which required some Sunday closings, did not violate the Charter because it did not have a religious purpose. Nonetheless, as of today, virtually all provincial Sunday Closing laws have ceased to exist. Some were struck down by provincial courts, but most were simply abrogated<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ssrn.com/abstract</arg><arg name="title">Sunday Observance Laws in North America<space/></arg><arg name="author">Louis-Philippe Raynault-Ollu<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Social Science Research Network (SSRN)<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 20, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-17</arg></template></extension><space/>often due to competitive reasons where out-of-province or foreign merchants were open.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Chile</heading><paragraph>In Chile most services and businesses are closed on both New Year's Day (January 1) and Labor Day (May 1). Alcoholic beverages in Chile are not sold on Sunday mornings, while on election days their sale is prohibited by law during the entire day (starting the Saturday before).</paragraph><paragraph>Late in 2010, some Congressmen (after the four-day Bicentennial holiday was proved successful) asked for a law that would forbid the opening of supermarkets and<space/><link><target>department store</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on Sundays, however retailers claimed that<space/><link><target>Sunday shopping</target></link><space/>made about 20% of their weekly sales, more than other day of the week, thus preventing the law from taking place.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cook Islands, Tonga and Niue</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Cook Islands</target></link>, blue laws were the first written legislation, enacted by the<space/><link><target>London Missionary Society</target></link><space/>in 1827, with the consent of<space/><italics><link><target>Ali'i</target><part>ariki</part></link></italics><space/>(chiefs). In<space/><link><target>Tonga</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Vava'u Code</target></link><space/>(1839) was inspired by<space/><link><target>Methodism</target><part>Methodist</part></link><space/><link><target>missionary</target></link><space/>teachings, and was a form of blue law. In<space/><link><target>Niue</target></link>, certain activities remain forbidden on Sunday, reflecting<space/><link><target>History of Niue</target><part>the country's history</part></link><space/>of observing Christian Sabbath tradition.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Denmark</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link><space/>the closing laws restricting retail trade on Sundays have been abolished with effect from October 1, 2012. From then on retail trade is only restricted on public holidays (New Years Day,<space/><link><target>Maundy Thursday</target></link>, Good Friday, Easter Sunday, Easter Monday, Day of Prayer, Ascension Day, Whit Sunday, Whit Monday, Christmas Day and Boxing Day) and on Constitution Day, Christmas Eve and New Year's Eve (on New Year's Eve from 3&amp;nbsp;pm only). On these days almost all shops will remain closed. Exempt are bakeries, DIYs, garden centres, gas stations and smaller supermarkets.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.retsinformation.dk/Forms/R0710.aspx?id=132057'>Lov om ndring af lov om detailsalg fra butikker m.v. - Liberalisering af reglerne om bningstid - retsinformation.dk</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>England and Wales</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Sunday Trading Act 1994</target></link><space/>permits large shops (those with a relevant floor area in excess of 280 square metres) to open for up to six hours on Sunday between the hours of 10&amp;nbsp;am and 6&amp;nbsp;pm. Small shops, those with an area of below 280 square metres, are free to set their own Sunday trading times. Some large shops, such as off-licences, service stations and garages, are exempt from the restrictions.</paragraph><paragraph>Christmas Day and Easter Sunday have been excluded as trading days. This applies even to garden centres, which earlier had been trading over Easter, but not to small shops (those with an area of below 280 square metres).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.gov.uk/trading-hours-for-retailers-the-law'>Trading hours for retailers: the law - GOV.UK</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Northern Ireland</heading><paragraph>Prior to 2008,<space/><link><target>Sunday football in Northern Ireland</target><part>no football was permitted to be played on Sundays</part></link><space/>by clubs affiliated to the<space/><link><target>Irish Football Association</target></link><space/>in Northern Ireland.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.theguardian.com/uk/2007/sep/02/northernireland.northernireland</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Norway</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Norway</target></link><space/>the sale of alcohol on Sundays and election day is strictly illegal, the sale of alcohol on Saturdays ends at 6&amp;nbsp;pm, while it ends at 8&amp;nbsp;pm on weekdays. Most stores are closed on Sundays.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Saudi Arabia</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Saudi Arabia</target></link>, all businesses except hospitals are made to close during<space/><link><target>Islamic prayers</target></link>, held five times daily.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Thailand</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Thailand</target></link>, stores are banned from selling alcohol between midnight-11am and 2pm-5pm. Within these hours however it is legal to buy a total quantity of at least ten litres of any alcoholic beverages. Alcohol sales are also banned during many holidays, especially those related to Buddhism and to the<space/><link><target>King of Thailand</target></link>, and election periods.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2011</arg></template><space/>The ban is sometimes skirted by wrapping newspaper or other covering around beer bottles so as not to openly violate it, especially at venues serving<space/><link><target>tourism in Thailand</target><part>tourists</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Turkey</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>alcohol sales (in addition to entertainment programs) are illegal on election day.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.tert.am/en/news/2014/08/09/turkey-prs-day/</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.malaysiandigest.com/world/512648-erdogan-eyes-triumph-in-turkey-elections.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Blue laws in the United States</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many states prohibit selling<space/><link><target>alcoholic beverage</target><part>alcohol</part></link><space/>for on and off-premises sales in one form or another on Sundays at some restricted time, under the idea that people should be in church on Sunday morning, or at least not drinking.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another feature of<space/><link><target>blue laws in the United States</target></link><space/>restricts the purchase of particular items on Sundays. Some of these laws restrict the ability to buy cars, groceries, office supplies, and housewares among other things. Though most of these laws have been relaxed or repealed in most states, they are still enforced in some other states.</paragraph><paragraph>Some states prohibit some forms of hunting in various degrees on Sundays. For example, Virginia allows the use of hounds to chase wild game but does not permit hunters to still hunt on Sunday.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Blue laws may also prohibit retail activity on days other than Sunday. In<space/><link><target>Massachusetts</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rhode Island</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Maine</target></link><space/>(which was previously part of Massachusetts),<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.mainelegislature.org/legis/statutes/17/title17sec3204.html</extension><space/>for example, blue laws prohibit most retail stores, including grocery stores, from opening on<space/><link><target>Thanksgiving</target></link><space/>and Christmas.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.boston.com/news/globe/editorial_opinion/editorials/articles/2006/11/25/a_turkey_of_a_blue_law/'>&quot;A turkey of a blue law&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Boston Globe</target></link></italics>. Retrieved November 25, 2006.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Bergen County, New Jersey</target></link>, is the last remaining county that prohibits the sale of clothing, shoes, furniture, home appliances and certain other items on Sundays for secular reasons voted to keep by residents through numerous referendums.<space/><link><target>Paramus, New Jersey</target></link>, bans any type of employment except necessary items like food, gasoline, entertainment venues, and hotels.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Court cases</heading><paragraph>Beginning in the mid-nineteenth century, religious and ethno-cultural minorities arrested for violating state and local blue laws appealed their convictions to state supreme courts. In<space/><italics>Specht v. Commonwealth</italics>(1848), for example, German Seventh Day Baptists in Pennsylvania employed attorney Thaddeus Stevens to challenge the constitutionality of Pennsylvania's Sunday law. As in cases in other states, litigants pointed to the provisions of state constitutions protecting religious liberty and maintained that Sunday laws were a blatant violation. Though typically unsuccessful (most state supreme courts upheld the constitutionality of Sunday laws), these constitutional challenges helped set a pattern by which subsequent moral minorities would seek to protect religious freedom and minority rights.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kyle G. Volk,<space/><italics>Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy</italics><space/>(Oxford, 2014), 59-68, 190-201.</extension></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target></link><space/>held in its landmark case,<space/><italics><link><target>McGowan v. Maryland</target></link></italics><space/>(1961), that<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link>'s blue laws violated neither the<space/><link><target>Free Exercise Clause</target></link><space/>nor the<space/><link><target>Establishment Clause</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>First Amendment to the United States Constitution</target></link>. It approved the state's blue law restricting commercial activities on Sunday, noting that while such laws originated to encourage attendance at Christian churches, the contemporary Maryland laws were intended to serve &quot;to provide a uniform day of rest for all citizens&quot; on a secular basis and to promote the secular values of &quot;health, safety, recreation, and general well-being&quot; through a common day of rest. That this day coincides with<space/><link><target>Christian Sabbath</target></link><space/>is not a bar to the state's secular goals; it neither reduces its effectiveness for secular purposes nor prevents adherents of other religions from observing their own holy days.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://caselaw.lp.findlaw.com/scripts/getcase.pl?court=US&amp;amp;vol=366&amp;amp;invol=420'>McGOWAN v. MARYLAND, 366 U.S. 420 (1961)</link>,<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target></link>, Decided May 29, 1961. Retrieved August 10, 2007. &quot;The present purpose and effect of most of our Sunday Closing Laws is to provide a uniform day of rest for all citizens; and the fact that this day is Sunday, a day of particular significance for the dominant Christian sects, does not bar the State from achieving its secular goals.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There were four landmark Sunday-law cases altogether in 1961. The other three were<space/><italics><link><target>Gallagher v. Crown Kosher Super Market of Mass., Inc.</target></link></italics>, 366 U.S. 617 (1961);<space/><italics><link><target>Braunfeld v. Brown</target></link></italics>, 366 U.S. 599 (1961);<space/><italics>Two Guys from Harrison vs. McGinley</italics>, 366 U.S. 582 (1961).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://worldincrisis.org/NSLC/NSLC-9.htm'>The LANDMARK Cases</link>, National Sunday Law Crisis. Retrieved May 21, 2008.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In March 2006, Texas judges upheld the state blue law that requires car dealerships to close either Saturday or Sunday each weekend.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kvia.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.kvia.com/Global/story.asp?S=4669315'>&quot;'Blue Law' for car sales upheld by Judge&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>KVIA</target></link>, March 22, 2006. Retrieved May 28, 2008. &quot;A Texas judge has upheld an old law that requires car dealerships in the Lone Star state to close one day each weekend. They must now choose to open either Saturday or Sunday.&quot;<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.kvia.com/Global/story.asp?S</arg><arg name="date">20150114174300<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Vanuatu</heading><paragraph>In Vanuatu the sale of alcohol in shops and supermarkets is forbidden from midday Saturday until Monday morning, although it is available at resorts and hotels.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>National Sunday Law</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Desuetude</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dry county</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Neo-prohibitionism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Raines law</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Religious law</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sunday shopping</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sundown town</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Religious coercion</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Algeo, Matthew (2006).<space/><italics>Last Team Standing</italics>. Philadelphia: Da Capo Press. ISBN 978-0-306-81472-3</listitem><listitem>Ruck, Rob; with Patterson, Maggie Jones and Weber, Michael P. (2010).<space/><italics>Rooney: A Sporting Life</italics>. Lincoln, NB: University of Nebraska Press. ISBN 978-0-8032-2283-0</listitem><listitem>Volk, Kyle G. (2014).<space/><italics>Moral Minorities and the Making of American Democracy</italics>. New York: Oxford University Press. ISBN 019937192X.</listitem><listitem>Westcott, Rich (2001).<space/><italics>A Century of Philadelphia Sports</italics>. Philadelphia: Temple University Press. ISBN 978-1-56639-861-9</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digital.library.okstate.edu/encyclopedia/entries/B/BL014.html'>Encyclopedia of Oklahoma History and Culture Blue Laws</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mass.gov/?pageID=elwdsubtopic&amp;amp;L=4&amp;amp;L0=Home&amp;amp;L1=Workers+and+Unions&amp;amp;L2=Wage+and+Employment+Related+Programs&amp;amp;L3=The+Massachusetts%27+Blue+Laws&amp;amp;sid=Elwd'>The Massachusetts' Blue Laws</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pantagraph.com/news/local/sunday-movies-come-to-bloomington-in/article_27ea9b0c-a481-11e2-889a-001a4bcf887a.html'>Blue Law - Pantagraph</link><space/>(Bloomington, IL newspaper)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Blue Law</target></template><link><target>Category:Political terminology of the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Working time</target></link><link><target>Category:Church and state law</target></link><link><target>Category:Sunday shopping</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>de:Sonntagsruhe</target></link></paragraph></article>