<article title='Book_of_Ruth'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the ancient Hebrew religious text</arg><arg>the 20th-century English language novel</arg><arg>The Book of Ruth (novel)</arg><arg>the 1960 film</arg><arg>The Story of Ruth</arg><arg>the 2009 film</arg><arg>The Book of Ruth: Journey of Faith</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Ketuvim<space/></arg><arg>historical</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Book of Ruth</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-he</target><arg>מגילת רות</arg></template>,<space/><link><target>Ashkenazi Hebrew</target><part>Ashkenazi pronunciation</part></link>:<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>[məˈɡɪləs rus]</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Megilath Ruth</italics>, &quot;the Scroll of Ruth&quot;, one of the<space/><link><target>Five Megillot</target></link>) is a book of the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link>/<link><target>Old Testament</target></link>. In the Jewish canon it is included in the third division, or the Writings (<link><target>Ketuvim</target></link>); in the<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target><part>Christian canon</part></link><space/>it is treated as a history book and placed between<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>1 Samuel</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">8</arg></template><space/>It is named after its central figure,<space/><link><target>Ruth (biblical figure)</target><part>Ruth</part></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Moab</target><trail>itess</trail></link>, the great-grandmother of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The book tells of Ruth's accepting the God of the Israelites as her God and the Israelite people as her own. In Ruth 1:16 and 17 Ruth tells<space/><link><target>Naomi (Bible)</target><part>Naomi</part></link>, her Israelite mother in law, &quot;Where you go I will go, and where you stay I will stay. Your people will be my people and your God my God. Where you die I will die, and there I will be buried. May the Lord deal with me, be it ever so severely, if even death separates you and me.&quot; The book is held in esteem by Jews who fall under the category of<space/><link><target>Conversion to Judaism</target><part>Jews-by-choice</part></link>, as is evidenced by the considerable presence of<space/><link><target>Boaz</target></link><space/>in rabbinic literature. The &quot;Book of Ruth&quot; also functions liturgically, as it is read during the<space/><link><target>Jewish holiday</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Shavuot</target></link><space/>(&quot;Weeks&quot;).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Atteridge</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">383</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The book is traditionally ascribed to the<space/><link><target>Samuel (Bible)</target><part>prophet Samuel</part></link>, but does not name its author.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hubbard</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">23</arg></template><space/>A date during the monarchy is suggested by the book's interest in the ancestry of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, but Ruth's identity as a non-Israelite and the stress on the need for an inclusive attitude towards foreigners suggests an origin in the fifth century BCE, when intermarriage had become controversial (as seen in<space/><link><target>Ezra-Nehemiah</target><part>Ezra</part></link><space/>9:1 and<space/><link><target>book of Nehemiah</target><part>Nehemiah</part></link><space/>13:1).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Leith</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">391</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld- Ruth im Feld des Boaz.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld</target></link>: &quot;Ruth in Boaz's Field&quot;, 1828</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The book is structured in four chapters:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Act 1: Prologue and Problem: Death and Emptiness (1:122)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Scene 1: Setting the scene (1:15)	</listitem><listitem>Scene 2: Naomi returns home (1:618)</listitem><listitem>Scene 3: Arrival of Naomi and Ruth in Bethlehem (1:1922)</listitem></list><paragraph>Act 2: Ruth Meets Boaz, Naomi's Relative, on the Harvest Field (2:123)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Scene 1: Ruth in the field of Boaz (2:117)</listitem><listitem>Scene 2: Ruth reports to Naomi (2:1823)</listitem></list><paragraph>Act 3: Naomi Sends Ruth to Boaz on the Threshing Floor (3:118)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Scene 1: Naomi Reveals Her Plan (3:15)</listitem><listitem>Scene 2: Ruth at the threshing-floor of Boaz (3:615)</listitem><listitem>Scene 3: Ruth reports to Naomi (3:1618)</listitem></list><paragraph>Act 4: Resolution and Epilogue: Life and Fullness (4:122)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Scene 1: Boaz with the men at the gate (4:112)</listitem><listitem>Scene 2: A son is born to Naomi (4:1317)<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>Genealogical appendix (4:1822)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Summary</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:1795-William-Blake-Naomi-entreating-Ruth-Orpah.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>300px</part><part>Naomi entreating Ruth and Orpah to return to the land of Moab by<space/><link><target>William Blake</target></link>, 1795</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>During the time of the<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link><space/>when there was a famine, an Israelite family from<space/><link><target>Bethlehem</target></link>&amp;nbsp; Elimelech, his wife<space/><link><target>Naomi (Bible)</target><part>Naomi</part></link>, and their sons<space/><link><target>Mahlon and Chilion</target></link>&amp;nbsp; emigrated to the nearby country of<space/><link><target>Moab</target></link>. Elimelech died, and the sons married two Moabite women: Mahlon married<space/><link><target>Ruth (biblical figure)</target><part>Ruth</part></link><space/>and Chilion married<space/><link><target>Orpah</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>After about ten years, the two sons of Naomi also died in Moab (1:4). Naomi decided to return to Bethlehem. She told her daughters-in-law to return to their own mothers, and remarry. Orpah reluctantly left; however, Ruth said, &quot;Intreat me not to leave thee,<space/><italics>[or]</italics><space/>to return from following after thee: for whither thou goest, I will go; and where thou lodgest, I will lodge: thy people<space/><italics>[shall be]</italics><space/>my people, and thy God my God: Where thou diest, will I die, and there will I be buried: the<space/><template><target>LORD</target></template><space/>do so to me, and more also,<space/><italics>[if aught]</italics><space/>but death part thee and me.&quot; (Ruth 1:1617 KJV)</paragraph><paragraph>The two women returned to Bethlehem at the beginning of the barley harvest, and in order to support her mother-in-law and herself, Ruth went to the fields to<space/><link><target>gleaning</target><part>glean</part></link>. As it happened, the field she went to belonged to a man named<space/><link><target>Boaz</target></link>, who was kind to her because he had heard of her loyalty to her mother-in-law. Ruth told Naomi of Boaz's kindness, and she gleaned in his field through the remainder of barley and wheat harvest.</paragraph><paragraph>Boaz was a close relative of Naomi's husband's family. He was therefore obliged by the<space/><link><target>Levirate</target></link><space/>law to marry Mahlon's widow, Ruth, in order to carry on his family's inheritance. Naomi sent Ruth to the threshing floor at night and told her to go where he slept, and &quot;uncover his feet, and lay thee down; and he will tell thee what thou shalt do.&quot; (3:4) Ruth did so. At midnight Boaz was afraid and turned to see that a woman lay at his feet. When asked who she was, she replied: &quot;I<space/><italics>[am]</italics><space/>Ruth thine handmaid: spread therefore thy skirt over thine handmaid; for thou<space/><italics>[art]</italics><space/>a near kinsman.&quot; (3:9) Boaz blessed her and agreed to do all that is required, and he noted that, &quot;all the city of my people doth know that thou<space/><italics>[art]</italics><space/>a virtuous woman.&quot; (3:11) He then acknowledged that he was a close relative, but that there was one who was closer, so he deferred to spread his cloak over her at that time, and she remained in submission at his feet until she returned into the city in the morning. Early that day, Boaz discussed the issue with the other male relative,<space/><link><target>Ploni Almoni</target></link><space/>(&quot;so-and-so&quot;), before the town elders. The other male relative was unwilling to jeopardize the inheritance of his own estate by marrying Ruth, and so relinquished his right of redemption, thus allowing Boaz to marry Ruth. They transferred the property and redeemed it by the nearer kinsman taking off his shoe and handing it over to Boaz. (Ruth 4:718) Boaz and Ruth were married and had a son named Obed: who is &quot;the father of Jesse, the father of David.&quot; (4:1317)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph>The book is traditionally ascribed to the<space/><link><target>Samuel (Bible)</target><part>prophet Samuel</part></link>, but this &quot;cannot be correct&quot;,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">521</arg></template><space/>and a substantial number of scholars date it to the Persian period (6th4th centuries BC).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Grabbe</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">105</arg></template><space/>The final genealogy linking Ruth to David is believed to be a post-exilic<space/><link><target>Priestly source</target><part>Priestly</part></link><space/>addition, as it adds nothing to the plot; nevertheless, it is carefully crafted and integrates the book into the history of Israel that runs from Genesis to Kings.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">211</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes and background</heading><heading level='3'>Levirate marriage and the &quot;redeemer&quot;</heading><paragraph>The Book of Ruth illustrates the complexity of trying to use laws given in books such as<space/><link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link><space/>as evidence of actual practice.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Grabbe</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">105</arg></template><space/>Naomi plans to provide security for herself and Ruth by arranging a<space/><link><target>Levirate marriage</target></link><space/>with Boaz. Her plan is overtly sexual: Ruth is to go to the threshing floor (a place associated with sexual activity), wait until Boaz has finished eating and drinking (a possible allusion to the story of Lot and his daughters, ancestors through incest of the Moabites), and to lie at his uncovered &quot;feet&quot; (a euphemism for genitals).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">210</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' group="Notes" name="Genitals">For &quot;feet&quot; as a euphemism for genitals see, for example, Amy-Jill Levine, &quot;Ruth,&quot; in Newsom and Ringe (eds.),<space/><italics>The Womens' Bible Commentary</italics>, pp.78-84. The usual interpretation, as given here, is that Ruth is told to uncover Boaz's genitals, but see Kirsten Nielsen, &quot;Other Writings,&quot; in McKenzie and Graham (eds.),<space/><italics>The Hebrew Bible Today</italics>, pp.175-176, where it is argued that Ruth is to uncover herself.</extension><space/>Since there was no heir to inherit Elimelech's land, custom required a close relative (usually the dead man's brother) to marry the widow of the deceased in order to continue his family line (<link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link><space/>25:510). This relative was called the<space/><link><target>go'el</target></link>, the &quot;kinsman-redeemer&quot;. As Boaz is not Elimelech's brother, nor is Ruth his widow, scholars refer to the arrangement here as &quot;Levirate-like&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">521-522</arg></template><space/>A complication arises in the story: another man is closer relative to Elimelech than Boaz and has first claim on Ruth. It is resolved through the custom that required land to stay in the family: a family could mortgage land to ward off poverty, but the law required a kinsman to purchase it back into the family (Leviticus 25:25ff). Boaz meets the near kinsman at the city gate (the place where contracts are settled); the kinsman first says he will purchase Elimelech's (now Naomi's) land, but, upon hearing he must also take Ruth as his wife, withdraws his offer. Boaz thus becomes Ruth and Naomi's &quot;kinsman-redeemer.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="pp">521-522</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Mixed marriage</heading><paragraph>The book can be read as a political parable relating to issues around the time of Ezra and Nehemiah (the 4th century BCE).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template><space/>The fictional nature of the story is established from the start through the names of the participants: the husband and father is Elimelech, meaning &quot;My God is King&quot;, and his wife is Naomi, &quot;Pleasing&quot;, but after the deaths of her sons Mahlon, &quot;Sickness&quot;, and Chilion, &quot;Wasting&quot;, she asks to be called Mara, &quot;Bitter&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template><space/>The reference to<space/><link><target>Moab</target></link><space/>raises questions, since in the rest of the biblical literature it is associated with hostility to Israel, sexual perversity, and idolatry, and<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Deut.</arg><arg>23:3–6</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Deuteronomy 23:3–6</arg></template><space/>excluded an Ammonite or a Moabite from &quot;the congregation of the<space/><template><target>LORD</target></template>; even to their tenth generation&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>West</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template><space/>Despite this, Ruth the Moabitess married a Judahite and even after his death still regarded herself a member of his family; she then married another Judahite and bore him a son who became an ancestor of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Grabbe</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">312</arg></template><space/>Contrary to the message of<space/><link><target>Ezra-Nehemiah</target></link>, where marriages between Jewish men and non-Jewish women were broken up, Ruth teaches that foreigners who convert to Judaism can become good Jews, foreign wives can become exemplary followers of Jewish law, and there is no reason to exclude them or their offspring from the community.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Grabbe</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">312</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hesed</heading><paragraph><link><target>Hesed</target></link>, &quot;loving kindness&quot;, and implying loyalty, is woven throughout Ruth, beginning at 1:8 with Naomi blessing her two daughters-in-law as she urges them to return to their Moabite families. She says, &quot;May the Lord deal kindly with you, as you have dealt with the dead and with me.&quot; Both Ruth and Boaz demonstrate<space/><italics>hesed</italics><space/>to their family members throughout the story. These are not acts of kindness with an expectation of measure for measure. Rather, they are acts of<space/><italics>hesed</italics><space/>that go beyond measure and demonstrate that a person can go beyond the minimum expectations of the law and choose the unexpected. However, the importance of the law is evident within the Book of Ruth, and the story reflects a need to stay within legal boundaries. Boaz, in going beyond measure in acquiring the property (demonstrating<space/><italics><link><target>hesed</target></link></italics>), redeems not only the land but both Naomi and Ruth as well. The two widows now have a secure and protected future.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Contemporary interpretations</heading><paragraph>Scholars have increasingly explored Ruth in ways which allow it to address contemporary issues.<space/><link><target>feminism</target><part>Feminists</part></link>, for example, have recast the story as one of the dignity of labour and female self-sufficiency, and even as a model for<space/><link><target>lesbianism</target><part>lesbian</part></link><space/>relations, while others have seen in it a celebration of the relationship between strong and resourceful women. Others have criticised it for its underlying, and potentially exploitative, acceptance of a system of patriarchy in which a woman's worth can only be measured through marriage and child-bearing. Others again have seen it as a book that champions outcast and oppressed peoples such as modern<space/><link><target>native Americans</target></link><space/>and migrant workers.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Irwin</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">699</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Genealogy: the descent of David from Ruth</heading><paragraph><template><target>familytree/start</target></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg>F</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>7</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg>:</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/>ELI<space/></arg><arg>y</arg><arg><space/>NAO<space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg name="ELI">[[Elimelech]]</arg><arg name="NAO">[[Naomi (biblical figure)|Naomi]]</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg>:</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg>,</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>^</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>.</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/>BOA<space/></arg><arg>~</arg><arg>y</arg><arg>~</arg><arg><space/>RUT<space/></arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg><space/>MAH<space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/>ORP<space/></arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg>~</arg><arg><space/>CHIL<space/></arg><arg name="BOA">[[Boaz]]</arg><arg name="RUT">'''Ruth'''</arg><arg name="MAH">[[Mahlon and Chilion|Mahlon]]</arg><arg name="ORP">[[Orpah]]</arg><arg name="CHIL">[[Mahlon and Chilion|Chilion]]</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg>!</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/>OBE<space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg name="OBE">[[Obed (biblical figure)|Obed]]</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg>!</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/>JES<space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg name="JES">[[Jesse]]</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg>!</arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg></template><template><target>familytree</target><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/>DAV<space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg><space/></arg><arg name="DAV">[[David]]</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>familytree/end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Goel</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">"Notes"</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Allen<space/></arg><arg name="first">Leslie C.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ruth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">LaSor<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">William Sanford<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Hubbard<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">David Allan<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-last">Bush<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-first">Frederic William<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-last">Allen<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-first">Leslie C.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Survey: The Message, Form, and Background of the Old Testament<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780802837882</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Atteridge<space/></arg><arg name="first">Harold W.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The HarperCollins Study Bible<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HarperCollins<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Coogan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael D.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Michael D. Coogan<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: The Hebrew Bible in Its Context<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780195332728<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Grabbe<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lester L.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Lester L. Grabbe<space/></arg><arg name="title">The History of the Jews and Judaism in the Second Temple Period, Volume 1: Yehud, the Persian Province of Judah<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Continuum<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780567089984<space/></arg><arg name="pages">105 &amp; 312</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hubbard<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert L. Jr.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Book of Ruth<space/></arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780802825261</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Irwin
</arg><arg name="first">B.P.
</arg><arg name="chapter">Ruth 4: Person
</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Longman 
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Tremper 
</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Enns
</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Peter
</arg><arg name="title">Dictionary of the Old Testament: Wisdom, Poetry & Writings
</arg><arg name="year">2008 
</arg><arg name="publisher">InterVarsity Press 
</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Leith<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mary Joan Winn<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ruth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Coogan<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Michael D.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Brettler<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Marc Zvi<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-last">Newsom<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-first">Carol Ann<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-last">Perkins<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-first">Pheme<space/></arg><arg name="title">The New Oxford Annotated Bible with the Apocryphal/Deuterocanonical Books: New Revised Standard Version<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780195288803</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Pardes, Ilana (1993). &quot;<link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=nSAEdDT8Su0C&amp;amp;pg=PA171#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=%22Book%20of%20Ruth%22&amp;amp;f=false'>The Book of Ruth: Idyllic Revisionism</link>&quot; in<space/><italics>Countertraditions in the Bible: A Feminist Approach</italics>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press. ISBN 978-0674175457</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Rowell<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gillian M.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ruth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Kroeger<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Catherine Clark<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Evans<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Mary J.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Ivp Women's Bible Commentary<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">InterVarsity Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780830814374</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">West<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gerald<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ruth<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Dunn<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">James D.G.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Rogerson<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">John William<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780802837110</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource</target><arg>Ruth (Bible)</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Book of Ruth</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Jewish translations and study guides</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et2901.htm'>''Ruth'' at Mechon Momre (Jewish Publication Society of America Version)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/Bible/Ruthtoc.html'>Jewish Virtual Library</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=483&amp;amp;letter=R&amp;amp;search=ruth'>Jewish Encyclopedia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/15778/jewish/Ruth.htm'>Ruth English translation [with Rashi commentary&amp;#93;</link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Christian translations and study guides</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hopeofisrael.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=37&amp;amp;Itemid=32'>The Kinsman Redeemer</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Ruth+1'>''Online Bible'' GospelHall.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Ruth;&amp;amp;version=31;'>Biblegateway</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.intervarsity.org/ism/article/1827'>Bible Study on Cross-Cultural Love InterVarsity website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/Joy-in-Trials-ebook/dp/B00A3Z6H1I/ref=la_B008FFD5NG_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1352804783&amp;amp;sr=1-1'>''Joy in Trials''</link><space/>Amazon.com</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Other links</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/13276a.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Ketuvim|History books]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Song of Songs]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Lamentations|Lamentations]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Judges|Judges]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>Christian<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Books of Samuel|1–2 Samuel]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ruth, Book Of</target></template><link><target>Category:Book of Ruth</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Ketuvim</target></link><link><target>Category:Moab</target></link><link><target>Category:Shavuot</target></link></paragraph></article>