<article title='Animism'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template><template><target>Anthropology of religion</target><arg>Basic</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Jarai tomb (guardian spirit sculpture).jpg|center|260px]]</arg></template><bold>Animism</bold><space/>(from<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>anima</arg></template></italics>, &quot;<link><target>breath</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Soul (spirit)</target><part>spirit</part></link>,<space/><link><target>life</target></link>&quot;)<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>EB</arg><arg>1878</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="ooviqc">Segal, p. 14.</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>worldview</target></link><space/>that non-human entitiessuch as animals, plants, and inanimate objectspossess a spiritual essence.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stringer"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Stringer</arg><arg name="first">Martin D.</arg><arg name="title">Rethinking Animism: Thoughts from the Infancy of our Discipline</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="volume">5</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pages">541–56</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2661147</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hornborg</arg><arg name="first">Alf</arg><arg name="title">Animism, fetishism, and objectivism as strategies for knowing (or not knowing) the world</arg><arg name="journal">Ethnos: Journal of Anthropology</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="volume">71</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">21–32</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/00141840600603129</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">What Is Religion?: An Introduction</arg><arg name="author">Haught, John F.</arg><arg name="page">19</arg><arg name="publisher">Paulist Press</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Animism is used in the<space/><link><target>anthropology of religion</target></link><space/>as a term for the belief system of some<space/><link><target>indigenous people</target><part>indigenous tribal peoples</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Ritual and Belief: Readings in the Anthropology of Religion</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="last">Hicks</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Rowman Altamira]]</arg><arg name="edition">3</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="page">359</arg><arg name="quote">Tylor's notion of animism—for him the first religion—included the assumption that early ''Homo sapiens'' had invested animals and plants with souls&nbsp;...</arg></template></extension><space/>especially prior to the development of organized religion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Animism</arg><arg name="publisher">ELMAR Project (University of Cumbria)</arg><arg name="date">1998–99</arg><arg name="others">Contributed by Helen James; coordinated by Dr. Elliott Shaw with assistance from Ian Favell</arg><arg name="url">http://www.philtar.ac.uk/encyclopedia/seasia/animism.html</arg></template></extension><space/>Although each culture has its own different mythologies and rituals, &quot;animism&quot; is said to describe the most common, foundational thread of indigenous peoples' &quot;spiritual&quot; or &quot;supernatural&quot; perspectives. The Animistic perspective is so fundamental, mundane, everyday and taken-for-granted that most animistic indigenous people do not even have a word in their languages that corresponds to &quot;animism&quot; (or even &quot;religion&quot;);<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Native American Religious and Cultural Freedom: An Introductory Essay</arg><arg name="work">The Pluralism Project</arg><arg name="publisher">President and Fellows of Harvard College and Diana Eck</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pluralism.org/reports/view/176</arg></template></extension><space/>the term is an<space/><link><target>Emic and etic</target><part>anthropological construct</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Largely due to such<space/><link><target>ethnolinguistic</target></link><space/>and cultural discrepancies, opinion has differed on whether<space/><italics>animism</italics><space/>refers to a broad religious belief or to a full-fledged religion in its own right. The currently accepted definition of animism was only developed in the late 19th century by Sir<space/><link><target>Edward Tylor</target></link>, who created it as &quot;one of<space/><link><target>anthropology</target></link>'s earliest concepts, if not the first&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bird-David</arg><arg name="first">Nurit</arg><arg name="title">"Animism" Revisited: Personhood, Environment, and Relational Epistemology</arg><arg name="journal">Current Anthropology</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="volume">40</arg><arg name="issue">S1</arg><arg name="page">S67</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/200061</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Animism encompasses the belief that there is no separation between the<space/><link><target>Spirituality</target><part>spiritual</part></link><space/>and physical (or material) world, and<space/><link><target>Soul (spirit)</target><part>soul</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>spirit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>exist, not only in humans, but also in some other animals, plants, rocks, geographic features such as mountains or rivers, or other entities of the natural environment, including thunder, wind, and shadows. Animism thus rejects<space/><link><target>Cartesian dualism</target></link>. Animism may further attribute souls to abstract concepts such as words,<space/><link><target>true name</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or metaphors in<space/><link><target>mythology</target></link>. Some members of the non-tribal world also consider themselves animists (such as author<space/><link><target>Daniel Quinn</target></link>, sculptor<space/><link><target>Lawson Oyekan</target></link>, and many<space/><link><target>Paganism (contemporary)</target><part>Neopagans</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Harvey"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Animism: Respecting the Living World</arg><arg name="last">Harvey</arg><arg name="first">Graham</arg><arg name="page">9</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia University Press</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Theories of animism</heading><heading level='3'>Tylor's definition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Edward Burnett Tylor.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Edward Burnett Tylor</target><part>Sir Edward Tylor</part></link><space/>was responsible for forming the definition of Animism currently accepted in anthropology.</part></link>The term &quot;animism&quot; appears to have been first developed (originally<space/><template><target>c.</target><arg>1720</arg></template><space/>as<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>animismus</arg></template></italics>) by the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target><part>German</part></link><space/>scientist<space/><link><target>Georg Ernst Stahl</target></link>. Stahl's animism was a<space/><link><target>biology</target><part>biological</part></link><space/>theory that<space/><link><target>soul (spirit)</target><part>souls</part></link><space/>formed the<space/><link><target>vital principle</target></link><space/>and that the normal phenomena of life and the abnormal phenomena of disease could be traced to spiritual causes.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>EB</arg><arg>1878</arg></template><space/>The earliest known usage in English appeared in 1819.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bird-David</arg><arg name="first">Nurit</arg><arg name="title">"Animism" Revisited: Personhood, Environment, and Relational Epistemology</arg><arg name="journal">Current Anthropology</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="volume">40</arg><arg name="issue">S1</arg><arg name="pages">S67-S68</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/200061</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The term was repurposed by the<space/><link><target>anthropology</target><part>anthropologist</part></link><space/><link><target>Edward Burnett Tylor</target><part>Sir Edward Tylor</part></link><space/>in his 1871 book<space/><italics>Primitive Culture</italics>,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>EB</arg><arg>1878</arg></template><space/>in which he defined it as &quot;the general doctrine of souls and other spiritual beings in general.&quot; According to Tylor, animism often includes &quot;an idea of pervading life and will in nature&quot;;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Sir Edward Burnett Tylor</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Primitive Culture: Researches Into the Development of Mythology, Philosophy, Religion, Art, and Custom</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1871</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>J. Murray</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>260<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>i.e., a belief that natural objects other than humans have souls. This formulation was little different from that proposed by<space/><link><target>Auguste Comte</target></link><space/>as &quot;<bold><link><target>fetishism</target></link></bold>&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kuper 2005 85"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kuper</arg><arg name="first">Adam</arg><arg name="title">Reinvention of Primitive Society: Transformations of a Myth (2nd Edition)</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">Florence, KY, USA</arg><arg name="page">85</arg></template></extension><space/>although the terms now have distinct uses.</paragraph><paragraph>As a self-proclaimed &quot;confirmed scientific rationalist&quot;, Tylor believed that animistic beliefs were &quot;childish&quot; and typical of &quot;cognitive underdevelopment&quot;, and that it was therefore common in &quot;primitive&quot; peoples such as those living in<space/><link><target>hunter gatherer</target></link><space/>societies. In fact, Tylor based his theory of animism on his experience of modern seances thereby constructing a model of 'primitive thought' (of which he had no first hand experience) from his first-hand knowledge of spiritualism. Stringer notes that his reading of<space/><italics>Primitive Culture</italics><space/>led him to believe that Tylor was far more sympathetic in regard to primitive populations than many of his contemporaries and that Tylor expressed no belief that there was any difference between the intellectual capabilities of savage people and westerners.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stringer"></extension><space/>To Tylor, the fundamental distinction between western and primitive cultures was education. Education was a social-cultural evolutionary process that produced differing levels of sophistication (progress) in different places.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Social evolutionist conceptions</heading><paragraph>Tylor's definition of animism was a part of a growing international debate on the nature of 'primitive society' by lawyers, theologians and philologists. The debate defined the field of research of a new science,<space/><link><target>anthropology</target></link>. By the end of the nineteenth century an orthodoxy on 'primitive society' had emerged although few anthropologists today would accept their definition; the 'nineteenth century armchair anthropologists' argued 'primitive society' (an evolutionary category) was ordered by kinship and was divided into exogamous<space/><link><target>Kinship</target><part>descent groups</part></link><space/>related by a series of marriage exchanges. Their religion was animism, the belief that natural species and objects had souls. With the development of private property, these descent groups were displaced by the emergence of the territorial state. These rituals and beliefs eventually evolved over time into the vast array of &quot;developed&quot; religions. According to Tylor, the more scientifically advanced a society became, the less members of that society believed in animism; however, any remnant ideologies of souls or spirits, to Tylor, represented &quot;survivals&quot; of the original animism of early humanity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kuper</arg><arg name="first">Adam</arg><arg name="title">The Invention of Primitive Society: Transformations of an Illusion</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge & Kegan Paul</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="pages">6–7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1869 (three years after Tylor proposed his definition of animism), the Edinburgh lawyer John Ferguson McLellan argued that the animistic thinking evident in<space/><link><target>fetishism</target></link><space/>gave rise to a religion he named<space/><link><target>Totemism</target></link>. Primitive people believed, he argued, that they were descended of the same species as their totemic animal.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kuper 2005 85"></extension><space/>Subsequent debate by the armchair anthropologists (including<space/><link><target>Johann Jakob Bachofen</target><part>J. J. Bachofen</part></link>,<space/><link><target>mile Durkheim</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sigmund Freud</target></link>) remained focused on<space/><link><target>totemism</target></link><space/>rather than animism, with few directly challenging Tylor's definition. Indeed, anthropologists &quot;have commonly avoided the issue of Animism and even the term itself rather than revisit this prevalent notion in light of their new and rich<space/><link><target>ethnographies</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bird-David 1999 S68"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bird-David</arg><arg name="first">Nurit</arg><arg name="title">"Animism" Revisited: Personhood, Environment, and Relational Epistemology</arg><arg name="journal">Current Anthropology</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="volume">40</arg><arg name="issue">S1</arg><arg name="page">S68</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/200061</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the anthropologist<space/><link><target>Tim Ingold</target></link>, animism shares similarities to<space/><link><target>totemism</target></link><space/>but differs in its focus on individual spirit beings which help to perpetuate life, whereas totemism more typically holds that there is a primary source, such as the land itself or the ancestors, who provide the basis to life. Certain indigenous religious groups such as the<space/><link><target>Australian Aboriginals</target></link><space/>are more typically totemic, whereas others like the<space/><link><target>Inuit</target></link><space/>are more typically animistic in their worldview.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ingold, Tim. (2000). &quot;Totemism, Animism and the Depiction of Animals&quot; in<space/><italics>The Perception of the Environment: Essays on Livelihood, Dwelling and Skill</italics>. London: Routledge, pp.&amp;nbsp;112113.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Animism as a relational ontology</heading><paragraph>After a lengthy period of disinterest, post-modern anthropologists are increasingly engaging with the concept of animism. Modernism is characterized by a Cartesian subject-object dualism that divides the subjective from the objective, and culture from nature; in this view, Animism is the inverse of<space/><link><target>scientism</target></link>, and hence inherently invalid. Drawing on the work of<space/><link><target>Bruno Latour</target></link>, these anthropologists question these modernist assumptions, and theorize that all societies continue to &quot;animate&quot; the world around them, and not just as a Tylorian survival of primitive thought. Rather, the instrumental reason characteristic of modernity is limited to our &quot;professional subcultures,&quot; which allows us to treat the world as a detached mechanical object in a delimited sphere of activity. We, like animists, also continue to create personal relationships with elements of the so-called objective world, whether pets, cars or teddy-bears, who we recognize as subjects. As such, these entities are &quot;approached as communicative subjects rather than the inert objects perceived by modernists.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hornborg</arg><arg name="first">Alf</arg><arg name="title">Animism, fetishism, and objectivism as strategies for knowing (or not knowing) the world</arg><arg name="journal">Ethnos</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="volume">71</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">22–4</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/00141840600603129</arg></template></extension><space/>These approaches are careful to avoid the modernist assumptions that the environment consists dichotomously of a physical world distinct from humans, and from modernist conceptions of the person as composed dualistically as body and soul.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bird-David 1999 S68"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nurit Bird-David argues that &quot;Positivistic ideas about the meaning of 'nature', 'life' and 'personhood' misdirected these previous attempts to understand the local concepts. Classical theoreticians (it is argued) attributed their own modernist ideas of self to 'primitive peoples' while asserting that the 'primitive peoples' read their idea of self into others!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bird-David 1999 S68"></extension><space/>She argues that animism is a &quot;relational epistemology&quot;, and not a Tylorian failure of primitive reasoning. That is, self-identity among animists is based on their relationships with others, rather than some distinctive feature of the self. Instead of focusing on the essentialized, modernist self (the &quot;individual&quot;), persons are viewed as bundles of social relationships (&quot;dividuals&quot;), some of which are with &quot;superpersons&quot; (i.e. non-humans).</paragraph><paragraph>Tim Ingold, like Bird-David, argues that animists do not see themselves as separate from their environment: &quot;Hunter-gatherers do not, as a rule, approach their environment as an external world of nature that has to be 'grasped' intellectually&amp;nbsp;... indeed the separation of mind and nature has no place in their thought and practice.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ingold</arg><arg name="first">Tim</arg><arg name="title">The Perception of the Environment: Essays in Livelihood, Dwelling and Skill</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="page">42</arg></template></extension><space/>Willerslev extends the argument by noting that animists reject this<space/><link><target>Cartesian dualism</target></link>, and that the animist self identifies with the world, &quot;feeling at once<space/><italics>within</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>apart</italics><space/>from it so that the two glide ceaselessly in and out of each other in a sealed circuit.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Willerslev</arg><arg name="first">Rane</arg><arg name="title">Soul Hunters: Hunting, Animism and personhood among the Siberian Yukaghirs</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="location">Berkeley</arg><arg name="page">24</arg></template></extension><space/>The animist hunter is thus aware of himself as a human hunter, but, through mimicry is able to assume the viewpoint, senses, and sensibilities of his prey, to be one with it.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Willerslev</arg><arg name="first">Rane</arg><arg name="title">Soul Hunters: Hunting, Animism and personhood among the Siberian Yukaghirs</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="location">Berkeley</arg><arg name="page">27</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Shamanism</target></link>, in this view, is an everyday attempt to influence spirits of ancestors and animals by mirroring their behaviours as the hunter does his prey.</paragraph><paragraph>Graham Harvey, in his 2013 Handbook of Contemporary Animism, identifies the animist perspective in line with Martin Buber's &quot;I-thou&quot; as opposed to &quot;I-it&quot;. In such, Harvey says, the Animist takes an I-thou approach to relating to his world, where objects and animals are treated as a &quot;thou&quot; rather than as an &quot;it&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Harvey</arg><arg name="first">Graham</arg><arg name="title">The Handbook of Contemporary Animism</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Religion</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Shaman tableau.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>A tableau presenting figures of various cultures filling in mediator-like roles, often being termed as &quot;shaman&quot; in the literature.</part></link>There is ongoing disagreement (and no general consensus) as to whether animism is merely a singular, broadly encompassing religious belief<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>David A. Leeming</arg><arg name="author2">Kathryn Madden<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Stanton Marlan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Encyclopedia of Psychology and Religion</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="date"><space/>6 November 2009</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Springer</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-387-71801-9</arg><arg name="page"><space/>42<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Insoll"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Archaeology, Ritual, Religion</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Psychology Press</arg><arg name="last">Insoll</arg><arg name="first">Timothy</arg><arg name="page">144</arg></template></extension><space/>or a worldview in and of itself, comprising many diverse mythologies found worldwide in many diverse cultures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harvey (2006), p. 6.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ishmael.org"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Daniel</arg><arg name="last">Quinn</arg><arg name="work">Ishmael.com</arg><arg name="title">Q and A #400</arg><arg name="work">Ishmael.org</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ishmael.org/Interaction/QandA/Detail.CFM?Record</arg></template></extension><space/>This also raises a controversy regarding the ethical claims animism may or may not make: whether animism ignores questions of<space/><link><target>ethics</target></link><space/>altogether<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Edward Burnett Tylor</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Primitive culture: researches into the development of mythology, philosophy, religion, language, art, and custom</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1920</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>J. Murray</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>360<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>or, by endowing various non-human elements of nature with spirituality or personhood,<extension extension_name='ref'>Clarke, Peter B., and Peter Beyer, eds. (2009).<space/><italics>The World's Religions: Continuities and Transformations.</italics><space/>London: Routledge, p. 15.</extension><space/>in fact promotes a complex<space/><link><target>Environmental ethics</target><part>ecological ethics</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Polity</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="title">Ecological Ethics</arg><arg name="edition">2</arg><arg name="first">Patrick</arg><arg name="last">Curry</arg><arg name="pages">142–3</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>In modern usage, the term is sometimes used improperly as a catch-all classification of &quot;other world religions&quot; alongside major organized religions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Characteristics</heading><paragraph>Tylor argued that Animism consisted of two unformulated propositions; all parts of nature had a soul, and these souls are capable of moving without requiring a physical form. This gives rise to<space/><link><target>fetishism</target></link>, the worship of visible objects as powerful, spiritual beings. The second proposition was that souls are independent of their physical forms. It gives rise to '<link><target>Ancestor worship</target><part>spiritism</part></link>', the worship of the souls of the dead and the unseen spirits of the heavens. Others such as Nurit Bird-David, associate Animism with various aspects of<space/><link><target>shamanism</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Fetishism/totemism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Fetishism</arg><arg>Totemism</arg></template>In many animistic world views, the human being is often regarded as on a roughly equal footing with other animals, plants, and natural forces.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fernandez-Armesto, p. 138.</extension><space/>Therefore, it is morally imperative to treat these agents with respect. In this world view, humans are considered a part of nature, rather than superior to, or separate from it.</paragraph><paragraph>Totemism (or fetishism) includes one or more of several features, such as the mystic association of animal and plant species, natural phenomena, or created objects with unilineally related groups (lineages, clans, tribes,<space/><link><target>Moiety (kinship)</target><part>moieties</part></link>,<space/><link><target>phratries</target></link>) or with local groups and families; the hereditary transmission of the totems (patrilineal or matrilineal); group and personal names that are based either directly or indirectly on the totem; the use of totemistic emblems and symbols; taboos and prohibitions that may apply to the species itself or can be limited to parts of animals and plants (partial taboos instead of partial totems); and a connection with a large number of animals and natural objects (multiplex totems) within which a distinction can be made between principal totems and subsidiary ones (linked totems).</paragraph><heading level='4'>Ancestor reverence</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Veneration of the dead</arg></template>Many animistic cultures observe some form of ancestor reverence. Whether they see the ancestors as living in an other world, or embodied in the natural features of this world, animists often believe that offerings and prayers to and for the dead are an important facet of maintaining harmony with the world of the spirits.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Shamanism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Shamanism</arg></template>A shaman is a person regarded as having access to, and influence in, the world of<space/><link><target>Evocation</target><part>benevolent and malevolent spirits</part></link>, who typically enters into a<space/><link><target>trance</target><part>trance state</part></link><space/>during a<space/><link><target>ritual</target></link>, and practices<space/><link><target>divination</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>healing</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.askoxford.com/concise_oed/shaman?view=uk'>Oxford Dictionary Online</link>.</extension><space/>Shamanism encompasses the premise that shamans are intermediaries or messengers between the human world and the spirit worlds. Shamans are said to treat ailments/illness by mending the soul. Alleviating traumas affecting the soul/spirit restores the physical body of the individual to balance and wholeness. The shaman also enters<space/><link><target>otherworld</target><part>supernatural realms</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Plane (esotericism)</target><part>dimensions</part></link><space/>to obtain solutions to problems afflicting the community. Shamans may visit other worlds/dimensions to bring guidance to misguided souls and to ameliorate illnesses of the human soul caused by foreign elements. The shaman operates primarily within the spiritual world, which in turn affects the human world. The restoration of balance results in the elimination of the ailment.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Eli72">Mircea Eliade,<space/><italics>Shamanism, Archaic Techniques of Ecstasy</italics>, Bollingen Series LXXVI, Princeton University Press 1972, pp. 37.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Distinction from pantheism</heading><paragraph>Animism is not the same as<space/><link><target>pantheism</target></link>, although the two are sometimes confused. Some religions are both pantheistic and animistic. One of the main differences is that while animists believe everything to be spiritual in nature, they do not necessarily see the spiritual nature of everything in existence as being united (monism), the way pantheists do. As a result, animism puts more emphasis on the uniqueness of each individual soul. In pantheism, everything shares the same spiritual essence, rather than having distinct spirits and/or souls.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul A. Harrison<space/><italics>Elements of Pantheism</italics><space/>2004, p. 11</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Carl McColman<space/><italics>When Someone You Love Is Wiccan: A Guide to Witchcraft and Paganism for Concerned Friends, Nervous parents and Curious Co-Workers</italics><space/>2002, p. 97</extension><space/>Additionally, Pantheism posits a source of this &quot;monism&quot;. This source may or may not have agency. In contrast, in Animism, the soul or essence or spirit of objects and living things are novel and separate from the whole, while still seen as irrevocably intertwined with one another in a community.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Examples</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Traditional African religion</target><part>Traditional African</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Afro-American religions</target></link><space/>are animistic.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Shinto</target></link>, the traditional religion of Japan, is highly animistic. In Shinto, spirits of nature, or<space/><link><target>kami</target></link>, are believed to exist everywhere, from the major (such as<space/><link><target>Amaterasu</target><part>the goddess of the sun</part></link>), which can be considered<space/><link><target>polytheism</target><part>polytheistic</part></link>, to the minor, which are more likely to be seen as a form of Animism.</listitem><listitem>Some<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target><part>Hindu</part></link><space/>groups are considered animist. The coastal<space/><link><target>Karnataka</target></link><space/>has a different tradition of praying to spirits (see also<space/><link><target>Folk Hinduism</target></link>). Likewise a popular Hindu ritual form of worship of North Malabar in Kerala, India is the Tabuh Rah blood offering to<space/><link><target>Theyyam</target></link><space/>gods, despite being forbidden in the Vedic philosophy of sattvic Hinduism,<space/><link><target>Jainism</target></link><space/>and Buddhism, Theyyam deities are propitiated through the cock sacrifice where the religious cockfight is a religious exercise of offering blood to the<space/><link><target>Theyyam</target></link><space/>gods.</listitem><listitem>Many traditional beliefs in<space/><link><target>the Philippines</target></link><space/>still practised to an extent today are animist and<space/><link><target>spiritism</target><part>spiritist</part></link><space/>in origin in that there are rituals aimed at pacifying malevolent spirits or are<space/><link><target>apotropaic magic</target><part>apotropaic</part></link><space/>in nature.</listitem><listitem>People in Malaysia, Indonesia, Singapore and Brunei to a certain degree, still practices animism although the majority of them are Muslims. Animistic beliefs were adapted into Islamic practices as people were not keen in abandoning the culture they have been practising for thousands of years. This includes the belief in<space/><link><target>ghost</target><trail>s</trail></link>, black magic, and tree/forest spirits e.g.<space/><link><target>Orang Bunian</target></link>.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mun (religion)</target><part>Mun</part></link>, (also called Munism or Bongthingism) is the traditional<space/><link><target>polytheism</target><part>polytheistic</part></link>, animist,<space/><link><target>shamanism</target><part>shamanistic</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>syncretism</target><part>syncretic</part></link><space/>religion of the<space/><link><target>Lepcha people</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bareh"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Encyclopaedia of North-East India: Sikkim<space/></arg><arg name="volume">7<space/></arg><arg name="series">Encyclopaedia of North-East India<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Hamlet Bareh<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">81-7099-787-9<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Mittal Publications<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="pages">284–86<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferrari"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Health and Religious Rituals in South Asia<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Fabrizio Ferrari<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">10. In the Shadow of the Devil. traditional patterns of Lepcha culture reinterpreted<space/></arg><arg name="first">Davide<space/></arg><arg name="last">Torri<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-136-84629-8<space/></arg><arg name="pages">149–156<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="West"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of the Peoples of Asia and Oceania<space/></arg><arg name="series">Facts on File library of world history<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Barbara A. West<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Infobase Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4381-1913-5<space/></arg><arg name="page">462<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Many traditional Native American religions are fundamentally animistic. See, for example, the Lakota Sioux prayer<space/><link><target>Mitakuye Oyasin</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Iroquois</target><part>Haudenausaunee</part></link><space/>Thanksgiving Address, which can take an hour to recite, directs thanks towards every being - plant, animal and other.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>New Age</target></link><space/>movement commonly demonstrates animistic traits in asserting the existence of nature spirits.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wouter J. Hanegraaff<space/><italics>New Age religion and Western culture</italics><space/>1998, p. 199</extension></listitem><listitem>Some<space/><link><target>Neopaganism</target><part>Neopagan</part></link><space/>groups, including Eco-Pagans, describe themselves as animists, meaning that they respect the diverse community of living beings and spirits with whom humans share the world/cosmos.<extension extension_name='ref'>Murphy Pizza, James R. Lewis<space/><italics>Handbook of Contemporary Paganism</italics>, 2008, pp.&amp;nbsp;408409</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Other usages</heading><heading level='3'>Psychology and animism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>psychology of religion</arg></template>Animism in the broadest sense, i.e., thinking of objects as animate, and treating them as if they were animate, is near-universal.<link><target>Jean Piaget</target></link><space/>applied the term in reference to an implicit understanding of the world in a child's mind which assumes that all events are the product of intention or consciousness. Piaget explains this with a cognitive inability to distinguish the external world from one's internal world.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Science and animism</heading><paragraph>In the early 20th century,<space/><link><target>William McDougall (psychologist)</target><part>William McDougall</part></link><space/>defended a form of Animism in his book<space/><italics>Body and Mind: A History and Defence of Animism</italics><space/>(1911).</paragraph><paragraph>The physicist<space/><link><target>Nick Herbert (physicist)</target><part>Nick Herbert</part></link><space/>has argued for &quot;quantum animism&quot; in which mind permeates the world at every level.<space/><template><target>blockquote</target><arg>The quantum consciousness assumption, which amounts to a kind of "quantum animism" likewise asserts that consciousness is an integral part of the physical world, not an emergent property of special biological or computational systems. Since everything in the world is on some level a quantum system, this assumption requires that everything be conscious on that level. If the world is truly quantum animated, then there is an immense amount of invisible inner experience going on all around us that is presently inaccessible to humans, because our own inner lives are imprisoned inside a small quantum system, isolated deep in the meat of an animal brain.<ref>Nick Herbert ''Holistic Physics – or – An Introduction to Quantum Tantra'' 2002, retrieved on 2014-05-01 from http://www.southerncrossreview.org/16/herbert.essay.htm</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Werner Krieglstein</target></link><space/>wrote regarding his quantum Animism:<template><target>blockquote</target><arg>Herbert's quantum Animism differs from traditional Animism in that it avoids assuming a dualistic model of mind and matter. Traditional dualism assumes that some kind of spirit inhabits a body and makes it move, a ghost in the machine. Herbert's quantum Animism presents the idea that every natural system has an inner life, a conscious center, from which it directs and observes its action.<ref>Werner J. Krieglstein ''Compassion: A New Philosophy of the Other'' 2002, p. 118</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Anecdotal cognitivism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Animatism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ecotheology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Folk religion</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hylozoism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mana</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nature worship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Panpsychism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Religion and environmentalism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sacred trees</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wildlife totemization</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Adler, Margot.<space/><italics>Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-Worshippers, and Other Pagans in America</italics>. Penguin, 2006.</listitem><listitem>&quot;Animism&quot;.<space/><italics>The Columbia Encyclopedia</italics>. 6th ed. 200107.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/65/an/animism.html'>''Bartleby.com''. Bartleby.com Inc. (10 July 2008)</link>.</listitem><listitem>Armstrong, Karen.<space/><italics>A History of God: The 4,000-Year Quest of Judaism, Christianity and Islam</italics>. Ballantine Books, 1994.</listitem><listitem>Bird-David, Nurit. 1991. &quot;Animism Revisited: Personhood, environment, and relational epistemology&quot;,<space/><italics>Current Anthropology</italics><space/>40, pp.&amp;nbsp;6791. Reprinted in Graham Harvey (ed.) 2002.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=PaLyYm7kFsAC&amp;amp;pg=PR1&amp;amp;dq=Readings+in+Indigenous+Religions&amp;amp;sig=JbLAs8L73O17IWhb22kasr5bCek#PPR1,M1'>''Readings in Indigenous Religions''</link><space/>(London and New York: Continuum) pp.&amp;nbsp;72105.</listitem><listitem>Dean, Bartholomew 2009<space/><italics>Urarina Society, Cosmology, and History in Peruvian Amazonia</italics>, Gainesville: University Press of Florida ISBN 978-0-8130-3378-5. (<link type='external' href='http://www.upf.com/book.asp?id=DEANXS07'>Online</link>)</listitem><listitem>Fernandez-Armesto, Felipe.<space/><italics>Ideas that Changed the World</italics>. Dorling Kindersley, 2003.</listitem><listitem>'Lamphun's Little-Known Animal Shrines' (Animist traditions in Thailand) in: Forbes, Andrew, and Henley, David,<space/><italics>Ancient Chiang Mai</italics><space/>Volume 1. Chiang Mai, Cognoscenti Books, 2012.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Oughter Lonie<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alexander Charles<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Animism|Animism]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 9th ed.]], [[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Baynes<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Thomas Spencer<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Charles Scribner's Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="date">1878<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1878}}<space/></arg><arg name="pp">55–57<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Segal, Robert</arg><arg name="title">Myth: A Very Short Introduction</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="url"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="first">Northcote Whitridge<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Anet|Anet]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 11th ed.]], [[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Chisholm<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Hugh<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Phillips<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Walter Alison<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">[[Cambridge, England|Cambridge]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">1911<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1911}}<space/></arg><arg name="pp">53–55</arg></template>.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Hallowell, A. Irving. &quot;Ojibwa ontology, behavior, and world view&quot; in Stanley Diamond (ed.) 1960.<space/><italics>Culture in History</italics><space/>(New York: Columbia University Press). Reprinted in Graham Harvey (ed.) 2002.<space/><italics>Readings in Indigenous Religions</italics><space/>(London and New York: Continuum) pp.&amp;nbsp;1749.</listitem><listitem>Harvey, Graham. 2005.<space/><italics>Animism: Respecting the Living World</italics><space/>(London: Hurst and co.; New York: Columbia University Press; Adelaide: Wakefield Press).</listitem><listitem>Ingold, Tim: 'Rethinking the animate, re-animating thought'. Ethnos, 71(1) / 2006: pp.&amp;nbsp;920.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wilhelm Maximilian Wundt</target><part>Wundt, W.</part></link><space/>(1906).<space/><italics>Mythus und Religion</italics>, Teil II. Leipzig 1906 (<italics>Vlkerpsychologie</italics>, volume II).</listitem><listitem>Quinn, Daniel.<space/><italics>The Story of B</italics></listitem><listitem>Kser, Lothar:<space/><italics>Animismus. Eine Einfhrung in die begrifflichen Grundlagen des Welt- und Menschenbildes traditionaler (ethnischer) Gesellschaften fr Entwicklungshelfer und kirchliche Mitarbeiter in bersee</italics>. Liebenzeller Mission, Bad Liebenzell 2004, ISBN 3-921113-61-X.<list type='bullet'><listitem>mit dem verkrzten Untertitel<space/><italics>Einfhrung in seine begrifflichen Grundlagen</italics><space/>auch bei: Erlanger Verlag fr Mission und Okumene, Neuendettelsau 2004, ISBN 3-87214-609-2.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Badenberg, Robert: &quot;How about 'Animism'? An Inquiry beyond Label and Legacy&quot;. In:<space/><italics>Mission als Kommunikation. Festschrift fr Ursula Wiesemann zu ihrem 75. Geburtstag</italics>, edited by Klaus W. Mller. VTR, Nrnberg 2007; ISBN 978-3-937965-75-8 and VKW, Bonn 2007; ISBN 978-3-938116-33-3.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>sisterlinks</target><arg name="d">no</arg><arg name="b">no</arg><arg name="s">no</arg><arg name="v">no</arg><arg name="voy">no</arg><arg name="species">no</arg><arg name="q">no</arg><arg name="n">no</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.roboethics.org/icra2007/contributions/KITANO%20Animism%20Rinri%20Modernization%20the%20Base%20of%20Japanese%20Robo.pdf'>Animism, Rinri, Modernization; the Base of Japanese Robotics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.snopes.com/religion/soulweight.asp'>Urban Legends Reference Pages: Weight of the Soul</link><link type='external' href='http://www.ishmael.org/Interaction/QandA/list.cfm'></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.animist-network.de/index_e.html'>Animist Network</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template><template><target>philosophy of religion</target></template><template><target>witchcraft</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Animism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Anthropology of religion</target></link><link><target>Category:Polytheism</target></link><link><target>Category:Spiritualism</target></link></paragraph></article>