<article title='Tank_destroyer'><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">March 2009</arg></template><link><target>File:Tank destroyers.jpg</target><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Two American<space/><link><target>M10 tank destroyer</target><part>M10 Wolverine</part></link><space/>tank destroyers in France during World War II</part></link>A<space/><bold>tank destroyer</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>tank hunter</bold><space/>is a type of<space/><link><target>armoured fighting vehicle</target></link>, armed with a direct-fire artillery<space/><link><target>Tank gun</target><part>gun</part></link><space/>or missile launcher, with limited operational capacities and<space/><italics>designed specifically</italics><space/>to engage<space/><link><target>tank</target><part>enemy armoured vehicles</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Tanks are generally<space/><link><target>armoured fighting vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>designed for<space/><link><target>front-line</target></link><space/>combat which combine<space/><link><target>operational mobility</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Military tactics</target><part>tactical</part></link><space/>offensive and defensive capabilities and perform all primary tasks of the armoured troops on the<space/><link><target>battle</target><trail>field</trail></link>; the tank destroyer on the other hand is specifically designed mainly for taking on enemy armour.<extension extension_name='ref'>von Senger and Etterlin (1960),<space/><italics>The World's Armored Fighting Vehicles</italics>, p.9.</extension><space/>Many have been based on a<space/><link><target>Continuous track</target><part>tracked</part></link><space/>tank<space/><link><target>chassis</target></link>, while others are wheeled.</paragraph><paragraph>Since<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, gun-armed tank destroyers have fallen out of favor as armies have favored multirole<space/><link><target>main battle tank</target><trail>s</trail></link>. However, lightly armored<space/><link><target>Anti-tank missile</target><part>anti tank guided missile</part></link><space/>(ATGM) carriers are commonly used for supplementary long-range anti-tank work. The resurgence of<space/><link><target>expeditionary warfare</target></link><space/>in the past twenty years has seen the emergence of gun-armed wheeled vehicles, sometimes called &quot;protected gun systems&quot;, which may bear a superficial resemblance to tank destroyers, but are employed as direct fire support units typically providing support in low-intensity operations such as the wars in<space/><link><target>Iraq War</target><part>Iraq</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>War in Afghanistan (2001present)</target><part>Afghanistan</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>World War II</heading><paragraph>Dedicated anti-tank vehicles made their first major appearance in the Second World War as combatants developed effective armored vehicles and tactics. Some were little more than stopgap solutions, mounting an<space/><link><target>anti-tank gun</target></link><space/>on a tracked vehicle to give mobility, while others were more sophisticated designs. An example of the development of tank destroyer technology throughout the war are the<space/><link><target>Marder III</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hetzer</target></link><space/>vehicle, that were very different in spite of being based on the same chassis: Marder was straightforwardly an anti-tank gun on tracks whereas Hetzer traded some firepower (its<space/><link><target>7.5 cm PaK 39</target><part>Pak 39</part></link>, designed to operate within the confines of a fully armored fighting compartment, fires the same projectiles from a reduced propellant charge compared to Marder's<space/><link><target>7.5 cm Pak 40</target><part>Pak 40</part></link>) for better armor protection and ease of concealment on the battlefield.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Except for most American designs, tank destroyers were all turretless and had fixed or<space/><link><target>casemate</target></link><space/>superstructures. When a tank destroyer was used against enemy tanks from a defensive position such as by ambush, the common lack of a rotating turret was not particularly critical, while the lower silhouette was highly desirable. The turretless design allowed accommodation of a more powerful gun, typically a dedicated anti-tank gun (in lieu of a regular tank's general-purpose<space/><link><target>tank gun</target><part>main gun</part></link><space/>that fired both anti-tank and high explosive ammunition) that had a longer barrel than could be mounted in a turreted tank on the same chassis. The lack of a turret increased the vehicle's internal volume, allowing for increased ammunition stowage and crew comfort.<extension extension_name='ref'>(<link><target>#References</target><part>Perrett 1987:84</part></link>)</extension><space/>Eliminating the turret allowed the vehicle to carry thicker armor than would otherwise be the case, and also allowed this armour to be concentrated in the hull. Sometimes there was no armored roof (only a weather cover) to keep the overall weight down to the limit that the chassis could bear. The absence of a turret meant that tank destroyers could be manufactured significantly cheaper, faster and more easily than the tanks on which they were based and found particular favor when production resources were lacking. After hard lessons early in the war, machine guns were mounted for use against infantry, but the limited traverse of the mounting meant that they were still less effective than those used on turreted tanks.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Polish</heading><paragraph>Variants of the Polish<space/><link><target>TKS</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>TK-3</target></link><space/>tankettes up-armed with 20&amp;nbsp;mm gun (2326 vehicles) were operationally deployed in the<space/><link><target>invasion of Poland</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>A. Joca, R. Szubaski, J. Tarczyski, Wrzesie 1939 Pojazdy Wojska Polskiego, Wyd. WKi, Warszawa 1990, s. 72.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>There were also 37&amp;nbsp;mm armed<space/><link><target>TKS-D</target></link><space/>(2 experimental vehicles) or 45&amp;nbsp;mm armed<space/><link><target>TKD</target></link><space/>(4 experimental vehicles). It is not sure whether they were used operationally at all.</extension><space/>They were used as an anti-tank component of the reconnaissance units.</paragraph><heading level='3'>French</heading><paragraph>Due to the quick defeat of France, few French vehicles were built. The Laffly W15 TCC (<italics>Chasseur de char</italics>) was an attempt to quickly build a light tank destroyer by mounting a 47mm SA37 anti-tank gun onto a lightly armored<space/><link><target>Laffly S15</target><part>Laffly W15T</part></link><space/>artillery tractor. Other French tank destroyers were being developed, including the SOMUA SAu-40, ARL V39 and various ad hoc conversions of the<space/><link><target>Lorraine 37L</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>German</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-782-0041-31, Nordafrika, Panzerjger 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Panzerjger'' I</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target><part>German</part></link><space/>tank destroyers were the<space/><italics><link><target>Panzerjger</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;tank hunters&quot;) which took an existing anti-tank gun and mounted it on a convenient chassis to give mobility, usually with just a three-sided<space/><link><target>gun shield</target></link><space/>for crew protection. For instance, 202 obsolete<space/><link><target>Panzer I</target></link><space/>light tanks were modified by removing the turret and were rebuilt as the<space/><link><target>Panzerjger I</target></link><space/>self-propelled<space/><link><target>koda Works</target><part>Skoda</part></link><space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>47 mm</arg></template><space/>anti-tank gun. Similarly,<space/><link><target>Panzer II</target></link><space/>tanks were used on the eastern front. Captured Soviet<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>76.2 mm</arg></template><space/>anti-tank guns were mounted on modified Panzer II chassis, producing the<space/><link><target>Marder II</target></link><space/>self-propelled anti-tank gun. The most common mounting was a German<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>75 mm</arg></template><space/>anti-tank gun on the Czech<space/><link><target>Panzer 38(t)</target></link><space/>chassis to produce the<space/><link><target>Marder III</target></link>. The Panzer 38(t) chassis was also used to make the Jagdpanzer 38 '<link><target>Hetzer</target></link>' casemate style tank destroyer. The Panzerjger series continued up to the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>88 mm</arg></template><space/>equipped<space/><link><target>Nashorn</target></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:StuG-III-latrun-2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Sturmgeschtz'' III</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>German tank destroyers based on the<space/><link><target>Panzer III</target></link><space/>and later German tanks were unique in that they had more armor than their tank counterparts. One of the more successful German tank destroyers was actually designed as a self-propelled artillery gun, the<space/><link><target>Sturmgeschtz III</target></link>. Based on the Panzer III tank chassis, the Sturmgeschtz III was originally fitted with a low-velocity gun, and was assigned to the artillery arm for infantry fire support. Later, after encountering Soviet tanks, it was refitted with a comparatively short-barreled high-velocity anti-tank gun, usually with a<space/><link><target>muzzle brake</target></link>, enabling it to function as a tank destroyer. The<space/><italics>Sturmgeschtz III</italics><space/>from its 1938 origin used a new casemate-style superstructure with an integrated design similar to the later<space/><italics><link><target>Jagdpanzer</target></link></italics><space/>to completely enclose the crew. It was employed in infantry support and offensive armored operations as well as in the defensive anti-tank role. The StuG III was the most-produced German armored fighting vehicle of any type built during the war years, with some 10,000 examples built from January 1940 through March 1945.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Jagdpanther2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''Jagdpanther''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Although the early German<space/><italics>Panzerjger</italics><space/>carried more effective weapons than the tanks on which they were based, they were generally lacking in protection for the crew, having thinly armored open-topped superstructures. The &quot;open-topped&quot; design format of the<space/><italics>Panzerjger</italics><space/>vehicles was succeeded by the<space/><italics>Jagdpanzer</italics><space/>'(&quot;hunting tanks&quot;) which mounted the gun in true casemate-style superstructures, completely enclosing the crew compartment in armor that would usually be integral to the hull. The first of these<space/><italics>Jagdpanzer</italics>s was the<space/><italics>Ferdinand</italics><space/>(later renamed the<space/><italics><link><target>Elefant</target></link></italics>), a 70-ton monster built from the already-built quantity of ninety-one Porsche<space/><link><target>VK4501</target></link>(P)-based<space/><link><target>Tiger I#Design history</target><part>Tiger I</part></link><space/>losing contract contender's hulls and drive systems, mounting a long-barreled<space/><link><target>8.8 cm Pak 43</target><part>88&amp;nbsp;mm</part></link><space/>cannon in an added casemate, more like the earlier<space/><italics>Panzerjgers</italics><space/>had with their added-on armor shielding for the guncrew, but in the<space/><italics>Elefant</italics><space/>completely enclosing the gun and firing crew in the added casemate, as the later purpose-built<space/><italics>Jagdpanzers</italics><space/>would. However, the<space/><italics>Elefant</italics><space/>proved to be mechanically unreliable and difficult to maneuver, and once all ninety-one unturreted &quot;Porsche Tiger&quot; hulls/drive systems were converted, no more were built. The German Army had more success with the<space/><link><target>Jagdpanther</target></link>. Introduced in mid-1944, the Jagdpanther was considered the best of the casemate-design Jagdpanzer designs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks">Forty and Livesey 2006 p. 33</extension><space/>It featured the same powerful PaK 43 88mm cannon used on the unwieldy<space/><italics>Elefant</italics>, now fitted to the chassis of the medium<space/><link><target>Panther tank</target></link>, providing greatly improved armor-penetrating capability in a medium-weight vehicle.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Jagdtiger 1 Bovington.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Jagdtiger''</part></link>Facing an increasingly defensive war, the German Army turned to larger and more powerfully armed Jagdpanzer designs, and in July 1944 the first<space/><italics><link><target>Jagdtiger</target></link></italics><space/>rolled off the production line; it was the heaviest German armored fighting vehicle to go into active service.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Jagdtiger</italics><space/>featured a huge<space/><link><target>12.8 cm Pak 44</target><part>128&amp;nbsp;mm PaK 44</part></link><space/>cannon and heavy armor protection. Only 88<space/><italics>Jagdtiger</italics><space/>vehicles were produced, barely matching the total number of the earlier Ferdinand/Elefant vehicles. They were first deployed to combat units in September 1944.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The decision of German armored vehicle designers to use a casemate-style superstructure for all tank destroyers had the advantage of a reduced silhouette, allowing the crew to more frequently fire from defilade ambush positions. Such designs were also easier and faster to manufacture and offered good crew protection from artillery fire and shell splinters. However, the lack of a rotating turret limited the gun's traverse to a few degrees. This meant that the entire tank normally had to be turned onto its target by the driver, a much slower process than simply rotating a powered turret.<extension extension_name='ref'>Irwin, John P.<space/><italics>Another River, Another Town</italics>, New York: Random House Publishers (2002), pp. 6161</extension><space/>If the vehicle became immobilized due to engine failure or track damage, it could not rotate its gun to counter opposing tanks, making it highly vulnerable to counterfire.<extension extension_name='ref'>Irwin, pp. 6161</extension><space/>This vulnerability was later exploited by opposing tank forces. Even the largest and most powerful of German tank destroyers were found abandoned on the field after a battle, having been immobilized by one or more hits by high explosive (HE) or armor-piercing (AP) shells to the track or front drive sprocket.<extension extension_name='ref'>Irwin, pp. 6162: Even the U.S. M4 Sherman could disable a Jagdpanther's track or fracture the front drive sprocket with a 75&amp;nbsp;mm HE shell. As the crew abandoned their vehicle, they were easy targets for enemy machinegun fire.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Soviet</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:ISU-122 skos RB.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Soviet<space/><link><target>ISU-122</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>casemate</target></link><space/>tank destroyer of the Second World War, shown here with postwar<space/><link><target>Polish Army</target></link><space/>markings</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Samokhodnaya ustanovka</arg></template>As with the Germans, most of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>Soviet</part></link><space/>designs mounted anti-tank guns, with limited traverse in casemate-style turretless hulls, in a general design format looking much like the Germans' own<space/><italics>Jagdpanzer</italics><space/>vehicles. The results were smaller, lighter, and simpler to build than tanks, but could carry larger guns. The Soviets produced the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>85 mm</arg></template><space/><link><target>SU-85</target></link><space/>and<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>100 mm</arg></template><space/><link><target>SU-100</target></link><space/>self-propelled guns based on the same chassis as the<space/><link><target>T-34</target></link><space/>medium tank, as well as the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>122 mm</arg></template><space/><link><target>ISU-122</target></link><space/>and<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>152 mm</arg></template><space/><link><target>ISU-152</target></link><space/>which shared components with the<space/><link><target>IS-2</target></link><space/>heavy tank and was nicknamed<space/><italics>Zveroboy</italics><space/>(&quot;beast killer&quot;) for its ability to destroy German<space/><link><target>Tiger I tank</target><part>Tigers</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Panther tank</target><part>Panthers</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elefant</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The predecessor of the ISU 152 was the SU 152, built on the KV1S chassis and shared many similarities (incl. its gun) with the ISU 152. The ISU-152 built as a heavy assault gun, relied on the weight of the shell fired from its M-1937/43 howitzer to defeat tanks.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks2">Forty and Livesey 2006 p. 329</extension><space/>In 1943, the Soviets also shifted all production of light tanks like the<space/><link><target>T-70</target></link><space/>to much simpler and better-armed<space/><link><target>SU-76</target></link><space/>self-propelled guns, which used the same drive train. The SU-76 was originally designed as an anti-tank vehicle, but was soon relegated to the infantry-support role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks3">Forty and Livesey 2006 p. 392</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>American</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Tank destroyer battalion (United States)</arg></template><link><target>United States Army</target><part>U.S. Army</part></link><space/>and counterpart<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>British</part></link><space/>designs were very different in conception. U.S. doctrine was based, in light of the<space/><link><target>fall of France</target></link>, on the perceived need to defeat German<space/><link><target>blitzkrieg</target></link><space/>tactics, and U.S. units expected to be faced with large numbers of German tanks attacking on relatively narrow fronts. These were<space/><italics>expected</italics><space/>to break through a thin screen of anti-tank guns, hence the decision that the main anti-tank units the<space/><link><target>Tank destroyer battalion (United States)</target><part>Tank Destroyer (TD) battalions</part></link><space/>should be concentrated and very mobile. In actual practice, such German attacks rarely happened; throughout the war only one battalion ever fought in an engagement quite like that which had originally been envisaged (the<space/><link><target>601st Tank Destroyer Battalion</target><part>601st</part></link>, at the<space/><link><target>Battle of El Guettar</target></link>). The Tank Destroyer Command eventually numbered over 100,000 men and 80 battalions each equipped with 36 self-propelled tank destroyers or towed guns.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Aberdean proving grounds 036.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>3in Gun Motor Carriage M10</part></link>Only<space/><link><target>Shoot-and-scoot</target><part>a few shots were expected to be fired from any firing position</part></link>. Strong reconnaissance elements were provided so that TDs would be able to use pre-arranged firing positions to best advantage.<space/><link><target>Flanking fire</target></link><space/>by TDs was emphasized, both to penetrate thinner enemy side armor, and to reduce the likelihood of accurate enemy return fire.</paragraph><paragraph>All American tank destroyers were officially known by exactly the same collective term used for American self-propelled artillery ordnance, &quot;Gun Motor Carriage&quot;. The designs were intended to be very mobile and heavily armed. Most of the tank-hull based designs used special open-topped turrets, of a differing design to the original tank it was to be based on, which was meant to both save weight and to accommodate a larger gun. The earliest expedient design was an<space/><link><target>M3 Half-track</target></link><space/>mounting an M1897<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>75 mm</arg></template><space/>gun in a limited-traverse mount, and called the<space/><link><target>M3 GMC</target><part>75 mm Gun Motor Carriage M3</part></link>. Another, considerably less successful, early design mounted a 37-mm anti-tank gun in the bed of a Dodge 3/4-ton truck - the<space/><link><target>M6 Fargo</target><part>37-mm GMC M6</part></link>. By far the most common US design was the<space/><link><target>M10 Tank Destroyer</target><part>3in Gun Motor Carriage M10 (Wolverine)</part></link>, later supplemented by the<space/><link><target>M36 tank destroyer</target><part>90&amp;nbsp;mm Gun Motor Carriage M36</part></link><space/>- both based on the<space/><link><target>M4 Sherman</target></link><space/>hull and powertrain - and the<space/><link><target>M18 Hellcat</target><part>76&amp;nbsp;mm Gun Motor Carriage M18 (Hellcat)</part></link>, based on a unique hull and powertrain design, with a slight visual resemblance to what was used for the later<space/><link><target>M24 Chaffee</target></link><space/>light tank. The M18 came closest to the US ideal; the vehicle was very fast, small, and mounted a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>76 mm</arg></template><space/>gun in a roofless open turret. The M36 Jackson GMC possessed the only American-origin operational gun that could rival<space/><link><target>8.8 cm Pak 43</target><part>the vaunted 88&amp;nbsp;mm</part></link><space/>German anti-tank ordnance, the<space/><link><target>90 mm Gun M1/M2/M3</target><part>90 mm M3 gun</part></link>, and the M36 remained in service well after World War II. The only dedicated American-origin, casemate hull design fighting vehicle of any type to be built during the war, that resembled the German and Soviet tank destroyers in hull and general gun mounting design, was the experimental<space/><link><target>T28 Super Heavy Tank</target></link>, which mounted a 105&amp;nbsp;mm T5E1 long-barrel cannon, which had a maximum firing range of 12 miles (20&amp;nbsp;km), and was originally designed as a self-propelled assault gun to breach Germany's<space/><link><target>Siegfried Line</target></link><space/>defenses.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Of these tank destroyers, only the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>90 mm</arg></template><space/>gun of the M36 proved to be effective against the frontal armor of Germans' larger armored vehicles at long range.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks3">Forty and Livesey 2006 p. 117</extension><space/>The open top and light armor made these tank destroyers vulnerable to anything greater than small-arms fire. As the number of German tanks encountered by American forces steadily decreased throughout the war, most battalions were split up and assigned to infantry units as supporting arms, fighting as<space/><link><target>assault gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or being used essentially as tanks.</paragraph><paragraph>Doctrinists' expectation that German tanks would be engaged in mass formation was a failed assumption. In reality, German attacks effectively utilized<space/><link><target>combined arms</target></link><space/>on the ground fighting cohesively. American tank destroyer battalions comprised three tank destroyer companies supported by nine security sections. The single-purpose tactics of the tank destroyer battalion failed to account for non-tank threats.<extension extension_name='ref' name="single purpose"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Gabel</arg><arg name="first1">Christopher R.</arg><arg name="title">Seek, Strike and Destroy: US Army Tank Destroyer Doctrine in World War II</arg><arg name="publisher">DIANE Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn">9781428915770</arg><arg name="pages">68-69</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British</heading><paragraph>British tanks in the early years of the war, both infantry and cruiser, were (with the exception of the pre-war Matilda I design) equipped with a gun capable of use against contemporary enemy tanks - the 40&amp;nbsp;mm<space/><link><target>Ordnance QF 2 pounder</target></link>. This was replaced with the 57&amp;nbsp;mm<space/><link><target>Ordnance QF 6 pounder</target></link><space/>when that became available. There was extra impetus given to the development of anti-tank weaponry, which culminated in the 76mm<space/><link><target>Ordnance QF 17 pounder</target></link>, widely considered one of the best anti-tank guns of the war.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tanks4">Forty and Livesey 2006 p. 116</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Towed anti-tank guns were the domain of the<space/><link><target>Royal Artillery</target></link><space/>rather than the<space/><link><target>Royal Armoured Corps</target></link><space/>and vehicles adapted to mount artillery, including anti-tank self-propelled guns such as the<space/><link><target>Deacon (artillery)</target><part>Deacon</part></link><space/>(6pdr on an armoured wheeled truck chassis) and<space/><link><target>Archer (tank destroyer)</target><part>Archer</part></link><space/>(17pdr on tracked chassis), were their preserve, as were US-supplied vehicles.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Archer SP 17 pdr Tank Destroyer.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Archer. The gun faced to the rear</part></link><link><target>Image:Achilles tank destroyer on the east bank of the Rhine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A British Achilles self-propelled anti-tank gun on the east bank of the<space/><link><target>Rhine</target></link>.</part></link>The self-propelled guns that were built in the &quot;tank destroyer&quot; mould came about through the desire to field the QF 17 pounder anti-tank gun and simultaneous lack of suitable standard tanks to carry it. As a result, they were of a somewhat extemporized nature. Mounting the gun on the<space/><link><target>Valentine tank</target></link><space/>chassis in a fixed superstructure gave the<space/><link><target>Archer (tank destroyer)</target><part>Archer</part></link>, looking somewhat like the light-chassis German<space/><link><target>Marder III</target></link><space/>in appearance. The 17 pounder was also used to re-equip the US-supplied<space/><link><target>M10 Tank Destroyer</target></link>, replacing the American 3-inch gun to produce the<space/><link><target>17pdr SP Achilles</target></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>While there was a general move to a general purpose gun that was usable against both tanks and in supporting infantry, there was a need to put the 17 pdr into a tank for use against the enemy's heavy tanks. The<space/><link><target>Cruiser Mk VIII Challenger</target></link><space/>was a project to bring a 17 pdr tank into use to support the<space/><link><target>Cromwell tank</target><part>Cromwell cruiser tank</part></link>. Delays led to it being outnumbered in use by the<space/><link><target>Sherman Firefly</target></link>, but a derivative of Challenger was the more-or-less open-topped variant<space/><italics>Avenger</italics><space/>which was delayed until post war before entering service. A cut-down 17 pdr - the 77mmHV was used to equip the<space/><link><target>Comet tank</target></link><space/>in the last year of the war.</paragraph><paragraph>The closest the British came to developing an armored tank destroyer in the vein of the German Jagdpanzers or Soviet ISU series was the Churchill 3-inch Gun Carrier - a<space/><link><target>Churchill tank</target></link><space/>chassis with a boxy superstructure in place of the turret and mounting a<space/><link><target>QF 3-inch 20 cwt</target><part>3-inch anti-aircraft gun</part></link>. Although a number were ordered, they were not put into service as the immediate threat passed. The design was rejected in favor of developing a 17 pounder armed Cromwell tank variant, ultimately leading to the<space/><link><target>Comet tank</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Tortoise (tank)</target><part>Tortoise</part></link><space/>&quot;heavy assault tank&quot; , intended for use in breaking through fixed defensive lines, was well armoured and had a very powerful 32-pounder (94 mm) gun, but did not reach service use.</paragraph><paragraph>By 1944, a number of the<space/><link><target>Sherman tank</target><part>Shermans</part></link><space/>in British use were being converted to<space/><link><target>Sherman Fireflies</target></link><space/>by adding the QF 17 pounder gun. Initially this gave each troop (platoon) of Shermans one powerfully armed tank. By war's end - through the production of more Fireflies and the replacement of Shermans by British tanks - about 50% of Shermans in British service were Fireflies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Post-World War II</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Charioteer-latrun-2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A<space/><link><target>FV 4101 Charioteer</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv B 145 Bild-F027421-0002, Kanonenjagdpanzer (KanJPz) - Jagdpanzer Kanone 90 mm.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A German Jagdpanzer Kanone with 90 mm gun.</part></link>In the face of the Warsaw Pact, a general need for extra firepower was identified. In the 1950s, the UK produced the<space/><link><target>FV 4101 Charioteer</target></link><space/>to beef up the tank regiments, mounting a 20 pounder gun in an oversize turret on the Cromwell tank hullit lacked the all round capability of the<space/><link><target>Centurion tank</target></link>. In the late 1960s, Germany developed the<space/><link><target>Kanonenjagdpanzer</target></link>, essentially a modernized World War II Jagdpanzer mounting a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>90 mm</arg></template><space/>gun. As Soviet designs became more heavily armored, the<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>90 mm</arg></template><space/>gun became ineffective and the Kanonenjagdpanzers were retrofitted for different roles or retired. Some provisions were made for the fitting of a 105&amp;nbsp;mm cannon, and many of the vehicles were modified to fire<space/><link><target>Euromissile HOT</target><part>HOT</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>TOW missile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in place of a main gun. These upgraded variants remained in service into the 1990s.<extension extension_name='ref'>(<link><target>#References</target><part>Gelbart 1996:137-8</part></link>)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>With the development of flexible<space/><link><target>anti-tank missile</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which were capable of installation on almost any vehicle in the 1960s, the concept of the tank destroyer has morphed into light vehicles with missiles. With the weight of<space/><link><target>main battle tank</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>growing to the forty to seventy-tonne range, airborne forces were unable to deploy reasonable anti-tank forces. The result was a number of attempts to make a light vehicle, including the conventional<space/><link><target>ASU-85</target></link>, the recoilless rifle-armed<space/><link><target>Ontos</target></link>, and missile-armed<space/><link><target>Malkara missile#FV1620 Humber Hornet</target><part>Hornet Malkara</part></link><space/>armored car and<space/><link><target>M551 Sheridan</target><part>Sheridan</part></link><space/>light assault vehicle. The latest entry into that category is the<space/><link><target>2S25</target><part>2S25 Sprut-SD</part></link>, armed with a current-issue 125 mm tank gun that is also capable of launching missiles like the<space/><link><target>9M119 Svir</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern</heading><paragraph>Many forces'<space/><link><target>infantry fighting vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(IFV) carry<space/><link><target>anti-tank missile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in every infantry platoon, and<space/><link><target>attack helicopter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have also added anti-tank capability to the modern battlefield. But there are still dedicated anti-tank vehicles with very heavy long-range missiles, and ones intended for<space/><link><target>Airborne forces</target><part>airborne</part></link><space/>use.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:NM142 x 3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A Norwegian anti-tank platoon equipped with<space/><link><target>NM142</target></link><space/>TOW missile launchers</part></link>There have also been dedicated anti-tank vehicles built on ordinary<space/><link><target>armoured personnel carrier</target><part>armored personnel carrier</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>armored car (military)</target><part>armored car</part></link><space/>chassis. Examples include the U.S.<space/><link><target>M901 ITV</target><part>M901 ITV (Improved TOW Vehicle)</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Norway</target><part>Norwegian</part></link><space/><link><target>NM142</target></link>, both on an<space/><link><target>M113 armored personnel carrier</target><part>M113</part></link><space/>chassis, several<space/><link><target>Soviet Army</target><part>Soviet</part></link><space/>ATGM launchers based on the<space/><link><target>BRDM</target></link><space/>reconnaissance car, the British<space/><link><target>FV438 Swingfire</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>FV102 Striker</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Germany</target><part>German</part></link><space/><link><target>Raketenjagdpanzer</target></link><space/>series built on the chassis of the<space/><link><target>HS 30</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Marder (IFV)</target><part>Marder</part></link><space/>IFV.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>United States Army</target><part>US Army</part></link><space/>combined arms battalion has two infantry companies with TOW missile-armed<space/><link><target>M2 Bradley</target><part>Bradley IFVs</part></link><space/>and can bring a large concentration of accurate and lethal fire to bear on an attacking enemy unit that uses AFVs. They can be complemented by mobile units of AH-64 Apache Helicopters armed with Hellfire antitank missiles.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Pzj Tow PIRANHA - Schweizer Armee - Steel Parade 2006.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Mowag Piranha</target></link>-based,<space/><link><target>BGM-71 TOW</target><part>TOW</part></link>-armed ATGM carrier of the<space/><link><target>Swiss Army</target></link></part></link>Missile carrying vehicles however are referred to as<space/><link><target>anti-tank missile carriers</target></link><space/>instead of tank destroyers.</paragraph><paragraph>Some gun-armed tank destroyers continue to be used.<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>has developed the tracked<space/><link><target>Type 89 (Tank Destroyer)</target><part>PTZ89</part></link><space/>and the wheeled<space/><link><target>PTL02</target></link><space/>tank destroyers. PTZ89 is armed with a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>120 mm</arg></template><space/>smoothbore cannon while PTL02, developed by NORINCO for the PLA's new light (rapid reaction) mechanized infantry divisions, carries a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>100 mm</arg></template><space/>one (a version armed with a 105&amp;nbsp;mm rifled gun is available for export). PTL02 is built on the 66 wheeled chassis of the<space/><link><target>WZ551</target></link><space/>APC.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link><space/>use the Italian-built<space/><link><target>Centauro</target></link>, a wheeled tank destroyer with a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>105 mm</arg></template><space/>cannon. The gun-armed tank destroyer may possibly see revival in the US Army through the introduction of the<space/><link><target>Stryker</target></link>, more specifically, the<space/><link><target>M1128 Mobile Gun System</target></link>, a Stryker variant armed with a<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>105 mm</arg></template><space/>cannon which has remote control and autoloading capabilities. Originally, the Canadian Forces had considered replacing their aging<space/><link><target>Leopard 1</target></link><space/>tanks with the Stryker Mobile Gun System. But with the increased use of<space/><link><target>Improvised explosive device</target><part>IEDs</part></link><space/>capable of destroying Strykers by insurgent forces, they opted instead to purchase the<space/><link><target>Leopard 2</target></link><space/>tank.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Armoured warfare</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jagdpanzer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Panzerjger</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Harry Yeide, (2005)<space/><italics>The Tank Killers: A History of America's World War II Tank Destroyer Force.</italics><space/>Havertown, PA: Casemate. ISBN 1-932033-26-2</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Bryan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Perrett<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1987<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Soviet Armour Since 1945<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Blandford Press<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7137-1735-1<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Marsh<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Gelbart<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tanks: Main battle and light tanks<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Brassey's<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-85753-168-X<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Forty, George and Livesy, Jack, eds.<space/><italics>The Complete Guide to Tanks &amp; Armoured Fighting Vehicles</italics>. London: Anness Publishing Ltd., 2006. ISBN 1-84681-110-4.</listitem><listitem>Tankdestroyer.net (Web based United States tank destroyer forces information resource)<space/><link type='external' href='http://tankdestroyer.net/'>Tankdestroyer.net</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=hCcDAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA75&amp;amp;dq=popular+science+April+1940&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=SHqMTJ6CK8fanAeroIC0Cw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=5&amp;amp;ved=0CEUQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>''Popular Science'', April 1940, ''Tanks Can Be Destroyed''</link><space/>article on early US Army concepts for tank destroyers</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.allmilitaryweapons.com/2011/08/list-of-tank-destroyer.html'>Tank Destroyer List</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Tank Destroyer</target></template><link><target>Category:Tank destroyers</target><part>*</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>ja:</target></link></paragraph></article>