<article title='Cruising_%28maritime%29'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>yacht cruising</arg><arg>cruising on cruise liners</arg><arg>Cruise ship</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cruiser at Green Island Panama.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>275px</part><part>A cruising sailboat anchored in the<space/><link><target>San Blas Islands</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>Panama</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Cruising</bold><space/>by boat is a lifestyle that involves living for extended time on a vessel while traveling from place to place for pleasure. Cruising generally refers to trips of a few days or more, and can extend to round-the-world voyages.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="quote">"The sea, the great unifier, is man's only hope. Now, as never before,<br><space/>the old phrase has a literal meaning: We are all in the same boat."</arg><arg name="source">[[Jacques Cousteau]]</arg></template>Boats were almost exclusively used for working purposes prior to the nineteenth century. In 1857, the philosopher<space/><link><target>Henry David Thoreau</target></link>, with his book<space/><italics>Canoeing in Wilderness</italics><space/>chronicling his canoe voyaging in the wilderness of Maine, was the first to convey the enjoyment of spiritual and lifestyle aspects of cruising.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:AnInlandVoyageBarge.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>'Canal barges in Belgium', an image from<space/><link><target>Robert Louis Stevenson</target></link>'s book, ''<link><target>An Inland Voyage</target></link>''.</part></link>The modern conception of cruising for pleasure was first popularised by the Scottish explorer and sportsman<space/><link><target>John MacGregor (sportsman)</target><part>John MacGregor</part></link>. He was introduced to the canoes and kayaks of the<space/><link><target>Indigenous peoples of the Americas</target><part>Native Americans</part></link><space/>on a camping trip in 1858, and on his return to the United Kingdom constructed his own 'double-ended' canoe in<space/><link><target>Lambeth</target></link>. The boat, nicknamed 'Rob Roy' after a famous relative of his, was built of lapstrake oak planking, decked in cedar covered with rubberized canvas with an open cockpit in the center. He cruised around the waterways of Britain, Europe and the Middle East and wrote a popular book about his experiences,<space/><italics>A Thousand Miles in the Rob Roy Canoe</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1866, Macgregor was a moving force behind the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Royal Canoe Club</target></link>, the first club in the world to promote pleasure cruising.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://sports.london-2012.co.uk/Kayaking/'>Canoe and Kayak</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://sports.london-2012.co.uk/Kayaking/<space/></arg><arg name="date">20080822061202<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.olympic.org/uk/sports/programme/history_uk.asp?DiscCode=CF&amp;amp;sportCode=CA'>Olympic Canoe and Kayak Flatwater History</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.olympic.org/uk/sports/programme/history_uk.asp?DiscCode</arg><arg name="date">20150403160838<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The first recorded<space/><link><target>regatta</target></link><space/>was held at on 27 April 1867, and it received Royal patronage in 1873. The latter part of the century saw cruising for leisure being enthusiastically taken up by the middle class. The author<space/><link><target>Robert Louis Stevenson</target></link><space/>wrote<space/><italics><link><target>An Inland Voyage</target></link></italics><space/>in 1877 as a<space/><link><target>travel literature</target><part>travelogue</part></link><space/>on his<space/><link><target>canoe</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>trip through<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Belgium</target></link>. Stevenson and his companion, Sir<space/><link><target>Simpson baronets</target><part>Walter Grindlay Simpson</part></link><space/>travelled in two 'Rob Roys' along the<space/><link><target>Oise River</target></link><space/>and witnessed the<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target><part>Romantic</part></link><space/>beauty of rural Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>The Canadian-American<space/><link><target>Joshua Slocum</target></link><space/>was one of the first people to carry out a long-distance sailing voyage for pleasure,<space/><link><target>circumnavigation</target><part>circumnavigating</part></link><space/>the world between 1895 and 1898. Despite opinion that such a voyage was impossible, Slocum rebuilt a derelict<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>37</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>sloop<space/><italics>Spray</italics><space/>and sailed her<space/><link><target>single-handed sailing</target><part>single-handed</part></link><space/>around the world. His book<space/><italics>Sailing Alone Around the World</italics><space/>was a classic adventure, and inspired many others to take to the seas.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Sailing Alone Around the World</italics>, Captain Joshua Slocum; Sheridan House, 1954. ISBN 0-911378-20-0</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dugout in San Blas Islands.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>240px</part><part>Cruisers can see traditional life in remote areas of the world; here, a<space/><link><target>Kuna (people)</target><part>Kuna</part></link><space/>paddles a dugout canoe in the<space/><link><target>San Blas Islands</target></link>.</part></link>Other cruising authors have provided both inspiration and instruction to prospective cruisers. Key among these during the post World War II period are Electa and<space/><link><target>Irving Johnson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Miles and Beryl Smeeton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bernard Moitessier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Peter Pye</target></link>, and Eric and Susan Hiscock. During the 1970s - 1990s<space/><link><target>Robin Lee Graham</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lin and Larry Pardey</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Annie Hill</target></link>, Herb Payson, Linda and Steve Dashew, Margaret and<space/><link><target>Hal Roth</target></link>, and Beth Leonard &amp;<space/><link><target>Evans Starzinger</target></link><space/>have provided inspiration for people to set off voyaging.</paragraph><paragraph>The development of ocean crossing rallies, most notably the ARC (<link><target>Atlantic Rally for Cruisers</target></link>), have encouraged less experienced sailors to undertake ocean crossings. These rallies provide a group of sailors crossing the same ocean at the same time with safety inspections, weather information and social functions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Types of boats used</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Yacht-Samar.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>A motor<space/><link><target>yacht</target></link><space/>in Lorient, Bretagne, France</part></link>Cruising is done on both<space/><link><target>sailboat</target><part>sail</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>motorboat</target><part>power</part></link><space/>boats,<space/><link><target>monohull</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>multihull</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>although sail predominates over longer distances, as ocean-going power boats are considerably more expensive to purchase and operate. The size of the typical cruising boat has increased over the years and is currently in the range of 10 to 15 metres although<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.yachtcouncil.com/boating-stories.asp?t=stories&amp;amp;news_id=248'>Around the world boat yachts and equipment</link></extension><space/>smaller boats have been used in around-the-world trips, but are generally not recommended given the dangers involved.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dixdesign.com/steward.htm'>Anthony Steward sailing around the world in small boat</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.inthepresentsea.com/escape.html'>Webb Chiles giving advice on sailing the globe</link></extension><space/>Many cruisers are &quot;long term&quot; and travel for many years, the most adventurous among them<space/><link><target>Circumnavigation</target><part>circle the globe</part></link><space/>over a period of three to ten years. Many others take a year or two off from work and school for shorter trips and the chance to experience the cruising lifestyle.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Cruise Ship Styles And Differences</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cruiseholidaysguide.com/Article/Cruise-Ship-Styles-and-Differences-244</arg><arg name="publisher">www.CruiseHolidaysGuide.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sailing near shore and at sea</heading><paragraph>Sailing at sea is totally different from sailing near shore. Before embarking on a sea voyage, planning and preparation will include studying charts, almanacs and navigation books and recent weather conditions of the route to be followed. In addition, supplies need to be stocked, navigation instruments checked and the ship itself needs to be inspected and the crew needs to be given exact instruction on the jobs are expected to perform (e.g. the watch; which is generally 4 hours on and 4 hours off, navigation, steering, rigging sails, ...). In addition, the crew needs to be well trained at working together and with the ship in question. Finally, the sailor must be mentally prepared for dealing with harsh situations. An alternative for those people may however be sailing near the coast (coastal cruising), which still gives a certain amount of safety. Sailing near the coast can be done as a ship is always granted '<link><target>innocent passage</target></link>' through the country (most countries usually<space/><link><target>Territorial waters</target><part>claim up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>22</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>off the coast</part></link>). When this method is practiced however, one must still remember that if the ship needs to stop (e.g. for repairs), a trip to a customs checkpoint to have<space/><link><target>passport</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>checked would be required.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Equipment</heading><paragraph>Cruisers use a variety of equipment and techniques to make their voyages possible, or simply more comfortable. The use of wind vane<space/><link><target>Self-steering gear</target><part>self steering</part></link><space/>was common on long distance cruising yachts but is increasingly being supplemented or replaced by electrical auto-pilots.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Solar panels on yacht at sea.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>solar panel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on this<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>yacht can keep her self-sufficient in electrical power.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Though in the past many cruisers had no means of generating<space/><link><target>electricity</target></link><space/>on board and depended on<space/><link><target>kerosene</target></link><space/>and dry-cell<space/><link><target>Battery (electricity)</target><part>batteries</part></link>, today electrical demands are much higher and nearly all cruisers have electrical devices such as lights, communications equipment and refrigeration. Although most boats can generate power from their inboard engines, an increasing number carry auxiliary generators. Carrying sufficient fuel to power engine and generator over a long voyage can be a problem, so many cruising boats are equipped with other ancillary generating devices such as<space/><link><target>Photovoltaic module</target><part>solar panel</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>wind turbine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and towed turbines. Cruisers choosing to spend extended time in very remote locations with minimal access to marinas can opt to equip their vessels with<space/><link><target>watermaker</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(<link><target>reverse-osmosis</target></link><space/>seawater desalination units) used to convert sea water to potable<space/><link><target>fresh water</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Communications satellite</target><part>Satellite communication</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are becoming more common on cruising boats. Many boats are now equipped with<space/><link><target>satellite telephone</target></link><space/>systems; however, these systems can be expensive to use, and may operate only in certain areas. Many cruisers still use<space/><link><target>High frequency</target><part>short wave</part></link><space/>maritime<space/><link><target>single-sideband modulation</target><part>SSB</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>amateur radio</target></link>, which has no running costs. These radios provide two-way voice communications, can receive weather fax graphics or<space/><link><target>GRIB</target></link><space/>files via a laptop computer, and with a compatible modem (e.g.<space/><link><target>PACTOR</target></link>) can send and receive email at very slow speed. Such emails are usually limited to basic communication using plain text, without<space/><link><target>HTML</target></link><space/>formatting or attachments.</paragraph><paragraph>Awareness of impending<space/><link><target>weather</target></link><space/>conditions is particularly important to cruising sailors who are often far from safe harbours and need to steer clear of dangerous weather conditions. Most cruising boats are equipped with a barometer or a weather station that records barometric pressure as well as temperature and provides rudimentary forecasting. For more sophisticated weather forecasting, cruisers rely on their ability to receive forecasts by radio, phone or satellite.</paragraph><paragraph>In order to avoid collisions with other vessels, cruisers rely on a maintaining a regular watch schedule. At night, color-coded running lights help determine the position and orientation of vessels.<space/><link><target>Radar</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aeronautical Information Service</target><part>AIS</part></link><space/>systems are often employed to detect vessels positions and movement in all conditions (day, night, rain and fog).</paragraph><paragraph>Cruisers navigate using paper charts and<space/><link><target>radar</target></link>. Modern yachts are often also equipped with a<space/><link><target>chartplotter</target></link><space/>which enables the use of electronic charts and is linked to<space/><link><target>GPS</target></link><space/>satellites that provide position reports. Some chartplotters have the ability to interface charts and radar images. Those that still wish to work with traditional charts as well as with GPS may do so using a<space/><link><target>Yeoman Plotter</target></link>. Certain advanced sailing vessels have a completely<space/><link><target>automated sailing system</target></link><space/>which includes a plotter, as well as course correcting through a link with the ship's steering organs (e.g. sails, propeller). One such device can be found at the<space/><link><target>The Maltese Falcon (yacht)</target><part>Maltese Falcon</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Expense</heading><paragraph>Purchasing and maintaining a yacht can be costly. Most cruising sailors do not own a house and consider their boat their home during the duration of their cruise. Many cruisers find they spend, on average, 4% of their boat's purchase price annually on boat maintenance.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beyond the Glitz and Glitter</arg><arg name="url">http://www.yachtsurvey.com/boatbuying.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Yacht Survey</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Like living a conventional life on land, the cost of cruising is variable. How much a person ends up spending depends largely on their spending habits (for example, eating out a lot and frequenting marinas vs. preparing local foods aboard and anchoring out) and the type of boat (fancy modern production boats are very expensive to purchase and maintain, whilst low-key cruising boats often involve much lower expenses). Most long-term cruisers prefer to live a simple life, usually with far lower expenses than people who live ashore.</paragraph><paragraph>An alternative solution is to<space/><link><target>Boat sharing</target><part>sail on someone else's yacht</part></link>. Those who know how to sail can sometimes find boats looking for an extra crewmember for a long trip, whilst some non-sailors are also able to find boats willing to carry a hitch-hiker.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Catching a Ride Across the Atlantic</arg><arg name="url">http://www.yachtmollymawk.com/2011/03/hich-hiking-across-the-atlantic/</arg><arg name="publisher">www.yachtmollymawk.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 May 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Crew-finding websites exist to help match-up people looking for a crossing with yachts with a berth available or looking for a temporary crewmember,<space/><link><target>Find a Crew</target></link><space/>for example. Another common tactic for finding a yacht is to visit local<space/><link><target>yacht club</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>marina</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and get to know the sailors there, in the hope that one of them will be able to provide a berth.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Safety</heading><paragraph>Travel by water brings hazards: collision, weather, and equipment failure can lead to dangerous situations such as a sinking or severely disabled and dangerous vessel. For this reason many long distance cruising yachts carry with them emergency equipment such as<space/><link><target>SART</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>EPIRB</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lifeboat (shipboard)</target><part>liferaft</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or proactive lifeboats. Medical emergencies are also of concern, as a medical emergency can occur on a long passage when the closest port is over a week away. For this reason before going cruising many people go through first aid training and carry medical kits. In some parts of the world (e.g., near the Horn of Africa)<space/><link><target>piracy</target></link><space/>can be a problem.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Other kinds of maritime cruising</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Camp cruising</bold>, also known as<space/><bold>beach cruising</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>gunkhole cruising</bold>, is a form of cruising in which sailors sail from point to point in an open or semi-enclosed boat, generally remaining within sight of land. Camp cruisers either camp ashore (&quot;camp cruising&quot; or &quot;beach cruising&quot;), or aboard the boat at anchor. The boats used may be specialized cruising<space/><link><target>dinghies</target></link>, small<space/><link><target>keelboats</target></link>,<space/><link><target>trailer sailer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or general purpose daysailing or racing boats pressed into service for the purpose.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><space/>Commute cruising</bold>, also known as<space/><bold>seasonal cruising</bold>, is becoming increasingly popular. Commute cruisers live aboard and sail for a few months at a time, exploring new or favorite areas, then leave the vessel in a new location or maybe return it to the same location, travel home for a few months, and return to the vessel to continue cruising during favorable seasons. This type of cruising is somewhat akin to owning a second home that travels by sea and allows for a dual lifestyle.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Daysailing</bold><space/>is recreational sailing that does not involve<space/><link><target>Dinghy racing</target><part>racing</part></link><space/>or cruising. Many<space/><link><target>Dinghy racing</target><part>racers</part></link><space/>refer to all non-racers as &quot;cruisers,&quot; including<space/><link><target>Dinghy sailing</target><part>dinghy</part></link><space/>and small keelboat sailors who primarily focus on daysailing.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Travel on<space/><bold><link><target>cruise ship</target><trail>s</trail></link></bold><space/>may be referred to as<space/><italics>cruising</italics>. Those who take frequent cruise ship vacations may be called<space/><italics>cruisers</italics>.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Expedition cruising</bold>, where the trips can be a combination of scientists working and tourists along for the adventure, or where scientists lead a group of tourists in order for the tourists to observe animals, plants or natural phenomena.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Boat building</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cabin Cruiser</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electric boat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gunkholing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Maritime mobile amateur radio</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>River cruise</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sailboat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sailing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Cruising Association</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Div col</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.ca/books/about/The_Handbook_of_Offshore_Cruising.html?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Handbook of offshore cruising: The Dream and Reality of Modern Ocean Cruising
</arg><arg name="authors"><space/>Jim Howard, Charles J. Doane
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>William F. Buckley, Jr.</target></link>,<space/><italics>Atlantic High</italics><space/>- an account of an Atlantic passage.</listitem><listitem>William F. Buckley, Jr.,<space/><italics>Racing Through Paradise</italics><space/>- etc. about a Pacific passage.</listitem><listitem>Michael Carr, &quot;Weather Prediction Simplified&quot;</listitem><listitem>Don Casey,<space/><italics>Dragged Aboard: a Cruising Guide for the Reluctant Mate</italics></listitem><listitem>Linda and<space/><link><target>Steve Dashew</target></link>,<space/><italics>Offshore Cruisers' Encyclopedia</italics></listitem><listitem>Linda and<space/><link><target>Steve Dashew</target></link>,<space/><italics>Mariner's Weather Handbook</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robin Lee Graham</target></link>,<space/><italics>Dove</italics><space/>- The story of a 16-year-old boy who sails around the world in a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>sloop in the nineteen-sixties</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>Adlard Coles
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780713635645
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Eric Hiscock
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Eric Hiscock
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cruising Under Sail
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2012-09-24
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.amazon.com/Cruising-Under-Sail-Eric-Hiscock/dp/0713635649/ref</arg></template><space/>- just the facts, a classic.</listitem><listitem>Beth A. Leonard,<space/><italics>The Voyager's Handbook</italics></listitem><listitem>Elbert Maloney,<space/><italics>Dutton's Navigation and Piloting</italics><space/>- a classic, professional reference, continuously updated.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lin and Larry Pardey</target><part>Lawrence and Lin Pardey</part></link>,<space/><italics>The Self-Sufficient Sailor</italics><space/>-</listitem><listitem>Lin Pardey, 'Care and Feeding of Sailing Crew'</listitem><listitem>Lin and Larry Pardey, &quot;Storm Tactics Handbook.&quot;</listitem><listitem>Merle Turner,<space/><italics>Celestial Navigation for the Cruising Navigator</italics><space/>- some theory.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alan Villiers</target></link>,<space/><italics>Cruise of the Conrad</italics>. Scribner's, 1937. Reprinted, Seafarer Books, 2006.</listitem><listitem>Jeff &amp; Raine Williams<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.j40.org'>''Around the World in Eighty Megabytes''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://followthehorizon.com'>Follow the Horizon</link><space/>Cruising Blog</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikivoyage</target><arg>Cruising on small craft</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Recreation/Boating/Sailing/Personal_Pages/</arg><arg>Personal boating and cruising logs</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Cruising (maritime)</target></link><link><target>Category:Sailing</target></link><link><target>Category:Types of travel</target></link></paragraph></article>