<article title='Canonization'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><link><target>Image:stcyprian.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Icon of<space/><link><target>St. Cyprian of Carthage</target></link>, who urged diligence in the process of canonization</part></link><bold>Canonization</bold><space/>(in<space/><link><target>American and British English spelling differences</target><part>American English</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oxford spelling</target></link>) or<space/><bold>canonisation</bold><space/>(in<space/><link><target>British English</target></link>) is the act by which the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target><part>Orthodox</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Oriental Orthodoxy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target><part>Roman Catholic</part></link>, or<space/><link><target>Anglican Church</target></link><space/>declares that a person who has died was a<space/><link><target>saint</target></link>, upon which declaration the person is included in the canon, or list, of recognized saints. Originally, people were recognized as saints without any formal process. Later, different processes, such as those used today in the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target><part>Orthodox</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target><part>Roman Catholic Churches</part></link>, were developed.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical development of the process</heading><paragraph>The first people honored as saints were the<space/><link><target>martyr</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Pious legends of their deaths were considered to affirm the truth of their faith in Christ.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Roman Rite</target></link>'s Canon of the<space/><link><target>Mass (liturgy)</target><part>Mass</part></link><space/>contains the names only of martyrs, along with that of the<space/><link><target>Virgin Mary</target></link><space/>and, since 1962, that of<space/><link><target>Saint Joseph</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>By the fourth century, however, &quot;<link><target>confessor</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;people who had confessed their faith not by dying but by word and lifebegan to be venerated publicly. Examples of such people are Saint<space/><link><target>Hilarion</target></link><space/>and Saint<space/><link><target>Ephrem the Syrian</target></link><space/>in the East, and Saint<space/><link><target>Martin of Tours</target></link><space/>and Saint<space/><link><target>Hilary of Poitiers</target></link><space/>in the West. Their names were inserted in the<space/><link><target>diptych</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the lists of saints explicitly venerated in the<space/><link><target>liturgy</target></link>, and their tombs were honoured in like manner as those of the martyrs. Since the witness of their lives was not as unequivocal as that of the martyrs, they were venerated publicly only with the approval by the local<space/><link><target>bishop</target></link>. This process is often referred to as &quot;local canonization&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>For the history of canonization, see Kemp, Canonization and Authority in the Western Church,</extension></paragraph><paragraph>This approval was required even for veneration of a reputed martyr. In his history of the<space/><link><target>Donatism</target><part>Donatist</part></link><space/><link><target>heresy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saint Optatus</target></link><space/>recounts that at<space/><link><target>Carthage</target></link><space/>a Catholic matron, named Lucilla, incurred the censures of the Church for having kissed the<space/><link><target>relic</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of a reputed martyr whose claims to martyrdom had not been juridically proved. And Saint<space/><link><target>Cyprian</target></link><space/>(died 258) recommended that the utmost diligence be observed in investigating the claims of those who were said to have died for the faith. All the circumstances accompanying the martyrdom were to be inquired into; the faith of those who suffered, and the motives that animated them were to be rigorously examined, in order to prevent the recognition of undeserving persons. Evidence was sought from the court records of the trials or from people who had been present at the trials.</paragraph><paragraph>Saint<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target></link><space/>(died 430) tells of the procedure which was followed in his day for the recognition of a martyr. The bishop of the diocese in which the martyrdom took place set up a canonical process for conducting the inquiry with the utmost severity. The acts of the process were sent either to the<space/><link><target>Metropolitan bishop</target><part>metropolitan</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>primate</target></link>, who carefully examined the cause, and, after consultation with the<space/><link><target>suffragan</target></link><space/>bishops, declared whether the deceased was worthy of the name of 'martyr' and public veneration.</paragraph><paragraph>Acts of formal recognition, such as the erection of an<space/><link><target>altar</target></link><space/>over the saint's tomb or transferring the saint's relics to a church, were preceded by formal inquiries into the sanctity of the person's life and the miracles attributed to that person's intercession.</paragraph><paragraph>Such acts of recognition of a saint were authoritative, in the strict sense, only for the<space/><link><target>diocese</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>ecclesiastical province</target></link><space/>for which they were issued, but with the spread of the fame of a saint, were often accepted elsewhere also.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Roman Catholic Church</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target></link><space/>(both the<space/><link><target>Latin Catholic Church</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eastern Catholic Churches</target></link>), the act of canonization is reserved to the<space/><link><target>Holy See</target></link><space/>and occurs at the conclusion of a long process requiring extensive proof that the person proposed for canonization lived and died in such an exemplary and holy way that he or she is worthy to be recognized as a saint. The Church's official recognition of sanctity implies that the persons are now in heavenly glory, that they may be publicly invoked and mentioned officially in the<space/><link><target>liturgy</target></link><space/>of the Church, most especially in the<space/><link><target>Litany of the Saints</target></link>. Other churches still follow the older practice (see, for instance,<space/><link><target>Canonization#Eastern Orthodox PracticeGlorification</target><part>below</part></link><space/>on the practice of the Orthodox Church).</paragraph><paragraph>In the Catholic Church, canonization involves a decree that allows veneration of the saint in the<space/><link><target>liturgy</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Roman Rite</target></link><space/>throughout the world. For permission to venerate on a local level, only<space/><link><target>beatification</target></link><space/>is needed, not canonization.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Beatification, in the present discipline, differs from canonization in this: that the former implies (1) a locally restricted, not a universal, permission to venerate, which is (2) a mere permission, and no precept; while canonization implies a universal precept&quot; (<link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02364b.htm'>Beccari, Camillo. &quot;Beatification and Canonization&quot;</link><space/><italics>The Catholic Encyclopedia</italics>. Vol. 2. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. Retrieved 27 May 2009).</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Medieval procedure</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Pintoricchio 018 detail.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Pope Pius II</target></link><space/>canonizes<space/><link><target>Catherine of Siena</target></link></part></link>In the Medieval West, the<space/><link><target>Holy See</target></link><space/>was asked to intervene in the question of canonizations, so as to ensure a more authoritative decision. The canonization of<space/><link><target>Saint Udalric, Bishop of Augsburg</target></link>, by<space/><link><target>Pope John XV</target></link><space/>in 993 is the first undoubted example of a papal canonization of a saint from outside Rome; some historians maintain that the first such canonization was that of Saint Swibert by<space/><link><target>Pope Leo III</target></link><space/>in 804.</paragraph><paragraph>Thereafter, recourse to the judgment of the popes was had with greater frequency.<space/><link><target>Walter of Pontoise</target></link><space/>was canonised by<space/><link><target>Hugh de Boves</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Archbishop of Rouen</target></link><space/>in 1153; Walter was the last saint in<space/><link><target>Western Europe</target></link><space/>to have been canonised by an authority other than the pope.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ofsnlu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archive.org/stream/dictionaryofchri01smituoft/dictionaryofchri01smituoft_djvu.txt</arg><arg name="title">William Smith, Samuel Cheetham, ''A Dictionary of Christian Antiquities'' (Murray, 1875), 283.</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.saint-mike.org/library/papal_library/AlexanderIII/biography.html</arg><arg name="title">Alexander III</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The last case of canonization by a metropolitan is said to have been that of St. Gaultier, or Gaucher, abbot of Pontoise, by the Archbishop of Rouen. A decree of<space/><link><target>Pope Alexander III</target></link>, 1170, gave the prerogative to the pope thenceforth, so far as the Western Church was concerned.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ofsnlu"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1173,<space/><link><target>Pope Alexander III</target></link>, after reprimanding certain bishops for having permitted veneration of a man who was far from holy, decreed: &quot;You shall not therefore presume to honour him in the future; for, even if miracles were worked through him, it is not lawful for you to venerate him as a saint without the authority of the Catholic Church.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Gregory IX,<space/><italics>Decretales</italics>, III, &quot;De reliquiis et veneratione sanctorum&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The procedure initiated by the text of Alexander III, confirmed by a<space/><link><target>papal bull</target><part>bull</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link><space/>in the year 1200, issued on the occasion of the canonization of<space/><link><target>Saint Cunegunde</target></link>, led to increasingly elaborate inquiries.</paragraph><heading level='3'>From the 18th to the 20th century</heading><paragraph>In his<space/><italics>De Servorum Dei beatifcatione et de Beatorum canonizatione</italics>, the eminent canonist Prospero Lambertini (16751758), who later became<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XIV</target></link>, elaborated upon the procedural norms issued by<space/><link><target>Pope Urban VIII</target></link><space/>(16231644)<extension extension_name='ref'>Apostolic Letter<space/><italics>Caelestis Hierusalem cives</italics><space/>of 5 July 1634;<space/><italics>Decreta servanda in beatificatione et canonizatione Sanctorum</italics><space/>of 12 March 1642</extension><space/>and the actual established practice. From his time until the 20th century proceedings were governed by his five-volume work published in 17341738. Its substance was incorporated into the<space/><link><target>Code of Canon Law</target></link><space/>of 1917.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.strasbourginstitute.org/wp-content/uploads/2013/07/Musoni-The-Catholic-Canonization-Process.pdf'>Aimable Musoni, &quot;Saints without Borders&quot;, pp. 910</link></extension><space/>The article<space/><link><target>Beatification and canonization process in 1914</target></link><space/>describes the procedures followed immediately before the publication of that Code.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman Catholic procedure since 1983</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Congregation for the Causes of Saints</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>apostolic constitution</target></link><space/><italics>Divinus Perfectionis Magister</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html</arg><arg name="title">DIVINUS PERFECTIONIS MAGISTER</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>of 25 January 1983, and the norms issued by the<space/><link><target>Congregation for the Causes of Saints</target></link><space/>on 7 February 1983, for its implementation on diocesan level, continued the work of simplification already initiated by<space/><link><target>Pope Paul VI</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html</arg><arg name="title">Divinus Perfectionis Magister</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Contrary to popular belief, the reforms did not eliminate the office of the Promoter of the Faith (Latin: promotor fidei), popularly known as the<space/><link><target>Devil's advocate</target></link>, whose duty was to question the material presented in favor of canonization. The reforms were intended to make the process less adversarial. In November 2012<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XVI</target></link><space/>appointed Monsignor Carmello Pellegrino to the office of Promoter of the Faith.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.google.com/translate?hl=en&amp;amp;sl=it&amp;amp;u=http://bari.repubblica.it/cronaca/2012/11/05/news/l_avvocato_del_diavolo_pugliese_tester_le_virt_degli_aspiranti_santi-45975067/&amp;amp;prev=search'>&quot;Devil's Advocate is Puglia 'It will test the virtues of aspiring saints'&quot;, ''la Repubblica'', November 5, 2012</link></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph><bold>The steps to canonization</bold><space/>that the candidates have to go through to become a saint:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Canonization</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>&quot;Servant of God&quot;</bold>: The process leading towards canonization begins at the diocesan level. A<space/><link><target>bishop</target></link><space/>with jurisdictionusually the bishop of the place where the candidate died or is buried, although another ordinary can be given this authoritygives permission to open an investigation into the virtues of the individual, responding to a petition by members of the faithful, either actually or<space/><link><target>pro forma</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link>, 1983,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html'>''Divinus Perfectionis Magister''</link>, Art I, Sec 1</extension><space/>This investigation usually opens no sooner than five years after the death of the person being investigated.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pietro Cardinal Palazzini, 1983,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_07021983_norme_en.html'>''Norms to be observed in inquiries made by bishops in the causes of saints''</link>, 9 a</extension><space/>The pope, as Bishop of Rome, may open a process and has the authority to waive the five-year waiting period, as was done for<space/><link><target>Mother Teresa</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/news_services/liturgy/saints/ns_lit_doc_20031019_madre-teresa_en.html'>'' Mother Teresa of Calcutta (19101997), biography''</link>, Office of Papal Liturgical Celebrations, Internet Office of the Holy See</extension><space/>and for<space/><link><target>Lcia Santos</target></link><space/>and for John Paul II himself by<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XVI</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.zenit.org/article-21764?l</arg><arg name="title">Sister Lucia's Beatification Process to Begin</arg><arg name="work">ZENIT - The World Seen From Rome</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Cardinal (Catholicism)</target><part>Cardinal</part></link><space/><link><target>Jos Saraiva Martins</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Claretians</target><part>C.M.F.</part></link>; 2005;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/documents/rc_con_csaints_doc_20050509_rescritto-gpii_en.html'>''Response of His Holiness Benedict XVI for the examination of the cause for beatification and canonization of the Servant of God John Paul II''</link></extension><space/>Normally, a guild or organization to promote the cause of the candidate's sainthood is created, an exhaustive search of the candidate's writings, speeches and sermons is undertaken, a detailed biography is written and eyewitness accounts are gathered. When sufficient information has been gathered, the investigation of the candidate, who is called<space/><bold>&quot;Servant of God&quot;</bold>, is presented by the local bishop to the<space/><link><target>Roman Curia</target></link>in particular, the Congregation for the Causes of the Saintswhere it is assigned a<space/><link><target>postulator</target></link>, whose task is to gather further information about the life of the Servant of God. Religious orders who regularly deal with the congregation often have their own designated postulator generals. At some point, permission is then granted for the body of the Servant of God to be exhumed and examined. A certification (&quot;non cultus&quot;) is made that no superstitious or heretical worship or improper cult has grown up around the servant or his or her tomb, and relics are taken.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>&quot;Venerable/Heroic in Virtue&quot;</bold>: When enough information has been gathered, the congregation will recommend to the<space/><link><target>pope</target></link><space/>that he make a proclamation of the Servant of God's<space/><link><target>heroic virtue</target></link><space/>(that is, that the servant exhibited the theological virtues of faith, hope and charity, and the cardinal virtues of prudence, justice, fortitude and temperance, to a heroic degree). From this point the one said to be &quot;heroic in virtue&quot; is referred to by the title<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>Venerable</target></link>&quot;</bold>. A Venerable has as yet no<space/><link><target>feast day</target></link>, no churches may be built in his or her honor, and the church has made no statement on the person's probable or certain presence in heaven, but<space/><link><target>prayer card</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other materials may be printed to encourage the faithful to pray for a<space/><link><target>miracle</target></link><space/>wrought by his or her intercession as a sign of God's will that the person be canonized.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>&quot;Blessed&quot;</bold>: Beatification is a statement by the church that it is &quot;worthy of belief&quot; that the person is in heaven, having come to salvation. This step depends on whether the Venerable is a<space/><link><target>martyr</target></link><space/>or a &quot;confessor&quot;.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>For a martyr, the Pope has only to make a declaration of martyrdom, a certification that the venerable gave his or her life voluntarily as a witness for the faith and/or in an<space/><link><target>act of heroic charity</target></link><space/>for others.</listitem><listitem>If the Venerable was not a martyrall non-martyrs are &quot;confessors&quot; as they &quot;confessed&quot; or bore witness to their faith by how they lived their livesit must be proven that a<space/><link><target>miracle</target></link><space/>has taken place by his or her intercession: that is, that God has shown a sign that the person is enjoying the Beatific Vision by God performing a miracle in response to the Blessed's prayers. Today, these miracles are almost always miraculous cures, as these are the easiest to establish based on the Catholic Church's requirements for a &quot;miracle&quot;. (The patient was sick, there was no known cure for the ailment, prayers were directed to the Venerable, the patient was cured, the cure was spontaneous, instantaneous, complete, and lasting, and doctors cannot find any natural explanation.)</listitem></list><paragraph>This allows<space/><link><target>beatification</target></link>, giving the venerable the new title<space/><bold>&quot;Blessed&quot;</bold><space/>(abbreviated &quot;Bl.&quot;) or, in Latin, Beatus or Beata. A feast day will be designated, but its observance is normally restricted to the Blessed's home diocese, to certain locations associated with him or her, and/or to the churches or houses of the blessed's religious order, if they belonged to one. Parishes may not normally be named in honor of a Blessed.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>&quot;Saint&quot;</bold><space/>(contracted &quot;St&quot; or &quot;S.&quot;): To be canonized a saint, at least two miracles must have been performed through the saint's intercession after his or her death (i.e., an additional miracle after that granting beatification). Canonization is a statement by the church that the person certainly enjoys the<space/><link><target>Beatific Vision</target></link>. The saint is assigned a feast day which<space/><italics>may</italics><space/>be celebrated anywhere within the Catholic Church, although it may or may not appear on the general calendar or local calendars as an<space/><italics>obligatory</italics><space/>feast, parish churches may be built in his or her honor, and the faithful may freely and without restriction celebrate and honor the saint.</paragraph><paragraph>In the case of the<space/><link><target>Eastern Catholic Churches</target></link>, individual churches<space/><italics><link><target>sui juris</target></link></italics><space/>retain, in theory, the right to glorify saints for their own jurisdictions, though this has rarely happened in practice.</paragraph><paragraph>Although a recognition of sainthood by the Pope does not directly concern a fact of divine revelation, it must still be &quot;definitively held&quot; by the faithful as infallible under (at the very least) the<space/><link><target>Infallibility of the Church</target><part>Universal Magisterium of the Church</part></link><space/>since it is a truth connected to revelation by historical necessity.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ewtn.com/library/CURIA/CDFADTU.HTM'>Doctrinal Commentary on the Concluding Formula of the ''Professio Fidei''</link>, by Cardinal Joseph Ratzinger (now Pope Benedict XVI), Congregation for the Doctrine of the Faith.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02364b.htm'>&quot;Beatification and Canonization&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The Catholic Encyclopedia</italics>, Vol. 2. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907, p. 366</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Equipollent canonization</heading><paragraph>Popes have several times extended to the whole Church, without carrying out the ordinary judicial process of canonization described above, the veneration as a saint, the &quot;<link><target>Cult (religious practice)</target><part>cultus</part></link>&quot;, of someone long venerated as such locally. This action by a Pope is known as equipollent (or equivalent) canonization or &quot;confirmation of cultus&quot;. According to the rules laid down by<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XIV</target></link>, there are three conditions for such a canonization: an ancient cultus, a general constant attestation by trustworthy historians to the virtues or martyrdom of the person, and an uninterrupted fame as a worker of miracles.</paragraph><paragraph>Pope Benedict XIV himself gave as examples the equipollent canonizations of the saints<space/><link><target>Romuald</target></link><space/>in 1595,<space/><link><target>Norbert</target></link><space/>in 1621,<space/><link><target>Bruno of Cologne</target><part>Bruno</part></link><space/>in 1623,<space/><link><target>Peter Nolasco</target></link><space/>in 1655,<space/><link><target>Raymond Nonnatus</target></link><space/>in 1681,<space/><link><target>Stephen of Hungary</target></link><space/>in 1686,<space/><link><target>Saint Margaret of Scotland</target><part>Margaret of Scotland</part></link><space/>in 1691,<space/><link><target>John of Matha</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Felix of Valois</target></link><space/>in 1694,<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory VII</target></link><space/>in 1728,<space/><link><target>Wenceslaus I, Duke of Bohemia</target><part>Wenceslaus of Bohemia</part></link><space/>in 1729, and<space/><link><target>Gertrude of Helfta</target></link><space/>in 1738. Later equipollent canonizations include those of<space/><link><target>Peter Damian</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Boniface</target></link><space/>in 1828,<space/><link><target>Cyril and Methodius</target></link><space/>in 1880,<space/><link><target>Ephrem the Syrian</target></link><space/>in 1920,<space/><link><target>Albert the Great</target></link><space/>in 1931,<space/><link><target>Margaret of Hungary (saint)</target><part>Margaret of Hungary</part></link><space/>in 1943,<space/><link><target>John of vila</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nikola Taveli</target></link><space/>and his three companion martyrs in 1970,<space/><link><target>Marko Krizin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Istvn Pongrcz</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Melchior Grodziecki</target></link><space/>in 1995, and<space/><link><target>Hildegard of Bingen</target></link><space/>in 2012.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pope Francis</target></link><space/>added<space/><link><target>Angela of Foligno</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Peter Faber</target></link><space/>in 2013, and<space/><link><target>Jos de Anchieta</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Marie of the Incarnation (Ursuline)</target><part>Marie of the Incarnation</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Franois de Laval</target><part>Francis-Xavier de Montmorency-Laval</part></link><space/>in 2014.<extension extension_name='ref'>Angelo Amato, &quot;La canonizzazione equipollente della mistica Angela da Foligno&quot; in<space/><italics>L'Osservatore Romano</italics><space/>(12 October 2013)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ewtn.com/library/mary/canonize.htm</arg><arg name="title">P. E. Hallett, "The Canonization of Saints"</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.catholicpamphlets.net/pamphlets/BEATIFICATION%20AND%20CANONISATION.pdf'>J.R. MacMahon, &quot;Beatification and Canonisation&quot;</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://latino.foxnews.com/latino/news/2014/04/03/pope-canonizes-jose-de-anchieta-known-as-brazil-apostle</arg><arg name="title">Pope canonizes Jose de Anchieta, known as Brazil's apostle</arg><arg name="work">Fox News Latino</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 October 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Orthodox Church</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:. . 1889 .jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Turkish<space/><link><target>Batak massacre</target><part>atrocities in Bulgaria</part></link><space/>(1876). On 3 April 2011, Batak massacre victims were canonized as saints.</part></link>For the process by which the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target><part>Orthodox Church</part></link><space/>grants official recognition to someone as a saint, see<space/><link><target>glorification</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Anglican Communion</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Saints in Anglicanism</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Mother Church</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Anglican Communion</target></link>, canonized<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>Charles I</part></link><space/>as a saint, in the<space/><link><target>Convocations of Canterbury and York</target></link><space/>of 1660.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mitchell2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mitchell</arg><arg name="first">Jolyon</arg><arg name="title">Martyrdom: A Very Short Introduction</arg><arg name="date">29 November 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">9780191642449</arg><arg name="page">99</arg><arg name="quote">In 1660 the convocations of Canterbury and York canonized King Charles.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Beatification</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Devil's advocate</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Glorification</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of canonizations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of saints</target><part>List of Christian saints after A.D. 450</part></link><space/>(incomplete list)</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of early Christian saints</target><part>List of Christian saints before A.D. 450</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Litany of the Saints</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Andr Vauchez</target></link>,<space/><italics>La saintet en Occident aux derniers sicles du Moyen ge (11981431)</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.publications.ecole-francaise.it/cgi-bin/ecole-francaise/details.cgi?address=&amp;amp;request=1%253d1003%25204%253d2%2520%2520%2522vauchez%2522&amp;amp;visrequest=%253cspan%2520class%253dvisrequestuse%253eAuteur%253c%252fspan%253e%253d%2520%2522%253cspan%2520class%253dvisrequestval%253evauchez%253c%252fspan%253e%2522&amp;amp;listrequest=&amp;amp;database=&amp;amp;item=17&amp;amp;format=&amp;amp;previous=&amp;amp;sort=1003+4+31&amp;amp;template=&amp;amp;stateless='>1, Rome, 1981 (''BEFAR'', 241) [Engl. transl. : ''Sainthood in the Later Middle Ages'', Cambridge, 1987 and Ital. Transl. : ''La santit nel Medioevo'', Bologne, 1989</link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Eric Waldram Kemp,<space/><italics>Canonization and Authority in the Western Church</italics>, Oxford University Press, 1948</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template><template><target>EB1911 poster</target><arg>Canonization</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Catholic</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_25011983_divinus-perfectionis-magister_en.html'>''Divinus Perfectionis Magister''</link><space/>Apostolic Constitution of Pope John Paul II (English)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/congregations/csaints/index.htm'>Congregation for the Causes of Saints</link><space/>Vatican Website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://friarsminor.org/xvii4-9.html'>Historical Sketch of Canonization</link><space/>Friarsminor.org</listitem><listitem><template><target>CathEncy</target><arg name="title">Beatification and Canonization</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02364b.htm</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Orthodox</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.roca.org/OA/14/14x.htm'>What does &quot;Glorification&quot; mean?</link><space/>Fr. Alexey Young</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pravmir.com/article_149.html'>Glorification of Saints Russian Orthodox Church</link><space/>Archpriest Georgiy Mitrofanov</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pravmir.com/article_153.html'>The blood of martyrs is the life-giving seed of Christianity!</link><space/>Glorification of saints in the 20th century</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/glorification_saints.htm'>On the Glorification of Saints</link><space/>Protopresbyter Michael Pomazansky</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.orthodoxphotos.com/Holy_Relics/St._John_Maximovitch/index.shtml'>Glorification of St. John Maximovitch</link><space/>Discussion and photos</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>canonization</target></template><template><target>Saints</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Saints days</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian worship practices</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Posthumous recognitions</target></link><link><target>Category:Religious behaviour and experience</target></link><link><target>Category:Sainthood</target></link></paragraph></article>