<article title='Beadwork'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template><link><target>File:Beadwork on Container (2131611625).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Ethiopia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>beadwork on basket, from the ethnographic collection of the National Museum,<space/><link><target>Addis Ababa</target></link></part></link><bold>Beadwork</bold><space/>is the art or craft of attaching<space/><link><target>bead</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to one another by stringing them with a<space/><link><target>sewing needle</target></link><space/>or beading needle and thread or thin wire, or sewing them to cloth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dict_beads"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beadwork</arg><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/beadwork</arg><arg name="publisher">Merriam-Webster</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Beads come in a variety of materials, shapes and sizes. Beads are used to create<space/><link><target>jewellery</target><part>jewelry</part></link><space/>or other articles of personal adornment; they are also used in wall hangings and<space/><link><target>sculpture</target></link><space/>and many other crafts.</paragraph><paragraph>Beadwork techniques are broadly divided into<space/><link><target>Bead weaving</target><part>loom</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bead weaving</target><part>off-loom</part></link><space/>weaving,<space/><link><target>Bead stringing</target><part>stringing</part></link>,<space/><link><target>bead embroidery</target></link>,<space/><link><target>bead crochet</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>bead knitting</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Most<space/><link><target>culture</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have employed beads for personal adornment.<space/><link><target>archaeology</target><part>Archaeological</part></link><space/>records show that people made and used beads as long as 5,000 years ago. Beads have also been used for<space/><link><target>religion</target><part>religious</part></link><space/>purposes, as good luck<space/><link><target>amulet</target><part>talismans</part></link>, and as curative agents.<link><target>File:MRAW Bellyband Tri Wing Ring from Contemporary Geometric Beadwork by Kate McKinnon .webm</target><part>thumb</part><part>MRAW Bellyband Tri Wing Ring from Contemporary Geometric Beadwork by Kate McKinnon</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern Beading</heading><paragraph>Modern beadwork is often used as a creative<space/><link><target>hobby</target></link><space/>to create<space/><link><target>jewelry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Handbag</target><part>purses</part></link>, coasters, and dozens of other crafts. Beads are available in many different designs, sizes, colors, and materials, allowing much variation among bead artisans and projects. Simple projects can be created in less than an hour by novice beaders, while complex beadwork may take weeks of meticulous work with specialized tools and equipment..</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ancient Beading</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Broad Collar, ca. 1336-1327 B.C.E., ca. 1327-1323 B.C.E., or ca.1323-1295 B.C.E.,40.522.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Broad Collar, ca. 1336-1327 B.C.E., ca. 1327-1323 B.C.E., or ca.1323-1295 B.C.E.,40.522,<space/><link><target>Brooklyn Museum</target></link></part></link><link><target>Egyptian faience</target><part>Faience</part></link><space/>is a mixture of powdered clays and lime, soda and silica sand. Mix this with a little water to make a paste and molded around a small stick or bit of straw. Now it is ready to be fired into a bead. As the bead heats up the soda sand and lime melt into glass that incorporates and covers the clay. The result is a hard bead covered in bluish glass.</paragraph><paragraph>This process was probably discovered first in Mesopotamia and then imported to Egypt. But, it was the Egyptians who made it their own art form. Since before the 1st dynasty of Narmer(3100 B.C.) to the last dynasty of the Ptolomies(33 B.C.) and to the present day, faience beads have been made in the same way.</paragraph><paragraph>These beads predate glass beads and were probably a forerunner of glass making. If you are a little short of clay and have a little extra lime and the fire is hotter than usual, the mixture will become glass. In fact some early tubular faience beads are clayish at one end and pure glass at the other end. Apparently the beads weren't fired evenly.</paragraph><paragraph>The uneven beads were noticed early on, this led to experimentation, slowly at first. It took a long time for new ideas to be accepted in a conservative, agricultural society. One of the first variations to take hold was to color the faience beads by adding metallic salts. By the beginning of the eighteenth dynasty(1850 B.C.), faience making and glass making had become two separate crafts.</paragraph><paragraph>Why were faience beads so common? They were cheaper and less labor-intensive to make than stone beads. Aside from personal use and daily wear they were used to create beaded netting to cover mummies. Most of the archaeological specimens come from burials.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Fernandes</arg><arg name="first1">Beverly</arg><arg name="title">Faience Beads from Egypt</arg><arg name="url">http://www.harlequinbeads.com/faience-beads-from-egypt-article</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 June 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As early as the Old Kingdom (circa 26702195 B.C.), Egyptian artisans fashioned images of gods, kings, and mortals wearing broad collars made of molded tubular and teardrop beads. These beaded collars may have been derived from floral prototypes. In antiquity the collar was called a<space/><italics>wesekh</italics>, literally &quot;the broad one.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Broad Collar</arg><arg name="url">http://www.brooklynmuseum.org/opencollection/objects/3453/Broad_Collar#</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 June 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the Americas, the Cherokee used bead work to tell stories. They told them by the patterns in the beads. They used dried berries, gray Indian corn, teeth, bones, claws, or sometimes sea shells when they traded with coastal tribes.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>3D beading</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Perlentier.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>230px</part><part>Icebear made of seed beads</part></link>[[File:Beadknitting.JPG|thumb|230px|<link><target>Bead knitting</target></link><space/>on double-pointed</paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>knitting needle</target><trail>s</trail></link>]]</preline></preblock><paragraph>3D, or three-dimensional, beading is less common than 2D, or two-dimensional, beading largely because free 3D beading patterns are not widely available on the internet.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Resources are scarce and difficult to find. It is mainly an East Asian art form, and most 3D beading resources arewritten in East Asian languages such as Japanese and Chinese, further impeding access for those in English-speaking countries. 3D beading is widely considered too complex for most beaders to manage although this sentiment is largely due to the apparent complexity of many Asian beading diagrams. It is a challenge for pattern designers to create 2D beading patterns that portray 3D beaded objects.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>3D beading generally uses the techniques of<space/><link><target>bead weaving</target></link>, which can be further divided into right angle weave and<space/><link><target>peyote stitch</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Most 3D beading patterns are done in right angle weave, but sometimes both techniques are combined in the same piece. Both stitches are done using either fishing line or nylon thread. Fishing line lends itself better to right angleweave because it is stiffer than nylon thread, so it holds the beads in a tighter arrangement and does not easily break when tugged upon.</paragraph><paragraph>On theother hand, nylon thread is more suited to peyote stitch because it is softer and more pliable than fishing line, which permits the beads ofthe stitch to sit straight without undue tension bending the arrangement out of place. Right angle weave is done using both ends of the fishingline, in which beads are strung in repeated circular arrangements, and the fishing line is pulled tight after each bead circle is made.</paragraph><paragraph>Peyotestitch is stitched using only one end of the nylon thread. The other end of the string is left dangling at the beginning of the piece, while the first end of the thread progresses through the stitch. In peyote stitch, beads are woven into the piece in a very similar fashion to knitting or cross stitching.</paragraph><paragraph>In fact, it is not uncommon for cross stitch patterns to be beaded in peyote stitch technique. Peyote stitch patterns are very easy to depict diagrammatically because they are typically stitched flat and then later incorporated into the piece or simply left as a flat tapestry.</paragraph><paragraph>Right angle weave lends itself better to 3D beading, but peyote stitch offers the advantage of allowing the beads to be more tightly knit, which is sometimes necessary to portray an object properly in three dimensions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>European beadwork</heading><paragraph>Beadwork in Europe has a history dating back millennia to a time when shells and animal bones were used as beads in<space/><link><target>necklace</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Glass beads were being made in<space/><link><target>Murano</target></link><space/>by the end of the 14th century. French beaded flowers were being made as early as the 16th century, and<space/><link><target>murano beads</target><part>lampwork glass</part></link><space/>was invented in the 18th century.<space/><link><target>beads#Seed beads</target><part>Seed beads</part></link><space/>began to be used for embroidery, crochet, and numerous<space/><link><target>Bead weaving#Off-loom beadweaving</target><part>off-loom</part></link><space/>techniques.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Native American beadwork</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Nat Am beadwork sampler.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>230px</part><part>Examples of contemporary Native American beadwork</part></link>Beadwork is a quintessentially<space/><link><target>Native American art</target></link><space/>form but, ironically, now mostly uses beads imported from Europe and Asia. Glass beads have been in use for almost five centuries in the Americas. Today a wide range of beading styles flourish.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite the widespread popularity of glass beads, many Natives continue the pre-contact method of using<space/><link><target>Quillwork</target><part>dyed porcupine quills</part></link><space/>in a similar manner as beads.<space/><link><target>Wampum</target></link><space/>is also still popular. A cylindrical tube of quahog or whelk shell, wampum consists of both white and the less-common purple beads. These shell beads are ceremonially and politically important to a range of Eastern tribes,<extension extension_name='ref'>Dubin, p. 170-171</extension><space/>and were used to depict several important treaties between the Native peoples and the colonists, as in the case of the<space/><link><target>Two Row Wampum Treaty</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Great Lakes,<space/><link><target>Ursulines</target><part>Ursuline</part></link><space/>nuns introduced floral patterns to tribes who quickly applied them to beadwork.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dubin, p. 50</extension><space/><link><target>Great Lakes</target></link><space/>tribes are known for their bandolier bags that might take an entire year to complete.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dubin, p. 218</extension><space/>During the 20th century the Plateau tribes, such as the<space/><link><target>Nez Perce (tribe)</target><part>Nez Perce</part></link>, perfected contour-style beadwork in which the lines of beads are stitched to emphasize the pictorial imagery. Plains tribes are master beaders, and today dance regalia for men and women feature a variety of beadwork styles. While Plains and Plateau tribes are renowned for their beaded<space/><link><target>Trap (carriage)</target><part>horse trappings</part></link>, Subarctic tribes such as the<space/><link><target>Dene</target></link><space/>create lavish beaded floral dog blankets.<extension extension_name='ref'>Berlo and Philips, p. 151</extension><space/>Eastern tribes have a completely different beadwork aesthetic:<space/><link><target>Innu</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mi'kmaq people</target><part>Mi'kmaq</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Penobscot people</target><part>Penobscot</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Haudenosaunee</target></link><space/>tribes are known for symmetrical scroll motifs in white beads, called the &quot;double curve.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Berlo and Phillips, p. 146</extension><space/>Iroquois are also known for &quot;embossed&quot; beading in which strings pulled taut force beads to pop up from the surface, creating a<space/><link><target>bas-relief</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Tammy Rahr</target></link><space/>(Cayuga) is a contemporary practitioner of this style.<space/><link><target>Zuni people</target><part>Zuni</part></link><space/>artists have developed a tradition of three-dimensional beaded sculptures.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Huichol Trabajando.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>240px</part><part>Huichol bead artist, photo by Mario Jareda Beivide</part></link><link><target>Huichol people</target><part>Huichol</part></link><space/>Indians of<space/><link><target>Jalisco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nayarit</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mexico</target></link><space/>have a completely unique approach to beadwork. They adhere beads one by one to a surface such as wood or a gourd with a mixture of resin and beeswax.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hillman, Paul.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.beadmuseumaz.org/Huichol/huichol4.htm'>The Huichol Web of Life: Creation and Prayer.</link><space/><italics>The Bead Museum.</italics><space/>(Retrieved 13 March 2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most Native beadwork is created for tribal use, but beadworkers also create conceptual work for the art world.<space/><link><target>Richard Aitson</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Kiowa</target></link>-<link><target>Apache</target></link>), enjoying both an Indian and non-Indian audience, is known for his fully beaded<space/><link><target>cradle board</target><part>cradleboards</part></link>. Another Kiowa beadworker,<space/><link><target>Teri Greeves</target></link>, has won top honors for her beadwork which consciously integrates both traditional and contemporary motifs such as beaded dancers on Converse high-tops. Greeves also beads on buckskin and explores such issues as warfare or Native American voting rights.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lopez, Antonio.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.southwestart.com/article/747'>Focus Artists:Teri Greeves.</link><space/><italics>Southwest Art.</italics><space/>2009 (Retrieved 13 March 2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Marcus Amerman</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Choctaw</target></link>, one of today's most celebrated bead artists, pioneered a movement of highly realistic beaded portraits.<extension extension_name='ref'>Berlo and Phillips, p. 32</extension><space/>His imagery ranges from 19th century Native leaders to pop icons including<space/><link><target>Janet Jackson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Brooke Shields</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Roger Amerman, Marcus' brother, and<space/><link><target>Martha Berry (artist)</target><part>Martha Berry</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Cherokee</target></link>, have effectively revived Southeastern beadwork, a style that had been lost because of the forced removal of their tribes to Indian Territory. Their beadwork commonly features white bead outlines, an echo of the shell beads or pearls Southeastern tribes used before contact.<extension extension_name='ref'>Berlo and Phillips, p. 87</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jamie Okuma (<link><target>Luiseo people</target><part>Luiseo</part></link>-<link><target>Shoshone</target></link>-<link><target>Bannock (tribe)</target><part>Bannock</part></link>) has won top awards with her beaded dolls, which can include entire families or horses and riders, all with fully beaded regalia. The antique Venetian beads she uses can be as small as size 22, about the size of a grain of salt.<extension extension_name='ref'>Indyke, Dottie.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.southwestart.com/article/1038'>Jamie Okuma.</link><space/><italics>Southwest Magazine.</italics><space/>2009 (Retrieved 13 March 2009)</extension><space/><link><target>Juanita Growing Thunder Fogarty</target></link>, Rhonda Holy Bear, and Charlene Holy Bear are also prominent beaded doll makers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Beetlewing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>French wire</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jewelry wire gauge</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Berlo<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Janet C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="author2">Ruth B. Phillips<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Native North American Art<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Oxford History of Art<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-284218-3<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Dubin, Lois Sherr (1999).<space/><italics>North American Indian Jewelry and Adornment: From Prehistory to the Present.</italics><space/>New York: Harry N. Abrams. ISBN 0-8109-3689-5</listitem><listitem>Beads and beadwork. (1996).<space/><italics>In Encyclopedia of north american indians, Houghton Mifflin.</italics><space/>Retrieved January 27, 2014, from http://search.credoreference.com.libproxy.pcc.edu/content/entry/hmenai/beads_and_beadwork/0?searchId=5802633999360673000&amp;result=3</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Beadwork</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Wikivoyage</target><arg>Bead shopping</arg></template><template><target>beadwork</target></template><template><target>textile arts</target></template><template><target>decorative arts</target></template><template><target>Prehistoric technology</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Beadwork</target><part>01</part></link><link><target>Category:Arts and crafts</target></link><link><target>Category:Beadworkers</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Decorative arts</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>