<article title='History_of_the_Democratic_Republic_of_the_Congo'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>History of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The region that is now the<space/><bold><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link></bold><space/>was first settled about 80,000 years ago.<space/><link><target>Bantu peoples</target><part>Bantu</part></link><space/>migration arrived in the region from<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>in the 7th century AD. The<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Kongo</target></link><space/>remained present in the region between the 14th and the early 19th centuries.<space/><link><target>Belgian colonial empire</target><part>Belgian colonization</part></link><space/>began when<space/><link><target>Leopold II of Belgium</target><part>King Leopold II</part></link><space/>founded the<space/><link><target>Congo Free State</target></link>, a corporate state run solely by King Leopold. Reports of widespread murder and torture in the rubber plantations led the Belgian government to seize the Congo from Leopold II and establish the<space/><link><target>Belgian Congo</target></link>. Under Belgian rule, the colony was run with the presence of numerous<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian organizations</part></link><space/>that wanted to Westernize the Congolese people.</paragraph><paragraph>After an uprising by the Congolese people, Belgium granted the Congo<space/><link><target>Congo Crisis</target><part>its independence</part></link><space/>in 1960. However, the Congo was left unstable because tribal leaders had more power than the central government.<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Prime Minister</part></link><space/><link><target>Patrice Lumumba</target></link><space/>tried to restore order with the aid of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>as part of the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>, causing the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>to support a coup led by Colonel<space/><link><target>Mobuto Sese Seko</target><part>Joseph Mobutu</part></link><space/>in 1965. Mobutu quickly seized complete power of the Congo and rename the country<space/><link><target>Zaire</target></link>. He sought to<space/><link><target>Africanization</target><part>Africanize</part></link><space/>the country, changing his own name to Mobuto Sese Seko, and demanded that African citizens to change their Western names to traditional African names. Mobuto sought to repress any opposition to his rule, in which he successfully did throughout the 1980s. However, with his regime weakened during the early 1990s, Mobuto was forced to agree to a power-sharing government with the opposition party. Mobuto remained the<space/><link><target>List of Presidents of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>head of state</part></link><space/>and promised elections for the next two years that never happened.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>First Congo War</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rwanda</target></link><space/>invaded Zaire, which overthrow Mobuto during the process.<space/><link><target>Laurent-Desire Kabila</target></link><space/>later took power and rename the country back to the Democratic Republic of the Congo. After a disappointing rule under Kabila, the<space/><link><target>Second Congo War</target></link><space/>broke out, resulting in a regional war with many different African nations taking part. Kabila was assassinated by his bodyguard in 2001, and his son,<space/><link><target>Joseph Kabila</target><part>Joseph</part></link>, succeeded him and later<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo general election, 2006</target><part>elected president by the Congolese government</part></link><space/>in 2006. Upon taking office, Kabila quickly sought peace, ending the era of war in Africa. Soldiers were left in the Congo for a few years and a power-sharing government between Kabila and the opposition party was set up. Kabila later resumed complete control over the Congo and was<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo general election, 2011</target><part>re-elected in a disputed election</part></link><space/>in 2011. Today, the Congo remains dangerously unstable.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early history</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Mercator Congo map.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>map of the Kingdom of Kongo</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Early Congolese history</arg></template>The area now known as the<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link><space/>was populated as early as 80,000 years ago, as shown by the 1988 discovery of the<space/><link><target>Semliki harpoon</target></link><space/>at Katanda, one of the oldest barbed harpoons ever found, and which is believed to have been used to catch giant river catfish.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://humanorigins.si.edu/evidence/behavior/katanda-bone-harpoon-point</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.springerlink.com/content/g36v03001423n142/</extension><space/>Congo was settled in the 7th and 8th centuries A.D. by<space/><link><target>Bantu peoples</target><part>Bantus</part></link><space/>from present-day<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>. During its history, the area has also been known as<space/><italics>Congo</italics>,<space/><italics>Congo Free State</italics>,<space/><italics>Belgian Congo</italics>, and<space/><italics>Zaire</italics>. The<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Kongo</target></link><space/>was a powerful kingdom that existed between the 14th and the early 19th century. It was the dominant force in the region until the arrival of the Portuguese. Second in importance was the<space/><link><target>Anziku Kingdom</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Colonial rule</heading><heading level='3'>Congo Free State (1885&amp;ndash;1908)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Congo Free State</arg></template><link><target>Image:MutilatedChildrenFromCongo.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Children mutilated during King Leopold II's rule</part></link>The Congo Free State was a<space/><link><target>corporate state</target></link><space/>privately controlled by<space/><link><target>Leopold II of Belgium</target></link><space/>through the<space/><italics><link><target>International African Association</target><part>Association internationale africaine</part></link></italics>, a non-governmental organization. Leopold was the sole shareholder and chairman. The state included the entire area of the present<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link>. Under Leopold II's administration, the Congo Free State became the site of one of the most infamous international scandals of the turn of the twentieth century. The report of the British Consul<space/><link><target>Roger Casement</target></link><space/>led to the arrest and punishment of white officials who had been responsible for cold-blooded killings during a rubber-collecting expedition in 1903, including one<space/><link><target>Belgium</target><part>Belgian</part></link><space/>national for causing the shooting of at least 122 Congolese natives. Estimates of the total death toll vary considerably. In the absence of a census, the first was made in 1924, it is even more difficult to quantify the population loss of the period. Roger Casement's famous 1904 report estimated ten million people. According to Casement's report, indiscriminate &quot;war&quot;, starvation, reduction of births and<space/><link><target>tropical diseases</target></link><space/>caused the country's depopulation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.urome.be/fr2/reflexions/casemrepo.pdf'>Report of the British Consul, Roger Casement, on the Administration of the Congo Free State</link></extension><space/>The European and U.S. press agencies exposed the conditions in the Congo Free State to the public in 1900. By 1908 public and diplomatic pressure led Leopold II to annex the Congo as the<space/><link><target>Belgian Congo</target></link><space/>colony.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Ewans</arg><arg name="first1">Sir Martin</arg><arg name="title">European atrocity, African catastrophe : Leopold II, the Congo Free State and its aftermath</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Curzon</arg><arg name="location">Richmond</arg><arg name="isbn">0700715894</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Belgian Congo (1908&amp;ndash;1960)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Belgian Congo</arg></template>On the 15 of November 1908<space/><link><target>Lopold II of Belgium</target><part>King Lopold II of Belgium</part></link><space/>formally relinquished personal control of the Congo Free State. The renamed Belgian Congo was put under the direct administration of the<space/><link><target>Belgium</target><part>Belgian</part></link><space/>government and its Ministry of Colonies.</paragraph><paragraph>Belgian rule in the Congo was based around the &quot;colonial trinity&quot; (<italics>trinit coloniale</italics>) of<space/><link><target>Government</target><part>state</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>missionary</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Privately held company</target><part>private company</part></link><space/>interests.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Turner</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">28</arg></template><space/>The privileging of Belgian commercial interests meant that large amounts of capital flowed into the Congo and that individual regions became<space/><link><target>economic specialization</target><part>specialised</part></link>. On many occasions, the interests of the government and private enterprise became closely tied and the state helped companies break strikes and remove other barriers imposed by the indigenous population.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Turner</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">28</arg></template><space/>The country was split into nesting, hierarchically organised administrative subdivisions, and run uniformly according to a set &quot;native policy&quot; (<italics>politique indigne</italics>)in contrast to the British and the French, who generally favoured the system of<space/><link><target>indirect rule</target></link><space/>whereby traditional leaders were retained in positions of authority under colonial oversight. There was also a high degree of<space/><link><target>racial segregation</target></link>. Large numbers of white immigrants who moved to the Congo after the end of<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>came from across the social spectrum, but were nonetheless always treated as superior to blacks.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Turner</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">29</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the 1940s and 1950s, the Congo experienced an unprecedented level of<space/><link><target>urbanisation</target></link><space/>and the colonial administration began various<space/><link><target>International development</target><part>development</part></link><space/>programmes aimed at making the territory into a &quot;model colony&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Freund</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">198–9</arg></template><space/>Notable advances were made in treating diseases such as<space/><link><target>African trypanosomiasis</target></link>. One of the results of these measures was the development of a new middle class of Europeanised African &quot;<italics><link><target>volu</target></link></italics>&quot; in the cities.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Freund</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">198–9</arg></template><space/>By the 1950s the Congo had a<space/><link><target>wage labour</target></link><space/>force twice as large as that in any other African colony.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Freund</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">198</arg></template><space/>The Congo's rich natural resources, including uranium<link><target>Belgian Congo in World War II#Uranium</target><part>much of the uranium</part></link><space/>used by the U.S. nuclear programme during World War II was Congoleseled to substantial interest in the region from both the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>and the United States as the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>developed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Borstelmann</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="pp">92–3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>The Congo Crisis (1960&amp;ndash;1965)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Congo Crisis</arg></template>Following riots in Leopoldville between 47 January 1959, and Stanleyville on 31 October 1959, the Belgians realised they could not maintain control of such a vast country in the face of rising demands for independence. The Belgians and Congolese political leaders held a Round Table Conference in Brussels beginning on 18 January 1960. At the end of the Conference on 27 January 1960 it was announced that elections would be held in the Congo on 22 May 1960, and full independence granted on 30 June 1960. The Congo was indeed granted its independence on 30 June 1960, adopting the name &quot;<link><target>Republic of the Congo (Lopoldville)</target><part>Republic of the Congo</part></link>&quot; (Rpublique du Congo). As the French colony of<space/><link><target>Republic of the Congo</target><part>Middle Congo</part></link><space/>(Moyen Congo) also chose the name Republic of Congo upon receiving its independence, the two countries were more commonly known as<space/><link><target>Republic of the Congo (Lopoldville)</target><part>Congo-Lopoldville</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Republic of the Congo</target><part>Congo-Brazzaville</part></link>, after their capital cities. President<space/><link><target>Mobutu</target></link><space/>changed the country's official name to Zaire in 1966.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1960, the country was in a very unstable stateregional tribal leaders held far more power than the central governmentand with the departure of the Belgian administrators, there were almost no skilled bureaucrats left in the country. The first Congolese university graduate was only in 1956, and virtually no one in the new nation had any idea of how to manage a country of such size.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Belgian Congo general election, 1960</target><part>Parliamentary elections in 1960</part></link><space/>produced the nationalist<space/><link><target>Patrice Lumumba</target></link><space/>as prime minister and pro-<link><target>Western world</target><part>Western</part></link><space/><link><target>Joseph Kasavubu</target></link><space/>as president of the renamed Democratic Republic of the Congo.</paragraph><paragraph>Even from this fleeting moment of independence democracy began to unravel. On 5 July 1960 a military mutiny by Congolese soldiers against their European officers broke out in the capital and rampant looting began. On 11 July 1960 the richest province of the country,<space/><link><target>State of Katanga</target><part>Katanga</part></link>, seceded under<space/><link><target>Moise Tshombe</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>sent 20,000 peacekeepers to protect Europeans in the country and try to restore order. Western paramilitaries and mercenaries, often hired by mining companies to protect their interests, also began to pour into the country. In this same period Congo's second richest province,<space/><link><target>South Kasai</target><part>Kasai</part></link>, also announced its independence on 8 August 1960.</paragraph><paragraph>Prime Minister Lumumba turned to the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>USSR</part></link><space/>for assistance.<space/><link><target>Nikita Khrushchev</target></link><space/>agreed to help, offering advanced weaponry and technical advisors. The<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>viewed the Soviet presence as an attempt to take advantage of the situation and gain a proxy state in<space/><link><target>sub-Saharan Africa</target></link>. UN forces were ordered to block any shipments of arms into the country. The United States also looked for a way to replace Lumumba as leader. President Kasavubu had clashed with Prime Minister Lumumba and advocated an alliance with the West rather than the Soviets. The U.S. sent weapons and CIA personnel to aid forces allied with Kasavubu and combat the Soviet presence. On 14 September 1960, with U.S. and<space/><link><target>CIA</target></link><space/>support, Colonel Joseph Mobutu overthrew the government and arrested Lumumba.</paragraph><paragraph>On 17 January 1961 Mobutu sent Lumumba to lisabethville (now<space/><link><target>Lubumbashi</target></link>), capital of Katanga. In full view of the press he was beaten and forced to eat copies of his own speeches. For the next three weeks, he was not seen or heard from. Then Katangan radio announced implausibly that he had escaped and been killed by some villagers. In fact he had been tortured and killed along with two others shortly after his arrival. It was soon clear that he had been murdered in custody. In 2001, a Belgian inquiry established that he had been shot by Katangan gendarmes in the presence of Belgian officers, under Katangan command. Lumumba was beaten, placed in front of a firing squad with 2 other allies, cut up, buried, dug up and what remained was dissolved in acid.<extension extension_name='ref'>De Witte, Ludo:<space/><italics>The Assassination of Lumumba</italics>, Verso, 2001.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Kisangani</target><part>Stanleyville</part></link>, those loyal to the deposed Lumumba set up a rival government under<space/><link><target>Antoine Gizenga</target></link><space/>which lasted from 31 March 1961 until it was reintegrated on 5 August 1961. After some reverses, UN and Congolese government forces succeeded in recapturing the breakaway provinces of<space/><link><target>South Kasai</target></link><space/>on 30 December 1961, and<space/><link><target>State of Katanga</target><part>Katanga</part></link><space/>on 15 January 1963.</paragraph><paragraph>A new crisis erupted in the<space/><link><target>Simba Rebellion</target></link><space/>of 1964-1965 which saw half the country taken by the rebels. European mercenaries, US, and Belgian troops were called in by the Congolese government to defeat the rebellion.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Zaire (1965&amp;ndash;1997)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Zaire</arg></template><link><target>File:Mobutu.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>Mobutu Sese Seko</part></link>Unrest and rebellion plagued the government until November 1965, when<space/><link><target>Mobuto Sese Seko</target><part>Lieutenant General Mobutu</part></link>, by then commander in chief of the national army, seized control of the country and declared himself president for five years. Mobutu quickly consolidated his power and was elected unopposed as president in 1970. Embarking on a campaign of cultural awareness, Mobutu renamed the country the Republic of Zaire in 1971 and required citizens to adopt African names as well as drop their French-language ones. Relative peace and stability prevailed until 1977 and 1978 when Katangan rebels, based in<space/><link><target>Angola</target></link>, launched a series of invasions (<link><target>Shaba I</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Shaba II</target><part>II</part></link>) into the Shaba (Katanga) region. The rebels were driven out with the aid of Belgian paratroopers.</paragraph><paragraph>Zaire remained a one-party state in the 1980s. Although Mobutu successfully maintained control during this period, opposition parties, most notably the<space/><link><target>Union for Democracy and Social Progress (Democratic Republic of the Congo)</target><part>Union pour la Dmocratie et le Progrs Social</part></link><space/>(UDPS), were active. Mobutu's attempts to quell these groups drew significant international criticism.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As the Cold War came to a close, internal and external pressures on Mobutu increased. In late 1989 and early 1990, Mobutu was weakened by a series of domestic protests, by heightened international criticism of his regime's human rights practices, by a faltering economy, and by government corruption, most notably his massive embezzlement of government funds for personal use.</paragraph><paragraph>In April 1990, Mobutu declared the Third Republic, agreeing to a limited multi-party system with elections and a constitution. As details of a reform package were delayed, soldiers in September 1991 began looting<space/><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link><space/>to protest their unpaid wages. Two thousand French and Belgian troops, some of whom were flown in on<space/><link><target>U.S. Air Force</target></link><space/>planes, arrived to evacuate the 20,000 endangered foreign nationals in Kinshasa.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1992, after previous similar attempts, the long-promised<space/><link><target>Sovereign National Conference</target></link><space/>was staged, encompassing over 2,000 representatives from various political parties. The conference gave itself a legislative mandate and elected Archbishop<space/><link><target>Laurent Monsengwo</target></link><space/>as its chairman, along with<space/><link><target>tienne Tshisekedi wa Mulumba</target></link>, leader of the UDPS, as prime minister. By the end of the year Mobutu had created a rival government with its own prime minister. The ensuing stalemate produced a compromise merger of the two governments into the<space/><link><target>High Council of Republic-Parliament of Transition</target></link><space/>(HCR-PT) in 1994, with Mobutu as head of state and<space/><link><target>Kengo Wa Dondo</target></link><space/>as prime minister. Although presidential and legislative elections were scheduled repeatedly over the next two years, they never took place.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>First Congo War (1996&amp;ndash;1997)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>second Congo War</arg></template>By 1996, tensions from the neighboring<space/><link><target>Rwanda</target></link><space/>war and<space/><link><target>genocide</target></link><space/>had spilled over to<space/><link><target>Zaire</target></link>:<space/><italics>see<space/><link><target>History of Rwanda</target></link></italics>. Rwandan<space/><link><target>Hutu</target></link><space/>militia forces (<link><target>Interahamwe</target></link>), who had fled Rwanda following the ascension of a<space/><link><target>Tutsi</target></link>-led government, had been using Hutu refugees camps in eastern Zaire as a basis for incursion against Rwanda. These Hutu militia forces soon allied with the Zairian armed forces (FAZ) to launch a campaign against Congolese ethnic Tutsis in eastern Zaire. In turn, these Tutsis formed a militia to defend themselves against attacks. When the Zairian government began to escalate its massacres in November 1996, the Tutsi militias erupted in rebellion against Mobutu.</paragraph><paragraph>The Tutsi militia was soon joined by various opposition groups and supported by several countries, including Rwanda and Uganda. This coalition, led by<space/><link><target>Laurent-Desire Kabila</target></link>, became known as the<space/><link><target>Alliance des Forces Dmocratiques pour la Libration du Congo-Zare</target></link><space/>(AFDL). The AFDL, now seeking the broader goal of ousting Mobutu, made significant military gains in early 1997. They were soon joined by various Zairean politicians, who had been unsuccessfully opposing the dictatorship of Mobutu for many years, and now saw an opportunity for them in the invasion of Zaire by two of the region's strongest military forces. Following failed peace talks between Mobutu and Kabila in May 1997, Mobutu left the country, and Kabila marched unopposed to Kinshasa on 20 May. Kabila named himself president, consolidated power around himself and the AFDL, and reverted the name of the country to the Democratic Republic of Congo.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Second Congo War (1998&amp;ndash;2003)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Second Congo War</arg></template>Kabila demonstrated little ability to manage the problems of his country, and lost his allies. To counterbalance the power and influence of Rwanda in DRC, the Ugandan troops instigated the creation of another rebel movement called the<space/><link><target>Movement for the Liberation of Congo</target></link><space/>(MLC), led by the Congolese warlord<space/><link><target>Jean-Pierre Bemba</target></link>. They attacked in August 1998, backed by Rwandan and Ugandan troops. Soon afterwards, Angola, Namibia, and Zimbabwe became involved militarily in the Congo, with Angola and Zimbabwe supporting the government. While the six African governments involved in the war signed a ceasefire accord in Lusaka in July 1999, the Congolese rebels did not and the ceasefire broke down within months. However, Kabila was assassinated in 2001 by one of his bodyguards and was succeeded by his son,<space/><link><target>Joseph Kabila</target><part>Joseph</part></link>. Upon taking office, Kabila called for multilateral peace talks to end the war. Kabila partly succeeded when a further peace deal was brokered between him, Uganda, and Rwanda leading to the apparent withdrawal of foreign troops.</paragraph><paragraph>Currently, the Ugandans and the MLC still hold a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>wide section of the north of the country; Rwandan forces and its front, the<space/><link><target>Rassemblement Congolais pour la Dmocratie</target></link><space/>(RCD) control a large section of the east; and government forces or their allies hold the west and south of the country. There were reports that the conflict is being prolonged as a cover for extensive looting of the substantial natural resources in the country, including<space/><link><target>diamond</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>copper</target></link>,<space/><link><target>zinc</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>coltan</target></link>. The conflict was reignited in January 2002 by ethnic clashes in the northeast and both Uganda and Rwanda then halted their withdrawal and sent in more troops. Talks between Kabila and the rebel leaders, held in<space/><link><target>Sun City, North West</target><part>Sun City</part></link>, lasted a full six weeks, beginning in April 2002. In June, they signed a peace accord in which Kabila would share power with former rebels. By June 2003, all foreign armies except those of Rwanda had pulled out of Congo. Few people in the Congo have been unaffected by the armed conflict. A survey conducted in 2009 by the ICRC and Ipsos shows that three quarters (76%) of the people interviewed have been affected in some wayeither personally or due to the wider consequences of armed conflict.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.icrc.org/Web/eng/siteeng0.nsf/htmlall/views-from-field-report-240609/$File/Our-World-Views-from-DRC-I-ICRC.pdf'>DRC, Opinion survey 2009</link>, by ICRC and Ipsos</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The response of the international community has been incommensurate with the scale of the disaster resulting from the war in the Congo. Its support for political and diplomatic efforts to end the war has been relatively consistent, but it has taken no effective steps to abide by repeated pledges to demand accountability for the war crimes and crimes against humanity that were routinely committed in Congo. United Nations Security Council and the U.N. Secretary-General have frequently denounced human rights abuses and the humanitarian disaster that the war unleashed on the local population. But they had shown little will to tackle the responsibility of occupying powers for the atrocities taking place in areas under their control, areas where the worst violence in the country took place. Hence Rwanda, like Uganda, has escaped any significant sanction for its role.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hrw.org/en/reports/2002/08/20/war-crimes-kisangani-0<space/></arg><arg name="title">Human Rights Watch: War Crimes in Kisangani<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hrw.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 August 2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2 May 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Transitional government (2003&amp;ndash;2006)</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Transitional Government of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</arg><arg>Democratic Republic of the Congo general election, 2006</arg></template>DR Congo had a<space/><link><target>Transitional Government of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>transitional government</part></link><space/>in July 2003 until the election was over. A constitution was approved by voters and on 30 July 2006 the Congo held its<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo general election, 2006</target><part>first multi-party elections</part></link><space/>since independence in 1960. After this<space/><link><target>Joseph Kabila</target></link><space/>took 45% of the votes and his opponent Jean-Pierre Bemba took 20%. That was the origin of a fight between the two parts from 2022 August 2006 in the streets of the capital,<space/><link><target>Kinshasa</target></link>. Sixteen people died before policemen and UN mission MONUC took control of the city. A new election was held on 29 October 2006, which Kabila won with 70% of the vote. Bemba has publicly commented on election &quot;irregularities,&quot; despite the fact that every neutral observer has praised the elections. On 6 December 2006 the Transitional Government came to an end as Joseph Kabila was sworn in as President.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Continued conflicts</heading><paragraph>The fragility of the state has allowed continued violence and human rights abuses in the east. There are three significant centers of conflict.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Ituri Province</target><part>Ituri</part></link>, where MONUC has proved unable to contain the numerous militia and groups driving the<space/><link><target>Ituri conflict</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>Northern<space/><link><target>Katanga Province</target><part>Katanga</part></link>, where<space/><link><target>Mai-Mai</target></link><space/>created by Laurent Kabila slipped out of the control of Kinshasa.</paragraph><paragraph>In October 2009<space/><link><target>Dongo conflict</target><part>a new conflict</part></link><space/>started in<space/><link><target>Dongo, Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Dongo</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Sud-Ubangi District</target></link><space/>where clashes had broken out over access to fishing ponds.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Kivu conflict</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Kivu conflict</arg></template><link><target>North Kivu</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South Kivu</target></link>, where<space/><link><target>Democratic Forces for the Liberation of Rwanda</target></link><space/>(FDLR) continues to threaten the Rwandan border and the<space/><link><target>Banyamulenge</target></link>, Rwanda supported<space/><link><target>RCD-Goma</target></link><space/>rebels (see<space/><link><target>Kivu war</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>In April 2012, ethnic<space/><link><target>Tutsi</target></link><space/>soldiers mutinied against the government of the<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link>. Mutineers formed a rebel group called the<space/><link><target>March 23 Movement</target></link><space/>(M23), composed of former members of the rebel<space/><link><target>National Congress for the Defence of the People</target></link><space/>(CNDP). On 20 November 2012, M23<space/><link><target>2012 East D.R. Congo conflict</target><part>took control</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Goma</target></link>, a provincial capital with a population of one million people.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-20405739<space/></arg><arg name="title">Goma: M23 rebels capture DR Congo city<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">18 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6CKPvBOsr<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Re-election of Joseph Kabila</heading><paragraph>In December 2011,<space/><link><target>Joseph Kabila</target></link><space/>was re-elected for a second term as president. After the results were announced on 9 December, there was violent unrest in Kinshasa and<space/><link><target>Mbuji-Mayi</target></link>, where official tallies showed that a strong majority had voted for the opposition candidate<space/><link><target>Etienne Tshisekedi</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">DR Congo election: Questions hang over Kabila's victory</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-16128729</arg><arg name="newspaper">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">10 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Official observers from the<space/><link><target>Carter Center</target></link><space/>reported that returns from almost 2,000 polling stations in areas where support for Tshisekedi was strong had been lost and not included in the official results. They described the election as lacking credibility.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Carter Center: DRC Presidential Election Results Lack Credibility (press release)</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cartercenter.org/news/pr/drc-121011.html</arg><arg name="newspaper">Carter Center</arg><arg name="date">10 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>On 20 December, Kabila was sworn in for a second term, promising to invest in infrastructure and public services. However, Tshisekedi maintained that the result of the election was illegitimate and said that he intended also to &quot;swear himself in&quot; as president.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">DR Congo President Joseph Kabila begins second term</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-africa-16261907</arg><arg name="newspaper">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">20 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 19 January 2015<space/><link><target>2015 Congolese protests</target><part>protests led by students at the University of Kinshasa broke out</part></link>. The protests began following the announcement of a proposed law that would allow Kabila to remain in power until a national census can be conducted (elections had been planned for<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo general election, 2016</target><part>2016</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reuters1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Ross</arg><arg name="first">Aaron</arg><arg name="date">21 January 2015</arg><arg name="title">UPDATE 2-Congo protests enter third day, rights group says 42 dead</arg><arg name="url">http://af.reuters.com/article/drcNews/idAFL6N0V01NX20150121?sp</arg><arg name="work">[[Reuters]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 January 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Jullien</arg><arg name="first">Maud</arg><arg name="date">21 January 2015</arg><arg name="title">DR Congo unrest: Catholic church backs protests</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.com/news/world-africa-30913739</arg><arg name="work">[[BBC]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 January 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>By Wednesday 21 January clashes between police and protesters had claimed at least 42 lives (although the government claimed only 15 people had been killed).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reuters1"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Former names of cities</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Former place names in the Democratic Republic of the Congo</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>History of Africa</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of heads of state of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of heads of government of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Politics of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of Kinshasa</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Turner|2007}}</arg><arg name="last1">Turner</arg><arg name="first1">Thomas</arg><arg name="title">The Congo Wars: Conflict, Myth, and Reality</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Zed Books</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84277-688-9</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Freund|1998}}</arg><arg name="last1">Freund</arg><arg name="first1">Bill</arg><arg name="title">The Making of Contemporary Africa: The Development of African Society since 1800</arg><arg name="date">1998</arg><arg name="publisher">Palgrave-Macmillan</arg><arg name="location">Basingstoke</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-333-69872-3</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Borstelmann</arg><arg name="first">Thomas</arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Borstelmann|1993}}</arg><arg name="title">Apartheid, Colonialism, and the Cold War: the United States and Southern Africa, 1945–1952</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-507942-6</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.boondocksnet.com/congo/'>&quot;Reforming the Heart of Darkness&quot;</link><space/>Concerning the Congo under Lopold II</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/country_profiles/1076399.stm'>BBC, Country profile: Democratic Republic of Congo</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/shared/spl/hi/guides/456900/456977/html/nn1page1.stm'>BBC, DR Congo: Key facts</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/3075537.stm'>BBC, Q&amp;A: DR Congo conflict</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/country_profiles/1072684.stm'>Timeline: Democratic Republic of Congo</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/in_pictures/7702602.stm'>BBC, In pictures: Congo crisis</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>History of Africa</target></template><template><target>DRC topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:History of the Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:History of Central Africa</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:History of Africa by country</target><part>Democratic Republic of the Congo</part></link></paragraph></article>