<article title='Carlo_Goldoni'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="name"><space/>Carlo Goldoni
</arg><arg name="image">Carlo Goldoni - 1750.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="alt">
</arg><arg name="caption">
</arg><arg name="pseudonym"><space/>Polisseno Fegeio, Pastor Arcade
</arg><arg name="birth_name">
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1707|02|25|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Venice]], [[Republic of Venice]], in present-day [[Italian Republic]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1793|02|06|1707|02|25|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Paris]], France
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Playwright • [[Libretto|Librettist]]
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>[[Italy|Italian]]
</arg><arg name="ethnicity">
</arg><arg name="citizenship">
</arg><arg name="education">
</arg><arg name="alma_mater">
</arg><arg name="period">
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Comedy (drama)|Comedy]]
</arg><arg name="subject">
</arg><arg name="movement">
</arg><arg name="notableworks"><space/>''[[Servant of Two Masters]]''<br />''[[The Mistress of the Inn]]''
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>Nicoletta Conio
</arg><arg name="partner">
</arg><arg name="children">
</arg><arg name="relatives">
</arg><arg name="influences">
</arg><arg name="influenced">
</arg><arg name="awards">
</arg><arg name="signature">
</arg><arg name="signature_alt">
</arg><arg name="website">
</arg><arg name="portaldisp">
</arg></template><bold>Carlo Osvaldo Goldoni</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>ˈkarlo ozˈvaldo ɡolˈdoːni</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>; 25 February 1707 6 February 1793) was an<space/><link><target>Italians</target><part>Italian</part></link><space/>playwright and<space/><link><target>Libretto</target><part>librettist</part></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Republic of Venice</target></link>. His works include some of Italy's most famous and best-loved plays. Audiences have admired the plays of Goldoni for their ingenious mix of wit and honesty. His plays offered his contemporaries images of themselves, often dramatizing the lives, values, and conflicts of the emerging<space/><link><target>middle class</target><trail>es</trail></link>. Though he wrote in French and Italian, his plays make rich use of the<space/><link><target>Venetian language</target></link>, regional vernacular, and colloquialisms. Goldoni also wrote under the<space/><link><target>pen name</target></link><space/>and title &quot;Polisseno Fegeio, Pastor Arcade,&quot; which he claimed in his memoirs the &quot;<link><target>Accademia degli Arcadi</target><part>Arcadians</part></link><space/>of Rome&quot; bestowed on him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Goldoni
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Carlo
</arg><arg name="others">John Black (trans.)
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Memoirs of Goldoni
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="format"><space/>Google books
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>6 September 2008
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1814
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Henry Colburn
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>331
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>XVII</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of his best known works is the comic play<space/><italics><link><target>Servant of Two Masters</target></link></italics>, which has been translated and adapted internationally numerous times. In 2011,<space/><link><target>Richard Bean</target></link><space/>adapted the play for the<space/><link><target>National Theatre of Great Britain</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics><link><target>One Man, Two Guvnors</target></link></italics>. Its popularity led to a transfer to the<space/><link><target>West End theatre</target><part>West End</part></link><space/>and in 2012 to<space/><link><target>Broadway theatre</target><part>Broadway</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Memoirs</heading><paragraph>There is an abundance of autobiographical information on Goldoni, most of which comes from the introductions to his plays and from his<space/><italics>Memoirs</italics>. However, these memoirs are known to contain many errors of fact, especially about his earlier years.</paragraph><paragraph>In these memoirs, he paints himself as a born comedian, careless, light-hearted and with a happy temperament, proof against all strokes of fate, yet thoroughly respectable and honorable.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early life and studies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Palazzo Centani e Rio San Toma.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Palazzo Centani'' birthplace of Goldoni in Venice</part></link>Goldoni was born in<space/><link><target>Venice</target></link><space/>in 1707, the son of Margherita and Giulio Goldoni. In his memoirs, Goldoni describes his father as a<space/><link><target>physician</target></link>, and claims that he was introduced to theatre by his grandfather Carlo Alessandro Goldoni. In reality, it seems that Giulio was an<space/><link><target>apothecary</target></link>; as for the grandfather, he had died four years before Carlo's birth. In any case, Goldoni was deeply interested in theatre from his earliest years, and all attempts to direct his activity into other channels were of no avail; his toys were puppets, and his books, plays.</paragraph><paragraph>His father placed him under the care of the philosopher Caldini at<space/><link><target>Rimini</target></link><space/>but the youth soon ran away with a company of strolling players and returned to Venice. In 1723 his father matriculated him into the stern<space/><link><target>Collegio Ghislieri</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Pavia</target></link>, which imposed the<space/><link><target>tonsure</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>monk</target><part>monastic habits</part></link><space/>on its students. However, he relates in his<space/><italics>Memoirs</italics><space/>that a considerable part of his time was spent in reading Greek and<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>comedies. He had already begun writing at this time and, in his third year, he composed a<space/><link><target>libel</target><trail>lous</trail></link><space/>poem (<italics>Il colosso</italics>) in which he ridiculed the daughters of certain Pavian families. As a result of that incident (and/or of a visit paid with some schoolmates to a local brothel) he was expelled from the school and had to leave the city (1725). He studied law at<space/><link><target>Udine</target></link>, and eventually took his degree at<space/><link><target>Modena</target></link>. He was employed as a law clerk at<space/><link><target>Chioggia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Feltre</target></link>, after which he returned to his native city and began practicing.<link><target>File:Monument to Carlo Goldoni (Venice).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Monument to Goldoni in<space/><link><target>Venice</target></link><space/>(sculpted by Antonio Dal Zotto)</part></link>Educated as a lawyer, and holding lucrative positions as secretary and counsellor, he seemed, indeed, at one time to have settled down to the practice of law, but following an unexpected summons to Venice, after an absence of several years, he changed his career, and thenceforth he devoted himself to writing plays and managing theatres. His father died in 1731. In 1732, to avoid an unwanted marriage, he left the town for<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>and then for<space/><link><target>Verona</target></link><space/>where the theatre manager Giuseppe Imer helped him on his way to becoming a comical poet as well as introducing him to his future wife, Nicoletta Conio. Goldoni returned with her to Venice, where he stayed until 1743.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Theatrical career</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Statua di Carlo Goldoni (Firenze).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Monument to Goldoni in<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link><space/>(sculpted by<space/><link><target>Ulisse Cambi</target></link>)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Goldoni entered the Italian theatre scene with a<space/><link><target>tragedy</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Amalasunta</target></link></italics>, produced in Milan. The play was a critical and financial failure.</paragraph><paragraph>Submitting it to Count Prata, director of the opera, he was told that his piece &quot;was composed with due regard for the rules of<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Horace</target></link>, but not according to those laid down for the Italian drama.&quot; &quot;In France&quot;, continued the count, &quot;you can try to please the public, but here in Italy it is the actors and actresses whom you must consult, as well as the composer of the music and the stage decorators. Everything must be done according to a certain form which I will explain to you.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Goldoni thanked his critic, went back to his inn and ordered a fire, into which he threw the manuscript of his<space/><italics>Amalasunta</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>His next play,<space/><italics>Belisario</italics>, written in 1734, was more successful, though of its success he afterward professed himself ashamed.</paragraph><paragraph>During this period he also wrote<space/><link><target>librettos</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>opera seria</target></link><space/>and served for a time as literary director of the<space/><link><target>Teatro San Giovanni Grisostomo</target><part>San Giovanni Grisostomo</part></link>, Venice's most distinguished<space/><link><target>opera house</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cgt">Banham (1998, 433).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>He wrote other tragedies for a time, but he was not long in discovering that his bent was for<space/><link><target>comedy</target></link>. He had come to realize that the Italian stage needed reforming; adopting<space/><link><target>Molire</target></link><space/>as his model, he went to work in earnest and in 1738 produced his first real comedy,<space/><italics>L'uomo di mondo</italics><space/>(&quot;The Man of the World&quot;). During his many wanderings and adventures in Italy, he was constantly at work and when, at<space/><link><target>Livorno</target></link>, he became acquainted with the manager Medebac, he determined to pursue the profession of playwriting in order to make a living. He was employed by Medebac to write plays for his theater in Venice. He worked for other managers and produced during his stay in that city some of his most characteristic works. He also wrote<space/><italics>Momolo Cortesan</italics><space/>in 1738. By 1743, he had perfected his hybrid style of playwriting (combining the model of<space/><link><target>Molire</target></link><space/>with the strengths of<space/><link><target>Commedia dell'arte</target></link><space/>and his own wit and sincerity). This style was typified in<space/><italics>La Donna di garbo</italics>, the first Italian comedy of its kind.</paragraph><paragraph>After 1748, Goldoni collaborated with the composer<space/><link><target>Baldassare Galuppi</target></link>, making significant contributions to the new form of '<link><target>opera buffa</target></link>'. Galuppi composed the score for more than twenty of Goldoni's librettos. As with his comedies, Goldoni's<space/><italics>opera buffa</italics><space/>integrate elements of the Commedia dell'arte with recognisable local and middle-class realities. His operatic works include two of the most successful musical comedies of the eighteenth century,<space/><italics>Il filosofo di campagna</italics><space/>(<italics>The Country Philosopher</italics>), set by Galuppi (1752) and<space/><italics><link><target>La buona figliuola</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Good Girl</italics>), set by<space/><link><target>Niccol Piccinni</target></link><space/>(1760).<extension extension_name='ref' name="cgt"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1753, following his return from Bologna he defected to the<space/><link><target>Teatro San Luca</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Vendramin</target></link><space/>family where he performed most of his plays to 1762.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Move to France and death</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Carlo Goldoni buste neige.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>130px</part><part>Bust of Goldoni, near<space/><link><target>Notre Dame de Paris</target><part>Notre Dame</part></link><space/>in Paris</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1757, he engaged in a bitter dispute with playwright<space/><link><target>Carlo Gozzi</target></link>, which left him utterly disgusted with the tastes of his countrymen; so much so that in 1761 he moved to Paris, where he received a position at court and was put in charge of the<space/><link><target>Comdie-Italienne</target><part>Theatre Italien</part></link>. He spent the rest of his life in France, composing most of his plays in French and writing his memoirs in that language.</paragraph><paragraph>Among the plays which he wrote in French, the most successful was<space/><italics><link><target>Le bourru bienfaisant</target></link></italics>, produced on the occasion of the marriage of<space/><link><target>Louis XVI of France</target><part>Louis XVI</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Marie Antoinette</target></link><space/>in 1771. He enjoyed considerable popularity in France; when he retired to<space/><link><target>Versailles (city)</target><part>Versailles</part></link>, the King gave him a pension. He lost this pension after the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>. The Convention eventually voted to restore his pension the day after his death. It was restored to his widow, at the pleading of the poet<space/><link><target>Andr Chnier</target></link>; &quot;She is old&quot;, he urged, &quot;she is seventy-six, and her husband has left her no heritage save his illustrious name, his virtues and his poverty.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Goldoni's impact on Italian theatre</heading><paragraph>In his<space/><italics>Memoirs</italics><space/>Goldoni amply discusses the state of Italian comedy when he began writing. At that time, Italian comedy revolved around the conventionality of the<space/><link><target>Commedia dell'arte</target></link>, or improvised comedy. Goldoni took to himself the task of superseding the comedy of masks and the comedy of intrigue by representations of actual life and manners. He rightly maintained that Italian life and manners were susceptible of artistic treatment such as had not been given them before.</paragraph><paragraph>His works are a lasting monument to the changes that he initiated: a dramatic revolution that had been attempted but not achieved before. Goldoni's importance lay in providing good examples rather than precepts. Goldoni says that he took for his models the plays of<space/><link><target>Molire</target></link><space/>and that whenever a piece of his own succeeded he whispered to himself: &quot;Good, but not yet Molire.&quot; Goldoni's plays are gentler and more optimistic in tone than Molire's.</paragraph><paragraph>It was this very success that was the object of harsh critiques by<space/><link><target>Carlo Gozzi</target></link>, who accused Goldoni of having deprived the Italian theatre of the charms of poetry and imagination. The great success of Gozzi's fairy dramas so irritated Goldoni that it led to his self-exile to France.</paragraph><paragraph>Goldoni gave to his country a classical form, which, though it has since been cultivated, has yet to be cultivated by a master.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>Goldoni's plays that were written while he was still in Italy ignore<space/><link><target>religion</target><part>religious</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ecclesiastical</target></link><space/>subjects. This may be surprising, considering his staunch<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target><part>Catholic</part></link><space/>upbringing. No thoughts are expressed about death or repentance in his memoirs or in his comedies. After his move to France, his position became clearer, as his plays took on a clear<space/><link><target>anti-clericalism</target><part>anti-clerical</part></link><space/>tone and often satirized the hypocrisy of monks and of the<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target><part>Church</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Goldoni was inspired by his love of humanity and the admiration he had for his fellow men. He wrote, and was obsessed with, the relationships that humans establish with one another, their cities and homes, the<space/><link><target>Humanism</target><part>Humanist</part></link><space/>movement, and the study of<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link>. The moral and civil values that Goldoni promotes in his plays are those of rationality, civility, humanism, the importance of the rising middle-class, a progressive stance to state affairs, honor and honesty. Goldoni had a dislike for arrogance, intolerance and the abuse of power.</paragraph><paragraph>Goldoni's main characters are no abstract examples of human virtue, nor monstrous examples of human vice. They occupy the middle ground of human temperament. Goldoni maintains an acute sensibility for the differences in social classes between his characters as well as environmental and generational changes. Goldoni pokes fun at the arrogant nobility and the pauper who lacks dignity.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Venetian and Tuscan</heading><paragraph>As in other theatrical works of the time and place, the characters in Goldoni's Italian comedies spoke originally either the literary Tuscan variety (which became modern Italian) or the<space/><link><target>Venetian language</target><part>Venetian dialect</part></link>, depending on their station in life. However, in some printed editions of his plays he often turned the Venetian texts into Tuscan, too.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Goldoni in popular culture</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>The film<space/><italics>Carlo Goldoni Venice, Grand Theatre of the World</italics>, directed by Alessandro Bettero, was released in 2007 and is available in English, Italian, French, and Japanese.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.goldonithemovie.com/index.php?lan=en goldonithemovie</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Selected works</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>List of works by Carlo Goldoni</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The following is a small sampling of Goldoni's enormous output.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tragedies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Rosmonda</italics><space/>(1734)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Griselda (Vivaldi)</target><part>Griselda</part></link></italics><space/>(1734)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Tragicomedies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Belisario</italics><space/>(1734)</listitem><listitem><italics>Rinaldo di Montalbano</italics><space/>(1736)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Comedies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Servant of Two Masters</target><part>Il servitore di due padroni</part></link></italics>, (1745) &quot;The Servant of Two Masters&quot; (now often retitled<space/><italics>Arlecchino servitore di due padroni</italics><space/>&quot;Harlequin Servant of two Masters&quot;)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>I due gemelli veneziani</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Two Venetian Twins&quot; (1747)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.piccoloteatro.org/gemelli/mainspett.htm'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.piccoloteatro.org/gemelli/mainspett.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20120215200039<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>La vedova scaltra</italics>, &quot;The Shrewd Widow&quot; (1748)<extension extension_name='ref' group="C"><italics>La vedova scaltra</italics><space/>was used for operas by<space/><link><target>Marcello Bernardini</target></link><space/>(as<space/><italics>La donna di spirito</italics>) in 1770,<space/><link><target>Vincenzo Righini</target></link><space/>in 1774,<space/><link><target>Niccol Piccinni</target></link><space/>in 1773,<space/><link><target>Pasquale Anfossi</target></link><space/>in 1780, and<space/><link><target>Ermanno Wolf-Ferrari</target></link><space/>in 1931 (see<space/><italics><link><target>La vedova scaltra</target></link></italics>).</extension></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>La putta onorata</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Honorable Maid&quot; (1749)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Il cavaliere e la dama</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Gentleman and the Lady&quot; (1749)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>La famiglia dell'antiquario</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Antiquarian's Family&quot; (1750)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Il teatro comico</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Comical Theatre&quot; (17501751)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Liar (Goldoni)</target><part>Il bugiardo</part></link></italics>, &quot;The Liar&quot; (17501751)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Il vero amico</target></link></italics>, &quot;The True Friend&quot; (1750) translated by Anna Cuffaro</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>I pettegolezzi delle donne</target></link></italics>, &quot;Women's Gossip&quot; (17501751)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Mistress of the Inn</target><part>La locandiera</part></link></italics>, &quot;The Mistress of the Inn&quot; (1751)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Il feudatario</target></link></italics><space/>&quot;The Feudal Lord&quot; (1752)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Gl'innamorati</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Lovers&quot; (1759)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Boors</target><part>I rusteghi</part></link></italics>, &quot;The Boors&quot; (1760)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Le baruffe chiozzotte</target></link></italics><space/>(1762) &quot;The Chioggia Scuffles&quot;</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Gli amori di Zelinda e Lindoro</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Love of Zelinda and Lindoro&quot; (1764)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Opera seria libretti</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Amalasunta</italics><space/>(1732)</listitem><listitem><italics>Gustavo</italics><space/>(c. 1738)</listitem><listitem><italics>Oronte, re de' Sciti</italics><space/>(1740)</listitem><listitem><italics>Statira</italics><space/>(c. 1740)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Opera buffa libretti</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>La contessina</italics><space/>(<italics>The Young Countess</italics>) by<space/><link><target>Maccari</target></link><space/>(1743)</listitem><listitem><italics>L'Arcadia in Brenta</italics><space/>(<italics>The<space/><link><target>Arcadia</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Brenta, Lombardy</target><part>Brenta</part></link></italics>) by<space/><link><target>Baldassare Galuppi</target><part>Galuppi</part></link><space/>(1749)</listitem><listitem><italics>Il mondo della luna</italics><space/>(<italics>The World on the Moon</italics>), set to music by<space/><link><target>Il mondo della luna (Galuppi)</target><part>Galuppi</part></link><space/>(1750),<space/><link><target>Il mondo della luna</target><part>Haydn</part></link><space/>(1777),<space/><link><target>Paisiello</target></link><space/>and other composers.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Il filosofo di campagna</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Country Philosopher</italics>) by Galuppi (1752)</listitem><listitem><italics>Il mercato di Malmantile</italics><space/>(<italics>The Malmantile Market</italics>) by<space/><link><target>Domenico Fischietti</target><part>Fischietti</part></link><space/>(1757)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>La buona figliuola</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Good Girl</italics>) by<space/><link><target>Niccol Piccinni</target></link><space/>(1760)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Lo speziale</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Apothecary</italics>) by<space/><link><target>Joseph Haydn</target></link><space/>(1768)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Intermezzo libretti</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Le donne vendicate</target></link></italics>, &quot;The Revenge of the Women&quot; (1751)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Cantatas and serenades</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>La ninfa saggia</italics>, &quot;The Wise Nymph&quot; (17??)</listitem><listitem><italics>Gli amanti felici</italics>, &quot;The Happy Lovers&quot; (17??)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Poetry</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Il colosso</italics>, a satire against Pavia girls which led to Goldoni being expelled from Collegio Ghislieri (1725)</listitem><listitem><italics>Il quaresimale in epilogo</italics><space/>(17251726)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Books</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Nuovo teatro comico</italics>, &quot;New Comic Theater&quot;, plays. Pitteri, Venice (1757)</listitem><listitem><italics>Mmoires</italics>, &quot;Memoirs&quot;. Paris (1787)</listitem><listitem>Goldoni's collected works. Zalta, Venice (17881795)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Selected translations of Goldoni's works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Il vero amico</italics>, &quot;The True Friend&quot; translated by Anna Cuffaro. Publisher: Sparkling Books.</listitem><listitem><italics>Archifanfaro</italics><space/>translated by<space/><link><target>W. H. Auden</target></link><space/>with an introduction by<space/><link><target>Michael Andre</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>Unmuzzled OX</target></link></italics>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template><extension extension_name='references' group="C"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Drama: Its History, Literature and Influence on Civilization</italics><space/>ed. Alfred Bates. New York: Historical Publishing Company, 1906. pp.&amp;nbsp;6368.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Holme<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Timothy<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Timothy Holme<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Servant of Many Masters: The Life and Times of Carlo Goldoni<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Jupiter<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-904041-61-1</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>oldwikisource:Author:Carlo Goldoni</arg><arg>Carlo Goldoni</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>URL</target><arg>www.carlogoldoni.net</arg></template><space/>the English website dedicated to Goldoni</listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Goldoni,+Carlo<space/></arg><arg name="name">Carlo Goldoni</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Carlo Goldoni</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">2188</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>URL</target><arg>www.sparklingbooks.com</arg></template><space/>for bilingual edition English/Italian of The True Friend/Il vero amico</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.uoc.edu/lletra/noms/cgoldoni/index.html'>Webpage devoted to Carlo Goldoni (lletrA (UOC), Catalan Literature Online)</link><space/><template><target>ca icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vicenzanews.it/apt_pro/goldonicarlo/'>Detailed biography</link>, prepared for the 200th anniversary of his death (1993)<space/><template><target>it icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.crs4.it/Letteratura/Innamorati/Innamorati.html'>Gli Innamorati</link><space/><template><target>it icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.liberliber.it/online/autori/autori-g/carlo-goldoni/la-locandiera/'>La Locandiera</link><space/><template><target>it icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.liberliber.it/biblioteca/g/goldoni/le_avventure_della_villeggiatura/html/index.htm'>La Avventura Della Villeggiatura</link><space/><template><target>it icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.liberliber.it/biblioteca/g/goldoni/index.htm'>Works by Goldoni at Progetto Manuzio</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.intratext.com/Catalogo/Autori/Aut408.HTM'>Works by Goldoni</link><space/>(text, concordances and frequency list)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.carnivalofvenice.com/area.asp?id=4&amp;amp;desc=The+Venice+Carnival+Indepentent+Guide+since+1998'>Venice Carnival 2007</link>, Tricentenary of Carlo Goldoni</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mondo-marion.com/arlecchino.html'>A riotous delight of commedia dell'arte</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/06631a.htm'>Carlo Goldoni</link><space/>biography in the<space/><link><target>Catholic Encyclopedia</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Goldoni, Carlo
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Italian writer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>25 February 1707
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Venice]], [[Republic of Venice]], in present-day [[Italy]]
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>6 February 1793
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Paris]], France
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Goldoni, Carlo</target></template><link><target>Category:1707 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1793 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Commedia dell'arte</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian dramatists and playwrights</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian opera librettists</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Venice</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian male dramatists and playwrights</target></link></paragraph></article>