<article title='Anemometer'><paragraph><link><target>File:Wea00920.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A hemispherical cup anemometer of the type invented in 1846 by<space/><link><target>John Thomas Romney Robinson</target></link></part></link>An<space/><bold>anemometer</bold><space/>is a device used for measuring<space/><link><target>wind</target></link><space/>speed, and is a common<space/><link><target>weather station</target></link><space/>instrument. The term is derived from the Greek word<space/><italics>anemos</italics>,which means wind, and is used to describe any wind speed measurement instrument used in<space/><link><target>meteorology</target></link><space/>. The first known description of an anemometer given by<space/><link><target>Leon Battista Alberti</target></link><space/>in 1450.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The anemometer has changed little since its development in the 15th century.<space/><link><target>Leon Battista Alberti</target></link><space/>is said to have invented the first mechanical anemometer around 1450. In following centuries, numerous others, including<space/><link><target>Robert Hooke</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Mayans</target></link>, developed their own versions, with some being mistakenly credited as the inventor. In 1846,<space/><link><target>John Thomas Romney Robinson</target></link><space/>improved upon the design by using four hemispherical cups and mechanical wheels.Later, in 1926,<space/><link><target>John Patterson (meteorologist)</target><part>John Patterson</part></link><space/>developed a three-cup anemometer, which was improved by Brevoort and Joiner in 1935. In 1991, Derek Weston added the ability to detect wind direction. Most recently, in 1994, Dr. Andrews Pflitsch developed the sonic anemometer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.logicenergy.com/articles/history-anemometer/</arg><arg name="title">History of the Anemometer</arg><arg name="publisher">Logic Energy</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 April 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Velocity anemometers</heading><heading level='3'>Cup anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Cup-Anemometer-Animation.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Cup anemometer animation</part></link>A simple type of anemometer was invented in 1845 by Dr.<space/><link><target>John Thomas Romney Robinson</target></link>, of<space/><link><target>Armagh Observatory</target></link>. It consisted of four<space/><link><target>hemispherical</target></link><space/>cups, each mounted on one end of four horizontal arms, which in turn were mounted at equal angles to each other on a vertical shaft. The air flow past the cups in any horizontal direction turned the shaft in a manner that was proportional to the wind speed. Therefore, counting the turns of the shaft over a set time period produced the average wind speed for a wide range of speeds. On an anemometer with four cups, it is easy to see that since the cups are arranged symmetrically on the end of the arms, the wind always has the hollow of one cup presented to it and is blowing on the back of the cup on the opposite end of the cross.</paragraph><paragraph>When Robinson first designed his anemometer, he asserted that the cups moved one-third of the speed of the wind, unaffected by the cup size or arm length. This was apparently confirmed by some early independent experiments, but it was incorrect. Instead, the ratio of the speed of the wind and that of the cups, the anemometer factor, depends on the dimensions of the cups and arms, and may have a value between two and a little over three. Every previous experiment involving an anemometer had to be repeated.</paragraph><paragraph>The three-cup anemometer developed by the Canadian<space/><link><target>John Patterson (meteorologist)</target><part>John Patterson</part></link><space/>in 1926 and subsequent cup improvements by Brevoort &amp; Joiner of the USA in 1935 led to a cupwheel design which was linear and had an error of less than 3% up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60</arg><arg>mi/h</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. Patterson found that each cup produced maximum torque when it was at 45 degrees to the wind flow. The three-cup anemometer also had a more constant torque and responded more quickly to gusts than the four-cup anemometer.</paragraph><paragraph>The three-cup anemometer was further modified by the Australian Dr Derek Weston in 1991 to measure both wind direction and wind speed. Weston added a tag to one cup, which causes the cupwheel speed to increase and decrease as the tag moves alternately with and against the wind. Wind direction is calculated from these cyclical changes in cupwheel speed, while wind speed is as usual determined from the average cupwheel speed.</paragraph><paragraph>Three-cup anemometers are currently used as the industry standard for<space/><link><target>wind resource assessment</target></link><space/>studies.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Vane anemometers</heading><paragraph>One of the other forms of mechanical velocity anemometer is the<space/><italics>vane anemometer</italics>. It may be described as a<space/><link><target>windmill</target></link><space/>or a propeller anemometer. Contrary to the Robinson anemometer, where the axis of rotation is vertical, the axis on the vane anemometer must be parallel to the direction of the wind and therefore horizontal. Furthermore, since the wind varies in direction and the axis has to follow its changes, a<space/><link><target>weather vane</target><part>wind vane</part></link><space/>or some other contrivance to fulfill the same purpose must be employed.</paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><italics>vane anemometer</italics><space/>thus combines a propeller and a tail on the same axis to obtain accurate and precise wind speed and direction measurements from the same instrument.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WMO"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.eumetcal.org/resources/ukmeteocal/rapid_cyclo/www/english/glossary/vaneanem.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Vane anemometer<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[World Meteorological Organization]]<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Eumetcal<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>April 6, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The speed of the fan is measured by a rev counter and converted to a windspeed by an electronic chip. Hence, volumetric flowrate may be calculated if the cross-sectional area is known.</paragraph><paragraph>In cases where the direction of the air motion is always the same, as in the ventilating shafts of mines and buildings for instance, wind vanes, known as air meters are employed, and give most satisfactory results.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Gallery</target><arg name="title">Vane anemometers
</arg><arg name="align">center
</arg><arg>File:Wind speed and direction instrument - NOAA.jpg</arg><arg>A vane style of anemometer
</arg><arg>File:Prop vane anemometer.jpg</arg><arg>[[Helicoid]] propeller anemometer incorporating a [[wind vane]] for orientation.
</arg><arg>File:Anemometer-IMG 4734-white.jpg</arg><arg>Hand-handled low-speed vane anemometer
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hot-wire anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hd sonde.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Hot-wire sensor</part></link>Hot wire anemometers use a very fine wire (on the order of several micrometres) electrically heated up to some temperature above the ambient. Air flowing past the wire has a cooling effect on the wire. As the electrical resistance of most metals is dependent upon the temperature of the metal (<link><target>tungsten</target></link><space/>is a popular choice for hot-wires), a relationship can be obtained between the resistance of the wire and the flow speed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.efunda.com/designstandards/sensors/hot_wires/hot_wires_intro.cfm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Hot-wire Anemometer explanation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>eFunda<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>September 18, 2006</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20061010125307/http://www.efunda.com/DesignStandards/sensors/hot_wires/hot_wires_intro.cfm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>10 October 2006<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Several ways of implementing this exist, and hot-wire devices can be further classified as CCA (<link><target>constant current</target></link><space/>anemometer), CVA (<link><target>Voltage source</target><part>constant voltage</part></link><space/>anemometer) and CTA (constant-temperature anemometer). The voltage output from these anemometers is thus the result of some sort of circuit within the device trying to maintain the specific variable (current, voltage or temperature) constant, following<space/><link><target>Ohm's law</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Additionally, PWM (<link><target>pulse-width modulation</target></link>) anemometers are also used, wherein the velocity is inferred by the time length of a repeating pulse of current that brings the wire up to a specified resistance and then stops until a threshold &quot;floor&quot; is reached, at which time the pulse is sent again.</paragraph><paragraph>Hot-wire anemometers, while extremely delicate, have extremely high frequency-response and fine spatial resolution compared to other measurement methods, and as such are almost universally employed for the detailed study of turbulent flows, or any flow in which rapid velocity fluctuations are of interest.</paragraph><paragraph>An industrial version of the fine-wire anemometer is the thermal flow meter, which follows the same concept but uses two pins or stings to monitor the variation in temperature. The stings contain fine wires, but encasing the wires makes them much more durable and capable of accurately measuring air, gas, and emissions flow in pipes, ducts, and stacks. Industrial applications often contain dirt that will damage the classic hot-wire anemometer.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Laser anemometer.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>360px</part><part>Drawing of a laser anemometer. The laser light is emitted (1) through the front lens (6) of the anemometer and is backscattered off the air molecules (7). The backscattered radiation (dots) re-enters the device and is reflected and directed into a detector (12).</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Laser Doppler anemometers</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>laser Doppler velocimetry</target></link>, laser Doppler anemometers use a beam of light from a<space/><link><target>laser</target></link><space/>that is divided into two beams, with one propagated out of the anemometer. Particulates (or deliberately introduced seed material) flowing along with air molecules near where the beam exits reflect, or backscatter, the light back into a detector, where it is measured relative to the original laser beam. When the particles are in great motion, they produce a<space/><link><target>Doppler shift</target></link><space/>for measuring wind speed in the laser light, which is used to calculate the speed of the particles, and therefore the air around the anemometer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Iten<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul D.<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 29, 1976<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://patft.uspto.gov/netacgi/nph-Parser?patentnumber</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Laser doppler anemometer<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>United States Patent and Trademark Office<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>September 18, 2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ultrasonic Windsensor.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>2D ultrasonic anemometer with 3 paths</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sonic anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:WindMaster.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>3D ultrasonic anemometer</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Sonic anemometers, first developed in the 1950s, use<space/><link><target>ultrasound</target><part>ultrasonic sound waves</part></link><space/>to measure wind velocity. They measure wind speed based on the time of flight of sonic pulses between pairs of<space/><link><target>transducer</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Measurements from pairs of transducers can be combined to yield a measurement of velocity in 1-, 2-, or 3-dimensional flow. The<space/><link><target>spatial resolution</target></link><space/>is given by the path length between transducers, which is typically 10 to 20<space/><link><target>centimeter</target><part>cm</part></link>. Sonic anemometers can take measurements with very fine<space/><link><target>temporal resolution</target></link>, 20<space/><link><target>hertz</target><part>Hz</part></link><space/>or better, which makes them well suited for<space/><link><target>turbulence</target></link><space/>measurements. The lack of moving parts makes them appropriate for long-term use in exposed automated weather stations and weather buoys where the accuracy and reliability of traditional cup-and-vane anemometers is adversely affected by salty air or large amounts of dust. Their main disadvantage is the distortion of the flow itself by the structure supporting the transducers, which requires a correction based upon wind tunnel measurements to minimize the effect. An international standard for this process,<space/><link><target>ISO 16622</target></link><space/><italics>MeteorologySonic anemometers/thermometersAcceptance test methods for mean wind measurements</italics><space/>is in general circulation. Another disadvantage is lower accuracy due to precipitation, where rain drops may vary the<space/><link><target>speed of sound</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Since the speed of sound varies with temperature, and is virtually stable with pressure change, sonic anemometers are also used as<space/><link><target>thermometers</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Two-dimensional (wind speed and wind direction) sonic anemometers are used in applications such as weather stations, ship navigation, wind turbines, aviation and<space/><link><target>weather buoy</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Three-dimensional sonic anemometers are widely used to measure gas emissions and ecosystem fluxes using the<space/><link><target>eddy covariance</target></link><space/>method when used with fast-response<space/><link><target>infrared gas analyzer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>laser</target></link>-based analyzers.</paragraph><paragraph>There are different technologies solution for Two-dimensional wind sensor.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Two ultrasounds paths</bold>: These sensors have 4 arms. This design is commonly used by wind sensor manufacturers because it's easier to develop compare to the three ultrasounds paths. The disadvantage of this type of sensor is that when the wind comes in the direction of an ultrasound path, the flow around the arms introduces aerodynamic turbulences which perturb the measurements and the sensor will lose accuracy.</listitem><listitem><bold>Three ultrasounds paths</bold>: These sensors have 3 arms. They are developed by some wind sensor manufacturers because they give one path redundancy of the measurement which improves the sensor accuracy and minimizes the aerodynamic turbulences.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Acoustic resonance anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Acoustic Resonance Wind Sensor.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Acoustic resonance anemometer</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Acoustic resonance anemometers are a more recent variant of sonic anemometer. The technology was invented by Dr Savvas Kapartis and patented (Acu-Res) by FT Technologies in 2000.<extension extension_name='ref'>European Patent No. EPO 801311 A and USA Patent No. 5,877,416 (1999)</extension><space/>Whereas conventional sonic anemometers rely on time of flight measurement, acoustic resonance sensors use resonating acoustic (ultrasonic) waves within a small purpose built cavity in order to perform their measurement.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Acoustic Resonance Anemometer.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Acoustic resonance principle</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Built into the cavity is an array of ultrasonic transducers, which are used to create the separate standing-wave patterns at ultrasonic frequencies. As wind passes through the cavity, a change in the waves property occurs (phase shift). By measuring the amount of phase shift in the received signals by each transducer, and then by mathematically processing the data, the sensor is able to provide an accurate horizontal measurement of wind speed and direction.</paragraph><paragraph>Acoustic resonance technology enables measurement within a small cavity, the sensors therefore tend to be typically smaller in size than other ultrasonic sensors. The small size of acoustic resonance anemometers makes them physically strong and very easy to heat and therefore resistant to icing. This combination of features means that they achieve high levels of data availability and are well suited to wind turbine control and to other uses that require small robust sensors such as battlefield meteorology. One issue with this sensor type is measurement accuracy when compared to a calibrated mechanical sensor. For many end uses, this weakness is compensated for by the sensors longevity and the fact that it does not require re-calibrating once installed.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ping-pong ball anemometers</heading><paragraph>A common anemometer for basic use is constructed from a<space/><link><target>ping-pong ball</target></link><space/>attached to a string. When the wind blows horizontally, it presses on and moves the ball; because ping-pong balls are very lightweight, they move easily in light winds. Measuring the angle between the string-ball apparatus and the vertical gives an estimate of the wind speed.</paragraph><paragraph>This type of anemometer is mostly used for middle-school level instruction which most students make themselves, but a similar device was also flown on<space/><link><target>Phoenix Mars Lander#Meteorological station</target><part>Phoenix Mars Lander</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.marslab.dk/TelltaleProject.html'>&quot;The Telltale project.&quot;</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.marslab.dk/TelltaleProject.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20140813041418<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Pressure anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Britannia Yacht Club tour, burgee, and wind gauge.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Britannia Yacht Club</target></link><space/>clubhouse tour, burgee, and wind gauge on roof</part></link>The first designs of anemometers which measure the pressure were divided into plate and tube classes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Plate anemometers</heading><paragraph>These are the modern anemometers and are simply a flat plate suspended from the top so that the wind deflects the plate. In 1450, the Italian art architect Leon Battista Alberti invented the first mechanical anemometer; in 1664 it was re-invented by Robert Hooke (who is often mistakenly considered the inventor of the first anemometer). Later versions of this form consisted of a flat plate, either square or circular, which is kept normal to the wind by a wind vane. The pressure of the wind on its face is balanced by a spring. The compression of the spring determines the actual force which the wind is exerting on the plate, and this is either read off on a suitable gauge, or on a recorder. Instruments of this kind do not respond to light winds, are inaccurate for high wind readings, and are slow at responding to variable winds. Plate anemometers have been used to trigger high wind alarms on bridges.They are used on these high places because they are in a plate shape; has a good measurement status on higher altitudes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tube anemometers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tube anemometer invented by William Henry Dines.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Tube anemometer invented by William Henry Dines. The movable part (right) to be put on top of the fixed part (left).</part></link><link><target>File:Instruments at Mount Washington Observatory.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Instruments at<space/><link><target>Mount Washington Observatory</target></link>. The pitot tube static anemometer is on the right.</part></link><link><target>File:Pitot tube static anemometer.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>The pointy head is the pitot port. The small holes are connected to the static port.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>James Lind's anemometer of 1775 consisted simply of a glass U tube containing a liquid<space/><link><target>manometer</target></link><space/>(pressure gauge), with one end bent in a horizontal direction to face the wind and the other vertical end remains parallel to the wind flow. Though the Lind was not the first it was the most practical and best known anemometer of this type. If the wind blows into the mouth of a tube it causes an increase of pressure on one side of the manometer. The wind over the open end of a vertical tube causes little change in pressure on the other side of the manometer. The resulting liquid change in the U tube is an indication of the wind speed. Small departures from the true direction of the wind causes large variations in the magnitude.</paragraph><paragraph>The highly successful metal pressure tube anemometer of William Henry Dines in 1892 utilized the same pressure difference between the open mouth of a straight tube facing the wind and a ring of small holes in a vertical tube which is closed at the upper end. Both are mounted at the same height. The pressure differences on which the action depends are very small, and special means are required to register them. The recorder consists of a float in a sealed chamber partially filled with water. The pipe from the straight tube is connected to the top of the sealed chamber and the pipe from the small tubes is directed into the bottom inside the float. Since the pressure difference determines the vertical position of the float this is a measured of the wind speed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Anemometer Comparisons</arg><arg name="first">W H<space/></arg><arg name="last">Dines</arg><arg name="journal">Quarterly Journal of the Royal Meteorological Society</arg><arg name="date">1892</arg><arg name="volume">18</arg><arg name="page">168</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 July 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Royal Meteorological Society (Great Britain), James Glaisher</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The great advantage of the tube anemometer lies in the fact that the exposed part can be mounted on a high pole, and requires no oiling or attention for years; and the registering part can be placed in any convenient position. Two connecting tubes are required. It might appear at first sight as though one connection would serve, but the differences in pressure on which these instruments depend are so minute, that the pressure of the air in the room where the recording part is placed has to be considered. Thus if the instrument depends on the pressure or suction effect alone, and this pressure or suction is measured against the air pressure in an ordinary room, in which the doors and windows are carefully closed and a newspaper is then burnt up the chimney, an effect may be produced equal to a wind of 10&amp;nbsp;mi/h (16&amp;nbsp;km/h); and the opening of a window in rough weather, or the opening of a door, may entirely alter the registration.</paragraph><paragraph>While the Dines anemometer had an error of only 1% at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>mi/h</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>it did not respond very well to low winds due to the poor response of the flat plate vane required to turn the head into the wind. In 1918 an aerodynamic vane with eight times the torque of the flat plate overcame this problem.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Pitot tube static anemometers</heading><paragraph>Modern tube anemometers use the same principle as in the Dines anemometer but using a different design. The implementation uses a<space/><link><target>pitot tube</target><part>pitot-static tube</part></link><space/>which is a pitot tube with two ports, pitot and static, that is normally used in measuring the airspeed of aircraft. The pitot port measures the dynamic pressure of the open mouth of a tube with pointy head facing wind, and the static port measures the static pressure from small holes along the side on that tube. The pitot tube is connected to a tail so that it always makes the tube's head to face the wind. Additionally, the tube is heated to prevent<space/><link><target>rime ice</target></link><space/>formation on the tube.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Instrumentation: Pitot Tube Static Anemometer, Part 1</arg><arg name="url">http://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-blogs/clarkb/instrumentation/14828</arg><arg name="publisher">Mt. Washington Observatory</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 July 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>There are two copper lines from the tube down to the devices to measure the difference in pressure of the two lines. The measurement devices can be<space/><link><target>manometer</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>pressure transducer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or analog<space/><link><target>chart recorder</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Instrumentation: Pitot Tube Static Anemometer, Part 2</arg><arg name="url">http://www.accuweather.com/en/weather-blogs/clarkb/instrumentation-1/15065</arg><arg name="publisher">Mt. Washington Observatory</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 July 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Effect of density on measurements</heading><paragraph>In the tube anemometer the pressure is measured, although the scale is usually graduated as a velocity scale. In cases where the density of the air is significantly different from the calibration value (as on a high mountain, or with an exceptionally low barometer) an allowance must be made. Approximately<space/><template><target>frac</target><arg>1</arg><arg>1</arg><arg>2</arg></template>% should be added to the velocity recorded by a tube anemometer for each 1000&amp;nbsp;ft (5% for each kilometer) above sea-level.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Effect of icing</heading><paragraph>At airports, it is essential to have accurate wind data under all conditions, including freezing precipitation. Anemometry is also required in monitoring and controlling the operation of wind turbines, which in cold environments are prone to in-cloud icing. Icing alters the aerodynamics of an anemometer and may entirely block it from operating. Therefore, anemometers used in these applications must be internally heated.<extension extension_name='ref'>Makkonen, L. et al. (2001) Anemometry in icing conditions. Journal of Atmospheric and Oceanic Technology 18:1457-1469</extension><space/>Both cup anemometers and sonic anemometers are nowadays available as a heated version.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Instrument location</heading><paragraph>In order for wind speeds to be comparable from location to location, the effects of the terrain needs to be considered, especially in regard to height. Other considerations are the presence of trees, and both natural canyons and artificial canyons (urban buildings). The standard anemometer height in open rural terrain is 10 meters.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Oke
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tim R.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Initial Guidance to Obtain Representative Meteorological Observations At Urban Sites
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.wmo.int/pages/prog/www/IMOP/publications/IOM-81/IOM-81-UrbanMetObs.pdf
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>February 4, 2013
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>Instruments and Observing Methods
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>81
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>World Meteorological Organization
</arg><arg name="location">
</arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg><arg name="page">
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>19–26
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>3.5 Wind speed and direction
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Nautical</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Air flow meter</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Anemoi</target></link>, for the ancient origin of the name of this technology</listitem><listitem><link><target>Anemoscope</target></link>, ancient device for measuring or predicting wind direction or weather</listitem><listitem><link><target>Automated airport weather station</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Particle image velocimetry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wind power forecasting</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wind run</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="contribution">[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Anemometer|Anemometer]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 9th ed.]], [[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Baynes<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Thomas Spencer<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Charles Scribner's Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="date">1878<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1878}}<space/></arg><arg name="pp">24–26<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Dines<space/></arg><arg name="first">William Henry<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Anemometer|Anemometer]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 11th ed.]], [[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Chisholm<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Hugh<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Phillips<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Walter Alison<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">[[Cambridge, England|Cambridge]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">1911<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1911}}<space/></arg><arg name="pp">2–3</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Meteorological Instruments, W.E. Knowles Middleton and Athelstan F. Spilhaus, Third Edition revised, University of Toronto Press, Toronto, 1953</listitem><listitem>Invention of the Meteorological Instruments, W.E. Knowles Middleton, The Johns Hopkins Press, Baltimore, 1969</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Anemometer</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>anemometer</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.technik.dhbw-ravensburg.de/~lau/ultrasonic-anemometer.html'>Description of the development and the construction of an ultrasonic anemometer</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arm.ac.uk/annrep/annrep2000/node13.html'>Robinson Cup Anemometer</link><space/>- Armagh Observatory</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gill.co.uk/products/anemometer/principleofoperation.htm'>Animation Showing Sonic Principle of Operation (Time of Flight Theory)</link><space/>- Gill Instruments</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.geag.de/txt_sammlung.htm'>Collection of historical anemometer</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fttech.co.uk/acu-res-technology'>Principle of Operation: Acoustic Resonance measurement</link><space/>- FT Technologies</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thermopedia.com/content/558'>Thermopedia, &quot;Anemometers (laser doppler)&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thermopedia.com/content/559'>Thermopedia, &quot;Anemometers (pulsed thermal)&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thermopedia.com/content/560'>Thermopedia, &quot;Anemometers (vane)&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://users.tpg.com.au/derekwtpg/diy_anemometer/theory.pdf'>Rotorvane Anemometer theory</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Meteorological equipment</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Italian inventions</target></link><link><target>Category:Measuring instruments</target></link><link><target>Category:Meteorological instrumentation and equipment</target></link><link><target>Category:Navigational equipment</target></link><link><target>Category:Wind power</target></link></paragraph></article>