<article title='Stab-in-the-back_myth'><paragraph><template><target>Antisemitism</target></template>The<space/><bold>stab-in-the-back myth</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-de</target><arg>Dolchstoßlegende</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>IPA-de</target><arg>ˈdɔlçʃtoːsleˌɡɛndə</arg><arg>pron</arg><arg>De-Dolchstoßlegende.ogg</arg></template>)<extension extension_name='ref'>Despite the similarity of the German word<space/><italics>Legende</italics><space/>and the English word &quot;legend&quot;, &quot;stab-in-the-back<space/><xhtml:u>myth</xhtml:u>&quot; is the<space/><link><target>WP:COMMONNAME</target><part>preferred term</part></link><space/>in English.</extension><space/>was the notion, widely believed in right-wing circles in Germany after 1918, that the German Army did not lose<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>but was instead betrayed by the civilians on the home front, especially the<space/><link><target>German Revolution of 191819</target><part>republicans who overthrew the monarchy</part></link>. Advocates denounced the German government leaders who signed the Armistice on November 11, 1918, as the &quot;<bold>November Criminals</bold>&quot; (<template><target>lang-de</target><arg>Novemberverbrecher</arg></template>).<link><target>File:Stab-in-the-back postcard.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>An illustration from a 1919 Austrian postcard showing a<space/><link><target>caricature</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/><link><target>Jews</target><part>Jew</part></link><space/>stabbing the<space/><link><target>German Army (German Empire)</target><part>German Army</part></link><space/>in the back with a dagger. The capitulation was blamed upon the unpatriotic populace, the<space/><link><target>socialism</target><part>Socialists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bolshevik</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>Weimar Republic</target></link>, and especially the Jews.</part></link>When the Nazis came to power in 1933 they made the legend an integral part of their official history of the 1920s, portraying the<space/><link><target>Weimar Republic</target></link><space/>as the work of the &quot;November criminals&quot; who used the stab in the back to seize power while betraying the nation. The Nazi propaganda depicted Weimar as &quot;a morass of corruption, degeneracy, national humiliation, ruthless persecution of the honest 'national opposition'fourteen years of rule by Jews, Marxists, and 'cultural Bolsheviks', who had at last been swept away by the National Socialist movement under<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target></link><space/>and the victory of the 'national revolution' of 1933&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kolb<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eberhard<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Weimar Republic<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="page">140<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0415344425<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Stab-in-the-back cartoon 1924.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>A 1924<space/><link><target>right-wing</target></link><space/>German political cartoon showing<space/><link><target>Philipp Scheidemann</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Social Democratic Party of Germany</target><part>German Social Democratic</part></link><space/>politician who proclaimed the<space/><link><target>Weimar Republic</target></link><space/>and was its second Chancellor, and<space/><link><target>Matthias Erzberger</target></link>, an anti-war politician from the<space/><link><target>Centre Party (Germany)</target><part>Centre Party</part></link>, who ended WWI by signing the<space/><link><target>Armistice with Germany (Compigne)</target><part>armistice</part></link><space/>with the<space/><link><target>Allies (World War I)</target><part>Allies</part></link>, as stabbing the<space/><link><target>German Army (German Empire)</target><part>German Army</part></link><space/>in the back</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Scholars inside and outside Germany unanimously reject the notion, pointing out the German army was out of reserves and was being overwhelmed in late 1918.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Watson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="title">Enduring the Great War: Combat, Morale and Collapse in the German and British Armies, 1914–1918<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge Military Histories<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="at">ch. 6<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780521881012<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>To many Germans, the expression &quot;stab in the back&quot; was evocative of<space/><link><target>Richard Wagner</target></link>'s 1876 opera<space/><italics><link><target>Gtterdmmerung</target></link></italics>, in which<space/><link><target>Hagen (legend)</target><part>Hagen</part></link><space/>murders his enemy<space/><link><target>Sigurd</target><part>Siegfried</part></link><space/>with a spear in his back.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="authorlink">John Roberts (historian)<space/></arg><arg name="last">Roberts<space/></arg><arg name="first">J. M.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Twentieth Century: The History of the World, 1901 to the Present<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Allen Lane/The Penguin Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="page">289<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-713-99257-3<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1973-076-58, Reichskanzler Cuno und Reichsprsident Ebert crop Ebert only.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part></part><part>''Reichsprsident''<space/><link><target>Friedrich Ebert</target></link>: (1923), as Provisional President of the Weimar Republic in 1919, he contributed to the myth, in telling home-coming veterans that &quot;no enemy has vanquished you&quot;.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the later part of the war, Germany was essentially a<space/><link><target>military dictatorship</target></link>, with the Supreme High Command (German: OHL, &quot;<link><target>Oberste Heeresleitung</target></link>&quot;) and<space/><link><target>Generalfeldmarschall</target><part>General Field Marshal</part></link><space/><link><target>Paul von Hindenburg</target></link><space/>as commander-in-chief advising<space/><link><target>Wilhelm II, German Emperor</target><part>the Kaiser</part></link>. After the<space/><link><target>Spring Offensive</target><part>last German offensive on the Western Front</part></link><space/>failed in 1918, the war effort was doomed. In response, OHL arranged for a rapid change to a civilian government. General<space/><link><target>Erich Ludendorff</target></link>, Germany's Chief of Staff, said:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>I have asked His Excellency to now bring those circles to power which we have to thank for coming so far. We will therefore now bring those gentlemen into the ministries. They can now make the peace which has to be made. They can eat the broth which they have prepared for us!<extension extension_name='ref' name="Siedler Verlag--Verlagsgruppe 2011">Nebelin, Manfred:<space/><italics>Ludendorff: Diktator im Ersten Weltkrieg</italics>, Munich: Siedler VerlagVerlagsgruppe Random House, 2011</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On November 11, 1918, the representatives of the newly formed<space/><link><target>Weimar Republic</target></link><space/>signed<space/><link><target>Armistice with Germany</target><part>an armistice with the Allies</part></link><space/>which would end World War I. The subsequent<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link><space/>led to further territorial and financial losses. As the Kaiser had been forced to abdicate and the military relinquished executive power, it was the temporary &quot;civilian government&quot; that sued for peacethe signature on the armistice document was of<space/><link><target>Matthias Erzberger</target></link>, a civilian, who was later murdered for his alleged treason; this led to the signing of the Treaty of Versailles.</paragraph><paragraph>The official birth of the term &quot;stab-in-the-back&quot; itself possibly can be dated to the autumn of 1919, when Ludendorff was dining with the head of the British Military Mission in Berlin, British general Sir<space/><link><target>Neill Malcolm</target></link>. Malcolm asked Ludendorff why it was that he thought Germany lost the war. Ludendorff replied with his list of excuses, including that the home front failed the army.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Malcolm asked him: &quot;Do you mean, General, that you were stabbed in the back?&quot; Ludendorff's eyes lit up and he leapt upon the phrase like a dog on a bone. &quot;Stabbed in the back?&quot; he repeated. &quot;Yes, that's it, exactly, we were stabbed in the back&quot;. And thus was born a legend which has never entirely perished.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.vqronline.org/articles/1938/spring/wheelerbennett-ludendorff-soldier/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ludendorff: The Soldier and the Politician<space/></arg><arg name="author">Wheeler-Bennett, John W.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Virginia Quarterly Review<space/></arg><arg name="date">Spring 1938<space/></arg><arg name="volume">14<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">187–202</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The phrase was to Ludendorff's liking, and he let it be known among the general staff that this was the &quot;official&quot; version, and so it was disseminated throughout German society. This was picked up by right-wing political factions and used as a form of attack against the SPD-led early Weimar government, which had come to power in the<space/><link><target>German Revolution of 19181919</target><part>German Revolution</part></link><space/>of November 1918.</paragraph><paragraph>The reviews in the German press that grossly misrepresented general<space/><link><target>Frederick Barton Maurice</target></link>'s book,<space/><italics>The Last Four Months</italics>, also contributed to the creation of this myth. &quot;Ludendorff made use of the reviews to convince Hindenburg.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="William L. Shirer 1960 p. 31"><link><target>William L. Shirer</target><part>Shirer, William L.</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Rise and fall of the Third Reich</target></link></italics>, Simon and Schuster (1960) p.31</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg name="In a hearing before the Committee on Inquiry of the National Assembly on November 18, 1919, a year after the war's end, Hindenburg declared, "As an English general has very truly said, the German Army was 'stabbed in the back'."<ref name">"William L. Shirer 1960 p. 31"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1919<space/><link><target>Deutschvlkischer Schutz und Trutzbund</target></link><space/>leader<space/><link><target>Alfred Roth</target></link>, writing under the pseudonym Otto Arnim, published the book<space/><italics>The Jew in the Army</italics><space/>which he said was based on evidence gathered during his participation on the<space/><italics><link><target>Judenzhlung</target></link></italics>, a military census which had in fact shown that German Jews had served in the front lines proportionately to their numbers. Roth's work claimed that most Jews involved in the war were only taking part as profiteers and spies, whilst he also blamed Jewish officers for fostering a defeatist mentality which impacted negatively on their soldiers. As such the book offered one of the earliest published versions of the stab-in-the-back legend.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Levy<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard S.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Antisemitism: A Historical Encyclopedia of Prejudice and Persecution<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="location">Santa Barbara<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO<space/></arg><arg name="pages">623–624<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1851094393</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 1919, the newly elected<space/><link><target>Weimar National Assembly</target></link><space/>initiated a<space/><italics>Untersuchungsausschu fr Schuldfragen</italics><space/>to investigate the causes of the World War and Germany's defeat. On November 18, von Hindenburg testified in front of this parliamentary commission, and cited a December 17, 1918<space/><italics>Neue Zrcher Zeitung</italics><space/>article that summarized two earlier articles in the<space/><italics><link><target>Daily Mail</target></link></italics><space/>by British General<space/><link><target>Frederick Barton Maurice</target></link><space/>with the phrase that the German army had been &quot;dagger-stabbed from behind by the civilian populace&quot; (<italics>von der Zivilbevlkerung von hinten erdolcht</italics>). (Maurice later disavowed having used the term himself.) It was particularly this testimony of Hindenburg that led to the wide spread of the<space/><italics>Dolchstolegende</italics><space/>in post-World War&amp;nbsp;I Germany.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Richard Steigmann-Gall</target></link><space/>says that the stab-in-the-back legend traces back to a sermon preached on February 3, 1918, by Protestant Court Chaplain<space/><link><target>Bruno Doehring</target></link>, six months before the war had even ended.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Steigmann-Gall 2003 16"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="authorlink">Richard Steigmann-Gall<space/></arg><arg name="last">Steigmann-Gall<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Holy Reich: Nazi Conceptions of Christianity, 1919–1945<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="page">16<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0521823714</arg></template></extension><space/>German scholar Boris Barth, in contrast to Steigmann-Gall, implies that Doehring did not actually use the term, but spoke only of 'betrayal'.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Barth<space/></arg><arg name="first">Boris<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dolchstoßlegenden und politische Desintegration: Das Trauma der deutschen Niederlage im Ersten Weltkrieg 1914–1933<space/></arg><arg name="language">de</arg><arg name="location">Düsseldorf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Droste<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="pages">167 and 340f<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">3770016157</arg></template><space/>Barth says Doehring was an army chaplain, not a court chaplain. The following references to Barth are on pages 148 (Mller-Meiningen), and 324 (NZZ article, with a discussion of the Ludendorff-Malcolm conversation).</extension><space/>Barth traces the first documented use to a centrist political meeting in the Munich Lwenbru-Keller on November 2, 1918, in which Ernst Mller-Meiningen, a member of the Progressive coalition in the Reichstag, used the term to exhort his listeners to keep fighting:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>As long as the front holds, we damned well have the duty to hold out in the homeland. We would have to be ashamed of ourselves in front of our children and grandchildren if we attacked the battle front from the rear and gave it a dagger-stab. (<italics>wenn wir der Front in den Rcken fielen und ihr den Dolchsto versetzten.)</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Barth also shows that the term was primarily popularized by the patriotic German newspaper<space/><italics>Deutsche Tageszeitung</italics><space/>that repeatedly quoted the<space/><italics>Neue Zrcher</italics><space/>article after Hindenburg had referred to it in front of the parliamentary inquiry commission.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Siegfrieds Abschied.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>Warrior to War:<space/><link><target>Sigurd</target><part>Siegfried</part></link><space/>departs from Kriemhild. (<link><target>Julius Schnorr von Carolsfeld</target></link>, c.&amp;nbsp;1843). In the<space/><link><target>Epic poetry</target><part>epic poem</part></link><space/>''<link><target>Nibelungenlied</target></link>'' (''Song of the Nibelungs''), Siegfried is infamously stabbed in the back by<space/><link><target>Hagen (legend)</target><part>Hagen</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Charges of a Jewish conspirational element in Germany's defeat drew heavily upon figures like<space/><link><target>Kurt Eisner</target></link>, a Berlin-born German Jew who lived in Munich. He had written about the illegal nature of the war from 1916 onward, and he also had a large hand in the Munich revolution until he was assassinated in February 1919. The Weimar Republic under Friedrich Ebert violently suppressed workers' uprisings with the help of<space/><link><target>Gustav Noske</target></link><space/>and Reichswehr General<space/><link><target>Wilhelm Groener</target><part>Groener</part></link>, and tolerated the<space/><link><target>paramilitary</target></link><space/><link><target>Freikorps</target></link><space/>forming all across Germany. In spite of such tolerance, the Republic's legitimacy was constantly attacked with claims such as the stab-in-the-back. Many of its representatives such as Matthias Erzberger and<space/><link><target>Walther Rathenau</target></link><space/>were assassinated, and the leaders were branded as &quot;criminals&quot; and Jews by the right-wing press dominated by<space/><link><target>Alfred Hugenberg</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The noted German historian<space/><link><target>Friedrich Meinecke</target></link><space/>attempted to trace the roots of the expression in a June 11, 1922 article in the Viennese newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Neue Freie Presse</target></link></italics>. In the 1924 national election, the Munich cultural journal<space/><italics><link><target>Sddeutsche Monatshefte</target></link></italics><space/>published a series of articles blaming the SPD and trade unions for Germany's defeat in World War&amp;nbsp;I, which came out during the trial of<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target></link><space/>and Ludendorff for high treason following the<space/><link><target>Beer Hall Putsch</target></link><space/>in 1923. The editor of an SPD newspaper sued the journal for<space/><link><target>defamation</target></link>, giving rise to what is known as the<space/><italics>Munich Dolchstoprozess</italics><space/>from October 19 to November 20, 1925. Many prominent figures testified in that trial, including members of the parliamentary committee investigating the reasons for the defeat, so some of its results were made public long before the publication of the committee report in 1928.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Dolchsto</italics><space/>was a central image in propaganda produced by the many right-wing and traditionally conservative political parties that sprang up in the early days of the Weimar Republic, including Hitler's<space/><link><target>National Socialist German Workers Party</target><part>NSDAP</part></link>. For Hitler himself, this explanatory model for World War I was of crucial personal importance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brendon8"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="authorlink">Piers Brendon<space/></arg><arg name="last">Brendon<space/></arg><arg name="first">Piers<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Dark Valley: A Panorama of the 1930s<space/></arg><arg name="page">8<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-375-40881-9</arg></template></extension><space/>He had learned of Germany's defeat while being treated for temporary blindness following a gas attack on the front.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brendon8"></extension><space/>In<space/><italics><link><target>Mein Kampf</target></link></italics>, he described a vision at this time which drove him to enter politics. Throughout his career, he railed against the &quot;November criminals&quot; of 1918, who had stabbed the German Army in the back.</paragraph><paragraph>Even provisional President Friedrich Ebert contributed to the myth when he saluted returning veterans with the oration that &quot;no enemy has vanquished you&quot; (<italics>kein Feind hat euch berwunden!</italics>) and &quot;they returned undefeated from the battlefield&quot; (<italics>sie sind vom Schlachtfeld unbesiegt zurckgekehrt</italics>) on November 10, 1918. The latter quote was shortened to<space/><italics>im Felde unbesiegt</italics><space/>(&quot;undefeated on the battlefield&quot;) as a semi-official slogan of the<space/><italics><link><target>Reichswehr</target></link></italics>. Ebert had meant these sayings as a tribute to the German soldier, but it only contributed to the prevailing feeling.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph>The theme of stab-in-the-back was articulated in 1919 most prominently by General<space/><link><target>Erich Ludendorff</target></link>, one of the two top German commanders. He blamed the Berlin government and the civilian population for the armistice/surrender of November 1918, saying they had failed to support him, had let him down, and had proved themselves unworthy of the traditions of a fighting nation. He popularized the<space/><italics>Dolchsto</italics><space/>terminology, and became a prominent right-wing leader in the 1920s.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Fraser<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lindley<space/></arg><arg name="title">Germany Between Two Wars: A Study of Propaganda and War-Guilt<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1945<space/></arg><arg name="page">16<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Post-war reactions and reflections</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:1920 poster 12000 Jewish soldiers KIA for the fatherland.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>325px</part><part>left</part><part>''&quot;12,000 Jewish soldiers died on the field of honor for the fatherland.&quot;'' A leaflet published in 1920 by German Jewish veterans in response to accusations of the lack of patriotism</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Conservatives, nationalists and ex-military leaders began to speak critically about the peace and Weimar politicians, socialists,<space/><link><target>communists</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jew</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and sometimes even Catholics were viewed with suspicion due to presumed extra-national loyalties. It was claimed that they had not supported the war and had played a role in selling out Germany to its enemies. These<space/><italics>November Criminals</italics>, or those who seemed to benefit from the newly formed Weimar Republic, were seen to have &quot;stabbed them in the back&quot; on the<space/><link><target>History of Germany during World War I#Home front</target><part>home front</part></link>, by either criticizing German<space/><link><target>nationalism</target></link>, instigating unrest and strikes in the critical military industries or profiteering. In essence, the accusation was that the accused committed<space/><link><target>treason</target></link><space/>against the &quot;benevolent and righteous&quot; common cause. These theories were given credence by the fact that when Germany surrendered in November 1918, its armies were still in French and Belgian territory, Berlin remained 450 miles from the nearest front, and the German armies retired from the field of battle in good order.</paragraph><paragraph>The Allies had been amply resupplied by the United States, which also had fresh armies ready for combat, but the UK and France were too war-weary to contemplate an invasion of Germany with its unknown consequences.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Frank Herbert Simonds 1919 p. 85"><link><target>Frank Herbert Simonds</target><part>Simonds, Frank Herbert</part></link>,<space/><italics>History of the World War, Volume 2</italics>, Doubleday (1919) p.85</extension><space/>On the<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Front</part></link>, although the<space/><link><target>Hindenburg Line</target></link><space/>had been penetrated and German forces were in retreat, the Allied army had not reached the western German frontier, and on the<space/><link><target>Eastern Front (World War I)</target><part>Eastern Front</part></link>, Germany had already won the war against Russia, concluded with the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Brest-Litovsk</target></link>. In the West, Germany had had successes with the<space/><link><target>Spring Offensive</target></link>. Contributing to the<space/><italics>Dolchstolegende</italics>, its failure was blamed on strikes in the arms industry at a critical moment of the offensive, leaving soldiers without an adequate supply of<space/><link><target>materiel</target></link>. The strikes were seen to be instigated by treasonous elements, with the Jews taking most of the blame.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Steigmann-Gall 2003 16"></extension><space/>This overlooked Germany's strategic position and ignored how the efforts of individuals were somewhat marginalized on the front, since the belligerents were engaged in a new kind of war. The<space/><link><target>industrialization of war</target></link><space/>had dehumanized the process, and made possible a new kind of defeat which the Germans suffered as a<space/><link><target>total war</target></link><space/>emerged.</paragraph><paragraph>The weakness of Germany's strategic position was exacerbated by the rapid collapse of the other Central Powers in late 1918, following Allied victories on the<space/><link><target>Macedonian front</target><part>Macedonian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Italian Campaign (World War I)</target><part>Italian</part></link><space/>fronts. Bulgaria was the first to sign an armistice on September 29, 1918, at<space/><link><target>Saloniki</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="indiana.edu-1918"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.indiana.edu/~league/1918.htm</arg><arg name="title">1918 Timeline</arg></template></extension><space/>On October 30 the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>capitulated at<space/><link><target>Mudros</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="indiana.edu-1918"></extension><space/>On November 3 Austria-Hungary sent a<space/><link><target>White flag</target><part>flag of truce</part></link><space/>to ask for an<space/><link><target>Armistice</target></link>. The terms, arranged by telegraph with the Allied Authorities in Paris, were communicated to the Austrian commander and accepted. The<space/><link><target>Armistice of Villa Giusti</target><part>Armistice with Austria-Hungary</part></link><space/>was signed in the Villa Giusti, near<space/><link><target>Padua</target></link>, on November 3. Austria and Hungary signed separate treaties following the collapse of the Austro-Hungarian empire.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, the idea of domestic betrayal resonated among its audience, and its claims would provide some basis for public support for the emerging<space/><link><target>National Socialist German Workers Party</target><part>National Socialist Party</part></link>, under an autocratic and<space/><link><target>chauvinism</target><part>chauvinistic</part></link><space/>form of<space/><link><target>nationalism</target></link>. Anti-Jewish sentiment was intensified by the<space/><link><target>Bavarian Soviet Republic</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Communist</target></link><space/>government which ruled the city of<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link><space/>for two weeks before being crushed by the<space/><link><target>Freikorps</target></link><space/><link><target>militia</target></link>. Many of the Bavarian Soviet Republic's leaders were Jewish, allowing anti-Jewish propagandists to connect Jews with Communism (and thus treason).</paragraph><paragraph>Richard M. Hunt argues in his 1958 article that the myth was an irrational belief which commanded the force of irrefutable emotional convictions for millions of Germans. He suggests that behind these myths was a sense of communal shame, not for causing the war, but for losing it. Hunt argues that it was not the guilt of wickedness, but the shame of weakness that seized Germany's<space/><link><target>national psychology</target></link>, and &quot;served as a solvent of the Weimar democracy and also as an ideological cement of Hitler's dictatorship&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hunt<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard M.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Myths, Guilt, and Shame in Pre-Nazi Germany<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Virginia Quarterly Review]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1958<space/></arg><arg name="volume">34<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">355–371<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://search.proquest.com/pao/docview/1291786296</arg><arg name="quote">In the last analysis, the deep emotion that gave rise to these myths in pre-Nazi Germany was essentially an overwhelming sense of communal shame. It was not at all a shame related to the responsibility for {{em|causing}} the war. Much more, it was a shame related to the responsibility for {{em|losing}} the war.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Second World War</heading><paragraph>The Allied policy of<space/><link><target>unconditional surrender</target></link><space/>was devised in 1943 in part to avoid a repetition of the stab-in-the-back theme. According to historian<space/><link><target>John Wheeler-Bennett</target></link>, speaking from the British perspective,<extension extension_name='blockquote'>It was necessary for the Nazi rgime and/or the German Generals to surrender unconditionally in order to bring home to the German people that they had lost the War of themselves; so that their defeat should not be attributed to a &quot;stab in the back&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wheeler-Bennett<space/></arg><arg name="first">John W.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Nemesis of Power: The German Army in Politics, 1918–1945<space/></arg><arg name="year">1954<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="page">559<space/></arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Antisemitism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Defeatism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>German Revolution of 191819</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nazism</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><bold>Notes</bold><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Further reading</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Chickering<space/></arg><arg name="first">Rodger<space/></arg><arg name="title">Imperial Germany and the Great War, 1914–1918<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0521547806<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Diest<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wilhelm<space/></arg><arg name="first2">E. J.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Feuchtwanger<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Military Collapse of the German Empire: the Reality Behind the Stab-in-the-Back Myth<space/></arg><arg name="journal">War in History<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="volume">3<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">186–207<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/096834459600300203<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Schivelbusch<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wolfgang<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Culture of Defeat: On National Trauma, Mourning, and Recovery<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Picador<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0312423195<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Watson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stabbed at the Front: After 1918 the Myth Was Created That the German Army Only Lost the War Because It Had Been 'Stabbed in the Back' by Defeatists and Revolutionaries on the Home Front. Reviews the Clear Evidence That in Reality It Simply Lost the Will to Go on Fighting<space/></arg><arg name="journal">History Today<space/></arg><arg name="volume">58<space/></arg><arg name="issue">11<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Stab-in-the-back legend</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ushmm.org/wlc/en/article.php?ModuleId=10005175'>Antisemitism</link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Florida Holocaust Museum</target></link><space/>website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.germanjewishsoldiers.com/introduction.php'>Die Judischen Gefallenen</link><space/>A Roll of Honor Commemorating the 12,000 German Jews Who Died for their Fatherland in World War I.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.history.ucsb.edu/faculty/marcuse/publications/reviews/BarthRev069.htm#ill'>Book review by Harold Marcuse, with 15 &quot;stab-in-the-back&quot; illustrations, 19181942</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DISPLAYTITLE:Stab-in-the-back legend</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Stab-In-The-Back Legend</target></template><link><target>Category:Antisemitic canards</target></link><link><target>Category:Conspiracy theories involving Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:German nationalism</target></link><link><target>Category:German Revolution of 191819</target></link><link><target>Category:Military history of Germany during World War II</target></link><link><target>Category:Propaganda legends</target></link><link><target>Category:Weimar Republic</target></link><link><target>Category:World War I</target></link></paragraph></article>