<article title='Crony_capitalism'><paragraph><template><target>Capitalism</target><arg>Development</arg></template><bold>Crony capitalism</bold><space/>is a term describing an economy in which success in business depends on close relationships between business people and government officials. It may be exhibited by favoritism in the distribution of legal permits, government grants, special<space/><link><target>tax break</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or other forms of<space/><link><target>Economic interventionism</target><part>state interventionism</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cis.org.au/publications/policy-magazine/article/2877-feature-crony-capitalism-and-the-east-asian-currency-and-financial-crises
</arg><arg name="author">Helen Hughes
</arg><arg name="volume">15<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="date">Spring 1999
</arg><arg name="title">Crony Capitalism and the East Asian Currency and Financial 'Crises'
</arg><arg name="magazine">Policy [http://www.cis.org.au/publications/policy-magazine]
</arg><arg name="quote">Japan’s dismal performance in the 1990s and the East Asian collapses of 1997 indicate that [[dirigisme]] can only boost economies in the short run and at high cost. It breaks down in the long run (Lindsey and Lukas 1998).
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-22
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT-20140327"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Kristof<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Nicholas Kristof<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Nation of Takers?<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2014/03/27/opinion/kristof-a-nation-of-takers.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 27, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[New York Times]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">March 27, 2014<space/></arg></template></extension>Crony capitalism is believed to arise when business<space/><link><target>cronyism</target></link><space/>and related<space/><link><target>self-serving</target></link><space/>behavior by businesses or businesspeople spills over into politics and government,<extension extension_name='ref' name="The Discovery that Business Corrupts Politics: A Reappraisal of the Origins of Progressivism, 1981"><italics>The Discovery that Business Corrupts Politics: A Reappraisal of the Origins of Progressivism</italics>, by McCormick, Richard. 1981. The American Historical Review, Vol. 86, No. 2 (Apr., 1981), pp. 247-274.</extension><space/>or when<space/><link><target>self-serving</target></link><space/>friendships and family ties between businessmen and the government influence the economy and society to the extent that it corrupts<space/><link><target>public good</target><part>public-serving</part></link><space/>economic and political ideals.</paragraph><paragraph>The term &quot;crony capitalism&quot; made a significant impact in the public arena as an explanation of the<space/><link><target>Asian financial crisis</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Crony Capitalism: Corruption and Development in South Korea and the Philippines<space/></arg><arg name="first">David C.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kang<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://catdir.loc.gov/catdir/samples/cam031/2001025806.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-00408-4
</arg><arg name="quote">Focused only on explaining successful outcomes, the conventional model provided no analytic way to explain the 1997 crisis. Countries previously regarded as miracles now were nothing more than havens for crony capitalists (p.3)</arg></template></extension><space/>It is also used to describe governmental decisions favoring &quot;cronies&quot; of governmental officials. In this context, the term is often used interchangeably with<space/><link><target>corporate welfare</target></link>; to the extent that there is a difference, it may be the extent to which a government action can be said to benefit individuals rather than entire industries.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In practice</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:World Map Index of perception of corruption.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Transparency International</target></link>'s overview of the index of perception of corruption, 2010</part><part>350px</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Crony capitalism exists along a continuum. In its lightest form, crony capitalism consists of<space/><link><target>collusion</target></link><space/>among market players which is officially tolerated or encouraged by the government. While perhaps lightly competing against each other, they will present a unified front (sometimes called a trade association or<space/><link><target>industry trade group</target></link>) to the government in requesting subsidies or aid or regulation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.theatlantic.com/technology/archive/2012/07/uber-vs-washington-dc-this-is-insane/259614/
</arg><arg name="title">Uber vs. Washington, D.C.: This Is Insane
</arg><arg name="date">July 10, 2012
</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 11, 2012
</arg><arg name="quote">a fight over a new competitor to the District's (often horrible) taxi service offers something I haven't seen in a while. Not routine retail-level corruption, nor skillful top-level favor trading, but instead what appears to be a blatant attempt to legislate favors for one set of interests by hamstringing another.</arg></template></extension><space/>Newcomers to a market may find it difficult to find loans, acquire shelf space, or receive official sanction. Some such systems are very formalized, such as sports leagues and the Medallion System of the<space/><link><target>Taxicabs of New York City</target></link>, but often the process is more subtle, such as expanding training and certification exams to make it more expensive for new entrants to enter a market and thereby limit competition. In technological fields, there may evolve a system whereby new entrants may be accused of infringing on<space/><link><target>patent</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that the established competitors never assert against each other. In spite of this, some competitors may succeed when the legal<space/><link><target>Barriers to entry</target><part>barriers</part></link><space/>are light.</paragraph><paragraph>The term crony capitalism is generally used when these practices come to dominate the economy as a whole or to dominate the most valuable industries in an economy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT-20140327"></extension><space/>Intentionally ambiguous laws and regulations are common in such systems. Taken strictly, such laws would greatly impede practically all business; in practice, they are only erratically enforced. The specter of having such laws suddenly brought down upon a business provides incentive to stay in the good graces of political officials. Troublesome rivals who have overstepped their bounds can have the laws suddenly enforced against them, leading to fines or even jail time. Even in high-income democracies with well-established legal systems and freedom of the press a larger state is associated with more political corruption.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hamilton, Alexander (2013), Small is beautiful, at least in high-income democracies: the distribution of policy-making responsibility, electoral accountability, and incentives for rent extraction<space/><link type='external' href='http://www-wds.worldbank.org/external/default/WDSContentServer/IW3P/IB/2013/01/07/000158349_20130107132037/Rendered/PDF/wps6305.pdf'></link>, World Bank.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The term crony capitalism was initially applied to states involved in the<space/><link><target>1997 Asian Financial Crisis</target></link><space/>such as Thailand and Indonesia. In these cases, the term was used to point out how family members of the ruling leaders become extremely wealthy with no non-political justification.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template><space/>Southeast Asian nations still score very poorly in rankings measuring this.<space/><link><target>Hong Kong</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Vines</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="title">Why Hong Kong’s latest No 1 ranking was greeted with silence</arg><arg name="url">http://www.scmp.com/business/money/wealth/article/1462317/why-hong-kongs-latest-no-1-ranking-was-greeted-silence</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 April 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">South China Morning Post</arg><arg name="date">1 April 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>http://scholarlycommons.law.northwestern.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1213&amp;context=facultyworkingpapers</extension><space/>are perhaps most noted for this, and the term has also been applied to the system of<space/><link><target>Business oligarch</target><part>Oligarchs</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/node/2668298?story_id</arg><arg name="title">Having it both ways<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Economist<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 20, 2004</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="economist.com"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">The countries where politically connected businessmen are most likely to prosper</arg><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/news/international/21599041-countries-where-politically-connected-businessmen-are-most-likely-prosper-planet</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 April 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Economist</arg><arg name="date">15 March 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>Other states to which the term has been applied include<space/><link><target>India</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://pd.cpim.org/2011/0619_pd/06192011_1.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Govt Patronises Crony Capitalism Again</arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 19, 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>11 August 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>in particular, the system after the 1990s liberalization whereby land and other resources were given at throwaway prices in the name of public private partnerships,<space/><link><target>Argentina</target></link>;,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/node/2704437?story_id</arg><arg name="title">Peronism and its perils<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Economist<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 3, 2004</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.conferenceboard.ca/economics/hot_eco_topics/default/12-06-20/the_scourge_of_crony_capitalism.aspx</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Scourge of Crony Capitalism</arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 20, 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>9 October 2013</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Wu Jinglian</target></link>, one of China's leading economists<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/node/2705670?story_id</arg><arg name="title">Keeping an eye on business<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Economist<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 27, 2004</arg></template></extension><space/>and a longtime advocate of its transition to free markets, says that it faces two starkly contrasting futures: a market economy under the rule of law or crony capitalism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.mckinseyquarterly.com/The_road_ahead_for_capitalism_in_China_1782<space/></arg><arg name="title">The road ahead for capitalism in China<space/></arg><arg name="work">The McKinsey Quarterly<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 2006<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wu<space/></arg><arg name="last">Jinglian</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many prosperous nations have also had varying amounts of cronyism throughout their history including the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>- especially in the 1600s and 1700s,<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT-20140327"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/news/international/21599041-countries-where-politically-connected-businessmen-are-most-likely-prosper-planet<space/></arg><arg name="title">Planet Plutocrat: The countries where politically connected businessmen are most likely to prosper<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Economist<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 15, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>and Japan.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Crony Capitalism Index</heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>The Economist</target></link></italics><space/>benchmarks countries based on a &quot;Crony Capitalism Index&quot; calculated via how much economic activity occurs in industries prone to cronyism. Its 2014 Crony Capitalism Index ranking listed<space/><link><target>Hong Kong</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target></link><space/>in the top 3 spots.<extension extension_name='ref' name="economist.com"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In sections of an economy</heading><paragraph><template><target>POV-section</target><arg name="date">November 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>More direct government involvement in a specific sector can also lead to specific areas of crony capitalism, even if the economy as a whole may be competitive. This is most common in natural resource sectors through the granting of mining or drilling concessions, but it is also possible through a process known as<space/><link><target>regulatory capture</target></link><space/>where the government agencies in charge of regulating an industry come to be controlled by that industry. Governments will often, in good faith, establish government agencies to regulate an industry. However, the members of an industry have a very strong interest in the actions of that regulatory body, while the rest of the citizenry are only lightly affected. As a result, it is not uncommon for current industry players to gain control of the &quot;watchdog&quot; and to use it against competitors. This typically takes the form of making it very expensive for a new entrant to enter the market.A<space/><link><target>Gibbons v. Ogden#Background</target><part>1824 landmark U.S. Supreme Court ruling</part></link><space/>overturned a New York State-granted monopoly (&quot;a veritable model of state munificence&quot; facilitated by one of the<space/><link><target>Founding Fathers</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Robert R. Livingston (chancellor)</target><part>Robert R. Livingston</part></link>) for the then-revolutionary technology of<space/><link><target>North River Steamboat</target><part>steamboats</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">T.J.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Styles<space/></arg><arg name="title">The First Tycoon: The Epic Life of [[Cornelius Vanderbilt]]
</arg><arg name="ISBN">978-0-375-41542-5
</arg><arg name="quote">Property requirements for suffrage under New York's constitution of 1777 hardened the culture of rank into law. Two distinct levels of wealth were required to vote, one for state assembly, and a second and higher level for the state senators and governor... [this [[suffrage]] scheme fostered] [[mercantilism]], which in the state empowered private parties to carry out activities thought to serve the public interest. The standard reward for such an undertaking was a [[monopoly]]—just what Chancellor Livingston sought when he offered to meet a most pressing public need, the need for steamboats...Livingston maneuvered...the monopoly through the legislature ("a veritable model of state munificence," as legal scholar Maurice G. Baxter writes—that gave him the right to seize steamboats the entered New York waters from other states. But Livingston had overreached. With so many inventors and investors interested in the steamboat, the monopoly on served to limit its adoption. The new technology was simply too important for the monopoly to remain unchallenged. (pp.39-42)
</arg></template></extension><space/>Leveraging the Supreme Court's establishment of Congressional supremacy over commerce, the<space/><link><target>Interstate Commerce Commission</target></link><space/>was established in 1887 with the intent of regulating railroad &quot;<link><target>robber baron (industrialist)</target><part>robber barons</part></link>&quot;. President<space/><link><target>Grover Cleveland</target></link><space/>appointed<space/><link><target>Thomas M. Cooley</target></link>, a railroad ally, as its first chairman and a permit system was used to deny access to new entrants and legalize<space/><link><target>price fixing</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first">Timothy<space/></arg><arg name="last">Lee<space/></arg><arg name="title">Entangling the Web<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2006/08/03/opinion/03lee.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[The New York Times]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 3, 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">December 13, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The defense industry in the United States is often described as an example of crony capitalism in an industry. Connections with<space/><link><target>United States Department of Defense</target><part>the Pentagon</part></link><space/>and lobbyists in Washington are described by critics as more important than actual competition, due to the political and secretive nature of defense contracts. In the<space/><link><target>Transatlantic relations#Boeing and Airbus subsidies</target><part>Airbus-Boeing WTO dispute</part></link>, Airbus (which receives outright<space/><link><target>subsidy</target><part>subsidies</part></link><space/>from European governments) has stated Boeing receives similar subsidies, which are hidden as inefficient defense contracts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Pulling Boeing Out of a Tailspin<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.businessweek.com/magazine/content/03_50/b3862121_mz029.htm<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Business Week]]<space/></arg><arg name="quote">A national treasure, once No. 1 in commercial aviation, Boeing has become a risk-averse company stumbling to compete in the marketplace and dependent on political connections and chicanery to get government contracts. Boeing needs a strong board and a rejuvenated corporate culture based on innovation and competitiveness, not crony capitalism.<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 15, 2003<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">December 13, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Other American defense companies were put under scrutiny for no-bid contracts for<space/><link><target>Iraq war</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hurricane Katrina</target></link><space/>related contracts purportedly due to having cronies in the Bush administration.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last">Dreier<space/></arg><arg name="title">Katrina and Power in America<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://scholar.oxy.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article</arg><arg name="quote">Three companies—the Shaw Group, [[Kellogg Brown & Root]] (KBR, a subsidiary of Haliburton, whose former CEO is Vice President [[Dick Cheney]]), and Boh Brothers Construction of New Orleans—quickly scooped up no-bid ACE contracts to perform the restoration. [[Bechtel]] and [[Fluor Corporation|Fluor]] (also with close GOP ties) also reaped huge contracts. The Department of Defense has been criticized for awarding Iraq reconstruction contracts to Haliburton and Bechtel without competition (Broder 2005)
</arg><arg name="work">[[Occidental College]]
</arg><arg name="date">3-1-2006
</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 22, 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gerald P. O'Driscoll, former vice president at the<space/><link><target>Federal Reserve Bank of Dallas</target></link>, stated that<space/><link><target>Fannie Mae</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Freddie Mac</target></link><space/>became examples of crony capitalism. Government backing let Fannie and Freddie dominate<space/><link><target>mortgage underwriting</target></link>. &quot;The politicians created the mortgage giants, which then returned some of the profits to the pols - sometimes directly, as campaign funds; sometimes as &quot;contributions&quot; to favored constituents.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nypost.com/seven/09092008/postopinion/opedcolumnists/fannie_freddie_bailout_baloney_128135.htm<space/></arg><arg name="work">New York Post<space/></arg><arg name="title">Fannie/Freddie Bailout Baloney<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gerald P.<space/></arg><arg name="last">O'Driscoll Jr<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 9, 2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Creation of crony capitalism in developing economies</heading><paragraph>In its worst form, crony capitalism can devolve into simple<space/><link><target>Political corruption</target><part>corruption</part></link>, where any pretense of a free market is dispensed with. Bribes to government officials are considered<space/><italics>de rigueur</italics><space/>and<space/><link><target>tax evasion</target></link><space/>is common; this is seen in many parts of Africa, for instance. This is sometimes called<space/><link><target>plutocracy</target></link><space/>(rule by wealth) or<space/><link><target>kleptocracy</target></link><space/>(rule by theft).</paragraph><paragraph>Corrupt governments may favor one set of business owners who have close ties to the government over others. This may also be done with racial, religious, or ethnic favoritism; for instance,<space/><link><target>Alawites</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Syria</target></link><space/>have a disproportionate share of power in the government and business there. (<link><target>Bashar al-Assad</target><part>President Assad</part></link><space/>is an Alawite.)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2011/05/01/world/asia/01makhlouf.html?_r=1&amp;amp;hp'>Syrian Businessman Becomes Magnet for Anger and Dissent</link><space/>&quot;Like Mr. Ezz in Egypt, he has become a symbol of how economic reforms turned crony socialism into crony capitalism, making the poor poorer and the connected rich fantastically wealthier.&quot;</extension><space/>This can be explained by considering personal relationships as a<space/><link><target>social network</target></link>. As government and business leaders try to accomplish various things, they naturally turn to other powerful people for support in their endeavors. These people form hubs in the network. In a developing country those hubs may be very few, thus concentrating economic and political power in a small interlocking group.</paragraph><paragraph>Normally, this will be untenable to maintain in business; new entrants will affect the market. However, if business and government are entwined, then the government can maintain the small-hub network.</paragraph><paragraph>Raymond Vernon, specialist in economics and international affairs,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.news.harvard.edu/gazette/1999/09.23/vernon.html
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Raymond Vernon Dies at 85<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>September 23, 1999
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>The Harvard University Gazette
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>President and Fellows of Harvard College
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>February 9, 2013<space/></arg></template></extension>wrote that the<space/><link><target>Industrial Revolution</target></link><space/>began in<space/><link><target>Great Britain</target></link>, because they were the first to successfully limit the power of veto groups (typically cronies of those with power in government) to block innovations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vernon (1989)</extension><space/>&quot;Unlike most other national environments, the British environment of the early 19th century contained relatively few threats to those who improved and applied existing inventions, whether from business competitors, labor, or the government itself. In other European countries, by contrast, the merchant guilds ... were a pervasive source of veto for many centuries. This power was typically bestowed upon them by government&quot;. For example, a Russian inventor produced a steam engine in 1766 and disappeared without a trace.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template><space/>&quot;[A] steam powered horseless carriage produced in France in 1769 was officially suppressed.&quot;<space/><link><target>James Watt</target></link><space/>began experimenting with steam in 1763, got a patent in 1769, and began commercial production in 1775.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vernon (1989, p. 8); see also<space/><link><target>Watt steam engine</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>James Watt#Patents</target><part>James Watt</part></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Raghuram Rajan</target></link>, governor of the<space/><link><target>Reserve Bank of India</target></link>, has said &quot;One of the greatest dangers to the growth of developing countries is the middle income trap, where crony capitalism creates oligarchies that slow down growth. If the debate during the elections is any pointer, this is a very real concern of the public in India today.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Crony capitalism a big threat to countries like India, RBI chief Raghuram Rajan says</arg><arg name="url">http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/business/india-business/Crony-capitalism-a-big-threat-to-countries-like-India-RBI-chief-Raghuram-Rajan-says/articleshow/40076743.cms</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 November 2014</arg><arg name="work">Times of India</arg><arg name="date">12 August 2014</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Tavleen Singh</target></link>, columnist for<space/><italics><link><target>The Indian Express</target></link></italics><space/>has disagreed. According to her, India's corporate success is not a product of crony capitalism, but because India is no longer under the influence of crony socialism.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://archive.indianexpress.com/news/no-crony-capitalism-in-india/821341/</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political viewpoints</heading><paragraph>While the problem is generally accepted across the political spectrum, ideology shades the view of the problem's causes and therefore its solutions. Political views mostly fall into two camps which might be called the socialist and capitalist critique. The socialist position is that broadly democratic government must regulate economic, or wealthy, interests in order to restrict monopoly. The capitalist position is that &quot;<link><target>natural monopolies</target></link>&quot; are rare, therefore governmental regulations generally abet established wealthy interests by restricting competition.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://gothamist.com/2014/11/29/uber_driving_down_price_of_taxi_med.php</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Socialist critique</heading><paragraph>Critics of capitalism including<space/><link><target>socialism</target><part>socialists</part></link><space/>and other<space/><link><target>anti-capitalism</target><part>anti-capitalists</part></link><space/>often assert that crony capitalism is the inevitable result of<space/><italics>any</italics><space/>capitalist system.<space/><link><target>Jane Jacobs</target></link><space/>described it as a natural consequence of collusion between those managing<space/><link><target>power (sociology)</target><part>power</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>trade</target></link>, while<space/><link><target>Noam Chomsky</target></link><space/>has argued that the word &quot;crony&quot; is superfluous when describing capitalism.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.chomsky.info/interviews/20081114.htm'>&quot;Black Faces in Limousines:&quot; A Conversation with Noam Chomsky</link><space/>from Chomsky.info accessed on June 5, 2009</extension><space/>Since businesses make money and money leads to political power, business will inevitably use their power to influence governments. Much of the impetus behind<space/><link><target>campaign finance reform in the United States</target></link><space/>and in other countries is an attempt to prevent economic power being used to take political power.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Ravi Batra</target></link><space/>argues that &quot;all official economic measures adopted since 1981...have devastated the middle class&quot; and that the<space/><link><target>Occupy Wall Street</target></link><space/>movement should push for their repeal and thus end the influence of the super wealthy in the political process, which he considers a manifestation of crony capitalism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.truth-out.org/occupy-wall-street-movement-and-coming-demise-crony-capitalism/1318341474<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Occupy Wall Street Movement and the Coming Demise of Crony Capitalism<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ravi<space/></arg><arg name="last">Batra<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Truthout]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 October 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 October 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Socialist economists, such as<space/><link><target>Robin Hahnel</target></link>, have criticized the term as an ideologically motivated attempt to cast what is in their view the fundamental problems of capitalism as avoidable irregularities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Let's Review<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bradley.edu/campusorg/bpn/znet/april08.txt<space/></arg><arg name="author">[[Robin Hahnel]]<space/></arg><arg name="quote">IMF officials Michel Camdessus and Stanley Fischer were quick to explain that the afflicted economies had only themselves to blame. Crony capitalism, lack of transparency, accounting procedures not up to international standards, and weak-kneed politicians too quick to spend and too afraid to tax were the problems according to IMF and US Treasury Department officials. The fact that the afflicted economies had been held up as paragons of virtue and IMF/World Bank success stories only a year before, the fact that neoliberalism’s only success story had been the Newly Industrialized Countries (NIC's) who were now in the tank, and the fact that the IMF and Treasury department story just didn’t fit the facts since the afflicted economies were no more rife with crony capitalism, lack of transparency, and weak-willed politicians than dozens of other economies untouched by the Asian financial crisis, simply did not matter.</arg></template></extension><space/>Socialist economists dismiss the term as an apologetic for failures of neoliberal policy and, more fundamentally, their perception of the weaknesses of market allocation.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Capitalist critique</heading><paragraph>Supporters of capitalism generally oppose crony capitalism as well, but consider it an aberration brought on by governmental favors incompatible with 'true'<space/><link><target>free market</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Crony Capitalism Comes Home</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/27/opinion/kristof-crony-capitalism-comes-homes.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">Nov 27, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">some financiers have chosen to live in a government-backed featherbed. Their platform seems to be socialism for tycoons and capitalism for the rest of us...featherbedding by both unions and tycoons...are impediments to a well-functioning market economy.</arg><arg name="author">Nicholas D. Kristof</arg><arg name="date">Oct 26, 2011</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Let's Take the "Crony" Out of "Crony Capitalism"</arg><arg name="url">http://www.creators.com/opinion/john-stossel/let-s-take-the-crony-out-of-crony-capitalism.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">Nov 26, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">The truth is that we don't have a free market — government regulation and management are pervasive — so it's misleading to say that "capitalism" caused today's problems. The free market is innocent. But it's fair to say that crony capitalism created the economic mess.</arg><arg name="author">[[John Stossel]]</arg><arg name="date">2010 (copyright)</arg></template></extension><space/>In this view, crony capitalism is the result of an excess of socialist-style interference in the market, which inherently will result in a toxic combination of corporations and government officials running the sector of the economy. Some advocates prefer to equate this problem with terms such as &quot;<link><target>Corporatism#Corporatism in politics and political economy</target><part>corporatism</part></link>, a modern form of<space/><link><target>mercantilism</target></link>&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">There's No Such Thing as "Crony Capitalism"</arg><arg name="url">http://www.dev.creators.com/conservative/ben-shapiro/there-s-no-such-thing-as-quot-crony-capitalism-quot.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">Nov 26, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">This "crony capitalism," [[Sarah Palin]] said, is "not the capitalism of free men and free markets." In general, she's right. But...her terminology...is dead wrong. The fact is that there is no such thing as "crony capitalism." In reality, it is [[corporatism]], a modern form of [[mercantilism]]. Corporatism is based on the notion that industries comprise the economy like body parts comprise the body — they must work in concert with one another, and they must take central direction.</arg><arg name="author">[[Ben Shapiro]]</arg><arg name="date">2011 (copyright)</arg></template></extension><space/>to emphasize that the only way to run a profitable business in such a system is to have help from corrupt government officials. Even if the initial regulation was well-intentioned (to curb actual abuses), and even if the initial lobbying by corporations was well-intentioned (to reduce illogical regulations), the mixture of business and government stifle competition,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Let's Take the "Crony" Out of "Crony Capitalism"</arg><arg name="url">http://www.creators.com/opinion/john-stossel/let-s-take-the-crony-out-of-crony-capitalism.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">Nov 26, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">Which are more likely to be hampered by vigorous regulatory standards: entrenched corporations with their overstaffed legal and accounting departments or small startups trying to get off the ground? Regulation can kill competition — and incumbents like it that way.</arg><arg name="author">[[John Stossel]]</arg><arg name="date">2010 (copyright)</arg></template></extension><space/>a collusive result called<space/><link><target>regulatory capture</target></link>. In his book<space/><italics>The Myth of the Robber Barons</italics>,<space/><link><target>Burton W. Folsom, Jr.</target></link><space/>distinguished those that engage in crony capitalismdesignated by him &quot;political entrepreneurs&quot;from those who compete in the marketplace without special aid from government, whom he calls &quot;market entrepreneurs&quot; who succeed &quot;by producing a quality product at a competitive price&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Myth of the Robber Barons</arg><arg name="url">http://www.burtfolsom.com/?page_id</arg><arg name="accessdate">Nov 28, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">The author, Burton Folsom, divides the entrepreneurs into two groups: market entrepreneurs and political entrepreneurs. The market entrepreneurs, such as Hill, Vanderbilt, and Rockefeller, succeeded by producing a quality product at a competitive price. The political entrepreneurs, for example, [[Edward Knight Collins|Edward Collins]] in steamships and the leaders of the [[Union Pacific Railroad]] in railroads, were men who used the power of government to succeed. They tried to gain subsidies or in some way use government to stop competitors.</arg><arg name="author">[[Burton W. Folsom, Jr.]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>cmn</target><arg>3</arg><arg>
* [[Capitalism]]
* [[Corporatocracy]]
* [[Corporate welfare]]
* [[Corporatism]]
* [[Crony-capitalism index]]
* [[Economic interventionism]]
* [[Government failure]]
* [[Government-owned corporation]]
* [[Inverted totalitarianism]]
* [[Iron triangle (US politics)]]
* [[Mercantilism]]
* [[Mixed economy]]
* [[Patrimonialism]]
* [[Political family]]
* [[Political machine]]
* [[Regulatory Capture]]
* [[Rent-seeking]]
* [[Stamocap]]
* [[Supercapitalism (concept in Italian Fascism)|Supercapitalism]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Vernon
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Raymond
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Technological Development
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>EDI Seminar Paper
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>39
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0821311622
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">15–45<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/1468-2362.00064<space/></arg><arg name="title">Domestic Crony Capitalism and International Fickle Capital: Is There a Connection?<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Wei<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Shang-Jin<space/></arg><arg name="journal">International Finance<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="jstor">4150189<space/></arg><arg name="pages">439–58<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Kang<space/></arg><arg name="first1">David C.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Transaction Costs and Crony Capitalism in East Asia<space/></arg><arg name="volume">35<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Comparative Politics<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/4150189</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">167–77<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s10551-007-9385-5<space/></arg><arg name="title">Corporate Social Responsibility and Crony Capitalism in Taiwan<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Ip<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Po-Keung<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Business Ethics<space/></arg><arg name="volume">79</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">81–105<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1353/lar.2004.0050<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">1555469<space/></arg><arg name="title">Propaganda and Crony Capitalism: Partisan Bias in Mexican Television News<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Hughes<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Sallie<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Lawson<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Chappell H.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Latin American Research Review<space/></arg><arg name="volume">39<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Shah</arg><arg name="first">Ajay</arg><arg name="title">Indian capitalism is not doomed</arg><arg name="url">http://ajayshahblog.blogspot.in/2012/09/indian-capitalism-is-not-doomed.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Ajay Shah's Blog</arg><arg name="date">7 September 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">220–33<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8683.2006.00504.x<space/></arg><arg name="title">Corporate Governance, Crony Capitalism and Economic Crises: Should the US business model replace the Asian way of 'doing business'?<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Singh<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Ajit<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Zammit<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Ann<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Corporate Governance: an International Review<space/></arg><arg name="volume">14<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">653–61<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/cje/22.6.653<space/></arg><arg name="title">Economic crisis in East Asia: The clash of capitalisms<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Johnson<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Chalmers<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Cambridge Journal of Economics<space/></arg><arg name="volume">22<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="jstor">4380313<space/></arg><arg name="pages">73–91<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Peev<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Evgeni<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ownership and Control Structures in Transition to 'Crony' Capitalism: The Case of Bulgaria<space/></arg><arg name="volume">40<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Eastern European Economics<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://mesharpe.metapress.com/openurl.asp?genre</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">117–32<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1057/palgrave.abm.9200126<space/></arg><arg name="title">What's Bad About Crony Capitalism?<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Enderwick<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Asian Business &#38; Management<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">175–91<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1540-5907.2006.00177.x<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">3694264<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bagehot or Bailout? An Analysis of Government Responses to Banking Crises<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Rosas<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Guillermo<space/></arg><arg name="journal">American Journal of Political Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume">50</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">47–66<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/0725513602069001004<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Problem of 'Crony Capitalism': Modernity and the Encounter with the Perverse<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Kahn<space/></arg><arg name="first1">J. S.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Formosa<space/></arg><arg name="first2">F.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Thesis Eleven<space/></arg><arg name="volume">69</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">34–40<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1525/ctx.2003.2.3.34<space/></arg><arg name="title">American cronyism: How executive networks inflated the corporate bubble<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Davis<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Gerald F.<space/></arg><arg name="author-link">Gerald F. Davis</arg><arg name="journal">[[Contexts]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">2<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">77–99<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s11079-005-5333-0<space/></arg><arg name="title">Crony Capitalism and Sovereign Default<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Vaugirard<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Victor<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Open Economies Review<space/></arg><arg name="volume">16</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.2202/1932-0213.1031<space/></arg><arg name="title">Family Values or Crony Capitalism?<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="last1">James<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Harold<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Capitalism and Society<space/></arg><arg name="volume">3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="pages">61–75<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1057/palgrave.jibs.8400171<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">3875215<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cronyism: A cross-cultural analysis<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Khatri<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Naresh<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Tsang<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Eric W K<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Begley<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Thomas M<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of International Business Studies<space/></arg><arg name="volume">37</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Khatri, Naresh (2013). Anatomy of Indian Brand of Crony Capitalism. http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2335201.</listitem><listitem>http://mpra.ub.uni-muenchen.de/19626/1/WP0802.pdf</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/21/weekinreview/21SANG.html?todaysheadlines'>New York Times, &quot;The Global Cost of Crony Capitalism&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2002/07/30/international/europe/30VLAD.html?todaysheadlines'>New York Times, &quot;Vladivostok Journal: Out of Russia's Gangland, and Into Cafe Society.&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.project-syndicate.org/commentary/stiglitz11/English'>Joseph Stiglitz, &quot;Crony capitalism American-style&quot;.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mises.org/story/872'>William Anderson, The Mises Institute, &quot;Myths About Enron&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.caip.cl//index.php?option=com_remository&amp;amp;Itemid=54&amp;amp;func=fileinfo&amp;amp;id=26'>Crony capitalism: The actors of change towards neoliberalism in Chile, by Patricio Imbert and Patricio Morales</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://uchicagolaw.typepad.com/beckerposner/2010/06/will-africa-finally-take-off-becker.html'>Will Africa Finally Take Off? Becker</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cronychronicles.org/'>Crony Chronicles - The Cronyism Resource</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Crony Capitalism</target></template><link><target>Category:Capitalism</target></link><link><target>Category:Political corruption</target></link><link><target>Category:Political terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Public choice theory</target></link><link><target>Category:Economic problems</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>de:Gnstlingskapitalismus</target></link></paragraph></article>