<article title='Call_centre'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the contact centres in family law</arg><arg>children's centre</arg></template><template><target>E-commerce</target></template><link><target>File:Police contact centre 1970.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A 1970 police call centre in<space/><link><target>Brierley Hill</target></link>, England</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>call centre</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>call center</bold><space/>is a centralised office used for receiving or transmitting a large volume of requests by<space/><link><target>telephone</target></link>. An inbound call centre is operated by a<space/><link><target>company</target></link><space/>to administer incoming product support or information inquiries from consumers. Outbound call centers are operated for<space/><link><target>telemarketing</target></link>, solicitation of charitable or political donations, debt collection and<space/><link><target>market research</target></link>. A<space/><bold>contact centre</bold><space/>is a location for centralised handling of individual communications, including<space/><link><target>Letter (message)</target><part>letter</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>fax</target><trail>es</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>live support software</target></link>,<space/><link><target>social media</target></link>,<space/><link><target>instant message</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>e-mail</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EWA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ewa-ltd.blogspot.com/2010/03/contact-centre-vs-communication-centre.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Contact Centre vs Communication Centre vs Call Centre</arg><arg name="publisher">EWA Bespoke Communications</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A call centre has an open workspace for<space/><link><target>Customer representative</target><part>call centre agents</part></link>, with work stations that include a computer for each agent, a<space/><link><target>telephone</target></link><space/>set/<link><target>Headphones</target><part>headset</part></link><space/>connected to a<space/><link><target>telecom switch</target></link>, and one or more supervisor stations. It can be independently operated or networked with additional centres, often linked to a corporate<space/><link><target>computer network</target></link>, including<space/><link><target>Mainframe computer</target><part>mainframes</part></link>,<space/><link><target>microcomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>local area network</target><part>LANs</part></link>. Increasingly, the voice and data pathways into the centre are linked through a set of new technologies called<space/><link><target>computer telephony integration</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The contact centre is a central point from which all customer contacts are managed. Through contact centres, valuable information about company are routed to appropriate people, contacts to be tracked and data to be gathered. It is generally a part of companys<space/><link><target>customer relationship management</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A contact centre can be defined as a coordinated system of people, processes, technologies and strategies that provides access to information, resources, and expertise, through appropriate channels of communication, enabling interactions that create value for the customer and organization.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Brad Cleveland</target><part>Cleveland, Brad</part></link>, &quot;Call Center Management on Fast Forward (Third Edition)&quot;,<space/><italics>ICMI Press</italics>, 2012</extension><space/>Contact centres, along with call centres and<space/><link><target>communication</target></link><space/>centres all fall under a larger umbrella labelled as the contact centre management industry. This is becoming a rapidly growing recruitment sector in itself, as the capabilities of contact centres expand and thus require ever more complex systems and highly skilled operational and management staff.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cactus Search"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cactussearch.co.uk/content/clients/roles-we-recruit<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cactus Search - List of Call Centre Management Roles We Recruit</arg><arg name="publisher">Cactus Search</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The majority of large companies use contact centres as a means of managing their customer interaction. These centres can be operated by either an in house department responsible or outsourcing customer interaction to a third party agency (known as Outsourcing Call Centres).</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>expand section</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template>The earliest call centers were created during the 1960s, and were known as &quot;Private Automated Business Exchanges&quot; (PABX). The earliest example of a call centre was in the UK is at the Birmingham Press and Mail.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Science and invention in Birmingham#cite note-45</target></link></extension><space/>They had a GEC PABX 4 ACD, installed in 1965.</paragraph><paragraph>The coining of the term &quot;call center&quot; is more recent, with the first published use of the term in 1983.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.callcentrehelper.com/the-history-of-the-call-centre-15085.htm</arg><arg name="title">The history of the call centre</arg><arg name="publisher">Call Centre Helper Magazine</arg><arg name="date">19 Jan 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 Nov 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Technology</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Call centre desk lakeland florida.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Call centre desk environment in<space/><link><target>Lakeland, Florida</target></link>, United States (2005)</part></link>Call centre technologies include<space/><link><target>speech recognition</target></link><space/>software to allow computers to handle first level of<space/><link><target>customer support</target></link>,<space/><link><target>text mining</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>natural language processing</target></link><space/>to allow better customer handling, agent training by automatic mining of<space/><link><target>best practices</target></link><space/>from past interactions,<space/><link><target>support automation</target></link><space/>and many other technologies to improve agent productivity and<space/><link><target>customer satisfaction</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://lvs004.googlepages.com/callcenters.pdf</arg><arg name="author">L Venkata Subramaniam</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="title">Call Centers of the Future</arg><arg name="publisher">i.t. magazine</arg><arg name="date">2008-02-01</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-05-29</arg><arg name="pages">48–51</arg></template></extension><space/>Automatic lead selection or lead steering is also intended to improve efficiencies,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.patentstorm.us/patents/7035699/description.html</arg><arg name="title">US Patent 7035699 - Qualified and targeted lead selection and delivery system</arg><arg name="date">2006-04-25</arg><arg name="publisher">Patent Storm</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-05-29</arg></template></extension><space/>both for inbound and outbound campaigns. This allows inbound calls to be directly routed to the appropriate agent for the task, whilst minimizing wait times and long lists of irrelevant options for people calling in. For outbound calls, lead selection allows management to designate what type of leads go to which agent based on factors including skill, socioeconomic factors and past performance and percentage likelihood of closing a sale per lead.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>universal queue</target></link><space/>standardizes the processing of communications across multiple technologies such as fax, phone, and email. The<space/><link><target>virtual queue</target></link><space/>provides callers with an alternative to waiting on hold when no agents are available to handle inbound call demand.<link><target>File:Aspect Tel-set telephone call centre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A typical call centre telephone. Note: no handset, phone is for headset use only (2005)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Premises-based technology</heading><paragraph>Historically, call centres have been built on<space/><link><target>Private branch exchange</target></link><space/>(PBX) equipment that is owned, hosted, and maintained by the call centre operator themselves. The PBX can provide functions such as<space/><link><target>automatic call distribution</target></link>,<space/><link><target>interactive voice response</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>skills-based routing</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Virtual call centre</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Software as a service</arg><arg>Telecommuting</arg></template>In virtual call centre model, the call centre's<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Future of Cloud-based Call Center Market – $10.9 Billion by 2019</arg><arg name="url">http://www.fonebell.in/the-future-of-cloud-based-call-center-market-10-9-billion-by-2019/</arg><arg name="publisher">By Fonebell</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 January 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>operator pays a monthly or annual fee to a vendor that hosts the call centre telephony equipment in their own data centre. In this model, the operator does not own, operate or host the equipment that the call centre runs on. Agents connect to the vendor's equipment through traditional<space/><link><target>PSTN</target></link><space/>telephone lines, or over<space/><link><target>voice over IP</target></link>. Calls to and from prospects or contacts originate from or terminate at the vendor's data centre, rather than at the call centre operator's premises. The vendor's telephony equipment then connects the calls to the call centre operator's agents.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.springerlink.com/content/kapq5p85xnhrwe5b/</arg><arg name="author">M. Popovic and V. Kovacevic</arg><arg name="title">An Approach to Internet-Based Virtual Call Center Implementation</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Novi Sad, Yugoslavia</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Virtual call centre technology allows people to work from home, instead of in a traditional, centralised, call centre location, which increasingly allows people with physical or other disabilities that prevent them from leaving the house, to work. The only thing that is mandatory is to have an Internet access and a workstation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nticentral.org/about/articles/nnyt03012006.shtm</arg><arg name="author">David S. Joachim</arg><arg name="title">Computer Technology Opens a World of Work to Disabled People<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Times</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cloud computing</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Cloud computing</arg></template><template><target>Technical</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template>Cloud computing for call centres extends cloud computing to<space/><link><target>software as a service</target></link>, or hosted, on-demand call centres by providing<space/><link><target>application programming interface</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(APIs) on the call centre cloud computing platform that allow call centre functionality to be integrated with cloud-based<space/><link><target>customer relationship management</target></link>, leads management, and other applications.<space/><link><target>Computer telephony integration</target></link><space/>APIs provide developers with access to basic telephony controls and sophisticated call handling on the call centre platform from a separate application. Configuration APIs provide programmatic control of administrative functions of the call centre platform which are typically accessed by a human administrator through a<space/><link><target>graphical user interface</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Description</heading><heading level='3'>Services</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:callcentre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A very large call centre in Lakeland, Florida (2006)</part></link>Contact centers run support or help desks, which regularly answers technical questions from customers and assists them using their equipment or software. Support desks are used by companies in the computing,<space/><link><target>telecommunications</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>consumer electronics</target></link><space/>industries.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Customer service</target></link><space/>contact centres answer specific queries relating to customer issues, in the banking and utility sectors these are frequently used to answer customer questions relating to their account or payments, this type of service may even be used to respond to customer complaints and undertake retention strategies for unsatisfied customers.</paragraph><paragraph>Contact centres also carry out sales and<space/><link><target>marketing</target></link><space/>activities; these can be performed through<space/><link><target>cold calling</target></link><space/>strategies and increasingly through live chat applications on company websites.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Dynamics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Callcentreterminal.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Call centre worker confined to a small workstation/booth, using<space/><link><target>CallWeb</target></link><space/>Internet-based survey software</part></link>A contact centre supports interaction with customers over a variety of media, including<space/><link><target>telephony</target></link>,<space/><link><target>e-mail</target></link>, and internet<space/><link><target>Online chat</target><part>chat</part></link>. A telephone answering service is a more personalised version of the call centre, where agents get to know more about their customers and their callers; and therefore look after calls just as if based in their customers' office.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="author">Raik Stolletz</arg><arg name="title">Performance Analysis and Optimization of Inbound Call Centers</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer-Verlag</arg><arg name="isbn">978-3-540-00812-5</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Calls may be<space/><italics>inbound</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>outbound</italics>. Inbound calls are made by consumers, for example to obtain information, report a malfunction, or ask for help. In contrast, outbound calls are made by agents to consumers, usually for sales purposes (<link><target>telemarketing</target></link>). A &quot;blended&quot; center combines both inbound and outbound campaigns where each type of agent (inbound or outbound) can handle the overflow of the other.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa3700/is_199611/ai_n8743570</arg><arg name="title">Setting up for integrated inbound/outbound telemarketing</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BNET]]</arg><arg name="author">Freeman, Laura M</arg><arg name="author2">Whitfield, Hilary C</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Call centre staff are often organised into a multi-tier support system for more efficient handling of calls. The first tier consists of operators, who initially answer calls and provide general information. If a caller requires more assistance, the call is forwarded to the second tier (in the appropriate department depending on the nature of the call). In some cases, there are three or more tiers of support staff. Typically the third tier of support is formed of product engineers/developers or highly skilled technical support staff for the product.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Outsourcing</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Outsourcing</arg></template>In contrast to in house management, outsourced bureau contact centres are a model of contact centre that provide services on a &quot;pay per use&quot; model. The overheads of the contact centre are shared by many clients, thereby supporting a very cost effective model, especially for low volumes of calls. Outsourced centers have grown in popularity. There is criticism of the outsourcing model.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Companies that regularly utilise outsourced contact centre services include<space/><link><target>British Sky Broadcasting</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Orange (telecommunications)</target><part>Orange</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="The Wall Street Journal"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.livemint.com/2008/11/15003857/Orange-says-outsourced-work-to.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Orange currently outsources work to Indian units of Convergys Corp</arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Wall Street Journal]]</arg></template></extension><space/>in the telecommunications industry,<space/><link><target>Adidas</target></link><space/>in the sports and leisure sector,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Adidas - Contact Centres"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ewa.ltd.uk/case-studies/adidas<space/></arg><arg name="title">adidas setup a dedicated customer care centre</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Adidas]]</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Audi</target></link><space/>in car manufacturing<extension extension_name='ref' name="Audi chose Confero as an outsourced call centre"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.confero.co.uk/casestudies.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Audi chose Confero as an outsourced contact centre<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Confero</arg></template></extension><space/>and charities such as the<space/><link><target>RSPCA</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Outsourced call centers are often located in the<space/><link><target>developing countries</target></link>, where wages are significantly lower. The<space/><link><target>call center industry in the Philippines</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>call center industry in the Bangladesh</target></link><space/>serve as good examples.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Call Centers in Healthcare</heading><paragraph>The healthcare industry has used outbound call center programs for years to help manage billing, collections, and patient communication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Billing and Collections</arg><arg name="url">http://www.modernhealthcare.com/section/articles?tagID</arg><arg name="website">Modern Healthcare</arg></template></extension><space/>The inbound call center is a new and increasingly popular service for many types of healthcare facilities, including large hospitals. Inbound call centers can be outsourced or managed in-house.<space/><link type='external' href='http://mountainstar.com/for-physicians/central-scheduling.dot'>MountainStar Healthcare</link><space/>is one of the first companies to build an inbound call center in-house.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Centralized Scheduling</arg><arg name="url">http://mountainstar.com/for-physicians/central-scheduling.dot</arg><arg name="website">MountainStar Healthcare</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>American Health Connection</target></link><space/>is an American healthcare call center corporation with a focus on inbound call centers that utilize outsourcing.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>American Health Connection</target></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>These healthcare call centers are designed to help streamline communications, enhance patient retention and satisfaction, reduce expenses and improve operational efficiencies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Evaluation</heading><heading level='3'>Mathematical theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Erlang distribution</arg></template><link><target>Queueing theory</target></link><space/>is a branch of mathematics in which models of service systems have been developed. A call centre can be seen as a queueing network and results from queueing theory such as the probability an arriving customer needs to wait before starting service useful for provisioning capacity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Gans<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>N.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Koole<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>G.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Mandelbaum<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>A.<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1287/msom.5.2.79.16071<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Telephone Call Centers: Tutorial, Review, and Research Prospects<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Manufacturing & Service Operations Management]]</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>5<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>79<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://ie.technion.ac.il/Labs/Serveng/files/CCReview.pdf</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>(<link><target>Erlang's C formula</target></link><space/>is such a result for an<space/><link><target>M/M/c queue</target></link><space/>and approximations exist for an<space/><link><target>M/G/k queue</target></link>.) Statistical analysis of call centre data has suggested arrivals are governed by an<space/><link><target>inhomogeneous Poisson process</target></link><space/>and jobs have a<space/><link><target>log-normal distribution</target><part>log-normal service time distribution</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Brown<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>L.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Gans<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>N.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Mandelbaum<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>A.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Sakov<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>A.<space/></arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Shen<space/></arg><arg name="first5"><space/>H.<space/></arg><arg name="last6"><space/>Zeltyn<space/></arg><arg name="first6"><space/>S.<space/></arg><arg name="last7"><space/>Zhao<space/></arg><arg name="first7"><space/>L.<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1198/016214504000001808<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Statistical Analysis of a Telephone Call Center<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Journal of the American Statistical Association]]</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>100<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>469<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>36<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://132.68.160.12/serveng/References/statanalysis.pdf</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Call centre operations have been supported by mathematical models beyond queueing, with<space/><link><target>operations research</target></link>, which considers a wide range of<space/><link><target>Optimization (mathematics)</target><part>optimisation problems</part></link><space/>seeking to reduce waiting times while keeping server utilisation and therefore efficiency high.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Borst<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>S.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Mandelbaum<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>A.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Reiman<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>M. I.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dimensioning Large Call Centers<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1287/opre.1030.0081<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Operations Research<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>52<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>17<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>30036558</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://iew3.technion.ac.il/serveng/References/Dimensioning.pdf</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Metrics</heading><paragraph>Some vital call centre performance metrics<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">31West.net - Gregory Campbell</arg><arg name="title">Call Center Metrics</arg><arg name="url">http://www.31west.net/blog/16-vital-call-center-metrics</arg></template></extension><template><target>Unreliable source?</target><arg name="certain">yes</arg><arg name="reason">Blog post is [[WP:SPS]]</arg><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template><space/>are listed below:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Customer Satisfaction</italics>: a measure of how products and services supplied by a company meet or surpass customer expectation. C-SAT is based on customers experience with the support or service. The scoring for this answer is most often based on a 0 to 10 scale.</listitem><listitem><italics>Average Handling time</italics>: a key measure for any contact center planning system, as it tells you how long a new item of work takes to be handled and not just the talk time.</listitem><listitem><italics>Revenue Per Call</italics>: usually used in sales projects which calculates the effort of a representative with respect to increasing sales. RPC can be calculated by dividing the total amount of sale by total number of calls.</listitem><listitem><italics>First Call Resolution</italics>: properly addressing the customers need the first time they call, thereby eliminating the need for the customer to follow up with a second call.</listitem><listitem><italics>Total Problem Resolution</italics>: percentage of time the problem has been completely resolved from the customer point of view. This KPI is mostly used for: Operational Excellence. This keeps troubleshooting time to a minimum, which, according to industry averages, currently accounts for as much as 80 percent of total problem resolution time, and gets the problem fixed.</listitem><listitem><italics>Net Promoter Score</italics>: measures the loyalty that exists between a provider and a consumer. NPS is based on a direct question: How likely is it that you would recommend our company/product/service to a friend or colleague? The scoring for this answer is most often based on a 0 to 10 scale.</listitem><listitem><italics>Quality Scores</italics>: by far the most common metric used. It provides the ability to look at the overall caller experience and the conversations that agents are using on their phone calls.</listitem><listitem><italics>Service Level Agreement</italics>: an agreement between two or more parties where one is the customer and the others are service providers. The contract may involve financial penalties and the right to terminate the contract if the SLA metrics are consistently missed.</listitem><listitem><italics>Active &amp; Waiting Calls</italics>: measures current volume of active calls compared to the number of callers waiting to be patched through to an agent. This is a real-time status metric that should be shared with all the agents to offer them insight on their performance. Agents should be encouraged to resolve calls on a timely basis in order to get to the next caller in queue and not keep the callers on wait.</listitem><listitem><italics>Call Abandonment</italics>: measures the number of calls that are disconnected before they can be connected to one of your agents. This metric is closely related to Service Level and Customer Satisfaction. Customers are not expected to be patient. They will hang up and possibly switch their brand loyalties.</listitem><listitem><italics>Forecast Accuracy</italics>: better described as forecasted contact load vs. actual contact load. It is a performance metric that reflects the percent variance between the number of inbound customer contacts forecasted for a particular time period and the number of said contacts actually received by the center during that time period.</listitem><listitem><italics>Staff Turnover/Retention</italics>: The best way to measure the satisfaction of your workforce is to look at the percentage of staff that leaves. There can be some telling information in these numbers and it is crucial to track and analyze the turnover rates in many ways.</listitem><listitem><italics>Up-Sell/ Cross-Sell Rate</italics>: simply the success rate of generating revenue above the original intention of the call. It is becoming an increasingly common practice, not just for pure revenue-generating call centers but for customer service centers as well.</listitem><listitem><italics>Staff Shrinkage</italics>: the percentage of time that employees are not available to handle calls. It is classified as non-productive time, and is made up of meeting and training time, breaks, paid time off, off-phone work, and general unexplained time where agents are not available to handle customer interactions.</listitem><listitem><italics>Blockage</italics>:a measure of accessibility that indicates what percentage of customers will not be able to get in touch with the contact center at a given time due to insufficient network facilities.</listitem><listitem><italics>Cost Per Call</italics>: A major factor determining revenue is the cost of running the organization. A common measure of operational efficiency is cost incurred for each minute of handling the call workload, commonly referred to as Cost per Call. This cost per call can be simply a labor cost per call, or it can be a fully loaded rate that includes payroll in addition to telecommunications, facilities, and other services costs.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Criticism and performance</heading><paragraph><template><target>Criticism section</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template>Some critics of call centres argue that the work atmosphere in such an environment is dehumanising.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.eurofound.europa.eu/ewco/2005/04/SE0504NU02.htm</arg><arg name="title">Working conditions and health in Swedish call centres</arg><arg name="publisher">[[European Foundation for the Improvement of Living and Working Conditions]]</arg><arg name="date">2005-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>Others point to the low rates of pay and restrictive working practices of some employers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.payscale.com/research/US/Industry</arg><arg name="title">Hourly Rate Survey Report for Industry: Call Center</arg><arg name="publisher">[[PayScale]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hse.gov.uk/lau/lacs/94-2.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="title">Advice regarding call centre working practices</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Health and Safety Executive]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20090220050612/http://www.hse.gov.uk/lau/lacs/94-2.pdf</arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-02-20</arg></template></extension><space/>There has been much controversy over such things as restricting the amount of time that an employee can spend in the toilet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hazards.org/toiletbreaks/index.htm</arg><arg name="title">Hazards 81 extended briefing: Toilet breaks: Give us a break!</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Hazards (magazine)|Hazards]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>Call centres have also been the subject of complaints by callers who find the staff often do not have enough skill or authority to resolve problems,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://blogs.zdnet.com/ip-telephony/?p</arg><arg name="title">Tone-deaf to customer complaints, Dell opens yet another call center in India</arg><arg name="date">2006-01-30</arg><arg name="publisher">[[ZDNet]]</arg><arg name="author">Shaw, Russell</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>while the staff sometimes appear apathetic.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/business/4738804.stm</arg><arg name="title">Abuse rattles Indian call centre staff</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">2006-02-22</arg><arg name="author">Ahmed, Zubair</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>Other research illustrates how call center workers develop ways to counter or resist this environment by integrating local cultural sensibilities or embracing a vision of a new life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Pal</arg><arg name="first">Mahuya</arg><arg name="author2">Buzzanell, Patrice</arg><arg name="title">Breaking the Myth of Indian Call Centers: A Postcolonial Analysis of Resistance</arg><arg name="journal">Communication Monographs</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="volume">80</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="page">199</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/03637751.2013.776172</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Telephone calls are easily monitored, and the close monitoring of call centre staff is widespread.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.callcentrehelper.com/call_centre_monitoring.htm</arg><arg name="title">Call Centre Monitoring</arg><arg name="work">Management</arg><arg name="publisher">callcentrehelper.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>This has the benefit<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.callcentermagazine.com/shared/article/showArticle.jhtml?articleId</arg><arg name="title">The Call Center Answer Team reaches out to the industry for to crack a tough nut</arg><arg name="work">Q&A: How Many Calls Should I Monitor</arg><arg name="publisher">callcentermagazine.com</arg><arg name="date">2003-07-30</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>of helping the company to plan the workload and time of its employees. However, it has also been argued that such close monitoring breaches the human right to privacy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.acewh.dal.ca/eng/reports/moving6.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="title">Who’s on the Line? Women in Call Centres Project</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Health Canada]]</arg><arg name="work">Atlantic Centre of Excellence for Women's Health</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-05</arg></template></extension><space/>Most call centres provide electronic reports that outline performance metrics, quarterly highlights and other information about the calls made and received.</paragraph><paragraph>Criticisms of call centres generally follow a number of common themes, from both callers and call centre staff. From callers, common criticisms include:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://online.wsj.com/google_login.html?url</arg><arg name="title">If You Want to Scream, Press... - Preview<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Online.wsj.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-28</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Operators working from a script</listitem><listitem>Ignoring or delaying the calls from the more difficult customers (call screening)</listitem><listitem>Incompetent or untrained operators incapable of processing customers' requests effectively<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nationalcallcenters.org/pubs/In_Queue/vol2no24.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">nationalcallcenters<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-02-09</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Obsequious behavior by operators (e.g., relentless use of &quot;sir&quot;, &quot;ma'am&quot; and &quot;I'd be more than happy to assist you&quot;)</listitem><listitem>Overseas location, with language and accent problems</listitem><listitem>Touch tone menu systems and automated queuing systems</listitem><listitem>Excessive waiting times to be connected to an operator</listitem><listitem>Complaints that departments of companies do not engage in communication with one another</listitem><listitem>Deceit over location of call centre</listitem><listitem>Requiring the caller to repeat the same information multiple times</listitem></list><paragraph>Common criticisms from staff include:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Close scrutiny by management (e.g. frequent random call monitoring)</listitem><listitem>Low compensation (pay and bonuses)</listitem><listitem>Restrictive working practices (some operators are required to follow a pre-written script)</listitem><listitem>High stress: a common problem associated with front-end jobs where employees deal directly with customers</listitem><listitem>Repetitive job task</listitem><listitem>Poor working conditions (e.g. poor facilities, poor maintenance and cleaning, cramped working conditions, management interference, lack of privacy and noisy)</listitem><listitem>Lack of support for employees with impaired vision and hearing problems</listitem><listitem>Rude and abusive customers</listitem><listitem>Lack of advancement opportunities (Most call center positions tend to be<space/><link><target>dead-end job</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>until the employee decides to leave the company, resulting in high<space/><link><target>Turnover (employment)</target><part>turnover rates</part></link><space/>within the call centre)</listitem></list><paragraph>The net-net of these concerns is that call centres as a business process exhibit levels of variability. The experience a customer gets and the results a company achieves on a given call are almost totally dependent on the quality of the agent answering that call.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fleming, J., Coffman, C., Harter, J. (2005) Manage Your Human Sigma, Harvard Business Review</extension><space/>Call centres are beginning to address this by using<space/><link><target>Agent-assisted Automation</target><part>agent-assisted automation</part></link><space/>to standardise the process all agents use.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nationalcallcenters.org/pubs/In_Queue/vol3no12.html#How_to_Win_a_No-Win_Situation<space/></arg><arg name="title">NACC<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Nationalcallcenters.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-28</arg></template></extension><space/>Anton and Phelps have provided a detailed manual on how to conduct the performance evaluation of the business,<extension extension_name='ref' name="hccc"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Anton
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jon
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Dru Phelps
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How to conduct a call center performance audit: A to Z
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://searchcrm.techtarget.com/searchCRM/downloads/HowToConducChapter2and9.pdf
<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>whereas others are using various scientific technologies to do the jobs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dmaa"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Paprzycki
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Marcin
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Data Mining Approach for Analyzing Call Center Performance
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Springer
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="location">Berlin
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/b97304
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-3-540-22007-7</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="epcs"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Evaluation of the Performance of customer service representatives in a call center using DEA/Network Model/Fussy Sets
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://scholar.lib.vt.edu/theses/available/etd-04132003-184221/
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="pacc"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Srinivasan 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Raj
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Performance analysis of a call center with interactive voice response units 
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>TOP
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>12
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>91–110
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Springer Berlin 
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/BF02578926
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Talim
<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>JéRome
<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Wang
<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Jinting</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><space/>However, more popular alternatives are using personality and skill based approaches.<extension extension_name='ref' name="uppoc"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Skyrme
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Pamela
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Using personality to predict outbound call center job performance
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://applyhrm.asp.radford.edu/Volume%2010/MS%2010_2_%20Abraham.pdf
<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="paaic"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Stolletz 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Raik
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Stefan Helber
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Performance analysis of an inbound call center with skills-based routing 
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>OR Spectrum
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>331–352
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/s00291-004-0161-y
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>The various challenges encountered by call operators are discussed by several authors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wcie"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Witt 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>L. A.
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>When Conscientiousness Isn’t Enough: Emotional Exhaustion and Performance Among Call Center Customer Service Representatives
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Management
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>30
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>149–160
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/j.jm.2003.01.007
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ircc"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Aguir 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Salah
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The impact of retrials on call center performance 
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>OR Spectrum
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>353–376
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/s00291-004-0165-7
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Karaesmen
<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Fikri
<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Aksin
<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>O. Zeynep
<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Chauvet
<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>Fabrice</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="istc"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Murthy 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Nagesh N.
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Impact of Simulation Training on Call Center Agent Performance: A Field-Based Investigation
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Management Science
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>54
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>384–399
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1287/mnsc.1070.0818
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Challagalla
<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>G. N.
<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Vincent
<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>L. H.
<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Shervani
<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>T. A.</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="wpmo"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Armony 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mor
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Itay Gurvich
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>When promotions meet operations: cross-selling and its effect on call-center performance
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gsb.stanford.edu/facseminars/pdfs/2006_12-08_Armony1.pdf
<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="drvda"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Goldberg 
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>L.S.
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">A.A. Grandey
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Display rules versus display autonomy: emotion regulation, emotional exhaustion, and task performance in a call center simulation
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/17638495
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 July 2008
<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Unionization</heading><paragraph>Unions in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>have made some effort to gain members from this sector,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="coauthors"><space/>Pradeep Kumar, Christopher Robert Schenk<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Paths to Union Renewal<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Broadview Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-55193-058-7<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>ed. by Pradeep Kumar ...<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>including the<space/><link><target>Communications Workers of America</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cwa-union.org/news/entry/Improving_Call_Center_Jobs_a_Top_Priority_for_CWA_Customer_Service_Activist/</arg><arg name="title">Improving Call Center Jobs a Top Priority for CWA Customer Service<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Communication Workers of America</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-02-23</arg></template></extension><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United Steelworkers</target></link>. In<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>National Union of Workers</target></link><space/>represents unionised workers; their activities form part of the Australian labour movement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://workers.labor.net.au/90/news22_call.html</arg><arg name="title">Call Centre Union Busters Get Wake-Up Call</arg><arg name="publisher">Workers Online</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-07-08</arg></template></extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>, Uni Global Union of<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target></link><space/>is involved in assisting unionisation in this realm<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.uniglobalunion.org/uniindep.nsf/callcentres?openpage</arg><arg name="title">Uni Global Union's call centre organising campaigns</arg><arg name="publisher">Uni Global Union</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-07-08</arg></template></extension><space/>and in Germany<space/><link><target>Vereinte Dienstleistungsgewerkschaft</target></link><space/>represents call centre workers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Media portrayals</heading><paragraph>Indian call centres have been the focus several documentary films, the 2004 film<space/><italics>Thomas L. Friedman Reporting: The Other Side of Outsourcing</italics>, the 2005 films<space/><italics>John and Jane</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Nalini by Day, Nancy by Night</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics>1-800-India: Importing a White-Collar Economy</italics>, and the 2006 film<space/><italics><link><target>Bombay Calling</target></link></italics>, among others.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hudson, Dale (2009), Undesirable Bodies and Desirable Labor: Documenting the Globalization and Digitization of Transnational American Dreams in Indian Call Centers,<space/><italics>Cinema Journal</italics><space/><bold>49</bold><space/>(1), pp. 82-102.</extension><space/>An Indian call centre is also the subject of the 2006 film<space/><italics><link><target>Outsourced (film)</target></link></italics><space/>and a key location in the 2008 film,<space/><italics><link><target>Slumdog Millionaire</target></link></italics>.<space/><italics>BBC The Call Centre</italics><space/>is an often distorted although humorous view of life in a Welsh Call Centre.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/p018vlpy</extension><space/>There are critics of call centres who argue that the working environment within call centre's are dehumanising.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Call centre#Dynamics</target></link></extension><space/><italics>The Call Centre</italics><space/>argues against this point, and tries to illustrate that you can have high employee engagement within a call centre.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.callcentrehelper.com/what-lessons-could-a-call-centre-manager-learn-from-the-bbc-tv-show-the-call-centre-42357.htm</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Automatic call distributor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Business process outsourcing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Call management</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of call centre companies</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Predictive dialing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Operator messaging</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Queue management system</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Skills based routing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Virtual queue</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Cusack M., &quot;Online Customer Care&quot;, American Society for Quality (ASQ) Press, 2000.</listitem><listitem>Cleveland B., &quot;Call Center Management on Fast Forward&quot;, ICMI Press, 2006.</listitem><listitem>Kennedy I.,<space/><italics>Call centres</italics>, School of Electrical and Information Engineering, University of the Witwatersrand, 2003.</listitem><listitem>Masi D.M.B., Fischer M.J., Harris C.M.,<space/><italics>Numerical Analysis of Routing Rules for Call centres</italics>, Telecommunications Review, 1998,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.noblis.org/Publications/TR98_8.doc'>noblis.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hse.gov.uk/research/rrhtm/rr169.htm'>HSE website</link><space/>Psychosocial risk factors in call centres: An evaluation of work design and well-being.</listitem><listitem>Reena Patel,<space/><italics>Working the Night Shift: Women in India's Call Center Industry</italics><space/>(Stanford University Press; 2010) 219 pages; traces changing views of &quot;women's work&quot; in India under globalization.</listitem><listitem>Fluss, Donna, &quot;The Real-Time Contact centre&quot;, 2005 AMACOM</listitem><listitem>Wegge, J., van Dick, R., Fisher, G., Wecking, C., &amp; Moltzen, K. (2006, January). Work motivation, organisational identification, and well-being in call centre work. Work &amp; Stress, 20(1), 60-83.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.copc.com/'>Customer Operations Performance Center Inc. website</link><space/>for more information on the COPC-2000 CSP Standard.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>commons category-inline</target><arg>call centres</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Mandelbaum, Avishai<space/><link type='external' href='http://iew3.technion.ac.il/serveng/References/ccbib.pdf'>Call Centers (Centres) Research Bibliography with Abstracts</link>. Faculty of Industrial Engineering and Management, Technion-Israel Institute of Technology.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Call Centre</target></template><link><target>Category:Computer telephony integration</target></link><link><target>Category:Marketing</target></link><link><target>Category:Outsourcing</target></link><link><target>Category:Telephony</target></link></paragraph></article>