<article title='Dukkha'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the Egyptian food</arg><arg>Dukka</arg></template><template><target>Multiple issues</target><arg name="{{cleanup|reason">Overreliance on religious sources; too many quotes|date</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Buddhist term</target><arg name="fontsize">100%
</arg><arg name="title">dukkha
</arg><arg name="pi"><space/>dukkha<br /><space/>([[Devanagari|Dev]]: दुक्ख)
</arg><arg name="sa"><space/>duḥkha<br /><space/>([[Devanagari|Dev]]: दुःख)
</arg><arg name="bn"><space/>{{lang|bn|দুঃখ}} ''dukkhô''
</arg><arg name="si"><space/>[[:si:දුක්ඛ|දුක්ඛ සත්‍යය]]
</arg><arg name="en"><space/>suffering,<br/>anxiety,<br>stress,<br/>discontentment,<br/>unsatisfactoriness,<br/>etc.
</arg><arg name="bo"><space/>སྡུག་བསྔལ།
</arg><arg name="bo-Latn">[[Wylie transliteration|Wylie]]: sdug bsngal;<space/><br />[[THL Simplified Phonetic Transcription|THL]]: dukngal
</arg><arg name="zh">苦
</arg><arg name="zh-Latn">kǔ
</arg><arg name="ja">苦
</arg><arg name="ja-Latn">ku
</arg><arg name="ko">苦<br/>(ko)
</arg><arg name="vi">khổ / Bất toại
</arg><arg name="my">ဒုက္ခ
</arg><arg name="my-Latn">doʊʔkʰa̰
</arg><arg name="th">[[:th:ทุกข์|ทุกข์]]
</arg></template><template><target>buddhism</target></template><bold>Dukkha</bold><space/>(<link><target>Pli</target></link>;<space/><link><target>Sanskrit</target></link>:<space/><italics>dukha</italics>;<space/><link><target>Standard Tibetan</target><part>Tibetan</part></link>:<space/><italics>sdug bsngal</italics>, pr. &quot;duk-ngel&quot;) is a<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target></link><space/>term commonly translated as &quot;<link><target>suffering</target></link>&quot;, &quot;anxiety&quot;, &quot;stress&quot;, or &quot;unsatisfactoriness&quot;.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>See the section [[#Translating the term dukkha]] for clarification of translated terms.</arg></template><space/>The principle of dukkha is one of the most important concepts in the Buddhist tradition. The<space/><link><target>Buddha</target></link><space/>is reputed to have said: &quot;I have taught one thing and one thing only,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>and the cessation of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.&quot; The classic formulation of these teachings on<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is the doctrine of the<space/><link><target>Four Noble Truths</target></link>, in which the Truth of Dukkha (Pali:<space/><italics>dukkha sacc</italics>; Sanskrit:<space/><italics>dukha-satya</italics>) is identified as the first.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Dukkha</italics><space/>is commonly explained according to three categories:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The obvious physical and mental suffering associated with<space/><link><target>Jti (Buddhism)</target><part>birth</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>growing old</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bydhi (Buddhism)</target><part>illness</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>dying</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>The anxiety or stress of trying to hold on to things that are constantly changing.</listitem><listitem>A basic unsatisfactoriness pervading all forms of existence, because all forms of life are changing, impermanent and without any inner core or substance.</listitem></list><paragraph>The Buddhist tradition emphasizes the importance of developing insight into the nature of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>, the conditions that cause it, and how it can be overcome. This process is formulated in the teachings on the Four Noble Truths.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>In ordinary usage, the Pali word<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>(Sanskrit<space/><italics>dukha</italics>) means suffering, pain, sorrow or misery, as opposed to the word<space/><italics><link><target>sukha</target></link></italics><space/>meaning happiness, comfort or ease.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 542-550</arg></template><space/>Contemporary scholar Winthrop Sargeant explains the etymological roots of these terms as follows:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sargeant</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">303</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The ancient Aryans who brought the Sanskrit language to India were a nomadic, horse- and cattle-breeding people who travelled in horse- or ox-drawn vehicles.<space/><italics>Su</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>dus</italics><space/>are prefixes indicating good or bad. The word<space/><italics>kha</italics>, in later Sanskrit meaning &quot;sky,&quot; &quot;ether,&quot; or &quot;space,&quot; was originally the word for &quot;hole,&quot; particularly an axle hole of one of the Aryan's vehicles. Thus<space/><italics>sukha</italics><space/>meant, originally, &quot;having a good axle hole,&quot; while<space/><italics>duhkha</italics><space/>meant &quot;having a poor axle hole,&quot; leading to discomfort.</listitem></list><paragraph>Joseph Goldstein explains the etymology as follows:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">289</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The word [<italics>dukkha</italics>] is made up of the prefix<space/><italics>du</italics><space/>and the root<space/><italics>kha</italics>.<space/><italics>Du</italics><space/>means bad or difficult.<space/><italics>Kha</italics><space/>means empty. Empty, here, refers to several thingssome specific, others more general. One of the specific meanings refers to the empty axle hole of a wheel. If the axle fits badly into the center hole, we get a very bumpy ride. This is a good analogy for our ride through sasra. On my first trip to Burma, a group of friends and I went up-country to visit Mahsi Sayadaws home temple. We made part of the journey in an oxcart, and it was undoubtedly similar to modes of transportation in the Buddhas time. This extremely bumpy journey was a very visceral example of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>, the first noble truth. In more general philosophical terms, empty means devoid of permanence and devoid of a self that can control or command phenomena. Here we begin to get a sense of other, more inclusive meanings of the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>. Words like unsatisfying, unreliable, uneaseful, and stressful all convey universal aspects of our experience.</listitem></list><paragraph>Nineteenth century translator<space/><link><target>Monier-Williams</target></link><space/>states that according to grammatical tradition,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is derived from<space/><italics><template><target>IAST</target><arg>dus-kha</arg></template></italics><space/>&quot;uneasy&quot;; but Monier-Williams asserts that the term is more likely a<space/><link><target>Prakrit</target><trail>ized</trail></link><space/>form of<space/><italics><template><target>IAST</target><arg>dus-stha</arg></template></italics><space/>&quot;unsteady, disquieted&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Monier-Williams</arg><arg>1899, 1964</arg><arg name="p">483</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Centrality to Buddhist thought</heading><paragraph>The principle of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is one of the most important concepts in the Buddhist tradition. The Buddha is reputed to have said: &quot;I have taught one thing and one thing only,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>and the cessation of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.&quot;<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">onethingonly</arg><arg name="The Buddha is reputed to have said: "I have taught one thing, and one thing only, ''dukkha'' and the cessation of ''dukkha''."
* David Maurice states: "[The Buddha] said: 'I teach only one thing, suffering and the release from suffering' (MN Alagadduupamasutta) [...]"<ref group">web>http://www.vgweb.org/bsq/d_maurice.htm</ref>
* The Dhamma wiki states: "The Buddha said many times that his role was to show us the way out of suffering, ‘One thing and one thing only do I teach, suffering and how to end suffering’ (Majjhima Nikaya 1. 140)."<ref group</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Piyadassi Thera states:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="piyadassi_ch3"></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>To the Buddha the entire teaching is just the understanding of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>, the unsatisfactory nature of all phenomenal existence, and the understanding of the way out of this unsatisfactoriness.</listitem></list><paragraph>The classic formulation of these teachings on<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is the doctrine of the<space/><link><target>Four Noble Truths</target></link>, in which the Truth of Dukkha (Pali:<space/><italics>dukkha sacc</italics>; Sanskrit:<space/><italics>dukha-satya</italics>) is identified as the first of the four truths.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Neither pessimistic nor optimistic, but realistic</heading><paragraph>The central importance of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>in Buddhist philosophy has caused some observers to consider Buddhism to be a pessimistic philosophy.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">earlytranslators</arg></template><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">realisticview</arg></template><space/>However, the emphasis on<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is simply a basic fact of life: clinging to temporary things and states is inherently unsatisfying.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">62</arg></template><space/>Labelling this as &quot;negative&quot; is a refusal to accept the reality of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">62</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some contemporary Buddhist teachers and translators emphasize that while the central message of Buddhism is optimistic, the Buddhist view of our situation in life (the conditions that we live in) is neither pessimistic nor optimistic, but realistic.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">realisticview</arg><arg name="Contemporary translators and teachers point out that the centrality of dukkha in Buddhist philosophy is not intended to be pessimistic, but rather to present a realistic view of life. For example:
* Zasep Tulku Rinpoche states: "Some people think just thinking about or considering suffering is pessimistic. But when the Buddha taught the four noble truths he first talked about suffering and the cause of suffering. It is not because he was pessimistic. He was being realistic. He was saying this is how it is. This is what is happening. Look! If you want to have cessation, happiness, freedom then you must look for the cause and you need a path. You have to see suffering otherwise you have no motivation to look for a path. Don't be naïve be realistic. Look! There is suffering, physically. Old age is happening. Sickness is around us. Death is happening all the time. So that's what I mean when I say Buddhism is realistic."<ref group">web name</arg></template><space/>Walpola Rahula explains the importance of this realistic point of view:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle locations 525-541</arg></template><template><target>quote</target><arg>First of all, Buddhism is neither pessimistic nor optimistic. If anything at all, it is realistic, for it takes a realistic view of life and of the world. It looks at things objectively (yathābhūtam). It does not falsely lull you into living in a fool's paradise, nor does it frighten and agonize you with all kinds of imaginary fears and sins. It tells you exactly and objectively what you are and what the world around you is, and shows you the way to perfect freedom, peace, tranquility and happiness.

One physician may gravely exaggerate an illness and give up hope altogether. Another may ignorantly declare that there is no illness and that no treatment is necessary, thus deceiving the patient with a false consolation. You may call the first one pessimistic and the second optimistic. Both are equally dangerous. But a third physician diagnoses the symptoms correctly, understands the cause and the nature of the illness, sees clearly that it can be cured, and courageously administers a course of treatment, thus saving his patient. The Buddha is like the last physician. He is the wise and scientific doctor for the ills of the world (Bhisakka or Bhaisajya-guru).</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lama Surya Das emphasizes the matter-of-fact nature of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lama Surya Das</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="loc">loc.1300</arg></template><template><target>quote</target><arg>Buddha Dharma does not teach that everything is suffering. What Buddhism does say is that life, by its nature, is difficult, flawed, and imperfect. [...] That's the nature of life, and that's the First Noble Truth. From the Buddhist point of view, this is not a judgement of life's joys and sorrows; this is a simple, down-to-earth, matter-of-fact description.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Buddha acknowledged that there is both happiness and sorrow in the world, but he taught that even when we have some kind of happiness, it is not permanent; it is subject to change. And due to this unstable, impermanent nature of all things, everything we experience is said to have the quality of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>or unsatisfactoriness. Therefore unless we can gain insight into that truth, and understand what is really able to provide lasting happiness, and what is unable to provide happiness, the experience of dissatisfaction will persist.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Traleg Kyabgon</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Thich Nhat Hanh<space/></arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Three patterns</heading><paragraph>Within the Buddhist tradition, dukkha is commonly explained according to three patterns or categories:<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="The Buddhist tradition identifies three ways to experience suffering:
* Walpola Rahula writes: "The conception of dukkha may be viewed from three aspects: (1) dukkha as ordinary suffering (dukkha-dukkha), (2) dukkha as produced by change (vipariṇāma-dukkha) and (3) dukkha as conditioned states (saṃkhāra-dukkha)."{{sfn|Walpola Rahula|2007|loc">loc. 590-592}}
* Bhikkhu Bodhi states: "The Buddha divides Dukkha into three types, depending on the depth: (a) Dukkha as ordinary suffering [...] (b) Dukkha due to change. [...] (c) The Dukkha of Conditioned Formations.<ref group</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Dukkha-dukkha</italics><space/>(dukkha as ordinary suffering) - the obvious physical and mental suffering associated with<space/><link><target>Jti (Buddhism)</target><part>birth</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>growing old</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bydhi (Buddhism)</target><part>illness</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>dying</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Viparima-dukkha</italics><space/>(dukkha as produced by change) - the anxiety or stress of trying to hold on to things that are constantly changing.</listitem><listitem><italics>Sakhra-dukkha</italics><space/>(dukkha of conditioned states) - a basic unsatisfactoriness pervading all forms of existence, because all forms of life are changing, impermanent and without any inner core or substance. On this level, the term indicates a lack of satisfaction, a sense that things never measure up to our expectations or standards.</listitem></list><heading level='3'><italics>Dukkha-dukkha</italics><space/>(the dukkha of painful experiences)</heading><heading level='4'>Translations</heading><paragraph>The Pali term<space/><italics>dukkha-dukkha</italics><space/>(Sanskrit:<space/><italics>duhkha-duhkhata</italics>) is translated as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Dukkha as ordinary suffering (Rahula; Bhikkhu Bodhi)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">loc. 590-592</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="bodhi-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>The dukkha of painful experiences (Goldstein)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">291</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The suffering of suffering (Trungpa; Sakyong Mipham; Ringu Tulku; Dalai Lama; Geshe Tashi Tsering)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">26-28</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Mipham</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">159-160</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ringu Tulku</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">24</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Dalai Lama</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">50</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 610-612</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Suffering of pain (Traleg Kyabgon)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Traleg Kyabgon</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Suffering as pain (Gethin)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">61</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The stressfulness of pain (Thanisarro Bhikkhu)<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="thanis-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>Ordinary, everyday dukkha or difficulties (Lama Surya Das)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lama Surya Das</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="pp">78-80</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Description</heading><paragraph>This level of dukkha includes:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The physical and mental sufferings of<space/><link><target>Jti (Buddhism)</target><part>birth</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>aging</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bydhi (Buddhism)</target><part>illness</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>dying</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>The anxiety or frustration of coming across what is not desirable.</listitem></list><paragraph>Joseph Goldstein states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">291</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>First, there is the dukkha of experiences that are painful in themselves. This is where the translation of dukkha as suffering most frequently applies. There is the obvious suffering caused by war, violence, hunger, natural disasters, political and social oppression, and injustice. These are very real situations for hundreds of millions of people.</listitem><listitem>There is the inevitable pain of the body, starting with childbirth, and then sickness, injury, and ageing common to us all. And most likely, we wont be feeling our best at the time of death. All of this is not a mistake; its just nature at work.</listitem><listitem>Theres also the optional but deeply conditioned suffering in the mind: feelings of fear, jealousy, anger, hatred, anxiety, grief, envy, frustration, loneliness. Theres a long list of what are called afflictive emotions. Many times, in reporting states like this to Sayadaw U Paita, he would say, Good. Now youre realizing the truth of dukkha. Each time we can open to the painful experiences of mind and body, we are investigating and realizing the first noble truth for ourselves.</listitem></list><paragraph>Geshe Tashi Tsering states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 614-617</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Even animals understand the suffering of suffering. It is unpleasant and explicitly undesirable. Nobody runs after this form of suffering, and we need no sophisticated explanations to understand it. Nor do we need to devise skillful stratagems to avoid itanimals, insects, and humans are all constantly involved with doing so already, even though none of our attempts seems very skillful. We all wish to be free from this gross suffering.</listitem></list><heading level='3'><italics>Viparinama-dukkha</italics><space/>(the dukkha of the changing nature of all things)</heading><heading level='4'>Translations</heading><paragraph>The Pali term<space/><italics>viparinama-dukkha</italics><space/>(Sanskrit:<space/><italics>viparima-duhkhatta</italics>) is translated as:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Dukkha as produced by change (Rahula)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">loc. 590-592</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Dukkha due to change (Bhikkhu Bodhi)<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="bodhi-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>The dukkha of the changing nature of all things (Goldstein)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">291</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The suffering of change (Trungpa; Sakyong Mipham; Ringu Tulku; Traleg Kyabgon; Dalai Lama; Geshe Tashi Tsering)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">26-28</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Mipham</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">159-160</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ringu Tulku</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">24</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Traleg Kyabgon</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Dalai Lama</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">50</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 610-612</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Suffering as change (Gethin)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">61</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The stressfulness of change (Thanisarro Bhikkhu)<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="thanis-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>Difficulties or dukkha caused by changing circumstances (Lama Surya Das)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lama Surya Das</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="pp">78-80</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The suffering of impermanence</listitem><listitem>The suffering of trying to hold on to things that are always changing. (Pema Chodron<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template>)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Description</heading><paragraph>This level of dukkha includes:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The anxiety or stress of trying to hold on to what is desirable.</listitem><listitem>The frustration of not getting what you want.</listitem></list><paragraph>The Tibetan teacher<space/><link><target>Chogyam Trungpa</target></link><space/>expands this category to include &quot;<italics>not knowing</italics><space/>what you want.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Joseph Goldstein states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">291-292</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The second way we experience dukkha, the unsatisfying, unreliable nature of things, is through the direct and increasingly refined perception of their changing nature. [It is said that] many people have become enlightened by hearing just this one short teaching: whatever has the nature to arise will also pass away. But because this statement is so glaringly obvious, we often ignore or overlook its deep implications. Although we may not always feel this flow of incessant change as suffering, we still come to realize that nothing can be counted on to bring lasting fulfillment, precisely because nothing lasts. This great truth of change inevitably leads us to times of association with what we dont want and separation from what we do. And these situations, in turn, often condition resistance to the unpleasant things that come and clinging to the pleasant ones.</listitem></list><paragraph>Geshe Tashi Tsering states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 628-633</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Because this level of suffering is much more subtle and not apparent without some analysis, it is more difficult to recognize. Without investigation, objects at this level actually appear to be causes of happiness, because they bring some temporary pleasure. However, if we have mindfulness, we can see them for what they are. Initially, things and events (such as relationships, possessions, and so forth) appear desirablethey look as if they will bring happiness. Thats why we become attracted to them. However, when time passes and circumstances change, the same desirable, handsome, beautiful object turns into something ugly or undesirablesomething we want to avoid.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Relation to impermanence</heading><paragraph>This level of dukkha is directly related to the Buddhist concept of<space/><link><target>impermanence</target></link>. For example, Geshe Tashi Tsering states that in order to understand this level of dukkha:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 637-640</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>[...] we need an understanding of the gross level of impermanencehow things come into being, remain, and then cease by the power of things other than themselves. Things arise by the power of others, and while they remain they are still under the power of others. Their cessation also depends on the power of others. Nothing happens independently. Understanding this gross level of impermanence and the fact that we actually have so little freedom will help us understand the more subtle levels of impermanence.</listitem></list><paragraph>Joseph Goldstein emphasizes the importance of reflecting on impermanence:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">292</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>On the conceptual level we understand [the changing nature of things] quite easily, but in our lives, how often are we living in anticipation of what comes next, as if that will finally bring us to some sort of completion or fulfillment? When we look back over our lives, what has happened to all those things we were looking forward to? Where are they now? This doesnt mean that we should never enjoy ourselves or enjoy different pleasant experiences. It just means we need to realize and remember the very transitory nature of that happiness and to deeply consider what our highest aspirations really are.</listitem><listitem>Some powerful reflections and reminders in this regard are that all times of being together will end in separation, that all accumulation will end in dispersion, and that all life will end in death. And at the moment of death, what really belongs to us? Surprisingly, reflecting in this way on the truth of dukkha, which simply sees how things are free of hope and fear, brings a great lightness of heart and mind. Its a great relief to be out of the grip of deluded enchantment. Theres a freshness and vivid clarity in seeing things as they are.</listitem></list><paragraph>Goldstein presents five reflections that are practiced on a daily basis within many Buddhist traditions:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">292</arg></template><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>Translation from: Bhikkhu Bodhi, ''The Numerical Discourses'', p. 686.)</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Bhikkhus, there are these five themes that should often be reflected upon by a woman or a man, by a householder or one gone forth. What five? (1) . . . I am subject to old age; I am not exempt from old age. (2) . . . I am subject to illness; I am not exempt from illness. (3) . . . I am subject to death; I am not exempt from death. (4) . . . I must be parted from everyone and everything dear and agreeable to me. (5) I am the owner of my kamma, the heir of my kamma; I have kamma as my origin, kamma as my relative, kamma as my resort; I will be the heir of whatever kamma, good or bad, that I do.</listitem></list><heading level='3'><italics>Sankhara-dukkha</italics><space/>(the dukkha of conditioned experience)</heading><heading level='4'>Translations</heading><paragraph>The Pali term<space/><italics>sankhara-dukkha</italics><space/>(Sanskrit:<space/><italics>samskara-duhkhatta</italics>) is referred to as:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Dukkha as conditioned states (Rahula)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">loc. 590-592</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The dukkha of conditioned formations (Bhikkhu Bhodi)<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="bodhi-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>The dukkha of conditioned experience (Goldstein)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">295</arg></template></listitem><listitem>All-pervasive suffering (Trungpa; Sakyong Mipham; Ringu Tulku)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">26-28</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Mipham</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">159-160</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ringu Tulku</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">24</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Pervasive suffering (Geshe Tashi Tsering)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 610-612</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Suffering of conditioning (Dalai Lama)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Dalai Lama</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">50</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Suffering as conditions (Gethin)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">61</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The stressfulness of fabrication (Thanisarro Bhikkhu)<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="thanis-types"></extension></listitem><listitem>Difficulties or dukkha caused by the flawed nature of conditioned existence (Lama Surya Das)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Lama Surya Das</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="pp">78-80</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The suffering of ego-clinging (Pema Chodron<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>)</listitem></list><paragraph>Traleg Kyabgon referred to the third type of suffering as<space/><italics>samsara-duhkhatta</italics><space/>(Sanskrit), which he translates as &quot;the suffering of conditioned existence.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Traleg Kyabgon</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Description</heading><paragraph>This is the deepest, most subtle level of dukkha; it includes &quot;a basic unsatisfactoriness pervading all existence, all forms of life, because all forms of life are changing, impermanent and without any inner core or substance.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="bodhi1"><link type='external' href='http://www.beyondthenet.net/dhamma/fourNoble.htm'>''The Four Noble Truths - By Bhikkhu Bodhi</link></extension><space/>On this level, the term indicates a lack of satisfaction, a sense that things never measure up to our expectations or standards.</paragraph><paragraph>This subtle form of suffering arises as a reaction to qualities of conditioned things, including the<space/><link><target>skandha</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the factors constituting the human mind.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pema Chodron</target></link><space/>describes this as the suffering of ego-clinging; the suffering of struggling with life as it is, as it presents itself to you; struggling against outer situations and yourself, your own emotions and thoughts, rather than just opening and allowing.</paragraph><paragraph>Phillip Moffitt states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Moffitt</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 530-533</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Every day, even during the pleasant moments, do you not experience an underlying unease about the future? This worry and anxiety is a manifestation of the third type of suffering the Buddha identified life's inherent unsatisfactoriness due to its insubstantial compositional nature. Each moment arises due to certain conditions, then it just disappears. There is not a lasting or substantial &quot;there there&quot; in daily life, thus it is often described as being like a dream.</listitem></list><paragraph>Phillip Moffit relates this level of dukkha with existential angst:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Moffitt</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 533-536</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>How often in your adult life have you experienced the queasiness and unease that come from a sense of meaninglessness in your life? Think of all those occasions when you felt as though you were wasting your life, or sleepwalking through it, or not living from your deepest, most heartfelt sense of your self. Remember the times when you've felt as though there is little you do each day that has any real, lasting significance. We've all fallen prey at some point in our lives to such dark times of self-doubt and existential angst.</listitem></list><paragraph>Geshe Tashi Tsering states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 660-665</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>This level of suffering, and the causes and conditions that bring it about, can be understood through the teachings on the subtle levels of impermanence. Pervasive suffering is present wherever we are born in cyclic existence; we cannot avoid it. And yet, because its causes and conditions are very deeply rooted, it is very difficult for us, as ordinary people, to even recognize it and acknowledge at all. However, only when we acknowledge it we can begin to abandon it. The effects of pervasive suffering spread throughout our lives and often manifest in the form of grosser sufferings, which makes it difficult for us to really come to grips with it. It is so enmeshed that even understanding it, let alone overcoming it, takes a lot of effort.</listitem></list><paragraph>Geshe Tashi Tsering asserts that we will not be free of this level of dukkha &quot;until we are free from<space/><link><target>Samsara (Buddhism)</target><part>samsara</part></link>, until we are buddhas.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Geshe Tashi Tsering</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 691</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This category (<italics>sankhara-dukkha</italics>) is also identified as one of the &quot;eight types of suffering&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Types</heading><heading level='3'>Eight types</heading><paragraph>Dukkha can also be categorized into eight types belonging to the three categories of inherited suffering, the suffering between the period of birth and death, and general misery. Chogyam Trunga explains these categories as follows:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">16-26</arg></template><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="Bhikkhu Bodhi presents a slightly different list of the eight types of suffering, as follows:<ref group">web>[http://www.beyondthenet.net/dhamma/firstNoble.htm ''The First Noble Truth - Dukkha'' by Bhikkhu Bodhi]</ref>
* Birth (''[[Jāti (Buddhism)|jāti]]'')
* Aging (''[[Jarāmaraṇa|jarā]]'')
* Disease (''[[Byādhi (Buddhism)|byādhi]]'')
* Death (''[[Jarāmaraṇa|maraṇa]]'')
* Sorrow, lamentation, pain , grief and despair
* Union with the unpleasant
* Separation from the pleasant
* Not getting what we desire</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Inherited suffering:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Birth (<link><target>Jti (Buddhism)</target><part>jti</part></link>):</italics><space/>the discomfort of birth and experiencing the world for the first time; and the discomfort of relating to new demands or experiences.</listitem><listitem><italics>Old age (<link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>jar</part></link>):</italics><space/>the discomfort involved in the process of aging and growing old; this can apply to psychological as well as physical discomfort of aging.</listitem><listitem><italics>Sickness (<link><target>Bydhi (Buddhism)</target><part>bydhi</part></link>):</italics><space/>the discomfort of physical or psychological illness.</listitem><listitem><italics>Death (<link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>maraa</part></link>):</italics><space/>includes the pain of separation and not being able to continue on in your endeavors, as well as the physical discomfort of dying.</listitem></list><paragraph>Suffering between the periods of birth and death:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Getting what you don't want:</italics><space/>being unable to avoid difficult or painful situations.</listitem><listitem><italics>Not being able to hold onto what is desirable:</italics><space/>the pain of trying to hold onto what is desirable, lovely, splendid, terrific.</listitem><listitem><italics>Not getting what you do want:</italics><space/>this underlies the previous two categories; the anxiety of not getting what you want.</listitem></list><paragraph>General misery:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>All-pervasive suffering:</italics><space/>a very subtle dissatisfaction that exists all the time; it arises as a reaction to the qualities of conditioned things (e.g. the impermanence of things).</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Six types</heading><paragraph><link><target>Aung San Suu Kyi</target></link><space/>presented a list of<space/><italics>six great dukkha</italics><space/>at her<space/><link><target>Nobel Lecture</target></link>, delivered on 16 June 2012. These are:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link type='external' href='http://www.nobelprize.org/nobel_prizes/peace/laureates/1991/kyi-lecture_en.html'>Aung San Suu Kyi, Nobel Peace Prize lecture, Oslo, 16 June, 2012</link></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>To be conceived (<italics><link><target>Jti (Buddhism)</target><part>jti</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>To age (<italics><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>jar</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>To sicken (<italics><link><target>Bydhi (Buddhism)</target><part>bydhi</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>To die (<italics><link><target>Jarmaraa</target><part>maraa</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>To be parted from those one<space/><link><target>love</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem>To be forced to live in<space/><link><target>propinquity</target></link><space/>with those one does not love</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Developing insight into dukkha</heading><heading level='3'>Four Noble Truths</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Four Noble Truths</arg></template>The Buddhist tradition emphasizes the importance of developing insight into the nature of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>, the conditions that cause it, and how it can be overcome. This process is formulated in the teachings on the<space/><link><target>Four Noble Truths</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Meditation</heading><paragraph><link><target>jhana</target><part>Meditation</part></link><space/>(Pali:<space/><italics>jhana</italics>) is considered to be an essential tool for developing insight into the nature of dukkha. Contemporary Buddhist teacher Ajahn Brahm emphasizes that without the experience of meditation, one's knowledge of the world is too limited to fully understand dukkha.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ajahn Brahm</arg><arg>2006</arg></template><space/>In the following simile, Ajahn Brahm compares the experience of dukkha to being in prison, and compares meditation (Pali:<space/><italics>jhana</italics>) to a tunnel that leads out of the prison:<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>This simile is comparable to Plato's ''[[Allegory of the Cave]]''</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Another simile [...] is that of the man who was born and raised in a prison and who has never set foot outside. All he knows is prison life. He would have no conception of the freedom that is beyond his world. And he would not understand that prison is suffering. If anybody suggested that his world was dukkha, he would disagree, for prison is the limit of his experience. But one day he might find the escape tunnel dug long ago that leads beyond the prison walls to the unimaginable and expansive world of real freedom. Only when he has entered that tunnel and escaped from his prison does he realize how much suffering prison actually was, and the end of that suffering, escaping from jail is happiness.

In this simile the prison is the body, the high prison walls are the five senses, and the relentless demanding prison guard is one's own will, the doer. The tunnel dug long ago, through which one escapes, is called jhana [meditation] (as at AN IX, 42). Only when one has experienced jhana does one realize that the five-sense world, even at its best, is really a five-walled prison, some parts of it is a little more comfortable but still a jail with everyone on death row! Only after deep jhana does one realize that "will" was the torturer, masquerading as freedom, but preventing one ever resting happily at peace. Only outside of prison can one gain the data that produces the deep insight that discovers the truth about dukkha.

In summary, without experience of jhana, one's knowledge of the world is too limited to fully understand dukkha, as required by the first noble truth, and proceed to enlightenment.{{sfn|Ajahn Brahm|2006}}<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Contemporary scholar Michael Carrithers emphasizes the need to examine one's life. Carrithers asserts that insofar as it is dynamic, ever-changing, uncontrollable and not finally satisfactory, unexamined life is itself precisely dukkha.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carrithers</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="loc">''op cit''., pp. 55-56.</arg></template><space/>Carrithers also asserts that the question which underlay the Buddha's quest was &quot;in what may I place lasting relevance?&quot; He did not deny that there are satisfactions in experience: the exercise of<space/><link><target>vipassana</target></link><space/>assumes that the meditator sees instances of happiness clearly. Pain is to be seen as pain, and pleasure as pleasure. It is denied that happiness dependent on conditions will be secure and lasting.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carrithers</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="loc">''op cit''., pp. 55-56.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Contemporary teacher Chogyam Trungpa presents a perspective on how meditation practice can help the practitioner relate with dukkha; he states:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="Understanding suffering [dukkha] is very important. The practice of meditation is designed not to develop pleasure, but to understand the truth of suffering; and in order to understand the truth of suffering, one also has to understand the truth of awareness. When true awareness takes place, suffering does not exist. Through awareness, suffering is somewhat changed in its perspective. It is not necessarily that you do not suffer, but the haunting quality that fundamentally you are in trouble is removed. It is like removing a splinter. It might hurt, and you might still feel pain, but the basic cause of that pain, the ego, has been removed.{{sfn|Chogyam Trungpa|2009|p">34}}<space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Compassion</heading><paragraph>Developing insight into<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is said to lead to greater compassion for other beings. For example, Joseph Goldstein states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="pp">296-298</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>[Developing insight into<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>] is the gateway not only to awakening, but also to the arising and nourishing of compassion. Compassion is that feeling in the heart that wants to help others and ourselves be free of suffering. Its the feeling described by the Japanese Zen poet<space/><link><target>Rykan</target></link>:<list type='ident'><listitem>O that my monks robes</listitem><listitem>were wide enough</listitem><listitem>to gather up all the people</listitem><listitem>in this floating world.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>The first noble truth leads us to the practice of compassion, because it is the practice of letting things in, letting people in, letting all parts of ourselves in.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Within the discourses</heading><paragraph>The Buddha taught on<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>repeatedly throughout his lifetime. In the<space/><italics>Alagadduupama sutta</italics>, the Buddha states:<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">onethingonly</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;I have taught one thing, and one thing only,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>and the cessation of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.&quot;</listitem></list><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>Anuradha Sutta</italics>, the Buddha states:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link><target>Samyutta Nikaya</target><part>SN</part></link><space/>22.86, trans., Thanissaro Bhikkhu, retrieved from &quot;Access to Insight&quot; at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sn/sn22/sn22.086.than.html</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Both formerly &amp; now, it is only<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>that I describe, and the cessation of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.&quot;</listitem></list><paragraph>The classic formulation of these teachings on<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is the doctrine of the<space/><link><target>Four Noble Truths</target></link>, in which the Truth of Dukkha (Pali:<space/><italics>dukkha sacc</italics>; Sanskrit:<space/><italics>dukha-satya</italics>) is identified as the first of the four truths. The Four Noble Truths are presented within the Buddha's first discourse,<space/><italics>Setting in Motion the Wheel of the Dharma (<link><target>Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta</target><part>Dharmacakra Pravartana Stra</part></link>)</italics>; in this discourse, the Buddha defines<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>as follows:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link type='external' href='http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/sn/sn56/sn56.011.than.html'>Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta, translated by Thanissaro Bhikkhu</link></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;This is the noble truth of dukkha:<space/><link><target>Jati (Buddhism)</target><part>birth</part></link><space/>is dukkha,<space/><link><target>Jaramarana</target><part>aging</part></link><space/>is dukkha,<space/><link><target>illness</target></link><space/>is dukkha,<space/><link><target>Jaramarana</target><part>death</part></link><space/>is dukkha; sorrow, lamentation, pain, grief and despair are dukkha; union with what is displeasing is dukkha; separation from what is pleasing is dukkha; not to get what one wants is dukkha; in brief, the<space/><link><target>Skandha</target><part>five aggregates</part></link><space/>subject to<space/><link><target>Upadana</target><part>clinging</part></link><space/>are dukkha.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bhikkhu Bodhi</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">1844</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>Cula-Malunkyovada Sutta</italics>, the Buddha states:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link><target>Majjhima Nikaya</target><part>MN</part></link><space/>63, trans.<space/><link><target>Thanissaro Bhikkhu</target></link>, retrieved from &quot;Access to Insight&quot; at http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/mn/mn.063.than.html</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;And what is declared by me? 'This is dukkha,' is declared by me. 'This is the origination of dukkha,' is declared by me. 'This is the cessation of dukkha,' is declared by me. 'This is the path of practice leading to the cessation of dukkha,' is declared by me. And why are they declared by me? Because they are connected with the goal, are fundamental to the holy life. They lead to disenchantment, dispassion, cessation, calming, direct knowledge, self-awakening, Unbinding. That's why they are declared by me.</listitem></list><paragraph>In the sutra<space/><link><target>Samyutta Nikaya</target></link><space/>#35, the Buddha says:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>What ordinary folk call happiness, the enlightened ones call dukkha.</listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><italics><link><target>Anapanasati Sutta</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Mahsatipahna Sutta</target></link></italics><space/>emphasize the importance of the practice of<space/><link><target>jnana</target><part>meditation (jnana)</part></link><space/>to purify the mind of the<space/><link><target>five hindrances</target></link><space/>before contemplating the nature<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>in the context of the Four Noble Truths.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Relation to the five skandhas</heading><paragraph>According to the Buddhist tradition, the<space/><italics>dukkha of conditioned states</italics><space/>(<italics>sakhra-dukkha</italics>) is related to clinging to the<space/><italics><link><target>five skandhas</target><part>skandhas</part></link></italics>. Oxford scholar Noa Ronkin presents her understanding of the relation between the<space/><italics>skandhas</italics><space/>(Sanskrit; Pali:<space/><italics>khandhas</italics>) and dukkha as follows:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="[Contemporary scholar] Sue Hamilton has provided a detailed study of the khandhas. Her conclusion is that the associating of the five skandhas as a whole with dukkha indicates that experience is a combination of a straightforward cognitive process together with the psychological orientation that colours it in terms of unsatisfactoriness. Experience is thus both cognitive and affective, and cannot be separated from perception. As one's perception changes, so one's experience is different: we each have our own particular cognitions, perceptions and volitional activities in our own particular way and degree, and our own way of responding to and interpreting our experience ''is'' our very experience. In harmony with this line of thought, Gethin observes that the skandhas are presented as five aspects of the nature of conditioned existence from the point of view of the experiencing subject; five aspects of one's experience. Hence each khandha represents 'a complex class of phenomena that is continuously arising and falling away in response to processes of consciousness based on the six spheres of sense. They thus become the five upādānakhandhas, encompassing both grasping and all that is grasped.'{{sfn|Ronkin|2005|p">43}}<space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Three marks of existence</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Three marks of existence</arg></template><italics>Dukkha</italics><space/>is also listed among the<space/><link><target>three marks of existence</target></link>. These are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Impermanence (<italics><link><target>anicca</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>Suffering (<italics>dukkha</italics>)</listitem><listitem>Not-self (<italics><link><target>anatta</target></link></italics>).</listitem></list><paragraph>In this context,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>denotes the experience that all formations (<italics><link><target>sankhara</target></link></italics>) are impermanent (<link><target>anicca</target></link>) - thus it explains the qualities which make the mind as fluctuating and impermanent entities. It is therefore also a gateway to<space/><link><target>anatta</target></link>, not-self.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Translating the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics></heading><paragraph>Contemporary translators of Buddhist texts use a variety of English words to convey the aspects of<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Early Western translators of Buddhist texts (before the 1970s) typically translated the Pali term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>as &quot;suffering&quot;, a translation that tended to convey the impression that Buddhism was a pessimistic or world-denying philosophy.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">earlytranslators</arg><arg name="Some observers, such as the early Western translators of Buddhist texts (prior to the 1970s), have presented Buddhism as a pessimistic or world-denying philosophy. For example:
* Walpola Rahula states: "The First Noble Truth (Dukkha-ariyasacca) is generally translated by almost all scholars as ‘The Noble Truth of Suffering’, and it is interpreted to mean that life according to Buddhism is nothing but suffering and pain. Both translation and interpretation are highly unsatisfactory and misleading. It is because of this limited, free and easy translation, and its superficial interpretation, that many people have been misled into regarding Buddhism as pessimistic.{{sfn|Walpola Rahula|2007|loc">Kindle locations 524-528}}
* Ringu Tulku states: "It is sometimes said that Buddhism is a very pessimistic religion, since it constantly talks about suffering. But Buddhism does not aim at creating suffering or a pessimistic attitude. It talks about suffering to engender an optimistic outlook. It conveys the message, "Yes there is suffering, but it can be removed." In order to do so, we have to open our eyes. If we pretend that everything is all right, it will not be of much avail, especially when a problem arises that is so great that it can not be denied." {{sfn|Ringu Tulku|2005|p</arg></template><space/>Later translators, however, including Walpola Rahula (<italics>What Buddha Taught</italics>, 1974) and nearly all contemporary translators, have emphasized that &quot;suffering&quot; is too limited a translation for the term dukkha, and have preferred to either leave the term untranslated or to clarify that translation with terms such as anxiety, stress, frustration, unease, unsatisfactoriness, etc.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle locations 524-528</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Prebish</arg><arg>1993</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Keown</arg><arg>2003</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="po1"><link type='external' href='http://www.4ui.com/eart/172eart1.htm'>''Is Buddhism a Pessimistic Way of Life?'' by Jeffrey Po</link></extension><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">untranslated</arg><arg name="Many contemporary translators prefer to leave the term untranslated or use additional English words.
* Geshe Tashi Tsering states: "The concept of suffering is a very subtle one, so much so that many books, instead of translating it, use the original word, dukkha in Pali or duhkha in Sanskrit. Suffering in English conveys only a gross level of meaning, and I can see why scholars are tempted to keep to the original or try other terms such as dissatisfaction."{{sfn|Geshe Tashi Tsering|2005|loc">Kindle Locations 586-591}}
* Joseph Goldstein states: "The problem is that there is no single word in English that fully captures the range of its meanings. [...] So while “suffering” as the often-used translation of dukkha might sometimes be appropriate, it can also be misleading. It doesn’t always resonate with our own lived experience. [...] Words like unsatisfying, unreliable, uneaseful, and stressful all convey universal aspects of our experience.{{sfn|Goldstein|2013|pp</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For example,<space/><link><target>Piyadassi Thera</target></link><space/>states:<extension extension_name='ref' group="web" name="piyadassi_ch3"><link type='external' href='http://www.dhammatalks.net/Books3/Piyadassi_Thera_The_Buddhas_Ancient_Path.htm#CHAPTER%203'>''The Ancient Path'' - By Piyadassi Thera, Chapter 3</link></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The word dukkha (or Sanskrit duhkha) is one of those Pali terms that cannot be translated adequately into English, by one word, for no English word covers the same ground as dukkha in Pali. Suffering, ill, anguish, unsatisfactoriness are some favourite renderings; the words pain, misery, sorrow, conflict, and so forth, are also used. The word dukkha, however, includes all that, and more than that.</listitem></list><paragraph>Contemporary scholar Rupert Gethin states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gethin</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">61</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Rich in meaning and nuance, the word<space/><italics>dukha</italics><space/>is one of the basic terms of Buddhist and other Indian religious discourse. Literally 'pain' or 'anguish', in its religious and philosophical contexts<space/><italics>dukha</italics><space/>is, however, suggestive of an underlying sense of 'unsatisfactoriness' or 'unease' that must ultimately mar even our experience of happiness.</listitem></list><paragraph>Contemporary translator Bhikkhu Bodhi states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bhikkhu Bodhi</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The Pli word [<italics>dukkha</italics>] is often translated as suffering, but it means something deeper than pain and misery. It refers to a basic unsatisfactoriness running through our lives, the lives of all but the enlightened. Sometimes this unsatisfactoriness erupts into the open as sorrow, grief, disappointment, or despair; but usually it hovers at the edge of our awareness as a vague unlocalized sense that things are never quite perfect, never fully adequate to our expectations of what they should be.</listitem></list><paragraph>Many contemporary teachers, scholars, and translators have used the term &quot;unsatisfactoriness&quot; to emphasize the subtlest aspects of dukkha.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">unsatisfactoriness</arg><arg name="Many contemporary teachers, scholars, and translators have used the term "unsatisfactoriness" to emphasize the subtle aspects of dukkha. For example:
* The Dalai Lama states:{{sfn|Dalai Lama|1998|p">38}} "So the first step we must take as practicing Buddhists is to recognize our present state as ''duhkha'', or suffering, frustration and unsatisfactoriness."
* Rupert Gethin states:{{sfn|Gethin|1998|p</arg></template><space/>For example, contemporary scholar<space/><link><target>Damien Keown</target></link><space/>states that in the context of the subtle aspects of dukkha:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Keown</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 932-934</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>[...] the word dukkha has a more abstract and pervasive sense: it suggests that even when life is not painful it can be unsatisfactory and unfulfilling. In this and many other contexts unsatisfactoriness captures the meaning of dukkha better than suffering.</listitem></list><paragraph>The writer<space/><link><target>Mark Epstein</target></link><space/>states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Epstein</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">46</arg></template><space/>'A more specific translation [of the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>] would be something on the order of pervasive unsatisfactoriness. '</paragraph><paragraph>In the glossary for his text<space/><italics>Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Awakening</italics>, Joseph Goldstein provides the following definition for<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>: &quot;Suffering, unsatisfactoriness, stress&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Goldstein</arg><arg>2013</arg><arg name="p">418</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many translators prefer to leave the term untranslated.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">untranslated</arg></template><space/>For example, scholar and translator Walpola Rahula states:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walpola Rahula</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="loc">Kindle Locations 542-550</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>It is true that the Pali word<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>(or Sanskrit<space/><italics>dukha</italics>) in ordinary usage means suffering, pain, sorrow or misery, as opposed to the word<space/><italics>sukha</italics><space/>meaning happiness, comfort or ease. But the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>as the First Noble Truth, which represents the Buddhas view of life and the world, has a deeper philosophical meaning and connotes enormously wider senses. It is admitted that the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>in the First Noble Truth contains, quite obviously, the ordinary meaning of suffering, but in addition it also includes deeper ideas such as imperfection, impermanence, emptiness, insubstantiality. It is difficult therefore to find one word to embrace the whole conception of the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>as the First Noble Truth, and so it is better to leave it untranslated, than to give an inadequate and wrong idea of it by conveniently translating it as suffering or pain.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Alternate translations</heading><paragraph>Contemporary translators have used a variety of English words to translate the term<space/><italics>dukkha</italics>; translators commonly use different words to translate aspects of the term. For example,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>has been translated as follows in many contexts:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Anguish</listitem><listitem>Anxiety (Chogyam Trungpa,<space/><italics>The Truth of Suffering</italics>, pp.&amp;nbsp;810)</listitem><listitem>Affliction (Brazier)</listitem><listitem>Dissatisfaction (Pema Chodron, Chogyam Trunpa)</listitem><listitem>Discomfort</listitem><listitem>Discontent</listitem><listitem>Frustration (Dalai Lama,<space/><italics>Four Noble Truths</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;38)</listitem><listitem>Misery</listitem><listitem>Sorrow</listitem><listitem>Stress (Thanissaro Bhikkhu, Jon Kabat-Zin)</listitem><listitem>Suffering (Thich Nhat Hanh, Ajahn Succito, Chogyam Trungpa, Rupert Gethin, Dalai Lama,<space/><italics>et al.</italics>)</listitem><listitem>Uneasiness (Chogyam Trungpa)</listitem><listitem>Unease (Rupert Gethin)</listitem><listitem>Unhappiness</listitem><listitem>Unsatisfactoriness (Dalai Lama, Bhikkhu Bodhi, Rupert Gethin,<space/><italics>et al.</italics>)<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="name">unsatisfactoriness</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Translations into other languages</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Chinese Buddhism</target></link>,<space/><italics>dukkha</italics><space/>is translated as<space/><italics>k</italics><space/>(<link><target>Wikt:</target><part></part></link><space/>&quot;bitterness; hardship; suffering; pain&quot;), and this<space/><link><target>loanword</target></link><space/>is pronounced<space/><italics>ku</italics><space/>() in<space/><link><target>Japanese Buddhism</target></link><space/>and<space/><italics>ko</italics><space/>() in<space/><link><target>Korean Buddhism</target></link><space/>and<space/><italics>kh</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Vietnamese Buddhism</target></link>. The Tibetan (phonetic) is<space/><italics>dukngal</italics>. In<space/><link><target>Shan language</target><part>Shan</part></link>, it is<space/><template><target>IPA-shn</target><arg>tuk˥kʰaː˥</arg><arg></arg></template><space/>and in<space/><link><target>Burmese language</target><part>Burmese</part></link>, it is<space/><template><target>IPA-my</target><arg>doʊʔkʰa̰</arg><arg></arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Within non-Buddhist literature</heading><heading level='3'>Hinduism</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>literature, the earliest<space/><link><target>Upanishads</target><part>Upani<template><target>IAST</target><arg>ṣ</arg></template>ads</part></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Brihadaranyaka Upanishad</target><part><template><target>IAST</target><arg>Bṛhadāraṇyaka</arg></template></part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Chandogya Upanishad</target><part><template><target>IAST</target><arg>Chāndogya</arg></template></part></link><space/>are believed to predate or coincide with the advent of Buddhism.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>See, e.g., [[Patrick Olivelle]] (1996), ''Upani{{IAST|ṣ}}ads'' (Oxford: Oxford University Press), ISBN 978-0-19-283576-5, p. xxxvi: "The scholarly consensus, well-founded I think, is that the [[Brihadaranyaka Upanishad|{{IAST|Bṛhadāraṇyaka}}]] and the {{IAST|Chāndogya}} are the two earliest [[Upanishads|Upani{{IAST|ṣ}}ads]].... The two texts as we have them are, in all likelihood, pre-Buddhist; placing them in the seventh to sixth centuries BCE may be reasonable, give or take a century or so."</arg></template><space/>In these texts' verses, the Sanskrit word<space/><italics>du<template><target>IAST</target><arg>ḥ</arg></template>kha</italics><space/>(translated below as &quot;suffering&quot; and &quot;distress&quot;) occurs only twice. In the<space/><template><target>IAST</target><arg>Bṛhadāraṇyaka Upaniṣad</arg></template>, it states (in English and Sanskrit):</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>English</tablehead><tablehead>Sanskrit</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>While we are still here, we have come to know it<space/><extension extension_name='nowiki'>[</extension><italics><link><target>tman (Hinduism)</target><part><template><target>IAST</target><arg>ā</arg></template>tman</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>]</extension>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>If you've not known it, great is your destruction.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Those who have known it they become immortal.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>As for the rest only suffering awaits them.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Brihadaranyaka Upanishad</target><part>BU</part></link><space/>4 April 2014, trans. Olivelle (1996), p. 66.</extension></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>IAST</target><arg>ihaiva santo 'tha vidmas tad vayaṃ na ced avedir mahatī vinaṣṭiḥ<br />ye tad vidur amṛtās te bhavanty athetare duḥkham evāpiyanti</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link><target>Brihadaranyaka Upanishad</target><part>BrhUp</part></link><space/>4,4.14. Retrieved 28 December 2008 from &quot;Georg-August-Universitt Gttingen&quot; at http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/ebene_1/fiindolo/gretil/1_sanskr/1_veda/4_upa/brup___u.htm.</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>In the<space/><template><target>IAST</target><arg>Chāndogya Upaniṣad</arg></template>, it is written:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>English</tablehead><tablehead>Sanskrit</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>When a man rightly sees,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>he sees no death, no sickness or distress.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>When a man rightly sees,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>he sees all, he wins all, completely.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Chandogya Upanishad</target><part>CU</part></link><space/>7.26.2, trans. Olivelle (1996), p. 166.</extension><template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>This statement is comparable to the Pali Canon's [[Dhammacakkappavattana Sutta]] ([[Samyutta Nikaya|SN]] 56.11) where sickness and death are identified as examples of ''dukkha''.</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>IAST</target><arg>na paśyo mṛtyuṃ paśyati na rogaṃ nota duḥkhatām<br />sarvaṃ ha paśyaḥ paśyati sarvam āpnoti sarvaśaḥ</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' group="web"><link><target>Chandogya Upanishad</target><part>ChUp</part></link><space/>7,26.2. Retrieved 27 December 2008 from &quot;Georg-August-Universitt Gttingen&quot; at http://www.sub.uni-goettingen.de/ebene_1/fiindolo/gretil/1_sanskr/1_veda/4_upa/chup___u.htm.</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Thus, as in Buddhism, these texts emphasize that one overcomes<space/><italics>du<template><target>IAST</target><arg>ḥ</arg></template>kha</italics><space/>through the development of a transcendent understanding.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>For a general discussion of the core Indian spiritual goal of developing transcendent "seeing," see, e.g., Hamilton, Sue (2000/2001), ''Indian Philosophy: A Very Short Introduction'', (Oxford: Oxford U. Press), pp. 9-10, ISBN 978-0-19-285374-5.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Panetics</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Ralph Siu</arg><arg>Suffering#Social_sciences</arg></template>In 1988, the Journal of Humanistic Psychology published an article by<space/><link><target>Ralph G.H. Siu</target></link><space/>entitled<space/><italics>PaneticsThe Study of the Infliction of Suffering</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://jhp.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/28/3/6'>Journal of Humanistic Psychology</link>, Vol. 28, No. 3, 6-22 (1988).</extension><space/>In the abstract for the article, Sui proposed using the term dukkha as a quantitative measurement; he wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>After analyzing the unceasing mutual inflictions of suffering by practically everyone and the neglect of this pervasive and degenerating human deficiency by the academic community, I urge the immediate creation of a new and vigorous academic discipline, called panetics, to be devoted to the study of the infliction of suffering. The nature, scope, illustrative contents, and social value are outlined. The dukkha is proposed as a semiquantitative unit of suffering to assist in associated analytical operations.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Related publications include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Panetics: The study of the infliction of suffering. J. Humanistic Psychology 28(3), 6-22. 1988</listitem><listitem>The humane chief of state and the Gross National Dukkhas (GND). Panetics 2(2), 1-5. 1993.</listitem><listitem>Panetics Trilogy. The International Society for Panetics, 1994.<list type='bullet'><listitem>Vol. I, Less Suffering for Everybody. Ibid.</listitem><listitem>Vol. II, Panetics and Dukkhas. Ibid.</listitem><listitem>Vol. III, Seeds of Reflection, Panetic Word Clusters. Ibid</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Four Noble Truths</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nirodha</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Noble Eightfold Path</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samudaya</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Suffering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Criticism of Buddhism#Nihilism and focus on sufferings</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Web references</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="group">web</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Ajahn Brahm<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Ajahn Brahm</arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mindfulness, Bliss, and Beyond: A Meditator's Handbook</arg><arg name="publisher">Wisdom Publications</arg><arg name="ISBN">0-86171-275-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Ajahn Sucitto<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Ajahn Sucitto<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="title">Turning the Wheel of Truth: Commentary on the Buddha's First Teaching<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Shambhala<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bhikkhu Bodhi<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Bhikkhu Bodhi<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Connected Discourses of the Buddha: A New Translation of the Samyutta Nikaya<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wisdom Publications<space/></arg><arg name="place">Boston<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-86171-331-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bhikkhu Bodhi<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Noble Eightfold Path: Way to the End of Suffering<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Independent Publishers Group, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Brazier<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">David Brazier</arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Feeling Buddha<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Robinson Publishing</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carrithers<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="year">1986<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Buddha. Cited in Founders of Faith<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg name="authorlink">Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg name="year">1976<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Myth of Freedom and the Way of Meditation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Shambhala<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg name="authorlink">Chogyam Trungpa</arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Truth of Suffering and the Path of Liberation<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Leif</arg><arg name="editor-first">Judy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Shambhala<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Dalai Lama</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="title">The Four Noble Truths</arg><arg name="publisher">Thorsons</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Dalai Lama</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="title">The Meaning of Life, translated and edited by Jeffrey Hopkins</arg><arg name="publisher">Wisdom</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Epstein<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mark<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Mark Epstein</arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">Thoughts Without A Thinker: Psychotherapy from a Buddhist Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Basic Books, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Geshe Tashi Tsering<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Four Noble Truths: The Foundation of Buddhist Thought, Volume I<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wisdom, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Gethin<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rupert<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Rupert Gethin<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="title">Foundations of Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Goldstein<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joseph<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Joseph Goldstein<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="title">One Dharma: The Emerging Western Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HarperCollins</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Goldstein<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joseph<space/></arg><arg name="year">2013<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mindfulness: A Practical Guide to Awakening<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sounds True, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Harvey<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="year">1990<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introduction to Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Holmes<space/></arg><arg name="first">Edward<space/></arg><arg name="year">1957<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Creed of the Buddha<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bodley Head</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kalupahana<space/></arg><arg name="first">David J.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">David Kalupahana</arg><arg name="year">1992<space/></arg><arg name="title">A history of Buddhist philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="place">Delhi<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Motilal Banarsidass Publishers Private Limited</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Keown<space/></arg><arg name="first">Damien<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Buddhism: A Very Short Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Keown</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Damien<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Damien Keown</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dictionary of Buddhism</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-19-860560-9<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Lama Surya Das<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="title">Awakening the Buddha Within<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Broadway Books, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Leifer<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ron</arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Happiness Project<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Snow Lion<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Lopez<space/></arg><arg name="first">Donald S.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Donald S. Lopez, Jr.</arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Story of Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HarperCollins<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Mipham<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sakyong<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Sakyong Mipham</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="title">Turning the Mind into an Ally<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Riverhead Books</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Moffitt<space/></arg><arg name="first">Phillip</arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dancing with Life: Buddhist Insights for Finding Meaning and Joy in the Face of Suffering<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rodale, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Monier-Williams<space/></arg><arg name="first">Monier<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Monier Monier-Williams</arg><arg name="year">1899, 1964<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Sanskrit-English Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="place">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.sanskrit-lexicon.uni-koeln.de/scans/MWScan/MWScanpdf/mw0483-dut.pdf</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Nanamoli<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bhikkhu<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Bhikkhu Nanamoli<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Middle Length Discourses of the Buddha: A New Translation of the Majjhima Nikaya</arg><arg name="place">Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wisdom Publications<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-86171-072-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Nhat Hanh<space/></arg><arg name="first">Thich<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Thich Nhat Hanh<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Heart of the Buddha's Teaching<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Three River Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Prebish</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1993<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Historical Dictionary of Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Scarecrow Press</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8108-2698-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Potter<space/></arg><arg name="first">Karl<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Encyclopedia of Indian Philosophies, Vol. IX: BudVetter dhist philosophy from 350 to 600 AD</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Ratan</arg><arg name="first1">M. V. Ram Kumar<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Rao</arg><arg name="first2">D. Bhaskara<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dukkha: Suffering in Early Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Discovery Publishing House</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ringu Tulku</arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">Daring Steps Toward Fearlessness: The Three Vehicles of Tibetan Buddhism</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Snow Lion</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ronkin<space/></arg><arg name="first">Noa<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">Early Buddhist Metaphysics: the Making of a Philosophical Tradition</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Sargeant<space/></arg><arg name="first">Winthrop<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Bhagavad Gita<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SUNY Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Smith</arg><arg name="first1">Huston</arg><arg name="last2">Novak</arg><arg name="first2">Philip</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Buddhism: A Concise Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HarperOne, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Snelling<space/></arg><arg name="first">John<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1987<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Buddhist handbook. A Complete Guide to Buddhist Teaching and Practice<space/></arg><arg name="place">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Century Paperbacks</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Thanissaro Bhikkhu<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Thanissaro Bhikkhu<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tittha Sutta: Sectarians</arg><arg name="id"><space/>[[Anguttara Nikaya|AN]] 3.61<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/an/an03/an03.061.than.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">12 November 2007</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Traleg Kyabgon</arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Essence of Buddhism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Shambhala</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Walpola Rahula<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Walpola Rahula<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="title">What the Buddha Taught</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Grove Press, Kindle Edition</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Rhys Davids, T.W. Stede, William (1921-1925).<space/><link type='external' href='http://dsalsrv02.uchicago.edu/cgi-bin/philologic/getobject.pl?p.1:152.pali'>The Pali Text Society's Pali-English dictionary</link>. Chipstead, London: Pali Text Society, pp.&amp;nbsp;324325</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph>Online commentaries:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20121030125519/http://buddhasociety.com/online-books/what-buddha-taught-walpola-rahula-9-1'>What Buddha Taught (free online version)</link></listitem></list><paragraph>Other sources:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shambhalasun.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=3207&amp;amp;Itemid=244'>''The Journey Starts Here''</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template>, Shambhala Sun</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.accesstoinsight.org/ptf/dukkha.html'>''Dukkha''</link>, edited by John T. Bullitt - Access to Insight</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://centrebouddhique.fr/the-buddhas-concept-of-dukkha/'>''The Buddha's Concept of Dukkha''</link>, Kingsley Heendeniya</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://buddhism-dict.net/cgi-bin/xpr-ddb.pl?82.xml+id(&#039;b82e6&#039;)'>''Ku'' entry</link><space/>(use &quot;guest&quot; with no password for one-time login),<space/><link><target>Digital Dictionary of Buddhism</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Buddhism topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Buddhist philosophical concepts</target></link><link><target>Category:Buddhist terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Suffering</target></link></paragraph></article>