<article title='Unitary_patent'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the unitary patent in the European Union</arg><arg>the unitary patent in Switzerland and Liechtenstein</arg><arg>Unitary patent (Switzerland and Liechtenstein)</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><table class="wikitable" width="300px" style="float:right"><tablecaption>Unitary patent in the European Union</tablecaption><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Unitary patent participants.svg</target><part>300px</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><template><target>legend</target><arg>#0088cc</arg><arg>States participating in the unitary patent regulation which have ratified the [[Agreement on a Unified Patent Court|UPC Agreement]] ''<small>(the unitary patent will only apply if both criteria are met).</small>''</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><template><target>legend</target><arg>#FFFF00</arg><arg>States participating in the unitary patent regulation which have not ratified the agreement.</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><template><target>legend</target><arg>#ff6666</arg><arg>EU members not participating in the unitary patent regulation.</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="border:none"><template><target>legend</target><arg>#4B0082</arg><arg>Other [[European Patent Convention]] parties ''<small>(no participation possible)</small>''.</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph><template><target>European patent law</target></template>The<space/><bold>European patent with unitary effect</bold><space/>(<bold>EPUE</bold>), more commonly known as the<space/><bold>unitary patent</bold>, is a new type of<space/><link><target>European patent</target></link><space/>in advanced stage of adoption which would be valid in participating<space/><link><target>member states of the European Union</target></link><template><target>refn</target><arg>All EU member states except Spain, which abstained due to the exclusive use of English, French, and German languages, and Croatia, which subsequently acceded to the EU, joined the unitary patent regulation. States will only participate in the unitary patent if they ratify the [[Agreement on a Unified Patent Court|UPC Agreement]].</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template>. Unitary effect can be registered for a European patent upon grant, replacing validation of the European patent in the individual countries concerned. The unitary effect means a single renewal fee, a single ownership, a single object of property, a single court (the<space/><link><target>Unified Patent Court</target></link>) and uniform protection - which means that revocation as well as infringement proceedings are to be decided for the unitary patent as a whole rather than for each country individually. Licensing is however to remain possible for part of the unitary territory.</paragraph><paragraph>Formal agreement on the two EU regulations,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1257"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri</arg><arg name="title">Regulation 1257/2012</arg><arg name="journal">[[Official Journal of the European Union]]</arg><arg name="volume">L 361/1</arg><arg name="date">31 December 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 February 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1260"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri</arg><arg name="title">Council Regulation 1260/2012</arg><arg name="journal">[[Official Journal of the European Union]]</arg><arg name="volume">L 361/89</arg><arg name="date">31 December 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>which made the unitary patent possible through<space/><link><target>Enhanced cooperation#Unitary patent</target><part>enhanced cooperation</part></link><space/>at EU level, was reached between the<space/><link><target>European Council</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>European Parliament</target></link><space/>on 17 December 2012. The legality of the two regulations was however challenged by Spain and Italy, who filed in total four actions for annulment, two of which were rejected, and two of which are currently pending before the<space/><link><target>European Court of Justice</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=137928&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=en&amp;amp;mode=req&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=197732'>Case C-146/13</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=137924&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=en&amp;amp;mode=req&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=279995'>Case C-147/13</link></extension><space/>All EU member states except<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Croatia</target></link><space/>participate in the enhanced cooperation. Unitary effect of newly granted European patents can be requested, from the date the related<space/><link><target>Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</target><part>Unified Patent Court Agreement</part></link><space/>enters into force for the first group of ratifiers,<template><target>refn</target><arg>All EU states may ratify or accede to the Agreement. Entry into force for the first group of ratifiers requires ratification by Germany, UK, France and at least ten additional states. Several states have initiated ratification procedures. As of July 2014 it has been ratified by five.</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg><arg name="name">"UPC entry into force"</arg></template><space/>and will extend to those participating member states for which the UPC Agreement had entered into force upon the registration of unitary effect.</paragraph><paragraph>The negotiations which resulted in the unitary patent can be traced back to various initiatives dating to the 1970s. At different times, the project, or very similar projects, have been referred to as the &quot;European Union patent&quot; (the name used in the EU treaties, which serve as the legal basis for EU competency), &quot;EU patent&quot;, &quot;Community patent&quot;, &quot;European Community Patent&quot;, &quot;EC patent&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>See for instance: European Patent Office (EPO) web site,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.epo.org/topics/news/2009/20091208.html'>''EU Council agrees on next steps regarding the Community patent (EU patent)''</link>, News, 8 December 2009. Consulted on 13 December 2009</extension><space/>and &quot;COMPAT&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stakeholders debate">European Commission, Internal Market,<space/><link type='external' href='http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/smn/smn42/docs/patents_en.pdf'>''Stakeholders debate future policy on patents''</link>, Single Market News, Nr. 42, July 2006 (pdf)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By not requiring translations into a language of each contracting state, and by requiring the payment of only a single renewal fee for the group of contracting states, the unitary patent aims to be cheaper than European patents. Instead, unitary patents will be accepted in English, French, or German with no further translation required after grant.<template><target>refn</target><arg>There is a transition period of maximum 12 years during which there will be one translation made, either into English if the application is in French or German, or into any EU official language if the application was in English.</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/><link><target>Machine translation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>will be provided, but will be, in the words of the regulation, &quot;for information purposes only and should not have any legal effect&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Regulation 1260/2012, whereas #11</extension><space/>The maintenance fees, with a single fee for the whole area, are also expected to be lower compared to renewal fees for the whole area but the fees have yet to be announced.</paragraph><paragraph>The proposed unitary patent will be a particular type of European patent, granted under the<space/><link><target>European Patent Convention</target></link>. A European patent, once granted, becomes a &quot;bundle of nationally enforceable patents&quot;, in the states which are designated by the applicant, and the unitary effect would effectively create a single enforceable region in a subgroup of those 38 states, which may coexist with nationally enforceable patents (&quot;classical&quot; patents) in the remaining states.<template><target>refn</target><arg>Similarly, Switzerland and Liechtenstein created a separate unitary patent under the European Patent Convention. However, the [[unitary patent for Switzerland and Liechtenstein]] is the only possible way to obtain a patent in these two countries. It is not possible to obtain a patent only in Switzerland but not Liechtenstein, or only in Liechtenstein but not Switzerland. In contrast, the existence of the EU unitary patent will still permit a patent proprietor not to choose the EU unitary patent and to rather select specific countries.</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/>&quot;Classical&quot;, non-unitary European patents hold exclusively for single countries and require the filing of a translation in some contracting states, in accordance with<space/><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>65</arg></template>.<template><target>refn</target><arg>Although the filing of a translation under {{EPC Article|65}} is often referred to as "validation", this term is in fact not used in the European Patent Convention. In designated states where no translation is required, no "rubber-stamping" -or any kind of additional examination- by the national patent office of the designated state is permitted.</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><heading level='3'>Legislative history</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Mikolaj Dowgielewicz eu minister 0c169 7655.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>In 2011,<space/><link><target>Mikoaj Dowgielewicz</target></link>, Polish Minister for European and Economic Affairs, said: &quot;We have our<space/><link><target>wikt:back to the wall</target><part>backs to the wall</part></link>: one or two member states are not willing to compromise and there will not be a breakthrough before the end of our<space/><link><target>Presidency of the Council of the European Union</target><part>Presidency</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mosca-2011"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.europolitics.info/presidency-throws-in-towel-on-litigation-court-art321522.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Presidency throws in towel on litigation court<space/></arg><arg name="author">Sophie Mosca<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Europolitics<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 December 2011</arg></template></extension></part></link>In 2009, three draft documents were published regarding a community patent: a European patent in which the European Community was designated:<space/></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Council regulation on the community patent,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://register.consilium.europa.eu/doc/srv?l</arg><arg name="title">Revised proposal for a council decision on the Community patent</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2014</arg><arg name="date">7 April 2009</arg><arg name="work">Council of European Union</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>Agreement on the European and Community Patents Court (open to the European Community and all states of the European Patent Convention)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://register.consilium.europa.eu/doc/srv?l</arg><arg name="title">Draft Agreement on the European Community and patents court</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2014</arg><arg name="date">7 April 2009</arg><arg name="work">Council of European Union</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>Decision to open negotiations regarding this Agreement</listitem></list><paragraph>Based on those documents, the European Council requested on 6 July 2009 an opinion from the Court of Justice of the European Union, regarding the compatibility of the envisioned Agreement with EU law: &quot;Is the envisaged agreement creating a Unified Patent Litigation System (currently named European and Community Patents Court) compatible with the provisions of the Treaty establishing the European Community?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>CELEX</target><arg>62009CV0001</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In December 2010, the use of the<space/><link><target>enhanced co-operation</target></link><space/>procedure, under which<space/><link><target>s:Consolidated version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union/Title III: Enhanced Cooperation</target><part>Articles 326334</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union</target></link><space/>provides that a group of member states of the European Union can choose to co-operate on a specific topic, was proposed by twelve Member States to set up a unitary patent applicable in all participating European Union Member States.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tait">Nikki Tait,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/fa9b799a-0799-11e0-8d80-00144feabdc0.html#axzz18DVrohfy'>&quot;Brussels backs single European patent plan&quot;</link>, FT.com, 14 December 2010. Consulted on 15 December 2010.</extension><space/>The use of this procedure had only been used once in the past, for harmonising rules regarding the<space/><link><target>applicable law</target></link><space/>in divorce across several EU Member States.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tait"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In early 2011, the procedure leading to the enhanced co-operation was reported to be progressing. Twenty-five Member States had written to the European Commission requesting to participate, with Spain and Italy remaining outside, primarily on the basis of ongoing concerns over translation issues. On 15 February, the European Parliament approved the use of the enhanced co-operation procedure for unitary patent protection by a vote of 471 to 160.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.europarl.europa.eu/en/pressroom/content/20110215IPR13680/html/EU-patent-Parliament-gives-go-ahead-for-enhanced-cooperation'>European patent: Parliament gives go ahead for enhanced cooperation</link>, European Parliament, published: 15 February 2011. Consulted on 15 February 2011.</extension><space/>and on 10 March 2011 the Council gave their authorisation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/intm/119732.pdf'>Council authorises enhanced cooperation for EU Patent</link></extension><space/>Two days earlier, on 8 March 2011, the<space/><link><target>Court of Justice of the European Union</target></link><space/>had issued its opinion, stating that the draft Agreement creating the European and Community Patent Court would be incompatible with EU law.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://curia.europa.eu/jcms/upload/docs/application/pdf/2011-03/cp110017en.pdf'>ECJ Press release of 8 March</link></extension><space/>The same day, the Hungarian Presidency of the Council insisted that this opinion would not affect the enhanced co-operation procedure.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.eu2011.hu/files/bveu/documents/PatentPressRelease_08032011.pdf'>Press release of 8 March</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 2011, negotiations on the enhanced co-operation system were reportedly advancing rapidlytoo fast, in some views.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.europolitics.info/business-competitiveness/european-patent-moves-forward-art318386-7.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">European patent moves forward<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Europolitics<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>It was announced that implementation required an enabling European Regulation, and a Court agreement between the states that elect to take part. The European Parliament approved the continuation of negotiations in September.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.europarl.europa.eu/en/pressroom/content/20111121IPR31956/html/A-step-closer-to-an-EU-patent'>A step closer to an EU patent</link>, European Parliament press release, JURI Justice and home affairs, 22 November 2011.</extension><space/>A draft of the agreement was issued on 11 November 2011 and was open to all member states of the European Union, but not to other European Patent Convention states.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://register.consilium.europa.eu/pdf/en/11/st16/st16741.en11.pdf'>Draft agreement on a Unified Patent Court and draft Statute Revised Presidency text</link>, Document no 16741/11, Council of the European Union, Brussels, 11 November 2011.</extension><space/>However, serious criticisms of the proposal remained mostly unresolved.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.les-bi.org/documents/UnifiedPatentCourt-ConcernsofPrinciple_10926472_1__8_.doc2.9-3.pdf'>&quot;Concerns of Principle&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>Licensing Executives Society International</target><part>LES</part></link><space/>Britain and Ireland (Sub-group), 14 June 2011</extension><space/>A meeting of the Competitiveness Council on 5 December failed to agree on the final text.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/intm/126579.pdf'>&quot;EU press release 18115/11, at p. 19&quot;</link>, 24 November 2011</extension><space/>In particular, there was no agreement on where the Central Division of a Unified Patent Court should be located,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/law/2011/nov/28/london-lawyers-want-patents-court<space/></arg><arg name="title">London backed by UK lawyers as home of new European patents court<space/></arg><arg name="author">Owen Bowcott<space/></arg><arg name="date">28 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Guardian<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>&quot;with London, Munich and Paris the candidate cities.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fleming2011"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.euractiv.com/innovation-enterprise/italy-spain-drop-opposition-eu-patent-news-509433<space/></arg><arg name="title">Italy, Spain could drop opposition to EU patent<space/></arg><arg name="author">Jeremy Fleming<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EurActiv.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Polish<space/><link><target>Presidency of the Council of the European Union</target><part>Presidency</part></link>, acknowledged on 16 December 2011 the failure to reach an agreement &quot;on the question of the location of the seat of the central division.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mosca-2011"></extension><space/>The Danish Presidency therefore inherited the issue.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mosca-2011"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.euractiv.com/future-eu/eu-presidency-nears-poland-vents-frustrations-news-509788<space/></arg><arg name="title">As EU presidency nears end, Poland vents frustrations<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EurActiv.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 December 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-12-16/agreement-on-eu-wide-patent-unlikely-this-year-poland-says.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Agreement on EU-Wide Patent Unlikely This Year, Poland Says<space/></arg><arg name="author">Jones Hayden<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bloomberg Businessweek<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>According to the President of the European Commission in January 2012, the only question remaining to be settled was the location of the Central Division of the Court.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/commission_2010-2014/president/news/speeches-statements/2012/01/20120118_speeches_1_en.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">EP Debate on the start of the Danish EU Presidency<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">European Commission (José Manuel Barroso)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 March 2012<space/></arg><arg name="quote">We must urgently reach agreement on the European patent. We have been discussing this for decades. I fully expect negotiations on this to be completed early in the Danish Presidency. I call on the three Member States, France, Germany and the United Kingdom, who are holding this up over a site issue of some offices, to swiftly find a compromise. Frankly, it is not acceptable! It is not acceptable that such a crucial initiative is blocked over such a trivial disagreement.</arg></template></extension><space/>However, evidence presented to the UK House of Commons<space/><link><target>European Scrutiny Committee</target></link><space/>in February suggested that the position was more complicated.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.publications.parliament.uk/pa/cm201012/cmselect/cmeuleg/uc1799ii/uc1799ii.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Uncorrected Transcript of Oral Evidence (To be published as HC 1799-ii), Oral Evidence Taken Before the European Scrutiny Committee, Draft agreement on a unified patent court and draft statute, Baroness Wilcox, Neil Feinson, Liz Coleman and Nicholas Fernandes, Evidence heard in Public Questions 73 – 125<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 February 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">House of Commons<space/></arg><arg name="quote">''Neil Feinson'': There is more than one issue outstanding. There is one very big issue, which is the location, and then there are a lot of technical issues that are outstanding.<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>At an EU summit at the end of January 2012, participants agreed to press on and finalise the system by June.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/127599.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Statement of the Members of the European Council, Towards Growth-Friendly Consolidation and Job-Friendly Growth<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">European Council<space/></arg><arg name="location">Brussels<space/></arg><arg name="quote">The participating Member States commit to reaching at the latest in June 2012 a final agreement on the last outstanding issue in the patent package.<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 March 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>On 26 April,<space/><link><target>Herman Van Rompuy</target></link>, President of the European Council, wrote to members of the Council, saying &quot;This important file has been discussed for many years and we are now very close to a final deal,.... This deal is needed now, because this is an issue of crucial importance for innovation and growth. I very much hope that the last outstanding issue will be sorted out at the May Competitiveness Council. If not, I will take it up at the June European Council.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/129860.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Letter from President of the European Council Herman Van Rompuy to the members of the European Council<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 April 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>The Competitiveness Council met on 30 May and failed to reach agreement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/intm/130562.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">PRESS RELEASE, 3169th Council meeting, Competitiveness (Internal Market, Industry, Research and Space), Brussels, 30–31 May 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A compromise agreement on the seat(s) of the unified court was eventually reached at the June European Council (2829 June 2012), splitting the central division according to technology between Paris (the main seat), London and Munich.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sciencebusiness27-06-12"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="EuObserver29-06-12"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://euobserver.com/19/116819<space/></arg><arg name="title">EU breaks 30-year deadlock on EU patent<space/></arg><arg name="work">Euobserver.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">29 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="author">Nikolaj Nielsen</arg></template></extension><space/>However, on 2 July 2012, the European Parliament decided to postpone the vote following a move by the European Council to modify the arrangements previously approved by MEPs in negotiations with the European Council. The modification was considered controversial and included the deletion of three key articles (68) of the legislation, seeking to reduce the competence of the European Union Court of Justice in unitary patent litigation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">EU patent: Parliament postpones vote due to Council's last-minute change</arg><arg name="url">http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/de/pressroom/content/20120703IPR48182/html/EU-patent-Parliament-postpones-vote-due-to-Council's-last-minute-change.</arg><arg name="publisher">europarl.europa.eu</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 August 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>On 9 July 2012, the Committee on Legal Affairs of the European Parliament debated the patent package following the decisions adopted by the General Council on 2829 June 2012 in camera in the presence of MEP<space/><link><target>Bernhard Rapkay</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">JURI debate on the patent package following the decisions adopted by the General Council</arg><arg name="url">http://www.europarl.europa.eu/sides/getDoc.do?pubRef</arg><arg name="publisher">europarl.europa.eu</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 November 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>A later press release by Rapkay quoted from a legal opinion submitted by the Legal Service of the European Parliament, which affirmed the concerns of MEPs to approve the decision of a recent EU summit to delete said articles as it &quot;nullifies central aspects of a substantive patent protection&quot;. A Europe-wide uniform protection of intellectual property would thus not exist with the consequence that the requirements of the corresponding EU treaty would not be met and that the European Court of Justice could therefore invalidate the legislation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Press Release MEP Rapkay</arg><arg name="url">http://spdnet.sozi.info/nrw/dortmund/brapkay/dl/EU_Patent_PM_Juli_2012.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">rapkay.sozi.info</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 November 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>By the end of 2012 a new compromise was reached between the European Parliament and the European Council, including a limited role for the European Court of Justice. The Unified Court will apply national patent laws, which the Court agreement makes the same in each country.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.sciencemag.org/scienceinsider/2012/12/after-decades-of-debate-eu-leade.html</arg><arg name="work">Science Magazine</arg><arg name="title">UPDATE: After Decades of Debate, E.U. Leaders Sign Off on Single Patent</arg><arg name="author">Tania Rabesandratana</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2013</arg><arg name="date">10 December 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>The legislation for the enhanced co-operation mechanism was approved by the<space/><link><target>European Parliament</target></link><space/>on 11 December 2012<extension extension_name='ref' name="EUPARL"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/content/20121203FCS04313/3/html/Parliament-approves-EU-unitary-patent-rules<space/></arg><arg name="title">Parliament approves EU unitary patent rules<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 December 2012<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 December 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work">European Parliament</arg></template></extension><space/>and the regulations were signed by the European Council and European Parliament officials on 17 December 2012.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1257"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1260"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 30 May 2011, Italy and Spain challenged the Council's authorisation of the use of enhanced co-operation to introduce the trilingual (English, French, German) system for the unitary patent, which they viewed as discriminatory to their languages, with the CJEU on the grounds that it did not comply with the EU treaties.<extension extension_name='ref' name="case1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://curia.europa.eu/juris/liste.jsf?num</arg><arg name="title">Spain v Council</arg><arg name="id">Case C-274/11 (Joined Cases C-274/11, C-295/11)</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Court of Justice of the European Union]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.euractiv.com/en/innovation-enterprise/italy-spain-take-patent-fight-court-news-505264'>&quot;Italy, Spain take patent fight to court&quot;</link>, EurActiv.com, Published 31 May 2011 Updated 7 June 2011.</extension><space/>In January 2013,<space/><link><target>Advocate General</target></link><space/><link><target>Yves Bot</target></link><space/>delivered his recommendation that the court reject the complaint. Suggestions by the Advocate General are advisory only, but are generally followed by the court.<extension extension_name='ref' name="UPDATE"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.reuters.com/article/2012/12/11/eu-patent-idUSL5E8NBBHB20121211</arg><arg name="title">UPDATE 1-Pan-European patent in prospect after years of dispute</arg><arg name="work">Reuters</arg><arg name="date">11 December 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>The case was dismissed by the court in April 2013,<extension extension_name='ref' name="case1"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.computing.co.uk/ctg/news/2261808/unified-eu-patent-scheme-moves-a-step-closer</arg><arg name="title">Unified EU patent scheme moves a step closer</arg><arg name="date">16 April 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 April 2013</arg><arg name="last">Palmer</arg><arg name="first">Danny</arg></template></extension><space/>however Spain launched two new challenges with the EUCJ in March 2013 against the regulations implementing the unitary patent package which have yet to be resolved. The court hearing for both cases has been scheduled to take place on 1 July 2014.<extension extension_name='ref' name="case2a"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://curia.europa.eu/juris/liste.jsf?num</arg><arg name="title">Spain v Parliament and Council</arg><arg name="id">Case C-146/13</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Court of Justice of the European Union]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="case2b"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://curia.europa.eu/juris/liste.jsf?num</arg><arg name="title">Spain v Council</arg><arg name="id">Case C-147/13</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Court of Justice of the European Union]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Advocate-General<space/><link><target>Yves Bot</target></link><space/>published his opinion on 18 November 2014, suggesting that both actions be dismissed (<template><target>ECLI</target><arg>ECLI:EU:C:2014:2380</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>ECLI</target><arg>ECLI:EU:C:2014:2381</arg></template>). The court handed down<space/><link><target>C-146/13 and C-147/13</target><part>its decisions</part></link><space/>on 5 May 2015 as<space/><template><target>ECLI</target><arg>ECLI:EU:C:2015:298</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>ECLI</target><arg>ECLI:EU:C:2015:299</arg></template><space/>fully dismissing the Spanish claims. Following a request by the government of Italy,<extension extension_name='ref' name="italyrequest"></extension><space/>it became a participant of the unitary patent regulations in September 2015.<extension extension_name='ref' name="italy"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/PDF/?uri</arg><arg name="title">COMMISSION DECISION (EU) 2015/1753 of 30 September 2015 on confirming the participation of Italy in enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Official Journal of the European Union]]</arg><arg name="volume">L 256/19</arg><arg name="date">1 October 2015</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>European patents</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>European Patent Convention</arg></template>European patents are granted in accordance with the provisions of the European Patent Convention,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>2</arg><arg>1</arg></template></extension><space/>via a<space/><link><target>Grant procedure before the European Patent Office</target><part>unified procedure</part></link><space/>before the<space/><link><target>European Patent Office</target></link>. A single<space/><link><target>patent application</target></link>, in one language,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>14</arg></template></extension><space/>may be filed at the European Patent Office or at a national patent office of certain Contracting States.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Art75-1-b"><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>75</arg><arg>1</arg><arg>b</arg></template></extension><template><target>refn</target><arg>However, [[Divisional applications under the European Patent Convention|divisional applications]] cannot be filed with a national patent office. They have to be filed with the European Patent Office ({{EPC Article|76|1}} in conjunction with {{EPC Rule|36|2}}).</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/><link><target>Patentability</target><part>Patentable invention</part><trail>s</trail></link>, according to the EPC, are &quot;any inventions, in all fields of technology, providing that they are<space/><link><target>Novelty under the European Patent Convention</target><part>new</part></link>, involve an<space/><link><target>inventive step under the European Patent Convention</target><part>inventive step</part></link>, and are susceptible of<space/><link><target>industrial applicability</target><part>industrial application</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>52</arg><arg>1</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast to the unified character of a European patent application, a granted European patent has, in effect, no unitary character, except for the centralized<space/><link><target>Opposition procedure before the European Patent Office</target><part>opposition procedure</part></link><space/>(which can be initiated within 9 months from grant, by somebody else than the patent proprietor), and the centralized<space/><link><target>Limitation and revocation procedures before the European Patent Office</target><part>limitation and revocation</part></link><space/>procedures (which can only be instituted by the patent proprietor).<extension extension_name='ref'>In addition to the opposition, limitation and revocation procedures, particular acts can still be performed before the EPO after grant, such as requesting a rectification of an incorrect designation of inventor under<space/><template><target>EPC Rule</target><arg>21</arg><arg>1</arg></template>. &quot;Rectification may [indeed] also be requested after the proceedings before the EPO are terminated.&quot; (<template><target>EPO Guidelines</target><arg>a</arg><arg>iii</arg><arg>5</arg><arg>6</arg></template>).</extension><space/>In other words, a European patent in one Contracting State, i.e. a &quot;national&quot; European patent,<template><target>refn</target><arg>There is no consistent usage of a particular expression to refer to "the European patent in a particular designated Contracting State for which it is granted". The article uses the expression "a "national" European patent"</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/>is effectively independent of the same European patent in each other Contracting State, except for the opposition, limitation and revocation procedures. The<space/><link><target>Enforcement of European patents</target><part>enforcement of a European patent</part></link><space/>is dealt with by national law.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>64</arg><arg>3</arg></template></extension><space/>The abandonment, revocation or limitation of the European patent in one state does not affect the European patent in other states.</paragraph><paragraph>The EPC provides however the possibility for a group of member states to allow European patents to have a unitary character also after grant. Until now, only Liechtenstein and Switzerland have opted to create a unified protection area (see<space/><link><target>Unitary patent (Switzerland and Liechtenstein)</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swisstreaty"><link type='external' href='http://archive.epo.org/epo/pubs/oj1980/p393_440.pdf'>Treaty between the Swiss Confederation and the Principality of Liechtenstein on Patent Protection (Patent Treaty) of 22 December 1978</link>,<space/><link><target>OJ EPO</target></link><space/>1980, 407, or<space/><template><target>de icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.admin.ch/opc/de/classified-compilation/19780344/index.html'>Vertrag zwischen der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft und dem Frstentum Liechtenstein ber den Schutz der Erfindungspatente</link><space/>Die Bundesbehrden der Schweizerischen Eidgenossenschaft.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Upon filing of a European patent application, all 38 Contracting States are automatically designated,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>79</arg><arg>1</arg></template></extension><space/>unless, when filing the application, the applicant withdraws one or more designations. This may be important to avoid conflicts with national (non European patent) applications.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>EPO Guidelines</target><arg>a</arg><arg>iii</arg><arg>11</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>4</arg></template></extension><space/>Designations may also be withdrawn after filing, at any time before grant. Upon grant, a European patent has immediate effect in all designated States, but to remain effective, yearly renewal fees have to be paid, in each State, and in certain countries translation requirements have to be met.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Legal basis and implementation</heading><paragraph>Three instruments were proposed for the implementation of the unitary patent:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.epo.org/law-practice/legislative-initiatives/eu-patent.html</arg><arg name="work">European Patent Office</arg><arg name="title">Unitary patent / EU patent</arg><arg name="date">16 May 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 June 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Regulation of the European Parliament and of the Council implementing enhanced co-operation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection</listitem><listitem>Council Regulation implementing enhanced co-operation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection with regard to the applicable translation arrangements</listitem><listitem>Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</listitem></list><paragraph>The system is based on EU law as well as the European Patent Convention (EPC).<space/><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>142</arg></template><space/>provides the legal basis for establishing a common system of patents for Parties to the EPC.<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>142</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>and its footnote 168:<space/></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;The group of EU member states participating in enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection implemented that cooperation by Regulation (EU) No. 1257/2012 of the European Parliament and of the Council and Council Regulation No. 1260/2012 (OJ EPO 2013, 110, 111 and 132), thereby availing itself of the authorisation given in Article 142(1) and the provisions of Part IX of the EPC. The third component of the EU &quot;patent package&quot; is the Agreement on a Unified Patent Court (OJ EPO 2013, 286, 287).&quot;</listitem></list></extension><space/>Previously, only Liechtenstein and Switzerland had used this possibility to create a unified protection area (see<space/><link><target>Unitary patent (Switzerland and Liechtenstein)</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swisstreaty"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Regulations regarding the unitary patent</heading><paragraph><template><target>Infobox EU legislation</target><arg name="type">Regulation
</arg><arg name="title">1257/2012: Implementing enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection<br><space/>1260/2012: Implementing enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection with regard to the applicable translation arrangements
</arg><arg name="number">1257/2012 & 1260/2012
</arg><arg name="Enhancedcooperation">Yes
</arg><arg name="Parties">All current EU members, except Spain and Croatia.
</arg><arg name="madeby">[[European Parliament]] and [[Council of the European Union|Council]]
</arg><arg name="madeunder">[[s:Consolidated version of the Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union/Title VII: Common Rules on Competition, Taxation and Approximation of Laws#Article 118|Article 118]] of the [[Treaty on the Functioning of the European Union|TFEU]], and<space/><br>[http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri</arg><arg name="OJref"><small>L361, 31.12.2012, p.1-8, 89-92</small>
</arg><arg name="OJrefurl">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri</arg><arg name="made">17 December 2012
</arg><arg name="commenced">20 January 2013
</arg><arg name="implementation">Applies from the date the [[Agreement on a Unified Patent Court|UPC Agreement]] enters into force 
</arg><arg name="CommProp"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ESCOpin"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ParlOpin"><space/>
</arg><arg name="Reports"><space/>
</arg><arg name="replaces"><space/>
</arg><arg name="amends"><space/>
</arg><arg name="amendedby"><space/>
</arg><arg name="replacedby">
</arg><arg name="status">Pending
</arg></template>The first two regulations were approved by the<space/><link><target>European Parliament</target></link><space/>on 11 December 2012, with future application set for the 25 member states then participating in the<space/><link><target>Enhanced cooperation#Unitary patent</target><part>enhanced cooperation for a unitary patent</part></link><space/>(all current EU member states except Croatia, Italy and Spain).<extension extension_name='ref' name="EUPARL"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://euobserver.com/political/118490<space/></arg><arg name="title">'Historic day' as EU patent deal ends 40-year wait<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Fox<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 December 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">EUobserver.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 December 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Delay2July"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Toch nog tegenslag voor Europees patent</arg><arg name="work">[[nu.nl]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nu.nl/economie/2849596/toch-nog-tegenslag-europees-patent.html</arg><arg name="language">Dutch</arg><arg name="date">2 July 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 July 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.europarl.europa.eu/oeil/popups/ficheprocedure.do?reference</arg><arg name="work">Legal Observatory of the European Parliament</arg><arg name="title">Enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection: implementation</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri</arg><arg name="title">Enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection: implementation; translation arrangements</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2012</arg><arg name="work">Legal Observatory of the European Parliament</arg></template></extension><space/>The instruments were adopted as regulations EU 1257/2012 and 1260/2012 on 17 December 2012, and entered into force in January 2013.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1257"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Regulation 1260"></extension><space/>Following a request by the government of Italy,<extension extension_name='ref' name="italyrequest"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work">Council of the European Union</arg><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/register/en/content/out/?&typ</arg><arg name="title">Notification by Italy of its intention to participate in the enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection and in the enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection with regard to the applicable translation arrangements</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 July 2015</arg><arg name="date">7 July 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>it became a participant of the unitary patent regulations in September 2015.&lt;ref name=&quot;italy/&gt;</paragraph><paragraph>As of July 2015, neither of the two remaining non-participants in the Unitary Patent (Spain and Croatia) had requested the European Commission to participate.</paragraph><paragraph>Although formally the Regulations will apply to all 26 participating states from the moment the<space/><link><target>Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</target><part>UPC Agreement</part></link><space/>enters into force for the first group of ratifiers,<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">notes</arg><arg name="name">"UPC entry into force"</arg></template><space/>the unitary effect of newly granted unitary patents will only extend to those of the 26 states where the UPC Agreement has entered into force.<extension extension_name='ref' name="geographical extension"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.unified-patent-court.org/images/documents/enhanced-european-patent-system.pdf</arg><arg name="title">An Enhanced European Patent System</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="publisher">Unified Patent Court</arg><arg name="date">30 June 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Role of the European Patent Office</heading><paragraph>Some administrative tasks relating to the European patents with unitary effect will be performed by the European Patent Office.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite video</target><arg name="people">Ingo Beckedorf<space/></arg><arg name="date">8–9 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="title">EPO boards of appeal and key decisions: The future of the boards in the light of the possible introduction of the unitary patent and Unified Patent Court (Part 3 of 3)<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://e-courses.epo.org/wbts/caselaw2012/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">European Patent Office<space/></arg><arg name="location">Munich, Germany<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 November 2013<space/></arg><arg name="minutes">5:33 to 5:45</arg></template></extension><space/>These tasks include the collection of<space/><link><target>renewal fees</target></link><space/>and registration of unitary effect upon grant, exclusive licenses and statements that licenses are available to any person. Decisions of the European Patent Office regarding the unitary patent are open to appeal to the Unified Patent Court, rather than to the<space/><link><target>EPO Boards of Appeal</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>s:Agreement on a Unified Patent Court#Article 32 .E2.80.93 Competence of the Court</target><part>Article 32(1)i, Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</part></link>, implementing Article 9.3 of<space/><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:361:0001:0008:EN:PDF'>Regulation 1257/2012</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Translation requirements</heading><paragraph>For a unitary patent ultimately no translation will be required, which significantly reduces the cost for protection in the whole area. However, during a transition period of maximum 12 years one translation needs to be provided, either into English if the application is in French or German, or into any EU official language if the application is in English. In addition,<space/><link><target>machine translation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>will be provided, which will be, in the words of the regulation, &quot;for information purposes only and should not have any legal effect&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In several contracting states, for &quot;national&quot; European patents a translation has to be filed within a three-month time limit after the publication of grant in the<space/><link><target>European Patent Bulletin</target></link><space/>under<space/><template><target>EPC Article</target><arg>65</arg></template>,<template><target>refn</target><arg>{{EPC Article|2|2}} provides that "[t]he European patent shall, in each of the Contracting States for which it is granted, have the effect of and be subject to the same conditions as a national patent granted by that State, unless this Convention provides otherwise." The provision of Article 65 EPC may therefore be viewed as an exception to Article 2(2) EPC. See also [[London Agreement (2000)]].</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/>otherwise the patent is considered never to have existed (void ab initio) in that state. For the 20 parties to the<space/><link><target>London Agreement (2000)</target><part>London Agreement</part></link>, this requirement has already been abolished or reduced (e.g. by dispensing with the requirement if the patent is available in English, and/or only requiring translation of the<space/><link><target>claim (patent)</target><part>claim</part><trail>s</trail></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="translation requirements for national EPs"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.epo.org/law-practice/legal-texts/html/natlaw/en/iv/index.htm</arg><arg name="title">National law relating to EPC: IV. Translation requirements after grant</arg><arg name="publisher">European Patent Office</arg><arg name="date"></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 August 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Translation requirements for the participating states in the enhanced cooperation for a unitary patent are shown below:</paragraph><table class="wikitable sortable"><tablerow><tablehead>Participating member State</tablehead><tablehead>Translation requirements for a non-unitary European patent<extension extension_name='ref' name="translation requirements for national EPs"></extension></tablehead><tablehead>Translation requirements for a unitary patent</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>France, Germany, Ireland, Luxembourg, United Kingdom</tablecell><tablecell>None</tablecell><tablecell rowspan="4">None (transitional period: one translation, so that the unitary patent is available during the transitional period in English and at least another EU official language)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Latvia, Lithuania,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.epo.org/law-practice/legal-texts/html/natlaw/en/iv/lt.htm</arg><arg name="title">National Law, Chapter IV: Lithuania. Translation requirements after grant</arg><arg name="publisher">European Patent Office</arg><arg name="date">28 January 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Slovenia</tablecell><tablecell>Claims in the official language of the concerned State</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Denmark, Finland, Hungary, Netherlands, Sweden</tablecell><tablecell>Description in English, claims in the official language of the concerned State</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Austria, Belgium, Bulgaria, Cyprus, Czech Republic, Estonia, Greece, Malta, Poland, Portugal, Romania, Slovakia</tablecell><tablecell>Translation of the complete patent in an official language of the concerned State</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='4'>Unitary patent as an object of property</heading><paragraph>Article 7 of Regulation 1257/2012 provides that, as an object of property, a European patent with unitary effect will be treated &quot;in its entirety and in all participating Member States as a national patent of the participating Member State in which that patent has unitary effect and in which the applicant had her/his residence or principal place of business or, by default, had a place of business on the date of filing the application for the European patent.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ullrich">Ullrich, Hanns, The Property Aspects of the European Patent with Unitary Effect: A National Perspective for a European Prospect? (April 15, 2013). Published in: I. Govaere, D. Hanf (eds.): Scrutinizing Internal and External Dimensions of European Law, Les dimensions internes et externs du droit europen lpreuve Liber Amicorum Paul Demaret, Brussels 2013, 481; Max Planck Institute for Intellectual Property &amp; Competition Law Research Paper No. 13-17 . Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=2347921</extension><space/>When the applicant had no domicile in a participating Member State,<space/><link><target>German law</target></link><space/>will apply.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ullrich"></extension><space/>Ullrich has the criticized the system, which is similar to the<space/><link><target>Community Trademark</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Community Design</target></link>, as being &quot;in conflict with both the purpose of the creation of unitary patent protection and with primary EU law.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ullrich"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Implementation of the regulations at the EPO</heading><paragraph>In January 2013, after the two regulations about the unitary patent had entered into force, but before the regulations applied, the participating member states in the unitary patent established (as member states of the European Patent Convention) a Select Committee of the<space/><link><target>Administrative Council of the European Patent Organisation</target></link><space/>in order to prepare the work for implementation of the provisions. The committee held its inaugural meeting on 20 March 2013. The work of the Select Committee has to proceed in parallel to the work of the Preparatory Committee for the creation of the Unified Patent Court. Implementation of the Unitary Patent - including the legal, administrative and financial measures - shall be completed in due time before the entry into operation of the Unified Patent Court. In May 2015, the communicated target date for completion of the remaining preparatory work of the Select Committee was 30 June 2015.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://data.consilium.europa.eu/doc/document/ST-9107-2015-INIT/en/pdf</arg><arg name="title">Implementing the Patent Package: Fourth progress report</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="publisher">Council of the EU</arg><arg name="date">21 May 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>The Committee reached agreement on the level of the renewal fees June 2015, while it stated that a decision on the distribution of those fees among member states was in Autumn 2015.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.epo.org/news-issues/news/2015/20150624.html</arg><arg name="title">Business-friendly fee pattern adopted for the unitary patent</arg><arg name="publisher">EPO</arg><arg name="date">25 June 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Unified Patent Court</arg></template><template><target>Location map+</target><arg><space/>European Union
</arg><arg name="width"><space/>360
</arg><arg name="caption">Locations of the Court of First Instance (Central division, "Court"), the Court of Appeal and the Arbitration center. In addition, several local and regional divisions of the Court of First Instance will be established.
</arg><arg name="places">
 {{Location map~ | European Union
 | label<space/></arg></template>The Agreement on a Unified Patent Court provides the legal basis for the Unified Patent Court: a patent court for European patents (with and without unitary effect), with jurisdiction in those countries where the Agreement is in effect. In addition to regulations regarding the court structure, it also contains substantive provisions relating to the right to prevent use of an invention and allowed use by non patent proprietors (e.g. for private non-commercial use), preliminary and permanent injunctions.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Parties</heading><paragraph>The Agreement was signed on 19 February 2013 by 24 EU member states, including all states then participating in the enhanced co-operation measures except<space/><link><target>Bulgaria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Poland</target></link>, while Italy, which did not originally join the enhanced co-operation measures but subsequently signed up, did sign the UPC agreement.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIGN"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/intm/135593.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Signing of the Unified Patent Court agreement</arg><arg name="date">19 February 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 February 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Council of the European Union]]</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/indprop/patent/ratification/index_en.htm</arg><arg name="title">Unitary patent – ratification progress</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 February 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">[[European Commission]]</arg></template></extension><space/>The agreement remains open to accession for all remaining EU member states, and Bulgaria signed the agreement on 5 March.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIGN"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite press release</target><arg name="title">Single European Patent: a major achievement but still some way to go</arg><arg name="url">http://europa.eu/rapid/press-release_SPEECH-13-132_en.htm?locale</arg><arg name="work">European Commission</arg><arg name="date">18 February 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Meanwhile, Poland decided to wait to see how the new patent system works before joining due to concerns that it would harm their economy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.worldipreview.com/news/will-poland-join-the-unitary-patent-system</arg><arg name="title">Will Poland join the Unitary Patent system?</arg><arg name="date">5 February 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 February 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">[[World Intellectual Property Review]]</arg></template></extension><space/>States which do not participate in the unitary patent regulations can still become parties to the UPC agreement, which would allow the new court to handle European patents validated in the country.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.europeanvoice.com/article/imported/countries-to-sign-up-to-unitary-patent-system-/76422.aspx</arg><arg name="title">Countries to sign up to unitary patent system</arg><arg name="last">Wishart</arg><arg name="first">Ian</arg><arg name="date">14 February 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Entry into force for the UPC will take place after 13 states (including Germany, France and the United Kingdom as the three states with the most patents in force) have ratified the Agreement.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EUPARL"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="SIGN"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/ueDocs/cms_Data/docs/pressData/en/intm/135391.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Background note – Competitiveness Council – Brussels, 18 and 19 February 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Court of Justice of the European Union]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 February 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 February 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="EPO"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.epo.org/law-practice/unitary/faq.html</arg><arg name="work">European Patent Organisation</arg><arg name="title">Unitary patent – frequently asked questions<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">12 December 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://consilium.europa.eu/homepage/highlights/eu-unitary-patent-–-a-historical-breakthrough?lang</arg><arg name="title">EU unitary patent – a historical breakthrough<space/></arg><arg name="work">Council of the European Union<space/></arg><arg name="date">29 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>As of July 2014, the agreement has been ratified by 5 states (including 1 of the required ratifiers: France).</paragraph><heading level='4'>Jurisdiction</heading><paragraph>The Unified Patent Court will have exclusive jurisdiction in<space/><link><target>patent infringement</target><part>infringement</part></link><space/>and revocation proceedings involving European patents with unitary effect, and during a transition period non-exclusive jurisdiction (that the patent holder can be opt out from) regarding European patents without unitary effect in the states where the Agreement applies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://documents.epo.org/projects/babylon/eponet.nsf/0/889924E4E28C5D0CC12578D3003F5046/$File/st11533_en.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 June 2011</arg><arg name="work">Council of the European Union<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="title">Draft agreement on a Unified Patent Court and draft Statute – Presidency text<space/></arg><arg name="quote">(...) the Unified Patent Court will be a court common to the Contracting Member States, thus situated within the judicial system of the European Union, with exclusive competence on their territories for European patents with unitary effect and European patents designating one or more Member States party to this Agreement</arg></template></extension><space/>It furthermore has jurisdiction to hear cases against decisions of the European Patent Office regarding unitary patents. As a court of several member states of the European Union it may (Court of First Instance) or must (Court of Appeal) ask prejudicial questions to the<space/><link><target>European Court of Justice</target></link><space/>when the interpretation of EU law (including the two unitary patent regulations, but excluding the UPC Agreement) is not obvious.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Organization</heading><paragraph>The court would have two divisions: a court of first instance and a court of appeal. The court of appeal and the registry would have their seats in Luxembourg, while the central division of the court of first instance would have its seat in Paris. The central division would have thematic branches in London and<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sciencebusiness27-06-12"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://bulletin.sciencebusiness.net/news/75784/Deal-reached-Unitary-patent-court-to-have-three-homes<space/></arg><arg name="title">Deal reached: Unitary patent court to have three homes<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work">Science</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/ec/131388.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">European Council, 28/29 June 2012, Conclusions (EUCO 76/12, CO EUR 4, CONCL 2)</arg><arg name="date">29 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">European Council (General Secretariat of the Council)<space/></arg><arg name="location">Brussels<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Given the highly specialised nature of patent litigation and the need to maintain high quality standards, thematic clusters will be created in two sections of the Central Division, one in London (chemistry, including pharmaceuticals, classification C, human necessities, classification A), the other in Munich (mechanical engineering, classification F).<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The court of first instance may further have local and regional divisions in all member states that wish to set up such divisions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Geographical scope of and request for unitary effect</heading><paragraph>While the regulations formally apply to all 26 member states participating in the<space/><link><target>Enhanced cooperation#Unitary patent</target><part>enhanced cooperation for a unitary patent</part></link>, from the date the<space/><link><target>Unified Patent Court Agreement</target><part>UPC agreement</part></link><space/>has entered into force for the first group of ratifiers,<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">notes</arg><arg name="name">"UPC entry into force"</arg></template><space/>unitary patents will only extend to the territory of those participating member states where the UPC Agreement had entered into force when the unitary effect was registered. If the unitary effect territory subsequently expands to additional participating member states for which the UPC Agreement later enters into force, this will be reflected for all subsequently registered unitary patents, but the territorial scope of the unitary effect of existing unitary patents will not be extended to these states.<extension extension_name='ref' name="geographical extension"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unitary effect can be requested up to one month after grant of the European patent, with retroactive effect from the date of grant. However, according to the<space/><italics>Draft Rules Relating to Unitary Patent Protection</italics>, unitary effect would be registered only if the European patent has been granted with the same set of<space/><link><target>claim (patent)</target><part>claim</part><trail>s</trail></link><template><target>refn</target><arg>A European patent may be granted by the EPO with claims which are, for one or more States, different from those applicable to the other designated States. This rare situation may arise by virtue of {{EPC Rule|18|2}} or {{EPC Rule|138}}.</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/>for all the 26 participating member states in the regulations,<template><target>refn</target><arg name="This requires that all 26 states participating in the [[Enhanced cooperation#Unitary patent|enhanced cooperation regulations]] have been designated upon filing of the European patent application. For European patent applications filed after 1 April 2009, all Contracting States party to the [[European Patent Convention|EPC]] at the time of filing of the application are automatically designated,<ref>{{cite web|url">http://www.epo.org/law-practice/legal-texts/html/guidelines/e/a_iii_11_2_2.htm|title</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template><space/>whether the unitary effect applies to them or not.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bristowsupc.com/assets/files/Draft%20Unitary%20Patent%20rules%20-%20June%202014.PDF</arg><arg name="title">Rules Relating to Unitary Patent Protection, Rule 5.I.2.</arg><arg name="work">President of the European Patent Office</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 July 2014</arg><arg name="date">6 June 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>European patents automatically become a bundle of &quot;national&quot; European patents upon grant. Upon the grant of unitary effect, the &quot;national&quot; European patents will retroactively be considered to never have existed in the territories where the unitary patent has effect. The unitary effect does not affect &quot;national&quot; European patents in states where the unitary patent does not apply. Any &quot;national&quot; European patents applying outside the &quot;unitary effect&quot; zone will co-exist with the unitary patent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="geographical extension"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Special territories of participating member states</heading><paragraph>As the unitary patent is introduced by an EU regulation, it is expected to not only be valid in the mainland territory of the participating member states that are party to the UPC, but also in those of their<space/><link><target>Special member state territories and the European Union</target><part>special territories</part></link><space/>that are part of the European Union. As of April 2014, this includes the following fourteen territories:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Cyprus:<space/><link><target>United Nations Buffer Zone in Cyprus</target><part>UN Buffer Zone</part></link></listitem><listitem>Finland:<space/><link><target>land</target></link></listitem><listitem>France:<space/><link><target>French Guiana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Guadeloupe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Martinique</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mayotte</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Runion</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Collectivity of Saint Martin</target><part>Saint Martin</part></link></listitem><listitem>Germany:<space/><link><target>Bsingen am Hochrhein</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Helgoland</target></link></listitem><listitem>Greece:<space/><link><target>Mount Athos</target></link></listitem><listitem>Portugal:<space/><link><target>Azores</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Madeira</target></link></listitem><listitem>United Kingdom:<space/><link><target>Gibraltar</target></link><template><target>refn</target><arg name="Gibraltar automatically participates EU regulations as part of the UK. As of June 2014, the UK had neither extended the [[European Patent Convention]] nor the [[Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property|Paris Convention]] (which is a requirement for becoming an EPC party)<ref>{{cite web|url">http://www.wipo.int/treaties/en/remarks.jsp?cnty_id</arg><arg name="group">notes</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>In addition to the territories above, the<space/><link><target>European Patent Convention</target></link><space/>has been extended by three member states participating in the<space/><link><target>Enhanced cooperation#Unitary patent</target><part>enhanced cooperation for a unitary patent</part></link><space/>to cover some of their dependent territories outside the European Union:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://archive.epo.org/epo/pubs/oj013/04_13/04_2523.pdf'>Synopsis of the territorial field of application of international patent treaties (situation on 1 March 2013)</link>, EPO OJ 4/2013, p. 269, footnote 3</extension><space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>France:<space/><link><target>French Polynesia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>French Southern and Antarctic Lands</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Caledonia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saint Barthlemy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saint-Pierre and Miquelon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wallis and Futuna</target></link></listitem><listitem>Netherlands:<space/><link><target>Caribbean Netherlands</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Curacao</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sint Maarten</target></link></listitem><listitem>UK:<space/><link><target>Isle of Man</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Among the dependencies in the second list, the<space/><link><target>Isle of Man</target></link><space/>intends to apply the unitary patent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Implementation order"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/318769/Consultation_Technical_Review_Unified_Patents_Court.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Technical Review and Call for Evidence on Secondary Legislation Implementing the Agreement on a Unified Patent Court and EU Regulations Establishing the Unitary Patent</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="publisher">Intellectual Property Office</arg><arg name="work">Annex C: Draft Statutory Instrument</arg><arg name="date">10 June 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Draft Dutch implementation provision provide for the &quot;Dutch European Patent&quot; to exist in parallel with the unitary patent: while the unitary patent will cover the European territory, the Dutch EP will be valid in<space/><link><target>Caribbean Netherlands</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Curacao</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sint Maarten</target></link><space/>and be subject to regular translation and renewal requirements.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.internetconsultatie.nl/europeesoctrooipakket</arg><arg name="title">Consultaties, Wijzigingswet Overeenkomst betreffende een eengemaakt octrooigerecht en Verordening (EU) 1257/2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 July 2015</arg><arg name="work">Government of the Netherlands</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Costs</heading><paragraph>Translation requirements as well as the requirement to pay yearly patent fees in all countries in which a European patent is designated, presently renders the European patent system costly in the European Union. In an impact assessment the European Commission estimated that the costs of obtaining a patent in all 27 EU countries would drop from over 32 000 euro (mainly due to translation costs) to 6 500 euro (for the combination of an EU, Spanish and Italian patent) due to introduction of the EU patent. Per capita costs of an EU patent were estimated at just 6 euro/million in the original 25 participating countries (and 12 euro/million in the 27 EU countries for protection with an EU, Italian and Spanish patent).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/indprop/docs/patent/sec2011-482-final_en.pdf</arg><arg name="title">IMPACT ASSESSMENT Accompanying document to the Proposal for a REGULATION OF THE EUROPEAN PARLIAMENT AND THE COUNCIL implementing enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection and Proposal for a COUNCIL REGULATION implementing enhanced cooperation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection with regard to the applicable translation arrangements</arg><arg name="work">European Commission</arg><arg name="page">36</arg><arg name="date">13 April 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>How the EU Commission has presented the expected cost savings has however been sharply criticized as exaggerated and based on unrealistic assumptions. The EU Commission has notably considered the costs for validating a European patent in 27 countries while in reality only about 1% of all granted European patents are currently validated in all 27 contracting states. Based on more realistic assumptions, the cost savings are expected to be much lower than actually claimed by the Commission.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.platow.de/eu-patent--kostenreduzierungen-deutlich-uebertrieben/4444686.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">EU-Patent – Kostenreduzierungen deutlich übertrieben<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rox<space/></arg><arg name="first">Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 June 2013<space/></arg><arg name="website">platow.de<space/></arg><arg name="language">German<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">EU Patent - Cost reductions clearly exaggerated<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 July 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Earlier attempts</heading><heading level='3'>1970s and 1980s: proposed Community Patent Convention</heading><paragraph>Work on a Community patent started in the 1970s, but the resulting Community Patent Convention (CPC) was a failure.</paragraph><paragraph>The &quot;<link><target>Luxembourg</target></link><space/>Conference on the Community Patent&quot; took place in 1975 and the<space/><bold>Convention for the European Patent for the common market</bold>, or (Luxembourg) Community Patent Convention (CPC), was signed at Luxembourg on 15 December 1975, by the 9 member states of the<space/><link><target>European Economic Community</target></link><space/>at that time.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citeweb</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri</arg><arg name="title">Convention for the European patent for the common market</arg><arg name="date">1976-01-26</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-06-27</arg><arg name="journal">[[Official Journal of the European Communities]]</arg><arg name="volume">L 17/1</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the CPC never entered into force. It was not ratified by enough countries.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citeweb</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">The Unitary EU Patent System</arg><arg name="year">2015</arg><arg name="first1">Justine</arg><arg name="last1">Pila</arg><arg name="first2">Christopher</arg><arg name="last2">Wadlow</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Bloomsbury Publishing]]</arg><arg name="pages">33-35</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Fourteen years later, the<space/><bold>Agreement relating to Community patents</bold><space/>was made at Luxembourg on 15 December 1989.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citeweb</target><arg name="url">http://eur-lex.europa.eu/legal-content/EN/TXT/?uri</arg><arg name="title">Agreement relating to Community patents</arg><arg name="date">1989-12-30</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-06-27</arg><arg name="journal">[[Official Journal of the European Communities]]</arg><arg name="volume">L 401/1</arg></template></extension><space/>It attempted to revive the CPC project, but also failed. This Agreement consisted of an amended version of the original Community Patent Convention. Twelve states signed the Agreement:<space/><link><target>Belgium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link>, France, Germany,<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Republic of Ireland</target><part>Ireland</part></link>, Italy,<space/><link><target>Luxembourg</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link>, Spain, and United Kingdom. All of those states would need to have ratified the Agreement to cause it to enter into force,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(01):EN:NOT'>89/695/EEC: Agreement relating to Community patents, Done at Luxembourg on 15 December 1989, Article 10</link></extension><space/>but only seven did so:<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link>, France, Germany,<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Luxembourg</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>, and United Kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citeweb</target><arg name="url">http://www.consilium.europa.eu/en/documents-publications/agreements-conventions/agreement/?aid</arg><arg name="title">Agreement relating to Community Patents</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-06-27</arg><arg name="publisher">Council of the European Union</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Official Journal of the European Patent Office</target></link><space/>4/2006 p. 328<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.european-patent-office.org/epo/pubs/oj006/04_06/04_3086.pdf'>(pdf)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, a majority of member states of the EEC at that time introduced some harmonisation into their national patent laws in anticipation of the entry in force of the CPC. A more substantive harmonisation took place at around the same time to take account of the European Patent Convention and the<space/><link><target>Convention on the Unification of Certain Points of Substantive Law on Patents for Invention</target><part>Strasbourg Convention</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>2000 to 2004: EU Regulation proposal</heading><paragraph>In 2000, renewed efforts from the European Union resulted in a Community Patent<space/><link><target>European Union regulation</target><part>Regulation</part></link><space/>proposal, sometimes abbreviated as<space/><bold>CPR</bold>. It provides that the patent, once it has been granted by the European Patent Office (EPO) in one of its procedural languages (English, German or French) and published in that language, with a translation of the claims into the two other procedural languages, will be valid without any further translation. This proposal is aimed to achieve a considerable reduction in translation costs.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, additional translations could become necessary in legal proceedings against a suspected infringer. In such a situation, a suspected infringer who has been unable to consult the text of the patent in the official language of the Member State in which he is domiciled, is presumed, until proven otherwise, not to have knowingly infringed the patent. To protect a suspected infringer who, in such a situation, has not acted in a deliberate manner, it is provided that the proprietor of the patent will not be able to obtain damages in respect of the period prior to the translation of the patent being notified to the infringer.</paragraph><paragraph>The proposed Community Patent Regulation should also establish a court holding exclusive jurisdiction to invalidate issued patents; thus, a Community Patent's validity will be the same in all EU member states. This court will be attached to the present<space/><link><target>European Court of Justice</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Court of First Instance</target></link><space/>through use of provisions in the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Nice</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Discussion regarding the Community patent had made clear progress in 2003 when a political agreement was reached on 3 March 2003. However, one year later in March 2004 under the Irish<space/><link><target>Presidency of the Council of the European Union</target><part>presidency</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Council of the European Union#Configurations</target><part>Competitiveness Council</part></link><space/>failed to agree on the details of the Regulation. In particular the time delays for translating the claims and the authentic text of the claims in case of an infringement remained problematic issues throughout discussions and in the end proved insoluble.</paragraph><paragraph>In view of the difficulties in reaching an agreement on the community patent,<extension extension_name='ref'>Axel H. Horns,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ipjur.com/blog2/index.php?/archives/138-A-Unified-European-Patent-System-The-Historical-Perspective.html#extended'>A Unified European Patent System The Historical Perspective</link>, IP::JUR blog, 18 February 2010. Consulted on 20 February 2010.</extension><space/>other legal agreements have been proposed outside the European Union legal framework to reduce the cost of translation (of patents when granted) and<space/><link><target>lawsuit</target><part>litigation</part></link>, namely the<space/><link><target>London Agreement (2000)</target><part>London Agreement</part></link>, which entered into force on 1 May 2008and which has reduced the number of countries requiring translation of European patents granted nowadays under the European Patent Convention, and the corresponding costs to obtain a European patent<extension extension_name='ref'>Bruno van Pottelsberghe de la Potterie, Malwina Mejer,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.springerlink.com/content/f861125075v61964/'>&quot;The London Agreement and the cost of patenting in Europe&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>European Journal of Law and Economics</target></link>, Vol. 29, Number 2, April 2010, pages 211237.</extension><space/>and the<space/><link><target>European Patent Litigation Agreement</target></link><space/>(EPLA), a proposal that has now lapsed.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Reactions to the failure</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:ProdiBari.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Romano Prodi</target></link><space/>(here on a picture taken in 2006) cited the failure to agree on a Europewide patent as a weak point of his five-year term as<space/><link><target>President of the European Commission</target></link>.</part></link>After the council in March 2004,<space/><link><target>European Commission</target><part>EU Commissioner</part></link><space/><link><target>Frits Bolkestein</target></link><space/>said that &quot;The failure to agree on the Community Patent I am afraid undermines the credibility of the whole enterprise to make Europe the most competitive economy in the world by 2010.&quot; Adding:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="It is a mystery to me how Ministers at the so-called 'Competitiveness Council' can keep a straight face when they adopt conclusions for the Spring European Council on making Europe more competitive and yet in the next breath backtrack on the political agreement already reached on the main principles of the Community Patent in March of last year. I can only hope that one day the vested, [[protectionism|protectionist]] interests that stand in the way of agreement on this vital measure will be sidelined by the over-riding importance and interests of European manufacturing industry and Europe's competitiveness. That day has not yet come.<ref>[http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference">MEMO/04/58 Commission Press Communique, 12 March 2004, "Results of the Competitiveness Council of Ministers, Brussels, 11 March 2004 Internal Market, Enterprise and Consumer Protection issues"]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jonathan Todd, Commission's Internal Market spokesman, declared:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Normally, after the common political approach, the text of the regulation is agreed very quickly. Instead, some Member States appear to have changed their positions. (...) It is extremely unfortunate that European industry's competitiveness, innovation and R&D are being sacrificed for the sake of preserving narrow vested interests.<ref>[http://cordis.europa.eu/itt/itt-en/04-3/policy03.htm cordis.europa.eu, ''Patently unclear'', 26 May 2004]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>European Commission President<space/><link><target>Romano Prodi</target></link>, asked to evaluate his five-year term, cites as his weak point the failure of many EU governments to implement the &quot;<link><target>Lisbon Agenda</target></link>&quot;, agreed in 2001. In particular, he cited the failure to agree on a Europewide patent, or even the languages to be used for such a patent, &quot;because member states did not accept a change in the rules; they were not coherent&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Wall Street Journal</target></link>, 25 October 2004</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Support for the Regulation</heading><paragraph>There is support for the Community patent from various quarters. From the point of view of the European Commission the Community Patent is an essential step towards creating a level playing field for trade within the European Union. For smaller businesses, if the Community patent achieves its aim of providing a relatively inexpensive way of obtaining patent protection across a wide trading area, then there is also support.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For larger businesses, however, other issues come into play, which have tended to dilute overall support. In general, these businesses recognise that the current European Patent system provides the best possible protection given the need to satisfy national sovereignty requirements such as regarding translation and enforcement. The Community Patent proposal was generally supported if it would do away with both of these issues, but there was some concern about the level of competence of the proposed European Patent Court. A business would be reluctant to obtain a Europe-wide patent if it ran the risk of being revoked by an inexperienced judge. Also, the question of translations would not go away unless the users of the system could see significant change in the position of some of the countries holding out for more of a patent specification to be translated on grant or before enforcement, it was understood that larger businesses (the bulk of the users of the patent system) would be unlikely to move away from the tried and tested European Patent.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Since 2005: stalemate and new debate</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Charlie McCreevy portrait.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>In 2007,<space/><link><target>Charlie McCreevy</target></link><space/>was quoted as saying that the proposal for an EU-wide patent was stuck in the<space/><link><target>mud</target></link>.</part></link>Thus, in 2005, the Community patent looked unlikely to be implemented in the near future. However, on 16 January 2006 the<space/><link><target>European Commission</target></link><space/>&quot;launched a public consultation on how future action in patent policy to create an EU-wide system of protection can best take account of stakeholders' needs.&quot; The Community patent was one of the issues the consultation focused on.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=IP/06/38&amp;amp;format=HTML&amp;amp;aged=0&amp;amp;language=EN&amp;amp;guiLanguage=en'>European Commission, Internal Market, ''Commission asks industry and other stakeholders for their views on future patent policy'', Brussels, 16 January 2006,</link></extension><space/>More than 2500 replies were received.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stakeholders debate"></extension><space/>According to the European Commission, the consultation showed that there is widespread support for the Community patent but not at any cost, and &quot;in particular not on the basis of the Common Political Approach reached by EU Ministers in 2003&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stakeholders debate"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In February 2007,<space/><link><target>European Commission</target><part>EU Commissioner</part></link><space/><link><target>Charlie McCreevy</target></link><space/>was quoted as saying:<template><target>quote</target><arg>The proposal for an EU-wide patent is stuck in the mud. It is clear to me from discussions with member states that there is no consensus at present on how to improve the situation.<ref>Chris Jones, [http://www.eupolitix.com/EN/News/200702/7be97fa5-3cb6-403f-aadf-103ad99a9950.htm ''McCreevy backs plans for single EU-US market''], TheParliament.com, 1 February 2007. Consulted on 2 February 2007.</ref><space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The European Commission released a white paper in April 2007 seeking to &quot;improve the patent system in Europe and revitalise the debate on this issue.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Commission of the European Communities,<link type='external' href='http://europa.eu/rapid/pressReleasesAction.do?reference=SPEECH/06/786&amp;amp;format=PDF&amp;amp;aged=0&amp;amp;language=EN&amp;amp;guiLanguage=en'>''Communication from the European Parliament and the Council Enhancing the patent system in Europe''</link>, Brussels, COM (2007), 29 March 2007</extension><space/>On 18 April 2007, at the European Patent Forum in<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link>, Germany,<space/><link><target>Gnter Verheugen</target></link>, Vice-President of the European Commission, said that his proposal to support the<space/><link><target>European economy</target></link><space/>was &quot;to have the London Agreement ratified by all member states, and to have a European patent judiciary set up, in order to achieve rapid implementation of the Community patent, which is indispensable&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="epo 20.04.07">European Patent Office web site,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.epo.org/focus/news/2007/070420.html'>''&quot;An incomplete European patent system puts European businesses at a competitive disadvantage&quot;''</link>. Consulted on 20 April 2007.</extension><space/>He further said that he believed this could be done within five years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="epo 20.04.07"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>CORDIS</target></link><space/>News,<space/><link type='external' href='http://cordis.europa.eu/fetch?CALLER=EN_NEWS&amp;amp;ACTION=D&amp;amp;SESSION=&amp;amp;RCN=27536'>''Forum on the future of IP vows to push ahead with Community Patent''</link>, 20 April 2007</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In October 2007, the Portuguese<space/><link><target>presidency of the Council of the European Union</target></link><space/>proposed an EU patent jurisdiction, &quot;borrowing heavily from the rejected draft European Patent Litigation Agreement (EPLA)&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Huw Jones,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.reuters.com/article/governmentFilingsNews/idUSL1128205820071011'>''EU president Portugal proposes new patent courts''</link>, Reuters, 11 October 2007.</extension><space/>In November 2007, EU ministers were reported to have made some progress towards a community patent legal system, with &quot;some specific results&quot; expected in 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'>Huw Jones,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/feedarticle?id=7097030'>''Ministers make progress along road to EU patent''</link><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">September 2009</arg></template>,<space/><link><target>The Guardian</target></link>, 22 November 2007. Consulted on 24 November 2007.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2008, the idea of using<space/><link><target>machine translation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to translate patents was proposed to solve the language issue, which is partially responsible for blocking progress on the community patent.<extension extension_name='ref'>James Nurton,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.managingip.com/Article/1918807/Translation-breakthrough-for-Community-patent.html'>''Translation breakthrough for Community patent''</link>,<space/><link><target>Managing Intellectual Property</target></link>, Weekly News, 26 April 2008. Consulted on 7 May 2008.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Council of the European Union,<space/><link type='external' href='http://register.consilium.europa.eu/pdf/en/08/st08/st08928.en08.pdf'>''Towards a Community patent Translation arrangements and distribution of fees''</link>, Working Document, 8928/08, 28 April 2008, pp 36.</extension><space/>Meanwhile, European Commissioner for Enterprise and Industry<space/><link><target>Gnter Verheugen</target></link><space/>declared at the European Patent Forum in May 2008 that there was an &quot;urgent need&quot; for a community patent.<extension extension_name='ref'>James Nurton,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.managingip.com/Article/1927639/Verheugen-adds-to-Community-patent-momentum.html'>''Verheugen adds to Community patent momentum''</link>, Managing Intellectual Property, Weekly News, 6 May 2008. Consulted on 7 May 2008.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Agreement in December 2009, and language issue</heading><paragraph>In December 2009, it was reported that the Swedish EU presidency had achieved a breakthrough in negotiations concerning the community patent. The breakthrough was reported to involve setting up a single patent court for the EU,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ipworld.com/ipwo/doc/view.htm?id=237175&amp;amp;searchCode=H'>EU patent finally on the horizon</link>, IPWorld, 7 December 2009. Consulted on 6 February 2010.</extension><space/>however ministers conceded much work remained to be done before the community patent would become a reality.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/8396279.stm'>EU moves towards common patent system (BBC, 4 December 2009)</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://euobserver.com/9/29099'>EU takes big step towards common patent system (EUObserver, 4 December 2009)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the agreed plan, the EU would accede to the<space/><link><target>European Patent Convention</target></link><space/>as a contracting state, and patents granted by the<space/><link><target>European Patent Office</target></link><space/>will, when validated for the EU, have unitary effect in the territory of the European Union.<extension extension_name='ref'>EPO web site,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.epo.org/topics/news/2009/20091208.html'>EU Council agrees on next steps regarding the Community patent (EU patent)</link>, News, 8 December 2009. Consulted on 15 January 2010.</extension><space/>On 10 November 2010, it was announced that no agreement had been reached and that, &quot;in spite of the progress made, [the Competitiveness Council of the European Union had] fallen short of unanimity by a small margin,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Council of the European Union,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.consilium.europa.eu/uedocs/cms_data/docs/pressdata/en/intm/117687.pdf'>Press Release 16041/10, Extraordinary Council meeting, Competitiveness (Internal Market, Industry, Research and Space), Brussels, 10 November 2010</link>. Consulted on 27 November 2010.</extension><space/>with commentators reporting that the Spanish representative, citing the aim to avoid any discrimination,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.euractiv.com/en/innovation/italy-and-spain-block-eu-wide-patent-talks-news-499638'>&quot;Italy and Spain block EU-wide patent talks&quot;</link>, Euractiv.com, 11 November 2010. Consulted on 27 November 2010.</extension><space/>had &quot;re-iterated at length the stubborn rejection of the Madrid Government of taking the 'Munich' three languages regime (English, German, French) of the European Patent Convention (EPC) as a basis for a future EU Patent.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ipjur.com/blog2/index.php?/archives/184-Spanish-Government-Knocking-Down-Compromise-On-EU-Patent-Languages-Regime.html'>Spanish Government Knocking Down Compromise On EU Patent Languages Regime</link>, IPJur blog, 10 November 2010. Consulted on 27 November 2010.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paris Convention for the Protection of Industrial Property</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Convention on the Unification of Certain Points of Substantive Law on Patents for Invention</target><part>Strasbourg Convention</part></link><space/>(1963)</listitem><listitem><link><target>European Patent Convention</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">notes</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Hilty, Reto; Jaeger, Thomas; Lamping, Matthias; Ullrich, Hanns<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 October 2012<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Unitary Patent Package: Twelve Reasons for Concern<space/></arg><arg name="series">Max Planck Institute for Intellectual Property & Competition Law Research Paper No. 12-12<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2139/ssrn.2169254<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ssrn.com/abstract</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 November 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem>L. McDonagh, 'Exploring perspectives of the Unified Patent Court and the Unitary Patent within the Business and Legal Communities' A Report Commissioned by the Intellectual Property Office (July 2014) available at<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/exploring-perspectives-of-the-up-and-upc'>UKIPO</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.epo.org/law-practice/unitary/unitary-patent.html'>Unitary patent</link><space/>on the European Patent Office web site</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ec.europa.eu/internal_market/indprop/patent/index_en.htm'>European Commission official website</link><space/>(Patents, Patent reform)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Formal texts of the European Union Patent and status of adoption</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:361:0001:0008:EN:PDF'>Regulation 1257/2012</link><space/>Implementing Enhanced co-operation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection (published 31 December 2012)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://register.consilium.europa.eu/pdf/en/12/st16/st16351.en12.pdf'>Agreement on a Unified Patent Court</link><space/>(international treaty between the 25 states, not in force)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=OJ:L:2012:361:0089:0092:EN:PDF'>Regulation 1260/2012</link><space/>implementing enhanced co-operation in the area of the creation of unitary patent protection with regard to the applicable translation arrangements (published 31 December 2012)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.upc.documents.eu.com/PDFs/2013-01-31_Rules_of_Procedure_Draft_14_(15829021_1).pdf'>Rules of procedure</link>, draft version 14 (published 31 January 2013)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bristowsupc.com/assets/files/Draft%20Unitary%20Patent%20rules%20-%20June%202014.PDF'>Rules Relating to Unitary Patent Protection</link>, Draft of 6 June 2014</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Non implemented instruments</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Amended Community Patent Convention (1989)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(01):EN:NOT'>1989's Agreement relating to Community patents</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(02):EN:NOT'>Implementing Regulations to the Convention for the European patent for the common market</link></listitem><listitem>Protocols related to<space/><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(03):EN:NOT'>Litigation</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(04):EN:NOT'>a common appeal court</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(05):EN:NOT'>its statute</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:41989A0695(06):EN:NOT'>modification of entry into force</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Proposal for a Council Regulation on the Community patent (2000)</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eur-lex.europa.eu/LexUriServ/LexUriServ.do?uri=CELEX:52000PC0412:EN:NOT'>Proposal of the Commission (28.11.2000)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ec.europa.eu/prelex/detail_dossier_real.cfm?CL=en&amp;amp;DosId=158078'>Current state of the legislation process</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Positions by various organisations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>April (French association)</target><part>April</part></link>:<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.unitary-patent.eu/'>Unitary patent: For a democratic innovation policy in Europe</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>European Patent Office</target><part>EPO</part></link>:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.epo.org/law-practice/legislative-initiatives/eu-patent.html'>on the EU patent</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Foundation for a Free Information Infrastructure</target><part>FFII</part></link>:<space/><link type='external' href='http://consultation.ffii.org/'>The Community Patent Consultation</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Free Software Foundation Europe</target><part>FSFE</part></link>:<space/><link type='external' href='http://fsfe.org/campaigns/swpat/current/unitary-patent.en.html'>EU: the unitary patent</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20060924145334/http://www.eurolinux.org/news/cpat01B/'>Eurolinux 2001: Appeal for a Lean and Balanced Community Patent</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Intellectual property laws of the European Union</target></template><template><target>European Patent Organisation</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Community Patent</target></template><link><target>Category:Enhanced cooperation</target><part>patent</part></link><link><target>Category:Patent law of the European Union</target></link><link><target>Category:Multi-speed Europe</target></link></paragraph></article>