<article title='Books_of_Kings'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target><arg>Book of Kings (disambiguation){{!}}Book of Kings</arg></template><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Nevi'im</arg><arg>historical</arg></template>The two<space/><bold>Books of Kings</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-he</target><arg>ספר מלכים</arg></template><space/><italics>Sepher M'lakhim</italics><space/>the two books were originally one)<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p.1</extension><space/>present the biblical view of<space/><link><target>history of ancient Israel and Judah</target></link><space/>from the death of<space/><link><target>David</target></link><space/>to the release of his successor<space/><link><target>Jehoiachin</target></link><space/>from imprisonment in Babylon, a period of some 400 years (<template><target>circa</target><arg>960</arg><arg>560&nbsp;BCE</arg></template>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sweeney">Sweeney, p.<link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=d4jn8uj49RIC&amp;amp;pg=PA1#v=snippet&amp;amp;q=960&amp;amp;f=false'>1</link></extension><space/>It concludes a series of books running from<space/><link><target>Book of Joshua</target><part>Joshua</part></link><space/>through<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Books of Samuel</target><part>Samuel</part></link>, which make up the section of the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>called the<space/><link><target>Former Prophets</target></link>; this series is also often referred to as the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link>, a body of writing which scholars believe was written to provide a theological explanation for the<space/><link><target>Siege of Jerusalem (587 BC)</target><part>destruction of the Jewish kingdom</part></link><space/>by Babylon in 586&amp;nbsp;BCE and a foundation for a return from exile.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sweeney"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contents</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Saabaghiberti.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Solomon greeting the Queen of Sheba gate of<space/><link><target>Florence Baptistry</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>David</target></link><space/>dies and<space/><link><target>Solomon</target></link><space/>comes to the throne. At the beginning of his reign he assumes God's promises to David and brings splendour to Israel and peace and prosperity to his people.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p.19</extension><space/>The centrepiece of Solomon's reign is the building of the<space/><link><target>Temple of Solomon</target><part>First Temple</part></link>: the claim that this took place 480 years after<space/><link><target>the Exodus</target></link><space/>from Egypt marks it as a key event in Israel's history.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p.40</extension><space/>At the end, however, he follows other gods and oppresses Israel.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p.20</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As a consequence of Solomon's failure to stamp out the worship of gods other than<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, the kingdom of David is split in two in the reign of his own son<space/><link><target>Rehoboam</target></link>, who becomes the first to reign over the<space/><link><target>kingdom of Judah</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sweeney, p.161</extension><space/>The kings who follow Rehoboam in Jerusalem continue the royal line of David (i.e., they inherit the promise to David); in the north, however, dynasties follow each other in rapid succession, and the kings are uniformly bad (meaning that they fail to follow Yahweh alone). At length God brings the<space/><link><target>Assyria</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>to destroy the northern kingdom, leaving Judah as the sole custodian of the promise.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Hezekiah</target></link>, the 14th king of Judah, &quot;did what was right in the eyes of the Lord&quot; and institutes a far reaching religious reform, centralising sacrifice at the temple at Jerusalem and destroying the images of other gods. Yahweh saves Jerusalem and the kingdom from an invasion by Assyria. But<space/><link><target>Manasseh of Judah</target><part>Manasseh</part></link>, the next king, reverses the reforms, and God announces that he will destroy Jerusalem because of this apostasy by the king. Mannasah's righteous grandson<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link><space/>reinstitutes the reforms of Hezekiah, but it is too late: God, speaking through the prophetess<space/><link><target>Huldah</target></link>, affirms that Jerusalem is to be destroyed.</paragraph><paragraph>God brings the<space/><link><target>Neo-Babylonian Empire</target><part>Babylonians</part></link><space/>against Jerusalem; Yahweh deserts his people, Jerusalem is razed and the Temple destroyed, and the priests, prophets and royal court are led into captivity. (The final verses record how<space/><link><target>Jehoiachin</target></link>, the last king, is set free and given honour by the king of Babylon).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn - Jeremia treurend over de verwoesting van Jeruzalem - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>thumbnail</part><part><link><target>Rembrandt</target></link>, &quot;Jeremiah Lamenting the Destruction of Jerusalem&quot;, c. 1630</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Textual history</heading><paragraph>In the original<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>(the Bible used by Jews) First and Second Kings are a single book, as are First and Second<space/><link><target>Book of Samuel</target><part>Samuel</part></link>. When this was translated into Greek in the last few centuries BCE, Kings was joined with Samuel in a four-part work called the Book of Kingdoms. The<space/><link><target>Greek Orthodox</target></link><space/>branch of Christianity continues to use the Greek translation (the<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link>), but when a Latin translation (called the<space/><link><target>Vulgate</target></link>) was made for the Western church, Kingdoms was first retitled the Book of Kings, parts One to Four, and eventually both Kings and Samuel were separated into two books each.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tomes, p.246</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Deuteronomistic history</heading><paragraph>According to Jewish tradition the author of Kings was<space/><link><target>Jeremiah</target></link>, whose life overlapped the fall of Jerusalem in 586&amp;nbsp;BCE.<extension extension_name='ref'>Spieckermann, p.337</extension><space/>The most common view today accepts<space/><link><target>Martin Noth</target></link>'s thesis that Kings concludes a unified series of books which reflect the language and theology of the<space/><link><target>Book of Deuteronomy</target></link>, and which biblical scholars therefore call the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Perdue, xxvii</extension><space/>Noth argued that the History was the work of a single individual living in the 6th century, but scholars today tend to treat it as made up of at least two layers,<extension extension_name='ref'>Wilson, p.85</extension><space/>a first edition from the time of<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link><space/>(late 7th century), promoting Josiah's religious reforms and the need for repentance, and (2) a second and final edition from the mid 6th century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fretheim">Fretheim, p.7</extension><space/>Further levels of editing have also been proposed, including: a late 8th century edition pointing to<space/><link><target>Hezekiah</target></link><space/>of Judah as the model for kingship; an earlier 8th century version with a similar message but identifying<space/><link><target>Jehu</target></link><space/>of Israel as the ideal king; and an even earlier version promoting the House of David as the key to national well-being.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sweeney, p.4</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sources</heading><paragraph>The editors/authors of the Deuteronomistic history cite a number of sources, including (for example) a &quot;<link><target>Acts of Solomon</target><part>Book of the Acts of Solomon</part></link>&quot; and, frequently, the &quot;<link><target>Chronicles of the Kings of Judah</target><part>Annals of the Kings of Judah</part></link>&quot; and a separate book, &quot;<link><target>Chronicles of the Kings of Israel</target></link>&quot;. The &quot;Deuteronomic&quot; perspective (that of the book of Deuteronomy) is particularly evident in prayers and speeches spoken by key figures at major transition points: Solomon's speech at the dedication of the Temple is a key example.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fretheim"></extension><space/>The sources have been heavily edited to meet the Deuteronomistic agenda,<extension extension_name='ref'>Van Seters, p.307</extension><space/>but in the broadest sense they appear to have been:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>1 Kings 12: The end of the &quot;<link><target>court history of David</target></link>&quot; (also called the Succession Narrative), which also constitutes most of 2 Samuel 920.</listitem><listitem>For the rest of Solomon's reign the text names its source as &quot;the book of the acts of Solomon&quot;, but other sources were employed, and much was added by the redactor.</listitem><listitem>Israel and Judah: The two &quot;chronicles&quot; of Israel and Judah provided the chronological framework, but few details apart from the succession of monarchs and the account of how the<space/><link><target>Temple of Solomon</target></link><space/>was progressively stripped as true religion declined. A third source, or set of sources, were cycles of stories about various prophets (<link><target>Elijah</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elisha</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Isaiah</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ahijah the Shilonite</target><part>Ahijah</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Micaiah</target></link>), plus a few smaller miscellaneous traditions. The conclusion of the book (2 Kings 25:1821, 2730) was probably based on personal knowledge.</listitem><listitem>A few sections were editorial additions not based on sources. These include various predictions of the downfall of the northern kingdom, the equivalent prediction of the downfall of Judah following the reign of<space/><link><target>Manasseh of Judah</target><part>Manasseh</part></link>, the extension of<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link>'s reforms in accordance with the laws of<space/><link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link>, and the revision of the narrative from<space/><link><target>Book of Jeremiah</target><part>Jeremiah</part></link><space/>concerning Judah's last days.<extension extension_name='ref'>McKenzie, pp.281284</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Themes and genre</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Genealogy of the kings of Israel and Judah.svg</target><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The kings of Israel and Judah</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>According to Richard Nelson, Kings is &quot;history-like,&quot; but it mixes legends, folktales, miracle stories and &quot;fictional constructions&quot; in with the annals, and its primary explanation for all that happens is God's offended sense of what is right; it is therefore more fruitful to read it as theological literature in the form of history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nelson, pp.1-2">Nelson, pp.<link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=RCgUvQOIvD0C&amp;amp;pg=PA1#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22fictional%20constructions%22&amp;amp;f=false'>12</link></extension><space/>The theological bias is seen in the way it judges each king of Israel on the basis of whether he recognises the authority of the temple in Jerusalem (none do, and therefore all are &quot;evil&quot;), and each king of Judah on the basis of whether he destroys the &quot;high places&quot; (rivals to the Temple in Jerusalem); it gives only passing mention to important and successful kings like<space/><link><target>Omri (King of Israel)</target><part>Omri</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jeroboam II</target></link><space/>and totally ignores one of the most significant events in ancient Israel's history, the<space/><link><target>battle of Qarqar</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sutherland, p.489</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The major themes of Kings are God's promise, the recurrent apostasy of the kings, and the judgement this brings on Israel:<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, pp.1014</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Promise: In return for Israel's promise to worship Yahweh alone, Yahweh makes promises to David and to Israel to David, the promise that his line will rule Israel forever, to Israel, the promise of the land they will possess.</listitem><listitem>Apostasy: the great tragedy of Israel's history, meaning the destruction of the kingdom and the Temple, is due to the failure of the people, but more especially the kings, to worship Yahweh alone (Yahweh being the god of Israel).</listitem><listitem>Judgement: Apostasy leads to judgement. Judgement is not punishment, but simply the natural (or rather, God-ordained) consequence of Israel's failure to worship Yahweh alone.</listitem></list><paragraph>Another and related theme is that of prophecy. The main point of the prophetic stories is that God's prophecies are always fulfilled, so that any not yet fulfilled will be so in the future. The implication, the release of Jehoiachin and his restoration to a place of honour in Babylon in the closing scenes of the book, is that the promise of an eternal Davidic dynasty is still in effect, and that the Davidic line will be restored.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sutherland, p.490</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Textual features</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tissot The Flight of the Prisoners.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>James Tissot</target></link>, ''The Flight of the Prisoners'' the fall of Jerusalem, 586&amp;nbsp;BCE.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chronology</heading><paragraph>The standard Hebrew text of Kings presents an impossible chronology.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sweeney, p.43</extension><space/>To take just a single example,<space/><link><target>Omri (King of Israel)</target><part>Omri</part></link>'s accession to the throne of Israel in the 31st year of<space/><link><target>Asa of Judah</target></link><space/>(1 Kings 16:23) cannot follow the death of his predecessor<space/><link><target>Zimri (king)</target><part>Zimri</part></link><space/>in the 27th year of Asa (1 Kings 16:15).<extension extension_name='ref'>Sweeney, pp.4344</extension><space/>The Greek text corrects the impossibilities but does not seem to represent an earlier version.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nelson, p.44</extension><space/>A large number of scholars have claimed to solve the difficulties, but the results differ, sometimes widely, and none have achieved consensus status.<extension extension_name='ref'>Moore &amp; Kelle, pp.269271</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Kings and 2 Chronicles</heading><paragraph>2 Chronicles covers much the same time-period as Kings, but it ignores the northern<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)</target><part>Kingdom of Israel</part></link><space/>almost completely, David is given a major role in planning the Temple, Hezekiah is given a much more far-reaching program of reform, and Manasseh is given an opportunity to repent of his sins, apparently to account for his long reign.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sutherland">Sutherland, p.247</extension><space/>It is usually assumed that the author of Chronicles used Kings as a source and re-wrote history as he would have liked it to have been.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sutherland"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>The Bible and history</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of ancient Israel and Judah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kingdom of Judah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kingdom of Israel (united monarchy)</target><part>Kingdom of Israel</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><heading level='3'>Commentaries on Kings</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Fretheim</arg><arg name="first">Terence E</arg><arg name="title">First and Second Kings</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-664-25565-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Nelson</arg><arg name="first">Richard Donald</arg><arg name="title">First and Second Kings</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-664-22084-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Sweeney</arg><arg name="first">Marvin</arg><arg name="title">I&II Kings: A Commentary</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-664-22084-6</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>General</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A</arg><arg name="chapter">Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen and Kent Harold Richards</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation</arg><arg name="publisher">T&T Clark</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-29289-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A</arg><arg name="chapter">Sources</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard</arg><arg name="title">Mercer Dictionary of the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Mercer University Press</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-86554-373-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Leuchter</arg><arg name="first1">Mark</arg><arg name="last2">Adam</arg><arg name="first2">Klaus-Peter</arg><arg name="chapter">Introduction</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Mark Leuchter, Klaus-Peter Adam, Karl-Peter Adam</arg><arg name="title">Soundings in Kings: Perspectives and Methods in Contemporary Scholarship</arg><arg name="publisher">Fortress Press</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4514-1263-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Moore</arg><arg name="first1">Megan Bishop</arg><arg name="last2">Kelle</arg><arg name="first2">Brad E</arg><arg name="title">Biblical History and Israel's Past: The Changing Study of the Bible and History</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8028-6260-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McKenzie</arg><arg name="first">Steven L</arg><arg name="chapter">The Books of Kings</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Steven L. McKenzie, Matt Patrick Graham</arg><arg name="title">The History of Israel's Traditions: The Heritage of Martin Noth</arg><arg name="publisher">Sheffield Academic Press</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-23035-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Perdue</arg><arg name="first">Leo G</arg><arg name="chapter">Preface: The Hebrew Bible in Current Research</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Leo G. Perdue</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell companion to the Hebrew Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-21071-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Spieckerman</arg><arg name="first">Hermann</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Leo G. Perdue</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Companion to the Hebrew Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-21071-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Sutherland</arg><arg name="first">Ray</arg><arg name="chapter">Kings, Books of, First and Second</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard</arg><arg name="title">Mercer Dictionary of the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Mercer University Press</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-86554-373-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Tomes</arg><arg name="first">Roger</arg><arg name="chapter">1 and 2 Kings</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James D. G. Dunn, John William Rogerson</arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans commentary on the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8028-3711-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Van Seters</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">In search of history: historiography in the ancient world and the origins of biblical history</arg><arg name="publisher">Eisenbrauns</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-57506-013-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Walton</arg><arg name="first">John H</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Andrew E. Hill, John H. Walton</arg><arg name="title">A Survey of the Old Testament</arg><arg name="publisher">Zondervan</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-310-22903-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wilson</arg><arg name="first">Robert R</arg><arg name="chapter">The Former Prophets: Reading the Books of Kings</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen, Kent Harold Richards</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation: Past, Present and Future: Essays in honor of Gene M. Tucker</arg><arg name="publisher">Continuum International Publishing Group</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-29289-6</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Books of Kings</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>1 Kings</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>2 Kings</arg></template><template><target>Wikisourcelang</target><arg>he</arg><arg>קטגוריה:ספר מלכים</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Original text</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt09a01.htm'><space/>''Melachim Aleph'' Kings A</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt09b01.htm'><space/>''Melachim Bet'' Kings B</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>Judaism</target><part>Jewish</part></link><space/>translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et09a01.htm'>1 Kings at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society 1917 translation)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et09b01.htm'>2 Kings at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society 1917 translation)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/>translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=1+Kings+1%3A1&amp;amp;version=NIV'>1 Kings</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=2%20Kings%201&amp;amp;version=NIV'>2 Kings</link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Other links</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/318629/books-of-Kings'>&quot;books of Kings.&quot;</link><space/>Encyclopdia Britannica Online.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=226&amp;amp;letter=K&amp;amp;search=Kings'>Books of Kings article</link><space/>(Jewish Encyclopedia)</listitem><listitem><template><target>CathEncy</target><arg name="wstitle">First and Second Books of Kings</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>CathEncy</target><arg name="wstitle">Third and Fourth Books of Kings</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Nevi'im|History books]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Books of Samuel|Samuel]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Isaiah|Isaiah]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br />[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Books of Chronicles|1–2 Chronicles]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Kings, Books Of</target></template><link><target>Category:Nevi'im</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-millennium BC books</target></link><link><target>Category:Books of Kings</target></link><link><target>Category:King lists</target></link></paragraph></article>