<article title='Computational_complexity_theory'><paragraph><bold>Computational complexity theory</bold><space/>is a branch of the<space/><link><target>theory of computation</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>theoretical computer science</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mathematics</target></link><space/>that focuses on classifying<space/><link><target>computational problems</target></link><space/>according to their inherent difficulty, and relating those<space/><link><target>Complexity class</target><part>classes</part></link><space/>to each other. A computational problem is understood to be a task that is in principle amenable to being solved by a computer, which is equivalent to stating that the problem may be solved by mechanical application of mathematical steps, such as an<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A problem is regarded as inherently difficult if its solution requires significant resources, whatever the<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>used. The theory formalizes this intuition, by introducing mathematical<space/><link><target>models of computation</target></link><space/>to study these problems and quantifying the amount of resources needed to solve them, such as time and storage. Other<space/><link><target>complexity</target></link><space/>measures are also used, such as the amount of communication (used in<space/><link><target>communication complexity</target></link>), the number of<space/><link><target>logic gate</target><part>gates</part></link><space/>in a circuit (used in<space/><link><target>circuit complexity</target></link>) and the number of processors (used in<space/><link><target>parallel computing</target></link>). One of the roles of computational complexity theory is to determine the practical limits on what<space/><link><target>computer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can and cannot do.</paragraph><paragraph>Closely related fields in theoretical computer science are<space/><link><target>analysis of algorithms</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>computability theory</target></link>. A key distinction between analysis of algorithms and computational complexity theory is that the former is devoted to analyzing the amount of resources needed by a particular algorithm to solve a problem, whereas the latter asks a more general question about all possible algorithms that could be used to solve the same problem. More precisely, it tries to classify problems that can or cannot be solved with appropriately restricted resources. In turn, imposing restrictions on the available resources is what distinguishes computational complexity from computability theory: the latter theory asks what kind of problems can, in principle, be solved algorithmically.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Computational problems</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:TSP Deutschland 3.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>333px</part><part>A traveling salesman tour through<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>s 15 largest cities.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Problem instances</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>computational problem</target></link><space/>can be viewed as an infinite collection of<space/><italics>instances</italics><space/>together with a<space/><italics>solution</italics><space/>for every instance. The input string for a computational problem is referred to as a problem instance, and should not be confused with the problem itself. In computational complexity theory, a problem refers to the abstract question to be solved. In contrast, an instance of this problem is a rather concrete utterance, which can serve as the input for a decision problem. For example, consider the problem of<space/><link><target>primality testing</target></link>. The instance is a number (e.g. 15) and the solution is &quot;yes&quot; if the number is prime and &quot;no&quot; otherwise (in this case &quot;no&quot;). Stated another way, the<space/><italics>instance</italics><space/>is a particular input to the problem, and the<space/><italics>solution</italics><space/>is the output corresponding to the given input.</paragraph><paragraph>To further highlight the difference between a problem and an instance, consider the following instance of the decision version of the<space/><link><target>traveling salesman problem</target></link>: Is there a route of at most 2000 kilometres passing through all of Germany's 15 largest cities? The quantitative answer to this particular problem instance is of little use for solving other instances of the problem, such as asking for a round trip through all sites in<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link><space/>whose total length is at most 10&amp;nbsp;km. For this reason, complexity theory addresses computational problems and not particular problem instances.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Representing problem instances</heading><paragraph>When considering computational problems, a problem instance is a<space/><link><target>string (computer science)</target><part>string</part></link><space/>over an<space/><link><target>Alphabet (computer science)</target><part>alphabet</part></link>. Usually, the alphabet is taken to be the binary alphabet (i.e., the set {0,1}), and thus the strings are<space/><link><target>bitstring</target><trail>s</trail></link>. As in a real-world computer, mathematical objects other than bitstrings must be suitably encoded. For example,<space/><link><target>integer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can be represented in<space/><link><target>binary notation</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>graph (mathematics)</target><part>graphs</part></link><space/>can be encoded directly via their<space/><link><target>adjacency matrix</target><part>adjacency matrices</part></link>, or by encoding their<space/><link><target>adjacency list</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in binary.</paragraph><paragraph>Even though some proofs of complexity-theoretic theorems regularly assume some concrete choice of input encoding, one tries to keep the discussion abstract enough to be independent of the choice of encoding. This can be achieved by ensuring that different representations can be transformed into each other efficiently.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Decision problems as formal languages</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Decision Problem.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>A<space/><link><target>decision problem</target></link><space/>has only two possible outputs, ''yes'' or ''no'' (or alternately 1 or 0) on any input.</part></link><link><target>Decision problem</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are one of the central objects of study in computational complexity theory. A decision problem is a special type of computational problem whose answer is either<space/><italics>yes</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>no</italics>, or alternately either 1 or 0. A decision problem can be viewed as a<space/><link><target>formal language</target></link>, where the members of the language are instances whose output is yes, and the non-members are those instances whose output is no. The objective is to decide, with the aid of an<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link>, whether a given input string is a member of the formal language under consideration. If the algorithm deciding this problem returns the answer<space/><italics>yes</italics>, the algorithm is said to accept the input string, otherwise it is said to reject the input.</paragraph><paragraph>An example of a decision problem is the following. The input is an arbitrary<space/><link><target>graph (mathematics)</target><part>graph</part></link>. The problem consists in deciding whether the given graph is<space/><link><target>connectivity (graph theory)</target><part>connected</part></link>, or not. The formal language associated with this decision problem is then the set of all connected graphs&amp;mdash;of course, to obtain a precise definition of this language, one has to decide how graphs are encoded as binary strings.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Function problems</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>function problem</target></link><space/>is a computational problem where a single output (of a<space/><link><target>total function</target></link>) is expected for every input, but the output is more complex than that of a<space/><link><target>decision problem</target></link>, that is, it isn't just yes or no. Notable examples include the<space/><link><target>traveling salesman problem</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>integer factorization problem</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>It is tempting to think that the notion of function problems is much richer than the notion of decision problems. However, this is not really the case, since function problems can be recast as decision problems. For example, the<space/><link><target>multiplication</target></link><space/>of two integers can be expressed as the set of triples (<italics>a</italics>,&amp;nbsp;<italics>b</italics>,&amp;nbsp;<italics>c</italics>) such that the relation<space/><italics>a</italics>&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;<italics>b</italics>&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;<italics>c</italics><space/>holds. Deciding whether a given triple is a member of this set corresponds to solving the problem of multiplying two numbers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Measuring the size of an instance</heading><paragraph>To measure the difficulty of solving a computational problem, one may wish to see how much time the best algorithm requires to solve the problem. However, the running time may, in general, depend on the instance. In particular, larger instances will require more time to solve. Thus the time required to solve a problem (or the space required, or any measure of complexity) is calculated as a function of the size of the instance. This is usually taken to be the size of the input in bits. Complexity theory is interested in how algorithms scale with an increase in the input size. For instance, in the problem of finding whether a graph is connected, how much more time does it take to solve a problem for a graph with 2<italics>n</italics><space/>vertices compared to the time taken for a graph with<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>vertices?</paragraph><paragraph>If the input size is<space/><italics>n</italics>, the time taken can be expressed as a function of<space/><italics>n</italics>. Since the time taken on different inputs of the same size can be different, the worst-case time complexity T(<italics>n</italics>) is defined to be the maximum time taken over all inputs of size<space/><italics>n</italics>. If T(<italics>n</italics>) is a polynomial in<space/><italics>n</italics>, then the algorithm is said to be a<space/><link><target>polynomial time</target></link><space/>algorithm.<space/><link><target>Cobham's thesis</target></link><space/>says that a problem can be solved with a feasible amount of resources if it admits a polynomial time algorithm.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Machine models and complexity measures</heading><heading level='3'>Turing machine</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Maquina.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>An artistic representation of a Turing machine</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Turing machine</arg></template>A Turing machine is a mathematical model of a general computing machine. It is a theoretical device that manipulates symbols contained on a strip of tape. Turing machines are not intended as a practical computing technology, but rather as a thought experiment representing a computing machineanything from an advanced supercomputer to a mathematician with a pencil and paper. It is believed that if a problem can be solved by an algorithm, there exists a Turing machine that solves the problem. Indeed, this is the statement of the<space/><link><target>ChurchTuring thesis</target></link>. Furthermore, it is known that everything that can be computed on other models of computation known to us today, such as a<space/><link><target>RAM machine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Conway's Game of Life</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cellular automata</target></link><space/>or any programming language can be computed on a Turing machine. Since Turing machines are easy to analyze mathematically, and are believed to be as powerful as any other model of computation, the Turing machine is the most commonly used model in complexity theory.</paragraph><paragraph>Many types of Turing machines are used to define complexity classes, such as<space/><link><target>deterministic Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>probabilistic Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>non-deterministic Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>quantum Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>symmetric Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>alternating Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>. They are all equally powerful in principle, but when resources (such as time or space) are bounded, some of these may be more powerful than others.</paragraph><paragraph>A deterministic Turing machine is the most basic Turing machine, which uses a fixed set of rules to determine its future actions. A probabilistic Turing machine is a deterministic Turing machine with an extra supply of random bits. The ability to make probabilistic decisions often helps algorithms solve problems more efficiently. Algorithms that use random bits are called<space/><link><target>randomized algorithm</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A non-deterministic Turing machine is a deterministic Turing machine with an added feature of non-determinism, which allows a Turing machine to have multiple possible future actions from a given state. One way to view non-determinism is that the Turing machine branches into many possible computational paths at each step, and if it solves the problem in any of these branches, it is said to have solved the problem. Clearly, this model is not meant to be a physically realizable model, it is just a theoretically interesting abstract machine that gives rise to particularly interesting complexity classes. For examples, see<space/><link><target>non-deterministic algorithm</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Other machine models</heading><paragraph>Many machine models different from the standard<space/><link><target>Turing machine equivalents#Multi-tape Turing machines</target><part>multi-tape Turing machines</part></link><space/>have been proposed in the literature, for example<space/><link><target>random access machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Perhaps surprisingly, each of these models can be converted to another without providing any extra computational power. The time and memory consumption of these alternate models may vary.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Arora</arg><arg>Barak</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="loc">Chapter 1: The computational model and why it doesn't matter</arg></template></extension><space/>What all these models have in common is that the machines operate<space/><link><target>deterministic algorithm</target><part>deterministically</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>However, some computational problems are easier to analyze in terms of more unusual resources. For example, a non-deterministic Turing machine is a computational model that is allowed to branch out to check many different possibilities at once. The non-deterministic Turing machine has very little to do with how we physically want to compute algorithms, but its branching exactly captures many of the mathematical models we want to analyze, so that<space/><link><target>non-deterministic time</target></link><space/>is a very important resource in analyzing computational problems.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Complexity measures</heading><paragraph>For a precise definition of what it means to solve a problem using a given amount of time and space, a computational model such as the<space/><link><target>deterministic Turing machine</target></link><space/>is used. The<space/><italics>time required</italics><space/>by a deterministic Turing machine<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>on input<space/><italics>x</italics><space/>is the total number of state transitions, or steps, the machine makes before it halts and outputs the answer (&quot;yes&quot; or &quot;no&quot;). A Turing machine<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>is said to operate within time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>), if the time required by<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>on each input of length<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>is at most<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>). A decision problem<space/><italics>A</italics><space/>can be solved in time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) if there exists a Turing machine operating in time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) that solves the problem. Since complexity theory is interested in classifying problems based on their difficulty, one defines sets of problems based on some criteria. For instance, the set of problems solvable within time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) on a deterministic Turing machine is then denoted by<space/><link><target>DTIME</target></link>(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)).</paragraph><paragraph>Analogous definitions can be made for space requirements. Although time and space are the most well-known complexity resources, any<space/><link><target>complexity measure</target></link><space/>can be viewed as a computational resource. Complexity measures are very generally defined by the<space/><link><target>Blum complexity axioms</target></link>. Other complexity measures used in complexity theory include<space/><link><target>communication complexity</target></link>,<space/><link><target>circuit complexity</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>decision tree complexity</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The complexity of an algorithm is often expressed using<space/><link><target>big O notation</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Best, worst and average case complexity</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sorting quicksort anim.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Visualization of the<space/><link><target>quicksort</target></link><space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>that has<space/><link><target>Best, worst and average case</target><part>average case performance</part></link><space/><extension extension_name='math'>\Theta(n\log n)</extension>.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>best, worst and average case</target></link><space/>complexity refer to three different ways of measuring the time complexity (or any other complexity measure) of different inputs of the same size. Since some inputs of size<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>may be faster to solve than others, we define the following complexities:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Best-case complexity: This is the complexity of solving the problem for the best input of size<space/><italics>n</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Worst-case complexity: This is the complexity of solving the problem for the worst input of size<space/><italics>n</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Average-case complexity: This is the complexity of solving the problem on an average. This complexity is only defined with respect to a<space/><link><target>probability distribution</target></link><space/>over the inputs. For instance, if all inputs of the same size are assumed to be equally likely to appear, the average case complexity can be defined with respect to the uniform distribution over all inputs of size<space/><italics>n</italics>.</listitem></list><paragraph>For example, consider the deterministic sorting algorithm<space/><link><target>quicksort</target></link>. This solves the problem of sorting a list of integers that is given as the input. The worst-case is when the input is sorted or sorted in reverse order, and the algorithm takes time<space/><link><target>Big O notation</target><part>O</part></link>(<italics>n</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>) for this case. If we assume that all possible permutations of the input list are equally likely, the average time taken for sorting is O(<italics>n</italics><space/>log<space/><italics>n</italics>). The best case occurs when each pivoting divides the list in half, also needing O(<italics>n</italics><space/>log<space/><italics>n</italics>) time.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Upper and lower bounds on the complexity of problems</heading><paragraph>To classify the computation time (or similar resources, such as space consumption), one is interested in proving upper and lower bounds on the minimum amount of time required by the most efficient algorithm solving a given problem. The complexity of an algorithm is usually taken to be its worst-case complexity, unless specified otherwise. Analyzing a particular algorithm falls under the field of<space/><link><target>analysis of algorithms</target></link>. To show an upper bound<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) on the time complexity of a problem, one needs to show only that there is a particular algorithm with running time at most<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>). However, proving lower bounds is much more difficult, since lower bounds make a statement about all possible algorithms that solve a given problem. The phrase &quot;all possible algorithms&quot; includes not just the algorithms known today, but any algorithm that might be discovered in the future. To show a lower bound of<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) for a problem requires showing that no algorithm can have time complexity lower than<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>Upper and lower bounds are usually stated using the<space/><link><target>big O notation</target></link>, which hides constant factors and smaller terms. This makes the bounds independent of the specific details of the computational model used. For instance, if<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;7<italics>n</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;15<italics>n</italics>&amp;nbsp;+&amp;nbsp;40, in big O notation one would write<space/><italics>T</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;O(<italics>n</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Complexity classes</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Complexity class</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Defining complexity classes</heading><paragraph>A<space/><bold>complexity class</bold><space/>is a set of problems of related complexity. Simpler complexity classes are defined by the following factors:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The type of computational problem: The most commonly used problems are decision problems. However, complexity classes can be defined based on<space/><link><target>function problem</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>counting problem (complexity)</target><part>counting problem</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>optimization problem</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>promise problem</target><trail>s</trail></link>, etc.</listitem><listitem>The model of computation: The most common model of computation is the deterministic Turing machine, but many complexity classes are based on non-deterministic Turing machines,<space/><link><target>Boolean circuit</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>quantum Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>monotone circuit</target><trail>s</trail></link>, etc.</listitem><listitem>The resource (or resources) that are being bounded and the bounds: These two properties are usually stated together, such as &quot;polynomial time&quot;, &quot;logarithmic space&quot;, &quot;constant depth&quot;, etc.</listitem></list><paragraph>Of course, some complexity classes have complicated definitions that do not fit into this framework. Thus, a typical complexity class has a definition like the following:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The set of decision problems solvable by a deterministic Turing machine within time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>). (This complexity class is known as DTIME(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)).)</listitem></list><paragraph>But bounding the computation time above by some concrete function<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>) often yields complexity classes that depend on the chosen machine model. For instance, the language {<italics>xx</italics><space/>|<space/><italics>x</italics><space/>is any binary string} can be solved in<space/><link><target>linear time</target></link><space/>on a multi-tape Turing machine, but necessarily requires quadratic time in the model of single-tape Turing machines. If we allow polynomial variations in running time,<space/><link><target>Cobham's thesis</target><part>Cobham-Edmonds thesis</part></link><space/>states that &quot;the time complexities in any two reasonable and general models of computation are polynomially related&quot;<space/><template><target>Harv</target><arg>Goldreich</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="loc">Chapter 1.2</arg></template>. This forms the basis for the complexity class<space/><link><target>P (complexity)</target><part>P</part></link>, which is the set of decision problems solvable by a deterministic Turing machine within polynomial time. The corresponding set of function problems is<space/><link><target>FP (complexity)</target><part>FP</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Important complexity classes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Complexity subsets pspace.svg</target><part>250px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A representation of the relation among complexity classes</part></link>Many important complexity classes can be defined by bounding the time or space used by the algorithm. Some important complexity classes of decision problems defined in this manner are the following:</paragraph><table><tablerow><tablecell><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Complexity class</tablehead><tablehead>Model of computation</tablehead><tablehead>Resource constraint</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">Deterministic time</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DTIME</target></link>(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>))</tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>P (complexity)</target><part>P</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time poly(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>EXPTIME</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time 2<xhtml:sup>poly(<italics>n</italics>)</xhtml:sup></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">Non-deterministic time</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NTIME</target></link>(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>))</tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell><tablecell>&amp;nbsp;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&amp;nbsp;</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NP (complexity)</target><part>NP</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time poly(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NEXPTIME</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Time 2<xhtml:sup>poly(<italics>n</italics>)</xhtml:sup></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Complexity class</tablehead><tablehead>Model of computation</tablehead><tablehead>Resource constraint</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">Deterministic space</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DSPACE</target></link>(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>))</tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>L (complexity)</target><part>L</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space O(log<space/><italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>PSPACE</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space poly(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>EXPSPACE</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space 2<xhtml:sup>poly(<italics>n</italics>)</xhtml:sup></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">Non-deterministic space</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NSPACE</target></link>(<italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>))</tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space<space/><italics>f</italics>(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NL (complexity)</target><part>NL</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space O(log<space/><italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NPSPACE</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space poly(<italics>n</italics>)</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>NEXPSPACE</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Non-deterministic Turing machine</tablecell><tablecell>Space 2<xhtml:sup>poly(<italics>n</italics>)</xhtml:sup></tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>The logarithmic-space classes (necessarily) do not take into account the space needed to represent the problem.</paragraph><paragraph>It turns out that PSPACE = NPSPACE and EXPSPACE = NEXPSPACE by<space/><link><target>Savitch's theorem</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Other important complexity classes include<space/><link><target>BPP (complexity)</target><part>BPP</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ZPP (complexity)</target><part>ZPP</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>RP (complexity)</target><part>RP</part></link>, which are defined using<space/><link><target>probabilistic Turing machine</target><trail>s</trail></link>;<space/><link><target>AC (complexity)</target><part>AC</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>NC (complexity)</target><part>NC</part></link>, which are defined using Boolean circuits; and<space/><link><target>BQP</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>QMA</target></link>, which are defined using quantum Turing machines.<space/><link><target>Sharp-P</target><part>#P</part></link><space/>is an important complexity class of counting problems (not decision problems). Classes like<space/><link><target>IP (complexity)</target><part>IP</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>AM (complexity)</target><part>AM</part></link><space/>are defined using<space/><link><target>Interactive proof system</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><link><target>ALL (complexity)</target><part>ALL</part></link><space/>is the class of all decision problems.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hierarchy theorems</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>time hierarchy theorem</arg><arg>space hierarchy theorem</arg></template>For the complexity classes defined in this way, it is desirable to prove that relaxing the requirements on (say) computation time indeed defines a bigger set of problems. In particular, although DTIME(<italics>n</italics>) is contained in DTIME(<italics>n</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>), it would be interesting to know if the inclusion is strict. For time and space requirements, the answer to such questions is given by the time and space hierarchy theorems respectively. They are called hierarchy theorems because they induce a proper hierarchy on the classes defined by constraining the respective resources. Thus there are pairs of complexity classes such that one is properly included in the other. Having deduced such proper set inclusions, we can proceed to make quantitative statements about how much more additional time or space is needed in order to increase the number of problems that can be solved.</paragraph><paragraph>More precisely, the<space/><link><target>time hierarchy theorem</target></link><space/>states that</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\operatorname{DTIME}\big(f(n) \big) \subsetneq \operatorname{DTIME} \big(f(n) \sdot \log^{2}(f(n)) \big)</extension>.</listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>space hierarchy theorem</target></link><space/>states that</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\operatorname{DSPACE}\big(f(n)\big) \subsetneq \operatorname{DSPACE} \big(f(n) \sdot \log(f(n)) \big)</extension>.</listitem></list><paragraph>The time and space hierarchy theorems form the basis for most separation results of complexity classes. For instance, the time hierarchy theorem tells us that P is strictly contained in EXPTIME, and the space hierarchy theorem tells us that L is strictly contained in PSPACE.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Reduction</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Reduction (complexity)</arg></template>Many complexity classes are defined using the concept of a reduction. A reduction is a transformation of one problem into another problem. It captures the informal notion of a problem being at least as difficult as another problem. For instance, if a problem<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>can be solved using an algorithm for<space/><italics>Y</italics>,<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is no more difficult than<space/><italics>Y</italics>, and we say that<space/><italics>X</italics><space/><italics>reduces</italics><space/>to<space/><italics>Y</italics>. There are many different types of reductions, based on the method of reduction, such as Cook reductions, Karp reductions and Levin reductions, and the bound on the complexity of reductions, such as<space/><link><target>polynomial-time reduction</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>log-space reduction</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The most commonly used reduction is a polynomial-time reduction. This means that the reduction process takes polynomial time. For example, the problem of squaring an integer can be reduced to the problem of multiplying two integers. This means an algorithm for multiplying two integers can be used to square an integer. Indeed, this can be done by giving the same input to both inputs of the multiplication algorithm. Thus we see that squaring is not more difficult than multiplication, since squaring can be reduced to multiplication.</paragraph><paragraph>This motivates the concept of a problem being hard for a complexity class. A problem<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is<space/><italics>hard</italics><space/>for a class of problems<space/><italics>C</italics><space/>if every problem in<space/><italics>C</italics><space/>can be reduced to<space/><italics>X</italics>. Thus no problem in<space/><italics>C</italics><space/>is harder than<space/><italics>X</italics>, since an algorithm for<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>allows us to solve any problem in<space/><italics>C</italics>. Of course, the notion of hard problems depends on the type of reduction being used. For complexity classes larger than P, polynomial-time reductions are commonly used. In particular, the set of problems that are hard for NP is the set of<space/><link><target>NP-hard</target></link><space/>problems.</paragraph><paragraph>If a problem<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is in<space/><italics>C</italics><space/>and hard for<space/><italics>C</italics>, then<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is said to be<space/><italics><link><target>complete (complexity)</target><part>complete</part></link></italics><space/>for<space/><italics>C</italics>. This means that<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is the hardest problem in<space/><italics>C</italics>. (Since many problems could be equally hard, one might say that<space/><italics>X</italics><space/>is one of the hardest problems in<space/><italics>C</italics>.) Thus the class of<space/><link><target>NP-complete</target></link><space/>problems contains the most difficult problems in NP, in the sense that they are the ones most likely not to be in P. Because the problem P&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;NP is not solved, being able to reduce a known NP-complete problem,<space/><xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>, to another problem,<space/><xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>, would indicate that there is no known polynomial-time solution for<space/><xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>. This is because a polynomial-time solution to<space/><xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub><space/>would yield a polynomial-time solution to<space/><xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>. Similarly, because all NP problems can be reduced to the set, finding an<space/><link><target>NP-complete</target></link><space/>problem that can be solved in polynomial time would mean that P&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;NP.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sipser2006"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Important open problems</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Complexity classes.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Diagram of complexity classes provided that P&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;NP. The existence of problems in NP outside both P and NP-complete in this case was established by Ladner.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ladner75"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Ladner</arg><arg name="first">Richard E.</arg><arg name="title">On the structure of polynomial time reducibility</arg><arg name="journal">[[Journal of the ACM]] (JACM)</arg><arg name="volume">22</arg><arg name="year">1975</arg><arg name="pages">151–171</arg><arg name="url">http://delivery.acm.org/10.1145/330000/321877/p155-ladner.pdf?key1</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="doi">10.1145/321864.321877</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="postscript">.</arg></template></extension></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>P versus NP problem</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>P versus NP problem</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The complexity class P is often seen as a mathematical abstraction modeling those computational tasks that admit an efficient algorithm. This hypothesis is called the<space/><link><target>CobhamEdmonds thesis</target></link>. The complexity class<space/><link><target>NP (complexity)</target><part>NP</part></link>, on the other hand, contains many problems that people would like to solve efficiently, but for which no efficient algorithm is known, such as the<space/><link><target>Boolean satisfiability problem</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Hamiltonian path problem</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>vertex cover problem</target></link>. Since deterministic Turing machines are special non-deterministic Turing machines, it is easily observed that each problem in P is also member of the class NP.</paragraph><paragraph>The question of whether P equals NP is one of the most important open questions in theoretical computer science because of the wide implications of a solution.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sipser2006">See<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Sipser</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="loc"><space/>Chapter 7: Time complexity</arg></template></extension><space/>If the answer is yes, many important problems can be shown to have more efficient solutions. These include various types of<space/><link><target>integer programming</target></link><space/>problems in<space/><link><target>operations research</target></link>, many problems in<space/><link><target>logistics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>protein structure prediction</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>biology</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">Protein folding in the hydrophobic-hydrophilic (HP) model is NP-complete</arg><arg name="last">Berger</arg><arg name="first">Bonnie A.</arg><arg name="author1-link">Bonnie Berger</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Computational Biology</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="volume">5</arg><arg name="pages">27–40</arg><arg name="pmid">9541869</arg><arg name="doi">10.1089/cmb.1998.5.27</arg><arg name="last2">Leighton</arg><arg name="first2">T</arg><arg name="author2-link">F. Thomson Leighton</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="postscript">.<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and the ability to find formal proofs of<space/><link><target>pure mathematics</target></link><space/>theorems.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Cook</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="authorlink">Stephen Cook</arg><arg name="title">The P versus NP Problem</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Clay Mathematics Institute]]</arg><arg name="date">April 2000</arg><arg name="url">http://www.claymath.org/millennium/P_vs_NP/Official_Problem_Description.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-10-18</arg><arg name="postscript">.</arg></template></extension><space/>The P versus NP problem is one of the<space/><link><target>Millennium Prize Problems</target></link><space/>proposed by the<space/><link><target>Clay Mathematics Institute</target></link>. There is a US$1,000,000 prize for resolving the problem.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title">The Millennium Grand Challenge in Mathematics</arg><arg name="last">Jaffe</arg><arg name="first">Arthur M.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Arthur Jaffe</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="journal">Notices of the AMS</arg><arg name="volume">53</arg><arg name="issue">6</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ams.org/notices/200606/fea-jaffe.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-10-18</arg><arg name="postscript">.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Problems in NP not known to be in P or NP-complete</heading><paragraph>It was shown by Ladner that if<space/><bold>P</bold><space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>then there exist problems in<space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>that are neither in<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>nor<space/><bold>NP-complete</bold>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ladner75"></extension><space/>Such problems are called<space/><link><target>NP-intermediate</target></link><space/>problems. The<space/><link><target>graph isomorphism problem</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>discrete logarithm problem</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>integer factorization problem</target></link><space/>are examples of problems believed to be NP-intermediate. They are some of the very few NP problems not known to be in<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>or to be<space/><bold>NP-complete</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>graph isomorphism problem</target></link><space/>is the computational problem of determining whether two finite<space/><link><target>Graph (mathematics)</target><part>graph</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are<space/><link><target>graph isomorphism</target><part>isomorphic</part></link>. An important unsolved problem in complexity theory is whether the graph isomorphism problem is in<space/><bold>P</bold>,<space/><bold>NP-complete</bold>, or NP-intermediate. The answer is not known, but it is believed that the problem is at least not NP-complete.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AK06"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first1"><space/>Vikraman
<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Arvind
<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Piyush P.
<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Kurur
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Graph isomorphism is in SPP
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Information and Computation
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>204
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>835–852
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/j.ic.2006.02.002
<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>.</arg></template></extension><space/>If graph isomorphism is NP-complete, the<space/><link><target>polynomial time hierarchy</target></link><space/>collapses to its second level.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Schöning<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Uwe<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Uwe Schöning<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Graph isomorphism is in the low hierarchy<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Proceedings of the 4th Annual [[Symposium on Theoretical Aspects of Computer Science]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1987<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>114–124<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/bfb0039599</arg></template>; also:<space/><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Computer and System Sciences<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>37<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>312–323<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0022-0000(88)90010-4</arg></template></extension><space/>Since it is widely believed that the polynomial hierarchy does not collapse to any finite level, it is believed that graph isomorphism is not NP-complete. The best algorithm for this problem, due to<space/><link><target>Laszlo Babai</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eugene Luks</target></link><space/>has run time 2<xhtml:sup>O((<italics>n</italics><space/>log(<italics>n</italics>)))</xhtml:sup><space/>for graphs with<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>vertices.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>integer factorization problem</target></link><space/>is the computational problem of determining the<space/><link><target>prime factorization</target></link><space/>of a given integer. Phrased as a decision problem, it is the problem of deciding whether the input has a factor less than<space/><italics>k</italics>. No efficient integer factorization algorithm is known, and this fact forms the basis of several modern cryptographic systems, such as the<space/><link><target>RSA (algorithm)</target><part>RSA</part></link><space/>algorithm. The integer factorization problem is in<space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>and in<space/><bold>co-NP</bold><space/>(and even in UP and co-UP<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Lance Fortnow</target></link>. Computational Complexity Blog: Complexity Class of the Week: Factoring. September 13, 2002. http://weblog.fortnow.com/2002/09/complexity-class-of-week-factoring.html</extension>). If the problem is<space/><bold>NP-complete</bold>, the polynomial time hierarchy will collapse to its first level (i.e.,<space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>will equal<space/><bold>co-NP</bold>). The best known algorithm for integer factorization is the<space/><link><target>general number field sieve</target></link>, which takes time O(e<xhtml:sup>(64/9)<xhtml:sup>1/3</xhtml:sup>(<italics>n</italics>.log 2)<xhtml:sup>1/3</xhtml:sup>(log (<italics>n</italics>.log 2))<xhtml:sup>2/3</xhtml:sup></xhtml:sup>) to factor an<space/><italics>n</italics>-bit integer. However, the best known<space/><link><target>quantum algorithm</target></link><space/>for this problem,<space/><link><target>Shor's algorithm</target></link>, does run in polynomial time. Unfortunately, this fact doesn't say much about where the problem lies with respect to non-quantum complexity classes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Separations between other complexity classes</heading><paragraph>Many known complexity classes are suspected to be unequal, but this has not been proved. For instance<space/><bold>P</bold><space/><bold>NP</bold><space/><bold><link><target>PP (complexity)</target><part>PP</part></link></bold><space/><bold>PSPACE</bold>, but it is possible that<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>=<space/><bold>PSPACE</bold>. If<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>is not equal to<space/><bold>NP</bold>, then<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>is not equal to<space/><bold>PSPACE</bold><space/>either. Since there are many known complexity classes between<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>PSPACE</bold>, such as<space/><bold>RP</bold>,<space/><bold>BPP</bold>,<space/><bold>PP</bold>,<space/><bold>BQP</bold>,<space/><bold>MA</bold>,<space/><bold>PH</bold>, etc., it is possible that all these complexity classes collapse to one class. Proving that any of these classes are unequal would be a major breakthrough in complexity theory.</paragraph><paragraph>Along the same lines,<space/><bold><link><target>co-NP</target></link></bold><space/>is the class containing the<space/><link><target>Complement (complexity)</target><part>complement</part></link><space/>problems (i.e. problems with the<space/><italics>yes</italics>/<italics>no</italics><space/>answers reversed) of<space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>problems. It is believed<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cs.princeton.edu/courses/archive/spr06/cos522/'>Boaz Barak's course on Computational Complexity</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cs.princeton.edu/courses/archive/spr06/cos522/lec2.pdf'>Lecture 2</link></extension><space/>that<space/><bold>NP</bold><space/>is not equal to<space/><bold>co-NP</bold>; however, it has not yet been proven. It has been shown that if these two complexity classes are not equal then<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>is not equal to<space/><bold>NP</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>Similarly, it is not known if<space/><bold>L</bold><space/>(the set of all problems that can be solved in logarithmic space) is strictly contained in<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>or equal to<space/><bold>P</bold>. Again, there are many complexity classes between the two, such as<space/><bold>NL</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>NC</bold>, and it is not known if they are distinct or equal classes.</paragraph><paragraph>It is suspected that<space/><bold>P</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>BPP</bold><space/>are equal. However, it is currently open if<space/><bold>BPP</bold><space/>=<space/><bold>NEXP</bold>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Intractability</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Combinatorial explosion</arg></template>Problems that can be solved in theory (e.g., given large but finite time), but which in practice take too long for their solutions to be useful, are known as<space/><italics>intractable</italics><space/>problems.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hopcroft, J.E., Motwani, R. and Ullman, J.D. (2007)<space/><link><target>Introduction to Automata Theory, Languages, and Computation</target></link>, Addison Wesley, Boston/San Francisco/New York (page 368)</extension><space/>In complexity theory, problems that lack polynomial-time solutions are considered to be intractable for more than the smallest inputs. In fact, the<space/><link><target>CobhamEdmonds thesis</target></link><space/>states that only those problems that can be solved in polynomial time can be feasibly computed on some computational device. Problems that are known to be intractable in this sense include those that are<space/><link><target>EXPTIME</target></link>-hard. If NP is not the same as P, then the NP-complete problems are also intractable in this sense. To see why exponential-time algorithms might be unusable in practice, consider a program that makes 2<xhtml:sup><italics>n</italics></xhtml:sup><space/>operations before halting. For small<space/><italics>n</italics>, say 100, and assuming for the sake of example that the computer does 10<xhtml:sup>12</xhtml:sup><space/>operations each second, the program would run for about 4&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;10<xhtml:sup>10</xhtml:sup><space/>years, which is the same order of magnitude as the<space/><link><target>age of the universe</target></link>. Even with a much faster computer, the program would only be useful for very small instances and in that sense the intractability of a problem is somewhat independent of technological progress. Nevertheless, a polynomial time algorithm is not always practical. If its running time is, say,<space/><italics>n</italics><xhtml:sup>15</xhtml:sup>, it is unreasonable to consider it efficient and it is still useless except on small instances.</paragraph><paragraph>What intractability means in practice is open to debate. Saying that a problem is not in P does not imply that all large cases of the problem are hard or even that most of them are. For example, the decision problem in<space/><link><target>Presburger arithmetic</target></link><space/>has been shown not to be in P, yet algorithms have been written that solve the problem in reasonable times in most cases. Similarly, algorithms can solve the NP-complete<space/><link><target>knapsack problem</target></link><space/>over a wide range of sizes in less than quadratic time and<space/><link><target>SAT solver</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>routinely handle large instances of the NP-complete<space/><link><target>Boolean satisfiability problem</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>An early example of algorithm complexity analysis is the running time analysis of the<space/><link><target>Euclidean algorithm</target></link><space/>done by<space/><link><target>Gabriel Lam</target></link><space/>in 1844.</paragraph><paragraph>Before the actual research explicitly devoted to the complexity of algorithmic problems started off, numerous foundations were laid out by various researchers. Most influential among these was the definition of Turing machines by<space/><link><target>Alan Turing</target></link><space/>in 1936, which turned out to be a very robust and flexible simplification of a computer.</paragraph><paragraph>As<space/><template><target>Harvtxt</target><arg>Fortnow</arg><arg>Homer</arg><arg>2003</arg></template><space/>point out, the beginning of systematic studies in computational complexity is attributed to the seminal paper &quot;On the Computational Complexity of Algorithms&quot; by Juris Hartmanis and Richard Stearns (1965), which laid out the definitions of time and<space/><link><target>space complexity</target></link><space/>and proved the hierarchy theorems. Also, in 1965<space/><link><target>Jack Edmonds</target><part>Edmonds</part></link><space/>defined a &quot;good&quot; algorithm as one with running time bounded by a polynomial of the input size.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard M. Karp, &quot;Combinatorics, Complexity, and Randomness&quot;, 1985 Turing Award Lecture</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Earlier papers studying problems solvable by Turing machines with specific bounded resources include<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvtxt</target><arg>Fortnow</arg><arg>Homer</arg><arg>2003</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>John Myhill</target></link>'s definition of<space/><link><target>linear bounded automata</target></link><space/>(Myhill 1960),<space/><link><target>Raymond Smullyan</target></link>'s study of rudimentary sets (1961), as well as<space/><link><target>Hisao Yamada</target></link>'s paper<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Yamada<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>H.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Real-Time Computation and Recursive Functions Not Real-Time Computable<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>IEEE Transactions on Electronic Computers<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>EC-11<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>6<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>753–760<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1962<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1109/TEC.1962.5219459</arg></template></extension><space/>on real-time computations (1962). Somewhat earlier,<space/><link><target>Boris Trakhtenbrot</target></link><space/>(1956), a pioneer in the field from the USSR, studied another specific complexity measure.<extension extension_name='ref'>Trakhtenbrot, B.A.: Signalizing functions and tabular operators. Uchionnye ZapiskiPenzenskogo Pedinstituta (Transactions of the Penza Pedagogoical Institute) 4, 7587 (1956) (in Russian)</extension><space/>As he remembers:<template><target>quote</target><arg>However, [my] initial interest [in automata theory] was increasingly set aside in favor of computational complexity, an exciting fusion of combinatorial methods, inherited from switching theory, with the conceptual arsenal of the theory of algorithms. These ideas had occurred to me earlier in 1955 when I coined the term "signalizing function", which is nowadays commonly known as "complexity measure".
</arg><arg>Boris Trakhtenbrot</arg><arg>From Logic to Theoretical Computer Science – An Update. In: ''Pillars of Computer Science'', LNCS 4800, Springer 2008.
</arg></template>In 1967,<space/><link><target>Manuel Blum</target></link><space/>developed an axiomatic complexity theory based on his<space/><link><target>Blum axioms</target><part>axioms</part></link><space/>and proved an important result, the so-called,<space/><link><target>Blum's speedup theorem</target><part>speed-up theorem</part></link>. The field really began to flourish in 1971 when the US researcher<space/><link><target>Stephen Cook</target></link><space/>and, working independently,<space/><link><target>Leonid Levin</target></link><space/>in the USSR, proved that there exist practically relevant problems that are<space/><link><target>NP-complete</target></link>. In 1972,<space/><link><target>Richard Karp</target></link><space/>took this idea a leap forward with his landmark paper, &quot;Reducibility Among Combinatorial Problems&quot;, in which he showed that 21 diverse<space/><link><target>combinatorics</target><part>combinatorial</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>graph theory</target><part>graph theoretical</part></link><space/>problems, each infamous for its computational intractability, are NP-complete.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="author"><space/>Richard M. Karp<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Reducibility Among Combinatorial Problems<space/></arg><arg name="chapter-url"><space/>http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~luca/cs172/karp.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Complexity of Computer Computations<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>R. E. Miller and J. W. Thatcher (editors)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New York: Plenum<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>85–103<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1972</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Div col</target><arg></arg><arg>25em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>:Category:Computational problems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Context of computational complexity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Descriptive complexity theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Game complexity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of complexity classes</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of computability and complexity topics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of important publications in theoretical computer science</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of unsolved problems in computer science</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Parameterized complexity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Proof complexity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quantum complexity theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Structural complexity theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Transcomputational problem</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Textbooks</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Arora<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Sanjeev<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink1">Sanjeev Arora
</arg><arg name="last2">Barak<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Boaz
</arg><arg name="title">Computational Complexity: A Modern Approach
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cs.princeton.edu/theory/complexity/
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press|Cambridge]]
</arg><arg name="year">2009
</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-42426-4
</arg><arg name="zbl">1193.68112
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Downey
</arg><arg name="first1">Rod
</arg><arg name="last2">Fellows
</arg><arg name="first2">Michael
</arg><arg name="authorlink2">Michael Fellows
</arg><arg name="title">Parameterized complexity
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.springer.com/sgw/cda/frontpage/0,11855,5-0-22-1519914-0,00.html?referer</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Springer-Verlag]]
</arg><arg name="location">Berlin, New York
</arg><arg name="year">1999
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Du
</arg><arg name="first">Ding-Zhu
</arg><arg name="coauthors">Ko, Ker-I
</arg><arg name="title">Theory of Computational Complexity
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[John Wiley & Sons]]
</arg><arg name="year">2000
</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-471-34506-0
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Goldreich
</arg><arg name="first">Oded
</arg><arg name="authorlink">Oded Goldreich
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.wisdom.weizmann.ac.il/~oded/cc-book.html
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Computational Complexity: A Conceptual Perspective
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="editor1-last">van Leeuwen
</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Jan
</arg><arg name="editor1-link"><space/>Jan van Leeuwen
</arg><arg name="title">Handbook of theoretical computer science (vol. A): algorithms and complexity
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[MIT Press]]
</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-444-88071-0
</arg><arg name="year">1990
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Papadimitriou
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Christos
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Christos Papadimitriou
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Computational Complexity
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>1st
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Addison Wesley
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-201-53082-1
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Sipser
</arg><arg name="first">Michael
</arg><arg name="authorlink">Michael Sipser
</arg><arg name="title">[[Introduction to the Theory of Computation]]
</arg><arg name="edition">2nd
</arg><arg name="year">2006
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Thomson Learning|Thomson Course Technology]]
</arg><arg name="location">USA
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-534-95097-3
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Garey-Johnson</target></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Surveys</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Khalil<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Hatem<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Ulery<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Dana<space/></arg><arg name="author2-link">Dana Ulery<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Review of Current Studies on Complexity of Algorithms for Partial Differential Equations<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ACM '76 Proceedings of the 1976 Annual Conference<space/></arg><arg name="year">1976<space/></arg><arg name="pages">197<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://portal.acm.org/citation.cfm?id</arg><arg name="doi">10.1145/800191.805573</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Cook<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Stephen<space/></arg><arg name="author1-link">Stephen Cook<space/></arg><arg name="title">An overview of computational complexity<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ACM<space/></arg><arg name="year">1983<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Commun. ACM<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0001-0782<space/></arg><arg name="volume">26<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="pages">400–408<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1145/358141.358144</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Fortnow<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Lance<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Homer<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Steven<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Short History of Computational Complexity<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Bulletin of the EATCS<space/></arg><arg name="volume">80<space/></arg><arg name="pages">95–133<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://people.cs.uchicago.edu/~fortnow/papers/history.pdf</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Mertens<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Stephan<space/></arg><arg name="title">Computational Complexity for Physicists<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">IEEE Educational Activities Department<space/></arg><arg name="location">Piscataway, NJ, USA<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Computing in Science and Engg.<space/></arg><arg name="issn">1521-9615<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">31–47<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1109/5992.998639<space/></arg><arg name="arxiv">cond-mat/0012185</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://complexityzoo.uwaterloo.ca/Complexity_Zoo'>The Complexity Zoo</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>springer</target><arg name="title">Computational complexity classes</arg><arg name="id">p/c130160</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>ComplexityClasses</target></template><template><target>Computer science</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Computational Complexity Theory</target></template><link><target>Category:Computational complexity theory</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>