<article title='Battle_of_Bouvines'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="date">July 27, 1214
</arg><arg name="conflict">Battle of Bouvines
</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Bataille de Bouvines gagnee par Philippe Auguste.jpg|300px]]
</arg><arg name="caption">''La Bataille de Bouvines'', by [[Horace Vernet]]. ([[Galerie des Batailles]], [[Palace of Versailles]]). The white Arabian horse and [[Moorish]] attendant (right) of Philippe Auguste at the Battle of Bouvines can be seen in this 19th-century painting.
</arg><arg name="partof">the [[Anglo-French war of 1202–14]]
</arg><arg name="date">27 July 1214
</arg><arg name="place">[[Bouvines]], [[County of Flanders]], [[Kingdom of France]]
</arg><arg name="result">Decisive French victory<ref name</arg><arg name="combatant1">[[File:Holy Roman Empire Arms-single head.svg|20px]] [[House of Welf|Holy Roman Empire]]<br>[[File:Blason Nord-Pas-De-Calais.svg|20px]] [[County of Flanders|Flanders]]<br>[[File:England COA.svg|20px]] [[Kingdom of England|England]]<br>[[File:Blason Courtenay.svg|20px]] [[County of Boulogne|Boulogne]]
</arg><arg name="combatant2">[[File:France Ancient.svg|20px]] [[France in the Middle Ages|France]]
</arg><arg name="commander1">[[File:Holy Roman Empire Arms-single head.svg|20px]] [[Otto IV, Holy Roman Emperor|Emperor Otto IV]]<br>[[File:Blason Geoffroy Plantagenet.svg|20px]] [[William de Longespee, 3rd Earl of Salisbury|William de Longespee]] {{POW}}<br>[[File:Blason Courtenay.svg|20px]] [[Renaud de Dammartin|Renaud of Boulogne]] {{POW}}<br>[[File:Blason Nord-Pas-De-Calais.svg|20px]] [[Infante Fernando, Count of Flanders|Ferrand of Flanders]] {{POW}}<br>[[File:Blason Lorraine.svg|15px]] [[Theobald I, Duke of Lorraine]] {{POW}}<br>[[File:Coat of arms of Brabant.svg|20px]] [[Henry I, Duke of Brabant]]
</arg><arg name="commander2">[[File:France Ancient.svg|20px]] [[Philip II of France|Philip II, King of France]]<br><space/>[[File:Blason Comtes Dreux.png|20px]] [[Robert II of Dreux|Robert II, Count of Dreux]]<br>[[File:France Ancient.svg|20px]] [[Philip of Dreux]]<br>[[File:Blason Ducs Bourgogne (ancien).svg|20px]] [[Eudes III, Duke of Burgundy|Eudes III of Burgundy]]<br>[[File:Armoiries Ponthieu.png|20px]] [[William IV, Count of Ponthieu|William II of Ponthieu]]
</arg><arg name="strength1">25,000 men<ref name</arg><arg name="strength2">15,000 men<ref name</arg><arg name="casualties1">≈1,000 dead<ref name</arg><arg name="casualties2">≈1,000 dead<ref name</arg></template><template><target>Campaignbox Anglo-French Bouvines</target></template><link><target>File:Bataille de Bouvines.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>French and Imperial knights clashing</part></link><link><target>File:Philippe II's victory at Bouvines.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>King<space/><link><target>Philip II of France</target></link>'s victory at Bouvines, by<space/><link><target>Vincent of Beauvais</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Prisonniers Bouvines.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ferrand of Flanders and Renaud of Boulogne marched as prisoners to Paris</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Battle of Bouvines,</bold><space/>which took place on 27 July 1214, was a medieval battle which ended the<space/><link><target>Anglo-French War (120214)</target><part>12021214 Anglo-French War</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://xenophongroup.com/montjoie/bouvines.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 September 2008</arg><arg name="title">The 'War' of Bouvines (1202-1214)</arg></template></extension><space/>It was fundamental in the early development of<space/><link><target>France in the Middle Ages</target></link><space/>by confirming the French crown's<space/><link><target>sovereignty</target></link><space/>over the<space/><link><target>Angevin Empire</target><part>Angevin lands</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Duchy of Brittany</target><part>Brittany</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Duchy of Normandy</target><part>Normandy</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Philip II of France</target><part>Philip Augustus</part></link><space/>of France defeated an army consisting of<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target><part>Imperial German</part></link>, English and Flemish soldiers, led by<space/><link><target>Otto IV of Germany</target></link>. Other leaders included Count<space/><link><target>Ferdinand, Prince of Portugal</target><part>Ferrand of Flanders</part></link>,<space/><link><target>William de Longespee, 3rd Earl of Salisbury</target><part>William de Longespee</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Renaud de Dammartin</target><part>Renaud of Boulogne</part></link>. The defeat was so decisive that Otto was deposed and replaced by<space/><link><target>Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Frederick II</part></link><space/><link><target>House of Hohenstaufen</target><part>Hohenstaufen</part></link>; Ferrand and Renaud were captured and imprisoned and<space/><link><target>John of England</target><part>King John of England</part></link><space/>was forced to agree to the<space/><link><target>Magna Carta</target></link><space/>by his discontented barons. Philip was himself able to take undisputed control of most of the territories in France that had belonged to King John of England, Otto's maternal uncle and ally.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Prelude</heading><paragraph>In 1214,<space/><link><target>Ferdinand, Count of Flanders</target><part>Ferdinand, Infante of Portugal, and Count of Flanders</part></link><space/>desired the return of the cities of Aire-sur-la-Lys and Saint-Omer, which he had recently lost to<space/><link><target>Philip II of France</target><part>Philip II, King of France</part></link><space/>in the Treaty of Pont--Vendin. He thus broke allegiance with Philip and assembled a broad coalition including<space/><link><target>Otto IV, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Emperor Otto IV</part></link>,<space/><link><target>John, King of England</target><part>King John I of England</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Henry I, Duke of Brabant</target><part>Duke Henry I of Brabant</part></link>,<space/><link><target>William I, Count of Holland</target><part>Count William I of Holland</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Theobald I, Duke of Lorraine</target><part>Duke Theobald I of Lorraine</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Henry III, Duke of Limburg</target><part>Duke Henry III of Limburg</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The campaign was planned by John, who was the fulcrum of the alliance; his plan was to draw the French away from Paris southward towards his forces and keep them occupied, while the main army, under Emperor Otto IV, marched on Paris from the north. John's plan was carried out at first, but the allies in the north moved slowly. John, after two encounters with the French, retreated to<space/><link><target>Aquitaine</target></link><space/>on 3 July.</paragraph><paragraph>On 23 July, after having summoned all his<space/><link><target>vassal</target><trail>s</trail></link>, Philip had an army consisting of 4,000 cavalry and 11,000-foot soldiers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BF1">Batailles franaise 1214 1559 du colonel Hard de Prini</extension><space/>The emperor finally succeeded in concentrating his forces at<space/><link><target>Valenciennes</target></link>, although John was out of the picture, and in the interval Philip Augustus had counter marched northward and regrouped. Philip now took the offensive himself, and in maneuvering to get a good cavalry ground upon which to fight he offered battle (27 July), on the plain east of Bouvines and the river Marque.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension><space/>Otto was surprised by the speed of his enemy and was thought to have been caught unprepared by the King of France<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://bataille.bouvines.free.fr/plans/plangen.php3?np=07'>The chroniclers say that Otto also strongly expressed his surprise to find himself facing the French army, while he believed they were on the run.</link></extension><space/>(who probably attracted the emperor into this trap<extension extension_name='ref'>This is the hypothesis of the rhyming chronicles by Philippe Mousket: &quot;At the approach of night, gathered the council, between him and his barons, For the good king, with his armies (around 21,555) wanted to go to Mortagne. But those of his followers knew not how to advise him. When everyone had said his piece, with the best of intentions, (v.21560) Girard the Sow spoke : &quot;Sire, will you not go there; Truly, there are difficulties and harshness, and there are also three large villages and two small rivers beyond (v.21565) that prevent us passing to reach this place. But if you return towards your land, and the Flemings, who want war, if you turn back, will say that you flee, (v.21570) And when you follow this path with pride, with confidence, without any order, as all of us want to be Sire, and you, without crown or anger. Command a good rearguard, (v.21575) So that they are never separated. And also save your battles, and keep your soldiers close to their arms as a ruse. They will be ready if they are attacked. (v.21580) When you see the Flemings coming, they will be at your convenience.&quot; Everything was well accepted, and nothing more was discussed. they all went to sleep, (v.21585) And when the day came, the king drew up his battle, and made his orders to the troops. The carting and pack animals left the front during this time. (v.21590) &quot;</extension>). Although he was under a Church<space/><link><target>interdict</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>The Elne synod decreed in 1027, that &quot;It is prohibited to attack the enemy from the ninth hour on Saturday until the early hours of Monday&quot;</extension><space/>Otto, already an excommunicate,<extension extension_name='ref'>Otto IV had promised Innocent III large territorial gains and support in the kingdom of Sicily. For failing to honour these promises, he was excommunicated in 1210 and 1211.</extension><space/>decided to launch an attack on what was then the French rearguard. Philippe Auguste gave battle. His army quickly retreated.</paragraph><paragraph>The Allied army drew up facing south-westward towards Bouvines, the heavy cavalry on the wings, the infantry in one great mass in the center, supported by the cavalry corps under the emperor himself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension><space/>The total force was estimated at 25,000 men; a much larger force of foot soldiers and slightly fewer cavalry than the French.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Army"></extension><space/>The French army of 15,000 men<extension extension_name='ref' name="Army"></extension><space/>took ground exactly opposite in a similar formation, cavalry on the wings, infantry, including the town militias in the centre, Philip with the cavalry reserve and the royal standard, the<space/><link><target>Oriflamme</target></link>, in rear of the men on foot.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension><space/>Philip's army contained about 2,000 knights (750 were from the<space/><link><target>Crown lands of France</target><part>royal demesne</part></link>) and 2,000 mounted sergeants with the rest being infantry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bradbury283">J. Bradbury,<space/><italics>Philip Augustus: King of France 11801223</italics>, 283</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Order of battle</heading><paragraph>Even today, the evaluation of forces is controversial. The classic French historiography often refers to Coalition troops three times more numerous than those of the King of France.<space/><link><target>Philippe Contamine</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aibl.fr/fr/membres/academ/contamine.html'>The opinion of Philippe Contamine</link></extension><space/>is not of this opinion: &quot;On the face of it, his opponents did not have a clear numerical superiority&quot;. It is said by<space/><link><target>William the Breton</target></link>, chaplain to Philip at the Battle of Bouvines, that the lines of soldiers stood in line in a space of 40 000 steps (15 hectares),<extension extension_name='ref'>La Philippide de Guillaume le Breton</extension><space/>which leaves very little clearance and predisposes to hand-to-hand fighting (<link><target>melee</target></link>). William the Breton also says in his column that<space/><italics>the two lines of combatants were separated by a pretty small space</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Philip Augustus had then launched an appeal to the municipalities in northern France, in order to obtain their support.</paragraph><paragraph>Seventeen of the thirty-nine municipalities of the<space/><link><target>Crown lands of France</target><part>royal demesne</part></link><space/>answered the call for<space/><link><target>militia</target></link>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Arras</target></link><space/>sent 1,000 men.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Abbeville</target></link><space/>region sent 2,000 men.</listitem><listitem>Paris sent a corps of 2,000 men, 1,750 of whom fought on the battlefield.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dictionary of streets and monuments in Paris and Louis Felix Lazarus 1879 Chapter III Page 13</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In total, the royal army totalled 7,000 soldiers.</paragraph><paragraph>The royal army was divided into three parts:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The right wing, composed of knights of<space/><link><target>Champagne, France</target><part>Champagne</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Franche-Comt</target><part>Burgundy</part></link>, was commanded by the Duke of Burgundy Eudes and his lieutenants: III Gaucher de Chtillon Count of Saint-Pol, Count Wilhelm I of Sancerre, Count of Beaumont and Mathieu de Montmorency and Adam II Viscount of Melun. In the front of the right wing were men of arms and militia from the parishes of Burgundy, Champagne, and<space/><link><target>Picardy (region)</target><part>Picardy</part></link><space/>led by mounted sergeants from<space/><link><target>Soissons</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The central battle was conducted by<space/><link><target>Philip Augustus</target></link><space/>and his chief knights William des Barres, Bartholomew of Roye, Girard Scophe known as &quot;Girard the Sow&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Girard Scophe was called the Sow, due to the Latin equivalent of his name: scrofa</extension><space/>William of Garland,<space/><link><target>Enguerrand III de Coucy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Duke of Nemours</target><part>Gautier de Nemours</part></link>. In front of the king and his knights were infantry from the towns of<space/><link><target>le de France</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Normandy</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The left wing, composed of knights and foot soldiers was led by<space/><link><target>Robert III, Count of Dreux</target><part>Robert of Dreux</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>William IV, Count of Ponthieu</target><part>Count William of Ponthieu</part></link>. The main body of the left wing consisted of Breton police and militia from<space/><link><target>Dreux</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Perche</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ponthieu</target></link>, and Vimeux.</listitem></list><paragraph>The bridge of Bouvines, the only means of retreat across the marshes, was guarded by 150 sergeants at arms of the king who formed the only reserve for the French.</paragraph><paragraph>Otto also divided his army into three groups:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The left flank, under the command of<space/><link><target>Ferdinand, Prince of Portugal</target><part>Ferrand of Flanders</part></link><space/>with his Flemish knights directed by Arnaud of Oudenaarde. The soldiers were from<space/><link><target>Flanders</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>County of Hainaut</target><part>Hainaut</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>The centre under the command of Otto and of<space/><link><target>Theobald I, Duke of Lorraine</target><part>Theobald Duke of Lorraine</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Henry I, Duke of Brabant</target><part>Henry Duke of Brabant</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Philip II, Marquis of Namur</target><part>Philip Courtenay Marquis of Namur</part></link>: together with many Saxon soldiers, knights, and infantry from<space/><link><target>Duchy of Brabant</target><part>Brabant</part></link><space/>and Germany. In front of the centre stood German infantry phalanxes formed deep, bristling with pikes and flanked by companies formed at each corner, then in the second line the Saxon infantry in reserve. Otto stood in between surrounded by 50 German knights.</listitem><listitem>The right flank, under the command of<space/><link><target>Renaud de Dammartin</target></link>, included equally Brabant infantry and English knights under the command of the<space/><link><target>William Longespe, 3rd Earl of Salisbury</target><part>Earl of Salisbury William Longespe</part></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>At the extreme right, the English archers supported the flank of both the Brabant infantry and the nobles of the two Lorraines.<extension extension_name='ref'>i.e.<space/><link><target>Duchy of Lorraine</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>County of Bar</target></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Battle</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template>The battle opened with a confused cavalry fight on the French right, in which individual feats of knightly gallantry were more noticeable (and better recorded in the chronicles) than any attempt at combined action. The serious fighting was between the two centers. The infantry of the Low Countries, who were at this time among the best in Europe, drove back the French. Philip led the cavalry reserve of nobles and knights to retrieve the day, and after a long and doubtful fight (in which he himself was unhorsed and narrowly escaped death), began to drive back the Flemings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile on the French left Robert de Dreux's troops are at first pressed by men led by William Longespe and Renaud de Dammartin are forced to defend the Bouvines bridge foot by foot. William Longespe was unhorsed and taken prisoner by<space/><link><target>Philip of Dreux</target></link>, (a.k.a. the fighting<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Diocese of Beauvais</target><part>Bishop of Beauvais</part></link>) and the English soldiers fled.<space/><link><target>Matthieu II of Montmorency</target><part>Mathieu de Montmorency</part></link><space/>captured twelve enemy banners (in memory of this feat, the shield of Montmorency includes an additional twelve eagles or sixteen altogether instead of four previously<extension extension_name='ref'>Gabriel Eysenbach,<space/><italics>History of Heraldry and the Science of Coats-of-Arms</italics>, 1848,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=WPRUAwtJkEoC&amp;amp;hl=fr&amp;amp;pg=PA321#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 321</link>. (Fr)</extension>).</paragraph><paragraph>On the other wing the French at last routed the Flemish cavalry and captured<space/><link><target>Ferdinand, Count of Flanders</target></link>, one of the leaders of the coalition. In the centre the battle was now a melee between the two mounted reserves led by the King and the Emperor in person. Here too the Imperial forces suffered defeat, Otto himself being saved only by the devotion of a handful of Saxon knights.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension><space/>The Imperial Eagle Standard was captured by the French.</paragraph><paragraph>The day was already decided in favour of the French when their wings began to close inwards to cut off the retreat of the imperial centre. The battle closed with the celebrated stand of<space/><link><target>Reginald of Boulogne</target></link><space/>(Renaud de Dammartin), a former vassal of King Philip, who formed a ring of seven hundred<space/><link><target>Brabant (duchy)</target><part>Brabant</part></link><space/>pikemen, and not only defied every attack of the French cavalry, but himself made repeated charges or sorties with his small force of knights. Eventually, and long after the Imperial army had begun its retreat, the gallant<space/><link><target>Sheltron</target><part>schiltrom</part></link><space/>formation was ridden down and annihilated by a charge of three thousand men-at-arms. Reginald was taken prisoner in the melee. The prisoners also included two other counts, Hainaut Ferrand and<space/><link><target>William Longespe, 3rd Earl of Salisbury</target><part>William Longespe</part></link>, twenty-five barons and over a hundred knights. The death toll amounted to about 170 knights of the defeated party, and many thousands of foot soldiers on either side.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB1911"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph>According to Jean Favier, Bouvines is &quot;one of the most decisive and symbolic battles in the history of France&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Dictionnaire de la France mdivale</italics>, Paris, Fayard, 1993, p. 176</extension><space/>For Philippe Contamine, &quot;the battle of Bouvines had both important consequences and a great impact&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Histoire militaire de la France</italics><space/>(tome 1, des origines 1715), Paris, PUF, 1992, p. 83</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Philip returned to<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link><space/>triumphant, marching his captive prisoners behind him in a long procession, as his grateful subjects came out to greet the victorious king. In the aftermath of the battle, Otto retreated to his castle of<space/><link><target>Harzburg</target></link><space/>and was soon overthrown as<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Emperor</target></link>, and replaced by<space/><link><target>Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Frederick II</part></link>. Count Ferdinand remained imprisoned following his defeat, while King John obtained a five-year truce, on very lenient terms given the circumstances.</paragraph><paragraph>Philip's decisive victory was crucial in ordering politics in both England and France. In the former, so weakened was the defeated King<space/><link><target>John of England</target></link><space/>that he soon needed to submit to his barons demands and agree to the<space/><link><target>Magna Carta</target></link>, limiting the power of the crown and establishing the basis for common law. In the latter, the battle was instrumental in forming the<space/><link><target>Absolute monarchy in France</target><part>strong central monarchy</part></link><space/>that would characterize France until the first<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>. It was also the first battle in the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link><space/>in which the full value of infantry was realized.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Edward Smedley</target><part>Smedley, Edward</part></link>.<space/><italics>The History of France, from the Final Partition of the Empire of Charlemagne to the Peace of Cambray</italics>, p. 72, London: Baldwin and Cradock, 1836.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Philip conquered most of Plantagenet's continental possessions, namely<space/><link><target>Anjou</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Brittany</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Maine (province)</target><part>Maine</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Duchy of Normandy</target><part>Normandy</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Touraine</target></link>, leading to the effective end of the<space/><link><target>Angevin Empire</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Commemoration</heading><paragraph>In thanksgiving for the victory, Philip Augustus founded the Abbey of Notre Dame de la Victoire, between Senlis and Mont l'Evque.<extension extension_name='ref'>Auguste Morel,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.fr/books?id=7iMjRpkY1o4C&amp;amp;pg=PA280&amp;amp;dq=%22abbaye+de+la+Victoire%22&amp;amp;hl=fr&amp;amp;ei=W0ruS6OSG5qGnQOztLH0Cw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=false'>''De Paris Cologne, Bruxelles, Senlis, Laon... itinraire descriptif et historique''</link>, Libr. de L. Hachette et Cie., 1864, p. 280</extension><link><target>File:St Pol.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A detail of one of the stained-glass windows installed in the parish church of Bouvines in 1914</part></link>In 1914, to mark the seventh centenary,<space/><link><target>Flix Dehau</target></link><space/>had the parish church of Bouvines rebuilt with a number of stained-glass windows representing the history of the battle.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Georges Duby</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Legend of Bouvines</italics><space/>(1990). In a careful study of the historiography of a single event, Duby examines how the Battle of Bouvines has been used and abused in French history.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Wargames</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Frdric Bey</target></link>,<space/><italics>Swords of Sovereignty: Bouvines 1214 and Worringen 1288</italics>, Au Fil de l'pe series,<space/><italics><link><target>Ludifolie Editions</target></link></italics><space/>(2012)</listitem><listitem>[Rob Markham] Age of Chivalry Quad - [3w wargames 1992]</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.deremilitari.org/RESOURCES/SOURCES/bouvines.htm'>Historical accounts</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://xenophongroup.com/montjoie/bouvines.htm'>Bouvines</link>: the battle in the context of the campaign in the war of 12021214</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg><arg name="refs">
<ref name</arg></template><template><target>coord</target><arg>50</arg><arg>35</arg><arg>0</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>3</arg><arg>13</arg><arg>30</arg><arg>E</arg><arg>type:event_region:FR</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Bouvines</target></template><link><target>Category:1214 in France</target></link><link><target>Category:Battles involving France</target><part>Bouvines 1214</part></link><link><target>Category:Battles involving the Holy Roman Empire</target><part>Bouvines 1214</part></link><link><target>Category:Battles involving Flanders</target><part>Bouvines 1214</part></link><link><target>Category:History of Nord (French department)</target></link><link><target>Category:Conflicts in 1214</target></link></paragraph></article>