<article title='Abraham_Joshua_Heschel'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the Polish-born American philosopher</arg><arg>the Polish Hasidic rabbi</arg><arg>Avraham Yehoshua Heshel</arg><arg>the 17th-century chief rabbi of Krakow</arg><arg>Avraham Yehoshua Heschel</arg></template><template><target>Infobox Jewish leader</target><arg name="honorific-prefix">
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Abraham Joshua Heschel
</arg><arg name="honorific-suffix"><space/>
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image">SelmaHeschelMarch.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Rabbi Abraham Joshua Heschel (2nd from right) in the [[Selma to Montgomery marches|Selma Civil Rights March]] with [[Martin Luther King]], Jr. (4th from right)<ref>Heschel later wrote, "When I marched in Selma, my feet were praying."</ref>
</arg><arg name="denomination"><space/>Orthodox, Conservative
</arg><arg name="synagogue">
</arg><arg name="synagogueposition">
</arg><arg name="yeshiva">
</arg><arg name="yeshivaposition">
</arg><arg name="organization">
</arg><arg name="organizationposition">
</arg><arg name="began"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ended"><space/>
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="semicha"><space/>
</arg><arg name="rabbi"><space/>
</arg><arg name="rank"><space/>
</arg><arg name="other_post"><space/>
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1907|01|11|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Warsaw]], [[Congress Poland]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1972|12|23|1907|01|11|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[New York]], US
</arg><arg name="buried"><space/>
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>Polish
</arg><arg name="residence"><space/>
</arg><arg name="parents"><space/>Moshe Mordechai Heschel, Reizel Perlow
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>Sylvia Straus
</arg><arg name="children"><space/>[[Susannah Heschel]]
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>
</arg><arg name="profession"><space/>Professor
</arg><arg name="employer"><space/>[[Jewish Theological Seminary of America]]
</arg><arg name="alma_mater"><space/>[[University of Berlin]]
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Abraham Joshua Heschel</bold><space/>(January 11, 1907&amp;nbsp; December 23, 1972) was a Polish-born American<space/><link><target>rabbi</target></link><space/>and one of the leading<space/><link><target>Jew</target><trail>ish</trail></link><space/>theologians and Jewish philosophers of the 20th century. Heschel, a professor of<space/><link><target>Jewish mysticism</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Jewish Theological Seminary of America</target></link>, authored a number of widely read books on<space/><link><target>Jewish philosophy</target></link><space/>and was active in the<space/><link><target>American Civil Rights movement</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tikkun.org/nextgen/the-legacy-of-abraham-joshua-heschel'>&quot;The Legacy of Abraham Joshua Heschel.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Tikkun</italics>. Accessed May 25, 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2007/12/24/arts/24conn.html'>&quot;A Rabbi of His Time, With a Charisma That Transcends It.&quot;</link><space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>. Accessed May 25, 2014.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><paragraph>Abraham Joshua Heschel was born in 1907 as the youngest of six children of Moshe Mordechai and Reizel Perlow. He was descended from preeminent European<space/><link><target>rabbi</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on both sides of his family.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"></extension><space/>His paternal great-great-grandfather and namesake was<space/><link><target>Rebbe</target></link><space/><link><target>Avraham Yehoshua Heshel</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Opatw</target><part>Apt</part></link><space/>in present-day<space/><link><target>Poland</target></link>. His mother was also a descendant of Avraham Yehoshua Heshel and other<space/><link><target>Hasidic dynasties</target></link>. His siblings were Sarah, Dvora Miriam, Esther Sima, Gittel, and Jacob. Their father Moshe died of<space/><link><target>influenza</target></link><space/>in 1916 when Abraham was nine.</paragraph><paragraph>After a traditional<space/><link><target>yeshiva</target></link><space/>education and studying for Orthodox rabbinical ordination<space/><link><target>semicha</target></link>, Heschel pursued his doctorate at the<space/><link><target>University of Berlin</target></link><space/>and a liberal rabbinic ordination at the<space/><link><target>Hochschule fr die Wissenschaft des Judentums</target></link>. There he studied under some of the finest Jewish educators of the time:<space/><link><target>Hanoch Albeck</target><part>Chanoch Albeck</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Ismar Elbogen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Julius Guttmann</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Leo Baeck</target></link>. Heschel later taught<space/><link><target>Talmud</target></link><space/>there. He joined a<space/><link><target>Yiddish</target></link><space/>poetry group, Jung Vilna, and in 1933, published a volume of Yiddish poems,<space/><italics>Der Shem Hamefoyrosh: Mentsch,</italics><space/>dedicated to his father.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"><link type='external' href='http://home.versatel.nl/heschel/Susannah.htm'>Abraham Joshua Heschel</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In late October 1938, when Heschel was living in a rented room in the home of a Jewish family in<space/><link><target>Frankfurt</target></link>, he was arrested by the<space/><link><target>Gestapo</target></link><space/>and deported to Poland. He spent ten months lecturing on<space/><link><target>Jewish philosophy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Torah</target></link><space/>at Warsaw's<space/><link><target>Institute for Jewish Studies</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"></extension><space/>Six weeks before the<space/><link><target>Occupation of Poland (193945)</target><part>German invasion of Poland</part></link>, Heschel left Warsaw for<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>with the help of<space/><link><target>Julian Morgenstern</target></link>, president of<space/><link><target>Hebrew Union College</target></link>, who had been working to obtain visas for Jewish scholars in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Heschel's sister Esther was killed in a German bombing. His mother was murdered by the<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target><part>Nazis</part></link>, and two other sisters, Gittel and Devorah, died in<space/><link><target>Nazi concentration camps</target></link>. He never returned to<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Austria</target></link><space/>or Poland. He once wrote, &quot;If I should go to Poland or Germany, every stone, every tree would remind me of contempt, hatred, murder, of children killed, of mothers burned alive, of human beings asphyxiated.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Heschel arrived in<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link><space/>in March 1940.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vzexea"></extension><space/>He served on the faculty of<space/><link><target>Hebrew Union College</target></link><space/>(HUC), the main seminary of<space/><link><target>Reform Judaism (North America)</target><part>Reform Judaism</part></link>, in<space/><link><target>Cincinnati, Ohio</target><part>Cincinnati</part></link><space/>for five years. In 1946, he took a position at the<space/><link><target>Jewish Theological Seminary of America</target></link><space/>(JTS) in New York City, the main seminary of<space/><link><target>Conservative Judaism</target></link>. He served as professor of<space/><link><target>Jewish ethics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kabbalah</target><part>Mysticism</part></link><space/>until his death in 1972.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Marriage and family</heading><paragraph>Heschel married Sylvia Straus, a concert pianist, on December 10, 1946, in<space/><link><target>Los Angeles</target></link>. Their daughter,<space/><link><target>Susannah Heschel</target></link>, became a Jewish scholar in her own right.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ushmm.org/museum/exhibit/focus/antisemitism/voices/transcript/?content=20071122'>Interview with Susannah Heschel</link></extension><space/>Heschel's papers are held in the<space/><link><target>Rubenstein Rare Book &amp; Manuscript Library</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Duke University</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://today.duke.edu/2012/08/heschel'>Duke to Acquire Papers of Rabbi Heschel, Influential Religious Leader</link>, Duke University, August 2012</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ideology</heading><paragraph>Heschel explicated many facets of Jewish thought, including studies on medieval Jewish<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kabbalah</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Hasidism</target></link>. According to some scholars, he was more interested in spirituality than in critical text study; the latter was a specialty of many scholars at JTS. He was not given a graduate assistant for many years and was relegated to teach mainly in the education school or Rabbinical school, not in the academic graduate program. Heschel became quite friendly with his colleague<space/><link><target>Mordecai Kaplan</target></link>. Though they differed in their approach to Judaism, they had a very cordial relationship and visited each other's homes from time to time.</paragraph><paragraph>Heschel believed the teachings of the Hebrew prophets were a clarion call for social action in the United States and worked for African Americans'<space/><link><target>civil rights</target></link><space/>and against the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Dreier</arg><arg name="first1">Peter</arg><arg name="title">'Selma's' Missing Rabbi</arg><arg name="url">http://www.huffingtonpost.com/peter-dreier/selmas-missing-rabbi_b_6491368.html/</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 March 2015</arg><arg name="publisher">Huffington Post</arg><arg name="date">January 17, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He also specifically criticized what he called &quot;pan-halakhism&quot;, or an exclusive focus upon religiously compatible behavior to the neglect of the non-legalistic dimension of rabbinic tradition.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Influence outside Judaism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Abraham Heschel with MLK.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Heschel, presenting Judaism and World Peace Award to Dr.<space/><link><target>Martin Luther King, Jr.</target></link>, December 7, 1965</part></link>Heschel is a widely read Jewish theologian whose most influential works include<space/><italics>Man Is Not Alone</italics>,<space/><italics>God in Search of Man</italics>,<space/><italics>The Sabbath,</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>The Prophets</italics>. At the<space/><link><target>Vatican Council II</target></link>, as representative of<space/><link><target>American Jews</target></link>, Heschel persuaded the<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target></link><space/>to eliminate or modify passages in its liturgy that demeaned the Jews, or referred to an expected conversion to Christianity. His theological works argued that religious experience is a fundamentally human impulse, not just a Jewish one. He believed that no religious community could claim a monopoly on religious truth.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gillman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Neil<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Neil Gillman</arg><arg name="title">Conservative Judaism: The New Century<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Behrman House Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>163<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Published work</heading><heading level='3'><italics>The Sabbath</italics><space/>(1951)</heading><paragraph><italics>The Sabbath: Its Meaning for Modern Man</italics><space/>is a work on the nature and celebration of<space/><link><target>Shabbat</target></link>, the Jewish Sabbath. This work is rooted in the thesis that Judaism is a religion of time, not space, and that the Sabbath symbolizes the sanctification of time.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Man Is Not Alone</italics><space/>(1951)</heading><paragraph><italics>Man Is Not Alone: A Philosophy of Religion</italics><space/>offers Heschel's views on how people can comprehend God. Judaism views God as being radically different from humans, so Heschel explores the ways that Judaism teaches that a person may have an encounter with the ineffable. A recurring theme in this work is the radical amazement that people feel when experiencing the presence of the Divine. Heschel then goes on to explore the problems of doubts and faith; what Judaism means by teaching that God is one; the essence of humanity and the problem of human needs; the definition of religion in general and of Judaism in particular; and human yearning for spirituality. He offers his views as to Judaism being a pattern for life.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>God in Search of Man</italics><space/>(1955)</heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>God in Search of Man</target><part>God in Search of Man: A Philosophy of Judaism</part></link></italics><space/>is a companion volume to<space/><italics>Man Is Not Alone</italics>. In this book Heschel discusses the nature of religious thought, how thought becomes faith, and how faith creates responses in the believer. He discusses ways that people can seek God's presence, and the radical amazement that we receive in return. He offers a criticism of nature worship; a study of humanity's metaphysical loneliness, and his view that we can consider God to be in search of humanity. The first section concludes with a study of<space/><link><target>Jews as a chosen people</target></link>. Section two deals with the idea of<space/><link><target>revelation</target></link>, and what it means for one to be a prophet. This section gives us his idea of revelation as an event, as opposed to a process. This relates to Israel's commitment to God. Section three discusses his views of how a Jew should understand the nature of Judaism as a religion. He discusses and rejects the idea that mere faith (without law) alone is enough, but then cautions against rabbis he sees as adding too many restrictions to Jewish law. He discusses the need to correlate ritual observance with spirituality and love, the importance of<space/><link><target>Kavanah</target></link><space/>(intention) when performing<space/><link><target>mitzvot</target></link>. He engages in a discussion of religious behaviorismwhen people strive for external compliance with the law, yet disregard the importance of inner devotion.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>The Prophets</italics><space/>(1962)</heading><paragraph>This work started out as his Ph.D. thesis in German, which he later expanded and translated into English. Originally published in a two-volume edition, this work studies the books of the Hebrew prophets. It covers their lives and the historical context that their missions were set in, summarizes their work, and discusses their psychological state. In it Heschel puts forward what would become a central idea in his theology: that the prophetic (and, ultimately, Jewish) view of God is best understood not as anthropomorphic (that God takes human form) but rather as anthropopathicthat God has human feelings.</paragraph><paragraph>In his book<space/><italics>The Prophets</italics>, Abraham Joshua Heschel describes the unique aspect of the Jewish prophets as compared to other similar figures. Whereas other nations have soothsayers and diviners who attempt to discover the will of their gods, according to Heschel the Hebrew prophets are characterized by their experience of what he calls theotropismGod turning towards humanity. Heschel argues for the view of Hebrew prophets as receivers of the &quot;Divine<space/><link><target>Pathos</target></link>&quot;, of the wrath and sorrow of God over his nation that has forsaken him. In this view, prophets do not speak for God so much as they remind their audience of God's voice for the voiceless, the poor and oppressed.</paragraph><paragraph>He writes:<template><target>Quote</target><arg>Prophecy is the voice that God has lent to the silent agony, a voice to the plundered poor, to the profane riches of the world. It is a form of living, a crossing point of God and man. God is raging in the prophet's words.</arg><arg>Abraham Joshua Heschel</arg><arg>''The Prophets Ch.&nbsp;1</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Torah min HaShamayim</italics><space/>(1962)</heading><paragraph>Many consider Heschel's<space/><italics>Torah min HaShamayim BeAspaklariya shel HaDorot</italics>, (<italics>Torah from Heaven in the mirror of the generations</italics>) to be his masterwork. The three volumes of this work are a study of classical rabbinic theology and<space/><link><target>aggadah</target></link>, as opposed to<space/><link><target>halakha</target></link><space/>(Jewish law.) It explores the views of the rabbis in the<space/><link><target>Mishnah</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Talmud</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Midrash</target></link><space/>about the nature of<space/><link><target>Torah</target></link>, the revelation of God to mankind, prophecy, and the ways that Jews have used scriptural exegesis to expand and understand these core Jewish texts. In this work, Heschel views the 2nd century sages Rabbis<space/><link><target>Akiva ben Yosef</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ishmael ben Elisha</target></link><space/>as paradigms for the two dominant world-views in Jewish theology</paragraph><paragraph>Two Hebrew volumes were published during his lifetime by<space/><link><target>Soncino Press</target></link>, and the third Hebrew volume was published posthumously by JTS Press in the 1990s. An English translation of all three volumes, with notes, essays and appendices, was translated and edited by Rabbi<space/><link><target>Gordon Tucker</target></link>, entitled<space/><italics>Heavenly Torah: As Refracted Through the Generations</italics>. In its own right it can be the subject of intense study and analysis, and provides insight into the relationship between God and Man beyond the world of Judaism and for all Monotheism.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Prophetic Inspiration After the Prophets</italics><space/>(1966)</heading><paragraph>Heschel wrote a series of articles, originally in Hebrew, on the existence of prophecy in Judaism after the destruction of the Holy<space/><link><target>Temple in Jerusalem</target></link><space/>in 70 CE. These essays were translated into English and published as<space/><italics>Prophetic Inspiration After the Prophets: Maimonides and Others</italics><space/>by the American Judaica publisher<space/><link><target>Ktav</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The publisher of this book states, &quot;The standard Jewish view is that prophecy ended with the ancient prophets, somewhere early in the Second Temple era. Heschel demonstrated that this view is not altogether accurate. Belief in the possibility of continued prophetic inspiration, and in its actual occurrence appear throughout much of the medieval period, and even in modern times. Heschel's work on prophetic inspiration in the Middle Ages originally appeared in two long Hebrew articles. In them he concentrated on the idea that prophetic inspiration was possible even in post-Talmudic times, and, indeed, had taken place at various times and in various schools, from the<space/><link><target>Geonim</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Maimonides</target></link><space/>and beyond.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Commemoration</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:AJ Heschel school 270 W89 jeh.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Abraham Joshua Heschel School</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Manhattan</target></link></part></link>Four schools have been named for Heschel, in the<space/><link><target>Upper West Side</target></link><space/>of New York City,<space/><link><target>Northridge, California</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Agoura Hills, California</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Toronto, Canada</target></link>. In 2009, a highway in Missouri was named &quot;Dr. Abraham Joshua Heschel Highway&quot; after a<space/><link><target>Springfield, Missouri</target></link><space/>area Neo-Nazi group cleaned the stretch of highway as part of an &quot;Adopt-A-Highway&quot; plan. Heschel's daughter, Susannah, has objected to the adoption of her father's name in this context.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2009/06/23/us/23heschel.html?ref</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="title">Daughter Against Use of Father’s Name to Subvert Neo-Nazis<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="last">Cooper<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 23, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">March 26, 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Selected bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Earth Is the Lord's: The Inner World of the Jew in Eastern Europe</italics>. 1949. ISBN 1-879045-42-7</listitem><listitem><italics>Man Is Not Alone: A Philosophy of Religion</italics>. 1951. ISBN 0-374-51328-7</listitem><listitem><italics>The Sabbath: Its Meaning for Modern Man</italics>. 1951. ISBN 1-59030-082-3</listitem><listitem><italics>Man's Quest for God: Studies in Prayer and Symbolism</italics>. 1954. ISBN 0-684-16829-4</listitem><listitem><italics>God in Search of Man: A Philosophy of Judaism</italics>. 1955. ISBN 0-374-51331-7</listitem><listitem><italics>The Prophets</italics>. 1962. ISBN 0-06-093699-1</listitem><listitem><italics>Who Is Man?</italics><space/>1965. ISBN 0-8047-0266-7</listitem><listitem><italics>Israel: An Echo of Eternity</italics>. 1969. ISBN 1-879045-70-2</listitem><listitem><italics>A Passion for Truth</italics>. 1973. ISBN 1-879045-41-9</listitem><listitem><italics>Heavenly Torah: As Refracted Through the Generations</italics>. 2005. ISBN 0-8264-0802-8</listitem><listitem><italics>Torah min ha-shamayim be'aspaklariya shel ha-dorot; Theology of Ancient Judaism</italics>. [Hebrew]. 2 vols. London: Soncino Press, 1962. Third volume, New York: Jewish Theological Seminary, 1995.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Ineffable Name of God: Man: Poems</italics>. 2004. ISBN 0-8264-1632-2</listitem><listitem><italics>Kotsk: in gerangl far emesdikeyt</italics>. [Yiddish]. 2 v. (694 p.) Tel-Aviv: ha-Menorah, 1973. Added t.p.: Kotzk: the struggle for integrity.<space/><italics>A Passion for Truth</italics><space/>is an adaptation of this larger work.</listitem><listitem><italics>Der mizrekh-Eyropeyisher Yid</italics><space/>(<template><target>lang-yi</target><arg>''The Eastern European Jew''</arg></template>). 45 p. Originally published: New-York: Shoken, 1946.</listitem><listitem><italics>Abraham Joshua Heschel: Prophetic Witness</italics><space/>&amp;<space/><italics>Spiritual Radical: Abraham Joshua Heschel in America, 1940-1972</italics>, biography by Edward K. Kaplan ISBN 0-300-11540-7</listitem><listitem>&quot;The Encyclopedia of Hasidism&quot; edited by Rabinowicz, Tzvi M.: ISBN 1-56821-123-6 Jason Aronson, Inc., 1996.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Kaplan<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Edward K.<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Samuel H. Dresner<space/></arg><arg name="title">Abraham Joshua Heschel: Prophetic Witness<space/></arg><arg name="date">1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-300-07186-3</arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kaplan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Edward K.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Spiritual Radical: Abraham Joshua Heschel in America, 1940-1972<space/></arg><arg name="date">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-300-13769-9</arg></template><space/></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://library.duke.edu/rubenstein/findingaids/heschelabraham/'>Guide to the Abraham Joshua Heschel Papers</link>, Rubenstein Library, Duke University.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ajc.org/atf/cf/{42d75369-d582-4380-8395-d25925b85eaf}/WIDE%20HORIZONS.PDF'>Heschel's role in Vatican II and his advocacy of interreligious respect</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.yctorah.org/component/option,com_docman/task,doc_view/gid,312'>Alan Brill Review of Heavenly Torah</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0411/is_3-4_53/ai_n14735950'>Arnold Jacob Wolf Review of Heavenly Torah</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.js.emory.edu/BLUMENTHAL/HeschelHTreview.htm'>David Blumenthal review of Heavenly Torah</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://heschel.org.il/en/content/who-was-heschel'>Who was Heschel?</link><space/>The Heschel Center for Environmental Learning and Leadership</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME">Heschel, Abraham Joshua
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION">Polish-American Conservative Judaism Rabbi
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH">1907-01-11
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH">[[Warsaw]], Poland
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH">1972-12-23
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">United States
</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Heschel, Abraham Joshua</target></template><link><target>Category:1907 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1972 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Warsaw</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Warsaw Governorate</target></link><link><target>Category:Polish Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Polish emigrants to the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Polish-Jewish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American Conservative rabbis</target></link><link><target>Category:African-Americans' civil rights activists</target></link><link><target>Category:American pacifists</target></link><link><target>Category:German Liberal rabbis</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century rabbis</target></link><link><target>Category:German philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish Theological Seminary of America people</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophers of Judaism</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:Polish philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:Jews and Judaism in Cincinnati, Ohio</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish pacifists</target></link><link><target>Category:American Jewish theologians</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophers of religion</target></link><link><target>Category:American ethicists</target></link><link><target>Category:German ethicists</target></link><link><target>Category:Polish ethicists</target></link><link><target>Category:Humboldt University of Berlin alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Hebrew Union College faculty</target></link><link><target>Category:Guggenheim Fellows</target></link><link><target>Category:German male writers</target></link></paragraph></article>