<article title='Dziga_Vertov'><paragraph><template><target>Eastern Slavic name</target><arg>Abelevich</arg><arg>Kaufman</arg></template><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="name"><space/>Dziga Vertov
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Dziga Vertov photograph.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Dziga Abelevich Kaufman
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>David Abelevich Kaufman
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{Birth date|1896|1|2|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Białystok]], [[Russian Empire]] (now [[Congress Poland|Poland]])
</arg><arg name="notable_works"><space/>''[[Man with a Movie Camera]]''
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{Death date and age|1954|2|12|1896|1|2|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Moscow]], [[Soviet Union]] (now [[Russia]])
</arg><arg name="influences"><space/>
</arg><arg name="influenced"><space/>
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>Soviet
</arg><arg name="death_cause"><space/>Cancer
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Elizaveta Svilova]]<space/><small>(1929-1954; his death)</small>
</arg><arg name="other_names"><space/>
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Film director, cinema theorist
</arg><arg name="years_active"><space/>1917-1954
</arg><arg name="family"><space/>[[Boris Kaufman]] (brother)<br><space/>[[Mikhail Kaufman]] (brother)
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>David Abelevich Kaufman</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg><space/>Дави́д А́белевич Ка́уфман</arg></template>) (2 January 1896 12 February 1954) also known as<space/><bold>Denis Kaufman</bold><space/>or his<space/><link><target>pseudonym</target></link><space/><bold>Dziga Vertov</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Vertof</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-uk</target><arg>Дзи́га Ве́ртов</arg></template>, &quot;spinning top&quot;) was a<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>Soviet</part></link><space/>pioneer<space/><link><target>documentary film</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>newsreel</target></link><space/>director, as well as a cinema theorist. His filming practices and theories influenced the<space/><link><target>cinma vrit</target></link><space/>style of documentary movie-making and the<space/><link><target>Dziga Vertov Group</target></link>, a radical film-making cooperative which was active in the 1960s.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 2012<space/><italics><link><target>Sight and Sound</target></link></italics><space/>poll, the critics voted Vertov's<space/><italics><link><target>Man with a Movie Camera</target></link></italics><space/>(1929) the 8th best film ever made.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Sight & Sound Revises Best-Films-Ever Lists</arg><arg name="url">http://www.studiodaily.com/2012/08/sight-sound-revises-best-films-ever-lists/</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 August 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">studiodaily</arg><arg name="date">1 August 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Vertov's brothers<space/><link><target>Boris Kaufman</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mikhail Kaufman</target></link><space/>were also noted filmmakers, as was his wife,<space/><link><target>Elizaveta Svilova</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Early years</heading><paragraph>Vertov was born<space/><bold>David Abelevich Kaufman</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>Дави́д А́белевич Ка́уфман</arg></template>) into a family of<space/><link><target>Jew</target><trail>ish</trail></link><space/>lineage in<space/><link><target>Biaystok</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Congress Poland</target><part>Poland</part></link>, then a part of the<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target></link>. His father was a librarian. He<space/><link><target>Russification</target><part>Russified</part></link><space/>his Jewish name David and<space/><link><target>patronymic</target></link><space/>Abelevich to<space/><bold>Denis Arkadievich</bold><space/>at some point after 1918.<extension extension_name='ref'>Early Soviet Cinema; Innovation, Ideology and Propaganda by David Gillespie Wallflower Press London 2005, page 57</extension><space/>Vertov studied music at Biaystok Conservatory until his family fled from the invading<space/><link><target>German Army (German Empire)</target><part>German Army</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Moscow</target></link><space/>in 1915. The Kaufmans soon settled in<space/><link><target>Saint Petersburg</target><part>Petrograd</part></link>, where Vertov began writing<space/><link><target>poetry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>science fiction</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>satire</target></link>. In 1916-1917 Vertov was studying medicine at the Psychoneurological Institute in Saint Petersburg and experimenting with &quot;sound collages&quot; in his free time. He eventually adopted the name &quot;Dziga Vertov&quot;, which translates loosely from<space/><link><target>Ukrainian language</target><part>Ukrainian</part></link><space/>as 'spinning top'.<extension extension_name='ref'>Documentary Film: A Very Short Introduction: A Very Short Introduction by Patricia Aufderheide; Oxford University Press, 28 November 2007, page 37</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early writings</heading><paragraph>Vertov is known for many early writings, mainly while still in school, that focus on the individual versus the perceptive nature of the camera lens, which he was known to call his &quot;second eye&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Most of Vertov's early work was unpublished, and few manuscripts remain after the<space/><link><target>World War II</target><part>Second World War</part></link>, though some material survived in later films and documentaries created by Vertov and his brothers,<space/><link><target>Boris Kaufman</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mikhail Kaufman</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Vertov is also known for quotes on perception, and its ineffability, in relation to the nature of qualia (sensory experiences).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>After the October Revolution</heading><paragraph>After the<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Revolution</target></link><space/>of 1917, at the age of 22, Vertov began editing for<space/><italics>Kino-Nedelya</italics><space/>(<template><target>lang</target><arg>ru</arg><arg>Кино-Неделя</arg></template>, the Moscow Cinema Committee's weekly film series, and the first newsreel series in Russia), which first came out in June 1918. While working for<space/><italics>Kino-Nedelya</italics><space/>he met his future wife, the film director and editor,<space/><link><target>Elizaveta Svilova</target></link>, who at the time was working as an editor at<space/><link><target>Goskino</target></link>. She began collaborating with Vertov, beginning as his editor but becoming assistant and co-director in subsequent films, such as<space/><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics><space/>(1929), and<space/><italics>Three Songs About Lenin</italics><space/>(1934).</paragraph><paragraph>Vertov worked on the<space/><italics>Kino-Nedelya</italics><space/>series for three years, helping establish and run a film-car on<space/><link><target>Mikhail Kalinin</target></link>'s agit-train during the ongoing<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target></link><space/>between<space/><link><target>Communist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>counterrevolutionary</target><part>counterrevolutionaries</part></link>. Some of the cars on the agit-trains were equipped with actors for live performances or<space/><link><target>printing press</target><trail>es</trail></link>; Vertov's had equipment to shoot, develop, edit, and project film. The trains went to battlefronts on<space/><link><target>agitprop</target><part>agitation-propaganda</part></link><space/>missions intended primarily to bolster the morale of the troops; they were also intended to stir up revolutionary fervor of the masses.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1919, Vertov compiled newsreel footage for his documentary<space/><italics>Anniversary of the Revolution;</italics><space/>in 1921 he compiled<space/><italics>History of the<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target><part>Civil War</part></link>.</italics><space/>The so-called &quot;Council of Three,&quot; a group issuing manifestoes in<space/><italics>LEF,</italics><space/>a radical Russian newsmagazine, was established in 1922; the group's &quot;three&quot; were Vertov, his (future) wife and editor Elizaveta Svilova, and his brother and<space/><link><target>cinematographer</target></link><space/><link><target>Mikhail Kaufman</target></link>. Vertov's interest in machinery led to a curiosity about the mechanical basis of<space/><link><target>film</target><part>cinema</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Kino-Pravda</italics></heading><paragraph>In 1922, the year that<space/><italics><link><target>Nanook of the North</target></link></italics><space/>was released, Vertov started the<space/><link><target>Kino-Pravda</target></link><space/>series.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><space/>The series took its title from the official government newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Pravda</target></link></italics>. &quot;Kino-Pravda&quot; (literally translated, &quot;film truth&quot;) continued Vertov's agit-prop bent. &quot;The Kino-Pravda group began its work in a basement in the centre of Moscow&quot; Vertov explained. He called it damp and dark. There was an earthen floor and holes one stumbled into at every turn. Dziga said, &quot; This dampness prevented our reels of lovingly edited film from sticking together properly, rusted our scissors and our splicers.&quot; &quot;Before dawn- damp, cold, teeth chattering- I wrap comrade Svilova in a third jacket.&quot; [quotation needed]</paragraph><paragraph>Vertov's driving vision, expounded in his frequent essays, was to capture &quot;film truth&quot;&amp;mdash;that is, fragments of actuality which, when organized together, have a deeper truth that cannot be seen with the naked eye. In the &quot;Kino-Pravda&quot; series, Vertov focused on everyday experiences, eschewing bourgeois concerns and filming marketplaces, bars, and schools instead, sometimes with a hidden camera, without asking permission first. The episodes of &quot;Kino-Pravda&quot; usually did not include reenactments or stagings (one exception is the segment about the trial of the Social Revolutionaries: the scenes of the selling of the newspapers on the streets and the people reading the papers in the trolley were both staged for the camera). The cinematography is simple, functional, unelaborate&amp;mdash;perhaps a result of Vertov's disinterest in both &quot;beauty&quot; and the &quot;grandeur of fiction.&quot; Twenty-three issues of the series were produced over a period of three years; each issue lasted about twenty minutes and usually covered three topics. The stories were typically descriptive, not narrative, and included vignettes and exposs, showing for instance the renovation of a trolley system, the organization of farmers into communes, and the trial of Social Revolutionaries; one story shows starvation in the nascent<space/><link><target>Communism</target><part>Communist</part></link><space/>state. Propagandistic tendencies are also present, but with more subtlety, in the episode featuring the construction of an airport: one shot shows the former<space/><link><target>Tsar</target></link>'s tanks helping prepare a foundation, with an intertitle reading &quot;Tanks on the labor front.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Vertov clearly intended an active relationship with his audience in the series&amp;mdash;in the final segment he includes contact information&amp;mdash;but by the 14th episode the series had become so experimental that some critics dismissed Vertov's efforts as &quot;insane&quot;. Vertov responds to their criticisms with the assertion that the critics were hacks nipping &quot;revolutionary effort&quot; in the bud, and concludes the essay with his promise to &quot;explode art's<space/><link><target>tower of Babel</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1924, p. 47</extension><space/>In Vertov's view, &quot;art's tower of Babel&quot; was the subservience of cinematic technique to narrative, commonly known as the<space/><link><target>Institutional Mode of Representation</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>By this point in his career, Vertov was clearly and emphatically dissatisfied with narrative tradition, and expresses his hostility towards dramatic fiction of any kind both openly and repeatedly; he regarded drama as another &quot;opiate of the masses&quot;. Vertov freely admitted one criticism leveled at his efforts on the &quot;Kino-Pravda&quot; seriesthat the series, while influential, had a limited release.</paragraph><paragraph>By the end of the &quot;Kino-Pravda&quot; series, Vertov made liberal use of<space/><link><target>stop motion</target></link>,<space/><link><target>freeze frame shot</target><part>freeze frames</part></link>, and other cinematic &quot;artificialities,&quot; giving rise to criticisms not just of his trenchant dogmatism, but also of his cinematic technique. Vertov explains himself in &quot;On 'Kinopravda'&quot;: in editing &quot;chance film clippings&quot; together for the Kino-Nedelia series, he &quot;began to doubt the necessity of a literary connection between individual visual elements spliced together.... This work served as the point of departure for 'Kinopravda.'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1924, p. 42</extension><space/>Towards the end of the same essay, Vertov mentions an upcoming project which seems likely to be<space/><italics><link><target>Man with the Movie Camera</target></link></italics>, calling it an &quot;experimental film&quot; made without a scenario; just three paragraphs above, Vertov mentions a scene from &quot;Kino Pravda&quot; which should be quite familiar to viewers of<space/><italics>Man with the Movie Camera</italics>: the peasant works, and so does the urban woman, and so too, the woman film editor selecting the negative....&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1924, p. 46</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics></heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Man with a Movie Camera</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>With Lenin's admission of limited private enterprise through his<space/><link><target>New Economic Policy</target></link><space/>(NEP) of 1921, Russia began receiving fiction films from afar, an occurrence that Vertov regarded with undeniable suspicion, calling drama a &quot;corrupting influence&quot; on the proletarian sensibility (&quot;On 'Kinopravda,'&quot; 1924). By this time Vertov had been using his newsreel series as a pedestal to vilify dramatic fiction for several years; he continued his criticisms even after the warm reception of<space/><link><target>Sergei Eisenstein</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Battleship Potemkin</target></link></italics><space/>in 1925.<space/><italics>Potemkin</italics><space/>was a heavily fictionalized film telling the story of a mutiny on a battleship which came about as a result of the sailors' mistreatment; the film was an obvious but skillful propaganda piece glorifying the proletariat. Vertov lost his job at<space/><link><target>Sovkino</target></link><space/>in January 1927, possibly as a result of criticizing a film which effectively preaches the line of the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>Communist Party</part></link>. He was fired for making<space/><italics>A Sixth Part of the World: Advertising and the Soviet Universe</italics><space/>for the State Trade Organization into a propaganda film, selling the Soviet as an advanced society under the NEP, instead of showing how they fit into the world economy. The Ukraine State Studio hired Vertov to create<space/><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics>.Vertov says in his essay &quot;The Man with a Movie Camera&quot; that he was fighting &quot;for a decisive cleaning up of film-language, for its complete separation from the language of theater and literature.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1928, p. 83</extension><space/>By the later segments of<space/><italics>Kino-Pravda</italics>, Vertov was experimenting heavily, looking to abandon what he considered film clichs (and receiving criticism for it); his experimentation was even more pronounced and dramatic by the time of<space/><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics>, which was filmed in<space/><link><target>Ukraine</target></link>. Some have criticized the obvious stagings in this film as being at odds with Vertov's credos of &quot;life as it is&quot; and &quot;life caught unawares&quot;: the scene of the woman getting out of bed and getting dressed is obviously staged, as is the reversed shot of the chess pieces being pushed off a chess board and the tracking shot which films Mikhail Kaufman riding in a car filming a third car.</paragraph><paragraph>However, Vertov's two credos, often used interchangeably, are in fact distinct, as<space/><link><target>Yuri Tsivian</target></link><space/>points out in the<space/><link><target>audio commentary (DVD)</target><part>commentary track</part></link><space/>on the DVD for<space/><italics>Man with the Movie Camera:</italics><space/>for Vertov, &quot;life as it is&quot; means to record life as it would be without the camera present. &quot;Life caught unawares&quot; means to record life when surprised, and perhaps provoked, by the presence of a camera.<extension extension_name='ref'>At 16:04 on the commentary track.</extension><space/>This explanation contradicts the common assumption that for Vertov &quot;life caught unawares&quot; meant &quot;life caught unaware of the camera.&quot; All of these shots might conform to Vertov's credo &quot;caught unawares.&quot; His slow motion, fast motion, and other camera techniques were a way to dissect the image, Mikhail Kaufman stated in an interview. It was to be the honest truth of perception. For example, in<space/><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics>, two trains are shown almost melting into each other, although we are taught to see trains as not riding that close, Vertov tried to portray the actual sight of two passing trains. Mikhail spoke about Eisenstein's films as being different from his and his brother's in that Eisenstein, &quot;came from the theatre, in the theatre one directs dramas, one strings beads.&quot; &quot;We all felt...that through documentary film we could develop a new kind of art. Not only documentary art, or the art of chronicle, but rather an art based on images, the creation of an image-oriented journalism&quot; Mikhail explained. More than even film truth,<space/><italics>Man with a Movie Camera</italics>, was supposed to be a way to make those in the Soviet Union more efficient in their actions. He slowed down his actions, such as the decision whether to jump or not, you can see the decision in his face, a psychological dissection for the audience. He wanted a peace between the actions of man and the actions of a machine, for them to be, in a sense, one.</paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Cine-Eye</italics></heading><paragraph>&quot;Cine-Eye&quot; is a montage method developed by Dziga Vertov which was first formulated in his work &quot;WE: Variant of a Manifesto&quot; in 1919.</paragraph><paragraph>Dziga Vertov believed his concept of Kino-Glaz, or &quot;Cine Eye&quot; in English, would help contemporary &quot;man&quot; evolve from a flawed creature into a higher, more precise form. He compared man unfavorably to machines: &quot;In the face of the machine we are ashamed of mans inability to control himself, but what are we to do if we find the unerring ways of electricity more exciting than the disorderly haste of active people [...]&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1922, p. 69</extension><space/>&quot;I am an eye. I am a mechanical eye. I, a machine, I am showing you a world, the likes of which only I can see&quot; Dziga was quoted as saying.</paragraph><paragraph>Like other Russian filmmakers, he attempted to connect his ideas and techniques to the advancement of the aims of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>. Whereas<space/><link><target>Sergei Eisenstein</target></link><space/>viewed his<space/><link><target>montage of attractions</target></link><space/>as a creative tool through which the film-viewing masses could be subjected to &quot;emotional and psychological influence&quot; and therefore able to perceive &quot;the ideological aspect&quot; of the films they were watching, Vertov believed the<space/><link><target>Kinoks</target><part>Kino-Eye</part></link><space/>would influence the actual evolution of man, &quot;from a bumbling citizen through the poetry of the machine to the perfect electric man.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Vertov 1922, pp. 69-71</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Vertov believed film was too &quot;romantic&quot; and &quot;theatricalised&quot; due to the influence of literature, theater, and music, and that these psychological film-dramas &quot;prevent man from being as precise as a stop watch and hamper his desire for kinship with the machine.&quot;He desired to move away from &quot;the pre-Revolutionary fictional models&quot; of filmmaking to one based on the rhythm of machines, seeking to &quot;bring creative joy to all mechanical labour&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vertov 1922, p. 71">Vertov 1922, p. 71</extension><space/>and to &quot;bring men closer to machines.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vertov 1922, p. 71"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Late career</heading><paragraph>Vertov's cinema success continued into the 1930s. In 1931, he released<space/><italics>Enthusiasm: Symphony of the<space/><link><target>Donbass</target></link></italics>, an examination into Soviet miners.<space/><italics>Enthusiasm</italics><space/>has been called a 'sound film', with sound recorded on location, and these mechanical sounds woven together, producing a symphony-like effect.</paragraph><paragraph>Three years later,<space/><italics>Three Songs about Lenin</italics><space/>looked at the revolution through the eyes of the Russian peasantry. For his film, however, Vertov had been hired by<space/><link><target>Gorky Film Studio</target><part>Mezhrabpomfilm</part></link>, a Soviet studio that produced mainly propaganda efforts. The film, finished in January 1934 for Lenin's obit, was only publicly released in November of that year. A new version of the film was published in 1938, including a longer sequence to reflect Stalin's &quot;achievements&quot; at the end of the film and leaving out footage with &quot;enemies&quot; of that time. Today there exists a 1970 reconstruction by<space/><link><target>Elizaveta Svilova</target></link>. With the rise and official sanction of<space/><link><target>socialist realism</target></link><space/>in 1934, Vertov was forced to cut his personal artistic output significantly, eventually becoming little more than an editor for Soviet newsreels.<space/><italics>Lullaby</italics>, perhaps the last film in which Vertov was able to maintain his artistic vision, was released in 1937. Dziga Vertov died of cancer in Moscow in 1954.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Family</heading><paragraph>Vertov's brother<space/><link><target>Boris Kaufman</target></link><space/>was a noted cinematographer who worked much later for directors such as<space/><link><target>Elia Kazan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sidney Lumet</target></link><space/>in America. (He won an Oscar for his work on<space/><italics><link><target>On the Waterfront</target></link></italics>.) His other brother, Mikhail Kaufman, worked as Vertov's cinematographer until he became a documentarian in his own right. In September 1929, Vertov married his long-time collaborator<space/><link><target>Elizaveta Svilova</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Influence and legacy</heading><paragraph>Vertov's legacy still lives on today. His ideas are echoed in<space/><link><target>cinma vrit</target></link>, the movement of the 1960s named after Vertov's Kino-Pravda. The 1960s and 1970s saw an international revival of interest in Vertov.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.filmreference.com/Directors-Ve-Y/Vertov-Dziga.html</arg><arg name="title">Dziga Vertov, by Erik Barnouw</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The independent, exploratory style of Vertov influenced and inspired many filmmakers and directors like the<space/><link><target>Situationist International</target><part>Situationist</part></link><space/><link><target>Guy Debord</target></link><space/>and independent companies such as &quot;Vertov Industries,&quot; in Hawaii. The<space/><link><target>Dziga Vertov Group</target></link><space/>borrowed his name. In 1960,<space/><link><target>Jean Rouch</target></link><space/>used Vertov's filming theory when making<space/><italics>Chronicle of a Summer</italics>. His partner<space/><link><target>Edgar Morin</target></link><space/>coined<space/><italics>Cinma vrit</italics><space/>term when describing the style, using direct translation of Vertovs KinoPravda.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Free Cinema</target></link><space/>movement in the United Kingdom during the 1950s, the<space/><link><target>Direct Cinema</target></link><space/>in North America in the late 1950s and early 1960s, and the<space/><italics><link><target>Candid Eye</target></link></italics><space/>series in Canada in the 1950s, all essentially owed a debt to Vertov.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">The technique of film and video editing: history, theory, and practice, by Ken Dancyger</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>This revival of Vertov's legacy included rehabilitation of his reputation in the Soviet Union, with retrospectives of his films, biographical works and writings. In 1962, the first Soviet monograph on Vertov was published, followed by another collection, 'Dziga Vertov: Articles, Diaries, Projects.' To recall the 30th anniversary of Vertov's death, three New York cultural organizations put on the first American retrospective of Vertov's work.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>New Media</target></link><space/>theorist<space/><link><target>Lev Manovich</target></link><space/>suggested Vertov as one of the early pioneers of<space/><link><target>database cinema</target></link><space/>genre in his essay<space/><italics>Database as a symbolic form</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Quotes</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;It is far from simple to show the truth, yet the truth is simple.&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nottingham.ac.uk/film/journal/filmrev/man-with-a-movie-camera.htm'></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;I am the machine that reveals the world to you as only I alone am able to see it.&quot;</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;I was returning from the railroad station. In my ears, there remained chugs and bursts of steam from a departing train. Somebody cries in laughter, a whistle, the station bell, the clanking locomotive...whispers, shouts, farewells. And walking away I thought I need to find a machine not only to describe but to register, to photograph these sounds. Otherwise, one cannot organize or assemble them. They fly like time. Perhaps a camera? That records the visual. But to organize the visual world and not the audible world? Is this the answer?&quot;- Dziga Vertov</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Our eyes see very little and very badly so people dreamed up the microscope to let them see invisible phenomena; they invented the telescope...now they have perfected the cinecamera to penetrate more deeply into the visible world, to explore and record visual phenomena so that what is happening now, which will have to be taken account of in the future, is not forgotten.&quot;</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Everybody who cares for his art seeks the essence of his own technique.&quot; (1922)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Filmography</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Kino glaz.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Poster for ''Kino-Glaz'', designed by<space/><link><target>Alexander Rodchenko</target></link><space/>(1924)</part></link><link><target>File:Soviet Toys (1924).webm</target><part>thumb</part><part>thumbtime=2</part><part>''Soviet Toys''</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>1919 (<italics>Kino Nedelya</italics>, Cinema Week)</listitem><listitem>1919 (Anniversary of the Revolution)</listitem><listitem>1922 (History of the Civil War)</listitem><listitem>1924 (Soviet Toys)</listitem><listitem>1924 - (<italics><link><target>Cinema Eye</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1925 (<italics><link><target>Kino-Pravda</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1926 (<link><target>A Sixth of the World</target></link>/The Sixth Part of the World)</listitem><listitem>1928 (The Eleventh Year)</listitem><listitem>1929 (<italics><link><target>Man with a Movie Camera</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1930 ( ) (<italics><link><target>Enthusiasm (film)</target><part>Enthusiasm</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1934 (<italics><link><target>Three Songs About Lenin</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1937 (<link><target>In Memory of Sergo Ordzhonikidze (1937 film)</target><part>In Memory of Sergo Ordzhonikidze</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>1937 (<italics><link><target>Lullaby (1937 film)</target><part>Lullaby</part></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>1938 (Three Heroines)</listitem><listitem>1942 ! (Kazakhstan for the Front!)</listitem><listitem>1944 - (In the Mountains of Ala-Tau)</listitem><listitem>1954 (News of the Day)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Political Cinema</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Databases</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>New Media Art</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cinma vrit</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pure cinema</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Montage (filmmaking)</target><part>Montage</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Abstract film</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Books and Articles</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Erik Barnouw</target><part>Barnouw, Erik</part></link>.<space/><italics>Documentary: a History of the Non-fiction Film.</italics><space/>Oxford University Press. Original copyright 1974.</listitem><listitem>Bohlman, Philip Vilas.<space/><italics>Music, Modernity, and the Foreign in the New Germany.</italics><space/>1994, pp.&amp;nbsp;121152</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ian Christie (film scholar)</target><part>Christie, Ian</part></link>. &quot;Rushes: Pordenone Retrospective: Gazing into the Future.&quot;, in:<space/><italics>Sight and Sound</italics>. 2005, 15, 1, 4-5, British Film Institute</listitem><listitem>Cook, Simon. &quot;<link type='external' href='https://www.academia.edu/2305468/Dziga_Vertovs_theory_of_vision'>Our Eyes, Spinning Like Propellers: Wheel of Life, Curve of Velocities, and Dziga Vertov's Theory of the Interva</link><space/>l.&quot;<space/><italics>October</italics>, 2007: 7991.</listitem><listitem>Ellis, Jack C.<space/><italics>The Documentary Idea: a Critical History of English-Language Documentary Film and Video.</italics><space/>Prentice Hall, 1989.</listitem><listitem>Feldman, Seth. &quot;'Peace between Man and Machine': Dziga Vertov's<space/><italics>The Man with a Movie Camera.</italics>&quot; in: Barry Keith Grant, and Jeannette Sloniowski, eds.<space/><italics>Documenting the Documentary: Close Readings of Documentary Film and Video.</italics><space/>Wayne State University Press, 1998. pp.&amp;nbsp;4053.</listitem><listitem>Feldman, Seth.<space/><italics>Evolution of style in the early work of Dziga Vertov.</italics><space/>1977, Arno Press, New York.</listitem><listitem>Graffy, Julian; Deriabin, Aleksandr; Sarkisova, Oksana; Keller, Sarah; Scandiffio, Theresa .<space/><italics>Lines of Resistance: Dziga Vertov and the Twenties</italics>; edited and with an introduction by Yuri Tsivian. Le Giornate del cinema muto, Gemona, Udine</listitem><listitem>Hicks, Jeremy.<space/><italics>Dziga Vertov: Defining Documentary Film.</italics><space/>London &amp; New York: I. B. Tauris, 2007.</listitem><listitem>Le Grice, Malcolm.<space/><italics>Abstract Film and Beyond.</italics><space/>Studio Vista, 1977.</listitem><listitem>MacKay, John. &quot;Allegory and Accommodation: Vertov's Three Songs of Lenin (1934) as a Stalinist Film.&quot; In<space/><italics>Film History: An International Journal</italics>; 18.4 (2006) 376-391.</listitem><listitem>MacKay, John.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.kinokultura.com/articles/jan05-mackay.html'>&quot;Disorganized Noise: ''Enthusiasm'' and the Ear of the Collective.&quot;</link><space/></listitem><listitem>MacKay, John. &quot;Film Energy: Process and Metanarrative in Dziga Vertov's The Eleventh Year (1928).&quot;<space/><italics>October</italics>; 121 (Summer 2007): 41-78.</listitem><listitem>MacKay, John.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.kinokultura.com/articles/apr05-mackay.html'>&quot;The 'Spinning Top' Takes Another Turn: Vertov Today.&quot;</link></listitem><listitem>Michelson, Annette &amp; Turvey, Malcolm, eds. &quot;New Vertov Studies.&quot; Special Issue of<space/><italics>October</italics>, (<italics>October</italics><space/>121 (Summer 2007)).</listitem><listitem>Roberts, Graham.<space/><italics>The Man with the Movie Camera.</italics><space/>I. B. Tauris, 2001. ISBN 1-86064-394-9</listitem><listitem>Singer, Ben. &quot;Connoisseurs of Chaos: Whitman, Vertov and the 'Poetic Survey,'&quot;<space/><italics>Literature/Film Quarterly</italics>; 15:4 (Fall 1987): 247-258.</listitem><listitem>Tode, Thomas &amp; Wurm, Barbara, Austrian Film Museum, eds.<space/><italics>Dziga Vertov. The Vertov Collection at the<space/><link><target>Austrian Film Museum</target></link>,</italics><space/>Bilingual (German-English). (Paperback - May 2006), FilmmuseumSynemaPublikationen.--<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.filmmuseum.at'>online version available here</link>.</listitem><listitem>Tsivian, Yuri, ed.<space/><italics>Lines of Resistance: Dziga Vertov and the Twenties</italics>. Le Giornate del Cinema Muto, 2004. ISBN 88-86155-15-8</listitem><listitem>Vertov, Dziga.<space/><italics>On Kinopravda.</italics><space/>1924, and<space/><italics>The Man with the Movie Camera.</italics><space/>1928, in: Annette Michelson ed. Kevin O'Brien tr.<space/><italics>Kino-Eye : The Writings of Dziga Vertov,</italics><space/>University of California Press, 1995.</listitem><listitem>Dziga Vertov.<space/><italics>We. A Version of a Manifesto.</italics><space/>1922, in Ian Christie, Richard Taylor eds.<space/><italics>The Film Factory: Russian and Soviet Cinema in Documents, 1896-1939</italics><space/>Routledge, 1994. ISBN 0-415-05298-X</listitem><listitem>Warren, Charles, ed.<space/><italics>Beyond Document: Essays on Nonfiction Film.</italics><space/>Wesleyan University Press, 1996.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>DVDs</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Dziga Vertov's Man with the Movie Camera</italics><space/>DVD, audio commentary track by Yuri Tsivian.</listitem><listitem><italics>Entuziazm (Simfonija Donbassa)</italics><space/>DVD, restored version and unrestored version plus documentary on Peter Kubelka's restoration.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Dziga Vertov</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>IMDb name</target><arg>895048</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;amp;GRid=23752761'>Dziga Vertov on Find A Grave</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>youtube</target><arg>7ZkvjWIEcoU</arg><arg>Man with the Movie Camera (1929), scored by the Alloy Orchestra in 1995 - 01:06:40</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://archive.sensesofcinema.com/contents/directors/03/vertov.html'>Senses Of Cinema: Dziga Vertov</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ubu.com/film/vertov.html'>Dziga Vertov's ''Kino-Eye'' and ''Three Songs About Lenin''</link><space/>at UBUWEB</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.europeanfilmgateway.eu/node/33/vertov/multilingual:1/showOnly:video'>Newsreels by Vertov on europeanfilmgateway.eu</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20100618211034<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.yale.edu/slavic/resources/download/Dziga-Vertov-Short-Biography-MacKay-1.doc<space/></arg><arg name="title">An up-to-date short bio of Vertov<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>youtube</target><arg>Zy_TK0SyQeY</arg><arg>Kino Eye (1924), scored by Robert Israel in 1999 - 01:22:55</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Dziga Vertov</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Vertov, Dziga
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Soviet documentary film maker
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>2 January 1896
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Białystok]], [[Russian Empire]] (now [[Congress Poland|Poland]])
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>12 February 1954
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Moscow]], [[Soviet Union]] (now [[Russia]])
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Vertov, Dziga</target></template><link><target>Category:1896 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1954 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Novodevichy Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet documentary film directors</target></link><link><target>Category:Documentary filmmakers</target></link><link><target>Category:Film theorists</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Biaystok</target></link><link><target>Category:Polish Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet cinematographers</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet film directors</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet film editors</target></link><link><target>Category:Soviet Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>