<article title='Community_college'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the transportation station in Boston</arg><arg>Community College (MBTA station)</arg></template><template><target>broader</target><arg>College</arg></template><link><target>File:Pasadena City College, Pasadena, California - 20040813.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>260px</part><part><link><target>Pasadena City College</target></link><space/>(PCC)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>community college</bold><space/>is a type of<space/><link><target>educational institution</target></link>. The term can have different meanings in different countries.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Australia</heading><paragraph>In Australia, the term community college is not used. Analogous to community colleges are colleges or institutes of<space/><link><target>Technical and further education</target><part>Technical and Further Education</part></link><space/>(TAFEs); institutions mostly regulated at state and territory level. There are also an increasing number of private providers of varying social esteem; often these are colloquially called &quot;colleges&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>TAFEs and other providers carry on the tradition of adult education, which was established in Australia around mid 19th century when evening classes were held to help adults enhance their numeracy and literacy skills.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ace.nsw.gov.au/page.asp?PID=115&amp;amp;MID=1&amp;amp;SID=115'>ace.nsw.gov.au</link></extension><space/>The majority of Australian universities can also be traced back to such forerunners, although obtaining a university charter has always changed their nature. In TAFEs and colleges today, courses are designed for personal development of an individual and/or for employment outcomes. Educational programs cover a variety of topics such as arts, languages, business and lifestyle; and are usually timetabled to be conducted in the evenings or weekends to accommodate people working full-time. Funding for colleges may come from government grants and course fees; and many are not-for-profit organisations. There are located in metropolitan, regional and rural locations of Australia.</paragraph><paragraph>Learning offered by TAFEs and colleges has changed over the years. By the 1980s many colleges had recognised a community need for computer training and since then thousands of people have been up-skilled through IT courses. The majority of colleges by the late 20th century had also become Registered Training Organisations; recognising the need to offer individuals a nurturing, non-traditional education venue to gain skills that would better prepare them for the workplace and potential job openings.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cca.edu.au/page/history.html'>cca.edu.au</link></extension><space/>TAFEs and colleges have not traditionally offered bachelor's degrees, instead providing pathway arrangements with universities to continue towards degrees. The American innovation of the associate degree is emerging at some institutions.<space/><link><target>Australian Qualifications Framework</target><part>Certificate courses I to IV</part></link>, diplomas and advanced diplomas are typically offered, the latter deemed equivalent to an undergraduate qualification, albeit typically in more vocational areas. Recently, some TAFE institutes (and private providers) have also become Higher Education providers in their own right and are now starting to offer bachelor's degrees programs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Canada</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>College (Canada)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>, the term community college is not widely used. There are 150 institutions that could be roughly equivalent of the US community college in certain contexts. They are usually referred to simply as &quot;<link><target>College (Canada)</target><part>colleges</part></link>&quot; since in<space/><link><target>Canadian English</target><part>common usage</part></link><space/>a degree granting institution is almost exclusively a<space/><link><target>university</target></link>. In the province of Quebec, even when speaking in English, all colleges are often incorrectly<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.immigration-quebec.gouv.qc.ca/en/employment/comparative-evaluation/education-system.html</arg><arg name="website">Quebec Government</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 June 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>called<space/><link><target>CEGEP</target><part>Cgeps</part></link>, the French acronym for the public system: &quot;Collge d'enseignement gnral et professionnel&quot;, meaning &quot;College of General and Vocational Education&quot;. (The word College can also refer to a private High School in Quebec).</paragraph><paragraph>Colleges are educational institutions providing<space/><link><target>higher education</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>tertiary education</target></link>, granting<space/><link><target>Academic certificate</target><part>certificates</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>diploma</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><link><target>Associate's degree</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>bachelor's degree</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are granted by universities, but, in some courses of study, there may be an agreement between colleges and universities to collaborate on the education requirements toward a degree. Only in Western Canada is the term associate degree used as in the United States. In other parts of Canada a degree is usually attained as a 4-year study program, and to a much lesser degree now (except in Quebec, where it is the norm), in 3 years.</paragraph><paragraph>Each province has its own educational system reflecting the decentralization of the Canadian provinces and therefore of the education system. However, most of the colleges began in the mid-1960s to provide education and training for the then-emerging baby boom generation and for immigrants from around the world who were starting to enter the country.</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Canadian community college systems</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nova Scotia Community College</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>New Brunswick Community College</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Red River Community College</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of colleges in Ontario</target><part>Ontario colleges</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>College education in Quebec</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>India</heading><paragraph>In India, 98 community colleges are recognized by the<space/><link><target>University Grants Commission (India)</target><part>University Grants Commission</part></link>. The courses offered by these colleges are diplomas, advance diplomas and certificate courses. The duration of these courses usually range from six months to two years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://indiatoday.intoday.in/education/story/ugc-approves-98-community-colleges-across-india/1/362600.html</arg><arg name="title">UGC approves 98 community colleges from five states</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 June 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Malaysia</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Community college (Malaysia)</arg></template>Community colleges in Malaysia are a network of educational institutions whereby vocational and technical skills training could be provided at all levels for school leavers before they entered the workforce. The community colleges also provide an infrastructure for rural communities to gain skills training through short courses as well as providing access to a post-secondary education.</paragraph><paragraph>At the moment, most community colleges award qualifications up to Level 3 in the<space/><link><target>Malaysian Qualifications Framework</target></link><space/>(Certificate 3) in both the Skills sector (Sijil Kemahiran Malaysia or the Malaysian Skills Certificate) as well as the Vocational and Training sector but the number of community colleges that are starting to award Level 4 qualifications (Diploma) are increasing. This is two levels below a bachelor's degree (Level 6 in the MQF) and students within the system who intend to further their studies to that level will usually seek entry into Advanced Diploma programs in public universities, polytechnics or accredited private providers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Philippines</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Philippines</target></link>, a community school functions as elementary or secondary school at daytime and towards the end of the day convert into a community college. This type of institution offers night classes under the supervision of the same principal, and the same faculty members who are given part-time college teaching load.<extension extension_name='ref' name="alcu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.mb.com.ph/issues/2005/02/20/OPED2005022029090.html
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The medium-term higher education development plan and the local colleges and universities
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2008-08-19
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Danao, Dr. Carolina P.
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>
</arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2005-02-20
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>
</arg><arg name="month"><space/>
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>''The Manila Bulletin Online''
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>
</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://www.mb.com.ph/issues/2005/02/20/OPED2005022029090.html
</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2005-02-20
</arg><arg name="quote"></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The concept of community college dates back to the time of the former<space/><bold>Minister of Education, Culture and Sports (MECS)</bold><space/>that had under its wings the Bureaus of Elementary Education, Secondary Education, Higher Education and Vocational-Technical Education. MECS Secretary, Dr. Cecilio Putong, who in 1971 wrote that a community school is a school established in the community, by the community, and for the community itself. Dr. Pedro T. Orata of Pangasinan shared the same idea, hence the establishment of a Community College, now called the City College of Urdaneta.<extension extension_name='ref' name="alcu"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A community college like the one in<space/><link><target>Abuyog</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Leyte (province)</target><part>Leyte</part></link><space/>can operate with only<space/><link><target>Philippine peso</target><part>PHP</part></link><space/>124,000 annual budget in a 2-storey structure housing more than 700 students.<extension extension_name='ref' name="alcu"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>United Kingdom (excluding Scotland)</heading><paragraph>In the United Kingdom, except for<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link>, a community college is a school which not only provides education for the school age population (1118) of the locality, but also additional services and education to adults and other members of the community.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/british/community-college'>dictionary.cambridge.org</link></extension><space/>This education includes but is not limited to sports, adult literacy and lifestyle education. Usually at the age of 16 when students finish their secondary school studies, they move on to a sixth form college where they study for their<space/><link><target>GCE Advanced Level</target><part>A-levels</part></link><space/>(although some secondary schools have integrated sixth forms). After the 2 year A-level period, they may then proceed to a college of further education or a university.</paragraph><heading level='2'>United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Community colleges in the United States</arg></template><link><target>File:Joliet Junior College Sign.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Joliet Junior College</target></link><space/>Main Campus, in<space/><link><target>Joliet, Illinois</target></link><space/>the first Community College in the U.S.</part></link><link><target>File:6304-FullertonJrCollege-1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Fullerton College</target></link><space/>the oldest community college (originally &quot;Junior College&quot;) in continuous operation in California, having been established in 1913</part></link><link><target>File:Monroe Community College Brighton Campus Main.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Monroe Community College</target></link><space/>main campus, in<space/><link><target>Rochester, NY</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>, community colleges, sometimes called<space/><link><target>junior college</target></link>,<space/><link><target>technical college</target><trail>s</trail></link>, two-year colleges, or city colleges, are primarily two-year<space/><link><target>public university</target><part>public</part></link><space/>institutions providing higher education and lower-level<space/><link><target>tertiary education</target></link>, granting<space/><link><target>Academic certificate</target><part>certificates</part></link>,<space/><link><target>diploma</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>associate's degree</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Many also offer<space/><link><target>continuing education</target><part>continuing</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>adult education</target></link>.After grad from a community college, some students transfer to a four-year<space/><link><target>liberal arts college</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>university</target></link><space/>for two to three years to complete a<space/><link><target>bachelor's degree</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Before the 1970s, community colleges in the United States were more commonly referred to as<space/><link><target>junior colleges</target></link>, and that term is still used at some institutions. However, the term &quot;junior college&quot; has evolved to describe<space/><link><target>Privately held company</target><part>private</part></link><space/>two-year institutions, whereas the term &quot;community college&quot; has evolved to describe publicly funded two-year institutions. The name derives from the fact that community colleges primarily attract and accept students from the local<space/><link><target>community</target></link>, and are often supported by local tax revenue.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Research</heading><paragraph>There are research organizations and publications who focus upon the activities of community college,<space/><link><target>junior college</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>technical college</target></link><space/>institutions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mellow, G.O. 2008">Mellow, G.O. &amp; Heelan, C. (2008).<space/><italics>Minding the Dream: The Process and Practice of the American Community College</italics>. New York: Rowman &amp; Littlefield. ISBN 978-0-7425-6292-9</extension><space/>Many of these institutions and organizations present the most current research and practical outcomes at annual<space/><link><target>community college conferences</target></link>.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>American Association of Community Colleges</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Cohen, A.M. &amp; Brawer, F.B. (2008).<space/><italics>The American Community College</italics><space/>(5th Ed.). San Francisco: Jossey-Bass. ISBN 978-0-470-17468-5</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Vaughn, G.B. (2000).<space/><italics>The Community College Story</italics>. Community College Press. ISBN 0-87117-323-9</extension><space/>has provided oversight on community college research since the 1920s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Geller, H.A. (2001). &quot;A brief history of community colleges and a personal view of some issues (open admissions, occupational training and leadership).&quot; http://www.eric.ed.gov/ERICWebPortal/contentdelivery/servlet/ERICServlet?accno=ED459881</extension><space/>AACC publishes a research journal called the Community College Journal.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gseis.ucla.edu/ccs/journals.htm'>gseis.ucla.edu</link></extension></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Community College Research Center</target></link><space/>(CCRC), located at Teachers College, Columbia University, is the leading independent authority on the nation's two year colleges. CCRC annually publishes numerous papers, reports, briefs, and practitioner packets on issues pertaining to community colleges and open-access four year colleges to help college and system leaders, administrators, faculty, and support staff improve institutional performance and student success.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Association of Community College Trustees</target></link><space/>(ACCT) has provided education for community college boards of directors and advocacy for community colleges since 1972. ACCT President and CEO<space/><link><target>J. Noah Brown</target></link><space/>has authored a book about the past, present, and future of community colleges called Charting a New Course for Community Colleges: Aligning Policies with Practice.</listitem><listitem>The mission of the Community College Research Center from Teachers College at Columbia University is to &quot;conduct research on the major issues affecting community colleges in the United States and to contribute to the development of practice and policy that expands access to higher education and promotes success for all students.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ccrc.tc.columbia.edu/</arg><arg name="title">CCRC</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 June 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Center for Community College Student Engagement</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>University of Texas at Austin</target></link><space/>administers surveys and provides data analysis support to member colleges regarding various factors of student engagement and involvement in community colleges in the United States and Canada.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ccsse.org/</arg><arg name="title">CCSSE – Community College Survey of Student Engagement</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 June 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The Office of Community College Research and Leadership at the<space/><link><target>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</target></link><space/>studies policies, programs, and practices designed to enhance outcomes for diverse youth and adults who seek to transition to and through college to employment. OCCRL's research spans the P-20 education continuum, with an intense focus on how community colleges impact education and employment outcomes for diverse learners. Results of OCCRL's studies of pathways and programs of study, extending from high school to community colleges and universities and to employment, are disseminated nationally and internationally. Reports and materials are derived from new knowledge captured and disseminated through OCCRL's website, scholarly publications, and other vehicles.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://occrl.illinois.edu</arg><arg name="title">Office of Community College Research and Leadership, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 June 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Additionally, several peer-reviewed journals extensively publish research on community colleges:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Community College Journal of Research and Practice</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>New Directions for Community Colleges</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Community College Review</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Journal of Applied Research in the Community College</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Journal of Transformative Leadership and Policy Studies</target></link></italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>University</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Folk high school</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Articulation (education)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Distance learning</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>E-learning</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lifelong learning</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>In Australia</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Technical and further education</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Workers' Educational Association</target></link><space/>also in the UK</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>In the Philippines</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Association of Local Colleges and Universities</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Local college and university</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>In the UK</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Further education</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Baker, G. A. III (1994). A handbook on the community college in America: Its history, mission, and management. Westport, CT: Greenwood Press.</listitem><listitem>Cohen, A.M., Brawer, F.B. (2003) The American Community College, 4th edition. San Francisco: Jossey Bass.</listitem><listitem>Dougherty, K. J. (1994). The contradictory college: The conflicting origins, impacts, and futures of the community college. Albany, NY: State University of New York Press.</listitem><listitem>Floyd, D.L., Skolnik, M.L., &amp; Walker, K.P., eds. (2005). The Community College Baccalaureate: Emerging Trends and Policy Issues. Sterling VA: Stylus Publishing.</listitem><listitem>Frye, J. H. (1992). The vision of the public junior college, 19001940. Westport, CT: Greenwood Press.</listitem><listitem>Kasper, H.T. (2002). The changing role of community college. Occupational Outlook Quarterly, 46(4), 1421.</listitem><listitem>Murray, J.P. (2002). The current state of faculty development in two-year colleges. New Directions for Community Colleges, 118, 8997.</listitem><listitem>Vaughan, George, Mellander, Gustavo, Beverly Blois (1997). The Community College Presidency. Washington,DC: The American Association of Community Colleges.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cca.edu.au/index.html'>Community Colleges Australia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ccrc.tc.columbia.edu'>Community College Research Center, Teachers College, Columbia University</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Schools</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Community College</target></template><link><target>Category:Community colleges</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Types of university or college</target></link><link><target>Category:Vocational education</target></link></paragraph></article>