<article title='Steel-string_acoustic_guitar'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox Instrument</target><arg name="name">Steel-string acoustic guitar
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Gibson_SJ200.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_capt"><space/>A [[Gibson Guitar Corporation|Gibson]] SJ200 model.
</arg><arg name="background">string
</arg><arg name="classification"><space/>[[String instrument]] ([[Plucked string instrument|plucked]])
</arg><arg name="hornbostel_sachs">321.322-6
</arg><arg name="hornbostel_sachs_desc">Composite [[chordophone]] sounded by a [[plectrum]]
</arg><arg name="range">[[File:Range guitar.svg|130px|center]]
</arg><arg name="related">
* '''[[Plucked string instrument|Guitar family]]''' ([[Classical guitar]], [[Electric guitar]], [[Flamenco guitar]], [[Bass guitar]])
* [[Lute]] (distantly related)
</arg><arg name="musicians">
</arg><arg name="midi">025/026 (Acoustic Steel Guitar)
</arg><arg name="articles">
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Playing acoustic guitar.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Playing a steel-string guitar without a pick (<link><target>fingerpicking</target></link>).</part></link><link><target>File:C.F._Martin_000-28EC_Eric_Clapton_model_Acoustic_Guitar.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part>A<space/><link><target>C. F. Martin &amp; Company</target><part>C.F. Martin</part></link><space/><link><target>Eric Clapton</target></link><space/>model.</part></link><link><target>File:Fender DG-41SCE Electro-acoustic guitar.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>170px</part><part><link><target>Fender Musical Instruments Corporation</target><part>Fender</part></link><space/>DG-41SCE.</part></link><link><target>File:Epiphone PR-5E VS Cutaway Acoustic Electric Guitar (Vintage Sunburst).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>170px</part><part><link><target>Epiphone</target></link><space/>PR-5E VS.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>steel-string acoustic guitar</bold><space/>is a modern form of<space/><link><target>guitar</target></link><space/>that descends from the<space/><link><target>classical guitar</target></link>, but is strung with steel strings for a brighter, louder sound. It is often referred to simply as an<space/><bold><link><target>acoustic guitar</target></link></bold>, though the nylon-strung classical guitar is also sometimes called an acoustic guitar.</paragraph><paragraph>The most common type is often called a<space/><link><target>flat-top guitar</target></link>, to distinguish it from the more specialized<space/><link><target>archtop guitar</target></link><space/>and other variations.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Standard tuning#Plucked strings</target><part>standard tuning</part></link><space/>for an acoustic guitar is E-A-D-G-B-E (low to high), although many players, particularly fingerpickers, use alternate tunings (<link><target>scordatura</target></link>), such as &quot;<link><target>Open G tuning</target><part>open G</part></link>&quot; (D-G-D-G-B-D), &quot;<link><target>open D tuning</target><part>open D</part></link>&quot; (D-A-D-F<template><target>music</target><arg>sharp</arg></template>-A-D), or &quot;<link><target>Drop D tuning</target><part>drop D</part></link>&quot; (D-A-D-G-B-E).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Construction</heading><paragraph>There are many variations in construction and materials used in steel-string guitars. Different combinations of woods and construction elements (for example, how the top is braced) affect the<space/><link><target>timbre</target></link><space/>or &quot;tone&quot; of the guitar. Many players and<space/><link><target>luthier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>feel a well-made guitar's tone improves over time.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Types</heading><paragraph>Acoustic guitars are commonly constructed in several different body types. In general, the guitar's soundbox can be thought of as composed of two connected chambers: the<space/><italics>upper bouts</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>lower bouts</italics><space/>(a<space/><italics>bout</italics><space/>being the rounded corner of an instrument body), which meet at the<space/><italics>waist</italics>, or the narrowest part of the body face near the soundhole. The proportion and overall size of these two parts helps determine the overall tonal balance and &quot;native sound&quot; of a particular body style the larger the body, the louder the volume.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A<space/><bold>&quot;00&quot;</bold>,<space/><bold>&quot;Double-Oh&quot;</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>&quot;Grand Concert&quot;</bold><space/>body type is the major body style most directly derived from the classical guitar. It has the thinnest soundbox and the smallest overall size of the major styles, making it very comfortable to play but also one of the quietest. Its smaller size makes it suitable for younger or smaller-framed players. These guitars are commonly called &quot;parlor steels&quot; as they are well-suited to smaller rooms.<space/><link><target>C. F. Martin &amp; Company</target><part>Martin</part></link>'s 00-xxx series and<space/><link><target>Taylor Guitars</target><part>Taylor</part></link>'s x12 series are common examples.</listitem><listitem>A<space/><bold>&quot;Grand Auditorium&quot;</bold><space/>guitar, sometimes called a &quot;<bold>000&quot;</bold><space/>or &quot;<bold>Triple-Oh&quot;</bold>, is very similar in design to the Grand Concert, but slightly wider and deeper. Many 000-style guitars also have a convex back panel to increase the volume of space in the soundbox without making the soundbox deeper at the edges, which would affect comfort and playability. The result is a very balanced tone, comparable to the 00 but with greater volume and dynamic range and slightly more low-end response, without sacrificing the ergonomics of the classical style, making these body styles very popular.<space/><link><target>Eric Clapton</target></link>'s signature Martin guitar, for example, is of this style. Martin's 000-xxx series and Taylor's x14 series are well-known examples of the Grand Auditorium style.</listitem><listitem>A<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>Dreadnought (guitar type)</target><part>Dreadnought</part></link>&quot;</bold>, currently the most common body type, incorporates a deeper soundbox, but a smaller and less-pronounced upper bout (the area of the soundbox between the waist and neck) than most styles, giving a somewhat wedge-shaped appearance hence its name, relating to a class of warship. The dreadnought style was designed by<space/><link><target>Martin Guitars</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="sweetwater1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Acoustic Guitar Buying Guide</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sweetwater.com/insync/acoustic-guitar-buying-guide/</arg><arg name="publisher">www.sweetwater.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>to produce a deeper sound than &quot;classic&quot;-style guitars, with very present bass fundamentals. This body style's combination of a small profile with a deep sound has made it immensely popular, and it has since been copied by virtually every major steel-string luthier.<space/><link><target>Martin Guitars</target><part>Martin</part></link>'s &quot;D&quot; series such as the<space/><link><target>Martin D-28</target><part>D-28</part></link><space/>are classic examples of the dreadnought.</listitem><listitem>A<space/><bold>&quot;Jumbo&quot;</bold><space/>body type is bigger again than a Grand Auditorium but similarly proportioned, and is generally designed to provide a deeper tone, similar to a dreadnought (the body style was designed by Gibson to compete with the dreadnought<extension extension_name='ref' name="sweetwater1"></extension>) but with maximum resonant space for greater volume and sustain. This comes at the expense of being oversized, with a very deep sounding box, and thus somewhat more difficult to play. The foremost example of this style is the<space/><link><target>Gibson J-200</target></link>, but like the dreadnought, most guitar manufacturers have at least one jumbo model.</listitem></list><paragraph>Any of these body type can optionally incorporate a &quot;<link><target>cutaway (guitar)</target><part>cutaway</part></link>&quot;. A cutaway guitar has a redesigned upper bout that removes a section of the soundbox on the underside of the neck, hence the name &quot;cutaway&quot;. This allows for easier access to the frets that are located on top of the soundbox past the heel of the neck. The tradeoff is reduced soundbox volume, and often a change in bracing, which can change the resonant qualities and hence the tone of the instrument.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>12-string guitar</target></link>&quot;</bold><space/>replaces each single string with a<space/><italics>course</italics><space/>of two strings. The lower pairs are tuned an octave apart. This guitar was made famous by Artists such as<space/><link><target>Lead Belly</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pete Seeger</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Leo Kottke</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>All of the guitars above are relatively traditional in looks and construction, and are commonly referred to as &quot;flattop&quot; guitars. All are commonly seen and heard in popular music genres, including<space/><link><target>rock music</target><part>rock</part></link>,<space/><link><target>blues</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Country music</target><part>country</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Folk music</target><part>folk</part></link>. However, other styles of guitar have been introduced and enjoy moderate popularity, generally in more specific genres:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold><link><target>archtop guitar</target></link></bold><space/>incorporates a top, either carved out of solid wood or heat-pressed using laminations, that is arched like instruments in the<space/><link><target>violin family</target></link>, usually with an f-hole rather than a round sound hole. These guitars are most commonly used by<space/><link><target>swing (genre)</target><part>swing</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>jazz</target></link><space/>players and often incorporate electronics in the form of a<space/><link><target>Pickup (music technology)</target><part>pickup</part></link>. However, many other kinds of acoustic guitars may incorporate these kinds of electronics as well.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>Selmer-Maccaferri guitar</target></link>&quot;</bold><space/>is usually played by those who follow the style of<space/><link><target>Django Reinhardt</target></link>. It is an unusual-looking instrument, distinguished by a fairly large body with squarish bouts, and either a &quot;D&quot;-shaped or longitudinal oval soundhole. The strings are gathered at the tail like an archtop guitar, but the top is flatter. It also has a wide fingerboard and slotted head like a nylon-string guitar. The loud volume and penetrating tone make it suitable for single-note<space/><link><target>guitar solo</target><part>soloing</part></link>, and it is frequently employed as a<space/><link><target>lead guitar</target><part>lead instrument</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>gypsy swing</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>resonator guitar</target></link></bold>&quot; or<space/><bold>&quot;<link><target>resophonic guitar</target></link></bold>&quot; produces sound with one or more metal cones (resonators) instead of the wooden soundboard (guitar top/face). Resonator guitars were originally designed to be louder than conventional acoustic guitars, which were overwhelmed by horns and percussion instruments in dance orchestras. They became prized for their distinctive sound, however, and found life with several musical styles (most notably bluegrass and also blues) well after electric amplification solved the issue of inadequate guitar sound levels.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Tonewoods</heading><paragraph>Traditionally, steel-string guitars have been made of a combination of various &quot;<link><target>tonewood</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;, or woods that have pleasing resonant qualities when used in instrument-making. Foremost are<space/><link><target>Sitka spruce</target></link>, the most common, and Alpine and Adirondack spruce, the most sought-after, woods for the making of guitar tops. The back and sides of a particular guitar are typically made of the same wood; Brazilian or East Indian<space/><link><target>rosewood</target></link><space/>and Honduras<space/><link><target>mahogany</target></link><space/>are traditional choices, however,<space/><link><target>maple</target></link><space/>has been prized for the figuring that can be seen when it is cut in a certain way (such as &quot;flame&quot; and &quot;quilt&quot; patterns). A common non-traditional wood gaining popularity is<space/><link><target>sapele</target></link>, which is tonally similar to mahogany but slightly lighter in color and possessing a deep grain structure that is visually appealing.</paragraph><paragraph>Due to decreasing availability and rising prices of premium-quality traditional<space/><link><target>tonewood</target><trail>s</trail></link>, many manufacturers have begun experimenting with alternative species of woods or more commonly available variations on the standard species. For example, some makers have begun producing models with<space/><link><target>Thuja plicata</target><part>redcedar</part></link><space/>or mahogany tops, or with<space/><link><target>spruce</target></link><space/>variants other than Sitka. Cedar is also common in the back and sides, as is<space/><link><target>basswood</target></link>. Entry-level models, especially those made in East Asia, often use<space/><link><target>nato wood</target></link>, which is again tonally similar to mahogany but is cheap to acquire. Some have also begun using non-wood materials, such as<space/><link><target>plastic</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>graphite</target></link>. Carbon-fiber and phenolic composite materials have become desirable for building necks, and some high-end luthiers produce all-carbon-fiber guitars.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Assembly</heading><paragraph>The steel-string acoustic guitar evolved from the nylon- or gut-string classical guitar, and because steel strings have higher tension, heavier construction is required overall. One innovation is a metal bar called a<space/><link><target>guitar#Truss rod</target><part>truss rod</part></link>, which is incorporated into the neck to strengthen it and provide adjustable counter-tension to the stress of the strings. Typically, a steel-string acoustic guitar is built with a larger soundbox than a standard classical guitar. A critical structural and tonal component of an acoustic guitar is the<space/><link><target>Guitar bracing</target><part>bracing</part></link>, a systems of struts glued to the inside of the back and top. Steel-string guitars use different bracing systems from classical guitars, typically using X-bracing instead of fan bracing. (Another simpler system, called ladder bracing, where the braces are all placed across the width of the instrument, is used on all types of flat-top guitars on the back.) Innovations in bracing design have emerged, notably the A-brace developed by British luthier Roger Bucknall of Fylde Guitars.</paragraph><paragraph>Most<space/><link><target>luthier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and experienced players agree that a good solid top (as opposed to laminated or<space/><link><target>plywood</target></link>) is the most important factor in the tone of the guitar. Solid backs and sides can also contribute to a pleasant sound, although laminated sides and backs are acceptable alternatives, commonly found in mid-level guitars (in the range of US$300$1000).</paragraph><paragraph>From the 1960s through the 1980s, &quot;by far the most significant developments in the design and construction of acoustic guitars&quot; were made by the<space/><link><target>Ovation Guitar Company</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Denyer 1992"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The guitar handbook
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ralph
<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Denyer
<space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/>Special contributors [[Isaac&nbsp;Guillory]] and Alastair&nbsp;M.&nbsp;Crawford
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>48
<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Ovation guitars (Acoustic guitars)
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-330-32750-X
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London and Sydney
<space/></arg><arg name="others">[[Robert&nbsp;Fripp]] (foreword)
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pan Books
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Fully revised and updated
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992
</arg></template></extension><space/>It introduced a composite &quot;roundback&quot; bowl, which replaced the square back and sides of traditional guitars; because of its engineering design, Ovation guitars could be amplified without producing the obnoxious feedback that had plagued acoustic guitars before. Ovation also pioneered with electronics, such as<space/><link><target>Pickup (music technology)</target><part>pickup</part></link><space/>systems and electronic tuners.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Denyer 1992"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Anonymous</arg><arg name="date">1 October 2004</arg><arg name="first">Music Trades</arg><arg name="title">Ovation's encore: How a host of product refinements have rekindled growth at Kaman&nbsp;Music's flagship guitar&nbsp;division</arg><arg name="series">The Guitar Market</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Music Trades]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-124136480.html</arg><arg name="id">(subscription required)</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Carter</arg><arg name="first">Walter</arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="title">The history of the Ovation guitar</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jon</arg><arg name="editor-last">Eiche</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Hal&nbsp;Leonard Corporation]]</arg><arg name="series">Musical Instruments Series</arg><arg name="location">Milwaukee, Wisconsin</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7935-5876-6</arg><arg name="edition">first</arg><arg name="pages">1–128</arg><arg name="id">HL00330187</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="title">From the ratcheting of helicopters to a guitar's hum</arg><arg name="first">Valerie</arg><arg name="last">Cruice</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="date">December 8, 1996</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="date">30–31 May 1999</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Marks</arg><arg name="first">Brenda</arg><arg name="title">Connecticut&nbsp;firm makes guitars, helicopter&nbsp;blades from same fiberglass</arg><arg name="publisher">Knight Ridder/Tribune Business News</arg><arg name="location">New Hartford, Conn.</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Waterbury Republican-American]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 April 2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-54758412.html</arg><arg name="subscription">yes</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>See<space/><link><target>Guitar</target></link><space/>for more details on the construction of acoustic guitars.</italics></paragraph><heading level='2'>Amplification</heading><paragraph>A steel-string guitar can be amplified with a:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>microphone</target></link>, possibly clipped to the guitar body;</listitem><listitem>detachable<space/><link><target>Pickup (music technology)</target><part>pickup</part></link>, often straddling the soundhole and using the same magnetic principle as a traditional electric guitar; or</listitem><listitem><link><target>transducer</target></link><space/>built into the body.</listitem></list><paragraph>The last type of guitar is commonly called an &quot;acoustic-electric&quot; or &quot;<link><target>electro-acoustic guitar</target><part>electro-acoustic</part></link>&quot; guitar, as it can be played either &quot;unplugged&quot; as an acoustic or plugged in as an electric. The most common type is a<space/><link><target>piezoelectric pickup</target></link>, which is composed of a thin sandwich of quartz crystal. When compressed, the crystal produces a small electric current, so when placed under the bridge saddle, the vibrations of the strings through the saddle, and of the body of the instrument, are converted to a weak electrical signal. This signal is often sent to a<space/><link><target>pre-amplifier</target></link>, which increases the signal strength and normally incorporates an<space/><link><target>Equalization (audio)</target><part>equalizer</part></link>. The output of the preamplifier then goes to a separate amplifier system similar to that for an electric guitar.</paragraph><paragraph>Several manufacturers produce specialised<space/><link><target>acoustic guitar amplifier</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are designed to give undistorted and full-range reproduction.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Music and players</heading><paragraph>Until the 1960s, the predominant forms of music played on the flat-top, steel-string guitar remained relatively stable and included acoustic<space/><link><target>blues</target></link>,<space/><link><target>American country music</target><part>country</part></link>,<space/><link><target>bluegrass music</target><part>bluegrass</part></link>,<space/><link><target>folk music</target><part>folk</part></link>, and several genres of<space/><link><target>rock music</target><part>rock</part></link>. The concept of playing solo steel-string guitar in a concert setting was introduced in the early 1960s by such performers as<space/><link><target>Davey Graham</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Fahey (musician)</target><part>John Fahey</part></link>, who used<space/><link><target>country blues</target></link><space/><link><target>fingerpicking</target></link><space/>techniques to compose original compositions with structures somewhat like<space/><link><target>European classical music</target></link>. Fahey contemporary<space/><link><target>Robbie Basho</target></link><space/>added elements of<space/><link><target>Indian classical music</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Leo Kottke</target></link><space/>used a Faheyesque approach to make the first solo steel-string guitar &quot;hit&quot; record.</paragraph><paragraph>Steel-string guitars are also important in the world of<space/><link><target>flatpicking</target></link>, as utilized by such artists as<space/><link><target>Clarence White</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tony Rice</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bryan Sutton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Doc Watson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David Grier</target></link>. Luthiers have been experimenting with redesigning the acoustic guitar for these players. These flat-top, steel-string guitars are constructed and voiced more for classical-like fingerpicking and less for chordal accompaniment (strumming). Some luthiers have increasingly focused their attention on the needs of fingerstylists and have developed unique guitars for this style of playing.</paragraph><paragraph>Many other luthiers attempt to recreate the guitars of the &quot;Golden Era&quot; of<space/><link><target>Martin Guitars</target><part>C.F. Martin &amp; Co</part></link>. This was started by Roy Noble, who built the guitar played by Clarence White from 1968 to 1972, and was followed by Bill Collings, Marty Lanham,<space/><link><target>Dana Bourgeois</target></link>, Randy Lucas, Lynn Dudenbostel and<space/><link><target>Wayne Henderson (luthier)</target><part>Wayne Henderson</part></link>, a few of the luthiers building guitars today inspired by vintage Martins, the preWorld War II models in particular. As prices for vintage Martins continue to rise exponentially, upscale guitar enthusiasts have demanded faithful recreations and luthiers are working to fill that demand.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Guitar</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Guitar</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of guitar manufacturers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Charlie Nothing#Dingulator</target><part>Dingulator</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Strumming</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Guitars</target><arg>Type</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Steel-String Acoustic Guitar</target></template><link><target>Category:Acoustic guitars</target></link><link><target>Category:American musical instruments</target></link><link><target>Category:Rhythm section</target></link></paragraph></article>