<article title='Buddhist_cuisine'><paragraph><template><target>Chinese</target><arg name="title">Buddhist Vegetarian Cuisine
</arg><arg name="pic">chinese-buddhist-cuisine-taiwan-1.jpg
</arg><arg name="piccap">A vegetarian restaurant in Taipei, Taiwan serving Buddhist cuisine in buffet style
</arg><arg name="t">齋菜</arg><arg name="s">斋菜</arg><arg name="j">zaai<sup>1</sup>coi<sup>3</sup></arg><arg name="p">zhāi cài</arg><arg name="wuu"><space/>{{IPA-wuu|tsa tsɛ|}}</arg><arg name="poj">che-chhài
</arg><arg name="kanji">精進料理</arg><arg name="kana">しょうじんりょうり</arg><arg name="revhep">shōjin ryōri</arg><arg name="kunrei">syouzin ryouri
</arg><arg name="hangul">사찰음식</arg><arg name="hanja">寺刹飮食</arg><arg name="rr">sachal eumsik<space/></arg><arg name="mr">sach'al ŭmsik
</arg><arg name="qn">đồ chay 
</arg></template><bold>Buddhist cuisine</bold><space/>is an<space/><link><target>East Asia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>cuisine</target></link><space/>which is followed by<space/><link><target>Bhikkhu</target><part>monks</part></link><space/>and many believers from areas historically influenced by<space/><link><target>Chinese Buddhism</target></link>. It is vegetarian or vegan, and it is based on the Dharmic concept of<space/><link><target>ahimsa</target></link><space/>(non-violence). Vegetarianism is common in other Dharmic faiths such as<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jainism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sikhism</target></link><space/>as well as East Asian religions like<space/><link><target>Taoism</target></link>. While<space/><link><target>Bhikkhu</target><part>monks</part></link><space/>are vegetarian year-round, many believers follow the Buddhist vegetarian diet temporarily, similar to Christian<space/><link><target>Lent</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Vegetarian cuisine is known as<space/><italics>ssh ()</italics><space/>(&quot;vegetarian food&quot;),<space/><italics>chns ()</italics><space/>(&quot;vegan&quot;),<space/><italics>zhici ()</italics><space/>(&quot;lent / fasting food&quot;) in<space/><link><target>China</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hong Kong</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Singapore</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Taiwan</target></link>;<space/><italics><space/>chay</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>;<space/><template><target>nihongo</target><arg></arg><arg>精進料理</arg><arg>shōjin ryōri</arg><arg>devotion cuisine</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link>;<space/><italics>sachal eumsik</italics><space/>(<template><target>lang</target><arg>ko</arg><arg>사찰음식</arg></template>&quot;temple food&quot;) in<space/><link><target>Korea</target></link>;<space/><italics>jai ()</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Thailand</target></link><space/>and by other names in many countries. The dishes that comprise Buddhist cuisine in any given place will be influenced by the style of food there.</paragraph><paragraph>The origin of &quot;Buddhist food&quot; as a distinct sub-style of cuisine is tied to monasteries, where one member of the community would have the duty of being the head cook and supplying meals that paid respect to the strictures of Buddhist precepts. Temples that were open to visitors from the general public might also serve meals to them and a few temples effectively run functioning restaurants on the premises. In Japan, this practice is generally known as<space/><template><target>nihongo</target><arg></arg><arg>精進料理</arg><arg>shōjin ryōri</arg><arg>devotion cuisine</arg></template>, and served at many temples, especially in<space/><link><target>Kyoto</target></link>. A more recent version, more Chinese in style, is prepared by the<space/><link><target>baku</target></link><space/>school of zen, and known as<space/><template><target>nihongo</target><arg></arg><arg>普茶料理</arg><arg>fucha ryōri</arg></template>; this is served at the head temple of<space/><link><target>Manpuku-ji</target></link>, as well as various subtemples. In modern times, commercial restaurants have also latched on to the style, catering both to practicing and non-practicing lay people.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Philosophies governing food</heading><heading level='3'>Vegetarianism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Buddhist vegetarianism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Most of the dishes considered to be uniquely Buddhist are vegetarian, but opinions and restrictions on the eating of meat, and whether it should be prohibited, vary among sects.</paragraph><paragraph>When monks and nuns who follow the<space/><link><target>Theravada</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>way feed themselves by<space/><link><target>alms</target></link>, they must eat leftover foods which are given to them, including meat.<extension extension_name='ref' name="aboutbudd"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://buddhism.about.com/od/basicbuddhistteachings/a/vegetarianism.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Buddhism and Vegetarianism<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 9, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[About.com]]<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>(The Pali/Sanskrit term for monks and nuns means &quot;one who seeks alms&quot;.) The exception to this alms rule is when monks and nuns have seen, heard or known that animal(s) have been specifically killed to feed the alms-seeker, in which case consumption of such meat would be<space/><link><target>karma</target><part>karmically</part></link><space/>negative.<extension extension_name='ref' name="aboutbudd"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.urbandharma.org/udharma3/meat.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">What the Buddha Said About Eating Meat<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 9, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Urban Dharma<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The same restriction is also followed by<space/><link><target>laity</target><part>lay</part></link><space/>Buddhists and is known as the consumption of the &quot;triply clean meat&quot; (). Additionally, the<space/><link><target>Pali Sutras</target></link><space/>where this rule is set forth tell of the Buddha refuting a suggestion by his student<space/><link><target>Devadatta</target></link><space/>to include vegetarianism in the monastic precepts.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Mahayana</target></link><space/>tradition, by contrast, acceptance of the Pali Sutras is contested and several of the sutras that comprise the<space/><link><target>Mahayana sutras</target><part>Mahayana canon</part></link><space/>contain several explicit prohibitions against consuming meat, in one case saying &quot;One who eats meat kills the seed of great compassion&quot;.<space/><link><target>Japanese Buddhism</target><part>Japanese Buddhist</part></link><space/>sects generally believe that Buddha ate meat.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gfbv"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Powers<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Going forth: Buddhist vision of vinaya - book review<space/><Internet><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ic.nanzan-u.ac.jp/SHUBUNKEN/publications/jjrs/pdf/739.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 July 2007<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>All Japanese Kamakura sects of Buddhism (<link><target>Zen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nichiren</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jdo sh</target><part>Jodo</part></link>) have relaxed Mahayana<space/><link><target>vinaya</target></link>, and as a consequence, vegetarianism is optional.<extension extension_name='ref' name="udvagi"></extension><space/><link><target>Tibetan Buddhism</target></link><space/>believes that<space/><link><target>Tantra techniques (Vajrayana)</target><part>tantric practice</part></link><space/>makes vegetarianism unnecessary.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://shambhalasun.com/sunspace/?p</arg><arg name="title">The Accidental Vegetarian<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 9, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Shambhala Sun]]<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The monastic community in Chinese Buddhism, Vietnamese Buddhism and most of Korean Buddhism strictly adhere to vegetarianism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="udvagi"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Still, both<space/><link><target>Mahayana</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Theravada</target></link><space/>Buddhists consider that one may practice vegetarianism as part of cultivating<space/><link><target>Bodhisattvas</target><part>Bodhisattvas's</part></link><space/><link><target>paramita</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="aboutbudd"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="udvagi"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.urbandharma.org/udharma3/vegi.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Buddhism and Vegetarianism<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 9, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Urban Dharma<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Other restrictions</heading><paragraph>East Asian &quot;Buddhist&quot; cuisine differs from Western vegetarian cuisine in one aspect, that is avoidance of killing plant life. Buddhist<space/><link><target>vinaya</target></link><space/>for monks and nuns prohibits harming of plants. Therefore, strictly speaking,<space/><link><target>root vegetable</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(such as potatoes, carrots or onion and garlic) are not to be used as this results in the death of the plant.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template><template><target>Dubious</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template><space/>The respective<space/><link><target>Vinaya</target></link><space/>forbid the monks and nuns the consumption of mango and garlic. Both prohibitions followed incidents in which monastics harvested more than they could eat in one day. This restriction of not eating garlic and mango is found in both the Theravada<space/><link><target>vinaya</target></link><space/>and in that of the Mahayana. The monastic has to follow this rule on all occasions, not just on holidays.</paragraph><paragraph>In addition to the ban on<space/><link><target>garlic</target></link><space/>practically all<space/><link><target>Mahayana</target></link><space/>monastics in<space/><link><target>China</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link><space/>specifically avoid eating strong-smelling plants, traditionally<space/><link><target>asafoetida</target></link>,<space/><link><target>shallot</target></link>, and mountain<space/><link><target>leek</target></link>, and refer to these as<space/><italics>w hn</italics><space/>(, or 'Five Acrid and Strong-smelling Vegetables') or<space/><italics>w xn</italics><space/>( or 'Five Spices') as they tend to excite senses. This is based on teachings found in the<space/><link><target>Brahamajala Sutra (Mahayana)</target><part>Brahamajala Sutra</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Surangama Sutra</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lankavatara Sutra</target></link><space/>(chapter eight). In modern times this rule is often interpreted to include other vegetables of the<space/><link><target>Allium</target><part>onion</part></link><space/><link><target>genus</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>coriander</target></link>. This food regime follows that of the Taoists who are bent on<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://absolutetruth.in/forums/topic/why-its-recommended-to-avoid-onion-and-garlic</arg><arg name="title">Why its recommended to avoid Onion and garlic</arg><arg name="work">Absolute-Truth Forums</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 January 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>the life of asceticism. The East-Asian Buddhist rationale is the same as that of the Taoists. This custom also draws parallels with some believers of<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jainism</target></link><space/>who also do not consume pungent tasting foods.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Shojin ryori ryuanji.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>An example of shjin-ryri taken in<space/><link><target>Kyoto</target></link>, Japan at the zen temple of<space/><link><target>Ryan-ji</target></link>.</part></link><space/>The food that a strict Buddhist takes, if not a vegetarian, is also specific. For many Chinese Buddhists beef and the consumption of large animals and exotic species is avoided. Then there would be the aforementioned &quot;triply clean meat&quot; rule. One restriction on food that is not known to many is the abstinence from eating animal innards and organs. This is known as<space/><italics>xishui</italics><space/>(), not to be confused with the term for sewage.</paragraph><paragraph>Alcohol and other drugs are also avoided by many Buddhists because of their effects on the mind and &quot;mindfulness&quot;. It is part of the Five Precepts which dictate that one is not to consume &quot;addictive materials&quot;. The definition of &quot;addictive&quot; depends on each individual but most Buddhists consider alcohol,<space/><link><target>tobacco</target></link><space/>and drugs other than medicine to be addictive. Although<space/><link><target>caffeine</target></link><space/>is now also known to be addictive, caffeinated drinks and especially<space/><link><target>tea</target></link><space/>are not included under this restriction; tea in particular is considered to be healthy and beneficial and its mild stimulant effect desirable. There are many legends about tea. Among meditators it is considered to keep the person alert and awake without overexcitement.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Simple and natural</heading><paragraph>In theory and practice, many regional styles of cooking may be adopted to be &quot;Buddhist&quot; as long as the cook, with the above restrictions in mind, prepares the food, generally in simple preparations, with expert attention to its quality, wholesomeness and flavor. Often working on a tight budget, the monastery cook would have to make the most of whatever ingredients were available.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Tenzo kyokun</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;Instructions for the Zen Cook&quot;),<space/><link><target>Soto Zen</target></link><space/>founder<space/><link><target>Eihei Dogen</target></link><space/>wrote the following about the Zen attitude toward food:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>In preparing food, it is essential to be sincere and to respect each ingredient regardless of how coarse or fine it is. (...) A rich buttery soup is not better as such than a broth of wild herbs. In handling and preparing wild herbs, do so as you would the ingredients for a rich feast, wholeheartedly, sincerely, clearly. When you serve the monastic assembly, they and you should taste only the flavour of the Ocean of Reality , the Ocean of unobscured Awake Awareness, not whether or not the soup is creamy or made only of wild herbs. In nourishing the seeds of living in the Way rich food and wild grass are not separate.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.wwzc.org/book/tenzo-kyokun-instructions-tenzo-0<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tenzo kyokun: Instructions for the Tenzo - White Wind Zen Community<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2012-10-15</arg></template></extension>&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ingredients</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Saigon Vegetarian food.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Vegetarian dishes at a Buddhist restaurant in Ho Chi Minh city</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Following its dominant status in most parts of East Asia where Buddhism is most practiced,<space/><link><target>rice</target></link><space/>features heavily in as a staple in the Buddhist meal, especially in the form of rice porridge or<space/><link><target>congee</target></link><space/>as the usual morning meal.<space/><link><target>Noodle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other grains may often be served as well. Vegetables of all sorts are generally either stir-fried or cooked in broth with seasonings and may be eaten with various sauces. Eggs and dairy are sometimes permitted and may show up on occasion in moderate amounts; dairy is not common in purely Japanese and Chinese preparations but may appear in dishes from American and European monasteries that follow the traditions. Eggs are seen as almost meat and many Buddhists avoid them. Seasonings will be informed by whatever is common in the local region; for example,<space/><link><target>soy sauce</target></link><space/>and vegan<space/><link><target>dashi</target></link><space/>figure strongly in Japanese monastery food while<space/><link><target>curry</target></link><space/>may be prominent in Southeast Asia. Sweets and desserts are not often consumed, but are permitted in moderation and may be served at special occasions such as in the context of a<space/><link><target>tea ceremony</target></link><space/>in the Zen tradition.</paragraph><paragraph>Buddhist vegetarian chefs have become extremely creative in imitating meat using prepared<space/><link><target>wheat gluten (food)</target><part>wheat gluten</part></link>, also known as seitan, kao fu () or wheat meat,<space/><link><target>soy</target></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>tofu</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>tempeh</target></link>),<space/><link><target>agar</target></link>,<space/><link><target>konyaku</target></link><space/>and other<space/><link><target>plant</target></link><space/>products. Some of their recipes are the oldest and most-refined<space/><link><target>meat analogue</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the world. Soy and wheat gluten are very versatile materials, because they can be manufactured into various shapes and textures, and they absorb flavorings (including, but not limited to, meat-like flavorings), while having very little flavor of their own. With the proper<space/><link><target>seasoning</target><trail>s</trail></link>, they can mimic various kinds of meat quite closely.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of these Buddhist vegetarian chefs are in the many<space/><link><target>monastery</target><part>monasteries</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>temple</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which serve allium-free and mock-meat (also known as 'meat analogues') dishes to the monks and visitors (including non-Buddhists who often stay for a few hours or days, to Buddhists who are not monks, but staying overnight for anywhere up to weeks or months). Many Buddhist restaurants also serve vegetarian, vegan, non-alcoholic or allium-free dishes.</paragraph><paragraph>Some Buddhists eat vegetarian on the 1st and 15th of the lunar calendar (lenten days), on Chinese New Year eve, and on saint and ancestral holy days. To cater to this type of customer, as well as full-time vegetarians, the menu of a Buddhist vegetarian restaurant usually shows no difference from a typical Chinese or East Asian restaurant, except that in recipes originally made to contain meat, a soy chicken substitute might be served instead.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Variations by sect or region</heading><paragraph>According to cookbooks published in English, formal monastery meals in the<space/><link><target>Zen</target></link><space/>tradition generally follow a pattern of<space/><link><target>ryki</target><part>&quot;three bowls&quot;</part></link><space/>in descending size. The first and largest bowl is a grain-based dish such as rice, noodles or<space/><link><target>congee</target></link>; the second contains the protein dish which is often some form of stew or soup; the third and smallest bowl is a vegetable dish or a salad.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FarreyO'Hara2000"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Edward Farrey</arg><arg name="author2">Nancy O'Hara</arg><arg name="title">3 Bowls: Vegetarian Recipes from an American Zen Buddhist Monastery</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 October 2012</arg><arg name="date">16 May 2000</arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-395-97707-1</arg><arg name="page">X</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Buddha's delight</target></link></listitem></list><preblock><preline>*<space/><link><target>Buddhist ethics</target></link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Buddhist vegetarianism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cultural elements of Buddhism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vegetarianism and religion</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Korean temple cuisine</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Buddhist cuisine</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shabkar.org'>Shabkar.org: Vegetarianism as a way of life for Buddhists</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shabkar.org/download/pdf/Shojin_Ryori_Culinary_Fundamentals_in_Zen.pdf'>Shojin Ryori: Vegetarian Cooking</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shabkar.org/scripture/tantras/index.htm'>Tantras on Buddhist food</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shabkar.org/scripture/sutras/index.htm'>Sutras on vegetarianism</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.headcity.com/uptown/bigmouth/hungry/chinese/middle.html'>Return To The Middle Kingdom: Chinese Vegetarian Eating in East Asia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://zecoow.com'>Toshio Tanahashi</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://vegetarian-china.info/'>vegetarian-china.info</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Buddhism topics</target></template><template><target>Diets</target></template><template><target>cuisines</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Buddhist Cuisine</target></template><link><target>Category:Buddhist cuisine</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Buddhist culture</target></link><link><target>Category:Buddhist vegetarianism</target></link><link><target>Category:Buddhism in China</target></link><link><target>Category:Regional cuisines of China</target></link></paragraph></article>