<article title='Cavalry'><paragraph><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>Calvary</arg></template><template><target>other uses</target></template><link><target>File:Edouard Detaille - Vive L'Empereur - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part><link><target>4th Hussar Regiment (France)</target><part>French 4th Hussars</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>battle of Friedland</target></link>, 1807</part></link><template><target>war</target></template><bold>Cavalry</bold><space/>(from<space/><link><target>French language</target><part>French</part></link><space/><italics>cavalerie</italics>, cf.<space/><italics>cheval</italics><space/>'horse') or<space/><bold>horsemen</bold><space/>were<space/><link><target>soldier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>warrior</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who fought mounted on<space/><link><target>horseback</target></link>. Cavalry were historically the most mobile of the combat arms. An individual soldier in the cavalry is known by a number of designations such as<space/><bold>cavalryman</bold>,<space/><bold>horseman</bold>,<space/><bold>dragoon</bold>, or<space/><bold>trooper</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>The designation of<space/><bold>cavalry</bold><space/>was not usually given to any<space/><link><target>Military animals</target><part>military force that used other animals</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>Camel cavalry</target><part>camels</part></link><space/>or mules.<space/><link><target>Infantry</target></link><space/>who moved on horseback, but dismounted to fight on foot, were known in the 17th and early 18th centuries as<space/><link><target>dragoon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, a class of<space/><link><target>mounted infantry</target></link><space/>which later evolved into cavalry proper while retaining their historic title.</paragraph><paragraph>From earliest times cavalry had the advantage of improved mobility, making it an</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>instrument which multiplied the fighting value of even the smallest forces, allowing them to outflank and avoid, to surprise and overpower, to retreat and escape according to the requirements of the moment.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.4, Rodger</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A man fighting from horseback also had the advantages of greater height, speed, and inertial mass over an opponent on foot. Another element of horse mounted warfare is the psychological impact a mounted soldier can inflict on an opponent.</paragraph><paragraph>The speed, mobility and shock value of the cavalry was greatly appreciated and exploited in armed forces in the Ancient and Middle Ages; some forces were mostly cavalry, particularly in nomadic societies of Asia, notably the Mongol armies. In Europe cavalry became increasingly<space/><link><target>Heavy cavalry</target><part>armoured</part></link><space/>(heavy), and eventually became known for the mounted<space/><link><target>knight</target><trail>s</trail></link>. During the 17th century cavalry in Europe lost most of its armor, ineffective against the muskets and cannon which were coming into use, and by the mid-19th century armor had mainly fallen into disuse, although some regiments retained a small thickened<space/><link><target>cuirass</target></link><space/>that offered protection against lances and sabres and some protection against shot.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Interwar period</target><part>period</part></link><space/>between the<space/><link><target>World war</target><part>World Wars</part></link>, many cavalry units were converted into<space/><link><target>motorized infantry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mechanized infantry</target></link><space/>units, or reformed as tank troops. However, some cavalry still served during the<space/><link><target>Second World War</target><part>World War II</part></link>, notably in the<space/><link><target>Red Army</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Mongolian People's Army</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Royal Italian Army</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Polish Land Forces</target></link>. Most cavalry units that are horse-mounted in modern armies serve in purely ceremonial roles, or as mounted infantry in difficult terrain such as mountains or heavily forested areas. Modern usage of the term refers to specialist units equipped with tanks (&quot;armored cavalry&quot;) or aircraft (&quot;air cavalry&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Role of cavalry</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Cavalry tactics</arg></template><link><target>File:Rytter fra Bagirmi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>African horseman of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Baguirmi</target><part>Baguirmi</part></link><space/>in full<space/><link><target>gambeson</target><part>padded armour</part></link><space/>suit</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In many modern armies, the term<space/><italics>cavalry</italics><space/>is still often used to refer to units that are a<space/><link><target>Combat Arms</target><part>combat arm</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>armed forces</target></link><space/>which in the past filled the traditional horse-borne land combat<space/><link><target>light cavalry</target></link><space/>roles. These include<space/><link><target>reconnaissance</target><part>scouting</part></link>,<space/><link><target>skirmishing</target></link><space/>with enemy reconnaissance elements to deny them knowledge of own disposition of troops, forward security, offensive reconnaissance by combat, defensive screening of friendly forces during retrograde movement,<space/><link><target>retreat (military)</target><part>retreat</part></link>, restoration of command and control, deception, battle handover and passage of lines, relief in place, linkup,<space/><link><target>Breakout (military)</target><part>breakout</part></link><space/>operations, and<space/><link><target>Raid (military)</target><part>raiding</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>shock attack</target><part>shock</part></link><space/>role, traditionally filled by<space/><link><target>heavy cavalry</target></link>, is generally filled by<space/><link><target>Military unit</target><part>unit</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with the &quot;<link><target>Armoured warfare</target><part>armored</part></link>&quot; designation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Assyriancavalry.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Assyrian cavalry</part></link>Before the<space/><link><target>Iron Age</target></link>, the role of cavalry on the battlefield was largely performed by light<space/><link><target>chariot</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The chariot originated with the<space/><link><target>Sintashta-Petrovka</target></link><space/>culture in<space/><link><target>Central Asia</target></link><space/>and spread by<space/><link><target>nomad</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>or semi-nomadic<space/><link><target>Indo-Iranians</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.1, Menon</extension><space/>The chariot was quickly adopted by settled peoples both as a military technology and an object of ceremonial status, especially by the<space/><link><target>pharaoh</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>New Kingdom of Egypt</target></link><space/>as well as the<space/><link><target>Assyrian army</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Babylonia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>royalty.</paragraph><paragraph>The power of mobility given by mounted units was recognized early on, but was offset by the difficulty of raising large forces and by the inability of<space/><link><target>horse</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(then mostly small) to carry heavy<space/><link><target>armor</target></link>. Cavalry techniques were an innovation of<space/><link><target>equestrian nomad</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the Central Asian and<space/><link><target>Iranian peoples</target><part>Iranian</part></link><space/>steppe and<space/><link><target>pastoral farming</target><part>pastoralist</part></link><space/><link><target>tribe</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as the<space/><link><target>Persian people</target><part>Persian</part></link><space/><link><target>Parthians</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sarmatians</target></link>.<link><target>File:ParthianHorseman.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Parthian horseman, now on display at the<space/><link><target>Palazzo Madama, Turin</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The photograph above left shows Assyrian cavalry from reliefs of 865860 BC. At this time, the men had no<space/><link><target>spur</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>saddle</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>saddle cloth</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or<space/><link><target>stirrup</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Fighting from the back of a horse was much more difficult than mere riding. The cavalry acted in pairs; the reins of the mounted archer were controlled by his neighbour's hand. Even at this early time, cavalry used swords, shields, and bows. The sculpture implies two types of cavalry, but this might be a simplification by the artist. Later images of Assyrian cavalry show saddle cloths as primitive saddles, allowing each archer to control his own horse.</paragraph><paragraph>As early as 490 BC a breed of large horses was bred in the Nisaean plain in Media to carry men with increasing amounts of armour (Herodotus 7,40 &amp; 9,20). But large horses were still very exceptional at this time. Excepting a few ineffective attempts to revive<space/><link><target>scythed chariot</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and continuing far eastern use, the use of chariots in battle was obsolete in civilized nations by the time of the Persian defeat at the hands of<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link>, but chariots remained in use for ceremonial purposes such as carrying the victorious general in a<space/><link><target>Roman triumph</target></link>, or for racing. The southern<space/><link><target>Britons (historical)</target><part>Britons</part></link><space/>met<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link><space/>with chariots in<space/><link><target>Caesar's invasions of Britain</target><part>55 and 54 BC</part></link>, but by the time of the<space/><link><target>Roman conquest of Britain</target></link><space/>a century later chariots were mostly obsolete, even in Britannia. However, the last mention of chariot use in battle was at<space/><link><target>Battle of Mons Graupius</target><part>Mons Graupius</part></link>, in 84 AD. Chariots remained in use in ancient China throughout the Warring States period.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ancient Greece: city-states, Thebes, Thessaly and Macedonia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Amphora Louvre F12.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>right</part><part>Warrior's departure; an<space/><link><target>Athens</target><part>Athenian</part></link><space/><link><target>amphora</target></link><space/>dated 550540 BC.</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>hippeis</arg><arg>companion cavalry</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the classical Greek period cavalry were usually limited to those citizens who could afford expensive war-horses. Three types of cavalry became common: light cavalry, whose riders, armed with javelins, could harass and skirmish; heavy cavalry, whose troopers, using lances, had the ability to close with their opponents; and finally those whose equipment allowed them to fight either on horseback or foot. The role of horsemen did however remain secondary to that of the<space/><link><target>hoplites</target></link><space/>or heavy infantry who comprised the main strength of the citizen levies of the various city states.</paragraph><paragraph>Cavalry played a relatively minor role in<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>ancient Greek</part></link><space/><link><target>city-states</target></link>, with conflicts decided by massed armored infantry. However,<space/><link><target>Ancient Thebes (Boeotia)</target><part>Thebes</part></link><space/>produced<space/><link><target>Pelopidas</target></link>, her first great cavalry commander, whose tactics and skills were absorbed by<space/><link><target>Phillip II of Macedon</target></link><space/>when Phillip was a guest-hostage in Thebes.<space/><link><target>Thessaly</target></link><space/>was widely known for producing competent cavalrymen, and later experiences in wars both with and against the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target><part>Persian</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>taught the<space/><link><target>Greeks</target></link><space/>the value of cavalry in skirmishing and pursuit. The<space/><link><target>Athens</target><part>Athenian</part></link><space/>author and soldier<space/><link><target>Xenophon</target></link><space/>in particular advocated the creation of a small but well-trained cavalry force; to that end, he wrote several manuals on horsemanship and cavalry operations.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Macedon</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>Kingdom in the north, on the other hand, developed a strong cavalry force that culminated in the<space/><italics>hetairoi</italics><space/>(<link><target>Companion cavalry</target></link>) of Philip II of Macedon and<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link>. In addition to these heavy cavalry, the Macedonian army also employed lighter horsemen called<space/><link><target>prodromoi</target></link><space/>for scouting and screening, as well as the<space/><link><target>Macedonian phalanx</target><part>Macedonian pike phalanx</part></link><space/>and various kinds of<space/><link><target>light infantry</target></link>. There were also the<space/><italics>Ippiko</italics><space/>(or &quot;Horserider&quot;), Greek &quot;heavy&quot; cavalry, armed with kontos (or cavalry lance), and sword. These wore leather armour or mail plus a helmet. They were medium rather than heavy cavalry, meaning that they were better suited to be scouts, skirmishers, and pursuers rather than front line fighters. This combination of cavalry and infantry helped to break enemy lines and were used effectively to dominate the opponents of the kingdom.</paragraph><paragraph>The effectiveness of this combined-arms system was most dramatically demonstrated in Alexander's conquest of<space/><link><target>Persia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bactria</target></link>, and northwestern India.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman Republic and Early Empire</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Roman cavalry</arg></template><link><target>File:Kln Reitergrabmal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>right</part><part>Tombstone of a Roman auxiliary trooper from Cologne, Germany. Second half of the 1st century AD</part></link>The cavalry in the early<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target></link><space/>remained the preserve of the wealthy<space/><link><target>landed class</target></link><space/>known as the<space/><italics><link><target>equites</target></link></italics>men who could afford the expense of maintaining a horse in addition to arms and armor heavier than those of the common<space/><link><target>Roman legion</target><part>legion</part><trail>s</trail></link>. As the class grew to be more of a social elite instead of a functional property-based military grouping, the Romans began to employ Italian<space/><link><target>socii</target></link><space/>for filling the ranks of their cavalry.The weakness of Roman cavalry was demonstrated by Hannibal Barca during the second Punic war where he used his superior mounted forces to win several battles. The most notable of these was the<space/><link><target>Battle of Cannae</target></link>, when he inflicted a catastrophic defeat on the Romans. At about the same time the Romans began to recruit foreign auxiliary cavalry from among<space/><link><target>Gauls</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Iberians</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Numidians</target></link>, the last being highly valued as mounted skirmishers and scouts (see<space/><link><target>Numidian cavalry</target></link>).<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link><space/>had a high opinion of his escort of Germanic mixed cavalry, giving rise to the<space/><italics><link><target>cohors equitata</target><part>Cohortes Equitatae</part></link></italics>. Early emperors maintained an<space/><link><target>Ala (Roman cavalry unit)</target><part>ala</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Batavi (Germanic tribe)</target><part>Batavi</part><trail>an</trail></link><space/>cavalry as their<space/><link><target>Germanic bodyguard</target><part>personal bodyguards</part></link><space/>until the unit was dismissed by<space/><link><target>Galba</target></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Batavian Rebellion</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>For the most part, Roman cavalry during the Republic functioned as an adjunct to the legionary infantry and formed only one-fifth of the showing force. This does not mean that its utility should be underestimated, as its strategic role in scouting, skirmishing, and outpost duties was crucial to the Romans' capability to conduct operations over long distances in hostile or unfamiliar territory. On some occasions Roman cavalry also proved its ability to strike a decisive tactical blow against a weakened or unprepared enemy, such as the final charge at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Aquilonia</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>After defeats such as the<space/><link><target>Battle of Carrhae</target></link>, the Romans learned the importance of large cavalry formations from the<space/><link><target>Parthian Empire</target><part>Parthians</part></link>. They would begin to substantially increase both the numbers and the training standards of the cavalry in their employ, just as nearly a thousand years earlier the first Iranians to reach the<space/><link><target>Iranian Plateau</target></link><space/>forced the<space/><link><target>Assyrian people</target><part>Assyrians</part></link><space/>to undertake a similar reform. Nonetheless, the Romans would continue to rely mainly on their<space/><link><target>heavy infantry</target></link><space/>supported by auxiliary cavalry.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Roman Cavalry 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>right</part><part>Reenactor as a Roman<space/><link><target>Auxiliaries (Roman military)</target><part>auxiliary</part></link><space/>cavalryman.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Late Roman Empire and the Migration Period</heading><paragraph>In the army of the late<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>, cavalry played an increasingly important role. The<space/><link><target>Spatha</target></link>, the classical sword throughout most of the 1st millennium was adopted as the standard model for the Empire's cavalry forces.</paragraph><paragraph>The most widespread employment of heavy cavalry at this time was found in the forces of the<space/><link><target>Parthia</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>and their<space/><link><target>Iran</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/><link><target>Sassanid Empire</target><part>Sassanid</part></link><space/>successors. Both, but especially the former, were famed for the<space/><link><target>cataphract</target></link><space/>(fully armored cavalry armed with lances) even though the majority of their forces consisted of lighter<space/><link><target>horse archer</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The West first encountered this eastern heavy cavalry during the<space/><link><target>Hellenistic</target></link><space/>period with further intensive contacts during the eight centuries of the<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><link><target>History of Iran</target><part>Persian</part></link><space/><link><target>wars</target></link>. At first the Parthians' mobility greatly confounded the Romans, whose armoured close-order infantry proved unable to match the speed of the Parthians. However, later the Romans would successfully adapt such heavy armor and cavalry tactics by creating their own units of cataphracts and<space/><italics>clibanarii</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.historynet.com/mhq/blromespersianmirage/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Roman-Persian Wars<space/></arg><arg name="work">Historynet.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 25, 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The decline of the Roman infrastructure made it more difficult to field large infantry forces, and during the 4th and 5th centuries cavalry began to take a more dominant role on the European battlefield, also in part made possible by the appearance of new, larger breeds of horses. The replacement of the Roman<space/><link><target>horse tack</target><part>saddle</part></link><space/>by variants on the Scythian model, with<space/><link><target>pommel (saddle)</target><part>pommel</part></link><space/>and cantle,<extension extension_name='ref'>The raised rear part of a saddle</extension><space/>was also a significant factor as was the adoption of<space/><link><target>stirrup</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and the concomitant increase in stability of the rider's seat. Armored Cataphracts began to be deployed in eastern Europe and the<space/><link><target>near East</target></link>, following the precedents established by<space/><link><target>History of Iran</target><part>Persia</part><trail>n</trail></link><space/>forces, as the main striking force of the armies in contrast to the earlier roles of cavalry as scouts, raiders, and outflankers.</paragraph><paragraph>The late Roman cavalry tradition and the mounted nobility of the Germanic invaders both contributed to the development of mediaeval knightly cavalry.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Arabs</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Mobile guard</arg><arg>List of battles of Muhammad</arg></template><link><target>File:Ikhwan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Arab camel cavalry</part></link><link><target>File:Eugne Ferdinand Victor Delacroix 025.jpg</target><part>upright</part><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>Morocco</target><part>Moroccan</part></link><space/>with his<space/><link><target>Arabian horse</target></link><space/>along the<space/><link><target>Barbary coast</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Islamic Prophet Muhammad made use of cavalry in many of his military campaigns including the<space/><link><target>Expedition of Dhu Qarad</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Mubarakpuri, The Sealed Nectar, p. 231. (<link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/61481iVee'>online</link>)</extension><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Expedition of Zaid ibn Haritha (Al-Is)</target><part>expedition of Zaid ibn Haritha in al-Is</part></link><space/>which took place in September, 627 AD, 5th month of 6 AH of the<space/><link><target>Islamic calendar</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hawarey"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hawarey</arg><arg name="first">[http://mosab.hawarey.org/ Dr. Mosab]</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9789957051648</arg><arg name="title">The Journey of Prophecy; Days of Peace and War (Arabic)</arg><arg name="publisher">Islamic Book Trust<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Early organized Arab mounted forces under the<space/><link><target>Rashidun</target></link><space/><link><target>caliphate</target></link><space/>comprised a<space/><link><target>light cavalry</target></link><space/>armed with<space/><link><target>lance</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sword</target></link>. Its main role was to attack the enemy flanks and rear. These relatively lightly armored horsemen formed the most effective element of the Muslim armies during the later stages of the Islamic conquest of the Levant. The best use of this lightly armed fast moving cavalry was revealed at the<space/><bold><link><target>Battle of Yarmouk</target></link></bold><space/>(636 AD) in which<space/><link><target>Khalid ibn Walid</target></link>, knowing the skills of his horsemen, used them to turn the tables at every critical instance of the battle with their ability to engage, disengage, then turn back and attack again from the flank or rear. A strong cavalry regiment was formed by Khalid ibn Walid which included the veterans of the campaign of Iraq and Syria. Early Muslim historians have given it the name<space/><italics>Mutaharrik tulai'a</italics>( ), or the<space/><link><target>Mobile guard</target></link>. This was used as an advance guard and a strong striking force to route the opposing armies with its greater mobility that give it an upper hand when maneuvering against any<space/><link><target>Byzantine</target></link><space/>army. With this mobile striking force, the conquest of Syria was made easy.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.239, Muir</extension><space/><link><target>File:Mamluke.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>upright</part><part>A Mamluk cavalryman</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Battle of Talas</target></link><space/>in 751 AD was a conflict between the Arab<space/><link><target>Abbasid</target></link><space/>Caliphate and the<space/><link><target>China</target><part>Chinese</part></link><space/><link><target>Tang dynasty</target></link><space/>over the control of<space/><link><target>Central Asia</target></link>. Chinese infantry were routed by<space/><link><target>Arab</target></link><space/>cavalry near the bank of the River Talas.</paragraph><paragraph>Later<space/><link><target>Mamluk</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were trained as cavalry soldiers. Mamluks were to follow the dictates of al-furusiyya,<extension extension_name='ref'>tradition of al-furusiyya is defined by principles of horsemanship, chivalry, and the mutual dependence of the rider and the horse</extension><space/>a code of conduct that included values like courage and generosity but also doctrine of cavalry tactics, horsemanship, archery and treatment of wounds.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Asia</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Horse archer</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Central Asia</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Mongol military tactics and organization</arg><arg>Mongol Empire#Military setup</arg></template><link><target>File:MongolCavalry crop.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Modern reenactment of Mongol military movement</part></link><link><target>File:Mongol warrior of Genghis Khan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Mongol</target></link><space/>warrior on horseback, preparing a mounted archery shot.</part></link><link><target>File:DiezAlbumsArmedRiders II.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The Mongols at war</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Xiongnu</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tujue</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Avars (Carpathians)</target><part>Avars</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kipchaks</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mongol</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Don Cossack</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and the various<space/><link><target>Turkic peoples</target></link><space/>are also examples of the horse-mounted groups that managed to gain substantial successes in military conflicts with settled agrarian and urban societies, due to their strategic and tactical mobility. As European states began to assume the character of bureaucratic<space/><link><target>nation-states</target></link><space/>supporting professional standing armies, recruitment of these mounted warriors was undertaken in order to fill the strategic roles of scouts and raiders. The best known instance of the continued employment of mounted tribal auxiliaries were the Cossack cavalry regiments of<space/><link><target>Tsarist Russia</target></link>. In eastern Europe, Russia, and out onto the<space/><link><target>steppes</target></link>, cavalry remained important much longer and dominated the scene of warfare until the early 17th century and even beyond, as the strategic mobility of cavalry was crucial for the semi-nomadic<space/><link><target>pastoralism</target><part>pastoralist</part></link><space/>lives that many steppe cultures led.<space/><link><target>Tibet</target><trail>ans</trail></link><space/>also had a tradition of cavalry warfare, in several military engagements with the Chinese<space/><link><target>Tang dynasty</target></link><space/>(618 907 AD).</paragraph><heading level='4'>East Asia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sakaotosi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>In the<space/><link><target>Battle of Ichi-no-Tani</target></link>, Japanese cavalry moving down a mountain-side</part></link><link><target>File:Emperor Taizongs horses by Yan Liben.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A bas-<link><target>relief</target></link><space/>of a soldier and horse with saddle and<space/><link><target>stirrup</target><trail>s</trail></link>, from the tomb of Chinese<space/><link><target>Emperor Taizong of Tang</target></link><space/>(r. 626649), c. 650</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Further east, the<space/><link><target>Military history of China (pre-1911)</target><part>military history of China</part></link>, specifically<space/><link><target>North China</target><part>northern China</part></link>, held a long tradition of intense military exchange between<space/><link><target>Han Chinese</target></link><space/>infantry forces of the settled dynastic empires and the mounted<space/><link><target>nomads</target></link><space/>or &quot;barbarians&quot; of the north. The<space/><link><target>naval history of China</target></link><space/>was centered more to the south, where mountains, rivers, and large lakes necessitated the employment of a large and well-kept<space/><link><target>Naval warfare</target><part>navy</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 307 BC,<space/><link><target>King Wuling of Zhao</target></link>, the ancient Chinese ruler of the former<space/><link><target>Jin (Chinese state)</target><part>State of Jin</part></link><space/>territory, ordered his military commanders and troops to adopt the<space/><link><target>trousers</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>nomad</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as well as practice the nomads' form of mounted archery to hone their new cavalry skills.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ebrey 29 30">Ebrey, 29-30.</extension><space/>Soon afterwards the cavalry tactics employed by the<space/><link><target>Zhao (state)</target><part>State of Zhao</part></link><space/>forced their enemies in the other<space/><link><target>Warring States</target></link><space/>to adopt the same techniques in order to mount any effective attack against their swift movements on the battlefield.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ebrey 30">Ebrey, 30.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The adoption of massed cavalry in China also broke the tradition of the<space/><link><target>Chariot (Ancient China)</target><part>chariot</part></link>-riding<space/><link><target>Four occupations</target><part>Chinese aristocracy</part></link><space/>in battle, which had been in use since the ancient<space/><link><target>Shang Dynasty</target></link><space/>(c. 1600 BC-1050 BC).<extension extension_name='ref' name="ebrey 29">Ebrey, 29.</extension><space/>By this time large Chinese infantry-based armies of 100,000 to 200,000 troops were now buttressed with several hundred thousand mounted cavalry in support or as an effective striking force.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ebrey 30"></extension><space/>The handheld pistol-and-trigger<space/><link><target>crossbow</target></link><space/>was invented in China in the 4th century BC;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ebrey cambridge 41">Ebrey,<space/><italics>The Cambridge Illustrated History of China</italics>, 41.</extension><space/>it was written by the<space/><link><target>Song dynasty</target></link><space/>scholars Zeng Gongliang, Ding Du, and Yang Weide in their book<space/><italics><link><target>Wujing Zongyao</target></link></italics><space/>(1044 AD) that massed missile fire by crossbowmen was the most effective defense against enemy cavalry charges.<extension extension_name='ref' name="peers 130">Peers, 130.we can right anything</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:The Qianlong Emperor in Ceremonial Armour on Horseback.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Qianlong Emperor</target></link><space/>in ceremonial armor on horseback, painted by<space/><link><target>Giuseppe Castiglione (16881766)</target><part>Giuseppe Castiglione</part></link>, dated 1739 or 1758</part></link>On many occasions the Chinese studied nomadic cavalry tactics and applied the lessons in creating their own potent cavalry forces, while in others they simply recruited the tribal horsemen wholesale into their armies; and in yet other cases nomadic empires proved eager to enlist Chinese infantry and engineering, as in the case of the<space/><link><target>Mongol Empire</target></link><space/>and its sinicized part, the<space/><link><target>Yuan Dynasty</target></link><space/>(12791368). The Chinese recognized early on during the<space/><link><target>Han Dynasty</target></link><space/>(202 BC 220 AD) that they were at a disadvantage in lacking the number of horses the northern nomadic peoples mustered in their armies.<space/><link><target>Emperor Wu of Han</target></link><space/>(r. 141 BC 87 BC) went to war with the<space/><link><target>Dayuan</target></link><space/>for this reason, since the Dayuan were hording a massive amount of tall, strong, Central Asian bred horses in the<space/><link><target>Hellenized</target></link><link><target>Greeks</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>region of<space/><link><target>Fergana</target></link><space/>(established slightly earlier by<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link>). Although experiencing some defeats early on in the campaign, Emperor Wu's war from 104 BC to 102 BC succeeded in gathering the prized tribute of horses from Fergana.</paragraph><paragraph>Cavalry tactics in China were enhanced by the invention of the saddle-attached<space/><link><target>stirrup</target></link><space/>by at least the 4th century, as the oldest reliable depiction of a rider with paired stirrups was found in a<space/><link><target>Jin Dynasty (265420)</target><part>Jin Dynasty</part></link><space/>tomb of the year 322 AD.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dien"><link type='external' href='http://www.silk-road.com/artl/stirrup.shtml'>Dien, Albert. &quot;THE STIRRUP AND ITS EFFECT ON CHINESE MILITARY HISTORY&quot;</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1310/is_1988_Oct/ai_6955868'>&quot;The stirrup - history of Chinese science.&quot; ''UNESCO Courier, October 1988</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.chinaculture.org/gb/en_madeinchina/2005-07/21/content_70825.htm'>&quot;The invention and influences of stirrup&quot;</link></extension><space/>The Chinese invention of the<space/><link><target>horse collar</target></link><space/>by the 5th century was also a great improvement from the breast harness, allowing the horse to haul greater weight without heavy burden on its skeletal structure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="needham volume 4 part 2 322">Needham, Volume 4, Part 2, 322.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="needham volume 4 part 2 305">Needham, Volume 4, Part 2, 305.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The horse warfare of<space/><link><target>History of Korea</target><part>Korea</part></link><space/>was first started during the ancient Korean kingdom<space/><link><target>Gojoseon</target></link>. Since at least the 3rd century BC, there was influence of northern<space/><link><target>nomadic</target></link><space/>peoples and<space/><link><target>Yemaek</target></link><space/>peoples on Korean warfare. By roughly the 1st century BC, the ancient kingdom of<space/><link><target>Buyeo Kingdom</target><part>Buyeo</part></link><space/>also had mounted warriors.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ebrey, 120.</extension><space/>The cavalry of<space/><link><target>Goguryeo</target></link>, one of the<space/><link><target>Three Kingdoms of Korea</target></link>, were called<space/><italics>Gaemamusa</italics><space/>(, ), and were renowned as a fearsome heavy cavalry force.<space/><link><target>Gwanggaeto the Great of Goguryeo</target><part>King Gwanggaeto the Great</part></link><space/>often led expeditions into the<space/><link><target>Baekje</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gaya confederacy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Buyeo Kingdom</target><part>Buyeo</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Later Yan</target></link><space/>and against<space/><link><target>Yamato period</target><part>Japanese</part></link><space/>invaders with his cavalry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lee, Peter H &amp; Wm. Theodore De Bary. Sources of Korean Tradition, page 24-26. Columbia University Press, 1997.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 12th century,<space/><link><target>Jurchen people</target><part>Jurchen</part></link><space/>tribes began to violate the GoryeoJurchen borders, and eventually invaded<space/><link><target>Goryeo</target></link><space/>Korea. After experiencing the invasion by the Jurchen, Korean general<space/><link><target>Yun Gwan</target></link><space/>realized that Goryeo lacked efficient cavalry units. He reorganized the Goryeo military into a professional army that would contain decent and well-trained cavalry units. In 1107, the Jurchen were ultimately defeated, and surrendered to Yun Gwan. To mark the victory, General Yun built nine fortresses to the northeast of the GoryeoJurchen borders ( 9, ).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>History of Japan</target><part>ancient Japanese</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Kofun period</target></link><space/>also adopted<space/><link><target>Kofun period#Introduction of equine culture to Japan</target><part>cavalry and equine culture</part></link><space/>by the 5th century AD. The emergence of the<space/><link><target>samurai</target></link><space/>aristocracy led to the development of armoured horse archers, themselves to develop into charging lancer cavalry as gunpowder weapons rendered bows obsolete.</paragraph><heading level='4'>South Asia</heading><paragraph>In the Indian subcontinent, cavalry played a major role from the<space/><link><target>Gupta Dynasty</target></link><space/>(320-600) period onwards. India has also the oldest evidence for the introduction of toe-<link><target>stirrup</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Indian literature contains numerous references to the cavalry forces of the<space/><link><target>Central Asia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>horse nomads like the<space/><link><target>Saka</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Kambojas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Yona</target><part>Yavanas</part></link>,<space/><link><target>The Pahlavas</target><part>Pahlavas</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paradas</target></link>. Numerous<space/><link><target>Puranas</target><part>Puranic</part></link><space/>texts refer to a conflict in ancient India (16th century BC)<extension extension_name='ref'>p. 182183, Pargiter.</extension><space/>in which the cavalry forces of five nations, called five hordes (<italics>paca.ganan</italics>) or<space/><link><target>Kshatriya</target><part>Katriya</part></link><space/>hordes (<italics>Katriya ganah</italics>), attacked and captured the throne of Ayudhya by dethroning its<space/><link><target>Vedic period</target><part>Vedic</part></link><space/>King Bahu<extension extension_name='ref'>Harivamsa 14.119; Vayu Purana 88.12743; Brahma Purana (8.3551); Brahamanda Purana (3.63.123141); Shiva Purana (7.61.23); Vishnu Purana (5.3.1521), Padama Purana (6.21.1633) etc.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Kurukshetra.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Manuscript illustration of the Battle of Kurukshetra</part></link><link><target>File:ChandraguptaIIOnHorse.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Coin of<space/><link><target>Chandragupta II</target></link><space/>or Vikramaditya, one of the most powerful emperors of the Gupta empire during times referred to as the Golden Age of India</part></link><link><target>File:Rajput warrior on horseback, with caption in Kayathi and Nagari..jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Rajput warrior on horseback.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ramayana</target></link>, numerous<space/><link><target>Puranas</target></link><space/>and some foreign sources numerously attest that Kamboja cavalry was frequently requisitioned in ancient wars. V. R. Ramachandra Dikshitar writes: &quot;Both the Puranas and the epics agree that the horses of the Sindhu and Kamboja regions were of the finest breed, and that the services of the Kambojas as cavalry troopers were requisitioned in ancient wars&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>War in Ancient India, 1944, p 178, V. R. Ramachandra Dikshtar, Military art and science.</extension><space/>J.A.O.S. writes: &quot;Most famous horses are said to come either from Sindhu or Kamboja; of the latter (i.e. the Kamboja), the Indian<space/><link><target>Indian epic poetry</target><part>epic</part></link><space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link><space/>speaks among the finest horsemen&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Journal of American Oriental society, 1889, p 257, American Oriental Society; The Social and Military Position of the Ruling Caste in Ancient India: As ..., 1972, p 201, Edward Washburn Hopkins - Caste; Mahabharata 10.18.13; cf: Ancient Indian Civilization, 1985, p 120, Grigori Maksimovich Bongard-Levin - History; Cf also: A History of Zoroastrianism, 1991, p 129, Mary Boyce, Frantz Grenet.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Mahabharata (950 c BC)<extension extension_name='ref'>p.182, Pargiter</extension><space/>speaks of the esteemed cavalry of the Kambojas, Sakas, Yavanas and<space/><link><target>Tusharas</target></link>, all of whom had participated in the<space/><link><target>Kurukshetra War and the Kambojas</target><part>Kurukshetra war</part></link><space/>under the supreme command of<space/><link><target>Kamboja Kingdom</target><part>Kamboja</part></link><space/>ruler<space/><link><target>Sudakshina Kamboja</target><part>Sudakshin Kamboj</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>MBH 1.185.13; Felicitation Volume Presented to Professor Sripad Krishna Belvalkar, 1957, p 260, Dr Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan, Shripad Krishna Belvalkar.</extension>Mahabharata and Vishnudharmotari Purana especially styles the Kambojas, Yavansa, Gandharas etc. as &quot;Ashva.yuddha.kushalah&quot; (expert cavalrymen).<extension extension_name='ref'>Ashva.yuddha.kushalah: Mahabharata 7.7.14; See also: Vishnudharmotra Purana, Part II, Chapter 118; Post Gupta Polity (AD 500700): A Study of the Growth of Feudal Elements and Rural Administration 1972, p 136, Ganesh Prasad Sinha; Wisdom in the Puranas 1969, p 64, professor Sen Sarma etc.</extension><space/>In the Mahabharata war, the Kamboja cavalry along with that of the Sakas, Yavanas is reported to have been enlisted by the<space/><link><target>Kuru (kingdom)</target><part>Kuru</part></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Duryodhana</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Hastinapur</target><trail>a</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Some Katriya Tribes of Ancient India, 1924, p 238, Dr B. C. Law - Kshatriyas; The Battle of Kurukshetra, 1987, p 389, Maggi Lidchi-Grassi - Kurukshetra (India).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Herodotus</target></link><space/>(484 c BC425 c BC) attests that the<space/><link><target>Gandhara</target><part>Gandarian</part></link><space/>mercenaries (i.e.<space/><italics>Gandharans/Kambojans</italics><space/>of Gandari Strapy of<space/><link><target>Achaemenids</target></link>) from the 20th strapy of the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target><part>Achaemenid</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were recruited in the army of emperor<space/><link><target>Xerxes I of Persia</target><part>Xerxes I</part></link><space/>(486-465 BC), which he led against the<space/><link><target>Greeks</target><part>Hellas</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodotus, Book VII 65, 70, 86, 187.</extension><space/>Similarly, the<space/><italics>men of the Mountain Land<space/></italics><space/>from north of<space/><link><target>Kabul</target><part>Kabol</part></link>-River equivalent to medieval<space/><link><target>Kohistan District, North West Frontier Province</target><part>Kohistan</part></link><space/>(Pakistan), figure in the army of<space/><link><target>Darius III</target></link><space/>against<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target><part>Alexander</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Battle of Gaugamela</target><part>Arbela</part></link><space/>with a cavalry and fifteen elephants.<extension extension_name='ref'>History of Persian Empire, p 232, Dr A. M. Olmstead; Arrian's Anabasis III, 8.3-6; Political History of Ancient India, 1996, p 216, Dr Raychaudhury.</extension><space/>This obviously refers to Kamboja cavalry south of Hindukush.</paragraph><paragraph>The Kambojas were famous for their horses, as well as cavalry-men (<italics>asva-yuddha-Kushalah</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Ashva.yuddha.kushalah: Mahabharata 7.7.14 Kumbhakonam Edition; See also: Vishnudharmotra Purana, Part II, Chapter 118; Post Gupta Polity (AD 500700): A Study of the Growth of Feudal Elements and Rural Administration 1972, p 136, Ganesh Prasad Sinha; Wisdom in the Puranas 1969, p 64, prof Sen Sarma; etc.; Kashmir Polity, C. 600-1200 A.D. 1986, p 237, V. N. Drabu - Political Science.</extension><space/>On account of their supreme position in horse (Ashva) culture, they were also popularly known as<space/><link><target>Ashvakas</target></link>, i.e. the &quot;horsemen&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hindu Polity: A Constitutional History of India in Hundu Times, 1943, p 145, Dr K. P. Jayaswal.</extension><space/>and their land was known as &quot;Home of Horses&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>i.e.:<space/><italics>Kambojo assa.nam ayata.nam</italics>. See: Samangalavilasini, Vol I, p 124; See also: Historie du Bouddhisme Indien, p 110, E. Lamotte; Political History of Ancient India, 1996, p 133 fn 6, pp 216-20, Dr H. C. Raychaudhury, Dr B. N. Mukerjee; Some Katriya Tribes of Ancient India, 1924, p 238, Dr B. C. - Kshatriyas; Studies in Indian History and Civilization, 1962, p 351, Dr Buddha Prakash - India.</extension><space/>They are the<space/><link><target>Assakenoi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aspasioi</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Classical antiquity</target><part>Classical</part></link><space/>writings, and the<space/><link><target>Ashvakayana</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ashvayana</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Pini</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Ashtadhyayi</target></link>. The Assakenoi had faced<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target><part>Alexander</part></link><space/>with 30,000 infantry, 20,000 cavalry and 30 war elephants.<extension extension_name='ref'>Age of the Nandas and Mauryas, 1967, p 49, Dr K. A. Nilakanta Sastri.</extension><space/>Scholars have identified the Assakenoi and Aspasioi clans of<space/><link><target>Kunar Valley</target><part>Kunar</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Swat, Pakistan</target><part>Swat</part></link><space/>valleys as a section of the<space/><link><target>Kambojas</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>&quot;Par ailleurs le Kamboja est rgulirement mentionn comme la &quot;patrie des chevaux&quot; (</italics>Asvanam ayatanam<italics>), et cette reputation bien etablie gagn peut-etre aux eleveurs de chevaux du Bajaur et du Swat l'appellation d'Aspasioi (du v.-p. aspa) et d'assakenoi (du skt asva &quot;cheval&quot;)&quot;</italics><space/>(See: Historie du Bouddhisme Indien, p 110, E. Lamotte; See also: Hindu Polity, A Constitutional History of India in Hindu Times, 1978, p 140, Dr K. P. Jayswal; Political History of Ancient India, 1996, p 133 fn 6, pp 21620, (Also Commentary, op. cit., p 576, fn 22), Dr H. C. Raychaudhury, Dr B. N. Mukerjee;; History of Indian Buddhism: From the Origins to the Saka Era, 1988, p 100 - History; East and West, 1950, pp 28, 15758, Istituto italiano per il Medio ed Estremo Oriente, Editor, Prof Giuseppe Tucci, Co-editors Prof Mario Bussagli, Prof Lionello Lanciotti; Panjab Past and Present, pp 910, Dr Buddha Parkash; Raja Poros, 1990, Publication Buareau, Punjabi University, Patiala; History of Panjab, Vol I, (Editors): Dr Fauja Singh, Dr L. M. Josh, Publication Bureau, Panjabi University, Patiala; History of Poros, 1967, p 89, Dr Buddha Prakash; Ancient Kamboja, People and country, 1981, pp 27172, 278, Dr J. L. Kamboj; These Kamboj People, 1979, pp 119, 192; Kambojas, Through the Ages, 2005, pp 129, 21819, S Kirpal Singh etc.</extension><space/>These hardy tribes had offered stubborn resistance to Alexander (326 c BC) during latter's campaign of the Kabul, Kunar and Swat valleys and had even extracted the praise of the Alexander's historians. These highlanders, designated as<space/><italics>&quot;parvatiya Ayudhajivinah&quot;</italics><space/>in Pini's Astadhyayi,<extension extension_name='ref'>Ashtadhyayi 4.3.91; India as Known to Pini, 1953, pp 424, 43639, 455457, Dr V. S. Aggarwala.</extension><space/>were rebellious, fiercely independent and freedom-loving cavalrymen who never easily yielded to any overlord.<extension extension_name='ref'>See: History of Punjab, Vol I, 1997, p 225, Dr Buddha Prakash; Raja Poros, 1990, p 9, Publication Bureau, Punjabi University Patiala.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Sanskrit</target></link><space/>drama<space/><italics>Mudra-rakashas</italics><space/>by<space/><italics>Visakha Dutta</italics><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Jainism</target><part>Jaina</part></link><space/>work<space/><italics>Parisishtaparvan</italics><space/>refer to<space/><link><target>Chandragupta Maurya</target><part>Chandragupta</part></link>'s (320 C BC298 c BC) alliance with<space/><link><target>Himalaya</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>king<space/><italics>Parvataka</italics>. The<space/><link><target>Himalaya</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>alliance gave Chandragupta a formidable composite army made up of the cavalry forces of the Shakas, Yavanas, Kambojas, Kiratas, Parasikas and Bahlikas as attested by Mudra-Rakashas (Mudra-Rakshasa 2).<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph>In Sanskrit:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>asti tava Shaka-Yavana-Kirata-Kamboja-Parasika-Bahlika parbhutibhih</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>Chankyamatipragrahittaishcha Chandergupta Parvateshvara</italics></listitem><listitem><italics>balairudidhibhiriva parchalitsalilaih samantaad uprudham Kusumpurama</italics></listitem><listitem>(Mudra-Rakshasa 2).</listitem></list></extension><space/>These hordes had helped<space/><link><target>Chandragupta Maurya</target></link><space/>defeat the ruler of<space/><link><target>Magadha</target></link><space/>and placed Vhandragupta on the throne, thus laying the foundations of<space/><link><target>Mauryan Dynasty</target></link><space/>in Northern India.</paragraph><paragraph>The cavalry of<space/><link><target>Hunas</target></link><space/>and the Kambojas is also attested in the<space/><link><target>Raghuvaa</target><part>Raghu Vamsa</part></link><space/>epic poem of Sanskrit poet<space/><link><target>Kalidasa</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Klidsa, 1960, p 141, Raghunath Damodar Karmarkar.</extension><space/>Raghu of Kalidasa is believed to be<space/><link><target>Chandragupta II</target></link><space/>(<italics>Vikaramaditya</italics>) (375413/15 AD), of the well-known<space/><link><target>Gupta Dynasty</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>As late as mediaeval era, the Kamboja cavalry had also formed part of the Gurjara-Pratihara armed forces from the 8th to the 10th centuries AD. They had come to<space/><link><target>Bengal</target></link><space/>with the<space/><link><target>Pratihara</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>when the latter conquered part of the province.<extension extension_name='ref'>Indian Historical Quarterly, XV-4, December 1939, p 511 Dr H. C. Ray.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>History of Ancient Bengal, 1971, pp 18283, Dr<space/><link><target>R. C. Majumdar</target></link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Indian Historical Quarterly, 1963, p 625.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Dynastic History of Magadha, 1977, p 208.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Epigraphia Indiaca, XVIII, p 304ff.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ancient Kambojas were constituted into military<space/><italics>Sanghas</italics><space/>and Srenis (Corporations) to manage their political and military affairs, as<space/><link><target>Arthashastra</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Kautiliya</target></link><space/>as well as the<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link><space/>amply attest for us. They are attested to be living as<space/><italics>Ayuddha-jivi</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>Shastr-opajivis</italics><space/>(Nation-in-arms), which also means that the Kamboja cavalry offered its<space/><link><target>military</target></link><space/>services to other nations as well. There are numerous references to Kambojas having been requisitioned as cavalry<space/><link><target>trooper (rank)</target><part>trooper</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in ancient wars by outside<space/><link><target>nation</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>European Middle Ages</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Horses in the Middle Ages</arg></template><link><target>File:Bayeux Tapestry scene51 Battle of Hastings Norman knights and archers.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.5</part><part>left</part><part>Horse-mounted<space/><link><target>Normans</target></link><space/>charging in the<space/><link><target>Bayeux Tapestry</target></link>, 11th century.</part></link>Although Roman cavalry had no stirrups, their horned saddle allowed the combination of a firm seat with substantial flexibility. But the introduction of the wraparound<space/><link><target>saddle</target></link><space/>during the Middle Ages provided greater efficiency in mounted shock combat and the important invention of the<space/><link><target>stirrup</target></link><space/>enabled a broader array of attacks to be delivered from the back of a horse. As a greater weight of man and armor could be supported in the saddle, the probability of being dismounted in combat was significantly reduced.</paragraph><paragraph>In particular, a charge with the lance couched under the armpit would no longer turn into<space/><link><target>pole vaulting</target></link>; this eventually led to an enormous increase in the impact of the charge. Last but not least, the introduction of<space/><link><target>spur</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>allowed better control of the mount during the &quot;knightly charge&quot; in full gallop. In western Europe there emerged what is considered the &quot;ultimate&quot;<space/><link><target>heavy cavalry</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>knight</target></link>. The knights and other similarly equipped mounted men-at-arms charged in close formation, exchanging flexibility for a massive, irresistible first charge.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:BritLibAddMS35166ApocalypseUnkFolio3SealBlackHorse.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A 13th-century depiction of a riding horse. Note resemblance to the modern<space/><link><target>Paso Fino</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Husitsky bojovy vuz replika.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A Hussite war wagon: it enabled peasants to defeat knights</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The mounted men-at-arms quickly became an important force in Western European tactics. Medieval military doctrine employed them as part of a combined-arms force along with various kinds of foot troops; however medieval chroniclers tended to pay undue attention to the knights at the expense of the rank and file, which led early students of military history to suppose that this heavy cavalry was the only force that mattered on medieval European battlefields, which was not the case.</paragraph><paragraph>Massed English longbowmen triumphed over French cavalry at<space/><link><target>Battle of Crcy</target><part>Crcy</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Poitiers (1356)</target><part>Poitiers</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Agincourt</target><part>Agincourt</part></link>, while at<space/><link><target>Battle of Gisors</target><part>Gisors</part></link><space/>(1188),<space/><link><target>Battle of Bannockburn</target><part>Bannockburn</part></link><space/>(1314), and<space/><link><target>Battle of Laupen</target><part>Laupen</part></link><space/>(1339), foot-soldiers proved their invulnerability to cavalry charges as long as they held their formation. Once the<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target><part>Swiss</part></link><space/>developed their<space/><link><target>pike square</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for offensive as well as defensive use, infantry started to become the principal arm. This aggressive new doctrine gave the Swiss victory over a range of adversaries, and their enemies found that the only reliable way to defeat them was by the use of an even more comprehensive<space/><link><target>combined arms</target></link><space/>doctrine, as evidenced in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Marignano</target></link>. The introduction of missile weapons that required less skill than the longbow, such as the<space/><link><target>crossbow</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>hand cannon</target></link>, also helped remove the focus somewhat from cavalry elites to masses of cheap infantry equipped with easy-to-learn weapons. These missile weapons were very successfully used in the<space/><link><target>Hussite Wars</target></link>, in combination with<space/><link><target>Wagenburg</target></link><space/>tactics.</paragraph><paragraph>This gradual rise in the dominance of infantry led to the adoption of dismounted tactics. From the earliest times knights and mounted men-at-arms had frequently dismounted to handle enemies they could not overcome on horseback, such as in the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Dyle</target></link><space/>(891) and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Bremule</target></link><space/>(1119), but after the 1350s this trend became more marked with the dismounted men-at-arms fighting as super-heavy infantry with two-handed<space/><link><target>sword</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>poleaxe</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In any case, warfare in the Middle Ages tended to be dominated by raids and sieges rather than pitched battles, and mounted men-at-arms rarely had any choice other than dismounting when faced with the prospect of assaulting a fortified position.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Renaissance Europe</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Retable de l'Agneau mystique (8).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Knighted cavalry and noblemen, painting by<space/><link><target>Jan van Eyck</target></link><space/>(c. 1390-1441).</part></link>Ironically, the rise of infantry in the early 16th century coincided with the &quot;golden age&quot; of heavy cavalry; a French or Spanish army at the beginning of the century could have up to half its numbers made up of various kinds of light and heavy cavalry, whereas in earlier medieval and later 17th-century armies the proportion of cavalry was seldom more than a quarter.</paragraph><paragraph>Knighthood largely lost its military functions and became more closely tied to social and economic prestige in an increasingly capitalistic Western society. With the rise of drilled and trained infantry, the mounted men-at-arms, now sometimes called<space/><italics><link><target>gendarme (historical)</target><part>gendarmes</part></link></italics><space/>and often part of the standing army themselves, adopted the same role as in the Hellenistic age, that of delivering a decisive blow once the battle was already engaged, either by charging the enemy in the flank or attacking their commander-in-chief.</paragraph><paragraph>From the 1550s onwards, the use of<space/><link><target>Gunpowder warfare</target><part>gunpowder weapons</part></link><space/>solidified infantry's dominance of the battlefield and began to allow true mass armies to develop. This is closely related to the increase in the size of armies throughout the early modern period; heavily armored cavalrymen were expensive to raise and maintain and it took years to replace a skilled horseman or a trained horse, while<space/><link><target>arquebusier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and later<space/><link><target>musketeer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>could be trained and kept in the field at much lower cost, and were much easier to replace.</paragraph><paragraph>The Spanish<space/><link><target>tercio</target></link><space/>and later formations relegated cavalry to a supporting role. The<space/><link><target>pistol</target></link><space/>was specifically developed to try to bring cavalry back into the conflict, together with manoeuvres such as the<space/><link><target>caracole</target></link>. The caracole was not particularly successful, however, and the charge (whether with sword, pistol, or lance) remained as the primary mode of employment for many types of European cavalry, although by this time it was delivered in much deeper formations and with greater discipline than before. The<space/><link><target>demi-lancer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and the heavily armored sword-and-pistol<space/><link><target>reiter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were among the types of cavalry whose heyday was in the 16th and 17th centuries, as for the<space/><link><target>Polish Hussars</target><part>Polish winged hussars</part></link>, a heavy cavalry force that achieved great success against<space/><link><target>Sweden</target><part>Swedes</part></link>, Russians, and<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target><part>Turks</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>18th-century Europe and Napoleonic Wars</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Simon-eylau.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Cavalry charge at<space/><link><target>Battle of Eylau</target><part>Eylau</part></link>, painted by<space/><link><target>Jean-Antoine-Simon Fort</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Cavalry retained an important role in this age of regularization and standardization across European armies. First and foremost they remained the primary choice for confronting enemy cavalry. Attacking an unbroken infantry force head-on usually resulted in failure, but extended linear infantry formations were vulnerable to flank or rear attacks. Cavalry was important at<space/><link><target>Battle of Blenheim</target><part>Blenheim</part></link><space/>(1704),<space/><link><target>Battle of Rossbach</target><part>Rossbach</part></link><space/>(1757),<space/><link><target>Battle of Eylau</target><part>Eylau</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Friedland</target><part>Friedland</part></link><space/>(1807), remaining significant throughout the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The greatest cavalry charge of modern history was at the 1807<space/><link><target>battle of Eylau</target></link>, when the entire 11,000-strong French cavalry reserve, led by Marchal Murat, launched a huge charge on and through the Russian infantry lines. However, in 1815 at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Waterloo</target></link>, repeated<space/><link><target>Battle of Waterloo#The French cavalry attack</target><part>charges by up to 9,000 French cavalrymen</part></link><space/>failed to break the line of the British and German infantry, who had formed<space/><link><target>Infantry square</target><part>square</part><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/empire_seapower/battle_waterloo_01.shtml#five'>BBC History: The Battle of Waterloo</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Massed infantry was deadly to cavalry, but offered an excellent target for<space/><link><target>artillery</target></link>. Once the bombardment had disordered the infantry formation, cavalry were able to<space/><link><target>rout</target></link><space/>and pursue the scattered foot soldiers. It was not until individual firearms gained accuracy and improved rates of fire that cavalry was diminished in this role as well. Even then light cavalry remained an indispensable tool for scouting, screening the army's movements, and harassing the enemy's supply lines until military aircraft supplanted them in this role in the early stages of World War I.</paragraph><heading level='3'>19th century</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Batalla de Carabobo.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>The charge of the Venezuelan First Division's cavalry at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Carabobo</target></link>.</part></link>By the 19th century, European cavalry fell into four main categories:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cuirassier</target><trail>s</trail></link>, heavy cavalry</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dragoon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, originally mounted infantry but later regarded as medium cavalry</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hussar</target><trail>s</trail></link>, light cavalry</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lancer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Uhlan</target><trail>s</trail></link>, light cavalry armed with<space/><link><target>lance</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem></list><paragraph>There were cavalry variations for individual nations as well: France had the<space/><italics>chasseurs cheval</italics>; Germany had the<space/><italics>Jger zu Pferd</italics>;<space/><link><target>Bavaria</target></link><space/>had the<space/><italics>Chevaulegers</italics>; and Russia had Cossacks. Britain, from the mid-18th century, had Light Dragoons as light cavalry and Dragoons, Dragoon Guards and<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link><space/>as heavy cavalry. Only after the end of the Napoleonic wars were the Household Cavalry equipped with cuirasses, and some other regiments were converted to lancers. In the<space/><link><target>United States Army</target></link><space/>the cavalry were almost always dragoons. The<space/><link><target>Imperial Japanese Army</target></link><space/>had its cavalry uniformed as<space/><link><target>hussar</target><trail>s</trail></link>, but they fought as dragoons.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Union cavalry charge culpepper.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Union Cavalry</target></link><space/>capture<space/><link><target>Confederate States Army</target><part>Confederate</part></link><space/>guns at<space/><link><target>Culpeper, Virginia</target><part>Culpepper</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Crimean War</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Charge of the Light Brigade</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>The Thin Red Line (Battle of Balaclava)</target><part>Thin Red Line</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Balaclava</target></link><space/>showed the vulnerability of cavalry, when deployed without effective support.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=_UreS--MoD0C&amp;amp;pg=PA40&amp;amp;dq=cavalry+crimean+war&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=DtOZT6yuJYbG0QWH2ejtBQ&amp;amp;ved=0CFMQ6AEwBQ#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=cavalry%20crimean%20war&amp;amp;f=false'>Guy Arnold, Historical Dictionary of the Crimean War, Scarecrow Press Inc 2002, ISBN 0-8108-4276-9 (pp. 40-41)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the early<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link><space/>the regular United States Army mounted rifle, dragoon, and two existing cavalry regiments were reorganized and renamed cavalry regiments, of which there were six. Over a hundred other federal and state cavalry regiments were organized, but the infantry played a much larger role in many battles due to its larger numbers, lower cost per rifle fielded, and much easier recruitment. However, cavalry saw a role as part of screening forces and in foraging and scouting. The later phases of the war saw the<space/><link><target>Union Army</target><part>Federal army</part></link><space/>developing a truly effective cavalry force fighting as<space/><link><target>Reconnaissance</target><part>scouts</part></link>, raiders, and, with repeating rifles, as<space/><link><target>mounted infantry</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Post Civil War, as the volunteer armies disbanded, the regular army cavalry regiments increased in number from six to ten, among them the<space/><link><target>U.S. 7th Cavalry Regiment</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Battle of the Little Bighorn</target><part>Little Bighorn</part></link><space/>fame, and the<space/><link><target>African-American</target></link><space/><link><target>U.S. 9th Cavalry Regiment</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>U.S. 10th Cavalry Regiment</target></link>. These units, along with others (both cavalry and<space/><link><target>infantry</target></link>), collectively became known as the<space/><link><target>Buffalo Soldier</target><trail>s</trail></link>.These regiments, which rarely took the field as complete organizations, served throughout the<space/><link><target>American Indian Wars</target></link><space/>through the close of the frontier in the 1890s. Volunteer cavalry regiments like the<space/><link><target>Rough Riders</target></link><space/>(which consisted of<space/><link><target>cowboy</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>rancher</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other outdoorsmen), were a cheap and popular unit in the United States Military at that time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Mathingham Hutton, &quot;T.R. takes charge,&quot; American History 33.n3 (August 1998), 30(11).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Valladolid - Academia de Caballeria 3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Monument to the Spanish Regiment of light cavalry of Alcntara''</part></link>During the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian War</target></link>, at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Mars-la-Tour</target></link><space/>in 1870, a Prussian cavalry brigade decisively smashed the centre of the French battle line, after skilfully concealing their approach. This event became known as<space/><bold>Von Bredow's Death Ride</bold><space/>after the brigade commander<space/><link><target>Adalbert von Bredow</target></link>; it would be used in the following decades to argue that massed cavalry charges still had a place on the modern battlefield.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books/about/The_Franco_Prussian_War.html?id=h2wEeRuei6AC'>The Franco-Prussian War: The German Invasion of France, 1870-1871, by Michael Howard and Michael Eliot Howard. Routledge 2001, ISBN 0-415-26671-8 (p.157)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>19th-century imperial expansion</heading><paragraph>Cavalry found a new role in colonial campaigns (<link><target>irregular military</target><part>irregular warfare</part></link>), where modern weapons were lacking and the slow moving infantry-artillery train or fixed fortifications were often ineffective against indigenous insurgents (unless the latter offered a fight on an equal footing, as at<space/><link><target>Battle of Tel el-Kebir</target><part>Tel-el-Kebir</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Omdurman</target><part>Omdurman</part></link>, etc.). Cavalry &quot;<link><target>flying column</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; proved effective, or at least cost-effective, in many campaignsalthough an astute native commander (like<space/><link><target>Samori</target></link><space/>in western Africa,<space/><link><target>Imam Shamil</target><part>Shamil</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Caucasus</target></link>, or any of the better<space/><link><target>Boer</target></link><space/>commanders) could turn the tables and use the greater mobility of their cavalry to offset their relative lack of firepower compared with European forces.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>British Indian Army</target></link><space/>maintained about forty regiments of cavalry, officered by British and manned by Indian<space/><link><target>sowars</target></link><space/>(cavalrymen). Among the more famous regiments in the lineages of the modern Indian and Pakistani armies are:<link><target>File:21lancers.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The charge of the 21st Lancers at<space/><link><target>Battle of Omdurman</target><part>Omdurman</part></link></part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Governor General's Bodyguard</target></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>President's Bodyguard (India)</target><part>President's Bodyguard</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>Skinner's Horse (now India's<space/><link><target>1st Horse (Skinner's Horse)</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>Gardner's Lancers (now India's<space/><link><target>2nd Lancers (Gardner's Horse)</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>Hodson's Horse (now India's<space/><link><target>Hodson's Horse</target><part>3rd Horse (Hodson's)</part></link>) of the Bengal Lancers fame</listitem><listitem><link><target>6th Bengal Cavalry</target></link><space/>(later amalgamated with<space/><link><target>7th Hariana Lancers</target></link><space/>to form<space/><link><target>18th King Edward's Own Cavalry</target></link>) now<space/><link><target>18th Cavalry</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Indian Army</target></link></listitem><listitem>Probyn's Horse (now Pakistani)</listitem><listitem>Royal Deccan Horse (now India's<space/><link><target>Deccan Horse</target><part>The Deccan Horse</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>Poona Horse (now India's<space/><link><target>The Poona Horse</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>Scinde Horse (now India's<space/><link><target>Scinde Horse</target><part>The Scinde Horse</part></link>)</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Guides Cavalry</target><part>Queen's Own Guides Cavalry</part></link><space/>(now partitioned between Pakistan and India).</listitem></list><paragraph>Several of these formations are still active, though they now are armoured formations, for example the Guides Cavalry in Pakistan.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://defencejournal.com/jun99/guides-cavalry.htm'>THE GUIDES CAVALRY (10th QUEEN VICTORIA'S OWN FRONTIER FORCE)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The French Army maintained substantial cavalry forces in Algeria and Morocco from 1830 until the end of the Second World War. Much of the Mediterranean coastal terrain was suitable for mounted action and there was a long established culture of horsemanship amongst the Arab and Berber inhabitants. The French forces included<space/><link><target>Spahi</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Chasseurs d' Afrique</target></link>,<space/><link><target>French Foreign Legion</target><part>Foreign Legion</part></link><space/>cavalry and mounted<space/><link><target>Goumier</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>L'Armee d'Afrique 1830-1962, General R. Hure, Paris-Limogues 1977</extension><space/>Both Spain and Italy raised cavalry regiments from amongst the indigenous horsemen of their respective North African territories.</paragraph><paragraph>Imperial Germany employed mounted formations in South West Africa as part of the<space/><link><target>Schutztruppen</target></link><space/>(colonial army) garrisoning the territory.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Charles</arg><arg name="last">Woolley</arg><arg name="page">94</arg><arg name="title">Uniforms of the German Colonial Troops</arg><arg name="ISBN">978-0-7643-3357-6</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>First World War</heading><heading level='4'>Pre-war developments</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Italian cavalry drill.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Italian cavalry officers practice their horsemanship in 1904 outside Rome.</part></link>At the beginning of the 20th century all armies still maintained substantial cavalry forces, although there was contention over whether their role should revert to that of mounted infantry (the historic dragoon function). Following the experience of the<space/><link><target>Second Boer War</target><part>South African War</part></link><space/>of 1899-1902 (where mounted Boer citizen commandos fighting on foot from cover proved superior to regular cavalry) the British Army withdrew lances for all but ceremonial purposes and placed a new emphasis on training for dismounted action.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1908 however the six British lancer regiments in existence resumed use of this impressive but obsolete weapon for active service. In 1882 the Imperial Russian Army converted all its line hussar and lancer regiments to dragoons, with an emphasis on mounted infantry training. In 1910 these regiments reverted to their historic roles, designations and uniforms.</paragraph><paragraph>By 1909 official regulations dictating the role of the Imperial German cavalry had been revised to indicate an increasing realization of the realities of modern warfare. The massive cavalry charge in three waves which had previously marked the end of annual maneuvers was discontinued and a new emphasis was placed in training on scouting, raiding and pursuit; rather than main battle involvement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Prit</arg><arg name="last">Buttar</arg><arg name="page">39</arg><arg name="title">Collusion of Empires</arg><arg name="ISBN">978-1-78200-648-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In spite of significant experience in mounted warfare in Morocco during 1908-14, the French cavalry remained a highly conservative institution.<extension extension_name='ref'>David Woodward, page 47 &quot;Armies of the World 1854-1914&quot;,SBN=399-12252-4</extension><space/>The traditional tactical distinctions between heavy, medium and light cavalry branches were retained.<extension extension_name='ref'>page 570, Volume 5, Encyclopdia Britannica eleventh edition</extension><space/>French cuirassiers wore breastplates and plumed helmets unchanged from the Napoleonic period, during the early months of World War I.<extension extension_name='ref'>Louis Delperier, pages 60-70 &quot;Les Cuirassiers 1845-1918&quot;, Argout-Editions Paris 1981</extension><space/>Dragoons were similarly equipped, though they did not wear cuirasses and did carry lances. Light cavalry were described as being &quot;a blaze of colour&quot;. French cavalry of all branches were well mounted and were trained to change position and charge at full gallop.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="last">Terraine</arg><arg name="page">57</arg><arg name="title">Mons Retreat to Victory</arg><arg name="ISBN">1-84022-243-3</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Cavalry during opening stages</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:KuK Kavallerie 1898.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Austro-Hungarian Army</target><part>Austro-Hungarian</part></link><space/>cavalry, 1898.</part></link><link><target>File:Kavallerie Wk I.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>German cavalryman in September 1914,<space/><link><target>German South-West Africa</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In August 1914 all combatant armies still retained substantial numbers of cavalry and the mobile nature of the opening battles on both<space/><link><target>Eastern Front (World War I)</target><part>Eastern</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Fronts</part></link><space/>provided a number of instances of traditional cavalry actions, though on a smaller and more scattered scale than those of previous wars. The Imperial German cavalry, while as colourful and traditional as any in peacetime appearance, had adopted a practice of falling back on infantry support when any substantial opposition was encountered.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Terraine, page 50,<space/><italics>Mons: Retreat to Victory</italics>, ISBN 1-84022-243-3</extension><space/>These cautious tactics aroused derision amongst their more conservative French and Russian opponents but proved appropriate to the new nature of warfare. A single attempt by the German army, on 12 August 1914, to use six regiments of massed cavalry to cut off the Belgian field army from<space/><link><target>Antwerp</target></link><space/>foundered when they were driven back in disorder by rifle fire.<extension extension_name='ref'>R Pawly, pages 10-11,<space/><italics>The Belgian Army in World War I</italics>, ISBN 978-1-84603-448-0</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Joe Robinson, Francis Hendriks and Janet Robinson<space/><italics>The Last Great Cavalry Charge - The Battle of the Silver Helmets Halen 12 August 1914</italics>, ISBN 978-1-78155-183-7</extension><space/>Once the front lines stabilised on the Western Front, a combination of barbed wire, machine guns and rapid fire rifles proved deadly to horse mounted troops.</paragraph><paragraph>On the Eastern Front a more fluid form of warfare arose from flat open terrain favorable to mounted warfare. On the outbreak of war in 1914 the bulk of the Russian cavalry was deployed at full strength in frontier garrisons and during the period that the main armies were mobilizing scouting and raiding into East Prussia and Austrian Galacia was undertaken by mounted troops trained to fight with sabre and lance in the traditional style.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vladimir A. Emmanuel, page 10,<space/><italics>The Russian Imperial Cavalry in 1914</italics>, ISBN 978-0-9889532-1-5</extension><space/>On 21 August 1914 the 4th Austro-Hungarian<space/><italics>Kavalleriedivison</italics><space/>fought a major mounted engagement at Jaroslavic with the Russian 10th Cavalry Division,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Prit</arg><arg name="last">Buttar</arg><arg name="page">209</arg><arg name="title">Collusion of Empires</arg><arg name="ISBN">978-1-78200-648-0</arg></template></extension><space/>in what was arguably the final historic battle to involve thousands of horsemen on both sides.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Jung, pages 1011,<space/><italics>The Austro-Hungarian Forces in World War I (1)<space/></italics>, ISBN 1-84176-594-5</extension><space/>While this was the last massed cavalry encounter on the Eastern Front, the absence of good roads limited the use of mechanized transport and even the technologically advanced Imperial German Army continued to deploy up to twenty-four horse-mounted divisions in the East, as late as 1917.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vladimir Littauer, page 6,<space/><italics>Russian Hussar</italics>, ISBN 1-59048-256-5</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Cavalry in Europe 191518</heading><paragraph>For the remainder of the War on the Western Front cavalry had virtually no role to play. The British and French armies dismounted many of their cavalry regiments and used them in infantry and other roles: the<space/><link><target>Life Guards (British Army)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link><space/>for example spent the last months of the War as a machine gun corps; and the<space/><link><target>Australian Light Horse</target></link><space/>served as light infantry during the Gallipoli campaign. In September 1914 cavalry comprised 9.28% of the total manpower of the<space/><link><target>British Expeditionary Force (World War I)</target><part>British Expeditionary Force</part></link><space/>in Franceby July 1918 this proportion had fallen to 1.65%.<extension extension_name='ref'>page 212,<space/><italics>The Oxford History of the British Army</italics>, ISBN 0-19-285333-3</extension><space/>The French cavalry numbered 102,000 in May 1915 but had been reduced to 63,000 by October 1918.<extension extension_name='ref'>page 216, Vol. XXX, Encyclopdia Britannica, 12th Edition, 1922</extension>The German Army dismounted nearly all their cavalry in the West, maintaining only one mounted division on that front by January 1917. At the same date however the Central Powers still had twenty-four divisions of horse cavalry active or in reserve along the Russian Front.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Vladimir</arg><arg name="last">Littauer</arg><arg name="page">6</arg><arg name="title">Russian Hussar</arg><arg name="ISBN">1-59048-256-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R42025, Warschau, Einmarsch deutscher Kavallerie.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>German<space/><link><target>Uhlan</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>after the capture of Warsaw, August 1915</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Some cavalry were retained as mounted troops behind the lines in anticipation of a penetration of the opposing trenches that it seemed would never come.<space/><link><target>Tanks</target></link>, introduced on the Western Front by the British in September 1916, had the capacity to achieve such breakthroughs but did not have the reliable range to exploit them. In their first major use at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Cambrai (1917)</target></link>, the plan was for a cavalry division to follow behind the tanks, however they were not able to cross a canal because a tank had broken the only bridge.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/battle_of_cambrai.htm'>History Learning Site: Battle of Cambrai</link></extension><space/>It was not until the German Army had been forced to retreat in the<space/><link><target>Hundred Days Offensive</target></link><space/>of 1918, that cavalry were again able to operate in their intended role. There was a successful charge by the British<space/><link><target>7th Dragoon Guards</target></link><space/>on the last day of the war.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.rdgmuseum.org.uk/history.htm'>Royal Dragoon Guards Museum: History Of The Royal Dragoon Guards</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the wider spaces of the Eastern Front a more fluid form of warfare continued and there was still a use for mounted troops. Some wide-ranging actions were fought, again mostly in the early months of the war.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Willmott"><italics>First World War</italics>, Willmott, H.P., Dorling Kindersley, 2003</extension><space/>However, even here the value of cavalry was overrated and the maintenance of large mounted formations at the front by the<space/><link><target>Military history of the Russian Empire</target><part>Russian Army</part></link><space/>put a major strain on the railway system, to little strategic advantage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Norman</arg><arg name="last">Stone</arg><arg name="page">220</arg><arg name="title">The Eastern Front 1914-17</arg><arg name="ISBN">0-684-14492-1</arg></template></extension><space/>In February 1917 the Russian regular cavalry (exclusive of Cossacks) was reduced by nearly a third from its peak number of 200,000, as two squadrons of each regiment were dismounted and incorporated into additional infantry battalions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Vladimir</arg><arg name="last">Littauer</arg><arg name="page">220</arg><arg name="title">Russian Hussar</arg><arg name="ISBN">1-59048-256-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Cavalry and mounted infantry in the Middle East</heading><paragraph>In the Middle East, during the<space/><link><target>Sinai and Palestine Campaign</target></link><space/>mounted forces (British, Indian, Ottoman, Australian, Arab and New Zealand) retained an important strategic role both as mounted infantry and cavalry.</paragraph><paragraph>In Egypt the<space/><link><target>mounted infantry</target></link><space/>formations like the<space/><link><target>New Zealand Mounted Rifles Brigade</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Australian Light Horse</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>ANZAC Mounted Division</target></link>, operating as mounted infantry, drove German and Ottoman forces back from<space/><link><target>Battle of Romani</target><part>Romani</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Battle of Magdhaba</target><part>Magdhaba</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Rafa</target><part>Rafa</part></link><space/>and out of the Egyptian Sinai Peninsula in 1916.</paragraph><paragraph>After a stalemate on the GazaBeersheba line between March and October 1917,<space/><link><target>Beersheba</target></link><space/>was captured by the<space/><link><target>Australian Mounted Division</target></link>'s 4th Light Horse Brigade. Their mounted charge succeeded after a<space/><link><target>Battle of Beersheba (1917)</target><part>coordinated attack</part></link><space/>by the British Infantry and Yeomanry cavalry and the Australian and New Zealand Light Horse and Mounted Rifles brigades. A series of coordinated attacks by these<space/><link><target>Egyptian Expeditionary Force</target></link><space/>infantry and mounted troops were also successful at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Mughar Ridge</target></link>, during which the British infantry divisions and the Desert Mounted Corps drove two Ottoman armies back to the JaffaJerusalem line. The infantry with mainly dismounted cavalry and mounted infantry fought in the<space/><link><target>Judean Hills</target></link><space/>to eventually almost encircle<space/><link><target>Battle of Jerusalem (1917)</target><part>Jerusalem</part></link><space/>which was occupied shortly after.</paragraph><paragraph>During a pause in operations necessitated by the<space/><link><target>Spring Offensive</target></link><space/>in 1918 on the Western Front joint infantry and mounted infantry attacks towards<space/><link><target>First Transjordan attack on Amman</target><part>Amman</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Second Transjordan attack on Shunet Nimrin and Es Salt</target><part>Es Salt</part></link><space/>resulted in retreats back to the<space/><link><target>Jordan Valley (Middle East)</target><part>Jordan Valley</part></link><space/>which continued to be occupied by mounted divisions during the summer of 1918.</paragraph><paragraph>The Australian Mounted Division was armed with swords and in September, after the successful<space/><link><target>Battle of Megiddo (1918)</target><part>breaching</part></link><space/>of the Ottoman line on the Mediterranean coast by<space/><link><target>Battle of Sharon (1918)</target><part>the British Empire infantry</part></link><space/>XXI Corps was followed by cavalry attacks by the<space/><link><target>Capture of Afulah and Beisan</target><part>4th Cavalry Division</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Nazareth (1918)</target><part>5th Cavalry Division</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Capture of Jenin (1918)</target><part>Australian Mounted Division</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which almost encircled two Ottoman armies in the Judean Hills<space/><link><target>Battle of Samakh (1918)</target><part>forcing their retreat</part></link>. Meanwhile,<space/><link><target>Chaytor's Force</target></link><space/>of infantry and mounted infantry in ANZAC Mounted Division<space/><link><target>Occupation of the Jordan Valley (1918)</target><part>held the Jordan Valley</part></link>, covering the right flank to later advance eastwards to<space/><link><target>Third Transjordan attack</target><part>capture Es Salt and Amman</part></link><space/>and half of a third Ottoman army. A subsequent pursuit by the<space/><link><target>Charge at Irbid</target><part>4th Cavalry Division</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jisr Benat Yakub</target><part>Australian Mounted Division</part></link><space/>followed by the<space/><link><target>Charge at Kiswe</target><part>5th Cavalry Division</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Damascus</target></link>. Armoured cars and 5th Cavalry Division lancers were continuing the pursuit of Ottoman units north of<space/><link><target>Aleppo</target></link><space/>when the<space/><link><target>Armistice of Mudros</target></link><space/>was signed by the Ottoman Empire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Falls<space/></arg><arg name="first">Cyril
</arg><arg name="author2">G. MacMunn
</arg><arg name="author3">A. F. Beck (Maps)
</arg><arg name="title">Military Operations Egypt & Palestine from the outbreak of war with Germany to June 1917
</arg><arg name="series">Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence
</arg><arg name="year">1930
</arg><arg name="volume">1 and 2 Parts I and II<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HM Stationery Office<space/></arg><arg name="location">London
</arg><arg name="oclc">610273484, 644354483, 256950972</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>PostWorld War I</heading><paragraph>A combination of military conservatism in almost all armies and post-war financial constraints prevented the lessons of 1914-18 being acted on immediately. There was a general reduction in the number of cavalry regiments in the British, French, Italian and other Western armies but it was still argued with conviction (for example in the 1922 edition of the<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link></italics>) that mounted troops had a major role to play in future warfare. The 1920s saw an interim period during which cavalry remained as a proud and conspicuous element of all major armies, though much less so than prior to 1914.</paragraph><paragraph>Cavalry was extensively used in the<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Soviet-Polish War</target></link>. The last major cavalry battle was the<space/><link><target>Battle of Komarw</target></link><space/>in 1920, between Poland and the Russian Bolsheviks. Colonial warfare in Morocco, Syria, the Middle East and the<space/><link><target>North-West Frontier Province (19011955)</target><part>North West Frontier</part></link><space/>of India provided some opportunities for mounted action against enemies lacking advanced weaponry.<link><target>File:Lietuvos kavalerija.Lithuanian cavalry.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.5</part><part><link><target>Lithuania</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>lancers training in the 1930s</part></link>The post-war German Army (<link><target>Reichsheer</target></link>) was permitted a large proportion of cavalry (18 regiments or 16.4% of total manpower) under the conditions of the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link>. The U.S. Cavalry abandoned its sabres in 1934 and commenced the conversion of its horsed regiments to mechanized cavalry, starting with the First Regiment of Cavalry in January 1933.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>British Army</target></link>, all cavalry regiments were mechanised between 1929 and 1941, redefining their role from horse to armoured vehicles to form the<space/><link><target>Royal Armoured Corps</target></link><space/>together with the<space/><link><target>Royal Tank Regiment</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The thirty-nine regiments of the<space/><link><target>British Indian Army</target></link><space/>were reduced to twenty-one as the result of a series of amalgamations immediately following World War I. The new establishment remained unchanged until 1936 when three regiments were redesignated as permanent training units, each with six, still mounted, regiments linked to them. In 1938 the process of mechanism began with the conversion of a full cavalry brigade (two Indian regiments and one British) to armoured car and tank units. By the end of 1940 all of the Indian cavalry had been mechanised, receiving light tanks, armoured cars or 15cwt trucks. The last horsed regiment of the Indian Army (other than the Viceregal Bodyguard and some Indian States Forces regiments) was the 19th King George's Own Lancers which had its last mounted parade at Rawalpindi on 28 October 1939. This unit still exists (though in the Pakistan Army) with an armour TOE.</paragraph><paragraph>During the 1930s the French Army experimented with integrating mounted and mechanised cavalry units into larger formations. Dragoon regiments were converted to motorised infantry (trucks and motor cycles), and cuirassiers to armoured units; while light cavalry (Chasseurs a' Cheval, Hussars and Spahis) remained as mounted sabre squadrons. The theory was that mixed forces comprising these diverse units could utilise the strengths of each according to circumstances. In practice mounted troops proved unable to keep up with fast moving mechanised units over any distance.</paragraph><heading level='3'>World War II cavalry</heading><paragraph>While most armies still maintained cavalry units at the outbreak of World War II in 1939, significant mounted action was largely restricted to the Polish, Balkan and Soviet campaigns.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Polish</heading><paragraph>A popular myth is that<space/><link><target>Polish cavalry</target></link><space/>armed with lances charged German tanks during the September 1939 campaign. This arose from misreporting of a single clash on 1 September near Krojanty, when two squadrons of the Polish 18th Lancers armed with sabres scattered German infantry before being caught in the open by German armoured cars.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Zaloga
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>S. J.
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Polish Army 193945
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Osprey
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-85045-417-4
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London
</arg></template></extension>Two examples illustrate how the myth developed. First, because motorised vehicles were in short supply, the Poles used horses to pull anti-tank weapons into position.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Time Staff</arg><arg name="date">April 22, 1940</arg><arg name="number"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The New Pictures</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Time</arg><arg name="volume"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,763905-1,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-07-17</arg></template></extension><space/>Second, there were a few incidents when Polish cavalry was trapped by German tanks, and attempted to fight free. However, this did not mean that the Polish army chose to attack tanks with horse cavalry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Davies324">Davies<space/><italics>God's Playground Volume II</italics><space/>pp. 324-325</extension><space/>Later, on the Eastern Front, the<space/><link><target>Red Army</target></link><space/>did deploy cavalry units effectively against the Germans.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Davies325">Davies<space/><italics>God's Playground Volume II</italics><space/>p. 325</extension><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 101I-054-1525-26, Frankreich, Kavallerie am Ausgang eines Dorfes.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A German cavalry patrol in May 1940, during the<space/><link><target>Battle of France</target></link>.</part></link>A more correct term would be &quot;mounted infantry&quot; instead of &quot;cavalry&quot;, as horses were primarily used as a means of transportation, for which they were very suitable in view of the very poor road conditions in pre-war Poland. Another myth describes Polish cavalry as being armed with both sabres and lances; lances were used for peacetime ceremonial purposes only and the primary weapon of the Polish cavalryman in 1939 was a rifle. Individual equipment did include a sabre, probably because of well-established tradition, but in the case of a melee combat this secondary weapon would probably be more effective than a rifle and bayonet. Moreover, the<space/><link><target>Polish cavalry brigade order of battle in 1939</target></link><space/>included, apart from the mounted soldiers themselves, light and heavy machine guns (wheeled),<space/><link><target>Anti-tank rifle, model 35</target></link>, anti-aircraft weapon, artillery like<space/><link><target>Bofors 37 mm</target></link><space/>anti tank gun or light and scout tanks, etc. The last cavalry vs. cavalry mutual charge in Europe took place in Poland during the<space/><link><target>battle of Krasnobrod</target></link>, when Polish and German cavalry units clashed with each other.</paragraph><paragraph>The last classical cavalry charge of the war was that made on March 1, 1945 during the<space/><link><target>Battle of Schoenfeld</target></link><space/>by the 1st &quot;Warsaw&quot; Independent Cavalry Brigade. Infantry and tanks had been employed to little effect against the German position, both of which floundered in the open wetlands only to be dominated by infantry and antitank fire from the German fortifications on the forward slope of Hill 157, overlooking the wetlands. The Germans had not taken cavalry into consideration when fortifying their position which, combined with the &quot;Warsaw&quot;s swift assault, overran the German anti-tank guns and consolidated into an attack into the village itself, now supported by infantry and tanks.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Greek</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Italian invasion of Greece</target></link><space/>in October 1940 saw mounted cavalry used effectively by the Greek defenders along the mountainous frontier with Albania. Three Greek cavalry regiments (two mounted and one partially mechanized) played an important role in the Italian defeat in this difficult terrain.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Armed Forces of World War II 1914-1945, Andrew Mollo, ISBN 0-85613-296-9</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Cavalleria sovietica.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Soviet cavalry in the winter of 194243</part></link></paragraph><heading level='4'>Soviet</heading><paragraph>By the final stages of the war only the Soviet Union was still fielding mounted units in substantial numbers, some in combined mechanized and horse units. The advantage of this approach was that in exploitation mounted infantry could keep pace with advancing tanks. Other factors favouring the retention of mounted forces included the high quality of Russian<space/><link><target>Cossacks</target></link><space/>and other horse cavalry; and the relative lack of roads suitable for wheeled vehicles in many parts of the Eastern Front. Another consideration was that the logistic capacity required to support very large motorised forces exceeded that necessary for mounted troops.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Italian</heading><paragraph>The last mounted saber charge by Italian cavalry occurred on August 24, 1942 at<space/><link><target>Isbuscenskij Charge</target><part>Isbuscenski</part></link><space/>(Russia), when a squadron of the &quot;Savoia Cavalry Regiment&quot; charged the &quot;812th Siberian Infantry Regiment&quot;. The remainder of the regiment, together with the Novara Lancers made a dismounted attack in an action that ended with the retreat of the Russians after heavy losses on both sides.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jeffrey T. Fowler, page 45 &quot;Axis Cavalry in World War II, ISBN 1-84176-323-3</extension><space/>The final Italian cavalry action occurred on October 17, 1942 in Poloj (Croatia) by a squadron of &quot;Alexandria Cavalry Regiment&quot; against a large group of Yugoslav partisans.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Other Axis</heading><paragraph>Romanian, Hungarian and Italian cavalry were dispersed or disbanded following the retreat of the Axis forces from Russia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jeffrey T. Fowler, pages 35-38 &quot;Axis Cavalry in World War II, ISBN 1-84176-323-3</extension><space/>Germany still maintained some mounted (mixed with bicycles) SS and Cossack units until the last days of the War.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Finnish</heading><paragraph>Finland used mounted troops against Russian forces effectively in forested terrain during winter warfare. The last Finnish cavalry unit was not disbanded until 1947.</paragraph><heading level='4'>US</heading><paragraph>The U.S. Army's last horse cavalry actions were fought during World War II: a) by the<space/><link><target>26th Cavalry Regiment (United States)</target><part>26th Cavalry Regiment</part></link>a small mounted regiment of<space/><link><target>Philippine Scouts</target></link><space/>which fought the Japanese during the retreat down the Bataan peninsula, until it was effectively destroyed by January 1942; and b) on captured German horses by the mounted reconnaissance section of the U.S. 10th Mountain Division in a spearhead pursuit of the German Army across the Po Valley in Italy in April 1945.<extension extension_name='ref'>Personal memoirs of Colonel Ernest Neal Cory, Jr., Esquire</extension><space/>The last horsed U.S. Cavalry (the<space/><link><target>2nd Cavalry Division (United States)</target><part>Second Cavalry Division</part></link>) were dismounted in March 1944.</paragraph><heading level='4'>British Empire</heading><paragraph>All British Army cavalry regiments had been mechanised since 1 March 1942 when the<space/><link><target>Queen's Own Yorkshire Dragoons</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Yeomanry</target></link>) was converted to a motorised role, following mounted service against the Vichy French in Syria the previous year. The final cavalry charge by British Empire forces occurred on 21 March 1942 when a 60 strong patrol of the Burma Frontier Force encountered Japanese infantry near<space/><link><target>Toungoo</target></link><space/>airfield in central<space/><link><target>Burma</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Sikh</target></link><space/><link><target>sowar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the Frontier Force cavalry, led by Captain Arthur Sandeman of<space/><link><target>The Central India Horse (21st King George V's Own Horse)</target></link>, charged in the old style with sabres and most were killed.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Mongolia</heading><paragraph>In the early stages of World War II, mounted units of the Mongolian People's Army were involved in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Khalkhin Gol</target></link><space/>against invading Japanese forces. Soviet forces under the command of Georgy Zhukov, together with Mongolian forces, defeated the Japanese Sixth army and effectively ended the SovietJapanese Border Wars. After the<space/><link><target>SovietJapanese Neutrality Pact</target></link><space/>of 1941, Mongolia remained neutral throughout most of the war, but its geographical situation meant that the country served as a buffer between Japanese forces and the Soviet Union. In addition to keeping around 10% of the population under arms, Mongolia provided half a million trained horses for use by the Soviet Army. In 1945 a partially mounted Soviet-Mongolian<space/><link><target>Cavalry Mechanized Group</target></link><space/>played a supporting role on the western flank of the<space/><link><target>Soviet invasion of Manchuria</target></link>. The last active service seen by cavalry units of the Mongolian Army occurred in 19461948, during border clashes between Mongolia and the<space/><link><target>Republic of China</target></link>.<link><target>File:Battle of Khalkhin Gol-Mongolian cavalry.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Mongolian cavalry in the Khalkhin Gol (1939)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>PostWorld War II to present day</heading><paragraph>While most modern &quot;cavalry&quot; units have some historic connection with formerly mounted troops this is not always the case. The modern Irish Defence Force (IDF) includes a &quot;Cavalry Corps&quot; equipped with armoured cars and<space/><link><target>FV101 Scorpion</target><part>Scorpion tracked combat reconnaissance vehicles</part></link>. The IDF has never included horse cavalry since its establishment in 1922 (other than a small mounted escort of<space/><link><target>Blue Hussars</target></link><space/>drawn from the Artillery Corps when required for ceremonial occasions). However, the mystique of the cavalry is such that the name has been introduced for what was always a mechanised force.</paragraph><paragraph>Some engagements in late 20th and early 21st century<space/><link><target>guerrilla warfare</target><part>guerrilla</part></link><space/>wars involved mounted troops, particularly against partisan or guerrilla fighters in areas with poor transport infrastructure. Such units were not used as cavalry but rather as mounted infantry. Examples occurred in Afghanistan,<space/><link><target>Portuguese-speaking African countries</target><part>Portuguese Africa</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rhodesia</target></link>. The French Army used existing mounted squadrons of<space/><link><target>Spahi</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to a limited extent for patrol work during the Algerian War (195462) and the Swiss Army maintained a mounted dragoon regiment for combat purposes until 1973. The<space/><link><target>Portuguese Army</target></link><space/>used horse mounted cavalry with some success in the<space/><link><target>Portuguese Colonial War</target><part>wars of independence in Angola and Mozambique</part></link><space/>in the 1960s and 1970s. During the 1964-79<space/><link><target>Rhodesian Bush War</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Rhodesian Army</target></link><space/>created an elite mounted infantry unit called<space/><link><target>Grey's Scouts</target></link><space/>to fight unconventional actions against the rebel forces of<space/><link><target>Robert Mugabe</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Joshua Nkomo</target></link>. The horse mounted infantry of the Scouts were effective and reportedly feared by their opponents in the rebel African forces. In the 1978 to present<space/><link><target>War in Afghanistan (1978present)</target><part>Afghan Civil War</part></link><space/>period there have been several instances of horse mounted combat.</paragraph><paragraph>South and Central American armies maintained mounted cavalry for longer than those of Europe, Asia or North America. The Mexican Army included a number of horse mounted cavalry regiments as late as the mid-1990s and the Chilean Army had five such regiments in 1983 as mounted mountain troops.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">English</arg><arg name="first">Adrian J.</arg><arg name="date">May 1985<space/></arg><arg name="title">Armed Forces of Latin America:Their Histories, Development, Present Strength and Military Potential</arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Jane's Information Group]]</arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0710603210<space/></arg><arg name="access-date"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Soviet Army</target></link><space/>retained horse cavalry divisions until 1955, and even at the dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991, there was an independent horse mounted cavalry squadron in<space/><link><target>Kyrgyzstan</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carey Schofield, Inside the Soviet Army, Headline, 1991, p.133-134</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Remaining operational mounted cavalry</heading><paragraph>Today, the<space/><link><target>Indian Army</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>61st Cavalry Regiment (India)</target><part>61st Cavalry</part></link><space/>is reported to be the largest remaining non-ceremonial horse-mounted cavalry in the world.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.indiapolo.com/Polopedia/Genesis/Indian_Army/61st_Cavalry/61st_cavalry.html'>India Polo Magazine</link></extension><space/>It was raised in 1951 from the amalgamated state cavalry squadrons of Gwailior, Jodhpur, and Mysore. While primarily utilised for ceremonial purposes, the regiment can be deployed for internal security or police roles if required.<extension extension_name='ref'>Henry Dallal,<space/><italics>Horse Warriors: India's 61st Cavalry</italics>, ISBN 0-9544083-1-4</extension><space/>The 61st Cavalry and the President's Body Guard parade in full<space/><link><target>dress uniform</target></link><space/>in New Delhi each year in what is probably the largest assembly of traditional cavalry still to be seen in the world. Both the Indian and the Pakistani armies maintain armoured regiments with the titles of<space/><link><target>Lancer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or Horse, dating back to the 19th century.</paragraph><paragraph>As of 2007 the Chinese<space/><link><target>People's Liberation Army</target></link><space/>employed two battalions of horse cavalry in Xinjing Military District for border patrol work. The PLA mounted units last saw action during border clashes with<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link><space/>in the 1970s and 80s, after which most cavalry units were disbanded as part of the major military downsizing of the 1980s.In the wake of the<space/><link><target>2008 Sichuan earthquake</target></link>, there have been calls to rebuild the army horse inventory for disaster relief in difficult terrain. Subsequent Chinese media reporting<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Global Times</italics><space/>20 November 2009 and<space/><italics>Xinhua News Agency</italics><space/>22 August 2011</extension><space/>confirms that the Chinese Army maintains operational horse cavalry at squadron strength in the Mongolia Autonomous Region for scouting and logistical purposes.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Modern ceremonial cavalry plus armored units retaining traditional titles</heading><paragraph>Cavalry or mounted gendarmerie units continue to be maintained for purely or primarily ceremonial purposes by the United States, British, French, Italian, Danish, Swedish, Dutch, Chilean, Portuguese, Moroccan, Algerian, Nepalese, Nigerian, Venezuelan, Brazilian, Peruvian, Paraguayan, Polish, Argentine, Senegalese, Jordanian, Pakistani, Indian, Spanish, Omani, Thai, Panamanian and Bulgarian armed forces. The Army of the Russian Federation has recently reintroduced a ceremonial mounted squadron wearing historic uniforms.</paragraph><paragraph>A number of armoured regiments in the<space/><link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>retain the historic designations of Hussars, Dragoons, Light Dragoons, Dragoon Guards, Lancers and Yeomanry. Only the<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link>, Consisting of: The<space/><link><target>Life Guards (United Kingdom)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link><space/>Mounted Squadron, The<space/><link><target>Blues and Royals</target></link><space/>Mounted Squadron, The State Trumpeters of The<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link><space/>and The<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link><space/>Mounted Band are maintained for mounted (and dismounted) ceremonial duties in London.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>French Army</target></link><space/>still has regiments with the historic designations of<space/><link><target>Cuirassiers</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hussars</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chasseurs</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dragoons</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Spahi</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Only the cavalry of the<space/><link><target>French Republican Guard</target><part>Republican Guard</part></link><space/>and a ceremonial<space/><italics>fanfare</italics><space/>detachment of trumpeters for the cavalry/armoured branch<extension extension_name='ref'>Cyr Darnoc De Saint-mande, pages 33-36,<space/><italics>Gazette des Uniformes</italics>, December 2002</extension><space/>as a whole are now mounted.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Canadian Army</target></link>, a number of regular and reserve units have cavalry roots, including<space/><link><target>The Royal Canadian Hussars (Montreal)</target></link>,<space/><link><target>the Governor General's Horse Guards</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lord Strathcona's Horse</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Royal Canadian Dragoons</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>South Alberta Light Horse</target></link>. Of these, only Lord Strathcona's Horse and the Governor General's Horse Guards maintain an official ceremonial horse-mounted cavalry troop or squadron.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Honours, Flags, and Heritage Structure of the Canadian Forces</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Both the Australian and New Zealand armies follow the British practice of maintaining traditional titles (<link><target>Australian Light Horse</target><part>Light Horse</part></link><space/>or Mounted Rifles) for modern mechanised units. However, neither country retains a horse-mounted unit.</paragraph><paragraph>Several<space/><link><target>armour</target><part>armored</part></link><space/>units of the modern<space/><link><target>United States Army</target></link><space/>retain the designation of &quot;<link><target>Armored cavalry</target></link>&quot;. The United States also has &quot;<link><target>Air assault</target><part>air cavalry</part></link>&quot; units equipped with<space/><link><target>helicopter</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The Horse Cavalry Detachment of the U.S. Army's<space/><link><target>1st Cavalry Division (United States)</target><part>1st Cavalry Division</part></link><space/>is made up of active duty soldiers, still functions as an active unit, trained to approximate the weapons, tools, equipment and techniques used by the United States Cavalry in the 1880s.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://pao.hood.army.mil/1stCavDiv/horseDet/default.html'>First Team! Horse Cavalry Detachment</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Hubbell, Gary. &quot;21st Century Horse Soldiers.&quot;<space/><italics>Western Horseman</italics>, December 2006, pp. 45-50</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Modern cavalry units with non-combat support roles</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>First Troop Philadelphia City Cavalry</target></link><space/>is a volunteer unit within the<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania Army National Guard</target></link><space/>which serves as a combat force when in federal service but acts in a mounted disaster relief role when in state service.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.firsttroop.com/about-us<space/></arg><arg name="title">About First Troop Philadelphia City Cavalry<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="website">First Troop Philadelphia City Cavalry Official Website<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>In addition, the Parsons' Mounted Cavalry is a Reserve Officer Training Corps unit which forms part of the<space/><link><target>Texas A&amp;M University Corps of Cadets</target><part>Corps of Cadets</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Texas A&amp;M University</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Some individual<space/><link><target>U.S. state</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>actively maintain cavalry units as a part of their respective<space/><link><target>state defense force</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The<space/><link><target>Maryland Defense Force</target></link><space/>includes a cavalry unit,<space/><link><target>Maryland Defense Force#Cavalry Troop A</target><part>Cavalry Troop A</part></link>, which serves primarily as a ceremonial unit.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://mddf.maryland.gov/troopa/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cavalry Troop A<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="website">Maryland Defense Force Official Website<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The unit training includes a saber qualification course based upon the 1926 U.S. Army course.<extension extension_name='ref' name="special"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sdfpubcntr.net/docs/sdfm07.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">An Overview of the Employment of Cavalry in History, With an Emphasis on the State Defense Force of the United States in the 21st Century<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Roberts<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Lt. Colonel (MD) Ron<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Cavalry Troop A also assists other Maryland agencies as a rural search and rescue asset.<extension extension_name='ref' name="special"></extension><space/>In Massachusetts, The<space/><link><target>National Lancers</target></link><space/>trace their lineage to a volunteer cavalry militia unit established in 1836 and are currently organized as an official part of the Massachusetts Organized Militia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nl"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nationallancers.org/aboutus.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Our History<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="website">National Lancers Official Website<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The National Lancers maintain three units, Troops A, B, and C, which serve in a ceremonial role and assist in search and rescue missions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nl"></extension><space/>In July 2004, the National Lancers were ordered into active state service to guard<space/><link><target>Camp Curtis Guild</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>2004 Democratic National Convention</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nl"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Governor's Horse Guard</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Connecticut</target></link><space/>maintains two companies which are trained in urban crowd control.<extension extension_name='ref' name="special"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:French heavy cavalry Paris August 1914.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>French<space/><link><target>cuirassiers</target></link>, wearing breastplates and helmets, parade through Paris on the way to battle, August 1914.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Polish cavalry in Sochaczew(1939)a.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Polish cavalry galloping through a bombed town during the<space/><link><target>Invasion of Poland (1939)</target><part>German invasion of Poland</part></link><space/>in 1939.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:W-3 Sok.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Polish<space/><link><target>PZL W-3 Sok</target></link><space/>of the 66 Air Cavalry Squadron, 25th Aeromobile Cavalry Brigade.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:US soldiers on horseback 1991 Afghanistan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>United States Army Special Forces</target><part>U.S. Special Forces</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Combat Controller</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on horseback with the<space/><link><target>Afghan Northern Alliance</target><part>Northern Alliance</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, which frequently used horses as military transport.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:PBG (my own photo).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>The mounted<space/><link><target>President's Bodyguard</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Indian Army</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Republican Guard Cavalry Regiment Bastille Day 2008.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><link><target>French Republican Guard</target></link><space/>2008<space/><link><target>Bastille Day military parade</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Napoli BW 2013-05-16 16-24-01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link><space/>using armoured cavalry, fighting Persian King<space/><link><target>Darius III</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Horseguards - Blues and Royals - Relve Whitehall - Londres.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Troopers of the<space/><link><target>Blues and Royals</target></link><space/>on mounted duty in Whitehall, London</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Independence Day Parade - Flickr - Kerri-Jo (36).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Turkmenistan</target></link><space/>ceremonial cavalry in the Independence Day parade 2011</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:A Mongolian soldier performs during the opening ceremony for exercise Khaan Quest 2013 at the Five Hills Training Area in Mongolia Aug. 3, 2013 130803-M-MG222-004.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>A Mongolian horseman, 2013</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>Light and armored cavalry</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Heavy cavalry</arg><arg>light cavalry</arg></template>Historically, cavalry was divided into<space/><link><target>Light cavalry</target><part>light</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>heavy cavalry</target><part>armoured cavalry</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>horse archer</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The differences were their role in combat, the size of the mount, and how much armor was worn by the mount and<space/><link><target>Equestrianism</target><part>rider</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Early light cavalry (like the auxiliaries of the Roman army) were typically used to<space/><link><target>Reconnaissance</target><part>scout</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>skirmish</target></link>, to cut down retreating infantry, and for defeating enemy missile troops. Armoured cavalry such as the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target><part>Byzantine</part></link><space/><link><target>cataphract</target></link><space/>were used as shock troopsthey would charge the main body of the enemy and, in many cases, their actions decided the outcome of the battle, hence the later term &quot;battle cavalry&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.490, Lynn</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Gunpowder warfare</target><part>Gunpowder Age</part></link>, armored cavalry become obsolete. However, many units retained<space/><link><target>cuirass</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>and helmets for their protective value against<space/><link><target>sword</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>bayonet</target></link><space/>strikes and the morale boost these provide to the wearers. By this time the main difference between light and battle cavalry was their training; the former was regarded as a tool for harassment and reconnaissance, while the latter was considered best for close-order charges.</paragraph><paragraph>Since the development of armored warfare the distinction between light and heavy armor has persisted basically along the same lines.<space/><link><target>Armored car (military)</target><part>Armored car</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>light tank</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have adopted the<space/><link><target>reconnaissance</target></link><space/>role while medium and heavy tanks are regarded as the decisive<space/><link><target>shock troops</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Social status</heading><paragraph>From the beginning of civilization to the 20th century, ownership of heavy cavalry horses has been a mark of wealth amongst settled peoples. A cavalry horse involves considerable expense in breeding, training, feeding, and equipment, and has very little productive use except as a mode of transport.</paragraph><paragraph>For this reason, and because of their often decisive military role, the cavalry has typically been associated with high<space/><link><target>social status</target></link>. This was most clearly seen in the<space/><link><target>Feudalism</target><part>feudal system</part></link>, where a lord was expected to enter combat armored and on horseback and bring with him an entourage of<space/><link><target>peasants</target></link><space/>on foot. If landlords and peasants came into conflict, the peasants would be ill-equipped to defeat armored knights.</paragraph><paragraph>In later national armies, service as an officer in the cavalry was generally a badge of high social status. For instance prior to 1914 most officers of British cavalry regiments came from a socially privileged background and the considerable expenses associated with their role generally required private means, even after it became possible for officers of the line infantry regiments to live on their pay. Options open to poorer cavalry officers in the various European armies included service with less fashionable (though often highly professional) frontier or colonial units. These included the British Indian cavalry, the Russian<space/><link><target>Cossacks</target></link><space/>or the French<space/><link><target>Chasseurs d' Afrique</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>During the 19th and early 20th centuries most monarchies maintained a mounted cavalry element in their royal or imperial guards. These ranged from small units providing ceremonial escorts and palace guards through to large formations intended for active service. The mounted escort of the Spanish Royal Household provided an example of the former and the twelve cavalry regiments of the Prussian Imperial Guard an example of the latter. In either case the officers of such units were likely to be drawn from the aristocracies of their respective societies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>On film</heading><paragraph>Some small sense of the noise and power of a cavalry charge can be gained from the 1970 film<space/><italics><link><target>Waterloo (1970 film)</target><part>Waterloo</part></link></italics>, which featured some 2000 cavalrymen,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2008</arg></template><space/>some of them cossacks. It included detailed displays of the horsemanship required to manage animal and weapons in large numbers at the gallop (unlike the real<space/><link><target>battle of Waterloo</target></link>, where deep mud significantly slowed the horses).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.channel4.com/history/microsites/H/history/t-z/waterloo.html'>''Waterloo''</link><space/>Film review by Major J G H Corrigan. Accessed 2008-02-07.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Gary Cooper</target></link><space/>movie<space/><italics><link><target>They Came to Cordura</target></link></italics><space/>contains an excellent scene of a cavalry regiment deploying from march to battleline formation. A smaller-scale cavalry charge can be seen in<space/><italics><link><target>The Lord of the Rings: The Return of the King</target></link></italics><space/>(2003); although the finished scene has substantial<space/><link><target>computer-generated imagery</target></link>, raw footage and reactions of the riders are shown in the Extended Version DVD Appendices.</paragraph><paragraph>Other films that show cavalry actions include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>The Charge of the Light Brigade (1968 film)</target><part>The Charge of the Light Brigade</part></link>, about the Battle of Balaclava in the Crimean War</listitem><listitem><link><target>Forty Thousand Horsemen</target><part>40,000 Horsemen</part></link>, about the Australian Light Horse during the<space/><link><target>Sinai and Palestine campaign</target></link><space/>of World War I</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Lighthorsemen (film)</target><part>The Lighthorsemen</part></link>, about the<space/><link><target>Battle of Beersheba (1917)</target><part>Battle of Beersheba</part></link>, 1917</listitem><listitem><link><target>War Horse (film)</target><part>War Horse</part></link>, about the British cavalry in Europe during World War I</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hubal (film)</target><part>Hubal</part></link>, about the last months (September 1939 - April 1940) of Poland's first World War II guerilla, Major Henryk Dobrzanski, &quot;Hubal&quot;</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Patriot (2000 film)</target><part>The Patriot</part></link><space/>Includes light cavalry use.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Some cavalry forces</heading><paragraph><template><target>Div col</target><arg name="cols">3</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chinacos</target></link><space/>(Mexican irregular cavalry of the 19th century)</listitem><listitem><link><target>278th Armored Cavalry Regiment</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bayreuth Dragoons</target></link></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Blues and Royals</target></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>who with The<space/><link><target>Life Guards (United Kingdom)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link><space/>form the<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry Regiment</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link><space/>Mounted<space/><link><target>Regiment</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cataphract</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>1st Cavalry Division (United States)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chasseurs d'Afrique</target></link><space/>(<link><target>French Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Companion cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cossack</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuirassier</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dragoon</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Grey's Scouts</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Rhodesian Army</target></link><space/>197580)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Garde Rpublicaine</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Gendarmerie Nationale (France)</target><part>French Gendarmerie</part></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Governor General's Horse Guards</target><part>Governor General's Horse Guards</part></link><space/>(Canada)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Guarda Nacional Republicana</target></link><space/>(Portuguese National Guard)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hakkapeliitta</target></link><space/>(Finnish cavalry of<space/><link><target>Thirty Years' War</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hobelar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(medieval light horse)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hussars</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kalmyks</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>King's Royal Hussars</target></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Queen's Royal Hussars</target></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Light Dragoons</target></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lancer</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Life Guards (United Kingdom)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>who with The<space/><link><target>Blues and Royals</target></link><space/>form the<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry Regiment</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Household Cavalry</target></link><space/>Mounted<space/><link><target>Regiment</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Australian Light Horse</target><part>Light Horse</part></link><space/>(<link><target>Australian Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mamluk</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Numidian cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Panserbataljonen</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Norwegian Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Polish cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Polish Hussars</target><part>Polish winged hussars</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Regulares</target></link><space/>(Spanish Morocco)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Scots Dragoon Guards</target></link><space/>(<link><target>British Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Yeomanry</target></link><space/>(a<space/><link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>Reserve Armoured<space/><link><target>Regiment</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Savari</target></link><space/>(Italian North African)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Savoia Cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sipahi</target></link><space/>(Ottoman)</listitem><listitem><link><target>South Alberta Light Horse</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Canadian Army</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Spahi</target></link><space/>(French North African)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tagma (military)</target><part>Tagma</part><trail>ta</trail></link><space/>(Byzantine)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Uhlan</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Cavalry</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Some distinguished historic or contemporary horse cavalrymen</heading><heading level='3'>Historic</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Greek Army</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Georgios Stanotas</target></link><space/>Commander of the Greek Cavalry Division in World War II.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;A Loyal and Zealous Soldier&quot; ( ), Christos Notaridis, ISBN 978-960-522-335-9</extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Contemporary</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Brazilian Army</target><part>Brazil</part></link>: Atade Barcelos Pereira, Regimento Osorio<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.osorio.org.br/cci_osorio.htm'>Atade Barcelos Pereira, Regimento Osorio</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>French Army</target><part>France</part></link>:<space/><link><target>Didier Courrges</target><part>Didier Courrges, Cadre Noir</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Italian Army</target><part>Italy</part></link>: Giulio Serafini, COMFOD 1<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cism-milsport.org/eng/b1_sport/06_equestrian/02_tc.asp'>Giulio Serafini, COMFOD 1</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Cavalry</target><part>USA</part></link>: Edwin Ramsey, 26th Cavalry regiment<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.edwinpriceramsey.com/'>Edwin Ramsey, 26th Cavalry regiment</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cavalry tactics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Elephantry</target></link>, a cavalry unit containing elephant-mounted troops</listitem><listitem><link><target>Heavy cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Horses in warfare</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Horses in World War I</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Horses in World War II</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Light cavalry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mounted police</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Royal Canadian Mounted Police</target></link>accorded the status of a regiment of Dragoons in 1921 and remained so until 1937.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armored reconnaissance</target></link><space/>- a modern role in most militaries for 'cavalry' titled units</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ebrey, Walthall, Palais (2006).<space/><italics>East Asia: A Cultural, Social, and Political History</italics>. Boston: Houghton Mifflin Company.</listitem><listitem>Ebrey, Patricia Buckley (1999). The Cambridge Illustrated History of China. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. ISBN 0-521-43519-6 (hardback); ISBN 0-521-66991-X (paperback).</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Military Operations Egypt & Palestine from the outbreak of war with Germany to June 1917<space/></arg><arg name="last">Falls<space/></arg><arg name="first">Cyril<space/></arg><arg name="series">Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence<space/></arg><arg name="author2">G. MacMunn<space/></arg><arg name="year">1930<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HM Stationery Office<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">610273484</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Military Operations Egypt & Palestine from June 1917 to the End of the War<space/></arg><arg name="last">Falls<space/></arg><arg name="first">Cyril<space/></arg><arg name="series">Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence<space/></arg><arg name="author2">A. F. Becke (maps)<space/></arg><arg name="year">1930<space/></arg><arg name="volume">2 Part I<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HM Stationery Office<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="oclc">644354483</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Military Operations Egypt & Palestine from June 1917 to the End of the War<space/></arg><arg name="last">Falls<space/></arg><arg name="first">Cyril<space/></arg><arg name="series">Official History of the Great War Based on Official Documents by Direction of the Historical Section of the Committee of Imperial Defence<space/></arg><arg name="author2">A. F. Becke (maps)<space/></arg><arg name="year">1930<space/></arg><arg name="volume">2 Part II<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HM Stationery Office<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="oclc">256950972</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Needham, Joseph (1986).<space/><italics>Science and Civilization in China: Volume 4, Physics and Physical Technology, Part 2, Mechanical Engineering</italics>. Taipei: Caves Books, Ltd.</listitem><listitem>Peers, C.J. (2006).<space/><italics>Soldiers of the Dragon: Chinese Armies 1500 BCAD 1840</italics>. Oxford: Osprey Publishing.</listitem><listitem>Menon, Shanti, Chariot racers of the Steppes,<space/><italics>Discover</italics>, April 1995 http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m1511/is_n4_v16/ai_16720826</listitem><listitem><link><target>Rodger, N. A. M.</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Safeguard of the Sea: A Naval History of Britain 6601649</italics>, W W Norton &amp; Co Ltd., 1999 ISBN 0-393-04579-X</listitem><listitem>Muir, William, Annals of the Early Caliphate: From Original Sources, Smith, Elder &amp; co., London, 1883</listitem><listitem>Pargiter, Frederick Eden, Dr., Chronology based on: Ancient Indian Historical Tradition, Oxford University Press, H. Milford, 1924, Reprint 1997</listitem><listitem>Lynn, John Albert,<space/><italics>Giant of the Grand Sicle: The French Army, 16101715</italics>, Cambridge University Press, 1997</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Cavalry</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.CavalryScouts.org'>CavalryScouts.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://napoleonistyka.atspace.com/French_Cavalry.html'>Napoleonic Cavalry</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.usregulars.com/Lippitt6.html'>Cavalry tactics from Francis J. Lippitt's, ''A Treatise on the Tactical Use of the Three Arms: Infantry, Artillery and Cavalry'' (1865)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lonesentry.com/articles/cavalry/index.html'>Cavalry in Mass (U.S. report on Russian cavalry organization and operations in World War II)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thehistorynet.com/wwii/blhorsewarriors/index2.html'>Italian Savoia Cavalry during World War 2</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.militaryhorse.org/'>Society of the Military Horse</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://kavallerie.8ung.at/'>Gesellschaft der Freunde der Kavallerie (German)</link></listitem><listitem>http://www.bharat-rakshak.com/LAND-FORCES/Army/Reg-Arm.html</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.counterpunch.org/hribal01182007.html'>''A Horse is Worth More than Riches''</link><space/>by Jason Hribal</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.historicaleye.com/horseandmule.html'>The Horse and Mule in the British Army during WW1</link></listitem><listitem>Historic films showing cavalry during World War I at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.europeanfilmgateway.eu/node/33/cavalry%20efg1914/multilingual:1/showOnly:video'>europeanfilmgateway.eu</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Cavalry</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Obsolete occupations</target></link><link><target>Category:Warfare of the Middle Ages</target></link><link><target>Category:Combat occupations</target></link></paragraph></article>