<article title='Diana_%28mythology%29'><paragraph><link><target>Image:Diane de Versailles Leochares 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The ''<link><target>Diana of Versailles</target></link>'', a 2nd-century Roman version in the Greek tradition of iconography</part></link><template><target>Ancient Roman religion</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Roman mythology</target></link>,<space/><bold>Diana</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-la</target><arg>djana</arg><arg></arg></template>) was the goddess of the<space/><link><target>hunting</target><part>hunt</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>moon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>childbirth</target></link>, being associated with wild animals and woodland, and having the power to talk to and control animals. She was equated with the<space/><link><target>Greek mythology</target><part>Greek goddess</part></link><space/><link><target>Artemis</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lar"><italics>Larousse Desk Reference Encyclopedia</italics>,<space/><link><target>The Book People</target></link>, Haydock, 1995, p. 215.</extension><space/>though she had an independent origin in Italy. Diana was worshipped in<space/><link><target>ancient Roman religion</target></link><space/>and is revered in<space/><link><target>Roman polytheistic reconstructionism</target><part>Roman Neopaganism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stregheria</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Dianic Wicca</target></link>, a largely feminist form of the practice, is named for her. Diana was known to be the virgin goddess of childbirth and women. She was one of the three maiden goddesses, Diana,<space/><link><target>Minerva (mythology)</target><part>Minerva</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vesta (mythology)</target><part>Vesta</part></link>, who swore never to marry.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Oak</target></link><space/>groves were especially sacred to her. According to mythology (in common with the Greek religion and their deity Artemis), Diana was born with her twin brother<space/><link><target>Apollo</target></link><space/>on the island of<space/><link><target>Delos</target></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Jupiter (mythology)</target><part>Jupiter</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Leto</target><part>Latona</part></link>. Diana made up a triad with two other Roman deities:<space/><link><target>Egeria (mythology)</target><part>Egeria</part></link><space/>the water nymph, her servant and assistant midwife; and<space/><link><target>Virbius</target></link>, the woodland god.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>Diana (pronounced with long '' and '') is an adjectival form developed from an ancient<space/><link><target>Asterisk#Historical linguistics</target><part>*</part></link><italics>divios</italics>, corresponding to later 'divus', 'dius', as in<space/><link><target>Dius Fidius</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dea Dia</target></link><space/>and in the neuter form<space/><italics>dium</italics><space/>meaning the sky.<extension extension_name='ref'>G.Dumzil<space/><italics>La religion Romaine archaique</italics><space/>Paris, 1974, part 3, chap. 1.</extension>It is rooted in Indoeuropean *d(e)y(e)w, meaning bright sky or daylight, from which also derived the name of<space/><link><target>Vedic</target></link><space/>god<space/><link><target>Dyaus</target></link><space/>and the Latin<space/><link><target>deus</target></link>, (god),<space/><italics>dies</italics>, (day, daylight), and &quot; diurnal&quot;, (daytime).</paragraph><paragraph>On the<space/><link><target>Linear B</target><part>Tablets of Pylos</part></link><space/>a theonym (<italics>diwia</italics>) is supposed as referring to a deity precursor of Artemis. Modern scholars mostly accept the identification.<extension extension_name='ref'>H. F. Pairault below cites three. Contrary G. Rousseau.</extension><template><target>qn</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The ancient Latin writers<space/><link><target>Varro</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cicero</target></link><space/>considered the etymology of Dna as allied to that of<space/><italics>dies</italics><space/>and connected to the shine of the Moon.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Mythology</heading><paragraph>The persona of Diana is complex and contains a number of archaic features. According to<space/><link><target>Georges Dumzil</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>G. Dumezil<space/><italics>La religion Romaine archaique</italics><space/>Paris 1974, part 3, chap.1.</extension><space/>it falls into a particular subset of celestial gods, referred to in histories of religion as<space/><italics>frame gods</italics>. Such gods, while keeping the original features of celestial divinities, i.e. transcendent heavenly power and abstention from direct rule in worldly matters, did not share the fate of other celestial gods in Indoeuropean religionsthat of becoming<space/><italics>dei otiosi</italics><space/>or gods without practical purpose,<extension extension_name='ref'>Mircea Eliade<space/><italics>Traite' d'histoire des religions</italics><space/>Paris, 1954.</extension><space/>since they did retain a particular sort of influence over the world and mankind.</paragraph><paragraph>The celestial character of Diana is reflected in her connection with light, inaccessibility, virginity, and her preference for dwelling on high mountains and in sacred woods.Diana therefore reflects the heavenly world (<italics>diuum</italics><space/>means sky or open air) in its sovereignty, supremacy, impassibility, and indifference towards such secular matters as the fates of mortals and states. At the same time, however, she is seen as active in ensuring the succession of kings and in the preservation of humankind through the protection of childbirth.</paragraph><paragraph>These functions are apparent in the traditional institutions and cults related to the goddess.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The institution of the<space/><link><target>rex Nemorensis</target></link>, Diana's<space/><italics>sacerdos</italics><space/>(priest) in the Arician wood, who held the position until someone else challenged and killed him in a duel, after breaking a branch from a certain tree of the wood. This ever open succession reveals the character and mission of the goddess as a guarantor of kingly status through successive generations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OvidFasti">Ovid<space/><italics>Fasti</italics><space/>III, 262-271.</extension><space/>Her function as bestower of authority to rule is also attested in the story related by Livy in which a Sabine man who sacrifices a<space/><link><target>:wikt:heifer</target><part>heifer</part></link><space/>to Diana wins for his country the seat of the Roman empire.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Titus Livius</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Ab Urbe Condita Libri (Livy)</target><part>Ab Urbe Condita</part></link></italics><space/>1:31-1:60.</extension></listitem><listitem>Diana was also worshipped by women who wanted to be pregnant or who, once pregnant, prayed for an easy delivery. This form of worship is attested in archeological finds of votive statuettes in her sanctuary in the<space/><link><target>nemus Aricinum</target></link><space/>as well as in ancient sources, e.g. Ovid.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OvidFasti"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>According to Dumezil the forerunner of all<space/><italics>frame gods</italics><space/>is an Indian epic hero who was the image (<link><target>avatar</target></link>) of the Vedic god Dyaus. Having renounced the world, in his roles of father and king, he attained the status of an immortal being while retaining the duty of ensuring that his dynasty is preserved and that there is always a new king for each generation.</paragraph><paragraph>The Scandinavian god<space/><link><target>Heimdallr</target></link><space/>performs an analogous function: he is born first and will die last. He too gives origin to kingship and the first king, bestowing on him regal prerogatives.Diana, although a female deity, has exactly the same functions, preserving mankind through childbirth and royal succession.</paragraph><paragraph>F. H. Pairault in her essay on Diana qualifies Dumzil's theory as &quot;<italics>impossible to verify</italics>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Dumezil's interpretation appears deliberately to ignore that of<space/><link><target>James G. Frazer</target></link>, who links Diana with the male god<space/><link><target>Janus</target></link><space/>as a divine couple. This looks odd as Dumzil's definition of the concept of<space/><italics>frame god</italics><space/>would fit well the figure of Janus.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Frazer<space/><italics>The golden bough</italics><space/>1922, chaps. 1, 12, 16.</extension><space/>Frazer identifies the two with the supreme heavenly couple Jupiter-Juno and additionally ties in these figures to the overarching Indoeuropean religious complex. This regality is also linked to the cult of trees, particularly<space/><link><target>Querquetulanae</target><part>oaks</part></link>.In this interpretative schema, the institution of the Rex Nemorensis and related ritual should be seen as related to the theme of the dying god and the<space/><link><target>King of the May</target><part>kings of May</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>J.G. Frazer<space/><italics>Dying gods</italics>, 1912; Geza Roheim<space/><italics>Animism, magic and the divine king</italics><space/>Routledge, London, 1972, part 3, (in particular chapter &quot;The king of May&quot;).</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Physical description</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bronze satuette Diana CdM Paris.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Gallo-Roman religion</target><part>Gallo-Roman</part></link><space/>bronze statuette of Diana (latter 1st century)</part></link>As a goddess of hunting, Diana often wears a short tunic and hunting boots. She is often portrayed holding a bow, and carrying a quiver on her shoulder, accompanied by a deer or hunting dogs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Artemis</arg><arg name="url">http://www.greekmythology.com/Olympians/Artemis/artemis.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-11</arg></template></extension><space/>Like Venus, she was portrayed as beautiful and youthful. The crescent moon, sometimes worn as a diadem, is a major attribute of the goddess.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Worship</heading><paragraph>Diana was initially just the hunting goddess,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Britanica15"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Diana, Roman religion</arg><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/topic/Diana-Roman-religion</arg><arg name="website">Encyclopaedia Britannica</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>associated with wild animals and woodlands. She also later became a<space/><link><target>moon goddess</target></link>, supplanting<space/><link><target>Titan (mythology)</target><part>Titan</part></link><space/>goddess<space/><link><target>Luna (goddess)</target><part>Luna</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Britanica15"></extension><space/>She also became the goddess of childbirth and ruled over the countryside. Catullus wrote a poem to Diana in which she has more than one alias: Latonia, Lucina, Iuno, Trivia, Luna.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.scribd.com/doc/35900939/Latin-Oration</arg><arg name="title">Latin Oration</arg><arg name="work">scribd.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Rome the cult of Diana should have been almost as old as the city itself as Varro mentions her in the list of deities to whom king<space/><link><target>Titus Tatius</target></link><space/>vowed a shrine. It is noteworthy that the list includes Luna and Diana Lucina as separate entities.Another testimony to the high antiquity of her cult is to be found in the<space/><italics>lex regia</italics><space/>of king<space/><link><target>Tullus Hostilius</target></link><space/>that condemns those guilty of incest to the<space/><italics>sacratio</italics><space/>to the goddess.</paragraph><paragraph>Diana was worshipped at a festival on August 13,<extension extension_name='ref'>The date coincides with the founding dates celebrated at Aricium. Arthur E. Gordon, &quot;On the Origin of Diana&quot;,<space/><italics>Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association</italics><space/><bold>63</bold><space/>(1932, pp. 177-192) p 178.</extension><space/>when King<space/><link><target>Servius Tullius</target></link>, himself born a slave, dedicated<space/><link><target>Temple of Diana (Rome)</target><part>her temple</part></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Aventine Hill</target></link><space/>in the mid-6th century BC. Being placed on the Aventine, and thus outside the<space/><italics><link><target>pomerium</target></link></italics>, meant that Diana's cult essentially remained a<space/><italics>foreign</italics><space/>one, like that of<space/><link><target>Dionysus</target><part>Bacchus</part></link>; she was never officially<space/><italics>transferred</italics><space/>to Rome as<space/><link><target>Juno (mythology)</target><part>Juno</part></link><space/>was after the sack of<space/><link><target>Veii</target></link>. It seems that her cult originated in<space/><link><target>Ariccia</target><part>Aricia</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Her cult at Aricia was first attested in Latin literature by<space/><link><target>Cato the Elder</target></link>, in a surviving quote by the late grammarian<space/><link><target>Priscian</target></link>. Supposed Greek origins for the Aricia cult are strictly a literary<space/><italics><link><target>topos</target></link></italics>. (Gordon 1932:178 note, and p. 181).</extension><space/>where her priest, the<space/><link><target>Rex Nemorensis</target></link><space/>remained. There the simple open-air fane was held in common by the Latin tribes,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>commune Latinorum Dianae templum</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Varro</target></link>,<space/><italics>Lingua Latina</italics><space/>V.43; the cult there was of<space/><italics>antiqua religione</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Pliny's Natural History</target></link>, xliv. 91, 242 and<space/><link><target>Ovid's Fasti</target></link><space/>III 327-331.</extension><space/>which Rome aspired to weld into a league and direct. Diana of the wood was soon thoroughly Hellenized,<extension extension_name='ref'>The<space/><italics><link><target>Potnia Theron</target></link></italics><space/>aspect of Hellenic Artemis is represented in<space/><link><target>Capua</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Segni</target><part>Signia</part></link>, Greek cities of<space/><link><target>Magna Graecia</target></link>, in the 5th century BC.</extension><space/>&quot;a process which culminated with the appearance of Diana beside Apollo in the first<space/><italics><link><target>lectisternium</target></link></italics><space/>at Rome&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon 1932:179.</extension><space/>Diana was regarded with great reverence and was a patroness of lower-class citizens, called plebeians, and<space/><link><target>slavery</target><part>slaves</part></link>; slaves could receive asylum in her temples. This fact is of difficult interpretation.<space/><link><target>Georg Wissowa</target></link><space/>proposed the explanation that it might be because the first slaves of the Romans must have been Latins of the neighbouring tribes.<extension extension_name='ref'>as quoted by Dumzil<space/><italics>La religion romaine archaique</italics><space/>Paris, 1974,part 3, chap. 1.</extension><space/>However, in Ephesus too there was the same custom of the asylum ().</paragraph><paragraph>According to Franoise Hlne Pairault's study,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Diana Nemorensis, desse latine, desse hellnise&quot; in<space/><italics>Mlanges d' archologie et d'histoire</italics><space/><bold>81</bold><space/>1969 p. 425-471.</extension><space/>historical and archaeological evidence point to the fact that both Diana of the Aventine and Diana Nemorensis were the product of the direct or indirect influence of the cult of Artemis spread by the Phoceans among the Greek towns of Campania<space/><link><target>Cumae</target><part>Cuma</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Capua</target></link>, which in turn passed it over to the Etruscans and the Latins by the 6th and 5th centuries BC.</paragraph><paragraph>The origin of the ritual of the rex Nemorensis should have to be traced to the legend of<space/><link><target>Orestes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Iphigenia</target></link><space/>more than that of Hippolitos. The formation of the Latin League led by Laevius (or Baebius) Egerius<extension extension_name='ref'>The historicity of this character is questioned by Dumzil as the name<space/><italics>Egerius</italics><space/>looks suspect to him.</extension><space/>happened under the influence of an alliance with the tyrant of Cuma Aristodemos<extension extension_name='ref'>Livy II 14, 5-9; Dionysius Halicarnasseus V 36, 1-4.</extension><space/>and is probably connected to the political events at end of the 6th century narrated by Livy and Dionysius, such as the siege of<space/><link><target>Ariccia</target><part>Aricia</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Porsenna</target></link>'s son Arruns. It is remarkable that the composition of this league does not reflect that of the Latin people who took part in the<space/><link><target>Latiar</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Feriae Latinae</target></link><space/>given by Pliny and it has not as its leader the<space/><italics>rex Nemorensis</italics><space/>but a<space/><italics>dictator Latinus</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pliny<space/><italics>Naturalis Historia</italics><space/>III 5 68-70.</extension><space/>It should thence be considered a political formation and not a traditional society founded on links of blood.</paragraph><paragraph>It looks as if the confrontation happened between two groups of Etruscans who fought for supremacy, those from<space/><link><target>Tarquinia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vulci</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Caere</target></link><space/>(allied with the Greeks of Capua) and those of<space/><link><target>Clusium</target></link>. This is reflected in the legend of the coming of Orestes to Nemi and of the inhumation of his bones in the Roman Forum near the temple of Saturn.<extension extension_name='ref'>Servius<space/><italics>ad Aeneidem</italics><space/>II 116; VI 136;<space/><link><target>Hyginus</target></link><space/><italics>Fabulae</italics><space/>261.</extension><space/>The cult introduced by Orestes at Nemi is apparently that of the<space/><link><target>Artemis Tauropolos</target></link>. The literary amplification<extension extension_name='ref'>Ovid<space/><italics>Metamorphoses</italics><space/>XIV 331-2<space/><italics>Scythicae regnum nemorale Dianae</italics>; Lucanus<space/><italics>Pharsalia</italics><space/>III 86 &quot;qua sublime nemus Scythicae qua regna Dianae&quot;. Silius Italicus<space/><italics>Punica</italics><space/>IV 367; VIII 362; Valerius Flaccus<space/><italics>Argonauticae</italics><space/>II 305.</extension><space/>reveals a confused religious background: different Artemis were conflated under the epithet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jean Bayet &quot;Les origines de l'Arcadisme romain&quot; p.135; M. P. Nilson<space/><italics>Griechische Religionsgeschichte</italics><space/>Munich 1955 p. 485 ff.</extension><space/>As far as Nemi's Diana is concerned there are two different versions, by<space/><link><target>Strabo</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Strabo V 249: .</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Servius Honoratus</target></link>. Strabo's version looks to be the most authoritative as he had access to first hand primary sources on the sanctuaries of Artemis, i.e. the priest of Artemis Artemidoros of Ephesus. The meaning of<space/><italics>Tauropolos</italics><space/>denotes an Asiatic goddess with lunar attributes, lady of the herds.<extension extension_name='ref'>Suidas s.v. : ; , . . Darehnberg -Saglio-Pottier<space/><italics>Dictionnaire des antiquits<space/></italics><space/>s.v. Diana fig.. 2357.</extension><space/>The only possible<space/><italics>interpretatio graeca</italics><space/>of high antiquity concerning<space/><italics>Diana Nemorensis</italics><space/>could have been the one based upon this ancient aspect of deity of light, master of wildlife.<space/><italics>Tauropolos</italics><space/>is an ancient epithet attached to<space/><link><target>Hecate</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Artemis</target></link><space/>and even<space/><link><target>Athena</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hesichius s.v. Tauropolai; Scholiasta ad Aristophanem<space/><italics>Lysistrata</italics><space/>447; Suidas above; Photius<space/><italics>Lexicon</italics><space/>s.v. Tuaropolos; N. Yalouris<space/><italics>Athena als Herrin der Pferde</italics><space/>in<space/><italics>Museum Helveticum</italics><space/><bold>7</bold><space/>1950 p. 99; E. Abel<space/><italics>Orphica, Hymni</italics><space/>I<space/><italics>in Hecaten</italics><space/>7.<space/><italics>Hymni magici</italics><space/>V<space/><italics>in Selenen</italics><space/>4.</extension><space/>According to the legend Orestes founded Nemi together with Iphigenia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Servius<space/><italics>ad Aeneidem</italics><space/>VI 136.</extension><space/>At Cuma the<space/><link><target>Sibyl</target><part>Sybil</part></link><space/>is the priestess of both<space/><link><target>Phoibos</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Trivia (mythology)</target><part>Trivia</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Aeneis</italics><space/>VI 35; F. H. Pairault p. 448 citing Jean Bayet<space/><italics>Origines de l' Hercule romain</italics><space/>p. 280 n. 4.</extension><space/><link><target>Hesiod</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Hesiod<space/><italics>Catalogue</italics>edited by Augusto Traversa, Naples 1951 p. 76 text 82; R. Merkelbach, M. L. West<space/><italics>Fragmenta Hesiodea Oxonii</italics><space/>1967, fragment 23.</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stesichorus</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Orestia</italics><space/>cited by Philodemos<space/><italics><space/></italics><space/>24 Gomperz II 52: fragment 38 B; Pausanias I 43, 1; II 22, 7.</extension><space/>tell the story according to which after her death Iphigenia was divinised under the name of Hecate, fact which would support the assumption that Artemis Tauropolos had a real ancient alliance with the heroine, who was her priestess in<space/><link><target>Taurid</target></link><space/>and her human paragon. This religious complex is in turn supported by the triple statue of Artemis-Hecate. A coin minted by P. Accoleius Lariscolus in 43 BC has been acknowledged as representing the archaic statue of Diana Nemorensis.<extension extension_name='ref'>A. Alfldi&quot;Diana Nemorensis&quot; in<space/><italics>American journal of Archaeology</italics><space/><bold>64</bold><space/>1960 p. 137-144.</extension><space/>It represents Artemis with the bow at one extremity, Luna-Selene with flowers at the other and a central deity not immediately identifiable, all united by a horizontal bar.</paragraph><paragraph>The iconographical analysis allows the dating of this image to the 6th century at which time there are Etruscan models. Two heads found in the sanctuary<extension extension_name='ref'>Excavation of 1791 by cardinal Despuig not mentioned in the report: cf. P. Riis who cites E. Lucidi<space/><italics>Memorie storiche dell'antichissimo municipio ora terra dell'Ariccia e delle sue colonie Genzano e Nemi</italics><space/>Rome 1796 p. 97 ff. finds at<space/><italics>Valle Giardino</italics>.</extension><space/>and the Roman theatre at Nemi,<extension extension_name='ref'>NSA 1931 p. 259-261 platesVI a-b.</extension><space/>which have a hollow on their back, lend support to this interpretation of an archaic Diana Trivia, in whom three different elements are associated. The presence of a Hellenised Diana at Nemi should be related to the presence of the cult in Campania, as Diana<space/><italics>Tifatina</italics><space/>was appelled<space/><italics>Trivia</italics><space/>in an imperial age inscription which mentions a<space/><italics>flamen Virbialis</italics><space/>dedicated by<space/><italics>eques</italics><space/>C. Octavius Verus.<extension extension_name='ref'>CIL X 3795.</extension><space/>Cuma too had a cult of a chthonic Hecate and certainly had strict contacts with Latium.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dionysius Hal. VII 6, 4: the people of Aricia help Aristdemos in bringing home the Etruscan booty.</extension><space/>The theological complex present in Diana looks very elaborated and certainly Hellenic, while an analogous Latin concept of Diana Trivia seems uncertain, as Latin sources reflect a Hellenised character of the goddess.<extension extension_name='ref'>Servius<space/><italics>Ad Aeneidem</italics><space/>IV 511; Ennius apud Varro<space/><italics>De Lingua Latina</italics><space/>VII 16; Catullus 34, 15.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Diana was one of the triple goddess, the same goddess being called Luna in heaven, Diana on earth, and<space/><link><target>Proserpina</target></link><space/>in hell.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Maurus Servius Honoratus</target><part>Servius</part></link>,<space/><italics>Commentary on Virgil's Aeneid</italics><space/>6.118.</extension><space/><link><target>Michael Drayton</target></link><space/>praises the Triple Diana in poem<space/><italics>The Man in the Moone</italics><space/>(1606): &quot;So these great three most powerful of the rest,<space/><link><target>Phoebe (mythology)</target><part>Phoebe</part></link>, Diana, Hecate, do tell. Her sovereignty in Heaven, in Earth and Hell&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alexander Chalmers, Samuel Johnson (1810),<space/><italics>The Works of the English Poets, from Chaucer to Cowper VOL.IV</italics><space/>p.421.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gil Harootunian, Gil Haroian-Guerin (1996).<space/><italics>The Fatal Hero: Diana, Deity of the Moon, As an Archetype of the Modern Hero in English Literature</italics>, p.261.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Edited by Cesare Barbieri and Francesca Rampazzi (2001),<space/><italics>Earth-Moon Relationships</italics><space/>p.7. ISBN 0-7923-7089-9.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Though some Roman patrons ordered marble replicas of the specifically Anatolian &quot;Diana&quot; of Ephesus, where the<space/><link><target>Temple of Artemis</target></link><space/>stood, Diana was usually depicted for educated Romans in her Greek guise. If she is accompanied by a deer, as in the<space/><italics><link><target>Diana of Versailles</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>illustration, above right</italics>) this is because Diana was the patroness of hunting. The deer may also offer a covert reference to the myth of<space/><link><target>Actaeon</target><part>Acteon</part></link><space/>(or Actaeon), who saw her bathing naked. Diana transformed Acteon into a stag and set his own hunting dogs to kill him.</paragraph><paragraph>Worship of Diana is mentioned in the<space/><link><target>Holy Bible</target><part>Bible</part></link>. In<space/><link><target>Acts of the Apostles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ephesian</target></link><space/>metal smiths who felt threatened by Saint Pauls preaching of Christianity, jealously rioted in her defense, shouting<space/><italics>Great is Diana of the Ephesians!</italics><space/>(Acts 19:28,<space/><link><target>New English Bible</target></link>). After the city secretary () quieted the crowd, he said,<space/><italics>Men of Ephesus, what person is there who does not know that the city of the Ephesians is the keeper (guardian) of the temple of the great Diana and of her image that fell from heaven ?</italics>&quot; (Acts 19:36)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Sanctuaries</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Diana Nemorensis</arg></template>Diana was an ancient goddess common to all Latin tribes. Therefore, many sanctuaries were dedicated to her in the lands inhabited by Latins. The first one is supposed to have been near<space/><link><target>Alba Longa</target></link><space/>before the town was destroyed by the Romans.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Ariccia</target><part>Aricia</part><trail>n</trail></link><space/>wood sanctuary near the<space/><link><target>lake of Nemi</target></link><space/>was Latin confederal as testified by the dedicatory epigraph quoted by Cato.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cato<space/><italics>Origins</italics><space/>fr. 62: &quot;Lucum Dianum In nemore Aricino Egerius Baebius (some scholars prefer to read Laevius) Tusculanus dedicavit dictator Latinus. Hi populi communiter: Tusculanus, Aricinus, Laurens, Coranus, Tiburtis, Pometius, Ardeatis, Rutulus.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>She had a shrine in Rome on the Aventine hill, according to tradition dedicated by king<space/><link><target>Servius Tullius</target></link>. Its location is remarkable as the Aventine is situated outside the<space/><link><target>pomerium</target></link>, i.e. original territory of the city, in order to comply with the tradition that Diana was a goddess common to all Latins and not exclusively of the Romans.</paragraph><paragraph>Other sanctuaries we know about are listed below:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Colle di Corne near<space/><link><target>Tusculum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pliny the Elder ''Naturalis Historia XVI, 242.</extension><space/>where she is referred to with the archaic Latin name of<space/><italics>deva Cornisca</italics><space/>and where existed a<space/><link><target>collegium</target></link><space/>of worshippers.<extension extension_name='ref'>CIL, 975; CIL XIV,2633.</extension></listitem><listitem>At vora, Portugal.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hifler, Joyce. &quot;The Goddess Diana. &quot; Witches Of The Craft.<space/><link type='external' href='http://witchesofthecraft.com/2012/01/12/the-goddess-diana/'></link><space/>(accessed November 27, 2012).</extension></listitem><listitem>Mount Algidus, also near Tusculum.<extension extension_name='ref'>Horace,<space/><italics>Carmina</italics><space/>I 21, 5-6;<space/><italics>Carmen Saeculare</italics>.</extension></listitem><listitem>At<space/><link><target>Lavinium</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>CIL XIV,2112.</extension></listitem><listitem>At<space/><link><target>Tibur</target></link><space/>(Tivoli), where she is referred to as<space/><italics>Diana Opifera Nemorensis</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>CIL, 3537.</extension></listitem><listitem>A sacred wood mentioned by Livy<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Livy</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Ab Urbe Condita Libri (Livy)</target><part>Ab Urbe Condita</part></link></italics><space/>XXVII 4.</extension><space/><italics>ad compitum Anagninum</italics><space/>(near<space/><link><target>Anagni</target></link>).</listitem><listitem>On Mount<space/><link><target>Tifata</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Capua</target></link><space/>in Campania.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roy Merle Peterson<space/><italics>The cults of Campania</italics><space/>Rome, Papers and Monographs of the American Academy in Rome, 1919, pp. 322-328.</extension></listitem><listitem>In<space/><link><target>Ephesus</target></link>, where she was worshipped as Diana of Ephesus and the temple<space/><link><target>Temple of Artemis</target><part>Artemision</part></link><space/>used to be one of world's seven wonders.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Diana by Augustus Saint-Gaudens 01.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>''Diana'' (1892 - 93),<space/><link><target>Augustus Saint-Gaudens</target></link>. Bronze,<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>In religion</heading><paragraph>Diana's cult has been related in<space/><link><target>Early Modern Europe</target></link><space/>to the cult of<space/><link><target>Nicevenn</target></link><space/>(a.k.a. Dame Habond, Perchta, Herodiana, etc.). She was related to myths of a female<space/><link><target>Wild Hunt</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Wicca</heading><paragraph>Today there is a<space/><link><target>Dianic Wicca</target><part>branch of Wicca</part></link><space/>named for her, which is characterized by an exclusive focus on the feminine aspect of the Divine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FalconDianic">Falcon River (2004)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.witchvox.com/va/dt_va.html?a=uswi&amp;amp;c=trads&amp;amp;id=8451'>''The Dianic Wiccan Tradition''</link>. From The Witches Voice. Retrieved 2007-05-23.</extension><space/>Diana's name is also used as the third divine name in a Wiccan energy chant- &quot;Isis Astarte Diana Hecate Demeter Kali Inanna&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">TRADITIONAL WICCA - CLASS 8</arg><arg name="url">http://bluemoonwicca.org/class08.html</arg><arg name="website">Blue Moon Wicca</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 July 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Stregheria</heading><paragraph>In Italy the old religion of<space/><link><target>Stregheria</target></link><space/>embraced the goddess Diana as Queen of the Witches; witches being the wise women healers of the time. Diana was said to have created the world of her own being having in herself the seeds of all creation yet to come. It was said that out of herself she divided the darkness and the light, keeping for herself the darkness of creation and creating her brother Apollo, the light. Diana was believed to have loved and ruled with her brother Apollo, the god of the Sun.<extension extension_name='ref'>Charles G. Leland,<space/><italics>Aradia: The Gospel of Witches</italics>, Theophania Publishing, US, 2010</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In language</heading><paragraph>Both the<space/><link><target>Romanian language</target><part>Romanian</part></link><space/>words for &quot;<link><target>fairy</target></link>&quot;<space/><italics>Zn</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="DEX"><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.toatecuvintele.ro/cuvant/Z%C3%A2n%C7%8E'>Zn</link></italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Dicionarul explicativ al limbii romne</target><part>DEX</part></link><space/>'98''</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Snzian</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Leonese language</target><part>Leonese</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Portuguese language</target><part>Portuguese</part></link><space/>word for &quot;water nymph&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>xana</target></link></italics>, and the Spanish word for &quot;shooting target&quot; and &quot;morning call&quot; (<italics>diana</italics>) seem to come from the name of Diana.</paragraph><heading level='3'>In the arts</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Paul-Jacques-Aim Baudry - Diana Reposing - Walters 3712.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Diana Reposing'' by<space/><link><target>Paul-Jacques-Aim Baudry</target></link>. The nude goddess, identified by the<space/><link><target>Lunar phase</target><part>crescent moon</part></link><space/>in her hair and the bow and<space/><link><target>quiver</target></link><space/>at her side, reclines on a blue drapery.</part></link><link><target>File:Chariot clock Diana, c. 1796.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>chariot clock</target></link><space/>depicting the goddess. France, c. 1796.</part></link>Since the<space/><link><target>Renaissance</target></link><space/>the myth of Diana has often been represented in the visual and dramatic arts, including the opera<space/><italics><link><target>L'arbore di Diana</target></link></italics>. In the 16th century, Diana's image figured prominently at the chteaus of<space/><link><target>Chteau de Fontainebleau</target><part>Fontainebleau</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Chteau de Chenonceau</target><part>Chenonceau</part></link>, &amp; at<space/><link><target>Chteau d'Anet</target><part>Anet</part></link>, in deference to<space/><link><target>Diane de Poitiers</target></link>, mistress of<space/><link><target>Henry II of France</target><part>Henri of France</part></link>. At<space/><link><target>Palace of Versailles</target><part>Versailles</part></link><space/>she was incorporated into the Olympian iconography with which<space/><link><target>Louis XIV of France</target><part>Louis XIV</part></link>, the Apollo-like &quot;Sun King&quot; liked to surround himself. Diana is also a character in the 1876<space/><link><target>Lo Delibes</target></link><space/>ballet<space/><italics><link><target>Sylvia (ballet)</target><part>Sylvia</part></link></italics>. The plot deals with Sylvia, one of Diana's nymphs and sworn to chastity, and Diana's assault on Sylvia's affections for the shepherd Amyntas.</paragraph><heading level='4'>In literature</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In &quot;<link><target>The Knight's Tale</target></link>&quot; in<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Chaucer</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Canterbury Tales</target></link></italics>, Emily prays to Diana to be spared from marriage to either Palamon or Arcite.</listitem><listitem>In &quot;Ode&quot; by<space/><link><target>John Keats</target></link>, he writes 'Browsed by none but Dian's fawns' (line 12)</listitem><listitem>In the sonnet &quot;To Science&quot; by<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target></link>, science is said to have &quot;dragged Diana from her car&quot;.</listitem><listitem>Diana Soren, the main character in<space/><link><target>Carlos Fuentes</target></link>' novel<space/><italics>Diana o la cazadora soltera</italics><space/>(<italics>Diana, or The Lone Huntress</italics>), is described as having the same personality as the goddess.</listitem><listitem>In &quot;Castaway&quot; by<space/><link><target>Augusta Webster</target></link>, women who claim they are virtuous despite never having been tempted are referred to as &quot;Dianas.&quot; (Line 128)</listitem><listitem>In Jonathan Swift's poem: &quot;The Progress of Beauty&quot;, as goddess of the moon, Diana is used in comparison to the 17th/early 18th century everyday woman Swift satirically writes about. Starts: 'When first Diana leaves her bed...'</listitem><listitem>In Geoffrey of Monmouth's<space/><italics><link><target>Historia Regum Britanniae</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;History of the Kings of Britain&quot;), Diana leads the Trojan Brutus to Britain, where he and his people settle.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>In Shakespeare</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>In<space/><link><target>William Shakespeare</target><part>Shakespeare's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Pericles, Prince of Tyre</target></link></italics><space/>Diana appears to Pericles in a vision, telling him to go to her temple and tell his story to her followers.</listitem><listitem>Diana is referenced in<space/><italics><link><target>As You Like It</target></link></italics><space/>to describe how Rosalind feels about marriage.</listitem><listitem>Diana is referred to in<space/><italics><link><target>Twelfth Night</target></link></italics><space/>when Orsino compares Viola (in the guise of Cesario) to Diana. &quot;Diana's lip is not more smooth and rubious&quot;</listitem><listitem>Speaking of his wife, Desdemona,<space/><link><target>Othello</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Moors</target><part>Moor</part></link><space/>says, &quot;Her name that was as fresh as Diana's visage, is now begrim'd and black as my own face.&quot;</listitem><listitem>There is a reference to Diana in<space/><italics><link><target>Much Ado About Nothing</target></link></italics><space/>where Hero is said to seem like 'Dian in her orb', in terms of her chastity.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>Henry IV, Part 1</target></link></italics>, Falstaff styles himself and his highway-robbing friends as &quot;Diana's foresters, gentlemen of the shade, minions of the moon&quot; who are governed by their &quot;noble and chase mistress the moon under whose countenance [they] steal&quot;.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>All's Well That Ends Well</target></link></italics><space/>Diana appears as a figure in the play and Helena makes multiple allusions to her, such as, &quot;Now, Dian, from thy altar do I fly...&quot; and &quot;...wish chastely and love dearly, that your Dian/was both herself and love...&quot; The Steward also says, &quot;...; Dian no queen of virgins,/ that would suffer her poor knight surprised, without/ rescue in the first assault or ransom afterward.&quot; It can be assumed that 'Dian' is simply a shortening of 'Diana' since later in the play when Parolles' letter to Diana is read aloud it reads 'Dian'.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yale University Press"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Cross</arg><arg name="first">Wilbur L.</arg><arg name="title">The Yale Shakespeare: the complete works</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">Barnes & Noble</arg><arg name="location">United States of America</arg><arg name="isbn">1-56619-104-1</arg><arg name="pages">365–399</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The goddess is also referenced indirectly in<space/><italics><link><target>A Midsummer Night's Dream</target></link></italics>. The character Hippolyta states &quot;And then the moon, like to a silver bow new bent in Heaven&quot;. She refers to Diana, goddess of the moon, who is often depicted with a silver hunting bow. In the same play the character Hermia is told by the Duke Theseus that she must either wed the character Demetrius &quot;Or on Diana's alter to protest for aye austerity and single life&quot;. He refers to her becoming a nun, with the goddesse Diana having connotations of chastity.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>The Merchant of Venice</target></link></italics><space/>Portia states &quot;I will die as chaste as Diana, unless I be obtained by the manner of my father's will&quot;. (I.ii)</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>Romeo and Juliet</target></link></italics>, Romeo describes Rosaline, saying that &quot;She hath Dian's wit&quot;.</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:Giampietrino 05.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Diana as the Huntress, by<space/><link><target>Giampietrino</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='4'>In painting and sculpture</heading><paragraph>Diana has been one of the most popular themes in art. Painters like<space/><link><target>Titian</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Peter Paul Rubens</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franois Boucher</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nicholas Poussin</target></link><space/>made use of her myth as a major theme. Most depictions of Diana in art featured the stories of Diana and<space/><link><target>Actaeon</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>Callisto (mythology)</target><part>Callisto</part></link>,or depicted her resting after hunting. Some famous work of arts with a Diana theme are :</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Diana and Actaeon (Titian)</target><part>Diana and Actaeon</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Diana and Callisto</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Death of Actaeon</target></link><space/>by Titian.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Diana and Callisto</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics>Diana Resting After Bath</italics>, and<space/><italics>Diana Getting Out of Bath</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Franois Boucher</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Diana Bathing With Her Nymphs</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Rembrandt</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Diana and Endymion</italics><space/>by Poussin.</listitem><listitem><italics>Diana and Callisto</italics>,<space/><italics>Diana and Her Nymph Departing From Hunt</italics>,<space/><italics>Diana and Her Nymphs Surprised By A Faun</italics><space/>by Rubens.</listitem><listitem><italics>Diana and Endymion</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Johann Michael Rottmayr</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The famous fountain at<space/><link><target>Palace of Caserta</target></link>, Italy, created by Paolo Persico, Brunelli, Pietro Solari, depicting Diana being surprised by Acteon.</listitem><listitem>A sculpture by<space/><link><target>Christophe-Gabriel Allegrain</target></link><space/>can be seen at the Muse du Louvre.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Diana (Saint-Gaudens)</target><part>&quot;Diana of the Tower&quot;</part></link></italics><space/>a copper statue by<space/><link><target>Augustus Saint-Gaudens</target></link><space/>was created as the weather vane for the second<space/><link><target>Madison Square Garden (1890)</target><part>Madison Square Garden</part></link><space/>in 1893. It now is on display at the<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Museum of Art</target></link></listitem><listitem>A<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dictionaryofsydney.org/item/18337'>sculpture</link><space/>by French sculptor Franois-Lon Sicard in the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cityofsydney.nsw.gov.au/waterexhibition/ornamentalfountains/ArchibaldFountain.html'>Archibald Fountain</link>, Sydney NSW Australia</listitem><listitem>In Parma at the convent of San Paolo, Antonio Allegri da Correggio painted the chamber of the Abbess Giovanna Piacenza's apartment. He was commissioned in 1519 to paint the ceiling and mantel of the fireplace. On the mantel he painted an image of Diana riding in a chariot possibly pulled by a stag.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>In<space/><italics>beaux arts</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:DianaAndPomona.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Pomona (mythology)</target><part>Pomona</part></link><space/>(left, symbolizing<space/><link><target>agriculture</target></link>), and Diana (symbolizing<space/><link><target>commerce</target></link>) as building decoration.</part></link><link><target>Beaux Arts architecture</target></link><space/>and garden design (late 19th and early 20th centuries) used classic references in a modernized form. Two of the most popular of the period were of<space/><link><target>Pomona (mythology)</target><part>Pomona</part></link><space/>(goddess of orchards) as a metaphor for Agriculture, and Diana, representing Commerce, which is a perpetual hunt for advantage and profits.</paragraph><heading level='4'>In film</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In<space/><link><target>Jean Cocteau</target></link>'s 1946 film<space/><italics><link><target>Beauty and the Beast (1946 film)</target><part>La Belle et la Bte</part></link></italics><space/>it is Diana's power which has transformed and imprisoned the beast.</listitem><listitem>Diana/<link><target>Artemis</target></link><space/>appears at the end of the 'Pastoral Symphony' segment of<space/><italics><link><target>Fantasia (1940 film)</target><part>Fantasia</part></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem>In his 1968 film<space/><italics><link><target>La Marie tait en noir</target></link></italics><space/><link><target>Franois Truffaut</target></link><space/>plays on this mythological symbol. Julie Kohler, played by Jeanne Moreau, poses as Diana/<link><target>Artemis</target></link><space/>for the artist Fergus. This choice seems fitting for Julie, a character beset by revenge, of which Fergus becomes the fourth victim. She poses with a bow and arrow, while wearing white.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>In opera</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Diana is a character in<space/><link><target>Hippolytus and Aricia</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>opera</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Jean-Philippe Rameau</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In the funeral oration of<space/><link><target>Diana, Princess of Wales</target></link><space/>in 1997, her brother drew an analogy between the ancient goddess of hunting and his sister - &quot;the most hunted person of the modern age&quot;.</listitem><listitem><link><target>William Moulton Marston</target></link><space/>used the Diana myth as a basis for<space/><link><target>Wonder Woman</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>For the album art of<space/><link><target>progressive metal</target></link><space/>band<space/><link><target>Protest the Hero</target></link>'s second studio album<space/><italics><link><target>Fortress (Protest the Hero album)</target><part>Fortress</part></link></italics>, Diana is depicted protected by rams and other animals. The theme of Diana is carried throughout the album.</listitem><listitem>DIANA Mayer &amp; Grammelspacher GmbH &amp; Co.KG, an airgun company, is named after Diana, the goddess of hunting.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;DIANA Mayer &amp; Grammelspacher GmbH &amp; Co.KG - THE DIANA TRADEMARK.&quot; COMPANY | THE DIANA TRADEMARK.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.diana-airguns.de/index.php?id=22&amp;amp;L=1&amp;amp;width=1920&amp;amp;height=1080'></link><space/>(accessed November 27, 2012).</extension></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Royal Netherlands Air Force</target></link><space/>323rd Squadron is named Diana and uses a depiction of Diana with her bow in its badge.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.f-16.net/units_article272.html</arg><arg name="title">F-16 Units - RNLAF 323rd squadron</arg><arg name="work">f-16.net</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The character of Diana from the video game<space/><italics><link><target>League of Legends</target></link></italics><space/>is largely based on the goddess.</listitem><listitem>She also is one of the main gods in the popular video game<space/><italics>Ryse</italics>, who help Marius Titus, the main character, fulfill his duty to Rome.</listitem><listitem>The character of Diana is the principal character in the children's novel<space/><italics>The Moon Stallion</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Brian Hayles</target></link><space/>(1978) and the BBC Television series of the same name<space/><italics>Diana</italics><space/>is played by the actress<space/><link><target>Sarah Sutton</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>In the manga and anime series<space/><link><target>Sailor Moon</target></link>, Diana is the feline companion to Chibiusa, Usagi's daughter. Diana is the daughter of Artemis and Luna. All of these characters are advisers to rulers of the kingdom of the moon and therefore have moon-associated names.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Artemis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Diana Nemorensis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dianic Wicca</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Janus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Domus de Janas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pachamama</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>A. Alfldi &quot;Diana Nemorensis&quot; in<space/><italics>American Journal of Archaeology</italics><space/><bold>64</bold><space/>1960 p.&amp;nbsp;137-144.</listitem><listitem>A. Alfldi<space/><italics>Early Rome and the Latins</italics><space/>Ann Arbor 1964 p.&amp;nbsp;47-100.</listitem><listitem>E. Paribeni &quot;A note on Diana Nemorensis&quot; in<space/><italics>American Journal of Archeology</italics><space/><bold>65</bold><space/>1961 p.&amp;nbsp;55.</listitem><listitem>P. J. Riis &quot;The Cult Image of Diana Nemorensis&quot; in<space/><italics>Acta Archaeologica</italics><space/>Kopenhagen<space/><bold>37</bold><space/>1966 p.&amp;nbsp;69 ff.</listitem><listitem>J. Heurgon in<space/><italics>Magna Graecia</italics><space/>1969 Jan. Feb. 1969 p.&amp;nbsp;12 ff.; March Apr. p.&amp;nbsp;1ff.</listitem><listitem>J.G. Frazer<space/><italics>Balder the Beautiful</italics><space/>II London 1913 p.&amp;nbsp;95 ff.; 302 ff.</listitem><listitem>L. Morpurgo &quot;Nemus Aricinum&quot; in<space/><italics>MonAntLincei</italics><space/><bold>13</bold><space/>1903 c. 300 ff.</listitem><listitem>A. Merlin &quot;L'Aventin dans l'antiquit&quot; Paris BFAR<space/><bold>97</bold><space/>1906.</listitem><listitem>G. Wissowa<space/><italics>Religion und Kultus der Rmer</italics><space/>Munich 1912 p.&amp;nbsp;198 ff.</listitem><listitem>F. Altheim<space/><italics>Griechischen Gtter im alten Rom</italics><space/>Giessen 1930 p.&amp;nbsp;93-172.</listitem><listitem>A.E. Gordon &quot;On the Origin of Diana&quot; in<space/><italics>Transactions of the AMerican Philological Association</italics><space/><bold>63</bold><space/>1932 p.&amp;nbsp;177ff.</listitem><listitem>A.E. Gordon<space/><italics>Local Cults in Aricia</italics><space/>University of California Publications in Classical Archaeology 2 1934 p.&amp;nbsp;1ff.</listitem><listitem>J. Heurgon &quot;Recherhes sur... Capoue prromaine&quot; in BFAR<space/><bold>154</bold><space/>Paris 1942 p.&amp;nbsp;307 ff.</listitem><listitem>J. Gag &quot;Apollon Romain&quot; in BFAR<space/><bold>182</bold><space/>Paris 1955.</listitem><listitem>J. Bayet<space/><italics>Histoire politique et psychologique de la religion romaine</italics><space/>Paris 1957 p.&amp;nbsp;20 ff., 39ff.</listitem><listitem>K. Latte<space/><italics>Rmische Religionsgeschichte</italics><space/>Munich 1960 p.&amp;nbsp;169-173.</listitem><listitem>R. Schilling &quot;Une victime des vicissitudes politiques, la Diane latine&quot; in<space/><italics>Hommages Jean Bayet, Collection Latomus</italics><space/><bold>45</bold><space/>Bruxelles 1960 p.&amp;nbsp;650 ff.</listitem><listitem>A. Momigliano &quot;Sul dies natalis del santuario federale di Diana sull' Aventino&quot; in<space/><italics>RAL</italics><space/><bold>17</bold><space/>1962 p.&amp;nbsp;387 ff.</listitem><listitem>G. Dumzil<space/><italics>La religion romaine archaque</italics><space/>Paris 1966 p.&amp;nbsp;398 ff.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target><arg>Diana</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.liverpoolmuseums.org.uk/picture-of-month/displaypicture.asp?venue=7&amp;amp;id=130'>''Landscape with Diana and Callisto'' painting</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wga.hu/art/d/domenich/diana.jpg'>''Diana and her Nymphs'' painting</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://warburg.sas.ac.uk/vpc/VPC_search/subcats.php?cat_1=5&amp;amp;cat_2=86'>The Warburg Institute Iconographic Database: ca 1150 images of Diana</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>-</target></template><template><target>Roman religion</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Diana (Mythology)</target></template><link><target>Category:Lunar goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Hunting goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Nature goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Childhood goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Virgin goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman goddesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Animal goddesses</target></link></paragraph></article>