<article title='Bill_Haley'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the singer</arg><arg>detailed information about his band</arg><arg>Bill Haley & His Comets</arg></template><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="{{More footnotes|article|date">February 2008}}
{{refimprove|date</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox musical artist</target><arg name="name"><space/>Bill Haley
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Bill Haley (1974).jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Bill Haley
</arg><arg name="background"><space/>solo_singer
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>William John Clifton Haley
</arg><arg name="alias"><space/>Jack Haley, Johnny Clifton
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1925|7|6|mf</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Highland Park, Michigan|Highland Park]], [[Michigan]], USA
</arg><arg name="death_cause"><space/>[[Myocardial infarction|Heart attack]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1981|2|9|1925|7|6|mf</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Harlingen, Texas|Harlingen]], [[Texas]], USA
</arg><arg name="origin"><space/>
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Rock and roll]], [[Country music|country]], [[rockabilly]]
</arg><arg name="occupations"><space/>Singer-songwriter, musician, [[bandleader]]
</arg><arg name="instrument"><space/>Vocals, guitar, [[slap bass]]
</arg><arg name="years_active"><space/>1946–1980
</arg><arg name="label"><space/>[[Decca Records|Decca]], [[Brunswick Records|Brunswick]] (UK), [[Cowboy Records|Cowboy]], [[Atlantic Records|Atlantic]], [[Keystone Records|Keystone]], [[Center Records|Center]], [[Holiday Records|Holiday]], [[Essex Records|Essex]], [[Warner Bros. Records]], [[Orfeón]], [[Dimsa Records|Dimsa]], [[Newtown Records|Newtown]], [[Guest Star Records|Guest Star]], [[Logo Records|Logo]], [[APT Records|APT]], [[Gone Records|Gone]], [[United Artists Records|United Artists]], [[Roulette Records|Roulette]], [[Sonet Records|Sonet]], [[Buddah Records|Buddah]], [[Antic Records|Antic]], [[Arzee Records|Arzee]], [[London Records|London]] (UK)
</arg><arg name="associated_acts"><space/>[[Bill Haley & His Comets]], [[The Down Homers]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>William John Clifton &quot;Bill&quot; Haley</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>h</arg><arg>eɪ</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>iː</arg></template>; July 6, 1925 February 9, 1981) was an American<space/><link><target>rock and roll</target></link><space/>musician. He is credited by many with first popularizing this form of music in the early 1950s with his group<space/><link><target>Bill Haley &amp; His Comets</target></link><space/>and million-selling hits such as &quot;<link><target>Rock Around the Clock</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>See You Later, Alligator</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Shake, Rattle and Roll</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Rocket 88</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Skinny Minnie</target></link>&quot;, and &quot;Razzle Dazzle&quot;. He has sold over 25 million records worldwide.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.seite3.ch/Bill+Haley+Radaumusiker/427172/detail.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Radaumusiker<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">seite3.ch</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 9, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Early life and career</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bill Haley, Pubilicity stil from 1955.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Sunday, August 7, 1955 rehearsal publicity photograph on the Ed Sullivan Show or Toast of the Town, CBS, Hartford, Connecticut</part></link>Bill Haley was born July 6, 1925 in<space/><link><target>Highland Park, Michigan</target><part>Highland Park</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Michigan</target></link>, as William John Clifton Haley. In 1929 the four-year-old Haley underwent an inner-ear mastoid operation which accidentally severed an optic nerve, leaving him blind in his left eye for the rest of his life.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fuchs"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Fuchs</arg><arg name="first1">Otto</arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley: The Father of Rock & Roll</arg><arg name="date">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Wagner</arg><arg name="isbn">9783866839014</arg><arg name="page">16</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 October 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>As a result of the effects of the<space/><link><target>Great Depression</target></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Detroit, Michigan</target><part>Detroit</part></link><space/>area, his father moved the family to<space/><link><target>Boothwyn, Pennsylvania</target><part>Boothwyn</part></link>, near<space/><link><target>Chester, Pennsylvania</target></link>, when Bill was seven years old. Haley's father William Albert Haley was from<space/><link><target>Kentucky</target></link><space/>and played the<space/><link><target>banjo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mandolin</target></link>, and his mother, Maude Green, who was originally from<space/><link><target>Ulverston</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cumbria, England</target><part>Cumbria</part></link>,<space/><link><target>England</target></link>, was a technically accomplished<space/><link><target>keyboardist</target></link><space/>with classical training.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.classicbands.com/haley.html</arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley and his Comets</arg><arg name="publisher">Classic Bands</arg></template></extension><space/>Haley told the story that when he made a simulated guitar out of cardboard, his parents bought him a real one.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. pages 15, 17. ISBN 0-8128-2909-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The anonymous sleeve notes accompanying the 1956 Decca album<space/><italics>Rock Around The Clock</italics><space/>describe Haley's early life and career thus: &quot;Bill got his first professional job at the age of 13, playing and entertaining at an auction for the fee of $1 a night. Very soon after this he formed a group of equally enthusiastic youngsters and managed to get quite a few local bookings for his band.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>The sleeve notes continue: &quot;When Bill Haley was fifteen [c. 1940] he left home with his guitar and very little else and set out on the hard road to fame and fortune. The next few years, continuing this story in a fairy-tale manner, were hard and poverty-stricken, but crammed full of useful experience. Apart from learning how to exist on one meal a day and other artistic exercises, he worked at an open-air park show, sang and yodelled with any band that would have him, and worked with a traveling medicine show. Eventually he got a job with a popular group known as the &quot;Down Homers&quot; while they were in Hartford, Connecticut. Soon after this he decided, as all successful people must decide at some time or another, to be his own boss again and he has been that ever since.' These notes fail to account for his early band, known as the Four Aces of Western Swing. During the 1940s Haley was considered one of the top cowboy yodelers in America as &quot;Silver Yodeling Bill Haley&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hillbilly-music.com/artists/story/index.php?id</arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley and the Saddlemen<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hillbilly-Music.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 9, 1981<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 4, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The sleeve notes conclude: &quot;For six years Bill Haley was a musical director of Radio Station WPWA in Chester, Pennsylvania, and led his own band all through this period. It was then known as Bill Haley's Saddlemen, indicating their definite leaning toward the tough Western style. They continued playing in clubs as well as over the radio around<space/><link><target>Philadelphia</target></link>, and in 1951 made their first recordings on Ed Wilson's Keystone Records in Philadelphia.&quot; On June 14, 1951 the Saddlemen recorded a cover of &quot;<link><target>Rocket 88</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bill Haley &amp; His Comets</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Bill Haley, 1974, Lige 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Bill Haley and the Comets performing during 1974</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Bill Haley & His Comets</arg></template>During the Labor Day weekend in 1952, the Saddlemen were renamed<space/><bold>Bill Haley with Haley's Comets</bold><space/>(inspired by the supposedly official pronunciation of<space/><link><target>Halley's Comet</target></link>, a name suggested by WPWA radio station program director, Bob Johnson, where Bill Haley had a live radio program from noon to 1 p.m., and in 1953, Haley's recording of &quot;<link><target>Crazy Man, Crazy</target></link>&quot; (co-written by him and his bass player,<space/><link><target>Marshall Lytle</target></link>, although Lytle would not receive credit until 2001) became the first rock and roll song to hit the American charts, peaking at no.15 on Billboard and no.11 on Cash Box. Soon after, the band's name was revised to<space/><bold>Bill Haley &amp; His Comets.</bold></paragraph><paragraph>In 1953, a song called &quot;<link><target>(We're Gonna) Rock Around the Clock</target><part>Rock Around the Clock</part></link>&quot; was written for Haley.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dawson 2005</extension><space/>He was unable to record it until April 12, 1954. Initially, it was relatively unsuccessful, peaking at no. 23 on the<space/><italics>Billboard</italics><space/>pop singles chart and staying on the charts for only one week.</paragraph><paragraph>Haley soon scored a major worldwide hit with a cover version of<space/><link><target>Big Joe Turner</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Shake, Rattle and Roll</target></link>&quot;, which went on to sell a million copies and was the first ever rock 'n' roll song to enter the British singles charts in December 1954, becoming a Gold Record. He retained elements of the original, but threw some country music aspects into the song (specifically, Western swing) and cleaned up the lyrics. Haley and his band were important in launching the music known as &quot;Rock and Roll&quot; to a wider, mostly white audience after a period of it being considered an underground genre.</paragraph><paragraph>When &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; appeared as the theme song of the 1955 film<space/><italics><link><target>Blackboard Jungle</target></link></italics><space/>starring<space/><link><target>Glenn Ford</target></link>, it soared to the top of the American<space/><italics><link><target>Billboard (magazine)</target><part>Billboard</part></link></italics><space/>chart for eight weeks. The single is commonly used as a convenient line of demarcation between the &quot;rock era&quot; and the music industry that preceded it.<space/><italics>Billboard</italics><space/>separated its statistical tabulations into 18901954 and 1955present. After the record rose to number one, Haley was quickly given the title &quot;Father of Rock and Roll&quot; by the media, and by teenagers who had come to embrace the new style of music. With the song's success, the age of rock music began overnight and instantly ended the dominance of the jazz and pop standards performed by<space/><link><target>Frank Sinatra</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jo Stafford</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Perry Como</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bing Crosby</target></link><space/>and others. Nevertheless, in the United Kingdom Haley was supported by former Dankworth Seven lead vocalist<space/><link><target>Frank Holder</target></link><space/>among others.</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; was the first record ever to sell over one million copies in both<space/><link><target>UK</target><part>Britain</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>West Germany</target><part>Germany</part></link><space/>and, in 1957, Haley became the first major American rock singer to tour Europe. Haley continued to score hits throughout the 1950s such as &quot;<link><target>See You Later, Alligator</target></link>&quot; and he starred in the first rock and roll musical films<space/><italics><link><target>Rock Around the Clock (film)</target><part>Rock Around the Clock</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Don't Knock the Rock</target></link></italics>, both in 1956. Haley was already 30 years old and so he was soon eclipsed in the United States by the younger, sexier<space/><link><target>Elvis Presley</target></link>, but continued to enjoy great popularity in Latin America, Europe and Australia during the 1960s.</paragraph><paragraph>Bill Haley and the Comets performed &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; on the<space/><link><target>Texaco Star Theater</target></link><space/>hosted by<space/><link><target>Milton Berle</target></link><space/>on Tuesday, May 31, 1955 on<space/><link><target>NBC</target></link><space/>in an a cappella and lip-synched version. Berle predicted that the song would go no. 1: &quot;A group of entertainers who are going right to the top.&quot; Berle also sang and danced to the song which was performed by the entire cast of the show. This was one of the earliest nationally televised performances by a rock and roll band and provided the new musical genre called &quot;rock and roll&quot; a much wider audience.</paragraph><paragraph>Bill Haley and the Comets were the first rock and roll act to appear on the iconic American musical variety series the<space/><link><target>Ed Sullivan Show</target></link><space/>on Sunday, August 7, 1955 on<space/><link><target>CBS</target></link><space/>in a broadcast that originated from the Shakespeare Festival Theater in Hartford, Connecticut. They performed a live version of &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot; with Franny Beecher on lead guitar and Dick Richards on drums. The band made their second appearance on the show on Sunday, April 28, 1957 performing the songs &quot;<link><target>Rudy's Rock</target></link>&quot; and &quot;Forty Cups of Coffee&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Bill Haley and the Comets appeared on<space/><italics><link><target>American Bandstand</target></link></italics><space/>hosted by<space/><link><target>Dick Clark</target></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>American Broadcasting Company</target><part>ABC</part></link><space/>twice in 1957, on the prime time show October 28, 1957 and on the regular daytime show on November 27, 1957. The band also appeared on Dick Clark's<space/><italics>Saturday Night Beechnut Show</italics>, also known as<space/><italics><link><target>The Dick Clark Show</target></link></italics>, a primetime TV series from New York on March 22, 1958 during the first season and on February 20, 1960, performing &quot;Rock Around the Clock&quot;, &quot;Shake, Rattle, and Roll&quot;, and &quot;Tamiami&quot;.<link><target>File:Bill Haley Elvis Presley 1955 Cleveland.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>Bill Haley and Elvis Presley at the Brooklyn High School Auditorium, Cleveland, Ohio, October 20, 1955</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Death and legacy</heading><paragraph>An admitted alcoholic (as indicated in a 1974 radio interview for the<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link>), Haley fought a battle with alcohol into the 1970s. Nonetheless, he and his band continued to be a popular touring act, benefiting from a 1950s nostalgia movement that began in the late 1960s and the signing of a lucrative record deal with the European<space/><link><target>Sonet Records</target><part>Sonet</part></link><space/>label. After performing for<space/><link><target>Elizabeth II</target><part>Queen Elizabeth II</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Royal Variety Performance</target></link><space/>on November 10, 1979, Haley made his final performances in South Africa in May and June 1980. Before the South African tour, he was diagnosed with a<space/><link><target>brain tumor</target></link>, and a planned tour of<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>in the autumn of 1980 was cancelled.</paragraph><paragraph>The October 25, 1980 edition of the German paper<space/><italics>Bild</italics><space/>reported that Haley had a brain tumor. It quoted British manager Patrick Maylan as saying that Haley &quot;had taken a fit and went over the seat. He didn't recognize anyone any more&quot; after being taken to his home in Beverly Hills. It also reported that a doctor at the clinic where Haley had been taken said, 'The tumor can't be operated on any more.'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bill Haley 1982. page 154">Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. page 154. ISBN 0-8128-2909-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics><link><target>Berliner Zeitung</target></link></italics><space/>reported a few days later that Haley had collapsed after a performance in Texas and been taken to the hospital in his home town of<space/><link><target>Harlingen, Texas</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bill Haley 1982. page 154"></extension><space/>However, this account is questionable as Bill Haley did not perform in the United States at all in 1980.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite his ill health, Haley began compiling notes for possible use as a basis for either a biographical film based on his life, or a published autobiography (accounts differ), and there were plans for him to record an album in<space/><link><target>Memphis, Tennessee</target></link>, when the brain tumor began affecting his behavior and he went back to his home in<space/><link><target>Harlingen, Texas</target><part>Harlingen</part></link>, where he died early in the morning of February 9, 1981.</paragraph><paragraph>Martha, Bill's widow, who was with him in these troubling times, denies he had a brain tumor as does his old, very close friend, Hugh McCallum. Martha and friends related that Bill did not want to go on the road any more and that ticket sales for that planned tour of Germany in the fall of 1980 were slow. According to McCallum, &quot;It's my unproven gut feeling that that [the brain tumor] was said to curtail talks about the tour and play the sympathy card.&quot;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It was obvious that his drinking problem was getting worse. By this time, Bill and Martha fought all the time and she told him to stop drinking or move out. He then did move out into a room in their pool house. Martha still took care of him and sometimes he would come in the house to eat, but he ate very little. &quot;There were days we never saw him,&quot; said his daughter Martha Maria.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline>In addition to Haley's drinking problems, it had also become obvious that he was having serious mental problems as well; Martha Maria said that, &quot;It was like sometimes he was drunk even when he wasn't drinking.&quot; After he'd been jailed by the Harlingen Police, Martha had the judge put Haley in the hospital where he was seen by a psychiatrist who said Bill's brain was overproducing a chemical, like adrenaline. The doctor prescribed a medication to stop the overproduction but said Bill would have to stop drinking. Martha said, &quot;This is pointless.&quot; She took him home, however, fed him and gave him his first dose. As soon as he felt better, he went back out to his room in the pool house and the downward spiral continued until his death on February 9, 1981.<extension extension_name='ref'>Falling Comet. Michael Hall. 2011. Texas Monthly, June 2011.</extension></preline></preblock><paragraph>Haley's death certificate listed &quot;Natural causes: Most likely heart attack&quot; as the 'Immediate Cause' of death. The next lines, 'Due to, or as a consequence of&quot; were blank.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. page 164. ISBN 0-8128-2909-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Haley made a succession of bizarre, mostly monologue late-night phone calls to friends and relatives in which he seemed incoherently drunk or ill. Haley's first wife has been quoted as saying, &quot;He would call and ramble and dwell on the past, his mind was really warped.&quot; A belligerent phone call to a business associate was taped and gives evidence of Haley's troubled state of mind.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll. John Swenson. 1982. Stein and Day. pages 155159. ISBN 0-8128-2909-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Media reports immediately following his death indicated Haley displayed deranged and erratic behavior in his final weeks, although there is little information about Haley's final days beyond a biography by John Swenson, released a year later, which described him painting the windows of his home black. After a small funeral service, Haley was cremated, although his widow Martha won't say what was done with the ashes.</paragraph><paragraph>Haley was posthumously inducted into the<space/><link><target>Rock and Roll Hall of Fame</target></link><space/>in 1987. His son Pedro represented him at the ceremony.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bruce Lee Smith"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.themonitor.com/articles/harlingen-22920-haley-pioneer.html</arg><arg name="title">Pioneer Haley almost forgotten in Harlingen</arg><arg name="author">Bruce Lee Smith</arg><arg name="publisher">AIM Media Texas</arg><arg name="date">February 6, 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>He has a star on the<space/><link><target>Hollywood Walk of Fame</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dawson, Jim and Whitcomb, Ian (2005).<space/><italics>Rock Around the Clock: The Record that Started the Rock Revolution!</italics>, p. 180. Hal Leonard Corporation. ISBN 0-87930-829-X</extension><space/>The Comets were separately inducted into the Hall of Fame as a group in 2012, after a rule change allowed the induction of backing groups (the Comets were mass-inducted alongside several other groups such as<space/><link><target>Hank Ballard</target></link>'s Midnighters and<space/><link><target>Gene Vincent</target></link>'s Blue Caps).</paragraph><paragraph>Songwriters<space/><link><target>Tom Russell</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dave Alvin</target></link><space/>addressed Haley's demise in musical terms with &quot;Haley's Comet&quot; on Alvin's 1991 album<space/><italics>Blue Blvd.</italics><space/><link><target>Dwight Yoakam</target></link><space/>sang backup on the tribute.</paragraph><paragraph>Surviving members of the 1954&amp;ndash;55 contingent of Haley's Comets reunited in the late 1980s and continued to perform for many years around the world. They released a concert DVD in 2004 on Hydra Records, played the<space/><link><target>Viper Room</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>West Hollywood</target></link><space/>in 2005, and performed at Dick Clark's American Bandstand Theater in<space/><link><target>Branson, Missouri</target></link>, beginning in 200607. As of 2014, only two members of this particular contingent are still alive (Joey Ambrose and Dick Richards), but they continue to perform in Branson and in Europe. At least two other groups also continue to perform in North America under the Comets name as of 2014.</paragraph><paragraph>In March 2007, the Original Comets pre-opened the Bill Haley Museum in<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link>, Germany.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rockithydra.de<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rockithydra<space/></arg><arg name="language">de<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rockithydra.de<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 4, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>On October 27, 2007, ex-Comets guitar player Bill Turner opened the Bill Haley Museum for the public.</paragraph><paragraph>Two of Haley's children, Bill Haley Jr. and Gina Haley, are themselves musicians and have in recent years recorded albums of their father's music and headlined tribute musical shows.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Bill+Haley+Columbia+Pictures+1956.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bill Haley on a lobby card from the 1956 Columbia Pictures film ''Rock Around The Clock''. (One hair lock is styled into a<space/><link><target>kiss curl</target></link>)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='4'>Asteroid</heading><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>Main article<space/><link><target>79896 Billhaley</target></link></italics></listitem></list><paragraph>In February 2006, the<space/><link><target>International Astronomical Union</target></link><space/>announced the naming of<space/><link><target>asteroid</target></link><space/><link><target>79896 Billhaley</target></link><space/>to mark the 25th anniversary of Bill Haley's death.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Children</heading><paragraph>Married three times, Bill Haley had at least ten children. John W. Haley, his eldest son, wrote<space/><italics>Sound and Glory</italics>, a biography of Haley,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rockabillyhall.com/BillHaley.html</arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley 1925–1981</arg><arg name="publisher">Rockabilly Hall of Fame</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 24, 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>and had another child, Sharyn, with his first wife, Dorothy Crowe. His youngest daughter,<space/><link><target>Gina Haley</target></link>, is a professional musician based in<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carman, Tim.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.houstonpress.com/1995-05-18/music/rock-and-roll-royalty/1'>&quot;Rock and Roll Royalty&quot;</link>, &quot;<link><target>The Houston Press</target></link>&quot;, Houston, May 18, 1995.</extension><space/>Scott Haley is an athlete. His youngest son Pedro is also a musician.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bruce Lee Smith"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He also had a daughter, Martha Maria, from his last marriage with Martha Velasco.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bruce Lee Smith"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bill Haley Jr. (Haley's second son and first with Joan Barbara &quot;Cuppy&quot; Haley-Hahn) publishes a regional business magazine in Southeastern Pennsylvania (<italics>Route 422 Business Advisor</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.422business.com/about_us.html</arg><arg name="title">Route 422 Business Advisor – About Us</arg><arg name="publisher">Route 422 Business Advisor</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 24, 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>He sings and plays guitar with a band called &quot;Bill Haley and the Satellites,&quot; and released a CD in 2011.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rockabillyhall.com/Extra.html#already</arg><arg name="title">Already Here – Bill Haley & The Satellites</arg><arg name="publisher">Rockabilly Hall of Fame</arg><arg name="date">February 7, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>He also has occasionally appeared with the &quot;Original Comets&quot; at the Bubba Mac Shack in<space/><link><target>Somers Point, New Jersey</target></link>, from 20042011,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://jerseyshorenightbeat.blogspot.com/2011/10/blog-post.html</arg><arg name="title">Jersey Shore Nightbeat</arg><arg name="publisher">Jersey Shore Nightbeat</arg><arg name="date">October 31, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>and at the Twin Bar re-dedication ceremony in<space/><link><target>Gloucester City, New Jersey</target></link>, in 2007. In February 2011, he formed a tribute band &quot;Bill Haley Jr. and the Comets,&quot; performing his father's music and telling the stories behind the songs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.montgomerynews.com/articles/2011/11/17/entertainment/doc4ec3cf37e92da127171573.txtl</arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley (Jr.) & Comets rock out again!</arg><arg name="author">Mike Morsch</arg><arg name="publisher">Montgomery News</arg><arg name="date">November 17, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Published biographies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1980, Haley began working on an autobiography entitled<space/><italics>The Life and Times of Bill Haley</italics><space/>but died after completing only 100 pages. The work is registered with the<space/><link><target>U.S. Copyright Office</target></link><space/>but has yet to be released to the public.</listitem><listitem>In 1982, John Swenson wrote<space/><italics>Bill Haley: The Daddy of Rock and Roll</italics><space/>(published in the UK under the title,<space/><italics>Bill Haley</italics>).</listitem><listitem>In 1990, Haley's eldest son, John W. Haley, along with John von Holle wrote<space/><italics>Sound and Glory</italics>, a biography focusing mostly on Haley's early life and peak career years. This book is out of print.</listitem><listitem>A German language biography was published soon after Haley's death, written by Peter Cornelsen and Harald D. Kain.</listitem><listitem>A book on the history of Haley's most famous recording,<space/><italics>Rock Around the Clock: The Record That Started the Rock Revolution</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Jim Dawson</target></link><space/>was published in June 2005.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rockabillyhall.com/Extra.html#clockbook<space/></arg><arg name="title">"EXTRA!" Page 1 / Bill Haley and the Comets<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rockabillyhall.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 4, 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Film portrayals</heading><paragraph>Unlike his contemporaries, Bill Haley has rarely been portrayed on screen. Following the success of<space/><italics><link><target>The Buddy Holly Story</target></link></italics><space/>in 1978, Haley expressed interest in having his life story committed to film, but this never came to fruition. In the 1980s and early 1990s, numerous media reports emerged that plans were underway to do a biopic based upon Haley's life, with<space/><link><target>Beau Bridges</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jeff Bridges</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Ritter</target></link><space/>all at one point being mentioned as actors in line to play Haley (according to<space/><italics><link><target>Goldmine (magazine)</target><part>Goldmine Magazine</part></link></italics>, Ritter attempted to buy the film rights to<space/><italics>Sound and Glory</italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>Bill Haley has also been portrayed not always in a positive light in several &quot;period&quot; films:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>John Paramor in<space/><italics><link><target>Shout! The Story of Johnny O'Keefe</target></link></italics><space/>(1985)</listitem><listitem>Michael Daingerfield in<space/><italics>Mr. Rock 'n' Roll: The Alan Freed Story</italics><space/>(1999)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dicky Barrett</target></link><space/>(of<space/><link><target>The Mighty Mighty Bosstones</target></link>) in<space/><italics><link><target>Shake, Rattle and Roll: An American Love Story</target></link></italics><space/>(also 1999)</listitem></list><paragraph>In March 2005, the British network<space/><link><target>British Sky Broadcasting</target><part>Sky TV</part></link><space/>reported that<space/><link><target>Tom Hanks</target></link><space/>was planning to produce a biopic on the life of Bill Haley, with production tentatively scheduled to begin in 2006.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sky.com/showbiz/picture_gallery/0,,50004-1175946-2,00.html'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.sky.com/showbiz/picture_gallery/0,,50004-1175946-2,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20130903075705<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>However this rumor was quickly debunked by Hanks.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Discography</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bill Haley Comets Ed Sullivan 1957.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Sunday, April 28, 1957 second appearance on the Ed Sullivan Show rehearsal photograph, CBS</part></link>Before the formation of Bill Haley and the Saddlemen, which later became the Comets, Haley released several singles with other groups. Dates are approximate due to lack of documentation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.billhaleycentral.com<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bill Haley Database<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Billhaleycentral.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 4, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As<space/><bold>Bill Haley and the Four Aces of Western Swing</bold>:<space/></paragraph><paragraph>1948</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Too Many Parties and Too Many Pals</italics><space/>(vocal by Tex King)/<italics>Four Leaf Clover Blues</italics><space/>(<link><target>Cowboy Records</target><part>Cowboy</part></link><space/>CR1201) August 1948<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Billboard Record Review Aug 14, 1948 page 121</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>1949</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Tennessee Border/Candy Kisses</italics><space/>(Cowboy CR1202) March 1949<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Billboard Advance Folk Record Releases Mar 19, 1949 page 38</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>As<space/><bold>Johnny Clifton and His String Band</bold>:</paragraph><paragraph>1950</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Stand Up and Be Counted/Loveless Blues</italics><space/>(<link><target>Center Records</target><part>Center</part></link><space/>C102)</listitem></list><paragraph>Many Haley discographies list two 1946 recordings by the<space/><link><target>Down Homers</target></link><space/>released on the<space/><link><target>Vogue Records</target></link><space/>label as featuring Haley. Haley historian Chris Gardner, as well as surviving members of the group, have confirmed that the two singles: &quot;Out Where the West Winds Blow&quot;/&quot;Who's Gonna Kiss You When I'm Gone&quot; (Vogue R736) and &quot;Boogie Woogie Yodel&quot;/&quot;Baby I Found Out All About You&quot; (Vogue R786) do not feature Haley.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://thegardnerfamily.org/haley/discography/recordings.html'>Thegardnerfamily.org</link></extension><space/>However, the tracks were nonetheless included in the compilation box set<space/><italics>Rock 'n' Roll Arrives</italics><space/>released by<space/><link><target>Bear Family Records</target></link><space/>in 2006.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>See the<space/><link><target>Bill Haley &amp; His Comets discography</target><part>discography of Bill Haley &amp; His Comets</part></link><space/>for a list of the singles and albums released by Haley with the Saddlemen and the Comets from 1950 onwards.</italics></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Unreleased recordings</heading><paragraph>Bill Haley recorded prolifically during the 1940s, often at the radio stations where he worked, or in formal studio settings. Virtually none of these recordings were ever released. Liner notes for a 2003 CD release by<space/><link><target>Hydra Records</target></link><space/>entitled<space/><italics>Bill Haley and Friends Vol. 2: The Legendary Cowboy Recordings</italics><space/>reveal that several additional Cowboy label single releases were planned for the Four Aces, but this never occurred.</paragraph><paragraph>A number of previously unreleased Haley country-western recordings from the 19461950 period began to emerge near the end of Haley's life, some of which were released by the<space/><link><target>Arzee Records</target><part>Arzee</part></link><space/>label, with titles such as &quot;Yodel Your Blues Away&quot; and &quot;Rose of My Heart.&quot; Still more demos, alternate takes, and wholly unheard-before recordings have been released since Haley's death. Notable examples of such releases include the albums<space/><italics>Golden Country Origins</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Grassroots Records</target></link><space/>of Australia and<space/><italics>Hillbilly Haley</italics><space/>by the British label,<space/><link><target>Rollercoaster Records</target><part>Rollercoaster</part></link>, as well as the aforementioned German release by Hydra Records. In 2006,<space/><link><target>Bear Family Records</target></link><space/>of Germany released what is considered to be the most comprehensive (yet still incomplete) collection of Haley's 19461950 recordings as part of its Haley box set<space/><italics>Rock n' Roll Arrives</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Compositions</heading><paragraph>Bill Haley's compositions included &quot;Four Leaf Clover Blues&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Crazy Man, Crazy</target></link>&quot;, &quot;What'Cha Gonna Do&quot;, &quot;Fractured&quot;, &quot;Live It Up&quot;, &quot;Farewell, So Long, Goodbye&quot;, &quot;Real Rock Drive&quot;, &quot;Rocking Chair on the Moon&quot;, &quot;Sundown Boogie&quot;, &quot;Green Tree Boogie&quot;, &quot;Tearstains on My Heart&quot;, &quot;Down Deep in My Heart&quot;, &quot;Straight Jacket&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Birth of the Boogie</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Two Hound Dogs</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Rock-A-Beatin' Boogie</target></link>&quot;, &quot;Hot Dog Buddy Buddy&quot;, &quot;R-O-C-K&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Rudy's Rock</target></link>&quot;, &quot;Calling All Comets&quot;, &quot;Tonight's the Night&quot;, &quot;Hook, Line and Sinker&quot;, &quot;Sway with Me&quot;, &quot;Paper Boy (On Main Street U.S.A.)&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Skinny Minnie</target></link>&quot;, &quot;B.B. Betty&quot;, &quot;Eloise&quot;, &quot;Whoa Mabel!&quot;, &quot;Vive la Rock and Roll&quot;, &quot;I've Got News For You&quot;, &quot;So Right Tonight&quot;, &quot;Ana Maria&quot;, &quot;Yucatn Twist&quot;, &quot;Football Rock and Roll&quot;, and &quot;Chick Safari&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>He also wrote or co-wrote songs for other artists such as &quot;Calypso Rock&quot; for Dave Day and The Red Coats on Kapp in 1956, &quot;A.B.C. Rock&quot; and &quot;Rocky the Rockin' Rabbit&quot; for<space/><link><target>Sally Starr (TV hostess)</target><part>Sally Starr</part></link><space/>on Arcade, &quot;Toodle-Oo-Bamboo&quot; for Ray Coleman and His Skyrockets on Skyrocket Records in 1959, &quot;The Cat&quot; for Cappy Bianco, and &quot;(Ya Gotta) Sing For the Ladies&quot; and &quot;Butterfly Love&quot; for Ginger Shannon and Johnny Montana in 1960 on Arcade as well as the unissued &quot;I'm Shook&quot; in 1958.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Quotations</heading><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>Frankly, our market is the teenagers. They are the ones we constantly try to please. We keep very close to them, listening for their new expressions and asking what they want in the way of music.</arg></template><italics><link><target>NME</target></link></italics><space/>October 1955<extension extension_name='ref' name="NME Rock 'N' Roll Years"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>John
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Tobler
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>1st
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Reed International Books Ltd 
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>19
</arg><arg name="id"><space/>CN 5585</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>There has to be a Cadillac music and a Ford music. Tchaikovsky and Bach is Cadillac music, while we play more down-to-earth Ford music. It's got a good solid beat that can't be missed... definitely designed for teenage kids to dance to.</arg></template><italics><link><target>NME</target></link></italics><space/>January 1957<extension extension_name='ref' name="NME Rock 'N' Roll Years 2"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>John
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Tobler
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>NME Rock 'N' Roll Years
</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>1st
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Reed International Books Ltd 
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>36
</arg><arg name="id"><space/>CN 5585</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Grammy Hall of Fame</heading><paragraph>The following recording by Bill Haley was inducted into the<space/><link><target>Grammy Hall of Fame</target></link>, which is a special Grammy award established in 1973 to honor recordings that are at least 25 years old and that have &quot;qualitative or historical significance.&quot;</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablecell colspan="6" style="text-align:center;"><bold>Bill Haley: Grammy Hall of Fame</bold><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.grammy.org/recording-academy/awards/hall-of-fame'>Grammy Hall of Fame Database</link>.</extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Year Recorded</tablehead><tablehead>Title</tablehead><tablehead>Genre</tablehead><tablehead>Label</tablehead><tablehead>Year Inducted</tablehead><tablehead>Notes</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow align="center"><tablecell>1954</tablecell><tablecell>&quot;<link><target>Rock Around the Clock</target></link>&quot;</tablecell><tablecell>Rock &amp; Roll (single)</tablecell><tablecell>Decca Records</tablecell><tablecell>1982</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Jim Dawson,<space/><italics>Rock Around the Clock: The Record That Started the Rock Revolution!</italics><space/>(San Francisco: Backbeat Books, 2005)</listitem><listitem>John W. Haley and John von Holle,<space/><italics>Sound and Glory</italics><space/>(Wilmington, DE: Dyne-American, 1990)</listitem><listitem>John Swenson,<space/><italics>Bill Haley</italics><space/>(London: W.H. Allen, 1982)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bill-haley.com/'>Bill Haley's new Comets web site</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/buddycruiser/bio4.html%3F1054745371300&amp;amp;date=2009-10-25+16:42:21'>Melody Manor (Bill Haley's house)</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://maps.google.com/maps?li=rwp&amp;amp;q=3190+FOULK+RD,+MARCUS+HOOK,+PA+19061&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;om=1&amp;amp;z=16&amp;amp;ll=39.850902,-75.484078&amp;amp;spn=0.007215,0.021458&amp;amp;iwloc=A'>Google Map</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>IMDb name</target><arg name="id">0006426</arg><arg name="name">Bill Haley</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.billhaleyjrandthecomets.com/'>Bill Haley Jr. and the Comets site</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Bill Haley &amp; His Comets</target></template><template><target>1987 Rock and Roll Hall of Fame</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Haley, William John Clifton
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Haley, Bill; Clifton, Johnny; Gregory, Scott; Haley, Jack
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Rock and roll music pioneer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>July 6, 1925
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Highland Park, Michigan]], US
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>February 9, 1981
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Harlingen, Texas]], US
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Haley, Bill</target></template><link><target>Category:Bill Haley</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1925 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1981 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Highland Park, Michigan</target></link><link><target>Category:Bill Haley &amp; His Comets members</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of English descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American radio personalities</target></link><link><target>Category:American rock singers</target></link><link><target>Category:American rockabilly guitarists</target></link><link><target>Category:Musicians from Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Delaware County, Pennsylvania</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Harlingen, Texas</target></link><link><target>Category:Rock and Roll Hall of Fame inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:American bandleaders</target></link><link><target>Category:Decca Records artists</target></link><link><target>Category:Songwriters from Michigan</target></link><link><target>Category:Yodelers</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century American singers</target></link><link><target>Category:American rock guitarists</target></link><link><target>Category:American male singers</target></link><link><target>Category:Singers from Pennsylvania</target></link></paragraph></article>