<article title='Epistle_to_the_Hebrews'><paragraph><template><target>Books of the New Testament</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Epistle to the Hebrews</bold>, or<space/><bold>Letter to the Hebrews</bold>, or in the Greek manuscripts, simply<space/><bold>To the Hebrews</bold><space/>( )<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Greek New Testament</italics>, Edited by Kurt Aland, Matthew Black, Carlo M. Martini, Bruce M. Metzger, and Allen Wikgren, in cooperation with the Institute for New Testament Textual Research, 2nd edition, United Bible Societies, 1973</extension><space/>is a text of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>. Its author refers to it as a &quot;word of exhortation&quot;,<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>13:22</arg></template><space/>using the same term used in<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>13:15</arg></template><space/>to describe a sermon. Since the<space/><link><target>Early Christianity</target><part>earliest days of the Church</part></link>, its<space/><link><target>Antilegomena</target><part>authorship and canonicity have been debated</part></link>. The text is traditionally attributed to<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target></link>, but doubt on<space/><link><target>Authorship of the Pauline epistles</target><part>Pauline authorship</part></link><space/>is reported already by<space/><link><target>Eusebius</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;some have rejected the Epistle to the Hebrews, saying that it is disputed by the church of Rome, on the ground that it was not written by Paul.&quot; Eusebius,<space/><italics>Hist. Eccl.</italics><space/>3.3.5 (<link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.viii.iii.html'>text</link>); cf. also 6.20.3 (<link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.xi.xx.html'>text</link>).</extension><space/>and modern biblical scholarship considers its authorship unknown,<extension extension_name='ref'>Alan C. Mitchell,<space/><italics>Hebrews</italics><space/>(Liturgical Press, 2007) page 6.</extension><space/>perhaps written in deliberate imitation of the style of Paul.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bart D. Ehrman,<space/><italics>Forged: Writing in the Name of God--Why the Bible's Authors Are Not Who We Think They Are</italics><space/>(HarperCollins, 2011) page 23.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Clare K. Rothschild,<space/><italics>Hebrews as Pseudepigraphon: The History and Significance of the Pauline Attribution of Hebrews</italics><space/>(Mohr Siebeck, 2009) page 4.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Scholars of Greek consider its writing to be more polished and eloquent than any other book of the New Testament. The book has earned the reputation of being a masterpiece.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Powell">Powell, Mark A.<space/><italics>Introducing the New Testament: a historical, literary, and theological survey</italics>. Baker Academic, 2009. ISBN 978-0-8010-2868-7</extension><space/>It also has been described as an intricate New Testament book.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mackie">Mackie, Scott D.<space/><italics>Eschatology and Exhortation in the Epistle to the Hebrews.</italics><space/>Tbingen: Mohr Siebeck, 2007. ISBN 978-3-16-149215-0</extension><space/>Scholars believe it was written for<space/><link><target>Jewish Christians</target></link><space/>who lived in<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem</target><part>Jerusalem</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Powell"></extension><space/>Its purpose was to exhort Christians to persevere in the face of persecution. The theme of the epistle is the doctrine of the person of Christ and his role as<space/><link><target>Mediator (Christ as Mediator)</target><part>mediator between God and humanity</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The epistle opens with an exaltation of Jesus as &quot;the radiance of God's glory, the express image of his being, and upholding all things by his powerful word&quot;.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>1:1–3</arg><arg></arg><arg>1:1–3</arg></template><space/>The epistle presents Jesus with the titles &quot;pioneer&quot; or &quot;forerunner&quot;, &quot;Son&quot; and &quot;<link><target>Son of God</target></link>&quot;, &quot;priest&quot; and &quot;<link><target>high priest</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mason">Mason, Eric F.<space/><italics>You Are a Priest Forever: Second Temple Jewish Messianism and the Priestly Christology of the Epistle to the Hebrews.</italics><space/>(STDJ 74; Leiden/Boston: Brill, 2008). ISBN 978-90-04-14987-8</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The epistle casts Jesus as both exalted Son and high priest, a unique dual<space/><link><target>Christology</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mackie, Scott D. &quot;Confession of the Son of God in the Exordium of Hebrews&quot;.<space/><italics>Journal for the Study of the New Testament,<space/></italics><space/>30.4 (2008)</extension><space/></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph>Hebrews uses Old Testament quotations interpreted in light of first century rabbinical Judaism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Utley, R. J.:<space/><italics>The Superiority of the New Covenant: Hebrews</italics>. Bible Lessons International; Marshall, Texas: 1999, Volume 10, p. 1.</extension><space/>New Testament and<space/><link><target>Second Temple Judaism</target></link><space/>scholar Eric Mason argues that the conceptual background of the priestly Christology of the Epistle to the Hebrews closely parallels presentations of the messianic priest and<space/><link><target>Melchizedek</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Qumran</target></link><space/>scrolls.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mason"></extension><space/>In both Hebrews and Qumran a priestly figure is discussed in the context of a Davidic figure; in both cases a divine decree appoints the priests to their eschatological duty; both priestly figures offer an eschatological sacrifice of atonement. Although the author of Hebrews was not directly influenced by Qumran's &quot;Messiah of Aaron&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Oegema, Gerbern S. &quot;You Are a Priest Forever&quot; book review.<space/><italics>Catholic Biblical Quarterly,<space/></italics><space/>Oct 2009, Vol. 71 Issue 4, p904-905.</extension><space/>these and other conceptions did provide &quot;a precedent... to conceive Jesus similarly as a priest making atonement and eternal intercession in the heavenly sanctuary&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mason"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.199</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authorship</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Authorship of the Epistle to the Hebrews</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By the end of the first century there was not a consensus over the authors identity.<space/><link><target>Clement of Rome</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Barnabas</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Apostle Paul</target></link>, and other names were proposed. Others later suggested<space/><link><target>Luke the Evangelist</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Apollos</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Priscilla and Aquila</target><part>Priscilla</part></link><space/>as possible authors.<extension extension_name='ref'>Utley, R. J.:<space/><italics>The Superiority of the New Covenant: Hebrews</italics>. Bible Lessons International; Marshall, Texas: 1999, Volume 10, p. 3.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Though no author is named, the original<space/><link><target>King James Version of the Bible</target></link><space/>titled the work &quot;The Epistle of Paul the Apostle to the Hebrews&quot;. However, the KJV's attribution to Paul was only a guess, and not a very good one according to the majority of recent scholarship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Powell"></extension><space/>Its vastly different style, different theological focus, different spiritual experienceall are believed to make Paul's authorship of Hebrews increasingly indefensible. At present, neither modern scholarship nor church teaching ascribes Hebrews to Paul.</paragraph><paragraph>Because of its anonymity, it had some trouble being accepted as<space/><link><target>Development of the Christian Biblical canon</target><part>part of the Christian canon</part></link>, being classed with the<space/><link><target>Antilegomena</target></link>. Eventually it was accepted as scripture because of its sound theology, eloquent presentation, and other intrinsic factors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Powell"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.431</arg></template><space/>In antiquity, certain circles began to ascribe it to Paul in an attempt to provide the anonymous work an explicit apostolic pedigree.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Harold W. Attridge</target><part>Attridge, Harold W.</part></link>:<space/><italics>Hebrews</italics>. Hermeneia; Philadelphia: Fortress, 1989, pp. 16.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 4th century,<space/><link><target>Jerome</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target></link><space/>supported<space/><link><target>Authorship of the Pauline epistles</target><part>Paul's authorship</part></link>: the Church largely agreed to include Hebrews as the fourteenth letter of Paul, and affirmed this authorship until the<space/><link><target>Reformation</target></link>. Scholars argued that in the 13th Chapter of Hebrews,<space/><link><target>Saint Timothy</target><part>Timothy</part></link><space/>is referred to as a companion. Timothy was Paul's missionary companion in the same way Jesus sent<space/><link><target>Disciple (Christianity)</target><part>disciples</part></link><space/>out in pairs of two. Also, the writer states that he wrote the letter from &quot;Italy&quot;, which also at the time fits Paul.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Introduction to the Letter to the Hebrews&quot;.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.mycrandall.ca/courses/NewTestament/Hebrews/Introduction.htm#I213'></link><space/>Accessed 17 Mar 2013</extension><space/>The difference in style is explained as simply an adjustment to a distinct audience, to the<space/><link><target>Jewish Christians</target></link><space/>who were being persecuted and pressured to go back to traditional<space/><link><target>Judaism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hahn">Hahn, Roger. &quot;The Book of Hebrews&quot;. Christian Resource Institute.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.crivoice.org/biblestudy/bbheb1.html'></link><space/>Accessed 17 Mar 2013]</extension>Many scholars now believe that the author was one of Paul's pupils or associates, citing stylistic differences between Hebrews and the other<space/><link><target>Pauline epistles</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NewAdvent">Fonck, Leopold. &quot;Epistle to the Hebrews&quot;.<space/><italics>The Catholic Encyclopedia.<space/></italics><space/>Vol. 7. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1910. Web: 30 Dec. 2009.</extension><space/>Recent scholarship has favored the idea that the author was probably a leader of a predominantly Jewish congregation to whom he or she was writing.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Rhee</arg><arg name="first">Victor (Sung-Yul)</arg><arg name="title">The Author of Hebrews as a Leader of the Faith Community</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the Evangelical Theological Society</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg><arg name="volume">55</arg><arg name="series">2</arg><arg name="pages">365–375</arg><arg name="url">http://www.etsjets.org/files/JETS-PDFs/55/55-2/JETS%2055-2_365-375_Rhee.pdf</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Andreas</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Köstenberger</arg><arg name="editor1-link">Andreas J. Köstenberger</arg><arg name="issn">0360-8808</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Believing the author to have been<space/><link><target>Priscilla and Aquila</target><part>Priscilla</part></link>, Hoppin posits that the name was omitted either to suppress its female authorship, or to protect the letter itself from suppression.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoppin, Ruth.<space/><italics>Priscilla's Letter: Finding the Author of the Epistle to the Hebrews.</italics><space/>Lost Coast Press, 2009. ISBN 978-1882897506</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Also convinced that Priscilla was the author of Hebrews,<space/><link><target>Gilbert Bilezikian</target></link>, professor of biblical studies at Wheaton College, remarks on &quot;the conspiracy of anonymity in the ancient church,&quot; and reasons: &quot;The lack of any firm data concerning the identity of the author in the extant writings of the church suggests a deliberate blackout more than a case of collective loss of memory.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>A.J. Gordon ascribes the authorship of<space/><italics>Hebrews</italics><space/>to<space/><link><target>Priscilla and Aquila</target><part>Priscilla</part></link>, writing that &quot;It is evident that the Holy Spirit made this woman Priscilla a teacher of teachers&quot;. Originally proposed by<space/><link><target>Adolf von Harnack</target></link><space/>in 1900,<extension extension_name='ref'>Adolph von Harnack, Probabilia uber die Addresse und den Verfasser des Habraerbriefes, Zeitschrift fur die Neutestamentliche Wissenschaft und die Kunde der aelteren Kirche (E. Preuschen, Berlin: Forschungen und Fortschritte, 1900), 1:1641.</extension><space/>Harnacks reasoning won the support of prominent Bible scholars of the early twentieth century. Harnack believes the letter was written in Romenot to the Church, but to the inner circle. In setting forth his evidence for Priscillan authorship, he finds it amazing that the name of the author was blotted out by the earliest tradition. Citing<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>13</arg><arg></arg><arg>Chapter&nbsp;13</arg></template>, he says it was written by a person of &quot;high standing and apostolic teacher of equal rank with Timothy&quot;. If<space/><link><target>Luke the Evangelist</target><part>Luke</part></link>, Clemens, Barnabas, or<space/><link><target>Apollos</target></link><space/>had written it, Harnack believes their names would not have been obliterated.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Lee Anna Starr,<space/><italics>The Bible Status of Woman</italics>. Zarephath, N.J.: Pillar of Fire, 1955, pp 187182.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Donald Guthrie (theologian)</target><part>Donald Guthrie</part></link>s commentary<space/><italics>The Letter to the Hebrews</italics><space/>(1983) mentions Priscilla by name as a suggested author.<extension extension_name='ref'>Donald Guthrie,<space/><italics>The Letter to the Hebrews</italics>, Tyndale New Testament Commentaries, Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans, 1983, reprinted 1999, p. 21</extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, the author's use of the masculine gender participle when referring to himself in Hebrews 11:32 (&quot;And what shall I more say? for the time would fail me to tell of Gideon, and of Barak, and of Samson, and of Jephtha; of David also, and Samuel, and of the prophets&quot;) makes it less likely it could be Priscilla or any other woman.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the 3rd century,<space/><link><target>Origen</target></link><space/>wrote of the letter, &quot;Men of old have handed it down as Paul's, but who wrote the Epistle God only knows&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/250106.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eusebius Church History Book VI Ch 25 v14<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Newadvent.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 November 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Date</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Dating the Bible</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The use of tabernacle terminology in Hebrews has been used to date the epistle before the<space/><link><target>Siege of Jerusalem (70)</target><part>destruction of the temple</part></link>, the idea being that knowing about the destruction of both Jerusalem and the temple would have influenced the development of the author's overall argument. Therefore, the most probable date for its composition is the second half of the year 63 or the beginning of 64, according to the<space/><link><target>Catholic Encyclopedia</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NewAdvent"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Audience</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Reader-response criticism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Traditional scholars<template><target>who</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/>have argued the letter's audience was<space/><link><target>Jewish Christians</target></link>, as early as the end of the 2nd century (hence its title, &quot;The Epistle to the Hebrews&quot;). Other scholars<template><target>who</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/>have suggested that Hebrews is part of an internal New Testament debate between the extreme<space/><link><target>Judaizers</target></link><space/>(who argued that non-Jews must<space/><link><target>Conversion to Judaism</target><part>convert to Judaism</part></link><space/>before they can receive the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>New Covenant</target><part>Jesus' new covenant</part></link>) versus the extreme<space/><link><target>Antinomianism</target><part>Antinomians</part></link><space/>(who argued that Jews must reject<space/><link><target>613 mitzvot</target><part>God's commandments</part></link><space/>and that<space/><link><target>Abrogation of Old Covenant laws</target><part>Jewish law was no longer in effect</part></link>).<space/><link><target>James the Just</target><part>James</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul of Tarsus and Judaism</target><part>Paul</part></link><space/>represent the moderates of each faction, respectively, and<space/><link><target>Saint Peter</target><part>Peter</part></link><space/>served as moderator.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Canon Debate&quot;, McDonald &amp; Sanders editors, 2002, chapter 32, page 577, by<space/><link><target>James D. G. Dunn</target></link>: &quot;For<space/><italics>Peter was probably in fact and effect the bridge-man</italics><space/>(pontifex maximus!)<space/><italics>who did more than any other to hold together the diversity of first-century Christianity.<space/></italics><space/>James the brother of Jesus and Paul, the two other most prominent leading figures in first-century Christianity, were too much identified with their respective &quot;brands&quot; of Christianity, at least in the eyes of Christians at the opposite ends of this particular spectrum. But Peter, as shown particularly by the Antioch episode in Gal 2, had both a care to hold firm to his Jewish heritage, which Paul lacked, and an openness to the demands of developing Christianity, which James lacked. John might have served as such a figure of the center holding together the extremes, but if the writings linked with his name are at all indicative of his own stance he was too much of an individualist to provide such a rallying point. Others could link the developing new religion more firmly to its founding events and to Jesus himself. But none of them, including the rest of the twelve, seem to have played any role of continuing significance for the whole sweep of Christianitythough James the brother of John might have proved an exception had he been spared&quot;. [Italics original]</extension><space/>The Epistle emphasizes that non-Jewish followers of Jesus do not need to convert to Judaism to share in all of God's promises to Jews. American Baptist theologian<space/><link><target>Edgar Goodspeed</target></link><space/>claims, &quot;But the writer's Judaism is not actual and objective, but literary and academic, manifestly gained from the reading of the<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link><space/>Greek version of the Jewish scriptures, and his polished Greek style would be a strange vehicle for a message to Aramaic-speaking Jews or Christians of Jewish blood&quot;.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It sets before the Jew the claims of Christianityto bring the Jew to the full realization of the relation of Judaism to Christianity, to make clear that Christ has fulfilled those temporary and provisional institutions, and has thus abolished them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dickson">&quot;Introduction to Hebrews&quot;.<space/><italics>The New Analytical Bible and Dictionary of the Bible (KJV).<space/></italics><space/>Chicago: John A. Dickson Publishing Co., 1950. p. 1387</extension><space/>This view is commonly referred to as<space/><link><target>Supersessionism</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Some had stopped assembling together, and this was possibly due to persecution.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb.</arg><arg>10:25</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Hebrews 18&quot;,<space/><link><target>William L. Lane</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Word Biblical Commentary</target></link>, 1991), Introduction p. lvii</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Purpose for writing</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Narrative criticism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Those to whom the author of Hebrews is writing seem to have begun to doubt whether Jesus could really be the Messiah for whom they were waiting, because they believed the Messiah prophesied in the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Scriptures</target></link><space/>was to come as a militant king and destroy the enemies of his people. Jesus, however, came as a mere man who was arrested by the Jewish leaders and who suffered and even died under Roman<space/><link><target>crucifixion</target></link>. And although<space/><link><target>Resurrection appearances of Jesus</target><part>he was seen resurrected</part></link>, he still<space/><link><target>Ascension of Christ</target><part>left the earth</part></link><space/>and his people, who now face persecution rather than victory. The book of Hebrews solves this problem by arguing that the Hebrew Scriptures also foretold that the Messiah would be a priest (although of a different sort than the traditional Levitical priests) and Jesus came to fulfill this role, as a sacrificial offering to God, to atone for sins.<space/><link><target>Second Coming of Christ</target><part>His role of a king is yet to come</part></link>, and so those who follow him should be patient and not be surprised that they suffer for now.<template><target>bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Hebrews</arg><arg>13:12–14</arg><arg>NIV</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some scholars today believe the document was written to prevent<space/><link><target>apostasy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Whitlark, Jason,<space/><italics>Enabling Fidelity to God: Perseverance in Hebrews in Light of the Reciprocity Systems of the Ancient Mediterranean World</italics><space/>(PBMS; Carlisle: Paternoster Press, 2008).</extension><space/>Some have interpreted apostasy to mean a number of different things, such as a group of Christians in one sect leaving for another more conservative sect, one of which the author disapproves. Some have seen apostasy as a move from the Christian assembly to pagan ritual. In light of a possibly Jewish-Christian audience, the apostasy in this sense may be in regard to Jewish-Christians leaving the Christian assembly to return to the Jewish<space/><link><target>synagogue</target></link>. The author writes, &quot;Let us hold fast to our confession&quot;.<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb.</arg><arg>4:14</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The book could be argued to affirm<space/><link><target>special creation</target></link>. It affirms that God by His Son, Jesus Christ, made the worlds. &quot;God...hath in these last days spoken unto us by his Son...by whom also he made the worlds&quot;.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb.</arg><arg>1:1–2</arg></template><space/>The epistle also states that the worlds themselves do not provide the evidence of how God formed them. &quot;Through faith we understand that the worlds were framed by the word of God, so that things which are seen were not made of things which do appear&quot;.<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Hebrews</arg><arg>11:3</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Bloch-SermonOnTheMount.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>240px</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Christians</target></link><space/>believe that<space/><link><target>Jesus</target></link><space/>is the mediator of the<space/><link><target>New Covenant</target></link>.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb.</arg><arg>8:6</arg></template><space/>His famous<space/><link><target>Sermon on the Mount</target><part>sermon from a hill</part></link><space/>representing<space/><link><target>Mount Zion</target></link><space/>is considered by many Christian scholars to be the<space/><link><target>Typology (theology)</target><part>antitype</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>See also<space/><link><target>Expounding of the Law#Antithesis of the Law</target><part>Antithesis of the Law</part></link>.</extension><space/>of the proclamation of the<space/><link><target>Old Covenant</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Mount Sinai</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="...the Epistle opens with the solemn announcement of the superiority of the New Testament Revelation by the Son over Old Testament Revelation by the prophets. {{bibleref2c-nb|Heb.|1:1–4}} It then proves and explains from the Scriptures the superiority of this New Covenant over the Old by the comparison of the Son with the angels as mediators of the Old Covenant, {{bibleref2c-nb|Heb|1:5–2:18}} with Moses and Joshua as the founders of the Old Covenant, {{bibleref2c-nb|Hebrews|3:1–4:16}} and finally, by opposing the high-priesthood of Christ after the order of Melchisedech to the Levitical priesthood after the order of Aaron. {{bibleref2c-nb|Hebrews|5:1–10:18}} (Leopold Fonck, The Catholic Encyclopedia, 1910)<ref name">"NewAdvent" /></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Style</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Form criticism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Hebrews is a very consciously &quot;literary&quot; document. The purity of its Greek was noted by<space/><link><target>Clement of Alexandria</target></link>, according to<space/><link><target>Eusebius of Caesarea</target><part>Eusebius</part></link><space/>(<italics>Historia Eccl.<space/></italics>, VI, xiv), and<space/><link><target>Origen of Alexandria</target></link><space/>asserted that every competent judge must recognize a great difference between this epistle and those of Paul (Eusebius, VI, xxv).</paragraph><paragraph>This letter consists of two strands: an expositional or doctrinal strand,<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>1:1–14</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>2:5–18</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>5:1–14</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>6:13–9:28</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>13:18–25</arg></template><space/>and a hortatory or strongly urging<extension extension_name='ref'>also translated &quot;exhorting&quot;</extension><space/>strand which punctuates the exposition parenthetically at key points as warnings to the readers.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>2:1–4</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>3:1–4:16</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>6:1–12</arg></template><space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb</arg><arg>10:1–13:17</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Hebrews does not fit the form of a traditional<space/><link><target>Hellenistic civilization</target><part>Hellenistic</part></link><space/><link><target>epistle</target></link>, lacking a proper prescript. Modern scholars generally believe this book was originally a<space/><link><target>sermon</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>homily</target></link>, although possibly modified after it was delivered to include the travel plans, greetings and closing.<space/><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Heb.</arg><arg>13:20–25</arg></template><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ehrman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bart D.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Bart D. Ehrman<space/></arg><arg name="title">The New Testament: A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-515462-2<space/></arg><arg name="page">411<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Hebrews contains many references to the<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link>specifically to its<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link><space/>text.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Christology</heading><paragraph>From<space/><italics>The Interpreter's Bible</italics><space/>1955<extension extension_name='blockquote'>We may sum up our authors Christology negatively by saying that he has nothing to do with the older Hebrew messianic hopes of a coming Son of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, who would be a divinely empowered human leader to bring in the<space/><link><target>kingdom of God</target></link><space/>on earth; and that while he still employs the figure of a militant, apocalyptic king ... who will<space/><link><target>Second Coming</target><part>come again</part></link>..., this is not of the essence of his thought about Christ.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Positively, our author presents Christ as divine in nature, and solves any possible objection to a divine being who participates in human experience, especially in the experience of death, by the priestly analogy. He seems quite unconscious of the logical difficulties of his position proceeding from the<space/><link><target>Hypostatic union</target><part>assumption that Christ is both divine and human</part></link>, at least human in experience although hardly in nature. TIB XI p. 588<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Interpreter's Bible:<space/></italics><space/>The Holy Scriptures in the King James and Revised Standard versions with general articles and introduction, exegesis, [and] exposition for each book of the Bible in twelve volumes,<space/><link><target>George Arthur Buttrick</target></link>, Commentary Editor, Walter Russell Bowie, Associate Editor of Exposition, Paul Scherer, Associate Editor of Exposition, John Knox Associate Editor of New Testament Introduction and Exegesis, Samuel Terrien, Associate Editor of Old Testament Introduction and Exegesis, Nolan B. Harmon Editor, Abingdon Press, copyright 1955 by Pierce and Washabaugh, set up printed, and bound by the Parthenon Press, at Nashville, Tennessee, Volume XI, Philippians, Colossians, Thessalonians, Pastoral Epistles [The First and Second Epistles to Timothy, and the Epistle to Titus], Philemon, Hebrews [Introduction and Exegesis by John Knox]</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Sola fide</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Hebrews</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Attridge, Harold W.<space/><italics>Hebrews</italics>. Philadelphia, PA: Fortress Press, 1989.</listitem><listitem>Bruce, Frederick F.<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Hebrews</italics>. New International Commentary on the New Testament. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans, 1964. Rev Ed 1990.</listitem><listitem>Guthrie, Donald<space/><italics>The Letter to the Hebrews</italics>. Grand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1983</listitem><listitem>Hagen, Kenneth.<space/><italics>Hebrews Commenting from Erasmus to Beze</italics>. Tbingen: J.C.B. Mohr (Paul Siebeck), 1981.</listitem><listitem>Heen, Erik M. and<space/><link><target>Philip Krey</target><part>Krey, Philip D.W.</part></link>, eds.<space/><italics>Ancient Christian Commentary on Scripture: Hebrews</italics>. Downers Grove, IL: Intervarsity Press, 2005.</listitem><listitem>Hughes, P.E.<space/><italics>A Commentary on the Epistle to the Hebrews</italics>. Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans Publishing Company, 1977.</listitem><listitem>Hurst, L. D.<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Hebrews: Its Background of Thought</italics>. Cambridge:<space/><link><target>Cambridge University Press</target></link>, 1989.</listitem><listitem>Koester, Craig R. &quot;Hebrews&quot;. Anchor Bible 36. New York: Doubleday, 2001.</listitem><listitem><link><target>William L. Lane</target><part>Lane, William L.</part></link><space/><italics>Hebrews 18</italics>.<space/><link><target>Word Biblical Commentary</target></link><space/>Vol. 47A. Dallas, TX: Word Books, 1991.</listitem><listitem>Lane, William L.<space/><italics>Hebrews 913</italics>.<space/><link><target>Word Biblical Commentary</target></link><space/>Vol. 47B. Dallas, TX: Word Books, 1991.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter O'Brien (theologian)</target><part>O'Brien, Peter T.</part></link><space/><italics>The Letter to the Hebrews</italics>. Pillar New Testament Commentary. Grand Rapids: Eerdmans / Nottingham: Apollos, 2010.</listitem><listitem>Paul Ellingworth<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.biblicalstudies.org.uk/pdf/er/hebrews_ellingworth.pdf'>Reading through Hebrews 17, Listening especially for the theme of Jesus as high priest</link>.<space/><italics>Epworth Review</italics><space/>12.1 (Jan. 1985): 8088.</listitem><listitem>Paul Ellingworth,<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Hebrews</italics>. New International Greek Testament Commentary, Eerdmans, 1993</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Hebrews (Bible)</arg></template>Online translations of the Epistle to the Hebrews:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Hebrews+1'>''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://net.bible.org/#!bible/Hebrews+1'>NET Bible</link></listitem></list><paragraph>Related articles:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/64496/biblical-literature/73458/The-Letter-to-the-Hebrews'>The letter to the Hebrews</link><space/>in &quot;biblical literature&quot;, Encyclopdia Britannica Online.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/goodspeed/ch16.html'>Goodspeed's introductory analysis of ''Hebrews''</link>, 1908 at earlychristianwritings.com</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/07181a.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia: Epistle to the Hebrews</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/ccel/easton/ebd2.html?term=Hebrews,%20Epistle%20to'>''Easton's Bible Dictionary'' 1897:</link><space/>Epistle to the Hebrews</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wesley.nnu.edu/fileadmin/imported_site/wesleyjournal/1981-wtj-16-2.pdf'>Holiness in Hebrews Wayne G. McCown</link><space/>page 58</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.plymouthbrethren.org/passage.php?passage_id=58'>Hebrews from the Biblical Resource Database</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">November 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf201.iii.viii.iii.html'>Eusebius' Church History 3.3</link>.5 includes comment by<space/><link><target>Eusebius</target></link><space/>on canonicity of Hebrews and also extensive note by<space/><link><target>Philip Schaff</target></link><space/>on topic</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://encyclopedia.jrank.org/HAN_HEG/HEBREWS_EPISTLE_TO_THE.html'>Encyclopdia Britannica: Hebrews, Epistle to the</link>, 1911 version</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Epistles|Epistle]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><small>[[Pauline epistles|Pauline Epistle]]<br>to</small><space/>[[Epistle to Philemon|Philemon]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><small>[[New Testament]]</small><br>[[Books of the Bible]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><small>[[General epistles|General Epistle]]<br>of</small><space/>[[Epistle of James|James]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Epistle To The Hebrews</target></template><link><target>Category:Epistle to the Hebrews</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Canonical epistles</target><part>Hebrews</part></link><link><target>Category:Early Jewish Christians</target></link><link><target>Category:Pauline-related books</target></link><link><target>Category:Works of unknown authorship</target></link><link><target>Category:Melchizedek</target></link></paragraph></article>