<article title='Antisemitism_in_the_Arab_world'><paragraph><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim countries</arg><arg>Islam and antisemitism</arg><arg>Racism in the Palestinian territories</arg></template><template><target>Multiple issues</target><arg name="{{Lead too long|date">June 2015}}
{{Refimprove|date</arg></template><template><target>Antisemitism</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><bold><link><target>Antisemitism</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Arab world</target></link></bold><space/>refers to discrimination against<space/><link><target>Jew</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in Arab countries. While<space/><link><target>Arab</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are also a<space/><link><target>Semitic</target></link><space/>people, the meaning of the English term &quot;antisemitism&quot; refers to discrimination against Jews (see<space/><link><target>Antisemitism#Etymology and usage</target><part>Antisemitism: Etymology and usage</part></link>).</preline></preblock><paragraph>Arab antisemitism is believed to have expanded since the 19th century. Jews, like other minority groups within the<space/><link><target>Muslim world</target></link>, were subject to various restrictions long before that (see<space/><link><target>Dhimmi</target></link>). However, despite its restrictive nature, dhimmi status also afforded the &quot;<link><target>People of the Book</target></link>&quot;, provided they did not contest the inferior social and legal status imposed on them, relative security against persecution and welfare most of the timea protection that was missing for non-Christians in most of Europe until the institutionalization of equality under a secular idea of citizenship after the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>and allowed them to enjoy their respective religious laws and ways of life.</paragraph><paragraph>Antisemitism in the Arab world has increased greatly in modern times, for many reasons: the breakdown of the Ottoman Empire and traditional Islamic society; European influence, brought about by Western<space/><link><target>imperialism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Christian Arabs</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (1986), p. 132</extension><space/><link><target>Nazi propaganda</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yadlin">Yadlin, Rifka. &quot;Antisemitism&quot;.<space/><italics>The Continuum Political Encyclopedia of the Middle East</italics>. Ed.<space/><link><target>Avraham Sela</target></link>. New York: Continuum, 2002. p. 52</extension><space/>resentment over Jewish nationalism that led to the colonization of the Ottoman Empire's southern Syrian province (see<space/><link><target>Zionism</target></link>); and the rise of Arab nationalism. The rise of<space/><link><target>political Islam</target></link><space/>during the 1980s and afterwards provided a new mutation of<space/><link><target>Islamic antisemitism</target></link>, which gave the hatred of Jews a religious component.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yadlin"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>For most of the past fourteen hundred years, according to<space/><link><target>Bernard Lewis</target></link>, Arabs have not been antisemitic as the word is used in the West. In his view this is because, for the most part, Arabs are not<space/><link><target>Christians</target></link><space/>brought up on stories of<space/><link><target>Jewish deicide</target></link>. In Islam, such stories are rejected by the<space/><link><target>Qur'an</target></link><space/>as a blasphemous absurdity. Since Muslims do not consider themselves as the &quot;true Israel&quot;, they do not feel threatened by the survival of Jews. Because Islam did not retain the<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link>, no clash of interpretations between the two faiths can therefore arise. There is, says Lewis, no Muslim theological dispute between their religious institutions and the Jews.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (1986), pp. 117-8</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While there were antisemitic incidents in the early twentieth century, antisemitism increased dramatically as a result of the Arab-Israeli conflict. After the 1948 Arab-Israeli War, the Palestinian exodus, the creation of the state of Israel, and<space/><link><target>Israel</target><trail>i</trail></link><space/>victories during the wars of<space/><link><target>Suez Crisis#Invasion</target><part>1956</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Six day war</target><part>1967</part></link><space/>were a severe humiliation to Israel's opponents - primarily Egypt, Syria and Iraq.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (1986), p. 204</extension><space/>However, by the mid 1970s the vast majority of Jews had<space/><link><target>Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim countries</target><part>either left or been expelled from Arab and Muslim countries</part></link>, moving primarily to Israel, France and the United States.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Shenhav"><link><target>Yehouda Shenhav</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=k7FoMi-qY4kC&amp;amp;source=gbs_navlinks_s'>The Arab Jews: A Postcolonial Reading of Nationalism, Religion, and Ethnicity</link></extension><space/>The reasons for the exodus are varied and disputed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Shenhav"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the 1980s, according to Bernard Lewis, the volume of antisemitic literature published in the Arab world, and the authority of its sponsors, seemed to suggest that classical antisemitism had become an essential part of Arab intellectual life, considerably more than in late nineteenth- and early twentieth-century France, and to a degree that has been compared to<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bernard Lewis 1986, p. 256">Lewis, Bernard.<space/><italics>Semites and Anti-Semites</italics>, New York/London: Norton, 1986, p. 256.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In their 2008 report on contemporary Arab-Muslim antisemitism, the Israeli<space/><link><target>Intelligence and Terrorism Information Center</target></link><space/>dates the beginning of this phenomenon to the spread of classic European<space/><link><target>Christian antisemitism</target></link><space/>into the Arab world starting in the late 19th century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="itic">&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.terrorism-info.org.il/malam_multimedia/English/eng_n/pdf/a_s_170408e.pdf'>Contemporary Arab-Muslim anti-Semitism, its Significance and Implications</link>&quot;,<space/><link><target>Intelligence and Terrorism Information Center at the Israel Intelligence Heritage &amp; Commemoration Center (IICC)</target></link>, April 17, 2008.</extension><space/>In 2014 the<space/><link><target>Anti-Defamation League</target></link><space/>published a global survey of worldwide antisemitic attitudes, reporting that in the Middle East, 74% of adults agreed with a majority of the survey's eleven antisemitic propositions, including that &quot;Jews have too much power in international financial markets&quot; and that &quot;Jews are responsible for most of the world's wars.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.timesofisrael.com/hating-the-jew-youve-never-met/</arg><arg name="title">Hating the Jew you've never met</arg><arg name="date">15 May 2014</arg><arg name="work">The Times of Israel</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 January 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The ADL Global 100: An Index of Anti-Semitism<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://global100.adl.org/</arg><arg name="publisher">Anti-Defamation League</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Medieval times</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>History of antisemitism#Middle Ages</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jews, along with<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Zoroastrianism</target><part>Zoroastrians</part></link>, typically had the legal status of<space/><link><target>dhimmi</target></link><space/>(protected minority) in the<space/><link><target>Muslim history</target><part>lands conquered by Muslim Arabs</part></link>, generally applied to non-Muslim minorities. Jews were generally seen as a religious group (not a separate race), thus being a part of the &quot;Arab family&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (1999), p. 131</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Dhimmi were subjected to a number of restrictions, the application and severity of which varied with time and place. Restrictions included residency in<space/><link><target>Racial segregation</target><part>segregated</part></link><space/>quarters, obligation to wear distinctive clothing, public subservience to Muslims, prohibitions against proselytizing and against marrying Muslim women, and limited access to the legal system (the testimony of a Jew did not count if contradicted by that of a Muslim). Dhimmis had to pay a special poll tax (the &quot;<link><target>jizya</target></link>&quot;), which exempted them from military service, and also from payment of the<space/><link><target>Zakat</target></link><space/>alms tax required of Muslims. In return, dhimmis were granted limited rights including a degree of tolerance, community autonomy in personal matters, and protection from being killed outright. Jewish communities, like Christian ones, were typically constituted as semi-autonomous entities managed by their own laws and leadership, who carried the responsibility for the community towards the Muslim rulers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Under Crescent and Cross: The Jews in the Middle Ages</arg><arg name="author">[[Mark R. Cohen|Cohen, Mark R.]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Princeton University Press]]</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">0-691-01082-X<space/></arg><arg name="page">74<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 10, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>By medieval standards, conditions for Jews under Islam was generally more formalized and better than those of Jews in Christian lands, in part due to the sharing of minority status with Christians in these lands. There is evidence for this claim in that the status of Jews in lands with no Christian minority was usually worse than their status in lands with one. For example, there were numerous incidents of<space/><link><target>list of events named massacres</target><part>massacres</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ethnic cleansing</target></link><space/>of Jews in North Africa,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20080927133652/http://www.theforgottenrefugees.com/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;task=view&amp;amp;id=66&amp;amp;Itemid=39'>The Forgotten Refugees</link></extension><space/>especially in<space/><link><target>Morocco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Algeria</target></link><space/>where eventually Jews were forced to live in<space/><link><target>mellah</target><part>ghettos</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roumani, Maurice.<space/><italics>The Case of the Jews from Arab Countries: A Neglected Issue</italics>, 1977, pp. 2627.</extension><space/>Decrees ordering the destruction of synagogues were enacted in the Middle Ages in<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Syria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Iraq</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Yemen</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/Jews_in_Arab_lands_(gen).html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Treatment of Jews in Arab/Islamic Countries<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Jewishvirtuallibrary.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 19, 1947<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>At certain times in Yemen, Morocco and<space/><link><target>Baghdad</target></link>, Jews were forced to convert to Islam or face death.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bat Ye'or,<space/><italics>The Dhimmi</italics>, 1985, p. 61</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The situation where Jews both enjoyed cultural and economic prosperity at times, but were widely persecuted at other times, was summarised by G. E. Von Grunebaum:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>It would not be difficult to put together the names of a very sizable number of Jewish subjects or citizens of the Islamic area who have attained to high rank, to power, to great financial influence, to significant and recognized intellectual attainment; and the same could be done for Christians. But it would again not be difficult to compile a lengthy list of persecutions, arbitrary confiscations, attempted forced conversions, or pogroms.<extension extension_name='ref'>G. E. Von Grunebaum,<space/><italics>Eastern Jewry Under Islam</italics>, 1971, p. 369.</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Views in Modernity</heading><paragraph>Some scholars hold that Arab antisemitism in the modern world arose in the nineteenth century, against the backdrop of conflicting Jewish and Arab nationalism, and was imported into the Arab world primarily by nationalistically minded Christian Arabs (and only subsequently was it &quot;Islamized&quot;), Mark Cohen states.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Oxford Handbook of Jewish Studies</italics>, p. 208</extension><space/>According to<space/><link><target>Bernard Lewis</target></link>:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="The volume of anti-Semitic books and articles published, the size and number of editions and impressions, the eminence and authority of those who write, publish and sponsor them, their place in school and college curricula, their role in the mass media, would all seem to suggest that classical anti-Semitism is an essential part of Arab intellectual life at the present time-almost as much as happened in Nazi Germany, and considerably more than in late nineteenth and early twentieth century France."<ref name">"Bernard Lewis 1986, p. 256" /></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nineteenth century</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Damascus affair</target></link><space/>was an accusation of<space/><link><target>ritual murder</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>blood libel against Jews</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Damascus</target></link><space/>in 1840. On February 5, 1840,<space/><link><target>Franciscan</target></link><space/><link><target>Capuchin friar</target></link><space/>Father Thomas and his Greek servant were reported missing, never to be seen again. The<space/><link><target>Turkey</target><part>Turkish</part></link><space/>governor and the French consul<space/><link><target>Ratti-Menton</target></link><space/>believed accusations of ritual murder and blood libel, as the alleged murder occurred before the Jewish<space/><link><target>Passover</target></link>. An investigation was staged, and Solomon Negrin, a Jewish barber,<space/><link><target>Forced confession</target><part>confessed under torture</part></link><space/>and accused other Jews. Two other Jews died under torture, and one (Moses Abulafia) converted to<space/><link><target>Islam</target></link><space/>to escape torture. More arrests and atrocities followed, culminating in 63 Jewish children being held<space/><link><target>hostage</target></link><space/>and mob attacks on Jewish communities throughout the Middle East. International outrage led to<space/><link><target>Ibrahim Pasha of Egypt</target><part>Ibrahim Pasha</part></link><space/>in Egypt ordering an investigation. Negotiations in<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link><space/>eventually secured the unconditional release and recognition of innocence of the nine prisoners still remaining alive (out of thirteen). Later in<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Moses Montefiore</target></link><space/>(leader of the British Jewish community) persuaded Sultan<space/><link><target>Abdlmecid I</target></link><space/>to issue a<space/><link><target>firman (decree)</target><part>firman</part></link><space/>(edict) intended to halt the spread of blood libel accusations in the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link>:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>... and for the love we bear to our subjects, we cannot permit the Jewish nation, whose innocence for the crime alleged against them is evident, to be worried and tormented as a consequence of accusations which have not the least foundation in truth....</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, pogroms spread through the Middle East and North Africa: Aleppo (1850, 1875), Damascus (1840, 1848, 1890), Beirut (1862, 1874), Dayr al-Qamar (1847), Jaffa (1876), Jerusalem (1847, 1870 and 1895), Cairo (1844, 1890, 190102), Mansura (1877), Alexandria (1870, 1882, 190107), Port Said (1903, 1908), and Damanhur (1871, 1873, 1877, 1891).<extension extension_name='ref'>Yossef Bodansky.<space/><italics>Islamic Anti-Semitism as a Political Instrument</italics><space/>Co-Produced by The Ariel Center for Policy Research and The Freeman Center for Strategic Studies, 1999. ISBN 978-0-9671391-0-4, see also<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of World History</italics><space/>By Peter N. Stearns, William Leonard Langer p. 527. 2001.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Dreyfus affair</target></link><space/>of the late nineteenth century had consequences in the Arab world. Passionate outbursts of antisemitism in France were echoed in areas of French influence, especially<space/><link><target>Maronite</target></link><space/><link><target>Lebanon</target></link>. The Muslim Arab press, however, was sympathetic to the falsely accused Captain Dreyfus, and criticized the persecution of Jews in France.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lewis (1986), p. 133</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Twentieth century</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Relations between Nazi Germany and the Arab world</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='4'>Pre-state antisemitism</heading><paragraph>While antisemitism has increased in the wake of the<space/><link><target>Arab-Israeli conflict</target></link>, there were<space/><link><target>pogrom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>against Jews prior to the foundation of Israel, including<space/><link><target>Nazism</target><part>Nazi</part></link>-inspired pogroms in<space/><link><target>Algeria</target></link><space/>in the 1930s, and attacks on the Jews of<space/><link><target>Iraq</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>in the 1940s. In 1941, 180 Jews were murdered and 700 were injured in the anti-Jewish riots known as the<space/><link><target>Farhud</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="haaretz"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author"><space/>Zvi Zameret</arg><arg name="date">October 29, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/opinion/a-distorted-historiography-1.321731<space/></arg><arg name="title">A distorted historiography<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Haaretz<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 11, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Four hundred Jews were injured in violent demonstrations in Egypt in 1945 and Jewish property was vandalized and looted. In Libya, 130 Jews were killed and 266 injured. In December 1947, 13 Jews were killed in Damascus, including 8 children, and 26 were injured. In Aleppo, rioting resulted in dozens of Jewish casualties, damage to 150 Jewish homes, and the torching of 5 schools and 10 synagogues. In Yemen, 97 Jews were murdered and 120 injured.<extension extension_name='ref' name="haaretz"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Speculated causes</heading><paragraph>Antisemitism in the<space/><link><target>Arab world</target></link><space/>increased in the twentieth century, as antisemitic propaganda and<space/><link><target>blood libel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were imported from Europe and as resentment against<space/><link><target>Zionism</target><part>Zionist</part></link><space/>efforts in<space/><link><target>British Mandate of Palestine</target></link><space/>spread. British troops stationed in Palestine arrived fresh from deployment in the<space/><link><target>Russian civil war</target></link>, fighting alongside the genocidal antisemitic<space/><link><target>White Movement</target></link>. The British forces are credited with introducing the<space/><link><target>antisemitic canard</target><part>antisemitic hoax</part></link><space/>called<space/><link><target>Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link><space/>to Palestine. In March 1921, Musa Khazem El Husseini, Mayor of Jerusalem, told<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link><space/>&quot;The Jews have been amongst the most active advocates of destruction in many lands.... It is well known that the disintegration of Russia was wholly or in great part brought about by the Jews, and a large proportion of the defeat of Germany and Austria must also be put at their door.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>quoted in Morris, Benny,<space/><italics>Righteous Victims</italics>, Knopf, 1999, p. 99.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Matthias Kntzel</target></link><space/>has suggested that the decisive transfer of<space/><link><target>antisemitism</target><part>Jewish conspiracy theory</part></link><space/>took place between 1937 and 1945 under the impact of Nazi propaganda targeted at the Arab world.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kntzel, Matthias, &quot;National Socialism and Anti-Semitism in the Arab World&quot;,<space/><italics>Jewish Political Studies Review</italics><space/>17:12 (Spring 2005).</extension><space/>According to Kuntzel, the Nazi Arabic radio service had a staff of 80 and broadcast every day in Arabic, stressing the similarities between Islam and Nazism and supported by the activities of the<space/><link><target>Mufti of Jerusalem</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Haj Amin al-Husayni</target></link><space/>(who broadcast pro-Nazi propaganda from Berlin). The Nazi regime also provided funding to the Egyptian<space/><link><target>Moslem Brotherhood</target></link>, which began calling for boycotts of Jewish businesses in 1936.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template>Bernard Lewis also describes Nazi influence in the Arab world, including its impact on<space/><link><target>Michel Aflaq</target></link><space/>(a Christian), the principal founder of<space/><link><target>Ba'athism</target><part>Ba'athist thought</part></link><space/>(which later dominated Syria and Iraq).<extension extension_name='blockquote'><preblock><preline>After the promulgation of the Nuremberg Laws, Hitler received telegrams of congratulation from all over the Arab and Muslim world, especially from Morocco and Palestine, where the Nazi propaganda had been most active.... Before long political parties of the Nazi and Fascist type began to appear, complete with paramilitary youth organizations, colored shirts, strict discipline and more or less charismatic leaders.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Bernard Lewis</target><part>Lewis, Bernard</part></link>.<space/><italics>Semites and Anti-Semites: An Inquiry into Conflict and Prejudice</italics>. New York: W. W. Norton, 1999. ISBN 978-0-393-31839-5, p. 148</extension></preline></preblock></extension><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 146-1987-004-09A, Amin al Husseini und Adolf Hitler.jpg</target><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Haj Amin al-Husseini</target></link><space/>meeting with<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target></link><space/>(December 1941)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>George Gruen attributes the increased animosity towards Jews in the<space/><link><target>Arab world</target></link><space/>to the breakdown of the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>and traditional<space/><link><target>Islamic</target></link><space/>society; domination by Western<space/><link><target>colonialism</target><part>colonial powers</part></link><space/>under which Jews gained a disproportionately large role in the commercial, professional, and administrative life of the region; the rise of<space/><link><target>Arab nationalism</target></link>, whose proponents sought the wealth and positions of local Jews through government channels; resentment over Jewish<space/><link><target>nationalism</target></link><space/>and the Zionist movement; and the readiness of unpopular<space/><link><target>regime</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>scapegoat</target></link><space/>local Jews for political purposes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gruen, George E.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jcpa.org/jl/jl102.htm'>&quot;The Other Refugees: Jews of the Arab World&quot;</link>, (<link><target>Jerusalem Center for Public Affairs</target></link>).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the<space/><link><target>1948 Arab-Israeli War</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>1948 Palestinian exodus</target><part>Palestinian exodus</part></link>, the creation of the state of<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, and the independence of Arab countries from European control, conditions for Jews in the Arab world deteriorated. Over the next few decades, almost all would flee the Arab world, some willingly, and some under threat (see<space/><link><target>Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim countries</target></link>). In 1945 there were between 758,000 and 866,000 Jews (see table below) living in communities throughout the Arab world. Today, there are fewer than 8,000. In some Arab states, such as<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>(which was once around 3% Jewish), the Jewish community no longer exists; in other Arab countries, only a few hundred Jews remain.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jewish Virtual Library:<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/myths3/MFrefugees.html'>Chapter 12: Refugees</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Robert L. Bernstein</target><part>Robert Bernstein</part></link>, founder of<space/><link><target>Human Rights Watch</target></link>, says that antisemitism is &quot;deeply ingrained and institutionalized&quot; in &quot;Arab nations in modern times&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.washingtonpost.com/opinions/why-do-human-rights-groups-ignore-palestinians-war-of-words/2011/09/26/gIQAWU5y2K_story.html'>Why do human rights groups ignore Palestinians' war of words?</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern examples</heading><heading level='4'>Israeli Arabs</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Racism by Israeli Arabs against Israeli Jews</arg></template>In the year 2003, Israeli-Arab<space/><link><target>Raed Salah</target></link>, the leader of the northern branch of the<space/><link><target>Islamic Movement in Israel</target></link><space/>published the following poem in the Islamic Movement's periodical:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>You Jews are criminal bombers of mosques,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Slaughterers of pregnant women and babies.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Robbers and germs in all times,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>The Creator sentenced you to be loser monkeys,<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Victory belongs to Muslims, from the Nile to the Euphrates.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://blogs.telegraph.co.uk/news/andrewgilligan/100092424/extremist-ife-sponsors-a-man-who-calls-jews-germs-and-monkeys'>&quot;Extremist IFE sponsors a man who calls Jews 'germs' and 'monkeys'&quot;</link></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During a speech in 2007, Salah accused Jews of<space/><link><target>blood libel</target><part>using children's blood to bake bread</part></link>. &quot;We have never allowed ourselves to knead [the dough for] the bread that breaks the fast in the holy month of Ramadan with children's blood,&quot; he said. &quot;Whoever wants a more thorough explanation, let him ask what used to happen to some children in Europe, whose blood was mixed in with the dough of the [Jewish] holy bread.&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Stern<space/></arg><arg name="first">Yoav<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.haaretz.com/news/islamic-movement-head-charged-with-incitement-to-racism-violence-1.238209<space/></arg><arg name="title">Islamic Movement head charged with incitement to racism, violence<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Haaretz<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">February 16, 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Kamal Khatib, deputy leader of the northern branch of the Islamic movement, referred in one of his speeches to the Jews as &quot;fleas&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Pontz<space/></arg><arg name="first">Zach<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.algemeiner.com/2012/12/20/scandal-at-haifa-university-as-islamic-movement-chairman-who-called-jews-fleas-arrives-on-campus<space/></arg><arg name="title">Scandal at Haifa University as Islamic Movement Chairman Who Called Jews "Fleas" Arrives on Campus<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Algemeiner Journal<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date">December 20, 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">May 17, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Egypt</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Antisemitism in Africa#Egypt</arg></template>Egyptian<space/><link><target>Muslim Brotherhood</target></link><space/>leader<space/><link><target>Mohammed Mahdi Akef</target></link><space/>has denounced what he called &quot;the myth of<space/><link><target>the Holocaust</target></link>&quot; in defending Iranian president<space/><link><target>Mahmoud Ahmadinejad</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Holocaust denial</target><part>denial</part></link><space/>of it.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/middle_east/4554986.stm'>&quot;Egyptian Islamists deny Holocaust&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link></italics>, December 23, 2005.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Egypt</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>government-run newspaper,<space/><italics>Al-Akhbar</italics>, on April 29, 2002, published an editorial denying the Holocaust as a fraud. The next paragraph decries the failure of the Holocaust to eliminate all of the Jews:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><paragraph>With regard to the fraud of the Holocaust.... Many French studies have proven that this is no more than a fabrication, a lie, and a fraud!! That is, it is a 'scenario' the plot of which was carefully tailored, using several faked photos completely unconnected to the truth. Yes, it is a film, no more and no less. Hitler himself, whom they accuse of Nazism, is in my eyes no more than a modest 'pupil' in the world of murder and bloodshed. He is completely innocent of the charge of frying them in the hell of his false Holocaust!!</paragraph><paragraph>The entire matter, as many French and British scientists and researchers have proven, is nothing more than a huge Israeli plot aimed at extorting the German government in particular and the European countries in general. But I, personally and in light of this imaginary tale, complain to Hitler, even saying to him from the bottom of my heart, 'If only you had done it, brother, if only it had really happened, so that the world could sigh in relief [without] their evil and sin.'</paragraph></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In an article in October 2000 columnist Adel Hammoda alleged in the state-owned Egyptian newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>al-Ahram</target></link></italics><space/>that Jews made Matza from the blood of (non-Jewish) children.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Al-Ahram</italics><space/>(Egypt), October 28, 2000</extension><space/>Mohammed Salmawy, editor of<space/><italics>Al-Ahram Hebdo</italics>, &quot;defended the use of old European myths like the<space/><link><target>blood libel against Jews</target><part>blood libel</part></link>&quot; in his newspapers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Clark, Kate (August 10, 2003).<space/><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3136059.stm'>&quot;Interpreting Egypt's anti-semitic cartoons&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link></italics>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In August 2010, Saudi columnist<space/><link><target>Iman Al-Quwaifli</target></link><space/>sharply criticized the &quot;phenomenon of sympathy for Adolf Hitler and for Nazism in the Arab world&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="memri"></extension><space/>specifically citing the words of Hussam Fawzi Jabar, an Islamic cleric who justified Hitler's actions against the Jews in an Egyptian talk show one month earlier.<extension extension_name='ref' name="memri"><link type='external' href='http://www.memri.org/report/en/0/0/0/0/0/0/4499.htm'>Saudi Columnist Condemns Sympathy for Hitler in the Arab World. August 4, 2010 Memri</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.memritv.org/clip/en/2556.htm'>Egyptian Cleric Hussam Fawzi Jabar: Hitler Was Right to Do What He Did to the Jews</link>, MEMRITV, Clip #2556, July 11, 2010.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cfr.org/egypt/hosni-mubarak-troublesome-ally/p23974'>Hosni Mubarak, Troublesome Ally</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Max Boot</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jeane J. Kirkpatrick</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Council on Foreign Relations</target></link><space/>(originally published in<space/><italics><link><target>The Wall Street Journal</target></link></italics><space/>(<link type='external' href='http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703439504576116152251152190.html?KEYWORDS=max+boot'></link>)), February 1, 2011.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In an October 2012 sermon broadcast on<space/><link><target>ERTU</target><part>Egyptian Channel 1</part></link><space/>(which was attended by Egyptian President<space/><link><target>Muhammad Morsi</target></link>) Futouh Abd Al-Nabi Mansour, the Head of Religious Endowment of the<space/><link><target>Matrouh Governorate</target></link>, prayed (as translated by<space/><link><target>MEMRI</target></link>):</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>O Allah, absolve us of our sins, strengthen us, and grant us victory over the infidels. O Allah, destroy the Jews and their supporters. O Allah, disperse them, rend them asunder. O Allah, demonstrate Your might and greatness upon them.<ref>[http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/3614.htm Egyptian President Morsi Joins Preacher in Prayer for Destruction and Dispersal of the Jews], MEMRI, clip 3614, October 19, 2012.</ref><ref>[http://www.israeltoday.co.il/NewsItem/tabid/178/nid/23448/Default.aspx Egyptian president prays for Jews' demise] by Ryan Jones, ''[[Israel Today]]'', October 23, 2012.</ref><ref>[http://www.cbn.com/cbnnews/insideisrael/2012/October/Hamas-Egypt-Use-Social-Aid-to-Promote-Jihad/ Hamas, Egypt Use Social Aid to Promote Jihad] by Tzippe Barrow, ''[[CBN News]]'', October 23, 2012.</ref><ref>[http://www.jewishpress.com/news/morsi-appears-religiously-fervent-in-prayer-to-destroy-jews/2012/10/22/0/ In Public Prayer Morsi Appeals to Allah to 'Destroy the Jews' (Video)] by Malkah Fleisher, ''[[The Jewish Press]]'', October 22, 2012.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Jordan</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>History of the Jews in Jordan</arg></template><link><target>Jordan</target></link><space/>does not allow entry to Jews with visible signs of Judaism or even with personal religious items in their possession. The Jordanian ambassador to Israel replied to a complaint by a religious Jew denied entry that security concerns required that travelers entering the Hashemite Kingdom not do so with prayer shawls (<link><target>Tallit</target></link>) and phylacteries (<link><target>Tefillin</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Jordan denies entry to Israeli with Jewish prayer items<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.haaretz.com/news/jordan-denies-entry-to-israeli-with-jewish-prayer-items-1.279743<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>July 10, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="work">Haaretz<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 11, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Jordanian authorities state that the policy is in order to ensure the Jewish tourists' safety.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Israeli tourists asked to hand over Jewish paraphernalia<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.eturbonews.com/4337/israeli-tourists-asked-hand-over-jewish-paraphernalia<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>August 13, 2008</arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>eTurboNews<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 23, 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July 2009, six<space/><link><target>Breslov (Hasidic dynasty)</target><part>Breslov</part></link><space/><link><target>Hasidic Judaism</target><part>Hasidim</part></link><space/>were deported after attempting entry into Jordan in order to visit the tomb of Aaron / Sheikh Harun on<space/><link><target>Mount Hor</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Petra</target></link>, because of an alert from the Ministry of Tourism. The group had taken a<space/><link><target>ferry</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Sinai</target></link>, Egypt because they understood that Jordanian authorities were making it hard for visible Jews to enter from Israel. The<space/><link><target>Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Israel)</target><part>Israeli Ministry of Foreign Affairs</part></link><space/>is aware of the issue.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/>Mendel, Arieh<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">he:חסידי ברסלב גורשו מירדן: "הם מאוד מאוכזבים"<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.haredim.co.il/ViewArticle.aspx?catID</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20111008033754/http://www.haredim.co.il/ViewArticle.aspx?catID</arg><arg name="archivedate">8 October 2015<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>July 21, 2009</arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Haredim.co.il<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg><arg name="language">he</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Saudi Arabia</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Antisemitism#Saudi Arabia</arg></template>A Saudi government website initially stated that Jews would not be granted tourist visas to enter the country.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid</arg><arg name="title">Visa requirements<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Saudi Commission for Tourism & Antiquities|Supreme Commission for Tourism]]<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20040206173019/http://www.sauditourism.gov.sa/sct/indexlist.php?catid</arg><arg name="archivedate">February 6, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Visas will not be issued for the following groups of people:
* An Israeli passport holder or a passport that has an Israeli arrival/departure stamp.
* Those who don't abide by the Saudi traditions concerning appearance and behaviors. Those under the influence of alcohol will not be permitted into the Kingdom.
* There are certain regulations for pilgrims and you should contact the consulate for more information.
* Jewish People</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.house.gov/apps/list/press/ny09_weiner/022604Saudi.html'>Official Saudi Arabia Tourism Website: No Jews Allowed. &quot;Jewish People&quot; May Not Receive Travel Visas Required To Travel Into The Kingdom</link><space/>by Congressman Anthony D. Weiner (D-Queens &amp; Brooklyn) February 26, 2004</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/3493448.stm'>&quot;Jews barred in Saudi tourist drive&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link></italics>, February 27, 2004.</extension>It has since removed this statement, and apologized for posting &quot;erroneous information&quot;. Members of religions other than Islam, including Jews, are not permitted to practice their religion publicly in Saudi Arabia; according to the U.S. State Department,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.uscirf.gov/countries/countriesconcerns/Countries/Saudi_Arabia.html'>United States Commission on International Religious Freedom. Countries of Particular Concern. Saudi Arabia</link></extension><space/>religious freedom &quot;does not exist&quot; in Saudi Arabia. Islam is the official religion of Saudi Arabia, and the tenets of that religion are enforced by law.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">International Religious Freedom Report 2004</arg><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/irf/2004/35507.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">US Department of State</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Antisemitism is common within religious circles.<space/><link><target>Abdul Rahman Al-Sudais</target></link>, the imam of the<space/><link><target>Masjid al-Haram</target><part>Grand mosque in Mecca</part></link>, Saudi Arabia, has been described as an antisemite<extension extension_name='ref' name="CFAC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.antisemitism.org.il/eng/events/9162/Canada_%E2%80%93_A_Saudi_Imam_is_Banned_From_Entering_the_Country
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Canada – A Saudi Imam is Banned From Entering the Country
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2007-03-18
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>May 18, 2004
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Coordination Forum for Countering Antisemitism
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>{{small|1</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="AN"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.arabnews.com/node/249729
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Canadian Embassy Denies Refusing Sheikh Al-Sudais Visa
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>August 22, 2012
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>May 20, 2004
</arg><arg name="quote">{{small|1</arg></template></extension><space/>for publicly praying to God to 'terminate' the Jews<extension extension_name='ref' name="OrlSent"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://articles.orlandosentinel.com/2003-12-03/news/0312030409_1_keynote-speaker-islamic-shah
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Islamic Conference Speaker Draws Wrath
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Jacobson
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Susan
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>August 22, 2012
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>December 3, 2003
</arg><arg name="quote">{{small|1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Saudi Arabian media often attacks Jews in books, news articles, at their Mosques and with what some describe as<space/><link><target>antisemitic</target></link><space/>satire. Saudi Arabian government officials and state religious leaders often promote the idea that Jews are conspiring to take over the entire world; as proof of their claims they publish and frequently cite<space/><italics><link><target>The Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link></italics><space/>as factual.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CMIP-KSA2001"><link type='external' href='http://www.edume.org/reports/10/38.htm'>CMIP report: The Jews in World History according to the Saudi textbooks</link>.<space/><italics>The Danger of World Jewry</italics>, by Abdullah al-Tall, pp. 140141 (Arabic).<space/><italics>Hadith and Islamic Culture</italics>, Grade 10, (2001) pp. 103104.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>PDFlink</target><arg>http://www.freedomhouse.org/religion/pdfdocs/KSAtextbooks06.pdf</arg></template><space/>2006 Saudi Arabia's Curriculum of Intolerance, Report by Center for Religious Freedom of Freedom House. 2006</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One Saudi Arabian government newspaper suggested that hatred of all Jews is justifiable. &quot;Why are they (the Jews) hated by all the people which hosted them, such as Iraq and Egypt thousands years ago, and Germany, Spain, France and the UK, up to the days they gained of power over the capital and the press, in order to rewrite the history?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Turki 'Abdallah as-Sudayri (April 15, 2002). &quot;All of History is against them&quot;.<space/><italics>Al-Riyadh</italics>, (Saudi government daily).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Saudi textbooks vilify Jews (and Christians and non-Wahabi Muslims): according to<space/><italics><link><target>The Washington Post</target></link></italics>, Saudi textbooks claimed by them to have been sanitized of antisemitism still call Jews apes (and Christians swine); demand that students avoid and not befriend Jews; claim that Jews<space/><link><target>Theistic Satanism</target><part>worship</part></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Devil (Islam)</target><part>devil</part></link>; and encourage Muslims to engage in Jihad to vanquish Jews.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Nina Shea</target><part>Shea, Nina</part></link><space/>(May 21, 2006).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/05/19/AR2006051901769.html'>&quot;This is a Saudi textbook. (After the intolerance was removed.)&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The Washington Post</italics>, p. B01.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Even during the height of the Saudi crackdown on extremism in 2004, a Saudi IQRA TV &quot;man on the street&quot; segment on feelings toward Jews, was entirely antagonistic. Interviewees described Jews as &quot;our eternal enemies&quot;, &quot;murderous&quot;, &quot;the enemies of Allah and His Prophet,&quot; &quot;murderers of prophets,&quot; &quot;the filthiest people on the face of this earth&quot;, etc.<extension extension_name='ref' name="memri-saudi"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">MEMRI TV Project: Saudi IQRA TV Examines Public Attitudes toward Jews</arg><arg name="url">http://www.memri.org/report/en/0/0/0/0/0/0/1228.htm</arg><arg name="website">MEMRI TV Project</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2014</arg><arg name="date">September 29, 2004</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bradley</arg><arg name="first">John R.</arg><arg name="title">Saudi Arabia Exposed : Inside a Kingdom in Crisis</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Palgrave
</arg><arg name="pages">96–7
</arg><arg name="quote">
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Syria</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Zeibak.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Clockwise from top left: Fara Zeibak, Mazal Zeibak, Eva Saad and Lulu Zeibak.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On March 2, 1974, the bodies of four<space/><link><target>Syrian Jewish</target></link><space/>women were discovered by border police in a cave in the Zabdani Mountains northwest of Damascus. Fara Zeibak 24, her sisters Lulu Zeibak 23, Mazal Zeibak 22 and their cousin Eva Saad 18, had contracted with a band of smugglers to flee Syrian to Lebanon and eventually to Israel. The girls' bodies were found raped, murdered and mutilated. The police also found the remains of two Jewish boys, Natan Shaya 18 and Kassem Abadi 20, victims of an earlier massacre.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman, Saul S. (1989). Without Future: The Plight of Syrian Jewry. Praeger Publishers. ISBN 978-0-275-93313-5</extension><space/>Syrian authorities deposited the bodies of all six in sacks before the homes of their parents in the Jewish ghetto in Damascus.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Le Figaro</italics>, March 9, 1974, &quot;Quatre femmes juives assassiness a Damas&quot;, (Paris: International Conference for Deliverance of Jews in the Middle East, 1974), p. 33.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1984 Syrian Defense Minister<space/><link><target>Mustafa Tlass</target></link><space/>published a book called<space/><italics>The Matzah of Zion</italics>, which claimed that Jews had killed Christian children in Damascus to make Matzas (see<space/><link><target>Damascus affair</target></link>). His book inspired the Egyptian TV series<space/><italics><link><target>Horseman Without a Horse</target></link></italics><space/>(see below) and a spinoff,<space/><italics>The Diaspora</italics>, which led to<space/><link><target>Hezbollah</target></link>'s al-Manar being banned in Europe for broadcasting it.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jorisch, Avi</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Beacon of Hatred: Inside Hizballahs Al-Manar Television</arg><arg name="publisher">Washington Institute for Near East Policy</arg><arg name="isbn">0-944029-88-4</arg><arg name="pp">103–104</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Former<space/><link><target>Ku Klux Klan</target></link><space/>leader<space/><link><target>David Duke</target></link><space/>visited Syria in November 2005 and made a speech that was broadcast live on Syrian television.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.davidduke.com/mp3/dukedamascus6.WMV<space/></arg><arg name="title">David Duke website.<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20110701060206/http://www.davidduke.com/mp3/dukedamascus6.WMV</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>July 1, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Tunisia</heading><paragraph>For a personal account of the discrimination and physical attacks experienced by Jews in Tunisia see the Jewish-Arab anti-colonialist writer<space/><link><target>Albert Memmi</target></link>'s account:<extension extension_name='ref'>Memmi, Albert.<link type='external' href='http://www.jimena.org/faq/memmi.htm'>&quot;Who is an Arab Jew?&quot;</link>, February 1975.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>At each crisis, with every incident of the slightest importance, the mob would go wild, setting fire to Jewish shops. This even happened during the Yom Kippur War. Tunisia's President, Habib Bourguiba, has in all probability never been hostile to the Jews, but there was always that notorious &quot;delay&quot;, which meant that the police arrived on the scene only after the shops had been pillaged and burnt. Is it any wonder that the exodus to France and Israel continued and even increased?</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On November 30, 2012, prominent Tunisian imam Sheikh Ahmad Al-Suhayli of<space/><link><target>Rads</target></link>, told his followers during a live broadcast on<space/><link><target>Hannibal TV</target></link><space/>that &quot;God wants to destroy this [Tunisian] sprinkling of Jews and is sterilizing the wombs of Jewish women.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="timesofisrael.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.timesofisrael.com/tunisian-imam-sued-for-call-to-sterilize-the-wombs-of-jewish-women/'>Tunisian imam sued for call to 'sterilize the wombs of Jewish women' Times of Israel. Dec. 20. 2012</link></extension><space/>This was the fourth time incitement against Jews has been reported in the public sphere since the overthrow of Tunisian President<space/><link><target>Zine El Abidine Ben Ali</target></link><space/>in 2011, thus prompting Jewish community leaders to demand security protection from the Tunisian government.<extension extension_name='ref' name="timesofisrael.com"></extension><space/>Al-Suhayli subsequently posted a video on the Internet in which he claimed that his statements had been misinterpreted.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.memritv.org/clip_transcript/en/3685.htm'>Tunisian Cleric Ahmad Al-Suhayli in Response to Lawsuit Following MEMRI TV Exposure: I Did Not Call to Kill All the Jews</link>, MEMRITV, Clip No. 3685 (transcript), December 16, 2012.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>History of the Jews in Tunisia</target></link><space/>goes back to Roman times. Before 1948, the Jewish population of Tunisia reached a peak of 110,000. Today it has a Jewish community of less than 2,000 people.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Ettinger<space/></arg><arg name="first">Yair<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.haaretz.com/print-edition/features/sociologist-claude-sitbon-do-the-jews-of-tunisia-have-reason-to-be-afraid-1.337440<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sociologist Claude Sitbon, do the Jews of Tunisia have reason to be afraid? - Israel News &#124; Haaretz Daily Newspaper<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Haaretz.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-01-17<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-06-05</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Palestinian territories</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Racism in the Palestinian territories</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Hamas</target></link>, an offshoot of the Egyptian<space/><link><target>Muslim Brotherhood</target></link>, has a foundational statement of principles, or &quot;covenant&quot; that claims that the French revolution, the Russian revolution, colonialism and both world wars were created by the Zionists. It also claims the<space/><link><target>Freemason</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rotary club</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are Zionist fronts and refers to the<space/><link><target>Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/mideast/hamas.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Hamas Covenant 1988 articles 22 and 32<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yale.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20110629170055/http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/mideast/hamas.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>June 29, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension>Claims that Jews and Freemasons were behind the French Revolution originated in Germany in the mid-19th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Norman Cohn</target><part>Cohn, Norman</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Warrant for Genocide</target></link>, The Myth of the Jewish World Conspiracy and the Protocols of the Elders of Zion</italics>, chapter 1.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Mudar Zahran, a Palestinian, writing for the<space/><link><target>Gatestone Institute</target></link>, says that &quot;the Palestinians have been used as fuel for the new form of anti-Semitism; this has hurt the Palestinians and exposed them to unprecedented and purposely media-ignored abuse by Arab governments, including some of those who claim love for the Palestinians, yet in fact only bear hatred to Jews. This has resulted in Palestinian cries for justice, equality, freedom and even basic human rights being ignored while the world getting consumed with delegitimizing Israel from either ignorance or malice.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Mudar Zahran<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.hudson-ny.org/1979/anti-semitism-20<space/></arg><arg name="title">Anti-semitism 2.0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hudson-ny.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 21, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20110721172129/http://www.hudson-ny.org/1979/anti-semitism-20</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>July 21, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.gatestoneinstitute.org/1979/anti-semitism-20'></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Mahmoud Abbas</target></link>, leader of the<space/><link><target>PLO</target></link>, published a Ph.D. thesis (at Moscow University) in 1982, called<space/><italics>The Secret Connection between the Nazis and the Leaders of the Zionist Movement</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Malone, Brynn.<space/><link type='external' href='http://hnn.us/articles/1414.html'>Was Abu Mazen a Holocaust Denier?</link>, History News Network.</extension>His doctoral thesis later became a book,<space/><link><target>The Other Side: the Secret Relationship Between Nazism and Zionism</target></link>, which, following his appointment as Palestinian Prime Minister in 2003, was heavily criticized as an example of<space/><link><target>Holocaust denial</target></link>. In his book, Abbas wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>It seems that the interest of the Zionist movement, however, is to inflate this figure [of Holocaust deaths] so that their gains will be greater. This led them to emphasize this figure [six million] in order to gain the solidarity of international public opinion with Zionism. Many scholars have debated the figure of six million and reached stunning conclusionsfixing the number of Jewish victims at only a few hundred thousand.<extension extension_name='ref'>Medoff, Dr. Rafael.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.wymaninstitute.org/articles/2003-03-denier.php'>&quot;A Holocaust-Denier as Prime Minister of 'Palestine'?&quot;</link><space/>(The David S. Wyman Institute for Holocaust Studies).</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gross, Tom.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.tomgrossmedia.com/mideastdispatches/archives/000032.html'>Abu Mazen and the Holocaust</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Itamar, Marcus<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.pmw.org.il/holocaust.htm'>PA Holocaust Denial</link><space/>(Palestinian Media Watch).</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Arab newspapers</heading><paragraph>Many<space/><link><target>Arab</target></link><space/>newspapers, such as<space/><italics><link><target>Al-Hayat Al-Jadidah</target></link></italics>, the Palestinian Authority's official newspaper, often write that &quot;the Jews&quot; control all the world's governments, and that &quot;the Jews&quot; plan<space/><link><target>genocide</target></link><space/>on all the Arabs in the<space/><link><target>West Bank</target></link>. Others write less sensational stories, and state that Jews have too much of an influence in the United States government. Often the leaders of other nations are said to be controlled by Jews.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template><space/>Articles in many official Arab government newspapers claim that<space/><italics><link><target>The Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link></italics>, reflects facts, and thus points to an international Jewish conspiracy to<space/><link><target>New World Order (conspiracy theory)#The Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target><part>take over the world</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Netanyahu's Plan completely matches the foundations of the greater Zionist plan which is organized according to specific stages that were determined when ''The Protocols of the Elders of Zion'' was composed and when Herzl along with Weizmann traveled around the world in order to determine the appropriate location for the implementation of this conspiracy, (official Palestinian Authority newspaper, Al-Hayat Al-Jadidah, November 30, 1997).</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The Jews seek to conquer the world.... We must expose the Zionist-Colonialist plot and its goals, which destroy not only our people but the entire world (PA Minister of Agriculture, [[Abdel Jawad Saleh]], quoted in ''[[Al-Hayat Al-Jadidah]]'', November 6, 1997)<ref>Jewish Virtual Library: [https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/anti-semitism/pastatements.html Palestinian Authority Anti-Semitism Since the Hebron Accord]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Lebanon</heading><paragraph><link><target>Hezbollah</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Al-Manar</target></link><space/>TV channel has often been accused of airing antisemitic broadcasts, blaming the Jews for a Zionist<space/><link><target>Conspiracy theory</target><part>conspiracy</part></link><space/>against the Arab world, and often airing excerpts from the<space/><italics>Protocols of the Elders of Zion</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Sciolino<space/></arg><arg name="first">Elaine<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Carole Corm<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res</arg><arg name="title">A New French Headache: When Is Hate on TV Illegal?<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The New York Times]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 9, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 11, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.adl.org/special_reports/protocols/protocols_recycled.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Anti-Semitic Series on Arab Television: Satellite Network Recycles The Protocols of the Elders of Zion<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Anti-Defamation League]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 9, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 11, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wiesenthal.com/siteapps/advocacy/ActionItem.aspx?c=fwLYKnN8LzH&amp;amp;b=297065'>&quot;Urge President Chirac to Block Hezbollah's Antisemitic and Hate TV&quot;.</link><space/><italics><link><target>Simon Wiesenthal Center</target></link></italics>. May 21, 2008.</extension><space/>which the<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link></italics><space/>describes as a &quot;fraudulent document that served as a pretext and rationale for anti-Semitism in the early 20th century&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Al-Manar</target></link><space/>recently aired a drama series, called<space/><italics>The Diaspora</italics>, which is based on historical antisemitic allegations. BBC reporters who watched the series said that:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'><preblock><preline>Correspondents who have viewed<space/><italics>The Diaspora</italics><space/>note that it quotes extensively from the<space/><italics>Protocols of the Elders of Zion</italics>, a notorious 19th-century publication used by the Nazis among others to fuel race hatred.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/3581514.stm'>&quot;France offers 'hate TV' reprieve&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>BBC News Online</italics>, August 20, 2004.</extension></preline></preblock></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In another incident, an Al-Manar commentator recently referred to &quot;Zionist attempts to transmit<space/><link><target>AIDS</target></link><space/>to Arab countries&quot;. Al-Manar officials deny broadcasting antisemitic incitement and state that their position is anti-Israeli, not antisemitic. However, Hezbollah has directed strong rhetoric both against Israel and Jews, and it has cooperated in publishing and distributing outright antisemitic literature. The government of Lebanon has not criticized continued broadcast of antisemitic material on television.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/nea/136073.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">2009 Human Rights Report: Lebanon<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">State.gov<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 11, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20110628052145/http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2009/nea/136073.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>June 28, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Due to protests by the<space/><link><target>Conseil Reprsentatif des Institutions juives de France</target><part>CRIF</part></link><space/>umbrella group of French Jews regarding allegations of antisemitic content, French Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Jean-Pierre Raffarin</target></link><space/>called for a ban on Al-Manar broadcasting in France on December 2, 2004; just two weeks after al-Manar was authorised to continue broadcasting in Europe by France's media watchdog agency.<extension extension_name='ref'>Usher, Sebastian (December 3, 2004) .<link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4064317.stm'>&quot;French seek 'anti-Semitic' TV ban&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link></italics>.</extension><space/>On December 13, 2004, France's highest administrative court banned Hizbullah's Al-Manar TV station on the grounds that it consistently incites racial hatred and antisemitism.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/europe/4093579.stm'>&quot;France pulls plug on Arab network&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link><space/>Online</italics>, December 14, 2004.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Yemen</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Geography of antisemitism#Yemen</arg></template>The 1940s and the<space/><link><target>Decleration of Israel</target><part>establishment of Israel</part></link><space/>saw rapid emigration of Jews out of Yemen, in the wake of anti-Jewish riots and massacres. By the late 1990s, only several hundred remained, mainly in a northwestern mountainous region named<space/><link><target>Sa'ada</target></link><space/>and town of<space/><link><target>Raida</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Houthi</target></link><space/>members put up notes on the Jews' doors, accusing them of corrupting Muslim morals. Eventually, the Houthi leaders sent threatening messages to the Jewish community: &quot;We warn you to leave the area immediately.... We give you a period of 10 days, or you will regret it.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://fighthatred.com/recent-events/national-political-hate/416-jews-flee-yemen-due-to-rising-anti-semitism'>Jews flee Yemen due to rising anti-Semitism, Fight Hartred</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>Horseman Without a Horse</italics></heading><paragraph>In 20012002,<space/><link><target>Arab Radio and Television Network</target><part>Arab Radio and Television</part></link><space/>produced a 30-part television miniseries entitled<space/><italics>Horseman Without a Horse</italics>, starring prominent Egyptian actor<space/><link><target>Mohamed Sobhi (actor)</target><part>Mohamed Sobhi</part></link>, which contains dramatizations of<space/><italics><link><target>The Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link></italics>. The United States and Israel criticized Egypt for airing the program, which includes racist falsehoods that have a history of being used &quot;as a pretext for persecuting Jews&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/middle_east/2386767.stm'>&quot;Egypt criticised for 'anti-Semitic' film&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBC News</target></link><space/>Online</italics>, November 1, 2002.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Opinion polling</heading><paragraph>In 2008 A<space/><link><target>Pew Research Center</target></link><space/>survey found that negative views concerning Jews were most common in the three predominantly Arab nations polled, with 97% of Lebanese having unfavorable opinion of Jews, 95% in Egypt and 96% in Jordan.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pewglobal.org/files/pdf/262.pdf'>Unfavorable Views of Jews and Muslims on the increase in Europe</link><space/>Pew Global Attitudes Research September 17, 2008, page 10</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dhimmi</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Covenant of Umar I</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pact of Umar II</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jizya</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mellah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Qutbism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Racism in the Arab world</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Islam and antisemitism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jewish exodus from Arab and Muslim lands</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Contemporary imprints of The Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target><part>Contemporary imprints of ''The Protocols of the Elders of Zion''</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Herf</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jeffrey</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Jeffrey Herf</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Jewish Enemy: Nazi Propaganda for the Arab World</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Yale University Press]]</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Ann Arbor, Michigan</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-300-14579-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bernard Lewis</target><part>Lewis, Bernard</part></link><space/>(1984).<space/><italics>The Jews of Islam</italics>. Princeton: Princeton University Press. ISBN 0-691-00807-8</listitem><listitem>Lewis, Bernard (1999).<space/><italics>Semites and anti-Semites</italics>. ISBN 0-393-31839-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jane Gerber</target><part>Gerber, Jane S.</part></link><space/>(1986). &quot;Anti-Semitism and the Muslim World&quot;. In<space/><italics>History and Hate: The Dimensions of Anti-Semitism</italics>, ed. David Berger. Jewish Publications Society. ISBN 0-8276-0267-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Andrew G. Bostom</target><part>Bostom, Andrew G.</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Legacy of Islamic Antisemitism: From Sacred texts to Solemn History</italics>. Prometheus Books. 2008. ISBN 978-1-59102-554-2</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Satloff</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Robert Satloff</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Among the Righteous: Lost Stories from the Holocaust's Long Reach into Arab Lands</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Perseus Book Group</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">1-58648-399-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Walter Laqueur</target><part>Laqueur, Walter</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Changing Face of Antisemitism: From Ancient Times To The Present Day</italics>. Oxford University Press. 2006. ISBN 0-19-530429-2</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leon Poliakov</target><part>Poliakov, Leon</part></link><space/>(1997). &quot;Anti-Semitism&quot;.<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopaedia Judaica</target></link></italics><space/>(CD-ROM Edition Version 1.0). Ed.<space/><link><target>Cecil Roth</target></link>. Keter Publishing House. ISBN 965-07-0665-8</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tom Segev</target><part>Segev, Tom</part></link>.<space/><italics>One Palestine, Complete: Jews and Arabs Under the British Mandate</italics>. Trans. Haim Watzman. New York: Henry Holt and Company, 2001.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Islamism and Anti-Semitism. Preliminary Evidence on Their Relationship from Cross-National Opinion Data<space/></arg><arg name="last">Tausch<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arno<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2015<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[SSRN]]</arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ssrn.com/abstract</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The New Global Antisemitism: Implications from the Recent ADL-100 Data (January 14, 2015). Middle East Review of International Affairs, Vol. 18, No. 3 (Fall 2014).<space/></arg><arg name="last">Tausch<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arno<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="year">2015<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[SSRN]]</arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="pages"></arg><arg name="url">http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert S. Wistrich</target><part>Wistrich, Robert S.</part></link>.<space/><italics>Hitler's Apocalypse: Jews and the Nazi Legacy</italics>. Weidenfeld &amp; Nicolson. 1985. ISBN 0-297-78719-5</listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert S. Wistrich</target><part>Wistrich, Robert S.</part></link>.<space/><italics>A Lethal Obsession: Anti-Semitism from Antiquity to the Global Jihad</italics>. Random House. 2010. ISBN 978-1-4000-6097-9</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><preblock><preline>*<link type='external' href='http://www.jcpa.org/JCPA/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DBID=1&amp;amp;LNGID=1&amp;amp;TMID=111&amp;amp;FID=625&amp;amp;PID=0&amp;amp;IID=2779'>The Holocaust in Arab Public Discourse: Historicized Politics and Politicized History</link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tau.ac.il/Anti-Semitism/asw98-9/arab.html'>Arab Anti-Semitism in 1998/99</link><space/>summary of Arab antisemitism, by the<space/><link><target>University of Tel Aviv</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.adl.org/main_Arab_World/default.htm'>Anti-Semitism in the Arab World</link><space/>a collection of materials updated regularly</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://thomas.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/z?c107:S.RES.366:'>S.RES.366</link><space/>Urging the Government of<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link><space/>and other Arab governments not to allow their government-controlled television stations to broadcast any program that lends legitimacy to the<space/><link><target>Protocols of the Elders of Zion</target></link>, and for other purposes. (Passed/agreed to in Senate on November 20, 2002).</listitem><listitem>http://www.memri.org Organization that monitors Middle-Eastern media for antisemitism. See<space/><link><target>MEMRI</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jcpa.org/Templates/ShowPage.asp?DRIT=3&amp;amp;DBID=1&amp;amp;LNGID=1&amp;amp;TMID=111&amp;amp;FID=624&amp;amp;PID=0&amp;amp;IID=644&amp;amp;TTL=Major_Anti-Semitic_Motifs_in_Arab_Cartoons'>Major Anti-Semitic Motifs in Arab Cartoons</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.freeman.org/m_online/dec03/rosen.htm'>Iraqis Wrestle with the Jewish Factor</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Antisemitism topics</target><arg name="state">uncollapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Antisemitism In The Arab World</target></template><link><target>Category:Arab world</target></link><link><target>Category:Blood libel</target></link><link><target>Category:Islam and antisemitism</target><part>Arab world</part></link><link><target>Category:Antisemitism in the Arab world</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Antisemitism by country or region</target><part>Arab world</part></link></paragraph></article>