<article title='Entropy'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>entropy in thermodynamics</arg></template><template><target>See introduction</target></template><template><target>Thermodynamics</target><arg name="cTopic">[[List of thermodynamic properties|System properties]]</arg></template><template><target>EntropySegments</target></template><template><target>hatnote</target><arg>Do not confuse this with [[Enthalpy]]</arg></template>In<space/><link><target>thermodynamics</target></link>,<space/><bold>entropy</bold><space/>(usual symbol<space/><italics>S</italics>) is a measure of the number of specific ways in which a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link><space/>may be arranged, commonly understood as a measure of<space/><link><target>Entropy (order and disorder)</target><part>disorder</part></link>. According to the<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link><space/>the entropy of an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>never decreases; such a system will spontaneously proceed towards thermodynamic equilibrium, the configuration with<space/><link><target>Maximum entropy thermodynamics</target><part>maximum entropy</part></link>. Systems that are not isolated may decrease in entropy, provided they increase the entropy of their environment by at least that same amount. Since entropy is a<space/><link><target>state function</target></link>, the change in the entropy of a system is the same for any process that goes from a given initial state to a given final state, whether the process is<space/><link><target>Reversible process (thermodynamics)</target><part>reversible</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Irreversible process</target><part>irreversible</part></link>. However, irreversible processes increase the combined entropy of the system and its environment.</paragraph><paragraph>The change in entropy (<italics>S</italics>) of a system was originally defined for a<space/><link><target>Reversible process (thermodynamics)</target><part>thermodynamically reversible process</part></link><space/>as</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = \int \frac{dQ_\text{rev}}T</extension>,</listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''T''</arg></template><space/>is the<space/><link><target>thermodynamic temperature</target><part>absolute temperature</part></link><space/>of the system, dividing an incremental reversible transfer of<space/><link><target>heat</target></link><space/>into that system (<template><target>math</target><arg>''dQ''</arg></template>). (If heat is transferred out the sign would be reversed giving a decrease in entropy of the system.) The above definition is sometimes called the macroscopic definition of entropy because it can be used without regard to any microscopic description of the contents of a system. The concept of entropy has been found to be generally useful and has several other formulations. Entropy was discovered when it was noticed to be a quantity that behaves as a<space/><link><target>function of state</target></link>, as a consequence of the second law of thermodynamics.</paragraph><paragraph>Entropy is an<space/><link><target>Intensive and extensive properties#Extensive properties</target><part>extensive property</part></link>. It has the<space/><link><target>dimension (physics)</target><part>dimension</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>energy</target></link><space/>divided by<space/><link><target>temperature</target></link>, which has a unit of<space/><link><target>joule</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per<space/><link><target>kelvin</target></link><space/>(J&amp;nbsp;K<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup>) in the<space/><link><target>International System of Units</target></link><space/>(or kg&amp;nbsp;m<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>&amp;nbsp;s<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>&amp;nbsp;K<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup><space/>in terms of base units). But the entropy of a pure substance is usually given as an<space/><link><target>Intensive and extensive properties#Intensive properties</target><part>intensive property</part></link><space/>either entropy per unit<space/><link><target>mass</target></link><space/>(SI unit: J&amp;nbsp;K<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup>&amp;nbsp;kg<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup>) or entropy per unit<space/><link><target>amount of substance</target></link><space/>(SI unit: J&amp;nbsp;K<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup>&amp;nbsp;mol<xhtml:sup>1</xhtml:sup>).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>absolute</italics><space/>entropy (<italics>S</italics><space/>rather than<space/><italics>S</italics>) was defined later, using either<space/><link><target>statistical mechanics</target></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>third law of thermodynamics</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the modern microscopic interpretation of entropy in statistical mechanics, entropy is the amount of additional information needed to specify the exact physical state of a system, given its thermodynamic specification. Understanding the role of thermodynamic entropy in various processes requires an understanding of how and why that information changes as the system evolves from its initial to its final condition. It is often said that entropy is an expression of the disorder, or<space/><link><target>randomness</target></link><space/>of a system, or of our lack of information about it. The second law is now often seen as an expression of the<space/><link><target>fundamental postulate of statistical mechanics</target></link><space/>through the modern definition of entropy.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Clausius.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>[[Rudolf Clausius]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>(1822–1888),</arg></template><space/>originator of the concept of entropy</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of entropy</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The analysis which led to the concept of entropy began with the work of French mathematician<space/><link><target>Lazare Carnot</target></link><space/>who in his 1803 paper<space/><italics>Fundamental Principles of Equilibrium and Movement</italics><space/>proposed that in any machine the accelerations and shocks of the moving parts represent losses of<space/><italics>moment of activity</italics>. In other words, in any natural process there exists an inherent tendency towards the dissipation of useful energy. Building on this work, in 1824 Lazare's son<space/><link><target>Nicolas Lonard Sadi Carnot</target><part>Sadi Carnot</part></link><space/>published<space/><italics><link><target>Reflections on the Motive Power of Fire</target></link></italics><space/>which posited that in all heat-engines, whenever &quot;<link><target>caloric theory</target><part>caloric</part></link>&quot; (what is now known as<space/><link><target>heat</target></link>) falls through a temperature difference, work or<space/><link><target>motive power</target></link><space/>can be produced from the actions of its fall from a hot to cold body. He made the analogy with that of how water falls in a<space/><link><target>water wheel</target></link>. This was an early insight into the<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://scienceworld.wolfram.com/biography/CarnotSadi.html</arg><arg name="title">Carnot, Sadi (1796–1832)</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-02-24</arg><arg name="publisher">Wolfram Research</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg></template></extension><space/>Carnot based his views of heat partially on the early 18th century &quot;Newtonian hypothesis&quot; that both heat and light were types of indestructible forms of matter, which are attracted and repelled by other matter, and partially on the contemporary views of<space/><link><target>Count Rumford</target></link><space/>who showed (1789) that heat could be created by friction as when cannon bores are machined.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">McCulloch</arg><arg name="first">Richard, S.</arg><arg name="title">Treatise on the Mechanical Theory of Heat and its Applications to the Steam-Engine, etc.</arg><arg name="publisher">D. Van Nostrand</arg><arg name="year">1876</arg></template></extension><space/>Carnot reasoned that if the body of the working substance, such as a body of steam, is returned to its original state at the end of a complete<space/><link><target>engine cycle</target></link>, that &quot;no change occurs in the condition of the working body&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>first law of thermodynamics</target></link>, deduced from the heat-friction experiments of<space/><link><target>James Joule</target></link><space/>in 1843, expresses the concept of energy, and its<space/><link><target>conservation of energy</target><part>conservation</part></link><space/>in all processes; the first law, however, is unable to quantify the effects of<space/><link><target>friction</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>dissipation</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1850s and 1860s, German physicist<space/><link><target>Rudolf Clausius</target></link><space/>objected to the supposition that no change occurs in the working body, and gave this &quot;change&quot; a mathematical interpretation by questioning the nature of the inherent loss of usable heat when work is done, e.g. heat produced by friction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Clausius"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Clausius</arg><arg name="first">Rudolf</arg><arg name="title">On the Motive Power of Heat, and on the Laws which can be deduced from it for the Theory of Heat</arg><arg name="publisher">Poggendorff's ''Annalen der Physick'', LXXIX (Dover Reprint)</arg><arg name="year">1850</arg><arg name="isbn">0-486-59065-8</arg></template></extension><space/>Clausius described entropy as the<space/><italics>transformation-content</italics>, i.e. dissipative<space/><link><target>energy</target></link><space/>use, of a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>working body</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>chemical species</target></link><space/>during a change of<space/><link><target>thermodynamic state</target><part>state</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Clausius"></extension><space/>This was in contrast to earlier views, based on the theories of<space/><link><target>Isaac Newton</target></link>, that heat was an indestructible particle that had mass.</paragraph><paragraph>Later, scientists such as<space/><link><target>Ludwig Boltzmann</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Josiah Willard Gibbs</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>James Clerk Maxwell</target></link><space/>gave entropy a statistical basis. In 1877 Boltzmann visualized a probabilistic way to measure the entropy of an ensemble of<space/><link><target>ideal gas</target></link><space/>particles, in which he defined entropy to be proportional to the logarithm of the number of microstates such a gas could occupy. Henceforth, the essential problem in<space/><link><target>statistical thermodynamics</target></link>, i.e. according to<space/><link><target>Erwin Schrdinger</target></link>, has been to determine the distribution of a given amount of energy E over N identical systems.<link><target>Carathodory</target></link><space/>linked entropy with a mathematical definition of irreversibility, in terms of trajectories and integrability.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Definitions and descriptions</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote box</target><arg name="align">left</arg><arg name="width">30em</arg><arg name="quote">Any method involving the notion of entropy, the very existence of which depends on the second law of thermodynamics, will doubtless seem to many far-fetched, and may repel beginners as obscure and difficult of comprehension.</arg><arg name="source">[[Willard Gibbs]], ''Graphical Methods in the Thermodynamics of Fluids''<ref>{{cite book|title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There are two related definitions of entropy: the<space/><link><target>Thermodynamics</target><part>thermodynamic</part></link><space/>definition and the<space/><link><target>statistical mechanics</target></link><space/>definition. Historically, the classical thermodynamics definition developed first. In the<space/><link><target>classical thermodynamics</target></link><space/>viewpoint, the system is composed of very large numbers of constituents (atoms, molecules) and the state of the system is described by the average thermodynamic properties of those constituents; the details of the system's constituents are not directly considered, but their behavior is described by macroscopically averaged properties, e.g. temperature, pressure, entropy, heat capacity. The early classical definition of the properties of the system assumed equilibrium. The classical thermodynamic definition of entropy has more recently been extended into the area of<space/><link><target>non-equilibrium thermodynamics</target></link>. Later, the thermodynamic properties, including entropy, were given an<space/><link><target>Statistical mechanics</target><part>alternative definition</part></link><space/>in terms of the statistics of the motions of the microscopic constituents of a system modeled at first classically, e.g. Newtonian particles constituting a gas, and later quantum-mechanically (photons,<space/><link><target>phonons</target></link>, spins, etc.). The statistical mechanics description of the behavior of a system is necessary as the definition of the properties of a system using classical thermodynamics become an increasingly unreliable method of predicting the final state of a system that is subject to some process.<space/></paragraph><heading level='3'>Function of state</heading><paragraph>There are many<space/><link><target>thermodynamic properties</target></link><space/>that are<space/><link><target>functions of state</target></link>. This means that at a particular thermodynamic state (which should not be confused with the microscopic state of a system), these properties have a certain value. Often, if two properties of the system are determined, then the state is determined and the other properties' values can also be determined. For instance, a gas at a particular temperature and pressure has its state fixed by those values, and has a particular volume that is determined by those values. As another instance, a system composed of a pure substance of a single<space/><link><target>Phase (matter)</target><part>phase</part></link><space/>at a particular uniform temperature and pressure is determined (and is thus a particular state) and is at not only a particular volume but also at a particular entropy.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. A. McGovern,<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://theory.phy.umist.ac.uk/~judith/stat_therm/node29.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">2.5 Entropy<space/></arg><arg name="date">20120923080936</arg></template></extension><space/>The fact that entropy is a function of state is one reason it is useful. In the Carnot cycle, the working fluid returns to the same state it had at the start of the cycle, hence the<space/><link><target>line integral</target></link><space/>of any state function, such as entropy, over the cycle is zero.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Reversible process</heading><paragraph>Entropy is defined for a<space/><link><target>reversible process (thermodynamics)</target><part>reversible process</part></link><space/>and for a system that, at all times, can be treated as being at a uniform state and thus at a uniform temperature. Reversibility is an ideal that some real processes approximate and that is often presented in study exercises. For a reversible process, entropy behaves as a conserved quantity and no change occurs in total entropy. More specifically, total entropy is conserved in a reversible process and not conserved in an irreversible process.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/16.unified/www/FALL/thermodynamics/notes/node48.html'>Irreversibility, Entropy Changes, and &quot;Lost Work&quot;</link><space/>Thermodynamics and Propulsion, Z. S. Spakovszky, 2002</extension><space/>One has to be careful about system boundaries. For example, in the Carnot cycle, while the heat flow from the hot reservoir to the cold reservoir represents an increase in entropy, the work output, if reversibly and perfectly stored in some energy storage mechanism, represents a decrease in entropy that could be used to operate the heat engine in reverse and return to the previous state, thus the<space/><italics>total</italics><space/>entropy change is still zero at all times if the entire process is reversible. Any process that does not meet the requirements of a reversible process must be treated as an irreversible process, which is usually a complex task. An irreversible process increases entropy.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.chem1.com/acad/webtext/thermeq/TE2.html'>What is entropy?</link><space/>Thermodynamics of Chemical Equilibrium by S. Lower, 2007</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Heat</target></link><space/><italics>transfer</italics><space/>situations require two or more non-isolated systems in thermal contact. In irreversible heat transfer, heat energy is irreversibly transferred from the higher<space/><link><target>temperature</target></link><space/>system to the lower temperature system, and the combined entropy of the systems increases. Each system, by definition, must have its own absolute temperature applicable within all areas in each respective system in order to calculate the entropy transfer. Thus, when a system at higher temperature<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''T''<sub>H</sub></arg></template><space/>transfers heat<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''dQ''</arg></template><space/>to a system of lower temperature<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''T''<sub>C</sub></arg></template>, the former loses entropy<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''dQ''/''T''<sub>H</sub></arg></template><space/>and the latter gains entropy<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''dQ''/''T''<sub>C</sub></arg></template>. Since<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''T''<sub>H</sub><space/>><space/>''T''<sub>C</sub></arg></template>, it follows that<space/><template><target>math</target><arg>''dQ''/''T''<sub>H</sub><space/>< ''dQ''/''T''<sub>C</sub></arg></template>, whence there is a net gain in the combined entropy.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Carnot cycle</heading><paragraph>The concept of entropy arose from<space/><link><target>Rudolf Clausius</target></link>'s study of the<space/><link><target>Carnot cycle</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>B. H. Lavenda, &quot;A New Perspective on Thermodynamics&quot; Springer, 2009, Sec. 2.3.4,</extension><space/>In a Carnot cycle, heat<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_H</extension><space/>is absorbed at temperature<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_H</extension><space/>from a 'hot' reservoir (an isothermal process), and given up as heat<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_C</extension><space/>to a 'cold' reservoir (isothermal process) at<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_C</extension>. According to Carnot's principle,<space/><link><target>work (physics)</target><part>work</part></link><space/>can only be produced by the system when there is a temperature difference, and the work should be some function of the difference in temperature and the heat absorbed (<extension extension_name='math'>Q_H</extension>). Carnot did not distinguish between<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_H</extension><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_C</extension>, since he was using the incorrect hypothesis that<space/><link><target>caloric theory</target></link><space/>was valid, and hence heat was conserved (the incorrect assumption that<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_H</extension><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>Q_C</extension><space/>were equal) when, in fact,<space/><extension extension_name='math'><space/>Q_H &gt; Q_C</extension>.<extension extension_name='ref'>S. Carnot, &quot;Reflexions on the Motive Power of Fire&quot;, translated and annotated by R. Fox, Manchester University Press, 1986, p. 26; C. Truesdell, &quot;The Tragicomical History of Thermodynamics, Springer, 1980, pp. 7885</extension><space/>Through the efforts of Clausius and<space/><link><target>Lord Kelvin</target><part>Kelvin</part></link>, it is now known that the maximum work that a system can produce is the product of the Carnot efficiency and the heat of the hot reservoir:</paragraph><paragraph>Equation 1:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>W=\left(\frac{T_H-T_C}{T_H}\right)Q_H = \left(1-\frac{T_C}{T_H}\right)Q_H</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In order to derive the Carnot efficiency,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>1-\frac{T_C}{T_H}</extension><space/>(a number less than one), Kelvin had to evaluate the ratio of the work output to the heat absorbed during the isothermal expansion with the help of the Carnot-Clapeyron equation which contained an unknown function, known as the Carnot function. The possibility that the Carnot function could be the temperature as measured from a zero temperature, was suggested by<space/><link><target>James Prescott Joule</target><part>Joule</part></link><space/>in a letter to Kelvin. This allowed Kelvin to establish his absolute temperature scale.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Clerk-Maxwell, &quot;Theory of Heat&quot;, 10th ed. Longmans, Green and Co., 1891, pp. 155158.</extension>It is also known that the work produced by the system is the difference between the heat of the hot reservoir and the heat of the cold reservoir:</paragraph><paragraph>Equation 2:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>W=Q_H-Q_C</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Since the latter is valid over the entire cycle, this gave Clausius the hint that at each stage of the cycle, work and heat would not be equal, but rather their difference would be a state function that would vanish upon completion of the cycle. The state function was called the internal energy and it became the<space/><link><target>first law of thermodynamics</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>R. Clausius, &quot;The Mechanical Theory of Heat&quot;, translated by T. Archer Hirst, van Voorst, 1867, p. 28</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Now equating the two expressions gives</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\frac{Q_H}{T_H}-\frac{Q_C}{T_C}=0<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>or</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\frac{Q_H}{T_H}=\frac{Q_C}{T_C}<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>This implies that there is a function of state which is conserved over a complete cycle of the Carnot cycle. Clausius called this state function<space/><italics>entropy</italics>. One can see that entropy was discovered through mathematics rather than through laboratory results. It is a mathematical construct and has no easy physical analogy. This makes the concept somewhat obscure or abstract, akin to how the concept of<space/><link><target>energy</target></link><space/>arose.</paragraph><paragraph>Clausius then asked what would happen if there should be less work produced by the system than that predicted by Carnot's principle. The right-hand side of the first equation would be the upper bound of the work output by the system, which would now be converted into an inequality&lt;math&gt; W&lt;\left(1-\frac{T_C}{T_H}\right)Q_H&lt;/math&gt;When the second equation is used to express the work as a difference in heats, we get&lt;math&gt; Q_H-Q_C&lt;\left(1-\frac{T_C}{T_H}\right)Q_H&lt;/math&gt;or<extension extension_name='math'><space/>Q_C&gt;\frac{T_C}{T_H}Q_H</extension>So more heat is given off to the cold reservoir than in the Carnot cycle. If we denote the entropies by<space/><extension extension_name='math'>S_i=Q_i/T_i</extension><space/>for the two states, then the above inequality can be written as a decrease in the entropy</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&lt;math&gt;S_H-S_C&lt;0&lt;/math&gt;</listitem></list><paragraph>or</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&lt;math&gt;S_H&lt;S_C&lt;/math&gt;</listitem></list><paragraph>In other words, the entropy that leaves the system is greater than the entropy that entered the system, implying that some irreversible process prevented the cycle from outputting the maximum amount of work as predicted by the Carnot equation.</paragraph><paragraph>The Carnot cycle and efficiency are invaluable as they define the upper bound of the possible work output and the efficiency of any classical thermodynamic system. Other cycles such as the Otto cycle, Diesel cycle, Brayton cycle etcetera can be analyzed from the standpoint of the Carnot cycle. Any machine or process that is claimed to produce an efficiency greater than the Carnot efficiency is not viable as it would violate the second law of thermodynamics. For very small numbers of particles in the system, statistical thermodynamics must be used. The efficiency of devices such as photovoltaic cells require an analysis from the standpoint of quantum mechanics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Classical thermodynamics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Entropy (classical thermodynamics)</arg></template><space/><template><target>Conjugate variables (thermodynamics)</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The thermodynamic definition of entropy was developed in the early 1850s by<space/><link><target>Rudolf Clausius</target></link><space/>and essentially describes how to measure the entropy of an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>thermodynamic equilibrium</target></link><space/>with its parts. Clausius created the term entropy as an extensive thermodynamic variable that was shown to be useful in characterizing the<space/><link><target>Carnot cycle</target></link>. Heat transfer along the isotherm steps of the Carnot cycle was found to be proportional to the temperature of a system (known as its<space/><link><target>absolute temperature</target></link>). This relationship was expressed in increments of entropy equal to the ratio of incremental heat transfer divided by temperature, which was found to vary in the thermodynamic cycle but eventually return to the same value at the end of every cycle. Thus it was found to be a<space/><link><target>function of state</target></link>, specifically a thermodynamic state of the system. Clausius wrote that he &quot;intentionally formed the word Entropy as similar as possible to the word Energy&quot;, basing the term on the<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/><link><target>wikt:</target><part></part></link><space/><italics>trop</italics>, &quot;transformation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Clausius
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rudolf
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ueber verschiedene für die Anwendung bequeme Formen der Hauptgleichungen der mechanischen Wärmetheorie: vorgetragen in der naturforsch. Gesellschaft den 24. April 1865
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1865
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>46
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' group="note">A machine in this context includes engineered devices as well as biological organisms.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While Clausius based his definition on a reversible process, there are also irreversible processes that change entropy. Following the<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link>, entropy of an isolated<space/><link><target>Thermodynamic system</target><part>system</part></link><space/>always increases. The difference between an isolated system and closed system is that heat may<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>flow to and from an isolated system, but heat flow to and from a closed system is possible. Nevertheless, for both closed and isolated systems, and indeed, also in open systems, irreversible thermodynamics processes may occur.</paragraph><paragraph>According to the<space/><link><target>Clausius theorem</target><part>Clausius equality</part></link>, for a reversible cyclic process:<extension extension_name='math'>\oint \frac{\delta Q_\text{rev}}{T} = 0.</extension>This means the line integral<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\int_L \frac{\delta Q_\text{rev}}{T}</extension><space/>is<space/><link><target>State function</target><part>path-independent</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>So we can define a state function<space/><italics>S</italics><space/>called entropy, which satisfies<extension extension_name='math'>d S = \frac{\delta Q_\text{rev}}{T}.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To find the entropy difference between any two states of a system, the integral must be evaluated for some reversible path between the initial and final states.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Atkins</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="author2">Julio De Paula</arg><arg name="title">Physical Chemistry, 8th ed.</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="page">79</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-870072-5</arg></template></extension><space/>Since entropy is a state function, the entropy change of the system for an irreversible path will be the same as for a reversible path between the same two states.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Engel</arg><arg name="first">Thomas</arg><arg name="author2">Philip Reid</arg><arg name="title">Physical Chemistry</arg><arg name="publisher">Pearson Benjamin Cummings</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="page">86</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8053-3842-X</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the entropy change of the surroundings will be different.</paragraph><paragraph>We can only obtain the change of entropy by integrating the above formula. To obtain the absolute value of the entropy, we need the<space/><link><target>third law of thermodynamics</target></link>, which states that<space/><italics>S</italics><space/>= 0 at<space/><link><target>absolute zero</target></link><space/>for perfect crystals.</paragraph><paragraph>From a macroscopic perspective, in<space/><link><target>classical thermodynamics</target></link><space/>the entropy is interpreted as a<space/><link><target>state function</target></link><space/>of a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link>: that is, a property depending only on the current state of the system, independent of how that state came to be achieved. In any process where the system gives up energy<space/><italics>E</italics>, and its entropy falls by<space/><italics>S</italics>, a quantity at least<space/><italics>T</italics><xhtml:sub>R</xhtml:sub><space/><italics>S</italics><space/>of that energy must be given up to the system's surroundings as unusable heat (<italics>T</italics><xhtml:sub>R</xhtml:sub><space/>is the temperature of the system's external surroundings). Otherwise the process will not go forward. In classical thermodynamics, the entropy of a system is defined only if it is in<space/><link><target>thermodynamic equilibrium</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Statistical mechanics</heading><paragraph>The statistical definition was developed by<space/><link><target>Ludwig Boltzmann</target></link><space/>in the 1870s by analyzing the statistical behavior of the microscopic components of the system. Boltzmann showed that this definition of entropy was equivalent to the thermodynamic entropy to within a constant number which has since been known as<space/><link><target>Boltzmann's constant</target></link>. In summary, the thermodynamic definition of entropy provides the experimental definition of entropy, while the statistical definition of entropy extends the concept, providing an explanation and a deeper understanding of its nature.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Entropy (statistical thermodynamics)</target><part>interpretation of entropy in statistical mechanics</part></link><space/>is the measure of uncertainty, or<space/><italics>mixedupness</italics><space/>in the phrase of<space/><link><target>Josiah Willard Gibbs</target><part>Gibbs</part></link>, which remains about a system after its observable macroscopic properties, such as temperature, pressure and volume, have been taken into account. For a given set of macroscopic variables, the entropy measures the degree to which the probability of the system is spread out over different possible<space/><link><target>Microstate (statistical mechanics)</target><part>microstates</part></link>. In contrast to the macrostate, which characterizes plainly observable average quantities, a microstate specifies all molecular details about the system including the position and velocity of every molecule. The more such states available to the system with appreciable probability, the greater the entropy. In statistical mechanics, entropy is a measure of the number of ways in which a system may be arranged, often taken to be a measure of &quot;disorder&quot; (the higher the entropy, the higher the disorder).<extension extension_name='ref' name="McH"><italics>McGraw-Hill Concise Encyclopedia of Chemistry</italics>, 2004</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Sethna78"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Barnes &amp; Noble's<space/><italics>Essential Dictionary of Science</italics>, 2004</extension><space/>This definition describes the entropy as being proportional to the natural logarithm of the number of possible microscopic configurations of the individual atoms and molecules of the system (<link><target>microstate (statistical mechanics)</target><part>microstates</part></link>) which could give rise to the observed macroscopic state (<link><target>macrostate</target></link>) of the system. The constant of proportionality is the<space/><link><target>Boltzmann constant</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Specifically, entropy is a<space/><link><target>logarithmic scale</target><part>logarithmic</part></link><space/>measure of the number of states with significant probability of being occupied:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>S = -k_{\mathrm{B}}\sum_i p_i \ln p_i,</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><italics>k</italics><xhtml:sub>B</xhtml:sub><space/>is the<space/><link><target>Boltzmann constant</target></link>, equal to<space/><template><target>val</target><arg>1.38065</arg><arg name="e">-23</arg><arg name="u">J/K</arg></template>.The summation is over all the possible microstates of the system, and<space/><italics>p<xhtml:sub>i</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>is the probability that the system is in the<space/><italics>i</italics>-th microstate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Perplexed"><link type='external' href='http://charlottewerndl.net/Entropy_Guide.pdf'>Frigg, R. and Werndl, C. &quot;Entropy A Guide for the Perplexed&quot;</link>. In Probabilities in Physics; Beisbart C. and Hartmann, S.Eds; Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2010</extension><space/>This definition assumes that the basis set of states has been picked so that there is no information on their relative phases. In a different basis set, the more general expression is</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>S = -k_{\mathrm{B}} \text{Tr}\,(\widehat{\rho} \ln(\widehat{\rho})),</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\widehat{\rho}</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>density matrix</target></link>,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\text{Tr}</extension><space/>is<space/><link><target>trace (linear algebra)</target></link><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\ln</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>matrix logarithm</target></link>.This density matrix formulation is not needed in cases of thermal equilibrium so long as the basis states are chosen to be energy eigenstates. For most practical purposes, this can be taken as the fundamental definition of entropy since all other formulas for<space/><italics>S</italics><space/>can be mathematically derived from it, but not vice versa.</paragraph><paragraph>In what has been called<space/><italics>the fundamental assumption of statistical thermodynamics</italics><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>Fundamental postulate of statistical mechanics</target><part>the fundamental postulate in statistical mechanics</part></link></italics>, the occupation of any microstate is assumed to be equally probable (i.e.<space/><italics>P</italics><xhtml:sub><italics>i</italics></xhtml:sub><space/>= 1/, where is the number of microstates); this assumption is usually justified for an isolated system in equilibrium.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schroeder, Daniel V.<space/><italics>An Introduction to Thermal Physics</italics>. Addison Wesley Longman, 1999, p. 57</extension><space/>Then the previous equation reduces to</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>S = k_{\mathrm{B}} \ln \Omega.</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In thermodynamics, such a system is one in which the volume, number of molecules, and internal energy are fixed (the<space/><link><target>microcanonical ensemble</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>The most general interpretation of entropy is as a measure of our uncertainty about a system. The<space/><link><target>equilibrium state</target></link><space/>of a system maximizes the entropy because we have lost all information about the initial conditions except for the conserved variables; maximizing the entropy maximizes our ignorance about the details of the system.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.physics.cornell.edu/sethna/StatMech/EntropyOrderParametersComplexity.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">EntropyOrderParametersComplexity.pdf www.physics.cornell.edu<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-17</arg></template></extension><space/>This uncertainty is not of the everyday subjective kind, but rather the uncertainty inherent to the experimental method and interpretative model.</paragraph><paragraph>The interpretative model has a central role in determining entropy. The qualifier &quot;for a given set of macroscopic variables&quot; above has deep implications: if two observers use different sets of macroscopic variables, they will observe different entropies. For example, if observer A uses the variables<space/><italics>U</italics>,<space/><italics>V</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>W</italics>, and observer B uses<space/><italics>U</italics>,<space/><italics>V</italics>,<space/><italics>W</italics>,<space/><italics>X</italics>, then, by changing<space/><italics>X</italics>, observer B can cause an effect that looks like a violation of the second law of thermodynamics to observer A. In other words: the set of macroscopic variables one chooses must include everything that may change in the experiment, otherwise one might see decreasing entropy!<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.mdpi.org/lin/entropy/cgibbs.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jaynes, E. T., "The Gibbs Paradox," In Maximum Entropy and Bayesian Methods; Smith, C. R; Erickson, G. J; Neudorfer, P. O., Eds; Kluwer Academic: Dordrecht, 1992, pp. 1–22<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Entropy can be defined for any<space/><link><target>Markov process</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>reversible dynamics</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>detailed balance</target></link><space/>property.</paragraph><paragraph>In Boltzmann's 1896<space/><italics>Lectures on Gas Theory</italics>, he showed that this expression gives a measure of entropy for systems of atoms and molecules in the gas phase, thus providing a measure for the entropy of classical thermodynamics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Entropy of a system</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:system boundary.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Temperature-entropy chart for steam, US units.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>temperatureentropy diagram</target></link><space/>for steam. The vertical axis represents uniform temperature, and the horizontal axis represents specific entropy. Each dark line on the graph represents constant pressure, and these form a mesh with light gray lines of constant volume. (Dark-blue is liquid water, light-blue is boiling water, and faint-blue is steam. Grey-blue represents supercritical liquid water.)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Entropy is the above-mentioned unexpected and, to some, obscure integral that arises directly from the Carnot cycle. It is reversible heat divided by temperature. It is, remarkably, a function of state and it is fundamental and very useful.</paragraph><paragraph>In a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link>, pressure, density, and temperature tend to become uniform over time because this<space/><link><target>equilibrium state</target></link><space/>has higher<space/><link><target>probability</target></link><space/>(more possible<space/><link><target>combination</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>microstate (statistical mechanics)</target><part>microstates</part></link>) than any other; see<space/><link><target>statistical mechanics</target></link>. As an example, for a glass of ice water in air at room temperature, the difference in temperature between a warm room (the surroundings) and cold glass of ice and water (the system and not part of the room), begins to be equalized as portions of the thermal energy from the warm surroundings spread to the cooler system of ice and water. Over time the temperature of the glass and its contents and the temperature of the room become equal. The entropy of the room has decreased as some of its energy has been dispersed to the ice and water. However, as calculated in the example, the entropy of the system of ice and water has increased more than the entropy of the surrounding room has decreased. In an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>such as the room and ice water taken together, the dispersal of energy from warmer to cooler always results in a net increase in entropy. Thus, when the &quot;universe&quot; of the room and ice water system has reached a temperature equilibrium, the entropy change from the initial state is at a maximum. The entropy of the<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link><space/>is a measure of how far the equalization has progressed.</paragraph><paragraph>Thermodynamic entropy is a non-conserved<space/><link><target>state function</target></link><space/>that is of great importance in the sciences of<space/><link><target>physics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>chemistry</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McH"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wiley91">Sandler S. I.,<space/><italics>Chemical and Engineering Thermodynamics, 3rd Ed.</italics><space/>Wiley, New York, 1999 p. 91</extension><space/>Historically, the concept of entropy evolved in order to explain why some processes (permitted by conservation laws) occur spontaneously while their<space/><link><target>T-symmetry</target><part>time reversals</part></link><space/>(also permitted by conservation laws) do not; systems tend to progress in the direction of increasing entropy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McQuarrie817">McQuarrie D. A., Simon J. D.,<space/><italics>Physical Chemistry: A Molecular Approach</italics>, University Science Books, Sausalito 1997 p. 817</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Haynie</arg><arg name="first">Donald, T.</arg><arg name="title">Biological Thermodynamics</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press]]</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-79165-0</arg></template></extension><space/>For<space/><link><target>isolated system</target><trail>s</trail></link>, entropy never decreases.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wiley91"></extension><space/>This fact has several important consequences in<space/><link><target>science</target></link>: first, it prohibits &quot;<link><target>perpetual motion</target></link>&quot; machines; and second, it implies the<space/><link><target>Entropy (arrow of time)</target><part>arrow of entropy</part></link><space/>has the same direction as the<space/><link><target>arrow of time</target></link>. Increases in entropy correspond to irreversible changes in a system, because some energy is expended as waste heat, limiting the amount of work a system can do.<extension extension_name='ref' name="McH"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Sethna78">Sethna, J.<space/><italics>Statistical Mechanics</italics><space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link><space/>2006 p. 78</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="OxSci"><italics>Oxford Dictionary of Science</italics>, 2005</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">de Rosnay</arg><arg name="first">Joel</arg><arg name="title">The Macroscope&nbsp;– a New World View (written by an [[M.I.T.]]-trained biochemist)</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper & Row, Publishers</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="isbn">0-06-011029-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unlike many other functions of state, entropy cannot be directly observed but must be calculated. Entropy can be calculated for a substance as the<space/><link><target>standard molar entropy</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>absolute zero</target></link><space/>(also known as absolute entropy) or as a difference in entropy from some other reference state which is defined as zero entropy. Entropy has the<space/><link><target>dimension (physics)</target><part>dimension</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>energy</target></link><space/>divided by<space/><link><target>temperature</target></link>, which has a unit of<space/><link><target>joule</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per<space/><link><target>kelvin</target></link><space/>(J/K) in the<space/><link><target>International System of Units</target></link>. While these are the same units as<space/><link><target>heat capacity</target></link>, the two concepts are distinct.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. A. McGovern,<space/><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="url">http://theory.phy.umist.ac.uk/~judith/stat_therm/node50.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Heat Capacities</arg><arg name="date">20120819175243</arg></template></extension><space/>Entropy is not a conserved quantity: for example, in an isolated system with non-uniform temperature, heat might irreversibly flow and the temperature become more uniform such that entropy increases. The<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link>, states that a closed system has entropy which may increase or otherwise remain constant. Chemical reactions cause changes in entropy and entropy plays an important role in determining in which direction a chemical reaction spontaneously proceeds.</paragraph><paragraph>One dictionary definition of entropy is that it is &quot;a measure of thermal energy per unit temperature that is not available for useful work&quot;. For instance, a substance at uniform temperature is at maximum entropy and cannot drive a heat engine. A substance at non-uniform temperature is at a lower entropy (than if the heat distribution is allowed to even out) and some of the thermal energy can drive a heat engine.</paragraph><paragraph>A special case of entropy increase, the<space/><link><target>entropy of mixing</target></link>, occurs when two or more different substances are mixed. If the substances are at the same temperature and pressure, there will be no net exchange of heat or work the entropy change will be entirely due to the mixing of the different substances. At a statistical mechanical level, this results due to the change in available volume per particle with mixing.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Arieh Ben-Naim</target><part>Ben-Naim, Arieh</part></link>, On the So-Called Gibbs Paradox, and on the Real Paradox, Entropy, 9, pp. 132136, 2007<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.mdpi.org/entropy/papers/e9030132.pdf'>Link</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Second law of thermodynamics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Second law of thermodynamics</arg></template>The second law of thermodynamics requires that, in general, the total entropy of any system will not decrease other than by increasing the entropy of some other system. Hence, in a system isolated from its environment, the entropy of that system will tend not to decrease. It follows that heat will not flow from a colder body to a hotter body without the application of work (the imposition of order) to the colder body. Secondly, it is impossible for any device operating on a cycle to produce net work from a single temperature reservoir; the production of net work requires flow of heat from a hotter reservoir to a colder reservoir, or a single expanding reservoir undergoing<space/><link><target>adiabatic cooling</target></link>, which performs<space/><link><target>adiabatic process</target><part>adiabatic work</part></link>. As a result, there is no possibility of a<space/><link><target>perpetual motion</target></link><space/>system. It follows that a reduction in the increase of entropy in a specified process, such as a<space/><link><target>chemical reaction</target></link>, means that it is energetically more efficient.</paragraph><paragraph>It follows from the second law of thermodynamics that the entropy of a system that is not isolated may decrease. An<space/><link><target>air conditioner</target></link>, for example, may cool the air in a room, thus reducing the entropy of the air of that system. The heat expelled from the room (the system), which the air conditioner transports and discharges to the outside air, will always make a bigger contribution to the entropy of the environment than will the decrease of the entropy of the air of that system. Thus, the total of entropy of the room plus the entropy of the environment increases, in agreement with the second law of thermodynamics.</paragraph><paragraph>In mechanics, the second law in conjunction with the<space/><link><target>fundamental thermodynamic relation</target></link><space/>places limits on a system's ability to do<space/><link><target>work (thermodynamics)</target><part>useful work</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Daintith"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Daintith</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Oxford Dictionary of Physics</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-280628-9</arg></template></extension><space/>The entropy change of a system at temperature<space/><italics>T</italics><space/>absorbing an infinitesimal amount of heat<space/><italics>q</italics>in a reversible way, is given by<space/><italics>q/T</italics>. More explicitly, an energy<space/><italics>T<xhtml:sub>R</xhtml:sub>S</italics><space/>is not available to do useful work, where<space/><italics>T<xhtml:sub>R</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>is the temperature of the coldest accessible reservoir or heat sink external to the system. For further discussion, see<space/><italics><link><target>Exergy</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Statistical mechanics demonstrates that entropy is governed by probability, thus allowing for a decrease in disorder even in an isolated system. Although this is possible, such an event has a small probability of occurring, making it unlikely.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://link.aps.org/doi/10.1103/PhysRevE.80.011117<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Entropy production theorems and some consequences," Physical Review E; Saha, Arnab; Lahiri, Sourabh; Jayannavar, A. M; The American Physical Society: 14 July 2009, pp. 1–10<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Link.aps.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Applications</heading><heading level='3'>The fundamental thermodynamic relation</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Fundamental thermodynamic relation</arg></template>The entropy of a system depends on its internal energy and the external parameters, such as the volume. In the thermodynamic limit this fact leads to an equation relating the change in the internal energy to changes in the entropy and the external parameters. This relation is known as the fundamental thermodynamic relation. If the volume is the only external parameter, this relation is:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>dU = T dS - P dV</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Since the internal energy is fixed when one specifies the entropy and the volume, this relation is valid even if the change from one state of thermal equilibrium to another with infinitesimally larger entropy and volume happens in a non-quasistatic way (so during this change the system may be very far out of thermal equilibrium and then the entropy, pressure and temperature may not exist).</paragraph><paragraph>The fundamental thermodynamic relation implies many thermodynamic identities that are valid in general, independent of the microscopic details of the system. Important examples are the<space/><link><target>Maxwell relations</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>relations between heat capacities</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Entropy in chemical thermodynamics</heading><paragraph>Thermodynamic entropy is central in<space/><link><target>chemical thermodynamics</target></link>, enabling changes to be quantified and the outcome of reactions predicted. The<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link><space/>states that entropy in an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>the combination of a subsystem under study and its surroundings increases during all spontaneous chemical and physical processes. The Clausius equation of<space/><italics>q</italics><xhtml:sub>rev</xhtml:sub>/<italics>T</italics><space/>=<space/><italics>S</italics><space/>introduces the measurement of entropy change,<space/><italics>S</italics>. Entropy change describes the direction and quantifies the magnitude of simple changes such as heat transfer between systems always from hotter to cooler spontaneously.</paragraph><paragraph>The thermodynamic entropy therefore has the dimension of energy divided by temperature, and the unit<space/><link><target>joule</target></link><space/>per<space/><link><target>kelvin</target></link><space/>(J/K) in the International System of Units (SI).</paragraph><paragraph>Thermodynamic entropy is an<space/><link><target>Intensive and extensive properties</target><part>extensive</part></link><space/>property, meaning that it scales with the size or extent of a system. In many processes it is useful to specify the entropy as an<space/><link><target>Intensive and extensive properties</target><part>intensive property</part></link><space/>independent of the size, as a specific entropy characteristic of the type of system studied. Specific entropy may be expressed relative to a unit of mass, typically the<space/><link><target>kilogram</target></link><space/>(unit:<space/><template><target>gaps</target><arg>J</arg><arg>kg<sup>−1</sup></arg><arg>K<sup>−1</sup></arg></template>). Alternatively, in chemistry, it is also referred to one<space/><link><target>Mole (unit)</target><part>mole</part></link><space/>of substance, in which case it is called the<space/><italics>molar entropy</italics><space/>with a unit of<space/><template><target>gaps</target><arg>J</arg><arg>mol<sup>−1</sup></arg><arg>K<sup>−1</sup></arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus, when one mole of substance at about<space/><template><target>gaps</target><arg>0</arg><arg>K</arg></template><space/>is warmed by its surroundings to<space/><template><target>gaps</target><arg>298</arg><arg>K</arg></template>, the sum of the incremental values of<space/><italics>q</italics><xhtml:sub>rev</xhtml:sub>/<italics>T</italics><space/>constitute each element's or compound's standard molar entropy, an indicator of the amount of energy stored by a substance at<space/><template><target>gaps</target><arg>298</arg><arg>K</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ctms"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Moore</arg><arg name="first">J. W.</arg><arg name="author2">C. L. Stanistski<space/></arg><arg name="author3">P. C. Jurs<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chemistry, The Molecular Science</arg><arg name="publisher">Brooks Cole</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">0-534-42201-2</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Jungermann"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Jungermann</arg><arg name="first1">A.H.</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="title">Entropy and the Shelf Model: A Quantum Physical Approach to a Physical Property</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Chemical Education</arg><arg name="volume">83</arg><arg name="issue">11</arg><arg name="pages">1686–1694</arg><arg name="doi">10.1021/ed083p1686</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2006JChEd..83.1686J</arg></template></extension><space/>Entropy change also measures the mixing of substances as a summation of their relative quantities in the final mixture.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Levine</arg><arg name="first">I. N.</arg><arg name="title">Physical Chemistry, 5th ed.</arg><arg name="publisher">McGraw-Hill</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="isbn">0-07-231808-2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Entropy is equally essential in predicting the extent and direction of complex chemical reactions. For such applications,<space/><italics>S</italics><space/>must be incorporated in an expression that includes both the system and its surroundings,<space/><italics>S</italics><xhtml:sub>universe</xhtml:sub><space/>=<space/><italics>S</italics><xhtml:sub>surroundings</xhtml:sub><space/>+<space/><italics>S</italics><space/><xhtml:sub>system</xhtml:sub>. This expression becomes, via some steps, the<space/><link><target>Gibbs free energy</target></link><space/>equation for reactants and products in the system:<space/><italics>G</italics><space/>[the Gibbs free energy change of the system] =<space/><italics>H</italics><space/>[the enthalpy change]<space/><italics>T</italics><space/><italics>S</italics><space/>[the entropy change].<extension extension_name='ref' name="ctms"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Entropy balance equation for open systems</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:First law open system.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>During<space/><link><target>Steady-state (chemical engineering)</target><part>steady-state</part></link><space/>continuous operation, an entropy balance applied to an open system accounts for system entropy changes related to heat flow and mass flow across the system boundary.</part></link>In<space/><link><target>chemical engineering</target></link>, the principles of thermodynamics are commonly applied to &quot;<link><target>Open system (systems theory)</target><part>open systems</part></link>&quot;, i.e. those in which heat,<space/><link><target>work (thermodynamics)</target><part>work</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>mass</target></link><space/>flow across the system boundary. Flows of both heat (<extension extension_name='math'>\dot{Q}</extension>) and work, i.e.<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\dot{W}_S</extension><space/>(<link><target>Work (thermodynamics)</target><part>shaft work</part></link>) and<space/><italics>P(dV/dt)</italics><space/>(pressure-volume work), across the system boundaries, in general cause changes in the entropy of the system. Transfer as heat entails entropy transfer<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\dot{Q}/T,</extension><space/>where<space/><italics>T</italics><space/>is the absolute<space/><link><target>thermodynamic temperature</target></link><space/>of the system at the point of the heat flow. If there are mass flows across the system boundaries, they will also influence the total entropy of the system. This account, in terms of heat and work, is valid only for cases in which the work and heat transfers are by paths physically distinct from the paths of entry and exit of matter from the system.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Max Born</target><part>Born, M.</part></link><space/>(1949).<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/naturalphilosoph032159mbp'>''Natural Philosophy of Cause and Chance''</link>, Oxford University Press, London, pp. 44, 146147.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Haase, R. (1971). Survey of Fundamental Laws, chapter 1 of<space/><italics>Thermodynamics</italics>, pages 197 of volume 1, ISBN 0122456017, ed. W. Jost, of<space/><italics>Physical Chemistry. An Advanced Treatise</italics>, ed. H. Eyring, D. Henderson, W. Jost, Academic Press, New York, p. 35.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To derive a generalized entropy balanced equation, we start with the general balance equation for the change in any<space/><link><target>extensive quantity</target></link><space/>in a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link>, a quantity that may be either conserved, such as energy, or non-conserved, such as entropy. The basic generic balance expression states that d/dt, i.e. the rate of change of in the system, equals the rate at which enters the system at the boundaries, minus the rate at which leaves the system across the system boundaries, plus the rate at which is generated within the system. For an open thermodynamic system in which heat and work are transferred by paths separate from the paths for transfer of matter, using this generic balance equation, with respect to the rate of change with time of the extensive quantity entropy<space/><italics>S</italics>, the entropy balance equation is:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Sandler</arg><arg name="first">Stanley, I.</arg><arg name="title">Chemical and Engineering Thermodynamics</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley & Sons</arg><arg name="year">1989</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-83050-X</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\frac{dS}{dt} = \sum_{k=1}^K \dot{M}_k \hat{S}_k + \frac{\dot{Q}}{T} + \dot{S}_{gen}</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\sum_{k=1}^K \dot{M}_k \hat{S}_k<space/></extension><space/>= the net rate of entropy flow due to the flows of mass into and out of the system (where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\hat{S}</extension><space/>= entropy per unit mass).</listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\frac{\dot{Q}}{T}</extension><space/>= the rate of entropy flow due to the flow of heat across the system boundary.</listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\dot{S}_{gen}</extension><space/>= the rate of<space/><link><target>entropy production</target></link><space/>within the system. This entropy production arises from processes within the system, including chemical reactions, internal matter diffusion, internal heat transfer, and frictional effects such as viscosity occurring within the system from mechanical work transfer to or from the system.</listitem></list><paragraph>Note, also, that if there are multiple heat flows, the term<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\dot{Q}/T</extension><space/>will be replaced by<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\sum \dot{Q}_j/T_j,</extension><space/>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\dot{Q}_j</extension><space/>is the heat flow and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_j</extension><space/>is the temperature at the<space/><italics>jth</italics><space/>heat flow port into the system.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Entropy change formulas for simple processes</heading><paragraph>For certain simple transformations in systems of constant composition, the entropy changes are given by simple formulas.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/k-12/Numbers/Math/Mathematical_Thinking/ideal_gases_under_constant.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">GRC.nasa.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">GRC.nasa.gov<space/></arg><arg name="date">2000-03-27<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Isothermal expansion or compression of an ideal gas</heading><paragraph>For the expansion (or compression) of an<space/><link><target>ideal gas</target></link><space/>from an initial volume<space/><extension extension_name='math'>V_0</extension><space/>and pressure<space/><extension extension_name='math'>P_0</extension><space/>to a final volume<space/><extension extension_name='math'>V</extension><space/>and pressure<space/><extension extension_name='math'>P</extension><space/>at any constant temperature, the change in entropy is given by:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = n R \ln \frac{V}{V_0} = - n R \ln \frac{P}{P_0} .</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Here<space/><extension extension_name='math'>n</extension><space/>is the number of<space/><link><target>Mole (unit)</target><part>moles</part></link><space/>of gas and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>R</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>ideal gas constant</target></link>. These equations also apply for expansion into a finite vacuum or a<space/><link><target>throttling process (thermodynamics)</target><part>throttling process</part></link>, where the temperature, internal energy and enthalpy for an ideal gas remain constant.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cooling and heating</heading><paragraph>For heating or cooling of any system (gas, liquid or solid) at constant pressure from an initial temperature<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T_0</extension><space/>to a final temperature<space/><extension extension_name='math'>T</extension>, the entropy change is</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = n C_P \ln \frac{T}{T_0}</extension>.</listitem></list><paragraph>provided that the constant-pressure molar<space/><link><target>heat capacity</target></link><space/>(or specific heat) C<xhtml:sub>P</xhtml:sub><space/>is constant and that no<space/><link><target>phase transition</target></link><space/>occurs in this temperature interval.</paragraph><paragraph>Similarly at constant volume, the entropy change is</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = n C_v \ln \frac{T}{T_0}</extension>,</listitem></list><paragraph>where the constant-volume heat capacity C<xhtml:sub>v</xhtml:sub><space/>is constant and there is no phase change.</paragraph><paragraph>At low temperatures near absolute zero, heat capacities of solids quickly drop off to near zero, so the assumption of constant heat capacity does not apply.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www4.ncsu.edu/~franzen/public_html/CH433/lecture/Third_Law.pdf'>The Third Law</link><space/>Chemistry 433, Stefan Franzen, ncsu.edu</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since entropy is a<space/><link><target>Functions of state</target><part>state function</part></link>, the entropy change of any process in which temperature and volume both vary is the same as for a path divided into two steps - heating at constant volume and expansion at constant temperature. For an ideal gas, the total entropy change is<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.grc.nasa.gov/WWW/K-12/airplane/entropy.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">GRC.nasa.gov<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">GRC.nasa.gov<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-07-11<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = nC_v \ln \frac{T}{T_0} + nR \ln \frac{V}{V_0}</extension>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Similarly if the temperature and pressure of an ideal gas both vary,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S = nC_P \ln \frac{T}{T_0} - nR \ln \frac{P}{P_0}</extension>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Phase transitions</heading><paragraph>Reversible<space/><link><target>phase transition</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>occur at constant temperature and pressure. The reversible heat is the enthalpy change for the transition, and the entropy change is the enthalpy change divided by the thermodynamic temperature. For fusion (<link><target>melting</target></link>) of a solid to a liquid at the melting point<space/><italics>T</italics><xhtml:sub>m</xhtml:sub>, the<space/><link><target>entropy of fusion</target></link><space/>is</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S_\text{fus} = \frac{\Delta H_\text{fus}}{T_\text{m}}.</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Similarly, for<space/><link><target>vaporization</target></link><space/>of a liquid to a gas at the boiling point<space/><italics>T</italics><xhtml:sub>b</xhtml:sub>, the<space/><link><target>entropy of vaporization</target></link><space/>is</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Delta S_\text{vap} = \frac{\Delta H_\text{vap}}{T_\text{b}}.</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Approaches to understanding entropy</heading><paragraph>As a fundamental aspect of thermodynamics and physics, several different approaches to entropy beyond that of Clausius and Boltzmann are valid.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Standard textbook definitions</heading><paragraph>The following is a list of additional definitions of entropy from a collection of textbooks:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>a measure of<space/><link><target>energy dispersal</target></link><space/>at a specific temperature.</listitem><listitem>a measure of disorder in the universe or of the availability of the energy in a system to do work.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gribbin's<space/><italics>Q Is for Quantum: An Encyclopedia of Particle Physics</italics>, Free Press ISBN 0-684-85578-X, 2000</extension></listitem><listitem>a measure of a system's<space/><link><target>thermal energy</target></link><space/>per unit temperature that is unavailable for doing useful<space/><link><target>work (thermodynamics)</target><part>work</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/189035/entropy'>&quot;Entropy&quot;</link><space/><italics>Encyclopdia Britannica</italics></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In Boltzmann's definition, entropy is a measure of the number of possible microscopic states (or microstates) of a system in thermodynamic equilibrium. Consistent with the Boltzmann definition, the second law of thermodynamics needs to be re-worded as such that entropy increases over time, though the underlying principle remains the same.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Order and disorder</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Entropy (order and disorder)</arg></template>Entropy has often been loosely associated with the amount of<space/><link><target>wikt:order</target><part>order</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Randomness</target><part>disorder</part></link>, or of<space/><link><target>Chaos theory</target><part>chaos</part></link>, in a<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target></link>. The traditional qualitative description of entropy is that it refers to changes in the status quo of the system and is a measure of &quot;molecular disorder&quot; and the amount of wasted energy in a dynamical energy transformation from one state or form to another. In this direction, several recent authors have derived exact entropy formulas to account for and measure disorder and order in atomic and molecular assemblies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brooks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Landsberg-A"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Landsberg<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>P.T.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Is Equilibrium always an Entropy Maximum?<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>J. Stat. Physics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>35<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>159–169<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/bf01017372</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1984JSP....35..159L<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Landsberg-B"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Landsberg<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>P.T.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Can Entropy and "Order" Increase Together?<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Physics Letters<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>102A<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>171–173<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0375-9601(84)90934-4</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1984PhLA..102..171L<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>One of the simpler entropy order/disorder formulas is that derived in 1984 by thermodynamic physicist Peter Landsberg, based on a combination of<space/><link><target>thermodynamics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>information theory</target></link><space/>arguments. He argues that when constraints operate on a system, such that it is prevented from entering one or more of its possible or permitted states, as contrasted with its forbidden states, the measure of the total amount of &quot;disorder&quot; in the system is given by:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landsberg-A"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Landsberg-B"></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mbox{Disorder}={C_D\over C_I}.\,</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Similarly, the total amount of &quot;order&quot; in the system is given by:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mbox{Order}=1-{C_O\over C_I}.\,</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In which<space/><italics>C<xhtml:sub>D</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>is the &quot;disorder&quot; capacity of the system, which is the entropy of the parts contained in the permitted ensemble,<space/><italics>C<xhtml:sub>I</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>is the &quot;information&quot; capacity of the system, an expression similar to Shannon's<space/><link><target>channel capacity</target></link>, and<space/><italics>C<xhtml:sub>O</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>is the &quot;order&quot; capacity of the system.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brooks"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Energy dispersal</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Entropy (energy dispersal)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The concept of entropy can be described qualitatively as a measure of energy dispersal at a specific temperature.<extension extension_name='ref'>Frank L. Lambert,<space/><link type='external' href='http://entropysite.oxy.edu/students_approach.html'>A Students Approach to the Second Law and Entropy</link></extension><space/>Similar terms have been in use from early in the history of<space/><link><target>classical thermodynamics</target></link>, and with the development of<space/><link><target>statistical thermodynamics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>quantum mechanics</target><part>quantum theory</part></link>, entropy changes have been described in terms of the mixing or &quot;spreading&quot; of the total energy of each constituent of a system over its particular quantized energy levels.</paragraph><paragraph>Ambiguities in the terms<space/><italics>disorder</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>chaos</italics>, which usually have meanings directly opposed to equilibrium, contribute to widespread confusion and hamper comprehension of entropy for most students.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carson, E. M. and J. R. Watson (Department of Educational and Professional Studies, Kings College, London),<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.rsc.org/pdf/uchemed/papers/2002/p2_carson.pdf'>Undergraduate students' understandings of entropy and Gibbs Free energy</link></italics>, University Chemistry Education 2002 Papers, Royal Society of Chemistry</extension><space/>As the<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link><space/>shows, in an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>internal portions at different temperatures will tend to adjust to a single uniform temperature and thus produce equilibrium. A recently developed educational approach avoids ambiguous terms and describes such spreading out of energy as dispersal, which leads to loss of the differentials required for work even though the total energy remains constant in accordance with the<space/><link><target>first law of thermodynamics</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Frank L. Lambert,<space/><link type='external' href='http://jchemed.chem.wisc.edu/HS/Journal/Issues/2002/Feb/abs187.html'>JCE 2002 (79) 187 [Feb&amp;#93; Disorder A Cracked Crutch for Supporting Entropy Discussions</link></extension><space/>(compare discussion in next section). Physical chemist<space/><link><target>Peter Atkins</target></link>, for example, who previously wrote of dispersal leading to a disordered state, now writes that &quot;spontaneous changes are always accompanied by a dispersal of energy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Atkins</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="title">The Second Law</arg><arg name="publisher">Scientific American Library</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-5004-X</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Relating entropy to energy<space/><italics>usefulness</italics></heading><paragraph>Following on from the above, it is possible (in a thermal context) to regard entropy as an indicator or measure of the<space/><italics>effectiveness</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>usefulness</italics><space/>of a particular quantity of energy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title">Book Review of "A Science Miscellany"</arg><arg name="journal">Khaleej Times</arg><arg name="publisher">Galadari Press, UAE</arg><arg name="date">23 February 1993</arg><arg name="page">XI</arg><arg name="author">Sandra Saary (Head of Science, Latifa Girls’ School, Dubai)</arg><arg name="url">http://DLMcN.com/entropy2.html</arg></template></extension><space/>This is because energy supplied at a high temperature (i.e. with low entropy) tends to be more useful than the same amount of energy available at room temperature. Mixing a hot parcel of a fluid with a cold one produces a parcel of intermediate temperature, in which the overall increase in entropy represents a &quot;loss&quot; which can never be replaced.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus, the fact that the entropy of the universe is steadily increasing, means that its total energy is becoming less useful: eventually, this will lead to the &quot;<link><target>heat death of the Universe</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Entropy and adiabatic accessibility</heading><paragraph>A definition of entropy based entirely on the relation of<space/><link><target>adiabatic accessibility</target></link><space/>between equilibrium states was given by<space/><link><target>Elliott H. Lieb</target><part>E.H.Lieb</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jakob Yngvason</target><part>J. Yngvason</part></link><space/>in 1999.<extension extension_name='ref'>Elliott H. Lieb, Jakob Yngvason:<space/><link type='external' href='http://de.arxiv.org/abs/cond-mat/9708200'>''The Physics and Mathematics of the Second Law of Thermodynamics''</link>, Phys. Rep. 310, pp. 196 (1999)</extension><space/>This approach has several predecessors, including the pioneering work of<space/><link><target>Constantin Carathodory</target></link><space/>from 1909<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Constantin Carathodory:<space/><italics>Untersuchungen ber die Grundlagen der Thermodynamik</italics>,<space/><link><target>Mathematische Annalen</target><part>Math. Ann.</part></link>, 67, pp. 355386, 1909</extension><space/>and the monograph by R. Giles from 1964.<extension extension_name='ref'>Robin Giles: ''Mathematical Foundationsof Thermodynamics&quot;, Pergamon, Oxford 1964</extension><space/>In the setting of Lieb and Yngvason one starts by picking, for a unit amount of the substance under consideration, two reference states<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X_0</extension><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X_1</extension><space/>such that the latter is adiabatically accessible from the former but not vice versa. Defining the entropies of the reference states to be 0 and 1 respectively the entropy of a state<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X</extension><space/>is defined as the largest number<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\lambda</extension><space/>such that<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X</extension><space/>is adiabatically accessible from a composite state consisting of an amount<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\lambda</extension><space/>in the state<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X_1</extension><space/>and a complementary amount,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>(1-\lambda)</extension>, in the state<space/><extension extension_name='math'>X_0</extension>. A simple but important result within this setting is that entropy is uniquely determined, apart from a choice of unit and an additive constant for each chemical element, by the following properties: It is monotonic with respect to the relation of adiabatic accessibility, additive on composite systems, and extensive under scaling.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Entropy in quantum mechanics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>von Neumann entropy</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>quantum statistical mechanics</target></link>, the concept of entropy was developed by<space/><link><target>John von Neumann</target></link><space/>and is generally referred to as &quot;<link><target>von Neumann entropy</target></link>&quot;,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>S = - k_\mathrm{B}\mathrm{Tr} ( \rho \log \rho ) \!</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where is the<space/><link><target>density matrix</target></link><space/>and Tr is the<space/><link><target>trace (linear algebra)</target><part>trace</part></link><space/>operator.</paragraph><paragraph>This upholds the<space/><link><target>correspondence principle</target></link>, because in the<space/><link><target>classical limit</target></link>, when the phases between the basis states used for the classical probabilities are purely random, this expression is equivalent to the familiar classical definition of entropy,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>S = - k_\mathrm{B}\sum_i p_i \, \log \, p_i</extension>,</listitem></list><paragraph>i.e. in such a basis the density matrix is diagonal.</paragraph><paragraph>Von Neumann established a rigorous mathematical framework for quantum mechanics with his work<space/><italics>Mathematische Grundlagen der Quantenmechanik</italics>. He provided in this work a theory of measurement, where the usual notion of<space/><link><target>wave function collapse</target></link><space/>is described as an irreversible process (the so-called von Neumann or projective measurement). Using this concept, in conjunction with the<space/><link><target>density matrix</target></link><space/>he extended the classical concept of entropy into the quantum domain.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Information theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote box</target><arg name="align">right</arg><arg name="width">30em</arg><arg name="quote">I thought of calling it "information", but the word was overly used, so I decided to call it "uncertainty". [...] Von Neumann told me, "You should call it entropy, for two reasons. In the first place your uncertainty function has been used in statistical mechanics under that name, so it already has a name. In the second place, and more important, nobody knows what entropy really is, so in a debate you will always have the advantage."</arg><arg name="source">Conversation between [[Claude Shannon]] and [[John von Neumann]] regarding what name to give to the attenuation in phone-line signals<ref>M. Tribus, E.C. McIrvine, [http://math.library.wisc.edu/reserves/proxy/Math801/energy.pdf Energy and information], Scientiﬁc American, 224 (September 1971), pp. 178–184</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Entropy (information theory)</arg><arg>Entropy in thermodynamics and information theory</arg><arg>Entropic uncertainty</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When viewed in terms of information theory, the entropy state function is simply the amount of information (in the Shannon sense) that would be needed to specify the full microstate of the system. This is left unspecified by the macroscopic description.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>information theory</target></link>,<space/><italics>entropy</italics><space/>is the measure of the amount of information that is missing before reception and is sometimes referred to as<space/><italics>Shannon entropy</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Roger<space/></arg><arg name="last">Balian<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Entropy, a Protean concept</arg><arg name="editor-last">Dalibard</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jean</arg><arg name="title">Poincaré Seminar 2003: Bose-Einstein condensation - entropy</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Birkhäuser</arg><arg name="location">Basel</arg><arg name="isbn">9783764371166</arg><arg name="pages">119&ndash;144</arg></template></extension><space/>Shannon entropy is a broad and general concept which finds applications in information theory as well as<space/><link><target>Maximum entropy thermodynamics</target><part>thermodynamics</part></link>. It was originally devised by<space/><link><target>Claude Shannon</target></link><space/>in 1948 to study the amount of information in a transmitted message. The definition of the information entropy is, however, quite general, and is expressed in terms of a discrete set of probabilities ''p<xhtml:sub>i</xhtml:sub><space/>so that</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>H(X) = -\sum_{i=1}^n p(x_i) \log p(x_i).</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>In the case of transmitted messages, these probabilities were the probabilities that a particular message was actually transmitted, and the entropy of the message system was a measure of the average amount of information in a message. For the case of equal probabilities (i.e. each message is equally probable), the Shannon entropy (in bits) is just the number of yes/no questions needed to determine the content of the message.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Perplexed"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The question of the link between information entropy and thermodynamic entropy is a debated topic. While most authors argue that there is a link between the two,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Brillouin</arg><arg name="first">Leon</arg><arg name="title">Science and Information Theory</arg><arg name="year">1956</arg><arg name="isbn">0-486-43918-6</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Georgescu-Roegen 1971"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Georgescu-Roegen</arg><arg name="first">Nicholas</arg><arg name="title">The Entropy Law and the Economic Process</arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="year">1971</arg><arg name="isbn">0-674-25781-2</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Chen</arg><arg name="first">Jing</arg><arg name="title">The Physical Foundation of Economics – an Analytical Thermodynamic Theory</arg><arg name="publisher">World Scientific</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">981-256-323-7</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Kalinin<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>M.I.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Kononogov<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>S.A.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Boltzmann's constant<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Measurement Techniques<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>48<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>632–636<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s11018-005-0195-9</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Arieh Ben-Naim</target><part>Ben-Naim A.</part></link><space/>(2008),<space/><italics>Entropy Demystified</italics><space/>(<link><target>World Scientific</target></link>).</extension><space/>a few argue that they have nothing to do with each other.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Perplexed"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The expressions for the two entropies are similar. If<space/><italics>W</italics><space/>is the number of microstates that can yield a given macrostate, and each microstate has the same<space/><italics>A priori</italics><space/>probability, then that probability is<space/><italics>p=1/W</italics>. The Shannon entropy (in<space/><link><target>Nat (unit)</target><part>nats</part></link>) will be:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>H = -\sum_{i=1}^W p \log (p)= \log (W)</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>and if entropy is measured in units of<space/><italics>k</italics><space/>per nat, then the entropy is given<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://bayes.wustl.edu/etj/node1.html</arg><arg name="title">Edwin T. Jaynes – Bibliography</arg><arg name="publisher">Bayes.wustl.edu</arg><arg name="date">1998-03-02</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-06</arg></template></extension><space/>by:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>H = k\,\log (W)</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>which is the famous<space/><link><target>Boltzmann's entropy formula</target><part>Boltzmann entropy formula</part></link><space/>when<space/><italics>k</italics><space/>is Boltzmann's constant, which may be interpreted as the thermodynamic entropy per nat. There are many ways of demonstrating the equivalence of &quot;information entropy&quot; and &quot;physics entropy&quot;, that is, the equivalence of &quot;Shannon entropy&quot; and &quot;Boltzmann entropy&quot;. Nevertheless, some authors argue for dropping the word entropy for the<space/><italics>H</italics><space/>function of information theory and using Shannon's other term &quot;uncertainty&quot; instead.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schneider, Tom, DELILA system (Deoxyribonucleic acid Library Language), (Information Theory Analysis of binding sites), Laboratory of Mathematical Biology, National Cancer Institute, FCRDC Bldg. 469. Rm 144, P.O. Box. B Frederick, MD 21702-1201, USA</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Interdisciplinary applications of entropy</heading><paragraph>Although the concept of entropy was originally a thermodynamic construct, it has been adapted in other fields of study, including<space/><link><target>information theory</target></link>,<space/><link><target>psychodynamics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>thermoeconomics</target></link>/<link><target>ecological economics</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>evolution</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brooks"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Brooks</arg><arg name="first">Daniel, R.</arg><arg name="author2">Wiley, E.O.</arg><arg name="title">Evolution as Entropy– Towards a Unified Theory of Biology</arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Chicago Press]]</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg><arg name="isbn">0-226-07574-5</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Avery</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Information Theory and Evolution</arg><arg name="publisher">World Scientific</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">981-238-399-9</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Yockey</arg><arg name="first">Hubert, P.</arg><arg name="title">Information Theory, Evolution, and the Origin of Life</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-80293-8</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Chiavazzo</arg><arg name="first1">Eliodoro</arg><arg name="last2">Fasano</arg><arg name="first2">Matteo</arg><arg name="last3">Asinari</arg><arg name="first3">Pietro</arg><arg name="title">Inference of analytical thermodynamic models for biological networks</arg><arg name="journal">Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications</arg><arg name="volume">392</arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.physa.2012.11.030</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0378437112009958</arg><arg name="pages">1122–1132</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2013PhyA..392.1122C<space/></arg></template></extension>For instance, an entropic argument has been recently proposed for explaining the preference of cave spiders in choosing a suitable area for laying their eggs.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Chiavazzo</arg><arg name="first1">Eliodoro</arg><arg name="last2">Isaia</arg><arg name="first2">Marco</arg><arg name="last3">Mammola</arg><arg name="first3">Stefano</arg><arg name="last4">Lepore</arg><arg name="first4">Emiliano</arg><arg name="last5">Ventola</arg><arg name="first5">Luigi</arg><arg name="last6">Asinari</arg><arg name="first6">Pietro</arg><arg name="last7">Pugno</arg><arg name="first7">Nicola Maria</arg><arg name="title">Cave spiders choose optimal environmental factors with respect to the generated entropy when laying their cocoon</arg><arg name="journal">Scientific Reports</arg><arg name="volume">5</arg><arg name="doi">10.1038/srep07611</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nature.com/srep/2015/150105/srep07611/full/srep07611.html</arg><arg name="pages">7611</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2015NatSR...5E7611C<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Thermodynamic and statistical mechanics concepts</heading><preblock><preline>* Entropy unit a non-S.I. unit of thermodynamic entropy, usually denoted &quot;e.u.&quot; and equal to one<space/><link><target>calorie</target></link><space/>per Kelvin per mole, or 4.184<space/><link><target>Joules</target></link><space/>per Kelvin per mole.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>GoldBookRef</target><arg name="file">E02151</arg><arg name="title">Entropy unit</arg></template></extension></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Gibbs entropy</target></link><space/>the usual statistical mechanical entropy of a thermodynamic system.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Boltzmann entropy</target></link><space/>a type of Gibbs entropy, which neglects internal statistical correlations in the overall particle distribution.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tsallis entropy</target></link><space/>a generalization of the standard Boltzmann-Gibbs entropy.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Standard molar entropy</target></link><space/>is the entropy content of one mole of substance, under conditions of standard temperature and pressure.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Residual entropy</target></link><space/>the entropy present after a substance is cooled arbitrarily close to<space/><link><target>absolute zero</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy of mixing</target></link><space/>the change in the entropy when two different<space/><link><target>chemical substance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>component (thermodynamics)</target><part>components</part></link><space/>are mixed.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Loop entropy</target></link><space/>is the entropy lost upon bringing together two residues of a polymer within a prescribed distance.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Conformational entropy</target></link><space/>is the entropy associated with the physical arrangement of a<space/><link><target>polymer</target></link><space/>chain that assumes a compact or<space/><link><target>globular protein</target><part>globular</part></link><space/>state in solution.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropic force</target></link><space/>a microscopic force or reaction tendency related to system organization changes, molecular frictional considerations, and statistical variations.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Free entropy</target></link><space/>an entropic thermodynamic potential analogous to the free energy.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropic explosion</target></link><space/>an explosion in which the reactants undergo a large change in volume without releasing a large amount of heat.</listitem><listitem>Entropy change a change in entropy<space/><italics>dS</italics><space/>between two<space/><link><target>equilibrium state</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>is given by the heat transferred<space/><italics>dQ<xhtml:sub>rev</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>divided by the<space/><link><target>absolute temperature</target></link><space/><italics>T</italics><space/>of the<space/><link><target>thermodynamic system</target><part>system</part></link><space/>in this interval.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sackur-Tetrode entropy</target></link><space/>the entropy of a monatomic classical ideal gas determined via quantum considerations.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>The arrow of time</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Entropy (arrow of time)</arg></template>Entropy is the only quantity in the physical sciences that seems to imply a particular direction of progress, sometimes called an<space/><link><target>arrow of time</target></link>. As time progresses, the second law of thermodynamics states that the entropy of an<space/><link><target>isolated system</target></link><space/>never decreases. Hence, from this perspective, entropy measurement is thought of as a kind of clock.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cosmology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Heat death of the universe</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Since a finite universe is an isolated system, the Second Law of Thermodynamics states that its total entropy is constantly increasing. It has been speculated, since the 19th century, that the universe is fated to a<space/><link><target>heat death of the universe</target><part>heat death</part></link><space/>in which all the<space/><link><target>energy</target></link><space/>ends up as a homogeneous distribution of thermal energy, so that no more work can be extracted from any source.</paragraph><paragraph>If the universe can be considered to have generally increasing entropy, then as<space/><link><target>Sir Roger Penrose</target></link><space/>has pointed out<space/><link><target>gravity</target></link><space/>plays an important role in the increase because gravity causes dispersed matter to accumulate into stars, which collapse eventually into<space/><link><target>black hole</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><link><target>Black hole entropy</target><part>The entropy of a black hole</part></link><space/>is proportional to the surface area of the black hole's event horizon.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">von Baeyer</arg><arg name="first">Christian, H.</arg><arg name="title">Information–the New Language of Science</arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">0-674-01387-5</arg></template><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="author">Srednicki M</arg><arg name="title">Entropy and area</arg><arg name="journal">Phys. Rev. Lett.</arg><arg name="volume">71</arg><arg name="issue">5</arg><arg name="pages">666–669</arg><arg name="date">August 1993</arg><arg name="pmid">10055336</arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.71.666</arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="bibcode">1993PhRvL..71..666S</arg><arg name="arxiv">hep-th/9303048</arg></template><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="author">[[David J E Callaway|Callaway DJE]]</arg><arg name="title">Surface tension, hydrophobicity, and black holes: The entropic connection</arg><arg name="journal">Phys. Rev. E</arg><arg name="volume">53</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pages">3738–3744</arg><arg name="date">April 1996</arg><arg name="pmid">9964684</arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/PhysRevE.53.3738</arg><arg name="arxiv">cond-mat/9601111</arg><arg name="bibcode">1996PhRvE..53.3738C</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Jacob Bekenstein</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stephen Hawking</target></link><space/>have shown that black holes have the maximum possible entropy of any object of equal size. This makes them likely end points of all entropy-increasing processes, if they are totally effective matter and energy traps. However, the escape of energy from black holes might be possible due to quantum activity, see<space/><link><target>Hawking radiation</target></link>. Hawking has recently changed his stance on some details, in a paper which largely redefined the event horizons of black holes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Buchan</arg><arg name="first">Lizzy</arg><arg name="title">Black holes do not exist, says Stephen Hawking<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cambridge-news.co.uk/News/Black-holes-do-not-exist-says-Stephen-Hawking-20140127060100.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge News</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 January 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The role of entropy in cosmology remains a controversial subject since the time of<space/><link><target>Ludwig Boltzmann</target></link>. Recent work has cast some doubt on the heat death hypothesis and the applicability of any simple thermodynamic model to the universe in general. Although entropy does increase in the model of an expanding universe, the maximum possible entropy rises much more rapidly, moving the universe further from the heat death with time, not closer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Layzer</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Growth of Order in the Universe</arg><arg name="publisher">MIT Press</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg></template></extension><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Chaisson</arg><arg name="first">Eric J.</arg><arg name="title">Cosmic Evolution: The Rise of Complexity in Nature</arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">0-674-00342-X</arg></template></extension><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="editor-last1">Lineweaver</arg><arg name="editor-first1">Charles H.</arg><arg name="editor-last2">Davies</arg><arg name="editor-first2">Paul C. W.</arg><arg name="editor-last3">Ruse</arg><arg name="editor-first3">Michael</arg><arg name="title">Complexity and the Arrow of Time</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-107-02725-1</arg></template></extension><space/>This results in an &quot;entropy gap&quot; pushing the system further away from the posited heat death equilibrium.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Stenger</arg><arg name="first">Victor J.</arg><arg name="title">God: The Failed Hypothesis</arg><arg name="publisher">Prometheus Books</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="isbn">1-59102-481-1</arg></template></extension><space/>Other complicating factors, such as the energy density of the vacuum and macroscopic<space/><link><target>quantum mechanics</target><part>quantum</part></link><space/>effects, are difficult to reconcile with thermodynamical models, making any predictions of large-scale thermodynamics extremely difficult.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">Benjamin Gal-Or</arg><arg name="title">Cosmology, Physics and Philosophy</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer Verlag</arg><arg name="year">1981, 1983, 1987</arg><arg name="isbn">0-387-96526-2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The entropy gap is widely believed<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><space/>to have been originally opened up by<space/><link><target>inflation (cosmology)</target><part>the early rapid exponential expansion</part></link><space/>of the universe.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Autocatalytic reactions and order creation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brownian ratchet</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>ClausiusDuhem inequality</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Configuration entropy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Departure function</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Enthalpy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy (information theory)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy (computing)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy and life</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy (order and disorder)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entropy rate</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Geometrical frustration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Laws of thermodynamics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Multiplicity function</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Orders of magnitude (entropy)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stirling's formula</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thermodynamic databases for pure substances</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thermodynamic potential</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="group">note</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>35em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Atkins</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="author2">Julio De Paula</arg><arg name="title">Physical Chemistry, 8th ed.</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-870072-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">Baierlein, Ralph</arg><arg name="title">Thermal Physics</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-65838-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">[[Arieh Ben-Naim|Ben-Naim]]</arg><arg name="first">Arieh</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="title">Entropy Demystified</arg><arg name="publisher">World Scientific</arg><arg name="isbn">981-270-055-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Callen</arg><arg name="first">Herbert, B</arg><arg name="title">Thermodynamics and an Introduction to Thermostatistics, 2nd Ed.</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-86256-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">Chang, Raymond</arg><arg name="title">Chemistry, 6th Ed.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">McGraw Hill</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-07-115221-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Cutnell</arg><arg name="first">John, D.</arg><arg name="coauthor">Johnson, Kenneth, J.</arg><arg name="title">Physics, 4th ed.</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons, Inc.</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-19113-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Dugdale</arg><arg name="first">J. S.</arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="title">Entropy and its Physical Meaning</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor and Francis (UK); CRC (US)</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7484-0569-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Fermi</arg><arg name="first">Enrico</arg><arg name="authorlink">Enrico Fermi</arg><arg name="year">1937</arg><arg name="title">Thermodynamics</arg><arg name="publisher">Prentice Hall</arg><arg name="isbn">0-486-60361-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">The Refrigerator and the Universe</arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="isbn">0-674-75325-9</arg><arg name="author">Goldstein, Martin; Inge, F</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Gyftopoulos</arg><arg name="first">E.P.</arg><arg name="author2">G.P. Beretta</arg><arg name="year">1991, 2005, 2010</arg><arg name="title">Thermodynamics. Foundations and Applications</arg><arg name="publisher">Dover</arg><arg name="isbn">0-486-43932-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Haddad</arg><arg name="first">Wassim M.</arg><arg name="author2">Chellaboina, VijaySekhar<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Nersesov, Sergey G.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Thermodynamics – A Dynamical Systems Approach</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Princeton University Press]]</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">0-691-12327-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Kroemer</arg><arg name="first">Herbert</arg><arg name="author2">Charles Kittel</arg><arg name="year">1980</arg><arg name="title">Thermal Physics</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">W. H. Freeman Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-1088-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Lambert, Frank L.;<space/><link type='external' href='http://entropysite.oxy.edu/'>entropysite.oxy.edu</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Penrose</arg><arg name="first">Roger</arg><arg name="authorlink">Roger Penrose</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="title">The Road to Reality: A Complete Guide to the Laws of the Universe</arg><arg name="isbn">0-679-45443-8</arg><arg name="publisher">A. A. Knopf</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Reif</arg><arg name="first">F.</arg><arg name="year">1965</arg><arg name="title">Fundamentals of statistical and thermal physics</arg><arg name="publisher">McGraw-Hill</arg><arg name="isbn">0-07-051800-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">Schroeder, Daniel V.</arg><arg name="title">Introduction to Thermal Physics</arg><arg name="publisher">New York: Addison Wesley Longman</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="isbn">0-201-38027-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Serway</arg><arg name="first">Raymond, A.</arg><arg name="title">Physics for Scientists and Engineers</arg><arg name="publisher">Saunders Golden Subburst Series</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="isbn">0-03-096026-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Spirax-Sarco Limited,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.spiraxsarco.com/resources/steam-engineering-tutorials/steam-engineering-principles-and-heat-transfer/entropy-a-basic-understanding.asp'>Entropy A Basic Understanding</link><space/>A primer on entropy tables for steam engineering</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="author">vonBaeyer; Hans Christian</arg><arg name="title">[[Maxwell's demon|Maxwell's Demon]]: Why Warmth Disperses and Time Passes</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-679-43342-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>b:Entropy for beginners</target><part>Entropy for beginners</part></link><space/>a wikibook</listitem><listitem><link><target>b:An Intuitive Guide to the Concept of Entropy Arising in Various Sectors of Science</target><part>An Intuitive Guide to the Concept of Entropy Arising in Various Sectors of Science</part></link><space/>a wikibook</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>entropy</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ER8d_ElMJu0'>Entropy and the Second Law of Thermodynamics</link><space/>- an A-level physics lecture with detailed derivation of entropy based on Carnot cycle</listitem><listitem>Khan Academy: entropy lectures, part of<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL1A79AF620ABA411C'>Chemistry playlist</link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sPz5RrFus1Q'>Proof: S (or Entropy) is a valid state variable</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PFcGiMLwjeY'>Thermodynamic Entropy Definition Clarification</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WLKEVfLFau4'>Reconciling Thermodynamic and State Definitions of Entropy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xJf6pHqLzs0'>Entropy Intuition</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dFFzAP2OZ3E'>More on Entropy</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://oyc.yale.edu/physics/phys-200/lecture-24'>The Second Law of Thermodynamics and Entropy</link><space/>- Yale OYC lecture, part of Fundamentals of Physics I (PHYS 200)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/chemistry/5-60-thermodynamics-kinetics-spring-2008/video-lectures/lecture-9-entropy-and-the-clausius-inequality/'>Entropy and the Clausius inequality</link><space/>MIT OCW lecture, part of 5.60 Thermodynamics &amp; Kinetics, Spring 2008</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=glrwlXRhNsg'>The Discovery of Entropy</link><space/>by Adam Shulman. Hour-long video, January 2013.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Moriarty</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="title">S Entropy</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sixtysymbols.com/videos/entropy.htm</arg><arg name="work">Sixty Symbols</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Brady Haran]] for the [[University of Nottingham]]</arg><arg name="author2">Merrifield, Michael</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Entropy'>Entropy</link><space/><link><target>Scholarpedia</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Statistical mechanics topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Concepts in physics</target></link><link><target>Category:Entropy</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of thermal and statistical physics</target></link><link><target>Category:State functions</target></link></paragraph></article>