<article title='Balfour_Declaration'><paragraph><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>Balfour Declaration of 1926</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox document</target><arg name="document_name"><space/>Balfour Declaration
</arg><arg name="image">Balfour portrait and declaration.JPG
</arg><arg name="image_caption">An image of Balfour and the Declaration
</arg><arg name="date_created"><space/>2 Nov 1917
</arg><arg name="signers"><space/>[[Arthur James Balfour]]
</arg><arg name="purpose"><space/>Confirming support from [[Her Majesty's Government (term)|the British government]] for the establishment in Palestine of a [[Homeland for the Jewish people|"national home"]] for the Jewish people
</arg><arg name="wikisource">Balfour Declaration</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Balfour Declaration</bold><space/>(dated 2 November 1917) was a letter from the United Kingdom's<space/><link><target>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</target><part>Foreign Secretary</part></link><space/><link><target>Arthur James Balfour</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Walter Rothschild, 2nd Baron Rothschild</target></link>, a leader of the British Jewish community, for transmission to the<space/><link><target>Zionist Federation of Great Britain and Ireland</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="His Majesty's government view with favour the establishment in Palestine of a national home for the Jewish people, and will use their best endeavours to facilitate the achievement of this object, it being clearly understood that nothing shall be done which may prejudice the civil and religious rights of existing non-Jewish communities in Palestine, or the rights and political status enjoyed by Jews in any other country.<ref>http://www.mfa.gov.il/mfa/foreignpolicy/peace/guide/pages/the%20balfour%20declaration.aspx</ref><ref>{{cite book| author-link"><space/>Malcolm Yapp| last<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The text of the letter was published in the press one week later, on 9 November 1917.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Schneer</arg><arg name="first">Jonathan</arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration: The Origins of the Arab-Israeli Conflict</arg><arg name="page">342</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>The &quot;Balfour Declaration&quot; was later incorporated into both the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Svres</target><part>Svres peace treaty</part></link><space/>with the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>British Mandate for Palestine (legal instrument)</target><part>Mandate for Palestine</part></link>. The original document is kept at the<space/><link><target>British Library</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The declaration was in contrast to the<space/><link><target>McMahonHussein Correspondence</target><part>McMahon-Hussein correspondence</part></link>, which promised the Arab independence movement control of the Middle East territories &quot;in the limits and boundaries proposed by the Sherif of Mecca&quot; in exchange for revolting against the Ottoman Empire.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><heading level='3'>World War I</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Timeline of World War I</arg></template>In 1914, war broke out in Europe between the<space/><link><target>Triple Entente</target></link><space/>(Britain, France and the<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target></link>) and the<space/><link><target>Central Powers</target></link><space/>(Germany,<space/><link><target>Austria-Hungary</target></link><space/>and later that year, the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link>). The war on the<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Front</part></link><space/>developed into a stalemate. Jonathan Schneer writes:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Thus the view from<space/><link><target>Whitehall</target></link><space/>early in 1916: If defeat was not imminent, neither was victory; and the outcome of the war of attrition on the Western Front could not be predicted. The colossal forces in a death-grip across Europe and in Eurasia appeared to have canceled each other out. Only the addition of significant new forces on one side or the other seemed likely to tip the scale. Britain's willingness, beginning early in 1916, to explore seriously some kind of arrangement with &quot;world Jewry&quot; or &quot;Great Jewry&quot; must be understood in this context.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Schneer</arg><arg name="first">Jonathan</arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration: The Origins of the Arab-Israeli Conflict</arg><arg name="page">152</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Zionism</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Zionism</arg></template><template><target>History of Israel</target></template>In 1896,<space/><link><target>Theodor Herzl</target></link>, a Jewish journalist living in<space/><link><target>Austria-Hungary</target></link>, published<space/><italics><link><target>Der Judenstaat</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;The Jews' State&quot; or &quot;The State of the Jews&quot;), in which he asserted that the only solution to the &quot;<link><target>Jewish Question</target></link>&quot; in Europe, including growing antisemitism, was through the establishment of a state for the Jews. Political Zionism had just been born.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman, Isaiah. &quot;Herzl, Theodor.&quot; Encyclopaedia Judaica. Ed. Michael Berenbaum and Fred Skolnik. 2nd ed. Vol. 9. Detroit: Macmillan Reference USA, 2007. 5466. Gale Virtual Reference Library. Web. 15 April 2010.</extension><space/>A year later, Herzl founded the<space/><link><target>World Zionist Organization</target><part>Zionist Organization</part></link><space/>(ZO), which at its<space/><link><target>First Zionist Congress</target><part>first congress</part></link>, &quot;called for the establishment of a home for the Jewish people in<space/><link><target>Ottoman Palestine</target><part>Palestine</part></link><space/>secured under public law&quot;. Serviceable means to attain that goal included the promotion of Jewish settlement there, the organisation of Jews in the<space/><link><target>Jewish Diaspora</target><part>diaspora</part></link>, the strengthening of Jewish feeling and consciousness, and preparatory steps to attain those necessary governmental grants.<extension extension_name='ref'>Avish, Shimon. &quot;Herzl, Theodor [18601904].&quot; Encyclopedia of the Modern Middle East and North Africa. Ed. Philip Mattar. 2nd ed. Vol. 2. New York: Macmillan Reference USA, 2004. 10211022. Gale Virtual Reference Library. Web. 15 April 2010.</extension><space/>Herzl died in 1904 without the political standing that was required to carry out his agenda of a Jewish home in Palestine.<extension extension_name='ref'>[Cleveland, William L. A History of the Modern Middle East. Boulder, CO: Westview, 2004. Print. p.224]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the first meeting between<space/><link><target>Chaim Weizmann</target></link><space/>and Balfour in 1906, Balfour asked what Weizmann's objections were to the idea of a Jewish homeland in<space/><link><target>Uganda</target></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>Uganda Protectorate</target></link><space/>in East Africa in the<space/><link><target>British Uganda Programme</target></link>), rather than in Palestine. According to Weizmann's memoir, the conversation went as follows:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Mr. Balfour, supposing I was to offer you Paris instead of London, would you take it?&quot; He sat up, looked at me, and answered: &quot;But Dr. Weizmann, we have London.&quot; &quot;That is true,&quot; I said, &quot;but we had Jerusalem when London was a marsh.&quot; He ... said two things which I remember vividly. The first was: &quot;Are there many Jews who think like you?&quot; I answered: &quot;I believe I speak the mind of millions of Jews whom you will never see and who cannot speak for themselves.&quot; ... To this he said: &quot;If that is so you will one day be a force.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Weizmann,<space/><italics>Trial and Error</italics>, p.111, as quoted in W. Lacquer, ''The History of Zionism&quot;, 2003, ISBN 978-1-86064-932-5. p.188</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Two months after Britain's declaration of war on the Ottoman Empire in November 1914,<space/><link><target>Zionist</target></link><space/>British cabinet member<space/><link><target>Herbert Samuel</target></link><space/>circulated a memorandum entitled<space/><italics><link><target>s:The Future of Palestine</target><part>The Future of Palestine</part></link></italics><space/>to his cabinet colleagues. The memorandum stated that &quot;I am assured that the solution of the problem of Palestine which would be much the most welcome to the leaders and supporters of the Zionist movement throughout the world would be the annexation of the country to the British Empire&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The McMahonHussein Correspondence</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>McMahon–Hussein Correspondence#The territorial reservations<space/></arg><arg name="l1">McMahon–Hussein Correspondence</arg></template><link><target>Henry McMahon (diplomat)</target><part>Henry McMahon</part></link><space/>had<space/><link><target>McMahon-Hussein Correspondence</target><part>exchanged letters</part></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Hussein bin Ali, Sharif of Mecca</target></link><space/>in 1915, in which he had promised Hussein control of<space/><link><target>Arab</target></link><space/>lands with the exception of<space/><italics>&quot;portions of<space/><link><target>Syria</target></link>&quot;</italics><space/>lying to the west of<space/><italics>&quot;the districts of<space/><link><target>Damascus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Homs</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hama</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aleppo</target></link>&quot;</italics>. Palestine lay to the southwest of the<space/><link><target>Vilayet of Damascus</target></link><space/>and wasn't explicitly mentioned. That modern-day Lebanese region of the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean</target></link><space/>coast was set aside as part of a future French Mandate. After the war the extent of the coastal exclusion was hotly disputed. Hussein had protested that the Arabs of<space/><link><target>Beirut</target></link><space/>would greatly oppose isolation from the Arab state or states, but did not bring up the matter of<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link><space/>or Palestine. Dr.<space/><link><target>Chaim Weizmann</target></link><space/>wrote in his autobiography<space/><italics>Trial and Error</italics><space/>that Palestine had been excluded from the areas that should have been Arab and independent. This interpretation was supported explicitly by the<space/><link><target>British government</target></link><space/>in the 1922 White Paper.</paragraph><paragraph>On the basis of McMahon's assurances the<space/><link><target>Arab Revolt</target></link><space/>began on 5 June 1916. However, the British and French also secretly concluded the<space/><link><target>SykesPicot Agreement</target></link><space/>on 16 May 1916.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Khouri">Khouri, Fred John (1985). The Arab-Israeli Dilemma. Syracuse University Press. ISBN 978-0-8156-2340-3, pp. 810.</extension><space/>This agreement divided many Arab territories into British- and French-administered areas and allowed for the internationalisation of Palestine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Khouri"></extension><space/>Hussein learned of the agreement when it was leaked by the new<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>Soviet</part></link><space/>government in December 1917, but was satisfied by two disingenuous telegrams from Sir<space/><link><target>Reginald Wingate</target></link>, High Commissioner of Egypt, assuring him that the British government's commitments to the Arabs were still valid and that the Sykes-Picot Agreement was not a formal treaty.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Khouri"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Hussein called on the<space/><link><target>Palestinian people</target><part>Arab population in Palestine</part></link><space/>to welcome the Jews as brethren and co-operate with them for the common welfare.<extension extension_name='ref'>Palestine, a Twice-promised Land?: The British, the Arabs &amp; Zionism, 19151920 By Isaiah Friedman, page 171</extension><space/>Following the publication of the Declaration the British had dispatched Commander<space/><link><target>David George Hogarth</target></link><space/>to see Hussein in January 1918 bearing<space/><link><target>Hogarth Message</target><part>the message</part></link><space/>that the &quot;political and economic freedom&quot; of the Palestinian population was not in question.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Khouri"></extension><space/>Hogarth reported that Hussein &quot;would not accept an independent Jewish State in Palestine, nor was I instructed to warn him that such a state was contemplated by Great Britain&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Huneidi, Sahar (2000).<space/><italics>A Broken Trust: Herbert Samuel, Zionism and the Palestinians, 19201925</italics>. IB Tauris. ISBN 978-1-86064-172-5, p. 66.</extension><space/>Continuing Arab disquiet over Allied intentions also led during 1918 to the British<space/><link><target>Declaration to the Seven</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Anglo-French Declaration</target></link>, the latter promising &quot;the complete and final liberation of the peoples who have for so long been oppressed by the Turks, and the setting up of national governments and administrations deriving their authority from the free exercise of the initiative and choice of the indigenous populations.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Khouri"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://unispal.un.org/UNISPAL.NSF/0/4C4F7515DC39195185256CF7006F878C'>Report of a Committee Set up to Consider Certain Correspondence Between Sir Henry McMahon and the Sharif of Mecca in 1915 and 1916</link>, UNISPAL, Annex A, paragraph 19.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Edward Grey, 1st Viscount Grey of Fallodon</target><part>Lord Grey</part></link><space/>had been the<space/><link><target>Foreign Secretary</target></link><space/>during the McMahon-Hussein negotiations. Speaking in the<space/><link><target>House of Lords</target></link><space/>on 27 March 1923, he made it clear that he entertained serious doubts as to the validity of the British government's interpretation of the pledges which he, as foreign secretary, had caused to be given to Hussein in 1915. He called for all of the secret engagements regarding Palestine to be made public.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/3d14c9e5cdaa296d85256cbf005aa3eb/4c4f7515dc39195185256cf7006f878c!OpenDocument'>Report of a Committee Set Up To Consider Certain Correspondence Between Sir Henry McMahon and The Sharif of Mecca</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://domino.un.org/unispal.nsf/3d14c9e5cdaa296d85256cbf005aa3eb/4c4f7515dc39195185256cf7006f878c!OpenDocument<space/></arg><arg name="date">20090130014731<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Many of the relevant documents in the National Archives were later declassified and published. Among them were the minutes of a Cabinet Eastern Committee meeting, chaired by<space/><link><target>Lord Curzon</target></link>, which was held on 5 December 1918. Balfour was in attendance. The minutes revealed that in laying out the government's position Curzon had explained that:<space/><italics>&quot;Palestine was included in the areas as to which Great Britain pledged itself that they should be Arab and independent in the future&quot;</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>cited in Palestine Papers, 19171922, Doreen Ingrams, page 48 from the UK Archive files PRO CAB 27/24.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>SykesPicot Agreement</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Sykes–Picot Agreement</arg></template>In May 1916 the governments of the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target><part>Russia</part></link><space/>signed the SykesPicot Agreement, which defined their proposed spheres of influence and control in Western Asia should the<space/><link><target>Triple Entente</target></link><space/>succeed in defeating the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>during<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. The agreement effectively divided the Arab provinces of the Ottoman Empire outside the Arabian peninsula into areas of future British and French control or influence.</paragraph><paragraph>The agreement proposed that an &quot;international administration&quot; would be established in an area shaded brown on the agreement's map, which was later to become Palestine, and that the form of the administration would be &quot;decided upon after consultation with Russia, and subsequently in consultation with the other allies, and the representatives of the Sherif of Mecca&quot;. Zionists believed their aspirations had been passed over.<space/><link><target>William Reginald Hall</target></link>, British<space/><link><target>Naval Intelligence Division (UK)</target><part>Director of Naval Intelligence</part></link><space/>criticised the agreement on the basis that &quot;the Jews have a strong material, and a very strong political, interest in the future of the country&quot; and that &quot;in the Brown area the question of Zionism, and also of British control of all Palestine railways, in the interest of Egypt, have to be considered&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Motivation for the Declaration</heading><heading level='3'>British Government</heading><paragraph><link><target>James L. Gelvin</target><part>James Gelvin</part></link>, a Middle East history professor, cites at least three reasons for why the British government chose to support Zionist aspirations. Issuing the Balfour Declaration would appeal to two of<space/><link><target>Woodrow Wilson</target></link>'s closest advisors, who were avid<space/><link><target>Zionism</target><part>Zionists</part></link>.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>The British did not know quite what to make of President Woodrow Wilson and his conviction (before America's entrance into the war) that the way to end hostilities was for both sides to accept &quot;peace without victory.&quot; Two of Wilson's closest advisors,<space/><link><target>Louis Brandeis</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Felix Frankfurter</target></link>, were avid Zionists. How better to shore up an uncertain ally than by endorsing Zionist aims? The British adopted similar thinking when it came to the<space/><link><target>Russia</target><trail>ns</trail></link>, who were in the midst of their revolution. Several of the most prominent revolutionaries, including<space/><link><target>Leon Trotsky</target></link>, were of<space/><link><target>Jews</target><part>Jewish</part></link><space/>descent. Why not see if they could be persuaded to keep Russia in the war by appealing to their latent Jewishness and giving them another reason to continue the fight? ... These include not only those already mentioned but also Britain's desire to attract Jewish financial resources.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gelvin
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Israel-Palestine Conflict: One Hundred Years of War
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>82 and 83</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At that time the<space/><link><target>British Empire</target><part>British</part></link><space/>were busy making promises. At a War Cabinet meeting, held on 31 October 1917, Balfour suggested that a declaration favourable to Zionist aspirations would allow Great Britain &quot;to carry on extremely useful propaganda both in Russia and<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>America</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Palestine Papers 19171922, Doreen Ingrams, page 16</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The cabinet believed that expressing support would appeal to Jews in Germany and America, and help the war effort.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748703545604575407364169729910.html'>''Wall Street Journal'' review of Jonathan Shneer, ''Balfour Declaration''</link><space/>&quot;As Mr. Schneer documents, the declaration was, among much else, part of a campaign to foster world-wide Jewish support for the Allied war effort, not least in the U.S.&quot;</extension><space/>It was also hoped to encourage support from the large Jewish population in Russia. According to James Renton, Senior Lecturer at Edge Hill University, an Honorary Research Fellow at University College London, and author of<space/><italics>The Zionist Masquerade: the Birth of the Anglo-Zionist Alliance: 19141918</italics><space/>(2007), Prime Minister<space/><link><target>David Lloyd George</target></link><space/>of the United Kingdom supported the creation of a Jewish homeland in Palestine because &quot;it would help secure post-war British control of Palestine, which was strategically important as a buffer to Egypt and the Suez Canal.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>James Renton,<space/><italics>The Balfour Declaration: its origins and consequences</italics>,<space/><italics>Jewish Quarterly</italics>, Spring 2008, Number 209, http://www.jewishquarterly.org/issuearchive/articleea91.html</extension><space/>In addition, Palestine was to later serve as a terminus for the flow of petroleum from Iraq via Jordan, three former Ottoman Turkish provinces that became British League of Nations mandates in the aftermath of the<space/><link><target>First World War</target></link>. The oil officially flowed along the<space/><link><target>Mosul-Haifa oil pipeline</target></link><space/>from 19351948, and unofficially up until 1954.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>David Lloyd George</target></link>, who was Prime Minister at the time of the Balfour Declaration, told the<space/><link><target>Peel Commission</target><part>Palestine Royal Commission</part></link><space/>in 1937 that the Declaration was made &quot;due to propagandist reasons.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peel23">Palestine Royal Commission Report, Cmd 5479, 1937, pp2324.</extension><space/>Citing the position of the Allied and Associated Powers in the ongoing war, Lloyd George said, in the Report's words, &quot;In this critical situation it was believed that Jewish sympathy or the reverse would make a substantial difference one way or the other to the Allied cause. In particular Jewish sympathy would confirm the support of American Jewry, and would make it more difficult for Germany to reduce her military commitments and improve her economic position on the eastern front.&quot; Lloyd George then said<extension extension_name='blockquote'>The Zionist leaders gave us a definite promise that, if the Allies committed themselves to giving facilities for the establishment of a national home for the Jews in Palestine, they would do their best to rally Jewish sentiment and support throughout the world to the Allied cause. They kept their word.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peel23"></extension></extension>Regarding the intended future of Palestine, Lloyd George testified:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>The idea was, and this was the interpretation put upon it at the time, that a Jewish State was not to be set up immediately by the Peace Treaty without reference to the wishes of the majority of the inhabitants. On the other hand, it was contemplated that when the time arrived for according representative institutions to Palestine, if the Jews had meanwhile responded to the opportunity afforded them by the idea of a national home and had become a definite majority of the inhabitants, then Palestine would thus become a Jewish Commonwealth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peel23"></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In his<space/><italics>Memoirs</italics>, published in 1939, Lloyd George further elucidated his position:<extension extension_name='ref'>David Lloyd George,<space/><italics>Memoirs of the Peace Conference</italics>, Volume II, New Haven, Yale University Press, 1939; chapter XXIII, pp. 724-734</extension><extension extension_name='blockquote'>The Balfour Declaration represented the convinced policy of all parties in our country and also in America, but the launching of it in 1917 was due, as I have said, to propagandist reasons.... The Zionist Movement was exceptionally strong in Russia and America.... It was believed, also, that such a declaration would have a potent influence upon world Jewry outside Russia, and secure for the Entente the aid of Jewish financial interests. In America, their aid in this respect would have a special value when the Allies had almost exhausted the gold and marketable securities available for American purchases. Such were the chief considerations which, in 1917, impelled the British Government towards making a contract with Jewry.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Britain planned that once Palestine had been conquered, the establishment of a national home for Jewish people, will ward off the inevitable French pressure for an international administration<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Battle for Palestine, 1917<space/></arg><arg name="last">Grainger<space/></arg><arg name="first">John D.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Boydell Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Woodbridge</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84383-263-8</arg></template><space/>p. 178</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Barr2011p60"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Weizmann-Balfour relationship</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:2011-08 Desk Balfour.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Lord Balfour's desk, in the<space/><link><target>Beth Hatefutsoth</target><part>Museum of the Jewish Diaspora</part></link>, in Tel Aviv</part></link>One of the main proponents of a Jewish homeland in Palestine was<space/><link><target>Chaim Weizmann</target></link>, the leading spokesperson in Britain for organised<space/><link><target>Zionism</target></link>. Weizmann was a chemist who had developed a process to synthesize<space/><link><target>acetone</target></link><space/>via<space/><link><target>fermentation (biochemistry)</target><part>fermentation</part></link>. Acetone is required for the production of<space/><link><target>cordite</target></link>, a powerful<space/><link><target>propellant</target></link><space/>explosive needed to fire ammunition without generating tell-tale smoke. Germany had cornered supplies of<space/><link><target>calcium acetate</target></link>, a major source of acetone. Other pre-war processes in Britain were inadequate to meet the increased demand in<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, and a shortage of cordite would have severely hampered Britain's war effort.<space/><link><target>David Lloyd-George</target><part>Lloyd-George</part></link>, then minister for munitions, was grateful to Weizmann and so supported his Zionist aspirations. In his<space/><italics>War Memoirs</italics>, Lloyd-George wrote of meeting Weizmann in 1916 that Weizmann:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>... explained his aspirations as to the repatriation of the Jews to the sacred land they had made famous. That was the fount and origin of the famous declaration about the National Home for the Jews in Palestine .... As soon as I became Prime Minister I talked the whole matter over with Mr Balfour, who was then Foreign Secretary.</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>This may, however, have been only a part of a longer series of discussions about Britain and Zionism held between Weizmann and Balfour which had begun at least a decade earlier. In late 1905 Balfour had requested of Charles Dreyfus, his Jewish constituency representative, that he arrange a meeting with Weizmann, during which Weizmann asked for official British support for Zionism; they were to meet again on this issue in 1914.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harry Defries,<space/><italics>Conservative Party Attitudes to Jews 19001950</italics>, Routledge, 2001, ISBN 978-0-7146-5221-4. pp.5051.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Jewish national home vs. Jewish state</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Homeland for the Jewish people</arg></template>Explication of the wording of the Balfour Declaration is found in the correspondence leading to the final version of the declaration. The phrase &quot;national home&quot; was intentionally used instead of &quot;state&quot; because of opposition to the Zionist program within the British Cabinet. Following discussion of the initial draft the Cabinet Secretary,<space/><link><target>Mark Sykes</target></link>, met with the Zionist negotiators to clarify their aims. His official report back to the Cabinet categorically stated that the Zionists did not want &quot;to set up a Jewish Republic or any other form of state in Palestine immediately&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Strawson</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="authorlink"></arg><arg name="title">Partitioning Palestine: Legal Fundamentalism in the Palestinian–Israeli Conflict</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Penguin Books]]
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London</arg><arg name="isbn">9780745323244</arg><arg name="page">33</arg></template></extension><space/>but rather preferred some form of protectorate as provided in the Palestine Mandate.In approving the Balfour Declaration,<space/><link><target>Leopold Amery</target></link>, one of the Secretaries to the British War Cabinet of 191718, testified under oath to the Anglo-American Committee of Inquiry in January 1946 from his personal knowledge that:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;The phrase 'the establishment in Palestine of a National Home for the Jewish people' was intended and understood by all concerned to mean at the time of the Balfour Declaration that Palestine would ultimately become a 'Jewish Commonwealth' or a 'Jewish State', if only Jews came and settled there in sufficient numbers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">The Palestine Yearbook of International Law 1984</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Martinus Nijhoff]]</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="isbn">9789041103383</arg><arg name="p">48</arg></template></extension></extension>Both the Zionist Organization and the British government devoted efforts over the following decades, including<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Churchill White Paper, 1922</target><part>1922 White Paper</part></link>, to denying that a state was the intention.<template><target>efn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg>See the report of the United Nations Special Committee on Palestine, UN Document A/364, 3 September 1947</arg></template><space/>However, in private, many British officials agreed with the interpretation of the Zionists that a state would be established when a Jewish majority was achieved.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Mansfield</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="authorlink"></arg><arg name="title">The Arabs</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Penguin Books]]</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="pages">176–77</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The initial draft of the declaration, contained in a letter sent by Rothschild to Balfour, referred to the principle<space/><italics>&quot;that Palestine should be reconstituted as the National Home of the Jewish people.&quot;</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Stein</arg><arg name="first">Leonard</arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration</arg><arg name="year">1961</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Simon and Schuster]]</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="page">470</arg></template></extension><space/>In the final text, the word<space/><italics>that</italics><space/>was replaced with<space/><italics>in</italics><space/>to avoid committing the entirety of Palestine to this purpose. Similarly, an early draft did not include the commitment that nothing should be done which might prejudice the rights of the non-Jewish communities. These changes came about partly as the result of the urgings of<space/><link><target>Edwin Samuel Montagu</target></link>, an influential<space/><link><target>anti-Zionist</target></link><space/>Jew and<space/><link><target>Secretary of State for India</target></link>, who was concerned that the declaration without those changes could result in increased<space/><link><target>anti-Semitic</target></link><space/>persecution. The draft was circulated and during October the government received replies from various representatives of the Jewish community. Lord Rothschild took exception to the new proviso on the basis that it presupposed the possibility of a danger to non-Zionists, which he denied.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Palestine Papers 1917–1922: Seeds of Conflict</arg><arg name="first">Doreen</arg><arg name="last">Ingrams</arg><arg name="p">13</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books/about/Palestine_papers.html?id</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Eland Books]]</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781906011383</arg></template></extension><space/>At San Remo, as shown in the transcript of the San Remo meeting on the evening of 24 April, the French proposed adding to the savings clause so that it would save for non-Jewish communities their &quot;political rights&quot; as well as their civil and religious rights. The French proposal was rejected.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Authorship</heading><paragraph>Sir John Evelyn Shuckburgh of the new Middle East department of the Foreign Office discovered that the correspondence prior to the declaration was not available in the Colonial Office, 'although Foreign Office papers were understood to have been lengthy and to have covered a considerable period'.&quot; The 'most comprehensive explanation' of the origin of the Balfour Declaration the Foreign Office was able to provide was contained in a small 'unofficial' note of Jan 1923 affirming that:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>little is known of how the policy represented by the Declaration was first given form. Four, or perhaps five men were chiefly concerned in the labour the Earl of Balfour, the late Sir Mark Sykes, and Messrs. Weizmann and Sokolow, with perhaps Lord Rothschild as a figure in the background. Negotiations seem to have been mainly oral and by means of private notes and memoranda of which only the scantiest records seem to be available.<template><target>efn</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg><arg name="Full text of note included CO 733/58, Secret Cabinet Paper CP 60 (23), 'Palestine and the Balfour Declaration, January 1923. FO unofficial note added 'little referring to the Balfour Declaration among such papers as have been preserved'. Shuckburgh's memo asserts that 'as the official records are silent, it can only be assumed that such discussions as had taken place were of an informal and private character'.<ref>{{cite book|url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In his posthumously published 1981 book<space/><italics><link><target>The Anglo-American Establishment</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Georgetown University</target></link><space/>history professor<space/><link><target>Carroll Quigley</target></link><space/>explained that the Balfour Declaration was actually drafted by<space/><link><target>Alfred Milner</target><part>Alfred, Lord Milner</part></link>. Quigley wrote:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>This declaration, which is always known as the Balfour Declaration, should rather be called &quot;the Milner Declaration,&quot; since Milner was the actual draftsman and was, apparently, its chief supporter in the War Cabinet. This fact was not made public until 21 July 1937. At that time Ormsby-Gore, speaking for the government in Commons, said, &quot;The draft as originally put up by Lord Balfour was not the final draft approved by the War Cabinet. The particular draft assented to by the War Cabinet and afterwards by the Allied Governments and by the United States...and finally embodied in the Mandate, happens to have been drafted by Lord Milner. The actual final draft had to be issued in the name of the Foreign Secretary, but the actual draftsman was Lord Milner.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Quigley</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Carroll</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Carroll Quigley</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-American Establishment</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.alexanderhamiltoninstitute.org/lp/Hancock/CD-ROMS/GlobalFederation%5CWorld%20Trade%20Federation%20-%20136%20-%20The%20Anglo-American%20Establishment.html</arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 1981</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Books in Focus</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-945001-01-0</arg><arg name="page"><space/>169<space/></arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>More recently,<space/><link><target>William D. Rubinstein</target></link>, Professor of Modern History at<space/><link><target>Aberystwyth University</target></link>, Wales, wrote that<space/><link><target>Conservative Party (UK)</target><part>Conservative</part></link><space/>politician and pro-Zionist<space/><link><target>Leo Amery</target></link>, as<space/><link><target>Assistant Secretary</target></link><space/>to the British war cabinet in 1917, was the main author of the Balfour Declaration.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">William D. Rubinstein<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">William Rubinstein<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Secret of Leopold Amery<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Historical Research<space/></arg><arg name="volume">73<space/></arg><arg name="issue">181, June 2000<space/></arg><arg name="pages">175–196<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Institute of Historical Research]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/1468-2281.00102<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reaction to the Declaration</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Balfour Declaration in the Times 9 November 1917.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Balfour Declaration as published in<space/><link><target>The Times</target></link><space/>9 November 1917</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Arab opposition</heading><paragraph>The Arabs expressed disapproval in November 1918 at the parade marking the first anniversary of the Balfour Declaration. The<space/><link><target>Muslim-Christian Associations</target><part>Muslim-Christian Association</part></link><space/>protested the carrying of new &quot;white and blue banners with two inverted triangles in the middle&quot;. They drew the attention of the authorities to the serious consequences of any political implications in raising the banners.<extension extension_name='ref'>Zu'aytir, Akram, Watha'iq al-haraka a-wataniyya al-filastiniyya (19181939), ed. Bayan Nuwayhid al-Hut. Beirut 1948. Papers, p. 5.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=sY27UmuT6-4C&amp;amp;pg=PA32&amp;amp;lpg=PA32&amp;amp;dq=white+and+blue+banners+with+two+inverted+triangles+in+the+middle&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=cw8LTR-SZk&amp;amp;sig=rEUKAgacREQ4UtiBzY2CmrV86lQ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=puQhUNyQF6fK0AGyi4GQDw&amp;amp;ved=0CGAQ6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=white%20and%20blue%20banners%20with%20two%20inverted%20triangles%20in%20the%20middle&amp;amp;f=false'>Cited by Huneidi, Sahar &quot;A Broken Trust, Herbert Samuel, Zionism and the Palestinians&quot;</link>. ISBN 978-1-86064-172-5 p.32.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Later that month, on the first anniversary of the occupation of<space/><link><target>Jaffa</target></link><space/>by the British, the Muslim-Christian Association sent a lengthy memorandum and petition to the military governor protesting once more any formation of a Jewish state.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Petition from the Moslem-Christian Association in Jaffa, to the Military Governor, on the occasion of the First Anniversary of British Entry into Jaffa', 16 November 1918, Zu'aytir papers pp. 78. Cited by Huneidi p.32.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On November 1918 the large group of Palestinian Arab dignitaries and representatives of political associations addressed a petition to the British authorities in which they denounced the declaration. The document stated:<template><target>quote</target><arg>...we always sympathized profoundly with the persecuted Jews and their misfortunes in other countries... but there is wide difference between such sympathy and the acceptance of such a nation...ruling over us and disposing of our affairs.<ref>Benny Morris. The Righteous Victims. 2001 ISBN 0-679-74475-4 p.76</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Zionist reaction</heading><paragraph><link><target>Chaim Weizmann</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nahum Sokolow</target></link>, the principal Zionist leaders based in London, had asked for the reconstitution of Palestine as &quot;the&quot;<space/><link><target>Jewish</target></link><space/>national home. As such, the declaration fell short of Zionist expectations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Balfour Declaration. (2007). In Encyclopdia Britannica. Retrieved 12 August 2007, from<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9011963'>Encyclopdia Britannica Online</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British opinion</heading><paragraph>British public and government opinion became increasingly less favourable to the commitment that had been made to<space/><link><target>Zionist</target></link><space/>policy. In February 1922, Winston Churchill telegraphed Herbert Samuel asking for cuts in expenditure and noting:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>In both Houses of Parliament there is growing movement of hostility, against Zionist policy in Palestine, which will be stimulated by recent<space/><link><target>Alfred Harmsworth, 1st Viscount Northcliffe</target><part>Northcliffe</part></link><space/>articles.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Conservative Party Attitudes to Jews, 1900-1950<space/></arg><arg name="first">Harry<space/></arg><arg name="last">Defries<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Psychology Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">2001<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-07-12<space/></arg><arg name="p">103<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780714652214</arg></template></extension><space/>I do not attach undue importance to this movement, but it is increasingly difficult to meet the argument that it is unfair to ask the British taxpayer, already overwhelmed with taxation, to bear the cost of imposing on Palestine an unpopular policy.<extension extension_name='ref'>CO 733/18, Churchill to Samuel, Telegram, Private and Personal, 25 February 1922. Cited Huneidi, Sahar &quot;A Broken Trust, Herbert Samuel, Zionism and the Palestinians&quot; 2001, ISBN 978-1-86064-172-5, p.57.</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Response by Central Powers</heading><paragraph>Immediately following the publication of the declaration Germany entered negotiations with Turkey to put forward counter proposals. A German-Jewish Society was formed:<space/><italics>Vereinigung jdischer Organisationen Deutschlands zur Wahrung der Rechte der Juden des Ostens</italics><space/>(V.J.O.D.) and in January 1918 the Turkish Grand Vizier, Talaat, issued a statement which promised legislation by which &quot;all justifiable wishes of the Jews in Palestine would be able to find their fulfilment&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>MacMunn, Lieut.-General Sir George (1928)<space/><italics>Military Operations. Egypt and Palestine. From the outbreak of war with Germany to June 1917.</italics><space/>HMSO. Pages 219,220.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Faisal-Weizmann Agreement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>British Mandate of Palestine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gathering of Israel</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>1947 UN Partition Plan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Declaration of Independence (Israel)</target><part>Declaration of Independence</part></link>, 14 May 1948</listitem><listitem><link><target>Madagascar Plan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>British Uganda Program</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>notelist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em<space/></arg><arg name="refs">

<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Schneer</arg><arg name="first">Jonathan</arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration: The Origins of the Arab-Israeli Conflict</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="date">2010</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4000-6532-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Smith</arg><arg name="first">Charles</arg><arg name="title">Palestine and the Arab-Israeli conflict</arg><arg name="place">Boston</arg><arg name="publisher">Bedford/St. Martin's</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Stein</arg><arg name="first">Leonard</arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration</arg><arg name="place">London</arg><arg name="date">1964</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://archive.timesonline.co.uk/tol/viewArticle.arc?articleId=ARCHIVE-The_Times-1917-11-09-07-010&amp;amp;pageId=ARCHIVE-The_Times-1917-11-09-07'>Original article reprinting the declaration from ''The Times'', 9 November 1917</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.knesset.gov.il/lexicon/eng/BalfourDeclaration_eng.htm'>Balfour Declaration lexicon entry</link><space/>Knesset website<space/><template><target>en icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://fr.jpost.com/servlet/Satellite?cid=1225199622058&amp;amp;pagename=JPost/JPArticle/ShowFull'>Happy Birthday Balfour Declaration- 91 Years Later- Jerusalem Post</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/mideast/brwh1922.htm'>Text of the 1922 White Paper</link><space/>from the Avalon Project</listitem><listitem>Donald Macintyre, The Independent, 26 May 2005,<space/><link type='external' href='http://news.independent.co.uk/world/middle_east/article223199.ece'>&quot;The birth of modern Israel: A scrap of paper that changed history&quot;</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://users.ox.ac.uk/~ssfc0005/The%20Balfour%20Declaration%20and%20its%20consequences.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Balfour Declaration and Its Consequences<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 June 2007<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Avi Shlaim<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.maannews.net/en/index.php?opr=ShowDetails&amp;amp;ID=26110'>Balfour: 117 words that changed the face of the Middle East</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://palestine-mandate.com/from-the-balfour-declaration-to-partition-to-two-states'>From the Balfour Declaration to Partition to Two States?</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jewishmag.com/145mag/herzl_hechler/herzl_hechler.htm'>Theodore Herzl and Rev. William Hechler and the Zionist Beginnings</link></listitem><listitem>http://www.jewish-american-society-for-historic-preservation.org/images/Brandeis_Blackstone_article.doc</listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Documents of Mandate Palestine</target></template><template><target>ArabIsraeli conflict</target></template><template><target>ArabIsraeli diplomacy</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Balfour Declaration Of 1917</target></template><link><target>Category:1917 in international relations</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 works</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 in Ottoman Syria</target></link><link><target>Category:Pro-Jewish edicts</target></link><link><target>Category:Historical documents</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Israel</target></link><link><target>Category:Israeli Declaration of Independence</target></link><link><target>Category:Official documents of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Zionism</target></link><link><target>Category:Zionism in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:World War I documents</target></link><link><target>Category:Documents of Mandatory Palestine</target></link><link><target>Category:Proclamations</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 in British-administered Palestine</target></link></paragraph></article>