<article title='Acts_of_the_Apostles'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the book in the Christian New Testament</arg><arg>the literature genre</arg><arg>Acts of the Apostles (genre)</arg><arg>the acronym</arg><arg>ACTS (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>uses of Act</arg><arg>Act (disambiguation){{!}}Act</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the New Testament</target></template>The<space/><bold>Acts of the Apostles</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-grc</target><arg>Πράξεις τῶν Ἀποστόλων</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Prxeis tn Apostln</italics>;<space/><template><target>lang-la</target><arg>Āctūs Apostolōrum</arg></template>), often referred to simply as<space/><bold>Acts</bold>, is the fifth book of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>; it tells of the founding of the<space/><link><target>Christian church</target></link><space/>and the spread of its message to the<space/><link><target>Roman empire</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">263</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Acts and the<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link><space/>make up a two-part work,<space/><link><target>Luke-Acts</target></link>, by the same anonymous author, usually dated to around 80-90 AD.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Charlesworth</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">no page number</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">195</arg></template><space/>The first part, the<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link>, tells how<space/><link><target>God in Christianity</target><part>God</part></link><space/>fulfilled his plan for the world's<space/><link><target>Salvation (Christianity)</target><part>salvation</part></link><space/>through the life, death and resurrection of<space/><link><target>Jesus of Nazareth</target></link>, the promised<space/><link><target>Messiah</target></link>. Acts continues the story of<space/><link><target>Christianity in the 1st century</target></link>, beginning with Jesus'<space/><link><target>Ascension of Jesus</target><part>Ascension</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Heaven</target></link>. The early chapters, set in<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem</target><part>Jerusalem</part></link>, describe the<space/><link><target>Pentecost</target><part>Day of Pentecost</part></link><space/>(the coming of the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link>) and the growth of the church in Jerusalem. Initially the Jews are receptive to the Christian message, but soon they turn against the followers of Jesus. Rejected by the Jews, under the guidance of the<space/><link><target>Apostle Peter</target></link><space/>the message is taken to the<space/><link><target>Gentiles</target></link>. The later chapters tell of<space/><link><target>Conversion of Paul the Apostle</target><part>Paul's conversion</part></link>, his mission in Asia Minor and the Aegean, and finally his imprisonment in Rome, where, as the book ends, he awaits trial.</paragraph><paragraph>Luke-Acts is an attempt to answer a theological problem, namely how the Messiah of the Jews came to have an overwhelmingly non-Jewish church; the answer it provides, and its central theme, is that the message of Christ was sent to the Gentiles because the<space/><link><target>Rejection of Jesus</target><part>Jews rejected it</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">263</arg></template><space/>Luke-Acts can be also seen as a defense of (or &quot;apology&quot; for) the Jesus movement addressed to the Jews: the bulk of the speeches and sermons in Acts are addressed to Jewish audiences, with the Romans featuring as external arbiters on disputes concerning Jewish customs and law.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pickett</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">6-7</arg></template><space/>On the one hand Luke portrays the Christians as a sect of the Jews, and therefore entitled to legal protection as a recognised religion; on the other, Luke seems unclear as to the future God intends for Jews and Christians, celebrating the Jewishness of Jesus and his immediate followers while also stressing how the Jews had rejected God's promised Messiah.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">563</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition and setting</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Authorship of Luke–Acts</arg></template><link><target>File:ApostleFedorZubov.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>240px</part><part>Ministry of the Apostles:<space/><link><target>Russian icons</target><part>Russian icon</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Fyodor Zubov</target></link>, 1660</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Title, unity of Luke-Acts, authorship and date</heading><paragraph>The title &quot;Acts of the Apostles&quot; (<link><target>Ancient Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>Πράξεις ἀποστόλων</arg></template><space/><italics>Praxeis Apostolon</italics>) was first used by<space/><link><target>Irenaeus</target></link><space/>in the late 2nd century. It is not known whether this was an existing title or one invented by Irenaeus; it does seem clear, however, that it was not given by the author.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">12</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The gospel of Luke and Acts make up a two-volume work which scholars call<space/><link><target>Luke-Acts</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">195</arg></template><space/>Together they account for 27.5% of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>, the largest contribution attributed to a single author, providing the framework for both the Church's liturgical calendar and the historical outline into which later generations have fitted their idea of the story of Jesus and the early church.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">556</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The author is not named in either volume.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">196</arg></template><space/>According to Church tradition dating from the 2nd century, he was the &quot;Luke&quot; named as a companion of the<space/><link><target>apostle Paul</target></link><space/>in three of the letters attributed to Paul himself; this view is still sometimes advanced, but &quot;a critical consensus emphasizes the countless contradictions between the account in Acts and the authentic Pauline letters.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Theissen</arg><arg>Merz</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">32</arg></template><space/>(An example can be seen by comparing Acts' accounts of Paul's conversion (Acts 9:1-31, 22:6-21, and 26:9-23) with Paul's own statement that he remained unknown to Christians in Judea after that event (Galatians 1:17-24).)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Perkins</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">253</arg></template><space/>He admired Paul, but his theology was significantly different from Paul's on key points and he does not (in Acts) represent Paul's views accurately.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">590</arg></template><space/>He was educated, a man of means, probably urban, and someone who respected manual work, although not a worker himself; this is significant, because more high-brow writers of the time looked down on the artisans and small business-people who made up the early church of Paul and were presumably Luke's audience.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Green</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest possible date for the composition of Acts is set by the events with which it ends, Paul's imprisonment in Rome c.63 CE, but an early date is now rarely put forward.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">587</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Theissen</arg><arg>Merz</arg><arg>1996 [tr. 1998]</arg><arg name="p">32</arg></template><space/>The last possible date would be set by its first definite citation by another author, but there is no unanimity on this some scholars find echoes of Acts in a work from c.95 CE called<space/><link><target>I Clement</target></link>, while others see no indisputable citation until the middle of the 2nd century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">587</arg></template><space/>If Acts uses<space/><link><target>Josephus</target></link><space/>as a source, as has been proposed, then it must have been composed after 93 CE; it does not show any knowledge of Paul's letters, a fact which also supports a late date; and the social situation it reflects is one in which the faithful need &quot;shepherds&quot; to protect them from heretical (possibly<space/><link><target>Marcion</target><trail>ite</trail></link>) &quot;wolves&quot;, which again reflects a late date.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">587</arg></template><space/>Most experts therefore date it to around 80-90 CE, although some suggest 90-110,<space/><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Charlesworth</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">no page number</arg></template><space/>and there is evidence that it was still being substantially revised well into the 2nd century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Perkins</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">250-253</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Genre, sources and historicity of Acts</heading><paragraph>Luke (or more accurately the anonymous author of Luke-Acts) aligned his work, Luke-Acts, to the &quot;narratives&quot; (,<space/><italics>diegesis</italics>) which many others had written, and described his own work as an &quot;orderly account&quot; ( ).<extension extension_name='ref'>Luke 1:1,3</extension><space/>Acts, the second part, is widely thought of as a history, but it lacks exact analogies in Hellenistic or Jewish literature.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Aune</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">77</arg></template><space/>The title &quot;Acts of the Apostles&quot; (<italics>Praxeis Apostolon</italics>) would seem to identify it with the genre telling of the deeds and achievements of great men (<italics>praxeis</italics>), but it was not the title given by the author.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">12</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Luke seems to have taken as his model the works of two respected Classical authors,<space/><link><target>Dionysius of Halicarnassus</target></link>, who wrote a well-known history of Rome, and the Jewish historian<space/><link><target>Josephus</target></link>, author of a<space/><link><target>Antiquities of the Jews</target><part>history of the Jews</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Balch</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">1104</arg></template><space/>Like them, he anchors his history by dating the birth of the founder (Romulus for Dionysius, Moses for Josephus, Jesus for Luke) and like them he tells how the founder is born from God, taught authoritatively, and appeared to witnesses after death before ascending to heaven.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Balch</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">1104</arg></template><space/>By and large the sources for Acts can only be guessed at,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bruce</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">40</arg></template><space/>but Luke would have had access to the<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link><space/>(a Greek translation of the Jewish scriptures), the<space/><link><target>gospel of Mark</target></link><space/>and the collection of &quot;sayings of Jesus&quot; called the<space/><link><target>Q source</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">577</arg></template><space/>He transposed a few incidents from Mark's gospel to the time of the Apostles for example, the material about &quot;clean&quot; and &quot;unclean&quot; foods in Mark 7 is used in Acts 10, and Mark's account of the accusation that Jesus has attacked the Temple (Mark 14:58) is used in a story about Stephen (Acts 6:14).)<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Witherington</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">8</arg></template><space/>There are also points of contacts (meaning suggestive parallels but something less than clear evidence) with<space/><link><target>1 Peter</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Letter to the Hebrews</target></link>, and 1 Clement.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">578</arg></template><space/>Other sources can only be inferred from internal evidence the traditional explanation of the three &quot;we&quot; passages, for example, is that they represent eye-witness accounts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bruce</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="p">40-41</arg></template><space/>The search for such inferred sources was popular in the 19th century, but by the mid-20th it had largely been abandoned.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">579</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Acts was read as a reliable history of the early church well into the post-Reformation era. By the 17th century, however, biblical scholars began to notice that it was incomplete and tendentious its picture of a harmonious church is quite at odds with that given by Paul's letters, and it omits important events such as the deaths of both Peter and Paul. The mid-19th century scholar<space/><link><target>Ferdinand Christian Baur</target><part>Ferdinand Baur</part></link><space/>suggested that Luke had re-written history to present a united Peter and Paul and advance a single orthodoxy against the<space/><link><target>Marcion</target><trail>ites</trail></link>. (Marcion was a 2nd-century heretic who wished to cut Christianity off entirely from the Jews). Baur continues to have enormous influence, but today there is less interest in determining Luke's historical accuracy (although this has never died out) than in understanding his theological program.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Holladay</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">no page numbers</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Audience and authorial intent</heading><paragraph>Luke was written to be read aloud to a group of Jesus-followers gathered in a house to share the Lord's supper.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Balch</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">1104</arg></template><space/>The author assumes an educated Greek-speaking audience, but directs his attention to specifically Christian concerns rather than to the Greco-Roman world at large.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Green</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">16-17</arg></template><space/>He begins his gospel with a preface addressed to<space/><link><target>Theophilus (biblical)</target><part>Theophilus</part></link>, informing him of his intention to provide an &quot;ordered account&quot; of events which will lead his reader to &quot;certainty&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Green</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template><space/>He did not write in order to provide Theophilus with historical justification &quot;did it happen?&quot; but to encourage faith &quot;what happened, and what does it all mean?&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Green</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">36</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Acts (or Luke-Acts) is intended as a work of &quot;edification.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Fitzmyer</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">55-65</arg></template><space/>Edification means &quot;the empirical demonstration that virtue is superior to vice,&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Aune</arg><arg>1988</arg><arg name="p">80</arg></template><space/>but is not all of Luke's purpose. He also engages with the question of a Christian's proper relationship with the Roman Empire, the civil power of the day: could a Christian obey God and also Caesar? The answer is ambiguous.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Pickett</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">6-7</arg></template><space/>The Romans never move against Jesus or his followers unless provoked by the Jews, in the trial scenes the Christian missionaries are always cleared of charges of violating Roman laws, and Acts ends with Paul in Rome proclaiming the Christian message under Roman protection; at the same time, Luke makes clear that the Romans, like all earthly rulers, receive their authority from Satan, while Christ is ruler of the<space/><link><target>kingdom of God</target></link>.<space/><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">562</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Manuscripts</heading><paragraph>There are two major textual variants of Luke-Acts, the<space/><link><target>Western text-type</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Alexandrian text-type</target><part>Alexandrian</part></link>. The oldest complete Alexandrian manuscripts date from the 4th century and the oldest Western ones from the 6th, with fragments and citations going back to the 3rd. Western texts of Acts are 10% longer than Alexandrian texts, the additions tending to enhance the Jewish rejection of the Messiah and the role of the Holy Spirit, in ways that are stylistically different from the rest of Acts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Thompson</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">332</arg></template><space/>These conflicts suggest that Luke-Acts was still being substantially revised well into the 2nd century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Perkins</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">250-253</arg></template><space/>The majority of scholars prefer the Alexandrian (shorter) text-type over the Western as the more authentic, but this same argument would favour the Western over the Alexandrian for the gospel of Luke, as in that case the Western version is the shorter. The debate therefore continues.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Thompson</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">332</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure and content</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Minuscule 223 (GA) f11r.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Acts 1:1-2a from the 14th century<space/><link><target>Minuscule 223</target></link></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Structure</heading><paragraph>Acts has two key structural principles. The first is the geographic movement from Jerusalem, centre of God's Covenantal people the Jews, to Rome, centre of the Gentile world. This structure reaches back to the author's preceding work, the<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link>, and is signaled by parallel scenes such as Paul's utterance in Acts 19:21, which echoes Jesus' words 9:51 (Paul has Rome as his destination, as Jesus had Jerusalem). The second key element is the roles of Peter and Paul, the first representing the Jewish Christian church, the second the mission to the Gentiles.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">569-570</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Transition: reprise of the preface addressed to Theophilus and the closing events of the gospel (Acts 1-1:26)</listitem><listitem>Petrine Christianity: the Jewish church from Jerusalem to Antioch (Acts 2:1-12:25)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>2:1-8:1 - beginnings in Jerusalem</listitem><listitem>8:2-40 - the church expands to Samaria and beyond</listitem><listitem>9:1-31 - conversion of Paul</listitem><listitem>9:32-12:25 - the conversion of Cornelius, and the formation of the Antioch church</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Pauline Christianity: the Gentile mission from Antioch to Rome (Acts 13:1-28:21)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>13:1-14:28 - the Gentile mission is promoted from Antioch</listitem><listitem>15:1-35 - the Gentile mission is confirmed in Jerusalem</listitem><listitem>15:36-28:31 - the Gentile mission, climaxing in Paul's passion story in Rome (21:17-28:31)</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Outline</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Dedication to<space/><link><target>Theophilus (Biblical)</target><part>Theophilus</part></link><space/>(1:12)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Resurrection appearances of Jesus</target><part>Resurrection appearances</part></link><space/>(1:3)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Great Commission</target></link><space/>(1:48)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ascension of Jesus Christ</target><part>Ascension</part></link><space/>(1:9)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Second Coming</target><part>Second Coming Prophecy</part></link><space/>(1:1011)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Saint Matthias</target><part>Matthias</part></link><space/>replaced<space/><link><target>Judas Iscariot</target><part>Judas</part></link><space/>(1:1226)<list type='bullet'><listitem>the<space/><italics><link><target>Cenacle</target><part>Upper Room</part></link></italics><space/>(1:13)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link><space/>came at<space/><link><target>Pentecost</target></link><space/>(2), see also<space/><link><target>Paraclete</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>St. Peter</target><part>Peter</part></link><space/>healed a crippled beggar (3:110)</listitem><listitem>Peter's speech at the<space/><link><target>Herod's Temple</target><part>Temple</part></link><space/>(3:1126)</listitem><listitem>Peter and<space/><link><target>John the Apostle</target><part>John</part></link><space/>before the<space/><link><target>Sanhedrin</target></link><space/>(4:122)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Resurrection of the dead</target></link><space/>(4:2)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Prayer in the New Testament</target><part>Believers' Prayer</part></link><space/>(4:2331)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Christianity and politics</target><part>Everything is shared</part></link><space/>(4:3237)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ananias and Sapphira</target></link><space/>(5:111)</listitem><listitem>Signs and Wonders (5:1216)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Apostles</target></link><space/>before the Sanhedrin (5:1742)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Seven Deacons</target><part>Seven Greeks appointed</part></link><space/>(6:17)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Saint Stephen</target></link><space/>before the Sanhedrin (6:87:60)<list type='bullet'><listitem>The &quot;<link><target>Cave of the Patriarchs</target></link>&quot; was located in<space/><link><target>Shechem</target></link><space/>(7:16)</listitem><listitem>&quot;Moses was educated in all the wisdom of the Egyptians&quot; (7:22)</listitem><listitem>First mentioning of Saul (Paul the Apostle) in the Bible (7:58)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul the Apostle#Early life</target><part>Paul the Apostle</part></link><space/>confesses his part in the martyrdom of<space/><link><target>Saint Stephen</target><part>Stephen</part></link><space/>(7:58-60)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Saul persecuted the<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem</target><part>Church of Jerusalem</part></link><space/>(8:13)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Philip the Evangelist</target></link><space/>(8:440)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Simon Magus</target></link><space/>(8:924)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ethiopian eunuch</target></link><space/>(8:2639)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conversion of Paul the Apostle</target></link><space/>(9:131, 22:122, 26:924)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paul the Apostle#Early life</target><part>Paul the Apostle</part></link><space/>confesses his active part in the martyrdom of<space/><link><target>Saint Stephen</target><part>Stephen</part></link><space/>(22:20)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Peter healed<space/><link><target>Aeneas (Bible)</target><part>Aeneas</part></link><space/>and raised<space/><link><target>Dorcas</target><part>Tabitha</part></link><space/>from the dead (9:3243)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Centurion Cornelius</target><part>Conversion of Cornelius</part></link><space/>(10:18, 2448)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter's vision of a sheet with animals</target></link><space/>(10:923, 11:118)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Antioch</target><part>Church of Antioch</part></link><space/>founded (11:1930)<list type='bullet'><listitem>term &quot;<link><target>Christian</target></link>&quot; first used (11:26)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Saint James the Great</target></link><space/>executed (12:12)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Liberation of Saint Peter</target><part>Peter's rescue from prison</part></link><space/>(12:319)</listitem><listitem>Death of Herod<space/><link><target>Agrippa I</target></link><space/>[in 44] (12:2025)<list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;the voice of a god&quot; (12:22)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul of Tarsus#First missionary journey</target><part>Mission of Barnabas and Saul</part></link><space/>(1314)<list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Saul, who was also known as Paul&quot; (13:9)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lystra#Paul's visit</target><part>called &quot;gods ... in human form&quot;</part></link><space/>(14:11)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target></link><space/>(15:135)</listitem><listitem>Paul separated from Barnabas (15:3641)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul of Tarsus#Second missionary journey</target><part>2nd</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul of Tarsus#Third missionary journey</target><part>3rd</part></link><space/>missions (1620)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Areopagus sermon</target></link><space/>(17:16-34)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Last Judgment</target><part>&quot;God...has set a day&quot;</part></link><space/>(17:3031)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Trial before<space/><link><target>Gallio</target></link><space/>c. 5152 (18:1217)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Paul of Tarsus#Arrest and death</target><part>Trip to Jerusalem</part></link><space/>(21)</listitem><listitem>Before the people and the<space/><link><target>Sanhedrin</target></link><space/>(2223)</listitem><listitem>Before<space/><link><target>Antonius Felix</target><part>Felix</part></link><link><target>Porcius Festus</target><part>Festus</part></link><link><target>Herod Agrippa II</target></link><space/>(2426)</listitem><listitem>Trip to<space/><link><target>Paul of Tarsus#Journey to Rome and beyond</target><part>Rome</part></link><space/>(2728)<list type='bullet'><listitem>called a god on<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Malta</target><part>Malta</part></link><space/>(28:6)</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Content</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Early Christianity</arg><arg>Jewish Christians</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link><space/>began with a prologue addressed to Theophilus; Acts likewise opens with an address to Theophilus and refers to &quot;my earlier book&quot;, almost certainly the gospel.</paragraph><paragraph>The apostles and other followers of Jesus meet and elect Matthias to replace Judas as a member of The Twelve. On<space/><link><target>Pentecost</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link><space/>descends and confers God's power on them, and Peter, along with John, preaches to many in Jerusalem, and performs Christ-like healings,<space/><link><target>Exorcism</target><part>casting out of evil spirits</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Resurrection of the dead</target><part>raising of the dead</part></link>. At first many<space/><link><target>Jewish Christians</target><part>Jews follow Christ</part></link><space/>and are baptized, but the Christians begin to be increasingly<space/><link><target>Persecution of Christians in the New Testament</target><part>persecuted</part></link><space/>by the Jews.<space/><link><target>Saint Stephen</target><part>Stephen</part></link><space/>is arrested for<space/><link><target>blasphemy</target></link>, and after a trial, is found guilty and<space/><link><target>Stoning</target><part>stoned</part></link><space/>by the Jews. Stephen's death marks a major turning point: the Jews have rejected the message, and henceforth it will be taken to the Gentiles.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">265</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The message is taken to the Samaritans, a people rejected by Jews, and to the<space/><link><target>Gentiles</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Saul of Tarsus</target></link>, one of the Jews who persecuted the Christians, is converted by a vision to become a follower of Christ (an event which Luke regards as so important that he relates it three times). Peter, directed by a series of visions, preaches to<space/><link><target>Cornelius the Centurion</target></link>, a Gentile God-fearer, who becomes a follower of Christ. The Holy Spirit descends on Peter and Cornelius, thus confirming that the message of eternal life in Christ is for all mankind. The Gentile church is established in Antioch (north-western Syria, the third-largest city of the empire), and here Christ's followers are first called Christians.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">266</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The mission to the Gentiles is promoted from Antioch and confirmed at<space/><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target><part>meeting in Jerusalem</part></link><space/>between Paul and the leadership of the Jerusalem church. Paul spends the next few years traveling through western Asia Minor and the Aegean,preaching, converting Gentiles, and founding new churches. On a visit to Jerusalem he is set on by a Jewish mob. Saved by the Roman commander, he is accused by the Jews of being a<space/><link><target>zealot</target><part>revolutionary</part></link>, the &quot;ringleader of the sect of the Nazarenes&quot;, and imprisoned. Paul asserts his right as a Roman citizen, to be tried in Rome and is sent by sea to Rome, where he spends another two years under house arrest, proclaiming the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of God</target></link><space/>and teaching the &quot;Lord Jesus Christ&quot;. Acts ends abruptly without recording the outcome of Paul's legal troubles.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Theology</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Saint Paul.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>235px</part><part>left</part><part>Paul's conversion, from ''Livre d'Heures d'tienne Chevalier'' (c.&amp;nbsp;14501460),<space/><link><target>Jean Fouquet</target></link>, in the<space/><link><target>Chteau de Chantilly</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the 1950s, Luke-Acts was seen as a historical work, written to defend Christianity before the Romans or Paul against his detractors; since then, however, the tendency has been to see the work as primarily theological.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Buckwalter</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template><space/>Luke's theology is expressed primarily through his overarching plot, the way scenes, themes and characters combine to construct his specific worldview.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Allen</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">326</arg></template><space/>His &quot;salvation history&quot; stretches from the Creation to the present time of his readers, in three ages: first, the time of &quot;the Law and the Prophets&quot; (Luke 16:16), the period beginning with Genesis and ending with the appearance of John the Baptist (Luke 1:5-3:1); second, the epoch of Jesus, in which the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of God</target></link><space/>was preached (Luke 3:2-24:51); and finally the period of the Church, which began when the risen Christ was taken into Heaven, and would end with his<space/><link><target>second coming of Christ</target><part>second coming</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Evans</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">no page numbers</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Luke-Acts is an attempt to answer a theological problem, namely how the Messiah promised to the Jews came to have an overwhelmingly non-Jewish church; the answer it provides, and its central theme, is that the message of Christ was sent to the Gentiles because the Jews rejected it.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">263</arg></template><space/>This theme is introduced at the opening of the gospel of Luke, when Jesus, rejected in Nazareth, recalls that the prophets were rejected by Israel and accepted by Gentiles; at the end of the gospel he commands his disciples to preach his message to all nations, &quot;beginning from Jerusalem.&quot; He repeats the command in Acts, telling them to preach &quot;in Jerusalem, in all Judea and Samaria, and to the end of the Earth.&quot; They then proceed to do so, in the order outlined: first Jerusalem, then Judea, then Samaria, then the entire (Roman) world.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">264</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For Luke, the Holy Spirit is the driving force behind the spread of the Christian message, and he places more emphasis on it than do any of the other evangelists. The Spirit is &quot;poured out&quot; at<space/><link><target>Pentecost</target></link>, on the first Samaritan and Gentile believers, and on disciples who had been baptised only by<space/><link><target>John the Baptist</target></link>, each time as a sign of God's approval. The Holy Spirit represents God's power (At his ascension, Jesus tells his followers, &quot;You shall receive power when the Holy Spirit has come upon you&quot;): through it the disciples are given speech to convert thousands in Jerusalem, forming the first church (the term is used for the first time in Acts 5).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Burkett</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">268-270</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Comparison with other writings</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Probably Valentin de Boulogne - Saint Paul Writing His Epistles - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>''Saint Paul Writing His Epistles'', ascribed to<space/><link><target>Valentin de Boulogne</target></link>, 17th century</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Gospel of Luke</heading><paragraph>As the second part of the two-part work Luke-Acts, Acts has significant links to the<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link>. Major turning points in the structure of Acts, for example, find parallels in Luke: the presentation of the child Jesus in the Temple parallels the opening of Acts in the Temple, Jesus' forty days of testing in the wilderness prior to his mission parallel the forty days prior to his Ascension in Acts, the mission of Jesus in Samaria and the Decapolis (the lands of the Samaritans and Gentiles) parallels the missions of the Apostles in Samaria and the Gentile lands, and so on (see<space/><link><target>Gospel of Luke</target></link>). These parallels continue through both books.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Tremmel</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">59</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There are also differences between Luke and Acts, amounting at times to outright contradiction. For example, the gospel seems to place the<space/><link><target>Ascension of Jesus</target><part>Ascension</part></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Easter Sunday</target></link>, immediately after the<space/><link><target>Resurrection of Christ</target><part>Resurrection</part></link>, while Acts 1 puts it forty days later.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Zwiep</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">39</arg></template><space/>There are similar conflicts over the theology. While not seriously questioning the single authorship of Luke-Acts, these differences do suggest the need for caution in seeking too much consistency in books written in essence as popular literature.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Parsons</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">17-18</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pauline epistles</heading><paragraph>Acts agrees with Paul's letters on the major outline of Paul's career: as Saul he is converted and becomes Paul the Christian missionary and apostle, establishing new churches in Asia Minor and the Aegean and struggling to free Gentile Christians from the<space/><link><target>Jewish Law</target></link>. There are also agreements on many incidents, such as Paul's escape from Damascus, where he is lowered down the walls in a basket. But details of these same incidents are frequently contradictory: for example, according to Paul it was a pagan king who was trying to arrest him in Damascus, but according to Luke it was, characteristically, the Jews (2 Corinthians 11:33 and Acts 9:24). Many of the disagreements are not so immediately obvious: Acts speaks of &quot;Christians&quot; and &quot;disciples&quot;, but Paul never uses either term, and there are striking differences in the accounts of Paul's relationship with the Jerusalem church and its leaders (Acts 9-15 vs. Galatians 1-2). Acts omits much from the letters, notably Paul's problems with his congregations (internal difficulties are said to be the fault of the Jews instead), and his apparent final rejection by the church leaders in Jerusalem (Acts has Paul and Barnabas deliver an offering that is accepted, a trip that has no mention in the letters). There are also major differences between Acts and Paul on<space/><link><target>Christology</target></link><space/>(the understanding of Christ's nature), eschatology (understanding of the &quot;last things&quot;), and<space/><link><target>twelve apostles</target><part>apostles</part><trail>hip</trail></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Boring</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">581, 588-590</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Historical reliability of the Acts of the Apostles</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Gospels</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of omitted Bible verses</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Textual variants in the New Testament#Acts of the Apostles</target><part>Textual variants in the Acts of the Apostles</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of the Apostles (genre)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Andrew</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Barnabas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of John</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of the Martyrs</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Paul</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Paul and Thecla</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Peter</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Peter and Paul</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Peter and the Twelve</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Pilate</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Philip</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Thomas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Acts of Timothy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Lost Chapter of the Acts of the Apostles</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Allen<space/></arg><arg name="first">O. Wesley, Jr.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Luke<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Petersen<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">David L.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">O'Day<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Gail R.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Theological Bible Commentary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Aune<space/></arg><arg name="first">David E.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The New Testament in its literary environment<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">Balch<space/></arg><arg name="first1">David L.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Luke<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Dunn<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">James D. G.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Rogerson<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">John William<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Boring<space/></arg><arg name="first">M. Eugene<space/></arg><arg name="title">An Introduction to the New Testament: History, Literature, Theology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Bruce<space/></arg><arg name="first">F.F.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Acts of the Apostles: The Greek Text with Introduction and Commentary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year">1990<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0802809667</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Buckwalter<space/></arg><arg name="first">Douglas<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Character and Purpose of Luke's Christology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Burkett<space/></arg><arg name="first">Delbert<space/></arg><arg name="title">An introduction to the New Testament and the origins of Christianity<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-00720-7<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Charlesworth<space/></arg><arg name="first">James H.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Historical Jesus: An Essential Guide<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Evans<space/></arg><arg name="first">Craig A.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Luke<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Baker Books<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Fitzmyer<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joseph A.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Anchor Bible: The Acts of the Apostles-A new Translation with Introduction and Commentary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Doubleday<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0385490207<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Green<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joel<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Theology of the Gospel of Luke<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Green<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joel<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Gospel of Luke<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Holladay<space/></arg><arg name="first">Carl R.<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Critical Introduction to the New Testament: Interpreting the Message and Meaning of Jesus Christ<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Matthews<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher R.<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Acts of the Apostles<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Coogan<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">Michael D.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Oxford Encyclopedia of the Books of the Bible<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Parsons<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mikeal C.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rethinking the Unity of Luke and Acts<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fortress Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Perkins<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pheme<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Pheme Perkins<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Barton<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">John<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Cambridge companion to biblical interpretation<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">The Synoptic Gospels and the Acts of the Apostles: Telling the Christian Story<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-48593-7<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Perkins<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pheme<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introduction to the Synoptic Gospels<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8028-6553-3<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Pickett<space/></arg><arg name="first">Raymond<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Luke and Empire: An Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Rhoads<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">David<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Esterline<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">David<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-last">Lee<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-first">Jae Won<space/></arg><arg name="title">Luke-Acts and Empire: Essays in Honor of Robert L. Brawley<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wipf and Stock Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">Theissen<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Gerd<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Merz<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Annette<space/></arg><arg name="title">The historical Jesus: a comprehensive guide<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Thompson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard P.<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Aune<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">David E.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Companion to The New Testament<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">Luke-Acts: The Gospel of Luke and the Acts of the Apostles<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley–Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Tremmel<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Four Gospels<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Xlibris<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">Witherington<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Ben<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Acts of the Apostles: A Socio-rhetorical Commentary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Zwiep<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arie W.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Christ, the Spirit and the Community of God: Essays on the Acts of the Apostles<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Mohr Siebeck<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Acts of the Apostles</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Acts (Bible)</arg><arg>Acts</arg></template><template><target>Wikiversity</target><arg>Biblical Studies (NT) #Acts: The Birth and Growth of the Early Church</arg></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10628_id314976.pdf'>A Brief Introduction to Luke-Acts is available online.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Acts;&amp;amp;version=31;9;'>''Book of Acts'' at Bible Gateway (NIV &amp; KJV)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/acts_long_01_intro.htm'>Tertullian.org: The Western Text of the Acts of the Apostles (1923) J. M. WILSON, D.D.</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wikisource-inline</target><arg name="list">
** {{Cite CE1913|wstitle</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Acts of the Apostles (genre)|Acts of the Apostles]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><small>[[Gospel]] of</small><br><space/>[[Gospel of John|John]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><small>[[New Testament]]</small><br>[[Books of the Bible]]</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><small>[[Pauline epistles|Paul's]] [[Epistle]]<br>to the</small><br><space/>[[Epistle to the Romans|Romans]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Acts of the Apostles</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template><template><target>New Testament people</target><arg>collapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Acts Of The Apostles</target></template><link><target>Category:Charismatic and Pentecostal Christianity</target></link><link><target>Category:New Testament books</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century Christianity</target></link><link><target>Category:1st-century books</target></link><link><target>Category:Acts of the Apostles</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>