<article title='Column'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Pillar</arg></template><link><target>File:National Capitol Columns - Washington, D.C..jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>National Capitol Columns at the<space/><link><target>United States National Arboretum</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Washington, D.C.</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:MosqueeKairouan 6bis.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Marble columns with antique capitals in the<space/><link><target>Mosque of Uqba</target><part>Great Mosque of Kairouan</part></link><space/>also known as the Mosque of Uqba, city of<space/><link><target>Kairouan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tunisia</target></link></part></link>A<space/><bold>column</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>pillar</bold><space/>in<space/><link><target>architecture</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>structural engineering</target></link><space/>is a structural element that transmits, through<space/><link><target>compression (physical)</target><part>compression</part></link>, the weight of the structure above to other structural elements below. In other words, a column is a compression member. The term column applies especially to a large round support (the<space/><italics>shaft</italics><space/>of the column) with a<space/><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>capital</part></link><space/>and a<space/><italics>base</italics><space/>or<space/><link><target>pedestal</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/column?show</arg><arg name="title">Column - Definition and More from the Free Merriam-Webster Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Merriam-webster.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2012-08-31<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-07-04</arg></template></extension><space/>and made of stone, or appearing to be so. A small wooden or metal support is typically called a post, and supports with a rectangular or other non-round section are usually called<space/><link><target>pier (architecture)</target><part>piers</part></link>. For the purpose of<space/><link><target>wind engineering</target><part>wind</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>earthquake engineering</target></link>, columns may be designed to resist lateral forces. Other<space/><link><target>compression member</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are often termed &quot;columns&quot; because of the similar stress conditions. Columns are frequently used to support<space/><link><target>Beam (structure)</target><part>beam</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>arch</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>on which the upper parts of walls or ceilings rest. In architecture, &quot;column&quot; refers to such a structural element that also has certain proportional and decorative features. A column might also be a decorative element not needed for structural purposes; many columns are &quot;engaged&quot;, that is to say form part of a wall.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Schema Saeulenordnungen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Illustration of Doric (left three), Ionic (middle three) and Corinthian (right two) columns.</part></link>All significant<space/><link><target>Iron Age</target></link><space/>civilizations of the<space/><link><target>Near East</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mediterranean</target></link><space/>made some use of columns. In<space/><link><target>Ancient Egyptian architecture</target></link><space/>as early as 2600 BC the architect<space/><link><target>Imhotep</target></link><space/>made use of stone columns whose surface was carved to reflect the organic form of bundled reeds; in later Egyptian architecture faceted cylinders were also common. Egyptian columns are famously present in the<space/><link><target>Great Hypostyle Hall</target></link><space/>of Karnak (ca. 1224 BC), where 134 columns are lined up in 16 rows, with some columns reaching heights of 24 metres.<link><target>File:Persepolis Colonne flandin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Plan, front view and side view of a typical<space/><link><target>Persepolis</target></link><space/>column, of<space/><link><target>Iran</target><part>Persia (Iran)</part></link></part></link>Some of the most elaborate columns in the ancient world were those of the<space/><link><target>Persia</target><trail>ns</trail></link>, especially the massive stone columns erected in<space/><link><target>Persepolis</target></link>. They included double-bull structures in their<space/><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>capitals</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Apadana</target><part>The Hall of Hundred Columns</part></link><space/>at Persepolis, measuring 70&amp;nbsp; 70 metres, was built by the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid</target></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Darius the Great of Persia</target><part>Darius I</part></link><space/>(524486 BC). Many of the ancient<space/><link><target>Persian column</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are standing, some being more than 30 metres tall.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2010</arg></template><link><target>File:Columns of the Temple of Apollo at Delphi, Greece.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Columns found at the<space/><link><target>Temple of Apollo (Delphi)</target><part>Temple of Apollo in Delphi</part></link></part></link>The Egyptians, Persians and other civilizations mostly used columns for the practical purpose of holding up the roof inside a building, preferring outside walls to be decorated with<space/><link><target>relief</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or painting, but the Ancient Greeks, followed by the Romans, loved to use them on the outside as well, and the extensive use of columns on the interior and exterior of buildings is one of the most characteristic features of classical architecture, in buildings like the<space/><link><target>Parthenon</target></link>. The Greeks developed the<space/><link><target>#Classical orders</target><part>classical orders</part></link><space/>of architecture, which are most easily distinguished by the form of the column and its various elements. Their<space/><link><target>Doric order</target><part>Doric</part></link>, Ionic, and Corinthian orders were expanded by the Romans to include the Tuscan and Composite orders (see below).</paragraph><paragraph>Columns, or at least large structural exterior ones, became much less significant in the architecture of the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>. The classical forms were abandoned in both<space/><link><target>Byzantine architecture</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Romanesque architecture</target><part>Romanesque</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Gothic architecture</target></link><space/>or Europe in favour of more flexible forms, with capitals often using various types of foliage decoration, and in the West scenes with figures carved in<space/><link><target>relief</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Renaissance architecture</target></link><space/>was keen to revive the classical vocabulary and styles, and the informed use and variation of the classical orders remained fundamental to the training of architects throughout<space/><link><target>Baroque architecture</target><part>Baroque</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Rococo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Neo-classical architecture</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Carpark Cinema Undercroft Albany II.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Modern column grid in a car park or parking garage</part></link>Early columns were constructed of stone, some out of a single piece of stone. Monolithic columns are among the heaviest stones used in<space/><link><target>architecture</target></link>. Other stone columns are created out of multiple sections of stone, mortared or dry-fit together. In many classical sites, sectioned columns were carved with a centre hole or depression so that they could be pegged together, using stone or metal pins. The design of most classical columns incorporates<space/><link><target>entasis</target></link><space/>(the inclusion of a slight outward curve in the sides) plus a reduction in diameter along the height of the column, so that the top is as little as 83% of the bottom diameter. This reduction mimics the parallax effects which the eye expects to see, and tends to make columns look taller and straighter than they are while entasis adds to that effect.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nomenclature</heading><paragraph>Classical columns have a bottom or<space/><link><target>plinth</target></link><space/>that rests on the<space/><link><target>stylobate</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Foundation (engineering)</target><part>foundation</part></link>. At the top a<space/><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>capital</part></link><space/>(also known as a chapiter) or<space/><link><target>finial</target></link><space/>decorate the column, depending on whether it is attached to a structure or free-standing.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern columns are constructed out of steel, poured or precast concrete, or brick. They may then be clad in an architectural covering (or veneer), or left bare. In modern terms the impost (or pier) is the topmost member of a column. The bottom-most part of the arch, called the springing, rests on the impost.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Equilibrium, instability, and loads</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Buckling#columns</arg></template><template><target>Mechanical_failure_modes</target></template><link><target>File:Columns in the inner court of the Bel Temple Palmyra Syria.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>These are composed of stacked segments and finished in the<space/><link><target>Corinthian order</target><part>Corinthian</part></link><space/>style (<link><target>Temple of Bel</target></link>, Syria)</part></link>As the axial load on a perfectly straight slender column with elastic material properties is increased in magnitude, this ideal column passes through three states: stable equilibrium, neutral equilibrium, and instability. The straight column under load is in stable equilibrium if a lateral force, applied between the two ends of the column, produces a small lateral deflection which disappears and the column returns to its straight form when the lateral force is removed. If the column load is gradually increased, a condition is reached in which the straight form of equilibrium becomes so-called neutral equilibrium, and a small lateral force will produce a deflection that does not disappear and the column remains in this slightly bent form when the lateral force is removed. The load at which neutral equilibrium of a column is reached is called the critical or<space/><link><target>buckling</target></link><space/>load. The state of instability is reached when a slight increase of the column load causes uncontrollably growing lateral deflections leading to complete collapse.</paragraph><paragraph>For an axially loaded straight column with any end support conditions, the equation of static equilibrium, in the form of a differential equation, can be solved for the deflected shape and critical load of the column. With hinged, fixed or free end support conditions the deflected shape in neutral equilibrium of an initially straight column with uniform cross section throughout its length always follows a partial or composite sinusoidal curve shape, and the critical load is given by</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='math'>f_{cr}\equiv\frac{\pi^2\textit{E}I_{min}}{{L}^2}\qquad (1)&lt;/math&gt;

where ''E'' = [[elastic modulus]] of the material, ''I&lt;sub&gt;min&lt;/sub&gt;'' = the minimal moment of inertia of the cross section, and ''L'' = actual length of the column between its two end supports. A variant of (1) is given by

&lt;math&gt;f_{cr}\equiv\frac{\pi^{2}E_T}{(\frac{KL}{r})^{2}}\qquad (2)</extension><link><target>File:ColumnEffectiveLength.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Table showing values of K for structural columns of various end conditions (adapted from Manual of Steel Construction, 8th&amp;nbsp;edition, American Institute of Steel Construction, Table C1.8.1)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>where<space/><italics>r</italics><space/>=<space/><link><target>radius</target></link><space/>of gyration of [column]cross-section which is equal to the square root of (I/A),<space/><italics>K</italics><space/>= ratio of the longest half<space/><link><target>sine</target></link><space/>wave to the actual column length, and<space/><italics>KL</italics><space/>= effective length (length of an equivalent hinged-hinged column). From Equation&amp;nbsp;(2) it can be noted that the buckling strength of a column is inversely proportional to the square of its length.</paragraph><paragraph>When the critical stress,<space/><italics>F</italics><xhtml:sub>cr</xhtml:sub><space/>(<italics>F</italics><xhtml:sub>cr</xhtml:sub><space/>=<italics>P</italics><xhtml:sub>cr</xhtml:sub>/<italics>A</italics>, where<space/><italics>A</italics>&amp;nbsp;= cross-sectional area of the column), is greater than the proportional limit of the material, the column is experiencing inelastic buckling. Since at this stress the slope of the material's stress-strain curve,<space/><italics>E</italics><xhtml:sub><italics>t</italics></xhtml:sub><space/>(called the<space/><link><target>tangent modulus</target></link>), is smaller than that below the proportional limit, the critical load at inelastic buckling is reduced. More complex formulas and procedures apply for such cases, but in its simplest form the critical buckling load formula is given as Equation&amp;nbsp;(3),</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='math'>f_{cr}\equiv{F_y}-\frac{F^{2}_{y}}{4\pi^{2}E}\left(\frac{KL}{r^2}\right)\qquad (3)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>where<space/><italics>E</italics><xhtml:sub><italics>t</italics></xhtml:sub><space/>= tangent modulus at the stress<space/><italics>F</italics><xhtml:sub>cr</xhtml:sub></paragraph><paragraph>A column with a cross section that lacks symmetry may suffer torsional buckling (sudden twisting) before, or in combination with, lateral buckling. The presence of the twisting deformations renders both theoretical analyses and practical designs rather complex.</paragraph><paragraph>Eccentricity of the load, or imperfections such as initial crookedness, decreases column strength. If the axial load on the column is not concentric, that is, its line of action is not precisely coincident with the centroidal axis of the column, the column is characterized as eccentrically loaded. The eccentricity of the load, or an initial curvature, subjects the column to immediate bending. The increased stresses due to the combined axial-plus-flexural stresses result in a reduced load-carrying ability.</paragraph><paragraph>Column elements are considered to be massive if minimal side dimension is equal or more than 400&amp;nbsp;mm. Massive columns have ability to increase concrete strength during long time period (even during exploitation period). Taking into account possible loads onto structure increase in future (and even threat of progressive failure, terroristic attacks, explosions etc.) massive columns have advantage comparing with not ones. A little economy today has no sense as usual for future. Moreover, relatively small sections are not technological for reinforced structures during their production. Balance between economy, mass of structures and so called &quot;sustainable&quot; construction is necessary.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Extensions</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Construction of Sigismund Column.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Construction of<space/><link><target>Sigismund's Column</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Warsaw</target></link>, detail of the 1646 engraving.</part></link>When a column is too long to be built or transported in one piece, it has to be extended or spliced at the construction site. A<space/><link><target>reinforced concrete column</target></link><space/>is extended by having the steel reinforcing bars protrude a few inches or feet above the top of the concrete, then placing the next level of reinforcing bars to overlap, and pouring the concrete of the next level. A steel column is extended by welding or bolting splice plates on the flanges and webs or walls of the columns to provide a few inches or feet of load transfer from the upper to the lower column section. A timber column is usually extended by the use of a steel tube or wrapped-around sheet-metal plate bolted onto the two connecting timber sections.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Foundations</heading><paragraph>A column that carries the load down to a foundation must have means to transfer the load without overstressing the foundation material. Reinforced concrete and masonry columns are generally built directly on top of concrete foundations. When seated on a concrete foundation, a steel column must have a base plate to spread the load over a larger area, and thereby reduce the bearing pressure. The base plate is a thick, rectangular steel plate usually welded to the bottom end of the column.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Classical orders</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Classical order</arg></template><link><target>File:San prospero colonne reggio emilia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Church of<space/><link><target>San Prospero</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Reggio Emilia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link></part></link>The<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>author<space/><link><target>Vitruvius</target></link>, relying on the writings (now lost) of<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>authors, tells us that the ancient<space/><link><target>Hellenic civilization</target><part>Greeks</part></link><space/>believed that their Doric order developed from techniques for building in wood. The earlier smoothed tree-trunk was replaced by a stone cylinder.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Doric order</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Doric order</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Doric order</target></link><space/>is the oldest and simplest of the classical orders. It is composed of a vertical<space/><link><target>cylinder (geometry)</target><part>cylinder</part></link><space/>that is wider at the bottom. It generally has neither a base nor a detailed<space/><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>capital</part></link>. It is instead often topped with an inverted<space/><link><target>frustum</target></link><space/>of a shallow cone or a cylindrical band of carvings. It is often referred to as the masculine order because it is represented in the bottom level of the<space/><link><target>Colosseum</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Parthenon</target></link>, and was therefore considered to be able to hold more weight. The height-to-thickness ratio is about 8:1. The shaft of a Doric Column is almost always<space/><link><target>Fluting (architecture)</target><part>fluted</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Greek Doric, developed in the western Dorian region of Greece, is the heaviest and most massive of the orders. It rises from the<space/><link><target>stylobate</target></link><space/>without any base; it is from four to six times as tall as its diameter; it has twenty broad flutes; the capital consists simply of a banded necking swelling out into a smooth echinus, which carries a flat square abacus; the Doric entablature is also the heaviest, being about one-fourth the height column. The Greek Doric order was not used after c. 100 B.C. until its rediscovery in the mid-eighteenth century.<link><target>File:Western colonnade at courtyard, UVa 2004.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Tuscan columns can be seen at the University of Virginia.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Tuscan order</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Tuscan order</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Tuscan order</target></link>, also known as Roman Doric, is also a simple design, the base and capital both being series of cylindrical disks of alternating diameter. The shaft is almost never fluted. The proportions vary, but are generally similar to Doric columns. Height to width ratio is about 7:1.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ionic order</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Ionic order</arg></template><link><target>File:Colonne-p1040009.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Ionic<space/><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>capital</part></link></part></link>The<space/><link><target>Ionic order</target><part>Ionic</part></link><space/>column is considerably more complex than the Doric or Tuscan. It usually has a base and the shaft is often fluted (it has grooves carved up its length). On the top is a capital in the characteristic shape of a<space/><link><target>scroll (parchment)</target><part>scroll</part></link>, called a<space/><link><target>volute</target></link>, or scroll, at the four corners. The height-to-thickness ratio is around 9:1. Due to the more refined proportions and scroll capitals, the Ionic column is sometimes associated with academic buildings. Ionic style columns were used on the second level of the Colosseum.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Corinthian order</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Corinthian order</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Corinthian order is named for the Greek<space/><link><target>city-state</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Corinth, Greece</target><part>Corinth</part></link>, to which it was connected in the period. However, according to the architectural historian<space/><link><target>Vitruvius</target></link>, the column was created by the sculptor<space/><link><target>Callimachus (sculptor)</target><part>Callimachus</part></link>, probably an<space/><link><target>Athens</target><part>Athenian</part></link>, who drew<space/><link><target>Acanthus (genus)</target><part>acanthus</part></link><space/>leaves growing around a votive basket. In fact, the oldest known Corinthian capital was found in<space/><link><target>Bassae</target></link>, dated at 427 BC. It is sometimes called the feminine order because it is on the top level of the Colosseum and holding up the least weight, and also has the slenderest ratio of thickness to height. Height to width ratio is about 10:1.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Composite order</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Composite order</target></link><space/>draws its name from the capital being a composite of the Ionic and Corinthian capitals. The acanthus of the Corinthian column already has a scroll-like element, so the distinction is sometimes subtle. Generally the Composite is similar to the Corinthian in proportion and employment, often in the upper tiers of<space/><link><target>colonnade</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Height to width ratio is about 11:1 or 12:1.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Solomonic</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:StPetersSalomonicColumnsCrop.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Two of Constantine's<space/><link><target>Solomonic column</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in their present-day location on a pier in<space/><link><target>St Peter's, Rome</target></link>. Part of<space/><link><target>St. Peter's baldachin</target><part>Bernini's Baldachin</part></link>, inspired by the original columns, is in the foreground.</part></link>A<space/><link><target>Solomonic column</target></link>, sometimes called &quot;<link><target>barley sugar</target></link>&quot;, begins on a base and ends in a capital, which may be of any order, but the shaft twists in a tight spiral, producing a dramatic, serpentine effect of movement. Solomonic columns were developed in the ancient world, but remained rare there. A famous marble set, probably 2nd century, was brought to<space/><link><target>St Peter's, Rome</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Constantine I</target></link>, and placed round the saint's shrine, and was thus familiar throughout the Middle Ages, by which time they were thought to have been removed from the<space/><link><target>Temple of Jerusalem</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Ward-Perkins, &quot;The shrine of St. Peter's and its twelve spiral columns&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Roman Studies</italics><space/><bold>42</bold><space/>(1952) p 21ff.</extension><space/>The style was used in bronze by<space/><link><target>Bernini</target></link><space/>for his spectacular<space/><link><target>St. Peter's baldachin</target></link>, actually a<space/><link><target>Ciborium (architecture)</target><part>ciborium</part></link><space/>(which displaced Constantine's columns), and thereafter became very popular with<space/><link><target>Baroque</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rococo</target></link><space/>church architects, above all in<space/><link><target>Latin America</target></link>, where they were very often used, especially on a small scale, as they are easy to produce in wood by<space/><link><target>Woodturning</target><part>turning on a lathe</part></link><space/>(hence also the style's popularity for<space/><link><target>Spindle (furniture)</target><part>spindles</part></link><space/>on furniture and stairs).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Pillar tombs</heading><paragraph><link><target>Pillar tomb</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are monumental graves, which typically feature a single, prominent pillar or column, often made of stone. A number of world cultures incorporated pillars into tomb structures. In the<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>Ancient Greek</part></link><space/>colony of<space/><link><target>Lycia</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target></link>, one of these edifices is located at the tomb of<space/><link><target>Xanthos</target></link>. In the town of<space/><link><target>Hannassa</target></link><space/>in southern<space/><link><target>Somalia</target></link>, ruins of houses with archways and<space/><link><target>courtyard</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have also been found along with other pillar tombs, including a rare octagonal tomb.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Arotssc"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Sanseverino</arg><arg name="first1">Hilary Costa</arg><arg name="title">Archaeological Remains on the Southern Somali Coast</arg><arg name="journal">Azania: Archaeological Research in Africa</arg><arg name="date">1983</arg><arg name="volume">18</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">151–164</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/00672708309511319</arg><arg name="url">http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.1080/00672708309511319#.VGJ0To938jg</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 November 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Columns</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Capital (architecture)</target><part>Capital</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entasis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Huabiao</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Marian and Holy Trinity columns</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pilaster</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pole (disambiguation)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Spur (architecture)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stanchion</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Room</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Columns and entablature</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Architectural elements</target></link><link><target>Category:Structural system</target></link><link><target>Category:Egyptian artefact types</target></link><link><target>Category:Earthquake engineering</target></link></paragraph></article>