<article title='Chapter_11%2C_Title_11%2C_United_States_Code'><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template><template><target>USBankruptcy</target></template><bold>Chapter 11</bold><space/>is a chapter of<space/><link><target>Title 11 of the United States Code</target><part>Title 11</part></link><space/>of the United States<space/><link><target>Bankruptcy in the United States</target><part>Bankruptcy Code</part></link>, which permits reorganization under the<space/><link><target>bankruptcy</target></link><space/>laws of the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>. Chapter 11 bankruptcy is available to every<space/><link><target>business</target></link>, whether organized as a<space/><link><target>corporation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>partnership</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>sole proprietorship</target></link>, and to individuals, although it is most prominently used by corporate entities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.uscourts.gov/FederalCourts/Bankruptcy/BankruptcyBasics/Chapter11.aspx</arg><arg name="title">Chapter 11 - Bankruptcy Basics</arg><arg name="work">United States Courts</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In contrast,<space/><link><target>Chapter 7, Title 11, United States Code</target><part>Chapter 7</part></link><space/>governs the process of a<space/><link><target>liquidation</target></link><space/>bankruptcy (although liquidation can go under this chapter), while<space/><link><target>Chapter 13, Title 11, United States Code</target><part>Chapter 13</part></link><space/>provides a reorganization process for the majority of private individuals.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Chapter 11 in general</heading><paragraph>When a business is unable to service its debt or pay its<space/><link><target>creditors</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>business</target></link><space/>or its creditors can file with a federal bankruptcy court for protection under either Chapter 7 or Chapter 11.</paragraph><paragraph>In Chapter 7, the business ceases operations, a trustee sells all of its assets, and then distributes the proceeds to its creditors. Any residual amount is returned to the owners of the company. In Chapter 11, in most instances the debtor remains in control of its business operations as a<space/><italics><link><target>debtor in possession</target></link></italics>, and is subject to the oversight and jurisdiction of the court.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Practitioner">Joseph Swanson and Peter Marshall,<space/><link><target>Houlihan Lokey</target></link><space/>and Lyndon Norley,<space/><link><target>Kirkland &amp; Ellis</target></link><space/>International LLP (2008). A Practitioner's Guide to Corporate Restructuring. City &amp; Financial Publishing, 1st edition ISBN 978-1-905121-31-1</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Features of Chapter 11 reorganization</heading><paragraph>Chapter 11 retains many of the features present in all, or most, bankruptcy proceedings in the U.S. It provides additional tools for debtors as well. Most importantly,<space/><template><target>usc</target><arg>11</arg><arg>1108</arg></template><space/>empowers the trustee to operate the debtor's business. In Chapter 11, unless a separate trustee is appointed for cause, the debtor, as debtor in possession, acts as trustee of the business.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>usc</target><arg>11</arg><arg>1107</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Chapter 11 affords the debtor in possession a number of mechanisms to restructure its business. A debtor in possession can acquire financing and<space/><link><target>loan</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on favorable terms by giving new lenders first priority on the business's earnings. The court may also permit the debtor in possession to reject and cancel contracts. Debtors are also protected from other litigation against the business through the imposition of an<space/><link><target>automatic stay</target></link>. While the automatic stay is in place, creditors are stayed from any collection attempts or activities against the debtor in possession, and most litigation against the debtor is stayed,<extension extension_name='ref' name="law.cornell.edu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/11/362</arg><arg name="title">11 U.S. Code ยง 362 - Automatic stay</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>or put on hold, until it can be resolved in bankruptcy court, or resumed in its original venue. An example of proceedings that are not necessarily stayed automatically are family law proceedings against a spouse or parent. Further, creditors may file with the court seeking relief from the automatic stay.</paragraph><paragraph>If the business is<space/><link><target>insolvent</target></link>, its debts exceed its assets and the business is unable to pay debts as they come due,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.cornell.edu/ucc/1/1-201#Insolvent</arg><arg name="title">ยง 1-201. General Definitions.</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>the bankruptcy restructuring may result in the company's owners being left with nothing; instead, the owners' rights and interests are ended and the company's creditors are left with ownership of the newly reorganized company.</paragraph><paragraph>All creditors are entitled to be heard by the court. 11 U.S.C. Sec. 1109 (b). The court is ultimately responsible for determining whether the proposed plan of reorganization complies with the bankruptcy law.</paragraph><paragraph>One controversy that has broken out in bankruptcy courts concerns the proper amount of disclosure that the court and other parties are entitled to receive from the members of the ad hoc creditor's committees that play a large role in many such proceedings.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ft.com/cms/s/2/166ef296-0abb-11df-b35f-00144feabdc0,dwp_uuid</arg><arg name="title">Bankruptcy Rules Committee rethinks 2019 pricing disclosure amid HF panic attack</arg><arg name="work">Financial Times</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chapter 11 plan</heading><paragraph>Chapter 11 usually results in reorganization of the debtor's business or personal assets and debts, but can also be used as a mechanism for liquidation. Debtors may &quot;emerge&quot; from a chapter 11 bankruptcy within a few months or within several years, depending on the size and complexity of the bankruptcy. The Bankruptcy Code accomplishes this objective through the use of a bankruptcy plan. The debtor in possession typically has the first opportunity to propose a plan during the period of exclusivity. This period allows the debtor 120 days from the date of filing for chapter 11, to propose a plan of reorganization before any other party in interest may propose a plan. If the debtor proposes a plan within the 120 day exclusivity period, a 180-day exclusivity period from the date of filing for chapter 11 is granted in order to allow the debtor to gain confirmation of the proposed plan.<extension extension_name='ref' name="law.cornell.edu"></extension><space/>With some exceptions, the plan may be proposed by any party in interest.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>usc</target><arg>11</arg><arg>1121</arg></template></extension><space/>Interested creditors then vote for a plan.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Confirmation</heading><paragraph>If the judge approves the reorganization plan and if the creditors all agree the plan can be confirmed. If at least one class of creditors votes against the plan and thus objects, the plan may nonetheless be confirmed if the requirements of<space/><link><target>cramdown</target></link><space/>are met. In order to be confirmed over their objection the plan must not discriminate against that class of creditors, and the plan must be found fair and equitable to that class.</paragraph><paragraph>Upon its confirmation, the plan becomes binding and identifies the treatment of debts and operations of the business for the duration of the plan.</paragraph><paragraph>If a plan cannot be confirmed, the court may either convert the case to a liquidation under chapter 7, or, if in the best interests of the creditors and the estate, the case may be dismissed resulting in a return to the status quo before bankruptcy. If the case is dismissed, creditors will look to non-bankruptcy law in order to satisfy their claims.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Automatic stay</heading><paragraph>Like other forms of bankruptcy, petitions filed under chapter 11 invoke the<space/><link><target>automatic stay</target></link><space/>of<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bknevada.com/index.php/chapter-3-case-administration/subchapter-iv-administrative-powers/362-automatic-stay'><space/>362</link>. The automatic stay requires all creditors to cease collection attempts, and makes many post-petition debt collection efforts void or voidable. Under some circumstances, some creditors, otherwise the<space/><link><target>United States Trustee</target></link><space/>can request for the court converting the case into a liquidation under chapter 7, or appointing a trustee to manage the debtor's business. The court will grant a motion to convert to chapter 7 or appoint a trustee if either of these actions is in the best interest of all creditors. Sometimes a company will liquidate under chapter 11, in which the pre-existing management may be able to help get a higher price for divisions or other assets than a chapter 7 liquidation would be likely to achieve. Appointment of a trustee requires some wrongdoing or gross mismanagement on the part of existing management and is relatively rare.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Executory contracts</heading><paragraph>Some contracts, known as<space/><link><target>executory contracts</target></link>, may be rejected if canceling them would be financially favorable to the company and its creditors. Such contracts may include labor union contracts, supply or operating contracts (with both vendors and customers), and real estate leases. The standard feature of executory contracts is that each party to the contract has duties remaining under the contract. In the event of a rejection, the remaining parties to the contract become unsecured creditors of the debtor. For example, in some districts a<space/><link><target>contract for deed</target></link><space/>is an executory contract, while in others it is not.</paragraph><paragraph>In the new millennium airlines have fallen under intense scrutiny for what many see as abusing Chapter 11 Bankruptcy as a simple tool for escaping labor contracts, usually 30-35% of an airline's operating cost.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">massachusetts institute of technology: Airline Data Project</arg><arg name="url">http://web.mit.edu/airlinedata/www/Employees&Compensation.html</arg><arg name="publisher">MIT</arg></template></extension><space/>Every major US. airline has filed for Chapter 11 since 2002.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Davies</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">AMR Files for Bankruptcy: The Last Giant to Fall</arg><arg name="url">http://abcnews.go.com/blogs/business/2011/11/american-airlines-plunges-into-bankruptcy/</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">ABC News</arg><arg name="date">Nov 29, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>In the space of 2 years (2002 - 2004) US. Airways filed for bankruptcy twice<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Warner</arg><arg name="first">Margeret</arg><arg name="title">US Airways Files....Again</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pbs.org/newshour/bb/transportation/july-dec04/usairways_9-13.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">Public Broadcasting Service</arg><arg name="date">Sep 13, 2004</arg></template></extension><space/>leaving the<space/><link><target>AFL-CIO</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Jablonski</arg><arg name="first">Donna</arg><arg name="title">AFL-CIO Cries Foul</arg><arg name="url">http://www.aflcio.org/Blog/Economy/TWU-Demands-Respect-from-American-Airlines-Bankruptcy-Court</arg><arg name="publisher">AFL-CIO</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>pilot unions and other airline employees claiming the rules of Chapter 11 have helped turn the USA into a<space/><link><target>corporatocracy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Trumbul</arg><arg name="first">Mark</arg><arg name="title">AMR Files for Chapter 11</arg><arg name="url">http://www.csmonitor.com/USA/2011/1129/AMR-What-does-Chapter-11-bankruptcy-mean-for-American-Airlines-fliers</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2012</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Christian Science Monitor</arg><arg name="date">Nov 29, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Priority</heading><paragraph>Chapter 11 follows the same priority scheme as other bankruptcy chapters. The priority structure is defined primarily by 507 of the Bankruptcy Code (<template><target>usc</target><arg>11</arg><arg>507</arg></template>.)</paragraph><paragraph>As a general rule, administrative expenses (the actual, necessary expenses of preserving the bankruptcy estate, including expenses such as employee wages, and the cost of litigating the chapter 11 case)are paid first.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/11/503</arg><arg name="title">11 U.S. Code ยง 503 - Allowance of administrative expenses</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Secured creditor</target><trail>s</trail></link>creditors who have a<space/><link><target>security interest</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>collateral (finance)</target><part>collateral</part></link>, in the debtor's propertywill be paid before unsecured creditors. Unsecured creditors' claims are prioritized by 507. For instance the claims of suppliers of products or employees of a company may be paid before other unsecured creditors are paid. Each priority level must be paid in full before the next lowest priority level may receive payment.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Section 1110</heading><paragraph>Section 1110 (<template><target>usc</target><arg>11</arg><arg>1110</arg></template>) generally provides a secured party with an interest in an aircraft the ability to take possession of the equipment within 60 days after a bankruptcy filing unless the airline cures all defaults. More specifically, the right of the lender to take possession of the secured equipment is not hampered by the automatic stay provisions of the U.S. Bankruptcy Code.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Stock</heading><paragraph>If the company's stock is publicly traded, a Chapter 11 filing generally causes it to be<space/><link><target>delisting (stock)</target><part>delisted</part></link><space/>from its primary stock exchange if listed on the<space/><link><target>New York Stock Exchange</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>American Stock Exchange</target></link>, or the<space/><link><target>NASDAQ</target></link>. On the NASDAQ the identifying fifth letter &quot;Q&quot; at the end of a stock symbol indicates the company is in bankruptcy (formerly the &quot;Q&quot; was placed in front of the pre-existing stock symbol; a celebrated example was<space/><link><target>Penn Central</target></link>, whose symbol was originally &quot;PC&quot; and became &quot;QPC&quot; after the company filed Chapter 11 in 1970). Many stocks that are delisted quickly resume listing as<space/><link><target>over-the-counter (finance)</target><part>over-the-counter</part></link><space/>(OTC) stocks. Actual share value does not reach zero unless the probability of restructuring is so low that a Chapter 7 filing is sure to follow.</paragraph><paragraph>Individuals may file Chapter 11, but due to the complexity and expense of the proceeding, this option is rarely chosen by debtors who are eligible for Chapter 7 or<space/><link><target>Chapter 13, Title 11, United States Code</target><part>Chapter 13</part></link><space/>relief.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Rationale</heading><paragraph>In enacting Chapter 11 of the Bankruptcy code, Congress concluded that it is sometimes the case that the value of a business is greater if sold or reorganized as a<space/><link><target>going concern</target></link><space/>than the value of the sum of its parts if the business's assets were to be sold off individually. It follows that it may be more economically efficient to allow a troubled company to continue running, cancel some of its debts, and give ownership of the newly reorganized company to the creditors whose debts were canceled. Alternatively, the business can be sold as a going concern with the net proceeds of the sale distributed to creditors ratably in accordance with statutory priorities. In this way, jobs may be saved, the (previously mismanaged) engine of profitability which is the business is maintained (presumably under better management) rather than being dismantled, and, as a proponent of a chapter 11 plan is required to demonstrate as a precursor to plan confirmation, the business's creditors end up with more money than they would in a Chapter 7 liquidation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Considerations</heading><paragraph>The reorganization and court process may take an inordinate amount of time, limiting the chances of a successful outcome and sufficient debtor in possession financing may be unavailable during an economic recession. A preplanned, preagreed approach between the debtor and its creditors (sometimes called a pre-packaged bankruptcy) may facilitate the desired result. A company undergoing Chapter 11 reorganization is effectively operating under the &quot;protection&quot; of the court until it emerges. An example is the<space/><link><target>airline industry</target></link><space/>in the United States; in 2006 over half the industry's<space/><link><target>seating capacity</target></link><space/>was on airlines that were in Chapter 11.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Delta and Northwest airlines both file for bankruptcy<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://money.cnn.com/2005/09/14/news/fortune500/bankruptcy_airlines/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>November 17, 2005<space/></arg><arg name="work">CNN<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005-09-14<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Chris<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Isidore<space/></arg><arg name="first2">/Money<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Senior</arg></template></extension><space/>These airlines were able to stop making debt payments, break their previously agreed upon labor union contracts, freeing up cash to expand routes or weather a price war against competitors &amp;mdash; all with the bankruptcy court's approval.</paragraph><paragraph>Studies on the impact of forestalling the creditors' rights to enforce their security reach different conclusions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.economist.com/displaystory.cfm?story_id</arg><arg name="title">The night of the killer zombies</arg><arg name="work">Economist.com</arg><arg name="date">2002-12-12</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-08-05</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Deadlines</heading><paragraph>Within 60 days of filing for Chapter 11 bankruptcy, the debtor must submit a written disclosure statement with the court containing information on assets, liabilities and business affairs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dcdmlawgroup.com/2014/02/3-deadlines-beware-filing-chapter-11-bankruptcy/</arg><arg name="title">3 Deadlines to Beware of When Filing a Chapter 11 Bankruptcy</arg><arg name="work">DCDM</arg><arg name="date">2014-02-17</arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-10-15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Statistics</heading><heading level='3'>Frequency</heading><paragraph>Chapter 11 cases dropped by 60% from 1991 to 2003. One 2007 study<extension extension_name='ref' name="WSJSpurn">(January 24, 2007), &quot;Small Firms Spurn Chapter 11&quot;,<space/><italics>Wall Street Journal</italics>, page B6B</extension><space/>found this was because businesses were turning to bankruptcy-like proceedings under state law, rather than the federal bankruptcy proceedings, including those under chapter 11. Insolvency proceedings under state law, the study stated, are currently faster, less expensive, and more private, with some states not even requiring court filings. However, a 2005 study<extension extension_name='ref' name="WSJSpurn"></extension><space/>claimed the drop may have been due to an increase in the incorrect classification of many bankruptcies as &quot;consumer cases&quot; rather than &quot;business cases&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Cases involving more than US$50 million in assets are almost always handled in federal bankruptcy court, and not in bankruptcy-like state proceeding.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Largest cases</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Bankruptcy in the United States</target><part>largest bankruptcy</part></link><space/>in history was of the US investment bank<space/><link><target>Lehman Brothers</target><part>Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc.</part></link>, which listed $639 billion in assets as of its Chapter 11 filing in 2008. The 16 largest corporate bankruptcies as of 13 December 2011:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bankruptcydata.com'>Bankruptcydata.com</link></extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable sortable" border="1"><tablerow><tablehead>Company</tablehead><tablehead>Filing date</tablehead><tablehead>Total Assets pre-filing</tablehead><tablehead>Assets adjusted to the year 2012</tablehead><tablehead>Filing court district</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Lehman Brothers</target><part>Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2008-09-15</tablecell><tablecell>$639,063,000,800</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|639063000000|2008|r">5}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Washington Mutual</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2008-09-26</tablecell><tablecell>$327,913,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|327913000000|2008|r">5}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>DE</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>MCI Inc.</target><part>Worldcom Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2002-07-21</tablecell><tablecell>$103,914,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|103914000000|2002|r">5}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>General Motors</target><part>General Motors Corporation</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.chapter11blog.com/chapter11/2009/06/general-motors-corporation-files-for-chapter-11.html</arg><arg name="title">Bankruptcy Reorganization Chapter</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension></tablecell><tablecell>2009-06-01</tablecell><tablecell>$82,300,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|82300000000|2009|r">5}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>CIT Group</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2009-11-01</tablecell><tablecell>$71,019,200,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|71019200000|2009|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Enron</target><part>Enron Corp.</part></link>*</tablecell><tablecell>2001-12-02</tablecell><tablecell>$63,392,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|63392000000|2001|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Conseco</target><part>Conseco, Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2002-12-18</tablecell><tablecell>$61,392,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|61392000000|2002|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>IL-N</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>MF Global</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2011-10-31</tablecell><tablecell>$41,000,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|41000000000|2011|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Chrysler</target><part>Chrysler LLC</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.chapter11blog.com/chapter11/2009/04/affidavit-of-cfo-filed-in-chrysler-chapter-11.html</arg><arg name="title">Bankruptcy Reorganization Chapter</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 August 2015</arg></template></extension></tablecell><tablecell>2009-04-30</tablecell><tablecell>$39,300,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|39300000000|2009|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Texaco</target><part>Texaco, Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>1987-04-12</tablecell><tablecell>$35,892,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|35892000000|1987|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Financial Corp. of America</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>1988-09-09</tablecell><tablecell>$33,864,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|33864000000|1988|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>CA-C</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Penn Central Transportation Company</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/4470905'></link></extension></tablecell><tablecell>1970-06-21</tablecell><tablecell>$7,000,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|7000000000|1970|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>PA-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Refco</target><part>Refco Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2005-10-17</tablecell><tablecell>$33,333,172,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|33333172000|2005|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Global Crossing</target><part>Global Crossing Ltd.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2002-01-28</tablecell><tablecell>$30,185,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|30185000000|2002|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Pacific Gas and Electric Company</target><part>Pacific Gas and Electric Co.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2001-04-06</tablecell><tablecell>$29,770,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|29770000000|2001|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>CA-N</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>UAL Corporation</target><part>UAL Corp.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2002-12-09</tablecell><tablecell>$25,197,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|25197000000|2002|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>IL-N</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Delta Air Lines</target><part>Delta Air Lines, Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2005-09-14</tablecell><tablecell>$21,801,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|21801000000|2005|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Delphi Automotive</target><part>Delphi Corporation, Inc.</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2005-10-08</tablecell><tablecell>$22,000,000,000</tablecell><tablecell>$<template><target>Formatprice</target><arg name="{{Inflation|US|21801000000|2005|r">4}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>NY-S</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph><extension extension_name='nowiki'>* The Enron assets were taken from the 10-Q filed on November 11, 2001. The company announced that the annual financials were under review at the time of filing for Chapter 11.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Similar programs in other countries</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>For similar programs in the United Kingdom, Australia, and New Zealand, see<space/><link><target>Administration (law)</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>For a similar program in Ireland see<space/><link><target>Examinership</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>For a similar program in Italy see<space/><link><target>Concordato preventivo</target></link><space/>(in Italian).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Government of the United States</arg><arg>Law</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/business/4342900.stm'>US changes bankruptcy protection laws</link>, via<space/><link><target>BBC News</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://uscode.house.gov/download/pls/Title_11.ZIP'>Complete Title 11 (ZIP file)</link>, via www.house.gov</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Title 11 of the United States Code</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:United States bankruptcy legislation</target></link><link><target>Category:Bankruptcy in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Companies that have filed for Chapter 11 bankruptcy</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Chapters of the United States Code</target></link><link><target>Category:Bankruptcy</target></link></paragraph></article>