<article title='DNA_replication'><paragraph><link><target>Image:DNA replication split.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>DNA replication. The<space/><link><target>double helix</target></link><space/>is unwound and each strand acts as a template for the next strand.<space/><link><target>Nucleotides</target><part>Bases</part></link><space/>are matched to synthesize the new partner strands.</part></link><space/><bold>DNA replication</bold><space/>is the process of producing two identical replicas from one original<space/><link><target>DNA</target></link><space/>molecule. This biological process occurs in all<space/><link><target>life on Earth</target><part>living organisms</part></link><space/>and is the basis for<space/><link><target>heredity</target><part>biological inheritance</part></link>. DNA is made up of two strands and each strand of the original DNA molecule serves as a template for the production of the complementary strand, a process referred to as<space/><link><target>semiconservative replication</target></link>. Cellular<space/><link><target>Proofreading (Biology)</target><part>proofreading</part></link><space/>and error-checking mechanisms ensure near perfect fidelity for DNA replication.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Berg">Imperfect DNA replication results in<space/><link><target>mutation</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Berg JM, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L, Clarke ND<space/></arg><arg name="title">Biochemistry<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fc,kgi?rid</arg><arg name="publisher">W.H. Freeman and Company<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-3051-0</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Alberts"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Biology of the Cell<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Science</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8153-3218-1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a<space/><link><target>cell (biology)</target><part>cell</part></link>, DNA replication begins at specific locations, or<space/><link><target>origin of replication</target><part>origins of replication</part></link>, in the<space/><link><target>genome</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="origins"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Berg JM, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L, Clarke ND</arg><arg name="title">Biochemistry</arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">[http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/bofghoks/bv.fcvbngi?rid</arg><arg name="publisher">W.H. Freeman and Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-3051-0</arg></template></extension><space/>Unwinding of DNA at the origin and synthesis of new strands results in<space/><link><target>replication fork</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>growing bidirectional from the origin. A number of<space/><link><target>protein</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are associated with the replication fork which helps in terms of the initiation and continuation of DNA synthesis. Most prominently,<space/><link><target>DNA polymerase</target></link><space/>synthesizes the new DNA by adding complementary<space/><link><target>nucleotides</target></link><space/>to the template strand.</paragraph><paragraph>DNA replication can also be performed<space/><italics><link><target>in vitro</target></link></italics><space/>(artificially, outside a cell). DNA polymerases isolated from cells and artificial DNA primers can be used to initiate DNA synthesis at known sequences in a template DNA molecule. The<space/><link><target>polymerase chain reaction</target></link><space/>(PCR), a common laboratory technique, cyclically applies such artificial synthesis to amplify a specific target DNA fragment from a pool of DNA.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background on DNA structure</heading><paragraph>DNA usually exists as a double-stranded structure, with both strands coiled together to form the characteristic<space/><link><target>double-helix</target></link>. Each single strand of DNA is a chain of four types of<space/><link><target>nucleotide</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Nucleotides in DNA contain a<space/><link><target>deoxyribose</target></link><space/>sugar, a<space/><link><target>phosphate</target></link>, and a<space/><link><target>nucleobase</target></link>. The four types of<space/><link><target>nucleotide</target></link><space/>correspond to the four<space/><link><target>nucleobase</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/><link><target>adenine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cytosine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>guanine</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>thymine</target></link>, commonly abbreviated as A,C, G and T. Adenine and guanine are<space/><link><target>purine</target></link><space/>bases, while cytosine and thymine are<space/><link><target>pyrimidine</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These nucleotides form phosphodiester bonds, creating the phosphate-deoxyribose backbone of the DNA double helix with the nucleobases pointing inward. Nucleotides (bases) are matched between strands through<space/><link><target>hydrogen bonding</target><part>hydrogen bonds</part></link><space/>to form<space/><link><target>base pair</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Adenine pairs with thymine (two hydrogen bonds), and guanine pairs with cytosine (stronger: three hydrogen bonds).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Directionality (molecular biology)</target><part>DNA strands have a directionality</part></link>, and the different ends of a single strand are called the &quot;3' (three-prime) end&quot; and the &quot;5' (five-prime) end&quot;. By convention, if the base sequence of a single strand of DNA is given, the left end of the sequence is the 5' end, while the right end of the sequence is the 3' end. The strands of the double helix are anti-parallel with one being 5' to 3', and the opposite strand 3' to 5'. These terms refer to the carbon atom in deoxyribose to which the next phosphate in the chain attaches. Directionality has consequences in DNA synthesis, because DNA polymerase can synthesize DNA in only one direction by adding nucleotides to the 3' end of a DNA strand.</paragraph><paragraph>The pairing of complementary bases in DNA through hydrogen bonding means that the information contained within each strand is redundant. The nucleotides on a single strand can be used to reconstruct nucleotides on a newly synthesized partner strand.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alberts, B., et al.,<space/><italics>Molecular Biology of the Cell,</italics><space/>Garland Science, 4th ed., 2002, pp. 238240 ISBN 0-8153-3218-1</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>DNA polymerase</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>DNA polymerase</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:DNA polymerase.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>DNA polymerases adds nucleotides to the 3' end of a strand of DNA.<extension extension_name='ref'>Allison, Lizabeth A.<space/><italics>Fundamental Molecular Biology</italics>. Blackwell Publishing. 2007. p.112 ISBN 978-1-4051-0379-4</extension><space/>If a mismatch is accidentally incorporated, the polymerase is inhibited from further extension. Proofreading removes the mismatched nucleotide and extension continues.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>DNA polymerase</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are a family of<space/><link><target>enzyme</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that carry out all forms of DNA replication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Berg JM, Tymoczko JL, Stryer L, Clarke ND</arg><arg name="title">Biochemistry</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">W.H. Freeman and Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-3051-0</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=stryer.section.3769'>Chapter 27, Section 2: DNA Polymerases Require a Template and a Primer</link></extension><space/>DNA polymerases in general cannot initiate synthesis of new strands, but can only extend an existing DNA or RNA strand paired with a template strand. To begin synthesis, a short fragment of RNA , called a<space/><link><target>primer (molecular biology)</target><part>primer</part></link>, must be created and paired with the template DNA strand.</paragraph><paragraph>DNA polymerase adds a new strand of DNA by extending the 3' end of an existing nucleotide chain, adding new<space/><link><target>nucleotide</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>matched to the template strand one at a time via the creation of<space/><link><target>phosphodiester bond</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The energy for this process of DNA polymerization comes from hydrolysis of the<space/><link><target>high-energy phosphate</target></link><space/>(phosphoanhydride) bonds between the three phosphates attached to each unincorporated<space/><link><target>nucleotide</target><part>base</part></link>. (Free bases with their attached phosphate groups are called<space/><link><target>nucleotide</target><trail>s</trail></link>; in particular, bases with three attached phosphate groups are called<space/><link><target>nucleoside triphosphate</target><trail>s</trail></link>.) When a nucleotide is being added to a growing DNA strand, the formation of a phosphodiester bond between the proximal phosphate of the nucleotide to the growing chain is accompanied by hydrolysis of a high-energy phosphate bond with release of the two distal phosphates as a<space/><link><target>pyrophosphate</target></link>. Enzymatic hydrolysis of the resulting pyrophosphate into inorganic phosphate consumes a second high-energy phosphate bond and renders the reaction effectively irreversible.<extension extension_name='ref' group="Note">The<space/><link><target>energetics</target></link><space/>of this process may also help explain the directionality of synthesisif DNA were synthesized in the 3' to 5' direction, the energy for the process would come from the 5' end of the growing strand rather than from free nucleotides. The problem is that if the high energy triphosphates were on the growing strand and not on the free nucleotides, proof-reading by removing a mismatched terminal nucleotide would be problematic: Once a nucleotide is added, the triphosphate is lost and a single phosphate remains on the backbone between the new nucleotide and the rest of the strand. If the added nucleotide were mismatched, removal would result in a DNA strand terminated by a monophosphate at the end of the &quot;growing strand&quot; rather than a high energy triphosphate. So strand would be stuck and wouldn't be able to grow anymore. In actuality, the high energy triphosphates hydrolyzed at each step originate from the free nucleotides, not the polymerized strand, so this issue does not exist.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In general, DNA polymerases are highly accurate, with an intrinsic error rate of less than one mistake for every 10<xhtml:sup>7</xhtml:sup><space/>nucleotides added.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pmid18166979"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">McCulloch SD, Kunkel TA<space/></arg><arg name="title">The fidelity of DNA synthesis by eukaryotic replicative and translesion synthesis polymerases<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Cell Research<space/></arg><arg name="volume">18<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">148–61<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2008<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">18166979<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1038/cr.2008.4<space/></arg><arg name="pmc">3639319</arg></template></extension><space/>In addition, some DNA polymerases also have proofreading ability; they can remove nucleotides from the end of a growing strand in order to correct mismatched bases. Finally, post-replication mismatch repair mechanisms monitor the DNA for errors, being capable of distinguishing mismatches in the newly synthesized DNA strand from the original strand sequence. Together, these three discrimination steps enable replication fidelity of less than one mistake for every 10<xhtml:sup>9</xhtml:sup><space/>nucleotides added.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pmid18166979"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The rate of DNA replication in a living cell was first measured as the rate of phage T4 DNA elongation in phage-infected E. coli.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>McCarthy D, Minner C, Bernstein H, Bernstein C<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>DNA elongation rates and growing point distributions of wild-type phage T4 and a DNA-delay amber mutant<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>J Mol Biol<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>106<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>963–81<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>789903<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(76)90346-6</arg></template></extension><space/>During the period of exponential DNA increase at 37&amp;nbsp;C, the rate was 749 nucleotides per second. The mutation rate per base pair per replication during phage T4 DNA synthesis is 1.7 per 10<xhtml:sup>8</xhtml:sup>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drake JW (1970)<space/><italics>The Molecular Basis of Mutation.</italics><space/>Holden-Day, San Francisco ISBN 0816224501 ISBN 978-0816224500</extension><space/>Thus DNA replication is both impressively fast and accurate.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Replication process</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Prokaryotic DNA replication</arg><arg>Eukaryotic DNA replication</arg></template>DNA Replication, like all biological polymerization processes, proceeds in three enzymatically catalyzed and coordinated steps: initiation, elongation and termination.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Initiation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Figure Role of initiators for initiation of DNA replication.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>Role of initiators for initiation of DNA replication.</part></link><link><target>File:EukPreRC.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Formation of pre-replication complex.</part></link>For a<space/><link><target>cell division</target><part>cell to divide</part></link>, it must first replicate its DNA.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Biology of the Cell<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Science</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8153-3218-1</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=mboc4.section.754'>Chapter 5: DNA Replication Mechanisms</link></extension><space/>This process is initiated at particular points in the DNA, known as &quot;<link><target>origin of replication</target><part>origin</part><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;, which are targeted by<space/><link><target>initiator protein</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="origins"></extension><space/>In<space/><italics><link><target>Escherichia coli</target><part>E. coli</part></link></italics><space/>this protein is<space/><link><target>DnaA</target></link>; in<space/><link><target>yeast</target></link>, this is the<space/><link><target>origin recognition complex</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Weigel C, Schmidt A, Rückert B, Lurz R, Messer W<space/></arg><arg name="title">DnaA protein binding to individual DnaA boxes in the Escherichia coli replication origin, oriC<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The EMBO Journal<space/></arg><arg name="volume">16<space/></arg><arg name="issue">21<space/></arg><arg name="pages">6574–83<space/></arg><arg name="date">November 1997<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">9351837<space/></arg><arg name="pmc">1170261<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/emboj/16.21.6574</arg></template></extension><space/>Sequences used by initiator proteins tend to be &quot;AT-rich&quot; (rich in adenine and thymine bases), because A-T base pairs have two hydrogen bonds (rather than the three formed in a C-G pair) which are easier to unzip.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Lodish H, Berk A, Zipursky LS, Matsudaira P, Baltimore D, Darnell J</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Cell Biology</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">W. H. Freeman and Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-3136-3</arg></template><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=mcb.section.3163#3179'>12.1. General Features of Chromosomal Replication: Three Common Features of Replication Origins</link></extension><space/>Once the origin has been located, these initiators recruit other proteins and form the<space/><link><target>pre-replication complex</target></link>, which unzips the double-stranded DNA.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Elongation</heading><paragraph>DNA polymerase has 5'-3' activity.All known DNA replication systems require a free 3'<space/><link><target>hydroxyl</target></link><space/>group before synthesis can be initiated (Important note: DNA is read in 3' to 5' direction whereas a new strand is synthesized in the 5' to 3' directionthis is often confused). Four distinct mechanisms for initiation of synthesis are recognized:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>All cellular life forms and many DNA<space/><link><target>virus</target><trail>es</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>phage</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>plasmid</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>use a<space/><link><target>primase</target></link><space/>to synthesize a short RNA primer with a free 3' OH group which is subsequently elongated by a DNA polymerase.<space/></listitem><listitem>The retroelements (including<space/><link><target>retrovirus</target><trail>es</trail></link>) employ a transfer RNA that primes DNA replication by providing a free 3 OH that is used for elongation by the<space/><link><target>reverse transcriptase</target></link>.<space/></listitem><listitem>In the<space/><link><target>adenovirus</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>29 family</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>bacteriophage</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the 3' OH group is provided by the side chain of an amino acid of the genome attached protein (the terminal protein) to which nucleotides are added by the DNA polymerase to form a new strand.<space/></listitem><listitem>In the single stranded DNA viruses a group that includes the<space/><link><target>circovirus</target><trail>es</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>geminivirus</target><trail>es</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>parvovirus</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>and others and also the many phages and<space/><link><target>plasmid</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that use the rolling circle replication (RCR) mechanism, the RCR endonuclease creates a nick in the genome strand (single stranded viruses) or one of the DNA strands (plasmids). The 5 end of the nicked strand is transferred to a<space/><link><target>tyrosine</target></link><space/>residue on the nuclease and the free 3 OH group is then used by the DNA polymerase to synthesize the new strand.</listitem></list><paragraph>The first is the best known of these mechanisms and is used by the cellular organisms. In this mechanism, once the two strands are separated,<space/><link><target>primase</target></link><space/>adds RNA primers to the template strands. The leading strand receives one RNA primer while the lagging strand receives several. The leading strand is continuously extended from the primer by a DNA polymerase with high<space/><link><target>processivity</target></link>, while the lagging strand is extended discontinuously from each primer forming Okazaki fragments.<space/><link><target>RNase</target></link><space/>removes the primer RNA fragments, and a low processivity DNA polymerase distinct from the replicative polymerase enters to fill the gaps. When this is complete, a single nick on the leading strand and several nicks on the lagging strand can be found.<space/><link><target>Ligase</target></link><space/>works to fill these nicks in, thus completing the newly replicated DNA molecule.</paragraph><paragraph>The primase used in this process differs significantly between<space/><link><target>bacteria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>archaea</target></link>/<link><target>eukaryote</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Bacteria use a primase belonging to the<space/><link><target>DnaG</target></link><space/>protein superfamily which contains a catalytic domain of the TOPRIM fold type.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/nar/26.18.4205 
</arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Aravind<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>L. 
</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Leipe<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>D. D. 
</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Koonin<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>E. V. 
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Toprim--a conserved catalytic domain in type IA and II topoisomerases, DnaG-type primases, OLD family nucleases and RecR proteins 
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Nucleic acids research 
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26 
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>18 
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>4205–4213 
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998 
</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>9722641 
</arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>147817
</arg></template></extension><space/>The TOPRIM fold contains an / core with four conserved strands in a<space/><link><target>Rossmann fold</target><part>Rossmann-like</part></link><space/>topology. This structure is also found in the catalytic domains of<space/><link><target>topoisomerase</target></link><space/>Ia, topoisomerase II, the OLD-family nucleases and DNA repair proteins related to the RecR protein.</paragraph><paragraph>The primase used by archaea and eukaryotes in contrast contains a highly derived version of the<space/><link><target>RNA recognition motif</target></link><space/>(RRM). This primase is structurally similar to many viral RNA dependent RNA polymerases, reverse transcriptases, cyclic nucleotide generating cyclases and DNA polymerases of the A/B/Y families that are involved in DNA replication and repair. In eukaryotic replication, the primase forms a complex with Pol .<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Frick</arg><arg name="first1">David</arg><arg name="last2">Richardson</arg><arg name="first2">Charles</arg><arg name="title">DNA Primases</arg><arg name="journal">Annual Review of Biochemistry</arg><arg name="date">July 2001</arg><arg name="volume">70</arg><arg name="pages">39–80</arg><arg name="url">http://www.annualreviews.org.ezaccess.libraries.psu.edu/doi/full/10.1146/annurev.biochem.70.1.39?url_ver</arg><arg name="doi">10.1146/annurev.biochem.70.1.39</arg><arg name="pmid">11395402</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Multiple DNA polymerases take on different roles in the DNA replication process. In<space/><italics><link><target>Escherichia coli</target><part>E. coli</part></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Pol III</target><part>DNA Pol III</part></link><space/>is the polymerase enzyme primarily responsible for DNA replication. It assembles into a replication complex at the replication fork that exhibits extremely high processivity, remaining intact for the entire replication cycle. In contrast,<space/><link><target>Pol I</target><part>DNA Pol I</part></link><space/>is the enzyme responsible for replacing RNA primers with DNA. DNA Pol I has a 5' to 3'<space/><link><target>exonuclease</target></link><space/>activity in addition to its polymerase activity, and uses its exonuclease activity to degrade the RNA primers ahead of it as it extends the DNA strand behind it, in a process called<space/><link><target>nick translation</target></link>. Pol I is much less processive than Pol III because its primary function in DNA replication is to create many short DNA regions rather than a few very long regions.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>eukaryote</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the low-processivity enzyme, Pol , helps to initiate replication. The high-processivity extension enzymes are Pol and Pol .</paragraph><paragraph>As DNA synthesis continues, the original DNA strands continue to unwind on each side of the bubble, forming a<space/><link><target>replication fork</target></link><space/>with two prongs. In bacteria, which have a single origin of replication on their circular chromosome, this process creates a &quot;<link><target>theta structure</target></link>&quot; (resembling the Greek letter theta: ). In contrast, eukaryotes have longer linear chromosomes and initiate replication at multiple origins within these.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Huberman JA, Riggs AD<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1968<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>On the mechanism of DNA replication in mammalian chromosomes<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>J Mol Biol<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>32<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>327–341<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>5689363<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0022-2836(68)90013-2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Replication fork</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Replication fork.svg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Scheme of the replication fork.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>a: template, b: leading strand, c: lagging strand, d: replication fork, e: primer, f:<space/><link><target>Okazaki fragments</target></link></part></link><link><target>Image:DNA replication.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Many enzymes are involved in the DNA replication fork.</part></link>The replication fork is a structure that forms within the nucleus during DNA replication. It is created by helicases, which break the hydrogen bonds holding the two DNA strands together. The resulting structure has two branching &quot;prongs&quot;, each one made up of a single strand of DNA. These two strands serve as the template for the leading and lagging strands, which will be created as DNA polymerase matches complementary nucleotides to the templates; the templates may be properly referred to as the leading strand template and the lagging strand template.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>DNA is always synthesized in the 5' to 3' direction.</bold><space/>Since the leading and lagging strand templates are oriented in opposite directions at the replication fork, a major issue is how to achieve synthesis of nascent (new) lagging strand DNA, whose direction of synthesis is opposite to the direction of the growing replication fork.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Leading strand</heading><paragraph>The leading strand is the strand of nascent DNA which is being synthesized in the same direction as the growing replication fork. A polymerase &quot;reads&quot; the leading strand<space/><italics>template</italics><space/>and adds complementary<space/><link><target>nucleotides</target></link><space/>to the nascent leading strand on a continuous basis.</paragraph><paragraph>The polymerase involved in leading strand synthesis is<space/><link><target>DNA polymerase III</target></link><space/>(DNA Pol III) in<space/><link><target>prokaryotes</target></link><space/>and Pol in eukaryotes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Johnson</arg><arg name="first1">RE</arg><arg name="last2">Klassen</arg><arg name="first2">R</arg><arg name="last3">Prakash</arg><arg name="first3">L</arg><arg name="last4">Prakash</arg><arg name="first4">S</arg><arg name="title">A Major Role of DNA Polymerase δ in Replication of Both the Leading and Lagging DNA Strands.</arg><arg name="journal">Molecular Cell</arg><arg name="date">July 2015</arg><arg name="volume">59</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="page">163-175</arg><arg name="pmid">26145172</arg></template></extension><space/>Pol can substitute for Pol in special circumstances.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kaplan Biochem"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hansen</arg><arg name="first">Barbara</arg><arg name="title">Biochemistry and Medical Genetics: Lecture Notes</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Kaplan Medical</arg><arg name="pages">21</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Lagging strand</heading><paragraph>The lagging strand is the strand of nascent DNA whose direction of synthesis is opposite to the direction of the growing replication fork. Because of its orientation, replication of the lagging strand is more complicated as compared to that of the leading strand.</paragraph><paragraph>The lagging strand is synthesized in short, separated segments. On the lagging strand<space/><italics>template</italics>, a<space/><link><target>primase</target></link><space/>&quot;reads&quot; the template DNA and initiates synthesis of a short complementary<space/><link><target>RNA</target></link><space/>primer. A DNA polymerase extends the primed segments, forming<space/><link><target>Okazaki fragment</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The RNA primers are then removed and replaced with DNA, and the fragments of DNA are joined together by<space/><link><target>DNA ligase</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>DNA polymerase III (in prokaryotes) or<space/><link><target>Pol</target></link><space/>(in eukaryotes) is responsible for extension of the primers added during replication of the lagging strand. Primer removal is performed by<space/><link><target>DNA polymerase I</target></link><space/>(in prokaryotes) and Pol (in eukaryotes).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://hdl.handle.net/1802/6537'>Distinguishing the pathways of primer removal during Eukaryotic Okazaki fragment maturation</link><space/>Contributor Author Rossi, Marie Louise. Date Accessioned: 2009-02-23T17:05:09Z. Date Available: 2009-02-23T17:05:09Z. Date Issued: 2009-02-23T17:05:09Z. Identifier Uri: http://hdl.handle.net/1802/6537. Description: Dr. Robert A. Bambara, Faculty Advisor. Thesis (PhD) School of Medicine and Dentistry, University of Rochester. UR only until January 2010. UR only until January 2010.</extension><space/>Eukaryotic primase is intrinsic to<space/><link><target>Polymerase (DNA directed), alpha 1</target><part>Pol</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Elizabeth R. Barry; Stephen D. Bell<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">DNA Replication in the Archaea<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Microbiology and Molecular Biology Reviews<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>70<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>876–887<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1128/MMBR.00029-06</arg><arg name="pmid">17158702</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pmc">1698513</arg></template></extension><space/>In eukaryotes, pol helps with repair during DNA replication.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Dynamics at the replication fork</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:1axc tricolor.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>The assembled human DNA clamp, a<space/><link><target>trimer (biochemistry)</target><part>trimer</part></link><space/>of the protein<space/><link><target>PCNA</target></link>.</part></link>As helicase unwinds DNA at the replication fork, the DNA ahead is forced to rotate. This process results in a build-up of twists in the DNA ahead.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Biology of the Cell<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Science</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8153-3218-1</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=mboc4.section.754#787'>DNA Replication Mechanisms: DNA Topoisomerases Prevent DNA Tangling During Replication</link></extension><space/>This build-up forms a torsional resistance that would eventually halt the progress of the replication fork.<space/><link><target>Topoisomerase</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are enzymes that temporarily break the strands of DNA, relieving the tension caused by unwinding the two strands of the DNA helix; topoisomerases (including<space/><link><target>DNA gyrase</target></link>) achieve this by adding negative<space/><link><target>DNA supercoil</target><part>supercoils</part></link><space/>to the DNA helix.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Reece<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>R. J. 
</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Maxwell<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>A. 
</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Wang<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>J. C. 
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.3109/10409239109114072 
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>DNA Gyrase: Structure and Function 
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Critical Reviews in Biochemistry and Molecular Biology 
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26 
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3–4 
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>335–375 
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991 
</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>1657531 
</arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bare single-stranded DNA tends to fold back on itself forming<space/><link><target>Biomolecular structure#Secondary structure</target><part>secondary structures</part></link>; these structures can interfere with the movement of DNA polymerase. To prevent this,<space/><link><target>single-strand binding protein</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>bind to the DNA until a second strand is synthesized, preventing secondary structure formation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Biology of the Cell<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Science</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8153-3218-1</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=mboc4.section.754#774'>DNA Replication Mechanisms: Special Proteins Help to Open Up the DNA Double Helix in Front of the Replication Fork</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>DNA clamp</target><part>Clamp proteins</part></link><space/>form a sliding clamp around DNA, helping the DNA polymerase maintain contact with its template, thereby assisting with processivity. The inner face of the clamp enables DNA to be threaded through it. Once the polymerase reaches the end of the template or detects double-stranded DNA, the sliding clamp undergoes a conformational change that releases the DNA polymerase. Clamp-loading proteins are used to initially load the clamp, recognizing the junction between template and RNA primers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alberts"></extension><xhtml:sup><list type='ident'><listitem>274-5</listitem></list></xhtml:sup></paragraph><heading level='3'>DNA replication proteins</heading><paragraph>At the replication fork, many replication enzymes assemble on the DNA into a complex molecular machine called the<space/><link><target>replisome</target></link>. The following is a list of major DNA replication enzymes that participate in the replisome:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Griffiths A.J.F., Wessler S.R., Lewontin R.C., Carroll S.B.</arg><arg name="title">Introduction to Genetic Analysis</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">W. H. Freeman and Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7167-6887-9</arg></template>[Chapter 7: DNA: Structure and Replication. pg 283290]</extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Enzyme</tablehead><tablehead>Function in DNA replication</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DNA Helicase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Also known as helix destabilizing enzyme. Unwinds the DNA double helix at the<space/><link><target>Replication Fork</target></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DNA Polymerase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Builds a new duplex DNA strand by adding nucleotides in the 5' to 3' direction. Also performs proof-reading and error correction. There exist many different types of DNA Polymerase, each of which perform different functions in different types of cells.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DNA clamp</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>A protein which prevents elongating DNA polymerases from dissociating from the DNA parent strand.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Single-strand binding protein</target><part>Single-Strand Binding (SSB) Proteins</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Bind to ssDNA and prevent the DNA double helix from re-annealing after DNA helicase unwinds it, thus maintaining the strand separation, and facilitating the synthesis of the nascent strand.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Topoisomerase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Relaxes the DNA from its super-coiled nature.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DNA Gyrase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Relieves strain of unwinding by DNA helicase; this is a specific type of topoisomerase</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>DNA Ligase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Re-anneals the semi-conservative strands and joins<space/><link><target>Okazaki Fragments</target></link><space/>of the lagging strand.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Primase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Provides a starting point of RNA (or DNA) for DNA polymerase to begin synthesis of the new DNA strand.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Telomerase</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Lengthens telomeric DNA by adding repetitive nucleotide sequences to the ends of<space/><bold><link><target>Eukaryotic chromosome fine structure</target><part>eukaryotic chromosomes</part></link></bold>. This allows germ cells and stem cells to avoid the Hayflick limit on cell division.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://science.howstuffworks.com/life/genetic/hayflick-limit.htm</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Will the Hayflick limit keep us from living forever?</arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>January 20, 2015<space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/>Howstuffworks</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg></template></extension></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Replication machinery</heading><paragraph><bold>Replication machineries</bold><space/>consist of factors involved in DNA replication and appearing on template ssDNAs. Replication machineries include primosomes also. The factors are replication enzymes; DNA polymerase, DNA helicases, DNA clamps and DNA topoisomerases, and replication proteins; e.g. single-stranded DNA binding proteins (SSB). In the replication machineries these components coordinate. In most of the bacteria, all of the factors involved in DNA replication are located on replication forks and the complexes stay on the forks during DNA replication. This replication machineries are called<space/><bold>replisomes</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>DNA replicase systems</bold>, these terms mean originally a generic term for proteins located on replication forks. In eukaryotic and some bacterial cells the replisomes are not formed.</paragraph><paragraph>Since replication machineries do not move relatively to template DNAs such as factories, they are called<space/><bold>replication factory</bold>.<extension extension_name='ref' name='watson237'>James D. Watson et al. (2008), &quot;Molecular Biology of the gene&quot;, Pearson Education: 237</extension><space/>In an alternative figure, DNA factories are similar to projectors and DNAs are like as cinematic films passing constantly into the projectors. In the replication factory model, after both DNA helicases for leading stands and lagging strands are loaded on the template DNAs, the helicases run along the DNAs into each other. The helicases remain associated for the remainder of replication process. Peter Meister et al. observed directly replication sites in<space/><link><target>budding yeast</target></link><space/>by monitoring<space/><link><target>green fluorescent protein</target></link>(GFP)-tagged DNA polymerases . They detected DNA replication of pairs of the tagged loci spaced apart symmetrically from a replication origin and found that the distance between the pairs decreased markedly by time.<extension extension_name='ref' name='in&amp;out'>Peter Meister, Angela Taddei1, Susan M. Gasser(June 2006), &quot;In and out of the Replication Factory&quot;,<space/><italics>Cell</italics><space/><bold>125</bold><space/>(7): 12331235</extension><space/>This finding suggests that the mechanism of DNA replication goes with DNA factories. Suggesting, couples of replication factories are loaded on replication origins and the factories associated with each other. Also, template DNAs move into the factories, which bring extrusion of the template ssDNAs and nascent DNAs. Peters finding is the first direct evidence of replication factory model. By later researches, it is revealed that DNA helicases form dimers in many eukaryotic cells and bacterial replication machineries stay in single intranuclear location during DNA synthesis.<extension extension_name='ref' name='watson237'></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The replication factories perform disentanglement of sister chromatids. The disentanglement is essential to distribute the chromatids into daughter cells after DNA replication. Because sister chromatids after DNA replication hold each other by<space/><bold><link><target>Cohesin</target></link></bold><space/>rings, there is the only chance for the disentanglement in DNA replication. Fixing of replication machineries as replication factories can improve a success rate of DNA replication. If replication forks move freely in chromosomes, catenation of nuclei is aggravated and impedes mitotic segregation.<extension extension_name='ref' name='in&amp;out'></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Termination</heading><paragraph>Eukaryotes initiate DNA replication at multiple points in the chromosome, so replication forks meet and terminate at many points in the chromosome; these are not known to be regulated in any particular way. Because eukaryotes have linear chromosomes, DNA replication is unable to reach the very end of the chromosomes, but ends at the<space/><link><target>telomere</target></link><space/>region of repetitive DNA close to the end. This shortens the telomere of the daughter DNA strand. Shortening of the telomeres is a normal process in<space/><link><target>somatic cell</target><trail>s</trail></link>. As a result, cells can only divide a certain number of times before the DNA loss prevents further division. (This is known as the<space/><link><target>Hayflick limit</target></link>.) Within the<space/><link><target>germ cell</target></link><space/>line, which passes DNA to the next generation,<space/><link><target>telomerase</target></link><space/>extends the repetitive sequences of the telomere region to prevent degradation. Telomerase can become mistakenly active in somatic cells, sometimes leading to<space/><link><target>cancer</target></link><space/>formation. Increased telomerase activity is one of the Hallmarks of cancer.</paragraph><paragraph>Termination requires that the progress of the DNA replication fork must stop or be blocked. Termination at a specific locus, when it occurs, involves the interaction between two components: (1) a termination site sequence in the DNA, and (2) a protein which binds to this sequence to physically stop DNA replication. In various bacterial species, this is named the DNA replication terminus site-binding protein, or<space/><link><target>Ter protein</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Because bacteria have circular chromosomes, termination of replication occurs when the two replication forks meet each other on the opposite end of the parental chromosome.<space/><italics>E. coli</italics><space/>regulates this process through the use of termination sequences that, when bound by the<space/><link><target>Tus protein</target></link>, enable only one direction of replication fork to pass through. As a result, the replication forks are constrained to always meet within the termination region of the chromosome.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>TA Brown</arg><arg name="title">Genomes</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BIOS Scientific Publishers]]</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85996-228-9</arg></template><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=genomes.section.8121#8156'>13.2.3. Termination of replication</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Regulation</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cell Cycle 2.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>The cell cycle of eukaryotic cells.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Eukaryotes</heading><paragraph>Within eukaryotes, DNA replication is controlled within the context of the<space/><link><target>cell cycle</target></link>. As the cell grows and divides, it progresses through stages in the cell cycle; DNA replication takes place during the S phase (synthesis phase). The progress of the eukaryotic cell through the cycle is controlled by<space/><link><target>cell cycle checkpoint</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Progression through checkpoints is controlled through complex interactions between various proteins, including<space/><link><target>cyclin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cyclin-dependent kinase</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Alberts B, Johnson A, Lewis J, Raff M, Roberts K, Walter P</arg><arg name="title">Molecular Biology of the Cell<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Science</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8153-3218-1</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/bv.fcgi?rid=mboc4.section.3214#3215'>Intracellular Control of Cell-Cycle Events: S-Phase Cyclin-Cdk Complexes (S-Cdks) Initiate DNA Replication Once Per Cycle</link></extension><space/>Unlike bacteria, eukaryotic DNA replicates in the confines of the nucleus.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Genomes</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Brown</arg><arg name="first"><space/>TA</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wiley-Liss</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford</arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>2nd</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>13</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www-ncbi-nlm-nih-gov.proxy1.lib.uwo.ca/books/NBK21113/</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The G1/S checkpoint (or restriction checkpoint) regulates whether eukaryotic cells enter the process of DNA replication and subsequent division. Cells that do not proceed through this checkpoint remain in the G0 stage and do not replicate their DNA.</paragraph><paragraph>Replication of chloroplast and mitochondrial genomes occurs independently of the cell cycle, through the process of<space/><link><target>D-loop replication</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Replication focus</heading><paragraph>In vertebrate cells, replication sites concentrate into positions called<space/><bold>replication foci</bold>.<extension extension_name='ref' name='in&amp;out'></extension><space/>Replication sites can be detected by immunostaining daughter strands and replication enzymes and monitoring GFP-tagged replication factors. By these methods it is found that replication foci of varying size and positions appear in S phase of cell division and their number per nucleus is far smaller than the number of genomic replication forks.</paragraph><paragraph>P. Heun et al.(2001) tracked GFP-tagged replication foci in budding yeast cells and revealed that replication origins move constantly in G1 and S phase and the<space/><link><target>Molecular dynamics</target><part>dynamics</part></link><space/>decreased significantly in S phase.<extension extension_name='ref' name='in&amp;out'></extension><space/>Traditionally, replication sites were fixed on spatial structure of chromosomes by<space/><link><target>nuclear matrix</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>lamin</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The Heuns results denied the traditional concepts, budding yeasts don't have lamins, and support that replication origins self-assemble and form replication foci.</paragraph><paragraph>By firing of replication origins, controlled spatially and temporally, the formation of replication foci is regulated. D. A. Jackson et al.(1998) revealed that neighboring origins fire simultaneously in mammalian cells.<extension extension_name='ref' name='in&amp;out'></extension><space/>Spatial juxtaposition of replication sites brings<space/><bold>clustering</bold><space/>of replication forks. The clustering do<space/><bold>rescue of stalled replication forks</bold><space/>and favors normal progress of replication forks. Progress of replication forks is inhibited by many factors; collision with proteins or with complexes binding strongly on DNA, deficiency of dNTPs, nicks on template DNAs and so on. If replication forks stall and remaining sequences from the stalled forks are not replicated, daughter strands have nick obtained un-replicated sites. The un-replicated sites on one parent's strand hold the other strand together but not daughter strands. Therefore, resulting sister chromatids cannot separate together and cannot divide into 2 daughter cells. When neighboring origins fire and a fork from one origin is stalled, fork from other origin access on an opposite direction of the stalled fork and duplicate the un-replicated sites. As other mechanism of the rescue there is application of<space/><bold>dormant replication origins</bold><space/>that excess origins don't fire in normal DNA replication.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bacteria</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hemimethylation.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Dam methylates adenine of GATC sites after replication.</part></link>Most bacteria do not go through a well-defined cell cycle but instead continuously copy their DNA; during rapid growth, this can result in the concurrent occurrence of multiple rounds of replication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Obligate Human Pathogen, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, Is Polyploid</arg><arg name="author">Tobiason DM, Seifert HS</arg><arg name="journal">PLoS Biology</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="volume">4</arg><arg name="issue">6</arg><arg name="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0040185</arg><arg name="pages">e185</arg><arg name="pmid">16719561</arg><arg name="pmc">1470461</arg></template><space/><template><target>open access</target></template></extension><space/>In<space/><italics>E. coli</italics>, the best-characterized bacteria, DNA replication is regulated through several mechanisms, including: the hemimethylation and sequestering of the origin sequence, the ratio of<space/><link><target>Adenosine triphosphate</target><part>adenosine triphosphate (ATP)</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Adenosine diphosphate</target><part>adenosine diphosphate (ADP)</part></link>, and the levels of protein DnaA. All these control the binding of initiator proteins to the origin sequences.</paragraph><paragraph>Because<space/><italics>E. coli</italics><space/><link><target>DNA methylation</target><part>methylates</part></link><space/>GATC DNA sequences, DNA synthesis results in hemimethylated sequences. This hemimethylated DNA is recognized by the protein<space/><link><target>SeqA protein domain</target><part>SeqA</part></link>, which binds and sequesters the origin sequence; in addition, DnaA (required for initiation of replication) binds less well to hemimethylated DNA. As a result, newly replicated origins are prevented from immediately initiating another round of DNA replication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Slater S, Wold S, Lu M, Boye E, Skarstad K, Kleckner N<space/></arg><arg name="title">E. coli SeqA protein binds oriC in two different methyl-modulated reactions appropriate to its roles in DNA replication initiation and origin sequestration<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Cell<space/></arg><arg name="volume">82<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="pages">927–36<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 1995<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">7553853<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0092-8674(95)90272-4</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>ATP builds up when the cell is in a rich medium, triggering DNA replication once the cell has reached a specific size. ATP competes with ADP to bind to DnaA, and the DnaA-ATP complex is able to initiate replication. A certain number of DnaA proteins are also required for DNA replication each time the origin is copied, the number of binding sites for DnaA doubles, requiring the synthesis of more DnaA to enable another initiation of replication.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Polymerase chain reaction</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Polymerase chain reaction</arg></template>Researchers commonly replicate DNA<space/><italics>in vitro</italics><space/>using the<space/><link><target>polymerase chain reaction</target></link><space/>(PCR). PCR uses a pair of<space/><link><target>primer (molecular biology)</target><part>primers</part></link><space/>to span a target region in template DNA, and then polymerizes partner strands in each direction from these primers using a thermostable<space/><link><target>DNA polymerase</target></link>. Repeating this process through multiple cycles amplifies the targeted DNA region. At the start of each cycle, the mixture of template and primers is heated, separating the newly synthesized molecule and template. Then, as the mixture cools, both of these become templates for annealing of new primers, and the polymerase extends from these. As a result, the number of copies of the target region doubles each round,<space/><link><target>exponential growth</target><part>increasing exponentially</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Saiki2"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Saiki</arg><arg name="first"><space/>RK</arg><arg name="author2">Gelfand DH</arg><arg name="author3">Stoffel S</arg><arg name="author4">Scharf SJ</arg><arg name="author5">Higuchi R</arg><arg name="author6">Horn GT</arg><arg name="author7">Mullis KB</arg><arg name="author8">Erlich HA<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/cgi-bin/ebind2html/pcr/009</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Primer-directed enzymatic amplification of DNA with a thermostable DNA polymerase</arg><arg name="journal">[[Science (journal)|Science]]</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988</arg><arg name="volume">239</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>487–91</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1126/science.2448875</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>2448875</arg><arg name="issue">4839</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg><arg name="group">Note</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>DNA replication</arg></template><template><target>DNA replication</target></template><template><target>Portal bar</target><arg>Molecular and cellular biology</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Dna Replication</target></template><link><target>Category:DNA replication</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Senescence</target></link></paragraph></article>