<article title='Alexios_I_Komnenos'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Alexius I</arg></template><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Alexios Komnenos</arg></template><template><target>Infobox Monarch</target><arg name="name">Aléxios&nbsp;I Komnēnós<br />Ἀλέξιος&nbsp;Α' Κομνηνός
</arg><arg name="title">[[List of Byzantine emperors|Emperor]] of the [[Byzantine Empire]]
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Alexios I Komnenos.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption">Portrait of Emperor Alexios&nbsp;I, from a Greek manuscript
</arg><arg name="succession">Byzantine Emperor
</arg><arg name="reign">1 April 1081<ref name</arg><arg name="coronation">5 April 1081<ref name</arg><arg name="predecessor">[[Nikephoros&nbsp;III Botaneiates]]
</arg><arg name="successor">[[John&nbsp;II Komnenos]]
</arg><arg name="spouse">? Argyre<br />[[Irene Doukaina]]
</arg><arg name="issue">[[Anna Komnene]]<br />[[Maria Komnene (1085&ndash;1136)|Maria Komnene]]<br />[[John&nbsp;II Komnenos]]<br />[[Andronikos Komnenos (1091&ndash;1131)|Andronikos Komnenos]]<br />[[Eudokia Komnene (1094&ndash;1131)|Eudokia Komnene]]<br />[[Theodora Komnene (b. 1096)|Theodora Komnene]]<br />[[Isaac Komnenos (son of Alexios I)|Isaac Komnenos]]<br />[[Manuel Komnenos (b. 1097)|Manuel Komnenos]]<br />[[Zoe Komnene]]
</arg><arg name="full name">
</arg><arg name="house">[[Komnenos dynasty|Komnenoi]]
</arg><arg name="house-type">Dynasty
</arg><arg name="father">[[John Komnenos (Domestic of the Schools)|John Komnenos]]
</arg><arg name="mother">[[Anna Dalassena]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date">1056
</arg><arg name="birth_place">
</arg><arg name="death_date">15 August 1118<br /><space/>(age 62)
</arg><arg name="death_place">
</arg><arg name="place of burial">
</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Alexios&amp;nbsp;I Komnenos</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-grc-gre</target><arg>Ἀλέξιος&nbsp;Αʹ Κομνηνός</arg></template>, 1048<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 4">Norwich, pg. 4</extension><space/>or 1056&amp;nbsp;&amp;ndash; 15 August 1118),<space/><link><target>Latinization (literature)</target><part>Latinized</part></link><space/>as<space/><bold>Alexius&amp;nbsp;I Comnenus</bold>, was<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target><part>Byzantine</part></link><space/><link><target>List of Byzantine Emperors</target><part>emperor</part></link><space/>from 1081 to 1118. Although he was not the founder of the<space/><link><target>Komnenos</target><part>Komnenian dynasty</part></link>, it was during his reign that the Komnenos family came to full power. Inheriting a collapsing empire and faced with constant warfare during his reign against both the<space/><link><target>Seljuq Turks</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Asia Minor</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Italo-Normans</target><part>Normans</part></link><space/>in the western<space/><link><target>Balkans</target></link>, Alexios was able to halt the Byzantine decline and begin the military, financial, and territorial recovery known as the<space/><italics><link><target>Komnenian restoration</target></link></italics>. His appeals to Western Europe for help against the Turks were also the catalyst that likely contributed to the convoking of the<space/><link><target>Crusades</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Life</heading><paragraph>Alexios was the son of the<space/><link><target>Domestic of the Schools</target></link><space/><link><target>John Komnenos (Domestic of the Schools)</target><part>John Komnenos</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Anna Dalassena</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 63">Kazhdan, pg. 63</extension><space/>and the nephew of<space/><link><target>Isaac&amp;nbsp;I Komnenos</target></link><space/>(emperor 10571059). Alexios' father declined the throne on the abdication of Isaac, who was thus succeeded by four emperors of other families between 1059 and 1081. Under one of these emperors,<space/><link><target>Romanos&amp;nbsp;IV Diogenes</target></link><space/>(10671071), Alexios served with distinction against the<space/><link><target>Seljuq Turks</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 4"></extension><space/>Under<space/><link><target>Michael&amp;nbsp;VII Doukas</target></link><space/><italics>Parapinakes</italics><space/>(10711078) and<space/><link><target>Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III Botaneiates</target></link><space/>(10781081), he was also employed, along with his elder brother<space/><link><target>Isaac Komnenos (brother of Alexios I)</target><part>Isaac</part></link>, against rebels in<space/><link><target>Asia Minor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link>, and in<space/><link><target>Epirus</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1074, western mercenaries led by<space/><link><target>Roussel de Bailleul</target></link><space/>rebelled in Asia Minor,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 2">Norwich, pg. 2</extension><space/>but Alexios successfully subdued them by 1076.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alexiad, 1.1">&quot;Alexiad&quot;, 1.1</extension><space/>In 1078, he was appointed commander of the field army in the West by Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 3">Norwich, pg. 3</extension><space/>In this capacity, Alexios defeated the rebellions of<space/><link><target>Nikephoros Bryennios the Elder</target></link><space/>(whose son or grandson later married Alexios' daughter Anna) and<space/><link><target>Nikephoros Basilakes</target></link>, the first at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Kalavrye</target></link><space/>and the latter in a surprise night attack on his camp.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 277">Canduci, pg. 277</extension><space/>Alexios was ordered to march against his brother-in-law<space/><link><target>Nikephoros Melissenos</target></link><space/>in Asia Minor but refused to fight his kinsman. This did not, however, lead to a demotion, as Alexios was needed to counter the expected invasion of the<space/><link><target>Italo-Normans</target><part>Normans</part></link><space/>of Southern Italy, led by<space/><link><target>Robert Guiscard</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Conspiracy and revolt of the Komnenoi against Botaneiates</heading><paragraph>While Byzantine troops were assembling for the expedition, the Doukas faction at court approached Alexios and convinced him to join a<space/><link><target>conspiracy (political)</target><part>conspiracy</part></link><space/>against Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III. The mother of Alexios, Anna Dalassena, was to play a prominent role in this coup d'tat of 1081, along with the current empress,<space/><link><target>Maria of Alania</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena">Garland, &quot;Anna Dalassena&quot;</extension><space/>First married to Michael&amp;nbsp;VII Doukas and secondly to<space/><link><target>Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III Botaneiates</target></link>, she was preoccupied with the future of her son by Michael&amp;nbsp;VII,<space/><link><target>Constantine Doukas</target></link>. Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III intended to leave the throne to one of his close relatives,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 59">Finlay, pg. 59</extension><space/>and this resulted in Maria's ambivalence and alliance with the Komnenoi, though the real driving force behind this political alliance was Anna Dalassene.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Alexiad&quot;, 2.2.12</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The empress was already closely connected to the Komnenoi through Maria's cousin Irene to Isaac Komnenos,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 59"></extension><space/>so the Komnenoi brothers were able to see her under the pretense of a friendly family visit. Furthermore, to aid the conspiracy Maria had adopted Alexios as her son, though she was only five years older than he.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 5">Norwich, pg. 5</extension><space/>Maria was persuaded to do so on the advice of her own &quot;Alans&quot; and her eunuchs, who had been instigated by Isaac Komnenos. Given Anna's tight hold on her family, Alexios must have been adopted with her implicit approval.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>As a result, Alexios and Constantine, Maria's son, were now adoptive brothers, and both Isaac and Alexios took an oath that they would safeguard his rights as emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Alexiad&quot; 2,1,46, 2.3.23,2.3.4; cf, Bryennius 4.2, who dates the adoption to early in the reign of Botaneiates</extension><space/>By secretly giving inside information to the Komnenoi, Maria was an invaluable ally.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Alexiad&quot;, 2.3.4,2.4.5</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Seal of Alexios Komnenos as Grand Domestic of the West.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Seal of Alexios as &quot;<link><target>Domestic of the Schools</target><part>Grand Domestic of the West</part></link>&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>As stated in the Alexiad, Isaac and Alexios left Constantinople in mid-February 1081 to raise an army against Botaneiates.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 6</extension><space/>However, when the time came, Anna quickly and surreptitiously mobilized the remainder of the family and took refuge in the<space/><link><target>Hagia Sophia</target></link>. From there she negotiated with the emperor for the safety of family members left in the capital, while protesting her sons' innocence of hostile actions. Under the falsehood of making a vesperal visit to worship at the church, she deliberately excluded the grandson of Botaneiates and his loyal tutor, met with Alexios and Isaac, and fled for the forum of Constantine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>The tutor discovered they were missing and eventually found them on the palace grounds, but Anna was able to convince him that they would return to the palace shortly. Then to gain entrance to both the outer and inner sanctuary of the church, the women pretended to the gatekeepers that they were pilgrims from<space/><link><target>Cappadocia</target></link><space/>who had spent all their funds and wanted to worship before starting their return trip. However, before they were to gain entry into the sanctuary, Straboromanos and royal guards caught up with them to summon them back to the palace.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>Anna then protested that the family was in fear for their lives, her sons were loyal subjects (Alexios and Isaac were discovered absent without leave), and had learned of a plot by enemies of the Komnenoi to have them both blinded and had, therefore, fled the capital so they may continue to be of loyal service to the emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Alexiad&quot;,2.5.5</extension><space/>She refused to go with them and demanded that they allow her to pray to the Mother of God for protection. This request was granted and Anna then manifested her true theatrical and manipulative capabilities:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>She was allowed to enter. As if she were weighed down with old age and worn out by grief, she walked slowly and when she approached the actual entrance to the sanctuary made two genuflections; on the third she sank to the floor and taking firm hold of the sacred doors, cried in a loud voice: "Unless my hands are cuff off, I will not leave this holy place except on one condition: that I receive the emperor's cross as guarantee of safety".<ref>"Alexiad", 2.5.6</ref></arg></template><link><target>File:Alex1.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Alexios I. Manuscript illustration.</part></link>Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III Botaneiates was forced into a public vow that he would grant protection to the family.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>Straboromanos tried to give Anna his cross, but for her it was not sufficiently large enough for all bystanders to witness the oath. She also demanded that the cross be personally sent by Botaneiates as a vow of his good faith. He obliged, sending a complete assurance for the family with his own cross. At the emperor's further insistence, and for their own protection, they took refuge at the convent of Petrion, where they were eventually joined by<space/><link><target>Maria of Bulgaria</target></link>, mother of Irene Doukaina.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>Botaneiates allowed them to be treated as refugees rather than as guests. They were allowed to have family members bring in their own food and were on good terms with the guards from whom they learned the latest news.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Alexiad&quot;, 2.5.79</extension><space/>Anna was highly successful in three important aspects of the revolt: she bought time for her sons to steal imperial horses from the stables and escape the city; she distracted the emperor, giving her sons time to gather and arm their troops; and she gave a false sense of security to Botaneiates that there was no real treasonous coup against him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Garland, Anna Dalassena"></extension><space/>After bribing the Western troops guarding the city, Isaac and Alexios Komnenos entered the capital victoriously on April 1, 1081.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 63</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During this time, Alexios was rumored to be the lover of Empress<space/><link><target>Maria Bagrationi</target><part>Maria of Alania</part></link>, the daughter of King<space/><link><target>Bagrat&amp;nbsp;IV of Georgia</target></link>, who had been successively married to<space/><link><target>Michael&amp;nbsp;VII</target></link><space/>Doukas and his successor Nikephoros&amp;nbsp;III Botaneiates, and who was renowned for her beauty.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 10</extension><space/>Alexios arranged for Maria to stay on the palace grounds, and it was thought that he was considering marrying her. However, his mother consolidated the Doukas family connection by arranging the Emperor's marriage to<space/><link><target>Irene Doukaina</target></link>, granddaughter of the<space/><link><target>John Doukas, Caesar</target><part>Caesar John Doukas</part></link>, the uncle of Michael&amp;nbsp;VII, who would not have supported Alexios otherwise. As a measure intended to keep the support of the Doukai, Alexios restored<space/><link><target>Constantine Doukas (co-emperor)</target><part>Constantine Doukas</part></link>, the young son of Michael&amp;nbsp;VII and Maria, as co-emperor<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 12</extension><space/>and a little later betrothed him to his own first-born daughter<space/><link><target>Anna Komnene</target><part>Anna</part></link>, who moved into the Mangana Palace with her fianc and his mother.</paragraph><paragraph>This situation changed drastically, however, when Alexios' first son<space/><link><target>John&amp;nbsp;II Komnenos</target></link><space/>was born in 1087:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 658">Kazhdan, pg. 658</extension><space/>Anna's engagement to Constantine was dissolved, and she was moved to the main Palace to live with her mother and grandmother. Alexios became estranged from Maria, who was stripped of her imperial title and retired to a monastery, and Constantine Doukas was deprived of his status as co-emperor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 658"></extension><space/>Nevertheless, he remained in good relations with the imperial family and succumbed to his weak constitution soon afterwards.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Wars against the Normans, Pechenegs, and Tzachas</heading><paragraph><template><target>Details</target><arg>Byzantine-Norman Wars</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The nearly thirty-seven year reign of Alexios was full of struggle. At the outset he faced the formidable attack of the Normans, led by<space/><link><target>Robert Guiscard</target></link><space/>and his son<space/><link><target>Bohemond I of Antioch</target><part>Bohemund</part></link>, who took<space/><link><target>Dyrrhachium</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Corfu</target></link><space/>and laid siege to<space/><link><target>Larissa</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Thessaly</target></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>Battle of Dyrrhachium (1081)</target><part>Battle of Dyrrhachium</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 277"></extension><space/>Alexios suffered several defeats before he was able to strike back with success. He enhanced his resistance by bribing the German king<space/><link><target>Henry IV, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Henry&amp;nbsp;IV</part></link><space/>with 360,000 gold pieces to attack the Normans in Italy,<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 21</extension><space/>which forced the Normans to concentrate on their defenses at home in 108384. He also secured the alliance of<space/><link><target>Henry, Count of Monte Sant'Angelo</target></link>, who controlled the<space/><link><target>Gargano Peninsula</target></link><space/>and dated his charters by Alexios' reign. Henry's allegiance would be the last example of Byzantine political control on peninsular Italy. The Norman danger subsided with the death of Guiscard in 1085, and the Byzantines recovered most of their losses.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 25</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexios next had to deal with disturbances in<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link>, where the heretical sects of the<space/><link><target>Bogomils</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Paulicians</target></link><space/>revolted and made common cause with the<space/><link><target>Pechenegs</target></link><space/>from beyond the<space/><link><target>Danube</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 101</extension><space/>Paulician soldiers in imperial service likewise deserted during Alexios' battles with the Normans.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 78</extension><space/>As soon as the Norman threat had passed, Alexios set out to punish the rebels and deserters, confiscating their lands. This led to a further revolt near<space/><link><target>Plovdiv</target><part>Philippopolis</part></link>, and the commander of the field army in the west, Gregory Pakourianos, was defeated and killed in the ensuing battle. In 1087 the Pechenegs raided into Thrace, and Alexios crossed into<space/><link><target>Moesia</target></link><space/>to retaliate but failed to take Dorostolon (<link><target>Silistra</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 102</extension><space/>During his retreat, the emperor was surrounded and worn down by the Pechenegs, who forced him to sign a truce and to pay protection money. In 1090 the Pechenegs invaded Thrace again,<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 104</extension><space/>while<space/><link><target>Tzachas</target></link>, the brother-in-law of the Sultan of<space/><link><target>Sultanate of Rm</target><part>Rum</part></link>, launched a fleet and attempted to arrange a joint siege of Constantinople with the Pechenegs.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 26</extension><space/>Alexios overcame this crisis by entering into an alliance with a horde of 40,000<space/><link><target>Cumans</target></link>, with whose help he crushed the Pechenegs at<space/><link><target>Battle of Levounion</target><part>Levounion</part></link><space/>in Thrace on 29 April 1091.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 27</extension></paragraph><paragraph>This put an end to the Pecheneg threat, but in 1094 the Cumans began to raid the imperial territories in the Balkans. Led by a pretender claiming to be Constantine Diogenes, a long-dead son of the Emperor<space/><link><target>Romanos&amp;nbsp;IV</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 86</extension><space/>the Cumans crossed the mountains and raided into eastern Thrace until their leader was eliminated at<space/><link><target>Adrianople</target></link>. With the Balkans more or less pacified, Alexios could now turn his attention to<space/><link><target>Asia Minor</target></link>, which had been almost completely overrun by the<space/><link><target>Seljuq Turks</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 108</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Byzantine-Seljuq Wars and the First Crusade</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Byzantine-Seljuq Wars</arg><arg>First Crusade</arg></template><link><target>File:First.Crusade.Map.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part><template><target>center</target><arg>Europe in 1097, during the [[First Crusade]]</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By the time Alexios ascended the throne, the Seljuqs had taken most of Asia Minor. Alexios was able to secure much of the coastal regions by sending peasant soldiers to raid the Seljuq camps, but these victories were unable to stop the Turks altogether.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 111</extension><space/>As early as 1090, Alexios had taken reconciliatory measures towards the<space/><link><target>Papacy</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 30</extension><space/>with the intention of seeking western support against the Seljuqs. In 1095 his ambassadors appeared before<space/><link><target>Pope Urban&amp;nbsp;II</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Council of Piacenza</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 279">Canduci, pg. 279</extension><space/>The help he sought from the West was simply some<space/><link><target>mercenary</target></link><space/>forces, not the immense hosts that arrived, to his consternation and embarrassment, after the pope preached the<space/><link><target>First Crusade</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Council of Clermont</target></link><space/>later that same year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 31</extension><space/>Not quite ready to supply this number of people as they traversed his territories, the emperor saw his Balkan possessions subjected to further pillage at the hands of his own allies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 33</extension><space/>Alexios dealt with the first disorganized group of Crusaders, led by the preacher<space/><link><target>Peter the Hermit</target></link>, by sending them on to Asia Minor, where they were massacred by the Turks in 1096.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 1479">Kazhdan, pg. 1479</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second and much more formidable host of crusaders gradually made its way to<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>, led in sections by<space/><link><target>Godfrey of Bouillon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bohemond I of Antioch</target><part>Bohemond of Taranto</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Raymond&amp;nbsp;IV of Toulouse</target></link>, and other important members of the western nobility.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 36</extension><space/>Alexios used the opportunity to meet the crusader leaders separately as they arrived, extracting from them oaths of homage and the promise to turn over conquered lands to the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 123</extension><space/>Transferring each contingent into Asia, Alexios promised to supply them with provisions in return for their oaths of homage. The crusade was a notable success for Byzantium, as Alexios recovered a number of important cities and islands. The<space/><link><target>siege of Nicaea</target></link><space/>by the crusaders forced the city to surrender to the emperor in 1097, and the subsequent crusader victory at<space/><link><target>Battle of Dorylaeum (1097)</target><part>Dorylaion</part></link><space/>allowed the Byzantine forces to recover much of western Asia Minor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 42">Norwich, pg. 42</extension><space/><link><target>John Doukas (megas doux)</target><part>John Doukas</part></link><space/>re-established Byzantine rule in<space/><link><target>Chios</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rhodes</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Smyrna</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ephesus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sardis</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Alaehir</target><part>Philadelphia</part></link><space/>in 10971099. This success is ascribed by Alexios' daughter Anna to his policy and diplomacy, but by the Latin historians of the crusade to his treachery and deception. In 1099, a Byzantine fleet of ten ships was sent to assist the crusaders in capturing<space/><link><target>Laodicea in Syria</target><part>Laodicea</part></link><space/>and other coastal towns as far as<space/><link><target>Tripoli, Lebanon</target><part>Tripoli</part></link>. The crusaders believed their oaths were made invalid when the Byzantine contingent under<space/><link><target>Tatikios</target></link><space/>failed to help them during the<space/><link><target>siege of Antioch</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 279"></extension><space/>Bohemund, who had set himself up as<space/><link><target>Principality of Antioch</target><part>Prince of Antioch</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 42"></extension><space/>briefly went to war with Alexios in the Balkans, but he was blockaded by the Byzantine forces and agreed to become a vassal of Alexios by the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Devol</target></link><space/>in 1108.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 48</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1116, though already terminally ill, Alexios conducted a series of defensive operations in Bythinia and Mysia to defend his Anatolian territories against the inroads of<space/><link><target>Malik Shah (Rm)</target><part>Malik Shah</part></link>, the Seljuq Sultan of Iconium. In 1117 he moved onto the offensive and pushed his army deep into the Turkish-dominated Anatolian Plateau, where he defeated the Seljuq sultan at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Philomelion</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alexiad, ed. Sewter, pp. 481-487</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Personal life</heading><paragraph>During the last twenty years of his life Alexios lost much of his popularity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 54</extension><space/>The years were marked by persecution of the followers of the<space/><link><target>Paulicianism</target><part>Paulician</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bogomilism</target><part>Bogomil</part></link><space/>heresies<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 81</extension>one of his last acts was to publicly burn at the stake<space/><link><target>Basil the Physician</target><part>Basil</part></link>, a Bogomil leader, with whom he had engaged in a theological dispute.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 1479"></extension><space/>In spite of the success of the crusade, Alexios also had to repel numerous attempts on his territory by the Seljuqs in 11101117.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 58</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alexios was for many years under the strong influence of an<space/><italics>eminence grise</italics>, his mother<space/><link><target>Anna Dalassene</target></link>, a wise and immensely able politician whom, in a uniquely irregular fashion, he had crowned as<space/><italics><link><target>Augusta (honorific)</target><part>Augusta</part></link></italics><space/>instead of the rightful claimant to the title, his wife Irene Doukaina.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norwich, pg. 59</extension><space/>Dalassena was the effective administrator of the Empire during Alexios' long absences in military campaigns: she was constantly at odds with her daughter-in-law and had assumed total responsibility for the upbringing and education of her granddaughter Anna Komnene.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Succession</heading><paragraph>Alexios' last years were also troubled by anxieties over the succession. Although he had crowned his son<space/><link><target>John&amp;nbsp;II Komnenos</target></link><space/>co-emperor at the age of five in 1092, his wife, Irene Doukaina wished to alter the succession in favor of their daughter Anna and Anna's husband,<space/><link><target>Nikephoros Bryennios the Younger</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 61">Norwich, pg. 61</extension><space/>Bryennios had been made<space/><italics><link><target>Caesar (title)</target><part>kaisar</part></link></italics><space/>(Caesar) and received the newly created title of<space/><italics><link><target>panhypersebastos</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;honoured above all&quot;), and remained loyal to both Alexios and John. Nevertheless, the intrigues of Irene and Anna disturbed even Alexios' dying hours.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Canduci, pg. 279"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Pretenders and rebels</heading><paragraph>Apart from all of his external enemies, a host of rebels also sought to overthrow Alexios from the imperial throne, thereby posing another major threat to his reign.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 1479"></extension><space/>Due to the troubled times the empire was enduring, he had by far the greatest number of rebellions against him of all the Byzantine emperors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 71">Finlay, pg. 71</extension><space/>These included:</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pre First Crusade</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Raictor</target></link>, a Byzantine monk who claimed to be the emperor<space/><link><target>Michael&amp;nbsp;VII</target></link>. He presented himself to<space/><link><target>Robert Guiscard</target></link><space/>who used him as a pretext to launch his invasion of the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 71"></extension></listitem><listitem>A conspiracy in 1084 involving several senators and officers of the army. This was uncovered before too many followers were enlisted. In order to conceal the importance of the conspiracy, Alexios merely banished the wealthiest plotters and confiscated their estates.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 71"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tzachas</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Seljuq Turks</target><part>Seljuq Turkic</part></link><space/><link><target>emir</target></link><space/>who assumed the title of emperor in 1092.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72">Finlay, pg. 72</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Constantine Humbertopoulos</target></link>, who had assisted Alexios in gaining the throne in 1081 conspired against him in 1091 with an<space/><link><target>Armenians</target><part>Armenian</part></link><space/>called Ariebes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>John Komnenos (governor of Dyrrhachium)</target><part>John Komnenos</part></link>, Alexios' nephew, governor of<space/><link><target>Dyrrachium</target></link>, accused of a conspiracy by<space/><link><target>Theophylact of Bulgaria</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Theodore Gabras</target></link>, the quasi-independent governor of<space/><link><target>Trabzon</target><part>Trebizond</part></link><space/>and his son<space/><link><target>Gregory Gabras</target><part>Gregory</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Michael Taronites</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>brother-in-law</target></link><space/>of Alexios.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nikephoros Diogenes</target></link>, the son of emperor<space/><link><target>Romanos&amp;nbsp;IV</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pseudo-Diogenes</target></link>, an impostor who assumed the identity of another of Romanos' sons, Leo Diogenes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 73">Finlay, pg. 73</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Karykes</target></link>, the leader of a revolt in<space/><link><target>Crete</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rhapsomates</target></link>, who tried to create an independent kingdom in<space/><link><target>Cyprus</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 72"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Post First Crusade</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Salomon (senator)</target><part>Salomon</part></link>, a<space/><link><target>Byzantine Senate</target><part>senator</part></link><space/>of great wealth who in 1106 engaged in a plot with four brothers of the Anemas family.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 74">Finlay, pg. 74</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gregory Taronites (governor of Chaldia)</target><part>Gregory Taronites</part></link>, another governor of Trebizond.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 74"></extension></listitem><listitem>The illegitimate descendant of a<space/><link><target>Bulgarians</target><part>Bulgarian</part></link><space/>prince named Aron formed a plot in 1107 to murder Alexios as he was encamped near<space/><link><target>Thessalonica</target></link>. The presence of the empress Irene and her attendants, however, made the execution of the plot difficult. In an attempt to have her return to<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>, the conspirators produced pamphlets that mocked and slandered the empress, and left them in her tent. A search for the author of the publications uncovered the whole plot, yet Aron was only banished due to his connection of the royal line of Bulgaria, whose blood also flowed in the veins of the empress Irene.<extension extension_name='ref'>Finlay, pg. 75</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Resurrection seal of Alexios I Komnenos.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Rare seal of Alexios I with a depiction of the<space/><link><target>Resurrection</target></link></part></link>Alexios&amp;nbsp;I had overcome a dangerous crisis and stabilized the Byzantine Empire, inaugurating a century of imperial prosperity and success.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norwich, pg. 61"></extension><space/>He had also profoundly altered the nature of the Byzantine government.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 69">Finlay, pg. 69</extension><space/>By seeking close alliances with powerful noble families, Alexios put an end to the tradition of imperial exclusivity and coopted most of the nobility into his extended family and, through it, his government. Those who did not become part of this extended family were deprived of power and prestige.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kazhdan, pg. 1479"></extension><space/>This measure, which was intended to diminish opposition, was paralleled by the introduction of new courtly dignities, like that of<space/><italics><link><target>panhypersebastos</target></link></italics><space/>given to Nikephoros Bryennios, or that of<space/><italics><link><target>sebastokrator</target></link></italics><space/>given to the emperor's brother Isaac Komnenos.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finlay, pg. 69"></extension><space/>Although this policy met with initial success, it gradually undermined the relative effectiveness of imperial bureaucracy by placing family connections over merit. Alexios' policy of integration of the nobility bore the fruit of continuity: every Byzantine emperor who reigned after Alexios&amp;nbsp;I Komnenos was related to him by either descent or marriage.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Family</heading><paragraph>By his marriage with<space/><link><target>Irene Doukaina</target></link>, Alexios&amp;nbsp;I had the following children:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>Anna Komnene</target></link>, who married the<space/><italics>Caesar</italics><space/><link><target>Nikephoros Bryennios the Younger</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Maria Komnene, who married (1) Gregory Gabras and (2)<space/><link><target>Nikephoros Katakalon</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>John&amp;nbsp;II Komnenos</target></link>, who succeeded as emperor.</listitem><listitem>Andronikos Komnenos,<space/><italics><link><target>sebastokrator</target></link></italics>. Died in battle 1117 (<link><target>Battle of Philomelion</target></link>).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Isaac Komnenos (son of Alexios I)</target><part>Isaac Komnenos</part></link>,<space/><italics>sebastokrator</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Eudokia Komnene, who married Michael Iasites.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Theodora Komnene Angelina</target><part>Theodora Komnene</part></link>, who married (1) Constantine Kourtikes and (2) Constantine Angelos. By him she was the grandmother of Emperors<space/><link><target>Isaac&amp;nbsp;II Angelos</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexios&amp;nbsp;III Angelos</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Manuel Komnenos</listitem><listitem>Zoe Komnene.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><heading level='3'>Primary Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Anna Comnena,<space/><italics><link><target>The Alexiad</target></link></italics>, translated E. R. A. Sewter, Penguin Classics, 1969</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Secondary Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Michael Angold (1997),<space/><italics>The Byzantine Empire, 10251204</italics>, Longman, 2nd ed., pp.&amp;nbsp;13670. ISBN 978-0-582-29468-4</listitem><listitem>Jonathan Harris (2014),<space/><italics>Byzantium and the Crusades</italics>, Bloomsbury, 2nd ed. ISBN 978-1-78093-767-0</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Kazhdan<space/></arg><arg name="editor-link">Alexander Kazhdan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Oxford Dictionary of Byzantium]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-504652-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Warren Treadgold (1997),<space/><italics>A History of the Byzantine State and Society</italics>, Stanford University Press, pp.&amp;nbsp;61229. ISBN 978-0-8047-2630-6</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Norwich</arg><arg name="first">John J.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Byzantium: The Decline and Fall<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-679-41650-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Canduci<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="title">Triumph & Tragedy: The Rise and Fall of Rome's Immortal Emperors<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pier 9<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-74196-598-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Garland<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lynda<space/></arg><arg name="title">Anna Dalassena – De Imperatoribus Romanis<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.roman-emperors.org/annadal.htm<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="first">Basile<space/></arg><arg name="last">Skoulatos<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Les personnages byzantins de I'Alexiade: Analyse prosopographique et synthese<space/></arg><arg name="language">French<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Louvain<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Nauwelaerts<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last"><space/>Plate<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>William<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alexios I Komnenos<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[William Smith (lexicographer)|William Smith]]<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia"><space/>[[Dictionary of Greek and Roman Biography and Mythology]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>129–130<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Little, Brown and Company<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1867<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/pageviewer-idx?c</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Varzos<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Konstantinos<space/></arg><arg name="script-title">el:Η Γενεαλογία των Κομνηνών<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>The Genealogy of the Komnenoi<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Thessaloniki<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Byzantine Research Centre<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Greek</arg></template>, Vols.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.kbe.auth.gr/bkm20a1.pdf'>A1</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.kbe.auth.gr/bkm20a2.pdf'>A2</link><space/>&amp;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.kbe.auth.gr/bkm20b.pdf'>B</link></listitem><listitem>George Finlay (1854),<space/><italics>History of the Byzantine and Greek Empires from 10571453</italics>, Volume 2, William Blackwood &amp; Sons</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last">Francopan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The First Crusade: the Call from the East<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[The Bodley Head]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Komnenian Byzantine army</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">20em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wildwinds.com/coins/byz/alexius_I/t.html'>Alexius coinage</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Komnenos]] dynasty</arg><arg></arg><arg>1056</arg><arg>15 August</arg><arg>1118</arg></template><template><target>s-reg</target><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Nikephoros III]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Byzantine Emperors|Byzantine Emperor]]</arg><arg name="years">1081–1118
</arg><arg name="regent1">[[Constantine Doukas (co-emperor)|Constantine Doukas]]</arg><arg name="years1">1081-1088</arg><arg name="regent2">[[John II Komnenos]]</arg><arg name="years2">1092-1118</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[John II Komnenos]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Roman Emperors</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Alexios 01 Komnenos</target></template><link><target>Category:Alexios I Komnenos</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Komnenos dynasty</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:11th-century Byzantine emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:12th-century Byzantine emperors</target></link><link><target>Category:Byzantine people of the ByzantineSeljuq Wars</target></link><link><target>Category:Christians of the First Crusade</target></link><link><target>Category:Christians of the Crusade of 1101</target></link><link><target>Category:Christians of the Norwegian Crusade</target></link><link><target>Category:1048 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1118 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Pechenegs</target></link><link><target>Category:Orthodox monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Anti-Gnosticism</target></link><link><target>Category:Domestics of the Schools</target></link><link><target>Category:1080s in the Byzantine Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:1090s in the Byzantine Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:1100s in the Byzantine Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:1110s in the Byzantine Empire</target></link></paragraph></article>