<article title='Archaeoastronomy'><paragraph><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>Stellar archaeology</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Newgrange ireland 750px.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>The rising<space/><link><target>Sun</target></link><space/>illuminates the inner chamber of<space/><link><target>Newgrange</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link>, only at the<space/><link><target>winter solstice</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Archaeoastronomy</bold><space/>(also spelled<space/><bold>archeoastronomy</bold>) is the study of how people in the past &quot;have understood the<space/><link><target>phenomenon</target><part>phenomena</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>sky</target></link>, how they used these phenomena and what role the sky played in their<space/><link><target>culture</target><trail>s</trail></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Sinclair 2006:13</extension><space/><link><target>Clive Ruggles</target></link><space/>argues it is misleading to consider archaeoastronomy to be the study of ancient<space/><link><target>astronomy</target></link>, as modern astronomy is a scientific discipline, while archaeoastronomy considers symbolically rich cultural interpretations of phenomena in the sky by other cultures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:19</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1999:155</extension><space/>It is often twinned with<space/><italics>ethnoastronomy</italics>, the<space/><link><target>anthropology</target><part>anthropological</part></link><space/>study of skywatching in contemporary societies. Archaeoastronomy is also closely associated with<space/><link><target>historical astronomy</target></link>, the use of historical records of heavenly events to answer astronomical problems and the<space/><link><target>history of astronomy</target></link>, which uses written records to evaluate past astronomical practice.</paragraph><paragraph>Archaeoastronomy uses a variety of methods to uncover evidence of past practices including archaeology, anthropology, astronomy, statistics and probability, and history. Because these methods are diverse and use data from such different sources, integrating them into a coherent argument has been a long-term difficulty for archaeoastronomers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Iwaniszewski 2003, 7-10</extension><space/>Archaeoastronomy fills complementary niches in<space/><link><target>landscape archaeology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cognitive archaeology</target></link>. Material evidence and its connection to the sky can reveal how a wider landscape can be integrated into<space/><link><target>Paganism</target><part>beliefs about the cycles of nature</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>Maya civilization#Astronomy</target><part>Mayan astronomy</part></link><space/>and its relationship with agriculture.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1980</extension><space/>Other examples which have brought together ideas of cognition and landscape include studies of the cosmic order embedded in the roads of settlements.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chiu &amp; Morrison 1980</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Magli 2008</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Archaeoastronomy can be applied to all cultures and all time periods. The meanings of the sky vary from culture to culture; nevertheless there are scientific methods which can be applied across cultures when examining ancient beliefs.<extension extension_name='ref'>McCluskey 2005</extension><space/>It is perhaps the need to balance the social and scientific aspects of archaeoastronomy which led Clive Ruggles to describe it as:<space/><italics>&quot;...[A] field with academic work of high quality at one end but uncontrolled speculation bordering on lunacy at the other.&quot;</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Carlson 1999</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History of archaeoastronomy</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>In his short history of 'Astro-archaeology' John Michell argued that the status of research into ancient astronomy had improved over the past two centuries, going 'from lunacy to heresy to interesting notion and finally to the gates of orthodoxy.' Nearly two decades later, we can still ask the question: Is archaeoastronomy still waiting at the gates of orthodoxy or has it gotten inside the gates?</arg><arg>Todd Bostwick quoting John Michell<ref>Bostwick 2006:13</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Two hundred years before Michell wrote the above, there were no archaeoastronomers and there were no<space/><link><target>Archaeology#History of archaeology</target><part>professional archaeologists</part></link>, but there were astronomers and<space/><link><target>Antiquarianism</target><part>antiquarians</part></link>. Some of their works are considered<space/><link><target>precursorial</target><part>precursors</part></link><space/>of archaeoastronomy; antiquarians interpreted the astronomical orientation of the ruins that dotted the English countryside as<space/><link><target>William Stukeley</target></link><space/>did of<space/><link><target>Stonehenge</target></link><space/>in 1740,<extension extension_name='ref'>Michell, 2001:9-10</extension><space/>while<space/><link><target>John Aubrey</target></link><space/>in 1678<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 1912:225</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Henry Chauncy</target></link><space/>in 1700 sought similar astronomical principles underlying the orientation of churches.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin, 2001:7</extension><space/>Late in the nineteenth century astronomers such as<space/><link><target>Richard Proctor</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Charles Piazzi Smyth</target></link><space/>investigated the astronomical orientations of<space/><link><target>Egyptian pyramids</target><part>the pyramids</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michell, 2001:17-18</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The term<space/><italics>archaeoastronomy</italics><space/>was first used by Elizabeth Chesley Baity (at the suggestion of Euan MacKie) in 1973,<extension extension_name='ref'>Sinclair 2006:17</extension><space/>but as a topic of study it may be much older, depending on how archaeoastronomy is defined. Clive Ruggles<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:312-3</extension><space/>says that<space/><link><target>Heinrich Nissen</target></link>, working in the mid-nineteenth century was arguably the first archaeoastronomer. Rolf Sinclair<extension extension_name='ref'>Sinclair 2006:8</extension><space/>says that<space/><link><target>Norman Lockyer</target></link>, working in the late 19th and early 20th centuries, could be called the 'father of archaeoastronomy.' Euan MacKie<extension extension_name='ref'>Mackie 2006:243</extension><space/>would place the origin even later, stating: &quot;...the genesis and modern flowering of archaeoastronomy must surely lie in the work of<space/><link><target>Alexander Thom</target></link><space/>in Britain between the 1930s and the 1970s.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Auglish.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Early archaeoastronomy surveyed Megalithic constructs in the British Isles, at sites like<space/><link><target>Auglish</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>County Londonderry</target></link>, in an attempt to find statistical patterns</part></link>In the 1960s the work of the engineer Alexander Thom and that of the astronomer<space/><link><target>Gerald Hawkins</target></link>, who proposed that<space/><link><target>Stonehenge</target></link><space/>was a<space/><link><target>Neolithic</target></link><space/>computer,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hawkins 1976</extension><space/>inspired new interest in the astronomical features of ancient sites. The claims of Hawkins were largely dismissed,<extension extension_name='ref'>Atkinson 1966</extension><space/>but this was not the case for Alexander Thom's work, whose survey results of<space/><link><target>megalith</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>sites hypothesized widespread practice of accurate astronomy in the British Isles.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thom 1988:9-10</extension><space/>Euan MacKie, recognizing that Thom's theories needed to be tested, excavated at the Kintraw standing stone site in Argyllshire in 1970 and 1971 to check whether the latter's prediction of an observation platform on the hill slope above the stone was correct. There was an artificial platform there and this apparent verification of Thom's long alignment hypothesis (Kintraw was diagnosed as an accurate<space/><link><target>winter solstice</target></link><space/>site) led him to check Thom's geometrical theories at the Cultoon<space/><link><target>stone circle</target></link><space/>in Islay, also with a positive result. MacKie therefore broadly accepted Thom's conclusions and published new prehistories of Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zkuawc">MacKie 1977</extension><space/>In contrast a re-evaluation of Thom's fieldwork by Clive Ruggles argued that Thom's claims of high accuracy astronomy were not fully supported by the evidence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gingerich 2000</extension><space/>Nevertheless Thom's legacy remains strong, Krupp<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp 1979:18</extension><space/>wrote in 1979, &quot;Almost singlehandedly he has established the standards for archaeo-astronomical fieldwork and interpretation, and his amazing results have stirred controversy during the last three decades.&quot; His influence endures and practice of statistical testing of data remains one of the methods of archaeoastronomy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hicks 1993</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Iwaniszewski 1995</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Uxmal01-panorama.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>leftt</part><part>250px</part><part>It has been proposed that<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target><part>Maya</part></link><space/>sites such as<space/><link><target>Uxmal</target></link><space/>were built in accordance with astronomical alignments.</part><trail>The</trail></link><space/>approach in the<space/><link><target>New World</target></link>, where anthropologists began to consider more fully the role of astronomy in<space/><link><target>Amerindian</target></link><space/>civilizations, was markedly different. They had access to sources that the<space/><link><target>prehistory</target></link><space/>of Europe lacks such as<space/><link><target>ethnography</target><part>ethnographies</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Zeilik 1985</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Zeilik 1986</extension><space/>and the historical records of the early<space/><link><target>Colonization of the Americas</target><part>colonizers</part></link>. Following the pioneering example of Anthony Aveni,<extension extension_name='ref'>Milbraith 1999:8</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Broda 2000:233</extension><space/>this allowed New World archaeoastronomers to make claims for motives which in the Old World would have been mere speculation. The concentration on historical data led to some claims of high accuracy that were comparatively weak when compared to the statistically led investigations in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin 1996</extension></paragraph><paragraph>This came to a head at a meeting sponsored by the<space/><link><target>International Astronomical Union</target></link><space/>(IAU) in<space/><link><target>Oxford</target></link><space/>in 1981.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1993:ix</extension><space/>The methodologies and research questions of the participants were considered so different that the conference proceedings were published as two volumes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1982</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Heggie 1982</extension><space/>Nevertheless the conference was considered a success in bringing researchers together and Oxford conferences have continued every four or five years at locations around the world. The subsequent conferences have resulted in a move to more interdisciplinary approaches with researchers aiming to combine the contextuality of archaeological research,<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni, 1989a:xixiii</extension><space/>which broadly describes the state of archaeoastronomy today, rather than merely establishing the existence of ancient astronomies, archaeoastronomers seek to explain why people would have an interest in the night sky.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Relations to other disciplines</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>...[O]ne of the most endearing characteristics of archaeoastronomy is its capacity to set academics in different disciplines at loggerheads with each other.</arg><arg>Clive Ruggles<ref>Ruggles 2000</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Archaeoastronomy has long been seen as an interdisciplinary field that uses written and unwritten evidence to study the astronomies of other cultures. As such, it can be seen as connecting other disciplinary approaches for investigating ancient astronomy: astroarchaeology (an obsolete term for studies that draw astronomical information from the alignments of ancient architecture and landscapes),<space/><link><target>history of astronomy</target></link><space/>(which deals primarily with the written textual evidence), and ethnoastronomy (which draws on the ethnohistorical record and contemporary ethnographic studies).<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1981: 1-2</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 2003: 150</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Reflecting Archaeoastronomy's development as an interdisciplinary subject, research in the field is conducted by investigators trained in a wide range of disciplines. Authors of recent doctoral dissertations have described their work as concerned with the fields of archaeology and cultural anthropology; with various fields of history including the history of specific regions and periods, the history of science and the history of religion; and with the relation of astronomy to art, literature and religion. Only rarely did they describe their work as astronomical, and then only as a secondary category.<extension extension_name='ref'>McCluskey 2004</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Both practicing archaeoastronomers and observers of the discipline approach it from different perspectives. George Gummerman and Miranda Warburton view archaeoastronomy as part of an archaeology informed by<space/><link><target>cultural anthropology</target></link><space/>and aimed at understanding a &quot;group's conception of themselves in relation to the heavens', in a word, its cosmology.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gummerman &amp; Warburton 2005</extension><space/>Todd Bostwick argued that &quot;archaeoastronomy is anthropology the study of human behavior in the past and present.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Bostwick 2006:3</extension><space/><link><target>Paul Bahn</target></link><space/>has described archaeoastronomy as an area of cognitive archaeology.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bahn 1996:49</extension><space/>Other researchers relate archaeoastronomy to the history of science, either as it relates to a culture's observations of nature and the conceptual framework they devised to impose an order on those observations<extension extension_name='ref'>McCluskey 2001</extension><space/>or as it relates to the political motives which drove particular historical actors to deploy certain astronomical concepts or techniques.<extension extension_name='ref'>Broda 2006</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Aldana 2007:14-15</extension><space/>Art historian Richard Poss took a more flexible approach, maintaining that the astronomical rock art of the North American Southwest should be read employing &quot;the hermeneutic traditions of western art history and art criticism&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Poss 2005:97</extension><space/>Astronomers, however, raise different questions, seeking to provide their students with identifiable<space/><link><target>Precursorism</target><part>precursors</part></link><space/>of their discipline, and are especially concerned with the important question of how to confirm that specific sites are, indeed, intentionally astronomical.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schaefer 2006a:30</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The reactions of professional archaeologists to archaeoastronomy have been decidedly mixed. Some expressed incomprehension or even hostility, varying from a rejection by the archaeological mainstream of what they saw as an archaeoastronomical fringe to an incomprehension between the cultural focus of archaeologists and the quantitative focus of early archaeoastronomers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1999: 3-9</extension><space/>Yet archaeologists have increasingly come to incorporate many of the insights from archaeoastronomy into archaeology textbooks<extension extension_name='ref'>Fisher 2006</extension><space/>and, as mentioned above, some students wrote archaeology dissertations on archaeoastronomical topics.</paragraph><paragraph>Since archaeoastronomers disagree so widely on the characterization of the discipline, they even dispute its name. All three major international scholarly associations relate archaeoastronomy to the study of culture, using the term<space/><italics>Astronomy in Culture</italics><space/>or a translation. Michael Hoskin sees an important part of the discipline as fact-collecting, rather than theorizing, and proposed to label this aspect of the discipline<space/><italics>Archaeotopography.</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin 2001:13-14.</extension><space/>Ruggles and Saunders proposed<space/><italics>Cultural Astronomy</italics><space/>as a unifying term for the various methods of studying folk astronomies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles &amp; Saunders 1993:1-31</extension><space/>Others have argued that astronomy is an inaccurate term, what are being studied are<space/><link><target>cosmology</target><part>cosmologies</part></link><space/>and people who object to the use of<space/><link><target>logos</target></link><space/>have suggested adopting the Spanish<space/><italics>cosmovisin</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:115-117</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When debates polarise between techniques, the methods are often referred to by a colour code, based on the colours of the bindings of the two volumes from the first Oxford Conference, where the approaches were first distinguished.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jgswke">Aveni 1986</extension><space/>Green (<link><target>Old World</target></link>) archaeoastronomers rely heavily on statistics and are sometimes accused of missing the cultural context of what is a social practice. Brown (<link><target>New World</target></link>) archaeoastronomers in contrast have abundant ethnographic and historical evidence and have been described as 'cavalier' on matters of measurement and statistical analysis.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin 2001:2</extension><space/>Finding a way to integrate various approaches has been a subject of much discussion since the early 1990s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles &amp; Saunders. 1993</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Iwaniszewski 2001</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Methodology</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>For a long time I have believed that such diversity requires the invention of some all-embracing theory. I think I was very naïve in thinking that such a thing was ever possible.</arg><arg>Stanislaw Iwaniszewski<ref>Iwaniszewski 2003:7</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There is no one way to do Archaeoastronomy. The divisions between archaeoastronomers tend not to be between the physical scientists and the social scientists. Instead it tends to depend on the location of kind of data available to the researcher. In the Old World, there is little data but the sites themselves; in the New World, the sites were supplemented by ethnographic and historic data. The effects of the isolated development of archaeoastronomy in different places can still often be seen in research today. Research methods can be classified as falling into one of two approaches, though more recent projects often use techniques from both categories.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Green archaeoastronomy</heading><paragraph>Green Archaeoastronomy is named after the cover of the book<space/><italics>Archaeoastronomy in the Old World</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1989:1</extension><space/>It is based primarily on statistics and is particularly apt for prehistoric sites where the social evidence is relatively scant compared to the historic period. The basic methods were developed by Alexander Thom during his extensive surveys of British megalithic sites.</paragraph><paragraph>Thom wished to examine whether or not prehistoric peoples used high-accuracy astronomy. He believed that by using horizon astronomy, observers could make estimates of dates in the year to a specific day. The observation required finding a place where on a specific date the sun set into a notch on the horizon. A common theme is a mountain which blocked the Sun, but on the right day would allow the tiniest fraction to re-emerge on the other side for a 'double sunset'. The animation below shows two sunsets at a<space/><link><target>hypothetical</target></link><space/>site, one the day before the<space/><link><target>summer solstice</target></link><space/>and one at the summer solstice, which has a double sunset. Horizon astronomy is arguably inaccurate, due to variations in refraction.</paragraph><paragraph><xhtml:center><link><target>File:Doublesunset.ogg</target></link></xhtml:center></paragraph><paragraph>To test this idea he surveyed hundreds of stone rows and circles. Any individual alignment could indicate a direction by chance, but he planned to show that together the distribution of alignments was non-random, showing that there was an astronomical intent to the orientation of at least some of the alignments. His results indicated the existence of eight, sixteen, or perhaps even thirty-two approximately equal divisions of the year. The two<space/><link><target>solstice</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the two<space/><link><target>equinox</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>and four<space/><link><target>cross-quarter day</target><trail>s</trail></link>, days half-way between a solstice and the equinox were associated with the medieval Celtic calendar.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thom 1967: 107-117</extension><space/>While not all these conclusions have been accepted, it has had an enduring influence on archaeoastronomy, especially in Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>Euan MacKie has supported Thom's analysis, to which he added an archaeological context by comparing Neolithic Britain to the Mayan civilization to argue for a stratified society in this period.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zkuawc"></extension><space/>To test his ideas he conducted a couple of excavations at proposed prehistoric observatories in Scotland. Kintraw is a site notable for its four-meter high standing stone. Thom proposed that this was a foresight to a point on the distant horizon between Beinn Shianaidh and Beinn o'Chaolias on Jura.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1999:25-29</extension><space/>This, Thom argued, was a notch on the horizon where a double sunset would occur at midwinter. However, from ground level, this sunset would be obscured by a ridge in the landscape, and the viewer would need to be raised by two meters: another observation platform was needed. This was identified across a gorge where a platform was formed from small stones. The lack of artifacts caused concern for some archaeologists and the petrofabric analysis was inconclusive, but further research at<space/><link><target>Maes Howe</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="MacKie 1997">MacKie 1997</extension><space/>and on the<space/><link><target>Bush Barrow</target></link><space/>Lozenge<extension extension_name='ref'>MacKie 2006:362</extension><space/>led MacKie to conclude that while the term 'science' may be anachronistic, Thom was broadly correct upon the subject of high-accuracy alignments.<extension extension_name='ref'>MacKie 2009</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast Clive Ruggles has argued that there are problems with the selection of data in Thom's surveys.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1999:19-29</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles and Barclay 2000: 69-70</extension><space/>A deeper criticism of Green archaeoastronomy is that while it can answer<space/><italics>whether</italics><space/>there was likely to be an interest in astronomy in past times, its lack of a social element means that it struggles to answer<space/><italics>why</italics><space/>people would be interested, which makes it of limited use to people asking questions about the society of the past. Keith Kintigh wrote: &quot;To put it bluntly, in many cases it doesn't matter much to the progress of anthropology whether a particular archaeoastronomical claim is right or wrong because the information doesnt inform the current interpretive questions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kintigh 1992</extension><space/>Nonetheless the study of alignments remains a staple of archaeoastronomical research, especially in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin 2001</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Brown archaeoastronomy</heading><paragraph>In contrast to the largely alignment-oriented statistically led methods of Green archaeoastronomy, Brown archaeoastronomy has been identified as being closer to the<space/><link><target>history of astronomy</target></link><space/>or to<space/><link><target>cultural history</target></link>, insofar as it draws on historical and ethnographic records to enrich its understanding of early astronomies and their relations to calendars and ritual.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jgswke"></extension><space/>The many records of native customs and beliefs made by the Spanish chroniclers means that Brown archaeoastronomy is most often associated with studies of astronomy in the Americas.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1989</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One famous site where historical records have been used to interpret sites is<space/><link><target>Chichen Itza</target></link>. Rather than analysing the site and seeing which targets appear popular, archaeoastronomers have instead examined the ethnographic records to see what features of the sky were important to the<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target><part>Maya</part><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>and then sought archaeological correlates. One example which could have been overlooked without historical records is the Mayan interest in the planet<space/><link><target>Venus</target></link>. This interest is attested to by the<space/><link><target>Dresden codex</target></link><space/>which contains tables with information about the Venus's appearances in the sky.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mlxqkn">Kelley and Milone 2005:369-370</extension><space/>These cycles would have been of astrological and ritual significance as Venus was associated with<space/><link><target>Quetzalcoatl</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Xolotl</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelley and Milone 2005:367-8</extension><space/>Associations of architectural features with settings of Venus can be found in Chichen Itza.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Chichen Itza Observatory 2 1.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>&quot;El Caracol&quot; a possible observatory temple at Chichen Itza.</part><trail>The</trail></link><space/>Temple of the Warriors bears iconography depicting feathered serpents associated with Quetzalcoatl or Kukulcan. This means that the building's alignment towards the place on the horizon where Venus first appears in the evening sky (when it coincides with the rainy season) may be meaningful.<extension extension_name='ref'>Milbraith 1988:70-71</extension><space/>Aveni claims that another building associated with the planet Venus in the form of Kukulcan, and the rainy season at Chichen Itza is the<space/><link><target>Caracol</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 2006:60-64</extension><space/>This is a building with circular tower and doors facing the cardinal directions. The base faces the most northerly setting of Venus. Additionally the pillars of a stylobate on the building's upper platform were painted black and red. These are colours associated with Venus as an evening and morning star.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1979:175-183</extension><space/>However the windows in the tower seem to have been little more than slots, making them poor at letting light in, but providing a suitable place to view out.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1997:137-138</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Aveni states that one of the strengths of the Brown methodology is that it can explore astronomies invisible to statistical analysis and offers the astronomy of the<space/><link><target>Inca</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as another example. The empire of the Incas was conceptually divided using<space/><italics>ceques</italics><space/>radial routes emanating from the capital at<space/><link><target>Cusco</target></link>. Thus there are alignments in all directions which would suggest there is little of astronomical significance, However, ethnohistorical records show that the various directions do have cosmological and astronomical significance with various points in the landscape being significant at different times of the year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1989:5</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Bauer and Dearborn 1995</extension><space/>In eastern Asia archaeoastronomy has developed from the History of Astronomy and much archaeoastronomy is searching for material correlates of the historical record. This is due to the rich historical record of astronomical phenomena which, in China, stretches back into the<space/><link><target>Han dynasty</target></link>, in the second century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Xu<space/><italics>et al.</italics><space/>2000:1-7</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A criticism of this method is that it can be statistically weak. Schaefer in particular has questioned how robust the claimed alignments in the Caracol are.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schaefer 2006a:42-48</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Schaefer 2006b</extension><space/>Because of the wide variety of evidence, which can include artefacts as well as sites, there is no one way to practice archaeoastronomy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Iwaniszewski 2003</extension><space/>Despite this it is accepted that archaeoastronomy is not a discipline that sits in isolation. Because archaeoastronomy is an interdisciplinary field, whatever is being investigated should make sense both archaeologically and astronomically. Studies are more likely to be considered sound if they use theoretical tools found in archaeology like<space/><link><target>analogy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>homology (anthropology)</target><part>homology</part></link><space/>and if they can demonstrate an understanding of accuracy and precision found in astronomy.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Source materials</heading><paragraph>Because archaeoastronomy is about the many and various ways people interacted with the sky, there are a diverse range of sources giving information about astronomical practices.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Alignments</heading><paragraph>A common source of data for archaeoastronomy is the study of alignments. This is based on the assumption that the axis of alignment of an archaeological site is meaningfully oriented towards an astronomical target. Brown archaeoastronomers may justify this assumption through reading historical or ethnographic sources, while Green archaeoastronomers tend to prove that alignments are unlikely to be selected by chance, usually by demonstrating common patterns of alignment at multiple sites.</paragraph><paragraph>An alignment is calculated by measuring the<space/><link><target>azimuth</target></link>, the angle from north, of the structure and the altitude of the horizon it faces<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles, 2005:112-113</extension><space/>The azimuth is usually measured using a<space/><link><target>theodolite</target></link><space/>or a<space/><link><target>compass</target></link>. A compass is easier to use, though the deviation of the Earth's magnetic field from true north, known as its<space/><link><target>magnetic declination</target></link><space/>must be taken into account. Compasses are also unreliable in areas prone to magnetic interference, such as sites being supported by scaffolding. Additionally a compass can only measure the azimuth to a precision of a half a degree.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.brunton.com/manuals/current/Compasses/Transit.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="title">''Brunton Pocket Transit Instruction Manual'', p. 22</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-02<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20060304060347/http://www.brunton.com/manuals/current/Compasses/Transit.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2006-03-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A theodolite can be considerably more accurate if used correctly, but it is also considerably more difficult to use correctly. There is no inherent way to align a theodolite with North and so the scale has to be<space/><link><target>calibration</target><part>calibrated</part></link><space/>using astronomical observation, usually the position of the Sun.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:423-425</extension><space/>Because the position of celestial bodies changes with the time of day due to the Earth's rotation, the time of these calibration observations must be accurately known, or else there will be a systematic error in the measurements. Horizon altitudes can be measured with a theodolite or a<space/><link><target>clinometer</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Artifacts</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:NAMA Machine d'Anticythre 1.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>The Antikythera mechanism (main fragment)</part><trail>For</trail></link><space/>artifacts such as the<space/><link><target>Nebra skydisk</target><part>Sky Disc of Nebra</part></link>, alleged to be a Bronze Age artefact depicting the cosmos,<extension extension_name='ref'>Scholsser 2002</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Meller 2004</extension><space/>the analysis would be similar to typical<space/><link><target>Archaeology#Post-excavation analysis</target><part>post-excavation analysis</part></link><space/>as used in other sub-disciplines in archaeology. An artefact is examined and attempts are made to draw analogies with historical or ethnographical records of other peoples. The more parallels that can be found, the more likely an explanation is to be accepted by other archaeologists.</paragraph><paragraph>A more mundane example is the presence of<space/><link><target>astrological symbol</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>found on some shoes and sandals from the Roman Empire. The use of shoes and sandals is well known, but Carol van Driel-Murray has proposed that astrological symbols etched onto sandals gave the footwear spiritual or medicinal meanings.<extension extension_name='ref'>van Driel-Murray 2002</extension><space/>This is supported through citation of other known uses of astrological symbols and their connection to medical practice and with the historical records of the time.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another well-known artefact with an astronomical use is the<space/><link><target>Antikythera mechanism</target></link>. In this case analysis of the artefact, and reference to the description of similar devices described by Cicero, would indicate a plausible use for the device. The argument is bolstered by the presence of symbols on the mechanism, allowing the disc to be read.<extension extension_name='ref'>T. Freeth<space/><italics>et al.</italics><space/>2006</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Art and inscriptions</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Fajadadiagram.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>Diagram showing the location of the sun daggers on the<space/><link><target>Fajada Butte</target></link><space/>petroglyph on various days</part><trail>Art</trail></link><space/>and inscriptions may not be confined to artefacts, but also appear painted or inscribed on an archaeological site. Sometimes inscriptions are helpful enough to give instructions to a site's use. For example a Greek inscription on a stele (from<space/><link><target>Itanos (city)</target><part>Itanos</part></link>) has been translated as:&quot;Patron set this up for Zeus Epopsios. Winter solstice. Should anyone wish to know: off the little pig and the stele the sun turns.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Inscriptiones Creticae III iv 11; Isager and Skydsgaard 1992:163</extension><space/>From Mesoamerica come<space/><link><target>Maya codices</target><part>Mayan</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aztec codices</target></link>. These are folding books made from<space/><link><target>Amatl</target></link>, processed tree bark on which are<space/><link><target>glyphs</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Maya script</target><part>Mayan</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Aztec script</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Dresden codex</target></link><space/>contains information regarding the Venus cycle, confirming its importance to the Mayans.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mlxqkn"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>More problematic are those cases where the movement of the Sun at different times and seasons causes light and shadow interactions with<space/><link><target>petroglyph</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Williamson 1987:109-114</extension><space/>A widely known example is the Sun Dagger of<space/><link><target>Fajada Butte</target></link><space/>at which a glint of sunlight passes over a spiral petroglyph.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sofaer 2008</extension><space/>The location of a dagger of light on the petroglyph varies throughout the year. At the summer solstice a dagger can be seen through the heart of the spiral; at the winter solstice two daggers appear to either side of it. It is proposed that this petroglyph was created to mark these events. Recent studies have identified many similar sites in the US Southwest and Northwestern Mexico.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fountain 2005</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Robins &amp; Ewing 1989</extension><space/>It has been argued that the number of solstitial markers at these sites provides statistical evidence that they were intended to mark the solstices.<extension extension_name='ref'>Preston &amp; Preston 2005: 115-118</extension><space/>The Sun Dagger site on Fajada Butte in Chaco Canyon, New Mexico, stands out for its explicit light markings that record all the key events of both the solar and lunar cycles: summer solstice, winter solstice, equinox, and the major and minor<space/><link><target>lunar standstill</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the moons 18.6 year cycle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Science Mag, Sofaer et al. 1979: 126</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Cambridge">Cambridge U, 1982 sofaer et al.: 126</extension><space/>In addition at two other sites on Fajada Butte, there are five light markings on petroglyphs recording the summer and winter solstices, equinox and solar noon.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sofaer and Sinclair: 1987. UNM, ABQ</extension><space/>Numerous buildings and interbuilding alignments of the great houses of Chaco Canyon and outlying areas are oriented to the same solar and lunar directions that are marked at the Sun Dagger site.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sofaer 1998: Lekson Ed, u of utah: 165</extension></paragraph><paragraph>If no ethnographic nor historical data are found which can support this assertion then acceptance of the idea relies upon whether or not there are enough petroglyph sites in North America that such a correlation could occur by chance. It is helpful when petroglyphs are associated with existing peoples. This allows ethnoastronomers to question informants as to the meaning of such symbols.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ethnographies</heading><paragraph>As well as the materials left by peoples themselves, there are also the reports of other who have encountered them. The historical records of the<space/><link><target>Conquistadores</target></link><space/>are a rich source of information about the pre-Columbian Americans.<space/><link><target>Ethnography</target><part>Ethnographers</part></link><space/>also provide material about many other peoples.</paragraph><paragraph>Aveni uses the importance of zenith passages as an example of the importance of ethnography. For peoples living between the tropics of Cancer and Capricorn there are two days of the year when the noon Sun passes directly overhead and casts no shadow. In parts of Mesoamerica this was considered a significant day as it would herald the arrival of rains, and so play a part in the cycle of agriculture. This knowledge is still considered important amongst Mayan Indians living in Central America today. The ethnographic records suggested to archaeoastronomers that this day may have been important to the ancient Mayans. There are also shafts known as 'zenith tubes' which illuminate subterranean rooms when the sun passes overhead found at places like<space/><link><target>Monte Albn</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Xochicalco</target></link>. It is only through the ethnography that we can speculate that the timing of the illumination was considered important in Mayan society.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1980:40-43</extension><space/>Alignments to the sunrise and sunset on the day of the zenith passage have been claimed to exist at several sites. However, it has been shown that, since there are very few orientations that can be related to these phenomena, they likely have different explanations.<extension extension_name='ref'>prajc and Snchez 2013</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Ethnographies also caution against over-interpretation of sites. At a site in<space/><link><target>Chaco Canyon</target></link><space/>can be found a<space/><link><target>pictograph</target></link><space/>with a star, crescent and hand. It has been argued by some astronomers that this is a record of the<space/><link><target>SN 1054</target><part>1054 Supernova</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brandt and Williamson 1979</extension><space/>However recent reexaminations of related 'supernova petroglyphs' raises questions about such sites in general<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp. et al. 2010: 42</extension><space/>and anthropological evidence suggests other inrepretations. The<space/><link><target>Zuni people</target></link>, who claim a strong ancestral affiliation with Chaco, marked their sun-watching station with a crescent, star, hand and sundisc, similar to those found at the Chaco site.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:89</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ethnoastronomy is also an important field outside of the Americas. For example anthropological work with Aboriginal Australians is producing much information about their<space/><link><target>Aboriginal astronomy</target><part>Indigenous astronomies</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Cairns 2005</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Hamacher 2012</extension><space/>and about their interaction with the modern world.<extension extension_name='ref'>Saethre 2007</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Recreating the ancient sky</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>...[A]lthough different ways to do science and different scientific results do arise in different cultures, this provides little support for those who would use such differences to question the sciences' ability to provide reliable statements about the world in which we live.</arg><arg>Stephen McCluskey<ref>McCluskey 2005:78</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Once the researcher has data to test, it is often necessary to attempt to recreate ancient sky conditions to place the data in its historical environment.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Declination</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Declination</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>To calculate what astronomical features a structure faced a coordinate system is needed. The stars provide such a system. If you were to go outside on a clear night you would observe the stars spinning around the celestial pole. This point is +90 if you are watching the North Celestial Pole or 90 if you are observing the Southern Celestial Pole.<extension extension_name='ref' name="byuqqi">Ruggles 1999:18</extension><space/>The concentric circles the stars trace out are lines of celestial latitude, known as<space/><italics>declination</italics>. The arc connecting the points on the horizon due East and due West (if the horizon is flat) and all points midway between the Celestial Poles is the Celestial Equator which has a declination of 0. The visible declinations vary depending where you are on the globe. Only an observer on the North Pole of Earth would be unable to see any stars from the Southern Celestial Hemisphere at night (see diagram below). Once a declination has been found for the point on the horizon that a building faces it is then possible to say whether a specific body can be seen in that direction.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Decdiag600.jpg</target><part>center</part><part>thumb</part><part>600px</part><part>Diagram of the visible portions of sky at varying latitudes.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Solar positioning</heading><paragraph>While the stars are fixed to their declinations the Sun is not. The rising point of the Sun varies throughout the year. It swings between two limits marked by the solstices a bit like a<space/><link><target>pendulum</target></link>, slowing as it reaches the extremes, but passing rapidly through the midpoint. If an archaeoastronomer can calculate from the azimuth and horizon height that a site was built to view a declination of +23.5 then he or she need not wait until 21 June to confirm the site does indeed face the summer solstice.<extension extension_name='ref'>A.F. Aveni 1997:23-27</extension><space/>For more information see<space/><link><target>History of solar observation</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Lunar positioning</heading><paragraph>The Moon's appearance is considerably more complex. Its motion, like the Sun, is between two limits known as<space/><link><target>Lunar standstill</target><part>''luni''stices</part></link><space/>rather than<space/><italics>sol</italics>stices. However, its travel between lunistices is considerably faster. It takes a<space/><link><target>Sidereal month#Sidereal month</target><part>sidereal month</part></link><space/>to complete its cycle rather than the year-long trek of the Sun. This is further complicated as the lunistices marking the limits of the Moon's movement move on<space/><link><target>Lunar standstill</target><part>an 18.6 year cycle</part></link>. For slightly over nine years the extreme limits of the moon are outside the range of sunrise. For the remaining half of the cycle the Moon never exceeds the limits of the range of sunrise. However, much lunar observation was concerned with the<space/><italics><link><target>Lunar phase</target><part>phase</part></link></italics><space/>of the Moon. The cycle from one<space/><link><target>New Moon</target></link><space/>to the next runs on an entirely different cycle, the<space/><link><target>Synodic month</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 1999:36-37</extension><space/>Thus when examining sites for lunar significance the data can appear sparse due the extremely variable nature of the moon. See<space/><link><target>Moon</target></link><space/>for more details.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Stellar positioning</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Precession of the equinoxes</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Earth precession.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Precessional movement.</part><trail>Finally</trail></link><space/>there is often a need to correct for the apparent movement of the stars. On the timescale of human civilisation the stars have largely maintained the same position relative to each other. Each night they appear to rotate around the celestial poles due to the Earth's rotation about its axis. However, the Earth spins rather like a<space/><link><target>spinning top</target></link>. Not only does the Earth rotate, it wobbles. The Earth's axis takes around 25,800 years to complete one full wobble.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:345-347</extension><space/>The effect to the archaeoastronomer is that stars did not rise over the horizon in the past in the same places as they do today. Nor did the stars rotate around<space/><link><target>Polaris</target></link><space/>as they do now. In the case of the<space/><link><target>Egyptian pyramids</target></link>, it has been shown they were aligned towards<space/><link><target>Thuban</target></link>, a faint star in the constellation of<space/><link><target>Draco (constellation)</target><part>Draco</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:354-355</extension><space/>The effect can be substantial over relatively short lengths of time, historically speaking. For instance a person born on 25 December in Roman times would have been born with the sun in the constellation<space/><link><target>Capricornus</target><part>Capricorn</part></link>. In the modern period a person born on the same date would have the sun in<space/><link><target>Sagittarius (constellation)</target><part>Sagittarius</part></link><space/>due to the<space/><link><target>precession of the equinoxes</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Transient phenomena</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Tapestry of bayeux10.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>Halley's Comet depicted on the<space/><link><target>Bayeux tapestry</target></link></part><trail>Additionally</trail></link><space/>there are often transient phenomena, events which do not happen on an annual cycle. Most predictable are events like<space/><link><target>eclipse</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In the case of<space/><link><target>solar eclipse</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>these can be used to date events in the past. A solar eclipse mentioned by<space/><link><target>Herodotus</target></link><space/>enables us to date a battle between the<space/><link><target>Medes</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lydia</target><trail>ns</trail></link>, which following the eclipse failed to happen, to 28 May, 585 BC.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Herodotus</arg><arg name="authorlink">Herodotus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/cgi-bin/ptext?lookup</arg><arg name="title">The Histories I.74</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></extension><space/>Other easily calculated events are<space/><link><target>supernova</target><trail>e</trail></link><space/>whose remains are visible to astronomers and therefore their positions and magnitude can be accurately calculated.</paragraph><paragraph>Some<space/><link><target>comet</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are predictable, most famously<space/><link><target>Halley's Comet</target></link>. Yet as a class of object they remain unpredictable and can appear at any time. Some have extremely lengthy<space/><link><target>orbital period</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which means their past appearances and returns cannot be predicted. Others may have only ever passed through the<space/><link><target>Solar System</target></link><space/>once and so are inherently unpredictable.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.space.com/spacewatch/050701_bright_comets.html'>Predicting the next bright comet</link>, Space.com.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Meteor shower</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>should be predictable, but some<space/><link><target>meteor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are cometary debris and so require calculations of orbits which are currently impossible to complete.<extension extension_name='ref'>Steel 1999</extension><space/>Other events noted by ancients include<space/><link><target>Aurora (astronomy)</target><part>aurorae</part></link>,<space/><link><target>sun dog</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>rainbow</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>all of which are as impossible to predict as the ancient weather, but nevertheless may have been considered important phenomena.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Major topics of archaeoastronomical research</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>What has astronomy brought into the lives of cultural groups throughout history? The answers are many and varied...</arg><arg>Von Del Chamberlain and M. Jane Young<ref>Chamberlain & Young 2005:xi</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The use of calendars</heading><paragraph>A common justification for the need for astronomy is the need to develop an accurate<space/><link><target>calendar</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>agriculture</target><part>agricultural</part></link><space/>reasons. Ancient texts like<space/><link><target>Hesiod</target></link>'s Works and Days, an ancient farming manual, would appear to contradict this. Instead astronomical observations are used in combination with<space/><link><target>ecology</target><part>ecological</part></link><space/>signs, such as<space/><link><target>bird migration</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to determine the seasons. Ethnoastronomical work with the<space/><link><target>Mursi people</target><part>Mursi</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ethiopia</target></link><space/>shows that haphazard astronomy continued until recent times in some parts of the world.<extension extension_name='ref'>Turton &amp; Ruggles 1978</extension><space/>All the same, calendars appear to be an almost universal phenomenon in societies as they provide tools for the regulation of communal activities.</paragraph><paragraph>An example of a non-agricultural calendar is the<space/><italics><link><target>Tzolk'in</target></link></italics><space/>calendar of the<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>pre-Columbian</target></link><space/><link><target>Mesoamerica</target></link>, which is a cycle of 260 days. This count is based on an<space/><link><target>260-day Mesoamerican calendar</target><part>earlier calendar and is found throughout Mesoamerica</part></link>. This formed part of a more comprehensive system of<space/><link><target>Maya calendar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which combined a series of astronomical observations and ritual cycles.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1989b</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Other peculiar calendars include ancient<space/><link><target>Hellenic calendar</target><part>Greek calendars</part></link>. These were nominally<space/><link><target>Lunar calendar</target><part>lunar</part></link>, starting with the<space/><link><target>New Moon</target></link>. In reality the calendar could pause or skip days with confused citizens inscribing dates by both the civic calendar and<space/><italics>ton theoi</italics>, by the<space/><link><target>moon</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>McCluskey 2000</extension><space/>The lack of any universal calendar for ancient Greece suggests that coordination of panhellenic events such as<space/><link><target>Panhellenic Games</target><part>games</part></link><space/>or rituals could be difficult and that astronomical symbolism may have been used as a politically neutral form of timekeeping.<extension extension_name='ref'>Salt &amp; Boutsikas 2005</extension><space/>Orientation measurements in Greek temples and Byzantine churches have been associated to deity's name day, festivities, and special events.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Liritzis<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>I<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Vassiliou<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>H<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Astronomical orientations of ancient temples at Rhodes and Attica with a tentative interpretation<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Mediterranean Archaeology & Archaeometry<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>69–79<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Liritzis.I and Vassiliou.H (2006) Were Greek temples oriented towards aurora?<space/><italics>Astronomy &amp; Geophysics</italics>, vol.47, 2, 1.14-1.18</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Liritzis.I and Vassiliou.H (2006) Does sunrise day correlate with eastern orientation of Byzantine Churches during significant solar dates and Saints day name? A preliminary study.<space/><italics>Byzantinische Zeitscrift</italics><space/>(K.G.Saur Munchen, Leipzig) 99, 2, 523-534</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Myth and cosmology</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Argo Navis Hevelius.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>The constellation<space/><link><target>Argo Navis</target></link><space/>drawn by Johannes Hevelius in 1690.</part><trail>Another</trail></link><space/>motive for studying the sky is to understand and explain the<space/><link><target>universe</target></link>. In these cultures<space/><link><target>mythology</target><part>myth</part></link><space/>was a tool for achieving this and the explanations, while not reflecting the standards of modern<space/><link><target>science</target></link>, are<space/><link><target>cosmology</target><part>cosmologies</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Inca</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>arranged their empire to demonstrate their cosmology. The capital,<space/><link><target>Cusco</target></link>, was at the centre of the empire and connected to it by means of ceques, conceptually straight lines radiating out from the centre.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bauer &amp; Dearborn 1995</extension><space/>These ceques connected the centre of the empire to the four<space/><italics>suyus</italics>, which were regions defined by their direction from Cusco. The notion of a quartered cosmos is common across the<space/><link><target>Andes</target></link>. Gary Urton, who has conducted fieldwork in the Andean villagers of Misminay, has connected this quartering with the appearance of the<space/><link><target>Milky Way</target></link><space/>in the night sky.<extension extension_name='ref'>Urton 1981</extension><space/>In one season it will bisect the sky and in another bisect it in a<space/><link><target>perpendicular</target></link><space/>fashion.</paragraph><paragraph>The importance of observing cosmological factors is also seen on the other side of the world. The<space/><link><target>Forbidden City</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Beijing</target></link><space/>is laid out to follow cosmic order though rather than observing four directions. The Chinese system was composed of five directions:<space/><link><target>North</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South</target></link>,<space/><link><target>East</target></link>,<space/><link><target>West</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Centre (geometry)</target><part>Centre</part></link>. The Forbidden City occupied the centre of ancient Beijing.<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp 1997a:1969</extension><space/>One approaches the Emperor from the south, thus placing him in front of the<space/><link><target>Circumpolar constellation</target><part>circumpolar stars</part></link>. This creates the situation of the heavens revolving around the person of the Emperor. The Chinese cosmology is now better known through its export as<space/><link><target>feng shui</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>There is also much information about how the universe was thought to work stored in the mythology of the<space/><link><target>constellation</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The Barasana of the<space/><link><target>Amazon Rainforest</target><part>Amazon</part></link><space/>plan part of their annual cycle based on observation of the stars. When their constellation of the Caterpillar-Jaguar (roughly equivalent to the modern Scorpius) falls they prepare to catch the pupating caterpillars of the forest as they fall from the trees.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoskin 1999:156</extension><space/>The caterpillars provide food at a season when other foods are scarce.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hugh-Jones 1982:191-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A more well-known source of constellation myth are the texts of the Greeks and Romans. The origin of their constellations remains a matter of vigorous and occasionally fractious debate.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schaefer 2002</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Blomberg 2003, esp page 76</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The loss of one of the sisters, Merope, in some Greek myths may reflect an astronomical event wherein one of the stars in the Pleiades disappeared from view by the naked eye.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pleiade.org/pleiades_02.html'>''The Pleiades in mythology''</link>, Pleiade Associates, Bristol, United Kingdom, accessed June 7, 2012</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Giorgio de Santillana</target></link>, professor of the History of Science in the School of Humanities at the<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</target></link>, along with Hertha von Dechend believed that the old mythological stories handed down from antiquity were not random fictitious tales but were accurate depictions of celestial<space/><link><target>cosmology</target></link><space/>clothed in tales to aid their oral transmission. The chaos, monsters and violence in ancient myths are representative of the forces that shape each age. They believed that ancient myths are the remains of preliterate<space/><link><target>astronomy</target></link><space/>that became lost with the rise of the Greco-Roman civilization. Santillana and von Dechend in their book<space/><italics>Hamlet's Mill, An Essay on Myth and the Frame of Time</italics><space/>(1969) clearly state that ancient myths have no historical or factual basis other than a cosmological one encoding astronomical phenomena, especially the<space/><link><target>precession of the equinoxes</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Giorgio de Santillana &amp; Hertha von Dechend,<space/><italics>Hamlet's Mill</italics>, David R Godine: Boston, 1977.</extension><space/>Santillana and von Dechend's approach is not widely accepted.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Displays of power</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:1st Pylon Karnak Temple.JPG</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>250px</part><part>left</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Precinct of Amun-Re</target></link><space/>was aligned on the midwinter solstice.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By including celestial motifs in clothing it becomes possible for the wearer to make claims the power on Earth is drawn from above. It has been said that the Shield of<space/><link><target>Achilles</target></link><space/>described by<space/><link><target>Homer</target></link><space/>is also a catalogue of constellations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hannah 1994</extension><space/>In North America shields depicted in<space/><link><target>Comanche</target></link><space/><link><target>petroglyph</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>appear to include Venus symbolism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp 1997a:2523</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Solstice</target><part>Solsticial</part></link><space/>alignments also can be seen as displays of power. When viewed from a ceremonial plaza on the<space/><link><target>Isla del Sol</target><part>Island of the Sun</part></link><space/>(the mythical origin place of the Sun) in<space/><link><target>Lake Titicaca</target></link>, the Sun was seen to rise at the June solstice between two towers on a nearby ridge. The sacred part of the island was separated from the remainder of it by a stone wall and ethnographic records indicate that access to the sacred space was restricted to members of the<space/><link><target>Inca</target></link><space/>ruling elite. Ordinary<space/><link><target>Pilgrimage</target><part>pilgrims</part></link><space/>stood on a platform outside the ceremonial area to see the solstice Sun rise between the towers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dearborn, Seddon &amp; Bauer, 1998</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Egypt the temple of<space/><link><target>Amun-Re</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Karnak</target></link><space/>has been the subject of much study. Evaluation of the site, taking into account the change over time of the<space/><link><target>obliquity of the ecliptic</target></link><space/>show that the Great Temple was aligned on the rising of the midwinter sun.<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp 1988</extension><space/>The length of the corridor down which sunlight would travel would have limited illumination at other times of the year.</paragraph><paragraph>In a later period the<space/><link><target>Serapeum</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link><space/>was also said to have contained a<space/><link><target>Sun</target><part>solar</part></link><space/>alignment so that, on a specific sunrise, a shaft of light would pass across the lips of the statue of<space/><link><target>Serapis</target></link><space/>thus symbolising the<space/><link><target>Sun</target></link><space/>saluting the god.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rufinus</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Major sites of archaeoastronomical interest</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of archaeoastronomical sites sorted by country</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Clive Ruggles</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Michel Cotte</target></link><space/>recently edited a book on heritage sites of astronomy and archaeoastronomy that provides a list of the main sites around the world.<extension extension_name='ref'>Clive Ruggles and Michel Cotte (ed.), Heritage Sites of Astronomy and Archaeoastronomy. ICOMOS and IAU, Paris, 2010.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>At Stonehenge in England and at Carnac in France, in Egypt and Yucatán, across the whole face of the earth, are found mysterious ruins of ancient monuments, monuments with astronomical significance... They mark the same kind of commitment that transported us to the moon and our spacecraft to the surface of Mars.</arg><arg>Edwin Krupp<ref>Krupp. 1979:1</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Newgrange</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Newgrange Eingang Stein.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The sunlight enters the tomb at Newgrange via the roofbox built above the door.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Newgrange</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Newgrange is a passage tomb in the Republic of Ireland dating from around 3,300 to 2,900 BC<extension extension_name='ref'>Eogan 1991</extension><space/>For a few days around the Winter Solstice light shines along the central passageway into the heart of the tomb. What makes this notable is not that light shines in the passageway, but that it does not do so through the main entrance. Instead it enters via a hollow box above the main doorway discovered by Michael O'Kelly.<extension extension_name='ref'>O'Kelly 1982:123-124</extension><space/>It is this roofbox which strongly indicates that the tomb was built with an astronomical aspect in mind. Clive Ruggles notes:<template><target>blockquote</target><arg name="...[F]ew people - archaeologists or astronomers- have doubted that a powerful astronomical symbolism was deliberately incorporated into the monument, demonstrating that a connection between astronomy and funerary ritual, at the very least, merits further investigation.<ref name"><space/>"byuqqi"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Egypt</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:All Gizah Pyramids.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The pyramids of<space/><link><target>Giza</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Giza Necropolis</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Since the first modern measurements of the precise cardinal orientations of the pyramids by<space/><link><target>Flinders Petrie</target></link>, various astronomical methods have been proposed for the original establishment of these orientations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Belmonte 2001</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Neugebauer 1980</extension><space/>It was recently proposed that this was done by observing the positions of two stars in<space/><link><target>Ursa Major</target><part>the Plough / Big Dipper</part></link><space/>which was known to Egyptians as the thigh. It is thought that a vertical alignment between these two stars checked with a<space/><link><target>plumb bob</target></link><space/>was used to ascertain where north lay. The deviations from true north using this model reflect the accepted dates of construction.<extension extension_name='ref'>Spence 2000</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Senenmout-constellations.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Constellations on the astronomical ceiling of<space/><link><target>Senemut</target></link><space/>Tomb</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Some have argued that the pyramids were laid out as<space/><link><target>Orion correlation theory</target><part>a map of the three stars</part></link><space/>in the belt of Orion,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hancock 1996:168</extension><space/>although this theory has been criticized by reputable astronomers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fairall">Fairall 1999</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Krupp">Krupp 1997b</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Astronomical ceiling of Senemut Tomb</target><part>astronomical ceiling of the tomb of Senenmut</part></link><space/>(ca 1470 BC) contains the Celestial Diagram depicting circumpolar constellations in the form of discs. Each disc is divided into 24 sections suggesting a 24-hour time period. Constellations are portrayed as sacred deities of Egypt. The observation of lunar cycles is also evident.</paragraph><heading level='3'>El Castillo</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>El Castillo, Chichen Itza</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>El Castillo, also known as Kukulcn's Pyramid, is a<space/><link><target>Mesoamerican pyramids</target><part>Mesoamerican step-pyramid</part></link><space/>built in the centre of<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target><part>Maya</part><trail>n</trail></link><space/>center of<space/><link><target>Chichen Itza</target></link><space/>in Mexico. Several architectural features have suggested astronomical elements. Each of the stairways built into the sides of the pyramid has 91 steps. Along with the extra one for the platform at the top, this totals 365 steps, which is possibly one for each day of the year (365.25) or the number of lunar orbits in 10,000 rotations (365.01).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Serpent head at the base of El Castillo.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>Plumed Serpent</part></link>A visually striking effect is seen every March and September as an unusual shadow occurs on the equinoxes. A shadow appears to descend the west balustrade of the northern stairway. The visual effect is of a serpent descending the stairway, with its head at the base in light. Additionally the western face points to sunset around 25 May, traditionally the date of transition from the dry to the rainy season.<extension extension_name='ref'>Krupp 1997a:267-269</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Stonehenge</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Summer Solstice Sunrise over Stonehenge 2005.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The sun rising over<space/><link><target>Stonehenge</target></link><space/>at the 2005 Summer<space/><link><target>Solstice</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Archaeoastronomy and Stonehenge</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many astronomical alignments have been claimed for Stonehenge, a complex of<space/><link><target>megalith</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Earthworks (archaeology)</target><part>earthwork</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Salisbury Plain</target></link><space/>of England. The most famous of these is the midsummer alignment, where the Sun rises over the Heel Stone. However, this interpretation has been challenged by some archaeologists who argue that the midwinter alignment, where the viewer is outside Stonehenge and sees the sun setting in the henge, is the more significant alignment, and the midsummer alignment may be a coincidence due to local topography.<extension extension_name='ref'>Parker Pearson<space/><italics>et al.</italics><space/>2007</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As well as solar alignments, there are proposed lunar alignments. The four station stones mark out a rectangle. The short sides point towards the midsummer sunrise and midwinter sunset. The long sides if viewed towards the south-east, face the most southerly rising of the moon. Aveni notes that these lunar alignments have never gained the acceptance that the solar alignments have received.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aveni 1997:65-66</extension><space/>The Heel Stone azimuth is one-seventh of circumference, matching the latitude of Avebury, while summer solstice sunrise azimuth is no longer equal to the construction era direction.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">Source for claim was a personal website; citation was removed, and should be replaced with a reliable source.<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Maeshowe</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:PicMaesEntrance.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The interior of<space/><link><target>Maeshowe</target></link><space/>chambered tomb.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Maeshowe</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This is an architecturally outstanding Neolithic chambered tomb on the Mainland of<space/><link><target>Orkney</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link><space/>probably dating to the early 3rd millennium BC, and where the setting sun at midwinter shines down the entrance passage into the central chamber (see Newgrange). In the 1990s further investigations were carried out to discover whether this was an accurate or an approximate solar alignment. Several new aspects of the site were discovered. In the first place the entrance passage faces the hills of the island<space/><link><target>Hoy</target></link>, about 10 miles away. Secondly, it consists of two straight lengths, angled at a few degrees to each other. Thirdly, the outer part is aligned towards the midwinter sunset position on a level horizon just to the left of Ward Hill on Hoy. Fourthly the inner part points directly at the Barnhouse standing stone about 400m away and then to the right end of the summit of Ward Hill, just before it dips down to the notch between it at Cuilags to the right. This indicated line points to sunset on the first Sixteenths of the solar year (according to A. Thom) before and after the winter solstice and the notch at the base of the right slope of the Hill is at the same declination. Fourthly a similar 'double sunset' phenomenon is seen at the right end of Cuilags, also on Hoy; here the date is the first Eighth of the year before and after the winter solstice, at the beginning of November and February respectively the Old Celtic festivals of<space/><link><target>Samhain</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Imbolc</target></link>. This alignment is not indicated by an artificial structure but gains plausibility from the other two indicated lines. Maeshowe is thus an extremely sophisticated calendar site which must have been positioned carefully in order to use the horizon foresights in the ways described.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MacKie 1997"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Uxmal</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Uxmal-Palace-of-the-Governor.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The Palace of the Governor at Uxmal.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Uxmal</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Uxmal is a Mayan city in the Puuc Hills of<space/><link><target>Yucatn Peninsula</target></link>, Mexico. The Governor's Palace at Uxmal is often used as an exemplar of why it is important to combine ethnographic and alignment data. The palace is aligned with an<space/><link><target>azimuth</target></link><space/>of 118 on the pyramid of Cehtzuc. This alignment corresponds approximately to the southernmost rising and, with a much greater precision, to the northernmost setting of Venus; both phenomena occur once every eight years. By itself this would not be sufficient to argue for a meaningful connection between the two events. The palace has to be aligned in one direction or another and why should the rising of Venus be any more important than the rising of the Sun, Moon, other planets, Sirius<space/><italics>et cetera</italics>? The answer given is that not only does the palace point towards significant points of Venus, it is also covered in<space/><link><target>glyph</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which stand for Venus and Mayan zodiacal constellations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ruggles 2005:163-165</extension><space/>Moreover, the great northerly extremes of Venus always occur in late April or early May, coinciding with the onset of the rainy season. The Venus glyphs placed in the cheeks of the Maya rain god Chac, most likely referring to the concomitance of these phenomena, support the west-working orientation scheme.<extension extension_name='ref'>prajc 2015</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chaco Canyon</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Chaco Canyon Chetro Ketl great kiva plaza NPS.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>The Great Kiva at Chaco Canyon.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In Chaco Canyon, the center of the ancient Pueblo culture in the American Southwest, numerous solar and lunar light markings and architectural and road alignments have been documented. These findings date to the 1977 discovery of the Sun Dagger site by Anna Sofaer.<extension extension_name='ref'>Science Magazine, Sofaer et al., 1979: 126</extension><space/>Three large stone slabs leaning against a cliff channel light and shadow markings onto two spiral petroglyphs on the cliff wall, marking the solstices, equinoxes and the lunar standstills of the 18.6 year cycle of the moon.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cambridge"></extension><space/>Subsequent research by the Solstice Project and others demonstrated that numerous building and interbuilding alignments of the great houses of Chaco Canyon are oriented to solar, lunar and cardinal directions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Malville and Putnam, 1989. Johnson Books:111</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Sofaer 1998. Lekson Ed, U of Utah: 165.</extension><space/>In addition, research shows that the Great North Road, a thirty-five mile engineered road, was constructed not for utilitarian purposes but rather to connect the ceremonial center of Chaco Canyon with the direction north.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sofaer, Marshall and Sinclair, 1989. Cambridge: 112.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Lascaux Cave</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Lascaux 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>According to one theory, the eyes of the bull, the bird, and the bird-man may represent the three stars Vega, Altair, and Deneb commonly known as the<space/><link><target>Summer Triangle</target></link>.</part></link>In recent years, new research has suggested that the<space/><link><target>Lascaux</target></link><space/>cave paintings in France may incorporate prehistoric star charts. Michael Rappenglueck of the<space/><link><target>University of Munich</target></link><space/>argues that some of the non-figurative dot clusters and dots within some of the figurative images correlate with the constellations of<space/><link><target>Taurus (constellation)</target><part>Taurus</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Pleiades</target></link><space/>and the grouping known as the &quot;<link><target>Summer Triangle</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bbcnews_starmap"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Whitehouse</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Ice Age star map discovered</arg><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/science/nature/871930.stm</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 December 2012</arg><arg name="date">9 August 2000</arg></template></extension><space/>Based on her own study of the astronomical significance of Bronze Age<space/><link><target>petroglyphs</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Valle des Merveilles</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Vallée des Merveilles</arg><arg name="publisher">Archeociel</arg><arg name="url">http://www.archeociel.com/nouvelle.htm</arg><arg name="language"><space/>French</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>and her extensive survey of other prehistoric cave painting sites in the regionmost of which appear to have been selected because the interiors are illuminated by the setting sun on the day of the<space/><link><target>winter solstice</target></link>French researcher Chantal Jgues-Wolkiewiez has further proposed that the gallery of figurative images in the Great Hall represents an extensive star map and that key points on major figures in the group correspond to stars in the main<space/><link><target>constellation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as they appeared in the Paleolithic.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Archeociel: Chantal Jègues Wolkiewiez</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.archeociel.com</arg><arg name="language">French</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Lascaux cave: a Prehistoric sky-map...</arg><arg name="url">http://issuu.com/lightmediation/docs/the_lascaux_cave___a_prehistoric_sky-map_3390?mode</arg><arg name="publisher">lightmeditation</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>January 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Appliying phylogenetics to myths of the Cosmic Hunt, Julien d'Huy suggested that the palaeolithic version of this story could be the following: there is an animal that is a horned herbivore, especially an elk. One human pursues this ungulate. The hunt locates or get to the sky. The animal is alive when it is transformed into a constellation. It forms the Big Dipper. This story may be represented in the famous Lascaux shaft scene<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Julien d'Huy. 2012.<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.academia.edu/3226058/2012._Un_ours_dans_les_%C3%A9toiles_recherche_phylog%C3%A9n%C3%A9tique_sur_un_mythe_pr%C3%A9historique._-_Pr%C3%A9histoire_du_sud-ouest_20_1_91-106'>Un ours dans les toiles: recherche phylogntique sur un mythe prhistorique.</link>.<space/><italics>Prhistoire du sud-ouest</italics>, 20 (1), 91-106; Julien d'Huy. 2013.<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.academia.edu/3045718/2013._A_Cosmic_Hunt_in_the_Berber_sky_a_phylogenetic_reconstruction_of_Palaeolithic_mythology._-_Les_Cahiers_de_lAARS_15_93-106'>A Cosmic Hunt in the Berber sky</link>.<space/><italics>Les Cahiers de l'AARS</italics>, 16, 93-106</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Fringe archaeoastronomy</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Archaeoastronomy and Vedic chronology</arg></template><template><target>quote</target><arg>At least now we have all the archaeological facts to go along with the astronomers, the Druids, the Flat Earthers and all the rest.</arg><arg>Sir Jocelyn Stephens<ref>Sir Jocelyn Stephens quoted in ''The Times'', 8 July 1994, 8.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Archaeoastronomy owes something of this poor reputation among scholars to its occasional misuse to advance a range of<space/><link><target>Pseudohistory</target><part>pseudo-historical</part></link><space/>accounts. During the 1930s, Otto S. Reuter compiled a study entitled<space/><italics>Germanische Himmelskunde</italics>, or &quot;Teutonic Skylore&quot;. The astronomical orientations of ancient monuments claimed by Reuter and his followers would place the ancient Germanic peoples ahead of the<space/><link><target>Ancient Near East</target></link><space/>in the field of astronomy, demonstrating the intellectual superiority of the &quot;<link><target>Aryan race</target><part>Aryans</part></link>&quot; (Indo-Europeans) over the<space/><link><target>Semites</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pedersen 1982:269</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since the 19th century, numerous scholars have sought to use<space/><link><target>Archaeoastronomy and Vedic chronology</target><part>archaeoastronomical calculations</part></link><space/>to demonstrate the antiquity of Ancient Indian Vedic culture, computing the dates of astronomical observations ambiguously described in ancient poetry to as early as 4000 BCE.<extension extension_name='ref'>Witzel 2001</extension><space/><link><target>David Pingree</target></link>, a historian of Indian astronomy, condemned &quot;the scholars who perpetrate wild theories of prehistoric science and call themselves archaeoastronomers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Pingree 1982:554-563, esp. p. 556</extension></paragraph><paragraph>More recently Gallagher,<extension extension_name='ref'>Gallagher 1983</extension><space/>Pyle,<extension extension_name='ref'>Pyle 1983</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Barry Fell</target><part>Fell</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Fell 1983</extension><space/>interpreted inscriptions in West Virginia as a description in Celtic<space/><link><target>Ogham</target></link><space/>alphabet of the supposed winter solstitial marker at the site. The controversial translation was supposedly validated by a problematic archaeoastronomical indication in which the winter solstice sun shone on an inscription of the sun at the site. Subsequent analyses criticized its cultural inappropriateness, as well as its linguistic and archeaoastronomical<extension extension_name='ref'>Wise 2003</extension><space/>claims, to describe it as an example of &quot;<link><target>Pseudoarchaeology</target><part>cult archaeology</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lesser, 1983</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Archaeoastronomy is sometimes related to the fringe discipline of<space/><link><target>Archaeocryptography</target></link>, when its followers attempt to find underlying mathematical orders beneath the proportions, size, and placement of archaeoastronomical sites such as Stonehenge and the Pyramid of Kukulcn at Chichen Itza.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Schmeh<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Klaus</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Pathology of Cryptology—A Current Survey<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Cryptologia<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>36<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Taylor and Francis Group<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>14–45<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1080/01611194.2011.632803<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>, at pp. 19-20.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Archaeoastronomical organisations and publications</heading><paragraph>There are currently three academic organisations for scholars of archaeoastronomy.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archaeoastronomy.org/'>ISAAC&amp;mdash;the International Society for Archaeoastronomy and Astronomy in Culture</link>&amp;mdash;was founded in 1995 and now sponsors the Oxford conferences and<space/><italics>Archaeoastronomy the Journal of Astronomy in Culture</italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archeoastronomy.org/'>SEAC&amp;mdash; La Socit Europenne pour lAstronomie dans la Culture</link>&amp;mdash;is slightly older; it was created in 1992. SEAC holds annual conferences in Europe and publishes refereed conference proceedings on an annual basis. There is also<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.arqueoastronomia.org/siac.htm'>SIAC&amp;mdash; La Sociedad Interamericana de Astronoma en la Cultura</link>, primarily a<space/><link><target>Latin America</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>organisation which was founded in 2003. Two new organisations focused on regional archaeoastronomy were founded in 2013:<space/><link type='external' href='http://members.ozemail.com.au/~mmichie/bulletin_oct13.pdf'>ASIA - the Australian Society for Indigenous Astronomy</link><space/>in Australia and<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.scoop.co.nz/stories/SC1306/S00043/modern-uses-for-ancient-maori-knowledge.htm'>SMART - the Society of Mori Astronomy Research and Traditions</link><space/>in New Zealand.</paragraph><paragraph>Additionally the<space/><italics>Journal for the History of Astronomy</italics><space/>publishes many archaeoastronomical papers. For twenty-seven volumes (from 1979 to 2002) it published an annual supplement<space/><italics>Archaeoastronomy</italics>. The<space/><italics><link><target>Journal of Astronomical History and Heritage</target></link></italics><space/>(National Astronomical Research Institute of Thailand) and<space/><italics>Culture &amp; Cosmos</italics><space/>(University of Wales, UK) also publish papers on archaeoastronomy.</paragraph><paragraph>Various national archaeoastronomical projects have been undertaken. Among them is the program at the Tata Institute of Fundamental Research named &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.tifr.res.in/~archaeo/'>Archaeo Astronomy in Indian Context</link>&quot; that has made interesting findings in this field.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.thehindu.com/sci-tech/science/first-indian-record-of-supernova-found-in-kashmir/article2221426.ece</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cultural astronomy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of archaeoastronomical sites sorted by country</target></link><space/>Sites where claims for the use of astronomy have been made.</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of artefacts of archaeoastronomical significance</target></link><space/>Artefacts which have been interpreted as being used for some astronomical purpose.</listitem><listitem><link><target>European Megalithic Culture</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Australian Aboriginal Astronomy</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aboriginal stone arrangements</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Australian Aboriginal Astronomy Project</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lunar standstill</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Medicine wheel</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mound builder (people)</target><part>Mound builders</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Petroform</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pleiades in folklore and literature</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Astronomical chronology</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aldana, G.</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="title">The Apotheosis of Janaab' Pakal: Science, History, and Religion at Classic Maya Palenque</arg><arg name="location">Boulder</arg><arg name="publisher">University Press of Colorado</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87081-866-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Atkinson, R.J.C.</arg><arg name="date">1966</arg><arg name="title">Moonshine on Stonehenge</arg><arg name="journal">[[Antiquity (journal)|Antiquity]]</arg><arg name="volume">49</arg><arg name="issue">159</arg><arg name="pages">212–6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1979</arg><arg name="chapter">Astronomy in Ancient Mesoamerica</arg><arg name="title">In Search of Ancient Astronomies</arg><arg name="editor">E.C. Krupp</arg><arg name="publisher">Chatto and Windus</arg><arg name="pages">154–185</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7011-2314-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1980</arg><arg name="title">Skywatchers of Ancient Mexico</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Texas</arg><arg name="isbn">0-292-77578-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1981</arg><arg name="chapter">Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="title">Advances in Archaeological Method and Theory</arg><arg name="editor">Michael B. Schiffer</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>4</arg><arg name="publisher">Academic Press</arg><arg name="page">177</arg><arg name="isbn">0-12-003104-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni. A.F. (ed.)</arg><arg name="date">1982</arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy in the New World: American Primitive Astronomy</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-24731-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Aveni. A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1986</arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy: Past, Present and Future</arg><arg name="journal">Sky and Telescope</arg><arg name="volume">72</arg><arg name="pages">456–60</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1986S&T....72..456A<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1989a</arg><arg name="title">World Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-34180-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1989b</arg><arg name="title">Empires of Time</arg><arg name="publisher">Basic Books</arg><arg name="isbn">0-465-01950-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">1997</arg><arg name="title">Stairways to the Stars: Skywatching in Three Great Ancient Cultures</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-32976-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1023/A:1022971730558</arg><arg name="author">Aveni. A.F.</arg><arg name="date">2003</arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy in the Ancient Americas</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Archaeological Research</arg><arg name="volume">11</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">149–91</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Aveni, A.F.</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">Evidence and Intentionality: On Evidence in Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures: Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="publisher">City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">57–70</arg><arg name="isbn">1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bahn, P.</arg><arg name="date">1995</arg><arg name="title">Archaeology: A Very Short introduction</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-285379-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bauer, B. and Dearborn, D.</arg><arg name="date">1995</arg><arg name="title">Astronomy and empire in the ancient Andes: the cultural origins of Inca sky watching</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Texas</arg><arg name="isbn">0-292-70837-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Belmonte, J. A.</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="title"><space/>On the Orientation of Old Kingdom Egyptian Pyramids</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Archaeoastronomy: Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume">32<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>26</arg><arg name="pages">S1–S20</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Blomberg, P.</arg><arg name="date">2003</arg><arg name="chapter">The early Hellenic Sky Map reconstructed from Archaeoastronomical and Textual Studies</arg><arg name="title">Ad Astra per Aspera et per Ludum: European Archaeoastronomy and the Orientation of Munuments in the Mediterranean Basin: Papers from Session I.13, held at the European Association of Archaeologists Eighth Annual Meeting in Thessaloniki 2002</arg><arg name="editor">Amanda-Alice Maravelia</arg><arg name="series">BAR International Series 1154</arg><arg name="publisher">Archaeopress</arg><arg name="pages">71–76</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84171-524-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bostwick, T.W.</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">Archaeoastronomy at the Gates of Orthodoxy: Introduction to the Oxford VII Conference on Archaeoastronomy Papers</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures: Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="publisher">City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">1–10</arg><arg name="isbn">1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Brandt, J.C. and Williamson, R.A.</arg><arg name="title">The 1054 Supernova and American Rock Art</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy: Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>10</arg><arg name="pages">S1–S38</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Broda, J.</arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="chapter">Mesoamerican Archaeoastronomy and the Ritual Calendar</arg><arg name="title">Astronomy Across Cultures</arg><arg name="editor">Helaine Selin</arg><arg name="editor-link">Helaine Selin</arg><arg name="publisher">Kluwer, Dordrect</arg><arg name="pages">225–267</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7923-6363-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Broda, J.</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">Zenith Observations and the Conceptualization of Geographical Latitude in Ancient Mesoamerica: A Historical Interdisciplinary Approach</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures; Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>15</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department<space/></arg><arg name="pages">183–212</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Cairns, H.C.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Discoveries in Aboriginal Sky Mapping (Australia)</arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain & Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Durham, North Carolina</arg><arg name="publisher">Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="pages">523–538</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Carlson, J.<space/></arg><arg name="date">Fall 1999<space/></arg><arg name="type">Autumn Equinox<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wam.umd.edu/~tlaloc/archastro/ae33.html</arg><arg name="title">Editorial: A Professor of Our Own</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy & Ethnoastronomy News</arg><arg name="volume">33</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Chamberlain, V.D. & Young, M.J.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Introduction</arg><arg name="title">Songs from the Sky: Indigenous Astronomical and Cosmological Traditions of the World</arg><arg name="editor">Von Del Chamberlain, John Carlson and M. Jane Young</arg><arg name="publisher">Ocarina Books</arg><arg name="pages">xi-xiv</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-9540867-2-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Chiu, B.C. & Morrison, P.<space/></arg><arg name="date">1980</arg><arg name="title">Astronomical Origin of the Offset Street Grid at Teotihuacan</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy: Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume">11<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>18</arg><arg name="pages">S55–S64</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Dearborn, D.S.P., Seddon, M.F., & Bauer, B.S.<space/></arg><arg name="date">1998</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Sanctuary of Titicaca: Where the Sun Returns to Earth</arg><arg name="journal">Latin American Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>9</arg><arg name="pages">240–258</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/971730</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3</arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>971730</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Eogan, G.</arg><arg name="date">1991</arg><arg name="title">Prehistoric and Early Historic Cultural Change at Brugh na Bóinne</arg><arg name="journal">Proceedings of the Royal Irish Academy</arg><arg name="volume">91C</arg><arg name="pages">105–132</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Fairall, A.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Anthony Patrick Fairall<space/></arg><arg name="date">1999</arg><arg name="url">http://www.antiquityofman.com/Orion_Fairall.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Precession and the layout of the Ancient Egyptian pyramids</arg><arg name="journal">[[Astronomy & Geophysics]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Royal Astronomical Society</arg><arg name="volume">40</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080228144915/http://www.antiquityofman.com/Orion_Fairall.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2008-02-28</arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Fell, B.</arg><arg name="date">1983</arg><arg name="url">http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_3.html</arg><arg name="title">Christian Messages in Old Irish Script Deciphered from Rock Carvings in W. Va</arg><arg name="journal">Wonderful West Virginia</arg><arg name="issue">47</arg><arg name="pages">12–19</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-27</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080509080053/http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_3.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>9 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Fisher, V.B.</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">Ignoring Archaeoastronomy: A Dying Tradition in American Archaeology</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures; Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>15</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">1–10</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Fountain, J.<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">A Database of Rock Art Solar Markers<space/></arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain & Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Durham, North Carolina: Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Freeth</arg><arg name="first1">T</arg><arg name="date">30 November 2006</arg><arg name="url">http://www.antikythera-mechanism.gr/node/35<space/></arg><arg name="title">Decoding the ancient Greek astronomical calculator known as the Antikythera Mechanism</arg><arg name="journal">Nature</arg><arg name="volume">444</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>587–591</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg><arg name="doi">10.1038/nature05357</arg><arg name="format"><space/>&ndash;<space/><sup>[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl</arg><arg name="pmid">17136087</arg><arg name="last2">Bitsakis</arg><arg name="first2">Y</arg><arg name="last3">Moussas</arg><arg name="first3">X</arg><arg name="last4">Seiradakis</arg><arg name="first4">JH</arg><arg name="last5">Tselikas</arg><arg name="first5">A</arg><arg name="last6">Mangou</arg><arg name="first6">H</arg><arg name="last7">Zafeiropoulou</arg><arg name="first7">M</arg><arg name="last8">Hadland</arg><arg name="first8">R</arg><arg name="last9">Bate</arg><arg name="first9">D</arg><arg name="displayauthors">8</arg><arg name="issue">7119</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2006Natur.444..587F<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Gallagher, I.J.</arg><arg name="date">1983</arg><arg name="url">http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_2.html</arg><arg name="title">Light Dawns on West Virginia History</arg><arg name="journal">Wonderful West Virginia</arg><arg name="issue">47</arg><arg name="pages">7–11</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-27</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080511200020/http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_2.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>11 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Gingerich, O.<space/></arg><arg name="date">24 March 2000<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.timeshighereducation.co.uk/story.asp?sectioncode</arg><arg name="title">Stone and star gazing</arg><arg name="journal">Times Higher Education Supplement</arg><arg name="page">24</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Gummerman, G.J. & Warburton, M</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">The Universe in Cultural Context: An Essay</arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain & Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Durham, North Carolina: Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hamacher, D.W.</arg><arg name="date">2012</arg><arg name="title">On the Astronomical Knowledge and Traditions of Aboriginal Australians<space/></arg><arg name="location">PhD Thesis</arg><arg name="publisher">Macquarie University, Sydney, Australia</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hancock, G</arg><arg name="date">1996</arg><arg name="title">Fingerprints of the Gods</arg><arg name="publisher">New York: Three Rivers Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-517-88729-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Hannah, R</arg><arg name="date">1994</arg><arg name="url">http://scholar.lib.vt.edu/ejournals/ElAnt/V2N4/hannah.html</arg><arg name="title">The Constellations on Achilles' Shield (Iliad 18. 485–489)</arg><arg name="journal">Electronic Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">II.4</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080421222540/http://scholar.lib.vt.edu/ejournals/ElAnt/V2N4/hannah.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>21 April 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hawkins, G</arg><arg name="date">1976</arg><arg name="title">Stonehenge Decoded</arg><arg name="publisher">Fontana</arg><arg name="isbn">0-00-632315-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Heggie, D.C.</arg><arg name="date">1982</arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy in the Old World</arg><arg name="publisher">CUP</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-24734-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Hicks, R.<space/></arg><arg name="date">Fall 1993<space/></arg><arg name="type">September Equinox<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wam.umd.edu/~tlaloc/archastro/ae9.html</arg><arg name="title">Beyond Alignments</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy & Ethnoastronomy News</arg><arg name="volume">9</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Hoskin, M</arg><arg name="date">1996</arg><arg name="title">Book Reviews: Proceedings of Oxford 3</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy: Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume">21<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>27</arg><arg name="pages">S85–S87</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hoskin, M</arg><arg name="date">1999</arg><arg name="title">The Cambridge Concise History of Astronomy''</arg><arg name="publisher">CUP</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-57600-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hoskin, M.</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="title">Tombs, Temples, and Their Orientations: A New Perspective on Mediterranean Prehistory</arg><arg name="publisher">Ocarina Books</arg><arg name="isbn">0-9540867-1-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hugh-Jones<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stephen<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Anthony F. Aveni and Gary Urton<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ethnoastronomy and Archaeoastronomy in the American Tropics<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/></arg><arg name="series">Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences<space/></arg><arg name="volume">385<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1982<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-89766-160-5<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>183–201</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>The Pleiades and Scorpius in Barasana Cosmology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Academy of Sciences<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York, New York<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Isager, S. and Skydsgaard, J.E.</arg><arg name="date">1992</arg><arg name="title">Ancient Greek Agriculture</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-00164-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Iwaniszewski, S.<space/></arg><arg name="date">Winter 1995<space/></arg><arg name="type">December Solstice<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wam.umd.edu/~tlaloc/archastro/ae18.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alignments and Orientations Again<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy & Ethnoastronomy News</arg><arg name="volume">18</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Iwaniszewski, S.</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="chapter">Time and space in social systems - further issues for theoretical archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="title">Astronomy, Cosmology and Landscape: Proceedings of the SEAC 98 Meeting, Dublin, Ireland</arg><arg name="editor">Clive Ruggles, Frank Prendergast and Tom Ray</arg><arg name="publisher">Ocarina Books</arg><arg name="pages">1–7</arg><arg name="isbn">0-9540867-0-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Iwaniszewski, S.</arg><arg name="date">2003</arg><arg name="chapter">The erratic ways of studying astronomy in culture</arg><arg name="title">Calendars, Symbols and Orientations: Legacies of Astronomy in Culture (Proceedings of the 9th annual meeting of the European Society from Astronomy in Culture (SEAC), Stockholm, 27–30 August 2001</arg><arg name="editor">Mary Blomberg, Peter E. Blomberg and Göran Henriksson</arg><arg name="publisher">Uppsala</arg><arg name="pages">7–10</arg><arg name="isbn">91-506-1674-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Johnson, W.</arg><arg name="date">1912</arg><arg name="title">Byways of British Archaeology</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Kelley, D.H. and Milone, E.F.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="title">Exporing Ancient Skies: An Encyclopedic Survey of Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer-Verlag</arg><arg name="isbn">0-387-95310-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Kintigh, K.<space/></arg><arg name="date">Fall 1992<space/></arg><arg name="type">September Equinox<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wam.umd.edu/~tlaloc/archastro/ae5.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">I wasn't going to say anything, but since you asked: Archaeoastronomy and Archaeology</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy & Ethnoastronomy News</arg><arg name="volume">5</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Krupp, E.C.</arg><arg name="date">1979</arg><arg name="title">In Search of Ancient Astronomies</arg><arg name="publisher">Chatto and Windus</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7011-2314-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Krupp, E.C.</arg><arg name="date">1988</arg><arg name="chapter">Light in the Temples</arg><arg name="title">Records in Stone: Papers in Memory of Alexander Thom</arg><arg name="editor">C.L.N. Ruggles</arg><arg name="publisher">CUP</arg><arg name="pages">473–499</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-33381-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Krupp, E.C.</arg><arg name="date">1997a</arg><arg name="title">Skywatchers, Shamans and Kings</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-32975-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Krupp, E.C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Ed Krupp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Pyramid Marketing Schemes<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Sky and Telescope<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 1997<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.antiquityofman.com/Krupp_pyramid_marketing_schemes.html</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Krupp<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>E. C.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink1"><space/>Ed Krupp<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Billo<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Evelyn<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Robert<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Star Trek: Recovery and Review of the First Alleged Supernova Rock Art<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Archaeoastronomy: The Journal of Astronomy in Culture<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>23<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>35–43<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Texas Press<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Lesser, W.H.</arg><arg name="date">1983</arg><arg name="url">http://cwva.org/ogam_rebutal/lesser_cult_arch.html</arg><arg name="title">Cult Archaeology Strikes Again: A Case for Pre-Columbian Irishmen in the Mountain State?</arg><arg name="journal">West Virginia Archeologist</arg><arg name="volume">35</arg><arg name="pages">48–52</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">McCluskey, S.C.</arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="title">The Inconstant Moon: Lunar Astronomies in Different Cultures</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy: the Journal of Astronomy in Culture</arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="pages">14–31</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">McCluskey, S.C.</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="chapter">Etnoscienza dei Pueblo</arg><arg name="title">Storia della Scienza, vol. 2, Cina, India, Americhe, Sec. 3, "Le Civilta Precolombiane"</arg><arg name="editor">Sandro Petruccioli<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rome: Istituto della Enciclopedia Italiana</arg><arg name="pages">1002–1009</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">McCluskey, S.C.</arg><arg name="date">2004</arg><arg name="title">The Study of Astronomies in Cultures as Reflected in Dissertations and Theses</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="volume">16</arg><arg name="pages">20–25</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">McCluskey, S.C.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Different Astronomies, Different Cultures and the Question of Cultural Relativism</arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain and Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="pages">69–79</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">MacKie, E</arg><arg name="date">1977</arg><arg name="title">Science and Society in Prehistoric Britain</arg><arg name="publisher">Paul Elek</arg><arg name="isbn">0-236-40041-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">MacKie, E</arg><arg name="date">1997</arg><arg name="title">Maeshowe and the winter solstice: ceremonial aspects of the Orkney Grooved Ware culture</arg><arg name="journal">Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">71<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>272<space/></arg><arg name="pages">338–359</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">MacKie, E</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">New Evidence for a Professional Priesthood in the European Early Bronze Age</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures: Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="publisher">City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">343–362</arg><arg name="isbn">1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">MacKie, E. W.</arg><arg name="date">2009</arg><arg name="title">The Prehistoric Solar Calendar: An Out of Fashion Idea Revisited with New Evidence</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Time and Mind]]</arg><arg name="volume">2<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1</arg><arg name="pages">9–46</arg><arg name="doi">10.2752/175169709x374263</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Magli, G.</arg><arg name="date">2008</arg><arg name="title">On the Orientation of Roman Towns in Italy</arg><arg name="journal">[[Oxford Journal of Archaeology]]</arg><arg name="volume">27<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1</arg><arg name="pages">63–71</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1468-0092.2007.00296.x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Meller, H.</arg><arg name="date">January 2004</arg><arg name="title">Star search</arg><arg name="journal">National Geographic</arg><arg name="pages">76–8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Michell, J.</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="title">A Little History of Astro-Archaeology</arg><arg name="publisher">Thames & Hudson</arg><arg name="isbn">0-500-27557-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Milbraith, S.</arg><arg name="date">1988</arg><arg name="chapter">Astronomical Images and Orientations in the Architecture of Chichen Itzá</arg><arg name="title">New Directions in American Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">A.F. Aveni</arg><arg name="series">BAR International Series</arg><arg name="volume">454</arg><arg name="publisher">BAR</arg><arg name="pages">54–79</arg><arg name="isbn">0-86054-583-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Milbraith, S.</arg><arg name="date">1999</arg><arg name="title">Star Gods of the Maya: Astronomy in Art, Folklore and Calendars</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Texas Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-292-75226-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Neugebauer</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Otto</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Otto Neugebauer</arg><arg name="title"><space/>On the Orientation of Pyramids</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Centaurus (journal)|Centaurus]]</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>24</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1–3</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1980</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1600-0498.1980.tb00362.x<space/></arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>1980Cent...24....1N<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">O'Kelly, M.J.</arg><arg name="date">1982</arg><arg name="title">Newgrange: Archaeology, Art and Legend</arg><arg name="publisher">Thames and Hudson</arg><arg name="isbn">0-500-39015-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Parker Pearson, M</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="title">The age of Stonehenge</arg><arg name="journal">Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">81<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>313<space/></arg><arg name="pages">617–639</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/s0003598x00095624</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Pedersen<space/></arg><arg name="first">Olaf<space/></arg><arg name="editor">D. C. Heggie<space/></arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy in the Old World</arg><arg name="date">1982<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-24734-9</arg><arg name="pages">265–274<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">The Present Position of Archaeo-Astronomy<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Pingree, D.</arg><arg name="date">1982</arg><arg name="title">Hellenophilia versus the History of Science</arg><arg name="journal">Isis</arg><arg name="volume">83</arg><arg name="pages">554–563</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/356288</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg></template>. reprinted in Michael H. Shank, ed.,<space/><italics>The Scientific Enterprise in Antiquity and the Middle Ages</italics><space/>(Chicago: Univ. of Chicago Pr., 2000), pp.&amp;nbsp;3039.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Poss, R.L.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Interpreting Rock Art: European and Anasazi Representations of Spirituality</arg><arg name="title">'Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain & Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Durham, North Carolina: Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="pages">81–98</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Preston R.A. & Preston A.L.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Consistent Forms of Solstice Sunlight Interaction with Petroglyphs throughout the Prehistoric American Southwest</arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain & Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Durham, North Carolina: Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Pyle, R.L.</arg><arg name="date">1983</arg><arg name="url">http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_1.html</arg><arg name="title">A Message from the Past</arg><arg name="journal">Wonderful West Virginia</arg><arg name="issue">47</arg><arg name="pages">3–6</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-27</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080511190245/http://cwva.org/wwvrunes/wwvrunes_1.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>11 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Robins M. & Ewing E.</arg><arg name="date">1989</arg><arg name="chapter">The Sun is in His House: Summer Solstice at San Carlos Mesa</arg><arg name="title">Rock Art Papers, vol. 6</arg><arg name="editor">Ken Hedges</arg><arg name="series">San Diego Museum Papers</arg><arg name="volume">24</arg><arg name="publisher">San Diego Museum</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www29.homepage.villanova.edu/christopher.haas/destructioni%20of%20Serapeum.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The destruction of the Serapeum<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22<space/></arg><arg name="author">Rufinus</arg><arg name="authorlink">Tyrannius Rufinus</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080406071455/http://www29.homepage.villanova.edu/christopher.haas/destructioni%20of%20Serapeum.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>6 April 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Ruggles, C.L.N.</arg><arg name="date">1993</arg><arg name="title">Archaeoastronomy in the 1990s</arg><arg name="publisher">Group D Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">1-874152-01-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Ruggles, C.L.N.</arg><arg name="date">1999</arg><arg name="title">Astronomy in Prehistoric Britain and Ireland</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Yale University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-300-07814-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Ruggles. C.L.N.<space/></arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="title">Ancient Astronomies - Ancient Worlds</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy:Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>25<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>31</arg><arg name="pages">S65–S76</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Ruggles, C.L.N.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="title">Ancient Astronomy</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-Clio</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85109-477-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor1-last">Ruggles</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Clive L. N.</arg><arg name="editor1-link">Clive Ruggles</arg><arg name="title">The Handbook of Archaeoastronomy and Ethnoastronomy</arg><arg name="date">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4614-6140-1<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/978-1-4614-6141-8</arg></template><space/>Three volumes; 217 articles.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Ruggles, C.L.N. and Barclay, G.</arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="title">Cosmology, calendars and society in Neolithic Orkney: a rejoinder to Euan MacKie</arg><arg name="journal">Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">74<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>283<space/></arg><arg name="pages">62–74</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Ruggles<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>C.L.N.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Cotte<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>M.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heritage Sites of Astronomy and Archaeoastronomy in the context of the UNESCO World Heritage Convention: A Thematic Study<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Paris<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>ICOMOS / IAU<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.astronomicalheritage.org/index.php?option</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-2-918086-01-7<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Ruggles, C.L.N. & Saunders, N.J.</arg><arg name="date">1993</arg><arg name="chapter">The Study of Cultural Astronomy</arg><arg name="title">Astronomies and Cultures</arg><arg name="editor">Clive L.N. Ruggles and Nicholas J. Saunders,<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University Press of Colorado</arg><arg name="pages">1–31</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87081-319-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Saethre, E.</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="title">Close encounters: UFO beliefs in a remote Australian Aboriginal community</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute</arg><arg name="volume">13<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">901–915</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9655.2007.00463.x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Salt, A. & Boutsikas, E.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="title">Knowing when to consult the oracle at Delphi</arg><arg name="journal">Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">79<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>305<space/></arg><arg name="pages">562–72</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Schaefer, B.E.</arg><arg name="date">2002</arg><arg name="title">The Great Ptolemy-Hipparchus Dispute</arg><arg name="journal">Sky and Telescope</arg><arg name="volume">103<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2</arg><arg name="pages">38–66</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Schaefer, B.E.</arg><arg name="date">2006a</arg><arg name="chapter">Case Studies of Three of the Most Famous Claimed Archaeoastronomical Alignments in North America</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures: Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="publisher">City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">27–56</arg><arg name="isbn">1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Schaefer, B.E.</arg><arg name="date">2006b</arg><arg name="chapter">No Astronomical Alignments at the Caracol</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures: Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="publisher">City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">71–77</arg><arg name="isbn">1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Schlosser, W.</arg><arg name="date">2002</arg><arg name="title">Zur astronomischen Deuteung der Himmelschreibe vom Nebra</arg><arg name="journal">Archäologie in Sachsen-Anhalt</arg><arg name="volume">1/02</arg><arg name="pages">21–3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Sinclair, R.M.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">The Nature of Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="title">Current Studies in Archaeoastronomy: Conversations Across Time and Space</arg><arg name="editor">John W. Fountain and Rolf M. Sinclair</arg><arg name="publisher">Carolina Academic Press</arg><arg name="pages">3–13</arg><arg name="isbn">0-89089-771-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Sinclair, R.M.</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg><arg name="chapter">The Nature of Archaeoastronomy"</arg><arg name="title">Viewing the Sky Through Past and Present Cultures; Selected Papers from the Oxford VII International Conference on Archaeoastronomy</arg><arg name="editor">Todd W. Bostwick and Bryan Bates</arg><arg name="series">Pueblo Grande Museum Anthropological Papers<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>15</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>City of Phoenix Parks and Recreation Department</arg><arg name="pages">13–26</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-882572-38-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Sofaer, A., ed.</arg><arg name="date">2008</arg><arg name="title">Chaco Astronomy: An Ancient American Cosmology</arg><arg name="publisher">Santa Fe, New Mexico: Ocean Tree Books</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-943734-46-0<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Steel, D.</arg><arg name="date">June 1999</arg><arg name="url">http://www.britarch.ac.uk/BA/ba45/ba45feat.html#steel</arg><arg name="title">Stonehenge and the Terror in the Sky</arg><arg name="journal">British Archaeology</arg><arg name="volume">45</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-09-06<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Spence, K</arg><arg name="date">16 November 2000</arg><arg name="title">Ancient Egyptian Chronoology and the astronomical orientation of the pyramids</arg><arg name="journal">Nature</arg><arg name="volume">406</arg><arg name="pages">320–324</arg><arg name="doi">10.1038/35042510</arg><arg name="pmid">11099032</arg><arg name="issue">6810</arg></template></listitem><listitem>prajc, I. (2015). Governor's Palace at Uxmal. In:<space/><italics>Handbook of Archaeoastronomy and Ethnoastronomy</italics>, ed. by Clive L. N. Ruggles, New York: Springer, pp. 773-781</listitem><listitem>prajc, I., and P. F. Snchez Nava (2013).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.iifilologicas.unam.mx/estculmaya/uploads/volumenes/xli/4%20Astronom%C3%ADa%20en%20la%20arquitectura.%20Sprajc-S%C3%A1nchez.pdf'>Astronoma en la arquitectura de Chichn Itz: una reevaluacin</link>.<space/><italics>Estudios de Cultura Maya</italics><space/>XLI: 3160.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Thom, A.</arg><arg name="date">1967</arg><arg name="title">Megalithic Sites in Britain</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">Clarendon Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-813148-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Thom. A.S.</arg><arg name="date">1988</arg><arg name="chapter">A personal note about my late father, Alexander Thom</arg><arg name="title">Records in Stone: Papers in Memory of Alexander Thom</arg><arg name="editor">C.L.N. Ruggles</arg><arg name="publisher">CUP</arg><arg name="pages">3–13</arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-33381-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Trotter, A.P.</arg><arg name="date">1927</arg><arg name="title">Stonehenge as an Astronomical Instrument</arg><arg name="journal">Antiquity</arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">42–53</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Turton, D. and Ruggles, C.L.N.</arg><arg name="date">1978</arg><arg name="title">Agreeing to Disagree: The Measurement of Duration in a Southwestern Ethiopian Community</arg><arg name="journal">[[Current Anthropology]]</arg><arg name="volume">19.3</arg><arg name="pages">585–600</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/202140</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Urton, G.</arg><arg name="date">1981</arg><arg name="title">At the crossroads of the earth and the sky: an Andean cosmology</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Texas</arg><arg name="isbn">0-292-70349-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">van Driel-Murray, C.</arg><arg name="date">2002</arg><arg name="chapter">Regarding the Stars</arg><arg name="title">TRAC 2001: Proceedings of the Eleventh Annual Theoretical Roman Archaeology Conference Glasgow 2001</arg><arg name="editor">M Carruthers, C. van Driel-Murray, A. Gardner, J. Lucas, L. Revell and E. Swift. Oxbow Books</arg><arg name="pages">96–103<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>1-84217-075-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://cwva.org/ogam_rebutal/solstice_2002.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Observations of the 2002 Winter Solstice at Luther Elkins Petroglyph (46 Wm 3)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-03-22<space/></arg><arg name="author">Wise, R.B.</arg><arg name="date">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Council for West Virginia Archaeology</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Williamson, Ray A.</arg><arg name="date">1987</arg><arg name="chapter">Light and Shadow, Ritual, and Astronomy in Anasazi Structures<space/></arg><arg name="title">Astronomy and Ceremony in the Prehistoric Southwest</arg><arg name="editor">John B. Carlson and W. James Judge<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Papers of the Maxwell Museum of Anthropology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Albuquerque, NM<space/></arg><arg name="pages">71–88</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-912535-03-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Witzel, M.</arg><arg name="date">May 2001</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ejvs.laurasianacademy.com/ejvs0703/ejvs0703d.txt</arg><arg name="title">Autochthonous Aryans? The Evidence from Old Indian and Iranian Text</arg><arg name="journal">Electronic Journal of Vedic Studies</arg><arg name="volume">7<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">§28–30</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Xu, Z. Pankenier, D.W. and Jiang, Y.</arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="title">East Asian Archaeoastronomy: Historical Records of Astronomical Observations of China, Japan and Korea</arg><arg name="publisher">Gordon & Breach Science Publ.</arg><arg name="isbn">90-5699-302-X</arg><arg name="location">Amsterdam</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Young, M.J.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="chapter">Ethnoastronomy and the Problem of Interpretation: A Zuni Example</arg><arg name="title">Songs from the Sky: Indigenous and Cosmological Traditions of the World</arg><arg name="editor">Von Del Chamberlain, John Carlson and M. Jane Young</arg><arg name="publisher">Ocarina Books</arg><arg name="isbn">0-9540867-2-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Zeilik, M.</arg><arg name="date">1985</arg><arg name="title">The Ethnoastronomy of the Historic Pueblos, I: Calendrical Sun Watching</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy:Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</arg><arg name="volume">8<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>16</arg><arg name="pages">S1–S24</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Zeilik, M.</arg><arg name="date">1986</arg><arg name="title">The Ethnoastronomy of the Historic Pueblos, II: Moon Watching</arg><arg name="journal">Archaeoastronomy:Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy'</arg><arg name="volume">10<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>17</arg><arg name="pages">S1–S22</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://assets.cambridge.org/052157/2916/sample/0521572916web.pdf'>Astronomy before History, by Clive Ruggles and Michael Hoskins</link>, a chapter from<space/><italics>The Cambridge Concise History of Astronomy,</italics><space/>Michael Hoskin ed., 1999</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cliveruggles.net/'>Clive Ruggles's webpage:</link><space/>images, bibliography, software, and synopsis of his course at the<space/><link><target>University of Leicester</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.traditionsofthesun.org/'>Traditions of the Sun</link><space/>NASA and others exploring the world's ancient observatories.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://sunearthday.nasa.gov/2005/images/ao_poster.pdf'>Ancient Observatories: Timeless Knowledge</link><space/>NASA Poster on ancient (and modern) observatories.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Societies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archaeoastronomy.org/'>ISAAC</link>, The International Society for Archaeoastronomy and Astronomy in Culture.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archeoastronomy.org/'>SEAC</link><space/>La Socit Europenne pour lAstronomie dans la Culture. Site in English.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arqueoastronomia.org/siac.htm'>SIAC</link><space/>La Sociedad Interamericana de Astronoma en la Cultura.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shastro.org.uk/'>Society for the History of Astronomy</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Journals</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wam.umd.edu/~tlaloc/archastro/ae.html'>Archaeoastronomy and Ethnoastronomy News</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shpltd.co.uk/aa.html'>Archaeoastronomy: Supplement to the Journal for the History of Astronomy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.utexas.edu/utpress/journals/jarch.html'>Archaeoastronomy: The Journal of Astronomy in Culture</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cultureandcosmos.com/'>Culture and Cosmos</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shpltd.co.uk/jha.html'>Journal for the History of Astronomy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://aaatec.org/archive.html'>Archaeoastronomy and Ancient Technologies (open access)</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Astronomy navbox</target><arg name="state">expanded</arg></template><template><target>Prehistoric technology</target></template><template><target>Good article</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Articles with inconsistent citation formats</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient astronomy</target></link><link><target>Category:Archaeoastronomy</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:History of astronomy</target></link><link><target>Category:History of astrology</target></link><link><target>Category:Traditional knowledge</target></link><link><target>Category:Earth mysteries</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>