<article title='Central_African_Armed_Forces'><paragraph><template><target>Update</target><arg name="inaccurate">yes</arg><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox national military</target><arg name="name"><space/>Central African Armed Forces
</arg><arg name="native name"><space/>"Forces armées centrafricaines (FACA)"
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image2"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>
</arg><arg name="headquarters"><space/>Camp Le Roux, [[Bangui]]
</arg><arg name="commander-in-chief"><space/>[[Alexandre-Ferdinand Nguendet]]
</arg><arg name="minister"><space/>
</arg><arg name="minister_title"><space/>Minister of Defense
</arg><arg name="commander"><space/>
</arg><arg name="active"><space/>4,500
</arg><arg name="reserve"><space/>
</arg><arg name="deployed"><space/>
</arg><arg name="amount"><space/>$15.5 million (2004)
</arg><arg name="percent_GDP"><space/>1.1
</arg><arg name="founded"><space/>1960
</arg><arg name="current_form"><space/>
</arg><arg name="disbanded"><space/>
</arg><arg name="branches"><space/>'''''Armée de Terre''''' ([[Ground Forces]])<br><space/>'''''l’Armée de l’air''''' ([[Air Force]])<br>''''' Gendarmerie nationale''''' ([[Gendarmerie]])<br><space/>''''' GR – Garde républicaine''''' (Presidential Guard)<br>'''''Police Nationale''''' (Police)
</arg><arg name="age"><space/>
</arg><arg name="available"><space/>'''''males age 18–49: ''''' 853,760 (2005 est.)
</arg><arg name="fit"><space/>'''''males age 18–49: ''''' 416,091 (2005 est.)
</arg><arg name="reaching"><space/>
</arg><arg name="conscription"><space/>Voluntary, after the age of 18 years
</arg><arg name="national conscription period"><space/>
</arg><arg name="domestic_suppliers"><space/>
</arg><arg name="international_suppliers"><space/>
</arg><arg name="exports"><space/>
</arg><arg name="imports"><space/>
</arg><arg name="history"><space/>[[Lord's Resistance Army insurgency]]<br>[[Central African Republic Bush War]]<br>[[Central African Republic conflict (2012–2014)|Central African Republic conflict]]
</arg><arg name="ranks"><space/>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Central African Armed Forces</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-fr</target><arg>'''Forces armées centrafricaines (FACA)'''</arg></template>) are the<space/><link><target>armed forces</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Central African Republic</target></link>, established after independence in 1960. Today they are a rather weak institution, dependent on international support to hold back the enemies in the current<space/><link><target>Central African Republic Civil War</target><part>civil war</part></link>. Its disloyalty to the president came to the fore during the mutinies in 19961997, but ever since then it has faced internal problems. It has been strongly criticised by human rights organisations due to its<space/><link><target>terrorism</target><part>terror</part></link>, including killings,<space/><link><target>torture</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sexual assault</target><part>sexual violence</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>It proved to be incompetent in 2013 when militants of the<space/><link><target>Slka</target></link><space/>rebel coalition seized power and overthrew President Boziz, committing executions of many FACA troops.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.monitor.upeace.org/innerpg.cfm?id_article=1026'>Understanding the 2013 CAR coup</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Role of military in domestic politics</heading><paragraph>The military has played an important role in the history of<space/><link><target>Central African Republic</target></link>. The immediate former president, General<space/><link><target>Franois Boziz</target></link><space/>is a former army chief-of-staff and his government includes several high-level military officers. Among the countrys five presidents since independence in 1960, three have been former army chiefs-of-staff, who have taken power through<space/><link><target>coups d'tat</target></link>. No president with military background has however been succeeded by a new military president.</paragraph><paragraph>The countrys first president,<space/><link><target>David Dacko</target></link><space/>was overthrown by his army chief-of-staff,<space/><link><target>Jean-Bdel Bokassa</target></link><space/>in 1966. Following Bokassa, David Dacko was restored in 1981, only to be overthrown once again by his new army chief of staff, General<space/><link><target>Andr Kolingba</target></link><space/>after only a few months in power.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1993,<space/><link><target>Ange-Flix Patass</target></link><space/>became the first elected president of the country. He became soon unpopular within the army, resulting in violent mutinies in 19961997. In May 2001, there was an unsuccessful coup attempt by Kolingba and once again Patass had to turn to friends abroad for support, this time<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>DR Congo</part></link><space/>were helpful. Some months later, in the end of October, Patass sacked his army chief-of-staff, Franois Boziz, and tried to arrest him. Boziz then fled to<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link><space/>and gathered a group of rebellions. In 2002, he seized<space/><link><target>Bangui</target></link><space/>for a short period. In March 2003 Boziz took power through a coup dtat .<extension extension_name='ref' name="one"><link type='external' href='http://www.franceevasion.com/toutsavoir/pays-republique-centrafricaine.htm'><space/>Histoire: Rpublique centrafricaine</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Importance of ethnicity</heading><paragraph>When General Kolingba became president in 1981, he implemented an ethnicity-based recruitment policy for the administration. Kolingba was a member of the<space/><link><target>Yakoma people</target></link><space/>from the south of the country, which made up approximately 5% of the total population. During his rule, members of Yakoma were granted all key positions in the administration and made up a majority of the military. This later had disastrous consequences, when Kolingba was replaced by a member of a northerner tribe, Ange-Flix Patass.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Army mutinies of 19961997</heading><paragraph>Soon after the election 1993, Patass became unpopular within the army, not least because of his inability to pay their wages (partly due to economic mismanagement and partly because<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>suddenly ended its economic support for the soldiers wages). Another reason for the irritation was that most of FACA consisted of soldiers from Kolingbas ethnic group, the<space/><link><target>Yakoma people</target><part>Yakoma</part></link>. During Patasss rule they were becoming increasingly marginalised, while Patass created militias favouring his own Gbaya tribe, as well as neighbouring Sara and Kaba. This resulted in army mutinies in 19961997, where fractions of the military clashed with the presidential guard, the<space/><italics>Unit de scurit prsidentielle (USP)</italics><space/>and militias loyal to Patass.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"><link type='external' href='http://www.sangonet.com/actu-snews/santeah/fich-RCA-unhcr2005.pdf'><space/>UNDP: Fiche Pays: Rpublique centrafricaine (2005)</link></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>On April 18, 1996, there was a first mutiny by 200300 soldiers who claimed that they had not received their wage since 19921993. The confrontations between the soldiers and the presidential guard resulted in 9 dead and 40 wounded. French forces were supporting (Operation Almandin I) and acted negotiators. The unrest ended when the soldiers were finally paid their wages by France and the President agreed not to start legal proceedings against the soldiers.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>On May 18, 1996, a second mutiny was led by 500 soldiers who refused to be disarmed and denounced the agreement reached in April. The French forces were once again called to Bangui (Operation Almadin II), supported by military from Chad and<space/><link><target>Gabon</target></link>. 3,500 foreigners were evacuated during the unrest, which killed 43 persons and wounded 238.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>On May 26, a peace agreement was signed between France and the mutineers. The latter were promised amnesty, allowed to retain their weapons. Their security was ensured by the French military.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>On November 15, 1996, there was a third mutiny and 1,500 French soldiers were flown in to ensure the safety of the foreigners. The mutineers demanded the discharge of the president.</listitem></list><paragraph>On 6 December, a negotiation process started, facilitated by Gabon,<space/><link><target>Burkina-Faso</target></link>, Chad and<space/><link><target>Mali</target></link>. The military supported by the opposition parties keeps claiming that Patass has to resign. In January, 1997, however, the<space/><link><target>Bangui Agreements</target></link><space/>were signed and the French EFAO troop was replaced by the 1,350 soldiers of the<space/><italics>Mission interafricaine de surveillance des Accords de Bangui (MISAB)</italics>. In March, all mutineers were granted amnesty. The fighting between MISAB and the mutineers continued with a large offensive in June, resulting in up to 200 casualties. After this final clash, the mutineers stayed calm.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the mutinies, President Patass suffered from a typical &quot;dictators paranoia&quot;, resulting in a period of cruel terror executed by the presidential guard and various militia within the FACA loyal to the president, such as the Karako. It was directed against the Yakoma tribe, of which it is estimated that 20,000 persons fled during this period. But the oppression also targeted other parts of the society. The president accused his former ally France of supporting his enemies and seeks new international ties. When he strengthened his presidential guard (creating the FORSIDIR, see below), Libya sent him 300 additional soldiers for his own personal safety. When former President Kolingba attempted a coup dtat in 2001 (which was, according to Patass, supported by France), the<space/><link><target>Movement for the Liberation of Congo</target></link><space/>(MLC) of<space/><link><target>Jean-Pierre Bemba</target></link><space/>in DR Congo came to his rescue.<extension extension_name='ref' name="three"><link type='external' href='http://web.amnesty.org/web/ar2002.nsf/afr/central+african+republic!Open'><space/>Amnesty International: Amnesty International Report 2002</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Crimes conducted by Patasss militias and Congolese soldiers during this period are now being investigated by the<space/><link><target>International Criminal Court</target></link>, who wrote that &quot;sexual violence appears to have been a central feature of the conflict&quot;, having identified more than 600 rape victims.<extension extension_name='ref' name="four"><link type='external' href='http://news.yahoo.com/s/afp/20070522/wl_africa_afp/icccentrafrica_070522145948'><space/>Yahoo News: ICC to investigate Central African Republic sexual violence, 22 May 2007</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Present situation</heading><paragraph>The FACA has been dominated by soldiers from the Yakoma ethnic group since the time of Kolingba. It has hence been considered disloyal by the two northerner presidents Patass and Boziz, both of whom have equipped and run their own militias outside FACA. The military also proved its disloyalty during the mutinies in 19961997. Although Francois Boziz has a background in FACA himself (being its chief-of-staff from 1997 to 2001), he has been cautious by retaining the defence portfolio, as well as by appointing his son Jean-Francis Boziz cabinet director in charge of running the Ministry of Defence. He kept his old friend General Antoine Gambi as Chief of Staff. Due to failure to curb deepening unrest in the northern part of the country, Gambi was in July 2006 replaced with Bozizs old friend from the military academy, Jules Bernard Ouand.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ten"><link type='external' href='http://www.afrik.com/article10063.html'><space/>AFRIK: Un nouveau chef pour larme centrafricaine, July 6, 2006</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Militarys relations with the society</heading><paragraph>The forces assisting Boziz in seizing the power in 2003 were not paid what they were promised and started looting, terrorising and killing ordinary citizens. Summary executions have taken place with the implicit approval of the government. The situation has deteriorated since early 2006 and the regular army and the presidential guard regularly execute extortion, torture, killings and other human rights violations. There is no possibility for the national judicial system to investigate these cases. At the end of 2006, there were an estimated 150,000 internally displaced people. During a UN mission in the northern part of the country in November 2006, the mission had a meeting with a prefect who said that he could not maintain law and order over the military and the presidential guards. The FACA conducts summary executions and burn houses. Only on the route between<space/><link><target>Kaga-Bandoro</target></link><space/>and Ouandago, some 2,000 houses have been burnt, leaving an estimated 10,000 persons homeless.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eleven"><link type='external' href='http://www.internal-displacement.org/8025708F004BE3B1/(httpInfoFiles)/63ACDE89E61019B5C125726F0035E8A0/$file/CAR_report_Jan2007.pdf'><space/>Internal displacement in Central African Republic: a protection crisis, January 26, 2007</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Reform of the army</heading><paragraph>Both the<space/><italics>Multinational Force in the Central African Republic</italics><space/>(FOMUC) and France are assisting in the current reform of the army. One of the key priorities of the reform of the military is make it more ethnically diversified. It should also integrate Bozizs own rebel group (mainly consisting of members of his own<space/><link><target>Gbaya people</target><part>Gbaya tribe</part></link>). Many of the Yakoma soldiers who left the country after the mutinies in 19961997 have now returned and must also be reintegrated into the army. At the same time, BONUCA holds seminars in topics such as the relationship between military and civil parts of society.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twelve"><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/2002/18174.htm'><space/>Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor: Country Reports on Human Rights Practices Central African Republic, March 31, 2003</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Equipment</heading><heading level='3'>Tanks</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Main Battle Tanks<list type='bullet'><listitem>4<space/><link><target>T-55</target></link><space/>main battle tanks (operational status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299">Military Balance 2010, page 299</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Armoured cars</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>8<space/><link><target>Ferret armoured car</target><part>Ferret</part></link><space/>(operational status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem><listitem>1<space/><link><target>BRDM-2</target></link><space/>(operation status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>APC</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>10<space/><link><target>Vhicule de l'Avant Blind</target><part>VAB</part></link>-VTT (operational status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem><listitem>4<space/><link><target>BTR-152</target></link><space/>(operation status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem><listitem>25<space/><link><target>ACMAT</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>IFV</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>3<space/><link><target>OT-90</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Artillery</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>12<space/><link><target>M40 recoilless rifle</target></link><space/>(operation status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem><listitem>12<space/><link><target>120-PM-43 mortar</target></link><space/>(operation status uncertain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Military Balance 2010, page 299"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Anti-tank missiles</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>10<space/><link><target>MILAN</target></link><space/>ATGM launchers</listitem><listitem>10<space/><link><target>BGM-71</target><trail>C</trail></link><space/><link><target>BGM-71 TOW</target><part>TOW</part></link><space/>ATGM launchers</listitem><listitem>10<space/><link><target>RPG-7</target></link><space/>ATRLs<extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Anti-aircraft weapons</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>ZPU</target></link>-1\2\4</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Personal weapons</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Israel Military Industries</target><part>IMI</part></link><space/><link><target>UZI</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>FN FAL</target></link><space/>50-00</listitem><listitem><link><target>Heckler &amp; Koch G3</target><part>H&amp;K G3</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>AKM</target></link>\<link><target>AK-47</target></link>\<link><target>Type 56 assault rifle</target><part>Type-56</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>M16A1</target></link><space/>*<extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Galil</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>MAT-49</target><part>MAT-49 SMG</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>FN MAG</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>RPD</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>PK machine gun</target><part>PKM</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>M2 Browning</target><part>Browning M2HB</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>6G30</target><part>6G30 GL</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Foreign military presence in support of the Government</heading><heading level='3'>Peacekeeping and peace enforcing forces</heading><paragraph>Since the mutinies, a number of<space/><link><target>peacekeeping</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Peace enforcement</target><part>peace enforcing</part></link><space/>international missions have been present in Central African Republic. There has been a discussion of the deployment of a regional<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>(UN) peacekeeping force in both Chad and Central African Republic. But it is considered to shore up the ineffectual Darfur Peace Agreement. The missions deployed in the country during the last 10 years are the following:<extension extension_name='ref' name="nine"><link type='external' href='http://www.smallarmssurvey.org/files/portal/spotlight/sudan/Sudan_pdf/SIB%205%20CAR.pdf'><space/>Sudan Issue Brief: A widening war around Sudan The proliferation of armed groups in the Central African Republic, January 2007</link></extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable" style="margin: 1em auto 1em auto"><tablecaption><bold>International Peace Supporting Missions in Central African Republic</bold></tablecaption><tablerow><tablehead>Mission Name</tablehead><tablecell>Organisation</tablecell><tablecell>Dates</tablecell><tablecell>Greatest Strength</tablecell><tablecell>Tasks</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold>Inter-African Mission to Monitor the Implementation of the<space/><link><target>Bangui Agreements</target></link></bold><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<italics>Mission interafricaine de surveillance des Accords de Bangui, MISAB</italics>)</tablecell><tablecell>Burkina Faso, Chad, Gabon, Mali, Senegal and<space/><link><target>Togo</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>February 1997 to April 1998</tablecell><tablecell>820</tablecell><tablecell>To monitor the fulfilling of the Bangui Agreements</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold>UN Mission in the Central African Republic</bold><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<italics>Mission des Nations Unies en Rpublique centrafricaine, MINURCA</italics>)</tablecell><tablecell>UN</tablecell><tablecell>April 1998 to February 2000</tablecell><tablecell>1,350</tablecell><tablecell>Maintain peace and security; supervise disarmament; technical assistance during 1998 elections</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold>United Nations Peace-building Office</bold><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<italics>Bureau politique dobservation des Nations Unies en Centrafrique, BONUCA</italics>)</tablecell><tablecell>UN</tablecell><tablecell>February 2000 to 1 January 2010</tablecell><tablecell>Five military and six civilian police advisers to follow up on security-related reforms and to assist in the implementation of the training programmes for the national police.</tablecell><tablecell>Consolidate peace and national reconciliation; strengthen democratic institutions; facilitate international mobilization for national reconstruction and economic recovery. Succeeded by UN Integrated Peace-building Office (BINUCA).</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold><link><target>Community of Sahel-Saharan States</target></link></bold><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<italics>CEN-SAD</italics>)</tablecell><tablecell>CEN-SAD</tablecell><tablecell>December 2001 to January 2003</tablecell><tablecell>300</tablecell><tablecell>Enforce and restore peace</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold>Multinational Force in the Central African Republic</bold><space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(<italics>Force multinationale en Centrafrique, FOMUC</italics>)</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Economic and Monetary Community of Central Africa</target></link><space/>(CEMAC)</tablecell><tablecell>January 2003 to July 2008</tablecell><tablecell>380</tablecell><tablecell>Ensure security; restructure FACA; and fight rebels in north-east. Replaced by MICOPAX.</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Chad</heading><paragraph>In addition to the multilateral forces, there have been bilateral support from other African countries, such as the Libyan and Congolese support to Patass, mentioned above. Boziz is in many ways dependent on Chad support. Chad has an interest in CAR, since it needs to ensure calmness close to its oil fields and<space/><link><target>Chad-Cameroon Petroleum Development and Pipeline Project</target><part>the pipeline leading to the Cameroonian coast</part></link>, close to the troubled northwest CAR. Before seizing power, Boziz built up his rebel force in Chad, trained and augmented by the Chadian. President<space/><link><target>Idriss Dby</target><part>Dby</part></link><space/>assisted him actively in taking the power in March 2003 (his rebel forces included 100 Chadian soldiers). After the coup, another 400 soldiers were sent. Current direct support includes the 150 non-FOMUC Chadian troops that patrol the border area near Gor, the Chadian soldiers patrolling Bangui, but most of all the Chadian soldiers within the presidential lifeguard.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nine"></extension><space/>The CEMAC Force includes 121 Chadian soldiers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>There has been an almost uninterrupted French military presence in Central African Republic since independence, regulated through agreements between the two Governments. The French troops were allowed to be based in the country and to intervene in cases of destabilisation. This was particularly important during the cold war era, when Francophone Africa was regarded as a natural French sphere of influence.</paragraph><paragraph>Additionally, the strategic location of the country made it a more interesting location for military bases than its neighbours and<space/><link><target>Bouar</target></link><space/>and Bangui were hence two of the most important French bases abroad.</paragraph><paragraph>However, in 1997, following<space/><link><target>Lionel Jospin</target><part>Lionel Jospins</part></link><space/>expression Neither interference nor indifference, France came to adopt new strategic principles for its presence in Africa. This included a reduced permanent presence on the continent and an increased support to multilateral interventions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="five"><link type='external' href='http://www.hartford-hwp.com/archives/27c/377.html'><space/>New York Times: Out of Africa? Not the French, 12 January 2003</link></extension><space/>In Central African Republic, the Bouar base and the Bal Camp (at that time home to 1,400 French soldiers) in Bangui were shut down, as the French concentrated its African presence to<space/><link><target>Abidjan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dakar</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Djibouti</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Libreville</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>NDjamena</target></link><space/>and the deployment of a<space/><italics>Force daction rapide</italics>, based in France.<extension extension_name='ref' name="six"><link type='external' href='http://www.uca.edu.ar/esp/sec-fpoliticas/esp/docs-publicaciones/coleccion/ed-especial/02martin.pdf'><space/>Guy Martin: Frances African policy in transition: disengagement and redeployment, University of Virginia, 2000</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, due to the situation in the country, France has retained a military presence. During the mutinies, 2,400 French soldiers were patrolling the streets of Bangui. Their official task was to evacuate foreign citizens, but this did not prevent direct confrontations with the mutineers (resulting in French and mutineer casualties). The level of French involvement resulted in protests among the Central African population, since many took sided with the mutineers and accused France of defending a dictator against the peoples will. Voices were also heard in France where some blamed France for its protection of a discredited ruler, totally incapable of exerting power and managing the country.<extension extension_name='ref' name="seven"><link type='external' href='http://www.african-geopolitics.org/show.aspx?ArticleId=3466'><space/>Francis Laloupo: Centrafrique, un destin confisqu</link></extension><space/>After the mutinies in 1997, the MISAB was a multilateral force, but it was armed, equipped, trained and managed by France. The Chadian, Gabonese and<space/><link><target>Republic of the Congo</target><part>Congolese</part></link><space/>soldiers of the current<space/><italics>Force multinationale en Centrafrique (FOMUC)</italics><space/>mission in the country also enjoys logistical support from French soldiers.</paragraph><paragraph>A study carried out by the US Congressional Research Service reveals however that France has again increased its arms sales to Africa and during the 19982005 period, France was the leading supplier of arms to the continent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eight"><link type='external' href='http://www.americanchronicle.com/articles/viewArticle.asp?articleID=16055'><space/>William Church: Africa: France Increases Arms Sales and Intervention, November 6, 2006</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Components and units</heading><heading level='3'>Air Force</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Central African Republic Air Force</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Air Force</target></link><space/>is almost inoperable. Lack of funding has almost grounded the air force apart from an AS 350 Ecureuil delivered in 1987.<space/><link><target>Dassault Mirage F1</target><part>Mirage F1</part></link><space/>planes from the French Air Force regularly patrol troubled regions of the country and also participate in direct confrontations until they were withdrawn and retired in 2014.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fourteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.reliefweb.int/rw/RWFiles2007.nsf/FilesByRWDocUnidFilename/F7B3CC0AA2F7ADE585257273005FD542-Full_Report.pdf/$File/Full_Report.pdf'><space/>Inter-agency Mission to Birao (CAR): 16 to 23 January 2007</link></extension><space/>According to some sources, Boziz used the money he got from the mining concession in<space/><link><target>Bakouma</target></link><space/>to buy two old<space/><link><target>Mil Mi-8</target><part>MI 8</part></link><space/>helicopters from Ukraine and one<space/><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target></link>, built in the 1950s, from USA.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fifteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.afriqueeducation.com/archive/sommaire/article.php?id=390&amp;amp;version=216'><space/>Centrafrique : Boziz ou la chronique dune chute annonce, 2004</link></extension><space/>The air force operates otherwise 7 light aircraft, including a single helicopter:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead style="text-align: left;">Aircraft</tablehead><tablehead style="text-align: left;">Type</tablehead><tablehead style="text-align: left;">Versions</tablehead><tablehead style="text-align: left;">In service<extension extension_name='ref' name="awst_20070115">&quot;World Military Aircraft Inventory&quot;, Aerospace Source Book 2007,<space/><italics><link><target>Aviation Week &amp; Space Technology</target></link></italics>, January 15, 2007.</extension></tablehead><tablehead style="text-align: left;">Notes</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Aermacchi AL-60</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Utility</tablecell><tablecell>AL-60C-5 Conestoga</tablecell><tablecell>6-10</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Eurocopter AS350</target><part>Eurocopter AS 350 Ecureuil</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Utility helicopter</tablecell><tablecell>AS 350B</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Mil Mi-8</target><part>Mil Mi-8 Hip</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Transport Helicopter</tablecell><tablecell>Mi-8</tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>Unconfirmed</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Lockheed C-130 Hercules</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Transport</tablecell><tablecell>C-130</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>Unconfirmed</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Garde rpublicaine (GR)</heading><paragraph>GR consists of so-called patriots that fought for Boziz when he seized power in 2003 (mainly from the Gbaya tribe), together with soldiers from Chad. They are guilty of numerous assaults on the civil population, such as terror, aggression, sexual violence. Only a couple of months after Bozizs seizure of power, in May 2003, taxi and truck drivers conducted a strike against these outrages.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>New amphibious force</heading><paragraph>Boziz has created an<space/><link><target>Amphibious warfare</target><part>amphibious force</part></link>. It is called the Second Battalion of the Ground Forces and it patrols the<space/><link><target>Ubangi River</target><part>Ubangi river</part></link>. The staff of the sixth region in Bouali (mainly made up of members of the former presidents lifeguard) was transferred to the city of Mongoumba, located on the river. This city had previously been plundered by forces from MLC, that had crossed the border.<extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.sangonet.com/ActualiteC16/2bataillons-creation_FB.html'><space/>Actualit Centrafrique de sangonet Dossier 16: Le prsident Boziz cre deux nouveaux bataillons, April 25, 2003</link></extension><space/>The riverine patrol force has approximately a hundred personnel and operates seven patrol boats.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://articles.janes.com/articles/Janes-Sentinel-Security-Assessment-Central-Africa/Navy-Central-African-Republic.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Veteran Soldiers</heading><paragraph>A program for disarmament and reintegration of veteran soldiers is currently taking place. A national commission for the disarmament, demobilisation and reintegration was put in place in September 2004. The commission is in charge of implementing a program wherein approximately 7,500 veteran soldiers will be reintegrated in civil life and obtain education.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Discontinued groups and units that are no longer part of FACA</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Séléka</arg></template><space/><bold>Slka rebels</bold>: the French document<space/><italics>Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos</italics><space/>pictures<space/><link><target>Slka</target><part>Slka rebels</part></link><space/>as mercenaries under the command of president. In the documentary the<space/><link><target>Slka</target><part>Slka fighters</part></link><space/>seem to use great deal M16 rifles in their fight against<space/><link><target>Anti-balaka</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="thirteen"><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>FORSIDIR</arg></template><space/><bold>FORSIDIR:</bold><space/>The presidential lifeguard, Unit de scurit prsidentielle (USP), was in March 1998 transformed to the<space/><italics>Force spciale de dfense des institutions rpublicaines (FORSDIR)</italics>. In contrary to the army which consisted mainly of southerner Yakoma members and which thereby was unreliable for the northerner president this unit consisted of northerners loyal to the president. Before eventually being dissolved in January 2000, this highly controversial group became feared for their terror and troubled Patasss relation with important international partners, such as France. Of its 1,400 staff, 800 were subsequently reintegrated into FACA, under the command of the chief-of-staff. The remaining 400 recreated the USP (once again under the command of the chief-of-staff).<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>USP</arg></template><space/><bold>Unit de scurit prsidentielle (USP):<space/></bold><space/>USP was Patasss presidential guard before and after FORSIDIR. When he was overthrown by Boziz in 2003, the USP was dissolved and while some of the soldiers have been absorbed by FACA, others are believed to have joined the pro-Patass<space/><link><target>Democratic Front of the Central African People</target></link><space/>rebel group that is fighting FACA in the north of the country.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Patriots</arg><arg>Liberators</arg></template><space/><bold>The Patriots or Liberators:<space/></bold><space/>Accompanied Boziz when he seized power in March 2003. They are now a part of Bozizs lifeguard, the Garde rpublicaine, together with soldiers from Chad.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>OCRB</arg></template><space/><bold>Office central de rpression du banditisme (OCRB):</bold><space/>OCRB was a special unit within the police created to fight the looting after the army mutinies in 1996 and 1997. OCRB was guilty of numerous summary executions and arbitrary detentions, for which it has never been put on trial.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>MLPC Militia</arg></template><space/><bold>MLPC Militia:<space/></bold><space/>Le Mouvement de libration du peuple centrafricain (MLPC) was the former president, Patasss political party. Its militia was active already during the 1993 election, but was strengthened during the mutinies 1996 and 1997, particularly through its Karako militia. Its core consisted of Sara people from Chad and Central African Republic but during the mutinies it recruited many young people in Bangui.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>DRC Militia</arg></template><space/><bold>DRC Militia:</bold><space/>Rassemblement dmocratique centrafricain (RDC) is the party of General Kolingba who was president during the 1980s. Its militia is said to have camps in Mobaye and have bonds to former officials of Kolingbas cousin<space/><link><target>Mobutu Sese Seko</target></link><space/>in DR Congo.<extension extension_name='ref' name="two"></extension><space/>html?</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>'France donates equipment to CAR,'<space/><link><target>Jane's Defence Weekly</target></link>, 28 January 2004, p.&amp;nbsp;20. First of three planned battalions of new army completed training and guaduated 15 January [2004]. See also JDW 12 November 2003.</listitem><listitem>Africa Research Bulletin: Political, Social and Cultural Series, Volume 43 Issue 12, Pages 16909A 16910A, Published Online: 26 January 2007: Operation Boali, French aid mission to FACA</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Central African Republic and Small Arms<space/></arg><arg name="last">Berman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eric G.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="author2">Louisa N. Lombard<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Small Arms Survey]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Geneva<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">2-8288-0103-9<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ct.html'>CIA World Factbook</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/4007.htm'>US Department of State Bureau of African Affairs: Background note</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.girafprod.com/portfolio/centrafrique-au-coeur-du-chaos/'>&quot;Spcial investigation: Centrafrique, au cur du chaos&quot; Giraf Prod 13 jan 2014</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Central African Republic topics</target></template><template><target>Military of Africa</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>CIA World Factbook</target><arg name="year">2004</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Central African Republic</target></template><link><target>Category:Government of the Central African Republic</target></link><link><target>Category:Military in Africa</target></link><link><target>Category:Military of the Central African Republic</target></link></paragraph></article>