<article title='Book_of_Exodus'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the second book of the Torah and the Old Testament</arg><arg>the events related in the Torah</arg><arg>The Exodus</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Exodus (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Torah<space/></arg><arg>Pentateuch</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Book of Exodus</bold><space/>or, simply,<space/><bold>Exodus</bold><space/>(from<space/><link><target>Biblical Greek</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>,<space/><italics>exodos</italics>, meaning &quot;going out&quot;;<space/><template><target>lang-he</target><arg>שמות</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Sh'mot</italics>, &quot;Names&quot;), is the second book of the<space/><link><target>Torah</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Dozeman, p. 1.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The book tells how the<space/><link><target>Israelites</target></link><space/>leave slavery in Egypt through the strength of<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, the God who has chosen Israel as his people. Led by their prophet<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link><space/>they journey through the wilderness to<space/><link><target>Mount Sinai</target></link>, where Yahweh promises them the land of<space/><link><target>Canaan</target></link><space/>(the &quot;<link><target>Promised Land</target></link>&quot;) in return for their faithfulness. Israel enters into a<space/><link><target>biblical covenant</target><part>covenant</part></link><space/>with Yahweh who gives them their laws and instructions for the<space/><link><target>Tabernacle</target></link>, the means by which he will dwell with them and lead them to the land, and give them peace.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Traditionally<space/><link><target>Mosaic authorship</target><part>ascribed to Moses</part></link><space/>himself, modern scholarship sees the book as initially a product of the<space/><link><target>Babylonian captivity</target><part>Babylonian exile</part></link><space/>(6th century BCE), with final revisions in the<space/><link><target>Yehud Medinata</target><part>Persian post-exilic period</part></link><space/>(5th century BCE).<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnstone, p. 72.</extension><space/><link><target>Carol Meyers</target></link><space/>in her commentary on Exodus suggests that it is arguably the most important book in the Bible, as it presents the defining features of Israel's identity: memories of a past marked by hardship and escape, a binding covenant with God, who chooses Israel, and the establishment of the life of the community and the guidelines for sustaining it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, p. xv.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph>There is no agreement among scholars on the structure of Exodus. One strong possibility is that it is a<space/><link><target>diptych</target></link><space/>(i.e., divided into two parts), with the division between parts 1 and 2 at the<space/><link><target>crossing of the Red Sea</target></link><space/>or at the beginning of the<space/><link><target>theophany</target></link><space/>(appearance of God) in chapter 19.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, p. 17.</extension><space/>On this plan, the first part tells of God's rescue of his people from Egypt and their journey under his care to Sinai (chapters 119) and the second tells of the covenant between them (chapters 2040).<extension extension_name='ref'>Stuart, p. 19.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Summary</heading><paragraph>Egypt's<space/><link><target>Pharaoh of the Exodus</target><part>Pharaoh</part></link>, fearful of the<space/><link><target>Israelites</target></link>' numbers, orders that all newborn boys be thrown into the<space/><link><target>Nile</target></link>. A<space/><link><target>Levite</target></link><space/>woman saves her baby by setting him adrift on the river<space/><link><target>Nile</target></link><space/>in an<space/><link><target>ark of bulrushes</target></link>. Pharaoh's daughter finds the child, names him<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link>, and brings him up as her own. But Moses is aware of his origins, and one day, when grown, he kills an Egyptian overseer who is beating a<space/><link><target>Hebrew</target></link><space/>slave and has to flee into<space/><link><target>Midian</target></link>. There he marries the daughter of<space/><link><target>Jethro (Bible)</target><part>Jethro</part></link><space/>a priest of Midian, and encounters God in a<space/><link><target>burning bush</target></link>. Moses asks God for his name: God replies: &quot;<link><target>I Am that I Am</target><part>I AM that I AM</part></link>.&quot; God tells Moses to return to Egypt and lead the Hebrews into<space/><link><target>Canaan</target></link>, the land promised to<space/><link><target>Abraham</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Moses returns to Egypt and fails to convince the Pharaoh to release the Israelites. God smites the Egyptians with terrible plagues (<link><target>10_plagues</target><part>Plagues of Egypt</part></link>) including a river of blood, many frogs, and the death of first-born sons. Moses leads the Israelites out of bondage after a final chase scene ensues when the Pharaoh reneges on his coerced consent (<link><target>Parting_of_the_Red_Sea</target><part>Crossing the Red Sea</part></link>). The desert proves arduous, and the Israelites complain and long for Egypt, but God provides<space/><link><target>manna</target></link><space/>and miraculous water for them. The Israelites arrive at the mountain of God, where Moses' father-in-law Jethro visits Moses; at his suggestion Moses appoints<space/><link><target>Biblical judges</target><part>judges</part></link><space/>over Israel. God asks whether they will agree to be his people. They accept. The people gather at the foot of the mountain, and with thunder and lightning, fire and clouds of smoke, and the sound of trumpets, and the trembling of the mountain, God appears on the peak, and the people see the cloud and hear the voice [or possibly &quot;sound&quot;] of God. Moses and<space/><link><target>Aaron</target></link><space/>are told to ascend the mountain. God pronounces the<space/><link><target>Ten Commandments</target></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>Ethical Decalogue</target></link>) in the hearing of all Israel. Moses goes up the mountain into the presence of God, who pronounces the<space/><link><target>Covenant Code</target></link><space/>(a detailed code of ritual and civil law), and promises<space/><link><target>Canaan</target></link><space/>to them if they obey. Moses comes down the mountain and writes down God's words and the people agree to keep them. God calls Moses up the mountain with Aaron and the elders of Israel, and they feast in the presence of God. God calls Moses up the mountain to receive a set of stone<space/><link><target>tablet (religious)</target><part>tablets</part></link><space/>containing the law, and he and<space/><link><target>Joshua</target></link><space/>go up, leaving Aaron below.</paragraph><paragraph>God gives Moses instructions for the construction of the<space/><link><target>tabernacle (Judaism)</target><part>tabernacle</part></link><space/>so that God could dwell permanently among his chosen people, as well as instructions for the<space/><link><target>Priestly robe (Judaism)</target><part>priestly vestments</part></link>, the altar and its appurtenances, the procedure to be used to ordain the priests, and the daily sacrifices to be offered. Aaron is appointed as the first<space/><link><target>High Priest of Israel</target><part>hereditary high priest</part></link>. God gives Moses the two tablets of stone containing the words of the ten commandments, written with the<space/><link><target>Finger of God (Commandments)</target><part>&quot;finger of God&quot;</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Exodus</arg><arg>31:18</arg></template>;<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Deuteronomy</arg><arg>9:10</arg><arg>9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While Moses is with God, Aaron makes a<space/><link><target>golden calf</target></link>, which the people worship. God informs Moses of their<space/><link><target>apostasy</target></link><space/>and threatens to kill them all, but relents when Moses pleads for them. Moses comes down from the mountain, smashes the stone tablets in anger, and commands the<space/><link><target>Levites</target></link><space/>to massacre the unfaithful Israelites. God commands Moses to make two new tablets on which He will personally write the words that were on the first tablets. Moses ascends the mountain, God dictates the Ten Commandments (the<space/><link><target>Ritual Decalogue</target></link>), and Moses writes them on the tablets.</paragraph><paragraph>Moses descends from the mountain, and his face is transformed, so that from that time onwards he has to hide his face with a veil. Moses assembles the Hebrews and repeats to them the commandments he has received from God, which are to keep the<space/><link><target>Sabbath</target></link><space/>and to construct the Tabernacle. &quot;And all the construction of the Tabernacle of the Tent of Meeting was finished, and the children of Israel did according to everything that God had commanded Moses&quot;, and from that time God dwelt in the Tabernacle and ordered the travels of the Hebrews.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rembrandt Harmensz. van Rijn 079.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Moses</target></link><space/>with the Ten Commandments, by<space/><link><target>Rembrandt</target></link><space/>(1659)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authorship</heading><paragraph>Jewish and Christian tradition viewed<space/><link><target>Mosaic authorship</target><part>Moses as the author of Exodus</part></link><space/>and the entire Pentateuch, but by the end of the 19th century the increasing awareness of the discrepancies, inconsistencies, repetitions and other features of the Pentateuch had led scholars to abandon this idea.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, p. 16.</extension><space/>In approximate round dates, the process which produced Exodus and the Pentateuch probably began around 600 BCE when existing oral and written traditions were brought together to form books recognisable as those we know, reaching their final form as unchangeable sacred texts around 400 BCE.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McEntire</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">8</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Genre and sources</heading><paragraph>The story of<space/><link><target>the exodus</target></link><space/>is the<space/><link><target>Origin myth#Founding myth</target><part>founding myth</part></link><space/>of Israel, telling how the<space/><link><target>Israelites</target></link><space/>were delivered from slavery by<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link><space/>and therefore belong to him through the<space/><link><target>Mosaic covenant</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sparks</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">73</arg></template><space/>The Book of Exodus is not historical narrative in any modern sense:<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p. 7.</extension><space/>modern history writing requires the critical evaluation of sources, and does not accept God as a cause of events,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dozeman">Dozeman, p. 9.</extension><space/>but in Exodus, everything is presented as the work of God, who appears frequently in person, and the historical setting is only very hazily sketched.<extension extension_name='ref'>Houston, p. 68.</extension><space/>The purpose of the book is not to record what really happened, but to reflect the historical experience of the exile community in Babylon and later Jerusalem, facing foreign captivity and the need to come to terms with their understanding of God.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fretheim, p. 8.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although mythical elements are not so prominent in Exodus as in<space/><link><target>Book of Genesis</target><part>Genesis</part></link>, some writers claim ancient legends have an influence on the book's content: for example, the story of the infant Moses's salvation from the Nile may have some basis in an earlier legend of king<space/><link><target>Sargon of Akkad</target><part>Sargon</part></link>, while the story of the<space/><link><target>parting of the Red Sea</target></link><space/>trades on Mesopotamian<space/><link><target>creation myth</target><trail>ology</trail></link>. Similarly, the<space/><link><target>Covenant Code</target></link><space/>(the law code in Exodus 20:2223:33) has some similarities in both content and structure with the<space/><link><target>Laws of Hammurabi</target></link>. These influences serve to reinforce the conclusion that the Book of Exodus originated in the exiled Jewish community of 6th-century Babylon, but not all the sources are Mesopotamian: the story of Moses's flight to Midian following the murder of the Egyptian overseer may draw on the Egyptian<space/><italics><link><target>Story of Sinuhe</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kugler,Hartin, p. 74.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:David Roberts-IsraelitesLeavingEgypt 1828.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>&quot;Departure of the Israelites&quot;, by<space/><link><target>David Roberts (painter)</target><part>David Roberts</part></link>, 1829</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Salvation</heading><paragraph>Biblical scholars describe the Bible's theologically-motivated history writing as &quot;<link><target>salvation history</target></link>&quot;, meaning a history of God's saving actions that give identity to Israel the promise of offspring and land to the ancestors,<space/><link><target>the exodus</target></link><space/>from Egypt ( in which God saves Israel from slavery), the wilderness wandering, the revelation at Sinai, and the hope for the future life in the<space/><link><target>promised land</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dozeman"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theophany</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>theophany</target></link><space/>is a manifestation (appearance) of a god in the Bible, an appearance of the God of Israel, accompanied by storms the earth trembles, the mountains quake, the heavens pour rain, thunder peals and lightning flashes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dozeman, p. 4.</extension><space/>The theophany in Exodus begins &quot;the third day&quot; from their arrival at Sinai in chapter 19: Yahweh and the people meet at the mountain, God appears in the storm and converses with Moses, giving him the<space/><link><target>Ten Commandments</target></link><space/>while the people listen. The theophany is therefore a public experience of divine law.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dozeman, p. 427.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second half of Exodus marks the point at which, and describes the process through which, God's theophany becomes a permanent presence for Israel via the<space/><link><target>Tabernacle</target></link>. That so much of the book (chapters 2531, 3540) is spent describing the plans of the Tabernacle demonstrates the importance it played in the perception of<space/><link><target>Second Temple Judaism</target></link><space/>at the time of the text's redaction by the Priestly writers: the Tabernacle is the place where God is physically present, where, through the priesthood, Israel could be in direct, literal communion with him.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dempster, p. 107.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Covenant</heading><paragraph>The heart of Exodus is the<space/><link><target>Mosaic covenant</target><part>Sinaitic covenant</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wenham, p. 29.</extension><space/>A covenant is a legal document binding two parties to take on certain obligations towards each other.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, p. 148.</extension><space/>There are several covenants in the Bible, and in each case they exhibit at least some of the elements found in real-life treaties of the ancient Middle East: a preamble, historical prologue, stipulations, deposition and reading, list of witnesses, blessings and curses, and ratification by animal sacrifice.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, pp. 149150.</extension><space/>Biblical covenants, in contrast to Eastern covenants in general, are between a god, Yahweh, and a people, Israel, instead of between a strong ruler and a weaker vassal.<extension extension_name='ref'>Meyers, p. 150.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Election of Israel</heading><paragraph>Israel is elected for salvation because the &quot;sons of Israel&quot; are &quot;the firstborn son&quot; of the God of Israel, descended through Shem and Abraham to the chosen line of<space/><link><target>Jacob</target></link><space/>whose name is changed to Israel. The goal of the divine plan as revealed in Exodus is a return to humanity's state in<space/><link><target>Garden of Eden</target><part>Eden</part></link>, so that God can dwell with the Israelites as he had with<space/><link><target>Adam and Eve</target></link><space/>through the Ark and Tabernacle, which together form a model of the universe; in later<space/><link><target>Abrahamic religion</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>this came to be interpreted as Israel being the guardian of God's plan for humanity, to bring &quot;God's creation blessing to mankind&quot; begun in Adam.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dempster, p. 100.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contents according to Judaism's weekly Torah portions</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Crossing fo The Red Sea.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>&quot;Crossing of the Red Sea&quot;,<space/><link><target>Nicholas Poussin</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Weekly Torah portion</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Shemot (parsha)</target><part>Shemot</part></link>, on Exodus 15: Affliction in Egypt, Moses is found and called, Pharaoh</listitem><listitem><link><target>Va'eira (parsha)</target><part>Va'eira</part></link>, on Exodus 69: Plagues 1 to 7 of Egypt</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bo (parsha)</target><part>Bo</part></link>, on Exodus 1013: Last plagues of Egypt, first Passover</listitem><listitem><link><target>Beshalach (parsha)</target><part>Beshalach</part></link>, on Exodus 1317: Parting the Sea, water, manna, Amalek</listitem><listitem><link><target>Yitro (parsha)</target><part>Yitro</part></link>, on Exodus 1820: Jethros advice, The Ten Commandments</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mishpatim (parsha)</target><part>Mishpatim</part></link>, on Exodus 2124: The Covenant Code</listitem><listitem><link><target>Terumah (parsha)</target><part>Terumah</part></link>, on Exodus 2527: God's instructions on the Tabernacle and furnishings</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tetzaveh (parsha)</target><part>Tetzaveh</part></link>, on Exodus 2730: God's instructions on the first priests</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ki Tissa</target></link>, on Exodus 3034: Census, anointing oil, golden calf, stone tablets, Moses radiant</listitem><listitem><link><target>Vayakhel (parsha)</target><part>Vayakhel</part></link>, on Exodus 3538: Israelites collect gifts, make the Tabernacle and furnishings</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pekudei (parsha)</target><part>Pekudei</part></link>, on Exodus 3840: The Tabernacle is set up and filled</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>The Exodus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ketef Hinnom</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Moses</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Song of the sea</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tabernacle (Judaism)</target><part>Tabernacle</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of films based on the Bible#Moses and the 40 years in the desert</target><part>Film adaptations of the Book of Exodus</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of the Jews in Egypt#Ancient times</target><part>History of the Jews in Ancient Egypt</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Childs</arg><arg name="first">Brevard S</arg><arg name="title">The book of Exodus</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664229689</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Dempster</arg><arg name="first">Stephen G</arg><arg name="author-link">Stephen Dempster</arg><arg name="title">Dominion and dynasty</arg><arg name="publisher">InterVarsity Press</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780830826155</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Dozeman</arg><arg name="first">Thomas B</arg><arg name="title">Commentary on Exodus</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802826176</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Fretheim</arg><arg name="first">Terence E</arg><arg name="title">Exodus</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664237349</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Houston</arg><arg name="first">Walter J</arg><arg name="chapter">Exodus</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">John Barton</arg><arg name="title">Oxford Bible Commentary</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">9780198755005</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Johnstone</arg><arg name="first">William D</arg><arg name="chapter">Exodus</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">James D. G. Dunn, John William Rogerson</arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans Bible Commentary</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802837110</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">Kugler</arg><arg name="first1">Robert</arg><arg name="last2">Hartin</arg><arg name="first2">Patrick</arg><arg name="title">An Introduction to the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802846365</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">McEntire</arg><arg name="first">Mark</arg><arg name="title">Struggling with God: An Introduction to the Pentateuch</arg><arg name="publisher">Mercer University Press</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780881461015</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Meyers</arg><arg name="first">Carol</arg><arg name="author-link">Carol Meyers</arg><arg name="title">Exodus</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780521002912</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sparkes
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kenton L.
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Dozeman
</arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Thomas B.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Methods for Exodus
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Genre Criticism
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv
</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Stuart</arg><arg name="first">Douglas K</arg><arg name="title">Exodus</arg><arg name="publisher">B&H Publishing Group</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780805401028</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Wenham</arg><arg name="first">Gordon</arg><arg name="title">The book of Leviticus</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802825223</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Translations of Exodus</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Exodus%201&amp;amp;version=ESV'>Exodus at Bible Gateway</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Exodus (Bible)</arg></template><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Book of Exodus</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et0201.htm'>Exodus at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society translation)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bible.ort.org/books/pentd2.asp?ACTION=displaypage&amp;amp;BOOK=2&amp;amp;CHAPTER=1'>Exodus (The Living Torah)</link><space/>Rabbi<space/><link><target>Aryeh Kaplan</target></link>'s translation and commentary at Ort.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/article.asp?aid=8161'>Shemot Exodus (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0201.htm'>''Shmot''</link><space/>(Original<space/><link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Torah|Pentateuch]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Genesis|Genesis]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Leviticus|Leviticus]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template><template><target>Ancient Near East</target></template><template><target>Book of Exodus</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Book Of Exodus</target></template><link><target>Category:Book of Exodus</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Torah books</target><part>2</part></link><link><target>Category:Books in political philosophy</target></link><link><target>Category:Tabernacle and Temples in Jerusalem</target></link></paragraph></article>