<article title='Economy_of_the_Czech_Republic'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox economy</target><arg name="country"><space/>Czech Republic
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Pankrácká pláň 3.jpg
</arg><arg name="width"><space/>270px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Pankrác financial district in [[Prague]]
</arg><arg name="currency"><space/>[[Czech koruna]] (Kč or CZK)
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>calendar year
</arg><arg name="organs"><space/>EU, [[World Trade Organization|WTO]] (via EU membership) and [[OECD]]
</arg><arg name="gdp rank"><space/>[[List of countries by GDP (PPP) per capita|38th]] ([[Purchasing Power Parity|PPP]])
</arg><arg name="gdp"><space/>{{increase}} $314.6 billion [[Purchasing Power Parity|PPP]] (2014 IMF) ; {{increase}}$205,7 billion nominal 
</arg><arg name="growth"><space/>{{increase}} 4.4% (Q2 2015 [https://www.czso.cz/csu/czso/cri/predbezny-odhad-hdp-2-ctvrtleti-2015])
</arg><arg name="per capita"><space/>{{increase}} $29,925 [[Purchasing Power Parity|PPP]] (2014)
</arg><arg name="per capita"><space/>{{increase}} $19,563 [[Nominal|Nom]] (2014)
</arg><arg name="sectors"><space/>agriculture: 1.8%, industry: 39.6%, services: 58.6% (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="inflation"><space/>{{increase}} 0.4% (Q2 2015)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="poverty"><space/>8,6% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="gini"><space/>26.4 (2012)
</arg><arg name="labor"><space/>5.304 million (2013 est.)
</arg><arg name="occupations"><space/>agriculture: 2.6%, industry: 37.4%, services: 60% (2012)
</arg><arg name="unemployment"><space/>{{decrease}}6%<ref name</arg><arg name="average gross salary"><space/>[[Czech koruna|CZK]] 26,287 / €972 / $1,299 per month (2015 Q2)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="industries"><space/>motor vehicles, metallurgy, machinery and equipment, glass, armaments
</arg><arg name="edbr"><space/>44th<ref name</arg><arg name="exports"><space/>{{increase}} $161.4 billion (2013 est. CIA)
</arg><arg name="export-goods"><space/>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials and fuel, chemicals 
</arg><arg name="export-partners"><space/>{{flag|Germany}} 31.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Slovakia}} 9.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Poland}} 6.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|France}} 5.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|United Kingdom}} 4.9%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Austria}} 4.7%<space/><br><space/>(2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="imports"><space/>{{increase}}$143.4 billion (2013 est. CIA)
</arg><arg name="import-goods"><space/>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials and fuels, chemicals 
</arg><arg name="import-partners"><space/>{{flag|Germany}} 29.5%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Poland}} 7.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Slovakia}} 7.4%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|China}} 6.3%<space/><br>{{flag|Netherlands}} 5.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Russia}} 5.3%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Austria}} 4.3% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="gross external debt"><space/>{{decrease}}$90.18 billion (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="debt"><space/>{{increase}}46.8% of GDP (1Q 2013 est.)
</arg><arg name="revenue"><space/>{{decrease}}$81.08 billion (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="expenses"><space/>{{decrease}}$87.25 billion (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="foreign reserves"><space/>{{decrease}}US$35.26 billion (31 December 2012)
</arg><arg name="aid"><space/>$2.4bn from EU funds (2004–06){{Citation needed|date</arg><arg name="credit"><space/>AA (Domestic)<br>AA- (Foreign)<br>AA+ (T&C Assessment)<br>([[Standard & Poor's]])<ref>{{cite web |title</arg><arg name="cianame"><space/>ez
</arg><arg name="spelling"><space/>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CBNod.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Czech National Bank in<space/><link><target>Prague</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Average brutto wage Czech Republic 1985-2008.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Average gross wage Czech Republic 19852008</part></link>The<space/><bold><link><target>Czech Republic</target></link></bold><space/>has one of the most developed industrialized<space/><link><target>economic system</target></link><space/>of the countries in<space/><link><target>Central Europe</target><part>Central</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Eastern Europe</target></link>. The country has quickly become the most stable and prosperous of the post-Communist states of Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2014, the Czech<space/><link><target>GDP per capita</target></link><space/>at purchasing power parity was $29,925.,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2015/01/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy</arg><arg name="title">International Monetary Fund's Report for Selected Countries and Subjects</arg><arg name="publisher">[[International Monetary Fund]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>and $19,563 at nominal value.</paragraph><paragraph>The principal industries are heavy and general machine-building,<space/><link><target>Iron (material)</target><part>iron</part></link><space/>and steel production, metalworking,<space/><link><target>chemistry</target><part>chemical</part></link><space/>production,<space/><link><target>electronics</target></link>, transportation equipment, textiles, glass, brewing, china,<space/><link><target>ceramic</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>pharmaceutical</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Its main agricultural products are<space/><link><target>sugar beet</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>fodder</target><part>fodder root</part><trail>s</trail></link>, potatoes, wheat, and<space/><link><target>hops</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Economy of Czechoslovakia (disambiguation){{!}}Economy of Czechoslovakia</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The country's strong industrial tradition dates back to the 19th century, when<space/><link><target>Bohemia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Moravia</target></link><space/>were the economic heartland of the<space/><link><target>Austro-Hungarian Empire</target></link>. The Czech lands produced a majority (about 70%) of all industrial goods in the Austro-Hungarian Empire, some of which were almost monopolistic. The Czechoslovak crown was introduced in April 1919. Introduced at a 1:1 ratio to the Austro-Hungarian currency, it became one of the most stable currencies in Europe.<space/><link><target>First Czechoslovak Republic</target><part>The First Republic</part></link><space/>became one of the 10 most developed countries of the world (behind the U.S., Canada, Australia, Switzerland, Argentina, Britain, France, Sweden and Belgium).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.penize.cz/ekonomika/244016-nas-ucet-za-komunismus</arg><arg name="title">Náš účet za komunismus</arg><arg name="date">18 October 2012</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The consequences of the<space/><link><target>Munich Agreement</target></link><space/>were disastrous for the economy. After the occupation and forced subordination of the economy to German economic interests, the crown was officially pegged to the mark at a ratio of 1:10, even though the unofficial exchange rate was 1 to 6-7 and Germans immediately started buying Czech goods in large quantities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">History of Czechoslovak currency</arg><arg name="url">http://www.zlate-mince.cz/OM9_Ceskoslovenska_mena.htm</arg><arg name="website">zlate-mince.cz</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 July 2014</arg><arg name="language">Czech</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In accordance with<space/><link><target>Stalinism</target><part>Stalin</part></link>'s development policy of planned interdependence, all the economies of the socialist countries were tightly linked to that of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Czechoslovakia</target></link><space/>was the most prosperous country in the<space/><link><target>Eastern Bloc</target></link>, however it continued to lag further behind the rest of the developed world. With the disintegration of the communist economic alliance in 1991, Czech manufacturers lost their traditional markets among former communist countries in the east.</paragraph><paragraph>Today, this heritage is both an<space/><link><target>asset</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>liability (financial accounting)</target><part>liability</part></link>. The Czech Republic has a well-educated population and a well-developed infrastructure<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>19891995</heading><paragraph>The &quot;<link><target>Velvet Revolution</target></link>&quot; in 1989, offered a chance for profound and sustained political and economic reform. Signs of economic resurgence began to appear in the wake of the<space/><link><target>shock therapy (economics)</target><part>shock therapy</part></link><space/>that the<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target></link><space/>(IMF) labelled the &quot;<italics>big bang</italics>&quot; of January 1991. Since then, consistent liberalization and astute economic management has led to the removal of 95% of all price controls, low unemployment, a positive<space/><link><target>balance of payments</target></link><space/>position, a stable<space/><link><target>exchange rate</target></link>, a shift of exports from former<space/><link><target>Eastern bloc</target><part>communist economic bloc</part></link><space/>markets to Western Europe, and relatively low<space/><link><target>foreign debt</target></link>. Inflation has been higher than in some other countries mostly in the 10% range<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template><space/>and the government has run consistent modest<space/><link><target>budget deficit</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Two government priorities have been strict<space/><link><target>fiscal policy</target><part>fiscal policies</part></link><space/>and creating a good climate for incoming investment in the republic. Following a series of currency<space/><link><target>devaluation</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>Czech koruna</target><part>crown</part></link><space/>has remained stable in relation to the US$.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template><space/>The Czech crown became fully<space/><link><target>convertibility</target><part>convertible</part></link><space/>for most business purposes in late 1995.</paragraph><paragraph>In order to stimulate the economy and attract foreign partners, the government has revamped the legal and administrative structure governing investment. With the breakup of the Soviet Union, the country, till that point highly dependent on exports to the USSR, had to make a radical shift in economic outlook: away from the East, and towards the West. This necessitated the restructuring of existing banking and telecommunications facilities, as well as adjusting commercial laws and practices to fit Western standards. Further minimizing reliance on a single major partner, successive Czech governments have welcomed U.S. investment (amongst others) as a counterbalance to the strong economic influence of Western European partners, especially of their powerful neighbour, Germany. Although<space/><link><target>foreign direct investment</target></link><space/>(FDI) runs in uneven cycles, with a 12.9% share of total FDI between 1990 and March 1998, the U.S. was the third-largest foreign investor in the Czech economy, behind Germany and the Netherlands.</paragraph><paragraph>Progress toward creating a stable investment climate was recognized when the Czech Republic became the first post-communist country to receive an investment-grade credit rating by international credit institutions.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The republic boasts a flourishing consumer production sector and has<space/><link><target>privatization</target><part>privatized</part></link><space/>most state-owned heavy industries through the<space/><link><target>voucher privatization</target></link><space/>system. Under the system, every citizen was given the opportunity to buy, for a moderate price, a book of vouchers that represents potential shares in any state-owned company. The voucher holders could then invest their vouchers, increasing the capital base of the chosen company, and creating a nation of citizen share-holders. This is in contrast to Russian privatization, which consisted of sales of communal assets to private companies rather than share-transfer to citizens. The effect of this policy has been dramatic. Under communism, state ownership of businesses was estimated to be 97%.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template><space/>Privatization through restitution of real estate to the former owners was largely completed in 1992. By 1998, more than 80% of enterprises were in private hands. Now completed,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template><space/>the program has made Czechs, who own shares of each of the Czech companies, one of the highest per-capita share owners in the world.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2009</arg></template><space/></paragraph><heading level='3'>19952000</heading><paragraph>The republic's economic transformation was far from complete. Political and financial crises in 1997, shattered the Czech Republic's image as one of the most stable and prosperous of post-Communist states. Delays in enterprise restructuring and failure to develop a well-functioning capital market played major roles in Czech economic troubles, which culminated in a currency crisis in May. The formerly pegged currency was forced into a floating system as investors sold their Korunas faster than the government could buy them. This followed a worldwide trend to divest from developing countries that year. Investors also worried the republic's economic transformation was far from complete. Another complicating factor was the current account deficit, which reached nearly 8% of GDP.</paragraph><paragraph>In response to the crisis, two<space/><link><target>austerity</target></link><space/>packages were introduced later in the spring (called vernacularly &quot;The Packages&quot;), which cut government spending by 2.5% of GDP. Growth dropped to 0.3% in 1997, 2.3% in 1998, and 0.5% in 1999. The government established a restructuring agency in 1999 and launched a revitalization program to spur the sale of firms to foreign companies. Key priorities included accelerating legislative convergence with EU norms, restructuring enterprises, and privatising banks and utilities. The economy, fueled by increased export growth and investment, was expected to recover by 2000.</paragraph><heading level='3'>20002005</heading><paragraph>Growth in 200005 was supported by exports to the EU, primarily to Germany, and a strong recovery of foreign and domestic investment. Domestic demand is playing an ever more important role in underpinning growth as interest rates drop and the availability of credit cards and mortgages increases. Current account deficits of around 5% of GDP are beginning to decline as demand for Czech products in the European Union increases. Inflation is under control. Recent accession to the EU gives further impetus and direction to structural reform. In early 2004 the government passed increases in the Value Added Tax (VAT) and tightened eligibility for social benefits with the intention to bring the public finance gap down to 4% of GDP by 2006, but more difficult pension and healthcare reforms will have to wait until after the next elections. Privatization of the state-owned telecommunications firm<space/><link><target>esk Telecom</target></link><space/>took place in 2005. Intensified restructuring among large enterprises, improvements in the financial sector, and effective use of available EU funds should strengthen output growth.</paragraph><heading level='3'>20052010</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Czech republic export 2007.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Czech republic export 2007</part></link><link><target>File:Czech republic import 2007.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Czech republic import 2007</part></link>Growth continued in the first years of the EU membership. The credit portion of the<space/><link><target>Financial crisis of 20072010</target></link><space/>did not affect the Czech Republic much, mostly due to its stable banking sector which has learned its lessons during a smaller crisis in the late 1990s and became much more cautious. As a fraction of the GDP, the Czech public debt is among the smallest ones in Central and Eastern Europe. Moreover, unlike many other post-communist countries, an overwhelming majority of the household debt over 99% is denominated in the local Czech currency. That's why the country wasn't affected by the shrunken money supply in the U.S. dollars.</paragraph><paragraph>However, as a large exporter, the economy was sensitive to the decrease of the demand in Germany and other trading partners. In the middle of 2009, the annual drop of the GDP for 2009 was estimated around 3% or 4.3%,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.earthtimes.org/articles/show/278536,czech-economy-to-shrink-by-43-per-cent-in-2009.html</arg><arg name="title">Earth Times: show/278536,czech-economy-to-shrink-by-43-per-cent-in-2009.html</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>a relatively modest decrease. The impact of the economic crisis may have been limited by the existence of the national currency that temporarily weakened in H1 of 2009, simplifying the life of the exporters.</paragraph><heading level='3'>20102015</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CZexport2013.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>The Czech Republic Export Treemap by Product (2013) from<space/><link type='external' href='http://atlas.cid.harvard.edu/explore/tree_map/export/cze/all/show/2013/'>Harvard Atlas of Economic Complexity</link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CZimport2013.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>The Czech Republic Import Treemap by Product (2013) from<space/><link type='external' href='http://atlas.cid.harvard.edu/explore/tree_map/import/cze/all/show/2013/'>Harvard Atlas of Economic Complexity</link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>From the<space/><link><target>Great Recession</target><part>financial crisis of 20072010</part></link>, Czech Republic is in stagnation or decreasing of GDP. Some commenters and economists criticising fiscally conservative policy of Petr Neas' right-wing government, especially criticising ex-minister of finance,<space/><link><target>Miroslav Kalousek</target></link>. Miroslav Kalousek in a 2008 interview, as minister of finance in the center-right government of Mirek Topolnek, said &quot;Czech Republic will not suffer by financial crisis&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://hn.ihned.cz/c1-28777680-mozna-vas-zklamu-krize-nam-nehrozi</arg><arg name="title">Miroslav Kalousek: Moná vás zklamu: krize nám nehrozí</arg><arg name="work">Hospodáøské noviny</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In September 2008, Miroslav Kalousek formed state budget with projection of 5% GDP increase in 2009. In 2009 and 2010, Czech Republic suffered strong economical crisis and GDP decreased by 4,5%. From 2009 to 2012, Czech Republic suffered highest state budget deficits in history of independent Czech Republic. From 2008 to 2012, the public debt of Czech Republic increased by 18,9%. Most decrease of industrial output was in construction industry (-25% in 2009, -15,5% in 2013). From 4Q 2009 to 1Q 2013, GDP decreased by 7,8%.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2012, Czech government increased<space/><link><target>VAT</target></link>. Basic VAT was increased from 20% in 2012 to 21% in 2013 and reduced VAT increased from 14% to 15% in 2013. Small enterprises sales decreased by 21% from 2012 to 2013 as result of increasing VAT.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.kurzy.cz/makroekonomika/sluzby/</arg><arg name="title">Sluby - vývoj treb ve slubách v ÈR, 2015</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Patria.cz predicting sales stagnation and mild increase in 2013.Another problem is foreign trade. The Czech Republic is considered an export economy (the Czech Republic has strong machinery and automobile industries), however in 2013, foreign trade rapidly decreased which led to many other problems and increase of state budget deficit.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2013, Czech National Bank, central bank, implemented controversial monetary step. To increase export and employment, CNB wilfully deflated Czech Crown (CZK), which inflation increased from 0.2% in November 2013, to 1.3% in 1Q 2014.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2014, GDP in the Czech Republic increased by 2% and is predicted to increase by 2.7% in 2015.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2015, Czech Republic's economy grew by 4,2% and it's the fastest growing economy in the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ceskatelevize.cz/ct24/ekonomika/314126-ceska-ekonomika-roste-nejrychleji-v-cele-eu/</arg><arg name="title">Česká ekonomika roste nejrychleji v celé EU</arg><arg name="publisher">[[ČT24]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 June 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>On 29 May 2015, it was announced that growth of the Czech economy has increased from calculated 3,9% to 4,2%.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.czso.cz/csu/czso/cri/tvorba-a-uziti-hdp-1-ctvrtleti-2015</arg><arg name="title">
Tvorba a užití HDP - 1. čtvrtletí 2015, Rychlejší růst české ekonomiky potvrzen (in Czech)</arg><arg name="publisher">Czech Statistical Office</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:GDPgrowthrates1q2015.png</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>left</part><part>GDP growth rates of 1st quarter 2015 of the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>countries.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>2015present</heading><paragraph>On August 2015, Czech<space/><link><target>GDP growth</target></link><space/>was 4,4%, making the Czech economy the highest growing in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2015-08-14/czechs-power-eu-s-fastest-gdp-growth-as-romania-hungary-stumble</arg><arg name="title">Czechs Power EU’s Fastest GDP Growth as Romania, Hungary Stumble</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Bloomberg News|Bloomberg Business]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 August 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Energy</heading><paragraph>The Czech Republic is reducing its dependence on highly polluting low-grade<space/><link><target>brown coal</target></link><space/>as a source of energy.<space/><link><target>Nuclear power</target></link><space/>currently provides about 30% of total power needs, and its share is projected to increase to 40%. Natural gas is procured from Russian<space/><link><target>Gazprom</target></link><space/>(roughly three-fourths of domestic consumption) and from Norwegian companies (most of the remaining one-fourth). Russian gas is imported via Ukraine (<link><target>Druzhba pipeline</target><part>Friendship pipeline</part></link>), Norwegian gas is transported through Germany. The gas consumption (approx. 100 TWh in 2003-5) is almost two times higher than the electricity consumption. South Moravia has a<space/><link><target>Oil and gas deposits in the Czech Republic</target><part>small amount of oil and gas deposits</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Statistical indicators</heading><paragraph><italics>From the<space/><link><target>CIA World Factbook</target></link><space/>2015</italics></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CzechGDP-AGR.png</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Czech Republic</target></link><space/>GDP Annual Growth Rate from 2005 to 2015</part></link><link><target>File:HDP CR.png</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Change of GDP per capita in CZK (1995-2011)</part></link><bold>GDP (pp.):</bold><space/>$299.7 billion (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>GDP Growth:</bold><space/>2.5% (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>GDP per capita (pp.):</bold><space/>$28,400 (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>GDP per capita (nom.):</bold><space/>$19,563 (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>GDP by sector:</bold><italics>Agriculture:</italics><space/>2.9%<italics>Industry:</italics><space/>38.7%<italics>Services:</italics><space/>60% (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Inflation:</bold><space/>0.5% (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Labour Force:</bold><space/>5.416 million (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Unemployment:</bold><space/>6.7% (May 2015)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ceskatelevize.cz/ct24/ekonomika/311166-pocet-nezamestnanych-klesl-pod-pul-milionu/'>Poet nezamstnanch klesl pod pl milionu</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Industrial production growth rate:</bold><space/>4% (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Household income or consumption by percentage share:</bold><space/>(2012)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>lowest 10%:</italics><space/>1.5%</listitem><listitem><italics>highest 10%:</italics><space/>29.1%</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Public Debt:</bold><space/>43.5% GDP (2014)</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Trade and finance</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Europe-GDP-PPP-per-capita-map.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>European GDP (PPP) per capita in 2012</part></link><bold>Exports:</bold><space/>$147.3 billion<italics>Export goods:</italics><space/>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials, fuel, chemicals (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Imports:</bold><space/>$135.1 billion<italics>Import goods:</italics><space/>machinery and transport equipment, raw materials and fuels, chemicals (2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Current Account balance:</bold><space/>-$4,533,000 (2007)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Export partners:</bold><space/>Germany 31.7%, Slovakia 9%, Poland 6%, France 5%, UK 4.9%, Austria 4.6% (2013)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Import partners:</bold><space/>Germany 30.3%, Poland 8.1%, Slovakia 7.2%, China 5.8%, Netherlands 5.5%, Russia 5.1%, Austria 4.1% (2013)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Reserves:</bold><space/>$59.15 billion (31 December 2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Foreign Direct Investment:</bold><space/>$86.75 billion (2007)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Czech Investment Abroad:</bold><space/>$6.058 billion (2007)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>External debt:</bold><space/>$116.1 billion (31 December 2014)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Value of Publicly Traded Shares:</bold><space/>$48.6 billion (2006)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Exchange rates:</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>koruny (K) per US$1</italics><space/>24.67 (May 2015), 18.75 (December 2010),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Economy of the Czech Republic"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ceemarket.com/CEE_basic_data.shtml</arg><arg name="title">CEE Basic Data - Key economic indicators and forecasts</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>18.277 (2007), 23.957 (2005), 25.7 (2004), 28.2 (2003), 32.7 (2002), 38.0 (2001), 38.6 (2001), 34.6 (1999), 32.3 (1998), 31.7 (1997), 27.1 (1996), 26.5 (1995)</listitem><listitem><italics>koruny (K) per EUR1</italics><space/>27.33 (May 2015), 25.06 (December 2010)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Economy of the Czech Republic"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Energy (<italics>production and consumption</italics>)</heading><paragraph><bold>Electricity production:</bold><space/>81.71 billion kWh (2012)<italics>Electricity production by source:</italics></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>fossil fuel:</italics><space/>75.54%</listitem><listitem><italics>hydro:</italics><space/>2.55%</listitem><listitem><italics>nuclear:</italics><space/>20.37%</listitem><listitem><italics>other:</italics><space/>1.54% (1998)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Electricity consumption:</bold><space/>70.45 billion kWh (2012)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Electricity exports:</bold><space/>27.46 billion kWh (2013)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Electricity imports:</bold><space/>10.57 billion kWh (2013)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Oil production:</bold><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18030</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2005)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Oil consumption:</bold><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>213000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2005 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Oil exports:</bold><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20930</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2004)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Oil imports:</bold><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>203700</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(2004)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Oil proved reserves:</bold><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15000000</arg><arg>oilbbl</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>(1 January 2006)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural gas production:</bold><space/>252 million m (2013 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural gas consumption:</bold><space/>8.477 billion m (2013 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural gas exports:</bold><space/>8 million m (2013 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural gas imports:</bold><space/>8.479 billion m (2013 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural gas proved reserves:</bold><space/>4.276 billion m (1 January 2014 est.)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural resources:</bold><space/>coal, timber, lignite, uranium, magnesite.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Agriculture products:</bold>wheat, rye, oats, corn, barley, potatoes, sugar beets, hops, fruit; pigs, cattle, poultry, horses; forest products</paragraph><heading level='2'>IT and Telecommunications</heading><paragraph><bold>Households with access to fixed and mobile telephone access</bold><extension extension_name='ref' name="ceeitandtelecom.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.ceeitandtelecom.com/CEE_ICT_data.shtml'>IT and telecommunications in Central and Eastern Europe</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.ceeitandtelecom.com/CEE_ICT_data.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="date">20131011091725<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>landline telephone</italics><space/>25% (2009)<list type='bullet'><listitem>according to the Czech Statistical Office:<extension extension_name='ref' name="czso.cz">http://www.czso.cz/csu/2013edicniplan.nsf/t/0E002419AC/$File/0001132115.xls</extension><space/>55,2% (2005); 31,1% (2008); 27,6% (2009); 24,2% (2010); 23,4% (2011); 21,8% (2012)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><italics>mobile telephone</italics><space/>94% (2009)<list type='bullet'><listitem>according to the Czech Statistical Office:<extension extension_name='ref' name="czso.cz"></extension><space/>81,2% (2005); 92,4% (2008); 94,6% (2009); 95,6% (2010); 96,2% (2011); 97,0% (2012)</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Individuals with mobile telephone access</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>according to the Czech Statistical Office:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.czso.cz/csu/2013edicniplan.nsf/t/0E0024189E/$File/0001132118.xls</extension><space/>75,8% (2005); 90,6% (2009); 93,9% (2011); 96,0% (2012); 96,0% (2013)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Broadband penetration rate</bold><extension extension_name='ref' name="ceeitandtelecom.com"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>fixed broadband</italics><space/>19.1% (2010)</listitem><listitem><italics>mobile broadband</italics><space/>3.5% (2010)</listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Individuals using computer and internet</bold><extension extension_name='ref' name="ceeitandtelecom.com"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>computer</italics><space/>67% (2009)<list type='bullet'><listitem>according to the Czech Statistical Office:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.czso.cz/csu/2013edicniplan.nsf/t/0E0024193D/$File/0001132119.xls</extension><space/>42,0% (2005); 59,2% (2009); 64,1% (2010); 67,1% (2011); 69,5% (2012); 70,2% (2013)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><italics>internet</italics><space/>64% (2009)<list type='bullet'><listitem>according to the Czech Statistical Office:<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.czso.cz/csu/2013edicniplan.nsf/t/0E002418A7/$File/0001132120.xls</extension><space/>32,1% (2005); 55,9% (2009); 61,8% (2010); 65,5% (2011); 69,5% (2012); 70,4% (2013)</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Czech Republic</arg><arg>Economics</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Healthcare in the Czech Republic</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>koda Works</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Czech National Bank</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Prague Stock Exchange</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Economy of Europe</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Resources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Statistick roenka esk republiky</italics><space/>(<italics>Statistical Yearbook of the Czech Republic</italics>) by the<space/><link><target>Czech Statistical Office</target></link>. The current line is published annually since 1957. Recent yearbooks can be read<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.praha.czso.cz/eng/redakce.nsf/i/statistical_yearbooks_of_the_czech_republic'>online</link><space/>(in Czech and English).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Czechoslovakia</target></link><space/>published its first statistical yearbook in 1920. Historically used names:<space/><italics>Statistick pruka Republiky eskoslovensk</italics>,<space/><italics>Statistick roenka Protektortu echy a Morava</italics><space/>(during the<space/><link><target>German occupation of Czechoslovakia</target><part>occupation</part></link>) and<space/><italics>Statistick roenka eskoslovensk socialistick republiky</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Statistics about the<space/><link><target>Czech lands</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Austria-Hungary</target></link><space/>were collected by<space/><italics>Zemsk statistick ad Krlovstv eskho</italics><space/>(<italics>Provincial Statistical Office of the Czech Kingdom</italics>) founded in 1897. Two detailed books (in Czech and German) were published in 1909 and 1913.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oecd.org/eco/surveys/economic-survey-czech-republic.htm'>OECD Economic Survey of the Czech Republic</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eng.kurzy.cz/cnb/'>Czech economic indicators</link><space/>Latest indicators collected by Czech national bank</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oecd.org/czech/'>OECD's Czech Republic country Web site</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20080530205253<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.czech.cz/en/economy-business-science/doing-business/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Doing business in Czech Republic<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.czso.cz/eng/csu.nsf/aktualniinformace'>Current economic data</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Wayback</target><arg name="date">20080611164507<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.czech.cz/en/economy-business-science/general-information/economy-development-and-potential/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Economy: Development and potential<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ceemarket.com/CEE_basic_data.shtml'>Economy of the Czech Republic Annual Trends</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wits.worldbank.org/CountryProfile/Country/CZE/Year/2012/Summary'>World Bank Summary Trade Statistics Czech Republic</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Czech Republic topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Members of the European Union (EU)</target></template><template><target>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</target></template><template><target>Economy of Europe</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Economy of the Czech Republic</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:European Union member economies</target><part>Czech Republic</part></link><link><target>Category:Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development member economies</target><part>Czech Republic</part></link></paragraph></article>