<article title='Cogito_ergo_sum'><paragraph><template><target>italic title</target></template><template><target>Descartes</target></template><bold><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Cogito ergo sum</arg></template></italics></bold><template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"capitalization"</arg></template><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/><link><target>philosophy</target><part>philosophical</part></link><space/><link><target>proposition</target></link><space/>by<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>[[René Descartes]]</arg></template><space/>usually translated into English as &quot;<bold>I think, therefore I am</bold>&quot;. The phrase originally appeared in<space/><link><target>French language</target><part>French</part></link><space/>as<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>''{{nowrap|je pense,}} {{nowrap|donc je suis}}''</arg></template><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Discourse on the Method</target></link></italics>, so as to reach a wider audience than Latin would have allowed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>William E.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Burns<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The scientific revolution: an encyclopedia</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>ABC-CLIO<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Santa Barbara, California<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-87436-875-8<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>84</arg></template></extension><space/>It appeared in Latin in his later<space/><italics><link><target>Principles of Philosophy</target></link></italics>. As Descartes explained, &quot;[W]e cannot doubt of our existence while we doubt .&quot; A fuller form,<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum</arg></template></italics><space/>(&quot;I doubt, therefore I think, therefore I am)<template><target>efn</target><arg>The ''{{lang|la|dubito}}'', often mistakenly attributed to Descartes, was coined by [[Antoine Léonard Thomas]] in a 1765 essay in praise of Descartes. (See [[Cogito ergo sum#Other forms|Other forms]].)</arg></template>, aptly captures Descartes intent.</paragraph><paragraph>This proposition became a fundamental element of<space/><link><target>Western philosophy</target></link>, as it purported to form a secure<space/><link><target>epistemology</target><part>foundation for knowledge</part></link><space/>in the face of<space/><link><target>radical doubt</target></link>. While other knowledge could be a figment of imagination, deception, or mistake, Descartes asserted that the very act of doubting one's own existence servedat minimumas proof of the reality of one's own mind; there must be a<space/><link><target>Consciousness</target><part>thinking entity</part></link>in this case the<space/><link><target>self</target></link>for there to be a thought.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In Descartes's writings</heading><paragraph>Descartes first wrote the phrase in French in his 1637<space/><italics><link><target>Discourse on the Method</target></link></italics>. He referred to it in Latin without explicitly stating the familiar form of the phrase in his 1641<space/><italics><link><target>Meditations on First Philosophy</target></link></italics>. The earliest written record of the phrase in Latin is in his 1644<space/><italics><link><target>Principles of Philosophy</target></link></italics>, where, in a margin note, he provides a clear explanation of his intent. Fuller forms of the phrase are attributable to other authors.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Discourse on the Method</heading><paragraph>The phrase first appeared (in French) in Descartes's 1637<space/><italics><link><target>Discourse on the Method</target></link></italics><space/>in the first paragraph of its fourth part:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>French:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg name=""… Ainsi, à cause que nos sens nous trompent quelquefois, je voulus supposer qu'il n'y avoit aucune chose qui fût telle qu'ils nous la font imaginer; et parce qu'il y a des hommes qui seque tout étoit faux, il falloit nécessairement que moi qui le pensois fusse quelque chose; et remarquant que cette vérité, '''''{{nowrap|je pense,}} {{nowrap|donc je suis}}''''',{{efn|name">"formatting"}} étoit si ferme et si assurée, que toutes les plus extravagantes suppositions des sceptiques n'étoient pas capables de l'ébranler, je jugeai que je pouvois la recevoir sans scrupule pour le premier principe de la philosophie que je cherchois."</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>English: &quot; Accordingly, seeing that our senses sometimes deceive us, I was willing to suppose that there existed nothing really such as they presented to us; and because some men err in reasoning, and fall into paralogisms, even on the simplest matters of geometry, I, convinced that I was as open to error as any other, rejected as false all the reasonings I had hitherto taken for demonstrations; and finally, when I considered that the very same thoughts (presentations) which we experience when awake may also be experienced when we are asleep, while there is at that time not one of them true, I supposed that all the objects (presentations) that had ever entered into my mind when awake, had in them no more truth than the illusions of my dreams. But immediately upon this I observed that, whilst I thus wished to think that all was false, it was absolutely necessary that I, who thus thought, should be somewhat; and as I observed that this truth,<space/><bold><italics><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>I think,</arg></template><space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg>therefore I am</arg></template></italics></bold>,<template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"formatting"</arg></template><space/>was so certain and of such evidence that no ground of doubt, however extravagant, could be alleged by the sceptics capable of shaking it, I concluded that I might, without scruple, accept it as the<space/><link><target>first principle</target></link><space/>of the philosophy of which I was in search.&quot;<template><target>efn</target><arg name="This translation, from {{Gutenberg | no">59 | name</arg></template><template><target>efn</target><arg name="The 1637 ''Discours'' was translated to Latin in the 1644 ''Specimina Philosophiae''<ref name">"Descartes1644Specimina">{{cite book|author</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Meditations on First Philosophy</heading><paragraph>In 1641, Descartes published (in Latin)<space/><italics><link><target>Meditations on first philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>in which he referred to the proposition, though not explicitly as &quot;cogito ergo sum&quot; in Meditation II:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Latin:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg name=""… hoc pronuntiatum: '''ego sum, ego existo''',{{efn|name">"formatting"}} quoties a me profertur, vel mente concipitur, necessario esse verum."</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>English: &quot; this proposition:<space/><bold>I am, I exist</bold>,<template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"formatting"</arg></template><space/>whenever it is uttered from me, or conceived by the mind, necessarily is true.&quot;<template><target>efn</target><arg name="This combines, for clarity and to retain phrase ordering, the translations of Cress<ref name">Cress1986/><space/>and Haldane.<ref name</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Principles of Philosophy</heading><paragraph>In 1644, Descartes published (in Latin) his<space/><italics><link><target>Principles of Philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>where the phrase &quot;ego cogito, ergo sum&quot; appears in Part 1, article 7:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Latin:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg name=""Sic autem rejicientes illa omnia, de quibus aliquo modo possumus dubitare, ac etiam, falsa esse fingentes, facilè quidem, supponimus nullum esse Deum, nullum coelum, nulla corpora; nosque etiam ipsos, non habere manus, nec pedes, nec denique ullum corpus, non autem ideò nos qui talia cogitamus nihil esse: repugnat enim ut putemus id quod cogitat eo ipso tempore quo cogitat non existere. Ac proinde haec cognitio, '''''ego cogito, ergo sum''''',{{efn|name">"formatting"}} est omnium prima & certissima, quae cuilibet ordine philosophanti occurrat."</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>English: &quot;While we thus reject all of which we can entertain the smallest doubt, and even imagine that it is false, we easily indeed suppose that there is neither God, nor sky, nor bodies, and that we ourselves even have neither hands nor feet, nor, finally, a body; but we cannot in the same way suppose that we are not while we doubt of the truth of these things; for there is a repugnance in conceiving that what thinks does not exist at the very time when it thinks. Accordingly, the knowledge,<space/><bold><italics>I think, therefore I am</italics></bold>,<template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"formatting"</arg></template><space/>is the first and most certain that occurs to one who philosophizes orderly.&quot;<template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"GutPrinc4391"</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>Descartes's<space/><link><target>marginalia</target><part>margin note</part></link><space/>for the above paragraph is:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Latin:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>"Non posse à nobis dubitari, quin existamus dum dubitamus: at que hoc esse primum quod ordine philosophando cognoscimus."</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>English: &quot;That we cannot doubt of our existence while we doubt, and that this is the first knowledge we acquire when we philosophize in order.&quot;<template><target>efn</target><arg name="name">"GutPrinc4391"</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other forms</heading><paragraph>The proposition is sometimes given as<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>''dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum''</arg></template>. This fuller form was penned by the eloquent French literary critic,<space/><link><target>Antoine Lonard Thomas</target></link>, in an award-winning 1765 essay in praise of Descartes, where it appeared as<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>"Puisque je doute, je pense; puisque je pense, j'existe."</arg></template><space/>In English, this is &quot;Since I doubt, I think; since I think I exist&quot;; with rearrangement and compaction, &quot;I doubt, therefore I think, therefore I am&quot;, or in Latin, &quot;dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum&quot;.<template><target>efn</target><arg name="The 1765 work, ''Éloge de René Descartes'',<ref name">Thomas1765/><space/>by Antoine Léonard Thomas, was awarded the 1765 Le Prix De L'académie Française and republished in the 1826 compilation of Descartes's work, ''Oeuvres de Descartes''<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A further expansion,<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>''dubito, ergo cogito, ergo sum—res cogitans''</arg></template><space/>(&quot;a thinking thing&quot;) extends the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>with Descartes's statement in the subsequent Meditation,<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>"Ego sum res cogitans, id est dubitans, affirmans, negans, pauca intelligens, multa ignorans, volens, nolens, imaginans etiam et sentiens …"</arg></template>, or, in English, &quot;I am a thinking (conscious) thing, that is, a being who doubts, affirms, denies, knows a few objects, and is ignorant of many &quot;.<template><target>efn</target><arg name="This translation by [[John Veitch (poet)|Veitch]]<ref name">"Veitch1880">{{cite book | author</arg></template><space/>This has been referred to as &quot;the expanded<space/><italics>cogito</italics>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kline1967"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kline<space/></arg><arg name="first">George L.<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first">John P.</arg><arg name="DUPLICATE_editor1-last">Anton<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">John Herman<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last">Randall, Jr.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Naturalism and Historical Understanding<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SUNY, Albany<space/></arg><arg name="year">1967<space/></arg><arg name="pages">85<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Randall's Interpretation of the Philosophies of Descartes, Spinoza, and Leibniz</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Interpretation</heading><paragraph>The phrase<space/><italics>cogito ergo sum</italics><space/>is not used in Descartes's<space/><italics><link><target>Meditations on First Philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>but the term &quot;the<space/><italics>cogito</italics>&quot; is used to refer to an argument from it. In the Meditations, Descartes phrases the conclusion of the argument as &quot;that the proposition,<space/><italics>I am, I exist,</italics><space/>is<space/><link><target>logical truth</target><part>necessarily true</part></link><space/>whenever it is put forward by me or conceived in my mind.&quot; (<italics>Meditation</italics><space/>II)</paragraph><paragraph>At the beginning of the second meditation, having reached what he considers to be the ultimate level of doubt his argument from the existence of a deceiving god Descartes examines his beliefs to see if any have survived the doubt. In his belief in his own existence, he finds that it is impossible to doubt that he exists. Even if there were a deceiving god (or an evil demon), one's belief in their own existence would be secure, for there is no way one could be deceived unless one existed in order to be deceived.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>But I have convinced myself that there is absolutely nothing in the world, no sky, no earth, no minds, no bodies. Does it now follow that I, too, do not exist? No. If I convinced myself of something [or thought anything at all], then I certainly existed. But there is a deceiver of supreme power and cunning who deliberately and constantly deceives me. In that case, I, too, undoubtedly exist, if he deceives me; and let him deceive me as much as he can, he will never bring it about that I am nothing, so long as I think that I am something. So, after considering everything very thoroughly, I must finally conclude that the proposition,<space/><italics>I am, I exist,</italics><space/>is necessarily true whenever it is put forward by me or conceived in my mind. (AT VII 25; CSM II 1617)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are three important notes to keep in mind here. First, he claims only the certainty of<space/><italics>his own</italics><space/>existence from the first-person point of view he has not proved the existence of other minds at this point. This is something that has to be thought through by each of us for ourselves, as we follow the course of the meditations. Second, he does not say that his existence is necessary; he says that<space/><italics>if he thinks</italics>, then necessarily he exists (see the<space/><link><target>instantiation principle</target></link>). Third, this proposition &quot;I am, I exist&quot; is held true not based on a deduction (as mentioned above) or on empirical induction but on the clarity and self-evidence of the proposition.Descartes does not use this first certainty, the<space/><italics>cogito</italics>, as a foundation upon which to build further knowledge; rather, it is the firm ground upon which he can stand as he works to restore his beliefs. As he puts it:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Archimedes used to demand just one firm and immovable point in order to shift the entire earth; so I too can hope for great things if I manage to find just one thing, however slight, that is certain and unshakable. (AT VII 24; CSM II 16)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to many Descartes specialists, including<space/><link><target>tienne Gilson</target></link>, the goal of Descartes in establishing this first truth is to demonstrate the capacity of his criterion the immediate clarity and distinctiveness of self-evident propositions to establish true and justified propositions despite having adopted a method of generalized doubt. As a consequence of this demonstration, Descartes considers science and mathematics to be justified to the extent that their proposals are established on a similarly immediate clarity, distinctiveness, and self-evidence that presents itself to the mind. The originality of Descartes's thinking, therefore, is not so much in expressing the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>a feat accomplished by other predecessors, as we shall see but on using the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>as demonstrating the most fundamental epistemological principle, that science and mathematics are justified by relying on clarity, distinctiveness, and self-evidence.<link><target>Baruch Spinoza</target></link><space/>in &quot;<italics><link><target>Principia philosophiae cartesianae</target></link></italics>&quot; at its<space/><italics>Prolegomenon</italics><space/>identified &quot;cogito ergo sum&quot; the &quot;<italics>ego sum cogitans</italics>&quot; (I am a thinking being) as the thinking<space/><link><target>substance theory</target><part>substance</part></link><space/>with his<space/><link><target>ontology</target><part>ontological</part></link><space/>interpretation. It can also be considered that<space/><italics>Cogito ergo sum</italics><space/>is needed before any living being can go further in life&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="last">Vesey<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Developing Consciousness</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>O-Books<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>United Kingdom<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-84694-461-1<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>16</arg></template></extension><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">The Vesey citation does not include this material; a proper source is needed.</arg><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Predecessors</heading><paragraph>Although the idea expressed in<space/><italics>cogito ergo sum</italics><space/>is widely attributed to Descartes, he was not the first to mention it.<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link><space/>spoke about the &quot;knowledge of knowledge&quot; (Greek<space/><italics><space/></italics><space/>-<space/><italics>nesis noseos</italics>) and<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>explains the idea in full length:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>But if life itself is good and pleasant (...) and if one who sees is conscious that he sees, one who hears that he hears, one who walks that he walks and similarly for all the other human activities there is a faculty that is conscious of their exercise, so that whenever we perceive, we are conscious that we perceive, and whenever we think, we are conscious that we think, and to be conscious that we are perceiving or thinking is to be conscious that we exist... (<italics><link><target>Nicomachean Ethics</target></link></italics>, 1170a25 ff.)</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>City of God (book)</target><part>De Civitate Dei</part></link></italics><space/>writes<space/><italics>Si [] fallor, sum</italics><space/>(&quot;If I am mistaken, I am&quot;) (book XI, 26), and also anticipates modern refutations of the concept. Furthermore, in the<space/><italics><link><target>Enchiridion of Augustine</target><part>Enchiridion</part></link></italics><space/>Augustine attempts to refute<space/><link><target>skepticism</target></link><space/>by stating, &quot;[B]y not positively affirming that they are alive, the skeptics ward off the appearance of error in themselves, yet they do make errors simply by showing themselves alive; one cannot err who is not alive. That we live is therefore not only true, but it is altogether certain as well&quot; (Chapter 7 section 20). Another predecessor was<space/><link><target>Avicenna</target></link>'s &quot;Floating Man&quot;<space/><link><target>thought experiment</target></link><space/>on human<space/><link><target>self-awareness</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>self-consciousness</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Leaman"><link><target>Hossein Nasr</target><part>Nasr, Seyyed Hossein</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oliver Leaman</target><part>Leaman, Oliver</part></link><space/>(1996),<space/><italics>History of Islamic Philosophy</italics>, p. 315,<space/><link><target>Routledge</target></link>, ISBN 0-415-13159-6.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 8th Century Hindu philosopher<space/><link><target>Adi Shankara</target></link><space/>wrote in a similar fashion, No one thinks, 'I am not', arguing that one's existence cannot be doubted, as there must be someone there to doubt.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Radhakrishnan.S">Radhakrishnan, S. (1948),<space/><italics>Indian Philosophy, vol II</italics>, p. 476,<space/><link><target>George Allen &amp; Unwin Ltd</target></link>,</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Gómez Pereira</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticisms</heading><paragraph>There have been a number of criticisms of the argument. One concerns the nature of the step from &quot;I am thinking&quot; to &quot;I exist.&quot; The contention is that this is a<space/><link><target>syllogism</target><part>syllogistic</part></link><space/>inference, for it appears to require the extra<space/><link><target>premise</target></link>: &quot;Whatever has the property of thinking, exists&quot;, a premise Descartes did not justify. In fact, he conceded that there would indeed be an extra premise needed, but denied that the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>is a syllogism (see below).</paragraph><paragraph>To argue that the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>is not a syllogism, one may call it self-evident that &quot;Whatever has the property of thinking, exists&quot;. In plain English, it seems incoherent to actually doubt that one exists and is doubting. Strict skeptics maintain that only the property of 'thinking' is indubitably a property of the meditator (presumably, they imagine it possible that a thing thinks but does not exist). This countercriticism is similar to the ideas of<link><target>Jaakko Hintikka</target></link>, who offers a nonsyllogistic interpretation of<space/><italics>cogito ergo sum</italics>. He claimed that one simply cannot doubt the proposition &quot;I exist&quot;. To be mistaken about the proposition would mean something impossible: I do not exist, but I am still wrong.</paragraph><paragraph>Perhaps a more relevant contention is whether the &quot;I&quot; to which Descartes refers is justified.In<space/><italics>Descartes, The Project of Pure Enquiry</italics>,<space/><link><target>Bernard Williams</target></link><space/>provides a history and full evaluation of this issue. Apparently, the first scholar who raised the problem was<space/><link><target>Pierre Gassendi</target></link>. He &quot;points out that recognition that one has a set of thoughts does not imply that one is a particular thinker or another. Were we to move from the observation that there is thinking occurring to the attribution of this thinking to a particular agent, we would simply assume what we set out to prove, namely, that there exists a particular person endowed with the capacity for thought&quot;. In other words, &quot;the only claim that is indubitable here is the agent-independent claim that there is cognitive activity present&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/gassendi/</arg><arg name="title">Pierre Gassendi</arg><arg name="author">Fisher, Saul</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 December 2014</arg></template><space/>from<space/><link><target>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></extension><space/>The objection, as presented by<space/><link><target>Georg Christoph Lichtenberg</target><part>Georg Lichtenberg</part></link>, is that rather than supposing an entity that is thinking, Descartes should have said: &quot;thinking is occurring.&quot; That is, whatever the force of the<space/><italics>cogito</italics>, Descartes draws too much from it; the existence of a thinking thing, the reference of the &quot;I,&quot; is more than the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>can justify.<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link><space/>criticized the phrase in that it presupposes that there is an &quot;I&quot;, that there is such an activity as &quot;thinking&quot;, and that &quot;I&quot; know what &quot;thinking&quot; is. He suggested a more appropriate phrase would be &quot;it thinks.&quot; In other words, the &quot;I&quot; in &quot;I think&quot; could be similar to the &quot;It&quot; in &quot;It is raining.&quot;<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>claims that the philosophers who argue for a self that can be found using reason are confusing &quot;similarity&quot; with &quot;identity&quot;. This means that the similarity of our thoughts and the continuity of them in this similarity do not mean that we can identify ourselves as a self but that our thoughts are similar.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Williams' argument in detail</heading><preblock><preline>In addition to the preceding two arguments against the<space/><italics>cogito</italics>, other arguments have been advanced by Bernard Williams. He claims, for example, that what we are dealing with when we talk of thought, or when we say &quot;I am thinking,&quot; is something conceivable from a<space/><link><target>Grammatical person</target><part>third-person</part></link><space/>perspective; namely objective &quot;thought-events&quot; in the former case, and an<space/><link><target>Objectivity (philosophy)</target><part>objective</part></link><space/>thinker in the latter.</preline></preblock><paragraph>Williams provides a meticulous and exhaustive examination of this objection. He argues, first, that it is impossible to make sense of &quot;there is thinking&quot; without relativizing it to<space/><italics>something.</italics><space/>However, this something cannot be Cartesian egos, because it is impossible to differentiate objectively between things just on the basis of the pure content of consciousness.</paragraph><paragraph>The obvious problem is that, through<space/><link><target>introspection</target></link>, or our experience of<space/><link><target>consciousness</target></link>, we have no way of moving to conclude the existence of any third-personal fact, to conceive of which would require something above and beyond just the purely subjective contents of the mind.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sren Kierkegaard's critique</heading><paragraph>The Danish philosopher<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>provided a critical response to the<space/><italics>cogito</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kierkegaard, Sren.<space/><italics>Philosophical Fragments</italics>. Trans. Hong, Princeton, 1985. p. 38-42.</extension><space/>Kierkegaard argues that the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>already presupposes the existence of &quot;I&quot;, and therefore concluding with existence is logically trivial. Kierkegaard's argument can be made clearer if one extracts the premise &quot;I think&quot; into two further premises:<extension extension_name='blockquote'><italics>&quot;x&quot; thinks</italics><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>I am that &quot;x&quot;</italics><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Therefore I think</italics><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Therefore I am</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Where &quot;x&quot; is used as a placeholder in order to disambiguate the &quot;I&quot; from the thinking thing.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schnbaumsfeld, Genia.<space/><italics>A Confusion of the Spheres</italics>. Oxford, 2007. p.168-170.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Here, the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>has already assumed the &quot;I&quot;'s existence as that which thinks. For Kierkegaard, Descartes is merely &quot;developing the content of a concept&quot;, namely that the &quot;I&quot;, which already exists, thinks.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kierkegaard, Sren.<space/><italics>Philosophical Fragments</italics>. Trans. Hong, Princeton, 1985. p. 40.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Kierkegaard argues that the value of the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>is not its logical argument, but its<space/><link><target>psychology</target><part>psychological</part></link><space/>appeal: a thought must have something that exists to think the thought. It is psychologically difficult to think &quot;I do not exist&quot;. But as Kierkegaard argues, the proper logical flow of argument is that existence is already assumed or presupposed in order for thinking to occur, not that existence is concluded from that thinking.<extension extension_name='ref'>Archie, Lee C., &quot;Sren Kierkegaard,<space/><italics>God's Existence Cannot Be Proved</italics>&quot;. Philosophy of Religion. Lander Philosophy, 2006.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>John Macmurray's Form of the Personal</heading><paragraph>The Scottish philosopher<space/><link><target>John Macmurray</target></link><space/>rejects the<space/><italics>cogito</italics><space/>outright in order to place action at the center of a philosophical system he entitles the Form of the Personal. &quot;We must reject this, both as standpoint and as method. If this be philosophy, then philosophy is a bubble floating in an atmosphere of unreality.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Macmurray, John.<space/><italics>The Self as Agent</italics>. Humanity books, 1991. p. 78.</extension><space/>The reliance on thought creates an irreconcilable<space/><link><target>dualism</target></link><space/>between thought and action in which the unity of experience is lost. Thus dissolving the integrity of our selves, and destroying any connection with reality. In order to formulate a more adequate<space/><italics>cogito</italics>, Macmurray proposes the substitution of &quot;I do&quot; for &quot;I think&quot;. Ultimately leading to a belief in God as an agent to whom all persons stand in relation.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Skepticism</heading><paragraph>Many<space/><link><target>Philosophical skepticism</target><part>philosophical skeptics</part></link><space/>and particularly<space/><link><target>Radical skepticism</target><part>radical skeptics</part></link><space/>would say that indubitable knowledge does not exist, is impossible, or has not been found yet, and would apply this criticism to the assertion that the &quot;cogito&quot; is beyond doubt.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Solipsism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gmez Pereira</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Notelist</target><arg name="refs">
{{efn|name<space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg><arg name="refs">
<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Abraham, W.E. &quot;Disentangling the Cogito&quot;,<space/><italics>Mind</italics><space/>83:329 (1974)</listitem><listitem>Boufoy-Bastick, Z.<space/><italics>Introducing 'Applicable Knowledge' as a Challenge to the Attainment of Absolute Knowledge<space/></italics>,<space/><italics>Sophia Journal of Philosophy</italics>, VIII (2005), pp 3952.</listitem><listitem>Descartes, R. (translated by John Cottingham),<space/><italics>Meditations on First Philosophy</italics>, in<space/><italics>The Philosophical Writings of Descartes</italics><space/>vol. II (edited Cottingham, Stoothoff, and Murdoch; Cambridge University Press, 1984) ISBN 0-521-28808-8</listitem><listitem>Hatfield, G.<space/><italics>Routledge Philosophy Guidebook to Descartes and the Meditations</italics><space/>(Routledge, 2003) ISBN 0-415-11192-7</listitem><listitem>Kierkegaard, S.<space/><italics>Concluding Unscientific Postscript</italics><space/>(Princeton, 1985) ISBN 978-0-691-02081-5</listitem><listitem>Kierkegaard, S.<space/><italics>Philosophical Fragments</italics><space/>(Princeton, 1985) ISBN 978-0-691-02036-5</listitem><listitem>Williams, B.<space/><italics>Descartes, The Project of Pure Enquiry</italics><space/>(Penguin, 1978)<space/><template><target>Oclc number</target><arg>4025089</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baird<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Forrest E.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="author2">Walter Kaufmann<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>From Plato to Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pearson Prentice Hall<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Upper Saddle River, New Jersey<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-13-158591-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.giffordlectures.org/Browse.asp?PubID=TPSAGT&amp;amp;Cover=TRUE'>Macmurray, John. &quot;The Self as Agent&quot; 1951</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>See External Links for Descartes's 1637<space/><link><target>Discourse on the Method</target></link></listitem><listitem>See External Links for Descartes's 1641<space/><link><target>Meditations on First Philosophy</target></link></listitem><listitem>See External Links for Descartes's 1644<space/><link><target>Principles of Philosophy</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>descartes-epistemology</arg><arg>Descartes's Epistemology</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rep.routledge.com/article/DA026SECT5'>Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Descartes The Cogito Argument</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>metaphysics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cogito Ergo Sum</target></template><link><target>Category:Concepts in epistemology</target></link><link><target>Category:Latin philosophical phrases</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophical arguments</target></link><link><target>Category:Latin quotations</target></link><link><target>Category:Concepts in metaphysics</target></link><link><target>Category:Ren Descartes</target></link><link><target>Category:Thought</target></link></paragraph></article>