<article title='Chrono_Cross'><paragraph><template><target>Featured article</target></template><template><target>Infobox video game</target><arg name="title"><space/>Chrono Cross
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>chronocrossbox.jpg
</arg><arg name="developer"><space/>[[Square Enix#Product development divisions|Square Product Development Division 3]]<ref>{{cite web |url</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Square (company)|Square]]
</arg><arg name="director"><space/>[[Masato Kato]]
</arg><arg name="producer"><space/>[[Hiromichi Tanaka]]
</arg><arg name="designer"><space/>Hiromichi Tanaka
</arg><arg name="programmer"><space/>Kiyoshi Yoshii
</arg><arg name="artist"><space/>[[Yasuyuki Honne]]<br>[[Nobuteru Yūki]]
</arg><arg name="writer"><space/>Masato Kato
</arg><arg name="composer"><space/>[[Yasunori Mitsuda]]
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>''[[Chrono (series)|Chrono]]''
</arg><arg name="platforms"><space/>[[PlayStation (console)|PlayStation]]
</arg><arg name="released"><space/>{{vgrelease new|JP|November 18, 1999|NA|August 15, 2000|JP|July 6, 2011<space/><small>(PSN)</small>|NA|November 8, 2011<space/><small>(PSN)</small><ref>{{cite web|title</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Role-playing video game|Role-playing]]
</arg><arg name="modes"><space/>[[Single-player video game|Single-player]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>nihongo</target><arg>'''''Chrono Cross'''''</arg><arg>クロノ・クロス</arg></template><space/>is a<space/><link><target>role-playing video game</target></link><space/><link><target>video game developer</target><part>developed</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>video game publisher</target><part>published</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Square (company)</target><part>Square</part></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>Square Enix</target></link>) for the<space/><link><target>PlayStation (console)</target><part>PlayStation</part></link><space/><link><target>video game console</target></link>. It is the successor to<space/><italics><link><target>Chrono Trigger</target></link></italics>, which was released in 1995 for the<space/><link><target>Super Nintendo Entertainment System</target></link>.<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>was developed primarily by scenarist and director<space/><link><target>Masato Kato</target></link><space/>and other designers from<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>, including art director<space/><link><target>Yasuyuki Honne</target></link><space/>and composer<space/><link><target>Yasunori Mitsuda</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Nobuteru Yki</target></link><space/>designed the characters of the game.</paragraph><paragraph>The story of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>focuses on a teenage boy named<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Serge</target><part>Serge</part></link><space/>and a theme of<space/><link><target>parallel universe (fiction)</target><part>parallel worlds</part></link>. Faced with an alternate reality in which he died as a child, Serge endeavors to discover the truth of the two worlds' divergence. The flashy thief<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Kid</target><part>Kid</part></link><space/>and many other characters assist him in his travels around the tropical archipelago El Nido. Struggling to uncover his past and find the mysterious Frozen Flame, Serge is chiefly challenged by<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Lynx</target><part>Lynx</part></link>, a shadowy antagonist working to apprehend him.</paragraph><paragraph>Upon its release in Japan in 1999 and North America in 2000,<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>received high ratings and critical acclaim, earning a perfect 10.0 score from<space/><link><target>GameSpot</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gamerankings"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gamerankings.com/htmlpages4/196917.asp</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GameRankings]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-07-27</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/>The game shipped<space/><template><target>Nowrap</target><arg>1.5 million</arg></template><space/>copies worldwide, leading to a Greatest Hits re-release and continued life in Japan as part of the<space/><link><target>Ultimate Hit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>series.<extension extension_name='ref' name="square-sales"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2003-08-04</arg><arg name="title">Square Enix IR Roadshow Document</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.square-enix.com/jp/ir/e/explanatory/download/0404-200308040000-01.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Square Enix]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-06</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimatehits"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2006-04-28</arg><arg name="first">Chris</arg><arg name="last">Winkler</arg><arg name="title">Square Enix Adds 16 to Ultimate Hits Series<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.rpgfan.com/news/2006/1219.html</arg><arg name="publisher">RPGFan</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>was released on July 6, 2011 on the Japanese<space/><link><target>PlayStation Network</target></link><space/>and on November 8, 2011 in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="psnnetwork"></extension><space/>Square also released a &quot;Millennium Edition&quot; featuring a calendar, clock, and music sampler disc.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Gameplay</heading><paragraph><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>features standard<space/><link><target>role-playing video game</target></link><space/>gameplay with some differences. Players advance the game by controlling the protagonist Serge through the game's world, primarily by foot and boat. Navigation between areas is conducted via an<space/><link><target>overworld</target></link><space/>map, much like<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger's</italics>, depicting the landscape from a scaled down overhead view. Around the island world are villages, outdoor areas, and dungeons, through which the player moves in three dimensions. Locations such as cities and forests are represented by more realistically scaled field maps, in which players can converse with locals to procure items and services, solve puzzles and challenges, or encounter enemies. Like<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>, the game features no<space/><link><target>random encounter</target><trail>s</trail></link>; enemies are openly visible on field maps or lie in wait to ambush the party.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2000-01-06</arg><arg name="first">Andrew</arg><arg name="last">Vestal</arg><arg name="title">GameSpot: Chrono Cross Review</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gamespot.com/chrono-cross/</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GameSpot]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-19</arg></template></extension><space/>Touching the monster switches perspectives to a battle screen, in which players can physically attack, use &quot;Elements&quot;, defend, or run away from the enemy. Battles are turn-based, allowing the player infinite time to select an action from the available menu. For both the playable characters and the computer-controlled enemies, each attack reduces their number of<space/><link><target>hit point</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(a numerically based<space/><link><target>life bar</target></link>), which can be restored through some Elements. When a playable character loses all hit points, he or she faints. If all the player's characters fall in battle, the game ends and must be restored from a previously saved chapterexcept for specific storyline-related battles that allow the player to lose.<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s developers aimed to break new ground in the genre, and the game features several innovations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2000-10-17</arg><arg name="title">Interview with Chrono Cross Developers</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://gamepro.org/sony/psx/games/features/7033.shtml</arg><arg name="work">Chrono Compendium</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GamePro]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-02</arg></template></extension><space/>For example, players can run away from all conflicts, including<space/><link><target>boss (video games)</target><part>boss</part></link><space/>fights and the final battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Battle and Elements</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chronocrossbattlescreenshot.png</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>In battle, players can attack, use Elements, defend, or run away</part><part>alt=Two characters in foreground in battle poise, menu with &quot;Attack&quot;, &quot;Element&quot;, &quot;Defend&quot;, &quot;Run Away&quot;, boxes with health statistics for characters &quot;Serge&quot;, &quot;Kid&quot;, and &quot;Mel&quot;, stone floor, gold robotic enemy facing the characters</part></link>The Element system of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>handles all magic, consumable items, and character-specific abilities. Elements unleash magic effects upon the enemy or party and must be equipped for use, much like the materia of 1997's<space/><italics><link><target>Final Fantasy&amp;nbsp;VII</target></link></italics>. Elements can be purchased from shops or found in treasure chests littered throughout areas. Once acquired, they are allocated to a grid whose size and shape are unique to each character. They are ranked according to eight tiers; certain high level Elements can only be assigned on equivalent tiers in a character's grid. As the game progresses, the grid expands, allowing more Elements to be equipped and higher tiers to be accessed. Elements are divided into six paired oppositional types, or &quot;colors,&quot; each with a natural effect. Red (fire/magma) opposes Blue (water/ice), Green (wind/flora) opposes Yellow (earth/lightning), and White (light/cosmos) opposes Black (darkness/gravity).<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/>Each character and enemy has an innate color, enhancing the power of using same-color Elements while also making them weak against elements of the opposite color.<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>also features a &quot;field effect&quot;, which keeps track of Element color used in the upper corner of the battle screen. If the field is purely one color, the power of Elements of that color will be enhanced, while Elements of the opposite color will be weakened. Characters also innately learn some special techniques (&quot;Techs&quot;) that are unique to each character but otherwise act like Elements. Like<space/><italics><link><target>Chrono Trigger</target></link></italics>, characters can combine certain Techs to make more powerful Double or Triple Techs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/>Consumable Elements may be used to restore<space/><link><target>hit point</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or heal<space/><link><target>status ailment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>after battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another innovative aspect of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>is its stamina bar.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/>At the beginning of a battle, each character has seven points of stamina. When a character attacks or uses an Element, stamina is decreased proportionally to the potency of the attack. Stamina slowly recovers when the character defends or when other characters perform actions in battle. Characters with stamina below one point must wait to take action. Use of an Element reduces the user's stamina bar by seven stamina points; this often means that the user's stamina gauge falls into the negative and the character must wait longer than usual to recover. With each battle, players can enhance<space/><link><target>Attribute (role-playing games)</target><part>statistic</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as strength and defense. However, no system of<space/><link><target>experience point</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>exists; after four or five upgrades, statistics remain static until players defeat a<space/><link><target>boss (video game)</target><part>boss</part></link>. This adds a star to a running count shown on the status screen, which allows for another few rounds of statistical increases.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/>Players can equip characters with weapons, armor, helmets, and accessories for use in battle; for example, the &quot;Power Seal&quot; upgrades attack power. Items and equipment may be purchased or found on field maps, often in<space/><link><target>Power-up</target><part>treasure chests</part></link>. Unlike Elements, weapons and armor cannot merely be purchased with money; instead, the player must obtain base materialssuch as copper, bronze, or bonefor a blacksmith to forge for a fee. The items can later be disassembled into their original components at no cost.<link><target>File:Navigatingelnido.png</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Players navigate the game's tropical setting by boat</part><part>alt=&quot;Home World&quot;, an archipelago featuring fishing settlements, a city, and a volcanic mountain range surrounding a stone fort</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Parallel dimensions</heading><paragraph>The existence of two major<space/><link><target>parallel universe (fiction)</target><part>parallel dimensions</part></link>, like time periods in<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>, plays a significant role in the game. Players must go back and forth between the worlds to recruit party members, obtain items, and advance the plot. Much of the population of either world have counterparts in the other; some party members can even visit their other versions. The player must often search for items or places found exclusively in one world. Events in one dimension sometimes have an impact in anotherfor instance, cooling scorched ground on an island in one world allows vegetation to grow in the other world. This system assists the presentation of certain themes, including the questioning of the importance of one's past decisions and humanity's role in destroying the environment.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ignreview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="last">Zdyrko</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Chrono Cross Review</arg><arg name="url">http://psx.ign.com/articles/162/162503p1.html</arg><arg name="publisher">IGN</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg></template></extension><space/>Rounding out the notable facets of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s gameplay are the<space/><link><target>New Game Plus</target><part>New Game+</part></link><space/>option and multiple endings. As in<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>, players who have completed the game may choose to start the game over using data from the previous session. Character levels, learned techniques, equipment, and items gathered copy over, while acquired money and some story-related items are discarded. On a New Game+, players can access twelve endings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="endingcount"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross Endings</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Endings_(Chrono_Cross).html</arg><arg name="work">Chrono Compendium</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg></template></extension><space/>Scenes viewed depend on players' progress in the game before the final battle, which can be fought at any time in a New Game+ file.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot</heading><heading level='3'>Characters</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Characters of Chrono Cross</arg></template><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>features a diverse cast of 45 party members. Each character is outfitted with an innate Element affinity and three unique special abilities that are learned over time. If taken to the world opposite their own, characters react to their counterparts (if available). Many characters tie in to crucial plot events. Since it is impossible to obtain all 45 characters in one playthrough, players must replay the game to witness everything. Through use of the<space/><link><target>New Game Plus</target><part>New Game+</part></link><space/>feature, players can ultimately obtain all characters on one save file. Several characters speak with unique accents, including French and Australian English.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Serge</target><part>Serge</part></link>, the game's protagonist, is a 17-year-old boy with blue hair who lives in the fishing village of Arni. One day, he slips into an alternate world in which he drowned ten years before. Determined to find the truth behind the incident, he follows a predestined course that leads him to save the world. He is assisted by<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Kid</target><part>Kid</part></link>, a feisty, skilled thief who seeks the mythical Frozen Flame. Portrayed as willful and<space/><link><target>tomboy</target><trail>ish</trail></link><space/>due to her rough, thieving past, she helps Serge sneak into Viper Manor. Kid was raised by<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Trigger#Lucca</target><part>Lucca</part></link><space/>as a child, and vows to find and defeat<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Lynx</target><part>Lynx</part></link>, an anthropomorphic panther who burned down Lucca's orphanage. A sadistic and cruel agent of the supercomputer FATE, Lynx is bent on finding Serge, with and succeeds in taking his body. He travels with<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Harle</target><part>Harle</part></link>, a mysterious, playful girl dressed like a<space/><link><target>harlequin</target></link>. Sent by the Dragon God to shadow Lynx and one day steal the Frozen Flame from Chronopolis, she painfully fulfills her duty though smitten with Serge. To this end, she helps Lynx manipulate the Acacia Dragoons, the powerful militia governing the islands of El Nido. As the Dragoons maintain order, they contend with Fargo, a former Dragoon turned pirate captain who holds a grudge against their leader, General Viper. Their home base, Viper Manor, is also infiltrated by Serge, Kid, and one of three charactersNikki, a musician, Pierre, a hero-in-training, or Guile, a mysterious magician. Though tussling with Serge initially, the Acacia Dragoonswhose ranks include the fierce warriors Karsh, Zoah, Marcy, and Glennlater assist him when the militaristic nation of Porre invades the archipelago. The invasion brings Norris and Grobyc to the islands, a heartful commander of an elite force and a prototype cyborg soldier, respectively. As they too seek the Frozen Flame, the plot unfolds amidst several other characters.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Story</heading><paragraph><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>begins with Serge located in El Nido, a tropical archipelago inhabited by ancient natives, mainland colonists, and beings called Demi-humans. Serge slips into an<space/><link><target>Parallel universe (fiction)</target><part>alternate dimension</part></link><space/>in which he drowned on the beach ten years prior, and meets the thief, &quot;Kid&quot;. He learns while infiltrating Viper Manor that ten years before the present, the universe split into two dimensionsone in which Serge lived, and one in which he perished.<extension extension_name='ref' name="split-dimensions"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Viper Manor</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>'''Prophet''': In your home world, you survived to live a happy and prosperous life. That is how you made it to the present point in time. However, here in this '"alternate"' world, you are, in fact, very dead and buried. You died 10 years ago, but this world's time line has flowed on regardless.</arg></template></extension><space/>Through Kid's Astral Amulet charm, Serge travels between the dimensions. At Fort Dragonia the use of a Dragonian artifact called the Dragon Tear, Lynx switches bodies with Serge. Unaware of the switch, Kid confides in Lynx, who stabs her as the real Serge helplessly watches. Lynx boasts of his victory and banishes Serge to a strange realm called the Temporal Vortex. He takes Kid under his wing, brainwashing her to believe the real Serge (in Lynx's body) is her enemy. Serge escapes with help from<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Cross#Harle</target><part>Harle</part></link>. Discovering that his new body prevents him from traveling across the dimensions, he sets out to regain his former body and learn more of the universal split that occurred ten years earlier. He travels to a forbidden lagoon known as the Dead Seaa wasteland frozen in time, dotted with futuristic ruins.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dead-sea"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform"><space/>PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Dead Sea</arg><arg name="quote">'''Member''': The waves are at a standstill&nbsp;... And&nbsp;... What is that dark shadow in the distance&nbsp;...?</arg></template></extension><space/>At the center, he locates a man named Miguel and presumably<space/><italics>Home</italics><space/>world's Frozen Flame. Charged with guarding the Dead Sea by an entity named FATE, Miguel and three visions of<space/><link><target>Crono</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Trigger#Marle</target><part>Marle</part></link>, and Lucca from<space/><italics><link><target>Chrono Trigger</target></link></italics><space/>explain that Serge's existence dooms<space/><italics>Home</italics><space/>world's future to destruction. To prevent Serge from obtaining the Frozen Flame, FATE destroys the Dead Sea.</paragraph><paragraph>Able to return to<space/><italics>Another</italics><space/>world, Serge allies with the Acacia Dragoons against Porre and locates that dimension's Dragon Tear, allowing him to return to his human form. He then enters the Sea of Eden,<space/><italics>Another</italics><space/>world's physical equivalent of the Dead Sea, finding a temporal research facility called Chronopolis. Lynx and Kid are inside; Serge defeats Lynx and the supercomputer FATE, allowing the six Dragons of El Nido to steal the Frozen Flame and retire to Terra Tower, a massive structure raised from the sea floor. Kid falls into a coma, and Harle bids the party goodbye to fly with the Dragons. Serge regroups his party and tends to Kid, who remains comatose. Continuing his adventure, he obtains and cleanses the Masamune sword from<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>. He then uses the Dragon relics and shards of the Dragon Tears to create the mythic Element Chrono Cross. The spiritual power of the Masamune later allows him to lift Kid from her coma. At Terra Tower, the prophet of time, revealed to be Belthasar from<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>, visits him with visions of Crono, Marle, and Lucca. Serge learns that the time research facility Chronopolis created El Nido thousands of years ago after a catastrophic experimental failure drew it to the past.<extension extension_name='ref' name="remodeling"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Chronopolis</arg><arg name="quote">'''Ghost''': Originally, El Nido was nothing but ocean. The El Nido Archipelago is purely artificial, created by FATE. It was a remodeling plan that took place 10,000 years ago.</arg></template></extension><space/>The introduction of a temporally foreign object in history caused the planet to pull in a counterbalance from a different dimension.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dinopolis"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="quote">'''Kid''': Perhaps our planet beckoned Dinopolis into the past&nbsp;... maybe as a measure against Chronopolis and humanity.</arg><arg name="level">Chronopolis</arg></template></extension><space/>This was Dinopolis, a city of Dragoniansparallel universe descendants of<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s Reptites. The institutions warred and Chronopolis subjugated the Dragonians. Humans captured their chief creationthe Dragon God, an entity capable of controlling nature.</paragraph><paragraph>Chronopolis divided this entity into six pieces and created an Elements system. FATE then<space/><link><target>terraforming</target><part>terraformed</part></link><space/>an archipelago, erased the memories of most Chronopolis's staff, and sent them to inhabit and populate its new paradise.<extension extension_name='ref' name="population"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Chronopolis</arg><arg name="quote">'''Ghost''': The research center staff, who had their memories of the future erased, left the center, and began a life outside amidst nature. This is how FATE's paradise came into existence.</arg></template></extension><space/>Thousands of years later, a panther demon attacked a three-year-old Serge. His father took him to find assistance at Marbule, but Serge's boat blew off course due to a raging magnetic storm caused by<space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Trigger#Schala</target><part>Schala</part></link>. Schala, the princess of the Kingdom of Zeal, had long ago accidentally fallen to a place known as the Darkness Beyond Time and began merging with Lavos, the chief antagonist of<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="schala-banishment"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Opassa Beach</arg><arg name="quote">'''Lucca''': Princess Schala was sucked into a dimensional vortex with the Lavos Mammon Machine. Schala and Lavos became unified into one even more powerful entity that would evolve into the Devourer of Time.</arg></template></extension><space/>Schala's storm nullified Chronopolis's defenses and allowed Serge to contact the Frozen Flame; approaching it healed Serge but corrupted his father.<extension extension_name='ref' name="magnetic-storm-healing"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Opassa Beach</arg><arg name="quote">'''Lucca''': Led by the pitiful crying the young Serge made as the panther demon's poison took hold of him&nbsp;... Princess Schala traveled ten thousand years in time to make contact with this dimension! This caused a raging magnetic storm that resulted in FATE's system malfunction, which led Serge to the Frozen Flame.</arg></template></extension><space/>A circuit in Chronopolis then designated Serge &quot;Arbiter&quot;, simultaneously preventing FATE from using the Frozen Flame by extension. The Dragons were aware of this situation, creating a seventh Dragon under the storm's cover named Harle, who manipulated Lynx to steal the Frozen Flame for the Dragons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="harle-birth"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="quote">Opassa Beach</arg><arg name="level"><space/>'''Crono''': In the meantime, the six Dragons had sent Harle forth to gain possession of the Flame. Harle made contact with FATE's biological incarnation, Lynx, and tricked him into temporarily joining forces.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After Serge returned home, FATE sent Lynx to kill Serge, hoping that it would release the Arbiter lock. Ten years after Serge drowned, the thief Kidpresumably on Belthasar's orderswent back in time to save Serge and split the dimensions. FATE, locked out of the Frozen Flame again, knew that Serge would one day cross to<space/><italics>Another</italics><space/>world and prepared to apprehend him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cross-prediction"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level"><space/>Opassa Beach</arg><arg name="quote">'''Crono''': You see, FATE calculated that you would one day cross the dimensions and try to make contact with the Flame.</arg></template></extension><space/>Lynx switched bodies with Serge to dupe the biological check of Chronopolis on the Frozen Flame. Belthasar then reveals that these events were part of a plan he had orchestrated named Project Kid. Serge continues to the top of Terra Tower and defeats the Dragon God. Continuing to the beach where the split in dimensions had occurred, Serge finds apparitions of Crono, Marle, and Lucca once more. They reveal that Belthasar's plan was to empower Serge to free Schala from melding with Lavos, lest they evolve into the &quot;Time Devourer&quot;, a creature capable of destroying<space/><link><target>spacetime</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="quest-purpose"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="quote">'''Lucca''': And now, about '"Project Kid"'... the time control project Belthasar planned out. The whole project existed to lead you to this one, special point in time! The founding of Chronopolis, the Time Crash, and the battle between FATE and the Dragon Gods&nbsp;... It was all coordinated so that you would get your hands on the Chrono Cross and come to this place!</arg><arg name="level">Opassa Beach</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Characters of Chrono Trigger#Lucca</target><part>Lucca</part></link><space/>explains that Kid is Schala's clone, sent to the modern age to take part in Project Kid.<extension extension_name='ref' name="daughter-clone"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>'''Lucca''': Before the destructive mind-set could become dominant, she cloned herself and sent her copy into this dimension&nbsp;... That's right&nbsp;... Kid is Schala's daughter-clone!</arg><arg name="level">Opassa Beach</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="chrono-cross-use"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Opassa Beach</arg><arg name="quote">'''Crono''': The Chrono Cross&nbsp;... It alone can combine the sounds of the planet that the six types of Elements produce! The melody and harmony that brim within all life-forms&nbsp;... Use the '"song of life"' to heal her enmity and suffering&nbsp;... We entreat you, Serge! Please save Schala&nbsp;...</arg></template></extension><space/>Serge uses a Time Egggiven to him by Belthasarto enter the Darkness Beyond Time and vanquish the Time Devourer, separating Schala from Lavos and restores the dimensions to one. Thankful, Schala muses on evolution and the struggle of life and returns Serge to his home, noting that he will forget the entire adventure. She then seemingly records the experience in her diary, noting she will always be searching for Serge in this life and beyond. A wedding photo of Kid and an obscured male sits on the diary's desk. Scenes then depict a real-life Kid searching for someone in a modern city, intending to make players entertain the possibility that their own Kid is searching for them. The ambiguous ending leaves the events of the characters' lives following the game up to interpretation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cross-resolutions"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross Resolutions</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Chrono_Cross_Resolutions</arg><arg name="work">Chrono Compendium</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Relation to<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics></heading><paragraph><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>employs story arcs, characters, and themes from<space/><italics><link><target>Radical Dreamers: Nusumenai Hseki</target><part>Radical Dreamers</part></link></italics>, a<space/><link><target>Satellaview</target></link><space/>side story to<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><space/>released in Japan. An illustrated<space/><link><target>Interactive fiction</target><part>text adventure</part></link>,<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics><space/>was created to wrap up an unresolved plot line of<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">Weekly Famitsu: Interview with Chrono Cross Developers</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Weekly_Famitsu.html</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Enterbrain, Inc.]] and [[Tokuma Shoten]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg></template></extension><space/>Though it borrows from<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics><space/>in its exposition,<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>is not a<space/><link><target>Video game remake</target><part>remake</part></link><space/>of<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics>, but a larger effort to fulfill that game's purpose; the plots of the games are irreconcilable.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>To resolve continuity issues and acknowledge<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics>, the developers of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>suggested the game happened in a parallel<space/><link><target>dimension</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="radical-continuity"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title"><space/>Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="developer">Square</arg><arg name="publisher">Square</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-15</arg><arg name="platform">PlayStation</arg><arg name="level">Chronopolis</arg><arg name="quote">'''Kid''': Kid: Radical Dreamers&nbsp;...!? And me name's on here, too! What the bloody hell is goin' on?<br>'''Kid''':&nbsp;... This seems to be an archive from a different time than our own. / '''Kid''': Aside from the two worlds we already know about&nbsp;... there may be other worlds and times which exist&nbsp;...</arg></template></extension><space/>A notable difference between the two games is that<space/><link><target>Magil</target><part>Magus</part></link>present in<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics><space/>as Gilis absent from<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics>. Director Masato Kato originally planned for Magus to appear in disguise as Guile, but scrapped the idea due to plot difficulties.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>In the DS version of Chrono Trigger, Kato teases the possibility of an amnesiac Magus.<extension extension_name='ref' name="magusdsending"><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Trigger</arg><arg name="developer">Square Enix</arg><arg name="publisher">Square Enix</arg><arg name="date">2008-11-25</arg><arg name="platform">Nintendo DS</arg><arg name="level">Twilight Grotto</arg><arg name="quote">'''Magus''': Hmph. If this is to be the way of things, then let me abandon all that was and fade away as well. Should a part of me somehow even then remain, then perhaps that will be the birth of something new—something with greater meaning than all this. / '''Magus''': Who&nbsp;... who am I? What's happened? I&nbsp;... I don't remember anything. There was something&nbsp;... something I needed to do. Something I needed to&nbsp;... to find. / '''Magus''': I must find a way to remember. I will.<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Development</heading><paragraph>Square began planning<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>immediately after the release of<space/><italics><link><target>Xenogears</target></link></italics><space/>in 1998.<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s scenario director Masato Kato had brainstormed ideas for a sequel as early as 1996, following the release of<space/><italics><link><target>Radical Dreamers: Nusumenai Hseki</target><part>Radical Dreamers</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>Square's managers selected a team, appointed<space/><link><target>Hiromichi Tanaka</target></link><space/>producer, and asked Kato to direct and develop a new<space/><italics><link><target>Chrono (series)</target><part>Chrono</part></link></italics><space/>game in the spirit of<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross Ultimania</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Supporting_Material_Translation.html#Developer_Interviews</arg><arg name="pages">478–481</arg><arg name="language">Japanese</arg><arg name="publisher">Square Enix</arg><arg name="isbn">4-925075-73-X</arg></template></extension><space/>Kato thought<space/><italics>Dreamers</italics><space/>was released in a &quot;half-finished state&quot;, and wanted to continue the story of the character Kid.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>Kato and Tanaka decided to produce an indirect sequel. They acknowledged that Square would soon re-release<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><space/>as part of<space/><italics><link><target>Final Fantasy Chronicles</target></link></italics>, which would give players a chance to catch up on the story of<space/><italics>Trigger</italics><space/>before playing<space/><italics>Cross</italics>. Kato thought that using a different setting and cast for<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>would allow players unfamiliar with<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><space/>to play<space/><italics>Cross</italics><space/>without becoming confused.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>team decided against integrating heavy use of<space/><link><target>time travel</target></link><space/>into the game, as they thought it would be &quot;rehashing and cranking up the volume of the last game&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Masato Kato cited the belief, &quot;there's no use in making something similar to before<space/><template><target>sic</target></template>&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>and noted, &quot;we're not so weak nor cheap as to try to make something exactly the same as<space/><italics>Trigger</italics>... Accordingly,<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>is not<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger 2</italics>. It doesn't simply follow on from<space/><italics>Trigger</italics>, but is another, different<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>that interlaces with<space/><italics>Trigger</italics>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>Kato and Tanaka further explained their intentions after the game's release:</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Tanaka.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Hiromichi Tanaka, producer</part><part>alt=A Japanese man with left-parted hair, a brown leather jacket, and a blue shirt</part></link><template><target>quote</target><arg name="We didn't want to directly extend Chrono Trigger into a sequel, but create a new Chrono with links to the original.<ref name">"weeklyfamitsu" /><space/>Yes, the platform changed; and yes, there were many parts that changed dramatically from the previous work. But in my view, the whole point in making ''Chrono Cross'' was to make a new ''Chrono'' with the best available skills and technologies of today. I never had any intentions of just taking the system from ''Trigger'' and moving it onto the PlayStation console. That's why I believe that ''Cross'' is ''Cross'', and NOT ''Trigger 2''.<ref name</arg><arg>Masato Kato</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="When creating a series, one method is to carry over a basic system, improving upon it as the series progresses, but our stance has been to create a completely new and different world from the ground up, and to restructure the former style. Therefore, ''Chrono Cross'' is not a sequel to ''Chrono Trigger''. Had it been, it would have been called ''Chrono Trigger 2''. Our main objective for ''Chrono Cross'' was to share a little bit of the ''Chrono Trigger'' worldview, while creating a completely different game as a means of providing new entertainment to the player. This is mainly due to the transition in platform generation from the SNES to the PS. The method I mentioned above, about improving upon a basic system, has inefficiencies, in that it's impossible to maximize the console's performance as the console continues to make improvements in leaps and bounds. Although essentially an RPG, at its core, it is a computer game, and I believe that games should be expressed with a close connection to the console's performance. Therefore, in regards to game development, our goal has always been to "express the game utilizing the maximum performance of the console at that time." I strongly believe that anything created in this way will continue to be innovative.<ref name">"gameprointerview" /></arg><arg>Hiromichi Tanaka</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Full production began on<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>in mid-1998.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>team reached 80 members at its peak, with additional personnel of 1020 cut-scene artists and 100 quality assurance testers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>The team felt pressure to live up to the work of<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s &quot;Dream Team&quot; development group, which included famous Japanese<space/><link><target>Mangaka</target><part>manga artist</part></link><space/><link><target>Akira Toriyama</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>Kato and Tanaka hired<space/><link><target>Nobuteru Yki</target></link><space/>for character design and<space/><link><target>Yasuyuki Honne</target></link><space/>for art direction and concept art.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite video game</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross<space/></arg><arg name="developer">[[Square Co., Ltd.]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Square Co., Ltd.<space/></arg><arg name="date">1999-11-18<space/></arg><arg name="language">Japanese</arg></template></extension><space/>The event team originally envisioned a short game, and planned a system by which players would befriend any person in a town for alliance in battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Developers brainstormed traits and archetypes during the character-creation process, originally planning 64 characters with unique endings that could vary in three different ways per character.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Kato described the character creation process: &quot;Take Pierre, for example: we started off by saying we wanted a wacko fake hero like Tata from<space/><italics>Trigger</italics>. We also said things like 'we need at least one powerful mom,' 'no way we're gonna go without a twisted brat,' and so on so forth.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As production continued, the length of<space/><italics>Cross</italics><space/>increased, leading the event team to reduce the number of characters to 45 and scrap most of the alternate endings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Developers humorously named the character Pip &quot;Tsumaru&quot; in Japanese (which means &quot;packed&quot;) as a pun on their attempts to pack as much content into the game as possible.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>To avoid the burden of writing unique, accented dialogue for several characters, team member Kiyoshi Yoshii coded a system that produces accents by modifying basic text for certain characters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>Art director Nobuteru Yuuki initially wanted the characters to appear in a more<space/><italics><link><target>Chibi (term)</target><part>chibi</part></link></italics><space/>format with diminutive proportions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="missingpiece"></extension><space/>The game world's fusion of high technology and ethnic, tribal atmospheres proved challenging at first.<extension extension_name='ref' name="missingpiece"></extension><space/>He later recalled striving to harmonize the time period's level of technology, especially as reflected in characters' garb.<extension extension_name='ref' name="missingpiece"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross Missing Piece</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Supporting_Material_Translation.html#Missing_Piece</arg><arg name="language">Japanese</arg><arg name="publisher">Square Enix</arg><arg name="isbn">4925075721</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>team devised an original battle system using a stamina bar and Elements.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>Kato planned the system around allowing players to avoid repetitive gameplay (also known as &quot;<link><target>grinding (gaming)</target><part>grinding</part></link>&quot;) to gain combat experience.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>Hiromichi Tanaka likened the Elements system to card games, hoping players would feel a sense of complete control in battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>The team programmed each battle motion manually instead of performing motion capture.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Developers strove to include<space/><link><target>tongue-in-cheek</target></link><space/>humor in the battle system's techniques and animations to distance the game from the<space/><italics>Final Fantasy</italics><space/>franchise.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Masato Kato planned for the game's setting to feature a small archipelago, for fear that players would become confused traveling in large areas with respect to parallel worlds.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>He hoped El Nido would still impart a sense of grand scale, and the development team pushed hardware limitations in creating the game's world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>To create field maps, the team modeled locations in 3D, then chose the best angle for 2D rendering.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>The programmers of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>did not use any existing Square programs or routines to code the game, instead writing new, proprietary systems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>Other innovations included variable-<link><target>frame rate</target></link><space/>code for fast-forward and slow-motion gameplay (awarded as a bonus for completing the game) and a &quot;CD-read swap&quot; system to allow quick data retrieval.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Masato Kato directed and wrote the main story, leaving sub-plots and minor character events to other staff.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>The event team sometimes struggled to mesh their work on the plot due to the complexity of the parallel worlds concept.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Masato Kato confirmed that<space/><italics>Cross</italics><space/>featured a central theme of parallel worlds, as well as the fate of Schala, which he was previously unable to expound upon in<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>. Concerning the ending sequences showing Kid searching for someone in a modern city, he hoped to make players realize that alternate futures and possibilities may exist in their own lives, and that this realization would &quot;not&amp;nbsp;... stop with the game&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>He later added, &quot;Paraphrasing one novelist's favorite words, what's important is not the message or theme, but how it is portrayed as a game. Even in Cross, it was intentionally made so that the most important question was left unanswered.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>Kato described the finished story as &quot;ole' boy-meets-girl type of story&quot; with sometimes-shocking twists.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>Kato rode his motorcycle to relieve the stress of the game's release schedule.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>He continued refining event data during the final stages of development while the rest of the team undertook debugging and quality control work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>Square advertised the game by releasing a short demo of the first chapter with purchases of<space/><italics><link><target>Legend of Mana</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossdemo"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Chrono Cross Demo</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Chrono_Cross_Demo.html</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-08-10</arg></template></extension><space/>The North American version of<space/><italics>Cross</italics><space/>required three months of translation and two months of debugging before release.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>Richard Honeywood translated, working with Kato to rewrite certain dialogue for ease of comprehension in English.<extension extension_name='ref' name="edgemagazine"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">February 2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">Edge Online: Q&A – Square Enix's Richard Honeywood</arg><arg name="url">http://www.edge-online.co.uk/archives/2006/02/qa_square_enixs_1.php</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20060517012317/http://www.edge-online.co.uk/archives/2006/02/qa_square_enixs_1.php</arg><arg name="archivedate">2006-05-17</arg><arg name="work">Edge Online</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-08-14</arg></template></extension><space/>He also added instances of wordplay and alliteration to compensate for difficult Japanese jokes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="edgemagazine"></extension><space/>Although the trademark<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>was registered in the European Union, the game was not released in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">OAMI-ONLINE – CTM-ONLINE – Trade mark consultation service</arg><arg name="url">http://oami.europa.eu/CTMOnline/RequestManager/en_Result_NoReg</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-05-12</arg></template><space/>To find the Chrono Cross trademarks, search &quot;Trade mark name&quot; for &quot;chrono cross&quot;.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Music</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Music of Chrono Cross</arg></template><template><target>listen</target><arg name="filename">dreamtimedreams.ogg
</arg><arg name="title">"The Dream that Time Dreams"
</arg><arg name="description">A 30-second sample of ''The Dream that Time Dreams'', illustrating the use in the game's music of melodies established in [[Radical Dreamers]].
</arg><arg name="format">[[Ogg]]
</arg><arg name="filename2">scarsoftime.ogg
</arg><arg name="title2">"Scars of Time"
</arg><arg name="description2">A 30-second sample of ''Scars of Time'', the iconic title piece featuring the guitar playing of [[Tomohiko Kira]].
</arg><arg name="format2">[[Ogg]]
</arg><arg name="filename3">radicaldreamers.ogg
</arg><arg name="title3">"Radical Dreamers ~ Unstolen Jewel"
</arg><arg name="description3">A 30-second sample of game's credits theme, demonstrating the voice of [[Noriko Mitose]].
</arg><arg name="format3">[[Ogg]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>was scored by freelance video game music composer<space/><link><target>Yasunori Mitsuda</target></link>, who previously worked on<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>. Director Masato Kato personally commissioned Mitsuda's involvement, citing a need for the &quot;Chrono sound&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Kato envisioned a &quot;Southeast Asian feel, mixed with the foreign tastes and the tones of countries such as Greece&quot;; Mitsuda centered his work around<space/><link><target>old world</target></link><space/>cultural influences, including<space/><link><target>Mediterranean</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Fado</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Celtic music</target><part>Celtic</part></link>, and percussive<space/><link><target>Music of Africa</target><part>African</part></link><space/>music.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2000-12-18</arg><arg name="first">Yasunori</arg><arg name="last">Mitsuda</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross OST Liner Notes</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Music_(Chrono_Cross)</arg><arg name="work">Chrono Compendium</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-08-16</arg></template></extension><space/>Mitsuda cited visual inspiration for songs: &quot;All of my subjects are taken from scenery. I love artwork.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><space/>To complement the theme of parallel worlds, he gave<space/><italics>Another</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Home</italics><space/>respectively dark and bright moods, and hoped players would feel the emotions of &quot;'burning soul,' 'lonely world,' and 'unforgettable memories'&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Mitsuda and Kato planned music samples and sound effects with the philosophy of &quot;a few sounds with a lot of content&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Xenogears</target></link></italics><space/>contributor<space/><link><target>Tomohiko Kira</target></link><space/>played guitar on the beginning and ending themes.<space/><link><target>Noriko Mitose</target></link>, as selected by Masato Kato, sang the ending song&quot;Radical Dreamers The Unstolen Jewel&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/><link><target>Ryo Yamazaki</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>synthesizer programmer</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Square Enix</target></link>, helped Mitsuda transfer his ideas to the PlayStation's sound capabilities; Mitsuda was happy to accomplish even half of what he envisioned.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>Certain songs were ported from the score of<space/><italics><link><target>Radical Dreamers: Nusumenai Hseki</target><part>Radical Dreamers</part></link></italics>, such as<space/><italics>Gale</italics>,<space/><italics>Frozen Flame</italics>, and<space/><italics>Viper Mansion</italics>. Other entries in the soundtrack contain<space/><link><target>leitmotif</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Radical Dreamers</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>The melody of<space/><italics>Far Promise ~ Dream Shore</italics><space/>features prominently in<space/><italics>The Dream That Time Dreams</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Voyage ~ Another World.</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimania"></extension><space/>Masato Kato faced internal opposition in hiring Noriko Mitose:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Personally, for me, the biggest pressure was coming from the ending theme song. From the start of the project, I had already planned to make the ending into a Japanese song, but the problem was now "who was going to sing the song?" There was a lot of pressure from the people in the PR division to get someone big and famous to sing it, but I was totally against the idea. And as usual, I didn't heed to the surrounding complaints, but this time, there was a pretty tough struggle.<ref name">"kato-acknowledgment" /></arg><arg>Masato Kato</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Yasunori Mitsuda.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>alt=A photograph of a thin, dark-haired Japanese man</part><part>Yasunori Mitsuda, composer</part></link>Production required six months of work. After wrapping, Mitsuda and Kato played<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>to record their impressions and observe how the tracks intermingled with scenes; the ending theme brought Kato to tears.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="crossost"></extension><space/>Players who preordered the game received a sampler disc of five songs, and Square released a three-<link><target>Compact Disc</target><part>CD</part></link><space/>official soundtrack in Japan after the game's debut. The soundtrack won the Gold Prize for the PlayStation Awards of 2000.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mitsuda2008"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Yasunori</arg><arg name="last">Mitsuda</arg><arg name="date">2008-01-28</arg><arg name="title">Radical Dreamer: Yasunori Mitsuda Interview from 1UP.com</arg><arg name="url">http://www.1up.com/do/feature?pager.offset</arg><arg name="work">[[1UP.com]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-02-08</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2005, Square Enix reissued the soundtrack due to popular demand. Earlier that year, Mitsuda announced a new arranged<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>album, scheduled for release in July 2005.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dengekionline"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year"><space/>2005</arg><arg name="title">New Year's News</arg><arg name="url">http://www.dengekionline.com/2005newyear/comment/2004comment02.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Dengeki Online<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20060107065754/http://www.dengekionline.com/2005newyear/comment/2004comment02.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">2006-01-07</arg></template></extension><space/>Mitsuda's contract with Square gave him ownership and full rights to the soundtrack of<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sekitopsx"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2008-11-24</arg><arg name="title">Yasunori Mitsuda Talks Chrono Trigger</arg><arg name="url">http://www.originalsoundversion.com/?p</arg><arg name="publisher">Original Sound Version</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-13</arg></template></extension><space/>It was delayed, and at a<space/><link><target>Play! A Video Game Symphony</target></link><space/>concert in May 2006, he revealed it would feature acoustic music and would be &quot;out within the year&quot;, later backtracking and alleging a 2007 release date.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nsiderinterview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2006-05-30</arg><arg name="title">N-Sider: PLAY! Concert Interviews</arg><arg name="url">http://www.n-sider.com/articleview.php?articleid</arg><arg name="work">N-Sider</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://palgn.com.au/article.php?id</arg><arg name="title">Yasunori Mitsuda Interview</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-05-22</arg><arg name="last">Peter</arg><arg name="first">James</arg><arg name="date">2006-10-13</arg><arg name="publisher">PAL Gaming Network</arg></template></extension><space/>Mitsuda posted a streaming sample of a finished track on his personal website in January 2009, and has stated the album will be released to coincide with the 10th anniversary of the Japanese debut of<space/><italics>Cross</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RPGFARRANGE"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://rpgfan.com/news/2008/1555.html</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross 10th Anniversary Arrange Album Update</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-27</arg><arg name="last">Gann</arg><arg name="first">Patrick</arg></template></extension><space/>Music from<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>has been featured in the September 2009<space/><italics>Symphonic Fantasies</italics><space/>concerts, part of the<space/><link><target>Symphonic Game Music Concert</target></link><space/>series conducted by<space/><link><target>Arnie Roth</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="symphonicfantasies"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="publisher">Symphonic Fantasies</arg><arg name="url">http://www.symphonicfantasies.com/post/78838894/jonne-valtonen-the-award-winning-finnish-composer</arg><arg name="title">Music from classic games arranged by Jonne Valtonen</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2009-01-22</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-06-01</arg></template></extension><space/>The track &quot;Dimension Break&quot; was remixed by Mitsuda for inclusion on the charity album<space/><italics><link><target>Play For Japan</target></link></italics><space/>in 2011. That same year, the<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>theme &quot;Time's Scar&quot; was voted first place in Hardcore Gaming 101's &quot;Best Video Game Music of All Time&quot; poll.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Kalata</arg><arg name="first">Kurt</arg><arg name="title">Best Video Game Music of All Time - 2011</arg><arg name="url">http://hg101.kontek.net/vgm/bestvgm2011.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Hardcore Gaming 101</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 December 2011</arg><arg name="date">2011-10-25</arg></template></extension><space/>&quot;Time's Scar&quot; was also featured in 2012 by<space/><link><target>NPR</target></link><space/>in a program about classically-arranged video game scores.<extension extension_name='ref' name="npr"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">A Classical Musician's Game Theory</arg><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/2012/12/10/166875717/a-classical-musicians-game-theory</arg><arg name="publisher">NPR</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 April 2013</arg><arg name="date">2012-12-10</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Release and reception</heading><paragraph><template><target>Video game reviews</target><arg name="GR"><space/>92%<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="MC"><space/>94 / 100<space/><ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="EGM"><space/>98%<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="Fam"><space/>36 / 40<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="GamePro"><space/>{{rating|4.5|5}}<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="GameRev"><space/>A-<space/><ref>[http://www.game-revolution.com/games/sony/rpg/chrono_cross.htm Chrono Cross Review]</ref>
</arg><arg name="GSpot"><space/>10 / 10<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="IGN"><space/>9.7 / 10<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="OPM"><space/>{{rating|5|5}}<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="rev1"><space/>''[[GMR (magazine)|GMR]]''
</arg><arg name="rev1Score"><space/>10 / 10<space/><ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>shipped 850,000 and 650,000 units in Japan and abroad respectively.<extension extension_name='ref' name="square-sales"></extension><space/>It was re-released once in the United States as a<space/><link><target>List of Sony Greatest Hits games</target><part>Sony Greatest Hits</part></link><space/>title and again as part of the Japanese<space/><link><target>Ultimate Hit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>series.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ultimatehits"></extension><space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>was also released on the<space/><link><target>PlayStation Network</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link><space/>on July 6, 2011, and in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>on November 8, 2011, but a<space/><link><target>PAL</target></link><space/>region release has not been announced.<extension extension_name='ref' name="psnnetwork"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Chrono Cross Crossing to PSN in Japan<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.escapistmagazine.com/news/view/106154-Chrono-Cross-Crossing-to-PSN-in-Japan<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010-12-15<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Funk<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2011-02-02</arg></template></extension><space/>Critics praised the game's complex plot, innovative battle system, varied characters, moving score, vibrant graphics, and success in breaking convention with its predecessor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ignreview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="gamerankingsreview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2000-09-05</arg><arg name="author">Jake</arg><arg name="title">Game Rankings: Chrono Cross Review</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gamerankings.com/htmlpages3/196917.asp</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GameRankings]]</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2010-12-20</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="rpgfanreview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2002-06-22</arg><arg name="title">RPGFan: Chrono Cross Review</arg><arg name="url">http://www.rpgfan.com/reviews/chronocross/Chrono_Cross-5.html</arg><arg name="publisher">RPGFan</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>Electronic Gaming Monthly</target></link></italics><space/>gave<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>a Gold Award, scoring it 10/10/9.5 in their three reviewer format; the first review declared the game to be &quot;a masterpiece, plain and simple&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="egm"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20001119205300/www.zdnet.com/egm/stories/main/0,11589,2610315,00.html</arg><arg name="url">http://www.zdnet.com/egm/stories/main/0,11589,2610315,00.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">November 19, 2000</arg><arg name="title">Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="date">2000-08-08</arg><arg name="work">[[Electronic Gaming Monthly]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-15</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>GameSpot</target></link><space/>awarded the game a perfect 10, one of only nine games in the 40,000 games listed on Gamespot to have been given the score, and its Console Game of the Year Award for 2000.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><space/><link><target>IGN</target></link><space/>gave the game a score of 9.7, and<space/><italics>Cross</italics><space/>appeared 89th in its 2008 Top 100 games list.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ignreview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="greatest-games3"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="title">IGN Top 100 Games 2008 – 89 Chrono Cross</arg><arg name="url">http://top100.ign.com/2008/ign_top_game_89.html</arg><arg name="publisher">IGN</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-13</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>Famitsu</target></link></italics><space/>rated the game 36 out of 40 from four reviewers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weeklyfamitsu"></extension><space/>As of December 2010,<space/><link><target>GameRankings</target></link><space/>rates<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>at 92%.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gamerankings"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Reviewers thought the game's flaws were its vague ending, confusing plot elements, and narrative pacing problems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ignreview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="rpgfanreview"></extension><space/>Fan reaction was largely positive, though certain fans complained that the game was a far departure from its predecessor,<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>;<space/><italics>Chrono Cross</italics><space/>broke convention by featuring more characters, fewer double and triple techs, fewer instances of time travel, and few appearances of<space/><italics>Trigger</italics><space/>characters and locations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="perfect-10"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">November 1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">Procyon Studio: Interview with Masato Kato</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cocoebiz.com/mitsuda/english/friends/kato.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://www.chronocompendium.com/Term/Procyon_Studio.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">2004-07-07</arg></template></extension><space/>Producer Hiromichi Tanaka and director Masato Kato were aware of the changes in development, specifically intending to provide an experience different from<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>Kato anticipated and rebuffed this discontent before the game's release, wondering what the<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>title meant to these fans and whether his messages ever &quot;really got through to them&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>He continued, &quot;<italics>Cross</italics><space/>is undoubtedly the highest quality<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>that we can create right now. (I won't say the 'best'<space/><italics>Chrono</italics>, but) If you can't accept that, then I'm sorry to say this but I guess your<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>and my<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>have taken totally different paths. But I would like to say, thank you for falling in love with<space/><italics>Trigger</italics><space/>so much.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="kato-acknowledgment"></extension><space/>Tanaka added, &quot;Of course, the fans of the original are very important, but what innovation can come about when you're bound to the past? I believe that gameplay should evolve with the hardware.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameprointerview"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sequel</heading><paragraph>There is no planned continuation of the<space/><link><target>Chrono (series)</target><part>''Chrono'' series</part></link>. In 2001,<space/><link><target>Hironobu Sakaguchi</target></link><space/>revealed the company's staff wanted to develop a new game and were discussing script ideas. Although Kato was interested in a new title, the project had not been<space/><link><target>greenlight</target><trail>ed</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chrono3discussion"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Shahed</arg><arg name="last">Ahmed</arg><arg name="date">2001-07-03</arg><arg name="title">New Chrono game in planning stages</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gamespot.com/news/2782608.html</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GameSpot]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg></template></extension><space/>Square then registered a trademark for<space/><italics><link><target>Chrono Break</target></link></italics><space/>worldwide, causing speculation concerning a new sequel. Nothing materialized, and the trademark was dropped in the United States on November 13, 2003,<extension extension_name='ref' name="sadtrademark"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2003-11-13</arg><arg name="title">Latest Status Info</arg><arg name="url">http://tarr.uspto.gov/servlet/tarr?regser</arg><arg name="work">Trademark Applications and Registration Retrieval</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-01</arg></template></extension><space/>though it still stands in Japan and the European Union.<extension extension_name='ref' name="brake-trademark"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2002-07-26</arg><arg name="title">Japanese Trademark and Patent Office</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ipdl.inpit.go.jp/homepg_e.ipdl</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2006-07-24</arg></template><space/>To find the Chrono Break patent, search &quot;Japanese Trademark Database&quot; for &quot;chronobrake&quot;. Click Index to find the result, and click the link.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2002-12-02<space/></arg><arg name="title">OAMI-ONLINE – CTM-ONLINE – Trade mark consultation service<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://oami.europa.eu/CTMOnline/RequestManager/en_Result_NoReg<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-05-12</arg></template><space/>To find the Chrono Brake trademark, search &quot;Trade mark name&quot; for &quot;chrono brake&quot;.</extension><space/>Kato later returned to Square Enix as a freelancer to work on<space/><italics><link><target>Children of Mana</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Dawn of Mana</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="children-team"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2005-10-03</arg><arg name="first">Bryan</arg><arg name="last">Boulette</arg><arg name="title">Children of Mana Team Announced</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.rpgamer.com/news/Q4-2005/100305a.html</arg><arg name="publisher">[[RPGamer]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-24</arg></template></extension><space/>Mitsuda also expressed interest in scoring a new<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>series game.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nsiderinterview"></extension><space/>In 2005, Kato and Mitsuda teamed up to do a game called<space/><italics><link><target>Deep Labyrinth</target></link></italics>, and again in 2008 for<space/><italics><link><target>Sands of Destruction</target></link></italics>, both for the<space/><link><target>Nintendo DS</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="deep-labyrinth"><link type='external' href='http://www.gamesarefun.com/news.php?newsid=5528'>Deep Labyrinth (DS) Screenshots</link>, Games Are Fun. Retrieved July 2, 2006.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Brandon</arg><arg name="last">Sheffield</arg><arg name="title">Q&A: Sands of Destruction Team Talks Battle System, Story Creation</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gamasutra.com/view/news/26020/QA_Sands_of_Destruction_Team_Talks_Battle_System_Story_Creation.php</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Gamasutra]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-08-02</arg></template></extension><space/>The February 2008 issue of<space/><italics><link><target>Game Informer</target></link></italics><space/>ranked the<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>series eighth among the &quot;Top Ten Sequels in Demand&quot;, naming the games &quot;steadfast legacies in the Square Enix catalogue&quot; and asking &quot;what's the damn holdup?!&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gameinformer"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="date">February 2008</arg><arg name="title">[[Game Informer]]</arg><arg name="pages">24–25</arg><arg name="publisher">GameStop</arg></template></extension><space/>In<space/><italics>Electronic Gaming Monthly</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension>s June 2008 &quot;Retro Issue&quot;, writer Jeremy Parish cited<space/><italics>Chrono</italics><space/>as the franchise video game fans would be most thrilled to see a sequel to.<extension extension_name='ref' name="egmretro"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="date">June 2008</arg><arg name="first">Jeremy</arg><arg name="last">Parish</arg><arg name="title">Missing in Action</arg><arg name="page">95</arg><arg name="publisher">Ziff Davis Media</arg></template></extension><space/>In the May 1, 2009, issue of<space/><italics>Famitsu</italics>,<space/><italics>Chrono Trigger</italics><space/>placed 14th out of 50 in a vote of most-wanted sequels by the magazine's readers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="famitsu14"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="date">May 2009</arg><arg name="journal">[[Famitsu]]</arg><arg name="title">Famitsu Readers Vote Their Most Wanted Sequels</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ps3hyper.com/news/famitsu-readers-voted-their-most-wanted-sequels/</arg></template></extension><space/>At<space/><link><target>Electronic Entertainment Expo</target><part>E3</part></link><space/>2009, SE Senior Vice President<space/><link><target>Shinji Hashimoto</target></link><space/>remarked, &quot;If people want a sequel, they should buy more!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sevp"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Alex</arg><arg name="last">Donaldson</arg><arg name="date">2009-06-05</arg><arg name="title">Square: Want more Chrono Trigger? Buy More!</arg><arg name="url">http://www.rpgsite.net/news/342.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-06-15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Games/Video_Games/Roleplaying/C/Chrono_Series/Chrono_Cross/</arg><arg>''Chrono Cross''</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chronocompendium.com/'>Chrono Compendium</link>, a series encyclopedia</listitem><listitem><template><target>StrategyWiki</target></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Chrono series</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Role-playing video games introduced in 1999</target></link><link><target>Category:Chrono series</target></link><link><target>Category:New Game Plus video games</target></link><link><target>Category:PlayStation games</target></link><link><target>Category:PlayStation Network games</target></link><link><target>Category:Single-player-only video games</target></link><link><target>Category:1999 video games</target></link><link><target>Category:Video games featuring parallel universes</target></link></paragraph></article>