<article title='Annales_School'><paragraph><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>Annalists</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Annales School</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>a'nal</arg></template>) is a group of historians associated with a style of<space/><link><target>historiography</target></link><space/>developed by French<space/><link><target>historians</target></link><space/>in the 20th century to stress long-term social history. It is named after its scholarly journal<space/><italics><link><target>Annales d'histoire conomique et sociale</target></link></italics>, which remains the main source of scholarship, along with many books and monographs.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.editions.ehess.fr/revues/annales-histoire-sciences-sociales/numeros-parus/'>for recent issues</link></extension><space/>The school has been highly influential in setting the agenda for historiography in France and numerous other countries, especially regarding the use of<space/><link><target>social science</target><part>social scientific</part></link><space/>methods by historians, emphasizing social rather than political or diplomatic themes, and for being generally hostile to the class analysis of<space/><link><target>Marxist historiography</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The school deals primarily with late medieval and early modern Europe (before the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>), with little interest in later topics. It has dominated French social history and influenced historiography in Europe and Latin America. Prominent leaders include co-founders<space/><link><target>Lucien Febvre</target></link><space/>(18781956) and<space/><link><target>Marc Bloch</target></link><space/>(18861944). The second generation was led by<space/><link><target>Fernand Braudel</target></link><space/>(19021985) and included<space/><link><target>Georges Duby</target></link><space/>(19191996),<space/><link><target>Pierre Goubert</target></link><space/>(19152012),<space/><link><target>:fr:Robert Mandrou</target><part>Robert Mandrou</part></link><space/>(19211984),<space/><link><target>Pierre Chaunu</target></link><space/>(19232009),<space/><link><target>Jacques Le Goff</target></link><space/>(19242014), and<space/><link><target>Ernest Labrousse</target></link><space/>(18951988). Institutionally it is based on the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>journal, the SEVPEN publishing house, the<space/><template><target>Lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>Fondation Maison des sciences de l'homme</arg></template><space/>(FMSH), and especially the 6th Section of the<space/><link><target>cole pratique des hautes tudes</target></link>, all based in Paris. A third generation was led by<space/><link><target>Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie</target></link><space/>(1929 ) and includes Jacques Revel,<extension extension_name='ref'>Since 1978, Revel has taught at the Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales (Paris), where he is<space/><italics>directeur d'tudes</italics><space/>(full professor); he served as president of the Ecole from 1995 to 2004.</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Philippe Aris</target></link><space/>(19141984), who joined the group in 1978. The third generation stressed<space/><link><target>History of mentalities</target><part>history from the point of view of mentalities</part></link>, or<space/><italics>mentalits</italics>. The fourth generation of Annales historians, led by<space/><link><target>Roger Chartier</target></link><space/>(1945 ), clearly distanced itself from the mentalities approach, replaced by the<space/><link><target>Cultural turn</target><part>cultural</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>linguistic turn</target></link>, which emphasize analysis of the social history of cultural practices.</paragraph><preblock><preline><space/></preline></preblock><paragraph>The main scholarly outlet has been the journal<space/><italics>Annales d'Histoire Economique et Sociale</italics><space/>(&quot;Annals of economic and social history&quot;), founded in 1929 by Lucien Febvre and Marc Bloch, which broke radically with traditional historiography by insisting on the importance of taking all levels of society into consideration and emphasized the collective nature of mentalities. Its contributors viewed events as less fundamental than the mental frameworks that shaped decisions and practices.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Braudel was editor of<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>from 1956 to 1968, followed by the medievalist Jacques Le Goff. However, Braudel's informal successor as head of the school was Le Roy Ladurie. Noting the political upheavals in Europe and especially in France in 1968,<space/><link><target>Eric Hobsbawm</target></link><space/>argues that &quot;in France the virtual hegemony of Braudelian history and the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>came to an end after 1968, and the international influence of the journal dropped steeply.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Eric J. Hobsbawm</arg><arg name="title">Interesting times: a twentieth-century life</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Pantheon Books</arg><arg name="page">295</arg></template></extension><space/>Multiple responses were attempted by the school. Scholars moved in multiple directions, covering in disconnected fashion the social, economic, and cultural history of different eras and different parts of the globe. By the time of crisis the school was building a vast publishing and research network reaching across France, Europe, and the rest of the world. Influence indeed spread out from Paris, but few new ideas came in. Much emphasis was given to quantitative data, seen as the key to unlocking all of social history.<extension extension_name='ref'>One of numerous spin-off journals was<space/><italics>Histoire &amp; mesure</italics><space/>(1986 ), devoted to quantitative history.</extension><space/>However, the Annales ignored the developments in quantitative studies underway in the U.S. and Britain, which reshaped economic, political and demographic research.<extension extension_name='ref'>Georg G. Iggers, ''Historiography in the Twentieth Century: From Scientific Objectivity to the Postmodern Challenge,&quot; 5961.</extension><space/>An attempt to require an<space/><italics>Annales</italics>-written textbook for French schools was rejected by the government.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hunt (1986)</extension><space/>By 1980<space/><link><target>postmodern</target></link><space/>sensibilities undercut confidence in overarching metanarratives. As<space/><link><target>Jacques Revel</target></link><space/>notes, the success of the Annales School, especially its use of social structures as explanatory forces, contained the seeds of its own downfall, for there is &quot;no longer any implicit consensus on which to base the unity of the social, identified with the real.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt, &quot;Microanalysis and the Construction of the Social,&quot; in<space/><italics>Histories: French Constructions of the Past,</italics><space/>ed. by Jacques Revel and Lynn Hunt (1995) 480.</extension><space/>The Annales School kept its infrastructure, but lost its<space/><italics>mentalits</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>On the decline of Annales, see Hunt (1986); for a summary of the movement see Burke,<space/><italics>French Historical Revolution</italics>, 106107.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>The journal</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Annales d'histoire économique et sociale</arg></template>The journal began in Strasbourg as<space/><italics>Annales d'histoire conomique et sociale</italics>; it moved to Paris and kept the same name from 1929 to 1939. It was successively renamed<space/><italics>Annales d'histoire sociale</italics><space/>(19391942, 1945),<space/><italics>Mlanges d'histoire sociale</italics><space/>(19421944),<space/><italics>Annales. Economies, socits, civilisations</italics><space/>(19461994), and<space/><italics>Annales. Histoire, Sciences Sociales</italics><space/>(1994 ).<extension extension_name='ref' name="journal names">P. Burke,<space/><italics>The French Historical Revolution. The Annales School 192989</italics>, p. 116 n. 2.</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>In 1962 Braudel and Gaston Berger used Ford Foundation money and government funds to create a new independent foundation, the<space/><template><target>Lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>Fondation Maison des sciences de l'homme</arg></template><space/>(FMSH), which Braudel directed from 1970 until his death. In 1970 the 6th Section and the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>relocated to the FMSH building. FMSH set up elaborate international networks to spread the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>gospel across Europe and the world. In 2013 it began publication of an English language edition, with all the articles translated.</paragraph><paragraph>The scope of topics covered by the journal is vast and experimentalthere is a search for total history and new approaches. The emphasis is on social history, and very long-term trends, often using quantification and paying special attention to geography<extension extension_name='ref'>See Lucien Febvre,<space/><italics>La Terre et l'volution humaine</italics><space/>(1922), translated as<space/><italics>A Geographical Introduction to History</italics><space/>(London, 1932).</extension><space/>and to the intellectual world view of common people, or &quot;mentality&quot; (<italics>mentalit</italics>). Little attention is paid to political, diplomatic, or military history, or to biographies of famous men. Instead the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>focused attention on the synthesizing of historical patterns identified from social, economic, and cultural history, statistics, medical reports, family studies, and even psychoanalysis.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>was founded and edited by<space/><link><target>Marc Bloch</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lucien Febvre</target></link><space/>in 1929, while they were teaching at the<space/><link><target>University of Strasbourg</target></link><space/>and later in Paris. These authors, the former a medieval historian and the latter an early modernist, quickly became associated with the distinctive<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>approach, which combined geography, history, and the sociological approaches of the<space/><italics><link><target>Anne Sociologique</target></link></italics><space/>(many members of which were their colleagues at Strasbourg) to produce an approach which rejected the predominant emphasis on politics, diplomacy and war of many 19th and early 20th-century historians as spearheaded by historians whom Febvre called Les Sorbonnistes. Instead, they pioneered an approach to a study of long-term historical structures (<italics>la<space/><link><target>longue dure</target></link></italics>) over events and political transformations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Colin Jones, &quot;Olwen Hufton's 'Poor', Richard Cobb's 'People', and the Notions of the longue dure in French Revolutionary Historiography,&quot;<space/><italics>Past &amp; Present,</italics><space/>2006 Supplement (Volume 1), pp. 178203<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/past_and_present/v2006/2006.1Sjones.html'>in Project Muse</link></extension><space/>Geography, material culture, and what later Annalistes called<space/><italics>mentalits,</italics><space/>or the psychology of the epoch, are also characteristic areas of study. The goal of the Annales was to undo the work of the Sorbonnistes, to turn French historians away from the narrowly political and diplomatic toward the new vistas in social and economic history.<extension extension_name='ref'>J.H. Hexter, &quot;Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien,&quot;<space/><italics><space/>Historians,</italics><space/>pp. 61</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Co-founder<space/><link><target>Marc Bloch</target></link><space/>(18861944) was a quintessential modernist who studied at the elite cole Normale Suprieure, and in Germany, serving as a professor at the University of Strasbourg until he was called to the Sorbonne in Paris in 1936 as professor of economic history. Bloch's interests were highly interdisciplinary, influenced by the geography of<space/><link><target>Paul Vidal de la Blache</target></link><space/>(18451918)<extension extension_name='ref'>Jason Hilkovitch &amp; Max Fulkerson, &quot;Paul Vidal de la Blache: A biographical sketch&quot; at<space/><link type='external' href='http://wwwstage.valpo.edu/geomet/histphil/test/vidal.html'></link></extension><space/>and the sociology of<space/><link><target>mile Durkheim</target></link><space/>(18581917). His own ideas, especially those expressed in his masterworks,<space/><italics>French Rural History</italics><space/>(<italics>Les caractres originaux de l'histoire rurale franaise,</italics><space/>1931) and<space/><italics>Feudal Society</italics>, were incorporated by the second-generation Annalistes, led by<space/><link><target>Fernand Braudel</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Precepts</heading><paragraph><link><target>Georges Duby</target></link>, a leader of the school, wrote that the history he taught:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>relegated the sensational to the sidelines and was reluctant to give a simple accounting of events, but strived on the contrary to pose and solve problems and, neglecting surface disturbances, to observe the long and medium-term evolution of economy, society and civilisation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Georges Duby,<space/><italics>Le dimanche de Bouvines</italics><space/>(1973), forward</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The Annalistes, especially<space/><link><target>Lucien Febvre</target></link>, advocated a<space/><italics>histoire totale</italics>, or<space/><italics>histoire tout court</italics>, a complete study of a historic problem.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Postwar</heading><paragraph>Bloch was shot by the<space/><link><target>Gestapo</target></link><space/>during the German occupation of France in World War II for his active membership of the<space/><link><target>French Resistance</target></link>, and Febvre carried on the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>approach in the 1940s and 1950s. It was during this time that he mentored Braudel, who would become one of the best-known exponents of this school. Braudel's work came to define a &quot;second&quot; era of<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>historiography and was very influential throughout the 1960s and 1970s, especially for his work on the Mediterranean region in the era of<space/><link><target>Philip II of Spain</target></link>. Braudel developed the idea, often associated with Annalistes, of different modes of historical time:<space/><italics>l'histoire quasi immobile</italics><space/>(the quasi motionless history) of historical geography, the history of social, political and economic structures (<italics>la<space/><link><target>longue dure</target></link></italics>), and the history of men and events, in the context of their structures.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>While authors such as<space/><link><target>Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Marc Ferro</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jacques Le Goff</target></link><space/>continue to carry the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>banner, today the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>approach has been less distinctive as more and more historians do work in<space/><link><target>cultural history</target></link>,<space/><link><target>political history</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>economic history</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'><italics>Mentalits</italics></heading><paragraph>Bloch's<space/><italics>Les Rois Thaumaturges</italics><space/>(1924)<extension extension_name='ref'>Translated as<space/><italics>The Royal Touch: Monarchy and Miracles in France and England</italics><space/>(1990)</extension><space/>looked at the long-standing folk belief that the king could cure<space/><link><target>scrofula</target></link><space/>by his<space/><link><target>royal touch</target><part>thaumaturgic touch</part></link>. The kings of France and England indeed regularly practiced the ritual. Bloch was not concerned with the effectiveness of the royal touchhe acted instead like an anthropologist in asking why people believed it and how it shaped relations between king and commoner. The book was highly influential in introducing comparative studies (in this case France and England), as well as long durations (&quot;longue dure&quot;) studies spanning several centuries, even up to a thousand years, downplaying short-term events. Bloch's revolutionary charting of mentalities, or<space/><italics>mentalits</italics>, resonated with scholars who were reading Freud and Proust. In the 1960s,<space/><link><target>Robert Mandrou</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Georges Duby</target></link><space/>harmonized the concept of<space/><italics>mentalit</italics><space/>history with<space/><link><target>Fernand Braudel</target></link>'s structures of historical time and linked mentalities with changing social conditions. A flood of<space/><italics>mentalit</italics><space/>studies based on these approaches appeared during the 1970s and 1980s. By the 1990s, however,<space/><italics>mentalit</italics><space/>history had become interdisciplinary to the point of fragmentation, but still lacked a solid theoretical basis. While not explicitly rejecting<space/><italics>mentalit</italics><space/>history, younger historians increasingly turned to other approaches.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Braudel</heading><paragraph>Fernand Braudel became the leader of the second generation after 1945. He obtained funding from the Rockefeller Foundation in New York and founded the 6th Section of the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, which was devoted to the study of history and the social sciences. It became an independent degree-granting institution in 1975 under the name<space/><link><target>School for Advanced Studies in the Social Sciences</target><part>cole des Hautes tudes en Sciences Sociales</part></link><space/>(EHESS). Braudel's followers admired his use of the longue dure approach to stress slow, and often imperceptible effects of space, climate and technology on the actions of human beings in the past. The<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>historians, after living through two world wars and incredible political upheavals in France, were deeply uncomfortable with the notion that multiple ruptures and discontinuities created history. They preferred to stress inertia and the longue dure. Special attention was paid to geography, climate, and demography as long-term factors. They believed the continuities of the deepest structures were central to history, beside which upheavals in institutions or the superstructure of social life were of little significance, for history lies beyond the reach of conscious actors, especially the will of revolutionaries. They rejected the Marxist idea that history should be used as a tool to foment and foster revolutions. In turn the Marxists called them conservatives.<extension extension_name='ref'>Olivia Harris, &quot;Braudel: Historical Time and the Horror of Discontinuity.&quot;<space/><italics>History Workshop Journal</italics><space/>(2004) (57): 161174. Issn: 1363-3554 Fulltext:<space/><link><target>OUP</target></link>. Only Aris was a true conservativeindeed a royalist.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Braudel's first book,<space/><italics>La Mditerrane et le Monde Mditerranen l'Epoque de Philippe II</italics><space/>(1949) (<italics>The Mediterranean and the Mediterranean World in the Age of Philip II</italics>) was his most influential. This vast panoramic view used ideas from other social sciences, employed effectively the technique of the longue dure, and downplayed the importance of specific events and individuals. It stressed geography but not<space/><italics>mentalit</italics>. It was widely admired, but most historians did not try to replicate it and instead focused on their specialized monographs. The book dramatically raised the worldwide profile of the Annales School.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Regionalism</heading><paragraph>Before<space/><italics>Annales,</italics><space/>French history supposedly happened in Paris. Febvre broke decisively with this paradigm in 1912, with his sweeping doctoral thesis on<space/><italics>Philippe II et la<space/><link><target>Franche-Comt</target></link>.</italics><space/>The geography and social structure of this region overwhelmed and shaped the king's policies set in Paris.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>historians did not try to replicate Braudel's vast geographical scope in<space/><italics>La Mditerrane.</italics><space/>Instead they focused on regions in France over long stretches of time. The most important was the study of the<space/><italics>Peasants of Languedoc</italics><space/>by Braudel's star pupil and successor Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie.<extension extension_name='ref'>Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie,<space/><italics>The Peasants of Languedoc,</italics><space/>(1966, translated 1977)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0252006356'>excerpt and text search</link></extension><space/>The regionalist tradition flourished especially in the 1960s and 1970s in the work of Pierre Goubert in 1960 on Beauvais and Ren Baehrel on Basse-Provence.<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>historians in the 1970s and 1980s turned to urban regions, including Pierre Deyon (Amiens), Maurice Garden (Lyon), Jean-Pierre Bardet (Rouen), Georges Freche (Toulouse), and Jean-Claude Perrot (Caen). By the 1970s the shift was underway from the earlier economic history to cultural history and the history of mentalities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ernst Hinrichs, &quot;Provinzen, Landschaften, Regionen in Der Modernen Franzsischen Geschichtswissenschaft Ein Essay,&quot;<space/><italics>Bltter Fr Deutsche Landesgeschichte</italics><space/>1994 130: 112. Issn: 0006-4408 Fulltext:<space/><link type='external' href='http://periodika.digitale-sammlungen.de/bdlg/Blatt_bsb00000334,00007.html'>online edition</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Impact outside France</heading><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>school systematically reached out to create an impact on other countries. Its success varied widely.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burke,<space/><italics>French Historical Revolution</italics><space/>(1990) ch 5.</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>approach was especially well received in Italy and Poland.<space/><link><target>Franciszek Bujak</target></link><space/>(18751953) and<space/><link><target>Jan Rutkowski</target></link><space/>(18861949), the founders of modern economic history in Poland and of the journal<space/><italics>Roczniki Dziejw Spolecznych i Gospodarczych</italics><space/>(1931 ), were attracted to the innovations of the Annales school. Rutkowski was in contact with Bloch and others, and published in the<space/><italics>Annales.</italics><space/>After the Communists took control in the 1940s Polish scholars were safer working on the Middle Ages and the early modern era rather than contemporary history. After the &quot;<link><target>Polish October</target></link>&quot; of 1956 the Sixth Section in Paris welcomed Polish historians and exchanges between the circle of the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>and Polish scholars continued until the early 1980s. The reciprocal influence between the French school and Polish historiography was particularly evident in studies on the Middle Ages and the early modern era studied by Braudel.<extension extension_name='ref'>Anita Krystyna Shelton,<space/><italics>The Democratic Idea in Polish History and Historiography</italics><space/>(1989). Even the Marxist journal<space/><italics>Kwartalnik Historii Kultury Materialnej,</italics><space/>founded in 1953, had an<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>flavor.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In South America the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>approach became popular. From the 1950s<space/><link><target>Federico Brito Figueroa</target></link><space/>was the founder of a new Venezuelan historiography based largely on the ideas of the Annales School. Brito Figueroa carried his conception of the field to all levels of university study, emphasizing a systematic and scientific approach to history and placing it squarely in the social sciences. Spanish historiography was influenced by the &quot;Annales School&quot; starting in 1950 with Jaime Vincens Vives (19101960).<extension extension_name='ref'>Nil Santiez-Ti, &quot;Temporalidad y discurso histrico: Propuesta de una renovacin metodolgica de la historia de la literatura espaola moderna.&quot; [Temporality and Historical Discourse: Proposal of a Methodological Renewal of the History of Modern Spanish Literature].<space/><italics>Hispanic Review</italics><space/>1997 65(3): 267290. Issn: 0018-2176 Fulltext:<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0018-2176%28199722%2965%3A3%3C267%3ATYDHPD%3E2.0.CO%3B2-%23'>in Jstor</link></extension><space/>In Mexico, exiled Republican intellectuals extended the Annales approach, particularly from the Center for Historical Studies of El Colegio de Mxico, the leading graduate studies institution of Latin America.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>British historians, apart from a few Marxists, were generally hostile. Academic historians decidedly sided with<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Elton</target></link>'s<space/><italics>The Practice of History</italics><space/>against<space/><link><target>Edward Hallett Carr</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>What Is History?</target></link></italics>. American, German, Indian, Russian and Japanese scholars generally ignored the school. The Americans developed their own form of &quot;new social history&quot; from entirely different roots. Both the American and the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>historians picked up important family reconstitution techniques from French demographer Louis Henry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burke,<space/><italics>French Historical Revolution</italics><space/>(1990), pp 56, 96100.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Wageningen University and Research Centre</target><part>Wageningen</part></link><space/>school centered on<space/><link><target>Bernard Slicher van Bath</target></link><space/>was viewed internationally as a Dutch counterpart of the Annales school, although Slicher van Bath himself vehemently rejected the idea of a quantitative &quot;school&quot; of historiography.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="first">Jan<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kuys<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bernard Hendrik Slicher van Bath<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Biografisch Woordenboek Gelderland<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Verloren<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.biografischwoordenboekgelderland.nl/bio/6_Bernard_Hendrik_Slicher_van_Bath</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Current</heading><paragraph>The current leader is<space/><link><target>Roger Chartier</target></link>, who is Directeur d'tudes at the<space/><link><target>School for Advanced Studies in the Social Sciences</target><part>cole des Hautes tudes en Sciences Sociales</part></link><space/>in Paris, Professeur in the<space/><link><target>Collge de France</target></link>, and Annenberg Visiting Professor of History at the<space/><link><target>University of Pennsylvania</target></link>. He frequently lectures and teaches in the United States, Spain, Mexico, Brazil and Argentina. His work in Early Modern European History focuses on the history of education, the history of the book and the history of reading. Recently, he has been concerned with the relationship between written culture as a whole and literature (particularly theatrical plays) for France, England and Spain. His work in this specific field (based on the criss-crossing between literary criticism, bibliography, and sociocultural history) is connected to broader historiographical and methodological interests which deal with the relation between history and other disciplines: philosophy, sociology, anthropology.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Chartier's typical undergraduate course focuses upon the making, remaking, dissemination, and reading of texts in early modern Europe and America. Under the heading of &quot;practices,&quot; his class considers how readers read and marked up their books, forms of note-taking, and the interrelation between reading and writing from copying and translating to composing new texts. Under the heading of &quot;materials,&quot; his class examines the relations between different kinds of writing surfaces (including stone, wax, parchment, paper, walls, textiles, the body, and the heart), writing implements (including styluses, pens, pencils, needles, and brushes), and material forms (including scrolls, erasable tables, codices, broadsides and printed forms and books). Under the heading of &quot;places,&quot; his class explores where texts were made, read, and listened to, including monasteries, schools and universities, offices of the state, the shops of merchants and booksellers, printing houses, theaters, libraries, studies, and closets. The texts for his course include the<space/><italics>Bible</italics>, translations of Ovid,<space/><italics>Hamlet</italics>,<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, Montaigne's essays, Pepys's diary, Richardson's<space/><italics>Pamela</italics>, and Franklin's autobiography.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dorothea Kraus, &quot;Appropriation et pratiques de la lecture. Les fondements mthodologiques et thoriques de l'approche de l'histoire culturelle de Roger Chartier&quot;, in :<space/><italics>Labyrinthe</italics><space/>n 3, 1999, 28<space/><link type='external' href='http://labyrinthe.revues.org/index56.html'>online</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>cole des hautes tudes en sciences sociales</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Historiography</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rural history</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nouvelle histoire</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Social history</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Aurell i Cardona, Jaume. &quot;Autobiographical Texts as Historiographical Sources: Rereading Fernand Braudel and Annie Kriegel,&quot;<space/><italics>Biography,</italics><space/>Volume 29, Number 3, Summer 2006, pp.&amp;nbsp;425445<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/biography/v029/29.3aurell.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Bintliff, John L. (ed.),<space/><italics>The Annales School and archaeology</italics>, Leicester : Leicester University Press (1991), ISBN 978-0-7185-1758-8</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Burguire, Andr.<space/><italics>L'cole des Annales: Une histoire intellectuelle.</italics><space/>Paris: Odile Jacob. 2006. Pp.&amp;nbsp;366. (English edition)<space/><italics>Annales School: An Intellectual History.</italics><space/>Ithaca NY: Cornell University Press. 2009. Pp.&amp;nbsp;309</listitem><listitem>Burke, Peter.<space/><italics>The French Historical Revolution: The Annales School 192989,</italics><space/>(1990), the major study in English<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0804718369'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Carrard, Philippe. &quot;Figuring France: The Numbers and Tropes of Fernand Braudel,&quot;<space/><italics>Diacritics</italics>, Vol. 18, No. 3 (Autumn, 1988), pp.&amp;nbsp;219<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0300-7162(198823)18%3A3%3C2%3AFFTNAT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Carrard, Philippe.<space/><italics>Poetics of the New History: French Historical Discourse from Braudel to Chartier,</italics><space/>(1992)</listitem><listitem>Clark, Stuart, ed.<space/><italics>The Annales School: Critical Assessments</italics><space/>(4 vol, 1999)</listitem><listitem>Crif, Giuliano. &quot;Scuola delle Annales e storia del diritto: la situazione italiana&quot;,<space/><italics>Mlanges de l'cole franaise de Rome: antiquit</italics>, vol. No. 93, (1981), pp.&amp;nbsp; 483-494<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/article/mefr_0223-5102_1981_num_93_1_1283'>in Perse</link></listitem><listitem>Dewald, Jonathan.<space/><italics>Lost Worlds: The Emergence of French Social History, 18151970</italics><space/>(2006) 250pp<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0271028904'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Dosse, Francois.<space/><italics>New History in France: The Triumph of the Annales,</italics><space/>(1994, first French edition, 1987)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0252063732'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Fink, Carole.<space/><italics>Marc Bloch: A Life in History,</italics><space/>(1989)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0521406714'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Forster, Robert. &quot;Achievements of the Annales School,&quot;<space/><italics>The Journal of Economic History,</italics><space/>Vol. 38, No. 1, (Mar., 1978), pp.&amp;nbsp;5876<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-0507(197803)38%3A1%3C58%3AAOTAS%3E2.0.CO%3B2-R'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Friedman, Susan W.<space/><italics>Marc Bloch, Sociology and Geography: Encountering Changing Disciplines</italics><space/>(1996)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0521561574'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Harris, Olivia. &quot;Braudel: Historical Time and the Horror of Discontinuity,&quot;<space/><italics>History Workshop Journal,</italics><space/>Issue 57, Spring 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;161174<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/history_workshop_journal/v057/57.1harris.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Herubel, Jean-Pierre V. M. &quot;Historiography's Horizon and Imperative: Febvrian Annales Legacy and Library History as Cultural History,&quot;<space/><italics>Libraries &amp; Culture,</italics><space/>Volume 39, Number 3, Summer 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;293312<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/libraries_and_culture/v039/39.3herubel01.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Hexter, J. H. &quot;Fernand Braudel and the Monde Braudellien,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Modern History,</italics><space/>1972, vol. 44, pp.&amp;nbsp;480539<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2801(197212)44%3A4%3C480%3AFBATMB%3E2.0.CO%3B2-6'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Hufton, Olwen. &quot;Fernand Braudel&quot;,<space/><italics>Past and Present,</italics><space/>No. 112. (Aug., 1986), pp.&amp;nbsp;208213.<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0031-2746(198608)112%3C208%3AFB%3E2.0.CO%3B2-7'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lynn Hunt</target><part>Hunt, Lynn</part></link>. &quot;French History in the Last Twenty Years: the Rise and Fall of the Annales Paradigm.&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Contemporary History</italics><space/>1986 21(2): 209224. Issn: 0022-0094 Fulltext:<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-0094%28198604%2921%3A2%3C209%3AFHITLT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-W'>in Jstor</link></listitem><listitem>Huppert, George. &quot;Lucien Febvre and Marc Bloch: The Creation of the Annales.&quot;<space/><italics>The French Review</italics><space/>Vol. 55, No. 4 (Mar., 1982), pp.&amp;nbsp;510513<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0016-111X%28198203%2955%3A4%3C510%3ALFAMBT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-H'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Iggers, G.G.<space/><italics>Historiography in the Twentieth Century: From Scientific Objectivity to the Postmodern Challenge</italics><space/>(1997), ch.5</listitem><listitem>Leroux, Robert,<space/><italics>Histoire et sociologie en France: de l'histoire-science la sociologie durkheimienne</italics>, Paris, Presses universitaires de France, 1998.</listitem><listitem>Long, Pamela O. &quot;The Annales and the History of Technology,&quot;<space/><italics>Technology and Culture,</italics><space/>Volume 46, Number 1, January 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;177186<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/technology_and_culture/v046/46.1long.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Megill, Allan. &quot;Coherence and Incoherence in Historical Studies: From the Annales School to the New Cultural History,&quot;<space/><italics>New Literary History,</italics>olume 35, Number 2, Spring 2004, pp.&amp;nbsp;207231<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/new_literary_history/v035/35.2megill.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Rubin, Miri.<space/><italics>The Work of Jacques Le Goff and the Challenges of Medieval History</italics><space/>(1997) 272 pages<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=Kwdr0Ws3KjwC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=inauthor:Miri+inauthor:Rubin&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;num=30&amp;amp;as_brr=0&amp;amp;ei=1LdnR-74OIWCtgOw0-WfAw&amp;amp;sig=LSYI-99vMK5s_sstLuWeCjsc3jw'>excerpts and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Moon, David. &quot;Fernand Braudel and the Annales School&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.scribd.com/doc/185264/Fernand-Braudel-and-the-Annales-School'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Poirrier, Philippe.<space/><italics>Aborder l'histoire</italics>, Paris, Seuil, 2000.</listitem><listitem>Roberts, Michael. &quot;The Annales school and historical writing.&quot; in Peter Lambert and Phillipp Schofield, eds.<space/><italics>Making History: An Introduction to the History and Practices of a Discipline.</italics><space/>(2004), pp 7892<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/read/107980518#'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Schilling, Derek. &quot;Everyday Life and the Challenge to History in Postwar France: Braudel, Lefebvre, Certeau,&quot;<space/><italics>Diacritics,</italics><space/>Volume 33, Number 1, Spring 2003, pp.&amp;nbsp;2340<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/diacritics/v033/33.1schilling.html'>in Project Muse</link></listitem><listitem>Steiner, Frederick. &quot;Material Life: Human Ecology and the Annales School&quot;, Landscape Architecture Volume 76, Number 1, pp.&amp;nbsp;6975.</listitem><listitem>Stirling, Katherine. &quot;Rereading Marc Bloch: the Life and Works of a Visionary Modernist.&quot;<space/><italics>History Compass</italics><space/>2007 5(2): 525538. Issn: 1478-0542 in<space/><link><target>History Compass</target></link></listitem><listitem>Stoianovich, Traian.<space/><italics>French Historical Method: The Annales Paradigm,</italics><space/>(1976)</listitem><listitem>Trevor-Roper, H. R. &quot;Fernand Braudel, the Annales, and the Mediterranean,&quot;<space/><italics>The Journal of Modern History,</italics><space/>Vol. 44, No. 4 (December, 1972), pp.&amp;nbsp;468479<space/><link type='external' href='http://links.jstor.org/sici?sici=0022-2801(197212)44%3A4%3C468%3AFBTAAT%3E2.0.CO%3B2-0'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Wrzosek, Wojciech.<italics>Historia, kultura, metafora. Powstanie nieklasycznej historiografii</italics><space/>(1995)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Major books and essays from the school</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Aris, Philippe et al. eds,<space/><italics>A History of Private Life</italics><space/>(5 vols. 198794)</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Bloch, Marc.<space/><italics>Les Rois Thaumaturges</italics><space/>(1924), translated as<space/><italics>The Royal Touch: Monarchy and Miracles in France and England</italics><space/>(1990)</listitem><listitem>Bloch, Marc.<space/><italics>Feudal Society: Vol 1: The Growth and Ties of Dependence</italics><space/>(1989);<space/><italics>Feudal Society: Vol 2: Social Classes and Political Organisation</italics>(1989)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0415039185'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Bloch, Marc.<space/><italics>French Rural History an Essay on Its Basic Characteristics</italics><space/>(1972)</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Braudel, Fernand.<space/><italics>La Mditerrane et le Monde Mditerranen l'Epoque de Philippe II</italics><space/>(1949) (translated as<space/><italics>The Mediterranean and the Mediterranean World in the Age of Philip II</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0520203089'>excerpt and text search vol. 1</link>)</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Braudel, Fernand.<space/><italics>Civilisation Matrielle, Economie et Capitalisme XVeXVIIIe Sicle</italics><space/>(3 vol. 1979) (translated as<space/><italics>Capitalism and Material Life</italics>;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0520081145'>excerpt and text search vol. 1</link>;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0520081161'>excerpt and text search vol 3</link>)</listitem><listitem>Burguire, Andr, and Jacques Revel.<space/><italics>Histoire de la France</italics><space/>(1989), textbook</listitem><listitem>Chartier, Roger.<space/><italics>Inscription and Erasure: Literature and Written Culture from the Eleventh to the Eighteenth Century</italics><space/>(2007)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0812239954'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Earle, P., ed.<space/><italics>Essays in European Economic History, 15001800,</italics><space/>(1974), translated articles from<space/><italics>Annales</italics></listitem><listitem>Ferro, Marc, ed.<space/><italics>Social Historians in Contemporary France: Essays from &quot;Annales&quot;,</italics><space/>(1972)</listitem><listitem>Goubert, Pierre.<space/><italics>The French Peasantry in the Seventeenth Century</italics><space/>(1986)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0521312698'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Goubert, Pierre.<space/><italics>The Ancien Rgime, 16001750</italics><space/>(1974)</listitem><listitem>Le Roy Ladurie, Emmanuel.<space/><italics>Montaillou: Cathars and Catholics in a French Village, 12941324</italics><space/>(1978)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0394729641'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Le Roy Ladurie, Emmanuel.<space/><italics>The Peasants of Languedoc</italics><space/>(1966; English translation 1974)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0252006356'>search</link></listitem><listitem>Hunt, Lynn, and Jacques Revel (eds).<space/><italics>Histories: French Constructions of the Past</italics>. The New Press. 1994. (A collection of 64 essays with many pieces from the Annales).</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Historiography from the school</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Bloch, Marc.<space/><italics>Mthodologie Historique</italics><space/>(1988); originally conceived in 1906 but not published until 1988; revised in 1996</listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Bloch, Marc.<space/><italics>Apologie pour l'histoire ou Mtier d'historien</italics><space/>(1949), translated as<space/><italics>The Historian's Craft</italics><space/>(1953)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=YZdCcT_1Z8YC&amp;amp;pg=PP1&amp;amp;dq=intitle:The+intitle:Historian%27s+intitle:Craft+inauthor:bloch&amp;amp;lr=&amp;amp;num=30&amp;amp;as_brr=0&amp;amp;ei=ObJnR7LDFIiUtgPAxdyhAw&amp;amp;sig=MM6otw23Cw_plPOu12kJ77tMJLw'>excerpt of 1992 introduction by Peter Burke (historian), and text search</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Braudel, Fernand.<space/><italics>Ecrits sur l'histoire</italics><space/>(1969), reprinted essays; translated as<space/><italics>On History,</italics><space/>(1980)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0226071510'>excerpt and text search</link><list type='bullet'><listitem>includes<space/><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>Braudel, Fernand. &quot;Histoire et Science Sociale: La Longue Dure&quot; (1958)<space/><italics>Annales E.S.C.,</italics><space/>13:4 OctoberDecember 1958, 725753</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Braudel, Fernand. &quot;Personal Testimony.&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Modern History</italics><space/>1972 44(4): 448467. Issn: 0022-2801<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1876804'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter Burke (historian)</target><part>Burke, Peter</part></link>, ed.<space/><italics>A New Kind of History From the Writings of Lucien Febvre,</italics><space/>(1973)</listitem><listitem>Duby, Georges.<space/><italics>History Continues,</italics><space/>(1991, translated 1994)</listitem><listitem>Febvre, Lucien.<space/><italics>A New Kind of History: From the Writings of Lucien Febvre</italics><space/>ed. by<space/><link><target>Peter Burke (historian)</target><part>Peter Burke</part></link><space/>(1973) translated articles from<space/><italics>Annales</italics></listitem><listitem>Le Roy Ladurie, Emmanuel.<space/><italics>The Mind and Method of the Historian</italics><space/>(1981)</listitem><listitem>Le Roy Ladurie, Emmanuel.<space/><italics>The Territory of the Historian</italics><space/>(1979)</listitem><listitem>Le Goff, Jacques and Paul Archambault. &quot;An Interview with Jacques Le Goff.&quot;<space/><italics>Historical Reflections</italics><space/>1995 21(1): 155185. ISSN 0315-7997</listitem><listitem>Le Goff, Jacques, ''History and Memory' (1996)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/023107591X'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Revel, Jacques, and Lynn Hunt, eds.<space/><italics>Histories: French Constructions of the Past,</italics><space/>(1995). 654pp</listitem><listitem>Revel, Jacques, ed.<space/><italics>Political Uses of the Past: The Recent Mediterranean Experiences</italics><space/>(2002)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0714682446'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Vovelle, M.<space/><italics>Ideologies and Mentalities</italics><space/>(1990)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.persee.fr/web/revues/home/prescript/revue/ahess'>Free access to all issues of the ''Annales'' from 1929 to 2002.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.editions.ehess.fr/revues/annales-histoire-sciences-sociales/numeros-parus/'>Recent issues of '' Annales: Histoire, Sciences Sociales'' (2003-present).</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://web.archive.org/web/20050525101030/http://www.strath.ac.uk/Departments/History/s_adams/annales.htm'>Professor David Moon, &quot;Fernand Braudel and the Annales School&quot; (lecture 2005)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.age-of-the-sage.org/history/historian/Fernand_Braudel.html'>Biography of Fernand Braudel.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www2.warwick.ac.uk/fac/arts/history/undergraduate/modules/hi323/seminar5/'>Detailed bibliographies of major historians.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://histoiremesure.revues.org/sommairepersee128454.html'>''Histoire et mesure'' (1986-200 ), articles on quantitative history. Full text of articles.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Annales School</target></template><template><target>Theories of History</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Historiography</target></link><link><target>Category:Theories of history</target></link><link><target>Category:20th century</target></link><link><target>Category:Historiography of France</target></link></paragraph></article>