<article title='Benedict_of_Nursia'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Saint Benedict</arg><arg>other saints named Benedict</arg><arg>Benedict (disambiguation){{!}}Benedict</arg></template><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>St. Benedict</arg><arg>organisations with this name</arg><arg>St. Benedict's (disambiguation){{!}}St. Benedict's</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><template><target>Infobox saint</target><arg name="name">Saint Benedict of Norcia
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>c. 480
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>21 March 543 
</arg><arg name="feast_day">11 July ([[General Roman Calendar]]), (Anglican Communion)<br>14 March ([[Byzantine Rite]])<br>21 March (pre-1970 General Roman Calendar)
</arg><arg name="venerated_in">[[Roman Catholicism]]<br>Anglican Communion<br>[[Eastern Orthodoxy]]<br>[[Lutheran Church]]
</arg><arg name="image">Fra Angelico 031.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize">220px
</arg><arg name="caption">''Saint Benedict''<space/><small>Detail from a fresco by [[Fra Angelico]]</small>
</arg><arg name="birth_place">Norcia (Umbria, Italy)
</arg><arg name="death_place">Monte Cassino
</arg><arg name="titles">Abbot<br>Patron of Europe
</arg><arg name="beatified_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="beatified_place">
</arg><arg name="beatified_by">
</arg><arg name="canonized_date">1220
</arg><arg name="canonized_place">Rome
</arg><arg name="canonized_by">[[Pope Honorius III]]
</arg><arg name="attributes">-Bell<br>-Broken tray<br>-Broken cup and serpent representing poison<br>-Broken utensil<br>-Bush<br>-Crosier<br>-Man in a Benedictine cowl holding Benedict's rule or a rod of discipline<br>-Raven
</arg><arg name="patronage">-Against poison<br>-Against witchcraft<br>-Agricultural workers<br>-Cavers<br>-Civil engineers<br>-[[Coppersmith]]s<br>-Dying people<br>-[[Erysipelas]]<br>-Europe<br>-Farmers<br>-Fever<br>-Gall stones<br>-[[Heerdt]] (Germany)<br>-[[Heraldry]] and [[Officers of arms]]<br>-the [[Institute of Christ the King Sovereign Priest]]<br>-Inflammatory diseases<br>-Italian architects<br>-Kidney disease<br>-Monks<br>-Nettle rash<br>-Norcia, (Italy)<br>-People in religious orders<br>-Schoolchildren<br>-Servants who have broken their master's belongings<br>-Speliologists<br>-Spelunkers<br>-Temptations
</arg><arg name="major_shrine">Monte Cassino Abbey, with his burial<br>
[[Saint-Benoît-sur-Loire]], near [[Orléans]], France<br>
Sacro Speco, at Subiaco, Italy
</arg><arg name="suppressed_date">
</arg><arg name="issues">
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Benedict of Nursia</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-it</target><arg>San Benedetto da Norcia</arg></template>) (c. 480 543 or 547) is a Christian saint, honoured by the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Anglican Communion</target><part>Anglican Church</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="Barry1995"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Barry</arg><arg name="first">Patrick</arg><arg name="title">St. Benedict and Christianity in England</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 November 2012</arg><arg name="date">1 July 1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Gracewing Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn">9780852443385</arg><arg name="page">32</arg></template></extension><space/>as the<space/><link><target>Patron saints of Europe</target><part>patron saint of Europe</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="SHMI"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Fr. Paolo O. Pirlo, SHMI</arg><arg name="title">My First Book of Saints</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Sons of Holy Mary Immaculate - Quality Catholic Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">971-91595-4-5</arg><arg name="pages">145–147</arg><arg name="chapter">St. Benedict</arg></template></extension><space/>and students.</paragraph><paragraph>Benedict founded twelve communities for monks at<space/><link><target>Subiaco, Italy</target></link><space/>(about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg></template><space/>to the east of Rome), before moving to<space/><link><target>Monte Cassino</target></link><space/>in the mountains of<space/><link><target>southern Italy</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Order of St Benedict</target></link><space/>is of later origin and, moreover, not an &quot;order&quot; as commonly understood but merely a confederation of autonomous congregations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holder2009"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Holder</arg><arg name="first">Arthur G.</arg><arg name="title">Christian Spirituality: The Classics</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 November 2012</arg><arg name="date">29 July 2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis</arg><arg name="isbn">9780415776028</arg><arg name="page">70</arg><arg name="quote">Today, tens of thousands of men and women throughout the world profess to live their lives according to Benedict's ''Rule''. These men and women are associated with over two thousand Roman Catholic, Anglican, and ecumenical Benedictine monasteries on six continents.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Benedict's main achievement is his &quot;<link><target>Rule of Saint Benedict</target></link>&quot;, containing<space/><link><target>precepts</target></link><space/>for his monks. It is heavily influenced by the writings of<space/><link><target>John Cassian</target></link>, and shows strong affinity with the<space/><link><target>Rule of the Master</target></link>. But it also has a unique spirit of balance, moderation and reasonableness (,<space/><italics>epieikeia</italics>), and this persuaded most religious communities founded throughout the Middle Ages to adopt it. As a result, his Rule became one of the most influential religious rules in Western<space/><link><target>Christendom</target></link>. For this reason, Benedict is often called the founder of western monasticism.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><paragraph>Apart from a short poem attributed to Mark of Monte Cassino, the only ancient account of Benedict is found in the second volume of<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory I</target></link>'s four-book<space/><italics><link><target>Dialogues</target></link></italics>, thought to have been written in 593.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ford"></extension><space/>The authenticity of this work has been hotly disputed, especially by Dr Francis Clarke in his two volume work<space/><italics>The Pseudo-Gregorian Dialogues</italics>. Book Two consists of a prologue and thirty-eight succinct chapters.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Life and Miracles of St. Benedict</italics><space/>(<italics>Book II, Dialogues</italics>), translated by Odo John Zimmerman, O.S.B. and Benedict R. Avery, O.S.B. (Westport, CT: Greenwood Press, 1980), p. iv.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregorys account of this saints life is not, however, a biography in the modern sense of the word. It provides instead a<space/><link><target>Hagiography</target><part>spiritual portrait</part></link><space/>of the gentle, disciplined abbot. In a letter to Bishop Maximilian of Syracuse, Gregory states his intention for his<space/><italics>Dialogues</italics>, saying they are a kind of<space/><italics>floretum</italics><space/>(an<space/><italics>anthology</italics>, literally, 'flowers') of the most striking miracles of Italian holy men.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fn_4">See Ildephonso Schuster,<space/><italics>Saint Benedict and His Times</italics>, Gregory J. Roettger, trans. (London: B. Herder, 1951), p. 2.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregory did not set out to write a chronological, historically anchored story of St. Benedict, but he did base his anecdotes on direct testimony. To establish his authority, Gregory explains that his information came from what he considered the best sources: a handful of Benedicts disciples who lived with the saint and witnessed his various miracles. These followers, he says, are Constantinus, who succeeded Benedict as<space/><link><target>Abbot</target></link><space/>of Monte Cassino; Valentinianus; Simplicius; and Honoratus, who was abbot of Subiaco when St Gregory wrote his<space/><italics>Dialogues</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In Gregory's day, history was not recognised as an independent field of study; it was a branch of grammar or rhetoric, and<space/><italics>historia</italics><space/>(defined as 'story') summed up the approach of the learned when they wrote what was, at that time, considered 'history.'<extension extension_name='ref' name="fn_6">See Deborah Mauskopf Deliyannis, editor,<space/><italics>Historiography in the Middle Ages</italics><space/>(Boston: Brill, 2003), pp. 12.</extension><space/>Gregorys<space/><italics>Dialogues</italics><space/>Book Two, then, an authentic medieval hagiography cast as a conversation between the Pope and his deacon Peter, is designed to teach spiritual lessons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ford"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life</heading><paragraph>He was the son of a<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>noble of<space/><link><target>Norcia</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ford"><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/02467b.htm'>Ford, Hugh. &quot;St. Benedict of Norcia.&quot; The Catholic Encyclopedia. Vol. 2. New York: Robert Appleton Company, 1907. 3 Mar. 2014</link></extension><space/>the modern Norcia, in<space/><link><target>Umbria</target></link>. A tradition which<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link><space/>accepts makes him a twin with his sister<space/><link><target>Scholastica</target></link>. If we accept the date 480 for his birth, we may fix the date of his abandonment of his studies and leaving home at about 500. St Gregory's narrative makes it impossible to suppose him younger than 19 or 20 at the time. He was old enough to be in the midst of his literary studies, to understand the real meaning and worth of the dissolute and licentious lives of his companions, and to have been deeply affected himself by the love of a woman. He was at the beginning of life, and he had at his disposal the means to a career as a Roman noble; clearly he was not a child.</paragraph><paragraph>Benedict doesn't seem to have left Rome for the purpose of becoming a<space/><link><target>hermit</target></link>, but only to find some place away from the life of the great city. He took his old nurse with him as a servant and they settled down to live in<space/><link><target>Enfide</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crawley"><link type='external' href='http://www.ewtn.com/library/MARY/BENEDICT.htm'>&quot;Saint Benedict, Abbot&quot;, ''Lives of Saints'', John J. Crawley &amp; Co., Inc.</link></extension><space/>Enfide, which the tradition of Subiaco identifies with the modern<space/><link><target>Affile</target></link>, is in the<space/><link><target>Monti Simbruini</target><part>Simbruini</part></link><space/>mountains, about forty miles from Rome and two from Subiaco.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Benedetto, Mauro e Placido.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>left</part><part>St Benedict orders<space/><link><target>Saint Maurus</target></link><space/>to the rescue of<space/><link><target>Saint Placidus</target></link>, by<space/><link><target>Fra Filippo Lippi</target></link>, 1445 A.D.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A short distance from Enfide is the entrance to a narrow, gloomy valley, penetrating the mountains and leading directly to Subiaco. The path continues to ascend, and the side of the ravine, on which it runs, becomes steeper, until a cave is reached above which the mountain now rises almost perpendicularly; while on the right, it strikes in a rapid descent down to where, in St Benedict's day,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg></template><space/>below, lay the blue waters of the lake. The cave has a large triangular-shaped opening and is about ten feet deep.On his way from Enfide, Benedict met a monk,<space/><link><target>Romanus of Subiaco</target></link>, whose monastery was on the mountain above the cliff overhanging the cave. Romanus had discussed with Benedict the purpose which had brought him to Subiaco, and had given him the monk's habit. By his advice Benedict became a hermit and for three years, unknown to men, lived in this cave above the lake. One day, the Devil brought before his imagination a beautiful woman he had formerly known, inflaming his heart with strong desire for her. Immediately, Benedict stripped off his clothes and rolled into a thorn-bush until his body was lacerated. Thus, through the wounds of the body he cured the wounds of his soul.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SHMI"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Later life</heading><paragraph>St Gregory tells us little of these years. He now speaks of Benedict no longer as a youth (<italics>puer</italics>), but as a man (<italics>vir</italics>) of God. Romanus, he twice tells us, served the saint in every way he could. The monk apparently visited him frequently, and on fixed days brought him food.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crawley"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During these three years of solitude, broken only by occasional communications with the outer world and by the visits of Romanus, Benedict matured both in mind and character, in knowledge of himself and of his fellow-man, and at the same time he became not merely known to, but secured the respect of, those about him; so much so that on the death of the abbot of a monastery in the neighbourhood (identified by some with<space/><link><target>Vicovaro</target></link>), the community came to him and begged him to become its abbot. Benedict was acquainted with the life and discipline of the monastery, and knew that &quot;their manners were diverse from his and therefore that they would never agree together: yet, at length, overcome with their entreaty, he gave his consent&quot; (ibid., 3). The experiment failed; the monks tried to poison him. The legend goes that they first tried to poison his drink. He prayed a blessing over the cup and the cup shattered. Thus he left the group and went back to his cave at Subiaco. There lived in the neighborhood a priest called Florentius who, moved by envy, tried to ruin him. He tried to poison him with poisoned bread. When he prayed a blessing over the bread, a raven swept in and took the loaf away. From this time his miracles seem to have become frequent, and many people, attracted by his sanctity and character, came to Subiaco to be under his guidance. Having failed by sending him poisonous bread, Florentius tried to seduce his monks with some prostitutes. To avoid further temptations, in 530 Benedict left Subiaco. He founded 12 monasteries in the vicinity of Subiaco, and, eventually, in 530 he founded the great Benedictine monastery of Monte Cassino,<extension extension_name='ref' name="SHMI"></extension><space/>which lies on a hilltop between Rome and Naples.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.benedictine-srs.org/nursia.html'>Nursia</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the invasion of Italy,<space/><link><target>Totila</target></link>, King of the<space/><link><target>Ostrogoths</target><part>Goths</part></link>, ordered a general to wear his kingly robes and to see whether Benedict would discover the truth. Immediately the Saint detected the impersonation, and Totila came to pay him due respect.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SHMI"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Veneration</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Totila e San Benedetto.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Totila</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>St. Benedict</target></link>. Painted by<space/><link><target>Spinello Aretino</target></link></part></link>He died at<space/><link><target>Monte Cassino</target></link><space/>not long after his sister, Saint Scholastica. Benedict died of a high fever on the day God had told him he was to die, and was buried in the same place as his sister. According to tradition, this occurred on 21 March 543 or 547. He was named patron protector of Europe by<space/><link><target>Pope Paul VI</target></link><space/>in 1964.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.catholic.org/saints/saint.php?saint_id</arg><arg name="title">St. Benedict of Norcia</arg><arg name="publisher">Catholic Online<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">31 July 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1980,<space/><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link><space/>declared him co-<link><target>patron saint</target><part>patron</part></link><space/>of Europe, together with<space/><link><target>Saints Cyril and Methodius</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Egregiae Virtutis"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Egregiae Virtutis<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_letters/documents/hf_jp-ii_apl_31121980_egregiae-virtutis_lt.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>26 April 2009</arg></template><space/><link><target>Apostolic letter</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link>, 31 December 1980<space/><template><target>la icon</target></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the pre-1970<space/><link><target>General Roman Calendar</target></link>, his feast is kept on 21 March, the day of his death according to some manuscripts of the<space/><italics>Martyrologium Hieronymianum</italics><space/>and that of<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>. Because on that date his<space/><link><target>liturgy</target><part>liturgical</part></link><space/><link><target>memorial (liturgy)</target><part>memorial</part></link><space/>would always be impeded by the observance of<space/><link><target>Lent</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Mysterii Paschalis</target><part>1969 revision</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>General Roman Calendar</target></link><space/>moved his memorial to 11 July, the date that appears in some Gallic liturgical books of the end of the 8th century as the feast commemorating his death (<italics>Natalis S. Benedicti</italics>). There is some uncertainty about the origin of this feast.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Calendarium Romanum&quot; (Libreria Editrice Vaticana), pp. 97 and 119</extension><space/>Accordingly, on 21 March the<space/><link><target>Roman Martyrology</target></link><space/>mentions in a line and a half that it is Benedict's day of death and that his memorial is celebrated on 11 July, while on 11 July it devotes seven lines to speaking of him, and mentions the tradition that he died on 21 March.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Martyrologium Romanum</italics><space/>199 (edito altera 2004); pages 188 and 361 of the 2001 edition (Libreria Editrice Vaticana ISBN 978-88-209-7210-3)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link><space/>commemorates St. Benedict on 14 March.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ocafs.oca.org/FeastSaintsLife.asp?FSID=100800'>Orthodox Church in America: The Lives of the Saints, March 14th<space/></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Anglican Communion</target></link><space/>has no single universal calendar, but a provincial<space/><link><target>List of Anglican Church calendars</target><part>calendar of saints</part></link><space/>is published in each province. In almost all of these, St Benedict is commemorated on 11 July.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Rule of St. Benedict</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Rule of St Benedict</arg></template>Seventy-three short chapters comprise the<space/><italics>Rule</italics>. Its wisdom is of two kinds: spiritual (how to live a Christocentric life on earth) and administrative (how to run a monastery efficiently). More than half the chapters describe how to be obedient and humble, and what to do when a member of the community is not. About one-fourth regulate the work of God (the Opus Dei). One-tenth outline how, and by whom, the monastery should be managed. And two chapters specifically describe the abbots pastoral duties.</paragraph><paragraph>Following the golden rule of<space/><italics>Ora et Labora - pray and work</italics>, the monks each day devoted eight hours to prayer, eight hours to sleep, and eight hours to manual work, sacred reading, or works of charity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SHMI"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>The Saint Benedict Medal</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Saint Benedict Medal</arg></template><link><target>File:StBenedictVadeRetroSatana.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>180px</part><part>left</part><part>Image of Saint Benedict with a cross and a scroll stating ''<link><target>Vade Retro Satana</target></link>'' which is abbreviated on the<space/><link><target>Saint Benedict Medal</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>This medal originally came from a cross in honour of St Benedict. On one side, the medal has an image of St Benedict, holding the Holy Rule in his left hand and a cross in his right. There is a raven on one side of him, with a cup on the other side of him. Around the medal's outer margin are the words<space/><italics>&quot;Eius in obitu nostro praesentia muniamur&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;May we, at our death, be fortified by His presence&quot;). The other side of the medal has a cross with the initials<space/><bold>CSSML</bold><space/>on the vertical bar which signify<space/><italics>&quot;Crux Sacra Sit Mihi Lux&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;May the Holy Cross be my light&quot;) and on the horizontal bar are the initials<space/><bold>NDSMD</bold><space/>which stand for<space/><italics>&quot;Non Draco Sit Mihi Dux&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;Let not the dragon be my overlord&quot;). The initials<space/><bold>CSPB</bold><space/>stand for<space/><italics>&quot;Crux Sancti Patris Benedicti&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;The Cross of the Holy Father Benedict&quot;) and are located on the interior angles of the cross. Either the inscription<space/><italics>&quot;PAX&quot;</italics><space/>(Peace) or the<space/><link><target>Christogram</target></link><space/><italics>&quot;IHS&quot;</italics><space/>may be found at the top of the cross in most cases. Around the medal's margin on this side are the<space/><italics><link><target>Vade Retro Satana</target></link></italics><space/>initials<space/><bold>VRSNSMV</bold><space/>which stand for<space/><italics>&quot;Vade Retro Satana, Nonquam Suade Mihi Vana&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;Begone Satan, do not suggest to me thy vanities&quot;) then a space followed by the initials<space/><bold>SMQLIVB</bold><space/>which signify<space/><italics>&quot;Sunt Mala Quae Libas, Ipse Venena Bibas&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;Evil are the things thou profferest, drink thou thy own poison&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benedict pp 60">&quot;The Life of St Benedict,&quot; by St. Gregory the Great, Rockford, IL: TAN Books and Publishers, pp 6062</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Benediktusmedaille.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>210px</part><part>Benedict depicted on a Jubilee<space/><link><target>Saint Benedict Medal</target></link><space/>for the 1400th anniversary of his birth in 1880</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>This medal was first struck in 1880 to commemorate the fourteenth centenary of St Benedict's birth and is also called the Jubilee Medal; its exact origin, however, is unknown. In 1647, during a witchcraft trial at<space/><link><target>Natternberg</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Metten Abbey</target></link><space/>in Bavaria, the accused women testified they had no power over Metten, which was under the protection of the cross. An investigation found a number of painted crosses on the walls of the abbey with the letters now found on St Benedict medals, but their meaning had been forgotten. A manuscript written in 1415 was eventually found that had a picture of Saint Benedict holding a scroll in one hand and a staff which ended in a cross in the other. On the scroll and staff were written the full words of the initials contained on the crosses. Medals then began to be struck in Germany, which then spread throughout Europe. This medal was first approved by<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XIV</target></link><space/>in his briefs of 23 December 1741, and 12 March 1742.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Benedict pp 60"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Saint Benedict has been also the motive of many collector's coins around the world. The<space/><link><target>Euro gold and silver commemorative coins (Austria)#2002 coinage</target><part>Austria 50 euro 'The Christian Religious Orders'</part></link>, issued on 13 March 2002 is one of them.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The influence of St. Benedict</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:2002 Austria 50 Euro Christian Religious Orders front.jpg</target><part>160px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Euro gold and silver commemorative coins (Austria)#2002 coinage</target><part>Austria 50 euro 'The Christian Religious Orders' commemorative coin</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The early Middle Ages have been called &quot;the Benedictine centuries.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Western Europe in the Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>17 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.northern.edu/marmorsa/medievallec1.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080602064810/http://www.northern.edu/marmorsa/medievallec1.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2 June 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>In April 2008, Pope<space/><link><target>Benedict XVI</target></link><space/>discussed the influence St Benedict had on Western Europe. The pope said that &quot;with his life and work St Benedict exercised a fundamental influence on the development of European civilization and culture&quot; and helped Europe to emerge from the &quot;dark night of history&quot; that followed the fall of the<space/><link><target>Roman empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Benedict XVI, &quot;Saint Benedict of Norcia&quot; Homily given to a general audience at St Peter's Square on Wednesday, 9 April 2008<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/benedict_xvi/audiences/2008/documents/hf_ben-xvi_aud_20080409_en.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>?</arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 August 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>St. Benedict contributed more than anyone else to the rise of monasticism in the West. His Rule was the foundational document for thousands of religious communities in the Middle Ages.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aug.edu/augusta/iconography/benedict.html'>Stracke, Prof. J.R., &quot;St. Benedict Iconography&quot;, Augusta State University</link></extension><space/>To this day, The Rule of St. Benedict is the most common and influential Rule used by monasteries and monks, more than 1,400 years after its writing. Today the Benedictine family is represented by two branches: the Benedictine Federation and the Cistercians.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.americancatholic.org/Features/Saints/saint.aspx?id=1441'>Foley O.F.M., Leonard, rev. McCloskey O.F.M., Pat, &quot;Saint of the Day&quot;, American Catholic</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The influence of St Benedict produced &quot;a true spiritual ferment&quot; in Europe, and over the coming decades his followers spread across the continent to establish a new cultural unity based on Christian faith.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Benedict of Norcia</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Saints</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Anthony the Great</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Benedictine</target><part>Benedictine Order</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Camaldolese</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hermit</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Poustinia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>San Beneto</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Saint Benedict Medal</target><part>St. Benedict Medal</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vade retro satana</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gardner</arg><arg name="first">Edmund G. (editor)</arg><arg name="title">''The Dialogues of Saint Gregory the Great''</arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/details/dialoguesofsaint00greg</arg><arg name="publisher">Warner</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1911</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Gallery of pictures related to St Benedict</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Melk16.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>St. Benedict and the cup of poison (Melk Abbey, Austria)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Gold-colored_small_Saint_Benedict_crucifix.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Small gold-coloured St Benedict Crucifix</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Saint Benedict Medal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Two sides of a<space/><link><target>Saint Benedict Medal</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Heiligenkreuz.St. Benedict.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Portrait (1926) by<space/><link><target>Herman Nieg</target></link><space/>(18491928); Heiligenkreuz Abbey, Austria</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:BenedictEpisodeCure.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&quot;St. Benedict at the Death of St. Scholastica&quot; (ca. 1250-60), Muse National de l'Age Mdivale, Paris, orig. at the Abbatiale of St. Denis</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Einsiedeln - St. Benedikt 2013-01-26 13-50-02 (P7700).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Statue in<space/><link><target>Einsiedeln</target></link>, Switzerland</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Library resources box</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/210/3/211.html'>St. Benedict</link><space/>(<link type='external' href='http://www.u.arizona.edu/~aversa/benedict.pdf'>pdf</link>) from<space/><link><target>Alban Butler</target><part>Fr. Alban Butler</part></link>'s<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/210/'>''Lives of the Saints''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.reephambenefice.org.uk/christophermorgancromar.html'>A Benedictine Oblate Priest The Rule in Parish Life</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.e-benedictine.com'>Guide to Saint Benedict</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg</target><arg name="no">50040<space/></arg><arg name="name">St. Benedict’s Rule for Monasteries<space/></arg></template>, translated by Leonard J. Doyle</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ccel.org/ccel/benedict/rule'>The Holy Rule of St. Benedict</link>, translated by Boniface Verheyen</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.osb.org'>The Order of Saint Benedict</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=m8MPAAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA124&amp;amp;dq=inauthor:gueranger&amp;amp;as_brr=1#PPR7,M1'>The Medal Or Cross of St. Benedict: Its Origin, Meaning, and Privileges</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/gregory_02_dialogues_book2.htm'>Life and Miracles of St Benedict</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="search">( "St. Benedict" OR "Saint Benedict" OR "Benedict, Saint" OR "Benedict of Norcia" )</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">5764</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.christianiconography.info/goldenLegend/benedict.htm'>&quot;The Life of St. Benedict&quot;</link><space/>from the Caxton translation of the<space/><italics>Golden Legend</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.paulandpeters.com/blog/st-benedict-nursia'>St. Benedict Of Norcia, Patron Of Poison Sufferers, Monks, And Many More</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.christianiconography.info/benedict.html'>Saint Benedict of Norcia</link><space/>at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.christianiconography.info/index.html'>Christian Iconography</link><space/>web site.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Life of St. Benedict: Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>17 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.lib.rochester.edu/camelot/teams/whbenintro.htm<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.stpetersbasilica.info/Exterior/Colonnades/Saints/St%20Benedict-17/StBenedict.htm'>Colonnade Statue in St Peter's Square</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.stpetersbasilica.info/Statues/Founders/Benedict/Benedict.htm'>Founder Statue in St Peter's Basilica</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>History of Christianity</target></template><template><target>Catholicism</target><arg></arg><arg>collapsed</arg></template><template><target>History of Catholic theology</target><arg></arg><arg>collapsed</arg></template><template><target>History of the Catholic Church</target><arg>collapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Benedict of Norcia
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Italian monk
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>480
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Norcia]] ([[Umbria]], Italy)
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>21 March 543 or 547
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">[[Monte Cassino]]
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Benedict Of Norcia</target></template><link><target>Category:480 births</target></link><link><target>Category:540s deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Catholic monasticism</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Founders of Roman Catholic religious communities</target></link><link><target>Category:Benedictine spirituality</target></link><link><target>Category:Twin people from Italy</target></link><link><target>Category:People from the Province of Perugia</target></link><link><target>Category:5th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century Christian saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Saints of the Golden Legend</target></link><link><target>Category:Witchcraft</target></link><link><target>Category:Benedictine saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Medieval Italian saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Nursing</target></link><link><target>Category:World Digital Library related</target></link></paragraph></article>