<article title='Politics_of_Cyprus'><paragraph><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="{{POV|date">November 2013}}
{{Refimprove|date</arg></template><template><target>Politics of Cyprus</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Republic of Cyprus</target></link><space/>is a<space/><link><target>unitary state</target><part>unitary</part></link><space/><link><target>presidential system</target><part>presidential</part></link><space/><link><target>representative democracy</target><part>representative republic</part></link>, whereby the<space/><link><target>President of Cyprus</target></link><space/>is both<space/><link><target>head of state</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>head of government</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Executive power</target></link><space/>is exercised by the government.<space/><link><target>Legislative power</target></link><space/>is vested in both the<space/><link><target>government</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>House of Representatives of Cyprus</target><part>parliament</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Judiciary</target></link><space/>is independent of the executive and the legislature.</paragraph><paragraph>Cyprus has been a divided island since 1974 when Turkey invaded the north in response to a military coup on the island which was backed by the Athens government.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Cyprus profile</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-17217956</arg><arg name="website">BBC News</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Since then, the internationally recognized Republic of Cyprus has controlled the south two-thirds, and the<space/><link><target>Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</target></link>, only recognized by Turkey, the northern one-third. The Government of the Republic of Cyprus has continued as the sole internationally recognized authority on the island (as well as the United Kingdom being internationally recognized with respect to the<space/><link><target>Sovereign Base Area</target><part>SBA</part><trail>s</trail></link>), though in practice its power extends only to the government-controlled area.</paragraph><paragraph>Cyprus operates under a<space/><link><target>multi-party system</target></link>, with socialist<space/><link><target>Progressive Party of Working People</target><part>AKEL</part></link><space/>and right-leaning<space/><link><target>Democratic Rally</target></link><space/>in the forefront. Centrist<space/><link><target>Democratic Party (Cyprus)</target><part>DIKO</part></link><space/>and lesser parties often form a<space/><link><target>political coalition</target><part>coalition</part></link><space/>with the President's party and are allotted a number of ministries.</paragraph><heading level='2'>United Cyprus</heading><paragraph>The 1960 Cypriot<space/><link><target>Constitution</target></link><space/>provided for a<space/><link><target>presidential system</target></link><space/>of government with<space/><link><target>separation of powers</target><part>independent</part></link><space/><link><target>executive (government)</target><part>executive</part></link>,<space/><link><target>legislative</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>judicial</target></link><space/>branches, as well as a complex system of checks and balances including a weighted power-sharing ratio designed to protect the interests of the<space/><link><target>Turkish Cypriots</target></link>. The executive, for example, was headed by a Greek Cypriot president,<space/><link><target>Archbishop Makarios</target></link><space/>III, and a Turkish Cypriot vice president,<space/><link><target>Fazil Kucuk</target><part>Dr Fazl Kk</part></link>, elected by their respective communities for 5-year terms and each possessing a right of veto over certain types of legislation and executive decisions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Politics of Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cyprusdirectory.net/explore-cyprus/cyprus-politics</arg><arg name="publisher">Cyprus Directory</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 November 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The House of Representatives was elected on the basis of separate voters' rolls. Since 1964, following clashes between the two communities, the Turkish Cypriot seats in the House remained vacant, while the Greek Cypriot<space/><link><target>Communal Chambers</target><part>Communal Chamber</part></link><space/>was abolished. The responsibilities of the chamber were transferred to the newfounded Ministry of Education.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Politics of Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.latchipremiumvillas.com/Location/Cyprus.aspx</arg><arg name="publisher">Chriseleni Villas</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 November 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>By 1967, when a<space/><link><target>Greek military junta of 1967-1974</target><part>military junta</part></link><space/>had seized power in Greece, the political impetus for enosis had faded, partly as a result of the non-aligned foreign policy of Cypriot President Makarios. Enosis remained an ideological goal, despite being pushed significantly further down the political agenda. Dissatisfaction in Greece with Makarios convinced the Greek colonels to sponsor the 1974 coup in Nicosia.</paragraph><paragraph>Turkey responded by launching a military operation on Cyprus in a move not approved by the other two international guarantor powers, Greece and the United Kingdom, claiming that this was for the protection of the Turkish minority from Greek militias. The invasion is called &quot;Cyprus Peace Operation&quot; by the Turkish side. Turkish forces captured the northern part of the island. Many thousands of others, from both sides, left the island entirely. In addition to many of the Greek Cypriot refugees (a third of the population), many Turkish Cypriots also moved to the UK.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Subsequently, the Turkish Cypriots established their own separatist institutions with a popularly elected<space/><italics><link><target>de facto</target></link></italics><space/>President and a Prime Minister responsible to the National Assembly exercising joint executive powers. In 1983, the Turkish Cypriots declared an independent state called the<space/><link><target>Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</target></link><space/>(TRNC), an action opposed by the United Nations Security Council. In 1985, the TRNC adopted a constitution and held its first elections.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Cyprus Overview</arg><arg name="url">http://www.appleton.co.uk/j_cyprus.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Appleton Company Services Limited</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 November 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Division of Cyprus</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Politics of Northern Cyprus</arg></template><link><target>Image:buffer zone.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>right</part><part>180px</part><part>The capital Nicosia remains divided since 1973. The UN buffer zone separates the two sectors.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1974, following a coup sponsored by the<space/><link><target>Greek military junta of 1967-1974</target></link><space/>and executed by the<space/><link><target>Cypriot National Guard</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>Turkish invasion of Cyprus</target><part>invasion of troops from Turkey</part></link><space/>(citing its authority as one of the three guarantor powers established by the Constitution), the Turkish Cypriots formally set up their own institutions with a popularly-elected president and a Prime Minister, responsible to the National Assembly, exercising joint executive powers. Cyprus has been divided,<space/><italics>de facto</italics>, into the Greek Cypriot controlled southern two-thirds of the island and the Turkish-occupied northern third. The<space/><bold>Republic of Cyprus</bold><space/>is the internationally recognised government of the Republic of Cyprus, that controls the southern two-thirds of the island. Aside from Turkey, all foreign governments and the United Nations recognise the sovereignty of the Republic of Cyprus over the whole island of Cyprus.</paragraph><paragraph>Turkey, which does not recognise the Republic of Cyprus, and the Turkish Cypriot administration of the northern part of the island, do not accept the Republic's rule over the whole island and refer to it not by its international name, but as the &quot;Greek Cypriot Administration of Southern Cyprus&quot;. Its territory, a result of the Turkish invasion of 1974 and whose status remains disputed, extends over the northern third of the island.</paragraph><paragraph>The north proclaimed its independence in 1975. In 1983, the Turkish Cypriots declared an independent &quot;Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus&quot;, which has never been<space/><link><target>non-recognized nations</target><part>recognized by any country</part></link><space/>except<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/610071/Turkish-Republic-of-Northern-Cyprus</arg><arg name="publisher">Britannica Online</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 November 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1985, they adopted a constitution and held electionsan arrangement recognized only by Turkey. For information pertaining to this, see<space/><link><target>Politics of the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</target></link>. The Organisation of the Islamic Conference (now the<space/><link><target>Organisation of Islamic Cooperation</target></link>) granted it observer member status under the name of &quot;Turkish Cypriot State&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Political conditions</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ministry of Commerce Industry and Tourism in Nicosia capital of Replubic of Cyprus.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Ministry of Commerce Industry and Tourism</part></link>The division of Cyprus has remained an<space/><link><target>intractable conflict</target><part>intractable</part></link><space/>political problem plaguing relations between Greece and<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link>, and drawing in<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>, of which both Greece and Turkey are members, and latterly the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link>, which has admitted Greece and Cyprus and which Turkey has been seeking to join for over twenty years.</paragraph><paragraph>The most recent developments on the island have included the reopening of the<space/><link><target>Green Line (Cyprus)</target><part>border</part></link><space/>between the two sides, and the failure of an attempt to reunify the island under the terms of a<space/><link><target>Annan Plan for Cyprus</target><part>United Nations-sponsored initiative</part></link><space/>guided by the UN<space/><link><target>Secretary-General</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kofi Annan</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>None of the Greek Cypriot parties has been able to elect a president by itself or dominate the 56-seat House of Representatives. The 165,000 Greek<space/><link><target>Cypriot refugees</target></link><space/>are also a potent political force, along with the independent<space/><link><target>Orthodox Church of Cyprus</target></link>, which has some influence in temporal as well as ecclesiastical matters.</paragraph><paragraph>The working of the Cypriot state was fraught with difficulty from the very early days after independence in 1960, and intercommunal tension and occasionally violence was, regrettably, a feature of the first decade of Cypriot independence. In 1963, the Cypriot president,<space/><link><target>Makarios III</target><part>Makarios</part></link>, proposed 13 amendments to the Constitution in order to remove obstacles to the smooth functioning and development of the state. This was done with the encouragement of the British High Commissioner in Cyprus, who considered the amendments a reasonable basis for discussion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">All about Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">http://www.mfa.gov.cy/mfa/embassies/embassy_beijing.nsf/DMLcy_en/DMLcy_en?Opendocument</arg><arg name="website">Embassy of the Republic of Cyprus in Beijing</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 December 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Violence erupted between Greek and Turkish Cypriots in December 1963 and by the following year the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>agreed to undertake peacekeeping operations (<link><target>United Nations Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus</target><part>UNFICYP</part></link>).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>United Nations</target><part>UN</part></link>-sponsored negotiations to develop institutional arrangements acceptable to the Greek Cypriot and Turkish Cypriot communities began in 1968; several sets of negotiations and other initiatives followed.</paragraph><paragraph>After the 1974<space/><link><target>Turkish invasion of Cyprus</target><part>invasion</part></link><space/>following a Greek<space/><link><target>Military dictatorship</target><part>junta</part></link>-based<space/><link><target>coup d'tat</target><part>coup</part></link><space/>attempt, Makarios secured international recognition of his Greek Cypriot government as the sole legal authority on Cyprus, which has proved to be a very significant strategic advantage for the Greek Cypriots in the decades since. Negotiations continued in the years after 1974 with varying degrees of regularity and success, but none resulted in a full reunification. On 15 November 1983 the Turkish Cypriot North declared independence and the formation of the<space/><link><target>Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</target></link><space/>(TRNC), which has been<space/><link><target>non-recognized nations</target><part>recognized</part></link><space/>only by<space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Europe :: Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/print/country/countrypdf_cy.pdf</arg><arg name="website">CIA</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 December 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Both sides publicly call for the resolution of intercommunal differences and creation of a new<space/><link><target>federation</target><part>federal system</part></link><space/>of government.</paragraph><paragraph>Following the<space/><link><target>Cypriot presidential election, 1998</target><part>1998 presidential election</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Glafkos Klerides</target><part>Klerides</part></link><space/>tried to form a government of national unity, by including six ministers from Klerides'<space/><link><target>Democratic Rally</target></link><space/>party, two ministers from the<space/><link><target>socialism</target><part>socialist</part></link><space/><link><target>Movement for Social Democracy</target><part>EDEK</part></link>, three from the<space/><link><target>Democratic Party (Cyprus)</target><part>Democratic Party</part></link><space/>(who broke ranks with party leader<space/><link><target>Spyros Kyprianou</target></link>) and one from the<space/><link><target>United Democrats</target></link>. However, a national unity government was not achieved due to the leftist<space/><link><target>AKEL</target></link><space/>and centrist Democratic Party rejecting the offer, preferring to remain opposition parties.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Reunification, the Annan Plan and EU entry</heading><paragraph>The results of early negotiations between the Greek and Turkish politicians resulted in a broad agreement in principle to reunification as a bicameral, bi-zonal<space/><link><target>federation</target></link><space/>with territory allocated to the Greek and Turkish communities within a united island. However, agreement was never reached on the finer details, and the two sides often met deadlock over the following points, among others:</paragraph><paragraph>The Greek side:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>took a strong line on the right of return for refugees to properties vacated in the 1974 displacement of Cypriots on both sides, which was based on both UN Resolutions and decisions of the European Court of Human Rights;</listitem><listitem>took a dim view of any proposals which did not allow for the repatriation of Turkish settlers from the mainland who had emigrated to Cyprus since 1974; and</listitem><listitem>supported a stronger central government.</listitem></list><paragraph>The Turkish side:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>favoured a weak central government presiding over two sovereign states in voluntary association, a legacy of earlier fears of domination by the majority Greek Cypriots; and</listitem><listitem>opposed plans for demilitarisation, citing security concerns.</listitem></list><paragraph>The continued difficulties in finding a settlement presented a potential obstacle to Cypriot entry to the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link>, for which the government had applied in 1997. UN-sponsored talks between the Greek and Turkish leaders,<space/><link><target>Glafkos Klerides</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rauf Denkta</target></link>, continued intensively in 2002, but without resolution. In December 2002, the EU formally invited Cyprus to join in 2004, insisting that EU membership would apply to the whole island and hoping that it would provide a significant enticement for reunification resulting from the outcome of ongoing talks. However, weeks before the UN deadline, Klerides was defeated in presidential elections by centre candidate<space/><link><target>Tassos Papadopoulos</target></link>. Papadopoulos had a reputation as a hard-liner on reunification and based his stance on international law and human rights. By mid-March, the UN declared that the talks had failed.</paragraph><paragraph>A United Nations plan sponsored by<space/><link><target>Secretary-General of the United Nations</target><part>Secretary-General</part></link><space/><link><target>Kofi Annan</target></link><space/>was announced on 31 March 2004, based on what progress had been made during the talks in Switzerland and fleshed out by the UN, was put for the first time to civilians on both sides in separate referendums on 24 April 2004. The Greek side overwhelmingly rejected the<space/><link><target>Annan Plan for Cyprus</target><part>Annan Plan</part></link>, and the Turkish side voted in favour.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Communal federalists seem to be supportive of bi-zonality in its strongest
form even at the expense of serious limitations on individual rights. Strong bizonality requires a minimal effort for the territorial coexistence of the Cypriot
communities, a feature especially important for the Turkish-Cypriot community
to form a clear majority in its constituent state. Thus, limiting the number
of Greek-Cypriots in the Turkish-Cypriot constituent unit, and preventing
them from using their political rights in the north, appears to be a necessary
territorial mechanism that would secure bi-zonality.<ref>{{cite journal
 | last"><space/>Peristianis
 | first<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In May 2004, Cyprus entered the EU, still divided,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Cyprus</arg><arg name="url">http://geography.about.com/library/cia/blccyprus.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">About.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 November 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>although in practice membership only applies to the southern part of the island which is in the control of the Republic of Cyprus. In acknowledgment of the Turkish Cypriot community's support for reunification, however, the EU made it clear that trade concessions would be reached to stimulate economic growth in the north, and remains committed to reunification under acceptable terms. Though some trade restrictions were lifted on the north to alleviate economic isolation for the Turkish Cypriots, further negotiations have not been a priority. There is now a focus on convincing Turkey to recognise the government of Cyprus, a requirement for Turkish admission advocated most strongly by Cyprus and France.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Constitution</heading><paragraph>The 16 August 1960 constitution envisioned power sharing between the Greek Cypriots and<space/><link><target>Turkish Cypriots</target></link>. Efforts to amends the constitution sparked the intercommunal strife in 1963. This constitution is still in force, though there is no Turkish Cypriot presence in the Cypriot government.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bold text</bold>==Executive branch==<template><target>office-table</target></template>|<link><target>President of Cyprus</target><part>President</part></link>|<link><target>Nicos Anastasiades</target></link>|<link><target>Democratic Rally</target></link>|28 February 2013|}The president, elected by popular vote for a five-year term, is both the chief of state and head of government; post of vice president is currently vacant; under the 1960 constitution, the post is reserved for a Turkish Cypriot. The Council of Ministers is appointed jointly by the president and vice president.</paragraph><paragraph>Currently there are eleven ministries:<space/></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Ministry of Agriculture, Natural Resources and the Environment. Minister:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.moa.gov.cy/moa/agriculture.nsf/page04_en/page04_en?OpenDocument'>Nicos Kouyialis</link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Energy, Commerce, Industry and Tourism. Minister:<space/><link><target>Georgios Lakkotrypis</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Communications and Works. Minister:<space/><link><target>Tasos Mitsopoulos</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Defence. Minister:<space/><link><target>Fotis Fotiou</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Education and Culture. Minister:<space/><link><target>Kyriakos Kenevezos</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Finance.<space/><link><target>Christos Georgiades</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Foreign Affairs. Minister:<space/><link><target>Giannakis Kasoulides</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Health. Minister:<space/><link><target>Petros Petrides</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of the Interior. Minister:<space/><link><target>Socratis Hasikos</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Justice and Public Order. Minister:<space/><link><target>Ionas Nikolaou</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ministry of Labour and Social Insurance:<space/><link><target>Zeta Aimilianidou</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Legislative branch</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>House of Representatives of Cyprus</target><part>House of Representatives</part></link><space/>(<italics>Vouli Antiprospon/Temsilciler Meclisi</italics>) has 59 members elected for a five-year term: 56 Greek Cypriot members chosen by<space/><link><target>proportional representation</target></link><space/>and 3 observer members representing the<space/><link><target>Maronite</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Armenians</target><part>Armenian</part></link><space/>minorities. 24 seats are allocated to the Turkish community, but are currently vacant.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Political parties and elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>elect</target><arg>List of political parties in Cyprus</arg><arg>Elections in Cyprus</arg></template><template><target>Cypriot presidential election, 2013</target></template><template><target>Cypriot legislative election, 2011</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political pressure groups and leaders</heading><list type='numbered'><listitem>Cypriot Workers Union (... )</listitem><listitem>Confederation of Revolutionary Labor Unions or Dev-Is<space/></listitem><listitem>Pan-Cyprian Labour Federation or PEO (... )</listitem><listitem><link><target>Eleftheria</target></link><space/>Citizens Initiative ( )</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Administrative divisions</heading><paragraph>6 districts;<space/><link><target>Famagusta</target></link><space/>(Ammochostos),<space/><link><target>Kyrenia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Larnaca</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Limassol</target></link><space/>(Lemesos),<space/><link><target>Nicosia</target></link><space/>(Lefkosia),<space/><link><target>Paphos</target></link>; note - occupied area's administrative divisions include Kyrenia, all but a small part of Famagusta (Ammochostos), and small parts of Lefkosia (Nicosia) and Larnaca.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Exclaves and enclaves</heading><paragraph>Cyprus has four<space/><link><target>exclave</target><trail>s</trail></link>, all in territory that belongs to the<space/><link><target>Akrotiri and Dhekelia</target><part>British Sovereign Base Area of Dhekelia</part></link>. The first two are the villages of<space/><link><target>Ormidhia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Xylotymvou</target></link>. Additionally there is the Dhekelia Power Station, which is divided by a British road into two parts. The northern part is an enclave, like the two villages, whereas the southern part is located by the sea and therefore not an enclave &amp;mdash;although it has no territorial waters of its own.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://geosite.jankrogh.com/cyprus.htm</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The UN buffer zone separating the territory controlled by the Turkish Cypriot administration from the rest of Cyprus runs up against Dhekelia and picks up again from its east side, off of<space/><link><target>Ayios Nikolaos, SBA</target><part>Ayios Nikolaos</part></link><space/>(connected to the rest of Dhekelia by a thin land corridor). In that sense, the buffer zone turns the south-east corner of the island, the<space/><link><target>Paralimni</target></link><space/>area, into a<space/><italics>de facto</italics>, though not<space/><italics><link><target>de jure</target></link></italics>, exclave.</paragraph><heading level='2'>International organization participation</heading><paragraph><link><target>Commonwealth of Nations</target><part>C</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Customs Cooperation Council</target><part>CCC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Council of Europe</target><part>CE</part></link>,<space/><link><target>European Bank for Reconstruction and Development</target><part>EBRD</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Economic Commission for Europe</target><part>ECE</part></link>,<space/><link><target>European Patent Organisation</target><part>EPO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>European Union</target><part>EU Member</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Food and Agriculture Organization</target><part>FAO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Group of 77</target><part>G-77</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Atomic Energy Agency</target><part>IAEA</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</target><part>IBRD</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Civil Aviation Organization</target><part>ICAO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Criminal Court</target><part>ICC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Chamber of Commerce</target><part>ICC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Development Association</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Fund for Agricultural Development</target><part>IFAD</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Finance Corporation</target><part>IFC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement</target><part>IFRCS</part></link><space/>(associate),<space/><link><target>International Hydrographic Organization</target><part>IHO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Labour Organization</target><part>ILO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target><part>IMF</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Maritime Organization</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Mobile Satellite Organization</target><part>Inmarsat</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Intelsat</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Interpol (organization)</target><part>Interpol</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Olympic Committee</target><part>IOC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Organization for Migration</target><part>IOM</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Organization for Standardization</target><part>ISO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Telecommunication Union</target><part>ITU</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Trade Union Confederation</target><part>ITUC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Non-Aligned Movement</target><part>NAM</part></link>(member since 1961, observer after 2004),<space/><link><target>Organization of American States</target><part>OAS</part></link><space/>(observer),<space/><link><target>Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons</target><part>OPCW</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe</target><part>OSCE</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Permanent Court of Arbitration</target><part>PCA</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations</target><part>UN</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Conference on Trade and Development</target><part>UNCTAD</part></link>,<space/><link><target>UNESCO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Industrial Development Organization</target><part>UNIDO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Universal Postal Union</target><part>UPU</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Federation of Trade Unions</target><part>WFTU</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target><part>WHO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Intellectual Property Organization</target><part>WIPO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Meteorological Organization</target><part>WMO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Tourism Organization</target><part>WToO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Trade Organization</target><part>WTrO</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cyprus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Minister of Communications and Works of the Republic of Cyprus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Minister of Labour and Social Insurance of the Republic of Cyprus</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">James Ker-Lindsay and Hubert Faustmann (eds.)</arg><arg name="title">The Government and Politics of Cyprus<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Peter Lang<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-3-03911-096-4</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Regional/Middle_East/Cyprus/Government</arg><arg>Cyprus Government</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.KyproEkloges.com'>Cyprus Elections by KyproEkloges.com</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Cyprus topics</target></template><template><target>Asia topic</target><arg>Politics of</arg></template><template><target>Politics of Europe</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Cyprus</target></template><link><target>Category:Politics of Cyprus</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Government of Cyprus</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>bn:#</target></link></paragraph></article>