<article title='Ethics'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template><template><target>Philosophy sidebar</target></template><bold>Ethics</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>moral philosophy</bold><space/>is the branch of<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>that involves systematizing, defending, and recommending concepts of right and wrong<space/><link><target>action (philosophy)</target><part>conduct</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="iep.utm.edu"><italics>Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/ethics/'>&quot;Ethics&quot;</link></extension><space/>The term<space/><italics>ethics</italics><space/>derives from the<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target></link><space/>word<space/><italics>ethikos</italics>, which is derived from the word<space/><italics><link><target>ethos</target></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>habit</target></link>, custom). The branch of philosophy<space/><link><target>axiology</target></link><space/>comprises the sub-branches of Ethics and<space/><link><target>aesthetics</target></link>, each concerned with concepts of value.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Random House Unabridged Dictionary</target></link></italics>:<space/><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/axiology'>Entry on Axiology.</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As a branch of philosophy, ethics investigates the questions What is the best way for people to live? and What<space/><link><target>action (philosophy)</target><part>actions</part></link><space/>are right or wrong in particular circumstances? In practice, ethics seeks to resolve questions of human morality, by defining concepts such as<space/><link><target>good and evil</target></link>, right and<space/><link><target>wrong</target></link>,<space/><link><target>virtue</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>vice</target></link>,<space/><link><target>justice</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>crime</target></link>. As a field of intellectual enquiry, moral philosophy also is related to the fields of<space/><link><target>moral psychology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>descriptive ethics</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>value theory</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The three major areas of study within ethics are:<extension extension_name='ref' name="iep.utm.edu"></extension></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>Meta-ethics</target></link>, concerning the theoretical meaning and reference of moral propositions, and how their<space/><link><target>truth value</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(if any) can be determined</listitem><listitem><link><target>Normative ethics</target></link>, concerning the practical means of determining a moral course of action</listitem><listitem><link><target>Applied ethics</target></link>, concerning what a person is obligated (or permitted) to do in a specific situation or a particular domain of action<extension extension_name='ref' name="iep.utm.edu"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Defining ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>POV-section</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Dino Lobaton states that &quot;standard definitions of<space/><italics>ethics</italics><space/>have typically included such phrases as 'the science of the ideal human character' or 'the science of moral duty'&amp;thinsp;&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">How Good People Make Tough Choices Rev Ed: Resolving the Dilemmas of Ethical Living<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kidder</arg></template></extension><space/>Richard William Paul and<space/><link><target>Linda Elder</target></link><space/>define ethics as &quot;a set of concepts and principles that guide us in determining what behavior helps or harms sentient creatures&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Cambridge Dictionary of Philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>states that the word ethics is &quot;commonly used interchangeably with '<link><target>morality</target></link>'&amp;nbsp;... and sometimes it is used more narrowly to mean the moral principles of a particular tradition, group or individual.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>John Deigh in Robert Audi (ed),<space/><italics>The Cambridge Dictionary of Philosophy</italics>, 1995.</extension><template><target>Clarify</target><arg name="reason">Add the full quote</arg><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template><space/>Paul and Elder state that most people confuse ethics with behaving in accordance with social conventions, religious beliefs and the law and don't treat ethics as a stand-alone concept.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Miniature Guide to Understanding the Foundations of Ethical Reasoning</arg><arg name="last1">Paul</arg><arg name="first1">Richard</arg><arg name="last2">Elder<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Linda</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Foundation for Critical Thinking Free Press</arg><arg name="location">United States</arg><arg name="isbn">0-944583-17-2</arg><arg name="page">np</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The word &quot;ethics&quot; in English refers to several things.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="accessdate">October 4, 2015</arg><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/ethic</arg><arg name="title">Definition of ethic by Merriam Webster</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Merriam Webster</arg></template></extension><space/>It can refer to philosophical ethicsa project that attempts to use reason in order to answer various kinds of ethical questions.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template><space/>It can also be used to describe a particular person's own, idiosyncratic principles or habits.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">January 24, 2014</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 22, 2014</arg><arg name="url">http://soulofwit.com/2014/01/24/Buddha-And-Socrates-Share-Common-Ground</arg><arg name="title">Buddha and Socrates share Common ground</arg><arg name="author">David Tanguay</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Soul of Wit</arg><arg name="archivedate">July 22, 2014</arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20140722174808/http://soulofwit.com/2014/01/24/Buddha-And-Socrates-Share-Common-Ground</arg></template></extension><space/>For example: &quot;Joe has good ethics.&quot; It may also be used to characterize the questions of right-conduct in some specific sphere, even when such right-conduct is not examined philosophically: &quot;business ethics,&quot; or &quot;the ethics of child-rearing&quot; may refer, but need not refer, to a philosophical examination of such issues.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template><space/>Philosophical ethics, or &quot;ethical theory,&quot; is not the exclusive use of the term &quot;ethics&quot; in English.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Meta-ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Meta-ethics</arg></template>Meta-ethics asks how we understand, know about, and what we mean when we talk about what is right and what is wrong.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bbc"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/introduction/intro_1.shtml</arg><arg name="title">What is ethics?</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 22, 2014</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>October 28, 2013</arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20131028131348/http://www.bbc.co.uk/ethics/introduction/intro_1.shtml</arg></template></extension><space/>An ethical question fixed on some particular practical questionsuch as, &quot;Should I eat this particular piece of chocolate cake?&quot;cannot be a meta-ethical question. A meta-ethical question is abstract and relates to a wide range of more specific practical questions. For example, &quot;Is it ever possible to have secure knowledge of what is right and wrong?&quot; would be a meta-ethical question.</paragraph><paragraph>Meta-ethics has always accompanied philosophical ethics. For example, Aristotle implies that less precise knowledge is possible in ethics than in other spheres of inquiry, and he regards ethical knowledge as depending upon habit and acculturation in a way that makes it distinctive from other kinds of knowledge. Meta-ethics is also important in<space/><link><target>George Edward Moore</target><part>G.E. Moore</part></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Principia Ethica</target></link></italics><space/>from 1903. In it he first wrote about what he called<space/><italics>the<space/><link><target>naturalistic fallacy</target></link></italics>. Moore was seen to reject<space/><link><target>Ethical naturalism</target><part>naturalism</part></link><space/>in ethics, in his<space/><link><target>Open Question Argument</target></link>. This made thinkers look again at second order questions about ethics. Earlier, the Scottish<space/><link><target>philosopher</target></link><space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>had put forward a similar view on the difference between<space/><link><target>Is-ought problem</target><part>facts and values</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Studies of how we know in ethics divide into<space/><link><target>Cognitivism (ethics)</target><part>cognitivism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>non-cognitivism</target></link>; this is similar to the contrast between descriptivists and non-descriptivists. Non-cognitivism is the claim that when we judge something as right or wrong, this is neither true nor false. We may for example be only expressing our emotional feelings about these things.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.iep.utm.edu/non-cogn/</extension><space/>Cognitivism can then be seen as the claim that when we talk about right and wrong, we are talking about matters of fact.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>ontology</target></link><space/>of ethics is about value-bearing things or properties, i.e. the kind of things or stuff referred to by ethical propositions. Non-descriptivists and non-cognitivists believe that ethics does not need a specific ontology, since ethical propositions do not refer. This is known as an anti-realist position. Realists on the other hand must explain what kind of entities, properties or states are relevant for ethics, how they have value, and why they guide and motivate our actions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miller, C. (2009). The Conditions of Moral Realism. The Journal of Philosophical Research, 34, 123-155.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Normative ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Normative ethics</arg></template>Normative ethics is the study of ethical action. It is the branch of ethics that investigates the set of questions that arise when considering how one ought to act, morally speaking. Normative ethics is distinct from<space/><link><target>meta-ethics</target></link><space/>because it examines standards for the rightness and wrongness of actions, while meta-ethics studies the meaning of moral language and the metaphysics of moral facts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bbc"></extension><space/>Normative ethics is also distinct from<space/><link><target>descriptive ethics</target></link>, as the latter is an empirical investigation of people's moral beliefs. To put it another way, descriptive ethics would be concerned with determining what proportion of people believe that killing is always wrong, while normative ethics is concerned with whether it is correct to hold such a belief. Hence, normative ethics is sometimes called prescriptive, rather than descriptive. However, on certain versions of the meta-ethical view called<space/><link><target>moral realism</target></link>, moral facts are both descriptive and prescriptive at the same time.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Cavalier</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="title">Meta-ethics, Normative Ethics, and Applied Ethics</arg><arg name="work">Online Guide to Ethics and Moral Philosophy</arg><arg name="url">http://caae.phil.cmu.edu/Cavalier/80130/part2/II_preface.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 26, 2014</arg><arg name="archivedate">November 12, 2013</arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20131112114345/http://caae.phil.cmu.edu/Cavalier/80130/part2/II_preface.html</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Traditionally, normative ethics (also known as moral theory) was the study of what makes actions right and wrong. These theories offered an overarching moral principle one could appeal to in resolving difficult moral decisions.</paragraph><paragraph>At the turn of the 20th century, moral theories became more complex and are no longer concerned solely with rightness and wrongness, but are interested in many different kinds of moral status. During the middle of the century, the study of normative ethics declined as meta-ethics grew in prominence. This focus on meta-ethics was in part caused by an intense linguistic focus in<space/><link><target>analytic philosophy</target></link><space/>and by the popularity of<space/><link><target>logical positivism</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1971<space/><link><target>John Rawls</target></link><space/>published<space/><italics><link><target>A Theory of Justice</target></link></italics>, noteworthy in its pursuit of moral arguments and eschewing of meta-ethics. This publication set the trend for renewed interest in normative ethics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Virtue ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Virtue ethics</arg></template><link><target>File:Socrates BM GR1973.03-27.16.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>170px</part><part>Socrates</part></link>Virtue ethics describes the character of a moral agent as a driving force for ethical behavior, and is used to describe the ethics of<space/><link><target>Socrates</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>, and other early Greek philosophers.<space/><link><target>Socrates</target></link><space/>(469399&amp;nbsp;BC) was one of the first<space/><link><target>Greek philosophy</target><part>Greek philosophers</part></link><space/>to encourage both scholars and the common citizen to turn their attention from the outside world to the condition of humankind. In this view,<space/><link><target>knowledge</target></link><space/>bearing on human life was placed highest, while all other knowledge were secondary.<space/><link><target>Self-knowledge (psychology)</target><part>Self-knowledge</part></link><space/>was considered necessary for success and inherently an essential good. A self-aware person will act completely within his capabilities to his pinnacle, while an ignorant person will flounder and encounter difficulty. To Socrates, a person must become aware of every fact (and its context) relevant to his existence, if he wishes to attain self-knowledge. He posited that people will naturally do what is good, if they know what is right. Evil or bad actions are the result of ignorance. If a criminal was truly aware of the intellectual and spiritual consequences of his actions, he would neither commit nor even consider committing those actions. Any person who knows what is truly right will automatically do it, according to Socrates. While he correlated knowledge with<space/><link><target>virtue</target></link>, he similarly equated virtue with<space/><link><target>Happiness</target><part>joy</part></link>. The truly wise man will know what is right, do what is good, and therefore be happy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">William S. Sahakian</arg><arg name="author2">Mabel Lewis Sahakian</arg><arg name="title">Ideas of the Great Philosophers</arg><arg name="year">1966</arg><arg name="publisher">Barnes & Noble</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-56619-271-2</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>32–33</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>(384323&amp;nbsp;BC) posited an ethical system that may be termed &quot;self-realizationism.&quot; In Aristotle's view, when a person acts in accordance with his nature and realizes his full potential, he will do good and be content. At birth, a baby is not a person, but a potential person. To become a &quot;real&quot; person, the child's inherent potential must be realized. Unhappiness and frustration are caused by the unrealized potential of a person, leading to failed goals and a poor life. Aristotle said, &quot;<link><target>Nature</target></link><space/>does nothing in vain.&quot; Therefore, it is imperative for people to act in accordance with their nature and develop their latent talents in order to be content and complete. Happiness was held to be the ultimate goal. All other things, such as civic life or<space/><link><target>wealth</target></link>, are merely means to the end. Self-realization, the awareness of one's nature and the development of one's talents, is the surest path to happiness.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>33–35</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Aristotle asserted that man had three natures: vegetable (physical/metabolism), animal (emotional/appetite) and rational (mental/conceptual). Physical nature can be assuaged through exercise and care, emotional nature through indulgence of instinct and urges, and mental through human reason and developed potential. Rational development was considered the most important, as essential to philosophical self-awareness and as uniquely human.<space/><link><target>Moderation</target></link><space/>was encouraged, with the extremes seen as degraded and immoral. For example,<space/><link><target>courage</target></link><space/>is the moderate virtue between the extremes of<space/><link><target>cowardice</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>recklessness (psychology)</target><part>recklessness</part></link>. Man should not simply live, but live well with conduct governed by moderate virtue. This is regarded as difficult, as virtue denotes doing the right thing, to the right person, at the right time, to the proper extent, in the correct fashion, for the right reason.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>35–37</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Stoicism</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Stoicism</target><part>Stoic</part></link><space/>philosopher<space/><link><target>Epictetus</target></link><space/>posited that the greatest good was contentment and serenity. Peace of mind, or<space/><link><target>Apatheia</target></link>, was of the highest value; self-mastery over one's desires and emotions leads to spiritual peace. The &quot;unconquerable will&quot; is central to this philosophy. The individual's will should be independent and inviolate. Allowing a person to disturb the mental equilibrium is in essence offering yourself in slavery. If a person is free to anger you at will, you have no control over your internal world, and therefore no freedom. Freedom from material attachments is also necessary. If a thing breaks, the person should not be upset, but realize it was a thing that could break. Similarly, if someone should die, those close to them should hold to their serenity because the loved one was made of flesh and blood destined to death. Stoic philosophy says to accept things that cannot be changed, resigning oneself to existence and enduring in a rational fashion. Death is not feared. People do not &quot;lose&quot; their life, but instead &quot;return&quot;, for they are returning to God (who initially gave what the person is as a person). Epictetus said difficult problems in life should not be avoided, but rather embraced. They are spiritual exercises needed for the health of the spirit, just as physical exercise is required for the health of the body. He also stated that sex and sexual desire are to be avoided as the greatest threat to the integrity and equilibrium of a man's mind. Abstinence is highly desirable. Epictetus said remaining abstinent in the face of temptation was a victory for which a man could be proud.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>38–41</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Contemporary virtue ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Virtue ethics</arg></template>Modern virtue ethics was popularized during the late 20th century in large part as a response to<space/><link><target>G. E. M. Anscombe</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Modern Moral Philosophy</target></link>&quot;. Anscombe argues that consequentialist and deontological ethics are only feasible as universal theories if the two schools ground themselves in divine law. As a deeply devoted Christian herself, Anscombe proposed that either those who do not give ethical credence to notions of divine law take up virtue ethics, which does not necessitate universal laws as agents themselves are investigated for virtue or vice and held up to &quot;universal standards,&quot; or that those who wish to be utilitarian or consequentialist ground their theories in religious conviction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vries"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Professor Michiel S. S. De De Vries</arg><arg name="author2">Professor Pan Suk Kim</arg><arg name="title">Value and Virtue in Public Administration: A Comparative Perspective</arg><arg name="date">October 28, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Palgrave Macmillan</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-230-35709-9</arg><arg name="page">42</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Alasdair MacIntyre</target></link>, who wrote the book<space/><italics><link><target>After Virtue</target></link></italics>, was a key contributor and proponent of modern virtue ethics, although MacIntyre supports a relativistic account of virtue based on<space/><link><target>Norm (social)</target><part>cultural norms</part></link>, not objective standards.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Vries"></extension><space/><link><target>Martha Nussbaum</target></link>, a contemporary virtue ethicist, objects to MacIntyre's relativism, among that of others, and responds to relativist objections to form an objective account in her work &quot;Non-Relative Virtues: An Aristotelian Approach.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Nussbaum</arg><arg name="first">Martha</arg><arg name="title">Non-Relative Virtues: An Aristotelian Approach</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg></template></extension><italics>Complete Conduct Principles for the 21st Century</italics><space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="ethics">John Newton, Ph.D.,<space/><italics>Complete Conduct Principles for the 21st Century</italics><space/>(2000). ISBN 0-9673705-7-4.</extension><space/>blended the Eastern virtue ethics and the Western virtue ethics, with some modifications to suit the 21st Century, and formed a part of contemporary virtue ethics.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ethics"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hedonism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Hedonism</arg></template>Hedonism posits that the principal ethic is maximizing<space/><link><target>pleasure</target></link><space/>and minimizing<space/><link><target>suffering</target><part>pain</part></link>. There are several schools of Hedonist thought ranging from those advocating the indulgence of even momentary desires to those teaching a pursuit of spiritual bliss. In their consideration of consequences, they range from those advocating<space/><link><target>self-gratification</target></link><space/>regardless of the pain and expense to others, to those stating that the most ethical pursuit maximizes pleasure and happiness for the most people.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>37</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Cyrenaic hedonism</heading><paragraph>Founded by<space/><link><target>Aristippus</target></link><space/>of Cyrene,<space/><link><target>Cyrenaics</target></link><space/>supported immediate gratification or pleasure. &quot;Eat, drink and be merry, for tomorrow we die.&quot; Even fleeting desires should be indulged, for fear the opportunity should be forever lost. There was little to no concern with the future, the present dominating in the pursuit for immediate pleasure. Cyrenaic hedonism encouraged the pursuit of enjoyment and indulgence without hesitation, believing pleasure to be the only good.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>37</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Epicureanism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Epicureanism</arg></template>Epicurean ethics is a hedonist form of virtue ethics.<space/><link><target>Epicurus</target></link><space/>&quot;presented a sustained argument that pleasure, correctly understood, will coincide with virtue&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-ancient/#9'>Ancient Ethical Theory</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></italics>.</extension><space/>He rejected the extremism of the<space/><link><target>Cyrenaics</target></link>, believing some pleasures and indulgences to be detrimental to human beings.<space/><link><target>Epicureanism</target><part>Epicureans</part></link><space/>observed that indiscriminate indulgence sometimes resulted in negative consequences. Some experiences were therefore rejected out of hand, and some unpleasant experiences endured in the present to ensure a better life in the future. To Epicurus the<space/><italics>summum bonum</italics>, or greatest good, was prudence, exercised through moderation and caution. Excessive indulgence can be destructive to pleasure and can even lead to pain. For example, eating one food too often will cause a person to lose taste for it. Eating too much food at once will lead to discomfort and ill-health. Pain and fear were to be avoided. Living was essentially good, barring pain and illness. Death was not to be feared. Fear was considered the source of most unhappiness. Conquering the fear of death would naturally lead to a happier life. Epicurus reasoned if there was an afterlife and immortality, the fear of death was irrational. If there was no life after death, then the person would not be alive to suffer, fear or worry; he would be non-existent in death. It is irrational to fret over circumstances that do not exist, such as one's state in death in the absence of an afterlife.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SahakianSahakian1966"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>37–38</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>State consequentialism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>State consequentialism</arg></template><link><target>State consequentialism</target></link>, also known as Mohist consequentialism,<extension extension_name='ref' name="readings"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Readings in classical Chinese philosophy</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="last">Ivanhoe</arg><arg name="first">P.J.</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Van Norden</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Bryan William</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Hackett Publishing]]</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87220-780-6<space/></arg><arg name="page">60</arg><arg name="quote">"he advocated a form of state consequentialism, which sought to maximize three basic goods: the wealth, order, and population of the state</arg></template></extension><space/>is an ethical theory that evaluates the moral worth of an action based on how much it contributes to the basic goods of a state.<extension extension_name='ref' name="readings"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>describes Mohist consequentialism, dating back to the 5th century BC, as &quot;a remarkably sophisticated version based on a plurality of intrinsic goods taken as constitutive of human welfare.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Fraser, Chris, &quot;<link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/mohism/'>Mohism</link>&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></italics><space/>, Edward N. Zalta.</extension><space/>Unlike utilitarianism, which views pleasure as a moral good, &quot;the basic goods in Mohist consequentialist thinking are&amp;nbsp;... order, material wealth, and increase in population&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cambridge"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">[[The Cambridge History of Ancient China]]</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="last">Loewe</arg><arg name="first">Michael</arg><arg name="last2">Shaughnessy</arg><arg name="first2">Edward L.</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press]]</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-47030-8</arg><arg name="page">761</arg></template></extension><space/>During<space/><link><target>Mozi</target></link>'s era, war and famines were common, and population growth was seen as a moral necessity for a harmonious society. The &quot;material wealth&quot; of Mohist consequentialism refers to<space/><link><target>Maslow's hierarchy of needs</target><part>basic needs</part></link><space/>like shelter and clothing, and the &quot;order&quot; of Mohist consequentialism refers to Mozi's stance against warfare and violence, which he viewed as pointless and a threat to social stability.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Norden"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Introduction to Classical Chinese Philosophy</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="last">Van Norden</arg><arg name="first">Bryan W.<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Hackett Publishing]]</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-60384-468-0</arg><arg name="page">52</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Stanford University</target><part>Stanford</part></link><space/><link><target>sinologist</target></link><space/><link><target>David S. Nivison</target><part>David Shepherd Nivison</part></link>, in<space/><italics><link><target>The Cambridge History of Ancient China</target></link></italics>, writes that the moral goods of Mohism &quot;are interrelated: more basic wealth, then more reproduction; more people, then more production and wealth&amp;nbsp;... if people have plenty, they would be good, filial, kind, and so on unproblematically.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cambridge"></extension><space/>The Mohists believed that morality is based on &quot;promoting the benefit of all under heaven and eliminating harm to all under heaven.&quot; In contrast to Bentham's views, state consequentialism is not utilitarian because it is not hedonistic or individualistic. The importance of outcomes that are good for the community outweigh the importance of individual pleasure and pain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Handbook"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Jay L. Garfield</arg><arg name="author2">William Edelglass</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford Handbook of World Philosophy</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">June 9, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-532899-8</arg><arg name="page">62</arg><arg name="quote">The goods that serve as criteria of morality are collective or public, in contrast, for instance, to individual happiness or well-being</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Consequentialism/Teleology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Consequentialism</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Ethical egoism</arg></template>Consequentialism refers to moral theories that hold that the consequences of a particular action form the basis for any valid moral judgment about that action (or create a structure for judgment, see<space/><link><target>#Rule consequentialism</target><part>rule consequentialism</part></link>). Thus, from a consequentialist standpoint, a morally right action is one that produces a good outcome, or consequence. This view is often expressed as the<space/><link><target>aphorism</target></link><space/><italics>&quot;The ends justify the means&quot;</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The term &quot;consequentialism&quot; was coined by<space/><link><target>G.E.M. Anscombe</target></link><space/>in her essay &quot;<link><target>Modern Moral Philosophy</target></link>&quot; in 1958, to describe what she saw as the central error of certain moral theories, such as those propounded by<space/><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target><part>Mill</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Henry Sidgwick</target><part>Sidgwick</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Anscombe"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="authorlink">G.E.M. Anscombe</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Modern Moral Philosophy</arg><arg name="journal">[[Philosophy (journal)|Philosophy]]</arg><arg name="volume">33</arg><arg name="pages">1–19<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.philosophy.uncc.edu/mleldrid/cmt/mmp.html</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/S0031819100037943<space/></arg><arg name="year">1958</arg><arg name="author">Anscombe, G. E. M.</arg><arg name="publisher">1958</arg><arg name="issue">124</arg></template></extension><space/>Since then, the term has become common in English-language ethical theory.</paragraph><paragraph>The defining feature of consequentialist moral theories is the weight given to the consequences in evaluating the rightness and wrongness of actions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mackie"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mackie</arg><arg name="first">J. L.</arg><arg name="authorlink">J._L._Mackie</arg><arg name="origyear">1977</arg><arg name="title">Ethics: Inventing Right and Wrong</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-013558-8</arg><arg name="year">1990</arg></template></extension><space/>In consequentialist theories, the consequences of an action or rule generally outweigh other considerations. Apart from this basic outline, there is little else that can be unequivocally said about consequentialism as such. However, there are some questions that many consequentialist theories address:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>What sort of consequences count as good consequences?</listitem><listitem>Who is the primary beneficiary of moral action?</listitem><listitem>How are the consequences judged and who judges them?</listitem></list><paragraph>One way to divide various consequentialisms is by the types of consequences that are taken to matter most, that is, which consequences count as good states of affairs. According to<space/><link><target>utilitarianism</target></link>, a good action is one that results in an increase in a positive effect, and the best action is one that results in that effect for the greatest number. Closely related is<space/><link><target>eudaimonia</target><part>eudaimonic</part></link><space/>consequentialism, according to which a full, flourishing life, which may or may not be the same as enjoying a great deal of pleasure, is the ultimate aim. Similarly, one might adopt an aesthetic consequentialism, in which the ultimate aim is to produce beauty. However, one might fix on non-psychological goods as the relevant effect. Thus, one might pursue an increase in<space/><link><target>Equality of outcome</target><part>material equality</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Freedom (political)</target><part>political liberty</part></link><space/>instead of something like the more ephemeral &quot;pleasure&quot;. Other theories adopt a package of several goods, all to be promoted equally. Whether a particular consequentialist theory focuses on a single good or many, conflicts and tensions between different good states of affairs are to be expected and must be adjudicated.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Utilitarianism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Utilitarianism</arg></template>Utilitarianism is an ethical theory that argues the proper course of action is one that maximizes a positive effect, such as &quot;happiness&quot;, &quot;welfare&quot;, or the ability to live according to personal preferences.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Ethics Toolkit: A Compendium of Ethical Concepts and Methods</arg><arg name="edition"></arg><arg name="last">Baqgini</arg><arg name="first">Julian</arg><arg name="author-link">Julian Baggini<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Fosl</arg><arg name="first2">Peter S.</arg><arg name="author2-link">Peter S. Fosl</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Blackwell</arg><arg name="location">Malden</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4051-3230-5</arg><arg name="pages">57–58</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Jeremy Bentham</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target></link><space/>are influential proponents of this school of thought. In<space/><italics>A Fragment on Government</italics><space/>Bentham says 'it is the greatest happiness of the greatest number that is the measure of right and wrong' and describes this as a fundamental<space/><link><target>axiom</target></link>. In<space/><italics>An Introduction to the Principles of Morals and Legislation</italics><space/>he talks of 'the principle of utility' but later prefers &quot;the greatest happiness principle&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bentham<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jeremy</arg><arg name="title">The Works of Jeremy Bentham: Published under the Superintendence of His Executor, John Bowring. Volume 1</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Adamant Media Corporation</arg><arg name="page">18</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4021-6393-7</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="John Stuart Mill"><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/files/11224/11224-h/11224-h.htm#CHAPTER_I'>Mill, John Stuart, Utilitarianism (Project Gutenberg online edition)</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Utilitarianism is the paradigmatic example of a consequentialist moral theory. This form of utilitarianism holds that what matters is the aggregate positive effect of everyone and not only of any one person.<space/><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target></link>, in his exposition of utilitarianism, proposed a hierarchy of pleasures, meaning that the pursuit of certain kinds of pleasure is more highly valued than the pursuit of other pleasures.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mill"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Utilitarianism</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="last">Mill</arg><arg name="first">John Stuart</arg><arg name="authorlink">John Stuart Mill</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-875163-2</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.utilitarianism.com/mill1.htm</arg></template></extension><space/>Other noteworthy proponents of utilitarianism are neuroscientist<space/><link><target>Sam Harris (author)</target><part>Sam Harris</part></link>, author of<space/><link><target>The Moral Landscape</target></link>, and moral philosopher<space/><link><target>Peter Singer</target></link>, author of, amongst other works,<space/><link><target>Practical Ethics</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>There are two types of utilitarianism,<space/><link><target>act utilitarianism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>rule utilitarianism</target></link>. In act utilitarianism the principle of utility is applied directly to each alternative act in a situation of choice. The right act is then defined as the one which brings about the best results (or the least amount of bad results). In rule utilitarianism the principle of utility is used to determine the validity of rules of conduct (moral principles). A rule like promise-keeping is established by looking at the consequences of a world in which people broke promises at will and a world in which promises were binding. Right and wrong are then defined as following or breaking those rules.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carnegie Mellon University"><link type='external' href='http://caae.phil.cmu.edu/cavalier/80130/part2/sect9.html'>, Department of Philosophy, CMU</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Deontology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Deontological ethics</arg></template>Deontological ethics or deontology (from<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>δέον</arg></template>,<space/><italics>deon</italics>, &quot;obligation, duty&quot;; and<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>-λογία</arg></template>,<space/><italics><link><target>-logy</target><part>-logia</part></link></italics>) is an approach to ethics that determines goodness or rightness from examining<space/><link><target>acts</target></link>, or the rules and duties that the person doing the act strove to fulfill.<extension extension_name='ref' name="plato.stanford.edu"><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-deontological/'>Stanford.edu</link></extension><space/>This is in contrast to<space/><link><target>consequentialism</target></link>, in which rightness is based on the consequences of an act, and not the act by itself. In deontology, an act may be considered right even if the act produces a bad consequence,<extension extension_name='ref'>Olson, Robert G. 1967. 'Deontological Ethics'. In Paul Edwards (ed.)<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of Philosophy</italics>. London:<space/><link><target>Collier Macmillan</target></link>: 343.</extension><space/>if it follows the<space/><italics>rule</italics><space/>that &quot;one should do unto others as they would have done unto them&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ethics-virtue/</extension><space/>and even if the person who does the act lacks virtue and had a bad intention in doing the act.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2009</arg></template><space/>According to deontology, we have a<space/><italics>duty</italics><space/>to act in a way that does those things that are<space/><link><target>inherently</target></link><space/>good as acts (&quot;truth-telling&quot; for example), or follow an objectively obligatory rule (as in<space/><link><target>rule utilitarianism</target></link>). For deontologists, the ends or consequences of our actions are not important in and of themselves, and our intentions are not important in and of themselves.</paragraph><paragraph>Immanuel Kant's theory of ethics is considered deontological for several different reasons.<extension extension_name='ref'>Orend, Brian. 2000.<space/><italics>War and International Justice: A Kantian Perspective</italics>. West Waterloo, Ontario:<space/><link><target>Wilfrid Laurier University Press</target></link>: 19.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, Eugene. 2006.<space/><italics>The Basics of Western Philosophy</italics>.<space/><link><target>Greenwood Press</target></link>: 160.</extension><space/>First, Kant argues that to act in the morally right way, people must act from duty (<italics>deon</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Kant, Immanuel. 1780. 'Preface'. In<space/><italics>The Metaphysical Elements of Ethics</italics>. Translated by Thomas Kingsmill Abbott</extension><space/>Second, Kant argued that it was not the consequences of actions that make them right or wrong but the motives (maxime) of the person who carries out the action.<link><target>File:Immanuel Kant (painted portrait).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link></part><part>right</part></link>Kant's argument that to act in the morally right way, one must act from duty, begins with an argument that the highest good must be both good in itself, and good without qualification.<extension extension_name='ref' name="transition">Kant, Immanuel. 1785. 'First Section: Transition from the Common Rational Knowledge of Morals to the Philosophical',<space/><link><target>Groundwork of the Metaphysic of Morals</target></link>.</extension><space/>Something is 'good in itself' when it is<space/><link><target>intrinsic value (ethics)</target><part>intrinsically good</part></link>, and 'good without qualification' when the addition of that thing never makes a situation ethically worse. Kant then argues that those things that are usually thought to be good, such as<space/><link><target>intelligence</target></link>, perseverance and<space/><link><target>pleasure</target></link>, fail to be either intrinsically good or good without qualification. Pleasure, for example, appears to not be good without qualification, because when people take pleasure in watching someone suffer, they make the situation ethically worse. He concludes that there is only one thing that is truly good:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Nothing in the worldindeed nothing even beyond the worldcan possibly be conceived which could be called good without qualification except a<space/><italics>good will</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="transition"></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pragmatic ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Pragmatic ethics</arg></template>Associated with the<space/><link><target>pragmatism</target><part>pragmatists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles Sanders Peirce</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William James</target></link>, and especially<space/><link><target>John Dewey</target></link>, pragmatic ethics holds that moral correctness evolves similarly to scientific knowledge: socially over the course of many lifetimes. Thus, we should prioritize social reform over attempts to account for consequences, individual virtue or duty (although these may be worthwhile attempts, provided social reform is provided for).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lafollette2000"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-first">Hugh</arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Lafollette</arg><arg name="series">Blackwell Philosophy Guides</arg><arg name="edition">1</arg><arg name="url">http://www.hughlafollette.com/papers/pragmati.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 2000</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Guide to Ethical Theory</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-20119-9<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Wiley-Blackwell]]</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Role ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Role ethics</arg></template>Role ethics is an ethical theory based on<space/><link><target>family</target></link><space/>roles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ames"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Roger T. Ames</arg><arg name="title">Confucian Role Ethics: A Vocabulary</arg><arg name="date">April 30, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Hawaiʻi Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8248-3576-7</arg></template></extension><space/>Unlike<space/><link><target>virtue ethics</target></link>, role ethics is not individualistic. Morality is derived from a person's relationship with their community.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fraser"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Chris Fraser</arg><arg name="author2">Dan Robins<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Timothy O'Leary</arg><arg name="title">Ethics in Early China: An Anthology</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">May 1, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Hong Kong University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-988-8028-93-1</arg><arg name="pages">17–35</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Confucianism</target><part>Confucian</part></link><space/>ethics is an example of role ethics.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ames"></extension><space/>Confucian roles center around the concept of<space/><link><target>filial piety</target></link><space/>or<space/><italics>xiao</italics>, a respect for family members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chang"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Wonsuk Chang</arg><arg name="author2">Leah Kalmanson</arg><arg name="title">Confucianism in Context: Classic Philosophy and Contemporary Issues, East Asia and Beyond</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">November 8, 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">[[State University of New York Press|SUNY Press]]</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4384-3191-8</arg><arg name="page">68</arg></template></extension><space/>According to Roger Ames and Henry Rosemont, &quot;Confucian normativity is defined by living one's family roles to maximum effect.&quot; Morality is determined through a person's fulfillment of a role, such as that of a parent or a child. Confucian roles are not<space/><link><target>rationalism</target><part>rational</part></link>, and originate through the<space/><italics>xin</italics>, or human emotions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fraser"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Anarchist ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Anarchism</arg></template><link><target>Anarchism</target><part>Anarchist</part></link><space/>ethics is an ethical theory based on the studies of anarchist thinkers. The biggest contributor to the anarchist ethics is the Russian zoologist, geographer, economist and political activist<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target></link>. The anarchist ethics is a big and vague field which can depend upon different historical situations and different anarchist thinkers, but as Peter Kropotkin explains, &quot;any bourgeois or proletarian ethics rests, after all, on the common basis, on the common ethnological foundation, which at times exerts a very strong inuence on the principles of the class or group morality.&quot; Still, most of the anarchist ethics schools are based on three fundamental ideas, which are: &quot;solidarity, equality and justice&quot;. Kropotkin argues that Ethics is evolutionary and is inherited as a sort of a social instinct through History, and by so, he rejects any religious and transcendental explanation of ethics.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://theanarchistlibrary.org/library/petr-kropotkin-ethics-origin-and-development.pdf'>&quot;Ethics: Origin and Development&quot; by Ptr Kropotkin</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Postmodern ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Postmodernism</arg></template><template><target>Synthesis</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template>The 20th century saw a remarkable expansion and evolution of critical theory, following on earlier<space/><link><target>Marxism</target><part>Marxist Theory</part></link><space/>efforts to locate individuals within larger structural frameworks of ideology and action.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Antihumanism</target><part>Antihumanists</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Louis Althusser</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Structuralism</target><part>structuralists</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Roland Barthes</target></link><space/>challenged the possibilities of individual agency and the coherence of the notion of the 'individual' itself.<template><target>Clarify</target><arg name="date">February 2010</arg></template><space/>As critical theory developed in the later 20th century,<space/><link><target>post-structuralism</target></link><space/>sought to problematize human relationships to knowledge and 'objective' reality.<space/><link><target>Jacques Derrida</target></link><space/>argued that access to meaning and the 'real' was always deferred, and sought to demonstrate via recourse to the linguistic realm that &quot;there is nothing outside context&quot; (&quot;<italics>il n'y a pas de hors-texte</italics>&quot; is often mistranslated as &quot;there is nothing outside the text&quot;); at the same time,<space/><link><target>Jean Baudrillard</target></link><space/>theorised that signs and symbols or simulacra mask reality (and eventually the absence of reality itself), particularly in the consumer world.</paragraph><paragraph>Post-structuralism and<space/><link><target>postmodernism</target></link><space/>argue that ethics must study the complex and relational conditions of actions. A simple alignment of ideas of right and particular acts is not possible. There will always be an ethical remainder that cannot be taken into account or often even recognized. Such theorists find narrative (or, following Nietzsche and Foucault,<space/><link><target>genealogy</target></link>) to be a helpful tool for understanding ethics because narrative is always about particular lived experiences in all their complexity rather than the assignment of an idea or norm to separate and individuated actions.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Zygmunt Bauman</target></link><space/>says<space/><link><target>Postmodernity</target></link><space/>is best described as Modernity without illusion, the illusion being the belief that humanity can be repaired by some ethic principle. Postmodernity can be seen in this light as accepting the messy nature of humanity as unchangeable.</paragraph><paragraph>David Couzens Hoy states that<space/><link><target>Emmanuel Levinas</target></link>'s writings on the face of the Other and<space/><link><target>Derrida</target></link>'s meditations on the relevance of death to ethics are signs of the &quot;ethical turn&quot; in Continental philosophy that occurred in the 1980s and 1990s. Hoy describes post-critique ethics as the &quot;obligations that present themselves as necessarily to be fulfilled but are neither forced on one or are enforceable&quot; (2004, p.&amp;nbsp;103).</paragraph><paragraph>Hoy's post-critique model uses the term<space/><italics>ethical resistance</italics>. Examples of this would be an individual's resistance to consumerism in a retreat to a simpler but perhaps harder lifestyle, or an individual's resistance to a terminal illness. Hoy describes Levinas's account as &quot;not the attempt to use power against itself, or to mobilize sectors of the population to exert their political power; the ethical resistance is instead the resistance of the powerless&quot;(2004, p.&amp;nbsp;8).</paragraph><paragraph>Hoy concludes that<template><target>quote</target><arg>The ethical resistance of the powerless others to our capacity to exert power over them is therefore what imposes unenforceable obligations on us. The obligations are unenforceable precisely because of the other's lack of power. That actions are at once obligatory and at the same time unenforceable is what put them in the category of the ethical. Obligations that were enforced would, by the virtue of the force behind them, not be freely undertaken and would not be in the realm of the ethical. (2004, p.184)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In present-day terms the powerless may include the unborn, the terminally sick, the aged, the insane, and non-human animals. It is in these areas that ethical action in Hoy's sense will apply. Until legislation or the state apparatus enforces a moral order that addresses the causes of resistance these issues will remain in the ethical realm. For example, should animal experimentation become illegal in a society, it will no longer be an ethical issue on Hoy's definition. Likewise one hundred and fifty years ago, not having a black slave in America would have been an ethical choice. This later issue has been absorbed into the fabric of an enforceable social order and is therefore no longer an ethical issue in Hoy's sense.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Applied ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Applied ethics</arg></template>Applied ethics is a discipline of philosophy that attempts to apply ethical theory to real-life situations. The discipline has many specialized fields, such as<space/><link><target>engineering ethics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>bioethics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>geoethics</target></link>, public service ethics and<space/><link><target>business ethics</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Specific questions</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2009</arg></template>Applied ethics is used in some aspects of determining public policy, as well as by individuals facing difficult decisions. The sort of questions addressed by applied ethics include: &quot;Is getting an abortion immoral?&quot; &quot;Is euthanasia immoral?&quot; &quot;Is affirmative action right or wrong?&quot; &quot;What are human rights, and how do we determine them?&quot; &quot;Do animals have rights as well?&quot; and &quot;Do individuals have the right of self determination?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="bbc"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A more specific question could be: &quot;If someone else can make better out of his/her life than I can, is it then moral to sacrifice myself for them if needed?&quot; Without these questions there is no clear fulcrum on which to balance law, politics, and the practice of arbitration in fact, no common assumptions of all participantsso the ability to formulate the questions are prior to rights balancing. But not all questions studied in applied ethics concern public policy. For example, making ethical judgments regarding questions such as, &quot;Is lying always wrong?&quot; and, &quot;If not, when is it permissible?&quot; is prior to any etiquette.</paragraph><paragraph>People in-general are more comfortable with dichotomies (two opposites). However, in ethics the issues are most often multifaceted and the best proposed actions address many different areas concurrently. In ethical decisions the answer is almost never a &quot;yes or no&quot;, &quot;right or wrong&quot; statement. Many buttons are pushed so that the overall condition is improved and not to the benefit of any particular faction.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Particular fields of application</heading><heading level='4'>Bioethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Bioethics</arg></template>Bioethics is the study of controversial ethics brought about by advances in<space/><link><target>biology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>medicine</target></link>. Bioethicists are concerned with the ethical questions that arise in the relationships among<space/><link><target>life sciences</target></link>,<space/><link><target>biotechnology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>medicine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>politics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>law</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link>. It also includes the study of the more commonplace questions of values (<link><target>primary care ethics</target><part>&quot;the ethics of the ordinary&quot;</part></link>) that arise in primary care and other branches of medicine.</paragraph><paragraph>Bioethics also needs to address emerging biotechnologies that affect basic biology and future humans. These developments include<space/><link><target>cloning</target></link>,<space/><link><target>gene therapy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>human genetic engineering</target></link>, astroethics and life in space,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.astroethics.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Astroethics</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 21, 2005</arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20131023060209/http://www.astroethics.com/</arg><arg name="archivedate">October 23, 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>and manipulation of basic biology through altered DNA, XNA and proteins,e.g.- &quot;three parent baby,where baby is born from genetically modified embryos, would have DNA from a mother, a father and from a female donor.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Freemont</arg><arg name="first1">P. F.</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Kitney</arg><arg name="first2">R. I.</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="title">Synthetic Biology</arg><arg name="publisher">[[World Scientific]]</arg><arg name="location">New Jersey</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84816-862-6</arg></template></extension><space/>Correspondingly, new bioethics also need to address life at its core. For example,<space/><link><target>biotic ethics</target></link><space/>value organic gene/protein life itself and seek to propagate it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bioethics"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Mautner</arg><arg name="first">Michael N.</arg><arg name="title">Life-centered ethics, and the human future in space</arg><arg name="journal">[[Bioethics (journal)|Bioethics]]</arg><arg name="volume">23</arg><arg name="pages">433–440</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1467-8519.2008.00688.x</arg><arg name="pmid">19077128</arg><arg name="url">http://www.astro-ecology.com/PDFLifeCenteredBioethics2009Paper.pdf<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>With such life-centered principles, ethics may secure a cosmological future for life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mautner</arg><arg name="first">Michael N.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Seeding the Universe with Life: Securing Our Cosmological Future</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Legacy Books]] (www.amazon.com)</arg><arg name="location">Washington D. C.</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="isbn">0-476-00330-X</arg><arg name="url">http://www.astro-ecology.com/PDFSeedingtheUniverse2005Book.pdf</arg><arg name="format">[[Portable Document Format|PDF]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Business ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Business ethics</arg></template>Business ethics (also corporate ethics) is a form of<space/><link><target>applied ethics</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>professional ethics</target></link><space/>that examines ethical principles and moral or ethical problems that arise in a business environment, including fields like<space/><link><target>Medical ethics</target></link>. It applies to all aspects of business conduct and is relevant to the conduct of individuals and entire organizations.</paragraph><paragraph>Business ethics has both<space/><link><target>Norm (philosophy)</target><part>normative</part></link><space/>and descriptive dimensions. As a corporate practice and a career specialization, the field is primarily normative. Academics attempting to understand business behavior employ descriptive methods. The range and quantity of business ethical issues reflects the interaction of profit-maximizing behavior with non-economic concerns.Interest in business ethics accelerated dramatically during the 1980s and 1990s, both within major corporations and within academia. For example, today most major corporations promote their commitment to non-economic values under headings such as ethics codes and social responsibility charters.Adam Smith said, &quot;People of the same trade seldom meet together, even for merriment and diversion, but the conversation ends in a conspiracy against the public, or in some contrivance to raise prices.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Smith, A (1776/ 1952) An Inquiry Into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations. Chicago, IL: University of Chicago Press, p. 55</extension><space/>Governments use laws and regulations to point business behavior in what they perceive to be beneficial directions. Ethics implicitly regulates areas and details of behavior that lie beyond governmental control.<extension extension_name='ref'>Berle, A. A., &amp; Means, G. C. (1932). The Modern Corporation and Private Property. New Jersey: Transaction Publishers. In this book, Berle and Means observe, &quot;Corporations have ceased to be merely legal devices through which the private business transactions of individuals may be carried on. Though still much used for this purpose, the corporate form has acquired a much larger significance. The corporation has, in fact, become both a method of property tenure and a means of organizing economic life. Grown to tremendous proportions, there may be said to have evolved a 'corporate system'as there once was a feudal systemwhich has attracted to itself a combination of attributes and powers, and has attained a degree of prominence entitling it to be dealt with as a major social institution.&amp;nbsp;... We are examining this institution probably before it has attained its zenith. Spectacular as its rise has been, every indication seems to be that the system will move forward to proportions which stagger imagination today&amp;nbsp;... They [management] have placed the community in a position to demand that the modern corporation serve not only the owners&amp;nbsp;... but all society.&quot; p. 1.</extension><space/>The emergence of large corporations with limited relationships and sensitivity to the communities in which they operate accelerated the development of formal ethics regimes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Jones</arg><arg>Parker</arg><arg>et al.</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Relational ethics</heading><paragraph>Relational ethics are related to an<space/><link><target>ethics of care</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GILLIGAN2009"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Carol GILLIGAN</arg><arg name="title">IN A DIFFERENT VOICE</arg><arg name="date">June 30, 2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-674-03761-8</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>62–63</arg></template><space/>They are used in qualitative research, especially ethnography and autoethnography. Researchers who employ relational ethics value and respect the connection between themselves and the people they study, and &quot;between researchers and the communities in which they live and work&quot; (Ellis, 2007, p.&amp;nbsp;4).<extension extension_name='ref'>Ellis, C. (2007). Telling secrets, revealing lives: Relational ethics in research with intimate others.<space/><italics>Qualitative Inquiry, 13,</italics><space/>3-29.</extension><space/>Relational ethics also help researchers understand difficult issues such as conducting research on intimate others that have died and developing friendships with their participants.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ellis, C. (1986).<space/><italics>Fisher folk. Two communities on Chesapeake Bay.</italics><space/>Lexington:<space/><link><target>University Press of Kentucky</target></link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Ellis, C. (1995).<italics>Final negotiations: A story of love, loss, and chronic illness.</italics><space/>Philadelphia:<space/><link><target>Temple University Press</target></link>.</extension><space/>Relational ethics in close personal relationships form a central concept of<space/><link><target>Ivan Bszrmnyi-Nagy#Contextual therapy</target><part>contextual therapy</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Machine ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Machine ethics</arg></template>In<space/><italics>Moral Machines: Teaching Robots Right from Wrong</italics>, Wendell Wallach and Colin Allen conclude that issues in<space/><link><target>machine ethics</target></link><space/>will likely drive advancement in understanding of human ethics by forcing us to address gaps in modern normative theory and by providing a platform for experimental investigation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallach2008"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first1">Wendell<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Wallach</arg><arg name="first2">Colin</arg><arg name="last2">Allen</arg><arg name="date">November 2008</arg><arg name="title">Moral Machines: Teaching Robots Right from Wrong</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-537404-9</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]</arg><arg name="location">USA</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension><space/>The effort to actually program a machine or artificial agent to behave as though instilled with a sense of ethics requires new specificity in our normative theories, especially regarding aspects customarily considered common-sense. For example, machines, unlike humans, can support a wide selection of<space/><link><target>List of machine learning algorithms</target><part>learning algorithms</part></link>, and controversy has arisen over the relative ethical merits of these options. This may reopen classic debates of normative ethics framed in new (highly technical) terms.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Military ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Geneva Conventions</arg><arg>Nuremberg Principles</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Military ethics are concerned with questions regarding the application of force and the ethos of the soldier and are often understood as applied professional ethics.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last2">Syse</arg><arg name="first2">Henrik</arg><arg name="last1">Cook</arg><arg name="first1">Martin L.</arg><arg name="title">What Should We Mean by 'Military Ethics'?</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Military Ethics</arg><arg name="volume">9</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="page">122</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Just war theory</target></link><space/>is generally seen to set the background terms of military ethics. However individual countries and traditions have different fields of attention.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Emmanuel</arg><arg name="last">Goffi</arg><arg name="authorlink">Emmanuel Goffi</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="title">Les Armée Françaises Face à la Morale</arg><arg name="trans_title">The French Army Facing Morale</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.ca/books?id</arg><arg name="language">fr</arg><arg name="location">France</arg><arg name="publisher">L'Harmattan</arg><arg name="isbn">978-2296542495</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Military ethics involves multiple subareas, including the following among others:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>what, if any, should be the laws of war</listitem><listitem>justification for the initiation of military force</listitem><listitem>decisions about who may be targeted in warfare</listitem><listitem>decisions on choice of weaponry, and what collateral effects such weaponry may have</listitem><listitem>standards for handling military prisoners</listitem><listitem>methods of dealing with violations of the laws of war</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Political ethics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Political ethics</target></link><space/>(also known as political morality or public ethics) is the practice of making moral judgements about political action and political agents.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thompson, Dennis F. &quot;Political Ethics.&quot;<space/><italics>International Encyclopedia of Ethics</italics>, ed. Hugh LaFollette (Blackwell Publishing, 2012).</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Public sector ethics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Public sector ethics</target></link><space/>is a set of principles that guide public officials in their service to their constituents, including their decision-making on behalf of their constituents. Fundamental to the concept of public sector ethics is the notion that decisions and actions are based on what best serves the public's interests, as opposed to the official's personal interests (including financial interests) or self-serving political interests.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, work of Institute for Local Government, at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ca-ilg.org/trust'>www.ca-ilg.org/trust</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Publication ethics</heading><paragraph>Publication ethics is the set of principles that guide the writing and publishing process for all professional publications. In order to follow the set of principles, authors should verify that the publication does not contain<space/><link><target>plagiarism</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>publication bias</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Publication ethics"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Morton</arg><arg name="first1">Neil</arg><arg name="title">Publication ethics</arg><arg name="journal">Pediatric Anesthesia</arg><arg name="date">October 2009</arg><arg name="volume">19</arg><arg name="issue">10</arg><arg name="pages">1011–1013</arg><arg name="url">http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/j.1460-9592.2009.03086.x/full</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>As a way to avoid misconduct in research these principles can also be applied to experiments which are referenced or analyzed in publications by ensuring the data is recorded, honestly and accurately.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Wager</arg><arg name="first1">E</arg><arg name="last2">Fiack</arg><arg name="first2">S</arg><arg name="last3">Graf</arg><arg name="first3">C</arg><arg name="last4">Robinson</arg><arg name="first4">A</arg><arg name="last5">Rowlands</arg><arg name="first5">I</arg><arg name="title">Science journal editors’ views on publication ethics: results of an international survey</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Medical Ethics</arg><arg name="date">31 March 2009</arg><arg name="volume">35</arg><arg name="pages">348–353</arg><arg name="url">http://jme.bmj.com/content/35/6/348.short</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Plagiarism is the failure to give credit to another authors work or ideas, when it is used in the publication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Scollon</arg><arg name="first1">Ron</arg><arg name="title">Plagiarism</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Linguistic Anthropology</arg><arg name="date">June 1999</arg><arg name="volume">9</arg><arg name="pages">188–190</arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu:2048/stable/43102462?Search</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>It is the obligation of the editor of the journal to ensure the article does not contain any plagiarism before it is published.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Wager</arg><arg name="first1">Elizabeth</arg><arg name="last2">Williams</arg><arg name="first2">Peter</arg><arg name="title">Why and how do journals retract articles? An analysis of Medline retractions 1988—2008</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Medical Ethics</arg><arg name="date">September 2011</arg><arg name="volume">37</arg><arg name="issue">9</arg><arg name="pages">567–570</arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu:2048/stable/23034717?Search</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>If a publication which has already been published is proven to contain plagiarism, then the editor of the journal can proceed to have the article retracted.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Sanjeev</arg><arg name="first1">Handa</arg><arg name="title">Plagiarism and publication ethics: Dos and don'ts</arg><arg name="journal">Indian Journal of Dermatology Venereology and Leprology</arg><arg name="date">2008</arg><arg name="volume">74</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="pages">301–303</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ijdvl.com/article.asp?issn</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Publication bias occurs when the publication is one-sided or &quot;<link><target>prejudiced</target></link><space/>against results&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Sigelman</arg><arg name="first1">Lee</arg><arg name="title">Publication Bias Reconsidered</arg><arg name="journal">Political Analysis</arg><arg name="date">2000</arg><arg name="volume">8</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">201–210</arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu:2048/stable/25791607?Search</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In best practice, an author should try to include information from all parties involved, or affected by the topic. If an author is prejudiced against certain results, than it can &quot;lead to erroneous conclusions being drawn.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Peters</arg><arg name="first1">Jamie L.</arg><arg name="last2">Sutton</arg><arg name="first2">Alex J.</arg><arg name="last3">Jones</arg><arg name="first3">David R.</arg><arg name="last4">Abrams</arg><arg name="first4">Keith R.</arg><arg name="last5">Rushton</arg><arg name="first5">Lesley</arg><arg name="last6">Moreno</arg><arg name="first6">Santiago G.</arg><arg name="title">Assessing publication bias in meta-analysis in the presence of between-study heterogeneity</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. Series A (Statistics in Society)</arg><arg name="date">July 2010</arg><arg name="volume">173</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">575–591</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Misconduct in research can occur when information from an experiment is falsely recorded or altered.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Smith</arg><arg name="first1">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Misconduct in Research: Editors Respond: The Committee on Publication Ethics (COPE) Is Formed</arg><arg name="journal">British Medical Journal</arg><arg name="date">July 26, 1997</arg><arg name="volume">315</arg><arg name="issue">7102</arg><arg name="pages">201–202</arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu:2048/stable/25175246?Search</arg><arg name="accessdate">March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Falsely recorded information occurs when the researcher &quot;fakes&quot; information or data, which was not used when conducting the actual experiment.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jstor.org.summit.csuci.edu"></extension><space/>By faking the data, the researcher can alter the results from the experiment to better fit the hypothesis they originally predicted. When conducting medical research, it is important to honor the healthcare rights of a patient by protecting their<space/><link><target>anonymity</target></link><space/>in the publication.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Publication ethics"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Moral psychology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Moral psychology</arg></template><bold>Moral psychology</bold><space/>is a field of study that began as an issue in<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>and that is now properly considered part of the discipline of<space/><link><target>psychology</target></link>. Some use the term &quot;moral psychology&quot; relatively narrowly to refer to the study of<space/><link><target>moral development</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, Lapsley (2006) and &quot;moral psychology&quot; (2007).</extension><space/>However, others tend to use the term more broadly to include any topics at the intersection of ethics and psychology (and<space/><link><target>philosophy of mind</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, Doris &amp; Stich (2008) and Wallace (2007). Wallace writes: &quot;Moral psychology is the study of morality in its psychological dimensions&quot; (p. 86).</extension><space/>Such topics are ones that involve the mind and are relevant to moral issues. Some of the main topics of the field are<space/><link><target>moral responsibility</target></link>, moral development,<space/><link><target>moral character</target></link><space/>(especially as related to<space/><link><target>virtue ethics</target></link>),<space/><link><target>altruism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>psychological egoism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>moral luck</target></link>, and moral disagreement.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Doris &amp; Stich (2008), 1.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Evolutionary ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Evolutionary ethics</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Evolution of morality</arg></template>Evolutionary ethics concerns approaches to ethics (morality) based on the role of evolution in shaping human psychology and behavior. Such approaches may be based in scientific fields such as<space/><link><target>evolutionary psychology</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>sociobiology</target></link>, with a focus on understanding and explaining observed ethical preferences and choices.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/evol-eth/</arg><arg name="title">Evolutionary Ethics</arg><arg name="author">Doris Schroeder</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 5, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">//web.archive.org/web/20131007081051/http://www.iep.utm.edu/evol-eth/<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">October 7, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Descriptive ethics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Descriptive ethics</arg></template>Descriptive ethics is on the less philosophical end of the spectrum, since it seeks to gather particular information about how people live and draw general conclusions based on observed patterns. Abstract and theoretical questions that are more clearly philosophicalsuch as, &quot;Is ethical knowledge possible?&quot;are not central to descriptive ethics. Descriptive ethics offers a<space/><link><target>Value-neutral</target><part>value-free</part></link><space/>approach to ethics, which defines it as a social science rather than<space/><link><target>humanities</target><part>a humanity</part></link>. Its examination of ethics doesn't start with a preconceived theory, but rather investigates<space/><link><target>revealed preference</target><part>observations of actual choices</part></link><space/>made by moral agents in practice. Some philosophers rely on descriptive ethics and choices made and unchallenged by a<space/><link><target>society</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>culture</target></link><space/>to derive categories, which typically vary by context. This can lead to<space/><link><target>situational ethics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>situated ethics</target></link>. These philosophers often view<space/><link><target>aesthetics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>etiquette</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>arbitration</target></link><space/>as more fundamental, percolating &quot;bottom up&quot; to imply the existence of, rather than explicitly prescribe, theories of value or of conduct. The study of descriptive ethics may include examinations of the following:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ethical code</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>applied by various groups. Some consider aesthetics itself the basis of ethics and a personal<space/><link><target>moral core</target></link><space/>developed through art and storytelling as very influential in one's later ethical choices.</listitem><listitem>Informal theories of etiquette that tend to be less rigorous and more situational. Some consider etiquette a simple negative ethics, i.e., where can one evade an uncomfortable truth without doing wrong? One notable advocate of this view is<space/><link><target>Judith Martin</target></link><space/>(&quot;Miss Manners&quot;). According to this view, ethics is more a summary of<space/><link><target>common sense</target></link><space/>social decisions.</listitem><listitem>Practices in arbitration and<space/><link><target>law</target></link>, e.g., the claim that ethics itself is a matter of balancing &quot;right versus right,&quot; i.e., putting priorities on two things that are both right, but that must be traded off carefully in each situation.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Revealed preference</target><part>Observed choices</part></link><space/>made by ordinary people, without expert aid or advice, who<space/><link><target>Voting</target><part>vote</part></link>, buy, and decide what is worth valuing. This is a major concern of sociology,<space/><link><target>political science</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>economics</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Philosophy</arg></template></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Contemporary ethics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Corporate social responsibility</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Deductive reasoning</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Descriptive ethics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dharma</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ethical movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Index of ethics articles</target></link><space/><italics>(alphabetical list of ethics-related articles)</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Moral psychology</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Outline of ethics</target></link><space/><italics>(list of ethics-related articles, arranged by sub-topic)</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Practical philosophy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Science of morality</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Theory of justification</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Hoy, D. (2005), Critical resistance from poststructuralism to postcritique,<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</target></link>, Massachusetts.</listitem><listitem>Lyon, D. (1999), Postmodernity, 2nd ed,<space/><link><target>Open University Press</target></link>, Buckingham.</listitem><listitem>Singer, P. (2000), Writings on an ethical life,<space/><link><target>Harper Collins Publishers</target></link>, London.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Nicomachean Ethics</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/'>London Philosophy Study Guide</link><space/>offers many suggestions on what to read, depending on the student's familiarity with the subject:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/Ethics.htm'>Ethics</link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Encyclopedia of Ethics</target></link></italics>. Lawrence C. Becker and Charlotte B. Becker, editors. Second edition in three volumes. New York: Routledge, 2002. A scholarly encyclopedia with over 500 signed,<space/><link><target>peer-review</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>articles, mostly on topics and figures of, or of special interest in,<space/><link><target>Western philosophy</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Joxe Azurmendi</target><part>Azurmendi, J.</part></link><space/>1998: &quot;The violence and the search for new values&quot; in<space/><italics>Euskal Herria krisian</italics>, (Elkar, 1999), pp.&amp;nbsp;11116. ISBN 84-8331-572-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>Simon Blackburn</target><part>Blackburn, S.</part></link><space/>(2001).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/title/being-good-a-short-introduction-to-ethics/oclc/51644518'>''Being good: A short introduction to ethics''. Oxford: Oxford University Press.</link></listitem><listitem>De Finance, Joseph,<space/><italics>An Ethical Inquiry</italics>, Rome, Editrice Pontificia Universit Gregoriana, 1991.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Miguel A. De La Torre</target><part>De La Torre, Miguel A.</part></link>, &quot;Doing Christian Ethics from the Margins,&quot; Orbis Books, 2004.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jacques Derrida</target><part>Derrida, J.</part></link><space/>1995,<space/><italics>The Gift of Death</italics>, translated by David Wills,<space/><link><target>University of Chicago Press</target></link>, Chicago.</listitem><listitem>Fagothey, Austin,<space/><italics>Right and Reason</italics>, Tan Books &amp; Publishers, Rockford, Illinois, 2000.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Emmanuel Levinas</target><part>Levinas, E.</part></link><space/>1969,<space/><italics>Totality and infinity, an essay on exteriority</italics>, translated by Alphonso Lingis,<space/><link><target>Duquesne University Press</target></link>, Pittsburgh.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="authorlink">Stephen Perle<space/></arg><arg name="last">Perle</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chiroweb.com/archives/22/06/16.html</arg><arg name="title">Morality and Ethics: An Introduction</arg><arg name="date"><space/>March 11, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 13, 2007</arg></template>,<space/><link><target>Panayot Butchvarov</target><part>Butchvarov, Panayot</part></link>. Skepticism in Ethics (1989).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert C. Solomon</target><part>Solomon, R.C.</part></link>,<space/><italics>Morality and the Good Life: An Introduction to Ethics Through Classical Sources</italics>, New York:<space/><link><target>McGraw-Hill Book Company</target></link>, 1984.</listitem><listitem>Vendemiati, Aldo,<space/><italics>In the First Person, An Outline of General Ethics</italics>, Rome, Urbaniana University Press, 2004.</listitem><listitem>John Paul II, Encyclical Letter<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_06081993_veritatis-splendor_en.html'>''Veritatis Splendor''</link>, August 6, 1993.</listitem><listitem>D'Urance, Michel,<space/><italics>Jalons pour une thique rebelle</italics>, Althia, Paris, 2005.</listitem><listitem>John Newton, Ph.D.<space/><italics>Complete Conduct Principles for the 21st Century</italics>, 2000. ISBN 0-9673705-7-4.</listitem><listitem>Guy Cools &amp; Pascal Gielen, The Ethics of Art. Valiz: Amsterdam, 2014.</listitem><listitem>Lafollette, Hugh [ed.]:<space/><italics>Ethics in Practice: An Anthology.</italics><space/>Wiley Blackwell, 4th edition, Oxford 2014. ISBN 978-0470671832</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template><template><target>Wikiversity</target></template><template><target>Wikisource portal</target></template><template><target>Library resources box</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>meta-ethics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>normative-ethics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>applied-ethics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>InPho</target><arg>taxonomy</arg><arg>2243</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>Ethics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.galilean-library.org/manuscript.php?postid=43789'>An Introduction to Ethics</link><space/>by Paul Newall, aimed at beginners.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ditext.com/frankena/ethics.html'>''Ethics</link>'', 2d ed., 1973. by<space/><link><target>William Frankena</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.open2.net/ethicsbites/index.html'>Ethics Bites</link>,<space/><link><target>Open University</target></link><space/>podcast series podcast exploring ethical dilemmas in everyday life.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bioethics.georgetown.edu/nrc/'>National Reference Center for Bioethics Literature</link><space/>World's largest library for ethical issues in medicine and biomedical research</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.utilitarian.net/singer/by/1985----.htm'>Ethics</link><space/>entry in Encyclopdia Britannica by<space/><link><target>Peter Singer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.philosophyarchive.com/index.php?title=Philosophy_of_Ethics'>The Philosophy of Ethics</link><space/>on Philosophy Archive</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.klice.co.uk/'>Kirby Laing Institute for Christian Ethics</link><space/>Resources, events, and research on a range of ethical subjects from a Christian perspective.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://icog.es/iageth/'>International Association for Geoethics (IAGETH)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.geoethics.org'>International Association for Promoting Geoethics (IAPG)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scu.edu/ethics/'>Markkula Center for Applied Ethics at Santa Clara University</link><space/>Resources for analyzing real-world ethical issues and tools to address them.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template><template><target>Ethics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Ethics</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Social philosophy</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of life</target></link></paragraph></article>