<article title='Ecumenical_council'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>ecumenical councils in general</arg><arg>the Roman Catholic councils</arg><arg>Catholic Ecumenical Councils</arg><arg>the Salvador Dalí painting</arg><arg>The Ecumenical Council (painting)</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Christianity</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><bold><link><target>ecumenical</target></link><space/>council</bold><space/>(or<space/><bold>oecumenical council</bold>; also<space/><bold>general council</bold>)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/140136/council#ref288192'>Encyclopaedia Britannica, &quot;Council&quot;</link></extension><space/>is a conference of ecclesiastical dignitaries and theological experts convened to discuss and settle matters of Church doctrine and practice in which those entitled to vote are convoked from the whole world (oikoumene) and which secures the approbation of the whole Church.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Catholic Encyclopedia<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04423f.htm</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The word &quot;ecumenical&quot; derives from the<space/><link><target>Greek language</target></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>(ἡ) οἰκουμένη (γῆ)</arg></template>, which literally means &quot;the inhabited world&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://americanheritage.yourdictionary.com/ecumenical'>American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language</link></extension><space/>but which was also applied more narrowly to mean the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>. Bishops belonging to what became known as the<space/><link><target>Church of the East</target></link><space/>participated in none of the councils later than the second, and further noteworthy<space/><link><target>schism (religion)</target><part>schisms</part></link><space/>led to non-participation by other members of what had previously been considered a single<space/><link><target>Christian Church</target></link>. Later ecumenical councils thus included bishops of only parts of the Church as previously constituted and were rejected or ignored by Christians not belonging to those parts.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>first seven Ecumenical Councils</target></link>, recognised by both the<space/><link><target>Eastern Christianity</target><part>eastern</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Western Christianity</target><part>western</part></link><space/>branches of<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target><part>Chalcedonian Christianity</part></link>, were convoked by Christian Roman Emperors, who also enforced the decisions of those councils within the<space/><link><target>state church of the Roman Empire</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Acceptance of councils as ecumenical and authoritative varies between different<space/><link><target>Christian denominations</target></link>. Disputes over<space/><link><target>christological</target></link><space/>and other questions have led certain branches to reject some councils that others accept.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Acceptance of councils by denomination</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Church of the East</target></link><space/>(accused by others of adhering to<space/><link><target>Nestorianism</target></link>) accepts as ecumenical only the first two councils.<space/><link><target>Oriental Orthodoxy</target><part>Oriental Orthodox Churches</part></link><space/>accept the first three.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.holypimoly.com/images/im_about_ortho/coptic_church.pdf'>Coptic Orthodox Christian Center, &quot;The Coptic Church&quot;</link></extension><space/>Both the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target></link><space/>recognise as ecumenical the first seven councils, held from the 4th to the 9th century. While the Eastern Orthodox Church accepts no later council or synod as ecumenical, the Roman Catholic Church continues to hold general councils of the bishops in<space/><link><target>full communion</target></link><space/>with the<space/><link><target>Pope</target></link>, reckoning them as ecumenical. In all, the Roman Catholic Church recognises twenty-one councils as ecumenical.<space/><link><target>Anglican</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and confessional<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target><part>Protestants</part></link><space/>accept either the first seven or the first four as ecumenical councils.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Infallibility of ecumenical councils</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Infallibility of the Church</arg></template>The doctrine of the<space/><italics>infallibility of ecumenical councils</italics><space/>states that solemn definitions of ecumenical councils, which concern faith or morals, and to which the whole Church must adhere, are infallible. Such decrees are often labeled as 'Canons' and they often have an attached<space/><link><target>anathema</target></link>, a penalty of<space/><link><target>excommunication</target></link>, against those who refuse to believe the teaching. The doctrine does not claim that every aspect of every ecumenical council is infallible.</paragraph><paragraph>Both the Eastern Orthodox and the Roman Catholic churches uphold versions of this doctrine. However, the Roman Catholic Church holds that solemn definitions of ecumenical councils meet the conditions of infallibility only when approved by the Pope,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>First Vatican Council</target><part>Vatican I</part></link>,<space/><italics>Dei Filius</italics><space/>ch. 3 1.<space/><link><target>Second Vatican Council</target><part>Vatican II</part></link>,<space/><italics>Lumen Gentium</italics><space/>25 2. 1983 Code of Canon Law 749 2.</extension><space/>while the Eastern Orthodox Church holds that an ecumenical council is itself infallible when pronouncing on a specific matter.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The infallibility of the Church does not mean that the Church, in the assembly of the Fathers or in the expression of the Conscience of the Church, has already formally expressed all the truths of faith and norms. The infallibility of the Church is confined to the formulation of truths in question. This infallibility is not wholly a God-inspired energy which would affect the participants of the synod to such an extent that they would be inspired to pronounce all the truths at one time as a whole system of a Christian catechism. The Synod does not formulate a system of beliefs encompassing all Christian teachings and truths, but only endeavors to define the particular disputed truth which was misunderstood and misinterpreted. The Church of Christ and its divine nature, as set forth above, is the foundation upon which the Eastern Orthodox Church [sic.] continues to administer and nourish its faithful, thereby protecting its fundamental essentials.&quot; Rev. George Mastrantonis, of the<space/><link><target>Archbishop of America</target><part>Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of America</part></link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Protestant churches would generally view ecumenical councils as fallible human institutions that have no more than a derived authority to the extent that they correctly expound Scripture (as most would generally consider occurred with the first four councils in regard to their dogmatic decisions).<extension extension_name='ref'>Hans Schneider, Councils of the Church, The Encyclopedia of Christianity (Grand Rapids, MI; Leiden, Netherlands: Wm. B. Eerdmans; Brill, 19992003), 701.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Council documents</heading><paragraph>Church councils were, from the beginning, bureaucratic exercises. Written documents were circulated, speeches made and responded to, votes taken, and final documents published and distributed. A large part of what is known about the beliefs of<space/><link><target>Christian heresy</target><part>heresies</part></link><space/>comes from the documents quoted in councils in order to be refuted, or indeed only from the deductions based on the refutations.</paragraph><paragraph>Most councils dealt not only with doctrinal but also with disciplinary matters, which were decided in<space/><italics><link><target>Canon law</target><part>canon</part><trail>s</trail></link></italics><space/>(&quot;laws&quot;). Study of the canons of church councils is the foundation of the development of<space/><link><target>canon law</target></link>, especially the reconciling of seemingly contradictory canons or the determination of priority between them. Canons consist of doctrinal statements and disciplinary measures most Church councils and local synods dealt with immediate disciplinary concerns as well as major difficulties of doctrine. Eastern Orthodoxy typically views the purely doctrinal canons as<space/><link><target>dogma</target><trail>tic</trail></link><space/>and applicable to the entire church at all times, while the disciplinary canons apply to a particular time and place and may or may not be applicable in other situations.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Circumstances of the first ecumenical councils</heading><paragraph>Of the seven councils recognised in whole or in part by both the Roman Catholic and the Eastern Orthodox Church as ecumenical, all were called by a<space/><link><target>Roman Emperor</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas J. Reese,<space/><italics>Inside the Vatican: The Politics and Organization of the Catholic Church</italics>, (Harvard University Press, 1996), 35.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="books.google.com"><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=oO2eY2BC6xIC&amp;amp;pg=PA742&amp;amp;dq=first+ecumenical+council+convened+by+Emperor&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=sF6PTt0py8C2B4Pw5YwM&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CC0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=first%20ecumenical%20council%20convened%20by%20Emperor&amp;amp;f=false'>Historical Theology: An Introduction to Christian Doctrine Gregg Allison, Wayne Grude</link>. mGoogle Books.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=QLWqXrW2X-8C&amp;amp;pg=PA14&amp;amp;dq=first+ecumenical+council+convened+by+Emperor&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=sF6PTt0py8C2B4Pw5YwM&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=3&amp;amp;ved=0CDcQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=first%20ecumenical%20council%20convened%20by%20Emperor&amp;amp;f=false'>The Ecumenical Patriarchate Demetrius Kimina</link>. sGoogle Books (27 March 2009).</extension><space/>The emperor gave them legal status within the entire<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>. All were held in the eastern part of the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>. The Pope did not attend, although he sent<space/><link><target>Papal legate</target><part>legates</part></link><space/>to some of them.</paragraph><paragraph>Church councils were traditional and the ecumenical councils were a continuation of earlier<space/><link><target>Ancient church councils (pre-ecumenical)</target><part>councils</part></link><space/>(also known as<space/><link><target>synod</target><trail>s</trail></link>) held in the Empire before Christianity was made legal. These include the<space/><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target></link><space/>(c. 50), the Council of Rome (155), the Second Council of Rome (193), the Council of Ephesus (193), the<space/><link><target>Councils of Carthage</target><part>Council of Carthage</part></link><space/>(251), the Council of Iconium (258),<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=o4ZtiKPqQikC&amp;amp;pg=PA348&amp;amp;lpg=PA348&amp;amp;dq=Council+of+Iconium+258+AD&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=HlIsqKwo-b&amp;amp;sig=kI4ji9xadUE8GLr_wfWqW0dPqgM&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=ewiNTuOIKsfhsQLM9oXVDg&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CBoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Council%20of%20Iconium%20258%20AD&amp;amp;f=false'>Edward Benson, ''Cyprian: His Life, His Times, His Work (Kessinger Publishing 2005 ISBN 978-1-41796979-1)</link>.</extension><space/>the<space/><link><target>Synods of Antioch</target><part>Council of Antioch</part></link><space/>(264), the<space/><link><target>Councils of Arabia</target></link><space/>(246247), the<space/><link><target>Council of Elvira</target></link><space/>(306), the<space/><link><target>Council of Carthage</target></link><space/>(311), the<space/><link><target>Synod of Neo-Caesarea</target></link><space/>(c. 314), the<space/><link><target>Council of Ancyra</target></link><space/>(314) and the<space/><link><target>Council of Arles</target></link><space/>(314).</paragraph><paragraph>The first seven councils recognised in both East and West as ecumenical and several others to which such recognition is refused were called by the Byzantine emperors. In the first millennium, various theological and political differences such as<space/><link><target>Nestorianism</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Dyophysitism</target></link><space/>caused parts of the Church to separate after councils such as those of<space/><link><target>First Council of Ephesus</target><part>Ephesus</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target><part>Chalcedon</part></link>, but councils recognised as ecumenical continued to be held.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Council of Hieria</target></link><space/>of 754, held at the imperial palace of that name close to Chalcedon in Anatolia, was summoned by Byzantine Emperor<space/><link><target>Constantine V</target></link><space/>and was attended by 338 bishops, who regarded it as the seventh ecumenical council<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=hbqG3XZrpEkC&amp;amp;pg=PA193&amp;amp;dq=Cunliffe+%22Constantine+summoned%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=KXDRUPTXC9CYhQemkYGABQ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Cunliffe%20%22Constantine%20summoned%22&amp;amp;f=false'>Hubert Cunliffe-Jones (editor), ''A History of Christian Doctrine'' (Continuum International 2006 ISBN 978-0-56704393-1), p. 193</link></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Second Council of Nicea</target></link>, which annulled that of Hieria, was itself annulled at a synod held in 815 in Constantinople under<space/><link><target>Emperor Leo V</target></link>. This synod, presided over by Patriarch<space/><link><target>Theodotos I of Constantinople</target></link>, declared the Council of Hieria to be the seventh ecumenical council,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=lL40wXlfa2UC&amp;amp;pg=PA56&amp;amp;dq=Cholij+%22proclaimed+the+seventh%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=83rRUM-cJIuGhQeIn4DYBQ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Cholij%20%22proclaimed%20the%20seventh%22&amp;amp;f=false'>Roman Cholij, ''Theodore the Stoudite'' (Oxford University Press 2002 ISBN 978-0-19924846-9), p. 56</link></extension><space/>but, although the Council of Hieria was called by an emperor and confirmed by another, and although it was held in the east, it later ceased to be considered ecumenical.</paragraph><paragraph>Similarly, the<space/><link><target>Second Council of Ephesus</target></link><space/>of 449, also held in Anatolia, was called by the Byzantine Emperor<space/><link><target>Theodosius II</target></link><space/>and, though annulled by the Council of Chalcedon, was confirmed by Emperor<space/><link><target>Basiliscus</target></link>, who annulled the Council of Chalcedon.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=jjBYQCpfCNkC&amp;amp;pg=PA440&amp;amp;dq=Chalcedon+Basiliscus&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=zrjRUN-OB8jWswa2_YG4Cw&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Chalcedon%20Basiliscus&amp;amp;f=false'>J.D. Fage, ''The Cambridge History of Africa'' (Cambridge University Press 1979 ISBN 978-0-52121592-3), vol. 2, p. 440</link></extension><space/>This too ceased to be considered an ecumenical council.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman Catholic views on those circumstances</heading><paragraph>The Roman Catholic Church does not consider the validity of an ecumenical council's teaching to be in any way dependent on where it is held or on the granting or withholding of prior authorization or legal status by any state, in line with the attitude of the 5th-century bishops who &quot;saw the definition of the church's faith and canons as supremely their affair, with or without the leave of the Emperor&quot; and who &quot;needed no one to remind them that Synodical process pre-dated the Christianisation of the royal court by several centuries&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.google.com/books?id=QxhR9ihUAWkC&amp;amp;pg=PA69&amp;amp;dq=McGuckin+%22synodical+process+pre-dated%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=CpWQTuXcN4O98gOBgJUy&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CC4Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>John Anthony McGuckin, '&amp;#39;Saint Cyril of Alexandria and the Christological Controversy'&amp;#39; (St Vladimir's Seminary Press 2004 ISBN 978-0-88141-259-8), p. 69</link>. Google.com.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Roman Catholic Church recognizes as ecumenical various councils held later than the<space/><link><target>First Council of Ephesus</target></link><space/>(after which churches out of communion with the Holy See because of the<space/><link><target>Nestorian Schism</target></link><space/>did not participate), later than the<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target></link><space/>(after which there was no participation by churches that rejected<space/><link><target>Dyophysitism</target></link>), later than the<space/><link><target>Second Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>(after which there was no participation by the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link>), and later than the<space/><link><target>Fifth Council of the Lateran</target></link><space/>(after which groups that adhered to Protestantism did not participate).</paragraph><paragraph>Of the twenty-one ecumenical councils recognised by the Roman Catholic Church, some gained recognition as ecumenical only later. Thus the Eastern<space/><link><target>First Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>became ecumenical only when its decrees were accepted in the West also.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04423f.htm'>Joseph Wilhelm, ''General Councils'' in ''Catholic Encyclopedia'' 1908;</link><space/>cf.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P17.HTM'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 247</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>List of ecumenical councils</heading><heading level='3'>First seven ecumenical councils</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>First seven Ecumenical Councils</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>history of Christianity</target></link>, the first seven Ecumenical Councils, from the<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>(325) to the<space/><link><target>Second Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>(787), represent an attempt to reach an<space/><link><target>orthodoxy</target><part>orthodox</part></link><space/>consensus and to unify<space/><link><target>Christendom</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>All of the original Seven Ecumenical Councils as recognised in whole or in part were called by an emperor of the Eastern Roman Empire and all were held in the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target><part>Eastern Roman Empire</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="books.google.com"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>a recognition denied to other councils similarly called by an Eastern Roman emperor and held in his territory, in particular the<space/><link><target>Second Council of Ephesus</target></link><space/>(449) and the<space/><link><target>Council of Hieria</target></link><space/>(754), which saw themselves as ecumenical.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>(325) repudiated<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link>, declared that Christ is &quot;<link><target>homoousios</target></link><space/>with the Father&quot; (of the same substance as the Father), and adopted the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed#The original Nicene Creed of 325</target><part>original Nicene Creed</part></link>; fixed<space/><link><target>Quartodecimanism</target><part>Easter date</part></link>; recognised authority of the<space/><link><target>Episcopal see</target><part>sees</part></link><space/>of Rome, Alexandria and Antioch outside their own<space/><link><target>Roman province</target><part>civil provinces</part></link><space/>and granted the see of Jerusalem a position of honour.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>First Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>(381) repudiated<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Macedonians (religious group)</target><part>Macedonianism</part></link>, declared that Christ is &quot;born of the Father before all time&quot;, revised the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target></link><space/>in regard to the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>First Council of Ephesus</target><part>Council of Ephesus</part></link><space/>(431) repudiated<space/><link><target>Nestorianism</target></link>, proclaimed the Virgin<space/><link><target>Mary (mother of Jesus)</target><part>Mary</part></link><space/>as the<space/><link><target>Theotokos</target></link><space/>(&quot;Birth-giver to God&quot;, &quot;God-bearer&quot;, &quot;Mother of God&quot;), repudiated<space/><link><target>Pelagianism</target></link>, and reaffirmed the Nicene Creed.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>This and all the following councils in this list are not recognised by all of the<space/><link><target>Church of the East</target></link>.</italics><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Second Council of Ephesus</target></link><space/>(449) declared<space/><link><target>Eutyches</target></link><space/>orthodox and attacked his opponents.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Though originally convened as an ecumenical council, this council is not recognised as ecumenical and is denounced as a<space/></italics>Robber Council<italics><space/>by the<space/><link><target>Chalcedonian</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(Catholics, Eastern Orthodox, Protestants).</italics></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target></link><space/>(451) repudiated the<space/><link><target>Eutyches</target><part>Eutychian</part></link><space/>doctrine of<space/><link><target>monophysitism</target></link>; adopted the<space/><link><target>Chalcedonian Creed</target></link>, which described the<space/><link><target>hypostatic union</target></link><space/>of the two natures of Christ, human and divine; reinstated those deposed in 449 and deposed<space/><link><target>Dioscorus of Alexandria</target></link>; and elevated the bishoprics of Constantinople and Jerusalem to the status of patriarchates. This is also the last council explicitly recognised by the<space/><link><target>Anglican Communion</target></link>.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>This and all the following councils in this list are rejected by<space/><link><target>Oriental Orthodoxy</target><part>Oriental Orthodox churches</part></link>.</italics></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Second Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>(553) repudiated the<space/><link><target>Three-Chapter Controversy</target><part>Three Chapters</part></link><space/>as Nestorian, condemned<space/><link><target>Origen of Alexandria</target></link>, and decreed the Theopaschite Formula.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Third Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>(680681) repudiated<space/><link><target>Monothelitism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Monoenergism</target></link>.<list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Quinisext Council</target></link>, also called Council in Trullo,<extension extension_name='ref'>The appellation &quot;troullos&quot; (Latin<space/><italics>trullus</italics>, dome) comes from a dome-roofed palace in Constantinople, where the council was hosted.</extension><space/>(692) addressed matters of discipline (in amendment to the 5th and 6th councils).<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Ecumenical status of this council was repudiated by the western churches.</italics></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Second Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>(787) restored the veneration of<space/><link><target>icon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(condemned at the<space/><link><target>Council of Hieria</target></link>, 754) and repudiated<space/><link><target>iconoclasm (Byzantine)</target><part>iconoclasm</part></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Further councils recognised as ecumenical in the Roman Catholic Church</heading><paragraph>As late as the 11th century, only seven councils were recognised as ecumenical in the Roman Catholic Church.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dvornik"><link type='external' href='http://www.orthodoxchristianity.net/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;catid=14:articles&amp;amp;id=22:which-councils-are-ecumenical'>Francis Dvornik, Which Councils are Ecumenical? Journal of Ecumenical Studies 3(2), 1966, pp. 314328</link>. Orthodoxchristianity.net (10 December 2006).</extension><space/>Then, in the time of<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory VII</target></link><space/>(10731085), canonists who in the<space/><link><target>Investiture Controversy</target></link><space/>quoted the prohibition in canon 22 of the Council of Constantinople of 869870 against laymen influencing the appointment of prelates elevated this council to the rank of ecumenical council.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dvornik"></extension><space/><template><target>unreliable source</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>Only in the 16th century was recognition as ecumenical granted by Catholic scholars to the Councils of the Lateran, of Lyon and those that followed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dvornik"></extension><space/>The following is a list of further councils generally recognised as ecumenical by Roman Catholic theologians:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=2rTz3HmuaEEC&amp;amp;pg=PA241&amp;amp;dq=Ecumenical+Councils+list+Catholic&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=JCeTVNHHNMmy7Qae6oD4Dg&amp;amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Ecumenical%20Councils%20list%20Catholic&amp;amp;f=false'>Norman Tanner, ''New Short History of the Catholic Church'' (A&amp;C Black 2011 ISBN 978-1-44116212-0), p. 242</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=gxEONS0FFlsC&amp;amp;pg=PA193&amp;amp;dq=Ecumenical+Councils+list+Catholic&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=DymTVKb8OqLe7AbAloGwDw&amp;amp;ved=0CEQQ6AEwBjgK#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Ecumenical%20Councils%20list%20Catholic&amp;amp;f=false'>Frank K. Flinn, ''Encyclopedia of Catholicism'' (Infobase Publising 2006 ISBN 978-0-81607565-2), PP. 193197</link></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>8.<space/><link><target>Fourth Council of Constantinople (Roman Catholic)</target></link></bold><space/>(869870) deposed<space/><link><target>Patriarch Photios I of Constantinople</target></link><space/>as a usurper and reinstated his predecessor<space/><link><target>Patriarch Ignatius of Constantinople</target><part>Saint Ignatius</part></link>. Photius had already been declared deposed by the Pope, an act to which the See of Constantinople acquiesced at this council.</listitem><listitem><bold>9.<space/><link><target>First Council of the Lateran</target></link></bold><space/>(1123) addressed<space/><link><target>Investiture Controversy</target><part>investment of bishops</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Emperor</target></link>'s role therein.</listitem><listitem><bold>10.<space/><link><target>Second Council of the Lateran</target></link></bold><space/>(1139) reaffirmed<space/><link><target>First Council of the Lateran</target><part>Lateran I</part></link><space/>and addressed clerical discipline (dress, marriages).</listitem><listitem><bold>11.<space/><link><target>Third Council of the Lateran</target></link></bold><space/>(1179) restricted papal election to the<space/><link><target>Cardinal (Catholicism)</target><part>cardinal</part><trail>s</trail></link>, condemned<space/><link><target>simony</target></link>, and introduced minimum ages for ordination (thirty for bishops).</listitem><listitem><bold>12.<space/><link><target>Fourth Council of the Lateran</target></link></bold><space/>(1215) defined<space/><link><target>transubstantiation</target></link>, addressed<space/><link><target>Primacy of the Roman Pontiff</target><part>papal primacy</part></link><space/>and clerical discipline.</listitem><listitem><bold>13.<space/><link><target>First Council of Lyon</target></link></bold><space/>(1245) proclaimed the deposition of<space/><link><target>Frederick II, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Emperor Frederick II</part></link><space/>and instituted a levy to support the Holy Land.</listitem><listitem><bold>14.<space/><link><target>Second Council of Lyon</target></link></bold><space/>(1274) attempted reunion with the Eastern churches, approved<space/><link><target>Franciscan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dominican Order</target><part>Dominican</part></link><space/><link><target>Mendicant orders</target><part>orders</part></link>, a tithe to support crusades, and<space/><link><target>Papal conclave</target><part>conclave</part></link><space/>procedures.</listitem><listitem><bold>15.<space/><link><target>Council of Vienne</target></link></bold><space/>(13111312) disbanded the<space/><link><target>Knights Templar</target></link>.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Council of Pisa</target></link></bold><space/>(1409) attempted to solve the<space/><link><target>Great Western Schism</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The council is not numbered because it was not convened by a pope and its outcome was repudiated at Constance.</italics></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>16.<space/><link><target>Council of Constance</target></link></bold><space/>(14141418) resolved the<space/><link><target>Great Western Schism</target></link><space/>and condemned<space/><link><target>Jan Hus</target><part>John Hus</part></link>. Also began<space/><link><target>conciliarism</target></link>.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Council of Siena</target></link></bold><space/>(14231424) addressed church reform.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Not numbered as it was swiftly disbanded.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>17.<space/><link><target>Council of Florence</target><part>Council of Basel, Ferrara and Florence</part></link></bold><space/>(14311445) addressed church reform and reunion with the Eastern Churches, but split into two parties. The fathers remaining at Basel became the apogee of<space/><link><target>conciliarism</target></link>. The fathers at Florence achieved union with<space/><link><target>Eastern Catholic Churches</target><part>various Eastern Churches</part></link><space/>and temporarily with the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><bold>18.<space/><link><target>Fifth Council of the Lateran</target></link></bold><space/>(15121517) addressed church reform.</listitem><listitem><bold>19.<space/><link><target>Council of Trent</target></link></bold><space/>(15451563, with interruptions) addressed church reform and repudiated Protestantism, defined the role and<space/><link><target>Biblical canon</target><part>canon</part></link><space/>of Scripture and the<space/><link><target>Sacraments of the Catholic Church</target><part>seven sacraments</part></link>, and strengthened clerical discipline and education. Considered the founding event of the<space/><link><target>Counter-Reformation</target></link>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Temporarily attended by Lutheran delegates.</italics></listitem><listitem><bold>20.<space/><link><target>First Vatican Council</target><part>First Council of the Vatican</part></link></bold><space/>(1870) defined<space/><link><target>primacy of the Roman Pontiff</target><part>pope's primacy in church governance</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>papal infallibility</target><part>his infallibility</part></link>, repudiated<space/><link><target>rationalism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>materialism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>atheism</target></link>, addressed<space/><link><target>revelation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>exegesis</target><part>interpretation of scripture</part></link><space/>and the relationship of<space/><link><target>faith</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>reason</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><bold>21.<space/><link><target>Second Vatican Council</target><part>Second Council of the Vatican</part></link></bold><space/>(19621965) addressed pastoral and disciplinary issues dealing with the Church and its relation to the modern world, including<space/><link><target>liturgy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ecumenism</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other councils that some Eastern Orthodox individuals see as ecumenical</heading><paragraph>Eastern Orthodox catechisms teach that there are seven ecumenical councils<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.goholycross.org/studies/councils.html'></link><space/>&quot;The Seven Ecumenical Councils of the Orthodox Catholic Church&quot;, Retrieved 2013-08-11</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://oca.org/orthodoxy/the-orthodox-faith/doctrine/sources-of-christian-doctrine/the-councils'></link><space/>&quot;Sources of Christian Doctrine &amp;ndash; The Councils&quot;, Retrieved 2013-08-11</extension><space/>and there are feast days for seven ecumenical councils.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pravoslavie.ru/english/47851.htm'></link><space/>&quot;Sunday of the Fathers of the First Six Councils&quot;, Retrieved 2013-08-11</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.anastasis.org.uk/octpate.htm'></link><space/>&quot;OFFICE OF THE HOLY FATHERS OF THE SEVENTH ECUMENICAL COUNCIL&quot;, Retrieved 2013-08-11</extension><space/>Nonetheless, some Eastern Orthodox consider the Council of Constantinople of 879880,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;In 879, two years after the death of Patriarch Ignatius, another council was summoned<space/><bold>(many consider it the Eighth Ecumenical Council)</bold>, and again St. Photius was acknowledged as the lawful archpastor of the Church of Constantinople&quot; (<link type='external' href='http://ocafs.oca.org/FeastSaintsViewer.asp?FSID=100442'>Orthodox Church in America)</link>.</extension><space/>that of Constantinople in 13411351 and that of Jerusalem in 1672 to be ecumenical:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Fourth Council of Constantinople (Eastern Orthodox)</target><part>Fourth Council of Constantinople</part></link></bold><space/>(879880) restored<space/><link><target>Patriarch Photios I of Constantinople</target><part>Photius</part></link><space/>to the See of Constantinople. This happened after the death of Ignatius and with papal approval.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Fifth Council of Constantinople</target></link></bold><space/>(13411351) affirmed<space/><link><target>Hesychasm</target><part>hesychastic theology</part></link><space/>according to<space/><link><target>Gregory Palamas</target></link><space/>and condemned<space/><link><target>Barlaam of Seminara</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Synod of Jassy</target></link></bold><space/>(1642) reviewed and amended the<space/><link><target>Peter Mogila</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Expositio fidei</italics><space/>(<italics>Statement of Faith</italics>, also known as the<space/><italics>Orthodox Confession</italics>).</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Synod of Jerusalem</target></link></bold><space/>(1672) defined Orthodoxy relative to Roman Catholicism and Protestantism, defined the<space/><link><target>Development of the Christian Biblical canon</target><part>orthodox Biblical canon</part></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>It is unlikely that formal recognition as ecumenical will be granted to these councils, despite the acknowledged orthodoxy of their decisions, so that only seven are universally recognized among the Eastern Orthodox as ecumenical.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.orthodoxanswers.org/details.asp?ID=551'>Documents</link>. Orthodox Answers (5 May 2010).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Pan-Orthodox Council now being prepared has sometimes been referred to as a potential &quot;Eighth Ecumenical Council&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.orthodoxinfo.com/ecumenism/towards.aspx'>Towards the &quot;Eighth&quot; Ecumenical Council</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Acceptance of the councils</heading><paragraph>Although some Protestants reject the concept of an ecumenical council establishing doctrine for the entire Christian faith, Roman Catholics, Anglicans, Eastern Orthodox and Oriental Orthodox all accept the authority of ecumenical councils in principle. Where they differ is in which councils they accept and what the conditions are for a council to be considered &quot;ecumenical&quot;. The relationship of the<space/><link><target>Pope</target><part>Papacy</part></link><space/>to the validity of ecumenical councils is a ground of controversy between Roman Catholicism and the Eastern Orthodox Churches. The Roman Catholic Church holds that recognition by the Pope is an essential element in qualifying a council as ecumenical;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2A.HTM'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 884</link>. Vatican.va (20 February 1946).</extension><space/>Eastern Orthodox view approval by the Bishop of Rome (the Pope) as being roughly equivalent to that of other patriarchs.Some have held that a council is ecumenical only when all five patriarchs of the<space/><link><target>Pentarchy</target></link><space/>are represented at it.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?ei=-nZzTtizFY2a-waNy_TQDA&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;id=CBQ9AAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;q=%22all+five+patriarchs%22#search_anchorFrancis'>Dvornik, '&amp;#39;The Ecumenical Councils'&amp;#39; (Hawthorn Books 1961), p. 80</link>. Books.google.com.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=7TQvAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;q=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=oXhzTpqGFI2XOpLwxKQM&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CCkQ6AEwADge'>Francis Aloysius Sullivan, '&amp;#39;Magisterium'&amp;#39; (Paulist Press 2010 ISBN 978-0-8091-2577-7) p. 86</link>. Books.google.com.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=3NtcXcy07X0C&amp;amp;pg=PA23&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=63ZzTo_vD8qXOu6RpcQM&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=10&amp;amp;ved=0CFQQ6AEwCTgK#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=falseE'>M. Conradie, R. H. Gouws, D. J. Prinsloo (editors), '&amp;#39;Christian Identity'&amp;#39; (University of the Western Cape 2005 ISBN 1-919980-88-1), p. 23</link>. Books.google.com.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=fMhzlnY0P0QC&amp;amp;pg=PA325&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=kXVzTqPJJoSA-wa67snaDA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22all%20five%20patriarchs%22%20ecumenical%20council&amp;amp;f=falseLeo'>Donald Davis, '&amp;#39;The First Seven Ecumenical Councils (325787)'&amp;#39; (Michael Glazier 1992 ISBN 978-0-8146-5616-7), p. 325</link>. Books.google.com.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=WtnR-6_PlJAC&amp;amp;pg=PA388&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=kXVzTqPJJoSA-wa67snaDA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=10&amp;amp;ved=0CFUQ6AEwCQ#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22all%20five%20patriarchs%22%20ecumenical%20council&amp;amp;f=falseKarl'>Rahner, '&amp;#39;Encyclopedia of Theology'&amp;#39; (Burns &amp; Oates 1999 ISBN 978-0-86012-006-3), p. 388</link>. Books.google.com.</extension><space/>Others reject this theory in part because there were no patriarchs of Constantinople and Jerusalem at the time of the first ecumenical council.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=0sjx26MOBm8C&amp;amp;pg=PA104&amp;amp;dq=%22all+five+patriarchs%22+ecumenical+council+%22one+holy%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=LbN0TqTcB46j-gai5LTUDA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CCwQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=falseKenneth'>D. Whitehead, '&amp;#39;One, Holy, Catholic, and Apostolic'&amp;#39; (Ignatius Press 2000 ISBN 978-0-89870-802-8), p. 104</link>. Books.google.com.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Church of the East</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Church of the East</target></link><space/>accepts two ecumenical councils, the First Council of Nicaea and the First Council of Constantinople. It was the formulation of Mary as the<space/><link><target>Theotokos</target></link><space/>which caused a schism with the Church of the East, now divided between the<space/><link><target>Assyrian Church of the East</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Ancient Church of the East</target></link>, while the<space/><link><target>Chaldean Catholic Church</target></link><space/>entered into<space/><link><target>full communion</target></link><space/>with Rome in the 16th century. Meetings between<space/><link><target>Pope John Paul II</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>List of Patriarchs of the Church of the East</target><part>Assyrian Patriarch</part></link><space/><link><target>Mar Dinkha IV</target></link><space/>led to a common Christological declaration on 11 November 1994 that &quot;the humanity to which the Blessed Virgin Mary gave birth always was that of the Son of God himself&quot;. Both sides recognised the legitimacy and rightness, as expressions of the same faith, of the Assyrian Church's liturgical invocation of Mary as &quot;the Mother of Christ our God and Saviour&quot; and the Catholic Church's use of &quot;the Mother of God&quot; and also as &quot;the Mother of Christ&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/roman_curia/pontifical_councils/chrstuni/documents/rc_pc_chrstuni_doc_11111994_assyrian-church_en.html'>Common Christological Declaration between the Catholic Church and the Assyrian Church of the East</link>. Vatican.va (11 November 1994).</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Oriental Orthodoxy</heading><paragraph><link><target>Oriental Orthodoxy</target></link><space/>accepts three ecumenical councils, the First Council of Nicaea, the First Council of Constantinople, and the Council of Ephesus. The formulation of the<space/><link><target>Chalcedonian Creed</target></link><space/>caused a schism in the Alexandrian and Syriac churches. Reconciliatory efforts between Oriental Orthodox with the Eastern Orthodox and the Catholic Church in the mid- and late-20th century have led to common<space/><link><target>Christology</target><part>Christological</part></link><space/>declarations. The Oriental and Eastern Churches have also been working toward reconciliation as a consequence of the<space/><link><target>Ecumenism</target><part>ecumenical movement</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Oriental Orthodox hold that the<space/><link><target>Dyophysite</target></link><space/>formula of two natures formulated at the<space/><link><target>Council of Chalcedon</target></link><space/>is inferior to the<space/><link><target>Miaphysite</target></link><space/>formula of &quot;One Incarnate Nature of God the Word&quot; (<link><target>Byzantine Greek</target></link>: Mia physis tou theou logou sarkousomene) and that the proceedings of Chalcedon themselves were motivated by<space/><link><target>imperialism</target><part>imperial politics</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Coptic Orthodox Church of Alexandria</target><part>The Alexandrian Church</part></link>, the main Oriental Orthodox body, also felt unfairly underrepresented at the council following the deposition of their Pope,<space/><link><target>Dioscorus of Alexandria</target></link><space/>at the council.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Eastern Orthodox Church</heading><paragraph>The Eastern Orthodox Church accepts<space/><link><target>First seven Ecumenical Councils</target><part>seven ecumenical councils</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://oca.org/OCchapter.asp?SID=2&amp;amp;ID=5/'>The Councils</link><space/>at Orthodox Church in America</extension><space/>with the<space/><link><target>Quinisext Council</target><part>Council in Trullo</part></link><space/>considered a continuation of the sixth.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.orthodoxchristian.info/pages/main.htm/'>The Ecumenical Councils of the Orthodox Church</link><space/>at OrthodoxChristianInfo</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Runciman, S., (1977), The Byzantine Theocracy, (Cambridge University Press), p61.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To be considered ecumenical, Orthodox accept a council that meets the condition that it was accepted by the whole church. That it was called together legally is also important a factor. A case in point is the<space/><link><target>Third Ecumenical Council</target></link><space/>where two groups met as duly called for by the emperor, each claiming to be the legitimate council. The Emperor had called for bishops to assemble in the city of Ephesus. Theodosius did not attend<extension extension_name='ref'>Runciman, S., (1977),<space/><italics>The Byzantine Theocracy</italics>, (Cambridge University Press), p37.</extension><space/>but sent his representative Candidian to preside.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wills2003"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Garry Wills</arg><arg name="title">Why I Am a Catholic</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 October 2011</arg><arg name="date">10 September 2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-618-38048-0</arg><arg name="pages">82–</arg></template></extension><space/>However, Cyril managed to open the council over Candidian's insistent demands that the bishops disperse until the delegation from Syria could arrive. Cyril was able to completely control the proceedings, completely neutralizing Candidian who favored Cyril's antagonist, Nestorius. When the pro-Nestorius Antiochene delegation finally arrived, they decided to convene their own council over which Candidian presided.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bury, J. B., (1958),<space/><italics>History of the later Roman Empire : from the death of Theodosius I to the death of Justinian (A.D. 395 to A.D. 565) (Volume 1)<space/></italics>,(Dover Publications; NY), p353</extension><space/>The proceedings of both councils were reported to the emperor who decided ultimately to depose Cyril, Memnon and Nestorius.<extension extension_name='ref'>McKinion, S. A., (2000),<space/><italics>Words, Imagery, and the Mystery of Christ: A Reconstruction of Cyril of Alexandria's Christology (Supplements to Vigiliae Christianae, V. 55)</italics>, (Brill Academic Pub) p13.</extension><space/>Nonetheless, the Orthodox accept Cyril's group as being the legitimate council because it maintained the same teaching that the church has always taught.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Paraphrasing a rule by St<space/><link><target>Vincent of Lrins</target></link><space/>Hasler states<template><target>quote</target><arg>...a teaching can only be defined if it has been held to be revealed at all times, everywhere, and by all believers.<ref>Hasler, A. B., (1981) ''How the Pope Became Infallible: Pius IX and the Politics of Persuasion'' (Doubleday; Garden City, NY), p153.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Orthodox believe that councils could over-rule or even depose popes. At the<space/><link><target>Sixth Ecumenical Council</target></link><space/><link><target>Pope Honorius I</target><part>Pope Honorius</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Patriarch Sergius I of Constantinople</target><part>Patriarch Sergius</part></link><space/>were declared heretics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sixth Ecumenical Council Session XIII. The Sentence Against the Monothelites.(L. and C., Concilia, Tom. VI., col. 943.)</extension><space/>The council anathematized them<extension extension_name='ref'>Session XVI. (Labbe and Cossart, Concilia, Tom. VI., col. 1010.)</extension><space/>and declared them tools of the devil<extension extension_name='ref'>The Definition of Faith. (Found in the Acts, Session XVIII., L. and C., Concilia, Tom. VI., col. 1019.)</extension><space/>and cast them out of the church<extension extension_name='ref'>The Prosphoneticus to the Emperor. (Labbe and Cossart, Concilia, Tom. VI., col. 1047 et seqq.)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is their position that since the Seventh Ecumenical Council, there has been no synod or council of the same scope. Local meetings of hierarchs have been called &quot;pan-Orthodox&quot;, but these have invariably been simply meetings of local hierarchs of whatever Eastern Orthodox jurisdictions are party to a specific local matter. From this point of view, there has been no fully &quot;pan-Orthodox&quot; (<bold>Ecumenical</bold>) council since 787. Unfortunately, the use of the term &quot;pan-Orthodox&quot; is confusing to those not within Eastern Orthodoxy, and it leads to mistaken impressions that these are<space/><italics><link><target>ersatz</target></link></italics><space/>ecumenical councils rather than purely local councils to which nearby Orthodox hierarchs, regardless of jurisdiction, are invited.</paragraph><paragraph>Others, including 20th century theologians Metropolitan<space/><link><target>Hierotheos (Vlachos)</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Naupactus</target></link>, Fr.<space/><link><target>John S. Romanides</target></link>, and Fr.<space/><link><target>George Metallinos</target></link><space/>(all of whom refer repeatedly to the &quot;Eighth and Ninth Ecumenical Councils&quot;), Fr.<space/><link><target>George Dragas</target></link>, and the 1848<space/><link><target>Encyclical of the Eastern Patriarchs</target></link><space/>(which refers explicitly to the &quot;Eighth Ecumenical Council&quot; and was signed by the<space/><link><target>patriarch</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Antioch</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link><space/>as well as the<space/><link><target>Holy Synod</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the first three), regard other synods beyond the<space/><link><target>Second Council of Nicaea</target><part>Seventh Ecumenical Council</part></link><space/>as being ecumenical.<template><target>Citation needed span</target><arg name="text">Before the 20th century, the Council at Constantinople in 879 AD was recognised as the 8th ecumenical council by people like the famous expert on Canon Law, [[Theodore Balsamon]] (11th century), St. Neilos of Rhodes, St. [[Mark of Ephesus]] (15th century), St. [[Symeon of Thessalonica]] (15th century), and the [[Patriarch Dositheos II of Jerusalem]] in his Tome of Joy (17th century).</arg><arg name="date">April 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From the Eastern Orthodox perspective, a council is accepted as being ecumenical if it is accepted by the Eastern Orthodox church at large clergy, monks and assembly of believers. Teachings from councils that purport to be ecumenical, but which lack this acceptance by the church at large, are, therefore, not considered ecumenical.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hasler<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. B.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="title">How the Pope Became Infallible: Pius IX and the Politics of Persuasion<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Doubleday<space/></arg><arg name="location">Garden City, NY<space/></arg><arg name="page">153</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="quote">An ecclesiological theory which has been popular since the time of the Slavophile philosopher [[Aleksey Khomyakov|Alexis Khomiakov]] first defined it is that ecumenicity—the idea that a particular council is of universal, infallible significance for the Church—is determined by the reception of the whole body of the Church.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://orthodoxwiki.org/Ecumenical_council#Ecumenicity/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ecumenicity at Orthodox Wiki</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="quote">So the new teachings, that are outside the ecumenical councils cannot be accepted because they have not been verified (by) the whole body of the Church.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://stjohndfw.info/sunday-of-the-holy-fathers-from-the-4th-ecumenical-council-the-right-worship.html/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sunday of the Holy Fathers from the 4th Ecumenical Council – The Right Worship]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Furthermore Orthodox understand councils were called for in reaction to crises within the church over matters of dogma. For Orthodox no further council would therefore be needed until such time as a major crises arose within the church.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Roman Catholic Church</heading><paragraph>Both the Roman Catholic and Eastern Orthodox churches recognize seven councils in the early centuries of the church, but Roman Catholics also recognize fourteen councils in later times called or confirmed by the Pope.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.google.com/search?tbm=bks&amp;amp;tbo=1&amp;amp;q=Reese+%22ecumenical+councils+in+the+west%22&amp;amp;btnG='>Thomas J. Reese, '&amp;#39;Inside the Vatican'&amp;#39; (Harvard University Press 1988 ISBN 978-0-674-93261-6), p. 35</link>. Google.com.</extension><space/>At the urging of German King<space/><link><target>Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Sigismund</part></link>, who was to become Holy Roman Emperor in 1433, the<space/><link><target>Council of Constance</target></link><space/>was convoked in 1414 by<space/><link><target>Antipope John XXIII</target></link>, one of three claimants to the papal throne, and was reconvened in 1415 by the Roman<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory XII</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=zAsjkHJ8aP8C&amp;amp;pg=PA401&amp;amp;dq=Deely+reconvened&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=G_fSUI6jB42QhQfYm4CIBQ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Deely%20reconvened&amp;amp;f=false'>John Deely, ''Four Ages of Understanding'' (University of Toronto Press 2001 ISBN 978-1-44261301-0), p. 401</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=k85JKr1OXcQC&amp;amp;pg=PA274&amp;amp;dq=Esp%C3%ADn+%22Pisan+line%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=DPrSULmTNcaHhQernoH4BQ&amp;amp;redir_esc=y#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Esp%C3%ADn%20%22Pisan%20line%22&amp;amp;f=false'>Orlando O. Espn, James B. Nickoloff (editors), ''An Introductory Dictionary of Theology and Religious Studies'' (Liturgical Press 2007 ISBN 978-0-81465856-7), p. 274</link></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Council of Florence</target></link><space/>is an example of a council accepted as ecumenical in spite of being rejected by the East, as the Councils of Ephesus and Chalcedon are accepted in spite of being rejected respectively by the<space/><link><target>Church of the East</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oriental Orthodoxy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Roman Catholic Church teaches that an ecumenical council is a gathering of the<space/><link><target>College of Bishops</target></link><space/>(of which the<space/><link><target>Pope</target><part>Bishop of Rome</part></link><space/>is an essential part) to exercise in a solemn manner its supreme and full power over the whole Church.<extension extension_name='ref'>The<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/__P2A.HTM'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 883884</link><space/>states: &quot;The college or body of bishops has no authority unless united with the Roman Pontiff, Peter's successor, as its head. As such, this college has supreme and full authority over the universal Church; but this power cannot be exercised without the agreement of the Roman Pontiff. The college of bishops exercises power over the universal Church in a solemn manner in an ecumenical council.&quot;</extension><space/>It holds that &quot;there never is an ecumenical council which is not confirmed or at least recognized as such by Peter's successor&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 884</extension><space/>Its present<space/><link><target>canon law (Catholic Church)</target><part>canon law</part></link><space/>requires that an ecumenical council be convoked and presided over, either personally or through a delegate, by the Pope, who is also to decide the agenda;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG1104/__P17.HTM'>Code of Canon Law, canon 338</link>. Vatican.va.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/apost_constitutions/documents/hf_jp-ii_apc_19901018_codex-can-eccl-orient-1_lt.htmlCode'>of Canons of the Eastern Churches, canon 51</link></extension><space/>but the church makes no claim that all past ecumenical councils observed these present rules, declaring only that the Pope's confirmation or at least recognition has always been required, and saying that the version of the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target></link><space/>adopted at the<space/><link><target>First Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>(381) was accepted by the Church of Rome only seventy years later, in 451.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/ENG0015/_P17.HTM#XT'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 247</link>. Vatican.va.</extension><space/>One writer has even claimed that this council was summoned without the knowledge of the pope.<extension extension_name='ref'>Whelton, M., (1998)<space/><italics>Two Paths: Papal Monarchy f Collegial Tradition</italics><space/>(Regina Orthodox Press; Salisbury, MA), p51.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Anglican Communion</heading><paragraph>While the Councils are part of the &quot;historic formularies&quot; of<space/><link><target>Anglicanism</target><part>Anglican</part></link><space/>tradition,<extension extension_name='ref'>For additional references to this section and for more on the Anglican position, see Dr CB Moss<space/><link type='external' href='http://anglicanhistory.org/cbmoss/seventh.pdf'>''The Church of England and the Seventh Council''</link></extension><space/>it is difficult to locate an explicit reference in Anglicanism to the unconditional acceptance of all Seven Ecumenical Councils. There is little evidence of dogmatic or canonical acceptance beyond the statements of individual Anglican theologians and bishops.</paragraph><paragraph>Bishop Chandler Holder Jones,<space/><link><target>Society of the Holy Cross</target><part>SSC</part></link>, explains:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="We indeed and absolutely believe all Seven Councils are truly ecumenical and catholic – on the basis of the received Tradition of the ancient Undivided Church of East and West. The Anglican formularies address only particular critical theological and disciplinary concerns of the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, and that certainly by design. Behind them, however, stands the universal authority of the Holy and Apostolic Tradition, which did not have to be rehashed or redebated by Anglican Catholics.<ref name">CHJ>[http://philorthodox.blogspot.com/2008/10/seven-ecumenical-councils-in.html The Seven Ecumenical Councils in Anglicanism]. Philorthodox.blogspot.com (2008-10-27). Retrieved on 2012-05-15.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He quotes William Tighe, Associate Professor of History at Muhlenberg College in Allentown, Pennsylvania (another member of the Anglo-Catholic wing of Anglicanism):<template><target>quote</target><arg name="...despite the fact that advocates of all sides to the 16th-century religious conflict, Catholic, Lutheran and Reformed alike, were given to claiming that their particular doctrinal stances and, in some cases, distinctive practices, were in accord with those of the Early Church Fathers, or at least with those of high standing (such as St. Augustine), none [but Anglicanism] were willing to require, or even permit, their confessional stances to be judged by, or subordinated to, a hypothetical 'patristic consensus' of the first four or five centuries of Christianity.' But Anglicanism most certainly did, and does so to this day.<ref name">CHJ/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thirty-Nine Articles</target><part>Article XXI</part></link><space/>teaches: &quot;General Councils ... when they be gathered together, forasmuch as they be an assembly of men, whereof all be not governed with the Spirit and word of God, they may err and sometime have erred, even in things pertaining to God. Wherefore things ordained by them as necessary to salvation have neither strength nor authority, unless it may be declared that they be taken out of Holy Scripture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>An Exposition Of The Thirty-Nine Articles V2: Historical And Doctrinal</italics><space/>by Edward Harold Browne.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 19th Canon of 1571 asserted the authority of the Councils in this manner: &quot;Let preachers take care that they never teach anything...except what is agreeable to the doctrine of the Old and New Testament, and what the Catholic Fathers and ancient Bishops have collected from the same doctrine.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Sufficiency of Holy Scripture as the Rule of Faith</italics><space/>By<space/><link><target>Daniel Wilson (bishop)</target><part>Daniel Wilson</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Anglican Diocese of Calcutta</target><part>Anglican Bishop of Calcutta</part></link>.</extension><space/>This remains the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link>'s teaching on the subject. A modern version of this appeal to catholic consensus is found in the Canon Law of the Church of England and also in the liturgy published in<space/><italics><link><target>Common Worship</target></link></italics>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The Church of England is part of the One, Holy, Catholic, and Apostolic Church, worshipping the one true God, Father, Son, and Holy Spirit. It professes the faith uniquely revealed in the Holy Scriptures and set forth in the catholic creeds, which faith the Church is called upon to proclaim afresh in each generation. Led by the Holy Spirit, it has borne witness to Christian truth in its historic formularies, the Thirty-nine Articles of Religion, ''The Book of Common Prayer'' and the Ordering of Bishops, Priests and Deacons.

I, AB, do so affirm, and accordingly declare my belief in the faith which is revealed in the Holy Scriptures and set forth in the catholic creeds and to which the historic formularies of the Church of England bear witness; and in public prayer and administration of the sacraments, I will use only the forms of service which are authorized or allowed by Canon.<ref>See ''Common Worship'' ISBN 0-7151-2000-X</ref></arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Lutheran and Methodist churches</heading><paragraph>Many Protestants (especially those belonging to the<space/><link><target>Magisterial Reformation</target><part>magisterial traditions</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target><part>Lutherans</part></link>, or those such as<space/><link><target>Methodism</target><part>Methodists</part></link>, that broke away from the Anglican Communion) accept the teachings of the first seven councils but do not ascribe to the councils themselves the same authority as Roman Catholics and the Eastern Orthodox do. The<space/><link><target>Lutheran World Federation</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>ecumenism</target><part>ecumenical</part></link><space/>dialogues with the<space/><link><target>Ecumenical Patriarch of Constantinople</target></link><space/>has affirmed all of the first seven councils as ecumenical and authoritative.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Other Protestant churches</heading><paragraph>Some, including some<space/><link><target>Christian Fundamentalism</target><part>fundamentalist Christians</part></link>, condemn the ecumenical councils for other reasons. Independency or<space/><link><target>congregationalist polity</target></link><space/>among Protestants may involve the rejection of any governmental structure or binding authority above local congregations; conformity to the decisions of these councils is therefore considered purely voluntary and the councils are to be considered binding only insofar as those doctrines are derived from the Scriptures. Many of these churches reject the idea that anyone other than the authors of Scripture can directly lead other Christians by original divine authority; after the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>, they assert, the doors of revelation were closed and councils can only give advice or guidance, but have no authority. They consider new doctrines not derived from the sealed<space/><link><target>Biblical canon</target><part>canon</part></link><space/>of Scripture to be both impossible and unnecessary whether proposed by church councils or by more recent<space/><link><target>prophet</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(even though the canon itself was fixed by these councils).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nontrinitarian churches</heading><paragraph>Ecumenical councils are not recognised by<space/><link><target>Nontrinitarianism</target><part>nontrinitarian</part></link><space/>churches such as<space/><link><target>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</target></link><space/>(and other<space/><link><target>List of sects in the Latter Day Saint movement</target><part>denominations</part></link><space/>within the<space/><link><target>Latter Day Saint movement</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Jehovah's Witnesses</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarians</part></link>. They view the ecumenical councils as misguided human attempts to establish doctrine, and as attempts to define dogmas by debate rather than by revelation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Buddhist councils</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Fairweather, Eugene R., and Edward R. Hardy.<space/><italics>The Voice of the Church: the Ecumenical Council</italics>. Greenwich, Conn.: Seabury Press, 1962. 127 p.<space/><italics>N.B</italics>.: Defines and approaches the topic from an Anglican orientation.<space/></listitem><listitem>Michalopoulos, Dimitris, &quot;The First Council of Nicaea: The end of a conflict or beginning of a struggle?&quot;,<space/><italics>Uluslarasi Iznik Semposyumu</italics>, Iznik (Turkey), 2005, pp.&amp;nbsp;4756. ISBN 975-7988-30-8.</listitem><listitem>Tanner, Norman P.<space/><italics>The Councils of the Church</italics>, ISBN 0-8245-1904-3.</listitem><listitem>Tanner, Norman P.<space/><italics>Decrees of the Ecumenical Councils</italics>, ISBN 0-87840-490-2.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Broken link:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.piar.hu/councils/~index.htm'>All Catholic Church Ecumenical Councils All the Decrees</link>*<space/><link type='external' href='http://90.1911encyclopedia.org/C/CO/COUNCIL.htm'>Council</link><space/>in the 1911<space/><link><target>Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/library/almanac_14388a.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia: The 21 Ecumenical Councils</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04423f.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia: General Councils</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/01_10_Concilia_Oecumenica.html'>Multilingual Full Documentations of the 21 Ecumenical Councils</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/01_50_1692-1769-_Mansi_JD.html'>Mansi JD, Sacrorum Conciliorum Nova Amplissima Collectio</link>, all the Latin documents of all the Councils</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.greekorthodox.org.au/general/faq/faqhistoryofchristianity/'>FAQ Ecumenical Synods</link><space/>Greek Orthodox Archdiocese of Australia</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://sites.google.com/site/canonsoc/'>The Canons of the Eastern Orthodox Church</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Ecumenical councils</target></template><template><target>Catholicism</target></template><template><target>Christian History</target><arg>collapsed</arg></template><template><target>Christianity footer</target><arg>collapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ecumenical Council</target></template><link><target>Category:Oriental Orthodoxy</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian church councils</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Eastern Orthodoxy</target></link><link><target>Category:Ecumenical councils</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Types of Christian organization</target></link></paragraph></article>