<article title='Diaspora'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Emigrants Leave Ireland by Henry Doyle 1868.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Emigrants Leave Ireland'' depicting the emigration to America following the<space/><link><target>Great Famine (Ireland)</target><part>Great Famine</part></link><space/>in Ireland.</part></link>A<space/><bold>diaspora</bold><space/>(from<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>, &quot;scattering, dispersion&quot;)<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"><template><target>LSJ</target><arg>diaspora/</arg><arg>διασπορά</arg><arg>ref</arg></template></extension><space/>is a scattered population whose origin lies within a smaller geographic locale. Diaspora can also refer to the movement of the population from its original homeland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="webster"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/diaspora<space/></arg><arg name="title">Diaspora<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-02-22<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Merriam Webster]]<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ember"></extension><space/>Diaspora has come to refer particularly to historical mass dispersions of an involuntary nature, such as the<space/><link><target>Jewish diaspora</target><part>expulsion of Jews from Judea</part></link>, the fleeing of<space/><link><target>Greeks</target></link><space/>after the fall of<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>, the African Trans-<link><target>Atlantic slave trade</target></link>, the southern Chinese or Hindus of<space/><link><target>South Asia</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>coolie</target><part>coolie trade</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Palestinian diaspora</target><part>deportation of Palestinians in the 20th century</part></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="ember"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Rozen</arg><arg name="first">Mina</arg><arg name="title">Homelands and Diasporas: Greeks, Jews and Their Migrations (International Library of Migration Studies)</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">I. B. Tauris</arg><arg name="location">London, England</arg><arg name="isbn">1845116429</arg></template></extension><space/>and the exile and deportation of Circassians.</paragraph><paragraph>Recently, scholars have distinguished between different kinds of diaspora, based on its causes such as<space/><link><target>imperialism</target></link>, trade or labor migrations, or by the kind of social coherence within the diaspora community and its ties to the ancestral lands. Some diaspora communities maintain strong political ties with their homeland. Other qualities that may be typical of many diasporas are thoughts of return, relationships with other communities in the diaspora, and lack of full integration into the host country.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ember"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor">[[Melvin Ember]], [[Carol R. Ember]] and [[Ian Skoggard]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of Diasporas: Immigrant and Refugee Cultures Around the World. Volume I: Overviews and Topics; Volume II: Diaspora Communities<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-306-48321-9<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins and development of the term</heading><paragraph>The term is derived from the Greek verb (<italics>diaspeir</italics>), &quot;I scatter&quot;, &quot;I spread about&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"></extension><space/>and that from (<italics>dia</italics>), &quot;between, through, across&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"></extension><space/>+ the verb (<italics>speir</italics>), &quot;I sow, I scatter&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"></extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target></link><space/>the term (<italics>diaspora</italics>) hence meant &quot;scattering&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"></extension><space/>and was inter alia used to refer to citizens of a dominant<space/><link><target>city-state</target></link><space/>who emigrated to a conquered land with the purpose of<space/><link><target>colonization</target></link>, to assimilate the territory into the empire.<extension extension_name='ref'>pp.1-2, Tetlow</extension><space/>An example of a diaspora from classical antiquity is the century-long exile of the<space/><link><target>Messenia (ancient region)</target><part>Messenians</part></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Sparta</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>rule.</paragraph><paragraph>Its use began to develop from this original sense when the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>was translated into Greek;<extension extension_name='ref'>p.81, Kantor</extension><space/>the first mention of a diaspora created as a result of exile is found in the<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="liddell"></extension><space/>first in</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link><space/>28:25, in the phrase<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg><space/>ἔσῃ ἐν διασπορᾷ ἐν πάσαις ταῖς βασιλείαις τῆς γῆς</arg></template>,<space/><italics>es en diaspora en pasais tais basileiais ts gs</italics>, translated to mean &quot;thou shalt be a dispersion in all kingdoms of the earth&quot;<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>and secondly in<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Psalms</target></link><space/>146(147).2, in the phrase<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>οἰκοδομῶν Ἰερουσαλὴμ ὁ Kύριος καὶ τὰς διασπορὰς τοῦ Ἰσραὴλ ἐπισυνάξει</arg></template>,<space/><italics>oikodomn Ierousalm ho Kyrios kai tas diasporas tou Isral episynax</italics>, translated to mean &quot;The Lord doth build up Jerusalem: he gathereth together the outcasts of Israel&quot;.<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>So after the Bible's translation into Greek, the word<space/><italics>Diaspora</italics><space/>would then have been used to refer to the Northern Kingdom exiled between 740-722 BC from Israel by the Assyrians,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Assyrian captivity of Israel</target></link></extension><space/>as well as Jews, Benjaminites, and Levites exiled from the Southern Kingdom in 587 BCE by the<space/><link><target>Babylonian exile</target><part>Babylonians</part></link>, and from<space/><link><target>Roman Judea</target></link><space/>in 70 CE by the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>pp.53, 105-106, Kantor</extension><space/>It subsequently came to be used to refer to the historical movements of the dispersed ethnic population of Israel, to the cultural development of that population or to that population itself.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.1, Barclay</extension><space/>In English when capitalized and without modifiers (that is simply,<space/><italics>the Diaspora</italics>), the term refers specifically to the<space/><link><target>Jewish diaspora</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="webster"></extension><space/>when uncapitalized the word<space/><italics>diaspora</italics><space/>may be used to refer to<space/><link><target>refugee</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Immigration</target><part>immigrant</part></link><space/>populations of other origins or ethnicities living &quot;away from an established or ancestral homeland&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="webster"></extension><space/>The wider application of<space/><italics>diaspora</italics><space/>evolved from the Assyrian two-way mass deportation policy of conquered populations to deny future territorial claims on their part.<extension extension_name='ref'>pp.96-97, Galil &amp; Weinfeld</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the<space/><italics><link><target>Oxford English Dictionary Online</target></link></italics>, the first known recorded usage of the word<space/><italics>diaspora</italics><space/>in the<space/><link><target>English language</target></link><space/>was in 1876 referring &quot;extensive<space/><italics>diaspora</italics><space/>work (as it is termed) of evangelizing among the National Protestant Churches on the continent&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.oed.com/viewdictionaryentry/Entry/52085</arg><arg name="title">diaspora, n.</arg><arg name="work">[[Oxford English Dictionary Online]]</arg><arg name="date">November 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 February 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The term became more widely assimilated into<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>English</part></link><space/>by the mid 1950s, with long-term<space/><link><target>expatriates</target></link><space/>in significant numbers from other particular countries or regions also being referred to as a diaspora.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2011</arg></template><space/>An academic field,<space/><link><target>diaspora studies</target></link>, has become established relating to this sense of the word.</paragraph><paragraph>In all cases, the term<space/><italics>diaspora</italics><space/>carries a sense of<space/><link><target>Forced migration</target><part>displacement</part></link><space/>the population so described finds itself for whatever reason separated from its national territory, and usually its people have a hope, or at least a desire, to return to their homeland at some point, if the &quot;homeland&quot; still exists in any meaningful sense. Some writers<template><target>Who</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template><space/>have noted that diaspora may result in a loss of nostalgia for a single home as people &quot;re-root&quot; in a series of meaningful displacements. In this sense, individuals may have multiple homes throughout their diaspora, with different reasons for maintaining some form of attachment to each. Diasporic cultural development often assumes a different course from that of the population in the original place of settlement. Over time, remotely separated communities tend to vary in culture, traditions, language and other factors. The last vestiges of cultural affiliation in a diaspora is often found in community resistance to<space/><link><target>language change</target></link><space/>and in maintenance of traditional religious practice.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Expanding definition</heading><paragraph>In an article published in 1991,<space/><link><target>William Safran</target></link><space/>set out six rules to distinguish diasporas from migrant communities. These included criteria that the group maintains a myth or collective memory of their homeland; they regard their ancestral homeland as their true home, to which they will eventually return; being committed to the restoration or maintenance of that homeland; and they relate &quot;personally or vicariously&quot; to the homeland to a point where it shapes their identity.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">5</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weinar</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">75</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Cohen</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template><space/>While Safran's definitions were influenced by the idea of the Jewish diaspora, he recognised the expanding use of the term.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Cohen</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Rogers Brubaker</target></link><space/>(2005) also notes that use of the term diaspora has been widening. He suggests that one element of this expansion in use &quot;involves the application of the term diaspora to an ever-broadening set of cases: essentially to any and every nameable population category that is to some extent dispersed in space&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">3</arg></template><space/>Brubaker has used the<space/><link><target>WorldCat</target></link><space/>database to show that 17 out of the 18 books on diaspora published between 1900 and 1910 were on the Jewish diaspora. The majority of works in the 1960s were also about the Jewish diaspora, but in 2002 only two out of 20 books sampled (out of a total of 253) were about the Jewish case, with a total of eight different diasporas covered.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">14</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Brubaker outlines the original use of the term diaspora as follows:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Most early discussions of diaspora were firmly rooted in a conceptual 'homeland'; they were concerned with a paradigmatic case, or a small number of core cases. The paradigmatic case was, of course, the Jewish diaspora; some dictionary definitions of diaspora, until recently, did not simply illustrate but defined the word with reference to that case.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Brubaker argues that the initial expansion of the use of the phrase extended it to other, similar cases, such as the<space/><link><target>Armenian diaspora</target><part>Armenian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Greek diaspora</target><trail>s</trail></link>. More recently, it has been applied to emigrant groups that continue their involvement in their homeland from overseas, such as the category of long-distance nationalists identified by<space/><link><target>Benedict Anderson</target></link>. Brubaker notes that (as examples): Albanians, Basques, Hindu Indians, Irish, Japanese, Kashmiri, Koreans, Kurds, Palestinians, and Tamils have been conceptualised as diasporas in this sense. Furthermore, &quot;labour migrants who maintain (to some degree) emotional and social ties with a homeland&quot; have also been described as diasporas.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In further cases of the use of the term, &quot;the reference to the conceptual homeland to the 'classical' diasporas has become more attenuated still, to the point of being lost altogether&quot;. Here, Brubaker cites &quot;transethnic and transborder linguistic categories...such as<space/><link><target>French language</target><part>Francophone</part></link>,<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>Anglophone</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lusophone</target></link><space/>'communities'&quot;, along with Hindu, Sikh, Buddhist, Confucian, Huguenot, Muslim and Catholic 'diasporas'.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="pp">2–3</arg></template><space/>Brubaker notes that,<space/><template><target>as of</target><arg>2005</arg><arg name="lc">on</arg></template>, there were also academic books or articles on the<space/><link><target>Dixie</target></link>, white, liberal, gay, queer and digital diasporas.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Brubaker</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">14</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some observers have labeled evacuation from<space/><link><target>New Orleans</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Gulf Coast</target></link><space/>in the wake of<space/><link><target>Hurricane Katrina</target></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>New Orleans diaspora</target></link>, since a significant number of evacuees have not been able to return, yet maintain aspirations to do so.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.dailyfinance.com/story/katrina-evacuees-economic-impact-new-homes-destinations/19614294/</arg><arg name="title">The Economic Impact of the 'Katrina Diaspora'</arg><arg name="first">Bruce</arg><arg name="last">Kennedy</arg><arg name="work">Daily Finance</arg><arg name="date">31 August 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 February 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/americas/4203360.stm</arg><arg name="title">Katrina scatters a grim diaspora</arg><arg name="first">Will</arg><arg name="last">Walden</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">1 September 2005</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 February 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Agnieszka Weinar (2010) notes the widening use of the term, arguing that recently, &quot;a growing body of literature succeeded in reformulating the definition, framing diaspora as almost any<space/><italics>population</italics><space/>on the move and no longer referring to the specific<space/><italics>context</italics><space/>of their existence&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Weinar</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">75</arg></template><space/>It has even been noted that as charismatic Christianity becomes increasingly globalized, many Christians conceive of themselves as a diaspora, and form an imaginary that mimics salient features of ethnic diasporas.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">McAlister</arg><arg name="first">Elizabeth</arg><arg name="title">Listening for Geographies</arg><arg name="url">http://works.bepress.com/elizabeth_mcalister/28/</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 November 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Professional communities of individuals no longer in their homeland can also be considered diaspora. For example, science diasporas are communities of scientists who conduct their research away from their homeland.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Burns</arg><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="title">The Potential of Science Diasporas</arg><arg name="journal">Science & Diplomacy</arg><arg name="date">December 9, 2013</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sciencediplomacy.org/perspective/2013/potential-science-diasporas</arg></template></extension><space/>In an article published in 1996, Khachig Tllyan<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Tölölyan</arg><arg name="first">Khachig</arg><arg name="title">Rethinking Diaspora(s): Stateless Power in the Transnational Moment</arg><arg name="journal">Diaspora: A Journal of Transnational Studies<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 1996</arg><arg name="volume">3</arg><arg name="issue">36</arg><arg name="url">https://muse.jhu.edu/journals/diaspora_a_journal_of_transnational_studies/summary/v005/5.1.tololyan.html</arg></template></extension><space/>argues that the media have used the term corporate diaspora in a rather arbitrary and inaccurate fashion, for example as applied to mid-level, mid-career executives who have been forced to find new places at a time of corporate upheaval (10) The use of<space/><link><target>corporate diaspora</target></link><space/>reflects the increasing popularity of the diaspora notion to describe a wide range of phenomena related to contemporary migration, displacement and transnational mobility. While corporate diaspora seems to avoid or contradict connotations of violence, coercion and unnatural uprooting historically associated to the notion of diaspora, its scholarly use may heuristically describe the ways in which corporations function alongside diasporas. In this way, corporate diaspora might foreground the racial histories of diasporic formations without losing sight of the cultural logic of<space/><link><target>late capitalism</target></link><space/>in which corporations orchestrate the transnational circulation of people, images, ideologies and capital.</paragraph><heading level='2'>European diasporas</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>European diaspora</arg></template><link><target>File:Greek Colonization Archaic Period.png</target><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Greek Homeland and Diaspora 6th century BCE</part></link>European history contains numerous diaspora-like events. In ancient times, the trading and colonising activities of the<space/><link><target>ancient Greeks</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>tribes from the<space/><link><target>Balkans</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target><part>Asia Minor</part></link><space/>spread people of Greek culture, religion and language around the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Black Sea</target></link><space/>basins, establishing Greek<space/><link><target>city states</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Magna Graecia</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Sicily</target></link>,<space/><link><target>southern Italy</target></link>), northern<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link>, eastern<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>south of France</target></link>, and the Black Sea coasts. Greeks founded more than 400 colonies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://highered.mcgraw-hill.com/sites/0072424354/student_view0/chapter10/table_of_contents.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Early development of Greek society<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Highered.mcgraw-hill.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-05</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link>'s conquest of the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target></link><space/>marked the beginning of the<space/><link><target>Hellenistic period</target></link>, which was characterized by a new wave of Greek colonization in<space/><link><target>Asia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>, with Greek ruling classes established in<space/><link><target>Ptolemaic dynasty</target><part>Egypt</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Seleucid Empire</target><part>southwest Asia</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Indo-Greek Kingdom</target><part>northwest India</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mars.wnec.edu/~grempel/courses/wc1/lectures/10hellenism.html'>Hellenistic Civilization</link></extension><space/>Subsequent waves of colonization and migration during the Middle Ages added to the older settlements, or created new ones, thus replenishng the<space/><link><target>Greek diaspora</target></link><space/>and making it one of the most long-standing and widespread in the world.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Migration Period</target></link><space/>relocations, which included several phases, are just one set of many in history. The first phase Migration Period displacement from between CE 300 and 500 included relocation of the<space/><link><target>Goths</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Ostrogoths</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Visigoths</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Vandals</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link>, various other<space/><link><target>Germanic people</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Burgundians</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lombards</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Angles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Suebi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Alemanni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Varangian</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Normans</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Alans</target></link><space/>and numerous<space/><link><target>Slavic peoples</target><part>Slavic tribes</part></link>. The second phase, between CE 500 and 900, saw<space/><link><target>Slavic peoples</target><part>Slavic</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Turkic people</target><part>Turkic</part></link>, and other tribes on the move, resettling in<space/><link><target>Eastern Europe</target></link><space/>and gradually making it predominantly Slavic, and affecting<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Caucasus</target></link><space/>as the first Turkic tribes (<link><target>Avars (Carpathians)</target><part>Avars</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Huns</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Khazars</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pechenegs</target></link>), as well as<space/><link><target>Bulgars</target></link>, and possibly<space/><link><target>Magyars</target></link><space/>arrived. The last phase of the<space/><link><target>Migration Period</target><part>migrations</part></link><space/>saw the coming of the Hungarian Magyars and the<space/><link><target>Vikings</target><part>Viking</part></link><space/>expansion out of<space/><link><target>Scandinavia</target></link><space/>into Europe and the<space/><link><target>British Isles</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>Greenland</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Iceland</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Such colonizing migrations cannot be considered indefinitely as diasporas; over very long periods, eventually the migrants assimilate into the settled area so completely that it becomes their new homeland. Thus the modern population of Hungary do not feel that they belong in the Western<space/><link><target>Siberia</target></link><space/>that the Hungarian Magyars left 12 centuries ago; and the<space/><link><target>England</target><part>English</part></link><space/>descendants of the<space/><link><target>Angles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link><space/>do not yearn to reoccupy the plains of Northwest Germany.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1492, a Spanish expedition headed by<space/><link><target>Christopher Columbus</target></link><space/>arrived in the<space/><link><target>Americas</target></link>, after which European exploration and colonization rapidly expanded. Historian<space/><link><target>James Axtell</target></link><space/>estimates that 240,000 people left Europe for the Americas in the 16th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/data/art/AXTELL01.ART<space/></arg><arg name="first">James<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Axtell<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Columbian Mosaic in Colonial America<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Humanities<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20091119071952/http://www.millersville.edu/~columbus/data/art/AXTELL01.ART<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">November 19, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="date">September–October 1991<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5</arg><arg name="volume">12</arg><arg name="pages">12–18<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">4636419</arg></template></extension><space/>Immigration continued. In the 19th century alone over 50 million Europeans migrated to North and South America.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Eltis<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kingston David<space/></arg><arg name="title">Economic Growth and the Ending of the Transatlantic Slave Trade<space/></arg><arg name="year">1987<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="page">139</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-536481-1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A specific 19th-century example is the<space/><link><target>Irish diaspora</target></link>, beginning in the mid-19th century and brought about by<space/><italics>An Gorta Mr</italics><space/>or &quot;The Great Hunger&quot; of the<space/><link><target>Great Famine (Ireland)</target><part>Irish Famine</part></link>. Estimates are that between 45% and 85% of Ireland's population emigrated, to countries including Britain, the United States, Canada, Argentina, Australia and<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link>. The size of the diaspora is demonstrated by the number of people around the world who claim Irish ancestry; some sources put the figure at 80-100 million.</paragraph><heading level='2'>African diaspora</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>African diaspora</arg></template>One of the largest diaspora of modern times is the<space/><link><target>African Diaspora</target></link>, which dates back several centuries. During the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Slave Trade</target></link>, 9.4 to 12 million people from North, West, West-Central and South-east Africa survived transportation to arrive in the<space/><link><target>Western Hemisphere</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>slavery</target><part>slaves</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/blackhistory/article-24156<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Welcome to Encyclopædia Britannica's Guide to Black History", '&#39;Encyclopædia Britannica'&#39;<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Britannica.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-05</arg></template></extension><space/>This population and their descendants were major influences on the culture of English, French, Italian, Portuguese and Spanish<space/><link><target>New World</target></link><space/>colonies. Prior to the trans-Atlantic slave trade, millions of Africans had moved and settled as merchants, seamen and slaves in different parts of Asia and Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Black Europe and the African Diaspora</italics>, Alexander Weheliye writes a section and clearly explains diaspora this way: &quot;Diaspora offers pathways that retrace laverings of difference in the aftermath of colonialism and slavery, as well as the effects of other forms of migration and displacement. Thus, diaspora enables the desedimentation of the nation from the interior by taking into account the groups that fail to comply with the reigning definition of the people as a cohesive political subject due to sharing one culture, one race, one language, one religion, and so on, and from the 'exterior' by drawing attention to the movements that cannot be contained by the nations administrative and ideological borders&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Black Europe and the African Diaspora</arg><arg name="last">Weheliye</arg><arg name="first">Alexander</arg><arg name="page">162</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="isbn">9780252076572</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Asian diaspora</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Jewish Children with their Teacher in Samarkand.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bukharan Jews</target></link><space/>in Samarkand, Central Asia, c. 1910</part></link><link><target>Chinese emigration</target></link><space/>(also known as the<space/><link><target>Overseas Chinese</target><part>Chinese Diaspora</part></link>)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Chinese diaspora: space, place, mobility, and identity<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ma<space/></arg><arg name="first">Laurence J. C.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Cartier<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Carolyn L.<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7425-1756-1<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>first occurred thousands of years ago. The mass emigration that occurred from the 19th century to 1949 was caused mainly by wars and starvation in<space/><link><target>mainland China</target></link>, as well as political corruption. Most immigrants were illiterate or poorly educated peasants and<space/><link><target>coolies</target></link><space/>(Chinese: , literally &quot;hard labor&quot;), who immigrated to developing countries in need of labor, such as the<space/><link><target>Americas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Malay Peninsula</target><part>Malaya</part></link><space/>and other places.</paragraph><paragraph>The largest Asian diaspora outside of Southeast Asia is the<space/><link><target>Non-resident Indian and person of Indian origin</target><part>Indian diaspora</part></link>. The overseas Indian community, estimated at over 25 million, is spread across many regions in the world, on every continent. It constitutes a diverse, heterogeneous and eclectic global community representing different regions, languages, cultures, and faiths (see<space/><italics><link><target>Desi</target></link></italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Romani people</target><part>Romani</part></link><space/>are<space/><link><target>Romani diaspora</target><part>widely dispersed</part></link>, with their largest concentrated populations in Europe. Linguistic and genetic evidence indicates the Romanies originated on the<space/><link><target>Indian subcontinent</target></link>, emigrating from India towards the northwest no earlier than the 11th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Genetic studies of the Roma (Gypsies): A review<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2350/2/5<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-16<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1186/1471-2350-2-5<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kalaydjieva<space/></arg><arg name="first">Luba<space/></arg><arg name="journal">BMC Medical Genetics<space/></arg><arg name="volume">2<space/></arg><arg name="page">5<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">11299048<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Gresham<space/></arg><arg name="first2">D<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Calafell<space/></arg><arg name="first3">F<space/></arg><arg name="pmc">31389<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At least three waves of<space/><link><target>People of Nepal</target><part>Nepalese diaspora</part></link><space/>can be identified. The earliest wave dates back to hundreds of years as early marriage and high birthrates propelled Hindu settlement eastward across Nepal, then into<space/><link><target>Sikkim</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bhutan</target></link>. A backlash developed in the 1980s as Bhutan's political elites realized that Bhutanese Buddhists were at risk of becoming a minority in their own country. At least 60,000 ethnic<space/><link><target>People of Nepal</target><part>Nepalese</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Bhutan</target></link><space/>have been resettled in the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/south_asia/7082586.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bhutan refugees are 'intimidated'<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Bhaumik, Subir<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>November 7, 2007<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2008-04-25</arg></template></extension><space/>A second wave was driven by British recruitment of mercenary soldiers beginning around 1815 and resettlement after retirement in the British Isles and southeast Asia. The third wave began in the 1970s as land shortages intensified and the pool of educated labor greatly exceeded job openings in Nepal. Job-related emigration created Nepalese enclaves in India, the wealthier countries of the Middle East, Europe and North America. Current estimates of the number of Nepalese living outside Nepal range well up into the millions.</paragraph><paragraph>In Siam, regional power struggles among several kingdoms in the region led to a large diaspora of ethnic Lao between the 1700s-1800s by Siamese rulers to settle large areas of the Siamese kingdom's northeast region, where Lao ethnicity is still a major factor in 2012. During this period, Siam decimated the Lao capital, capturing, torturing and killing the Lao king Anuwongse.</paragraph><paragraph>From the 1860s,<space/><link><target>Circassians</target></link><space/>were dispersed through the Levant, Europe, North America, Australia, and within historical<space/><link><target>Circassia</target></link><space/>in the North Caucasus currently in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>.<space/><template><target>Further</target><arg>Circassian diaspora</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Internal diasporas</heading><paragraph>In the US, approximately 4.3 million people moved outside their home states in 2010, according to IRS tax exemption data.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Bruner</arg><arg name="first">Jon</arg><arg name="title">Migration in America</arg><arg name="url">http://www.forbes.com/sites/jonbruner/2011/11/16/migration-in-america/</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Forbes</arg><arg name="date">16 November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>In a 2011 TEDx presentation, Detroit native Garlin Gilchrist referenced the formation of distinct &quot;Detroit diaspora&quot; communities in Seattle and Washington, D.C.,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Gilchrist</arg><arg name="first">Garlin</arg><arg name="title">From Detroit. To Detroit</arg><arg name="url">http://tedxtalks.ted.com/video/TEDxLansing-Garlin-Gilchrist-De</arg><arg name="work">TEDxLansing</arg><arg name="publisher">TED</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="date">6 August 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>while layoffs in the auto industry also led to substantial blue-collar migration from Michigan to Wyoming in the mid 2000s.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Silke Carty</arg><arg name="first">Sharon</arg><arg name="title">Wyoming wins over Michigan job seekers</arg><arg name="url">http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/money/economy/employment/2006-12-04-wyoming-job-seekers-michigan_x.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">USA Today</arg><arg name="date">5 December 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>In response to a statewide exodus of talent, the State of Michigan continues to host &quot;MichAGAIN&quot; career recruiting events in places throughout the US with significant Michigan diaspora populations.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Walsh</arg><arg name="first">Tom</arg><arg name="title">MichAgain program aims to return talented people, investments to Michigan</arg><arg name="url">http://www.freep.com/article/20110410/COL06/104100443/Tom-Walsh-MichAgain-program-aims-return-talented-people-investments-Michigan</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Detroit Free Press</arg><arg name="date">10 April 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Mainland China, millions of migrant workers have sought greater opportunity in the country's booming coastal metropolises, though this trend has slowed with the further development of China's interior.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Kenneth</arg><arg name="first">Rapoza</arg><arg name="title">Chinese Migrant Workers Enticed To Stay Home</arg><arg name="url">http://www.forbes.com/sites/kenrapoza/2013/02/19/china-migrant-workers-enticed-to-stay-home/</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Forbes</arg><arg name="date">19 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Migrant social structures in these Chinese mega-cities are often based on place of origin, such as a shared hometown or province, and it is common for recruiters and foremen to select entire work crews from the same village.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">China's migrant workers</arg><arg name="journal">Wildcat</arg><arg name="volume">Winter 2007/08</arg><arg name="issue">80</arg><arg name="url">http://libcom.org/history/chinas-migrant-workers</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>In two separate June 2011 incidents, Sichuanese migrant workers organized violent protests against alleged police misconduct and migrant labor abuse near the southern manufacturing hub of Guangzhou.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Demick</arg><arg name="first">Barbara</arg><arg name="title">China tries to restore order after migrant riots</arg><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/2011/jun/13/world/la-fg-china-riot-20110614</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 October 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Los Angeles Times</arg><arg name="date">13 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>20th century</heading><paragraph>The 20th century saw huge population movements. Some involved large-scale transfers of people by government action. Some migrations occurred to avoid conflict and warfare. Other diasporas were created as a consequence of political decisions, such as the end of<space/><link><target>colonialism</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>World War II and the end of colonial rule</heading><paragraph>As<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>unfolded, Nazi Germany deported and killed millions of Jews and many millions of others were likewise enslaved or murdered, including Ukrainians, Russians and other Slavs. Some Jews fled from persecution to unoccupied parts of western Europe and the Americas before borders closed. Later, other eastern European refugees moved west, away from Soviet annexation,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.kirmus.ee/baltic_archives_abroad_2006/participants.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">An International Conference on the Baltic Archives Abroad<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Kirmus.ee<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-05</arg></template></extension><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Iron Curtain</target></link><space/>regimes after World War II. Hundreds of thousands of these anti-Soviet political refugees and Displaced Persons ended up in western Europe, Australia, Canada and the United States of America.</paragraph><paragraph>After World War II, the Soviet Union and Communist-controlled<space/><link><target>Poland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hungary</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Yugoslavia</target></link><space/>expelled millions of<space/><link><target>ethnic Germans</target></link>, most of whom were descendants of immigrants who had settled in those areas nearly two centuries before. This was allegedly in retaliation for the German Nazi invasion and their pan-German attempts at annexation. Most of the refugees moved to the West, including western Europe, and with tens of thousands seeking refuge in the United States.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Spain</target></link><space/>sent many political activists into exile during<space/><link><target>Francisco Franco</target><part>Franco</part></link>'s military regime from 1936 to his death in 1975.</paragraph><paragraph>Following World War II, the creation of the state of<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, and a series of uprisings against colonialist rule, the<space/><link><target>Middle East</target></link><space/>nations became more hostile in relation to their historic Jewish populations, sepharadim and mizrahiml, of nearly 1 million people. Most of them emigrated, with the majority resettling in Israel.</paragraph><paragraph>At the same time, the<space/><link><target>Palestinian diaspora</target></link><space/>resulted from Israel's creation in 1948, in which 750,000 people were expelled or fled from their homes. The diaspora was enlarged by the effects of the<space/><link><target>1967 Arab-Israeli War</target></link>. Many Palestinians continue to live in refugee camps maintained by Middle Eastern nations, but others have resettled in the Middle East and other countries.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Partition of India</target><part>1947 Partition</part></link><space/>resulted in the migration of millions of people between<space/><link><target>India</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link>. Millions were murdered in the religious violence of the period, with estimates of fatalities up to 2 million people. Thousands of former subjects of the<space/><link><target>British Raj</target></link><space/>went to the<space/><link><target>UK</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Indian subcontinent</target></link><space/>after India and Pakistan became independent in 1947.</paragraph><paragraph>From the late 19th century, and formally from 1910, Japan made Korea a colony. Millions of Chinese fled to western provinces not occupied by Japan (that is, in particular Ssuchuan/Szechwan and Yunnan in the Southwest and Shensi and Kansu in the Northwest) and to Southeast Asia. More than 100,000 Koreans moved across the Amur River into Eastern Russia (then the Soviet Union) away from the Japanese.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Cold War and the formation of post-colonial states</heading><paragraph>During and after the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>-era, huge populations of refugees migrated from conflict, especially from then-<link><target>developing countries</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Upheaval in the Middle East and Central Asia, some of which was related to power struggles between the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>, created new refugee populations which developed into global diasporas.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia</target></link>, many<space/><link><target>Vietnamese people</target></link><space/>emigrated to<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>and later millions to the United States, Australia and Canada after the Cold War-related<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link>. Later, 30,000<space/><link><target>French people</target><part>French</part></link><space/><italics>colons</italics><space/>from<space/><link><target>Cambodia</target></link><space/>were displaced after being expelled by the<space/><link><target>Khmer Rouge</target></link><space/>regime under<space/><link><target>Pol Pot</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2008</arg></template><space/>A small, predominantly Muslim ethnic group, the<space/><link><target>Cham (Asia)</target><part>Cham people</part></link><space/>long residing in Cambodia, were nearly eradicated.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2009</arg></template><space/>The mass exodus of Vietnamese people from Vietnam coined the term '<link><target>Boat people</target></link>'.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Southwest China</target></link>, many<space/><link><target>Tibetan people</target></link><space/>emigrated to India, following the<space/><link><target>14th Dalai Lama</target></link><space/>in 1959 after the failure of his<space/><link><target>1959 Tibetan uprising</target><part>Tibetan uprising</part></link>. This wave lasted until the 1960s, and another wave followed when Tibet was opened up to trade and tourism in the 1980s. It is estimated that about 200,000 Tibetans live now dispersed worldwide, half of whom in are<space/><link><target>India</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nepal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bhutan</target></link>. In lieu of lost citizenship papers, the<space/><link><target>Central Tibetan Administration</target></link><space/>offers<space/><link><target>Green Book (Tibetan document)</target><part>Green Book</part></link><space/>identity documents to Tibetan refugees.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Sri Lankan Tamils</target></link><space/>have historically migrated to find work, notably during the British colonial period. Since the beginning of the civil war in 1983, more than 800,000 Tamils have been displaced within<space/><link><target>Sri Lanka</target></link><space/>as local diaspora, and over a half million<space/><link><target>Tamils</target></link><space/>living as the<space/><link><target>Tamil diaspora</target></link><space/>in destinations such as India, Australia, New Zealand, Canada, the UK and Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target><part>Afghan</part></link><space/>diaspora resulted from the 1979 invasion by the former Soviet Union; both official and unofficial records<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2008</arg></template><space/>indicate that the war displaced over 6 million people, resulting in the creation of the largest refugee population worldwide today.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">Nov 2009</arg><arg name="date">November 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many<space/><link><target>Iranian people</target><part>Iranians</part></link><space/>fled the 1979<space/><link><target>Iranian Revolution</target></link><space/>which culminated in the fall of the<space/><link><target>1953 Iranian coup d'tat</target><part>USA/British-ensconced</part></link><space/><link><target>Mohammad Reza Pahlavi</target><part>Shah</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Assyrian people</target><part>Assyrian</part></link><space/>diaspora expanded by the Civil War in<space/><link><target>Lebanon</target></link>, the coming into power of the Islamic republic of<space/><link><target>Iran</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Ba'ath</target><trail>ist</trail></link><space/>dictatorship in<space/><link><target>Iraq</target></link>, and the present-day unrest in Iraq pushed Assyrians on the roads of exile.<extension extension_name='ref'>Codeswitching Worldwide II,<template><target>Vague</target><arg name="date">August 2008</arg></template><space/>by Rodolfo Jacobson</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>, a new series of diasporas formed following the end of colonial rule. In some cases as countries became independent, numerous minority descendants of Europeans emigrated; others stayed in the lands which had been family homes for generations.<space/><link><target>Uganda</target></link><space/>expelled<space/><link><target>Expulsion of Asians from Uganda</target><part>80,000 South Asians in 1972</part></link><space/>and took over their businesses and properties. The 1990s Civil war in<space/><link><target>Rwanda</target></link><space/>between rival ethnic groups<space/><link><target>Hutu</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Tutsi</target></link><space/>turned deadly and produced a mass efflux of refugees.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Latin America</target></link>, following the 1959<space/><link><target>Cuban Revolution</target></link><space/>and the introduction of<space/><link><target>communism</target></link>, over a million people have left<space/><link><target>Cuba</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">1959: The Cuban Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="work">Upfront: The Newsmagazine for Teens<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Scholastic<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://teacher.scholastic.com/scholasticnews/indepth/upfront/features/index.asp?article</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There was a<space/><link><target>Jamaican diaspora</target></link><space/>around the start of the 21st century. More than 1 million<space/><link><target>People of the Dominican Republic</target><part>Dominicans</part></link><space/>live abroad a majority living in the US.<template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Nearly 20 Percent of All Dominicans Live Abroad<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Dominican Today</arg><arg name="url">http://www.dominicantoday.com/dr/economy/2011/6/14/39878/Nearly-20-of-all-Dominicans-live-abroad<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>{{inconsistent citations}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A million<space/><link><target>Colombia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>refugees have left Colombia since 1965 to escape the country's violence and civil wars. In<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>, thousands of<space/><link><target>Argentina</target><trail>n</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Chile</target><trail>an</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Uruguay</target><trail>an</trail></link><space/>refugees fled to Europe during periods of<space/><link><target>military junta</target><part>military rule</part></link><space/>in the 1970s and 1980s. In<space/><link><target>Central America</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nicaraguan Diaspora</target><part>Nicaraguans</part></link>,<space/><link><target>El Salvador</target><part>Salvadorans</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target><trail>ns</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Honduras</target><part>Hondurans</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Costa Rica</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>(however, the country had no dictators) and<space/><link><target>Panama</target><trail>nians</trail></link><space/>fled conflict and poor economic conditions.</paragraph><paragraph>Hundreds of thousands of people fled from the<space/><link><target>Rwandan Genocide</target></link><space/>in 1994 into neighboring countries. Thousands of refugees from deteriorating conditions in<space/><link><target>Zimbabwe</target></link><space/>have gone to<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>. The long war in<space/><link><target>Democratic Republic of the Congo</target><part>Congo</part></link>, in which numerous nations have been involved, has also created millions of refugees.</paragraph><heading level='2'>21st century</heading><paragraph><template><target>expand section</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template>Following the<space/><link><target>Iraq War</target></link>, nearly 3&amp;nbsp;million Iraqis had been displaced as of 2011, with 1.3&amp;nbsp;million within the Iraq and 1.6 million in neighboring countries, mainly Jordan and Syria.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Will Iraq's 1.3 million refugees ever be able to go home?<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[The Independent]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.independent.co.uk/news/world/middle-east/will-iraqs-13-million-refugees-ever-be-able-to-go-home-6277667.html<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kim<space/></arg><arg name="last">Sengupta</arg></template></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Syrian Civil War</target></link><space/>has forced further migration, with at least 4 million displaced as per UN estimates.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>UNHCR Syria Regional Refugee Response</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://data.unhcr.org/syrianrefugees/regional.php</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-09-15</arg><arg name="first"><space/>United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees</arg><arg name="last"><space/>(UNHCR)</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Following the presidency of<space/><link><target>Hugo Chvez</target></link><space/>and the establishment of his<space/><link><target>Bolivarian Revolution</target></link>, over 1.6 million<space/><link><target>Venezuelan people</target><part>Venezuelan</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>emigrated from Venezuela in what has been called the<space/><link><target>Bolivarian diaspora</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EUdiaspora"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Olivares</arg><arg name="first1">Francisco</arg><arg name="title">Best and brightest for export</arg><arg name="url">http://www.eluniversal.com/nacional-y-politica/140913/best-and-brightest-for-export</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2014</arg><arg name="agency">El Universal</arg><arg name="date">13 September 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="NEWSWEEKdiaspora"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Hugo Chavez is Scaring Away Talent</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newsweek.com/hugo-chavez-scaring-away-talent-80337</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 September 2014</arg><arg name="agency">Newsweek</arg><arg name="date">30 June 2009</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ELIMPdec2014"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">La emigración venezolana a diferencia de otras "se va con un diploma bajo el brazo"</arg><arg name="url">http://elimpulso.com/articulo/la-emigracion-venezolana-a-diferencia-de-otras-se-va-con-un-diploma-bajo-el-brazo#</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 December 2014</arg><arg name="agency">El Impulso</arg><arg name="date">17 December 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The analysis of a study by the<space/><link><target>Central University of Venezuela</target></link><space/>titled<space/><italics>Venezuelan Community Abroad. A New Method of Exile</italics><space/>by<space/><italics><link><target>El Universal (Caracas)</target><part>El Universal</part></link></italics><space/>states that the Bolivarian diaspora in Venezuela has been caused by the &quot;deterioration of both the economy and the social fabric, rampant crime, uncertainty and lack of hope for a change in leadership in the near future&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EUdiaspora"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Diaspora populations on the Internet</heading><paragraph>There are numerous web-based news portals and forum sites dedicated to specific diaspora communities, often organized on the basis of an origin characteristic and a current location characteristic (e.g.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.chineseinboston.com/'>ChineseInBoston.com</link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Van Den Bos</arg><arg name="first1">Matthijs</arg><arg name="last2">Nell</arg><arg name="first2">Liza</arg><arg name="title">Territorial bounds to virtual space: transnational online and offline networks of Iranian and Turkish–Kurdish immigrants in the Netherlands</arg><arg name="journal">Global Networks: A Journal of Transnational Affairs</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="volume">6</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">201–220</arg><arg name="url">http://islamicgroupatasu.wikispaces.com/file/view/Van+den+bos.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1471-0374.2006.00141.x</arg></template></extension><space/>The location-based networking features of mobile applications such as China's<space/><link><target>WeChat</target></link><space/>have also created de facto online diaspora communities when used outside of their home markets.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Chester</arg><arg name="first">Ken</arg><arg name="title">How WeChat And Zalo Shine a Light On The Asian American Diaspora</arg><arg name="url">http://www.techinasia.com/wechat-zalo-asian-american-diaspora/</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Tech in Asia</arg><arg name="date">7 August 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Furthermore, in this evolutionary process, in which web-based portals and forums are created to aid Diasporas, is that, platforms are not only focusing on specific communities. The term Diaspora is evolving towards a more general term that can apply to a vast percentage of the World population and platforms have been developed to engage with them (e.g.<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.diasporaengager.com/'>DiasporaEngager.com</link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://DiasporaEngager.com/'>DiasporaEngager: International diaspora engagement social media</link></extension><space/>Recently a global map of the international diasporas and their stakeholders has been made by<space/><bold>DiasporaEngager</bold><space/>(<link type='external' href='https://www.diasporaengager.com/map'>DiasporaEngager.com/map</link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://diasporaengager.com/map/'>'''Diaspora Map''': Map of the International Diasporas and their Stakeholders</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Now, large companies from the emerging countries are looking at leveraging diaspora communities to enter the more mature market.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://hbr.org/2013/10/diaspora-marketing<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Globe: Diaspora Marketing, Nirmalya Kumar and Jan-Benedict E.M. Steenkamp<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard Business Review<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>Gran Torino</target></link></italics>, a 2008 drama starring<space/><link><target>Clint Eastwood</target></link>, was the first mainstream American film to feature the<space/><link><target>Hmong American</target></link><space/>diaspora.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Peterson-de la Cueva</arg><arg name="first">Lisa</arg><arg name="title">Gran Torino connects Hmong Minnesotans with Hollywood</arg><arg name="url">http://www.tcdailyplanet.net/article/2008/11/18/hmong-minnesotans-connect-hollywood-gran-torino.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 September 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Twin Cities Daily Planet</arg><arg name="date">24 November 2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Div col</target></template></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of diasporas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armenian Genocide</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Boat people</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Displaced person</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ethnic cleansing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Exodus</target><part>Exodus</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Expatriate</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Forced migration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Holocaust</target><part>Holocaust</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human migration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Immigration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Long Walk of the Navajo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>1948 Palestinian exodus</target><part>Nakba</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Population transfer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Refugee</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rural exodus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Slave trade</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stateless nation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Trail of Tears</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ummah</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Barclay, John M. G., (ed.),<space/><italics>Negotiating Diaspora: Jewish Strategies in the Roman Empire</italics>, Continuum International Publishing Group, 2004</listitem><listitem>Baser, B and Swain, A. Diasporas as Peacemakers: Third Party Mediation in Homeland Conflicts with Ashok Swain. International Journal on World Peace 25, 3, September 2008.</listitem><listitem>Braziel, Jana Evans. 2008. Diaspora - an introduction. Malden, MA: Blackwell.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.sscnet.ucla.edu/soc/faculty/brubaker/Publications/29_Diaspora_diaspora_ERS.pdf</arg><arg name="title">The 'diaspora' diaspora</arg><arg name="first">Rogers</arg><arg name="last">Brubaker</arg><arg name="authorlink">Rogers Brubaker</arg><arg name="journal">Ethnic and Racial Studies</arg><arg name="volume">28</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">1–19</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/0141987042000289997</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 February 2011</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Bueltmann, Tanja, et al. eds.<space/><italics>Locating the English Diaspora, 1500-2010</italics><space/>(Liverpool University Press, 2012)</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Global Diasporas: An Introduction</arg><arg name="first">Robin</arg><arg name="last">Cohen</arg><arg name="authorlink">Robin Cohen</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="location">Abingdon</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-43550-1</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gershon Galil</target><part>Galil, Gershon</part></link>, &amp;<space/><link><target>Moshe Weinfeld</target><part>Weinfeld, Moshe</part></link>, Studies in Historical Geography and Biblical Historiography: Presented to Zekharyah alai, BRILL, 2000</listitem><listitem>Forbes, Andrew, and Henley, David,<space/><italics>People of Palestine</italics><space/>(Chiang Mai: Cognoscenti Books, 2012), ASIN: B0094TU8VY</listitem><listitem>Kenny, Kevin, Diaspora: A Very Short Introduction. New York: Oxford University Press, 2013.</listitem><listitem>Kantor, Mattis,<space/><italics>The Jewish time line encyclopedia: a year-by-year history from Creation to the Present</italics>, (New updated edition), Jason Aronson, Northvale NJ, 1992</listitem><listitem>Luciuk, Lubomyr, &quot;Searching for Place: Ukrainian Displaced Persons, Canada and the Migration of Memory,&quot; University of Toronto Press, 2000.</listitem><listitem>Oonk, G, 'Global Indian Diasporas: trajectories of migration and theory, Amsterdam University Press, 2007Free download: http://dare.uva.nl/aup/en/record/260518</listitem><listitem>Shain, Yossi, Kinship and Diasporas in International Politics, Michigan University Press, 2007</listitem><listitem>Sami Mahroum, Cynthia Eldridge, Abdallah S Daar (2006), Transnational diaspora options: How developing countries could benefit from their emigrant populations. International Journal on Multicultural Societies, 2006.</listitem><listitem>S Mahroum, P De Guchteneire (2007), Transnational Knowledge Through Diaspora Networks-Editorial. International Journal of Multicultural Societies 8 (1), 1-3</listitem><listitem>Tetlow, Elisabeth Meier, Women, Crime, and Punishment in Ancient Law and Society, Continuum International Publishing Group, 2005</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="first">Agnieszka</arg><arg name="last">Weinar</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="chapter">Instrumentalising diasporas for development: International and European policy discourses</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Rainer</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Bauböck</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Thomas</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Faist</arg><arg name="title">Diaspora and Transnationalism: Concepts, Theories and Methods</arg><arg name="publisher">Amsterdam University Press</arg><arg name="location">Amsterdam</arg><arg name="pages">73–89</arg><arg name="isbn">90-8964-238-2</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem>B. Xharra and M. Whlisch,<space/><italics>Beyond Remittances: Public Diplomacy and Kosovo's Diaspora</italics>, Foreign Policy Club, Pristina (2012), http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=2108317.</listitem><listitem>Weheliye, Alexander G. &quot;My Volk to Come: Peoplehood in Recent Diaspora Discourse and Afro-German Popular Music.&quot; Black Europe and the African Diaspora. Ed. Darlene Clark. Hine, Trica Danielle. Keaton, and Stephen Small. Urbana: U of Illinois, 2009. 161-79. Print.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>diaspora</arg></template><template><target>commons category</target><arg>diasporas</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><template><target>Prone to spam</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Z148</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/di-dn/diaspora/diaspora.htm'>Livius.org: Diaspora</link></listitem><listitem>http://dare.uva.nl/aup/en/record/260518 Open access book on Diasporas</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://diasporas.se'>DIASPORAS.SE</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.unaoc.org/communities/migrationintegration'>Integration : Building Inclusive Societies (IBIS)</link><space/>UN Alliance of Civilizations online community on Good Practices of Integration of Migrants across the World</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.DiasporaEngager.com:'>International Diaspora Engagement Platform - DiasporaEngager</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Diasporas</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Diaspora studies</target></link></paragraph></article>