<article title='Mail_%28armour%29'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Chainmail</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Chainmail (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Maille</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eastern riveted armor.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Riveted mail and plate coat ''zirah bagtar''. Armour of this type was introduced into India under the Mughals.</part></link><bold>Mail</bold><space/>(chainmail, maille) is a type of<space/><link><target>armour</target></link><space/>consisting of small metal rings linked together in a pattern to form a mesh.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gaul warrior Vacheres 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Statue of a<space/><link><target>Gaul</target><part>Gallic</part></link><space/>warrior in mail.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest example of mail was found in a<space/><link><target>Dacians</target><part>Dacian</part></link><space/>chieftain's burial located in<space/><link><target>Ciumeti</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Romania</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rusu, M., &quot;Das Keltische Frstengrab von Ciumeti in Rumnien&quot;, Germania 50, 1969, pp. 267269</extension><space/>Its invention is commonly credited to the Celts,<extension extension_name='ref' name="books.google.com"><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=HscIwvtkq2UC&amp;amp;pg=PA79&amp;amp;dq=laminar+armor&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=nOMGTqrNNfGv0AGWpbi6Cw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=3&amp;amp;ved=0CDYQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=laminar%20armor&amp;amp;f=true'>''The ancient world'', Richard A. Gabriel, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2007 P.79</link></extension><space/>but there are examples of<space/><link><target>Etruscan military history</target><part>Etruscan</part></link><space/>pattern mail dating from at least the 4th century BC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Oriental Armour, H. Russell Robinson, 1967 Walker and Co., New York, pp. 11-12</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Catalogue of the Exhibition of Ancient Helmets and Examples of Mail, William Burgess &amp; Baron De Cosson</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Stone, G.C. (1934): A Glossary of the Construction, Decoration and Use of Arms And Armor in All Countries and in All Times, Dover Publications, New York</extension><space/>Mail may have been inspired by the much earlier<space/><link><target>scale armour</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Philip Sidnell,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=l4KYsLl0sVIC&amp;amp;pg=PA159#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>''Warhorse: Cavalry in Ancient Warfare''</link>, Continuum International Publishing Group, 2006 ISBN 1-85285-374-3, p.159</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Robert E. Krebs, Carolyn A. Krebs,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=0H0fjBeseVEC&amp;amp;pg=PA309#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>''Groundbreaking Scientific Experiments, Inventions, and Discoveries of the Ancient World''</link>, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2003 ISBN 0-313-31342-3, p.309</extension><space/>Mail spread to North Africa, the Middle East, Central Asia, India, Tibet, South East Asia, and Japan.</paragraph><paragraph>Mail continues to be used in the 21st century as a component of stab-resistant<space/><link><target>personal armor</target><part>body armour</part></link>, cut-resistant gloves for butchers and woodworkers, shark-resistant<space/><link><target>wetsuit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for defense against shark bites, and a number of other applications.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The origins of the word mail are not fully known. One theory is that it originally derives from the Latin word<space/><italics>macula</italics>, meaning &quot;spot&quot; or opacity (as in<space/><link><target>macula of retina</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="oed">&quot;mail, n.3&quot;.<space/><italics>OED Online</italics>. December 2011. Oxford University Press.</extension><space/>Another theory relates the word to the old French maillier, meaning to hammer (related to the modern English word malleable).<extension extension_name='ref' name="oed"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first attestations of the word mail are in Old French and Anglo-Norman: maille maile, or male or other variants, which became mailye maille maile, male, or meile in Middle English.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/m/mec/med-idx?type=id&amp;amp;id=MED26516'>&quot;maille&quot; ''The Middle English Dictionary Online''.</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The modern usage of terms for mail armour is highly contested in popular and, to a lesser degree, academic culture. Medieval sources referred to armour of this type simply as mail, however chain-mail has become a commonly used, if incorrect<space/><link><target>neologism</target></link><space/>first attested in Sir Walter Scotts 1822 novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Fortunes of Nigel</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;chain-mail, n.&quot;<space/><italics>OED Online</italics>. December 2011. Oxford University Press.</extension><space/>Since then the word mail has been commonly, if incorrectly, applied to other types of armour, such as in plate-mail (first attested in 1835).<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;plate-mail, n.&quot;<space/><italics>OED Online</italics>. December 2011. Oxford University Press.</extension><space/>The more correct term is<space/><link><target>plate armour</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Civilizations that used mail invented specific terms for each garment made from it. The standard terms for European mail armour derive from French: leggings are called<space/><link><target>chausses</target></link>, a hood is a<space/><link><target>coif</target></link>, and mittens,<space/><link><target>mitons</target></link>. A mail collar hanging from a helmet is a<space/><link><target>camail</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>aventail</target></link>. A shirt made from mail is a<space/><link><target>hauberk</target></link><space/>if knee-length and a<space/><link><target>haubergeon</target></link><space/>if mid-thigh length. A layer (or layers) of mail sandwiched between layers of fabric is called a<space/><link><target>jazerant</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A waist-length coat in medieval Europe was called a byrnie, although the exact construction of a byrnie is unclear, including whether it was constructed of mail or other armour-types. Noting that the byrnie was the &quot;most highly valued piece of armour&quot; to the<space/><link><target>Charlemagne</target><part>Carolingian</part></link><space/>soldier, Bennet, Bradbury, DeVries, Dickie, and Jestice<extension extension_name='ref'>Bennet, M., Bradbury, J., DeVries, K., Dickie, I., &amp; Jestice, P.<space/><italics>Fighting Techniques of the Medieval World</italics>. Thomas Dunne Books, 2005, p. 82</extension><space/>indicate that:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>There is some dispute among historians as to what exactly constituted the Carolingian byrnie. Relying... only on artistic and some literary sources because of the lack of archaeological examples, some believe that it was a heavy leather jacket with metal scales sewn onto it. It was also quite long, reaching below the hips and covering most of the arms. Other historians claim instead that the Carolingian byrnie was nothing more than a coat of mail, but longer and perhaps heavier than traditional early medieval mail. Without more certain evidence, this dispute will continue.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Mail armour in Europe</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:MWP Pancerni 2 polowa 17 wieku.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Mail armour and equipment of Polish medium cavalryman, from the second half of the 17th century</part></link>The use of mail as battlefield armour was common during the<space/><link><target>Iron Age</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>, becoming less common over the course of the 16th and 17th centuries. It is believed that the<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target></link><space/>first came into contact with mail fighting the Gauls in<space/><link><target>Cisalpine Gaul</target></link>, now<space/><link><target>Northern Italy</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.middle-ages.org.uk/chainmail.htm</extension><space/>but a different pattern of mail was already in use among the Etruscans.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>The Roman army adopted the technology for their troops in the form of the<space/><link><target>lorica hamata</target></link><space/>which was used as a primary form of armour through the Imperial period.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Harold dead bayeux tapestry.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Panel from the<space/><link><target>Bayeux Tapestry</target></link><space/>showing<space/><link><target>Normans</target><part>Norman</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxon</target></link><space/>soldiers in mail armour. Note the scene of stripping a mail hauberk from the dead at the bottom.</part></link>After the fall of the Western Empire much of the infrastructure needed to create<space/><link><target>plate armour</target></link><space/>diminished. Eventually the word &quot;mail&quot; came to be synonymous with armour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Francis Grose, A Treatise on Ancient Armour and Weapons, London, 1786</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Samuel R. Meyrick, A Critical Inquiry into Ancient Armour, as it Existed in Europe, but Particularly in England, from the Norman Conquest to the Reign of King Charles II: with a Glossary of Military Terms of the Middle Ages, (London, 1824</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Charles Henry Ashdown, British and Foreign Arms and Armour, (London, 1909</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Eugne Emmanuel Viollet-le-duc, Encyclopdie Mdivale and Dictionnaire Raisonne du Mobilier Francais de l'Epoque Carlovingienne a la Renaissance.</extension><space/>It was typically an extremely prized commodity as it was expensive and time consuming to produce and could mean the difference between life and death in a battle. Mail from dead combatants was frequently looted and was used by the new owner or sold for a lucrative price. As time went on and infrastructure improved it came to be used by more soldiers. Eventually with the rise of the lanced<space/><link><target>cavalry charge</target></link>, impact warfare, and high-powered<space/><link><target>crossbows</target></link>, mail came to be used as a secondary armour to plate for the mounted nobility.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By the 14th century,<space/><link><target>plate armour</target></link><space/>was commonly used to supplement mail. Eventually mail was supplanted by plate for the most part as it provided greater protection against windlass crossbows, bludgeoning weapons, and lance charges. However, mail was still widely used by many soldiers as well as<space/><link><target>brigandine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>padded jack</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These three types of armour made up the bulk of the equipment used by soldiers with mail being the most expensive. It was sometimes more expensive than plate armour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reed Jr., Robert W. &quot;Armour Purchases and Lists from the Howard Household Books&quot;,<space/><italics>The Journal of the Mail Research Society</italics>, Vol. 1. No. 1, July 2003</extension><space/>Mail typically persisted longer in less technologically advanced areas such as Eastern Europe but was in use everywhere into the 16th century.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the late 19th and early 20th century mail was used as a material for<space/><link><target>Ballistic vest</target><part>bulletproof vests</part></link>, most notably by the<space/><link><target>Wilkinson Sword</target></link><space/>Company.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Men Who Wear Armour.</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Daily Mail</arg><arg name="year">1886</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Randolph</arg><arg name="first">T.H.</arg><arg name="title">The Wilkinson Sword Catalog</arg><arg name="year">1892</arg><arg name="publisher">The Wilkinson Sword Co. Ltd.</arg><arg name="pages">41</arg></template></extension><space/>Results were unsatisfactory; Wilkinson mail worn by the<space/><link><target>Isma'il Pasha</target><part>Khedive of Egypt</part></link>'s regiment of &quot;Iron Men&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=KdJn9JbSYygC&amp;amp;pg=PA38&amp;amp;lpg=PA38&amp;amp;dq=khedive+iron+men&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=vvmfcaypMz&amp;amp;sig=f-cvAQJQKn0KZcKYFUEC5W8LVtQ&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=Fh1uTrS4JKra0QGGhOiGBQ&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CBgQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=khedive%20iron%20men&amp;amp;f=false'>Google Books</link><space/>Iron Men</extension><space/>was manufactured from split rings which proved to be too brittle, and the rings would fragment when struck by bullets and aggravate the damage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Robinson</arg><arg name="first">H. Russel</arg><arg name="title">Oriental Armour</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="pages">85</arg></template></extension><space/>The riveted mail armour worn by the opposing Sudanese Madhists did not have the same problem but also proved to be relatively useless against the firearms of British forces at the<space/><link><target>battle of Omdurman</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Stone</arg><arg name="first">George Cameron</arg><arg name="title">A Glossary of the Construction, Decoration and Use of Arms and Armor: In All Countries and in All Times</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="pages">69</arg></template></extension><space/>During World War I Wilkinson Sword transitioned from mail to a lamellar design which was the precursor to the<space/><link><target>flak jacket</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Also during World War I a mail fringe, designed by Captain Cruise of the British Infantry, was added to helmets to protect the face. This proved unpopular with soldiers, in spite of being proven to defend against a three-ounce (100 g)<space/><link><target>Shrapnel shell</target><part>shrapnel</part></link><space/>round fired at a distance of one hundred yards (90 m).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Mail armour in Asia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 135-S-14-13-33, Tibetexpedition, Neujahrsparade, Rta pa.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Tibetan warrior in mail reinforced by additional<space/><link><target>mirror armour</target><part>mirror plate</part></link></part></link>Mail Armour was introduced to the Middle East and Asia through the Romans and was adopted by the<space/><link><target>Sassanid</target></link><space/>Persians starting in the 3rd century AD, where it was supplemental to the scale and lamellar armours already used. Mail was commonly also used as horse armour for<space/><link><target>cataphracts</target></link><space/>and heavy cavalry as well as armour for the soldiers themselves. Asian mail was typically lighter than the European variety and sometimes had prayer symbols stamped on the rings as a sign of their craftsmanship as well as for divine protection.<extension extension_name='ref'>David G Alexander, Decorated and inscribed mail shirts in the Metropolitan Museum, Waffen- und Kostumkunde 27 (1985), 2936</extension><space/>Indeed, mail armour is mentioned in the<space/><link><target>Koran</target></link><space/>as being a gift revealed by Allah to David:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>21:80<space/><italics>It was We Who taught him the making of coats of mail for your benefit, to guard you from each other's violence: will ye then be grateful?</italics><space/>(Yusuf Ali's translation).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>From the Middle East mail was quickly adopted in Central Asia by the Sogdians and by India in the South. It was not commonly used in Mongol armies due to its weight and the difficulty of its maintenance, but it eventually became the armour of choice in India. Indian mail was often used with plate protection.<space/><link><target>Plated mail</target></link><space/>was in common use in India until the<space/><link><target>Battle of Plassey</target></link><space/>and the subsequent British conquest of the sub-continent.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>used plated mail widely and it was used in their armies until the 18th century by heavy cavalry and elite units such as the Janissaries. They spread its use into North Africa where it was adopted by<space/><link><target>Mamluk</target></link><space/>Egyptians and the Sudanese who produced it until the early 20th century.</paragraph><paragraph>Mail was introduced to<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>when its allies in Central Asia paid tribute to the<space/><link><target>Tang Dynasty</target><part>Tang Emperor</part></link><space/>in 718 by giving him a coat of &quot;link armour&quot; assumed to be mail. China first encountered the armour in 384 when its allies in the nation of<space/><link><target>Kuchi</target></link><space/>arrived wearing &quot;armour similar to chains&quot;. Once in China mail was imported but was not produced widely. Due to its flexibility and comfort, it was typically the armour of high-ranking guards and those who could afford the import rather than the armour of the rank and file, who used the easier to produce and maintain brigandine and<space/><link><target>Lamellar armour</target><part>lamellar</part></link><space/>types. However, it was one of the only military products that China imported from foreigners. Mail spread to Korea slightly later where it was imported as the armour of imperial guards and generals.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Japanese mail armour</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Kusari (Japanese mail armour)</arg></template><link><target>File:Japanese kusari armor.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Edo period Japanese (samurai) chain armour or kusari gusoku</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link><space/>mail is called<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Japanese chain mail</target><part>kusari</part></link></italics><space/>which means chain. When the word<space/><italics>kusari</italics><space/>is used in conjunction with an armoured item it usually means that mail makes up the majority of the armour composition.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=J5PgapzD6FoC&amp;amp;pg=PA70&amp;amp;dq=kusari&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=509hTfGDMIa0lQfds-CTDA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=5&amp;amp;sqi=2&amp;amp;ved=0CD0Q6AEwBA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=kusari&amp;amp;f=true'>''A Glossary of the Construction, Decoration and Use of Arms and Armor: In All Countries and in All Times'', George Cameron Stone, Courier Dover Publications, 1999 p. 403</link></extension><space/>An example of this would be<space/><italics>kusari gusoku</italics><space/>which means chain armour.<space/><italics>Kusari</italics><space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari katabira</target><part>jackets</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari zukin</target><part>hoods</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari han kote</target><part>gloves</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari vests</target><part>vests</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari suneate</target><part>shin</part></link></italics>, shoulder,<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari haidate</target><part>thigh guards</part></link></italics>, and other armoured clothing were produced, even<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari tabi</target><part>kusari tabi</part></link></italics><space/>socks.</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Japanese chain mail</target><part>Kusari</part></link></italics><space/>was used in<space/><link><target>Japanese armour</target><part>samurai armour</part></link><space/>at least from the time of the Mongol invasion (1270s) but particularly from the Nambokucho period (13361392).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=QOH-icuirzAC&amp;amp;pg=PA92&amp;amp;dq=Japanese+mail+armor&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=P7tgTYPtNIeglAfPrbDnCw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=2&amp;amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwAQ#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Japanese%20mail%20armor&amp;amp;f=true'>''Brassey's Book of Body Armor'', Robert C. Woosnam-Savage, Anthony Hall, Brassey's, 2002 p.92</link></extension><space/>The Japanese used many different weave methods including: a square 4-in-1 pattern (<italics>so gusari</italics>), a hexagonal 6-in-1 pattern (<italics>hana gusari</italics>) and a European 4-in-1 (<italics>nanban gusari</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Ian Bottomley &amp; A.P. Hopson<space/><italics>Arms and Armor of the Samurai: The History of Weaponry in Ancient Japan</italics><space/>P.57 &amp; P.186 ISBN 1-86222-002-6</extension><space/>The rings of Japanese mail were much smaller than their European counterparts; they would be used in patches to link together plates and to drape over vulnerable areas such as the armpits.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Riveted kusari</bold><space/>was known and used in Japan. On page 58 of the book<space/><italics>Japanese Arms &amp; Armor: Introduction</italics><space/>by H. Russell Robinson, there is a picture of Japanese riveted kusari,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Japanese Arms &amp; Armor: Introduction</italics><space/>by H. Russell Robinson, London, Arms &amp; Armour P., p.58, ISBN 9780853680192.</extension><space/>andthis quote from the translated reference of Sakakibara Kozan's 1800 book,<space/><italics>The Manufacture of Armour and Helmets in Sixteenth Century Japan</italics>, shows that the Japanese not only knew of and used riveted kusari but that they manufactured it as well.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>...&amp;nbsp;karakuri-namban (riveted namban), with stout links each closed by a rivet. Its invention is credited to Fukushima Dembei Kunitaka, pupil, of Hojo Awa no Kami Ujifusa, but it is also said to be derived directly from foreign models. It is heavy because the links are tinned (biakuro-nagashi) and these are also sharp edged because they are punched out of iron plate<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?ei=07dgTeb5KYH6lwey1JGIDA&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;id=s2oiAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;dq=kusari+armor&amp;amp;q=kusari#search_anchor'>The manufacture of armour and helmets in sixteenth century Japan: (Chkokatch seisakuben) Kzan Sakakibara, C. E. Tuttle, 1964 p.84</link></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Butted and or split (twisted) links</bold><space/>made up the majority of<space/><italics>kusari</italics><space/>links used by the Japanese. Links were either<space/><italics>butted</italics><space/>together meaning that the ends touched each other and were not riveted, or the<space/><italics>kusari</italics><space/>was constructed with links where the wire was turned or twisted<extension extension_name='ref' name="b1"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">George Cameron Stone</arg><arg name="title">A Glossary of the Construction, Decoration and Use of Arms and Armor: In All Countries and in All Times</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2011</arg><arg name="date">2 July 1999</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-486-40726-5</arg><arg name="page">424</arg></template></extension><space/>two or more times; these split links are similar to the modern split ring commonly used on keychains. The rings were lacquered black to prevent rusting, and were always stitched onto a backing of cloth or leather. The kusari was sometimes concealed entirely between layers of cloth.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?ei=07dgTeb5KYH6lwey1JGIDA&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;id=s2oiAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;dq=kusari+armor&amp;amp;q=kusari#search_anchor'>''The manufacture of armour and helmets in sixteenth century Japan'': (Chkokatch seisakuben) Kzan Sakakibara, C. E. Tuttle, 1964 p.85</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Kusari gusoku</bold><space/>or chain armour was commonly used during the<space/><link><target>Edo period</target></link><space/>1603 to 1868 as a stand-alone defence. According to George Cameron Stone</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Entire suits of mail<space/><italics>kusari gusoku</italics><space/>were worn on occasions, sometimes under the ordinary clothing<extension extension_name='ref' name="stone61"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">George Cameron Stone</arg><arg name="title">A Glossary of the Construction, Decoration and Use of Arms and Armor: In All Countries and in All Times<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2011</arg><arg name="date">2 July 1999</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-486-40726-5</arg><arg name="page">61</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><preblock><preline><space/><space/><space/></preline></preblock><paragraph>Ian Bottomley in his book &quot;Arms and Armor of the Samurai: The History of Weaponry in Ancient Japan&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Ian Bottomley&amp; A.P. Hopson &quot;Arms and Armor of the Samurai: The History of Weaponry in Ancient Japan&quot; pp.155156 ISBN 1-86222-002-6</extension><space/>shows a picture of a kusari armour and mentions<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Kusari katabira</target><part>kusari katabira</part></link></italics><space/>(chain jackets) with detachable arms being worn by samurai police officials during the Edo period. The end of the samurai era in the 1860s, along with the 1876 ban on wearing swords in public, marked the end of any practical use for mail and other armour in Japan. Japan turned to a conscription army and uniforms replaced armour.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=zPyswmGDBFkC&amp;amp;pg=PA43&amp;amp;dq=meiji+sword+ban&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=gN53TZvlMJT3rAGo79H_CQ&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;sqi=2&amp;amp;ved=0CDIQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=meiji%20sword%20ban&amp;amp;f=false'>The connoisseur's book of Japanese swords, Kkan Nagayama, Kodansha International</link>, 1998 p.43</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Effectiveness</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bayeux haubert.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Mail byrnie from the Museum of Bayeux</part></link>Mail armour provided an effective defence against slashing blows by<space/><link><target>blade</target><part>edged weapon</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and penetration by thrusting and piercing weapons; in fact, a study conducted at the<space/><link><target>Royal Armouries</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Leeds</target></link><space/>concluded that &quot;it is almost impossible to penetrate using any conventional medieval weapon.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Medieval Military Surgery&quot;, Medieval History Magazine, Vol 1 is 4, December 2003</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Deadliest Warrior</target></link>: episode 2; katana unable to penetrate mail</extension><space/>Generally speaking, mail's resistance to weapons is determined by four factors: linkage type (riveted, butted, or welded), material used (iron versus bronze or steel), weave density (a tighter weave needs a thinner weapon to surpass), and ring thickness (generally ranging from 18 to 14 gauge (1.021.63&amp;nbsp;mm diameter wire) in most examples). Mail, if a warrior could afford it, provided a significant advantage to a warrior when combined with competent fighting techniques. When the mail was not riveted, a well-placed thrust from a spear or thin sword could penetrate, and a<space/><link><target>Pollaxe (polearm)</target><part>pollaxe</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>halberd</target></link><space/>blow could break through the armour. In India, punching daggers known as<space/><link><target>Katar (dagger)</target><part>katars</part></link><space/>were developed that could pierce the light butted mail used in the area. Some evidence indicates that during armoured combat, the intention was to actually get around the armour rather than through itaccording to a study of skeletons found in<space/><link><target>Visby</target></link>, Sweden, a majority of the skeletons showed wounds on less well protected legs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="thordeman"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Thordeman</arg><arg name="first">Bengt</arg><arg name="title">Armour From The Battle of Wisby 1361</arg><arg name="year">1940</arg><arg name="publisher">Kungl. Vitterhets Historie och Antikvitets Akademien</arg><arg name="location">Stockholm, Sweden</arg><arg name="pages">160</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The flexibility of mail meant that a blow would often injure the wearer,<extension extension_name='ref'>D. Edge and J. Paddock. Arms and Armour of the Medieval Knight, (London: Bison), 1988</extension><space/>potentially causing serious bruising or fractures, and it was a poor defence against head trauma. Mail-clad warriors typically wore separate rigid<space/><link><target>helmet</target><part>helms</part></link><space/>over their mail coifs for head protection. Likewise, blunt weapons such as<space/><link><target>Mace (club)</target><part>mace</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>war hammer</target><part>warhammer</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>could harm the wearer by their impact without penetrating the armour; usually a soft armour, such as<space/><link><target>gambeson</target></link>, was worn under the hauberk. Medieval surgeons were very well capable of setting and caring for bone fractures resulting from blunt weapons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA">Mitchell, Piers D Medicine in the Crusades: Warfare, Wounds and the Medieval Surgeon [Cambridge University Press, 2007]</extension><space/>With the poor understanding of hygiene however, cuts that could get infected were much more of a problem.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>Thus mail armour proved to be sufficient protection in most situations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Williams, The Knight and the Blast Furnace. pp 942-43</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Horsfall, I. et al., &quot;An Assessment of Human Performance in Stabbing,&quot; Forensic Science International, 102 (1999). pp 79-89</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Manufacture</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Fotothek df tg 0008481 Stndebuch ^ Handwerk ^ Plattner ^ Rstung ^ Harnisch ^ Kettenhemd.jpg</target><part>170px</part><part>thumb</part><part>A manuscript from 1698 showing the manufacture of mail</part></link>Several patterns of linking the rings together have been known since ancient times, with the most common being the 4-to-1 pattern (where each ring is linked with four others). In Europe, the 4-to-1 pattern was completely dominant. Mail was also common in East Asia, primarily Japan, with several more patterns being utilised and an entire nomenclature developing around them.</paragraph><paragraph>Historically, in Europe, from the pre-Roman period on, the rings composing a piece of mail would be<space/><link><target>rivet</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>closed to reduce the chance of the rings splitting open when subjected to a thrusting attack or a hit by an arrow.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>Up until the 14th century European mail was made of alternating rows of riveted rings and solid rings. After that point mail was almost all made from riveted rings only.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Example2006"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Richardson<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>T.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Armour in England, 1325–99<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/j.jmedhist.2011.06.001<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Medieval History<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>37<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>304–320<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Both were commonly made of<space/><link><target>wrought iron</target></link>, but some later pieces were made of heat-treated steel. Wire for the riveted rings was formed by either of two methods. One was to hammer out wrought iron into plates and cut or slit the plates. These thin pieces were then pulled through a<space/><link><target>draw plate</target></link><space/>repeatedly until the desired diameter was achieved.<space/><link><target>Waterwheel</target></link><space/>powered drawing mills are pictured in several period manuscripts. Another method was to simply forge down an iron<space/><link><target>Billet (bar stock)</target><part>billet</part></link><space/>into a rod and then proceed to draw it out into wire. The solid links would have been made by punching from a sheet. Guild marks were often stamped on the rings to show their origin and craftsmanship.<space/><link><target>Forge welding</target></link><space/>was also used to create solid links, but there are few possible examples known; the only well documented example from Europe is that of the camail (mail neck-defence) of the 7th century<space/><link><target>Coppergate helmet</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>D. Tweddle, The Anglian Helmet from Coppergate, Archaeology of York 17/8, York Archaeological Trust 1992</extension><space/>Outside of Europe this practice was more common such as &quot;theta&quot; links from India. Very few examples of historic butted mail have been found and it is generally accepted that butted mail was never in wide use historically except in Japan where mail (<italics>kusari</italics>) was commonly made from<space/><italics>butted</italics><space/>links.<extension extension_name='ref' name="b1"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern uses</heading><heading level='3'>Practical uses</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Neptunic shark suit 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>170px</part><part>Neptunic shark suit</part></link>Mail is used as protective clothing for butchers against meat-packing equipment. Workers may wear up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8</arg><arg>lb</arg><arg>kg</arg></template><space/>of mail under their white coats.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ericsecho.org/investigation2.htm
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Fast-Food Nation: Meat and Potatoes 
</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-12-05 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Schlosser 
</arg><arg name="first">Eric 
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Eric Schlosser 
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>September 3, 1998
</arg><arg name="work">Rolling Stone magazine (USA), Issue 794, 
</arg></template></extension><space/>Butchers also commonly wear a single mail glove to protect themselves from self-inflicted injury while cutting meat.</paragraph><paragraph>Woodcarvers sometimes use similar mail gloves to protect their hands from cuts and punctures.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>British police</target></link><space/>use mail gloves for dealing with knife-armed aggressors.</paragraph><paragraph>Scuba divers use mail to protect them from sharkbite, as do animal control officers for protection against the animals they handle. Shark expert and underwater filmmaker<space/><link><target>Ron &amp; Valerie Taylor</target><part>Valerie Taylor</part></link><space/>was among the first to develop and test<space/><link><target>shark suit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in 1979 while diving with sharks.</paragraph><paragraph>Mail is widely used in industrial settings as shrapnel guards and splash guards in metal working operations.</paragraph><paragraph>Electrical applications for mail include RF leakage testing and being worn as a<space/><link><target>faraday cage</target></link><space/>suit by tesla coil enthusiasts and high voltage electrical workers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite AV media</target><arg name="people">Douglas, David (director)</arg><arg name="publisher">Smithsonian Institution's National Air and Space Museum</arg><arg name="title">Straight Up: Helicopters in Action</arg><arg name="date">2002</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Blake</arg><arg name="first">Terry</arg><arg name="title">Dr Zeus - Testing of HV Suit w Twin Musical Tesla Coils</arg><arg name="url">http://www.dr-zeus.com/</arg><arg name="work">Daily Planet Segment 2008</arg><arg name="publisher">Discovery Channel</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Stab-proof vests</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Stab vest</arg></template>Conventional textile-based ballistic vests are designed to stop soft-nosed bullets but offer little defense from knife attacks. Knife-resistant armours are designed to defend against knife attacks; some of these use layers of metal plates, mail and metallic wires.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=FMgpdulJsGgC&amp;amp;pg=PA368&amp;amp;dq=chainmail+stab+proof+vest&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=5l2hTay4PIqWtwfj1qCeAw&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=4&amp;amp;ved=0CE4Q6AEwAzgU#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>Illustrated Directory of Special Forces, Ray Bonds, David Miller, Zenith Imprint, 2003 p. 368</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Historical re-enactment</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Roman soldier 175 aC in northern province.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>170px</part><part>Roman soldier 175 a.C. from a northern province, (re-enactment).</part></link>Many<space/><link><target>historical reenactment</target></link><space/>groups, especially those whose focus is<space/><link><target>Ancient history</target><part>Antiquity</part></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>, commonly use mail both as practical armour and for costuming. Mail is especially popular amongst those groups which use steel weapons. A modern hauberk made from 1.5&amp;nbsp;mm diameter wire with 10&amp;nbsp;mm inner diameter rings weighs roughly<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>kg</arg><arg>lb</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>and contains 15,00045,000 rings.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>One of the drawbacks of mail is the uneven weight distribution; the stress falls mainly on shoulders. Weight can be better distributed by wearing a belt over the mail, which provides another point of support.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Mail worn today for re-enactment and recreational use can be made in a variety of styles and materials. Most recreational mail today is made of butted links which are galvanized or stainless steel. This is historically inaccurate but is much less expensive to procure and maintain than historically accurate reproductions. Mail can also be made of titanium, aluminium, bronze, or copper. Riveted mail offers significantly better protection ability as well as historical accuracy than mail constructed with butted links. Riveted mail can be more labour-intensive and expensive to manufacture. Japanese mail (<italics>kusari</italics>) is one of the few historically correct examples of mail being constructed with such<space/><italics>butted links</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="b1"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Decorative uses</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Major's shoulder chains.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Major's shoulder chains</part></link><link><target>File:ChainMaille Dragon's Back Bracelet or Roundmaille Weave.jpg</target><part>150px</part><part>thumb</part><part>A modern example of the use of ''mail'', a bracelet using the ''roundmaille weave''.</part></link>Mail remained in use as a decorative and possibly high-status symbol with military overtones long after its practical usefulness had passed. It was frequently used for the<space/><link><target>epaulette</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of military uniforms. It is still used in this form by the British<space/><link><target>Territorial Army (United Kingdom)</target><part>Territorial Army</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Royal Canadian Armoured Corps</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Canadian Army</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Mail has applications in sculpture and jewellery, especially when made out of precious metals or colourful<space/><link><target>anodizing</target><part>anodized</part></link><space/>metals. Mail artwork includes headdresses, Christmas ornaments, chess sets, and jewelry. For these non-traditional applications, hundreds of weaves or patterns have been invented.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://rescyou.deviantart.com/gallery/'>DeviantArt.com</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In film</heading><paragraph>In some films, knitted string spray-painted with a metallic paint is used instead of actual mail in order to cut down on cost (an example being<space/><italics><link><target>Monty Python and the Holy Grail</target></link></italics>, which was filmed on a very small budget). Films more dedicated to costume accuracy often use<space/><link><target>Acrylonitrile butadiene styrene</target><part>ABS plastic</part></link><space/>rings, for the lower cost and weight. Such ABS mail coats were made for<space/><link><target>The Lord of the Rings (film series)</target><part>''The Lord of the Rings'' film trilogy</part></link>, in addition to many metal coats. The metal coats are used rarely because of their weight, except in close-up filming where the appearance of ABS rings is distinguishable. A large scale example of the ABS mail used in the<space/><italics>Lord of the Rings</italics><space/>can be seen in the entrance to the<space/><link><target>Royal Armouries</target></link><space/>museum in Leeds in the form of a large curtain bearing the logo of the museum. It was acquired from the makers of the film's armour,<space/><link><target>Weta Workshop</target></link>, when the museum hosted an exhibition of WETA armour from their films. For the film<space/><italics><link><target>Mad Max Beyond Thunderdome</target></link></italics>, Tina Turner is said to have worn actual mail and she complained how heavy this was.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Kusari tabi.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Edo period 1800s Japanese (samurai) chain socks or<space/><italics>kusari tabi</italics></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Kusari katabira 6.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Japanese Edo period mail jacket<space/><italics><link><target>Commons:Category:Japanese chain mail</target><part>kusari katabira</part></link></italics>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Kusari kote.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Edo period Japanese (samurai) mail gauntlets<space/><italics>kusari han kote</italics>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Rriveted kusari kote.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>A rare example of Japanese riveted mail.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Kusari examples.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Examples of Edo period Japanese (samurai) mail<space/><italics>kusari</italics>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Riveted armor and plate.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Close up of Mughal riveted mail and plate coat<space/><italics>zirah Bagtar</italics>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Eastern riveted hood detail.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Close up detail of Mughal riveted mail hood<space/><italics>kulah zirah</italics>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Eastern riveted armor 1.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Mughal riveted mail and plate coat<space/><italics>zirah Bagtar</italics>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Eastern riveted armor hood.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Mughal riveted mail hood ''kulah zirah.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Suit of chain mail from DHM museum Berlin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>A suit of mail on display at the<space/><link><target>Deutsches Historisches Museum</target></link><space/>in Berlin.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Morgan Bible 28r detail.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&quot;<link><target>David (biblical king)</target><part>David</part></link><space/>rejects the unaccustomed armour&quot; (detail of fol. 28r of the 13th century<space/><link><target>Morgan Bible</target></link>). The image depicts a method of removing a<space/><link><target>hauberk</target></link>.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Indian theta or bar link mail 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Indian theta link mail (bar link mail), 17th century.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Ottoman krug front plate, detail view.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Ottoman riveted mail, 16th century.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>European riveted mail hauberk, close up view.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>European riveted mail.</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Mail-based armours</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><xhtml:small>(made from mail)</xhtml:small></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lorica hamata</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lorica plumata</target></link><space/>with scales attached to a backing of mail</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hauberk</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Plated mail</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tatami (Japanese armour)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Banded mail</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kusari (Japanese mail armour)</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Armours supplementary to mail</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><xhtml:small>(typically worn under mail armour:)</xhtml:small></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Gambeson</target></link><space/>(Also known as quilted armour or a padded jack)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><xhtml:small>(can be worn over mail armour)</xhtml:small></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mirror armour</target></link><space/>(supplementary oriental plates worn with mail)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Scale armour</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lamellar armour</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Coat of plates</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brigandine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Splint armour</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Transitional armour</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>others</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ring armour</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cataphract</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Proofing (armour)</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Chainmail</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Japanese chain mail</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.erikds.com/'>Erik D. Schmid/The Mail Research Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vam.ac.uk/res_cons/conservation/journal/consjournal37/thetreatment/index.html'>The Treatment of Mail on an Arm Guard from the Armoury of the Shah Shuja: Ethical Repair and in situ Documentation in Miniature</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.armatura.connectfree.co.uk/arma/mail.htm'>Excavated lorica hamata</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://corvuschainmaille.ning.com/'>Maillers Worldwide - weaves/tutorials/articles, and gallery photos</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mailleartisans.org/'>The Maille Artisans International League (MAIL) Hundreds of weaves/tutorials/articles, and gallery pictures</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.myarmoury.com/feature_mail.html'>&quot;Mail: Unchained&quot;, an article taking an in-depth look at the construction and usage of European chainmail</link></listitem><listitem>Construction tips<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://homepage.ntlworld.com/trevor.barker/farisles/guilds/armour/mail.htm'>Butted mail: A Mailmaker's Guide</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ringinator.com'>The Ringinator - Tool for making jump rings</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://realbeer.com/jjpalmer/HowtoChain.html'>The Apprentice Armorer's Illustrated Handbook For Making Mail</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theringlord.org/forum/'>The Ring Lord Chainmail Discussion Forum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cgmaille.com/tutorials.html'>Phong's Chainmaille Tutorials</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ringdb.candtdesigns.com/'>Ring Guide Sizing Specialty Square Rings to Round Weaves</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Ancient Roman originals can be seen on the pages of the Roman Military Equipment Web museum,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.romancoins.info/MilitaryEquipment.html'>Romancoins.info</link></listitem><listitem>http://artofchainmail.com/patterns/european/index.html</listitem><listitem>http://www.iranicaonline.org/articles/armor-ii</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chain-mail.weebly.com/'>Chain Mail 101: Learn all about making Chain Mail</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Elements of Medieval armor</target></template><template><target>Types of armour</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Mail (Armour)</target></template><link><target>Category:Medieval armour</target></link><link><target>Category:Military equipment of Antiquity</target></link><link><target>Category:Personal armour</target></link></paragraph></article>