<article title='Bakassi'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Coord</target><arg>4</arg><arg>35</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>8</arg><arg>36</arg><arg>E</arg><arg>type:landmark</arg><arg name="name">Bakassi</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cameroon Nigeria border coast.jpg</target><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>-<link><target>Cameroon</target></link><space/>border region on the coast from a 1963 map, with Biafrai peninsula in the middle</part></link><link><target>File:Un-bakassi.png</target><part>200px</part><part>right</part></link><bold>Bakassi</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>peninsula</target></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Africa</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target><part>Atlantic</part></link><space/><link><target>Gulf of Guinea</target></link>. It lies between the<space/><link><target>Cross River (Nigeria)</target><part>Cross River</part></link><space/>estuary, near the city of<space/><link><target>Calabar</target></link><space/>in the west, and the<space/><link><target>Rio del Ray</target></link><space/>estuary on the east. It is governed by<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link>, following the transfer of sovereignty from neighbouring<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>as a result of a judgment by the<space/><link><target>International Court of Justice</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/files/94/7453.pdf'>The Land and Maritime Boundary Between Cameroon and Nigeria (Cameroon v. Nigeria: Equatorial Guinea intervening)</link>, Judgment,<space/><italics>ICJ Reports</italics><space/>2002, p.303</extension><space/>On 22 November 2007, the Nigerian Senate rejected the transfer, since the<space/><link><target>Greentree Agreement</target></link><space/>ceding the area to Cameroon was contrary to Section 12(1) of the 1999 Constitution.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Rosenne's the World Court: What it is and how it Works<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Terry D. Gill, Harm Dotinga, [[Shabtai Rosenne]], Erik Jaap Molenaar, Alex G. Oude Elferink</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">United Nations Publications</arg><arg name="pages">212</arg><arg name="isbn">90-04-13816-1</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>Regardless, the territory was transferred to Cameroon on 14 August 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4789647.stm</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Geography and economy</heading><paragraph>The peninsula lies between latitudes 425 and 510N and longitudes 820 and 908E . It consists of a number of low-lying, largely mangrove covered islands covering an area of around 665&amp;nbsp;km (257&amp;nbsp;sq&amp;nbsp;mi). The population of Bakassi is the subject of some dispute, but is generally put at between 150,000 and 300,000 people.</paragraph><paragraph>Bakassi is situated at the extreme eastern end of the Gulf of Guinea, where the warm east-flowing<space/><link><target>Guinea Current</target></link><space/>(called Aya Efiat in<space/><link><target>Efik language</target><part>Efik</part></link>) meets the cold north-flowing<space/><link><target>Benguela Current</target></link><space/>(called Aya Ubenekang in Efik). These two ocean currents interact creating huge foamy breakers which constantly advance towards the shore, and building submarine shoals rich in fish, shrimps, and a wide variety of other marine life forms. This makes the Bakassi area a very fertile fishing ground, comparable only to<space/><link><target>Newfoundland (island)</target><part>Newfoundland</part></link><space/>in North America and<space/><link><target>Scandinavia</target></link><space/>in Western Europe. Most of the population make their living through fishing.</paragraph><paragraph>The peninsula is commonly described as &quot;oil-rich&quot;, though in fact no commercially viable deposits of oil have been discovered. However, the area has aroused considerable interest from oil companies in the light of the discovery of rich reserves of high grade<space/><link><target>crude oil</target></link><space/>in Nigeria. At least eight multinational oil companies have participated in the exploration of the peninsula and its offshore waters. In October 2012,<space/><link><target>China Petroleum &amp; Chemical Corporation</target></link><space/>announced it had discovered new oil and gas resources in the Bakassi region.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.menafn.com/menafn/46121fb4-d997-47a3-b228-ba8526460fc5/Addax-Petroleum-Discovers-New-Oil-Gas-Resources-Cameroon?src=main'>Addax Petroleum Discovers New Oil, Gas Resources in Cameroon</link>,<space/><italics>MenaFN.com</italics>, 10 October 2012</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Scramble for Africa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Queen Victoria</target></link><space/>signed a Treaty of Protection with the King and Chiefs of<space/><link><target>Akwa Akpa</target></link>, known to Europeans as<space/><link><target>Old Calabar</target></link><space/>on 10 September 1884. This enabled the<space/><link><target>British Empire</target></link><space/>to exercise control over the entire territory around Calabar, including Bakassi. The territory subsequently became<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>part of<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>, although the border was never permanently delineated. However, documents released by the Cameroonians, in parity with that of the British and Germans, clearly places Bakassi under Cameroonian Territory as a consequence of colonial era Anglo-German agreements. After<space/><link><target>Southern Cameroons</target></link><space/>voted in 1961 to leave Nigeria and became a part of Cameroon, Bakassi remained under<space/><link><target>Calabar</target></link><space/>administration in Nigeria until ICJ judgement of 2002.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nowa Omoigui,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.omoigui.com/files/the_bakassi_story.pdf'>The Bakassi Story</link>,<space/><italics>Omoigui.com</italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Population</heading><paragraph>Bakassi inhabitants are mainly The Oron people, the people of<space/><link><target>Cross River State</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Akwa Ibom State</target></link><space/>of Nigeria.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Territorial dispute</heading><paragraph>Nigeria and Cameroon have disputed the possession of Bakassi for some years, leading to considerable tension between the two countries. In 1981 the two countries went to the brink of war over Bakassi and another area around<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link>, at the other end of the two countries' common border. More armed clashes broke out in the early 1990s. In response, Cameroon took the matter to the<space/><link><target>International Court of Justice</target></link><space/>(ICJ) on 29 March 1994.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bola A. Akinterinwa,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nigerdeltacongress.com/earticles/equatorial_guinea_and_the_bakass.htm'>Equatorial Guinea and the Bakassi Dispute</link>,<space/><italics>Nigerdeltacongress.com</italics>, April 2002</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The case was extremely complex, requiring the court to review diplomatic exchanges dating back over 100 years. Nigeria relied largely on Anglo-German correspondence dating from 1885 as well as treaties between the colonial powers and the indigenous rulers in the area, particularly the 1884 Treaty of Protection. Cameroon pointed to the Anglo-German treaty of 1913, which defined<space/><link><target>sphere of influence</target><part>sphere of control</part></link><space/>in the region, as well as two agreements signed in the 1970s between Cameroon and Nigeria. These were the Yaound II Declaration of 4 April 1971 and the<space/><link><target>Maroua Declaration</target></link><space/>of 1 June 1975, which were devised to outline<space/><link><target>maritime boundary</target><part>maritime boundaries</part></link><space/>between the two countries following their independence. The line was drawn through the Cross River estuary to the west of the peninsula, thereby implying Cameroonian ownership over Bakassi. However, Nigeria never ratified the agreement, while Cameroon regarded it as being in force.</paragraph><heading level='3'>ICJ verdict</heading><paragraph>The ICJ delivered its judgment on 10 October 2002, finding (based principally on the Anglo-German agreements) that sovereignty over Bakassi did indeed rest with Cameroon. It instructed Nigeria to transfer possession of the peninsula, but did not require the inhabitants to move or to change their nationality. Cameroon was thus given a substantial Nigerian population and was required to protect their rights, infrastructure and welfare.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mike Chinedu Anekwe,<space/><link type='external' href='http://nigeriaworld.com/articles/2002/dec/273.html'>ICJ ruling on Bakassi: Matters arising</link>,<space/><italics>Nigeriaworld.com</italics>, 27 December 2002</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The verdict caused consternation in Nigeria. It aroused vitriolic comments from Nigerian officials and the Nigerian media alike. Chief<space/><link><target>Richard Akinjide</target></link>, a former Nigerian Attorney-General and Minister of Justice who had been a leading member of Nigeria's legal team, described the decision as &quot;50% international law and 50% international politics&quot;, &quot;blatantly biased and unfair&quot;, &quot;a total disaster&quot;, and a &quot;complete fraud&quot;. The Nigerian newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian (Nigeria)</target><part>The Guardian</part></link></italics><space/>went further, declaring that the judgment was &quot;a rape and unforeseen potential international conspiracy against Nigerian territorial integrity and sovereignty&quot; and &quot;part of a Western ploy to foment and perpetuate trouble in Africa&quot;. The outcome of the controversy was a<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>Nigerian refusal to withdraw its troops from Bakassi and transfer sovereignty. The Nigerian government did not, however, openly reject the judgment but instead called for an agreement that would provide &quot;peace with honour, with the interest and welfare of our people.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.thisdayonline.com/archive/2002/10/30/20021030news03.html<template><target>Dead link</target><arg>October 2012</arg><arg name="date">October 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The ICJ judgment was backed up by the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>, whose charter potentially allowed sanctions or even the use of force to enforce the court's ruling.<space/><link><target>Secretary-General</target></link><space/><link><target>Kofi Annan</target></link><space/>stepped in as a mediator and chaired a tripartite summit with the two countries' presidents on 15 November 2002, which established a commission to facilitate the peaceful implementation of the ICJ's judgement. A further summit was held on 31 January 2004. This has made significant progress, but the process has been complicated by the opposition of Bakassi's inhabitants to being transferred to Cameroon.<extension extension_name='ref'>By Gilbert da Costa,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.wwenglish.com/en/voa/stan/2006/08/2006080813544.htm'></link>,<space/><italics>VOA</italics>, 8 August 2006</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bakassian leaders threatened to seek independence if Nigeria renounced sovereignty. This secession was announced on 9 July 2006, as the &quot;<link><target>Democratic Republic of Bakassi</target></link>&quot;. The decision was reportedly made at a meeting on 2 July 2006 and<space/><link><target>Vanguard (Nigeria)</target><part>The Vanguard</part></link><space/>newspaper of Nigeria reported the decision to secede. The decision was reportedly made by groups of militants including<space/><link><target>Southern Cameroons</target></link><space/>under the aegis of<space/><link><target>Southern Cameroons Peoples Organisation</target></link><space/>(SCAPO),<space/><link><target>Bakassi Movement for Self-Determination</target></link><space/>(BAMOSD), and the<space/><link><target>Movement for the Emancipation of the Niger Delta</target></link><space/>(MEND).<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.postnewsline.com/2008/07/rebels-declare.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Resolution</heading><paragraph>On 13 June 2006, President<space/><link><target>Olusegun Obasanjo</target></link><space/>of Nigeria and President<space/><link><target>Paul Biya</target></link><space/>of Cameroon resolved the dispute in talks led by UN Secretary General<space/><link><target>Kofi Annan</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link>. Obasanjo agreed to withdraw Nigerian troops within 60 days and to leave the territory completely in Cameroonian control within the next two years. Annan said, &quot;With today's agreement on the Bakassi peninsula, a comprehensive resolution of the dispute is within our grasp. The momentum achieved must be sustained.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://allafrica.com/stories/200606130612.html'>Cameroon: Presidents Obasanjo And Biya Shake Hands On Disputed Bakassi Peninsula</link>,<space/><italics>Allafrica</italics>, 13 June 2006</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Withdrawal</heading><paragraph>Nigeria began to withdraw its forces, comprising some 3,000 troops, beginning 1 August 2006, and a ceremony on 14 August marked the formal handover of the northern part of the peninsula. The remainder stayed under Nigerian civil authority for two more years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4789647.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Nigeria hands Bakassi to Cameroon<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 August 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 April 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 22 November 2007, the<space/><link><target>Senate of Nigeria</target><part>Nigerian Senate</part></link><space/>passed a resolution declaring that the withdrawal from the Bakassi Peninsula was illegal. The government took no action, and handed the final parts of Bakassi over to Cameroon on 14 August 2008 as planned, but a Federal High Court had stated this should be delayed until all accommodations for resettled Bakassians had been settled; the government did not seem to plan to heed this court order,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7537020.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Nigeria to appeal Bakassi delay<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 August 2008<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">31 March 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>and set the necessary mechanisms into motion to override it. Fishermen displaced from Bakassi were first settled in a landlocked area called<space/><link><target>New Bakassi</target></link>, which they claimed was already inhabited and not suitable for fishermen like them but only for farmers.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://english.people.com.cn/90001/90777/90855/6464970.html'>Nigerian High Court stops government on Bakassi handover</link>,<space/><italics>People's Daily Online</italics>, 1 August 2008</extension><space/>The displaced people were then moved to Akpabuyo, and eventually established a new community of<space/><link><target>Dayspring, Nigeria</target><part>Dayspring</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title">Hasten PVC distribution, Bakassi indigenes beg INEC<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 February 2015<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Nigerian Eye<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nigerianeye.com/2015/02/hasten-pvc-distribution-bakassi.html<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6XzSDbpo5<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">22 April 2015<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the formal handover of Bakassi by Nigeria to Cameroon in 2006, the territory of Bakassi is still reflected as part of the 774 local governments in Nigeria as embodied in the First Schedule, Part I of the 1999 Constitution of the Federal Republic of Nigeria, 1999.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.nigeria-law.org/ConstitutionOfTheFederalRepublicOfNigeria.htm</extension><space/>After the Nigerian 2015 General Elections, Nigeria's 8th National Assembly still accommodates the Calabar-South/Akpabuyo/Bakassi Federal Constituency represented by Hon. Essien Ekpeyong Ayi of the<space/><link><target>People's Democratic Party (Nigeria)</target><part>People's Democratic Party</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.premiumtimesng.com/news/top-news/182259-list-new-house-of-reps-members-for-nigerias-8th-national-assembly.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.icj-cij.org/docket/index.php?pr=294&amp;amp;code=cn&amp;amp;p1=3&amp;amp;p2=3&amp;amp;p3=6&amp;amp;case=94&amp;amp;k=74'>International Court of Justice, press release on decision</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thisdayonline.com/archive/2002/10/24/20021024rec01.html'>Nigerian Government official statement in response to the ruling</link>[Adey]</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/5255246.stm'>BBC News report on handover, 8 August 2006</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/7559895.stm'>BBC News report on handover, 14 August 2008</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://crossriverforum.org/bakassi.html'>Archive of Articles on the Bakassi conundrum</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>LGAs and communities of Cross River State</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Peninsulas of Cameroon</target></link><link><target>Category:Landforms of Nigeria</target></link><link><target>Category:Territorial disputes of Cameroon</target></link><link><target>Category:Territorial disputes of Nigeria</target></link><link><target>Category:CameroonNigeria border</target></link></paragraph></article>