<article title='Agarose_gel_electrophoresis'><paragraph><link><target>Image:DNAgel4wiki.png</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Digital image of 3 plasmid restriction digests run on a 1% w/v agarose gel, 3 volt/cm, stained with ethidium bromide. The DNA size marker is a commercial 1&amp;nbsp;kbp ladder. The position of the wells and direction of DNA migration is noted.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Agarose gel electrophoresis</bold><space/>is a method of<space/><link><target>gel electrophoresis</target></link><space/>used in<space/><link><target>biochemistry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>molecular biology</target></link>,microbial genetics, and clinical chemistry to separate a mixed population of DNA or proteins in a matrix of<space/><link><target>agarose</target></link>. The proteins may be separated by charge and/or size (<link><target>isoelectric focusing</target></link><space/>agarose electrophoresis is essentially size independent), and the<space/><link><target>DNA</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>RNA</target></link><space/>fragments by length.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Kryndushkin DS, Alexandrov IM, Ter-Avanesyan MD, Kushnirov VV</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Yeast [PSI+] prion aggregates are formed by small Sup35 polymers fragmented by Hsp104<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Biological Chemistry<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>278<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>49<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>49636–43<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>14507919<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1074/jbc.M307996200</arg></template></extension><space/>Biomolecules are separated by applying an<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>to move the charged molecules through an<space/><link><target>agarose</target></link><space/>matrix, and the biomolecules are separated by size in the agarose gel matrix.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sambrook J, Russel DW (2001). Molecular Cloning: A Laboratory Manual 3rd Ed. Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press. Cold Spring Harbor, NY.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Agarose gels are easy to cast and are particularly suitable for separating DNA of size range most often encountered in laboratories, which accounts for the popularity of its use. The separated DNA may be viewed with stain, most commonly under UV light, and the DNA fragments can be extracted from the gel with relative ease. Most agarose gels used are between 0.7 - 2% dissolved in a suitable electrophoresis buffer.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Properties of agarose gel</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Two percent Agarose Gel in Borate Buffer cast in a Gel Tray (Front, angled).jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>An agarose gel cast in tray used for gel electrophoresis</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Agarose gel is a three-dimensional matrix formed of helical agarose molecules in supercoiled bundles that are aggregated into three-dimensional structures with channels and pores through which biomolecules can pass.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual<space/></arg><arg name="author">Joseph Sambrook, David Russell<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 5, protocol 1<space/></arg><arg name="page">5.4<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87969-577-4<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The 3-D structure is held together with hydrogen bonds and can therefore be disrupted by heating back to a liquid state. The melting temperature is different from the gelling temperature, depending on the sources, agarose gel has a gelling temperature of 35-42&amp;nbsp;C and a melting temperature of 85-95&amp;nbsp;C. Low-melting and low-gelling agaroses made through chemical modifications are also available.</paragraph><paragraph>Agarose gel has large pore size and good gel strength that made it particularly suitable as an anticonvection medium for the electrophoresis of DNA and large protein molecules. The pore size of a 1% gel has been estimated from 100&amp;nbsp;nm to 200-500&amp;nbsp;nm,<extension extension_name='ref' name="zimm"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="viovy"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Reviews of Modern Physics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>72<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>813–872<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">Electrophoresis of DNA and other polyelectrolytes: Physical mechanisms</arg><arg name="author">Jean-Louis Viovy<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/RevModPhys.72.813<space/></arg><arg name="bibcode">2000RvMP...72..813V</arg></template></extension><space/>and its gel strength allows gels as dilute as 0.15% to form a slab for gel electrophoresis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="serwer"></extension><space/>Low-concentration gels (0.1 - 0.2%) however are fragile and therefore hard to handle. Agarose gel has lower resolving power than polyacrylamide gel for DNA but has a greater range of separation, and is therefore used for DNA fragments of usually 50-20,000 bp in size. The limit of resolution for standard agarose gel electrophoresis is around 750 kb, but resolution of over 6 Mb is possible with<space/><link><target>pulsed field gel electrophoresis</target></link><space/>(PFGE).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual<space/></arg><arg name="author">Joseph Sambrook, David Russell<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 5, protocol 1<space/></arg><arg name="page">5.2–5.3<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87969-577-4<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>It can also be used to separate large proteins, and it is the preferred matrix for the gel electrophoresis of particles with effective radii larger than 5-10&amp;nbsp;nm. A 0.9% agarose gel has pores large enough for the entry of<space/><link><target>bacteriophage T4</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="serwer"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Agarose gels: Properties and use for electrophoresis<space/></arg><arg name="author">Philip Serwer<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Electrophoresis<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="pages">375–382<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1002/elps.1150040602</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The agarose polymer contains charged groups, in particular<space/><link><target>pyruvate</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sulphate</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="lonza"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://bio.lonza.com/uploads/tx_mwaxmarketingmaterial/Lonza_BenchGuides_SourceBook_Appendix_B_-_Agarose_Physical_Chemistry.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Appendix B: Agarose Physical Chemistry<space/></arg><arg name="work">Lonza Group<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>These negatively charged groups create a flow of water in the opposite direction to the movement of DNA in a process called<space/><link><target>electroendosmosis</target></link><space/>(EEO), and can therefore retard the movement of DNA and cause blurring of bands. Higher concentration gel would have higher electroosmotic flow. Low EEO agarose is therefore generally preferred for use in agarose<space/><link><target>gel electrophoresis of nucleic acids</target></link>, but high EEO agarose may be used for other purposes. The lower sulphate content of low EEO agarose, particularly low-melting point (LMP) agarose, is also beneficial in cases where the DNA extracted from gel is to be used for further manipulation as the presence of contaminating sulphates may affect some subsequent procedures, such as<space/><link><target>ligation (molecular biology)</target><part>ligation</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>PCR</target></link>. Zero EEO agaroses however are undesirable for some applications as they may be made by adding positively charged group and such groups can affect subsequent enzyme reactions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual<space/></arg><arg name="author">Joseph Sambrook, David Russell<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 5, protocol 1<space/></arg><arg name="page">5.7<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87969-577-4<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Migration of nucleic acids in agarose gel</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Gel electrophoresis of nucleic acids</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Factors affecting migration of nucleic acid in gel</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Plasmid miniprep.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>280px</part><part>Gels of plasmid preparations usually show a major band of supercoiled DNA with other fainter bands in the same lane. Note that by convention DNA gel is displayed with smaller DNA fragments nearer to the bottom of the gel. This is because historically DNA gels were run vertically and the smaller DNA fragments move downwards faster.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A number of factors can affect the migration of nucleic acids: the dimension of the gel pores (gel concentration), size of DNA being electrophoresed, the voltage used, the ionic strength of the buffer, and the concentration of intercalating dye such as ethidium bromide if used during electrophoresis.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>G. Lucotte, F. Baneyx<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Introduction to Molecular Cloning Techniques<space/></arg><arg name="page">32<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley-Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0471188490<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Smaller molecules travel faster than larger molecules in gel, and double-stranded DNA moves at a rate that is inversely proportional to the log<xhtml:sub>10</xhtml:sub><space/>of the number of base pairs. This relationship however breaks down with very large DNA fragments, and separation of very large DNA fragments requires the use of<space/><link><target>pulsed field gel electrophoresis</target></link><space/>(PFGE).</paragraph><paragraph>For standard agarose gel electrophoresis, larger molecules are resolved better using a low concentration gel while smaller molecules separate better at high concentration gel. High concentrations gel however requires longer run times (sometimes days).</paragraph><paragraph>The movement of the DNA may be affected by the<space/><link><target>Chemical structure</target><part>conformation</part></link><space/>of the DNA molecule, for example,<space/><link><target>DNA supercoil</target><part>supercoiled DNA</part></link><space/>usually moves faster than relaxed DNA because it is tightly coiled and hence more compact. In a normal plasmid DNA preparation, multiple forms of DNA may be present.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="title">DNA Structure and Function<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Richard R. Sinden<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>97<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Academic Press Inc<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0126457506</arg></template></extension><space/>Gel electrophoresis of the plasmids would normally show the negatively supercoiled form as the main band, while nicked DNA (open circular form) and the relaxed closed circular form appears as minor bands. The rate at which the various forms move however can change using different electrophoresis conditions,<extension extension_name='ref' name="sambrook1"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Molecular Cloning - A Laboratory Manual<space/></arg><arg name="author">Joseph Sambrook, David Russell<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 5, protocol 1<space/></arg><arg name="page">5.5-5.6<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87969-577-4<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and the mobility of larger circular DNA may be more strongly affected than linear DNA by the pore size of the gel.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Biochim Biophys Acta<space/></arg><arg name="year">1972<space/></arg><arg name="volume">269<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">192–200<space/></arg><arg name="title">The gel electrophoresis of DNA<space/></arg><arg name="author">Aaij C, Borst P<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">5063906<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/0005-2787(72)90426-1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ethidium bromide which intercalates into circular DNA can change the charge, length, as well as the superhelicity of the DNA molecule, therefore its presence in gel during electrophoresis can affect its movement. Agarose gel electrophoresis can be used to resolve circular DNA with different supercoiling topology.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Biochemistry<space/></arg><arg name="author">Donald Voet and Judith G. Voet<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="pages">877–878<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0471586517<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>DNA damage due to increased<space/><link><target>cross-link</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>will also reduce electrophoretic DNA migration in a dose-dependent way.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1016/S0887-2333(00)00022-9<space/></arg><arg name="author">Blasiak J, Trzeciak A, Malecka-Panas E, Drzewoski J, Wojewódzka M<space/></arg><arg name="title">In vitro genotoxicity of ethanol and acetaldehyde in human lymphocytes and the gastrointestinal tract mucosa cells<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Toxicology in Vitro<space/></arg><arg name="volume">14<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="pages">287–295<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="pmid">10906435</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1093/mutage/gep008<space/></arg><arg name="author">Lu Y, Morimoto K<space/></arg><arg name="title">Is habitual alcohol drinking associated with reduced electrophoretic DNA migration in peripheral blood leukocytes from ALDH2-deficient male Japanese?<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Mutagenesis<space/></arg><arg name="volume">24<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="pages">303–308<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://mutage.oxfordjournals.org/content/24/4/303.long<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="pmid">19286920</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The rate of migration of the DNA is proportional to the voltage applied, i.e. the higher the voltage, the faster the DNA moves. The resolution of large DNA fragments however is lower at high voltage. The mobility of DNA may also change in an unsteady field - in a field that is periodically reversed, the mobility of DNA of a particular size may drop significantly at a particular cycling frequency.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zimm"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Quarterly Reviews of Biophysics<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="volume">25<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">171–204<space/></arg><arg name="title">Problems and prospects in the theory of gel electrophoresis of DNA<space/></arg><arg name="author">Zimm BH, Levene SD<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.damtp.cam.ac.uk/user/gold/pdfs/teaching/ufk_papers/electrokinetics/zimm.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>1518924<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/s0033583500004662</arg></template></extension><space/>This phenomenon can result in band inversion in field inversion gel electrophoresis (FIGE), whereby larger DNA fragments move faster than smaller ones.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Migration anomalies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Smiley&quot; gels - this edge effect is caused when the voltage applied is too high for the gel concentration used.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>G. Lucotte, F. Baneyx<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Introduction to Molecular Cloning Techniques<space/></arg><arg name="page">41<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley-Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0471188490<space/></arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>Overloading of DNA - overloading of DNA slows down the migration of DNA fragments.</listitem><listitem>Contamination - presence of impurities, such as salts or proteins can affect the movement of the DNA.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Mechanism of migration and separation</heading><paragraph>The negative charge of its phosphate backbone moves the DNA towards the positively charged anode during electrophoresis. However, the migration of DNA molecules in solution, in the absence of a gel matrix, is independent of molecular weight during electrophoresis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zimm"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="old &amp; primrose"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Principle of Gene Manipulation - An Introduction to Genetic Engineering<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Robert W. Old, Sandy B. Primrose<space/></arg><arg name="page">9<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell Scientific<space/></arg><arg name="edition">5th<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780632037124<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The gel matrix is therefore responsible for the separation of DNA by size during electrophoresis, and a number of models exist to explain the mechanism of separation of biomolecules in gel matrix. A widely accepted one is the Ogston model which treats the polymer matrix as a sieve. A globular protein or a<space/><link><target>random coil</target></link><space/>DNA moves through the interconnected pores, and the movement of larger molecules is more likely to be impeded and slowed down by collisions with the gel matrix, and the molecules of different sizes can therefore be separated in this sieving process.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zimm"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Ogston model however breaks down for large molecules whereby the pores are significantly smaller than size of the molecule. For DNA molecules of size greater than 1 kb, a<space/><link><target>reptation</target></link><space/>model (or its variants) is most commonly used. This model assumes that the DNA can crawl in a &quot;snake-like&quot; fashion (hence &quot;reptation&quot;) through the pores as an elongated molecule. At higher electric field strength, this turned into a biased reptation model, whereby the leading end of the molecule become strongly biased in the forward direction and pulls the rest of the molecule along.<extension extension_name='ref' name="microfluidics"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Microfluidics for Biological Applications<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Tian, Wei-Cheng; Finehout, Erin<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 4 - Genetic Analysis in Miniaturized Electrophoresis Systems<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Li Zhu, Hong Wang<space/></arg><arg name="page">125<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Springer<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-387-09480-9<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Real-time fluorescence microscopy of stained molecules, however, showed more subtle dynamics during electrophoresis, with the DNA showing considerable elasticity as it alternately stretching in the direction of the applied field and then contracting into a ball, or becoming hooked into a U-shape when it gets caught on the polymer fibres.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Smith, S.B., Aldridge, P.K., & Callis, J.B.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Observation of individual DNA molecules undergoing gel electrophoresis<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume">243<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4888<space/></arg><arg name="pages">203–206<space/></arg><arg name="year">1989<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>2911733<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1126/science.2911733</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Nature<space/></arg><arg name="year">1989</arg><arg name="volume">338<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6215</arg><arg name="pages">520–2<space/></arg><arg name="title">Conformational dynamics of individual DNA molecules during gel electrophoresis<space/></arg><arg name="author">Schwartz DC, Koval M</arg><arg name="pmid">2927511<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1038/338520a0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>General procedure</heading><paragraph>The details of an agarose gel electrophoresis experiment may vary depending on methods, but most follow a general procedure.<link><target>File:Agarose Gel Electrophoresis - Assembling the Rig and Loading-Running the Gel.webm</target><part>thumb</part><part>none</part><part>Video showing assembly of the rig and loading/running of the gel.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Casting of gel</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Loading DNA samples into an agarose gel for electrophoresis - CPHST - USDA photo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>180px</part><part>Loading DNA samples into the wells of an agarose gel using a multi-channel pipette.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The gel is prepared by dissolving the agarose powder in an appropriate buffer, such as TAE or TBE, to be used in electrophoresis.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Agarose Gel Electrophoresis for the Separation of DNA Fragments<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.jove.com/video/3923/agarose-gel-electrophoresis-for-the-separation-of-dna-fragments<space/></arg><arg name="author">Pei Yun Lee, John Costumbrado, Chih-Yuan Hsu, Yong Hoon Kim<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Journal of Visualized Experiments<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>22546956<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The agarose is dispersed in the buffer before heating it to near-boiling point, but avoid boiling. The melted agarose is allowed to cool sufficiently before pouring the solution into a cast as the cast may warp or crack if the agarose solution is too hot. A comb is placed in the cast to create wells for loading sample, and the gel should be completely set before use.</paragraph><paragraph>The concentration of gel affects the resolution of DNA separation. For a standard agarose gel electrophoresis, a 0.8% gives good separation or resolution of large 510kb DNA fragments, while 2% gel gives good resolution for small 0.21kb fragments. 1% gels is often used for a standard electrophoresis.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Agarose gel electrophoresis (basic method)<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.methodbook.net/dna/agarogel.html</arg><arg name="work">Biological Protocols</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 August 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>The concentration is measured in weight of agarose over volume of buffer used (g/ml). High percentage gels are often brittle and may not set evenly, while low percentage gels (0.1-0.2%) are fragile and not easy to handle. Low-melting-point (LMP) agarose gels are also more fragile than normal agarose gel. Low-melting point agarose may be used on its own or simultaneously with standard agarose for the separation and isolation of DNA.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal"><space/>Biotechniques</arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="volume">10<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">171-2</arg><arg name="title">Simultaneous use of standard and low-melting agarose for the separation and isolation of DNA by electrophoresis<space/></arg><arg name="authors">Fotadar U1, Shapiro LE, Surks MI<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">2059440</arg></template></extension><space/>PFGE and FIGE are often done with high percentage agarose gels.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Loading of samples</heading><paragraph>Once the gel has set, the comb is removed, leaving wells where DNA samples can be loaded. Loading buffer is mixed with the DNA sample before the mixture is loaded into the wells. The loading buffer contains a dense compound, which may be glycerol, sucrose, or<space/><link><target>Ficoll</target></link>, that raises the density of the sample so that the DNA sample may sink to the bottom of the well. If the DNA sample contains residual ethanol after its preparation, it may float out of the well. The loading buffer also include colored dyes such as<space/><link><target>xylene cyanol</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>bromophenol blue</target></link><space/>used to monitor the progress of the electrophoresis. The DNA samples are loaded using a<space/><link><target>pipette</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Electrophoresis</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Electrophoresis - Moving along gel.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Agarose gel slab in electrophoresis tank with bands of dyes indicating progress of the electrophoresis. The DNA moves towards anode.</part></link>Agarose gel electrophoresis is most commonly done horizontally in a submarine mode whereby the slab gel is completely submerged in buffer during electrophoresis. It is also possible, but less common, to perform the electrophoresis vertically, as well as horizontally with the gel raised on agarose legs using an appropriate apparatus.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Physical Biochemistry: Applications to Biochemistry and Molecular Biology<space/></arg><arg name="author">David Freifelder<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">WH Freeman<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>292–293<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0716714446</arg></template></extension><space/>The buffer used in the gel is the same as the running buffer in the electrophoresis tank, which is why electrophoresis in the submarine mode is possible with agarose gel.</paragraph><paragraph>For optimal resolution of DNA greater than 2<template><target>Spaces</target></template>kb in size in standard gel electrophoresis, 5 to 8 V/cm is recommended (the distance in cm refers to the distance between electrodes, therefore this recommended voltage would be 5 to 8 multiplied by the distance between the electrodes in cm).<extension extension_name='ref' name="sambrook1"></extension><space/>Voltage may also be limited by the fact that it heats the gel and may cause the gel to melt if it is run at high voltage for a prolonged period, especially if the gel used is LMP agarose gel. Too high a voltage may also reduce resolution, as well as causing band streaking for large DNA molecules. Too low a voltage may lead to broadening of band for small DNA fragments due to dispersion and diffusion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://bio.lonza.com/uploads/tx_mwaxmarketingmaterial/Lonza_BenchGuides_SourceBook_Section_III_-_Loading_and_Running_DNA_in_Agarose_Gels.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Section III: Loading and Running DNA in Agarose Gels<space/></arg><arg name="work">Lonza Group<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since DNA is not visible in natural light, the progress of the electrophoresis is monitored using colored dyes. Xylene cyanol (light blue color) comigrates large DNA fragments, while Bromophenol blue (dark blue) comigrates with the smaller fragments. Less commonly used dyes include<space/><link><target>Cresol Red</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Orange G</target></link><space/>which migrate ahead of bromophenol blue. A<space/><link><target>Molecular weight size marker</target><part>DNA marker</part></link><space/>is also run together for the estimation of the molecular weight of the DNA fragments. Note however that the size of a circular DNA like plasmids cannot be accurately gauged using standard markers unless it has been linearized by<space/><link><target>restriction digest</target></link>, alternatively a supercoiled DNA marker may be used.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Staining and visualization</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:AgarosegelUV.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The gel with UV illumination: DNA stained with<space/><link><target>ethidium bromide</target></link><space/>appears as glowing orange bands.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>DNA as well as RNA are normally visualized by staining with<space/><link><target>ethidium bromide</target></link>, which intercalates into the major grooves of the DNA and fluoresces under UV light. The ethidium bromide may be added to the agarose solution before it gels, or the DNA gel may be stained later after electrophoresis. Destaining of the gel is not necessary but may produce better images. Other methods of staining are available; examples are<space/><link><target>SYBR Green I</target><part>SYBR Green</part></link>,<space/><link><target>GelRed</target></link>,<space/><link><target>methylene blue</target></link>,<space/><link><target>brilliant cresyl blue</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nile blue</target></link><space/>sulphate, and<space/><link><target>crystal violet</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ncbe.reading.ac.uk/ncbe/protocols/DNA/PDF/DNA14.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">DNA revealed<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>National Centre for Biotechnology education<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Reading<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>SYBR Green, GelRed and other similar commercial products are sold as safer alternatives to ethidium bromide as it has been shown to be<space/><link><target>mutagenic</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Ames test</target></link>, although the<space/><link><target>carcinogenicity</target></link><space/>of ethidium bromide has not actually been established. SYBR Green requires the use of a blue-light transilluminator. DNA stained with crystal violet can be viewed under natural light without the use of a UV transilluminator which is an advantage, however it may not produce a strong band.</paragraph><paragraph>When stained with ethidium bromide, the gel is viewed with an<space/><link><target>ultraviolet</target></link><space/>(UV) transilluminator. Standard transilluminators use wavelengths of 302/312-nm (UV-B), however exposure of DNA to UV radiation for as little as 45 seconds can produce damage to DNA and affect subsequent procedures, for example reducing the efficiency of<space/><link><target>Transformation efficiency</target><part>transformation</part></link>,<space/><italics>in vitro</italics><space/><link><target>Transcription (genetics)</target><part>transcription</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>PCR</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Biotechniques<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="volume">21<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5<space/></arg><arg name="pages">898–903<space/></arg><arg name="title">Protection of DNA during preparative agarose gel electrophoresis against damage induced by ultraviolet light<space/></arg><arg name="author">Gründemann D, Schömig E.<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">8922632<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.biotechniques.com/multimedia/archive/00009/96215rr02_9961a.pdf<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Exposure of the DNA to UV radiation therefore should be limited. Using a higher wavelength of 365&amp;nbsp;nm (UV-A range) causes less damage to the DNA but also produces much weaker fluorescence with ethidium bromide. Where multiple wavelengths can be selected in the transillumintor, the shorter wavelength would be used to capture images, while the longer wavelength should be used when it is necessary to work on the gel for any extended period of time.</paragraph><paragraph>The transilluminator apparatus may also contain image capture devices, such as a digital or polaroid camera, that allow an image of the gel to be taken or printed.<link><target>File:Cutting of the agarose gel.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Cutting out agarose gel slices. Protective equipment must be worn when using UV transilluminator.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Downstream procedures</heading><paragraph>The separated DNA bands are often used for further procedures, and a DNA band may be cut out of the gel as a slice, dissolved and purified. The gels may also be used for blotting techniques.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Buffers</heading><paragraph>In general, the ideal buffer should have good conductivity, produce less heat and have a long life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Gel electrophoresis – Principles and Basics<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Sameh Magdeldin<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">InTech<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-953-51-0458-2<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>There are a number of buffers used for agarose electrophoresis; common ones for nucleic acids include<space/><link><target>TAE buffer</target><part>Tris/Acetate/EDTA</part></link><space/>(TAE) and<space/><link><target>TBE buffer</target><part>Tris/Borate/EDTA</part></link><space/>(TBE). Many other buffers have been proposed, e.g.<space/><link><target>LB buffer</target><part>lithium borate</part></link><space/>(LB), which is almost never used, based on Pubmed citations, iso electric histidine, pK matched goods buffers, etc.; in most cases the purported rationale is lower current (less heat) and or matched ion mobilities, which leads to longer buffer life. Tris-phosphate buffer has high buffering capacity but cannot be used if DNA extracted is to be used in phosphate sensitive reaction. Borate is problematic; Borate can polymerize, and/or interact with cis diols such as those found in RNA. TAE has the lowest buffering capacity but provides the best resolution for larger DNA. This means a lower voltage and more time, but a better product. LB is relatively new and is ineffective in resolving fragments larger than 5 kbp; However, with its low conductivity, a much higher voltage could be used (up to 35 V/cm), which means a shorter analysis time for routine electrophoresis. As low as one base pair size difference could be resolved in 3% agarose gel with an extremely low conductivity medium (1 mM lithium borate).<extension extension_name='ref'>Brody, J.R., Kern, S.E. (2004): History and principles of conductive media for standard DNA electrophoresis.<space/><italics>Anal Biochem.</italics><space/>333(1):1-13. PMID 15351274<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.cc.ahs.chula.ac.th/Molmed/DNA%20electro%27s%20conductive%20media.pdf'>PDF</link></extension><space/>The buffers used contain EDTA to inactivate many nucleases which require divalent cation for their function.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Applications</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Estimation of the size of DNA molecules following restriction enzyme digestion, e.g. in<space/><link><target>restriction enzyme</target><part>restriction mapping</part></link><space/>of cloned DNA.</listitem><listitem>Analysis of<space/><link><target>PCR</target></link><space/>products, e.g. in molecular<space/><link><target>Preimplantation genetic diagnosis</target><part>genetic diagnosis</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>genetic fingerprinting</target></link></listitem><listitem>Separation of DNA fragments for extraction and purification.</listitem><listitem>Separation of restricted genomic DNA prior to<space/><link><target>Southern blot</target><part>Southern transfer</part></link>, or of RNA prior to<space/><link><target>Northern Blot</target><part>Northern transfer</part></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Agarose gels are easily cast and handled compared to other matrices and nucleic acids are not chemically altered during electrophoresis. Samples are also easily recovered. After the experiment is finished, the resulting gel can be stored in a plastic bag in a refrigerator.</paragraph><paragraph>Electrophoresis is performed in buffer solutions to reduce pH changes due to the electric field, which is important because the charge of DNA and RNA depends on pH, but running for too long can exhaust the buffering capacity of the solution. Further, different preparations of genetic material may not migrate consistently with each other, for morphological or other reasons.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Gel electrophoresis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Immunodiffusion</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Immunoelectrophoresis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Northern blot</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>PCR</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Restriction endonuclease</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Southern blot</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://arbl.cvmbs.colostate.edu/hbooks/genetics/biotech/gels/index.html'>How to run a DNA or RNA gel</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://arbl.cvmbs.colostate.edu/hbooks/genetics/biotech/gels/virgel.html'>Animation of gel analysis of DNA restriction fragments</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jove.com/video/3923/agarose-gel-electrophoresis-for-the-separation-of-dna-fragments'>Video and article of agarose gel electrophoresis</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/7.02/virtual_lab/RDM/RDM1virtuallab.html'>Step by step photos of running a gel and extracting DNA</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://maradydd.livejournal.com/417631.html'>Drinking straw electrophoresis!</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://en.wikiversity.org/w/index.php?title=Agarose_gel_electrophoresis&amp;amp;action=edit&amp;amp;redlink=1'>A typical method from wikiversity</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://teach.genetics.utah.edu/content/build_gel_box.pdf'>Building a gel electrophoresis chamber</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Agarose Gel Electrophoresis</target></template><link><target>Category:Biological techniques and tools</target></link><link><target>Category:Molecular biology</target></link><link><target>Category:Electrophoresis</target></link><link><target>Category:Polymerase chain reaction</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>