<article title='Eureka_Rebellion'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Eureka Stockade</arg></template><template><target>Use Australian English</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="conflict">The Eureka Rebellion
</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Eureka stockade battle.jpg|300px]]
</arg><arg name="caption">Eureka Stockade Riot. J. B. Henderson (1854) watercolour
</arg><arg name="date">3 December 1854
</arg><arg name="place"><space/>[[Eureka, Victoria|Eureka]], [[Ballarat]], Victoria, Australia
</arg><arg name="result">Miners' rebellion defeated by the Victorian authorities
</arg><arg name="combatant1">{{flagicon|UKGBI}} [[Victoria (Australia)#Creation of separate colony of Victoria|Colony of Victoria]]
* {{flagicon|UKGBI}} [[British Army]]
* {{flagicon|UKGBI}} [[Victoria Police]]
</arg><arg name="combatant2"><space/>[[File:Eureka Flag.svg|23px]] Stockade insurgents
</arg><arg name="commander1"><space/>[[John Wellesley Thomas|J. W. Thomas]]<br/>[[Charles Pasley (engineer)|Charles Pasley]]
</arg><arg name="commander2"><space/>[[File:Eureka Flag.svg|23px]] [[Peter Lalor]] [[Wounded in action|+]]<br/>[[Henry Ross]] [[Wounded in action|+]] [[Surrender (military)|#]]
</arg><arg name="strength1">276
</arg><arg name="strength2"><space/>120 
</arg><arg name="casualties1"><space/>6 dead
</arg><arg name="casualties2"><space/>22 - 60 dead (estimated),<ref name</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Eureka Rebellion</bold><space/>in 1854 was a<space/><link><target>rebellion</target></link><space/>of gold<space/><link><target>miners</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ballarat</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Victoria (Australia)</target><part>Victoria</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>, who revolted against the colonial authority of the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>. The Battle of the<space/><bold>Eureka Stockade</bold>, by which the rebellion is popularly known, was fought between miners and the<space/><link><target>Colonial forces of Australia</target></link><space/>on 3 December 1854 at<space/><link><target>Eureka, Victoria</target><part>Eureka Lead</part></link><space/>and named for the<space/><link><target>stockade</target></link><space/>structure erected by miners during the conflict.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Wendy Lewis]], Simon Balderstone and John Bowan<space/></arg><arg name="title">Events That Shaped Australia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New Holand<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-74110-492-9<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The rebellion lasted for less than half an hour and resulted in the deaths of at least 27 people, the majority of whom were rebels.</paragraph><paragraph>The event was the culmination of a period of<space/><link><target>civil disobedience</target></link><space/>in the Ballarat region during the<space/><link><target>Victorian gold rush</target></link><space/>with miners objecting to the expense of a<space/><link><target>Miner's Licence</target></link>, taxation via the licence without representation and the actions of the government, the police and military.<extension extension_name='ref' name="licence">&quot;The government was forced to abandon the<space/><link><target>Miner's Licence</target><part>licence</part></link><space/>substitute it with a cheaper<space/><link><target>Miner's Right</target><part>miner's right</part></link><space/>which also conferred on men the right to vote&quot; The<space/><italics>Victorians: Arriving</italics>; Richard Broome, 1984. P.92.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Withers, WB History of Ballarat and some Ballarat Reminiscences, Facsimile Edition Published by Ballarat Heritage Services 1999, First Published 1800, Pp 6364.</extension><space/>The local rebellion grew from a<space/><link><target>Ballarat Reform League</target></link><space/>movement and culminated in the erection by the rebels of a crude battlement and a swift and deadly siege by colonial forces.</paragraph><paragraph>Mass public support for the captured rebels in the colony's capital of Melbourne when they were placed on trial resulted in the introduction of the<space/><link><target>Electoral Act 1856</target></link>, which mandated full white<space/><link><target>male suffrage</target></link><space/>for elections for the<space/><link><target>Victorian Legislative Assembly</target><part>lower house in the Victorian parliament</part></link>, the second instituted political democracy in Australia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="licence"></extension><space/>As such, the Eureka Rebellion is controversially identified with the birth of democracy in Australia and interpreted by some as a political revolt.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Dr. H.V. Evatt, leader of the ALP, wrote that &quot;The Eureka Stockade was of crucial importance in the making of Australian democracy&quot;; Robert Menzies, later Liberal Prime Minister, said that &quot;the Eureka revolution was an earnest attempt at democratic government&quot;; and, Ben Chifley, former ALP Prime Minister, wrote that &quot;Eureka was more than an incident or passing phase. It was greater in significance than the short-lived revolt against tyrannical authority would suggest. The permanency of Eureka in its impact on our development was that it was the first real affirmation of our determination to be masters of our own political destiny.&quot; (from<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Eureka Rebellion
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>National Republicans
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://home.alphalink.com.au/~eureka/eukand.htm<space/></arg></template>, quoting<space/><italics>Historical Studies: Eureka Supplement</italics>, Melbourne University Press, Carlton, Vic., 1965, pages 1256)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sunter<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Anne Beggs<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/lab/85/sunter.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Contested Memories of Eureka: Museum Interpretations of the Eureka Stockade<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Labour History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>History Cooperative</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 December 2006</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Geoffrey Blainey</target></link><space/>commented in 1963 that &quot;Eureka became a legend, a battlecry for nationalists. republicans, liberals, radicals, or communists, each creed finding in the rebellion the lessons they liked to see.&quot; ...&quot;In fact the new colonies' political constitutions were not affected by Eureka, but the first Parliament that met under Victoria's new constitution was alert to the democratic spirit of the goldfields, and passed laws enabling each adult man in Victoria to vote at elections, to vote by<space/><link><target>secret ballot</target></link>, and to stand for the Legislative Assembly.&quot;<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Blainey<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Geoffrey<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Geoffrey Blainey<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Rush That Never Ended<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1963<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Melbourne University Press<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>56–7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><heading level='3'>Protests on the Goldfields: 18511854</heading><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Hiscock</target><part>Hiscock's gold rush</part></link><space/>began on 12 August 1851 following the publication in the<space/><italics><link><target>Geelong Advertiser</target></link></italics><space/>of Thomas Hiscock's gold findings at Hiscock's, 3 kilometres west of<space/><link><target>Buninyong</target></link><space/>(now<space/><link><target>Magpie (Victoria)</target><part>Magpie</part></link>, approximately 10 kilometres south of Eureka). Just days later on 16 August 1851, Lieutenant-Governor<space/><link><target>Charles La Trobe</target><part>Latrobe</part></link><space/>proclaimed in the Government Gazette crown rights for all mining proceeds and a licence fee of 30 shillings per month effective from 1 September 1851.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.roymorgan.com/resources/pdf/papers/20110502.pdf'>Charles La Trobe, Victoria's Separation &amp; Gold Tax 'turning a wild colonial country into a civilised one'</link><space/>Roy Morgan Research</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 26 August, a rally of 40-50 miners opposing the fee was held at Hiscock's gully the first of many such protests in the colony.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Argus 30 Aug 1851">GOLD. Pg 2. The Argus. 30 August 1851</extension><space/>The miners opposed government policies of oppression including the licence fee and demanded rights to vote and to buy land.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Argus 30 Aug 1851"></extension><space/>This first meeting was followed by dissent across the colony's mining settlements.</paragraph><paragraph>In December the government announced that it intended to triple the licence fee from 1 to 3 a month, from 1 January 1852.<extension extension_name='ref'>pg. 24. Bate, Weston. Lucky City</extension><space/>This move incited protests around the colony, including the<space/><link><target>Forest Creek Monster Meeting</target></link><space/>of December 1851. In Ballarat, historian Weston Bate noted that diggers became so agitated that they began to gather arms. The government hastily repealed its plans due to the reaction.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, the oppressive licence hunts continued and increased in frequency causing general dissent among the diggers. In addition, Weston Bate noted that the Ballarat diggings were in strong opposition to the strict liquor licensing laws imposed by the government.</paragraph><paragraph>Changes to the Goldfields Act in 1853 allowed licence searches to occur at any time which further incensed the diggers. In<space/><link><target>Bendigo</target></link><space/>in 1853, an<space/><link><target>Anti-Gold Licence Association</target></link><space/>was formed and the miners were apparently on the brink of an armed clash with authorities. Again in 1854, Bendigo miners responded to an increase in the frequency of twice weekly licence hunts with threats of armed rebellion.<extension extension_name='ref'>pg. 55. Bate, Weston. Lucky City</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Murder of James Scobie and the burning of Bentley's Hotel</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>James Scobie</arg></template><link><target>File:Doudiet Eureka Riot - Burning of Bentley's Hotel 1854.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Burning of Bentley's Hotel sketched by<space/><link><target>Charles Doudiet</target></link></part></link>On 6 October 1854, Scottish miner James Scobie was murdered at the Eureka hotel.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.prov.vic.gov.au/eureka/murder_of_Raz_scobie.htm'>Murder of James Scobie</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.prov.vic.gov.au/eureka/murder_of_Raz_scobie.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20150214071010<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Ten days later, on 17 October 1854, between 1,000 and 10,000 miners gathered at the hotel to protest the acquittal of James Bentley, the hotel proprietor and prime suspect in Scobie's murder, by a corrupt magistrate.</paragraph><paragraph>The miners rioted and Bentley and his wife Catherine fled for their lives as the hotel was burnt down by the angry mob. A small group of soldiers were unable to suppress the riot.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Further unrest</heading><paragraph>On 22 October 1854, Ballarat Catholics met to protest the treatment of Father Smyth.The next day, the arrests of miners McIntyre and Fletcher for the Eureka Hotel fire provoked a mass meeting which attracted 4,000 miners. The meeting resolved to establish a 'Digger's Rights Society', to protect their rights. On 1 November 1854, 3,000 miners met once again at Bakery Hill. They were addressed by Thomas Kennedy, Henry Holyoake, George Black and<space/><link><target>Henry Ross</target></link>. The diggers were further angered by the arrest of another seven of their number for the Eureka Hotel fire.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ballarat Reform League</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Ballarat Reform League</arg></template>On Saturday, 11 November 1854 a crowd estimated at more than 10,000 miners gathered at<space/><link><target>Bakery Hill, Victoria</target><part>Bakery Hill</part></link>, directly opposite the government encampment. At this meeting, the Ballarat Reform League was created, under the chairmanship of<space/><link><target>Chartism</target><part>Chartist</part></link><space/><link><target>John Basson Humffray</target></link>. Several other Reform League leaders, including Kennedy and Holyoake, had been involved with the Chartist movement in England. Many of the miners had past involvement in the Chartist movement and the social upheavals in Britain, Ireland, and continental Europe during the 1840s.</paragraph><paragraph>In setting its goals, the Ballarat Reform League used the British Chartist movement's principles. The meeting passed a resolution &quot;that it is the inalienable right of every citizen to have a voice in making the laws he is called on to obey, that taxation without representation is tyranny.&quot; The meeting also resolved to secede from the United Kingdom if the situation did not improve.<extension extension_name='ref' name="macdougal"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>MacDougal<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ian<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://webdiary.com.au/cms/?q</arg><arg name="title"><space/>29 November and the Birth of Australian Democracy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Webdiary<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 January 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Throughout the following weeks, the League sought to negotiate with Commissioner<space/><link><target>Robert William Rede</target><part>Robert Rede</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Governor of Victoria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles Hotham</target><part>Sir Charles Hotham</part></link>, both on the specific matters relating to Bentley and the Scobie's death, and the men being tried for the burning of the Eureka Hotel, and on the broader issues of abolition of the licence, suffrage and democratic representation of the gold fields, and disbanding of the Gold Commission. Governor Hotham, on 16 November 1854, appointed a Royal Commission on goldfields problems and grievances. However, Commissioner Rede, rather than hear miner's grievances, increased the police presence in the gold fields and summoned reinforcements from Melbourne. Many historians (most notably<space/><link><target>Manning Clark</target></link>) attribute this to his belief in his right to exert authority over the &quot;rabble.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>On 28 November 1854, the reinforcements marching from Melbourne were attacked by a crowd of miners. A number were injured and a drummer boy was allegedly killed. The rumour of the drummer boy's death was perpetuated, even with a memorial erected to him in Ballarat Cemetery for many years, although historical research has shown that the boy, John Egan, continued military service until dying in 1860.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://freepages.history.rootsweb.com/~garter1/drummerboy.htm'>Drummer Boy John Egan (Regiment No. 3059) Eureka's first Military Casualty</link>. Retrieved 29 November 2006.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At a meeting of about 12,000 'diggers' on the following day, (29 November), the Reform League delegation relayed its failure to achieve any success in negotiations with the authorities. The miners resolved on open resistance to the authorities and to burn the hated licences.</paragraph><paragraph>Rede responded by ordering police to conduct a licence search on 30 November. Eight defaulters were arrested, and most of the military resources available had to be summoned to extricate the arresting officers from the<space/><link><target>angry mob</target></link><space/>that had assembled.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/documents.htm?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rede's account of the Gravel Pits riots and call for Martial Law to be proclaimed<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Eureka on Trial<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Public record Office of Victoria<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 February 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>This raid prompted a change in the leadership of the Reform League, to people who argued in favour of 'physical force' rather than the 'moral force' championed by Humffray and the old leadership.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.takver.com/history/eureka.htm#aa522'>Reclaiming the Radical Spirit of the Eureka Rebellion in 1854</link>. Retrieved 29 November 2006.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Battle of the Eureka Stockade</heading><heading level='3'>Paramilitary mobilisation and swearing allegiance to the Southern Cross</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Doudiet Swearing allegiance to the Southern Cross.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Swearing Allegiance to the Southern Cross'', watercolour by<space/><link><target>Charles Doudiet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Art Gallery of Ballarat</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Eureka-restored.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Eureka Flag</target></link><space/>at the Art Gallery of Ballarat</part></link>In the rising tide of anger and resentment amongst the miners, a more militant leader,<space/><link><target>Peter Lalor</target></link>, was elected. In swift fashion, a military structure was assembled. Brigades were formed, and captains were appointed. Licences were burned, and on 1 December at Bakery Hill, &quot;The disaffected miners... held a meeting where at the Australian flag of independence was solemnly consecrated and vows proffered for its defence.&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Three Despatches From Sir Charles Hotham, Public Record Office, Melbourne, (1981?).</extension><space/>with the 'Eureka oath' being sworn by Peter Lalor to the affirmation of his fellow demonstrators, who encamped themselves around the flag to resist further licence hunts and harassment by the authorities: &quot;We swear by the Southern Cross to stand truly by each other and fight to defend our rights and liberties.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/escalating_tensions.htm#3<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Escalating Tensions: The Southern Cross<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Eureka on Trial<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Public record Office of Victoria<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 February 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The white and blue Eureka Flag, said to be designed by a Canadian miner, &quot;Captain&quot;<space/><link><target>Henry Ross</target></link>, and bearing nothing but the<space/><link><target>Crux</target><part>Southern Cross</part></link>, was then flown for the first (recorded) occasion; according to the Ballarat Times, which first mentioned the flag a week earlier on 24 November 1854, at &quot;about eleven o'clock the 'Southern Cross' was hoisted, and its maiden appearance was a fascinating object to behold.&quot; The flag was believed to have been sewn by Anastasia Hayes. Reportedly influenced by earlier designs such as the<space/><link><target>Australian Federation Flag</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.australianflag.org.au/wp-content/uploads/2010/08/ANFA-Newsletter-2009-Comp.pdf</extension><space/>as a gesture of defiance<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template>, it deliberately excluded the British<space/><link><target>Flag of the United Kingdom</target><part>Union Flag</part></link>, which is included in the official<space/><link><target>flag of Australia</target></link>. The Eureka flag was commonly referred to at the time as the Australian flag, and as the Southern Cross, with<space/><italics>The Age</italics><space/>variously reporting, on 28 November: &quot;The Australian flag shall triumphantly wave in the sunshine of its own blue and peerless sky, over thousands of Australia's adopted sons&quot;;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Ballarat Times</italics>, cited in<space/><italics>The Age</italics>, 28 November 1854, p. 5.</extension><space/>the day after the battle: &quot;They assembled round the Australian flag, which has now a permanent flag-staff&quot;;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Age</italics>, 4 December 1854, p. 5.</extension><space/>and during the 1855 Eureka trials, that it was sworn that the Eureka flag was also known as the &quot;digger's flag&quot; and also as &quot;the Southern Cross&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Age</italics>, 24 February 1855, p. 5</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>&quot;Remember Vinegar Hill&quot;: Irish dimension factors in dwindling numbers at stockade</heading><paragraph><italics>The Argus</italics><space/>newspaper of 4 December 1854 reported that the Union Jack &quot;had&quot; to be hoisted underneath the Eureka flag at the stockade, and that both flags were by then in the possession of the foot police.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.slv.vic.gov.au/ergo/eureka_stockade<space/></arg><arg name="title">ergo &#124; Research, resources and essay writing<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Slv.vic.gov.au<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20110706123102/http://www.slv.vic.gov.au/ergo/eureka_stockade<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">6 July 2011<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Revolt at Eureka&quot;, Pictorial Social Studies, Vol 16, pp. 25 27.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article4801224
</arg><arg name="title">By Express. Fatal Collision at Ballaarat.
</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Argus (Australia)|The Argus]]
</arg><arg name="location">Melbourne, Vic.
</arg><arg name="date">4 December 1854
</arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011
</arg><arg name="page">5<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some have questioned whether this sole contemporaneous report of the otherwise unaccounted for Union Jack being present is accurate.<extension extension_name='ref'>M. Clark.<space/><italics>Sources of Australian History</italics>, Oxford University Press, Melbourne, 1966, pp. 278,301.</extension><space/>Former CEO of the<space/><link><target>Royal Australian Historical Society</target></link>, John Vaughan, theorised that the Union Jack in the adjacent government camp may have created an optical illusion, whilst others in defence of this alternative scenario have stressed that the investigating journalist may have had available eyewitness reports of the two flags having been seized, and that it was possibly an 11th hour response to the divided loyalties among the heterogeneous rebel force which was in the process of melting away (at one stage 1,500 of 17,280 men in Ballarat were present, with only 150 taking part in the battle), with Lalor's choice of password for the night of 2 December - &quot;<link><target>Battle of Vinegar Hill</target><part>Vinegar Hill</part></link>&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Desmond O'Grady. Raffaello! Raffaello!: A Biography of Raffaello Carboni, Hale and Iremonger, Sydney, 1985, pp. 155.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>H.R. Nicholls. &quot;Reminiscences of the Eureka Stockade&quot;,<space/><italics>The Centennial Magazine: An Australian Monthly</italics>, (May 1890) (available in an annual compilation; Vol. II: August 1889 to July 1890), pp. 749.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Raffaello Carboni.<space/><italics>The Eureka Stockade</italics>, Currey O'Neil, Blackburn, Vic., 1980, pp. 90.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>William Bramwell Withers.<space/><italics>The History of Ballarat, From the First Pastoral Settlement to the Present Time</italics>, (facsimile of the second edition of 1887), Queensberry Hill Press, Carlton, Vic., 1980, pp. 105.</extension><space/>causing support for the rebellion to fall away among those who were otherwise disposed to resist the military, as word spread that the question of<space/><link><target>Irish home rule</target></link><space/>had become involved.<extension extension_name='ref'>One writer has stated that &quot;the collapse of the rising at Ballarat may be regarded as mainly attributable to the password given by Lalor on the night before the assault. Asked by one of the subordinate leaders of the revolt for the &quot;night pass&quot;, he gave &quot;Vinegar Hill&quot;... Many at Ballaarat, who were disposed before that to resist the military, now quietly withdrew from the movement... when the news circulated that Irish independence had crept into it&quot; (also known as the Castle Hill uprising, Vinegar Hill was the site of an 1804 rebellion by convicts in the colony of New South Wales, involving mainly Irish transportees). C.H. Currey. The Irish at Eureka, Angus and Robertson, Sydney, 1954, pp. 93.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="flagsociety.org.au">http://www.flagsociety.org.au/what_happened_to_the_eureka_jack.pdf</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregory Black, military historian and author of<space/><italics>Eureka Stockade: A Ferocious and Bloody Battle</italics>, concedes two flags may have been flown on the day of the battle, as the miners were claiming to be defending their British rights, with a further article in<space/><italics>The Argus</italics><space/>on 9 December 1854, reporting that Constable Hugh King had found a Union Jack like flag being carried by a prisoner;<extension extension_name='ref'>According to Constable Hugh King's testimony: &quot;...three or four hundred yards a heavy fire from the stockade was opened on the troops and me. When the fire was opened on us we received orders to fire. I saw some of the 40th wounded lying on the ground but I cannot say that it was before the fire on both sides. I think some of the men in the stockade should-they had a flag flying in the stockade; it was a white cross of five stars on a blue ground. - flag was afterwards taken from one of the prisoners like a union jack we fired and advanced on the stockade, when we jumped over, we were ordered to take all we could prisoners...&quot; http://wiki.prov.vic.gov.au/index.php/Eureka_Stockade:Depositions_VPRS_5527/P_Unit_2,_Item_9</extension><space/>and, according to<space/><italics>The Eureka Encyclopedia</italics>, Sergeant John McNeil at the time shredded a flag at the Spencer Street Barracks in Melbourne, which was said to be the Eureka flag, but which may well have been a Union Jack.</paragraph><paragraph>It is certain that Irish born people were strongly represented at the Eureka Stockade.<extension extension_name='ref'>C.H. Curry, 'The Irish at Eureka', Angus &amp; Robertson, 1954</extension><space/>Eureka historians have discovered that as well as comprising most of the miners inside the stockade at the finish, the area where the defensive position was established was overwhelmingly populated by the Irish to begin with.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lateline"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/stories/s290806.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lateline – 7/5/2001: Historians discuss Eureka legend. Australian Broadcasting Corp<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abc.net.au<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-08</arg></template></extension><space/>Professor<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Blainey</target></link><space/>has advanced the view, that the white cross behind the stars on the Eureka flag &quot;really [is] an<space/><link><target>Irish cross</target></link><space/>rather than being [a] configuration of the Southern Cross&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lateline"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Departing detachment of Independent Californian Rangers leaves small garrison behind</heading><paragraph>During 2 December, the peak rebel force trained in and around the stockade. A further two hundred Americans, the Independent Californian Rangers, under the leadership of James McGill, arrived about 4pm. The Americans were armed with revolvers and Mexican knives and possessed horses. In a fateful decision, McGill decided to take most of the Californian Rangers away from the stockade to intercept rumoured British reinforcements coming from Melbourne. Rede's spies observed these actions. That night many of the miners went back to their own tents after the traditional Saturday night carousing, with the assumption that the Queen's military forces would not be sent to attack on the Sabbath (Sunday). A small contingent of miners remained at the stockade overnight, which the spies reported to Rede.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Stockade</heading><paragraph>The stockade itself was a ramshackle affair<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Benwell</arg><arg name="first">Phillip</arg><arg name="title">EUREKA</arg><arg name="url">http://www.monarchist.org.au/articlesarchive_detail.html?_SKU</arg><arg name="publisher">The Australian Monarchist League Inc</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 July 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>which was hastily constructed over the following days from timber and overturned carts. The structure was never meant to be a military stockade or fortress. In the words of Lalor: &quot;it was nothing more than an enclosure to keep our own men together, and was never erected with an eye to military defence&quot;. Lalor had already outlined a plan whereby, &quot;if the government forces come to attack us, we should meet them on the Gravel Pits, and if compelled, we should retreat by the heights to the old Canadian Gully, and there we shall make our final stand&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade history, Part 2: Peter Lalor's Statement in The Argus of 10 April 1855</arg><arg name="url">http://home.alphalink.com.au/~eureka/lalor.htm</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Siege of the Eureka Stockade</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Map of eureka stockade 1854.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Map of the stockade and opposing forces</part></link>By the beginning of December, the police contingent at Ballarat had been joined and surpassed in number by soldiers from<space/><link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>garrisons in Victoria, including detachments from the<space/><link><target>Suffolk Regiment</target><part>12th (East Suffolk) Regiment of Foot</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>40th Regiment of Foot</target><part>40th (2nd Somersetshire) Regiment of Foot</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>At 3&amp;nbsp;am on Sunday, 3 December, a party of 276 soldiers and police, under the command of Captain<space/><link><target>John Wellesley Thomas</target><part>John W. Thomas</part></link><space/>approached the Eureka Stockade and a battle ensued.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eureka stockade battle.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Watercolour of the Eureka Stockade, J. B. Henderson, 1854</part></link><link><target>File:Eureka stockade.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>1891 depiction of the Eureka Stockade by Beryl Ireland</part></link>There is no agreement as to which side fired first, but the battle was fierce, brief, and terribly one-sided. The ramshackle army of miners was hopelessly outclassed by a military regiment and was routed in about 10 minutes. During the height of the battle, Lalor was shot in his left arm, took refuge under some timber and was smuggled out of the stockade and hidden. His arm was later amputated.</paragraph><paragraph>Stories tell how women ran forward and threw themselves over the injured to prevent further indiscriminate killing. The Commission of Inquiry would later say that it was &quot;a needless as well as a ruthless sacrifice of human life indiscriminate of innocent or guilty, and after all resistance had disappeared.&quot;<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template>Early in the battle &quot;Captain&quot; Henry Ross was shot dead.</paragraph><paragraph>According to Lalor's report, fourteen miners (mostly Irish) died inside the stockade and an additional eight died later from injuries they sustained. A further dozen were wounded but recovered. Three months after the Eureka Stockade, Peter Lalor wrote: &quot;As the inhuman brutalities practised by the troops are so well known, it is unnecessary for me to repeat them. There were 34 digger casualties of which 22 died. The unusual proportion of the killed to the wounded, is owing to the butchery of the military and troopers after the surrender.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Joseph Toscano,<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.takver.com/history/eureka.htm#aa502'>The Killing Times</link></italics><space/>Reclaiming the Radical Spirit of the Eureka Rebellion in 1854, (2004) Accessed 20 October 2008</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the battle, trooper<space/><link><target>John King (Eureka)</target><part>John King</part></link><space/>the police constable, took down the Eureka flag. By 8&amp;nbsp;am, Captain<space/><link><target>Charles Pasley (engineer)</target><part>Charles Pasley</part></link>, the second in command of the British forces, sickened by the carnage, saved a group of prisoners from being bayoneted and threatened to shoot any police or soldiers who continued with the slaughter. Pasley's valuable assistance was acknowledged in despatches printed and laid before the<space/><link><target>Victorian Legislative Council</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dnb"><template><target>DNB</target><arg name="wstitle">Pasley, Charles (1824-1890)</arg><arg name="volume">43</arg><arg name="last">Vetch</arg><arg name="first">Robert Hamilton</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One hundred and fourteen diggers, some wounded, were marched off to the Government camp about two kilometres away, where they were kept in an overcrowded lock-up, before being moved to a more spacious barn on Monday morning.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Estimates of the death toll</heading><paragraph>Of the soldiers and police, six were killed, including Captain Wise.<space/><link><target>Martial law</target></link><space/>was imposed, and all armed resistance collapsed. News of the battle spread quickly to Melbourne and other gold field regions, turning a perceived Government military victory in repressing a minor insurrection into a public relations disaster. Thousands of people in Melbourne turned out to condemn the authorities, in defiance of their mayor and some Legislative Councillors, who tried to rally support for the government.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ballaratreformleague1">The Eureka Stockade : Gateway to Democracy by Weston Bate (Historian) http://www.ballaratreformleague.org.au/ballarat.htm</extension><space/>In Ballarat, only one man responded to the call for special constables,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ballaratreformleague1"></extension><space/>although in Melbourne 1500 were sworn in and armed with batons.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mary Proctor: Convict, Pioneer and Settler By Jeff Atkinson</extension><space/>Many people voiced their support for the diggers' requested reforms.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Exact numbers of deaths and injuries and persons are difficult to determine as many miners &quot;fled to the surrounding bush and it is likely a good many more died a lonely death or suffered the agony of their wounds, hidden from the authorities for fear of repercussions.&quot; according to Eureka researcher and author Dorothy Wickham. The official register of deaths in the Ballarat District Register shows 27 names associated with the stockade battle at Eureka.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dorothy Wickham,<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.ballaratgenealogy.org.au/art/eureka-d.htm'>Deaths at Eureka</link></italics><space/>an extract from her book &quot;Deaths at Eureka&quot;, 64pp, 1996 ISBN 0-646-30283-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>Clare Wright</target></link><space/>quotes one source, Thomas Pierson, who noted in the margin to his diary<space/><italics>time has proved that near 60 have died of the diggers in all</italics>. According to Wright, Captain Thomas estimated that 30 diggers died on the spot and<space/><italics>many more died of their wounds subsequently.</italics><space/>Even the Geelong Advertiser on 8 December 1854 stated that deaths were<space/><italics>more numerous than originally supposed.</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wright, Clare 2013 pp 428"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While it has been thought all the deaths at Eureka were men, research by historian Clare Wright details that at least one woman lost her life in the massacre. Wright's research details the important role of women on the goldfields and in the reform movement. Her book<space/><italics>Forgotten Rebels of Eureka</italics><space/>details how Charles Evans diary describes a funeral for a woman who was mercilessly butchered by a mounted trooper while pleading for the life of her husband during the Eureka massacre. Her name and the fate and identity of her husband remain unknown.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wright, Clare,<space/><italics>The Forgotten Rebels of Eureka</italics><space/>(2013) Text Publishing, Melbourne ISBN 9781922147370, pp 429</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Blainey</target></link><space/>has commented, &quot;Every government in the world would probably have counter-attacked in the face of the building of the stockade.&quot;<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2010</arg></template><space/>For a few weeks it appeared that the status quo had been restored, and Rede ruled the camps with an iron fist.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Trials for sedition and high treason</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Reward notice lalor black eureka.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>A reward of 400&amp;nbsp;pounds was issued for<space/><link><target>Peter Lalor</target></link><space/>and George Black</part></link>The first trial relating to the rebellion was a charge of<space/><link><target>Australian sedition law</target><part>sedition</part></link><space/>against<space/><link><target>Henry Seekamp</target></link><space/>of the<space/><italics>Ballarat Times</italics>. Seekamp was arrested in his newspaper office on 4 December 1854, for a series of articles that appeared in the<space/><italics>Ballarat Times</italics>. Many of these articles were written by George Lang, the son of the prominent republican and Presbyterian Minister of Sydney, the Reverend<space/><link><target>John Dunmore Lang</target></link>. He was tried and convicted of seditious libel by a Melbourne jury on 23 January 1855 and, after a series of appeals, sentenced to six months imprisonment on 23 March. He was released from prison on 28 June 1855, precisely three months early.</paragraph><paragraph>Of the approximately 120 'diggers' detained after the rebellion, thirteen were brought to trial. They were:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/state_treason_trials.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The State Trials<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Eureka on Trial<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Public record Office of Victoria<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 February 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Timothy Hayes</target></link>, Chairman of the<space/><link><target>Ballarat Reform League</target></link>, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>James McFie Campbell, a black man from<space/><link><target>Kingston, Jamaica</target><part>Kingston</part></link>, Jamaica</listitem><listitem><link><target>Raffaello Carboni</target></link>, an Italian and trusted lieutenant who was in charge of the European diggers as he spoke a few European languages. Carboni self-published his account of the Eureka Stockade a year after the Stockade, the only comprehensive eyewitness account</listitem><listitem>Jacob Sorenson, a Jew from Scotland</listitem><listitem><link><target>John Manning (journalist)</target><part>John Manning</part></link>, a<space/><italics>Ballarat Times</italics><space/>journalist, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>John Phelan, a friend and business partner of Peter Lalor, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>Thomas Dignum, born in Sydney</listitem><listitem>John Joseph, a black American from New York City or Baltimore, United States</listitem><listitem>James Beattie, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>William Molloy, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>Jan Vennick, from the Netherlands</listitem><listitem>Michael Tuohy, from Ireland</listitem><listitem>Henry Reid, from Ireland</listitem></list><paragraph>The first trial started on 22 February 1855, with defendants being brought before the court on charges of high treason. Joseph was one of three Americans arrested at the stockade, with the United States Consul intervening for the release of the other two Americans. The prosecution was handled by<space/><link><target>Attorney-General of Victoria</target><part>Attorney-General</part></link><space/><link><target>William Stawell</target></link><space/>representing the Crown<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Australian Dictionary of Biography</target><arg name="last">Francis<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1976
<space/></arg><arg name="volume">6
<space/></arg><arg name="id2">stawell-sir-william-foster-4635
<space/></arg><arg name="pp">174-177
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stawell, Sir William Foster (1815 - 1889)
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-02</arg></template></extension><space/>before Chief Justice<space/><link><target>William Beckett</target></link>. The jury deliberated for about half an hour before returning a verdict of &quot;not guilty&quot;. &quot;A sudden burst of applause arose in the court&quot; reported<space/><link><target>The Argus (Australia)</target><part>The Argus</part></link>, but was instantly checked by court officers. The Chief Justice condemned this as an attempt to influence the jury; he sentenced two men identified by the Crown Solicitor as having applauded to a week in prison for contempt.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Argus, 24 February 1885 &lt;http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-page186129&gt;</extension><space/>Over 10,000 people had come to hear the jury's verdict.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template><space/>John Joseph was carried around the streets of Melbourne in a chair in triumph, according to<space/><link><target>The Ballarat Star</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Under the auspices of Victorian Chief Justice<space/><link><target>Redmond Barry</target></link>, all the other 13 accused men were rapidly acquitted to great public acclaim. The trials have on several occasions been called a farce.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Molony, &quot;Eureka&quot;, Ringwood 1989</extension><space/>Rede himself was quietly removed from the camps and reassigned to an insignificant position in rural Victoria.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Commission of Enquiry</heading><paragraph>When Hotham's Royal Commission report, initiated before the conflict, was finally handed down it was scathing in its assessment of all aspects of the administration of the gold fields, and particularly the Eureka Stockade affair. According to Blainey, &quot;It was perhaps the most generous concession offered by a governor to a major opponent in the history of Australia up to that time. The members of the commission were appointed before Eureka...they were men who were likely to be sympathetic to the diggers.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>The report made several major recommendations, one of which was to restrict Chinese immigration. Its recommendations were only put into effect after the Stockade. The<space/><link><target>Miner's Licence</target><part>gold licences</part></link><space/>were then abolished, and replaced by an annual<space/><link><target>Miner's Right</target><part>miner's right</part></link><space/>and an export fee based on the value of the gold. Mining wardens replaced the gold commissioners, and police numbers were cut drastically. The Legislative Council was expanded to allow representation to the major goldfields and<space/><link><target>Peter Lalor</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Basson Humffray</target></link><space/>were elected for Ballarat, although there were property qualifications with regards to eligibility to vote in upper house elections in Victoria until the 1950s. After 12 months, all but one of the demands of the Ballarat Reform League had been granted. Lalor and Humffray both enjoyed distinguished careers as politicians, with Lalor later elected as Speaker of the Legislative Assembly of Victoria.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Peter Lalor</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Peter Lalor</arg></template><link><target>File:Peter Lalor as Speaker.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Eureka leader<space/><link><target>Peter Lalor</target></link><space/>in later life as Speaker of the House in the Legislative Assembly of Victoria</part></link>Following the battle, rebel leader,<space/><link><target>Irish Australian</target></link><space/>Peter Lalor, wrote in a statement to the colonists of Victoria, &quot;There are two things connected with the late outbreak (Eureka) which I deeply regret. The first is, that we shouldn't have been forced to take up arms at all; and the second is, that when we were compelled to take the field in our own defence, we were unable (through want of arms, ammunition and a little organisation) to inflict on the real authors of the outbreak the punishment they so richly deserved.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Lalor
<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Peter Lalor
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Peter Lalor's Narrative
<space/></arg><arg name="work">Eureka on Trial
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Public Record Office Victoria, (2003)
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1855
<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/lalors_letter.htm
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lalor stood for Ballarat in the 1856 elections and was elected unopposed. As he was the Eureka hero his policies were not scrutinised at all before the election.</paragraph><paragraph>During a speech in the Legislative Council in 1856 he said, &quot;I would ask these gentlemen what they mean by the term 'democracy'. Do they mean Chartism or Republicanism? If so, I never was, I am not now, nor do I ever intend to be a democrat. But if a democrat means opposition to a tyrannical press, a tyrannical people, or a tyrannical government, then I have been, I am still, and will ever remain a democrat.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Historians, including Weston Bate suggested that there was some hypocrisy in Lalor's folk hero status due to his post-stockade political opportunism and self-interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bate, Weston. &quot;Lucky City&quot;. Page 184</extension><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political legacy</heading><paragraph>On 24 November 1857 a bill granting universal suffrage for white males was passed in Victorian parliament. It was the first in Australia to grant universal male<space/><link><target>suffrage</target></link>. Peter Lalor is recorded to have voted against the bill in parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bate, Weston. &quot;Lucky City&quot;. Page 133</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Debate regarding political significance</heading><paragraph>The actual significance of Eureka upon Australia's politics is not decisive. It has been variously mythologised by particular interest groups as a revolt of free men against imperial tyranny, of independent free enterprise against burdensome taxation, of labour against a privileged ruling class, or as an expression of<space/><link><target>Republicanism in Australia</target><part>republicanism</part></link>, yet the writings of<space/><link><target>Raffaello Carboni</target></link>, who was present at the Stockade, make it clear that &quot;amongst the foreigners&amp;nbsp;... there was no democratic feeling, but merely a spirit of resistance to the licence fee&quot;; and he also disputes the accusations &quot;that have branded the miners of Ballarat as disloyal to their QUEEN&quot; (emphasis as in the original).<extension extension_name='ref'>RC:108,153</extension><space/>The affair continues to raise echoes in Australian politics to the present day, and from time to time one group or another calls for the existing Australian flag to be replaced by the Eureka Flag.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.smh.com.au/national/eureka-an-answer-to-that-jack-in-the-corner-gets-a-little-bit-warmer-20110125-1a4be.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Sydney Morning Herald<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eureka? An answer to that Jack in the corner gets a little bit warmer</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.smh.com.au/national/eminent-australians-rally-around-as-call-goes-out-for-a-new-flag-20110125-1a4b5.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Sydney Morning Herald<space/></arg><arg name="title">Eminent Australians rally around as call goes out for a new flag</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some historians believe that the prominence of the event in the public record has come about because Australian history does not include a major armed rebellion phase equivalent to the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link>, or the<space/><link><target>American War of Independence</target></link>, making the Eureka story inflated well beyond its real significance. Others, however, maintain that Eureka was a seminal event and that it marked a major change in the course of Australian history.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/lateline/stories/s290806.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lateline – 7/5/2001: Historians discuss Eureka legend . Australian Broadcasting Corp<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ABC<space/></arg><arg name="location">Australia<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1980, historian<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Blainey</target></link><space/>drew attention to the fact that many miners were temporary migrants from Britain and the United States, who did not intend to settle permanently in Australia. He wrote:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Nowadays it is common to see the noble [[Eureka Flag|Eureka flag]] and the rebellion of 1854 as the symbol of Australian independence, of freedom from foreign domination; but many saw the rebellion in 1854 as an uprising by outsiders who were exploiting the country's resources and refusing to pay their fair share of taxes. So we make history do its handsprings.<ref>[[Geoffrey Blainey]], ''A Land Half Won'', Melbourne: Sun Books, 1983 (first printed in 1980), ISBN 0-7251-0411-2, p.158</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1999, the Premier of New South Wales,<space/><link><target>Bob Carr</target></link>, dismissed the Eureka Stockade as a &quot;protest without consequence&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/7.30/stories/s73410.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">7.30 Report – 14 December 1999: The Eureka rebellion<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ABC<space/></arg><arg name="location">Australia<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 December 1999<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Deputy Prime Minister<space/><link><target>John Anderson (Australian politician)</target><part>John Anderson</part></link><space/>made the Eureka flag a federal election campaign issue in 2004 saying &quot;I think people have tried to make too much of the Eureka Stockade...trying to give it a credibility and standing that it probably doesn't enjoy.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.abc.net.au/news/australia/vic/ballarat/200409/s1196347.htm'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/news/australia/vic/ballarat/200409/s1196347.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20110629005912<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2004, the Premier of Victoria, Steve Bracks, delivered an opening address at the Eureka 150 Democracy Conference<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>s:Steve Bracks Eureka 150 Democracy Conference</target><part>Steve Bracks, Opening Address, Eureka 150 Democracy Conference</part></link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>stating &quot;that Eureka was about the struggle for basic democratic rights. It was not about a riot it was about rights.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Commemoration</heading><paragraph><template><target>Quote box</target><arg name="width"><space/>30em
</arg><arg name="bgcolor"><space/>#F9F9F9
</arg><arg name="align"><space/>right
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>"...&nbsp;I think it may be called the finest thing in Australasian history. It was a revolution—small in size; but great politically; it was a strike for liberty, a struggle for principle, a stand against injustice and oppression. ... It is another instance of a victory won by a lost battle. It adds an honorable page to history; the people know it and are proud of it. They keep green the memory of the men who fell at the Eureka stockade, and Peter Lalor has his monument."
</arg><arg name="source"><space/>{{mdash}} [[Mark Twain]], ''[[Following the Equator]]'' (1897)<ref>{{cite web
 | last<space/></arg></template>The materials used to build the stockade were rapidly removed to be used for the mines, and the entire area around the site was so extensively worked that the original landscape became unrecognisable, so identifying the exact location of the stockade is now virtually impossible.</paragraph><paragraph>A diggers memorial was erected in the Ballarat Cemetery on 22 March 1856 near marked graves. Sculpted in stone from the<space/><link><target>Barrabool Hills</target></link><space/>by James Leggatt in Geelong it features a pillar bearing the names of the deceased miners and bearing the inscription &quot;Sacred to the memory of those who fell on the memorable 3rd of December, 1854, in resisting the unconstitutional proceedings of the Victorian Government.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>A Soldiers Memorial was erected many years later in 1876 and is an obelisk constructed of limestone sourced from<space/><link><target>Waurn Ponds</target></link><space/>with the words &quot;Victoria&quot; and &quot;Duty&quot; carved in its north and south faces respectively. In 1879 a cast iron fence was added to the memorials and graves.</paragraph><paragraph>Over the next thirty years, press interest in the events that had taken place at the Eureka Stockade dwindled, but Eureka was kept alive at the campfires and in the pubs, and in memorial events in Ballarat. In addition, key figures such as Lalor and Humfray were still in the public eye.</paragraph><paragraph>Eureka had not been forgotten: it was readily remembered.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg></template><space/>Similar flags have been flown at rebellions since including a flag similar<space/><template><target>Clarify</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template><space/>to the Eureka flag which was flown above the<space/><link><target>Barcaldine, Queensland</target><part>Barcaldine</part></link><space/>strike camp in the<space/><link><target>1891 Australian shearers' strike</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1889, Melbourne businessmen employed renowned American<space/><link><target>cyclorama</target></link><space/>artist<space/><link><target>Thaddeus Welch</target></link>, who teamed up with local artist Izett Watson to paint<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1000</arg><arg>sqft</arg><arg>m2</arg></template><space/>of canvas of the Eureka Stockade, wrapped around a wooden structure. When it opened in Melbourne, the exhibition was an instant hit. The Age reported in 1891 that &quot;it afforded a very good opportunity for people to see what it might have been like at Eureka&quot;.<space/><italics>The Australasian</italics><space/>claimed &quot;that many persons familiar with the incidents depicted, were able to testify to the fidelity of the painted scene&quot;. The people of Melbourne flocked to the cyclorama, paid up and had their picture taken before it. It was eventually dismantled and disappeared from sight.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eureka Stockade.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>1886 Memorial stone at the<space/><link><target>Eureka, Victoria#Eureka Stockade Memorials</target><part>Eureka Monument</part></link></part></link>Memorials to soldiers and miners are located in the<space/><link><target>Ballaarat Old Cemetery</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.heritage.vic.gov.au/page_239.asp?submit_action=detailed_result&amp;amp;ID=239&amp;amp;KW1=eureka&amp;amp;query=e82db8dc6517362a4a25678b00095532/a564bd7fddeb0bbeca257390007d2763?OpenDocument&amp;amp;Highlight=0,eureka'>Search the Heritage Register and Inventory</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.heritage.vic.gov.au/page_239.asp?submit_action</arg><arg name="date">20130513125431<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and the Eureka Stockade Memorial is located within the Eureka Stockade Gardens and is listed on the<space/><link><target>Australian National Heritage List</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade Gardens
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Department of the Environment, Water, Heritage and the Arts]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://environment.gov.au/heritage/places/national/eureka-stockade/index.html
</arg><arg name="accessdate">8 July 2008
</arg></template></extension>/</paragraph><paragraph>In 1954, the centenary of the event was officially celebrated; according to Geoffrey Blainey, who was in attendance, no one, apart from a small group of communists, was there.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.theage.com.au/news/National/Children-of-rebellion-maintain-the-rage/2004/11/26/1101219745009.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Age<space/></arg><arg name="location">Melbourne, Australia<space/></arg><arg name="first">James<space/></arg><arg name="last">Button<space/></arg><arg name="title">Children of rebellion maintain the rage<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 November 2004</arg></template></extension><space/>Plays commemorating the events were held at major theatres.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A purpose built<space/><link><target>Interpretation centre</target></link><space/>was erected in 1998 in suburb of<space/><link><target>Eureka, Victoria</target><part>Eureka</part></link><space/>near the site of the stockade. Designed to be a new landmark for Ballarat, the building featured an enormous<space/><link><target>sail</target></link><space/>emblazoned with the Eureka Flag.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.eurekaballarat.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Eureka Centre<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eurekaballarat.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Before its development there was considerable debate over whether a replica or reconstruction of wooden structures was appropriate, however it was eventually decided against and this is seen by many as a reason for the apparent failure of the centre to draw significant tourist numbers. Due primarily to falling visitor numbers the centre was redeveloped between 200911.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.eurekaballarat.com/redevelopment-2009-11.aspx'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.eurekaballarat.com/redevelopment-2009-11.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="date">20111006154245<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1992,<space/><link><target>Sovereign Hill</target></link><space/>commenced a commemorative<space/><link><target>Son et lumire (show)</target><part>Son et lumire</part></link><space/>known as &quot;Blood Under the Southern Cross&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://sovereignhill.com.au/sound-light-show/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sovereign Hill Sound and Light Show<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sovereignhill.com.au<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">29 November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>which became a tourist drawcard and was revised and expanded from 2003.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.thecourier.com.au/news/local/news/general/revamp-upgrades-eureka-story/318334.aspx'>Revamp Upgrades Eureka Story.</link><space/>The Courier 5 June 2003</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eureka 150th official commemoration.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>150th anniversary official commemoration at the Eureka Centre, 3 December 2004</part></link>In 2004, the 150th anniversary was celebrated. An Australian postage stamp featuring the Eureka Flag was released along with a set of commemorative coins. A ceremony in Ballarat known as the lantern walk was held at dawn. However, Prime Minister<space/><link><target>John Howard</target></link><space/>did not attend any commemorative events, and refused to allow the flag to fly over Parliament House.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gerard Henderson.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theage.com.au/news/Gerard-Henderson/Eureka-a-short-war-thats-long-on-history/2004/11/29/1101577415151.html'>Eureka: A short war that's long on history</link><space/>The Age, 30 November 2004</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Frank Walker<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2004/11/27/1101495457395.html'>After 150 years, Eureka flag still stirs rebellion</link><space/>Sydney Morning Herald, 28 November 2004</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 2004 then<space/><link><target>Premiers of Victoria</target><part>Premier of Victoria</part></link><space/><link><target>Steve Bracks</target></link><space/>announced that the<space/><link><target>Ballarat V/Line rail service</target></link><space/>would be renamed the<space/><italics>Eureka Line</italics><space/>to mark the 150th anniversary to take effect from late 2005 at the same time as a renaming of Spencer Street Station to<space/><link><target>Southern Cross Station</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dpc.vic.gov.au/domino/Web_Notes/newmedia.nsf/0/1439B82149192718CA256F57007F0D2B?Open
</arg><arg name="title">EUREKA RAIL LINE TO OPEN EXCITING ERA FOR REGIONAL RAIL
</arg><arg name="work">Media Release: OFFICE OF THE PREMIER
</arg><arg name="publisher">dpc.vic.gov.au
</arg><arg name="date">25 November 2004
</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 November 2008
</arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">August 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>however the proposal was criticised by community groups including the<space/><link><target>Public Transport Users Association</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ptua.org.au/files/newsletters/2004/200412.pdf
</arg><arg name="title">PTUA News
</arg><arg name="date">December 2004
</arg><arg name="publisher">Public Transport Users Association
</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 November 2008
</arg></template></extension><space/>Renaming of the line did not go ahead, however Spencer Street (railway) Station did become<space/><link><target>Southern Cross Station</target></link><space/>on 13 December 2005 with Bracks stating the name would resonate with Victorians because it &quot;stands for democracy and freedom because it flew over the Eureka Stockade&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mathew Murphy<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theage.com.au/news/national/times-up-at-last-for-railway-landmark/2005/12/13/1134236064367.html'>Time's up at last for railway landmark</link><space/>The Age, 14 December 2005</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eureka Tower Australian Flag.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Eureka Tower</target></link><space/>designed with symbolism of the Eureka rebellion, with its use of the blue glass and white trims from the Eureka flag, gold glass to represent the gold and the red stripe blood spilled during the battle.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://eurekaskydeck.com.au/uploads/documents/English%20Skydeck%20Visitors%20Guide_Web.pdf'>Eureka Skydeck 88: English Visitor Guide</link></extension></part></link><link><target>Eureka Tower</target></link>, completed in 2006 is named in honour of the event and features symbolic aspects in its design including an architectural red stripe representing the blood spilt during the battle.</paragraph><paragraph>The site of the Eureka Stockade in<space/><link><target>Ballarat</target></link><space/>is currently being redeveloped with the support of grants from the City of Ballarat and the Victorian and Federal Governments.</paragraph><paragraph>It will feature the new<space/><link><target>Museum of Australian Democracy at Eureka</target></link><space/>(M.A.D.E) that will draw on the touchstone of Eureka and its newly restored flag, and put the Eureka Stockade into the context of 260 years of democracy.</paragraph><paragraph>M.A.D.E's highly interactive exhibition, based on the premise of<space/><italics>People + Power = Democracy</italics>, is expected to open in early 2013, followed by a national rollout of public onsite and online programs.</paragraph><paragraph>Deputy Premier, the Hon. Peter Ryan, told the Legislative Assembly, sitting in Ballarat in 2012, that M.A.D.E would be 'a magnificent tribute to the events' of the Eureka Stockade.</paragraph><paragraph>The Museum's<space/><italics>M.A.D.E You Look</italics><space/>booklet says M.A.D.E will be 'an online platform and immersive museum with a refreshing approach to culture, civics, history and citizenship. M.A.D.E puts the past into a contemporary context, celebrates Australias achievements and inspires new ways of thinking about issues like equality, freedom of speech, parliamentary representation and the rule of law'. The museum 'will ignite debate about what it means to be an effective Australian in the 21st Century'.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Publications</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Deaths at Eureka by D. Wickham,<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"><link type='external' href='http://www.ballaratheritage.com.au/bookstore/alpha1.html'>&quot;Ballarat Heritage Services-Bookstore&quot;</link><space/><italics><link><target>Ballarat Heritage Services</target></link></italics></extension></listitem><listitem>The Eureka Encyclopaedia by Corfield, Gervasoni and Wickham<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>The Eureka Flag: Our Starry Banner by D.Wickham, C. Gervasoni, V. DAngri.<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>History of Ballarat &amp; Some Ballarat Reminiscences, by Withers (facsimile)<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>Outbreak at Ballarat: Eureka from the Mount Alexander Mail by Clare Gervasoni<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>Shot in the Dark: A Pre-Eureka Incident by Dorothy Wickham<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>The Story of Eureka by John Lynch, -In 1895 Lynch, one of Lalors Captains at Eureka, wrote an account of the epic days at Ballarat in the 1850s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>Women of the Diggings: Ballarat 1854 by Dorothy Wickham.<extension extension_name='ref' name="balthert"></extension></listitem><listitem>What happened to the Eureka Jack?<space/><link><target>Australian Flag Society</target></link><space/>publication.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flagsociety.org.au"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Popular culture</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chips Rafferty Eureka Stockade.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Australian actor<space/><link><target>Chips Rafferty</target></link><space/>portrays Peter Lalor in the 1949 film ''<link><target>Eureka Stockade (1949 film)</target><part>Eureka Stockade</part></link>''.</part></link>The Eureka Stockade is referenced in several poems by<space/><link><target>Henry Lawson</target></link><space/>including &quot;<link><target>Flag of the Southern Cross</target></link>&quot; (1887), &quot;Eureka (A Fragment)&quot; (1889), &quot;The Fight at Eureka Stockade&quot; (1890), and &quot;<link><target>Freedom on the Wallaby</target></link>&quot; (1891).</paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Eureka Stockade (1907 film)</target><part>Eureka Stockade</part></link></italics><space/>(1907), directed by Arthur and<space/><link><target>George Cornwell</target></link><space/>and produced by the Australasian Cinematograph Company, was the second feature film made in Australia (the first being the 1906 production,<space/><italics><link><target>The Story of the Kelly Gang</target></link></italics>). The film was first screened on 19 October 1907 at the<space/><link><target>Melbourne Athenaeum</target></link>. The film impressed critics of the time and was found to be a stirring portrayal of the events surrounding the Eureka Stockade, but failed to connect with audiences during the two weeks it was screened. The surviving seven minute fragment (stored at the<space/><link><target>National Film and Sound Archive</target></link>) shows street scenes of Ballarat. Other scenes in the lost reels of the film were believed to have included gold seekers leaving London, issuing of licences, licence hunting, diggers chained to logs and rescued by mates, diggers burning Bentley's Hotel, the Rebellion, building the stockade, troops storming the stockade and the stockade in ruins.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade (1907)
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Film and Sound Archive]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://colsearch.nfsa.afc.gov.au/nfsa/search/summary/summary.w3p;adv</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 June 2013
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>The Loyal Rebel</target></link></italics>, also known as<space/><italics>Eureka Stockade</italics>, is an Australian silent film made in 1915. Directed by<space/><link><target>Alfred Rolfe (director)</target><part>Alfred Rolfe</part></link>, it starred Maisie Carte, Wynn Davies, Reynolds Denniston,<space/><link><target>Charles Villiers (actor)</target><part>Charles Villiers</part></link>, Percy Walshe, Jena Williams, and Leslie Victor as Peter Lalor.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0356838/?ref_=fn_al_tt_5/'>''The Loyal Rebel'' at IMDb</link><space/><xhtml:sub>Retrieved 09.April 2013</xhtml:sub></extension><space/>It is considered a<space/><link><target>lost film</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A 1949 British film, titled<space/><italics><link><target>Eureka Stockade (1949 film)</target><part>Eureka Stockade</part></link></italics><space/>(released in the United States as<space/><italics>Massacre Hill</italics>), was shot in Australia. The film starred<space/><link><target>Chips Rafferty</target></link><space/>as Peter Lalor, and<space/><link><target>Raffaello Carboni</target></link>. It was directed by<space/><link><target>Harry Watt (director)</target><part>Harry Watt</part></link>, produced by<space/><link><target>Leslie Norman (director)</target><part>Leslie Norman</part></link><space/>and written by<space/><link><target>Walter Greenwood</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ralph Smart</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Harry Watt (director)</target><part>Harry Watt</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade (1949)
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[imdb]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0041340/
</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 May 2009
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Eureka Stockade (miniseries)</target><part>Eureka Stockade</part></link></italics><space/>was a two-part television mini-series which aired on the Seven Network in 1984.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade Pt 01
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Film and Sound Archive]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://colsearch.nfsa.afc.gov.au/nfsa/search/display/display.w3p;adv</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 May 2009
</arg></template></extension><space/>starring<space/><link><target>Bryan Brown</target></link><space/>as Peter Lalor. Directed by Rod Hardy, produced by Henry Crawford and written by Tom Hegarty.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Eureka Stockade (1984)
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[imdb]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0087220/
</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 May 2009
</arg></template></extension><space/>The cast included<space/><link><target>Carol Burns</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bill Hunter (actor)</target><part>Bill Hunter</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Brett Cullen</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>An Australian documentary from 2006, directed by Don Parham. The film focuses mainly on Governor<space/><link><target>Charles Hotham</target><part>Sir Charles Hotham</part></link><space/>(played by Brian Lipson), Raffaello Carboni (Barry Kay), and Douglas Huyghue (Tim Robertson). The accounts of these eyewitnesses are the main source for the monologues directly aimed at the audience, and, as the caption at the start of the film says: &quot;the lines spoken by actors in this film are the documented words of the historical characters.&quot;The cast also included<space/><link><target>Julia Zemiro</target></link><space/>as Celeste de Chabrillan and Andrew Larkins as Peter Lalor.It was filmed in<space/><link><target>Ballarat</target></link><space/>and<space/><italics>Toorac House</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Melbourne</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0979937/?ref_=fn_al_tt_4/'>''Riot or Revolution: Eureka Stockade 1854'' at IMDb</link><space/><xhtml:sub>Retrieved 9 April 2013</xhtml:sub></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.parham-media.com/docos/riotorr/ror_notes.htm/'>''Riot or Revolution: Eureka Stockade 1854'' cast and notes</link><space/>at IMDb<space/><xhtml:sub>Retrieved 9 April 2013</xhtml:sub></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Flag of Australia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Eureka Flag</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of Victoria</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Butler Cole Aspinall</target></link>, one of the defence counsel</listitem><listitem><link><target>Darwin Rebellion</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Eureka Encyclopaedia</italics>, Justin Corfield, Dorothy Wickham, Clare Gervasoni,<space/><link><target>Ballarat Heritage Services</target></link>, (2004), ISBN 1-876478-61-6 Winner of Victorian Local History Award. Nominated for Prime Ministers Prize for History</listitem><listitem><italics>Massacre at Eureka The Untold Story</italics>, Bob O'Brien, ISBN 0-909874-19-0</listitem><listitem><italics>Eureka</italics>, John Molony, ISBN 0-522-84962-8</listitem><listitem><italics>The Forgotten Rebels of Eureka</italics>, Clare Wright (2013) Text Publishing, Melbourne ISBN 9781922147370</listitem><listitem><italics>The Eureka Stockade</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Raffaello Carboni</target></link>, (1855).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/3546'>Title from Project Gutenberg</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.slv.vic.gov.au/collections/treasures/lazarus1.html'>Samuel Lazarus Diary of the Eureka uprising</link><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/home.htm'>Eureka on Trial</link><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://users.netconnect.com.au/~ianmac/eureka.html'>Eureka Stockade, Ballarat, Victoria, Australia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20040215210823/http://www.slv.vic.gov.au/slv/exhibitions/goldfields/eureka/chronol.htm'>Life on the Goldfields: Eureka Stockade</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eureka150.vic.gov.au/'>150th Anniversary of the Eureka Stockade</link><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/goldrush/'>The Australian Gold Rush</link><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cultureandrecreation.gov.au/articles/eurekastockade/'>Eureka Stockade</link><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.smh.com.au/news/Opinion/Time-to-reclaim-this-legend-as-our-driving-force/2004/11/28/1101577352049.html?from=storylhs'>&quot;Time to reclaim this legend as our driving force&quot;</link><space/>by Macgregor Duncan, Andrew Leigh, David Madden, Peter Tynan,<space/><italics>Sydney Morning Herald</italics>, 29 November 2004. Retrieved 7 May 2006</listitem><listitem>Bert and Bon Strange, Eureka, Gold Graft and Grievances, B&amp;B Strange, Ballarat, 1973.</listitem><listitem>Weston Bate, Lucky City: The First Generation at Ballarat 18511901, Melbourne University Press, Melbourne, 1978, page 67.</listitem><listitem>Peter Lalor, A Statement to the Colonists of Victoria, reprinted in Bob OBrien, Massacre at Eureka: The Untold Story, Sovereign Hill Museums Association, 1998.</listitem><listitem>Professor Geoffrey Blainey, Eureka its many meanings, University of Ballarat, 26 November 2004.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://nla.gov.au/nla.news-article4806503<space/></arg><arg name="title">TO THE COLONISTS OF VICTORIA.<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Argus (Australia)|The Argus (Melbourne, Vic. : 1848 - 1957)]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Melbourne, Vic.<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 April 1855<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 June 2013<space/></arg><arg name="page">7<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">National Library of Australia</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://eureka.imagineering.com.au/lalors_kikletter.htm'>Peter Lalor's letter, ''The Argus'' 10 April 1886</link><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">May 2010</arg></template><space/>Server not available site no longer exists</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Dogstar/History/Bentley.html'>Eureka Stockade Saga 18542007</link><space/>Injustice for James and Catherine Bentley.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Dogstar/History/Catholics.html'>Catholics at the Stockade</link><space/>Father Smythe urged the miners to go home and attend mass the next day</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Dogstar/History/150.html'>The 150th anniversary of Eureka Stockade</link><space/>A large police presence on the anniversary.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Dogstar/History/eureka.html'>Characters at the Eureka Stockade</link><space/>A review of feminist revisionist history Clare Wright's The Forgotten rebels of Eureka</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Tuohy.html'>Tuohy Not Guilty of Treason</link><space/>One of 13 miners acquitted of treason</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Hanrahan.html'>Michael Hanrahan from Ireland to Ballarat 1854</link><space/>Irish Pikemen leader at the Stockade</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hereticpress.com/Dogstar/History/Emigration.html'>Clipper ships 92 days to Australia 1854</link><space/>Emigration on Clipper Ships 92 days at sea</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Spoken Wikipedia</target><arg>Eureka_Stockade.ogg</arg><arg>2006-06-29</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://prov.vic.gov.au/whats-on/exhibitions/eureka-on-trial'>Victorian Archives of the Eureka Stockade</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.made.org/'>The Museum of Australian Democracy at Eureka (M.A.D.E), formerly The Eureka Centre</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://handle.slv.vic.gov.au/10381/132726'>Overpainted photograph of the 1891 Euraks Stockade cyclorama</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cv.vic.gov.au/stories/eureka-stories/'>Images and video of Eureka from the Public Records Office Victoria</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eurekaflag.com.au/eurekastockade_3.html'>Eureka Stockade</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.migrationheritage.nsw.gov.au/exhibition/objectsthroughtime/1854-the-eureka-flag/'>The Eureka Flag, 1854</link><space/>NSW Migration Heritage Centre statement of historical significance</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:1854 in Australia</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Victoria (Australia)</target></link><link><target>Category:Ballarat</target></link><link><target>Category:Chartism</target></link><link><target>Category:Rebellions in Australia</target></link><link><target>Category:Political history of Australia</target></link><link><target>Category:Protests in Australia</target></link><link><target>Category:1854 riots</target></link><link><target>Category:Riots and civil disorder in Australia</target></link></paragraph></article>