<article title='Atomic_number'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of elements by atomic number</arg></template><link><target>File:Atomic number depiction.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Atomic Number Depiction</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>An explanation of the superscripts and subscripts seen in atomic number notation. Atomic number is the number of protons, and therefore also the total positive charge, in the atomic nucleus.</part></link><link><target>Image:Bohr-atom-PAR.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>The '''RutherfordBohr model''' of the<space/><link><target>hydrogen atom</target></link><space/>(<template><target>nowrap</target><arg name="''Z'' {{">}} 1</arg></template>) or a hydrogen-like ion (<template><target>nowrap</target><arg>''Z'' ><space/>1</arg></template>). In this model it is an essential feature that the photon energy (or frequency) of the electromagnetic radiation emitted (shown) when an electron jumps from one orbital to another, be proportional to the mathematical square of atomic charge (<template><target>nowrap</target><arg>''Z<sup>2</sup>''</arg></template>). Experimental measurement by<space/><link><target>Henry Moseley</target></link><space/>of this radiation for many elements (from<space/><template><target>nowrap</target><arg name="''Z'' {{">}} 13 to 92</arg></template>) showed the results as predicted by Bohr. Both the concept of atomic number and the Bohr model were thereby given scientific credence.</part></link>In<space/><link><target>chemistry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>physics</target></link>, the<space/><bold>atomic number</bold><space/>of a<space/><link><target>chemical element</target></link><space/>(also known as its<space/><bold>proton number</bold>) is the number of<space/><link><target>proton</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>found in the<space/><link><target>atomic nucleus</target><part>nucleus</part></link><space/>of an<space/><link><target>atom</target></link><space/>of that element, and therefore identical to the<space/><link><target>charge number</target></link><space/>of the nucleus. It is conventionally represented by the symbol<space/><bold><italics>Z</italics></bold>. The atomic number uniquely identifies a chemical element. In an<space/><link><target>electric charge</target><part>uncharged</part></link><space/>atom, the atomic number is also equal to the number of<space/><link><target>electron</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The atomic number,<space/><italics>Z</italics>, should not be confused with the<space/><link><target>mass number</target></link>,<space/><italics>A</italics>, which is the number of<space/><link><target>nucleon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the total number of protons and<space/><link><target>neutron</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the nucleus of an atom. The number of neutrons,<space/><italics>N</italics>, is known as the<space/><link><target>neutron number</target></link><space/>of the atom; thus,<space/><italics>A</italics><space/>=<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>+<space/><italics>N</italics><space/>(these quantities are always<space/><link><target>natural number</target><part>whole numbers</part></link>). Since protons and neutrons have approximately the same mass (and the mass of the electrons is negligible for many purposes) and the<space/><link><target>Binding energy#Mass_change</target><part>mass defect</part></link><space/>of nucleon binding is always small compared to the nucleon mass, the<space/><link><target>atomic mass</target></link><space/>of any atom, when expressed in<space/><link><target>Atomic mass unit</target><part>unified atomic mass units</part></link><space/>(making a quantity called the &quot;<link><target>atomic mass</target><part>relative isotopic mass</part></link>&quot;), is roughly (to within 1%) equal to the whole number<space/><italics>A</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Atoms with the same atomic number<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>but different neutron numbers<space/><italics>N</italics>, and hence different atomic masses, are known as<space/><link><target>isotope</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A little more than three-quarters of naturally occurring elements exist as a mixture of isotopes (see<space/><link><target>monoisotopic element</target><trail>s</trail></link>), and the average isotopic mass of an isotopic mixture for an element (called the relative atomic mass) in a defined environment on Earth, determines the element's standard<space/><link><target>atomic weight</target></link>. Historically, it was these atomic weights of elements (in comparison to hydrogen) that were the quantities measurable by chemists in the 19th century.</paragraph><paragraph>The conventional symbol<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>comes from the<space/><link><target>German language</target><part>German</part></link><space/>word<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>de</arg><arg>'''''Z'''ahl''</arg></template><space/>meaning number/numeral/figure, which, prior to the modern synthesis of ideas from chemistry and physics, merely denoted an element's numerical place in the<space/><link><target>periodic table</target></link>, whose order is approximately, but not completely, consistent with the order of the elements by atomic weights. Only after 1915, with the suggestion and evidence that this<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>number was also the nuclear charge and a physical characteristic of atoms, did the word<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>de</arg><arg>''Atom'''z'''ahl''</arg></template><space/>(and its English equivalent<space/><italics>atomic number</italics>) come into common use in this context.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>The periodic table and a natural number for each element</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:DIMendeleevCab.jpg</target><part>150px</part><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>Russian chemist Dmitri Mendeleev created a periodic table of the elements that ordered them numerically by atomic weight, yet occasionally used chemical properties in contradiction to weight.</part></link>Loosely speaking, the existence or construction of a<space/><link><target>periodic table</target></link><space/>of elements creates an ordering of the elements, and so they can be numbered in order.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Dmitri Mendeleev</target></link><space/>claimed that he arranged his first periodic tables in order of<space/><link><target>atomic weight</target></link><space/>(&quot;Atomgewicht&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref' name="dm1869"><link type='external' href='http://www.aip.org/history/curie/periodic.htm'>The Periodic Table of Elements</link>, American Institute of Physics</extension><space/>However, in consideration of the elements' observed chemical properties, he changed the order slightly and placed<space/><link><target>tellurium</target></link><space/>(atomic weight 127.6) ahead of<space/><link><target>iodine</target></link><space/>(atomic weight 126.9).<extension extension_name='ref' name="dm1869"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.rsc.org/chemsoc/visualelements/pages/history_ii.html'>The Development of the Periodic Table</link>, Chemsoc</extension><space/>This placement is consistent with the modern practice of ordering the elements by proton number,<space/><italics>Z</italics>, but that number was not known or suspected at the time.</paragraph><paragraph>A simple numbering based on periodic table position was never entirely satisfactory, however. Besides the case of iodine and tellurium, later several other pairs of elements (such as argon and potassium, cobalt and nickel) were known to have nearly identical or reversed atomic weights, thus requiring their placement in the periodic table to be determined by their chemical properties. However the gradual identification of more and more chemically similar<space/><link><target>lanthanide</target></link><space/>elements, whose atomic number was not obvious, led to inconsistency and uncertainty in the periodic numbering of elements at least from<space/><link><target>lutetium</target></link><space/>(element 71) onwards (<link><target>hafnium</target></link><space/>was not known at this time).<space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Niels Bohr.jpg</target><part>140px</part><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>Niels Bohr's 1913<space/><link><target>Bohr model</target></link><space/>of the atom required van den Broek's atomic number of nuclear charges, and Bohr believed that Moseley's work contributed greatly to the acceptance of the model.</part></link>[[File:Henry Moseley.jpg|140px|thumb|Henry Moseley helped develop the concept of atomic number by showing experimentally (1913) that Van den Broek's 1911 hypothesis combined with the<space/><link><target>Bohr model</target></link><space/>nearly correctly predicted atomic X-ray emissions.]]</paragraph><heading level='3'>The Rutherford-Bohr model and van den Broek</heading><paragraph>In 1911,<space/><link><target>Ernest Rutherford</target></link><space/>gave a<space/><link><target>Rutherford model</target><part>model</part></link><space/>of the atom in which a central core held most of the atom's mass and a positive charge which, in units of the electron's charge, was to be approximately equal to half of the atom's atomic weight, expressed in numbers of hydrogen atoms. This central charge would thus be approximately half the atomic weight (though it was almost 25% different from the atomic number of gold (<italics>Z</italics>&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;79,<space/><italics>A</italics>&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;197), the single element from which Rutherford made his guess). Nevertheless, in spite of Rutherford's estimation that gold had a central charge of about 100 (but was element Z = 79 on the periodic table), a month after Rutherford's paper appeared,<space/><link><target>Antonius van den Broek</target></link><space/>first formally suggested that the central charge and number of electrons in an atom was<space/><italics>exactly</italics><space/>equal to its place in the periodic table (also known as element number, atomic number, and symbolized<space/><italics>Z</italics>). This proved eventually to be the case.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Moseley's 1913 experiment</heading><paragraph>The experimental position improved dramatically after research by<space/><link><target>Henry Moseley</target></link><space/>in 1913.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.rsc.org/Education/Teachers/Resources/periodictable/pre16/order.doc'>Ordering the Elements in the Periodic Table</link>, Royal Chemical Society</extension><space/>Moseley, after discussions with Bohr who was at the same lab (and who had used Van den Broek's hypothesis in his<space/><link><target>Bohr model</target></link><space/>of the atom), decided to test Van den Broek's and Bohr's hypothesis directly, by seeing if spectral lines emitted from excited atoms fitted the Bohr theory's postulation that the frequency of the spectral lines be proportional to the square of<space/><italics>Z</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>To do this, Moseley measured the wavelengths of the innermost photon transitions (K and L lines) produced by the elements from aluminum (<italics>Z</italics>&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;13) to gold (<italics>Z</italics>&amp;nbsp;=&amp;nbsp;79) used as a series of movable anodic targets inside an<space/><link><target>x-ray tube</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.chemistry.co.nz/henry_moseley_article.htm'>Moseley's paper with illustrations</link></extension><space/>The square root of the frequency of these photons (x-rays) increased from one target to the next in an arithmetic progression. This led to the conclusion (<link><target>Moseley's law</target></link>) that the atomic number does closely correspond (with an offset of one unit for K-lines, in Moseley's work) to the calculated<space/><link><target>electric charge</target></link><space/>of the nucleus, i.e. the element number<space/><italics>Z</italics>. Among other things, Moseley demonstrated that the<space/><link><target>lanthanide</target></link><space/>series (from<space/><link><target>lanthanum</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>lutetium</target></link><space/>inclusive) must have 15 membersno fewer and no morewhich was far from obvious from the chemistry at that time.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The proton and the idea of nuclear electrons</heading><paragraph>In 1915 the reason for nuclear charge being quantized in units of Z, which were now recognized to be the same as the element number, was not understood. An old idea called<space/><link><target>Prout's hypothesis</target></link><space/>had postulated that the elements were all made of residues (or &quot;protyles&quot;) of the lightest element hydrogen, which in the Bohr-Rutherford model had a single electron and a nuclear charge of one. However, as early as 1907 Rutherford and<space/><link><target>Thomas Royds</target></link><space/>had shown that alpha particles, which had a charge of +2, were the nuclei of helium atoms, which had a mass four times that of hydrogen, not two times. If Prout's hypothesis were true, something had to be neutralizing some of the charge of the hydrogen nuclei present in the nuclei of heavier atoms.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1917 Rutherford succeeded in generating hydrogen nuclei from a<space/><link><target>nuclear reaction</target></link><space/>between alpha particles and nitrogen gas, and believed he had proven Prout's law. He called the new heavy nuclear particles protons in 1920 (alternate names being proutons and protyles). It had been immediately apparent from the work of Moseley that the nuclei of heavy atoms have more than twice as much mass as would be expected from their being made of<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>nuclei, and thus there was required a hypothesis for the neutralization of the extra<space/><link><target>protons</target></link><space/>presumed present in all heavy nuclei. A helium nucleus was presumed to be composed of four protons plus two &quot;nuclear electrons&quot; (electrons bound inside the nucleus) to cancel two of the charges. At the other end of the periodic table, a nucleus of gold with a mass 197 times that of hydrogen, was thought to contain 118 nuclear electrons in the nucleus to give it a residual charge of + 79, consistent with its atomic number.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The discovery of the neutron makes Z the proton number</heading><paragraph>All consideration of nuclear electrons ended with<space/><link><target>James Chadwick</target></link>'s discovery of the neutron in 1932. An atom of gold now was seen as containing 118 neutrons rather than 118 nuclear electrons, and its positive charge now was realized to come entirely from a content of 79 protons. After 1932, therefore, an element's atomic number Z was also realized to be identical to the<space/><link><target>proton number</target></link><space/>of its nuclei.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The symbol of Z</heading><paragraph>The conventional symbol<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>possibly comes from the<space/><link><target>German language</target><part>German</part></link><space/>word<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>de</arg><arg>''Atom'''z'''ahl''</arg></template><space/>(atomic number).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://antoine.frostburg.edu/chem/senese/101/atoms/faq/why-is-atomic-number-Z.shtml'>Origin of symbol Z</link></extension><space/>However, prior to 1915, the word<space/><italics>Zahl</italics><space/>(simply<space/><italics>number</italics>) was used for an element's assigned number in the periodic table.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Chemical properties</heading><paragraph>Each element has a specific set of chemical properties as a consequence of the number of electrons present in the neutral atom, which is<space/><italics>Z</italics><space/>(the atomic number). The<space/><link><target>electron configuration</target><part>configuration</part></link><space/>of these electrons follows from the principles of<space/><link><target>quantum mechanics</target></link>. The number of electrons in each element's<space/><link><target>electron shell</target><trail>s</trail></link>, particularly the outermost<space/><link><target>valence shell</target></link>, is the primary factor in determining its<space/><link><target>chemical bonding</target></link><space/>behavior. Hence, it is the atomic number alone that determines the chemical properties of an element; and it is for this reason that an element can be defined as consisting of<space/><italics>any</italics><space/>mixture of atoms with a given atomic number.</paragraph><heading level='2'>New elements</heading><paragraph>The quest for new elements is usually described using atomic numbers. As of 2010, elements with atomic numbers 1 to 118 have been observed. Synthesis of new elements is accomplished by bombarding target atoms of heavy elements with ions, such that the sum of the atomic numbers of the target and ion elements equals the atomic number of the element being created. In general, the<space/><link><target>half-life</target></link><space/>becomes shorter as atomic number increases, though an &quot;<link><target>island of stability</target></link>&quot; may exist for undiscovered isotopes with certain numbers of protons and neutrons.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>History of the periodic table</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Effective atomic number</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Atomic theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Prout's hypothesis</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Atomic Number</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>Category:Chemical properties</target></link></preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>Category:Nuclear physics</target></link><link><target>Category:Atoms</target></link><link><target>Category:Dimensionless numbers of chemistry</target></link></paragraph></article>