<article title='Charles_Baudelaire'><paragraph><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Charles Pierre Baudelaire
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Étienne Carjat, Portrait of Charles Baudelaire, circa 1862.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Charles Baudelaire by [[Étienne Carjat]], 1863
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>April 9, 1821
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>Paris, France
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{Death date and age|1867|8|31|1821|4|9}}
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>Paris, France
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Poet, art critic
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>French
</arg><arg name="period"><space/>1844–1866
</arg><arg name="movement"><space/>[[Symbolism (arts)|Symbolist]], [[Modernism|Modernist]]
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>Baudelaire signatur .svg
</arg></template><template><target>French literature sidebar</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Charles Pierre Baudelaire</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>əl</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>ɛər</arg></template>;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/baudelaire'>&quot;Baudelaire&quot;</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Random House Webster's Unabridged Dictionary</target></link></italics>.</extension><space/><template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>ʃaʁl bodlɛʁ</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>; April 9, 1821 August 31, 1867) was a<space/><link><target>French poetry</target><part>French poet</part></link><space/>who also produced notable work as an essayist,<space/><link><target>art critic</target></link>, and pioneering<space/><link><target>Translation</target><part>translator</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>His most famous work,<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Flowers of Evil</italics>), expresses the changing nature of beauty in modern, industrializing Paris during the 19th century. Baudelaire's highly original style of prose-poetry influenced a whole generation of poets including<space/><link><target>Paul Verlaine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arthur Rimbaud</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stphane Mallarm</target></link><space/>among many others. He is credited with coining the term &quot;<link><target>modernity</target></link>&quot; (<italics>modernit</italics>) to designate the fleeting, ephemeral experience of life in an urban metropolis, and the responsibility art has to capture that experience.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;By modernity I mean the transitory, the fugitive, the contingent which make up one half of art, the other being the eternal and the immutable.&quot; Charles Baudelaire, &quot;The Painter of Modern Life&quot; in<space/><italics>The Painter of Modern Life and Other Essays</italics>, edited and translated by Jonathan Mayne. London: Phaidon Press, 13.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Baudelaire the poet</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Who among us has not dreamt, in moments of ambition, of the miracle of a poetic prose, musical without rhythm and rhyme, supple and staccato enough to adapt to the lyrical stirrings of the soul, the undulations of dreams, and sudden leaps of consciousness. This obsessive idea is above all a child of giant cities, of the intersecting of their myriad relations.</arg><arg>Dedication of ''[[Le Spleen de Paris]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Baudelaire is one of the major innovators in<space/><link><target>French literature</target></link>. His poetry is influenced by the French romantic poets of the earlier 19th century, although its attention to the formal features of verse connects it more closely to the work of the contemporary &quot;Parnassians&quot;. As for theme and tone, in his works we see the rejection of the belief in the supremacy of nature and the fundamental goodness of man as typically espoused by the romantics and expressed by them in rhetorical, effusive and public voice in favor of a new urban sensibility, an awareness of individual moral complexity, an interest in vice (linked with<space/><link><target>Decadent movement</target><part>decadence</part></link>) and refined sensual and aesthetic pleasures, and the use of urban subject matter, such as the city, the crowd, individual passers-by, all expressed in highly ordered verse, sometimes through a cynical and ironic voice. Formally, the use of sound to create atmosphere, and of &quot;symbols&quot;, (images that take on an expanded function within the poem), betray a move towards considering the poem as a self-referential object, an idea further developed by the Symbolists<space/><link><target>Paul Verlaine</target><part>Verlaine</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stphane Mallarm</target><part>Mallarm</part></link>, who acknowledge Baudelaire as a pioneer in this regard.</paragraph><paragraph>Beyond his innovations in versification and the theories of symbolism and &quot;correspondences&quot;, an awareness of which is essential to any appreciation of the literary value of his work, aspects of his work that regularly receive (or have received) much critical discussion include the role of women, the theological direction of his work and his alleged advocacy of &quot;satanism&quot;, his experience of drug-induced states of mind, the figure of the dandy, his stance regarding democracy and its implications for the individual, his response to the spiritual uncertainties of the time, his criticisms of the bourgeois, and his advocacy of modern music and painting (e.g.,<space/><link><target>Richard Wagner</target><part>Wagner</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target><part>Delacroix</part></link>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early life</heading><paragraph>Baudelaire was born in Paris, France, on April 9, 1821, and baptized two months later at<space/><link><target>Saint-Sulpice, Paris</target><part>Saint-Sulpice</part></link><space/>Roman Catholic Church.<extension extension_name='ref'>Charles Baudelaire, Richard Howard.<space/><italics>Les Fleurs Du Mal</italics>. David R. Godine Publisher, 1983, p.xxv. ISBN 0-87923-462-8, ISBN 978-0-87923-462-1.</extension><space/>His father, Franois Baudelaire, a senior civil servant and amateur artist, was 34 years older than Baudelaire's mother. Franois died during Baudelaire's childhood, in 1827. The following year, Caroline married Lieutenant Colonel Jacques Aupick, who later became a French ambassador to various noble courts. Biographers have often seen this as a crucial moment, considering that finding himself no longer the sole focus of his mother's affection left him with a trauma, which goes some way to explaining the excesses later apparent in his life. He stated in a letter to her that, &quot;There was in my childhood a period of passionate love for you.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 16</extension><space/>Baudelaire regularly begged his mother for money throughout his career, often promising that a lucrative publishing contract or journalistic commission was just around the corner.</paragraph><paragraph>Baudelaire was educated in<space/><link><target>Lyon</target></link>, where he boarded. Baudelaire at fourteen was described by a classmate: &quot;He was much more refined and distinguished than any of our fellow pupils [...] we are bound to one another [...] by shared tastes and sympathies, the precocious love of fine works of literature.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 35</extension><space/>Baudelaire was erratic in his studies, at times diligent, at other times prone to &quot;idleness&quot;. Later, he attended the<space/><link><target>Lyce Louis-le-Grand</target></link><space/>in Paris, studying law, a popular course for those not yet decided on any particular career. Baudelaire began to frequent prostitutes and may have contracted<space/><link><target>gonorrhea</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>syphilis</target></link><space/>during this period. Baudelaire began to run up debts, mostly for clothes. Upon gaining his<space/><link><target>Academic degree</target><part>degree</part></link><space/>in 1839, he told his brother &quot;I don't feel I have a vocation for anything.&quot; His stepfather had in mind a career in law or diplomacy, but instead Baudelaire decided to embark upon a literary career. His mother later recalled: &quot;Oh, what grief! If Charles had let himself be guided by his stepfather, his career would have been very different.... He would not have left a name in literature, it is true, but we should have been happier, all three of us.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 70</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Baudelaire 1844.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Portrait of Baudelaire, painted in 1844 by Emile Deroy (18201846)</part></link>His stepfather sent him on a voyage to<space/><link><target>Calcutta, India</target></link>, in 1841 in the hope of ending his dissolute habits. The trip provided strong impressions of the sea, sailing, and exotic ports, that he later employed in his poetry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, pp. 6768</extension><space/>(Baudelaire later exaggerated his aborted trip to create a legend about his youthful travels and experiences, including &quot;riding on elephants&quot;.) Baudelaire returned to the taverns where he began to compose some of the poems of &quot;Les Fleurs du Mal&quot;. At 21, he received a good-sized inheritance but squandered much of it within a few years. His family obtained a decree to place his property in trust,<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 71</extension><space/>which he resented bitterly, at one point arguing that allowing him to fail alone financially would have been the one sure way of teaching him the value of maintaining well-ordered finances.</paragraph><paragraph>Baudelaire became known in artistic circles as a<space/><link><target>dandy</target></link><space/>and free-spender. During this time,<space/><link><target>Jeanne Duval</target></link><space/>became his mistress. His mother thought Duval a &quot;Black Venus&quot; who &quot;tortured him in every way&quot; and drained him of money at every opportunity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 75</extension><space/>She was rejected by his family. He made a suicide attempt during this time.</paragraph><paragraph>Baudelaire took part in the<space/><link><target>Revolutions of 1848 in France</target><part>Revolutions of 1848</part></link><space/>and wrote for a revolutionary newspaper. However, his interest was passing, as he was later to note in his political writings in his journals.</paragraph><paragraph>In the early 1850s, Baudelaire struggled with poor health, pressing debts, and irregular literary output. He often moved from one lodging to another to escape creditors. He received many projects that he was unable to complete, though he did finish translations of stories by<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Upon the death of his stepfather in 1857, Baudelaire received no mention in the will but he was heartened nonetheless that the division with his mother might now be mended. At 36 he wrote her: &quot;believe that I belong to you absolutely, and that I belong only to you&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 219.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Published career</heading><paragraph>His first published work was his art review &quot;Salon of 1845&quot;, which attracted immediate attention for its boldness. Many of his critical opinions were novel in their time, including his championing of<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target><part>Delacroix</part></link>, and some of his views seem remarkably in tune with the future theories of the Impressionist painters.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1846, Baudelaire wrote his second Salon review, gaining additional credibility as an advocate and critic of<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target></link>. His support of<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target><part>Delacroix</part></link><space/>as the foremost Romantic artist gained widespread notice.<extension extension_name='ref' name="crapkq">Richardson 1994, p. 110.</extension><space/>The following year Baudelaire's novella<space/><italics><link><target>La Fanfarlo</target></link></italics><space/>was published.</paragraph><heading level='4'><italics>The Flowers of Evil</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Fleurs du mal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>The first edition of ''<link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target></link>'' with author's notes</part></link>Baudelaire was a slow and fastidious worker, often sidetracked by<space/><link><target>Laziness</target><part>indolence</part></link>, emotional distress and illness, and it was not until 1857 that he published his first and most famous volume of poems,<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Flowers of Evil</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Clark</arg><arg name="first1">Carol</arg><arg name="title">Selected Poems</arg><arg name="section">Notes on the Text</arg><arg name="date">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books Ltd</arg><arg name="location">By Charles Baudelaire. London</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-14-044624-1</arg><arg name="page">xxiii</arg></template></extension><space/>Some of these poems had already appeared in the<space/><italics><link><target>Revue des deux mondes</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>Review of Two Worlds</italics>) in 1855, when they were published by Baudelaire's friend<space/><link><target>Auguste Poulet Malassis</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chisholm</arg><arg>1911</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Baudelaire, Charles. Les Fleurs du mal. Paris:<space/><italics>Revue des Deux Mondes</italics><space/>(XXVe anne, seconde srie de la nouvelle priode, tome dixime), 1855. pp. 10791093</extension><space/>Some of the poems had also previously appeared a &quot;fugitive verse&quot; in various French magazines during the previous decade.<extension extension_name='ref'>Huneker, James. Introductory preface to:<space/><italics>The Poems and Prose Poems of Charles Baudelaire</italics>. New York: Brentano's, 1919. p. xvii</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The poems found a small, appreciative audience, but greater public attention was given to their subject matter. The effect on fellow artists was, as<space/><link><target>Thodore de Banville</target></link><space/>stated, &quot;immense, prodigious, unexpected, mingled with admiration and with some indefinable anxious fear&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 236.</extension><space/><link><target>Gustave Flaubert</target></link>, recently attacked in a similar fashion for<space/><italics><link><target>Madame Bovary</target></link></italics><space/>(and acquitted), was impressed and wrote to Baudelaire: &quot;You have found a way to rejuvenate Romanticism.... You are as unyielding as marble, and as penetrating as an English mist.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 241.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The principal themes of<space/><link><target>Human sexuality</target><part>sex</part></link><space/>and death were considered scandalous. He also touched on lesbianism, sacred and profane love, metamorphosis, melancholy, the corruption of the city, lost innocence, the oppressiveness of living, and wine. Notable in some poems is Baudelaire's use of imagery of the sense of smell and of fragrances, which is used to evoke feelings of<space/><link><target>nostalgia</target></link><space/>and past intimacy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 231.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The book, however, quickly became a byword for unwholesomeness among mainstream critics of the day. Some critics called a few of the poems &quot;masterpieces of passion, art and poetry&quot; but other poems were deemed to merit no less than legal action to suppress them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, pp. 232237</extension><space/>J. Habas writing in<space/><italics><link><target>Le Figaro</target></link></italics>, led the charge against Baudelaire, writing: &quot;Everything in it which is not hideous is incomprehensible, everything one understands is putrid.&quot; Then Baudelaire responded to the outcry, in a prophetic letter to his mother:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;You know that I have always considered that literature and the arts pursue an aim independent of morality. Beauty of conception and style is enough for me. But this book, whose title (<italics>Fleurs du mal</italics>) says everything, is clad, as you will see, in a cold and sinister beauty. It was created with rage and patience. Besides, the proof of its positive worth is in all the ill that they speak of it. The book enrages people. Moreover, since I was terrified myself of the horror that I should inspire, I cut out a third from the proofs. They deny me everything, the spirit of invention and even the knowledge of the French language. I don't care a rap about all these imbeciles, and I know that this book, with its virtues and its faults, will make its way in the memory of the lettered public, beside the best poems of V. Hugo, Th. Gautier and even Byron.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 238.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Rops Les Epaves 1866.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Illustration cover for ''<link><target>Les paves</target></link>'', by Baudelaire's friend<space/><link><target>Flicien Rops</target></link></part></link>Baudelaire, his publisher and the<space/><link><target>printer (publisher)</target><part>printer</part></link><space/>were successfully prosecuted for creating an offense against public<space/><link><target>morality</target><part>morals</part></link>. They were fined, but Baudelaire was not imprisoned.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 248</extension><space/>Six of the poems were suppressed, but printed later as<space/><italics><link><target>Les paves</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>The Wrecks</italics>) (<link><target>Brussels</target></link>, 1866). Another edition of<space/><italics>Les Fleurs du mal</italics>, without these poems, but with considerable additions, appeared in 1861. Many notables rallied behind Baudelaire and condemned the sentence.<space/><link><target>Victor Hugo</target></link><space/>wrote to him: &quot;Your<space/><italics>fleurs du mal</italics><space/>shine and dazzle like stars.... I applaud your vigorous spirit with all my might.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="yvjown">Richardson 1994, p. 250.</extension><space/>Baudelaire did not appeal the judgment, but his fine was reduced. Nearly 100 years later, on May 11, 1949, Baudelaire was vindicated, the judgment officially reversed, and the six banned poems reinstated in France.<extension extension_name='ref' name="yvjown"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the poem &quot;Au lecteur&quot; (&quot;To the Reader&quot;) that prefaces<space/><italics>Les Fleurs du mal</italics>, Baudelaire accuses his readers of<space/><link><target>hypocrisy</target></link><space/>and of being as guilty of<space/><link><target>sin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and lies as the poet:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>... If rape or arson, poison or the knife</listitem><listitem>Has wove no pleasing patterns in the stuff</listitem><listitem>Of this drab canvas we accept as life</listitem><listitem>It is because we are not bold enough!<list type='ident'><listitem>(<link><target>Roy Campbell (poet)</target><part>Roy Campbell</part></link>'s translation)</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Final years</heading><paragraph>Baudelaire next worked on a translation and adaptation of<space/><link><target>Thomas De Quincey</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Confessions of an English Opium Eater</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 311.</extension><space/>Other works in the years that followed included<space/><italics><link><target>Le Spleen de Paris</target><part>Petits Pomes en prose</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>Small<space/><link><target>prose poetry</target><part>Prose poems</part></link></italics>); a series of art reviews published in the<space/><italics>Pays, Exposition universelle</italics><space/>(<italics>Country, World Fair</italics>); studies on<space/><link><target>Gustave Flaubert</target></link><space/>(in<space/><italics><link><target>L'Artiste</target></link></italics>, October 18, 1857); on<space/><link><target>Thophile Gautier</target></link><space/>(<italics>Revue contemporaine</italics>, September 1858); various articles contributed to Eugene Crepet's<space/><italics>Potes francais</italics>;<space/><italics><link><target>Les Paradis artificiels</target></link>: opium et haschisch</italics><space/>(<italics>French poets; Artificial Paradises: opium and hashish</italics>) (1860); and<space/><italics>Un Dernier Chapitre de l'histoire des oeuvres de Balzac</italics><space/>(<italics>A Final Chapter of the history of works of Balzac</italics>) (1880), originally an article &quot;Comment on paye ses dettes quand on a du gnie&quot; (&quot;How one pays one's debts when one has genius&quot;), in which his criticism turns against his friends<space/><link><target>Honor de Balzac</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thophile Gautier</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Grard de Nerval</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Chisholm</arg><arg>1911</arg></template><link><target>Image:Jeanne Duval.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Jeanne Duval</target></link>, in a painting by<space/><link><target>douard Manet</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Apollonie Sabatier-Vincent Vidal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Apollonie Sabatier</target></link>, muse and one time mistress, painted by<space/><link><target>Vincent Vidal</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Charles Baudelaire tomb in Montparnasse Cemetery.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Cenotaph of Charles Baudelaire, Montparnasse Cemetery</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By 1859, his illnesses, his long-term use of<space/><link><target>laudanum</target></link>, his life of stress and poverty had taken a toll and Baudelaire had aged noticeably. But at last, his mother relented and agreed to let him live with her for a while at<space/><link><target>Honfleur</target></link>. Baudelaire was productive and at peace in the seaside town, his poem<space/><italics>Le Voyage</italics><space/>being one example of his efforts during that time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 281.</extension><space/>In 1860, he became an ardent supporter of<space/><link><target>Richard Wagner</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>His financial difficulties increased again, however, particularly after his publisher Poulet Malassis went bankrupt in 1861. In 1864, he left Paris for Belgium, partly in the hope of selling the<space/><link><target>copyright</target><part>rights</part></link><space/>to his works and also to give lectures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 400</extension><space/>His long-standing relationship with<space/><link><target>Jeanne Duval</target></link><space/>continued on-and-off, and he helped her to the end of his life. Baudelaire's relationships with actress Marie Daubrun and with courtesan<space/><link><target>Apollonie Sabatier</target></link>, though the source of much inspiration, never produced any lasting satisfaction. He smoked<space/><link><target>opium</target></link>, and in Brussels he began to<space/><link><target>alcoholism</target><part>drink to excess</part></link>. Baudelaire suffered a massive stroke in 1866 and<space/><link><target>paralysis</target></link><space/>followed. After more than a year of<space/><link><target>aphasia</target></link>, he received the<space/><link><target>last rites</target></link><space/>of the Catholic Church.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.library.vanderbilt.edu/baudelaire/englishintro.html'>Library.vanderbilt.edu</link></extension><space/>The last two years of his life were spent, in a semi-paralyzed state, in &quot;maisons de sant&quot; in Brussels and in Paris, where he died on August 31, 1867. Baudelaire is buried in the<space/><link><target>Cimetire du Montparnasse</target></link>, Paris.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of Baudelaire's works were published posthumously. After his death, his mother paid off his substantial debts, and at last she found some comfort in Baudelaire's emerging fame. &quot;I see that my son, for all his faults, has his place in literature.&quot; She lived another four years.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Critiques</heading><paragraph>Baudelaire was an active participant in the artistic life of his times. As critic and essayist, he wrote extensively and perceptively about the luminaries and themes of French culture. He was frank with friends and enemies, rarely took the diplomatic approach and sometimes responded violently verbally, which often undermined his cause.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 268.</extension><space/>His associations were numerous and included:<space/><link><target>Gustave Courbet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Honor Daumier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franz Liszt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Champfleury</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Victor Hugo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gustave Flaubert</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Balzac</target></link><space/>and the artists and writers that follow.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Edgar Allan Poe</heading><paragraph>In 1846 and 1847, Baudelaire became acquainted with the works of<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target><part>Poe</part></link>, in which he found tales and poems that had, he claimed, long existed in his own brain but never taken shape. Baudelaire had much in common with Poe (who died in 1849 at age forty). The two poets display a similar sensibility of the<space/><link><target>macabre</target></link><space/>and supernatural turn of mind; each struggled with illness, poverty, and melancholy. Like Poe, Baudelaire believed in the doctrine of<space/><link><target>original sin</target></link>, denounced democracy and the idea of progress and of man's natural goodness, and Poe held a disdainful aristocratic attitude similar to Baudelaire's<space/><link><target>dandy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Baudelaire, Selected writings on art and artists, CUP Archive, 1981, Introduction, p. 17.</extension><space/>Baudelaire saw in Poe a precursor and tried to be his French contemporary counterpart.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson 1994, p. 140.</extension><space/>From this time until 1865, he was largely occupied with translating Poe's works; his translations were widely praised. Baudelaire was not the first French translator of Poe, but his &quot;scrupulous translations&quot; were considered among the best. These were published as<space/><italics>Histoires extraordinaires</italics><space/>(<italics>Extraordinary stories</italics>) (1852),<space/><italics>Nouvelles histoires extraordinaires</italics><space/>(<italics>New extraordinary stories</italics>) (1857),<space/><italics><link><target>The Narrative of Arthur Gordon Pym of Nantucket</target><part>Aventures d'Arthur Gordon Pym</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Eureka: A Prose Poem</target><part>Eureka</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics>Histoires grotesques et srieuses</italics><space/>(<italics>Grotesque and serious stories</italics>) (1865). Two essays on Poe are to be found in his<space/><italics>Oeuvres compltes</italics><space/>(<italics>Complete works</italics>) (vols. v. and vi.).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Eugne Delacroix</heading><paragraph>A strong supporter of the Romantic painter<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target><part>Delacroix</part></link>, Baudelaire called him &quot;a poet in painting&quot;. Baudelaire also absorbed much of Delacroix's aesthetic ideas as expressed in his journals. As Baudelaire elaborated in his &quot;Salon of 1846&quot;, &quot;As one contemplates his series of pictures, one seems to be attending the celebration of some grievous mystery.... This grave and lofty melancholy shines with a dull light ... plaintive and profound like a melody by Weber.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="crapkq"></extension><space/>Delacroix, though appreciative, kept his distance from Baudelaire, particularly after the scandal of<space/><italics>Les Fleurs du mal</italics>. In private correspondence, Delacroix stated that Baudelaire &quot;really gets on my nerves&quot; and he expressed his unhappiness with Baudelaire's persistent comments about &quot;melancholy&quot; and &quot;feverishness&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Lois Boe<space/></arg><arg name="last">Hyslop<space/></arg><arg name="title">Baudelaire, Man of His Time<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980<space/></arg><arg name="page">14<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-300-02513-0<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Richard Wagner</heading><paragraph>Baudelaire had no formal musical training, and knew little of composers beyond<space/><link><target>Beethoven</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carl Maria von Weber</target></link>. Weber was in some ways<space/><link><target>Richard Wagner</target><part>Wagner</part></link>'s precursor, using the<space/><link><target>leitmotif</target></link><space/>and conceiving the idea of the &quot;total art work&quot; (&quot;Gesamtkunstwerk&quot;), both of which gained Baudelaire's admiration. Before even hearing Wagner's music, Baudelaire studied reviews and essays about him, and formulated his impressions. Later, Baudelaire put them into his non-technical analysis of Wagner, which was highly regarded, particularly his essay &quot;Richard Wagner et Tannhuser Paris&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="yhkyza">Hyslop (1980), p. 68.</extension><space/>Baudelaire's reaction to music was passionate and psychological. &quot;Music engulfs (possesses) me like the sea.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="yhkyza"></extension><space/>After attending three Wagner concerts in Paris in 1860, Baudelaire wrote to the composer: &quot;I had a feeling of pride and joy in understanding, in being possessed, in being overwhelmed, a truly sensual pleasure like that of rising in the air.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 69</extension><space/>Baudelaire's writings contributed to the elevation of Wagner and to the cult of<space/><link><target>Wagnerism</target></link><space/>that swept Europe in the following decades.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Thophile Gautier</heading><paragraph><link><target>Thophile Gautier</target><part>Gautier</part></link>, writer and poet, earned Baudelaire's respect for his perfection of form and his mastery of language, though Baudelaire thought he lacked deeper emotion and spirituality. Both strove to express the artist's inner vision, which<space/><link><target>Heinrich Heine</target></link><space/>had earlier stated: &quot;In artistic matters, I am a supernaturalist. I believe that the artist can not find all his forms in nature, but that the most remarkable are revealed to him in his soul.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 131.</extension><space/>Gautier's frequent meditations on death and the horror of life are themes which influenced Baudelaire writings. In gratitude for their friendship and commonality of vision, Baudelaire dedicated<space/><italics>Les Fleurs du mal</italics><space/>to Gautier.</paragraph><heading level='3'>douard Manet</heading><paragraph><link><target>douard Manet</target><part>Manet</part></link><space/>and Baudelaire became constant companions from around 1855. In the early 1860s, Baudelaire accompanied Manet on daily sketching trips and often met him socially. Manet also lent Baudelaire money and looked after his affairs, particularly when Baudelaire went to Belgium. Baudelaire encouraged Manet to strike out on his own path and not succumb to criticism. &quot;Manet has great talent, a talent which will stand the test of time. But he has a weak character. He seems to me crushed and stunned by shock.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 55.</extension><space/>In his painting<space/><italics><link><target>Music in the Tuileries</target></link></italics>, Manet includes portraits of his friends<space/><link><target>Thophile Gautier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jacques Offenbach</target></link>, and Baudelaire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Music in the Tuileries Gardens<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Gallery (London)|The National Gallery]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nationalgallery.org.uk/cgi-bin/WebObjects.dll/CollectionPublisher.woa/wa/work?workNumber</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 13, 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>While it's difficult to differentiate who influenced whom, both Manet and Baudelaire discussed and expressed some common themes through their respective arts. Baudelaire praised the modernity of Manet's subject matter: &quot;almost all our originality comes from the stamp that 'time' imprints upon our feelings.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 53.</extension><space/>When Manet's famous<space/><italics><link><target>Olympia (painting)</target><part>Olympia</part></link></italics><space/>(1863), a portrait of a nude prostitute, provoked a scandal for its blatant realism mixed with an imitation of<space/><link><target>Sleeping Venus (Giorgione)</target><part>Renaissance motifs</part></link>, Baudelaire worked privately to support his friend, though he offered no public defense (he was, however, ill at the time). When Baudelaire returned from Belgium after his stroke, Manet and his wife were frequent visitors at the nursing home and she would play passages from Wagner for Baudelaire on the piano.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 51.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nadar</heading><paragraph><link><target>Nadar (photographer)</target><part>Nadar</part></link><space/>(Flix Tournachon) was a noted caricaturist, scientist and important early photographer. Baudelaire admired Nadar, one of his closest friends, and wrote: &quot;Nadar is the most amazing manifestation of vitality.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 65.</extension><space/>They moved in similar circles and Baudelaire made many social connections through him. Nadar's ex-mistress<space/><link><target>Jeanne Duval</target></link><space/>became Baudelaire's mistress around 1842. Baudelaire became interested in photography in the 1850s and, denouncing it as an art form, advocated its return to &quot;its real purpose, which is that of being the servant to the sciences and arts&quot;. Photography should not, according to Baudelaire, encroach upon &quot;the domain of the impalpable and the imaginary&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hyslop (1980), p. 63.</extension><space/>Nadar remained a stalwart friend right to Baudelaire's last days and wrote his obituary notice in<space/><italics><link><target>Le Figaro</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Philosophy</heading><paragraph>Many of Baudelaire's philosophical proclamations were considered scandalous and intentionally provocative in his time. He wrote on a wide range of subjects, drawing criticism and outrage from many quarters.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Love</heading><paragraph>&quot;There is an invincible taste for prostitution in the heart of man, from which comes his horror of solitude. He wants to be 'two'. The man of genius wants to be 'one'.... It is this horror of solitude, the need to lose oneself in the external flesh, that man nobly calls 'the need to love'.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sncxdz">Richardson 1994, p. 50</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Marriage</heading><paragraph>&quot;Unable to suppress love, the Church wanted at least to disinfect it, and it created marriage.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sncxdz"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The artist</heading><paragraph>&quot;The more a man cultivates the arts, the less randy he becomes.... Only the brute is good at coupling, and copulation is the lyricism of the masses. To copulate is to enter into anotherand the artist never emerges from himself.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sncxdz"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pleasure</heading><paragraph>&quot;Personally, I think that the unique and supreme delight lies in the certainty of doing '<link><target>evil</target></link>'and men and women know from birth that all pleasure lies in evil.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sncxdz"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;But what can eternity of damnation matter to someone who has felt, if only for a second, the infinity of delight??&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>Politics</heading><paragraph>Along with Poe, Baudelaire named the arch-<link><target>reactionary</target></link><space/><link><target>Joseph de Maistre</target></link><space/>as his<space/><link><target>matre penser</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://assets.cambridge.org/052183/094X/excerpt/052183094X_excerpt.htm</arg><arg name="title">The Cambridge Companion to Baudelaire</arg><arg name="work">cambridge.org</arg></template></extension><space/>and adopted increasingly aristocratic views. In his journals, he wrote &quot;There is no form of rational and assured government save an aristocracy. A monarchy or a republic, based upon democracy, are equally absurd and feeble. The immense nausea of advertisements. There are but three beings worthy of respect: the priest, the warrior and the poet. To know, to kill and to create. The rest of mankind may be taxed and drudged, they are born for the stable, that is to say, to practise what they call professions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://xtf.lib.virginia.edu/xtf/view?docId</arg><arg name="title">Intimate journals :: :: University of Virginia Library</arg><arg name="work">virginia.edu</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The public</heading><paragraph>&quot;In this regards, my friend, you're like the public, to whom one should never offer a delicate perfume. It exasperates them. Give them only carefully selected garbage.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Crosby"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Time</heading><paragraph>&quot;The will to work must dominate, for art is long and time is brief.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crosby">Baudelaire, Charles. Translated by William H. Crosby,<space/><italics>The Flowers of Evil &amp; Paris Spleen</italics>, BOA Editions, Ltd., 1991.</extension><space/>(<link><target>Ars longa, vita brevis</target><part>quoting Hippocrates</part></link>)</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Each man bears within himself his own dose of natural opium, incessantly secreted and renewed, and, from birth to death, how many hours can we count filled with pleasure,with prosperous and effective action?&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Crosby"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Influence</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Gustave Courbet 033.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Portrait by<space/><link><target>Gustave Courbet</target></link>, 1848</part></link>Baudelaire's influence on the direction of modern French (and English) language literature was considerable. The most significant French writers to come after him were generous with tributes; four years after his death,<space/><link><target>Arthur Rimbaud</target></link><space/>praised him in a letter as 'the king of poets, a true God'.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rimbaud, Arthur:<space/><italics>Oeuvres compltes</italics>, p. 253, NRF/Gallimard, 1972.</extension><space/>In 1895,<space/><link><target>Stphane Mallarm</target></link><space/>published a sonnet in Baudelaire's memory, 'Le Tombeau de Charles Baudelaire'.<space/><link><target>Marcel Proust</target></link>, in an essay published in 1922, stated that along with<space/><link><target>Alfred de Vigny</target></link>, Baudelaire was 'the greatest poet of the nineteenth century'.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Concerning Baudelaire</italics><space/>in Proust, Marcel:<space/><italics>Against Sainte-Beuve and Other Essays</italics>, p. 286, trans. John Sturrock, Penguin, 1994.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the English-speaking world,<space/><link><target>Edmund Wilson</target></link><space/>credited Baudelaire as providing an initial impetus for the<space/><link><target>Symbolism (arts)</target><part>Symbolist</part></link><space/>movement, by virtue of his translations of Poe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wilson, Edmund:<space/><italics>Axel's Castle</italics>, p. 20, Fontana, 1962 (originally published 1931).</extension><space/>In 1930,<space/><link><target>T. S. Eliot</target></link>, while asserting that Baudelaire had not yet received a &quot;just appreciation&quot; even in France, claimed that the poet had &quot;great genius&quot; and asserted that his &quot;technical mastery which can hardly be overpraised ... has made his verse an inexhaustible study for later poets, not only in his own language&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Baudelaire', in Eliot, T. S.:<space/><italics>Selected Essays</italics>, pp. 422 and 425, Faber &amp; Faber, 1961.</extension><space/>Eliot also alluded to Baudelaire's poetry directly in his own poetry. For example, he quoted the last line of Baudelaire's 'Au Lecteur' in the last line of Section I of 'The Waste Land.'</paragraph><paragraph>At the same time that Eliot was affirming Baudelaire's importance from a broadly conservative and explicitly Christian viewpoint,<extension extension_name='ref'>cf. Eliot, 'Religion in Literature', in Eliot, op. cit., p. 388.</extension><space/><link><target>Left-wing politics</target><part>left-wing</part></link><space/>critics such as Wilson and<space/><link><target>Walter Benjamin</target></link><space/>were able to do so from a dramatically different perspective. Benjamin translated Baudelaire's<space/><italics>Tableaux Parisiens</italics><space/>into German and published a major essay on translation<extension extension_name='ref'>'The Task of the Translator', in Benjamin, Walter:<space/><italics>Selected Writings Vol. 1: 19131926</italics>, pp. 253263, Belknap/Harvard, 1996.</extension><space/>as the foreword.</paragraph><paragraph>In the late 1930s, Benjamin used Baudelaire as a starting point and focus for his monumental attempt at a<space/><link><target>Historical materialism</target><part>materialist</part></link><space/>assessment of 19th-century culture,<space/><italics><link><target>Arcades Project</target><part>Das Passagenwerk</part></link>.</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Benjamin, Walter:<space/><italics>The Arcades Project</italics>, trans. Howard Eiland and Kevin McLaughlin, Belknap/Harvard, 1999.</extension><space/>For Benjamin, Baudelaire's importance lay in his anatomies of the<space/><link><target>crowd</target></link>, of the city and of<space/><link><target>modernity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>'The Paris of the Second Empire in Baudelaire' in Benjamin, Walter:<space/><italics>Selected Writings Vol. 4 19381940</italics>, pp. 392, Belknap/Harvard, 2003.</extension><space/><link><target>Franois Porche</target></link><space/>published a poetry collection called<space/><italics>Charles Baudelaire: Poetry Collection</italics><space/>in memory of Baudelaire.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1982, avant-garde performance artist and vocalist<space/><link><target>Diamanda Gals</target></link><space/>recorded an adaptation of his poem<space/><italics><link><target>The Litanies of Satan</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics><link><target>Les Litanies de Satan</target></link></italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>The song &quot;How Beautiful You Are&quot; by<space/><link><target>The Cure</target></link><space/>from their 1987 album<space/><italics><link><target>Kiss Me, Kiss Me, Kiss Me</target></link></italics><space/>was inspired by and based on Baudelaire's poem &quot;The Eyes of the Poor&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Robert Smith and his Books</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chainofflowers.com/rockfolk0703.html</arg><arg name="work">chainofflowers.com</arg><arg name="publisher">Rock and Folk Magazine</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 1998 Spanglish classic novel<space/><italics><link><target>Yo-Yo Boing!</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Giannina Braschi</target></link><space/>features a debate between artists and writers on the greatness of Baudlelaire versus<space/><link><target>Arthur Rimbaud</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Antonin Artaud</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Yo-Yo Boing!, Introduction by Doris Sommer, Harvard University</arg><arg name="publisher">Latin American Literary Review Press</arg><arg name="date">1998</arg><arg name="ISBN">0-935480-97-8</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>in 2002, alt-rock band<space/><link><target>...And You Will Know Us by the Trail of Dead</target></link><space/>included a song titled &quot;Baudelaire&quot; on their album<space/><italics><link><target>Source Tags and Codes</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2008, the Italian band<space/><link><target>Baustelle</target></link><space/>dedicates to him the song &quot;Baudelaire&quot; on its album<space/><italics><link><target>Amen (Baustelle)</target><part>Amen</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The 2011 Latin American postcolonial novel &quot;<link><target>United States of Banana</target></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>Giannina Braschi</target></link><space/>features cameo appearances by Baudelaire, along with fellow poets<space/><link><target>Antonin Artaud</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arthur Rimbaud</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Csar Vallejo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rubn Daro</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">United States of Banana</arg><arg name="publisher">Amazon Crossing</arg><arg name="date">November 2011</arg><arg name="isbn">9781611090673</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Baudelaire family</target><part>Baudelaires</part></link>, protagonists of Lemony Snicket's<space/><italics><link><target>A Series of Unfortunate Events</target></link></italics>, were named after him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Kramer</arg><arg name="first">Melody</arg><arg name="title">A Series Of Unfortunate Literary Allusions</arg><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/2011/07/15/6253438/a-series-of-unfortunate-literary-allusions</arg><arg name="work">npr.org</arg><arg name="publisher">NPR</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 October 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Vanderbilt University</target></link><space/>has &quot;assembled one of the world's most comprehensive research collections on ... Baudelaire&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.library.vanderbilt.edu/bandy/pdf/Baudelaire.pdf'>Library.vanderbilt.edu</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Japanese<space/><link><target>comic</target></link><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>manga</target></link></italics><space/><italics><link><target>The Flowers of Evil (manga)</target><part>Aku no Hana</part></link></italics>, by Shz Oshimi, is inspired by Baudelaire's<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target></link></italics>. The anime was aired in 2013 and drew attention due to its heavy use of<space/><link><target>rotoscope</target></link><space/>animation. The<space/><link><target>protagonist</target></link><space/>in both manga and the anime, Takao Kasuga, is a bookworm whose favorite book is<space/><italics>Les fleurs du mal,</italics><space/>translated in Japanese as<space/><italics>Aku no Hana</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Les Fleurs du mal</italics><space/>has a number of scholarly references<space/><link type='external' href='https://scholar.google.com/scholar?cites=6832748742697412329&amp;amp;as_sdt=2005&amp;amp;sciodt=0,5&amp;amp;hl=en'>Citations</link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Baudelaire, Bibliothque de la Pliade, uvres compltes, volume I, dos et jaquette.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Baudelaire, Bibliothque de la Pliade, ''uvres compltes'' (''Complete Works''), volume I.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Salon de 1845</italics>, 1845</listitem><listitem><italics>Salon de 1846</italics>, 1846</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>La Fanfarlo</target></link></italics>, 1847</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target></link></italics>, 1857</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Les paradis artificiels</target></link></italics>, 1860</listitem><listitem><italics>Rflexions sur Quelques-uns de mes Contemporains</italics>, 1861</listitem><listitem><italics>Le Peintre de la Vie Moderne</italics>, 1863</listitem><listitem><italics>Curiosits Esthtiques</italics>, 1868</listitem><listitem><italics>L'art romantique</italics>, 1868</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Le Spleen de Paris</target></link></italics>, 1869</listitem><listitem><italics>Oeuvres Posthumes et Correspondance Gnrale</italics>, 18871907</listitem><listitem><italics>Fuses</italics>, 1897</listitem><listitem><italics>Mon Coeur Mis Nu</italics>, 1897</listitem><listitem><italics>Oeuvres Compltes</italics>, 192253 (19 vols.)</listitem><listitem><italics>Mirror of Art</italics>, 1955</listitem><listitem><italics>The Essence of Laughter</italics>, 1956</listitem><listitem><italics>Curiosits Esthtiques</italics>, 1962</listitem><listitem><italics>The Painter of Modern Life and Other Essays</italics>, 1964</listitem><listitem><italics>Baudelaire as a Literary Critic</italics>, 1964</listitem><listitem><italics>Arts in Paris 18451862</italics>, 1965</listitem><listitem><italics>Selected Writings on Art and Artist</italics>, 1972</listitem><listitem><italics>Selected Letters of Charles Baudelaire</italics>, 1986</listitem><listitem><italics>Twenty Prose Poems</italics>, 1988</listitem><listitem><italics>Critique d'art; Critique musicale</italics>, 1992</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Musical adaptations</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>French composer<space/><link><target>Claude Debussy</target></link><space/>set five of Baudelaire's poems to music in 1890:<space/><italics>Le Balcon</italics>,<space/><italics>Harmonie du soir</italics>,<space/><italics>Le Jet d'eau</italics>,<space/><italics>Recueillement</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>La Mort des amants</italics>.</listitem><listitem>French singer-songwriter<space/><link><target>Lo Ferr</target></link><space/>devoted himself to set Baudelaire's poetry into music in three albums:<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal (album, 1957)</target><part>Les Fleurs du mal</part></link></italics><space/>in 1957 (12 poems),<space/><italics><link><target>Lo Ferr chante Baudelaire</target></link></italics><space/>in 1967 (24 poems, including one from<space/><italics>Le Spleen de Paris</italics>), and the posthumous<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal (suite et fin)</target></link></italics><space/>(21 poems), recorded in 1977 but released in 2008.</listitem><listitem>Soviet/Russian composer<space/><link><target>David Tukhmanov</target></link><space/>has set Baudelaire's poem to music (cult album<space/><italics>On a Wave of My Memory</italics>, 1975).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>ru icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://popsa.info/bio/006/006b.html'>David Tukhmanov</link></extension></listitem><listitem>Warwickshire poet Sin Lavinia Valeriana, artist name The Raveness, is known to adore Baudelaire and written in homage to his work featured on her best selling poetry record 'Of blood and absinthe'(2012) is a poem entitled<space/><italics>Sinful Extraordinaire</italics><space/>a poem earlier published in her book<space/><italics>Lavinia Volume one</italics><space/>(2006) ISBN 9781502313966.</listitem><listitem>American avant-garde composer, vocalist and performer<space/><link><target>Diamanda Gals</target></link><space/>made an interpretation in original French of<space/><italics><link><target>Les Litanies de Satan</target></link></italics><space/>from<space/><italics><link><target>Le Fleurs du Mal</target></link></italics>, in her debut album titled<space/><italics><link><target>The Litanies of Satan</target></link></italics>, which consists of tape and electronics effects with layers of her voice.</listitem><listitem>French singer David TMX recorded the poem &quot;Lesbos&quot; from<space/><italics>The Flowers of Evil</italics>.</listitem><listitem>French metal/shoegaze groups<space/><link><target>Alcest</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Amesoeurs</target></link><space/>used his poetry for the lyrics of the tracks &quot;lvation&quot; (on<space/><italics><link><target>Le Secret (EP)</target><part>Le Secret</part></link></italics>) and &quot;Recueillement&quot; (on<space/><italics><link><target>Amesoeurs (album)</target><part>Amesoeurs</part></link></italics>), respectively.<space/><link><target>Celtic Frost</target></link><space/>used his poem<space/><italics><link><target>Les Fleurs du mal</target><part>Tristesses de la lune</part></link></italics><space/>as a lyrics for song on album<space/><link><target>Into the Pandemonium</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Israeli singer<space/><link><target>Maor Cohen</target></link>'s 2005 album, the<space/><link><target>Hebrew</target></link><space/>name of which translates to French as &quot;Les Fleurs Du Mal&quot;, is a compilation of songs from Baudelaire's book of the same name. The texts were translated to Hebrew by Israeli poet<space/><link><target>Dori Manor</target></link>, while the music was composed by Cohen himself.</listitem><listitem>Italian singer<space/><link><target>Franco Battiato</target></link><space/>set<space/><italics>Invitation au voyage</italics><space/>to music as<space/><italics>Invito Al Viaggio</italics><space/>on his 1999 album<space/><italics>Fleurs (Esempi Affini Di Scritture E Simili)</italics>.</listitem><listitem>American composer<space/><link><target>Gerard Pape</target></link><space/>set<space/><italics>Tristesses de la lune/Sorrows of the Moon</italics><space/>from<space/><italics>Fleurs du Mal</italics><space/>for voice and electronic tape.</listitem><listitem>French band Marc Seberg wrote an adaptation of Recueillement for their 1985 album Le Chant Des Terres.</listitem><listitem>Russian heavy metal band<space/><link><target>Black Obelisk (band)</target><part>Black Obelisk</part></link><space/>used Russian translations of several Baudelaire poems as lyrics for their songs.</listitem><listitem>French singer<space/><link><target>Mylene Farmer</target></link><space/>performed &quot;L'Horloge&quot; to music by<space/><link><target>Laurent Boutonnat</target></link><space/>on the album&quot; Ainsi soi je&quot; and the opening number of her 1989 concert tour.</listitem><listitem>German aggrotech band<space/><link><target>C-Drone-Defect</target></link><space/>used the translation of &quot;Le Rebelle&quot; by<space/><link><target>Roy Campbell (poet)</target><part>Roy Campbell</part></link><space/>as lyrics for the song &quot;Rebellis&quot; on their 2009 album &quot;Dystopia&quot;.</listitem><listitem>English rock band<space/><link><target>The Cure</target></link><space/>used the translation of &quot;Les yeux des pauvres&quot; as lyrics for the song &quot;How Beautiful You Are&quot;.</listitem><listitem>French singer-songwriter and musician<space/><link><target>Serge Gainsbourg</target></link><space/>has set Baudelaire's poem &quot;Dancing Snake&quot; (Le serpent qui danse) to music in his 1964 song &quot;Baudelaire&quot;.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Poetry</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>pater la bourgeoisie</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>20em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Baudelaire, Charles Pierre</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Baudelaire<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Richardson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joanna<space/></arg><arg name="year">1994<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">St. Martin's Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-312-11476-1<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>30736784</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource author</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cordite.org.au/translations/owen-baudelaire/'>Twilight to Dawn: Charles Baudelaire</link>. Translations,<space/><italics>Cordite Poetry Review</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.baudelaire.cz'>www.baudelaire.cz</link><space/>Largest Internet site dedicated to Charles Baudelaire. Poems and prose are available in English, French and Czech.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://baudelaire.litteratura.com'>Charles Baudelaire</link><space/>Site dedicated to Baudelaire's poems and prose, containing<space/><italics>Fleurs du mal</italics>,<space/><italics>Petit poemes et prose</italics>,<space/><italics>Fanfarlo</italics><space/>and more in French.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.charlesbaudelaire.org'>Charles Baudelaire International Association</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sydneyconsortium.com/tv/biodiversity-and-the-arts-nikolas-kompridis.shtml'>Nikolas Kompridis on Baudelaire's poetry, art, and the &quot;memory of loss&quot;</link><space/>(Flash/HTML5)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://baudelaireetbengale.blogspot.com'>baudelaireetbengale.blogspot.com</link>the influence of Baudelaire on Bengali poetry</listitem><listitem><template><target>YouTube</target><arg>bbZJICi3XrA</arg><arg>Alexander Barykin — The Invitation to Travel</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Online texts</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Baudelaire,+Charles<space/></arg><arg name="name">Charles Baudelaire</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Charles Pierre Baudelaire</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">888</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://baudelaire.litteratura.com'>Charles Baudelaire</link>Largest site dedicated to Baudelaire's poems and prose, containing<space/><italics>Fleurs du mal</italics>,<space/><italics>Petit poemes et prose</italics>,<space/><italics>Fanfarlo</italics><space/>and more in French.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.poetry-archive.com/b/baudelaire_charles.html'>Poems by Charles Baudelaire</link>Selected works at Poetry Archive</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://poemsintranslation.blogspot.com/search/label/Baudelaire'>Baudelaire's poems</link><space/>at Poems Found in Translation</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tonykline.co.uk/Browsepages/French/Baud18.htm'>Baudelaire Eighteen Poems</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.onedit.net/issue8/seanb/seanb.html'>&quot;baudelaire in english&quot;, Onedit.net</link>Sean Bonney's experimental translations of Baudelaire (humor)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://athena.unige.ch/athena/baudelaire/baudelaire.html'>Baudelaire, ''Les Fleurs du Mal'' and ''Petits Pomes en Prose'' (''Le Spleen de Paris''), at athena.unige.ch</link><space/><template><target>fr icon</target></template></listitem></list><heading level='4'>Single works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://fleursdumal.org'>FleursDuMal.org</link>Definitive online presentation of<space/><italics>Fleurs du mal</italics>, featuring the original French alongside multiple English translations</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.inkwatercolor.com/download/baudelairelesfleursdumal.pdf'>An illustrated version (8 Mb) of Les Fleurs du Mal, 1861 edition</link><space/>(Charles Baudelaire / une dition illustre par<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.inkwatercolor.com'>inkwatercolor.com</link>)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.grohaz.com/Philosophy/TheRebel.html'>&quot;The Rebel&quot;</link>poem by Baudelaire</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theflaneur.co.uk/lesfoules.html'>Les Foules (The Crowds)</link>English translation</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Romanticism</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Baudelaire, Charles
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Baudelaire, Charles Pierre
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>French poet
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>April 9, 1821
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Paris, France
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>August 31, 1867
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Paris
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Baudelaire, Charles</target></template><link><target>Category:Charles Baudelaire</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1821 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1867 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century French journalists</target></link><link><target>Category:Male journalists</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century French poets</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century French writers</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Montparnasse Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from syphilis</target></link><link><target>Category:Decadent literature</target></link><link><target>Category:French art critics</target></link><link><target>Category:French-language poets</target></link><link><target>Category:French translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Male translators</target></link><link><target>Category:Lyce Louis-le-Grand alumni</target></link><link><target>Category:Obscenity controversies</target></link><link><target>Category:People with bipolar disorder</target></link><link><target>Category:Potes maudits</target></link><link><target>Category:Psychedelic drug advocates</target></link><link><target>Category:Sonneteers</target></link><link><target>Category:Symbolist poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Translators of Edgar Allan Poe</target></link><link><target>Category:Writers from Paris</target></link></paragraph></article>