<article title='Dance_Dance_Revolution'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Infobox VG series</target><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:Dance Dance Revolution logo 2009.png|250px]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Current Dance Dance Revolution series logo (2009-present)
</arg><arg name="genre">[[Music video game|Music]], [[Exergaming|Exercise]]
</arg><arg name="developer">[[Konami]]
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Konami]], [[Nintendo]], [[Disney]], Keen, Betson
</arg><arg name="platform of origin">[[Arcade game|Arcade]]
</arg><arg name="first release version">''[[Dance Dance Revolution (1998 video game)|Dance Dance Revolution]]''
</arg><arg name="first release date">November 21, 1998
</arg><arg name="latest release version">''[[Dance Dance Revolution (2013 video game)|Dance Dance Revolution]]''
</arg><arg name="latest release date">May 12, 2014
</arg><arg name="spinoffs">''Dance Dance Revolution Solo''
</arg><arg name="website">[http://www.konami.jp/bemani/ddr/jp/ DDR Gateway](Japanese)
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>nihongo</target><arg>'''''Dance Dance Revolution'''''</arg><arg>ダンスダンスレボリューション</arg><arg>Dansu Dansu Reboryūshon</arg></template>, abbreviated<space/><bold>DDR</bold><space/>and also known as<space/><bold><italics>Dancing Stage</italics></bold><space/>in earlier games in<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Australasia</target></link>, and some other games in<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link>, is a<space/><link><target>music video game</target></link><space/>series produced by<space/><link><target>Konami</target></link>. Introduced in<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link><space/>in 1998 as part of the<space/><link><target>Bemani</target></link><space/>series, and released in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>and Europe in 1999,<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>is the pioneering series of the rhythm and dance<space/><link><target>Music genre</target><part>genre</part></link><space/>in video games. Players stand on a &quot;dance platform&quot; or stage and hit colored<space/><link><target>Arrow Cross</target><part>arrows laid out in a cross</part></link><space/>with their feet to musical and visual cues. Players are judged by how well they time their dance to the patterns presented to them and are allowed to choose more music to play to if they receive a passing score.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>has been given much critical acclaim for its originality and stamina in the video game market. There have been dozens of<space/><link><target>Arcade game</target><part>arcade</part></link>-based releases across several countries and hundreds of home<space/><link><target>video game console</target></link><space/>releases, promoting a music library of original songs produced by Konami's in-house artists and an eclectic set of<space/><link><target>Music licensing</target><part>licensed music</part></link><space/>from many different genres. The<space/><italics>DDR</italics><space/>series has inspired similar games such as<space/><italics><link><target>List of Pump it Up video games</target><part>Pump It Up</part></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Andamiro</target></link><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>In the Groove (series)</target><part>In the Groove</part></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Roxor</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Gameplay</heading><paragraph>The core gameplay involves the player, stepping his or her feet to correspond with the arrows that appears on screen and the beat. During normal gameplay, arrows scroll upwards from the bottom of the screen and pass over a set of stationary arrows near the top (referred to as the &quot;guide arrows&quot; or &quot;receptors&quot;, officially known as the Step Zone). When the scrolling arrows overlap the stationary ones, the player must step on the corresponding arrows on the dance platform, and the player is given a judgment for their accuracy of every streaked notes (From highest to lowest: Marvelous,<extension extension_name='ref'>First appeared in the Nonstop and Challenge mode of DDR Extreme and first used for normal gameplay as of DDR SuperNova 2.</extension><space/>Perfect, Great, Good, Almost,<extension extension_name='ref'>Boo for DDR 5thMIX and earlier. Not present in DDR X2 onwards.</extension><space/>Miss<extension extension_name='ref'>Boo for DDR SuperNOVA1, DDR SuperNOVA2, and DDR X only.</extension>).</paragraph><paragraph>Additional arrow types are added in later mixes. For instance,<space/><italics>Freeze Arrows</italics><space/>(introduced in<space/><link><target>DDRMAX Dance Dance Revolution 6thMix</target><part>DDRMAX</part></link>) which is a long green arrow that must be held down until the tail of it reaches the Step Zone, that is given an &quot;O.K.!&quot; judgment if it succeed or &quot;N.G.&quot; if fails to do so, or<space/><italics>Shock Arrows</italics><space/>(introduced in<space/><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution X</target><part>DDRX</part></link>), walls of arrows with lightning effects which must be avoided, which are scored in the same way as Freezes (O.K./N.G.); if they are stepped on, a N.G. is awarded, the life bar decreases, and the steps become hidden for a short period of time. Until<space/><italics>DDR SuperNOVA2</italics>, the N.G. judgment did not break the combo, though it does decrease the life bar.</paragraph><paragraph>Successfully hitting the arrows in time with the music fills the &quot;Dance Gauge&quot;, or<space/><link><target>life bar</target></link>, while failure to do so drains it. If the Dance Gauge is fully depleted during gameplay, the player fails the song, usually resulting in a<space/><link><target>game over</target></link>. Otherwise, the player is taken to the Results Screen, which rates the player's performance with a<space/><link><target>letter grade</target></link><space/>and a numerical<space/><link><target>score (video games)</target><part>score</part></link>, among other statistics. The player may then be given a chance to play again, depending on the settings of the particular machine (the limit is usually 3-5 songs per game).</paragraph><paragraph>Aside from play style Single, Dance Dance Revolution provides two other play styles: Versus (Player 1 side of play style Single and player 2 side of play style Single playing together) and Double (One player utilizes both pads to play). Some games offer additional modes beyond these, such as Course mode (players must play a set of songs back-to-back) and Battle mode (two players compete with a tug-of-war life bar by sending distracting modifiers to each other). Earlier versions also have Couple/Unison Mode, where two players must cooperate to play the song. This mode later become the basis for &quot;TAG Play&quot; in newer games.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Difficulty</heading><paragraph>Depending on the edition of the game, dance steps are broken into various levels of difficulty, often by color. Difficulty is loosely separated into 3-5 categories depending on timeline:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Year range</tablehead><tablehead>Edition range</tablehead><tablehead colspan="5">Difficulty</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>1998-1999</tablecell><tablecell>1st to 2ndMIX, &amp; 3rdMIX PLUS</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ffff">Easy/Soft</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Basic</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Another</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Maniac<extension extension_name='ref'>For play style Single, Versus, or Couple only in DDR 2ndMIX and earlier.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>1999</tablecell><tablecell>3rdMIX only</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ffff">Soft</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Basic</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Another</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">SSR</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2000-2001</tablecell><tablecell>4thMIX, 4thMIX PLUS, &amp; 5thMIX</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Basic</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Trick</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Maniac-S/Maniac-D</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #8888ff">Maniac</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2001</tablecell><tablecell>MAX</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Light</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Standard</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Heavy</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2002</tablecell><tablecell>MAX2</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Light</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Standard</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Heavy</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #8888ff">Oni<extension extension_name='ref'>Appears only on certain songs on certain NonStop courses only.</extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2002</tablecell><tablecell>EXTREME</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ffff">Beginner</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Light</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Standard</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Heavy</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #8888ff">Oni/Challenge</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2006present</tablecell><tablecell>SuperNOVA onwards<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(Pro mode in X2 and X3 VS 2ndMIX)</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ffff">Beginner</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88">Basic</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ff8888">Difficult</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ff88">Expert</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #8888ff">Challenge</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>2010-2011</tablecell><tablecell>X2 and X3 VS 2ndMIX (Happy mode)</tablecell><tablecell style="background: #88ffff"><space/><italics>(Kantan / Beginner)</italics></tablecell><tablecell style="background: #ffff88"><space/><italics>(Futsuu / Basic)</italics></tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell><tablecell>N/A</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>DDR 1st Mix established the three main difficulties (Basic, Another, and Maniac) and it began using the foot rating with a scale of 1 to 8. In addition, each difficulty rating would also be labeled with a title.<extension extension_name='ref'>1 for Simple, 2 for Moderate, 3 for Ordinary, 4 for Superior, 5 for Marvelous, 6 for Genuine, 7 for Paramount, 8 for Exorbitant.</extension><space/>DDR 2nd Mix Club Version 2 increased the scale to 9,<extension extension_name='ref'>9 for: Catastrophic in DDR 3rdMIX, Evolutionary in the DDR 2ndMIX mode of DDR X3 vs DDR 2ndMIX.</extension><space/>which would be implemented in the main series beginning in DDR 3rd Mix. DDR 3rd Mix also renamed the Maniac difficulty to &quot;SSR&quot; and made it playable through a special mode (SSR Mode), which can only be accessed via input code and is played on Flat (all arrows are the same color) by default. The SSR mode was eliminated in 3rdMix Plus, and the Maniac routines were folded back into the regular game. In addition to the standard three difficulties, the first three titles of the series and their derivations also featured a &quot;Easy&quot; mode (&quot;Soft&quot; in 3rd Mix), which provided simplified step charts for songs (and reduced song list in some versions). In this mode, one cannot access other difficulties, akin to the aforementioned SSR mode. While this mode is never featured again, it would become the basis for the fully accessible Beginner difficulty implemented in newer games. DDR 4th Mix removed the names of the song and made it simple by removing those names and organizing the difficulty by order. DDR 4th Mix Plus renamed several song's Maniac charts as Maniac-S (for Single) and Maniac-D (for Double), while adding newer and harder stepcharts for the old ones as the &quot;second&quot; Maniac. These new charts were used as the default Maniac stepchart in DDR 5th Mix while the older ones were removed.</paragraph><paragraph>Beginning in DDRMAX, a &quot;Groove Radar&quot; was introduced, showing how difficult a particular sequence is in various categories, such as the maximum density of steps, and so on. The step difficulty was removed in favor of the Groove Radar. DDRMAX2 (and subsequent versions) re-added the foot ratings and restored the pre-4th Mix Plus Maniac stepcharts as the default Heavy stepcharts. DDRMAX2 also increased the difficulty scale to 10<extension extension_name='ref'>10 for Revolutionary in the DDR 2ndMIX mode of DDR X3 vs DDR 2ndMIX.</extension><space/>(with the existing boss song, &quot;MAX 300&quot; from DDRMAX revealed to be the first) and added an official Oni/Challenge difficulty which can only be accessed in Oni/Challenging Mode. On DDR Extreme, Beginner difficulty is added for beginners and the Oni/Challenge is freely accessible. The game also adds the infamous &quot;flashing 10&quot; foot for songs that are considered too hard to be rated normally and only exists in several songs.</paragraph><paragraph>Although DDR SuperNova still has the foot ratings, it removed the flashing 10-foot that existed on certain songs for unknown reasons. Later on, DDR SuperNOVA2 removed the foot rating and replaced it with bars. However, all songs from the previous games remain identical, with very few changes to certain song difficulties.</paragraph><paragraph>On<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution X</target></link></italics>, the foot/bar rating system was given its first major overhaul, now ranking songs on a scale of 1-20, the first 10 represented by yellow bars, and the second 10 represented by additional red blocks shown in place of yellow bars. All songs from previous versions were re-rated on the new scale. The same system was carried over to<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution X2</target></link></italics>, although the difficulty bars were removed, replaced by simple difficulty numbers with the foot mark returning as the difficulty symbol for the first time since DDR SuperNova. As of<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution (2013 video game)</target><part>Dance Dance Revolution (2013 edition)</part></link></italics>, no songs are officially rated maximum (20); the highest rating available is 19, shared between four songs:<space/><italics>POSSESSION</italics><space/>on Double Challenge, and<space/><italics>EGOISM 440</italics>,<space/><italics>PARANOiA Revolution</italics>, and<space/><italics>Valkyrie dimension</italics><space/>on Single Challenge and Double Challenge. However, the game still allows players to rate their custom edit data up to maximum.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Groove Radar</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>DDRMAX Dance Dance Revolution 6thMix#Groove Radar</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The foot-rating system was completely removed for 6th Mix, and replaced by the<space/><italics>Groove Radar</italics>. The Groove Radar is a<space/><link><target>star plot</target><part>graphical representation</part></link><space/>of the difficulty of a song based in five different areas: Stream, Voltage, Air, Chaos, and Freeze.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Stream</italics><space/>- Indicates the overall density of the steps of the song. A high number of steps is not necessary for a high stream measurement (although it is a factor), since the songs' running time may range from as short as 1 minutes and 17 seconds to as long as 2 minutes and 17 seconds (not counting the long versions/Xmix, which go beyond 3 minutes).</listitem><listitem><italics>Voltage</italics><space/>- Indicates the peak density of the steps (the highest density of arrows that ever appear on the screen at once). Songs with a high BPM (300 or more) usually have a high voltage measurement, since it allows more steps to appear in increasingly halved beats (4th step in a 300 BPM song equals to 8th beat step in a 150 BPM song, and so on), though songs with lower BPM can have a high voltage, even if the halved beats usually cap at 32nd beat (64th beat steps exist in very few songs).</listitem><listitem><italics>Chaos</italics><space/>- Indicates &quot;off-beat&quot; steps; those that do not occur in 4th or 8th beats.<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>Air</italics><space/>- Indicates the amount of double steps (i.e. jumps) and shock arrows within the song.</listitem><listitem><italics>Freeze</italics><space/>- Indicates the number of freeze arrows within the song</listitem></list><paragraph>Each game usually has a song that max out a category within the radar. If a song in a following mix or update has a higher category measurement, then the groove radar is renewed so the new song can max out that category, while all previous songs are re-rated in respect to the new radar.</paragraph><paragraph>As of the 2014 update to<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution (2013 video game)</target><part>Dance Dance Revolution</part></link></italics>, the groove radar also employs a numerical measurement in addition to a graphical representation. Before the update, the radar did not disclose the number by default, though it could be shown by holding the SELECT button while heading to the song select screen.</paragraph><paragraph>The Groove Radar was not very popular among seasoned DDR veterans. The foot-rating system would be restored to work with the Groove Radar in the<space/><link><target>DDRMAX Dance Dance Revolution</target><part>North American home version of the game</part></link><space/>and in the next arcade version,<space/><italics><link><target>DDRMAX2 Dance Dance Revolution 7thMix</target><part>DDRMAX2</part></link></italics>, and almost all future versions (except for versions based on the<space/><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution Extreme (North America)</target><part>North American version of Extreme</part></link>, which only use foot ratings). All of the 6th Mix songs on 7thMix received foot-ratings, excluding songs that are removed from DDRMAX2.</paragraph><paragraph>SuperNOVA 2 featured special edits of songs specifically meant to max out specific categories on the radar, culminating with<space/><italics>Dead End (Groove Radar Special)</italics>, maxing out all 5 categories. While not related, SuperNOVA 2 also featured a variation known as &quot;My Groove Radar&quot; as part of e-Amusement, which is also divided into five categories, though it is meant to measure the player's stats on songs rather than showing the song's difficulty.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Extra Stage system</heading><paragraph>The Extra Stage, originally introduced in 1st Mix and reintroduced in DDRMAX (and appears in subsequent arcade versions), rewards a player for receiving a grade of &quot;AA&quot; or higher on either Expert or Challenge difficulties on the final stage. The player receives the opportunity to play a free extra song, which often defaults to a very difficult song with forced modifiers (such as 1.5x speed and Reverse) and a life bar identical to the battery bar similar to Challenge mode with 1-4 lives depending on their score in the final stage (or a non-regaining life bar before Supernova 2). Beginning on SuperNova 2, players may be able to access the modifier menu and the forced modifiers (save for the battery bar) are no longer used. However, the Replicant-D Action event in DDR X2 did not allow players to select modifiers for its Encore Extra Stage.</paragraph><paragraph>The default song for the extra stage is predetermined, although as of Extreme, any song can be played on the extra stage, although there is still a song that is designated as<space/><italics>the</italics><space/>Extra Stage (which usually is marked with red letters* on the song wheel, and must be unlocked for regular play). A player who attains a grade of &quot;AA&quot; (or &quot;A&quot; in SuperNova) on the Extra Stage is invited to play an additional stage, &quot;One More Extra Stage&quot; (OMES, or Encore Extra Stage post-SuperNova), with another special song option played in sudden death mode, in which any combo-breaking step or missed freeze will cause an instant failure. SuperNova 2 and X allowed players to play any song for Encore Extra Stage, but X2 went back to the original predetermined songs, though the players are still able to change the modifiers. Usually if this final boss is beaten, a special credits sequence is played.</paragraph><paragraph>With the implementation of<space/><link><target>e-Amusement</target></link><space/>in DDR, mixes after SuperNova have contained multiple songs as extra stages, often based on specific conditions, such as playing specific difficulties or songs.</paragraph><paragraph>From 7th Mix onward, the BPM of Extra Stage songs was displayed as a random, changing number, instead of the song's true BPM. For every Extra Stage song except for MAX. (period), the random BPM display was replaced with the normal BPM display in the next mix, and as of<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution X</italics>, after said song has been unlocked for normal play.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Hardware</heading><heading level='3'>Arcade machines</heading><paragraph>A standard<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>arcade machine consists of two parts, the<space/><link><target>arcade cabinet</target><part>cabinet</part></link><space/>and the dance platform. The cabinet has a wide bottom section, which houses large floor speakers and glowing<space/><link><target>neon lamp</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Above this sits a narrower section that contains the<space/><link><target>computer display</target><part>monitor</part></link>, and on top is a lighted marquee graphic, with two small speakers and flashing lights on either side. Below the monitor are two sets of buttons (one for each player), each consisting of two triangular selection buttons and a center rectangular button, used mainly to confirm a selection or start the game.<link><target>File:Dance Dance Revolution Extreme arcade machine left side stage.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>200px</part><part>The dance stage, divided into 9 sections, 4 of them in the cardinal directions contain pressure sensors for the detection of steps.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>dance pad</target><part>dance stage</part></link><space/>is a raised metal platform divided into two sides. Each side houses a set of four<space/><link><target>acrylic glass</target></link><space/>pads<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.betson.com/parts/Konami/1-10'>Betson Enterprises Online Catalog - Konami</link></extension><space/>arranged and pointing in the orthogonal directions (left, up, down and right), separated by metal squares. Each pad sits atop four pressure activated switches, one at each edge of each pad, and a software-controlled<space/><link><target>cold cathode</target></link><space/>lamp illuminating the translucent pad. A metal safety bar in the shape of an upside-down &quot;U&quot; is mounted to the dance stage behind each player. Some players make use of this safety bar to help maintain proper balance, and to relieve weight from the legs so that arrows can be pressed with greater speed and accuracy.</paragraph><paragraph>Some DDR cabinets are equipped with Sony PlayStation memory card slots, allowing the player to insert a compatible memory card before starting a game and save their high scores to the card. Additionally, the equivalent home versions of DDR allow players to create and save custom step patterns (edits) to their memory card the player can then play those steps on the arcade machine if the same song exists on that machine. This feature is supported in 2ndMix through Extreme. SuperNova didn't support memory card slots. However, it introduced Konami's internet based link system<space/><italics><link><target>e-Amusement</target></link></italics><space/>to the series, which can save stats and unlocks for individual players (but cannot store edits). This functionality however, could only be used in Japan. During the North American release of<space/><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution SuperNOVA 2</target></link>, an e-Amuse capable machine was made available at a Brunswick Zone Arcade in<space/><link><target>Naperville, Illinois</target></link>. Both it and another machine located in the Konami offices of<space/><link><target>El Segundo, California</target></link><space/>are currently the only e-Amuse capable machines in the United States.</paragraph><paragraph>The Solo arcade cabinet is smaller and contains only one dance pad, modified to include six arrow panels instead of four (the additional panels are &quot;upper-left&quot; and &quot;upper-right&quot;). These pads generally don't come with a safety bar, but include the option for one to be installed at a later date. The Solo pad also lacks some of the metal plating that the standard pad has, which can make stepping difficult for players who are used to playing on standard machines. An upgrade was available for Solo machines called the &quot;Deluxe pad&quot;, which was closer to the standard cabinet's pad. Additionally Solo machines only incorporate two sensors, located horizontally in the center of the arrow, instead of four sensors (one on each edge).</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead rowspan="2">Characteristics</tablehead><tablehead colspan="4">Order of sequence of generation of arcade cabinet</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>First</tablehead><tablehead>First (Refresh)</tablehead><tablehead>Second</tablehead><tablehead>Third</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Photo</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:Dance Dance Revolution North American arcade machine 3.jpg</target><part>180px</part><part>center</part></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:DDR_X2.png</target><part>180px</part><part>center</part></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Year released</tablecell><tablecell>1998</tablecell><tablecell>2006</tablecell><tablecell>2008</tablecell><tablecell>2013</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Thematic color of arcade cabinet</tablecell><tablecell>Black</tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>Black (<bold>Fusion</bold>)</listitem><listitem>Red (<bold>SuperNova</bold>)</listitem><listitem>Blue (<bold>US SuperNova 2 only</bold>)</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell>Black</tablecell><tablecell>White</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Initial system board</tablecell><tablecell>System 573</tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bemani Python (<bold>Fusion</bold>)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.system16.com/hardware.php?id=977'>System 16 - Konami Bemani Python Hardware (Konami)</link></extension><space/>or Python 2 (<bold>SuperNova</bold><space/>series)</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2">Bemani PC type 4</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Upgrade options</tablecell><tablecell>2ndMix to 2013 edition;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>2014 edition via online only</tablecell><tablecell>SuperNova 2 to 2013 edition;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>2014 edition via online only</tablecell><tablecell>X2 to 2013 edition;<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>2014 edition via online only</tablecell><tablecell>2014 edition via online only</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Screen</tablecell><tablecell>CRT-based,<extension extension_name='ref'>Displays a<space/><link><target>Aspect ratio (image)#4:3 standard</target><part>4:3</part></link><space/>picture.</extension><space/>29&quot; at<space/><link><target>Low-definition television</target><part>240i</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>480i</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>CRT-based, 29&quot; at<space/><link><target>480p</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>LCD-based, 37&quot;, 720p</tablecell><tablecell>LCD-based, 42&quot;, 1080p</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Front lights</tablecell><tablecell>colspan=&quot;2&quot;<space/><template><target>Ya</target><arg>[[Neon]]</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Ya</target><arg>[[LED]]</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>rowspan=&quot;2&quot;<space/><template><target>Na</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Lateral LED lights</tablecell><tablecell>colspan=&quot;2&quot;<space/><template><target>Na</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Ya</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>e-Amusement</target></link><space/>card reader</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Na</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Ya</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Ya</target></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Ya</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Memory card slots</tablecell><tablecell>colspan=&quot;2&quot;<space/><template><target>Partial</target><arg>Some models only</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>ya</target></template></tablecell><tablecell>rowspan=&quot;2&quot;<space/><template><target>Na</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Panel lights</tablecell><tablecell>colspan=&quot;3&quot;<space/><template><target>Ya</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Panel colors</tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><list type='bullet'><listitem>Pink (vertical)</listitem><listitem>Baby blue (horizontal)</listitem><listitem>Black background</listitem><listitem>White text and arrow borders</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>Pink (vertical)</listitem><listitem>Baby blue (horizontal)</listitem><listitem>Black background and arrow borders</listitem><listitem>White arrows</listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem>Pink (vertical)</listitem><listitem>Baby blue (horizontal)</listitem><listitem>White Lovers background and arrows</listitem></list></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Handle bar colors</tablecell><tablecell colspan="2">Red</tablecell><tablecell>Black</tablecell><tablecell>Baby blue and pink</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>First edition of DDR using such cabinet</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution (1998 video game)</target><part>1st</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution SuperNOVA</target><part>SuperNOVA</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution X</target><part>X</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution (2013 video game)</target><part>2013 edition</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Arcade System</heading><paragraph>The first<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>as well as its followup<space/><italics>DDR 2ndMix</italics><space/>uses Bemani System 573 Analog as its hardware. DDR 3rdMix replaces this with a slightly upgraded Bemani System 573 Digital which would be used up to<space/><italics>DDR Extreme</italics>. Both of these are based on PlayStation.</paragraph><paragraph>Beginning in<space/><italics>Dancing Stage Fusion</italics>, the hardware is replaced by Bemani Python, a PlayStation 2-based hardware. In the next version,<space/><italics>DDR SuperNova</italics>, this was changed to Bemani Python 2 which was first introduced on the fellow Bemani game<space/><italics>GuitarFreaks V and Drummania V</italics>. Bemani Python 2 would also be used in the followup<space/><italics>DDR SuperNova 2</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Along with the cabinet change,<space/><italics>DDR X</italics><space/>also changes its hardware to the PC-based Bemani PC Type 4. This more powerful hardware allows for high definition graphics<extension extension_name='ref'>Except for first generation DDR arcade cabinets.</extension><space/>and enhanced features. Bemani PC Type 4 is still used to this day.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Releases</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Dance Dance Revolution video games</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>has been released in many different countries on many different platforms. Originally released in Japan as an<space/><link><target>arcade game</target></link><space/>and then a Sony<space/><link><target>PlayStation</target></link><space/>game, which was a bestseller.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Dengeki PlayStation</target></link><space/>sales chart, August 1999, published in<space/><link><target>Official UK PlayStation Magazine</target></link><space/>issue 48</extension><space/>DDR was later released in North American, Europe, Korea, the whole of Asia, Australia, New Zealand, South America and Mexico on multiple platforms including the Sony<space/><link><target>PlayStation 2</target></link>, Microsoft<space/><link><target>Xbox (console)</target><part>Xbox</part></link>, Nintendo<space/><link><target>Wii</target></link>, and many others. Due to demand, Japanese versions of the game, which are usually different from the games released in other countries, are often<space/><link><target>import</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Copyright infringement</target><part>bootlegged</part></link>. DDR fansites make an attempt to keep track of the locations of arcade machines throughout the major regions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Home releases</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:DDR HandController.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>The use of dedicated<space/><link><target>gamepads</target></link><space/>is only possible on home console versions.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>DDR games have been released on various<space/><link><target>video game console</target><trail>s</trail></link>, including the<space/><link><target>PlayStation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dreamcast</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nintendo 64</target></link>,<space/><link><target>PlayStation 2</target></link>,<space/><link><target>PlayStation 3</target></link>,<space/><link><target>GameCube</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wii</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Xbox (console)</target><part>Xbox</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Xbox 360</target></link>, and even<space/><link><target>personal computer</target><part>PCs</part></link>. Home versions often contain new songs, songs from the arcade version, and additional features that take advantage of the capabilities of the console (e.g.; Xbox 360 versions such as the<space/><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution Universe</target></link><space/>series include support for online multiplayer and downloadable songs over<space/><link><target>Xbox Live</target></link>, and high definition graphics). DDR has even reached Nintendo's<space/><link><target>Game Boy Color</target></link>, with five versions of<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution GB</target></link></italics><space/>released in Japan; these included a series of three mainstream DDR games, a Disney Mix, and an Oha Star. The games come with a small thumb pad that fits over the Game Boy Color's controls to simulate the dance pad.</paragraph><paragraph>Home versions are commonly bundled with soft plastic<space/><link><target>dance pad</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that are similar in appearance and function to the<space/><link><target>Nintendo</target></link><space/><link><target>Power Pad</target></link>. Some third-party manufacturers produce hard metal pads at a higher price.</paragraph><paragraph>A version of DDR was also produced for the PC in North America. It uses the interface of<space/><italics><link><target>Dance Dance Revolution 4thMix</target></link></italics>, and contains around 40 songs from the first six mainstream arcade releases. It has not been as well received as the console versions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Similar games</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Stemania4 Alpha4.png</target><part>250px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Gameplay screen in StepMania 4, an open source DDR clone.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Due to the success of the<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics><space/>franchise, many other games with similar or identical gameplay have been created.</paragraph><paragraph>Commercial competitors of DDR include the popular<space/><link><target>Korea</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>series<space/><link><target>List of Pump it Up video games</target><part>Pump It Up</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>American</part></link><space/>series<space/><link><target>In the Groove (series)</target><part>In the Groove</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Roxor</target></link>, the latter of which was met with<space/><link><target>In the Groove (video game)#Lawsuit</target><part>legal action by Konami</part></link><space/>and resulted in Konami's acquisition of the game's<space/><link><target>intellectual property</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.gamesindustry.biz/articles/konami-reaches-settlement-in-ddr-lawsuit</arg><arg name="title">Publisher acquires rights to Roxor game<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-10-20</arg><arg name="publisher">GamesIndustry.biz</arg></template></extension><space/>As well as<space/><link><target>TechnoMotion</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>F2 Systems</target></link>,<space/><link><target>EZ2Dancer</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Amuseworld</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>MC Groovz Dance Craze</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Mad Catz</target></link>. A Christian version of DDR, named<space/><link><target>Dance Praise</target></link>, has been made by<space/><link><target>Digital Praise</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Ubisoft</target></link><space/>produced a dance game based on<space/><link><target>Disney</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Jungle Book (1967 film)</target><part>The Jungle Book</part></link></italics><space/>titled<space/><italics><link><target>The Jungle Book Groove Party</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Fan-made versions of DDR have also been created, many freely available to the public under<space/><link><target>open source</target></link><space/>licenses. The most popular of these is<space/><link><target>StepMania</target></link><space/>(pictured), upon which the game<space/><italics>In the Groove</italics><space/>is based. These simulators allow for players to create and play their own songs to their own programmed steps. As a result, many DDR fans have held contests and released &quot;mixes&quot; of custom songs and steps for these simulators. Notably the<space/><link><target>Japan</target><trail>ese</trail></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://foonmix.nothing.sh/'>Foonmix</link><space/>series and the<space/><link><target>DDR East Invasion</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bemanistyle.com/forum/tags/tournamix/'>Tournamix</link><space/>competitions. Other simulators include<space/><link><target>Dance With Intensity</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pyDance</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Microsoft Windows</target><part>Windows</part></link>, both of which are no longer developed, and<space/><link><target>Feet of Fury</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Homebrew (video games)</target><part>homebrew</part></link><space/>game for the Sega<space/><link><target>Dreamcast</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Besides direct clones, many other games have been released that center around rhythm and dance due to DDR's popularity.<space/><link><target>Dance! Online</target></link><space/>released by<space/><link><target>Acclaim Entertainment</target><part>Acclaim</part></link><space/>combines<space/><link><target>dance pad</target></link><space/>play with an<space/><link><target>Massively multiplayer online game</target><part>MMO</part></link><space/>element.<space/><link><target>American Broadcasting Company</target><part>ABC</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Dancing with the Stars (video game)</target><part>Dancing With the Stars</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Codemasters</target></link>'<space/><link><target>Dance Factory (game)</target><part>Dance Factory</part></link><space/>are more recent examples of games that pay homage to DDR and the genre it created. Konami itself uses music from its other rhythm game series such as<space/><italics><link><target>Beatmania</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Beatmania IIDX</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Drummania</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>GuitarFreaks</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Pop'n Music</target></link></italics>, as well as making references to DDR in its other games and vice versa.</paragraph><heading level='2'>DDR today</heading><paragraph>Tournaments are held worldwide, with participants usually competing for higher scores or number of Perfects (referred to as &quot;Perfect Attack&quot; tournaments). Less common are &quot;freestyle&quot; tournaments, where players develop actual dance routines to perform while following the steps in the game.<extension extension_name='ref'>IGN Staff<space/><link type='external' href='http://psx.ign.com/articles/084/084175p1.html'>IGN: Dance Dance Revolution Tournament Report</link>, Retrieved on 2008-05-23.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Playing styles</heading><paragraph>Many DDR players, in order to better focus on timing and pattern reading, will minimize any extraneous body movement during gameplay. These players are commonly referred to as &quot;technical&quot;, &quot;tech&quot; or &quot;perfect attack&quot; (PA) players. These technical players usually play the most difficult songs on the highest difficulty levels in an attempt to perfect their scores. The more &quot;technical&quot; a song gets the more the player must use minimalistic movements in order to hit all the arrows with perfection. These players perfect using their heel as well.</paragraph><paragraph>Other DDR players choose to incorporate complex or flashy techniques into their play movements, and some of these &quot;freestyle&quot; players develop intricate dance routines to perform during a song. Freestyle players tend to choose songs on lower difficulty levels, so that the player is not restricted in their movements by large quantities of required steps. Some players can even dance facing away from the screen.</paragraph><paragraph>Somewhere in the middle are the players which choose to do a little bit of both of the formers. There are criticisms of the In The Groove style of play which focuses on &quot;perfect attack&quot;. More traditional players say it takes the fun away from the game the harder the step-charts get, which makes players use much less movement overall to conserve stamina. By doing this, it is no longer a dance game and many arrows do not fit perfectly with the beat because there are simply too many of them. The middle players enjoy moving to the beat and still trying to improve their scores without having to adopt the In the Groove style of play.</paragraph><paragraph>A freestyling act can also involve performing other stunts while playing. On an episode of<space/><link><target>American Broadcasting Company</target><part>ABC's</part></link><space/>short-lived series<space/><link><target>Master of Champions</target></link>, Billy Matsumoto won the episode when he played 5th Mix's &quot;Can't Stop Fallin' In Love (Speed Mix)&quot; on Heavy mode while juggling three lit torches.</paragraph><heading level='3'>As exercise</heading><paragraph>Many news outlets have reported how playing DDR can be good<space/><link><target>aerobic exercise</target></link>; some regular players have reported<space/><link><target>weight loss</target></link><space/>of 1050 pounds (520&amp;nbsp;kg). In one example, a player found that including DDR in her day-to-day life resulted in a loss of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>95</arg><arg>lb</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://getupmove.com/weightloss/tanya.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Welcome to Get Up Move!<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Web.archive.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">2007-10-11<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-09-13<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20071011193120/http://getupmove.com/weightloss/tanya.asp<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2007-10-11</arg></template></extension><space/>Some other examples would be Matthew Keene's account of losing upwards of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>and Yashar Esfandi's claim of losing<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>85</arg><arg>lb</arg></template><space/>in four months through incorporation of DDR.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://web.archive.org/web/20051204022559/http://www.getupmove.com/weightloss/matt.asp</extension><space/>Although the quantity of calories burned by playing DDR have not been scientifically measured, the amount of active movement required to play implies that DDR provides at least some degree of healthy exercise.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2006<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link><space/>introduced DDR to the physical education curriculum at all of its 765<space/><link><target>State school</target><part>public schools</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MTVNews"><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title">West Virginia Adds Dance Dance Revolution to Gym Class</arg><arg name="publisher">MTV</arg><arg name="url">http://www.mtv.com/news/articles/1521605/20060125/index.jhtml?headlines</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-09-22</arg></template></extension><space/>In<space/><link><target>Norway</target></link>, 'Machine Dance' has even been registered as an official sport.<extension extension_name='ref' name="DDRNorway"><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title">Positive Gaming: Machine Dance as Fitness and Sport</arg><arg name="url">http://www.positivegaming.com/company/index.php?id</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20071011214904/http://positivegaming.com/company/index.php?id</arg><arg name="archivedate">2007-10-11</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-09-22</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many home versions of the game have a function to estimate calories burned, given a player's weight. Additionally, players can use &quot;workout mode&quot; to make a diary of calories burned playing DDR and any self-reported changes in the player's weight.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Use in schools</heading><paragraph>At the start of 2006, Konami announced that the DDR games would be used as part of a fitness program to be phased into<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link>'s 765 state schools, starting with its 103 middle schools, over the next two years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MTVNews"></extension><space/>The program was conceived by a researcher at<space/><link><target>West Virginia University</target></link>'s Motor Development Center.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>California Institute of Technology</target></link><space/>allows its students to use DDR to fulfill part of its<space/><link><target>physical education</target></link><space/>requirement, as students may design their own fitness program.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://pr.caltech.edu/catalog/courses/listing/pe.html#mytarget</arg><arg name="title">Caltech Course Catalog- Physical Education</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>University of Kansas</target></link><space/>has a class for Dance Dance Revolution open for students to take as a 1 credit hour course.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Weslander<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eric<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www2.ljworld.com/news/2007/aug/11/dance_dance_revolution_cyberculture_ku_offers_dive/<space/></arg><arg name="title">10 cool classes / LJWorld.com<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">.ljworld.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2007-08-11<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-09-13</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Cyber Coach</target></link><space/>has sold in excess of 600 systems in schools in the UK and features the DDR Game Disco Disco 2.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.Cyber-coach.co.uk</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>As a sport</heading><paragraph>In 2004 Dance Dance Revolution became an official sporting event in Norway.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://cie.acm.org/articles/international-survey-on-the-dance-dance-revolution-game/</arg><arg name="title">International survey on the Dance Dance Revolution game</arg><arg name="first">Johanna</arg><arg name="last">Hoysniemi</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 29, 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>The first official club DDR Oslo was founded in 2004. The tournaments in Norway was divided into two parts, first there was a group play where the 2 or 3 best players from each group went to the final rounds. Elimination of the player with the lowest game score was used for each round in the finals. The scoring system used was based on people dancing to 2 or 3 songs. Some random selected songs (which had to be played by everyone) and some player chosen songs (which introduced some strategy into the game, as some songs had higher possible scoring than other songs).<space/><link><target>Dancing Stage EuroMix 2</target></link><space/>was officially used for the Norwegian tournaments.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Awards</heading><paragraph>The success of the Dance Dance Revolution series has resulted in Guinness World Records awarding the series with: Gamer's Edition 2008. The records include &quot;Longest Dance Dance Revolution Marathon&quot; which is currently held by Alex Skudlarek at 16 hours, 18 minutes, and nine seconds. and &quot;Most Widely Used Video Game in Schools.&quot;<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dance Masters</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>Dance Evolution</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kinect</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Xbox (console)</target><part>Xbox</part></link>) game software developed by DDR Creators.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dance Revolution</target></link>, a television series inspired by<space/><italics>Dance Dance Revolution</italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Dance Dance Revolution video games</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dance pad</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Exergaming</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Konami Corporation v. Roxor Games Inc.</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Dance Dance Revolution songs</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Music video game</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Carrie Swidecki</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.acefitness.org/getfit/studies/DDRStudy2007.pdf'>2007 DDR Study</link>, American Council on Exercise.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.konami.jp/bemani/ddr/jp/'>DDR Global Gateway</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Bemani series</target></template><template><target>DanceDanceRevolution</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Bemani games</target></link><link><target>Category:Dance Dance Revolution games</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Video game franchises</target></link><link><target>Category:Video game franchises introduced in 1998</target></link></paragraph></article>