<article title='Economy_of_Eritrea'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox economy</target><arg name="country"><space/>Eritrea
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Eritrea-1Nakfa.jpg
</arg><arg name="width">
</arg><arg name="caption">Eritrean nakfa
</arg><arg name="currency"><space/>[[Eritrean nakfa]] (ERN)
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>Calendar year
</arg><arg name="organs"><space/>[[Common Market for Eastern and Southern Africa|COMESA]], [[African Development Bank|AfDB]]
</arg><arg name="gdp rank"><space/>[[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|156th]] (nominal) / [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|156th]] (PPP)
</arg><arg name="gdp"><space/>{{nowrap|Nominal: $3.881 billion (2014 est.)}}<ref name</arg><arg name="growth"><space/>7.53% (2012 est.)<ref name</arg><arg name="per capita"><space/>$593 (nominal) (2014 est.)<ref name</arg><arg name="sectors"><space/>agriculture (11.6%), industry (30.6%), services (57.8%) (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="inflation"><space/>17% (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="poverty"><space/>50% (2004 est.)
</arg><arg name="gini">
</arg><arg name="edbr"><space/>184th (2014)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="labor"><space/>1.935 million (2007 est.)
</arg><arg name="occupations"><space/>agriculture (80%), services and industry (20%)
</arg><arg name="unemployment"><space/>
</arg><arg name="industries"><space/>[[beverages]], [[cement]], clothing and textiles, [[food processing]], light manufacturing, [[salt]]
</arg><arg name="exports"><space/>$304.5 million (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="export-goods"><space/>food, livestock, small manufactures, sorghum, textiles
</arg><arg name="export-partners"><space/>[[China]] 8.5%, [[Egypt]] 4.8% [[Italy]] 30.5%, [[Saudi Arabia]] 8.8%, [[Sudan]] 24%, [[UK]] 5.7% (2008 est.)
</arg><arg name="imports"><space/>$939.7 million (2011 est.)
</arg><arg name="import-goods"><space/>machinery, petroleum products, food, manufactured goods
</arg><arg name="import-partners"><space/>[[Brazil]] 5.9%, [[China]] 11.1%, [[Egypt]] 11.9%, [[India]] 8.9%, [[Italy]] 7.2%, [[Germany]] 7.2%, [[Saudi Arabia]] 15.7%, [[South Africa]] 6.5%, [[South Korea]] 4.3% (2008 est.)
</arg><arg name="debt"><space/>118% of GDP (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="gross external debt"><space/>$1.026 billion (31 December 2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="revenue"><space/>$838.8 million (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="expenses"><space/>$1.19 billion (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="reserves"><space/>$171.2 million (2012 est.)
</arg><arg name="credit"><space/>
</arg><arg name="cianame"><space/>er
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>The Economy of Eritrea</bold><space/>has experienced considerable growth in recent years, indicated by an improvement in<space/><link><target>Gross domestic product</target></link><space/>(GDP) in October 2012 of 7.5 percent over 2011.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.imf.org/external/country/ERI/index.htm'></link>, International Monetary Fund. Retrieved October 2012.</extension><space/>However, worker<space/><link><target>remittance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from abroad are estimated to account for 32 percent of gross domestic product.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"><link type='external' href='http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/profiles/Eritrea.pdf'>Eritrea country profile</link>.<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link><space/><link><target>Federal Research Division</target></link><space/>(September 2005).<space/><italics>This article incorporates text from this source, which is in the public domain.</italics></extension><space/>Eritrea has an extensive amount of resources such as copper, gold, granite, marble, and potash. The Eritrean economy has undergone extreme changes due to the<space/><link><target>Eritrean War of Independence</target><part>War of Independence</part></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In 2011, Eritrea's GDP grew by 8.7 percent making it one of the fastest growing economies in the world.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://inewp.com/?p=11290</extension><space/>The Economist Intelligence Unit (EIU) expects it to maintain a high growth rate of 8.5 percent in 2013.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://country.eiu.com/Eritrea</arg><arg name="title">Eritrea</arg><arg name="author">EIU Digital Solutions</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 June 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Economic history</heading><paragraph>In the early 1950s, when Eritrea was awarded to<space/><link><target>Ethiopia</target></link>, it possessed a far more sophisticated urban and industrial infrastructure than Ethiopia. Eritrean critics said industrialization in the years since then focused on other parts of Ethiopia. Ethiopia nationalized Eritreas 42 largest factories and systematically dismantled the Eritrean industrial sector during the protracted civil war. By the time of its independence from Ethiopia in 1991, Eritreas economy had been destroyed by war and was dependent on income from ports and its small agricultural base. The onset of conflict with Ethiopia, which lasted from 1998 to 2000, halted all bilateral trade, severely reducing port activity and income in Eritrea. According to<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link><space/>estimates, Eritrea lost US$225 million worth of<space/><link><target>livestock</target></link><space/>and 55,000 homes during the war. GDP growth fell to zero in 1999 and to -1% in 2000.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.countryfacts.com/eritrea/economy/</arg><arg name="title">Eritrea Economy GDP Currency Exports</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 June 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Planting of crops was prevented in Eritrea's most productive western region, causing food production to drop by 62%.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2008</arg></template><space/>Damage to public buildings is estimated at US$24 million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Gross domestic product (GDP)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tree map exports 2009 Eritrea.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Graphical depiction of Eritrea's product exports in 28 color-coded categories.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Eritrea's GDP, estimated at $4.037 billion in 2011, is 8.7 percent above the GDP in 2010. The growth was due to increased agricultural output and the expansion of the mining industry along with increasing gold prices. Breakdowns of the Eritrean economy by sector are not readily available; however, according to some estimates, in 2011 services accounted for 55 percent of the GDP, industry for 34 percent, and agriculture for the remaining 11 percent.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/er.html</arg><arg name="title">The World Factbook</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 June 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>The growth of the GDP, however, is compromised by the ongoing and shaky troubles with the country's borders.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Industries</heading><heading level='3'>Agriculture, Forestry, and Fishing</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Agriculture in Eritrea</arg></template>In 2004,<space/><link><target>agriculture</target></link><space/>employed nearly 80 percent of the population but accounted for only 12.4 percent of gross domestic product (GDP) in Eritrea. The agricultural sector has improved with the use of modern farming equipment and techniques, and dams. Nevertheless, it is compromised by a lack of financial services and investment. Major agricultural products are<space/><link><target>barley</target></link>,<space/><link><target>beans</target></link>,<space/><link><target>dairy products</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lentil</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>meat</target></link>,<space/><link><target>millet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Skinning</target><part>leather</part></link>,<space/><link><target>sorghum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>teff</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>wheat</target></link>. The displacement of 1 million Eritreans as a result of the war with Ethiopia, and the widespread presence of<space/><link><target>land mines</target></link><space/>all have played a role in the declining productivity of the agricultural sector. Currently, almost a quarter of the countrys most productive land remains unoccupied because of the lingering effects of the 19982000 war with Ethiopia.</paragraph><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>forestry</target></link><space/>is not a significant economic activity in Eritrea, its forested area covers<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1585000</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg name="abbr">off</arg></template>, or 13.5 percent of the total land area. Total roundwood production in 2004 was 1,266,000 cubic meters, nearly all of it used for<space/><link><target>fuel</target></link>. Since 1993, the Eritrean Peoples Liberation Front army has been involved in tree planting and other<space/><link><target>afforestation</target></link><space/>activities; the annual average rate of<space/><link><target>deforestation</target></link><space/>during 19902000 was 0.3 percent.</paragraph><paragraph>Reliable figures on the extent and value of the<space/><link><target>fishing industry</target></link><space/>in Eritrea are difficult to obtain. However, Eritreas long coastline offers the opportunity for significant expansion of the fishing industry from its current, largely artisanal, stage. Eritrea exports fish and sea cucumbers from the Red Sea to markets in Europe and Asia, and there is hope that the construction of a new, jet-capable airport in<space/><link><target>Massawa</target></link>, as well as rehabilitation of the port there, may support increased exports of high-value seafood. In 2002, exports were about 14,000 tons, but the maximum stable yield is thought to be nearly 80,000 tons. A fish processing plant was built in 1998 that now exports 150 tons of frozen fish every month to markets in<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>Britain</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link>. Tensions with<space/><link><target>Yemen</target></link><space/>over fishing rights in the<space/><link><target>Red Sea</target></link><space/>flared up in 1995 and again in 2002, and Eritreas difficult relations with other nations could hamper further development of the industry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Animal husbandry</heading><paragraph><link><target>Sheep</target></link>,<space/><link><target>goat</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>cattle</target></link><space/>(especially<space/><link><target>zebu</target></link>), and<space/><link><target>camel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>make up the majority of Eritreas livestock. In 2001, Eritrea had 2,100,000 sheep, 1,700,000 goats, 1,950,000 head of cattle, 75,000 camels, and 1.4 million<space/><link><target>chicken</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Total meat production that year was 30,900 tons; cows milk, 39,200 tons; and eggs, 2,000 tons. The government is emphasizing development of agriculture and animal husbandry in order to decrease the reliance on international relief, caused by war.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mining and minerals</heading><paragraph>Eritreas substantial mineral deposits are largely unexplored. According to the Eritrean government, artisanal mining in 1998 collected 573.4 kilograms of<space/><link><target>gold</target></link>, however the number of gold reserves is unknown. International observers also have noted Eritreas excellent potential for quarrying ornamental marble and granite. As of 2001, some 10 mining companies had obtained licenses to prospect for different minerals in Eritrea. The government of Eritrea reportedly is in the process of conducting a geological survey for use by potential investors in the mining sector. The presence of hundreds of thousands of land mines in Eritrea, particularly along the border with Ethiopia, presents a serious impediment to future development of the mining sector.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevsun Resources completed its Bisha mining project in early 2011. Estimated production will be 350,000 ounces of gold per year until the gold runs out, at which point the mine will produce copper and zinc.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nevsun.com/projects/bisha-main/</arg><arg name="title">Nevsun Resources: Bisha Mine, Bisha Project, Gold Production, Gold Mine Africa, Mining Africa, Copper Mine, Mining Eritrea, Base Metal Properties, High-Grade Gold</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">11 June 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Industry and Manufacturing</heading><paragraph>By the end the War of Independence, all industrial production had stopped due to the Ethiopians' nationalizing and breaking apart of Eritrea's largest factories, as well as the destruction of infrastructure by the weapons of the then Ethiopian government. The remaining plants were generally inefficient, and most of these industries required significant investment to achieve productivity. Since then, there has been a growth in industry. Manufactured items in 2002 included beverages, processed foods,<space/><link><target>tobacco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>leather</target></link>,<space/><link><target>textiles</target></link>, metal products, chemicals, printing, nonmetallic minerals, construction materials,<space/><link><target>salt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>paper</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>matches</target></link>. The government sought privatization of these industries, and issued incentives such as exemptions from income tax, preferential treatment in allocation of foreign exchange for imports, and provisions for remittance of foreign exchange abroad. In 2002, there were approximately 2,000 manufacturing companies operating in the country.</paragraph><paragraph>The oil industry has potential, as major oil deposits are believed to lie under the<space/><link><target>Red Sea</target></link>. In 2001, the United States firm<space/><link><target>CMS Energy</target></link><space/>entered into an exploration agreement with Eritrea for exploration in the<space/><link><target>Dismin Block</target></link><space/>in northeastern Eritrea. Due to high operating costs, the countrys sole oil refinery, at<space/><link><target>Assab</target></link>, was closedin 1997. It had a crude refining capacity of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template>. The construction industry is growing, as projects range from the construction and expansion of power plants; road, airport, and dam construction; upgrading sea ports; and the construction of schools and hospitals.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2005, industry had a 26.3% share of the GDP; since 2011, it has grown to 34%. Recent industries include food processing, beverages, clothing and textiles, salt, cement, and commercial ship repair.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Energy</heading><paragraph>Households consume more than 80 percent of total energy production.<space/><link><target>Electricity production</target></link><space/>in 2001 was estimated at 220.5 million kilowatt-hours. Consumption for that year was estimated at 205.1-kilowatt hours. An 88-megawatt electricity plant funded by<space/><link><target>Saudi Arabia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kuwait</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Abu Dhabi</target></link><space/>was completed just south of Massawa in 2003, its completion delayed nearly three years by the war with Ethiopia. Annual consumption of petroleum in 2001 was estimated at 370,000 tons. Eritrea has no domestic petroleum production; the Eritrean Petroleum Corporation conducts purchases through international competitive tender. According to the U.S. Department of Commerce, opportunities exist for both on- and offshore oil and natural gas exploration; however, these prospects have yet to come to fruition. The use of<space/><link><target>Wind energy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>solar power</target></link><space/>have slightly increased, due to the growth of solar power manufacturing companies in the country. The Eritrean government has expressed interest in developing alternative energy sources, including geothermal, solar, and wind power.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Services</heading><paragraph>In 2011, services accounted for 55 percent of gross domestic product. Financial services, the bulk of the services sector, are principally rendered by the<space/><link><target>National Bank of Eritrea</target></link><space/>(the nations central bank), the Commercial Bank of Eritrea, the Housing and Commerce Bank of Eritrea, the Agricultural and Industrial Bank of Eritrea, the Eritrean Investment and Development Bank, and the National Insurance Corporation of Eritrea.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Tourism</heading><paragraph>Eritreas lack of access to funds, the presence of large numbers of land mines, and the continued tensions that flare up between Eritrea and its neighbors have deterred the development of a<space/><link><target>tourist industry</target></link><space/>in Eritrea. According to the<space/><link><target>World Tourism Organization</target></link>, international tourism receipts in 2002 were only US$73 million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Banking and Finance</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Banking in Eritrea</arg></template>According to the<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target></link>, commercial banks in Eritreaall government owned and operatedappear to be in compliance with prudent regulations. Although the commercial banking sector is largely profitable, mostly owing to income from foreign exchange transactions, the sector is burdened by a high proportion of non-performing loans. Core lending activities do not generate sufficient income to cover operating costs at most commercial banks.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Labor force</heading><paragraph>Agriculture employs about 80 percent of the population in Eritrea, and the remaining 20 percent are employed in industry and services. The GDP per capita at nominal value was $475 in 2011.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Currency, exchange rate, and inflation</heading><paragraph>The official currency is the<space/><link><target>Eritrean nakfa</target></link><space/>(ERN), introduced in November 1997. In early 2005, likely in an effort to increase foreign capital reserves, the Eritrean government decreed that all transactions in Eritrea must be conducted in nakfa. It soon became illegal for individuals to hold and exchange foreign currency. As of January 1, 2005, the government set the foreign exchange rate at US$1=ERN15.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Inflation</target></link><space/>continues to be a problem in Eritrea, particularly as years of drought push grain prices higher and defense expenditures remain high. The International Monetary Fund estimates that in 2003 (the most recent year for which figures are available) average inflation reached 23 percent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Government Budget</heading><paragraph>Eritrea does not publish a budget, making its fiscal condition difficult to assess. According to the International Monetary Fund, the overall fiscal deficit in 2003 was 17 percent of gross domestic product (GDP). Government expenditures for that year were estimated to be US$375 million, with revenues of only US$235.7 million. In 2002 the fiscal deficit was 32 percent of GDP. Current expenditures continue to exceed budgeted spending, particularly in defense and other discretionary expenditures. Monetary policy remains subservient to the financing demands of the government, and debt is unsustainably high. This situation is not likely to change until demobilization of the military occurs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension><space/>According to the CIA World Factbook, the Eritrean Government has revenues of $715.2 million, and outlays of $1.021 billion.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/er.html| CIA - The World Factbook</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Foreign economic relations</heading><paragraph><link><target>China</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>are aggressively pursuing market opportunities in Eritrea. There is growing interest in U.S. products and services in Eritrea, although U.S. investment in Eritrea is still small.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2011, Eritrea imported goods worth US$899.9 million, including machinery, petroleum products, food, and manufactured goods. Eritreas main suppliers were Brazil, China, Egypt, India, Italy, Germany, Saudi Arabia, and South Africa. In 2011 exports from Eritrea were valued at US$415.4 million, and the bulk were food, livestock, small manufactures, sorghum, and textiles. The major markets for Eritrean goods were China, Egypt, Italy, Saudi Arabia, Sudan, and the UK. More recently, fish, flowers, and salt have joined the list of exports.</paragraph><paragraph>Foreign investment is hindered by government regulations that seek to protect domestic industries from foreign competition and by a generally unfavorable investment climate. Major foreign investors in Eritrea include China, South Korea, Italy, South Africa, and Germany, as well as the<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The government prefers private-sector investment to official aid programs and declines foreign aid; therefore its relations with aid-dispensing nations and international institutions have often been difficult.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Eritrea</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Eritrea</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Banking in Eritrea</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of companies based in Eritrea</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template><template><target>CIA World Factbook</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Regional/Africa/Eritrea/Business_and_Economy/Economic_Development</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.trademap.org/open_access/Index.aspx?proceed=true&amp;amp;reporter=232'>Eritrea latest trade data on ITC Trade Map</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.imf.org/external/np/sec/pn/2005/pn0518.htm'>IMF Executive Board Concludes Consultation with Eritrea February 2005</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Economy of</arg></template><template><target>Eritrea topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Economy Of Eritrea</target></template><link><target>Category:Economy of Eritrea</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:African Union member economies</target><part>Eritrea</part></link></paragraph></article>