<article title='Arianism'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Arian</arg></template><template><target>Distinguish2</target><arg>"[[Aryan race|Aryanism]]", which is a racial ideology</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Arianism</target></template><bold>Arianism</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Nontrinitarianism</target><part>nontrinitarian</part></link><space/>belief which asserts that<space/><link><target>Jesus</target><part>Jesus Christ</part></link><space/>is the<space/><link><target>Son of God</target></link>, but is entirely distinct from and subordinate to<space/><link><target>God the Father</target></link>. Arianism is defined as those teachings attributed to<space/><link><target>Arius</target></link>, which are in opposition to current mainstream Christian teachings on the nature of the<space/><link><target>Trinity</target></link><space/>and the nature of Christ. It was first attributed to Arius (<link><target>circa</target><part>c.</part></link><space/>AD 250336), a Christian<space/><link><target>presbyter</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link>, Egypt. The Arian<space/><link><target>Christology</target><part>concept of Christ</part></link><space/>is that the Son of God did not always exist, but was created byand is therefore distinct fromGod the Father. This belief is grounded in the<space/><link><target>Gospel of John</target></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg>14:28</arg></template>)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rowan<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Rowan Williams<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Arius: heresy and tradition<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>98<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8028-4969-4<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>passage: &quot;You heard me say, 'I am going away and I am coming back to you.' If you loved me, you would be glad that I am going to the Father, for the Father is greater than I.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>In contrast to Arianism, the trinitarian viewpoint was formally affirmed by the first two<space/><link><target>Ecumenical Council</target><trail>s</trail></link>, thereby rejecting the idea that Christ is a distinct personality from the singular Lord of the Old Testament.. All mainstream branches of Christianity consider Arianism to be<space/><link><target>Heterodoxy</target><part>heterodox</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>herecy</target><part>heretical</part></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template><space/>The Ecumenical<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target></link><space/>of 325 deemed it to be a heresy. At the regional<space/><link><target>First Synod of Tyre</target></link><space/>in 335, Arius was exonerated.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Socrates of Constantinople</target></link>,<space/><italics>Church History</italics>, book 1, chapter 33. Anthony F. Beavers,<space/><italics>Chronology of the Arian Controversy</italics>.</extension><space/>After his death, he was again<space/><link><target>anathema</target><part>anathemised</part></link><space/>and pronounced a heretic again at the Ecumenical<space/><link><target>First Council of Constantinople</target></link><space/>of 381.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.viii.i.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">First Council of Constantinople, Canon 1<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ccel.org</arg></template></extension><space/>The Roman Emperors<space/><link><target>Constantius II#Christianity under Constantius</target><part>Constantius II</part></link><space/>(337361) and<space/><link><target>Valens#Struggles with the religious nature of the Empire</target><part>Valens</part></link><space/>(364378) were Arians or<space/><link><target>Semi-Arianism</target><part>Semi-Arians</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Arianism is also often used to refer to other<space/><link><target>nontrinitarian</target></link><space/>theological systems of the 4th century, which regarded<space/><link><target>Jesus Christ</target></link>the Son of God, the<space/><link><target>Logos (Christianity)</target><part>Logos</part></link>as either a created being (as in Arianism proper and<space/><link><target>Anomoeanism</target></link>), or as neither uncreated nor created in the sense other beings are created (as in<space/><link><target>Semi-Arianism</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origin</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Arius</arg><arg>Arian controversy</arg></template>Arius taught that God the Father and the Son of God did not always exist together eternally.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ritchies.net"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Story of the Church - Part 2, Topics 2 & 3</arg><arg name="first">Mark S.</arg><arg name="last">Ritchie</arg><arg name="website">The Story of the Church</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ritchies.net/p2wk2.htm</arg></template></extension><space/>Arians taught that the Logos was a divine being created by God the Father before the world; that the Son of God is subordinate to God the Father.<extension extension_name='ref'>M'Clintock and Strong's Cyclopedia, Volume 7, page 45a.</extension><space/>Arius and his followers appealed to Bible verses such as Jesus saying that the father is &quot;greater than I&quot; (<link><target>Gospel of John</target><part>John</part></link><space/><template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>John</arg><arg>14:28</arg></template>), and &quot;The Lord created me at the beginning of his work&quot; (<link><target>Book of Proverbs</target><part>Proverbs</part></link><space/><template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Proverbs</arg><arg>8:22</arg></template>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="FiorenzaGalvin1991"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Francis Schüssler Fiorenza</arg><arg name="author2">John P. Galvin</arg><arg name="title">Systematic theology: Roman Catholic perspectives</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 April 2010</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="publisher">Fortress Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8006-2460-6</arg><arg name="pages">164–</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Controversy over Arianism arose in the late 3rd century and persisted throughout most of the 4th century. It involved most church membersfrom simple believers, priests and monks to bishops, emperors and members of Rome's imperial family. Such a deep controversy within the Church during this period of its development could not have materialized without significant historical influences providing a basis for the Arian doctrines.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hanson2007"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hanson</arg><arg name="first">R P C</arg><arg name="title">The Search for the Christian Doctrine of God</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Baker Academic</arg><arg name="location">Grand Rapids</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8010-3146-X</arg><arg name="pages">127–128</arg></template></extension><space/>Of the roughly three hundred bishops in attendance at the<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target><part>Council of Nicea</part></link>, only two bishops did not sign the<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target></link>, which condemned Arianism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Chadwick</arg><arg name="first">Henry</arg><arg name="title">Faith and Order at the Council of Nicea</arg><arg name="journal">The Harvard Theological Review</arg><arg name="date">July 1960</arg><arg name="volume">53</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">171–195</arg><arg name="jstor">1508399</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/S0017816000027000</arg></template></extension><space/>Two Roman emperors,<space/><link><target>Constantius II</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Valens</target></link>, became Arians, as did prominent<space/><link><target>Goths</target><part>Gothic</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Vandal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lombards</target><part>Lombard</part></link><space/>warlords both before and after the fall of the Western Roman Empire.</paragraph><paragraph>Arius had been a pupil of<space/><link><target>Lucian of Antioch</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>School of Antioch</target><part>Lucian's private academy in Antioch</part></link><space/>and inherited from him a modified form of the teachings of<space/><link><target>Paul of Samosata</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Leighton Pullan, Early Christian Doctrine, Third Edition, Oxford Church Text Books (New York: Edwin S. Gorham, 1905), p.87.</extension><space/>After the dispute over Arianism became politicized and a general solution to the divisiveness was soughtwith a great majority holding to the Trinitarian positionthe Arian position was officially declared<space/><link><target>heterodox</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Arianism continued to exist for several decades, although the apparent resurgence of Arianism after Nicaea was more an anti-Nicene reaction exploited by Arian sympathizers than a pro-Arian development.<extension extension_name='ref'>Everett Ferguson, Church History: From Christ to Pre-Reformation, vol. 1 (Grand Rapids, MI: Zondervan, 2005), 200.</extension><space/>By the end of the 4th century it had surrendered its remaining ground to Trinitarianism in the official Roman church hierarchy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="carm"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://carm.org/arianism-and-its-influence-today</arg><arg name="title">Arianism and Its Influence Today&#124;Arius&#124;Idea That Jesus Christ Is Not Equal to the Father By Nature</arg><arg name="publisher">carm.org</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 October 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In western Europe, Arianism, which had been taught by<space/><link><target>Ulfilas</target></link>, the Arian missionary to the Germanic tribes, was dominant among the<space/><link><target>Goths</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lombards</target></link><space/>(and, significantly for the late Empire, the<space/><link><target>Vandals</target></link>); but it ceased to be the mainstream belief by the 8th century, as the rulers of these Germanic tribes gradually adopted Catholicism, beginning with<space/><link><target>Clovis I</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link><space/>in 496, then<space/><link><target>Reccared I</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Visigoths</target></link><space/>in 587 and<space/><link><target>Aripert I</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Lombards</target></link><space/>in 653. It was crushed through a series of military and political conquests,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template><space/>culminating in religious<space/><italics>and</italics><space/>political domination of Europe over the next 1,000 years by Trinitarian forces in the Catholic Church. Trinitarianism has remained the dominant doctrine in all major branches of the Eastern and Western Church and later within<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>"In addition, if any writing composed by Arius should be found, it should be handed over to the flames, so that not only will the wickedness of his teaching be obliterated, but nothing will be left even to remind anyone of him. And I hereby make a public order, that if someone should be discovered to have hidden a writing composed by Arius, and not to have immediately brought it forward and destroyed it by fire, his penalty shall be death. As soon as he is discovered in this offence, he shall be submitted for capital punishment.&nbsp;... "</arg><arg name="Edict by Emperor Constantine against the Arians<ref>{{cite web|url">http://www.fourthcentury.com/index.php/urkunde-33 |title</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Beliefs</heading><paragraph>Reconstructing what Arius actually taught and why is a formidable task, both because little of his own work survives except in quotations selected for polemical purposes by his opponents, and also because there is no certainty about what theological and philosophical traditions formed his thought.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Bauckham, Review of Arius: Heresy and Tradition by Rowan Williams, Themelios: Volume 14, No. 2, January/February 1989, 1989, 75.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Arians do not believe in the traditional doctrine of the Trinity, which holds that God encompasses three persons in one being.<extension extension_name='ref' name="www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Newton's Arian beliefs</arg><arg name="publisher">School of Mathematics and Statistics, [[University of St. Andrews]]</arg><arg name="location">Scotland</arg><arg name="url">http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/history/Extras/Newton_Arian.html</arg></template></extension><space/>The letter of Arian Auxentius<extension extension_name='ref' name="faculty.georgetown.edu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Auxentius on Wulfila: Translation by Jim Marchand</arg><arg name="url">http://faculty.georgetown.edu/jod/texts/auxentius.trans.html</arg></template></extension><space/>regarding the Arian missionary<space/><link><target>Ulfilas</target></link>, gives the clearest picture of Arian beliefs. Arian<space/><link><target>Ulfilas</target></link>, who was ordained a bishop by Arian<space/><link><target>Eusebius of Nicomedia</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>returned to his people to work as a missionary, believed: God, the Father, (&quot;unbegotten&quot; God; Almighty God) always existing and who is the only true God (John 17:3). The Son of God, Jesus Christ, (&quot;only-begotten God&quot; John 1:18;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">New American Standard Bible {{ndash}} John 1</arg><arg name="website">Bible Hub</arg><arg name="url">http://biblehub.com/nasb/john/1.htm</arg></template></extension><space/>Mighty God Isaiah 9:6) begotten before time began (Proverbs 8:22-29; Revelation 3:14; Colossians 1:15) and who is Lord/Master (1 Cor 8:6). The Holy Spirit (the illuminating and sanctifying power, who is neither God nor Lord/Master.<space/><link><target>First Epistle to the Corinthians</target><part>First Corinthians</part></link><space/><template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Corinthians</arg><arg>8:5</arg></template>-<template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Corinthians</arg><arg>8:6</arg></template><space/>was cited as<space/><link><target>proof text</target></link>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Indeed, even though there may be so-called gods in heaven or on earth — as in fact there are many gods and many lords/masters — yet for us there is one God (Gk. ''theos'' – θεος), the Father, from whom are all things and for whom we exist, and one Lord/Master (''kyrios'' – κυριος), Jesus Christ, through whom are all things and through whom we exist.</arg><arg>[[NRSV]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The creed of Arian<space/><link><target>Ulfilas</target></link><space/>(c. 311 383), which concludes a letter praising him written by Auxentius,<extension extension_name='ref' name="faculty.georgetown.edu"></extension><space/>distinguishes God the Father (&quot;unbegotten&quot;), who is the only true God from Son of God (&quot;only-begotten&quot;), who is Lord/Master; and the Holy Spirit (the illuminating and sanctifying power), who is neither God nor Lord/Master:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="I, Ulfila, bishop and confessor, have always so believed, and in this, the one true faith, I make the journey to my Lord; I believe in only one God the Father, the unbegotten and invisible, and in his only-begotten son, our Lord/Master and God, the designer and maker of all creation, having none other like him. Therefore there is one God of all, who is also God of our God; and in one Holy Spirit, the illuminating and sanctifying power, as Christ said after his resurrection to his apostles: "And behold, I send the promise of my Father upon you; but tarry ye in the city of Jerusalem, until ye be clothed with power from on high" (Luke 24:49) and again "But ye shall receive power, when the Holy Ghost is come upon you" (Acts 1:8); Neither God nor Lord/Master, but the faithful minister of Christ; not equal, but subject and obedient in all things to the Son. And I believe the Son to be subject and obedient in all things to God the Father.<ref>{{cite book|last">Heather and Matthews|title</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A letter from<space/><link><target>Arius</target></link><space/>(c. 250336) to the Arian<space/><link><target>Eusebius of Nicomedia</target></link><space/>(died 341) succinctly states the core beliefs of the Arians:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Some of them say that the Son is an eructation, others that he is a production, others that he is also unbegotten. These are impieties to which we cannot listen, even though the heretics threaten us with a thousand deaths. But we say and believe and have taught, and do teach, that the Son is not unbegotten, nor in any way part of the unbegotten; and that he does not derive his subsistence from any matter; but that by his own will and counsel he has subsisted before time and before ages as perfect as God, only begotten and unchangeable, and that before he was begotten, or created, or purposed, or established, he was not. For he was not unbegotten. We are persecuted, because we say that the Son has a beginning, but that God is without beginning.</arg><arg>Theodoret: Arius's Letter to Eusebius of Nicomedia</arg><arg>translated in Peters' ''Heresy and Authority in [[Medieval Europe]]'', p. 41</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>First Council of Nicaea and its aftermath</heading><paragraph>In 321, Arius was denounced by a<space/><link><target>synod</target></link><space/>at Alexandria for teaching a heterodox view of the relationship of Jesus to God the Father. Because Arius and his followers had great influence in the schools of Alexandriacounterparts to modern universities or seminariestheir theological views spread, especially in the eastern Mediterranean.</paragraph><paragraph>By 325, the controversy had become significant enough that the<space/><link><target>Emperor Constantine</target></link><space/>called an assembly of bishops, the<space/><link><target>First Council of Nicaea</target></link>, which condemned Arius' doctrine and formulated the original<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed#The original Nicene Creed of 325</target><part>Nicene Creed of 325</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.vii.iii.html</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>NPNF2-14</arg><arg name="title">The Seven Ecumenical Councils<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Christian Classics Ethereal Library<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The Nicene Creed's central term, used to describe the relationship between the Father and the Son, is<space/><link><target>Homoousios</target></link><space/>(<template><target>lang-grc</target><arg>ὁμοούσιος</arg></template>), or<space/><link><target>Consubstantiality</target></link>, meaning &quot;of the same substance&quot; or &quot;of one being&quot;. (The<space/><link><target>Athanasian Creed</target></link><space/>is less often used but is a more overtly anti-Arian statement on the Trinity.)</paragraph><paragraph>The focus of the Council of Nicaea was the nature of the Son of God, and his precise relationship to God the Father. (see<space/><link><target>Paul of Samosata</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Synods of Antioch</target></link>). Arius taught that Jesus Christ was divine/holy and was sent to earth for the salvation of mankind<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk"></extension><space/>but that Jesus Christ was not equal to God the Father (infinite, primordial origin) in rank<space/><italics>and</italics><space/>that God the Father and the Son of God were not equal to the Holy Spirit (power of God the Father).<extension extension_name='ref' name="ritchies.net"></extension><space/>Under Arianism, Christ was instead not<space/><link><target>consubstantiality</target><part>consubstantial</part></link><space/>with God the Father<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Pomazansky">&quot;The oneness of Essence, the Equality of Divinity, and the Equality of Honor of God the Son with the God the Father.&quot; Orthodox Dogmatic Theology: A Concise Exposition Protopresbyter Michael Pomazansky pages 9295</extension><space/>since both the Father and the Son under Arius were made of &quot;like&quot; essence or being (see<space/><link><target>homoiousia</target></link>) but not of the same essence or being (see<space/><link><target>homoousia</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pomazansky"></extension><space/>God the Father is a Deity and is divine<space/><italics>and</italics><space/>the Son of God is not a Deity but divine (I, the LORD, am Deity alone. Isaiah 46:9).<extension extension_name='ref' name="www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk"></extension><space/>God the Father sent Jesus to earth for salvation of mankind (John 17:3).<space/><link><target>Ousia</target></link><space/>is essence or being, in Eastern Christianity, and is the aspect of God that is completely incomprehensible to mankind and human perception. It is all that subsists by itself and which has not its being in another,<extension extension_name='ref'>The Mystical Theology of the Eastern Church, SVS Press, 1997. (ISBN 0-913836-31-1) James Clarkef &amp; Co Ltd, 1991. (ISBN 0-227-67919-9) V Lossky pg&amp;nbsp;5051</extension><space/>God the Father and God the Son and God the Holy Spirit all being uncreated.<extension extension_name='ref'>Orthodox Dogmatic Theology: A Concise Exposition Protopresbyter Michael Pomazansky pages 57 As quoted by<space/><link><target>John Damascene</target></link>:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>God is unoriginate, unending, eternal, constant, uncreated, unchanging, unalterable, simple, incomplex, bodiless, invisible, intangible, indescribable, without bounds, inaccessible to the mind, uncontainable, incomprehensible, good, righteous, that Creator of all creatures, the almighty<space/><link><target>Pantocrator</target></link>.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to the teaching of Arius, the pre-existent Logos and thus the incarnate Jesus Christ was a created being; that only the Son was directly created and begotten by God the Father, before ages, but was of a distinct, though similar, essence or substance from the Creator; his opponents argued that this would make Jesus less than God, and that this was heretical.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pomazansky"></extension><space/>Much of the distinction between the differing factions was over the phrasing that Christ expressed in the New Testament to express submission to God the Father.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pomazansky"></extension><space/>The theological term for this submission is<space/><link><target>kenosis</target></link>. This Ecumenical council declared that Jesus Christ was a distinct being of God in existence or reality (<link><target>hypostasis (philosophy)</target><part>hypostasis</part></link>), which the Latin fathers translated as persona. Jesus was God in essence, being and or nature (<link><target>ousia</target></link>), which the Latin fathers translated as substantia.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Constantine burning Arian books.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Constantine I (emperor)</target><part>Constantine</part></link><space/>burning Arian books, illustration from a compendium of<space/><link><target>canon law</target></link>, ''c''. 825</part></link>Constantine is believed to have exiled those who refused to accept the Nicean creedArius himself, the deacon<space/><link><target>Euzoios</target></link>, and the Libyan bishops<space/><link><target>Theonas of Marmarica</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Secundus of Ptolemais</target></link>and also the bishops who signed the creed but refused to join in condemnation of Arius, Eusebius of Nicomedia and<space/><link><target>Theognis of Nicaea</target></link>. The Emperor also ordered all copies of the<space/><italics>Thalia</italics>, the book in which Arius had expressed his teachings, to be<space/><link><target>Book burning</target><part>burned</part></link>. However, there is no evidence that his son and ultimate successor,<space/><link><target>Constantius II</target></link>, who was an Arian Christian, was exiled.</paragraph><paragraph>Although he was committed to maintaining what the church had defined at Nicaea, Constantine was also bent on pacifying the situation and eventually became more lenient toward those condemned and exiled at the council. First he allowed Eusebius of Nicomedia, who was a protg of his sister, and Theognis to return once they had signed an ambiguous statement of faith. The two, and other friends of Arius, worked for Arius' rehabilitation. At the<space/><link><target>First Synod of Tyre</target></link><space/>in AD 335, they brought accusations against<space/><link><target>Pope Athanasius I of Alexandria</target><part>Athanasius</part></link>, bishop of Alexandria, the primary opponent of Arius; after this, Constantine had Athanasius banished, since he considered him an impediment to reconciliation. In the same year, the Synod of Jerusalem under Constantine's direction readmitted<space/><link><target>Arius</target></link><space/>to communion in AD 336. Arius, however, died on the way to this event in Constantinople. Some scholars suggest that Arius may have been poisoned by his opponents.<extension extension_name='ref'>Edward Gibbons &quot;The Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire&quot;, Chapter 21, (177688), Jonathan Kirsch, &quot;God Against the Gods: The History of the War Between Monotheism and Polytheism&quot;, 2004, and<space/><link><target>Charles Freeman (historian)</target><part>Charles Freeman</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Closing of the Western Mind</target></link>: The Rise of Faith and the Fall of Reason</italics>, 2002.</extension><space/>Eusebius and Theognis remained in the Emperor's favour, and when Constantine, who had been a<space/><link><target>catechumen</target></link><space/>much of his adult life, accepted<space/><link><target>baptism</target></link><space/>on his deathbed, it was from Eusebius of Nicomedia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gonzalez</arg><arg name="first">Justo</arg><arg name="title">The Story of Christianity Vol.1</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="publisher">Harper Collins</arg><arg name="isbn">0-06-063315-8</arg><arg name="page">176</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Theological debates</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:PalatiumTheodoricMosaicDetail.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Once the Orthodox Trinitarians succeeded in defeating Arianism, they censored any signs that the perceived heresy left behind. This mosaic in<space/><link><target>Basilica of Sant'Apollinare Nuovo</target></link><space/>in Ravenna has had images of the Arian king, Theoderic, and his court removed. However, on some columns their hands remain.</part></link>The Council of Nicaea did not end the controversy, as many bishops of the Eastern provinces disputed the<space/><italics><link><target>homoousios</target></link></italics>, the central term of the Nicene creed, as it had been used by<space/><link><target>Paul of Samosata</target></link>, who had advocated a<space/><link><target>Monarchianism</target><part>monarchianist</part></link><space/><link><target>Christology</target></link>. Both the man and his teaching, including the term<space/><italics>homoousios</italics>, had been condemned by the<space/><link><target>Synods of Antioch</target></link><space/>in 269.</paragraph><paragraph>Hence, after Constantine's death in 337, open dispute resumed again. Constantine's son<space/><link><target>Constantius II</target></link>, who had become Emperor of the eastern part of the Empire, actually encouraged the Arians and set out to reverse the Nicene creed. His advisor in these affairs was Eusebius of Nicomedia, who had already at the Council of Nicea been the head of the Arian party, who also was made bishop of Constantinople.</paragraph><paragraph>Constantius used his power to exile bishops adhering to the Nicene creed, especially St<space/><link><target>Athanasius of Alexandria</target></link>, who fled to Rome. In 355 Constantius became the sole Emperor and extended his pro-Arian policy toward the western provinces, frequently using force to push through his creed, even exiling<space/><link><target>Pope Liberius</target></link><space/>and installing<space/><link><target>Antipope Felix II</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>As debates raged in an attempt to come up with a new formula, three camps evolved among the opponents of the Nicene creed. The first group mainly opposed the Nicene terminology and preferred the term<space/><italics>homoiousios</italics><space/>(alike in substance) to the Nicene<space/><italics>homoousios</italics>, while they rejected Arius and his teaching and accepted the equality and coeternality of the persons of the Trinity. Because of this centrist position, and despite their rejection of Arius, they were called &quot;semi-Arians&quot; by their opponents. The second group also avoided invoking the name of Arius, but in large part followed Arius' teachings and, in another attempted compromise wording, described the Son as being like (<italics><link><target>Acacians</target><part>homoios</part></link></italics>) the Father. A third group explicitly called upon Arius and described the Son as unlike (<italics><link><target>Anomoeanism</target><part>anhomoios</part></link></italics>) the Father. Constantius wavered in his support between the first and the second party, while harshly persecuting the third.</paragraph><paragraph>The debates among these groups resulted in numerous synods, among them the<space/><link><target>Council of Sardica</target></link><space/>in 343, the<space/><link><target>Council of Sirmium</target></link><space/>in 358 and the double<space/><link><target>Council of Rimini</target></link><space/>and Seleucia in 359, and no fewer than fourteen further creed formulas between 340 and 360, leading the pagan observer<space/><link><target>Ammianus Marcellinus</target></link><space/>to comment sarcastically: &quot;The highways were covered with galloping bishops.&quot; None of these attempts were acceptable to the defenders of Nicene orthodoxy: writing about the latter councils, Saint<space/><link><target>Jerome</target></link><space/>remarked that the world &quot;awoke with a groan to find itself Arian.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>After Constantius' death in 361, his successor<space/><link><target>Julian (emperor)</target><part>Julian</part></link>, a devotee of<space/><link><target>State religion of Rome</target><part>Rome's pagan gods</part></link>, declared that he would no longer attempt to favor one church faction over another, and allowed all exiled bishops to return; this resulted in further increasing dissension among Christians. The Emperor<space/><link><target>Valens</target></link>, however, revived Constantius' policy and supported the &quot;Homoian&quot; party, exiling bishops and often using force. During this persecution many bishops were exiled to the other ends of the Empire, (e.g.,<space/><link><target>St Hilary of Poitiers</target></link><space/>to the Eastern provinces). These contacts and the common plight subsequently led to a rapprochement between the Western supporters of the Nicene creed and the<space/><italics>homoousios</italics><space/>and the Eastern semi-Arians.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Theodosius and the Council of Constantinople</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Theodosius I</arg></template>It was not until the co-reigns of Gratian and Theodosius that Arianism was effectively wiped out among the ruling class and elite of the Eastern Empire. Theodosius' wife St<space/><link><target>Aelia Flacilla</target><part>Flacilla</part></link><space/>was instrumental in his campaign to end Arianism. Valens died in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Adrianople (378)</target><part>Battle of Adrianople</part></link><space/>in 378 and was succeeded by<space/><link><target>Theodosius I</target></link>, who adhered to the Nicene creed. This allowed for settling the dispute.</paragraph><paragraph>Two days after Theodosius arrived in Constantinople, 24 November 380, he expelled the<space/><link><target>Homoiousian</target></link><space/>bishop,<space/><link><target>Demophilus of Constantinople</target></link>, and surrendered the churches of that city to<space/><link><target>Gregory Nazianzus</target></link>, the leader of the rather small Nicene community there, an act which provoked rioting. Theodosius had just been baptized, by bishop Acholius of Thessalonica, during a severe illness, as was common in the early Christian world. In February he and<space/><link><target>Gratian</target></link><space/>had published an edict<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf202.iii.xii.iv.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sozomen's Church History VII.4<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ccel.org<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>that all their subjects should profess the faith of the bishops of Rome and Alexandria (i.e., the Nicene faith), or be handed over for punishment for not doing so.</paragraph><paragraph>Although much of the church hierarchy in the East had opposed the Nicene creed in the decades leading up to Theodosius' accession, he managed to achieve unity on the basis of the Nicene creed. In 381, at the<space/><link><target>First Council of Constantinople</target><part>Second Ecumenical Council</part></link><space/>in Constantinople, a group of mainly Eastern bishops assembled and accepted the<space/><link><target>Nicene-Constantinopolitan Creed</target><part>Nicene Creed of 381</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>The text of this version of the<space/><link><target>Nicene creed</target></link><space/>is available at<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/ccel/schaff/npnf214.ix.iii.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Holy Creed Which the 150 Holy Fathers Set Forth, Which is Consonant with the Holy and Great Synod of Nice<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ccel.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 November 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>which was supplemented in regard to the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link>, as well as some other changes: see<space/><link><target>Comparison of Nicene Creeds of 325 and 381</target><part>Comparison between Creed of 325 and Creed of 381</part></link>. This is generally considered the end of the dispute about the Trinity and the end of Arianism among the Roman, non-Germanic peoples.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later debates</heading><paragraph><link><target>Epiphanius of Salamis</target></link><space/>labelled the party of<space/><link><target>Basil of Ancyra</target></link><space/>in 358 &quot;<link><target>Semi-Arianism</target></link>&quot;. This is considered unfair by Kelly who states that some members of the group were virtually orthodox from the start but disliked the adjective<space/><italics>homoousios</italics><space/>while others had moved in that direction after the out-and-out Arians had come into the open.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly J.N.D.<space/><italics>Early Christian Doctrines</italics><space/>A&amp;G Black 1965, p. 249</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early medieval Germanic kingdoms</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Gothic Christianity</arg><arg>Germanic Christianity</arg></template>During the time of Arianism's flowering in<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>, the Gothic convert<space/><link><target>Ulfilas</target></link><space/>(later the subject of the letter of Auxentius cited above) was sent as a missionary to the Gothic barbarians across the<space/><link><target>Danube River</target><part>Danube</part></link>, a mission favored for political reasons by emperor Constantius II. Ulfilas' initial success in converting this Germanic people to an Arian form of Christianity was strengthened by later events. When the Germanic peoples entered the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link><space/>and founded successor-kingdoms in the western part, most had been Arian Christians for more than a century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Baptistery.Arians06.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Ceiling Mosaic of the<space/><link><target>Arian Baptistry</target></link></part></link>The conflict in the 4th century AD had seen Arian and Nicene factions struggling for control of the Church. In contrast, in the Arian German kingdoms established on the wreckage of the Western Roman Empire in the 5th century, there were entirely separate Arian and Nicene Churches with parallel hierarchies, each serving different sets of believers. The Germanic elites were Arians, and the majority population was Nicene. Many scholars see the persistence of Germanic Arianism as a strategy that was followed in order to differentiate the Germanic elite from the local inhabitants and their culture and also to maintain the Germanic elite's separate group identity.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Most Germanic tribes were generally tolerant of the Nicene beliefs of their subjects. However, the Vandals tried for several decades to force their Arian beliefs on their North African Nicene subjects, exiling Nicene clergy, dissolving monasteries, and exercising heavy pressure on non-conforming Christians.</paragraph><paragraph>By the beginning of the 8th century, these kingdoms had either been conquered by Nicene neighbors (Ostrogoths, Vandals, Burgundians) or their rulers had accepted Nicene Christianity (Visigoths, Lombards).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxons</target></link><space/>were unlike the other Germanic peoples in that they entered the empire as pagans and converted to<space/><link><target>Chalcedonian Christianity</target></link><space/>directly, guided by their kings,<space/><link><target>Clovis I</target><part>Clovis</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Frassetto, Michael,<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of barbarian Europe</italics>, (ABC-CLIO, 2003), 128.</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>thelberht of Kent</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Remnants in the West, 5th to 7th centuries</heading><paragraph>However, much of southeastern Europe and<space/><link><target>central Europe</target></link>, including many of the<space/><link><target>Goths</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vandals</target></link><space/>respectively, had embraced Arianism (the<space/><link><target>Visigoths</target></link><space/>converted to Arian Christianity in 376), which led to Arianism being a religious factor in various wars in the Roman Empire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>quote</target><arg>The inhibiting and paralyzing force of superstitious beliefs penetrated to every department of life, and the most primary and elementary activities of society were influenced. War, for example, was not a simple matter of a test of strength and courage, but supernatural matters had to be taken carefully into consideration. When [[Clovis I|Clovis]] said of the Goths in southern Gaul, "I take it hard that these Arians should hold a part of the Gauls; let us go with God's aid and conquer them and bring the land under our dominion", [note: see p. 45 (Book II:37)] he was not speaking in a hypocritical or arrogant manner but in real accordance with the religious sentiment of the time. What he meant was that the Goths, being heretics, were at once enemies of the true God and inferior to the orthodox Franks in their supernatural backing. Considerations of duty, strategy, and self-interest all reinforced one another in [[Clovis I|Clovis]]'s mind. However, it was not always the orthodox side that won. We hear of a battle fought a few years before Gregory became bishop of Tours between king [[Sigebert I|Sigibert]] and the [[Huns]], [note: Book IV:29] in which the Huns "by the use of magic arts caused various false appearances to arise before their enemies and overcame them decisively." Medieval Study Guide to Gregory of Tours History of the Franks.</arg><arg>St [[Gregory of Tours]]<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/gregory-hist.html</arg></template></extension><space/>In the west, organized Arianism survived in<space/><link><target>North Africa</target></link>, in Hispania, and parts of Italy until it was finally suppressed in the 6th and 7th centuries.<space/><link><target>Grimoald I of Benevento</target><part>Grimwald</part></link>,<space/><link><target>King of the Lombards</target></link><space/>(662671), and his young son and successor<space/><link><target>Garibald</target></link><space/>(671), were the last Arian kings in Europe.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Arianism resurfaces after the Reformation, 16th century</heading><paragraph>Following the<space/><link><target>Protestant Reformation</target></link><space/>from 1517, it did not take long for Arian and other<space/><link><target>non-trinitarian</target></link><space/>views to resurface. The first recorded English<space/><link><target>antitrinitarian</target></link><space/>was<space/><link><target>John Assheton</target></link><space/>who was forced to recant before<space/><link><target>Thomas Cranmer</target></link><space/>in 1548. At the<space/><link><target>Anabaptist</target></link><space/><link><target>Council of Venice</target></link><space/>1550, the early Italian instigators of the<space/><link><target>Radical Reformation</target></link><space/>committed to the views of<space/><link><target>Servetus</target><part>Miguel Servet</part></link><space/>(died 1553), and these were promulgated by<space/><link><target>Giorgio Biandrata</target></link><space/>and others into Poland and Transylvania.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Roland Bainton</target></link>,<space/><italics>Hunted Heretic. The Life and Death of Michael Servetus</italics></extension><space/>The antitrinitarian wing of the Polish Reformation separated from the<space/><link><target>Calvinist</target></link><space/><italics>ecclesia maior</italics><space/>to form the<space/><italics>ecclesia minor</italics><space/>or<space/><link><target>Polish Brethren</target></link>. These were commonly referred to as &quot;Arians&quot; due to their rejection of the Trinity, though in fact the<space/><link><target>Socinians</target></link>, as they were later known, went further than Arius to the position of<space/><link><target>Photinus</target></link>. The epithet &quot;Arian&quot; was also applied to the early<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarians</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>John Biddle (Unitarian)</target><part>John Biddle</part></link><space/>though in denial of the<space/><link><target>pre-existence of Christ</target></link><space/>they were again largely Socinians not Arians.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>George Huntston Williams</target></link>.<space/><italics>The Radical Reformation</italics>, 3rd edition. Volume 15 of Sixteenth Century Essays and Studies. Ann Arbor, MI: Edwards Brothers, 1992</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 18th century the &quot;dominant trend&quot; in Britain, particularly in<space/><link><target>Latitudinarianism</target></link>, was towards Arianism, with which the names of<space/><link><target>Samuel Clarke</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Benjamin Hoadly</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Whiston</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Isaac Newton</target></link><space/>are associated.<extension extension_name='ref'>William Gibson, Robert G. Ingram<space/><italics>Religious identities in Britain, 16601832</italics><space/>p92</extension><space/>To quote the<space/><italics>Encyclopdia Britannica</italics><template><target>'s</target></template><space/>article on Arianism: &quot;In modern times some<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarians</part></link><space/>are virtually Arians in that they are unwilling either to reduce Christ to a mere human being or to attribute to him a divine nature identical with that of the Father.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Arianism.&quot; Encyclopdia Britannica. Encyclopdia Britannica 2007 Deluxe Edition. Chicago: Encyclopdia Britannica, 2007.</extension><space/>However, their doctrines cannot be considered representative of traditional Arian doctrines or vice versa.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A similar view was held by the ancient anti-Nicene<space/><link><target>Pneumatomachi</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link>:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>Πνευματομάχοι</arg></template>, breath or spirit and fighters, combining as fighters against the spirit), so called because they opposed the deifying of the Nicene Holy Ghost. However, the Pneumatomachi were adherents of<space/><link><target>Macedonianism</target></link>, and though their beliefs were somewhat reminiscent of Arianism,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wace">Wace, Henry; Piercy, William C., eds. Dictionary of Christian Biography and Literature to the End of the Sixth Century (1911, third edition) London: John Murray.</extension><space/>they were distinct enough to be distinguishably different.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wace"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Iglesia ni Cristo</target></link><space/>is one of the largest groups that teaches a similar doctrine, though they are really closer to Socinianism, believing the Word in John 1:1 is God's plan of salvation, not Christ. So Christ did not preexist.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Arianism today</heading><paragraph><link><target>Jehovah's Witnesses</target></link><space/>are often referred to as &quot;modern-day Arians&quot; or sometimes &quot;<link><target>Semi-Arians</target></link>&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Institute for Metaphysical Studies<link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=KRkzOWYc7JkC&amp;amp;pg=PA210&amp;amp;lpg=PA210&amp;amp;dq=jehovah%27s+witness+are+semi-arian&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=ENxfCQxiN_&amp;amp;sig=WB7HP4iYP9_5NPDxzyMVTdI27FU&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=jmSXU_WkK5PjsASgpIFA&amp;amp;ved=0CF4Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=jehovah%27s%20witness%20are%20semi-arian&amp;amp;f=false'>The Arian Christian Bible</link><space/>- Metaphysical Institute, 2010. Page 209. Retrieved 10 June 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Adam Bourque -<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.miskeptics.org/2012/07/ten-things-you-didnt-know-about-jehovahs-witnesses/'>Ten Things You Didnt Know about Jehovahs Witnesses.</link>Michigen Skeptics Association. Retrieved 10 June 2014.</extension><space/>usually by their opponents.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Dorsett</arg><arg name="first">Tommy</arg><arg name="title">Modern Day Arians: Who Are They?</arg><arg name="url">http://www.believersweb.org/view.cfm?ID</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 May 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Trinity: Arius and the Nicene Creed</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bible.ca/trinity/trinity-history-arius.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 May 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Young</arg><arg name="first">Alexey</arg><arg name="title">Jehovah's Witnesses</arg><arg name="url">http://www.fatheralexander.org/booklets/english/jehovah_e.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 May 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>While there are some significant similarities in theology and doctrine, the Witnesses differ from Arians by saying that the Son can fully know the Father (something Arius himself denied), and by their denial of literal personality to the<space/><link><target>Holy Spirit</target></link>. Arius considered the Holy Spirit to be a person or a high-ranking angel, which had a beginning as a creature, whereas the Witnesses consider the Holy Spirit to be God's &quot;active force&quot; or &quot;energy&quot;, which had no beginning, and is not an actual person. The original Arians also generally prayed directly to Jesus, whereas the Witnesses pray to God, through Jesus as a mediator.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Should You Believe in the Trinity?</arg><arg name="journal">Awake!</arg><arg name="date">August 2013</arg><arg name="pages">12–13</arg><arg name="url">http://wol.jw.org/en/wol/d/r1/lp-e/102013286</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 November 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Adherents</heading><paragraph>The teachings of the first two ecumenical councils - which entirely reject Arianism - are held by the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Oriental Orthodox Churches</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Assyrian Church of the East</target></link><space/>and all<space/><link><target>Reformation</target></link>-founded<space/><link><target>Protestant</target></link><space/>churches (Lutheran, Reformed/Presbyterian, and Anglican). Also, nearly all Protestant groups (such as Methodist, Baptist, most Pentecostals) entirely reject the teachings associated with Arianism. Modern groups which currently appear as embracing some of the principles of Arianism include<space/><link><target>Unitarianism</target><part>Unitarians</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Latter Day Saints</target></link><space/>(Mormon), the<space/><link><target>Jehovah's Witnesses</target></link><space/>and some sects within<space/><link><target>Branhamism</target></link>. Although the origins of their beliefs are not necessarily attributed to the teachings of Arius, many of the core beliefs are entirely similar.<extension extension_name='ref'>The latter three of which consider themselves not Protestants, but<space/><link><target>primitive Christianity</target><part>primitive Christians</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Christian Restorationist</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which is disputed by most traditions of mainstream historic Christianity ; Latter-day Saints believe they are within the fold of historic Christianity, but mainstream historic Christianity contests this identification (For the historic Christian view of the LDS, see the Old Catholic Encyclopedia, &quot;Mormons&quot;, at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/10570c.htm'>''Old Catholic Encyclopedia'', &quot;Mormons&quot;</link>, and<space/><italics>Is Mormonism Christian?</italics>, Gordon H Fraser, Moody Press 1977 (not available online). For the LDS view of historic Christianity, see both<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.lds.org/ensign/1987/07/is-the-lds-view-of-god-consistent-with-the-bible?lang=eng'>''Is the LDS view of God Consistent with the Bible?'' Ensign, July 1987</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.lds.org/new-era/1998/05/are-mormons-christians?lang=eng'>''Are Mormons Christian?'' New Era, May 1998</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Church of God (7th day) - Salem Conference</target></link><space/>may be considered to be Arian.<template><target>quotation</target><arg>We believe in one true God who is the creator of all. He is omnipotent, omniscient, and omnipresent. He sent his son to Earth to be a sacrifice for our sins. He is a separate being from his son, Jesus. The Holy Spirit is the power of God and not a separate being with a separate consciousness. We do not believe in the teaching of the Trinity, in which the Father, Son, and Holy Spirit are three parts of a single being who is God. We believe the Father and the Son are separate beings with separate consciousnesses and that the Holy Spirit is not a conscious being but instead the power of God.</arg><arg name="FAQs – Does the Church of God (7th Day) believe in the Trinity?<ref>{{cite web|url">http://www.churchofgod-7thday.org/FAQs.html#Trinity |title</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Other groups opposing the Trinity are not necessarily Arian.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Iglesia ni Cristo</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Bienvenido Santiago &quot;Is Jesus Christ Called 'God' in John 1:1?&quot; in God's Message magazine JulySeptember 1995</extension><link><target>Christadelphians</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Pearce F.<space/><italics>Jesus: God the Son or Son of God?</italics><space/>CMPA</extension><space/><link><target>Church of God General Conference</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Sir Anthony Buzzard, 3rd Baronet</target><part>Anthony Buzzard</part></link><space/>and Charles Hunting<space/><italics>The Doctrine of the Trinity: Christianity's Self-Inflicted Wound</italics></extension><space/>and other &quot;<link><target>Biblical Unitarian</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; are typically<space/><link><target>Socinianism</target><part>Socinian</part></link><space/>in their Christology, not Arian.</listitem><listitem>There are also various<space/><link><target>Binitarian</target></link><space/>churches, believing basically that God is two persons, the Father and Son, but the Holy Spirit is not a person. They include the<space/><link><target>Church of God (Seventh Day)</target></link><space/>and various offshoots, in particular the former Radio Church of God, founded by Herbert W. Armstrong, renamed the<space/><link><target>Worldwide Church of God</target></link>, which after Armstrong's death converted to Trinity, causing many small churches to break off, most still loyal to the teachings of Armstrong, for example<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Church of God</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Living Church of God</target></link>, and many others. Other Binitarian churches include the Gospel Assemblies, a group of Pentecostal denominations that believe God adopted the name Jesus, and the<space/><link><target>Church of Jesus Christ (Bickertonite)</target></link>, an offshoot of Mormonism, which believes God is two personages, not persons. Binitarian churches generally believe that the Father is greater than the Son. So that is a view somewhat similar to Arianism.</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints</target></link><space/>also rejects Trinitarian doctrine.<space/><link><target>Joseph Smith</target></link><space/>taught that the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghost are three separate and distinct entities, three omnipotent Gods, with the Father and the Son possessing physical bodies of flesh and bone but the Holy Ghost existing only as a spirit, enabling it to dwell within us. However, Mormon doctrine differs from Arianism in a number of ways, particularly in the doctrines of<space/><link><target>eternal progression</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>exaltation (Mormonism)</target><part>exaltation</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.olivercowdery.com/smithhome/1880s-1890s/1891ERK.htm</arg><arg name="last">Tuttle</arg><arg name="first">Dainel S</arg><arg name="title">Mormons</arg><arg name="journal">A Religious Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="year">1981</arg><arg name="page">1578</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Columns-list</target><arg>2</arg><arg>
* [[Arian controversy]]
* [[First Council of Nicea]]
* [[Christology]]
* [[Germanic Christianity]]
* [[Ilm al-Kalam]]
* [[Non-Trinitarian churches]]
* [[Nontrinitarianism]]
* [[Subordinationism]]
* [[Unitarianism]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Athanasius</arg><arg name="last"><space/>of Alexandria</arg><arg name="title">History of the Arians</arg><arg name="place">London</arg><arg name="date">2013</arg><arg name="url">http://www.limovia.net</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-78336-206-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">[[Athanasius of Alexandria]]</arg><arg name="title">History of the Arians</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-47.htm Part I, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-48.htm Part II, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-49.htm Part III, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-50.htm Part IV, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-51.htm Part V, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-52.htm Part VI, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-53.htm Part VII, http://www.ccel.org/fathers2/NPNF2-04/Npnf2-04-54.htm Part VIII</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Lewis</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Ayres</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Nicaea and its Legacy: An Approach to Fourth-Century Trinitarian Theology</arg><arg name="place">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="date">2004</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="first">Mark<space/></arg><arg name="last">Belletini<space/></arg><arg name="title">Arius in the Mirror: The Alexandrian Dissent And How It Is Reflected in Modern Unitarian Universalist Practice and Discourse<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://firstuucolumbus.org/sermons/ariuspaper.htm<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Arianism. Roman Heresy and Barbarian Creed</arg><arg name="editor">Roland Steinacher Guido M. Berndt</arg><arg name="volume">vol.1</arg><arg name="place">Farnham, UK</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Ashgate</arg><arg name="date">2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Ivor J.</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Davidson</arg><arg name="title">A Public Faith</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>2</arg><arg name="journal">Baker History of the Church</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8010-1275-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="first">R. P. C.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Hanson<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">The Search for the Christian Doctrine of God: The Arian Controversy 318–381<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>T & T Clark<space/></arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-03092-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">J. N. D.</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Kelly</arg><arg name="title">Early Christian Doctrines</arg><arg name="date">1978</arg><arg name="isbn">0-06-064334-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="author">[[John Henry Newman]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newmanreader.org/works/arians/index.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Arians of the Fourth Century</arg><arg name="date">1833</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Sarah</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Parvis</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Marcellus of Ancyra And the Lost Years of the Arian Controversy 325–345</arg><arg name="place">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Documents of the Arian Controversy</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="language">German and original languages only</arg><arg name="place"><space/>Berlin and New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Walter De Gruyter</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Eliseo</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Rodriguez</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/The-Doctrine-Trinity-Dead-Fundamental/dp/1490922164</arg><arg name="title">The Doctrine of the Trinity is Dead: The Original Gospel (Lost Fundamental Doctrines)</arg><arg name="volume">vol. 1</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1490922164</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">William C.</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Rusch</arg><arg name="title">The Trinitarian Controversy</arg><arg name="publisher">Sources of Early Christian Thought</arg><arg name="date">1980</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8006-1410-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Philip Schaff|Schaff, Philip]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/s/schaff/history/3_ch09.htm</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Theological Controversies and the Development of Orthodoxy: The History of the Christian Church</arg><arg name="volume">vols. III and IX</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Rowan Williams|Williams, Rowan]]</arg><arg name="title">Arius: Heresy and Tradition</arg><arg name="edition">revised edition</arg><arg name="date">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8028-4969-5</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Brennecke</arg><arg name="first">Hanns Christof</arg><arg name="contribution">Arianism</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of Christianity</arg><arg name="editor-last">Fahlbusch</arg><arg name="editor-first">Erwin</arg><arg name="volume">1</arg><arg name="pages">121–122</arg><arg name="place">Grand Rapids</arg><arg name="publisher">Wm. B. Eerdmans</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8028-2413-7</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourthcentury.com/urkunden-chart-2007/'>Documents of the Early Arian Controversy</link><space/>Chronological survey of the sources</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourthcentury.com/index.php/urkunde-chart-opitz'>English translations of all extant letters relating to early Arianism</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourthcentury.com/notwppages/arius-supporters-map.htm'>A map of early sympathizers with Arius</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite CE1913</target><arg name="wstitle">Arianism</arg><arg name="author">[[William Francis Barry|William Barry]]<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=1757&amp;amp;letter=A'>Jewish Encyclopedia: Arianism</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://tera-3.ul.cs.cmu.edu/cgi-bin/getImage.pl?target=/data/www/NASD/4a7f1db4-5792-415c-be79-266f41eef20a/009/499/PTIFF/00000052.tif&amp;amp;rs=1'>Concordia Cyclopedia: Arianism (page 1)</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://tera-3.ul.cs.cmu.edu/cgi-bin/getImage.pl?target=/data/www/NASD/4a7f1db4-5792-415c-be79-266f41eef20a/009/499/PTIFF/00000053.tif&amp;amp;rs=1'>(page 2)</link><space/><link type='external' href='http://tera-3.ul.cs.cmu.edu/cgi-bin/getImage.pl?target=/data/www/NASD/4a7f1db4-5792-415c-be79-266f41eef20a/009/499/PTIFF/00000054.tif&amp;amp;rs=1'>(page 3)</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite AmCyc</target><arg name="wstitle">Arianism<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.third-millennium-library.com/MedievalHistory/FOURTH_CENTURY_ARIANS/ARIANS_DOOR.html'>''The Arians of the fourth century'' by John Henry &quot;Cardinal&quot; Newman in &quot;btm&quot; format</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.the-highway.com/arian_Hanko1.html'>Concise Summary of the Arian Controversy</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Arianism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Christology</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Christian controversies</target></link><link><target>Category:Heresy in Christianity</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link></paragraph></article>