<article title='Foreign_relations_of_Chad'><paragraph><template><target>update</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template><template><target>Politics of Chad</target></template>The<space/><bold>foreign relations of Chad</bold><space/>are motivated primarily by the desire for outside investment in<space/><link><target>Chad</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>industry and support for<space/><link><target>Chadian President</target></link><space/><link><target>Idriss Dby</target></link>. Chad is officially non-aligned but has close relations with<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, the former colonial power. Relations with neighbouring<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>vary periodically. Lately, the Idris Dby regime has been waging an intermittent<space/><link><target>proxy war</target></link><space/>with Sudan. Aside from those two countries, Chad generally enjoys good relations with its neighbouring states.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Relations with other African and Arab states</heading><paragraph>Although relations with Libya improved with the presidency of<space/><link><target>Idriss Dby</target></link>, strains persist. Chad has been an active champion of regional cooperation through the Central African Economic and Customs Union, the Lake Chad and Niger River Basin Commissions, and the Interstate Commission for the Fight Against the Drought in the Sahel.</paragraph><paragraph>Delimitation of international boundaries in the vicinity of<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link>, the lack of which led to border incidents in the past, has been completed and awaits ratification by<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite centuries-old cultural ties to the<space/><link><target>Arab World</target></link>, the Chadian Government maintained few significant ties to Arab states in North Africa or Southwest Asia in the 1980s. However, Chad has not recognised the State of<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link><space/>since former<space/><link><target>Chadian President</target></link><space/><link><target>Franois (Ngarta) Tombalbaye</target></link><space/>broke off relations in September 1972 as an act of solidarity with the Palestinians, and other Arabs under Israeli occupation. President Habr hoped to pursue closer relations with Arab states as a potential opportunity to break out of his Chad's post-imperial dependence on France, and to assert Chad's unwillingness to serve as an arena for superpower rivalries. In addition, as a northern Christian, Habr represented a constituency that favored co-operation and solidarity with Arabs, both African, and Asian. For these reasons, he was expected to seize opportunities during the 1990s to pursue closer ties with the Arab World. In 1988, Chad recognized the<space/><link><target>State of Palestine</target></link>, which maintains a mission in N'Djamena.</paragraph><paragraph>During the 1980s, Arab opinion on the Chadian-Libyan conflict over the Aozou Strip was divided. Several Arab states supported Libyan territorial claims to the Strip, among the most outspoken of which was Algeria, which provided training for anti-Habr forces, although most recruits for its training programs were from Nigeria or Cameroon, recruited and flown to Algeria by Libya. Lebanon's Progressive Socialist Party also sent troops to support Qadhafi's efforts against Chad in 1987. In contrast, numerous other Arab states opposed the Libyan actions, and expressed their desire to see the dispute over the Aozou Strip settled peacefully. By the end of 1987, Algiers and N'Djamena were negotiating to improve relations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Libya</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad-Libya relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Chadian-Libyan relations were ameliorated when Libyan-supported<space/><link><target>Idriss Dby</target></link><space/>unseated Habr on December 2. Gaddafi was the first head of state to recognize the new regime, and he also signed treaties of friendship and cooperation on various levels; but regarding the Aouzou Strip Dby followed his predecessor, declaring that if necessary he would fight to keep the strip out of Libya's hands.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Chad The Devil Behind the Scenes</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Time (magazine)|Time]]</arg><arg name="year"><space/></arg><arg name="date">1990-12-17</arg><arg name="url">http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,971950,00.html?iid</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>M. Azevedo, p. 150</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Aouzou dispute was concluded for good on February 3, 1994, when the judges of the ICJ by a majority of 16 to 1 decided that the Aouzou Strip belonged to Chad. The court's judgement was implemented without delay, the two parties signing as early as April 4 an agreement concerning the practical modalities for the implementation of the judgement. Monitored by international observers, the withdrawal of Libyan troops from the Strip began on April 15 and was completed by May 10. The formal and final transfer of the Strip from Libya to Chad took place on May 30, when the sides signed a joint declaration stating that the Libyan withdrawal had been effected.<extension extension_name='ref'>G. Simons, p. 78</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nigeria</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad-Nigeria relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Nigeria's 1983 economic austerity campaign produced strains with neighboring states, including Chad. Nigeria expelled several hundred thousand foreign workers, mostly from its oil industry, which faced drastic cuts as a result of declining world oil prices. At least 30,000 of those expelled were Chadians. Despite these strains, however, Nigerians had assisted in the halting process of achieving stability in Chad, and both nations reaffirmed their intention to maintain close ties.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sudan</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad-Sudan relations</arg><arg>Battle of Amdjereme</arg></template>On December 24, 2005, Chad declared itself as in a &quot;state of belligerance&quot; with neighboring Sudan. The conflict in the border region of Darfur has become an increasingly bi-national affair as increasing numbers of Sudanese flee to refugee camps in Chad, and Sudanese government troops and militias cross the borders to strike at both these camps and specific ethnic groups. Although the<space/><link><target>Government of Chad</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Government of Sudan</target></link><space/>signed the<space/><link><target>Tripoli Agreement</target></link><space/>on February 8, 2006, officially ending hostilities, fighting continues. On 11 August 2006, Chad and Sudan resumed relations at the behest of Libyan president<space/><link><target>Muammar Gaddafi</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4775111.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chad and Sudan resume relations<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 9, 2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Chad broke diplomatic relations with<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>at least twice in 2006 because it believed the<space/><link><target>Sudanese government</target></link><space/>was supporting<space/><link><target>Janjaweed</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>UFDC</target></link><space/>rebels financially and with arms. Two accords were signed, the<space/><link><target>Tripoli Accord</target></link>, which was signed on February 8 and failed to end the fighting, and the more recently signed N'Djamena Agreement. On May 11, 2008 Sudan announced it was cutting diplomatic relations with Chad, claiming that it was helping rebels in<space/><link><target>Darfur</target></link><space/>to attack the Sudanese capital<space/><link><target>Khartoum</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/7394422.stm</arg><arg name="title">BBC NEWS - Africa - Sudan cuts Chad ties over attack</arg><arg name="work">bbc.co.uk</arg></template></extension><template><target>loc</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Relations with Western countries</heading><paragraph>Chad is officially non-aligned but has close relations with<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, the former colonial power, which has about 1,200 troops stationed in the capital<space/><link><target>N'Djamena</target></link>. It receives economic aid from countries of the European Community, the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>, and various international organizations.<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>supplies aid and has an<space/><link><target>ambassador</target></link><space/>resident in<space/><link><target>N'Djamena</target></link>. Traditionally strong ties with the<space/><link><target>Western world</target><part>Western</part></link><space/>community have weakened over the past two years due to a dispute between the<space/><link><target>Government of Chad</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link><space/>over how the profits from Chad's<space/><link><target>petroleum</target></link><space/>reserves are allocated. Although oil output to the West has resumed and the dispute has officially been resolved, resentment towards what the Dby administration considered foreign meddling lingers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad-France relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>France</target></link><space/>was<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link>'s most important<space/><link><target>foreign aid</target><part>foreign donor</part></link><space/>and patron for the first three decades following<space/><link><target>Decolonization in Chad#French federation versus full independence</target><part>independence</part></link><space/>in 1960. At the end of the 1980s, economic ties were still strong, and France provided development assistance in the form of loans and grants. It was no longer Chad's leading customer for<space/><link><target>Agriculture in Chad</target><part>agricultural exports</part></link>, but it continued to provide substantial military support.</paragraph><paragraph>Chad remained a member of the<space/><link><target>African Financial Community</target></link><space/>(Communaut Financire AfricaineCFA), which linked the value of its currency, the<space/><link><target>CFA franc</target></link>, to the<space/><link><target>French franc</target></link>. French private and government investors owned a substantial portion of Chad's industrial and financial institutions, and the French treasury backed the<space/><link><target>Bank of Central African States</target></link><space/>(Banque des Etats de l'Afrique CentraleBEAC), which served as the central bank for Chad and six other member nations. Chad's dependence on France declined slightly during<space/><link><target>Habr</target></link>'s tenure as president, in part because other foreign donors and investors returned as the war subsided and also because increased rainfall since 1985 improved food production. French official attitudes toward Chad had changed from the 1970s policies under the leadership of<space/><link><target>Giscard d'Estaing</target></link><space/>to those of the<space/><link><target>Mitterrand</target></link><space/>era of the 1980s. Economic, political, and strategic goals, which had emphasized maintaining French influence in Africa, exploiting Chad's natural resources, and bolstering<space/><link><target>francophone Africa</target></link>'s status as a bulwark against the spread of<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target><part>Soviet</part></link><space/>influence, had been replaced by nominally<space/><link><target>anticolonialist</target></link><space/>attitudes. The<space/><link><target>French legislative election, 1981</target><part>election</part></link><space/>in France of the<space/><link><target>Socialist Party (France)</target><part>Socialist</part></link><space/>government in 1981 had coincided with<space/><link><target>History of Chad#The Habr.C3.A9 era .281982.E2.80.9390.29</target><part>conditions of near-anarchy in Chad</part></link>, leading France's Socialist Party to reaffirm its ideological stance against high-profile intervention in Africa. Hoping to avoid a confrontation with<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link>, another important client state in the region, President Mitterrand limited French military involvement to a defense of the region surrounding<space/><link><target>N'Djamena</target></link><space/>in 1983 and 1984. Then, gradually increasing its commitment to reinforce Habr's presidency, France once again increased its military activity in Chad.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Chad has an embassy in<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ambatchad-paris.org'>Embassy of Chad in Paris (in French)</link></extension></listitem><listitem>France has an embassy in<space/><link><target>N'djamena</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ambafrance-td.org</arg><arg name="title">Ambassade de France au Tchad</arg><arg name="work">ambafrance-td.org</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Romania</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad–Romania relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>ChadRomania relations were established on 15 July 1969. However, neither country has an embassy in the other's capital, and although an agreement on trade was signed in 1969, followed by an agreement on economic and technical cooperation in 1971,<space/><template><target>Asof</target><arg>2007</arg><arg name="lc">on</arg></template>, the volume of bilateral trade remained insignificant.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.mae.ro/index.php?unde</arg><arg name="publisher">Minister of Foreign Affairs</arg><arg name="publication-place">Romania</arg><arg name="date">May 2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-26</arg><arg name="title">Republica CIAD</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In November 2007, Romania announced that they would deploy 120 troops to Chad and the<space/><link><target>Central African Republic</target></link><space/>in connection with<space/><link><target>United Nations Mission in the Central African Republic and Chad</target><part>a European Union peacekeeping mission</part></link><space/>there.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Romanian prime minister approves mission to Chad</arg><arg name="date">2008-01-30</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-26</arg><arg name="url">http://www.eubusiness.com/news-eu/1201722422.02/</arg><arg name="agency">AFP</arg><arg name="periodical">EUBusiness.com</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></extension><space/>Romania continued to condemn violence in Chad and blamed it on rebel groups.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Romanian Foreign Ministry concerned about developments in Chad</arg><arg name="url">http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="date">2008-02-05</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-26</arg><arg name="periodical">BBC News</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension><space/>However, by mid-2008, Romanian defence minister<space/><link><target>Teodor Melecanu</target></link><space/>indicated that his country would not send further troops to the mission in Chad, stating that they had reached their limits and did not want involvement in a war theatre.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Romania not sending troops to 2009 EU Chad mission</arg><arg name="periodical">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">2008-07-01</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-03-26</arg><arg name="url">http://nl.newsbank.com/nl-search/we/Archives?p_product</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>File:Embassy of Chad (Washington, D.C.).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Embassy of Chad in Washington, D.C.</target></link></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Foreign relations of the Republic of Korea</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Establishment of diplomatic relations between<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link><space/>and Chad was on 6 August 1961.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.mofa.go.kr/ENG/countries/middleeast/countries/20070804/1_24489.jsp?menu</arg><arg name="title">Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of Korea-Middle East and Africa</arg><arg name="author">Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of Korea</arg><arg name="work">Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Republic of Korea</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Chad-United States relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The US embassy in N'Djamena, established at Chadian independence in 1960, was closed from the onset of the heavy fighting in the city in 1980 until the withdrawal of the<space/><link><target>Libya</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>forces at the end of 1981. It was reopened in January 1982. The<space/><link><target>U.S. Agency for International Development</target></link><space/>(USAID) and the<space/><link><target>U.S. Information Service</target></link><space/>(USIS) offices resumed activities in Chad in September 1983. The United States Department of State issued a travel advisory to U.S. citizens in 2009, recommending that citizens not affiliated with humanitarian efforts avoid all travel to eastern Chad and the Chad/<link><target>Central African Republic</target></link><space/>border area due to insecurity caused by banditry, recent clashes between Chadian government and rebel forces, and political tension between Chad and<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="USStateWarning"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://travel.state.gov/travel/cis_pa_tw/tw/tw_2876.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Travel Warning - Chad<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>U.S. Department of State Bureau of Consular Affairs<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 2, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>August 26, 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Chad has an embassy in<space/><link><target>Washington, DC</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.chadembassy.us</arg><arg name="title">www.chadembassy.info</arg><arg name="work">www.chadembassy.info</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>United States has an embassy in N'djamena.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ndjamena.usembassy.gov</arg><arg name="title">Home - Embassy of the United States Ndjamena, Chad</arg><arg name="work">usembassy.gov</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Relations with Asian countries</heading><paragraph>Chad and<space/><link><target>Taiwan</target></link><space/>had<space/><link><target>Foreign relations of Taiwan</target><part>relations</part></link><space/>from 1962 to 1972 and 1997 to 2006 when, for financial and security reasons, Chad announced its intention to recognize<space/><link><target>China</target></link>. Taiwan broke off relations with Chad on August 5, 2006 (hours before a scheduled official visit by Premier<space/><link><target>Su Tseng-chang</target></link>) and Chad formally recognized the PRC on August 6.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.cna.com.tw/eng/topread.php?id=200608060023</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Membership of international organizations</heading><paragraph>Chad belongs to the following international organizations:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>and some of its specialized and related agencies</listitem><listitem><link><target>Organization for African Unity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Central African Customs and Economic Union</target></link><space/>(UDEAC)</listitem><listitem><link><target>African Financial Community</target></link><space/>(Franc Zone)</listitem><listitem>Agency for the Francophone Community</listitem><listitem><link><target>African, Caribbean and Pacific Group of States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>African Development Bank</target></link></listitem><listitem>Central African States Development Bank</listitem><listitem>Economic and Monetary Union of Central African (CEMAC)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Economic Commission for Africa</target></link>;<space/><link><target>Group of 77</target><part>G-77</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Civil Aviation Organization</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Development Association</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Islamic Development Bank</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Fund for Agricultural Development</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Finance Corporation</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>International Federation of the Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies</listitem><listitem><link><target>International Labour Organization</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Intelsat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Interpol (organization)</target><part>Interpol</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Olympic Committee</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Telecommunication Union</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International Trade Union Confederation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Non-Aligned Movement</target><part>NAM</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Organisation of Islamic Cooperation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Universal Postal Union</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>World Confederation of Labour</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>World Intellectual Property Organization</target></link>;</listitem><listitem><link><target>World Meteorological Organization</target></link>;</listitem><listitem><link><target>World Tourism Organization</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>World Trade Organization</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of diplomatic missions in Chad</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of diplomatic missions of Chad</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template><template><target>loc</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Navboxes</target><arg name="title"><space/>International membership
</arg><arg name="list">
{{African Union}}
{{Community of Sahel-Saharan States}}
{{La Francophonie|state</arg></template><template><target>Chadian-Sudanese conflict</target></template><template><target>Foreign relations of Chad</target></template><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Foreign relations of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Foreign Relations Of Chad</target></template><link><target>Category:Foreign relations of Chad</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>