<article title='Ambrosiaster'><paragraph><magic_variable>NOTOC</magic_variable><bold>Ambrosiaster</bold><space/>is the name given to the writer of a commentary on St<space/><link><target>Paul of Tarsus</target><part>Paul's</part></link><space/>epistles, &quot;brief in words but weighty in matter,&quot; and valuable for the criticism of the<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>text of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>. The commentary itself was written during the papacy of<space/><link><target>Pope Damasus I</target></link>, that is, between 366 and 384, and is considered an important document of the Latin text of Paul before the<space/><link><target>Vulgate</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Jerome</target></link>, and of the interpretation of Paul prior to<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OCD"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>This commentary was erroneously attributed for a long time to St<space/><link><target>Ambrose</target></link>. In 1527, though,<space/><link><target>Erasmus</target></link><space/>threw doubt on the accuracy of ascribing the authorship of this document to Ambrose. Erasmus is generally falsely credited for having coined the name &quot;Ambrosiaster&quot; (literally in Latin: &quot;would be-Ambrose&quot;) to describe its author. The credit for this nickname should go to the Maurists, as Ren Hoven has shown. The name has remained with the unknown author.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OCD"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kinzig<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Wolfram<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Ambrosiaster<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Oxford Classical Dictionary]]<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Hornblower<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Simon<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-link">Simon Hornblower<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Spawforth<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Anthony<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-link">Anthony Spawforth<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>3rd<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Oxford University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-19-521693-8</arg></template></extension><space/>Attempts to identify this Ambrosiaster with known authors has continued, but with no success. Because<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target><part>Augustine</part></link><space/>cites Ambrosiaster's commentary on Romans 5.12 under the name of &quot;Hilary&quot;, many critics have attempted to identify Ambroasiaster with one of the many writers named &quot;Hilary&quot; active in the period. In 1899,<space/><link><target>Germain Morin</target></link><space/>suggested that the writer was Isaac,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Rev. d'hist. et de litt. religieuses</italics>, tom. iv. 97 f.</extension><space/>a converted Jew and writer of a tract on the Trinity and Incarnation, who was exiled to<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link><space/>in 378-380 and then relapsed to<space/><link><target>Judaism</target></link>; but he afterwards abandoned this theory of the authorship in favour of<space/><link><target>Decimus Hilarianus Hilarius</target></link>, proconsul of<space/><link><target>North Africa during the Classical Period</target><part>Africa</part></link><space/>in 377. Alternatively,<space/><link><target>P. A. Ballerini</target></link><space/>attempted to sustain the traditional attribution of the work to Ambrose, in his complete edition of that Father's work. This is extremely problematic, though, since it would require Ambrose to have written the book before he became a bishop, and then added to it in later years, incorporating later remarks of<space/><link><target>Hilary of Poitiers</target></link><space/>on Romans.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Alexander Souter</target></link>,<space/><italics>Study of Ambrosiaster</italics><space/>(Cambridge Univ. Press, 1905)</extension><space/>No identifications, therefore, have acquired lasting popularity with scholars, and his identity remains a mystery.</paragraph><paragraph>Several other minor works have been attributed to this same author, along with a lengthy collection of exegetical and polemical tractates, the<space/><italics>Quaestiones Veteris et Novi Testamenti,</italics><space/>which manuscripts have traditionally ascribed to<space/><link><target>Augustine of Hippo</target><part>Augustine</part></link>. In 1905, Alexander Souter established that this work should also be attributed to Ambrosiaster.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OCD"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="David G Hunter 2010 p307">David G Hunter, &quot;Fourth-century Latin writers&quot;, in Frances Young, Lewis Ayres and Andrew Louth, eds,<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of Early Christian Literature</italics>, (2010), p307</extension><space/>Fragments of several other works have been ascribed with some certainty to Ambrosiaster: a commentary on Matthew 24, a discussion of the parable of the three measures of flour into which a woman placed yeast, and a treatment of Peter's denial and the arrest of Jesus in Gethsemane. The attribution of other fragments to Ambrosiaster, though, is more tentative.<extension extension_name='ref' name="David G Hunter 2010 p307"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the elusive identity of Ambrosiaster, several facts about him can be established. Internal evidence suggests he was active at Rome during the reign of Pope Damasus (366-384), and almost certainly a member of the Roman clergy. There are strong indications he objected to Jerome's efforts to revise the Old Latin versions of the Gospels, and that he was critical of Jerome's activity among ascetic women at Rome. Ambrosiaster shows a deep interest in Judaism and often notes that Christian practices derive from Jewish tradition.<extension extension_name='ref'>David G Hunter, &quot;Fourth-century Latin writers&quot;, in Frances Young, Lewis Ayres and Andrew Louth, eds,<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of Early Christian Literature</italics>, (2010), p308</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Ambrosiaster</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><heading level='3'>Texts</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Heinrich Joseph Vogels, Vinzenz Bulhart, and Rudolf Hanslik. 1966.<space/><italics>Ambrosiastri qui dicitur Commentarius in Epistulas Paulinas.</italics><space/>Corpus scriptorum ecclesiasticorum Latinorum vol. 81, pt. 1-3. Vindobonae: Hoelder-Pichler-Tempsky.</listitem><listitem>Alexander Souter, ed., Pseudo-Augustini Quaestiones Veteris et Novi Testamenti CXXVII.<space/><link><target>CSEL</target></link><space/>50 (Vienna: F. Tempsky; Leipzig: J. Freytag, 1908).</listitem><listitem>Isaac Judaeus,<space/><italics>Isacis Judaei Quae supersunt</italics>, ed. A. Hoste, CCL 9 (Turnhout: Brepols, 1957), pp.&amp;nbsp;33148. These brief works of Isaac the Jew are highly dissimilar to the Pauline Commentaries and Quaestiones of Ambrosiaster in both style and content.</listitem><listitem>also see links below</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Studies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bussires, Marie-Pierre. Lesprit de Dieu et lEsprit Saint dans les Questions sur l'Ancien et le Nouveau Testament de l'Ambrosiaster. In: REAug 56 (2010) 2544.</listitem><listitem>Bussires, Marie-Pierre. Les quaestiones 114 et 115 de lAmbrosiaster ontelles t influences par lapologtique de Tertullian? REAug 48 (2002): 101130.</listitem><listitem>Bussires, Marie-Pierre. Linfluence du synode tenu Rome en 382 sur lexgse de lAmbrosiaster. Sacris Erudiri 45 (2006): 107124.</listitem><listitem>Bussires, Marie-Pierre. Ambrosiaster. Contre les Paens. Sur le destin. Texte, traduction et commentaire. Paris, ditions du Cerfs (Sources chrtiennes 512), 2007.<space/></listitem><listitem>Cain, Andrew, In Ambriosiasters Shadow: A Critical Reevaluation of the Last Surviving Letter Exchange between Pope Damasus and Jerome. REAug 51 (2005): 257277.</listitem><listitem>Cooper, Stephen and David G. Hunter, Ambrosiaster redactor sui: The Commentaries on the Pauline Epistles (Excluding Romans). 'RAug'56 (2010): 6991.</listitem><listitem>De Bruyn, Theodore S. Ambrosiaster's interpretations of Romans 1:26-27. VChr 65 (2011) 463483.</listitem><listitem>De Bruyn, Theodore S.Ambrosiaster's revisions of his Commentary on Romans and Roman synodal statements about the Holy Spirit. REAug 56 (2010) 4568.</listitem><listitem>Hoven, Ren, Notes sur rasme et les auteurs anciens, in Lantiquit classique 38 (1969): 172-74.<space/></listitem><listitem>Hunter, David, &quot;The Significance of Ambrosiaster,&quot; Journal of Early Christian Studies 17:1, 126 2009</listitem><listitem>Lunn-Rockliffe, Sophie, Ambrosiasters Political Theology. Oxford, 2007.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Claudio Moreschini</target><part>Moreschini, Claudio</part></link>, and Enrico Norelli. 2005 &quot;Ambrosiaster,&quot; in<space/><italics>Early Christian Greek and Latin Literature: A Literary History</italics>. Peabody, Mass: Hendrickson Publishers. vol. 2, p.&amp;nbsp;296-98.</listitem><listitem>Mundle, Wilhelm. 1919.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/MN41487ucmf_0'>''Die Exegese der paulinischen Briefe im Kommentar des Ambrosiaster.''</link></listitem><listitem>Queis, Dietrich Traugott von, and Augustine. 1972.<space/><italics>Ambrosiaster: Quaestiones Veteris et Novi Testamenti. Quaestio 115: De fato</italics>. Basel.</listitem><listitem>Souter, Alexander. 1905.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/studyofambrosias00soutuoft'>''A study of Ambrosiaster''</link>. Cambridge [Eng.]: The University Press.</listitem><listitem>Souter, Alexander. 1927.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/MN41485ucmf_1'>''The earliest Latin commentaries on the Epistles of St. Paul; a study''</link>. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/04z/z_0339-0397__Ambrosius__In_Epistolam_Beati_Pauli_Ad_Romanos__MLT.pdf.html'>The text of Ambrosiaster's ''Commentary on the Epistles of Paul,'' taken from Migne's Patrologia Latina vol 17, and attributed to Ambrose, is available here.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?vid=OCLC12663742&amp;amp;id=qP8gi6xv400C&amp;amp;pg=PP13&amp;amp;lpg=PP13&amp;amp;#PPA42,M1'>A less readable but printable PDF version of the Migne &quot;Commentaries&quot; is available from Google books.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=RyUQAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;printsec=titlepage&amp;amp;source=gbs_summary_r&amp;amp;cad=0#PPR2,M1'>A facsimile of Souter's 1908 edition of the Quaestiones is available from Google books.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/04z/z_0354-0430__Augustinus__Quaestiones_Veteris_Et_Novi_Testamenti_%5BIncertus%5D._Admonitio__MLT.pdf.html'>The text of Ambrosiaster's ''Quaestiones'', taken from Migne's Patrologia Latina vol. 35 and attributed to Augustine, is available here.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:4th-century Christian texts</target></link></paragraph></article>