<article title='DASS2'><paragraph><template><target>Unreferenced</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Digital Access Signalling System 2</bold><space/>(<bold>DASS2</bold>) is an obsolescent<space/><link><target>protocol (computing)</target><part>protocol</part></link><space/>defined by<space/><link><target>British Telecom</target></link><space/>for digital links to<space/><link><target>PSTN</target></link><space/>based on<space/><link><target>Integrated Services Digital Network</target><part>ISDN</part></link>. Although still available on request, it has been superseded by<space/><link><target>ETS 300 102</target></link><space/>(&quot;EuroISDN&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>DASS2 is an improved version over<space/><link><target>DASS1</target></link>, based on experiences with<space/><link><target>DPNSS</target></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In the UK, the ISDN concept was first introduced to customers by BT with theirDASS2 connections. DASS2 (Digital Access Signalling System) is a BT designedsignalling standard. It was introduced before the<space/><link><target>Q.931</target></link><space/>standard was finalisedby the International Community. British Telecom used the term ISDN whendescribing their DASS2 lines.</paragraph><paragraph>DASS2 lines are provided to the customer on a 2Mbit/s link and can handle 30simultaneous calls (64kbit/s each). DASS2 is still offered by BT and other UKcarriers. Q.931 is the name of the<space/><link><target>CCITT</target></link><space/>document that describes the agreedsignalling format for International ISDN. The CCITT used to be InternationalTelegraph and Telephone Consultative Committee. This is the organisation that set out the internationally agreed standards for telecommunications. This organisation hassubsequently evolved into the ITU. In the United Kingdom the Q.931 basedprotocol is ETS 300 102 (also known as EuroISDN). This is a very closeimplementation of the original CCITT specification. This is a 2Mbit/s service aswith DASS2 but the feature capability is far greater and has negated theproblems associated with DASS2 including echo problems and circuit spikes. Inthe UK both DASS 2 and EuroISDN (ETS 300 102) lines are available to customers with EuroISDN as the preferred signalling type. Customers will normally choosethe desired signalling system, as this will be dictated by their CPE (Customer Premises Equipment),usually a PABX.</paragraph><paragraph>Most modern PABXs can handle many different types of signalling system, howeverthe trend seems to be away from the DASS2 which is no longer being developed byBT and have been known to deny problems with their DASS2 circuits, and movetowards the internationally recognised Q.931 standard. The Q.931 standard is aninternational standard utilised by many countries telephony service providers.</paragraph><paragraph>The CCITT specify the standards for the layer 1, layer 2 and layer 3 signallingmessages. The layer 3 messages are the messages that actually control the callsetup, teardown, and routing.</paragraph><paragraph>The layer 3 messages or Call Control messages are the minimum messages that mustbe understood by the interfacing equipment. Individual service providers maypublish their own documentation that details further messages that will betransported in addition to Q.931 messages. There are a number of additionalEuropean documents that cover supplementary services. These cover features thatmay be instigated by exchanges via the ISDN and require a higher degree of layer 3 implementation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>DSS1</target></link><space/>(<link><target>ETSI</target></link><space/>&quot;<link><target>Europe</target><part>Euro</part></link>-ISDN&quot;, also used in many non-European countries)</listitem><listitem><link><target>DSS2</target></link><space/>(Digital Subscriber Signalling System No. 2) - enhanced DSS1.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>BT Group</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Dass2</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:BT Group</target></link><link><target>Category:Integrated Services Digital Network</target></link></paragraph></article>