<article title='Cuauht%C3%A9moc'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Infobox monarch</target><arg name="name">Cuauhtémoc 
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Bust of Cuauhtémoc (Zócalo, Mexico City).jpg
</arg><arg name="caption">Bust of Cuauhtémoc in [[Plaza de la Constitución|el Zócalo]], [[Mexico City]].
</arg><arg name="title">[[List of Tenochtitlan rulers|11th]] [[Hueyi Tlatoani|Tlatoani of Tenochtitlan]]<br/>Ruler of the [[Aztec Triple Alliance]]
</arg><arg name="reign">1520–1521
</arg><arg name="predecessor">[[Cuitlahuac]]
</arg><arg name="successor">[[Diego Velázquez Tlacotzin|Tlacotzin]]
</arg><arg name="father">[[Ahuitzotl]]
</arg><arg name="mother">Tlilancapatl
</arg><arg name="birth_date">Circa 1497
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>28 February {{death year and age|1525|1495}}
</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Cuauhtmoc</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-nah</target><arg>kʷaːʍˈtemoːk</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>IPA-es</target><arg>kwauˈtemok</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>Cuahutemoc.ogg</arg></template><space/>also known as<space/><bold>Cuauhtemotzin</bold>,<space/><bold>Guatimozin</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Guatemoc</bold>; c. 1495) was the<space/><link><target>Aztec</target><part>Mexica</part></link><space/>ruler (<italics><link><target>tlatoani</target></link></italics>) of<space/><link><target>Tenochtitlan</target></link><space/>from 1520 to 1521, making him the last Aztec Emperor. The name Cuuhtemc means &quot;one who has descended like an eagle&quot;, and is commonly rendered in English as &quot;Descending Eagle,&quot; as in the moment when an eagle folds its wings and plummets down to strike its prey. This is a name that implies aggressiveness and determination.</paragraph><paragraph>Cuauhtmoc took power in 1520 as successor of<space/><link><target>Cuitlhuac</target></link><space/>and was a cousin of the late emperor<space/><link><target>Moctezuma II</target></link>. His young wife, who was later known as<space/><link><target>Isabel Moctezuma</target></link>, was one of Moctezuma's daughters. He ascended to the throne when he was around 25 years old, while<space/><link><target>Tenochtitlan</target></link><space/>was being besieged by the<space/><link><target>Spain</target><part>Spanish</part></link><space/>and devastated by an epidemic of<space/><link><target>smallpox</target></link><space/>brought to the New World by the invaders. After the<space/><link><target>Massacre in the Great Temple</target><part>killings in the Great Temple</part></link>, there were probably few Aztec captains available to take the position.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life and rule</heading><paragraph>Cuauhtemoc's date of birth is unknown and he does not enter the historical record until he became emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones: Forging National Identity in Modern Mexico</italics>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press 2011, 11</extension><space/>He was the eldest legitimate son of emperor<space/><link><target>Ahuitzotl</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones</italics>, p. 14 and footnote 8, p. 242. Gillingham discusses the sources for this contention, including Tezozomoc, Fernando Alva Ixtlilxochitl, Juan de Torquemada, and Bernardino de Sahagn.</extension><space/>and may well have attended the last New Fire ceremony marking the beginning of a new 52-year cycle in the Aztec calendar.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miguel Len-Portilla, &quot;Cuauhtmoc&quot; in<space/><italics>The Oxford Encyclopedia of Mesoamerican Cultures</italics>, David Carrasco, ed. New York: Oxford University Press 2001, vol. 1, p. 289</extension><space/>Like the rest of Cuauhtemoc's early biography, this is inferred from knowledge of his age, and the likely events and life path of someone of his rank.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones</italics>, 14-15.</extension><space/>Following education in the<space/><link><target>calmecac</target></link>, the school for elite boys, and then military service, he was named ruler of Tlatelolco, with the title<space/><italics>cuauhtlatoani</italics><space/>(&quot;eagle ruler&quot;)<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1">Len-Portilla, &quot;Cuauhtemoc&quot; ibid.</extension><space/>in 1515.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones</italics>, p. 19</extension><space/>To have reached this position of rulership, Cuauhtemoc had to be a male of high birth, and a warrior who had captured enemies for sacrifice.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones</italics>, p. 19.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When Cuauhtemoc was elected tlatoani in 1520, Tenochtitlan had already been rocked by the invasion of the Spanish and their indigenous allies, the death of Moctezuma II, and the death of Moctezuma's brother<space/><link><target>Cuitlahuac</target></link>, who succeeded him as ruler, but died of smallpox shortly afterwards. In keeping with traditional practice, the most able candidate among the high noblemen was chosen by vote of the highest noblemen, Cuauhtemoc assumed the rulership.<extension extension_name='ref'>Len-Portilla, &quot;Cuauhtemoc&quot;, ibid.</extension><space/>Although under Cuitlahuac Tenochtitlan began mounting a defense against the invaders, it was increasingly isolated militarily and largely faced the crisis alone, as the numbers of Spanish allies increased with the desertion of many polities previously under its control.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cuauhtmoc.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>200px</part><part>Cuauhtmoc</part></link>Cuauhtmoc called for reinforcements from the countryside to aid the defense of Tenochtitln, after eighty days of warfare against the Spanish. Of all the Nahuas, only Tlatelolcas remained loyal, and the surviving Tenochcas looked for refuge in<space/><link><target>Tlatelolco (altepetl)</target><part>Tlatelolco</part></link>, where even women took part in the battle. Cuauhtmoc was captured on August 13, 1521, while fleeing<space/><link><target>Tenochtitln</target></link><space/>by crossing<space/><link><target>Lake Texcoco</target></link><space/>with his wife, family, and friends.</paragraph><paragraph>He surrendered to<space/><link><target>Hernn Corts</target></link><space/>along with the surviving<space/><italics><link><target>pipiltin</target></link></italics><space/>(nobles) and, according to Spanish sources, he asked Corts to take his knife and &quot;strike me dead immediately&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Diaz">Diaz, B., 1963, The Conquest of New Spain, London: Penguin Books, ISBN 0140441239</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>395–396,401–404</arg></template><space/>According to the same Spanish accounts, Corts refused this offer and treated his foe magnanimously. &quot;You have defended your capital like a brave warrior,&quot; he declared, &quot;A Spaniard knows how to respect valor, even in an enemy.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>William H. Prescott,<space/><italics>History of the Conquest of Mexico</italics><space/>(New York, 1843), vol. 3, p. 206.</extension><space/>At Cuauhtmoc's request, Corts also allowed the defeated Mexica to depart the city unmolested. Subsequently, however, when the booty found did not measure up to the Spaniards' expectations,<extension extension_name='ref'>Prescott, vol. 3, p. 211.</extension><space/>Cuauhtmoc was tortured in an unsuccessful attempt to discover its whereabouts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Prescott, vol. 3, pp. 234-235.</extension><space/>On the statue to Cuauhtemoc on the Paseo de la Reforma in Mexico City, there is a bas relief showing the Spaniards' torture of the emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/pictures/resource/det.4a26888/'>Bas-relief on statue to Gautamozin</link></extension><space/>Eventually some gold was recovered, though far less than Corts and his men expected.</paragraph><paragraph>Cuauhtmoc continued to hold his position under the Spanish, keeping the title of tlatoani, but he was no longer the sovereign ruler.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension><space/>He ordered the construction of a renaissance-style two-storied stone palace in Tlatelolco, in which he settled after the destruction of Mexico City; the building survived and was known as the Tecpan or palace.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Execution</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CuauhtemocLastMsgDF.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Mosaic of what is considered to be Cuauhtemoc's last address as tlatoani in Nahuatl and Spanish</part></link>In 1525, Corts took Cuauhtmoc and several other indigenous nobles on his expedition to<space/><link><target>Honduras</target></link>, fearing that Cuauhtmoc could have led an insurrection in his absence.<extension extension_name='ref' name="otbjad">Restall (2004, p.148).</extension><space/>While the expedition was stopped in the<space/><link><target>Chontal Maya people</target><part>Chontal Maya</part></link><space/>capital of Itzamkanac, known as<space/><link><target>Acalan</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Nahuatl</target></link>, Corts had Cuauhtmoc<space/><link><target>execution</target><part>executed</part></link><space/>for allegedly conspiring to kill him and the other Spaniards.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:MonumentCuauhtemocPaseo2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Monument to Cuauhtmoc</target></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Paseo de la Reforma</target><part>Avenida Reforma</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Mexico City</target></link>. The inscription at the bottom of the statue translates as &quot;In memory of Cuauhtmoc (spelled Quautemoc) and his warriors who battled heroically in defense of their country.&quot;</part></link>There are a number of discrepancies in the various accounts of the event. According to Corts himself, on 27 February 1525 it was revealed to him by a citizen of<space/><link><target>Tenochtitlan</target></link><space/>named Mexicalcingo that Cuauhtmoc,<space/><link><target>Coanacoch</target></link><space/>(the ruler of<space/><link><target>Texcoco (altepetl)</target><part>Texcoco</part></link>) and<space/><link><target>Tetlepanquetzal</target></link><space/>(the ruler of<space/><link><target>Tlacopan</target></link>) were plotting his death. Corts interrogated them until each confessed, and then had Cuauhtmoc, Tetlepanquetzal, and another lord named Tlacatlec hanged. Corts wrote that the other lords would be too frightened to plot against him again, as they believed he had uncovered the plan through magic powers. Corts's account is supported by the historian<space/><link><target>Francisco Lpez de Gmara</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Restall (2004, pp.149150).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Bernal Daz del Castillo</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>conquistador</target></link><space/>serving under Corts who recorded his experiences in his book<space/><italics><link><target>The True History of the Conquest of New Spain</target></link></italics>, the supposed plot was revealed by two men, named Tapia and Juan Velsquez. Daz portrays the executions as unjust and based on no evidence, and admits to having liked Cuauhtmoc personally. He also records Cuauhtmoc giving the following speech to Corts, through his<space/><link><target>interpreting</target><part>interpreter</part></link><space/><link><target>Malinche</target></link>:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Oh Malinzin [i.e., Cortés]! Now I understand your false promises and the kind of death you have had in store for me. For you are killing me unjustly. May God demand justice from you, as it was taken from me when I entrusted myself to you in my city of Mexico!</arg></template>Daz wrote that afterwards, Corts suffered from<space/><link><target>insomnia</target></link><space/>due to<space/><link><target>guilt (emotion)</target><part>guilt</part></link>, and badly injured himself while wandering at night.<extension extension_name='ref'>Restall (2004, pp.150,152).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Fernando de Alva Corts Ixtlilxchitl</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Mestizo</target></link><space/>historian and descendant of Coanacoch, wrote an account of the executions in the 17th century partly based on Texcocan<space/><link><target>oral tradition</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="otbjad"></extension><space/>According to Ixtlilxchitl the three lords were joking cheerfully with each other, due to a rumor that Corts had decided to return the expedition to Mexico, when Corts asked a spy to tell him what they were talking about. The spy reported honestly, but Corts invented the plot himself. Cuauhtmoc, Coanacoch and Tetlepanquetzal were all hanged, as well as eight others. However, Corts cut down Coanacoch, the last to be hanged, after his brother began rallying his warriors. Coanacoch did not have long to enjoy his reprieveIxtlilxchitl wrote that he died a few days later.<extension extension_name='ref'>Restall (2004, p.152).</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Monumento de Cuauhtemoc.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Monument to Cuauhtmoc in<space/><link><target>Veracruz, Veracruz</target><part>Veracruz, Mexico</part></link></part></link><link><target>Tlacotzin</target></link>, Cuauhtmoc's<space/><italics><link><target>cihuacoatl (position)</target><part>cihuacoatl</part></link></italics>, was appointed his successor as<space/><italics>tlatoani</italics>. He died the next year before returning to Tenochtitlan.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cuauhtemoc's bones</heading><paragraph><template><target>Aztecbox</target></template><link><target>File:El suplicio de Cuauhtmoc.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>left</part><part>&quot;The Martyrdom to Cuauhtmoc&quot;, a 19th-century painting by<space/><link><target>Leandro Izaguirre</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The modern-day town of<space/><link><target>Ixcateopan</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Mexican state</target><part>state</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Guerrero</target></link><space/>is home to an<space/><link><target>ossuary</target></link><space/>purportedly containing Cuauhtmoc's remains. Archeologist<space/><link><target>Eulalia Guzmn</target></link>, a &quot;passionate indigenista&quot;, excavated the bones in 1949, which were discovered shortly after bones found in Mexico City of Corts had been authenticated by the Instituto Nacional de Antropologa e Historia (INAH). Initially Mexican scholars congratulated Guzmn, but after a similar examination by scholars at INAH, their authenticity as Cuauhtemoc's was rejected - the bones in the ossuary belonged to several different persons, several of them seemingly women. This finding caused a public uproar. A panel assembled by Guzmn gave support to the initial contention. The Secretariat of Public Education (SEP) had another panel examine the bones, which gave support to INAH's original finding, but did not report on the finding publicly.<extension extension_name='ref'>Benjamin Keen,<space/><italics>The Aztec Image in Western Thought</italics>, New Brunswick: Rutgers University Press 1971, pp 468-69.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wigberto Jimnez Moreno, &quot;Los hallazgos de Ixcateopan,&quot;<space/><italics>Historia Mexicana</italics><space/>XII (1962-63), 161-181</extension><space/>A scholarly study of the controversy was published in 2011 arguing that the available data suggests that the grave is an elaborate hoax prepared by a local of Ichcateopan as a way of generating publicity, and subsequently supported by Mexican nationalists such as Guzman who wished to use the find for political purposes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Gillingham,<space/><italics>Cuauhtemoc's Bones: Forging National Identity in Modern Mexico</italics>. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico Press 2011.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Monumento a Cuauhtmoc.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Monument to Cuauhtmoc at ''Praa Cuauhtmoc'' (Cuauhtmoc Square),<space/><link><target>Rio de Janeiro</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Brazil</target></link>. Dedicated in 1922, the monument was a gift from the Mexican government to Brazil in celebration of the 100th anniversary of the<space/><link><target>Brazilian independence</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.educacaopublica.rj.gov.br/biblioteca/historia/0092.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">''Xochipilli e Cuauhtémoc - o México no Rio de Janeiro''<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">www.educacaopublica.rj.gov.br<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 1, 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 21, 2015</arg><arg name="language">Portuguese</arg><arg name="author">Cláudia Sampaio</arg></template></extension></part></link>Cuauhtemoc is the embodiment of indigenist nationalism in Mexico, being the only Aztec emperor who survived the conquest by the<space/><link><target>Spanish Empire</target></link><space/>(and their native allies). He is honored by<space/><link><target>Monument to Cuauhtmoc</target><part>a monument on the Paseo de la Reforma</part></link>, his face has appeared on Mexican banknotes, and he is celebrated in paintings, music, and popular culture.</paragraph><paragraph>Many places in Mexico are named in honour of Cuauhtmoc. These include<space/><link><target>Cuauhtmoc, Chihuahua</target><part>Ciudad Cuauhtmoc</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Chihuahua (state)</target><part>Chihuahua</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Cuauhtmoc, D.F.</target><part>Cuauhtmoc</part></link><space/>borough of the<space/><link><target>Mexican Federal District</target></link>, as well as Ciudad Cuauhtmoc, in the state of Veracruz.</paragraph><paragraph>There is a<space/><link><target>Metro Cuauhtmoc</target><part>Cuauhtmoc station</part></link><space/>on Line 1 of the<space/><link><target>Mexico City metro</target></link><space/>as well as one for Moctezuma, but none for Hernn Corts. There is also a metro stop named for him Monterrey<space/><link><target>Metrorrey</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Cuauhtmoc is also one of the few non-Spanish<space/><link><target>given name</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for Mexican boys that is perennially popular.<link><target>Cuauhtmoc Crdenas</target></link><space/>Solrzano, a prominent Mexican politician, is named after him. In the Aztec campaign of the<space/><link><target>Personal computer game</target><part>PC game</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Age of Empires II: The Conquerors</target></link></italics>, the player plays as Cuauhtmoc, despite the name<space/><italics><link><target>Moctezuma II</target><part>Montezuma</part></link></italics><space/>for the campaign itself, and Cuauhtmoc narrates the openings and closings to each scenario. In the next installment to the series,<space/><italics><link><target>Age of Empires 3: The War Chiefs</target></link></italics>, Cuauhtmoc was the leader of Aztecs. The<space/><link><target>Mexico</target><part>Mexican</part></link><space/>football player<space/><link><target>Cuauhtmoc Blanco</target></link><space/>was also named after him.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1996<space/><link><target>Rage Against The Machine</target></link><space/>single<space/><italics><link><target>People of the Sun</target></link></italics>, lyricist<space/><link><target>Zack De La Rocha</target></link><space/>rhymes &quot;When the fifth sun sets get back reclaimed, The spirit of Cuauhtmoc alive and untamed&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Cuauhtmoc, in the name Guatemoc, is portrayed sympathetically in the adventure novel<space/><italics><link><target>Montezuma's Daughter</target></link></italics>, by<space/><link><target>Henry Rider Haggard</target><part>H. Rider Haggard</part></link>. First appearing in Chapter XIV, he becomes friends with the protagonist after they save each other's lives. His coronation, torture, and death are described in the novel.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target><arg name="indent">yes</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Andrews, J. Richard<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introduction to Classical Nahuatl<space/></arg><arg name="edition">revised<space/></arg><arg name="location">Norman<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[University of Oklahoma Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-8061-3452-6<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">50090230</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Restall, Matthew<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Matthew Restall<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[Seven Myths of the Spanish Conquest]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Oxford and New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="edition">1st pbk</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-517611-1<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">56695639</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Paul</arg><arg name="last">Gillingham</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="title">Cuauhtémoc's Bones: Forging National Identity in Modern Mexico</arg><arg name="publisher">University of New Mexico Press</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Cuauhtémoc (emperor)</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite Appletons'</target><arg name="wstitle">Cuauhtemotzín</arg><arg name="year">1900<space/></arg><arg name="short">x<space/></arg><arg name="notaref">x</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Cuitláhuac]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Tlatoani of Tenochtitlan]]</arg><arg name="years">1520–1521</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Diego Velázquez Tlacotzin]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Cuauhtemoc
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Tlatoani of Tenochtitlan
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>unknown
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>unknown
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>28 February 1525
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cuauhtemoc</target></template><link><target>Category:Tenochca tlatoque</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century rulers</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century monarchs in North America</target></link><link><target>Category:16th-century indigenous people of the Americas</target></link><link><target>Category:1500s births</target></link><link><target>Category:1525 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Mexican torture victims</target></link><link><target>Category:Executed reigning monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Mexican people executed by hanging</target></link><link><target>Category:People executed by New Spain</target></link><link><target>Category:People executed by Spain by hanging</target></link></paragraph></article>