<article title='Baseball_statistics'><paragraph><bold>Statistics</bold><space/>play an important role in summarizing<space/><link><target>baseball</target></link><space/>performance and evaluating players in the sport.</paragraph><paragraph>Since the flow of a baseball game has natural breaks to it, and normally players act individually rather than performing in clusters, the sport lends itself to easy record-keeping and<space/><link><target>statistics</target></link>. Statistics have been kept for<space/><link><target>professional baseball</target></link><space/>since the creation of the<space/><link><target>National League</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>American League</target></link>, now part of<space/><link><target>Major League Baseball</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Many statistics are also available from outside of Major League Baseball, from<space/><link><target>sports league</target><part>leagues</part></link><space/>such as the<space/><link><target>National Association of Professional Base Ball Players</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Negro League</target><trail>s</trail></link>, although the consistency of whether these records were kept, of the standards with respect to which they were calculated, and of their accuracy varied from league to league.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Development of statistics</heading><paragraph>The practice of keeping<space/><link><target>document</target><part>records</part></link><space/>of player achievements was started in the 19th century by<space/><link><target>Henry Chadwick (writer)</target><part>Henry Chadwick</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Palmer</arg><arg name="first">Pete</arg><arg name="authorlink">Pete Palmer</arg><arg name="author2">[[Paul Adomites]]<space/></arg><arg name="author3">David Nemec<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Matthew D. Greenberger<space/></arg><arg name="author5">Dan Schlossberg<space/></arg><arg name="author6">Dick Johnson<space/></arg><arg name="author7">Mike Tully<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cooperstown: Hall of Fame Players</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Publications International</arg><arg name="location">Lincolnwood, Illinois</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7853-4530-2</arg><arg name="page">21</arg><arg name="chapter">Birth of the Game</arg></template></extension><space/>Based on his experience with the sport of<space/><link><target>cricket</target></link>, Chadwick devised the predecessors to modern day<space/><link><target>statistics</target></link><space/>including<space/><link><target>Batting average#Baseball</target><part>batting average</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Run (baseball)</target><part>runs</part></link><space/>scored, and<space/><link><target>Earned run</target><part>runs allowed</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Traditionally, statistics such as batting average (the number of hits divided by the number of at bats) and earned run average (the average number of earned runs allowed by a pitcher per nine innings) have dominated attention in the statistical world of baseball. However, the recent advent of<space/><link><target>sabermetrics</target></link><space/>has created statistics drawing from a greater breadth of player performance measures and playing field variables. Sabermetrics and comparative statistics attempt to provide an improved measure of a player's performance and contributions to his team from year to year, frequently against a statistical performance average.</paragraph><paragraph>Comprehensive, historical baseball statistics were difficult for the average fan to access until 1951, when researcher<space/><link><target>Hy Turkin</target></link><space/>published<space/><italics>The Complete Encyclopedia of Baseball</italics>. In 1969,<space/><link><target>Macmillan Publishing</target></link><space/>printed its first<space/><italics><link><target>Baseball Encyclopedia</target></link></italics>, using a<space/><link><target>computer</target></link><space/>to compile statistics for the first time. Known as &quot;Big Mac&quot;, the encyclopedia became the standard baseball reference until 1988, when<space/><italics><link><target>Total Baseball</target></link></italics><space/>was released by Warner Books using more sophisticated technology. The publication of<space/><italics>Total Baseball</italics><space/>led to the discovery of several &quot;phantom ballplayers&quot;, such as<space/><link><target>Lou Proctor</target></link>, who did not belong in official record books and were removed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ESPN"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="editor">[[Pete Palmer]] and Gary Gillette</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">The 2005 ESPN Baseball Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="title">Introduction</arg><arg name="edition">1st</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Sterling</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">1-4027-2568-X</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Use of statistics</heading><paragraph>Throughout modern baseball, a few core statistics have been traditionally referenced<space/><link><target>Batting average#Baseball</target><part>batting average</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Runs batted in</target><part>RBI</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>home run</target><trail>s</trail></link>. To this day, a player who leads the league in all of these three statistics earns the &quot;<link><target>Triple crown (baseball)</target><part>Triple Crown</part></link>.&quot; For pitchers,<space/><link><target>Win (baseball)</target><part>wins</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Earned run average</target><part>ERA</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>strikeouts</target></link><space/>are the most often-cited statistics, and a pitcher leading his league in these statistics may also be referred to as a &quot;Triple Crown&quot; winner. General managers and<space/><link><target>scout (sport)</target><part>baseball scouts</part></link><space/>have long used the major statistics, among other factors and opinions, to understand player value. Managers, catchers and pitchers use the statistics of batters of opposing teams to develop pitching strategies and set<space/><link><target>baseball positioning</target><part>defensive positioning</part></link><space/>on the field. Managers and batters study opposing pitcher performance and motions in attempting to improve hitting.</paragraph><paragraph>Some<space/><link><target>sabermetric</target></link><space/>statistics have entered the mainstream baseball world that measure a batter's overall performance including<space/><link><target>on-base plus slugging</target></link>, commonly referred to as OPS. OPS adds the hitter's<space/><link><target>on-base percentage</target></link><space/>(number of times reached base by any means divided by total plate appearances) to his<space/><link><target>slugging percentage</target></link><space/>(<link><target>total bases</target></link><space/>divided by at-bats). Some argue that the OPS formula is flawed and that more weight should be shifted towards OBP (on-base percentage).<extension extension_name='ref' name="ESPN"></extension><space/>The statistic<space/><link><target>wOBA</target></link><space/>(weighted on-base average) attempts to correct for this.</paragraph><paragraph>OPS is also useful when determining a pitcher's level of success. &quot;Opponent On-base Plus Slugging&quot; (OOPS) is becoming a popular tool to evaluate a pitcher's actual performance. When analyzing a pitcher's statistics, some useful categories to consider include<space/><link><target>K/9IP</target></link><space/>(strikeouts per nine innings),<space/><link><target>Strikeout-to-walk ratio</target><part>K/BB</part></link><space/>(strikeouts per walk),<space/><link><target>Home runs per nine innings</target><part>HR/9</part></link><space/>(Home runs per nine innings),<space/><link><target>Walks plus hits per inning pitched</target><part>WHIP</part></link><space/>(walks plus hits per inning pitched) and OOPS (opponent on-base plus slugging).</paragraph><paragraph>However, since 2001, more emphasis has been placed on<space/><link><target>Defense independent pitching statistics</target><part>Defense-Independent Pitching Statistics</part></link>, including Defense-Independent ERA (dERA), in an attempt to evaluate a pitcher's performance regardless of the strength of the defensive players behind him.</paragraph><paragraph>All of the above statistics may be used in certain game situations. For example, a certain hitter's ability to hit left-handed pitchers might incline a manager to increase his opportunities to face left-handed pitchers. Other hitters may have a history of success against a given pitcher (or vice versa), and the manager may use this information to create a favorablematch-up. Broadcast commentators often refer to this as &quot;playing the percentages&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Commonly used statistics</heading><paragraph>Most of these terms also apply to<space/><link><target>softball</target></link>. Commonly used statistics with their<space/><link><target>abbreviation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are explained here. The explanations below are for quick reference and do not fully or completely define the statistic; for the strict definition, see the linked article for each statistic.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Batting statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1B<space/><link><target>Single (baseball)</target><part>Single</part></link>: hits on which the batter reaches first base safely without the contribution of a<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>fielding error</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>2B<space/><link><target>Double (baseball)</target><part>Double</part></link>: hits on which the batter reaches second base safely without the contribution of a<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>fielding error</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>3B<space/><link><target>Triple (baseball)</target><part>Triple</part></link>: hits on which the batter reaches third base safely without the contribution of a<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>fielding error</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>AB<space/><link><target>At bat</target></link>: Plate appearances, not including bases on balls, being hit by pitch, sacrifices, interference, or obstruction.</listitem><listitem>AB/HR<space/><link><target>At bats per home run</target></link>: at bats divided by home runs.</listitem><listitem>BA<space/><link><target>Batting average</target></link><space/>(also abbreviated<space/><italics>AVG</italics>): hits divided by at bats (H/AB)</listitem><listitem>BB<space/><link><target>Base on balls</target></link><space/>(also called a &quot;walk&quot;): hitter not swinging at four pitches called out of the strike zone and awarded first base.</listitem><listitem>BABIP<space/><link><target>Batting average on balls in play</target></link>: frequency at which a batter reaches a base after putting the ball in the field of play. Also a pitching category.</listitem><listitem>BB/K<space/><link><target>Walk-to-strikeout ratio</target></link>: number of bases on balls divided by number of strikeouts</listitem><listitem>BsR<space/><link><target>Base Runs</target></link>: Another run estimator, like Runs Created; a favorite of writer<space/><link><target>Tom Tango</target></link></listitem><listitem>EQA<space/><link><target>Equivalent average</target></link>: a player's batting average absent park and league factors</listitem><listitem>FC<space/><link><target>Fielder's choice</target></link>: times reaching base safely because a fielder chose to try for an out on another runner</listitem><listitem>GO/AO<space/><link><target>Ground ball fly ball ratio</target></link>: number of ground ball outs divided by number of fly ball outs</listitem><listitem>GDP or GIDP<space/><link><target>Double play</target><part>Ground into double play</part></link>: number of ground balls hit that became double plays</listitem><listitem>GPA<space/><link><target>Gross Production Average</target></link>: 1.8 times on-base percentage plus slugging percentage, divided by four</listitem><listitem>GS<space/><link><target>grand slam (baseball)</target><part>Grand Slam</part></link>: a<space/><link><target>home run</target></link><space/>with the bases loaded, resulting in four runs scoring, and four<space/><link><target>Run batted in</target><part>RBI</part></link><space/>credited to the batter.</listitem><listitem>H<space/><link><target>Hit (baseball)</target><part>Hit</part><trail>s</trail></link>: times reached base because of a batted, fair ball without error by the defense</listitem><listitem>HBP<space/><link><target>Hit by pitch</target></link>: times touched by a pitch and awarded first base as a result</listitem><listitem>HR<space/><link><target>Home run</target><trail>s</trail></link>: hits on which the batter successfully touched all four bases, without the contribution of a<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>fielding error</part></link>.</listitem><listitem>ITPHR<space/><link><target>Inside-the-park home run</target></link>:hits on which the batter successfully touched all four bases, without the contribution of a<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>fielding error</part></link><space/>or the ball going outside the ball park.</listitem><listitem>IBB<space/><link><target>Intentional base on balls</target></link>: times awarded first base on balls (see BB above) deliberately thrown by the pitcher. Also known as IW (intentional walk).</listitem><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>ISO</arg></template>ISO Isolated power: a hitter's ability to hit for extra bases, calculated by subtracting batting average from slugging percentage</listitem><listitem>K<space/><link><target>Strike out</target></link><space/>(also abbreviated<space/><italics>SO</italics>): number of times that a third strike is taken or swung at and missed, or bunted foul. Catcher must catch the third strike or batter may attempt to run to first base.</listitem><listitem>LOB<space/><link><target>Left on base</target></link>: number of runners neither out nor scored at the end of an inning.</listitem><listitem>OBP<space/><link><target>On-base percentage</target></link>: times reached base (H + BB + HBP) divided by at bats plus walks plus hit by pitch plus sacrifice flies (AB + BB + HBP + SF).</listitem><listitem>OPS<space/><link><target>On-base plus slugging</target></link>: on-base percentage plus slugging average</listitem><listitem>PA<space/><link><target>Plate appearance</target></link>: number of completed batting appearances</listitem><listitem>PA/SO<space/><link><target>Plate appearances per strikeout</target></link>: number of times a batter strikes out to their plate appearance</listitem><listitem>R<space/><link><target>Run (baseball)</target><part>Runs scored</part></link>: number of times a player crosses home plate</listitem><listitem>RC<space/><link><target>Runs created</target></link>: statistic that attempts to measure how many runs a player has contributed to his team</listitem><listitem>RP<space/><link><target>Runs produced</target></link>: statistic that attempts to measure how many runs a player has contributed</listitem><listitem>RBI<space/><link><target>Run batted in</target></link>: number of runners who score due to a batters' action, except when batter grounded into double play or reached on an error</listitem><listitem>RISP<space/><link><target>Runner In Scoring Position</target></link>: a breakdown of the batter's batting average with runners in<space/><link><target>scoring position</target></link>, which include runners at second and third bases.</listitem><listitem>SF<space/><link><target>Sacrifice fly</target></link>: Fly balls hit to the outfield which although caught for an out, allow a baserunner to advance</listitem><listitem>SH<space/><link><target>Sacrifice hit</target></link>: number of sacrifice bunts which allow runners to advance on the basepaths</listitem><listitem>SLG<space/><link><target>Slugging average</target></link>: total bases achieved on hits divided by at-bats (TB/AB)</listitem><listitem>TA<space/><link><target>Total average</target></link>: total bases, plus walks, plus hit by pitch, plus steals, minus caught stealing divided by at bats, minus hits, plus caught stealing, plus grounded into double plays [(TB + BB + HBP + SB - CS)/(AB - H + CS + GIDP)]</listitem><listitem>TB<space/><link><target>Total bases</target></link>: one for each single, two for each double, three for each triple, and four for each home run [H + 2B + (2 * 3B) + (3 * HR)] or [1B + (2 * 2B) + (3 * 3B) + (4 * HR)]</listitem><listitem>TOB<space/><link><target>Times on base</target></link>: times reaching base as a result of hits, walks, and hit-by-pitches (H + BB + HBP)</listitem><listitem>XBH<space/><link><target>Extra base hit</target><trail>s</trail></link>: total hits greater than singles (2B + 3B + HR)</listitem><listitem>XR<space/><link><target>Extrapolated Runs</target></link>: A linear run estimator developed by<space/><link><target>Jim Furtado</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Baserunning statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>SB<space/><link><target>Stolen base</target></link>: number of bases advanced by the runner while the ball is in the possession of the defense.<list type='bullet'><listitem>CS<space/><link><target>Caught stealing</target></link>: times tagged out while attempting to steal a base</listitem><listitem>SBA/ATT Stolen base attempts: total number of times the player has attempted to steal a base (SB+CS)</listitem><listitem>SB%<space/><link><target>Stolen base percentage</target></link>: the percentage of bases stolen successfully. (SB) divided by (SBA)(stolen bases attempted).</listitem><listitem>DI<space/><link><target>Defensive Indifference</target></link>: if the catcher does not attempt to throw out a runner (usually because the base would be insignificant), the runner is not awarded a steal. Scored as a fielder's choice.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>R<space/><link><target>Run (baseball)</target><part>Run</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>scored: times reached home plate legally and safely</listitem><listitem><template><target>anchor</target><arg>UBR</arg></template>UBR Ultimate base running: a metric that assigns linear weights to every individual baserunning event in order to measure the impact of a player's baserunning skill</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Pitching statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>BB<space/><link><target>Base on balls</target></link><space/>(also called a &quot;walk&quot;): times pitching four balls, allowing the batter to take first base</listitem><listitem>BB/9<space/><link><target>Base on balls</target></link><space/>divided by 9 (<link><target>Bases on balls per 9 innings pitched</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>BF<space/><link><target>Total batters faced</target></link>: opponent team's total plate appearances</listitem><listitem>BK<space/><link><target>Balk</target></link>: number of times pitcher commits an illegal pitching action while in contact with the pitching rubber as judged by umpire, resulting in baserunners advancing one base</listitem><listitem>BS<space/><link><target>Blown save</target></link>: number of times entering the game in a<space/><link><target>save (baseball statistics)</target><part>save</part></link><space/>situation, and being charged the run (earned or not) which eliminates his team's lead</listitem><listitem>CERA<space/><link><target>Component ERA</target></link>: an estimate of a pitcher's ERA based upon the individual components of his statistical line (K, H, 2B, 3B, HR, BB, HBP)</listitem><listitem>CG<space/><link><target>Complete game</target></link>: number of games where player was the only pitcher for his team</listitem><listitem>DICE<space/><link><target>Defense-Independent Component ERA</target></link>: an estimate of a pitcher's ERA based upon the defense-independent components of his statistical line (K, HR, BB, HBP) but which also uses number of outs (IP), which is not defense independent.</listitem><listitem>ER<space/><link><target>Earned run</target></link>: number of runs that did not occur as a result of errors or passed balls</listitem><listitem>ERA<space/><link><target>Earned run average</target></link>: total number of earned runs (see &quot;ER&quot; above), multiplied by 9, divided by innings pitched</listitem><listitem>ERA+<space/><link><target>Adjusted ERA+</target></link>: earned run average adjusted for the<space/><link><target>baseball park</target><part>ballpark</part></link><space/>and the league average</listitem><listitem>FIP<space/><link><target>Fielding independent pitching</target></link>: a metric, scaled to resemble an ERA, that focuses on events within the pitcher's control home runs, walks, and strikeouts but also uses in its denominator the number of outs the team gets (see IP), which is not entirely within the pitcher's control.<list type='bullet'><listitem>xFIP: This variant substitutes a pitcher's own home run percentage with the league average</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>FPOM<space/><link><target>First Pitch Outs Made</target></link>: Number of outs earned where the batter ground or flies out on the first pitch.</listitem><listitem>G<space/><link><target>Games pitched</target><part>Games</part></link><space/>(AKA &quot;appearances&quot;): number of times a pitcher pitches in a season</listitem><listitem>GF<space/><link><target>Games finished</target></link>: number of games pitched where player was the final pitcher for his team as a relief pitcher</listitem><listitem>GIDP<space/><link><target>Double Play</target><part>Double Plays Induced</part></link>: number of double play groundouts induced</listitem><listitem>G/F<space/><link><target>Ground ball fly ball ratio</target></link>: ground balls allowed divided by fly balls allowed</listitem><listitem>GS<space/><link><target>Games started</target><part>Starts</part></link>: number of games pitched where player was the first pitcher for his team</listitem><listitem>H<space/><link><target>Hits allowed</target></link>: total hits allowed</listitem><listitem>H/9<space/><link><target>Hits per nine innings</target></link>: hits allowed times nine divided by innings pitched (also known as<space/><link><target>H/9IP</target></link><space/><link><target>Hits allowed per 9 innings pitched</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>HB<space/><link><target>Hit by pitch</target><part>Hit batsman</part></link>: times hit a batter with pitch, allowing runner to advance to first base</listitem><listitem>HLD (or H)<space/><link><target>Hold (baseball statistics)</target><part>Hold</part></link>: number of games entered in a save situation, recorded at least one out, did not surrender the lead, and did not complete the game</listitem><listitem>HRA<space/><link><target>Home runs allowed</target></link>: total home runs allowed</listitem><listitem>IBB<space/><link><target>Intentional base on balls</target></link><space/>allowed</listitem><listitem>IP<space/><link><target>Innings pitched</target></link>: the number of outs a team gets while a pitcher is pitching divided by 3</listitem><listitem>IP/GS Average number of innings pitched per game started</listitem><listitem>IR<space/><link><target>Inherited runners</target></link>: number of runners on base when the pitcher enters the game</listitem><listitem>IRA<space/><link><target>Inherited runs allowed</target></link>: number of inherited runners allowed to score</listitem><listitem>K<space/><link><target>Strikeout</target></link>: number of batters who received strike three</listitem><listitem>K/9<space/><link><target>Strikeouts per nine innings</target></link>: strikeouts times nine divided by innings pitched (<link><target>Strikeouts per 9 innings pitched</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>K/BB<space/><link><target>Strikeout-to-walk ratio</target></link>: number of strikeouts divided by number of base on balls</listitem><listitem>L<space/><link><target>Loss (baseball)</target><part>Loss</part></link>: number of games where pitcher was pitching while the opposing team took the lead, never lost the lead, and went on to win</listitem><listitem><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>LOB%</arg></template>LOB% Left-on-base percentage: LOB% represents the percentage of baserunners a pitcher does not allow to score. LOB% tends to regress toward 7072% over time, so unusually high or low percentages could indicate that pitcher's ERA could be expected to rise or lower in the future. An occasional exception to this logic is a pitcher with a very high strikeout rate.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fangraphs.com/library/index.php/pitching/lob/</arg><arg name="title">LOB% : FanGraphs Sabermetrics Library</arg><arg name="last">Slowinski</arg><arg name="first">Steve</arg><arg name="date">February 17, 2010</arg><arg name="work">[[Fangraphs]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 June 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>OBA<space/><link><target>Opponents batting average</target></link>: hits allowed divided by at-bats faced</listitem><listitem>PC-ST - An individual pitcher's total game pitches [Pitch Count] and [ST] his no. of strikes thrown within that PC.</listitem><listitem>PIT Pitches thrown (<link><target>Pitch count</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>PFR<space/><link><target>Power finesse ratio</target></link>: The sum of strikeouts and walks divided by innings pitched.</listitem><listitem>pNERD Pitcher's<space/><link><target>NERD (sabermetrics)</target><part>NERD</part></link>: expected aesthetic pleasure of watching an individual pitcher</listitem><listitem>QS<space/><link><target>Quality start</target></link>: a game in which a starting pitcher completes at least six innings and permits no more than three earned runs</listitem><listitem>RA<space/><link><target>Run average</target></link>: number of runs allowed times nine divided by innings pitched</listitem><listitem>RRA<space/><link><target>Relief Run Average</target></link>: A function of how many inherited base runners a relief pitcher allowed to score.</listitem><listitem>SHO<space/><link><target>Shutout (baseball)</target><part>Shutout</part></link>: number of complete games pitched with no runs allowed</listitem><listitem>SO<space/><link><target>Strikeout</target></link><space/>Also may be notated as &quot;K&quot;.</listitem><listitem>SV<space/><link><target>Save (sport)</target><part>Save</part></link>: number of games where the pitcher enters a game led by the pitcher's team, finishes the game without surrendering the lead, is not the winning pitcher, and either (a) the lead was three runs or fewer when the pitcher entered the game; (b) the potential tying run was on base, at bat, or on deck; or (c) the pitcher pitched three or more innings</listitem><listitem>SVO<space/><link><target>Save opportunity</target></link>: When a pitcher 1) enters the game with a lead of three or fewer runs and pitches at least one inning, 2) enters the game with the potential tying run on base, at bat, or on deck, or 3) pitches three or more innings with a lead and is credited with a save by the official scorer</listitem><listitem>W<space/><link><target>Win (baseball)</target><part>Win</part></link>: number of games where pitcher was pitching while his team took the lead and went on to win, also the starter needs to pitch at least 5 innings of work (also related:<space/><link><target>winning percentage</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>W + S - Wins in relief + saves.</listitem><listitem><template><target>anchor</target><arg>whiff rate</arg></template>whiff rate: a term, usually used in reference to pitchers, that divides the number of pitches swung at and missed by the total number of swings in a given sample. If a pitcher throws 100 pitches at which batters swing, and the batters fail to make contact on 26 of them, the pitcher's whiff rate is 26%.</listitem><listitem>WHIP<space/><link><target>Walks plus hits per inning pitched</target><part>Walks and hits per inning pitched</part></link>: average number of walks and hits allowed by the pitcher per inning</listitem><listitem>WP<space/><link><target>Wild pitch</target><trail>es</trail></link>: charged when a pitch is too high, low, or wide of home plate for the catcher to field, thereby allowing one or more runners to advance or score</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Fielding statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>A<space/><link><target>Assist (baseball statistics)</target><part>Assists</part></link>: number of outs recorded on a play where a fielder touched the ball, except if such touching is the putout</listitem><listitem>CI Catcher's Interference (e.g., catcher makes contact with bat)</listitem><listitem>DP<space/><link><target>Double plays</target></link>: one for each double play during which the fielder recorded a putout or an assist.</listitem><listitem>E<space/><link><target>Error (baseball statistics)</target><part>Errors</part></link>: number of times a fielder fails to make a play he should have made with common effort, and the offense benefits as a result</listitem><listitem>FP<space/><link><target>Fielding percentage</target></link>: total plays (chances minus errors) divided by the number of total chances</listitem><listitem>INN<space/><link><target>Innings</target></link>: number of innings that a player is at one certain position</listitem><listitem>PB<space/><link><target>Passed ball</target></link>: charged to the catcher when the ball is dropped and one or more runners advance</listitem><listitem>PO<space/><link><target>Putout</target></link>: number of times the fielder tags, forces, or appeals a runner and he is called out as a result</listitem><listitem>RF<space/><link><target>Range factor</target></link>: 9*(putouts + assists)/innings played. Used to determine the amount of field that the player can cover</listitem><listitem>TC<space/><link><target>Total chances</target></link>: assists plus putouts plus errors</listitem><listitem>TP<space/><link><target>triple play (baseball)</target><part>Triple play</part></link>: one for each triple play during which the fielder recorded a putout or an assist</listitem><listitem><template><target>anchor</target><arg>UZR</arg></template>UZR<space/><link><target>Ultimate zone rating</target></link>: the ability of a player to defend an assigned &quot;zone&quot; of the field compared to an average defensive player at his position</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Overall player value</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>VORP<space/><link><target>Value over replacement player</target></link>: a statistic that calculates a player's overall value in comparison to a &quot;replacement-level&quot; player. There are separate formulas for players and pitchers</listitem><listitem><link><target>Win shares</target></link>: a complex metric that gauges a player's overall contribution to his team's wins</listitem><listitem>WAR<space/><link><target>Wins above replacement</target></link>: a non-standard formula to calculate the number of wins a player contributes to his team over a &quot;replacement-level player&quot;</listitem></list><heading level='3'>General statistics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>G<space/><link><target>Games played</target></link>: number of games where the player played, in whole or in part</listitem><listitem>GS<space/><link><target>Games started</target></link>: number of games a player starts</listitem><listitem>GB<space/><link><target>Games behind</target></link>: number of games a team is behind the division leader</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pythagorean expectation</target></link>: estimates a team's expected winning percentage based on runs scored and runs allowed.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>MLB statistical standards</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Interleague play#Interleague statistics</arg></template>It is difficult to determine quantitatively what is considered to be a &quot;good&quot; value in a certain statistical category, and qualitative assessments may lead to arguments. Using full-season statistics available at the Official Site of Major League Baseball<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mlb.mlb.com/stats/historical/leaders.jsp?c_id=mlb&amp;amp;baseballScope=mlb&amp;amp;statType=1&amp;amp;sortByStat=All&amp;amp;timeFrame=1&amp;amp;timeSubFrame=2004'>Major League Baseball Historical Statistics</link></extension><space/>for the 2004 through 2011 seasons, the following tables show top ranges in various statistics, in alphabetical order. For each statistic, two values are given:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Top5: the top five players bettered this value in all of the reported seasons</listitem><listitem>Best: this is the best of all of the players for all of the reported seasons</listitem></list><table border="0" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0"><tablerow valign="top"><tablecell><table class="wikitable" style="text-align:center"><tablecaption><italics>Batting Statistics</italics></tablecaption><tablerow><tablehead><italics>Statistic</italics></tablehead><tablehead>Top5</tablehead><tablehead>Best</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>BA</tablehead><tablecell>.322</tablecell><tablecell>.372</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>HR</tablehead><tablecell>36</tablecell><tablecell>58</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>RBI</tablehead><tablecell>116</tablecell><tablecell>156</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>SLG</tablehead><tablecell>.565</tablecell><tablecell>.812</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>SB</tablehead><tablecell>39</tablecell><tablecell>78</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>OPS</tablehead><tablecell>.971</tablecell><tablecell>1.422</tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell><tablecell><table class="wikitable" style="text-align:center;"><tablecaption><italics>Pitching Statistics</italics></tablecaption><tablerow><tablehead><italics>Statistic</italics></tablehead><tablehead>Top5</tablehead><tablehead>Best</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>CG</tablehead><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>11</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>ERA</tablehead><tablecell>3.19</tablecell><tablecell>1.87</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>G</tablehead><tablecell>77</tablecell><tablecell>94</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>GS</tablehead><tablecell>33</tablecell><tablecell>35</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>IP</tablehead><tablecell>225.1</tablecell><tablecell>255</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>K</tablehead><tablecell>206</tablecell><tablecell>290</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>SHO</tablehead><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>SV</tablehead><tablecell>38</tablecell><tablecell>62</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>W</tablehead><tablecell>16</tablecell><tablecell>24</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>WHIP</tablehead><tablecell>1.14</tablecell><tablecell>0.90</tablecell></tablerow></table></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Baseball</arg></template><template><target>div col</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Baseball awards</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cy Young Award</target></link><space/>winners</listitem><listitem><link><target>Glossary of baseball</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hank Aaron Award</target></link><space/>winners (best offensive performer)</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball awards</target><part>List of MLB awards</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>MLB Most Valuable Player Award</target></link><space/>winners</listitem><listitem><link><target>MLB Rookie of the Year Award</target></link><space/>winners</listitem><listitem><link><target>Official Baseball Rules</target></link><space/>(OBR)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pitch (baseball)</target><part>List of pitches</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rawlings Gold Glove Award</target></link><space/>winners</listitem><listitem><link><target>Retrosheet</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sabermetrics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Silver Slugger Award</target></link><space/>winners</listitem><listitem><link><target>Society for American Baseball Research</target></link><space/>(SABR)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Strike zone</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Triple crown (baseball)</target><part>Triple Crown in Major League Baseball</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Albert, Jim, and Jay M. Bennett.<space/><italics>Curve Ball: Baseball, Statistics, and the Role of Chance in the Game</italics>. New York: Copernicus Books, 2001. ISBN 0-387-98816-5. A book on new statistics for baseball. MLB Record Book by: MLB.com</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Alan Schwarz</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Numbers Game: Baseball's Lifelong Fascination with Statistics</italics><space/>(New York: St. Martin's, 2005). ISBN 0-312-32223-2.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/baseball_basics/abbreviations.jsp'>The Official Site of Major League baseball - Baseball Basics: Abbreviations</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Baseball statistics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Baseball records</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Baseball Statistics</target></template><link><target>Category:Baseball statistics</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>