<article title='Battlecruiser'><paragraph><template><target>good article</target></template><link><target>File:HMS Hood (51) - March 17, 1924.jpg</target><part>400px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Hood</arg><arg>51</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, the largest battlecruiser ever built,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Breyer, p. 168">Breyer, p. 168</extension><space/>in Australia on 17 March 1924</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>battlecruiser</bold>, or<space/><bold>battle cruiser</bold>, was a large<space/><link><target>capital ship</target></link><space/>built in the first half of the 20th century. They were similar in size and cost to a<space/><link><target>battleship</target></link>, and typically carried the same kind of heavy guns, but generally carried less armour and were faster. The first battlecruisers were designed in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>in the first decade of the century, as a development of the<space/><link><target>armoured cruiser</target></link>, at the same time the<space/><link><target>dreadnought</target></link><space/>succeeded the<space/><link><target>pre-dreadnought battleship</target></link>. The original aim of the battlecruiser was to hunt down slower, older armoured cruisers and destroy them with heavy gunfire. However, as more and more battlecruisers were built, they increasingly became used alongside the better-protected battleships.</paragraph><paragraph>Battlecruisers served in the navies of<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target><part>Britain</part></link>,<space/><link><target>German Imperial Navy</target><part>Germany</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Navy</target><part>Ottoman Empire</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Royal Australian Navy</target><part>Australia</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Imperial Japanese Navy</target><part>Japan</part></link><space/>during World War I, most notably at the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Falkland Islands</target></link><space/>and in the several raids and skirmishes in the<space/><link><target>North Sea</target></link><space/>which culminated in a pitched fleet battle, the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jutland</target></link>. British battlecruisers in particular suffered heavy losses at Jutland, where their light armour made them very vulnerable to large-caliber shells. By the end of the war, capital ship design had developed with battleships becoming faster and battlecruisers becoming more heavily armoured, blurring the distinction between a battlecruiser and a<space/><link><target>fast battleship</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Washington Naval Treaty</target></link>, which limited capital ship construction from 1922 onwards, treated battleships and battlecruisers identically, and the new generation of battlecruisers planned was scrapped under the terms of the treaty.</paragraph><paragraph>From the 1930s, only the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/>continued to use 'battlecruiser' as a classification for warships, for the WWI-era capital ships that remained in the fleet. (While Japan's battlecruisers remained in service, they were significantly reconstructed and re-rated as battleships.) Nevertheless, the fast, light capital ships developed by Germany and France of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Scharnhorst</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Dunkerque</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>classes, respectively, are sometimes referred to as battlecruisers.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="The German {{sclass-|Scharnhorst|battleship|1}}s and {{sclass-|Deutschland|cruiser|1}}s and the French {{sclass-|Dunkerque|battleship|1}}s are all sometimes referred to as battlecruisers, although the owning navies referred to them as "battleships" ({{lang-de|Schlachtschiffe}}), "armored ships" ({{lang-de|Panzerschiffe}}) and "battleships" ({{lang-fr|Bâtiments de ligne}}) respectively. Since neither their operators nor a significant number of naval historians classify them as such, they are not discussed in this article.<ref>Gröner, pp. 31, 60</ref><ref>Gille, p. 139</ref><ref>Koop & Schmolke, p. 4</ref><ref name">"Gardiner & Chesneau, p. 259">Chesneau, p. 259</ref><ref>Bidlingmaier, pp. 73–74</ref></arg><arg name="group">Note</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>saw the modernized battlecruisers in action again, only one of which survived the war. There was also renewed interest in large &quot;cruiser-killer&quot; type warships, but few were ever begun, as construction of capital ships was curtailed in favor of more-needed convoy escorts, aircraft carriers, and cargo ships. In the post<link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>era, the Soviet<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kirov</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>of large guided missile cruisers have also been termed &quot;battlecruisers&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph>The battlecruiser was developed by the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/>in the first years of the 20th century as an evolution of the<space/><link><target>armoured cruiser</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondhaus, p. 199</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 13</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first armoured cruisers had been built in the 1870s, as an attempt to give armour protection to ships fulfilling the typical<space/><link><target>cruiser</target></link><space/>roles of patrol, trade protection and power projection. However, the results were rarely satisfactory, as the weight of armour required for any meaningful protection usually meant that the ship became almost as slow as a battleship. As a result, navies preferred to build<space/><link><target>protected cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with an armoured deck protecting their engines, or simply no armour at all.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1890s, technology began to change this balance. New<space/><link><target>Krupp armour</target><part>Krupp steel</part></link><space/>armour meant that it was now possible to give a cruiser side armour which would protect it against the<space/><link><target>Quick firing guns</target><part>quick-firing guns</part></link><space/>of enemy battleships and cruisers alike.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sumida, p.19</extension><space/>In 1896-7 France and Russia, who were regarded as likely allies in the event of war, started to build large, fast armoured cruisers taking advantage of this. In the event of a war between Britain and France or Russia, or both, these cruisers threatened to cause serious difficulties for the<space/><link><target>British Empire</target></link>'s worldwide trade.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 47</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Britain, which had concluded in 1892 that it needed twice as many cruisers as any potential enemy to adequately protect its empire's sea lanes, responded to the perceived threat by laying down its own large armoured cruisers. Between 1899 and 1905, it completed or laid down seven<space/><link><target>ship class</target><part>classes</part></link><space/>of this type, a total of 35 ships.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lambert 2002, pp. 2022</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Osborne, pp. 6162</extension><space/>This building program, in turn, prompted the French and Russians to increase their own construction. The<space/><link><target>Imperial German Navy</target></link><space/>began to build large armoured cruisers for use on their overseas stations, laying down eight between 1897 and 1906.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 142</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Osborne, pp. 62, 74</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The cost of this cruiser arms race was significant. In the period 188996, the Royal Navy spent 7.3 million on new large cruisers. From 18971904, it spent 26.9 million.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sumida, p.351, Table 9. Figures are for First-Class Cruisers and exclude armament.</extension><space/>Many armoured cruisers of the new kind were just as large and expensive as the equivalent battleship.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:HMS Shannon (1906).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shannon</arg><arg>1906</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, a ''Minotaur''-class armoured cruiser</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The increasing size and power of the armoured cruiser led to suggestions in British naval circles that cruisers should displace battleships entirely. The battleship's main advantage was its 12-inch heavy guns, and heavier armour designed to protect from shells of similar size. However, for a few years after 1900 it seemed that those advantages were of little practical value. The<space/><link><target>torpedo</target></link><space/>now had a range of 2,000 yards, and it seemed unlikely that a battleship would engage within torpedo range. However, at ranges of more than 2,000 yards it became increasingly unlikely that the heavy guns of a battleship would score any hits, as the heavy guns relied on primitive aiming techniques. The secondary batteries of 6-inch quick-firing guns, firing more plentiful shells, were more likely to hit the enemy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sumida, p. 42-44</extension><space/>As naval expert<space/><link><target>Fred T. Jane</target></link><space/>wrote in June 1902,<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Is there anything outside of 2,000 yards that the big gun in its hundreds of tons of medieval castle can effect, that its weight in 6-inch guns without the castle could not effect equally well? And inside 2,000, what, in these days of gyros, is there that the torpedo cannot effect with far more certainty?<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Sumida , p.44</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1904, Admiral<space/><link><target>John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher</target><part>John &quot;Jacky&quot; Fisher</part></link><space/>became<space/><link><target>First Sea Lord</target></link>, the senior officer of the Royal Navy. He had for some time thought about the development of a new fast armoured ship. He was very fond of the &quot;second-class battleship&quot;<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Renown</arg><arg>1895</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, a faster, more lightly armoured battleship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 15</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Mackay, pp. 21213</extension><space/>As early as 1901, there is confusion in Fisher's writing about whether he saw the battleship or the cruiser as the model for future developments. This did not stop him from commissioning designs from<space/><link><target>naval architect</target></link><space/>W. H. Gard for an armoured cruiser with the heaviest possible armament for use with the fleet. The design Gard submitted was for a ship between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>14000</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>15000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg></template>, capable of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg name="lk">in</arg></template>, armed with four 9.2-inch and twelve<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7.5</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>guns in twin<space/><link><target>gun turret</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and protected with six inches of armour along her<space/><link><target>belt armour</target><part>belt</part></link><space/>and 9.2-inch turrets,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>4</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>on her 7.5-inch turrets, 10 inches on her<space/><link><target>conning tower</target></link><space/>and up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2.5</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>on her decks. However, mainstream British naval thinking between 1902 and 1904 was clearly in favour of heavily armoured battleships, rather than the fast ships that Fisher favoured.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 48</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Battle of Tsushima proved conclusively the effectiveness of heavy guns over intermediate ones and the need for a uniform main caliber on a ship for fire control. Even before this, the Royal Navy had begun to consider a shift away from the mixed-calibre armament of the 1890s<space/><link><target>pre-dreadnought</target></link><space/>to an &quot;all-big-gun&quot; design, and preliminary designs circulated for battleships with all 12-inch or all 10-inch guns and armoured cruisers with all 9.2-inch guns.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 1617</extension><space/>In late 1904, not long after the Royal Navy had decided to use 12-inch guns for its next generation of battleships because of their superior performance at long range, Fisher began to argue that big-gun cruisers could replace battleships altogether. The continuing improvement of the torpedo meant that<space/><link><target>submarine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>destroyer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>would be able to destroy battleships; this in Fisher's view heralded the end of the battleship or at least compromised the validity of heavy armour protection. Nevertheless, armoured cruisers would remain vital for commerce protection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mackay, pp. 32425</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 1718</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Sumida, p. 52</extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Of what use is a battle fleet to a country called (A) at war with a country called (B) possessing no battleships, but having fast armoured cruisers and clouds of fast torpedo craft? What damage would (A's) battleships do to (B)? Would (B) wish for a few battleships or for more armoured cruisers? Would not (A) willingly exchange a few battleships for more fast armoured cruisers? In such a case, neither side wanting battleships is presumptive evidence that they are not of much value&quot;&amp;nbsp; Fisher to<space/><link><target>William Palmer, 2nd Earl of Selborne</target><part>Lord Selborne</part></link><space/>(<link><target>First Lord of the Admiralty</target></link>), 20 October 1904<extension extension_name='ref'>quoted in Sumida, p. 52</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Fisher's views were very controversial within the Royal Navy, and even given his position as First Sea Lord, he was not in a position to insist on his own approach. Thus he assembled a &quot;Committee on Designs&quot;, consisting of a mixture of civilian and naval experts, to determine the approach to both battleship and armoured cruiser construction in the future. While the stated purpose of the Committee was to investigate and report on future requirements of ships, Fisher and his associates had already made key decisions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="R19">Roberts, p. 19</extension><space/>The terms of reference for the Committee were for a battleship capable of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>21</arg><arg>kn</arg></template><space/>with 12-inch guns and no intermediate calibres, capable of docking in existing<space/><link><target>drydock</target><trail>s</trail></link>;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Breyer">Breyer, p. 115</extension><space/>and a cruiser capable of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25.5</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, also with 12-inch guns and no intermediate armament, armoured like<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Minotaur</arg><arg>1906</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, the most recent armoured cruiser, and also capable of using existing docks.<extension extension_name='ref' name="R19"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>First battlecruisers</heading><paragraph>Under the Selborne plan of 1902, the Royal Navy intended to start three new battleships and four armoured cruisers each year. However, in late 1904 it became clear that the 190506 programme would have to be considerably smaller, because of lower than expected tax revenue and the need to buy out two Chilean battleships under construction in British yards, lest they be purchased by the Russians for use against the Japanese, Britain's ally. These economies meant that the 190506 programme consisted only of one battleship, but three armoured cruisers. The battleship became the revolutionary battleship<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Dreadnought</arg><arg>1906</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and the cruisers became the three ships of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. Fisher later claimed, however, that he had argued during the Committee for the cancellation of the remaining battleship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sumida, p. 55</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:HMS Invincible (1907) British Battleship.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, Britain's first battlecruiser</part></link>The construction of the new class were begun in 1906 and completed in 1908, delayed perhaps to allow their designers to learn from any problems with<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Breyer"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 2425</extension><space/>The ships fulfilled the design requirement quite closely. On a displacement similar to<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>, the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s were<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>longer to accommodate additional<space/><link><target>boiler (steam generator)</target><part>boiler</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and more powerful<space/><link><target>steam turbine</target><part>turbines</part></link><space/>to propel them at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. Moreover, the new ships could maintain this speed for days, whereas pre-dreadnought battleships could not generally do so for more than an hour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burr, pp. 78</extension><space/>Armed with eight<space/><link><target>BL 12 inch Mk X naval gun</target><part>12-inch Mk X guns</part></link>, compared to ten on<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>, they had<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>7</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>of armour protecting the hull and the gun turrets. (<italics>Dreadnought</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s armour, by comparison, was<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>11</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>12</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>at its thickest.)<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 11417</extension><space/>The class had a very marked increase in speed, displacement and firepower compared to the most recent armoured cruisers but no more armour.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GG24"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s were to fill the same role as the armoured cruisers they succeeded, they were expected to do so more effectively. Specifically their roles were:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Heavy reconnaissance.</bold><space/>Because of their power, the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s could sweep away the screen of enemy cruisers to close with and observe an enemy battlefleet before using their superior speed to retire.</listitem><listitem><bold>Close support for the battle fleet.</bold><space/>They could be stationed at the ends of the battle line to stop enemy cruisers harassing the battleships, and to harass the enemy's battleships if they were busy fighting battleships. Also, the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s could operate as the fast wing of the battlefleet and try to outmanouevre the enemy.</listitem><listitem><bold>Pursuit.</bold><space/>If an enemy fleet ran, then the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s would use their speed to pursue, and their guns to damage or slow enemy ships.</listitem><listitem><bold>Commerce protection.</bold><space/>The new ships would hunt down enemy cruisers and commerce raiders.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 18</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Confusion about how to refer to these new battleship-size armoured cruisers set in almost immediately. Even in late 1905, before work was begun on the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s, a Royal Navy memorandum refers to &quot;large armoured ships&quot; meaning both battleships and large cruisers. In October 1906, the Admiralty began to classify all post-Dreadnought battleships and armoured cruisers as &quot;<link><target>capital ships</target></link>&quot;, while Fisher used the term &quot;dreadnought&quot; to refer either to his new battleships or the battleships and armoured cruisers together.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mackay, pp. 32526</extension><space/>At the same time, the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>class themselves were referred to as &quot;cruiser-battleships&quot;, &quot;dreadnought cruisers&quot;; the term &quot;battlecruiser&quot; was first used by Fisher in 1908. Finally, on 24 November 1911, Admiralty Weekly Order No. 351 laid down that &quot;All cruisers of the Invincible and later types are for the future to be described and classified as battle cruisers to distinguish them from the armoured cruisers of earlier date.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Admiralty Weekly Orders.<space/><bold>351.Description and Classification of Cruisers of the Invincible and Later Types.</bold><space/>ADM 182/2, quoted at<space/><link type='external' href='http://dreadnoughtproject.org/tfs/index.php/The_Battle_Cruiser_in_the_Royal_Navy#Tactics'>The Dreadnought Project: The Battle Cruiser in the Royal Navy.</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Along with questions over the new ships' nomenclature came uncertainty about their actual role due to their lack of protection. If they were primarily to act as scouts for the battle fleet and hunter-killers of enemy cruisers and commerce raiders, then the seven inches of belt armour with which they had been equipped would be adequate. If, on the other hand, they were expected to reinforce a battle line of dreadnoughts with their own heavy guns, they were too thin-skinned to be safe from an enemy's heavy guns. The<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s were essentially extremely large, heavily armed, fast armoured cruisers. However, the viability of the armoured cruiser was already in doubt. A cruiser that could have worked with the Fleet might have been a more viable option for taking over that role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GG24">Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 24</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="M494">Massie, p. 494</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Because of the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s<template><target>'</target></template><space/>size and armament, naval authorities considered them capital ships almost from their inceptionan assumption that might have been inevitable. Complicating matters further was that many naval authorities, including Lord Fisher, had made overoptimistic assessments from the Battle of Tsushima in 1905 about the armoured cruiser's ability to survive in a battle line against enemy capital ships due to their superior speed. These assumptions had been made without taking into account the Russian<space/><link><target>Baltic Fleet</target></link>'s inefficiency and tactical ineptitude. By the time the term &quot;battlecruiser&quot; had been given to the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s, the idea of their parity with battleships had been fixed in many people's minds.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GG24"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="M494"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Not everyone was so convinced.<space/><italics>Brassey<template><target>'</target></template>s Naval Annual</italics>, for instance, stated that with vessels as large and expensive as the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s, an admiral &quot;will be certain to put them in the line of battle where their comparatively light protection will be a disadvantage and their high speed of no value.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>As quoted in Massie, pp. 49495</extension><space/>Those in favor of the battlecruiser countered with two pointsfirst, since all capital ships were vulnerable to new weapons such as the<space/><link><target>torpedo</target></link>, armour had lost some of its validity; and second, because of its greater speed, the battlecruiser could control the range at which it engaged an enemy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman, p. 10</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Battlecruisers in the dreadnought arms race</heading><paragraph>Between the launching of the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s to just after the outbreak of the First World War, the battlecruiser played a junior role in the developing dreadnought arms race, as it was never wholeheartedly adopted as the key weapon in British imperial defence, as Fisher had presumably desired. The biggest factor for this lack of acceptance was the marked change in Britain's strategic circumstances between their conception and the commissioning of the first ships. The prospective enemy for Britain had shifted from a Franco-Russian alliance with many armoured cruisers to a resurgent and increasingly belligerent Germany. Diplomatically, Britain had entered the<space/><link><target>Entente cordiale</target></link><space/>in 1904 and the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Russian Entente</target></link>. Neither France nor Russia posed a particular naval threat; the Russian navy had largely been sunk or captured in the<space/><link><target>Russo-Japanese War</target></link><space/>of 19045, while the French were in no hurry to adopt the new<space/><link><target>dreadnought</target></link>-type design. Britain also boasted very cordial relations with two of the significant new naval powers, Japan (bolstered by the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Japanese Alliance</target></link>, signed in 1902 and renewed in 1905), and the USA. These changed strategic circumstances, and the great success of the<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>, ensured that she rather than the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>became the new model capital ship. Nevertheless, battlecruiser construction played a part in the renewed naval arms-race sparked by the<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondhaus, pp. 199202</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:HMS Queen Mary.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Queen Mary</arg></template>, the third ''Lion''-class battlecruiser</part></link>For their first few years of service, the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s entirely fulfilled Fisher's vision of being able to sink any ship fast enough to catch them, and run from any ship capable of sinking them. An<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>would also, in many circumstances, be able to take on an enemy<space/><link><target>pre-dreadnought battleship</target></link>. Naval circles concurred that the armoured cruiser in its current form had come to the logical end of its development and the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s were so far ahead of any enemy armoured cruiser in firepower and speed that it proved difficult to justify building more or bigger cruisers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 25</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Mackay pp. 32425</extension><space/>This lead was extended by the surprise both<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>produced by having been built in secret; this prompted most other navies to delay their building programmes and radically revise their designs.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondhaus, pp. 20102</extension><space/>This was particularly true for cruisers, because the details of the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>class were kept secret for longer; this meant that the last German armoured cruiser,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Blücher</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, was armed with only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>21</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>guns, and was no match for the new battlecruisers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Staff, pp. 34</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Royal Navy's early superiority in capital ships led to the rejection of a 190506 design that would, essentially, have fused the battlecruiser and battleship concepts into what would eventually become the fast battleship. The 'X4' design combined the full armour and armament of<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics><space/>with the 25 knot speed of<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>. The additional cost could not be justified given the existing British lead and the new Liberal government's need for economy; the slower and cheaper<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Bellerophon</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, a relatively close copy of<space/><italics>Dreadnought</italics>, was adopted instead.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 26</extension><space/>The X4 concept would eventually be fulfilled in the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Queen Elizabeth</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>and later by other navies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 6162</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The next British battlecruisers were the three<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, slightly improved<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s built to fundamentally the same specification, partly due to political pressure to limit costs and partly due to the secrecy surrounding German battlecruiser construction, particularly about the heavy armour of<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Von der Tann</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 2829</extension><space/>This class came to be widely seen as a mistake<extension extension_name='ref'>Brown 1999, p. 57</extension><space/>and the next generation of British battlecruisers were markedly more powerful. By 190910 a sense of national crisis about rivalry with Germany outweighed cost-cutting, and a naval panic resulted in the approval of a total of eight capital ships in 190910.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondhaus, p. 203</extension><space/>Fisher pressed for all eight to be battlecruisers,<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 32</extension><space/>but was unable to have his way; he had to settle for six battleships and two battlecruisers of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Lion</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. The<space/><italics>Lion</italics>s carried eight<space/><link><target>BL 13.5 inch Mk V naval gun</target><part>13.5-inch guns</part></link>, the now-standard caliber of the British &quot;super-dreadnought&quot; battleships. Speed increased to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>27</arg><arg>kn</arg></template><space/>and armour protection, while not as good as in German designs, was better than in previous British battlecruisers, with<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>9</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg><arg name="spell">in</arg></template><space/>armour belt and<space/><link><target>barbette</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The two<space/><italics>Lion</italics>s were followed by the very similar<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Queen Mary</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 3133</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:German battlecruiser SMS Seydlitz in port, prior to World War I (retouched).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>SMS ''Seydlitz''</part><part>alt=A large gray ship in port. The two funnels in the center of the ship emit clouds of smoke.</part></link>By 1911 Germany had built battlecruisers of her own, and the superiority of the British ships could no longer be assured. Moreover, the German Navy did not share Fisher's view of the battlecruiser. In contrast to the British focus on increasing speed and firepower, Germany progressively improved the armour and staying power of their ships to better the British battlecruisers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondhaus, pp. 20203</extension><space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics>, begun in 1908 and completed in 1910, carried eight 11.1-inch guns, but with 11.1-inch (283&amp;nbsp;mm) armour she was far better protected than the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s. The two<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Moltke</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template>s were quite similar but carried ten 11.1-inch guns of an improved design.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 26972</extension><space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, designed in 1909 and finished in 1913, was a modified<space/><italics>Moltke</italics>; speed increased by one knot to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>26.5</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, while her armour had a maximum thickness of 12 inches, equivalent to the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Helgoland</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s of a few years earlier.<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>was Germany's last battlecruiser completed before World War I.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 267, 272</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The next step in battlecruiser design came from Japan. The<space/><link><target>Imperial Japanese Navy</target></link><space/>had been planning the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kongō</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>ships from 1909, and was determined that, since the Japanese economy could support relatively few ships, each would be more powerful than its likely competitors. Initially the class was planned with the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>s as the benchmark. On learning of the British plans for<space/><italics>Lion</italics>, and the likelihood that new<space/><link><target>U.S. Navy</target></link><space/>battleships would be armed with<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>14</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>guns, the Japanese decided to radically revise their plans and go one better. A new plan was drawn up, carrying eight 14-inch guns, and capable of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>27.5</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, thus marginally having the edge over the<space/><italics>Lion</italics>s in speed and firepower. The heavy guns were also better-positioned, being<space/><link><target>superfire</target><part>superfiring</part></link><space/>both fore and aft with no turret amidships. The armour scheme was also marginally improved over the<space/><italics>Lion</italics>s, with nine inches of armour on the turrets and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>on the barbettes. The first ship in the class was built in Britain, and a further three constructed in Japan.<extension extension_name='ref'>Evans &amp; Peattie, pp. 16163</extension><space/>The Japanese also re-classified their powerful armoured cruisers of the<space/><italics>Tsukuba</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Ibuki</italics><space/>classes, carrying four 12-inch guns, as battlecruisers; nonetheless, their armament was weaker and they were slower than any battlecruiser.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 233</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Kongo Postcard.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Kong''</part></link>The next British battlecruiser,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Tiger</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, was intended initially as the fourth ship in the<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>class, but was substantially redesigned. She retained the eight 13.5-inch guns of her predecessors, but they were positioned like those of<space/><italics>Kong</italics><space/>for better fields of fire. She was faster (making<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>29</arg><arg>kn</arg></template><space/>on<space/><link><target>sea trial</target><trail>s</trail></link>), and carried a heavier secondary armament.<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>was also more heavily armoured on the whole; while the maximum thickness of armour was the same at nine inches, the height of the main armour belt was increased.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 3738</extension><space/>Not all the desired improvements for this ship were approved, however. Her designer,<space/><link><target>Sir Eustace Tennyson d'Eyncourt, 1st Baronet</target><part>Sir Eustace Tennyson d'Eyncourt</part></link>, had wanted small-bore<space/><link><target>water-tube boiler</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and geared turbines to give her a speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>32</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, but he received no support from the authorities and the engine makers refused his request.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 136</extension></paragraph><paragraph>1912 saw work begin on three more German battlecruisers of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Derfflinger</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, the first German battlecruisers to mount 12-inch guns. These ships, like<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>and the<space/><italics>Kong</italics>s, had their guns arranged in superfiring turrets for greater efficiency. Their armour and speed was similar to the previous<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>class.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 27778</extension><space/>In 1913, the<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target></link><space/>also began the construction of the four-ship<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Borodino</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, which were designed for service in the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target></link>. These ships were designed to carry twelve 14-inch guns, with armour up to 12 inches thick, and a speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>26.6</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. The heavy armour and relatively slow speed of these ships made them more similar to German designs than to British ships; construction of the<space/><italics>Borodino</italics>s was halted by the First World War and all were scrapped after the end of the<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 399</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>World War I</heading><heading level='3'>Construction</heading><paragraph>For most of the combatants, capital ship construction was very limited during the war. Germany finished the<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>class and began work on the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Mackensen</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. The<space/><italics>Mackensen</italics>s were a development of the<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>class, with 13.8-inch guns and a broadly similar armour scheme, designed for<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 28384</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Britain, Jackie Fisher returned to the office of First Sea Lord in October 1914. His enthusiasm for big, fast ships was unabated, and he set designers to producing a design for a battlecruiser with 15-inch guns. Because Fisher expected the next German battlecruiser to steam at 28 knots, he required the new British design to be capable of 32 knots. He planned to reorder two<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Revenge</arg><arg>battleship</arg></template>s, which had been approved but not yet laid down, to a new design. Fisher finally received approval for this project on 28 December 1914 and they became the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Renown</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. With six<space/><link><target>BL 15 inch Mk I naval gun</target><part>15-inch guns</part></link><space/>but only 6-inch armour they were a further step forward from<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>in firepower and speed, but returned to the level of protection of the first British battlecruisers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 4647</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the same time, Fisher resorted to subterfuge to obtain another three fast, lightly armoured ships that could use several spare<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>gun turrets left over from battleship construction. These ships were essentially light battlecruisers, and Fisher occasionally referred to them as such, but officially they were classified as<space/><italics>large light cruisers</italics>. This unusual designation was required because construction of new capital ships had been placed on hold, while there were no limits on<space/><link><target>light cruiser</target></link><space/>construction. They became<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Courageous</arg><arg>50</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and her sisters<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Glorious</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Furious</arg><arg>47</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and there was a bizarre imbalance between their main guns of 15 inches (or<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>in<space/><italics>Furious</italics>) and their armour, which at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="spell">in</arg></template><space/>thickness was on the scale of a light cruiser. The design was generally regarded as a failure (nicknamed in the Fleet<space/><italics>Outrageous</italics>,<space/><italics>Uproarious</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Spurious</italics>), though the later conversion of the ships to<space/><link><target>aircraft carrier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>was very successful.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 5052</extension><space/>Fisher also speculated about a new mammoth, but lightly built battlecruiser, that would carry<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>guns, which he termed<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Incomparable</arg></template>; this never got beyond the concept stage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 172</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is often held that the<space/><italics>Renown</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Courageous</italics><space/>classes were designed for Fisher's plan to land troops (possibly Russian) on the German Baltic coast. Specifically, they were designed with a reduced<space/><link><target>draft (hull)</target><part>draught</part></link>, which might be important in the shallow Baltic. This is not clear-cut evidence that the ships were designed for the Baltic: it was considered that earlier ships had too much draught and not enough<space/><link><target>Freeboard (nautical)</target><part>freeboard</part></link><space/>under operational conditions. Roberts argues that the focus on the Baltic was probably unimportant at the time the ships were designed, but was inflated later, after the disastrous<space/><link><target>Dardanelles Campaign</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 51</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The final British battlecruiser design of the war was the<space/><template><target>sclass2-</target><arg>Admiral</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, which was born from a requirement for an improved version of the<space/><italics>Queen Elizabeth</italics><space/>battleship. The project began at the end of 1915, after Fisher's final departure from the Admiralty. While initially envisaged as a battleship, senior sea officers felt that Britain had enough battleships, but that new battlecruisers might be required to combat German ships being built (the British overestimated German progress on the<space/><italics>Mackensen</italics><space/>class as well as their likely capabilities). A battlecruiser design with eight 15-inch guns, 8&amp;nbsp;inches of armour and capable of 32 knots was decided on. The experience of battlecruisers at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jutland</target></link><space/>meant that the design was radically revised and transformed again into a fast battleship with armour up to 12 inches thick, but still capable of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>31.5</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. The first ship in the class,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Hood</arg><arg>51</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, was built according to this design to counter the possible completion of any of the Mackensen-class ship. The plans for her three sisters, on which little work had been done, were revised once more later in 1916 and in 1917 to improve protection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, pp. 5561</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Admiral class would have been the only British ships capable of taking on the German<space/><italics>Mackensen</italics><space/>class; nevertheless, German shipbuilding was drastically slowed by the war, and while two<space/><italics>Mackensen</italics>s were launched, none were ever completed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="R601">Roberts, pp. 6061</extension><space/>The Germans also worked briefly on a further three ships, of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Ersatz Yorck</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, which were modified versions of the<space/><italics>Mackensen</italics>s with 15-inch guns.<extension extension_name='ref'>Grner, pp. 5859</extension><space/>Work on the three additional Admirals was suspended in March 1917 to enable more escorts and merchant ships to be built to deal with the new threat from U-boats to trade. They were finally cancelled in February 1919.<extension extension_name='ref' name="R601"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Battlecruisers in action</heading><paragraph>The first combat involving battlecruisers during World War I was the<space/><link><target>Battle of Heligoland Bight (1914)</target><part>Battle of Heligoland Bight</part></link><space/>in August 1914. A force of British light cruisers and destroyers entered the<space/><link><target>Heligoland Bight</target></link><space/>(the part of the North Sea closest to<space/><link><target>Hamburg</target></link>) to attack German destroyer patrols. When they met opposition from light cruisers,<space/><link><target>Vice Admiral</target></link><space/><link><target>David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</target><part>David Beatty</part></link><space/>took his squadron of five battlecruisers into the Bight and turned the tide of the battle, ultimately sinking three German light cruisers and killing their commander,<space/><link><target>Rear Admiral</target></link><space/><link><target>Leberecht Maass</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burr, pp. 2122</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The German battlecruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Goeben</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>perhaps made the most impact early in the war. Stationed in the Mediterranean, she and the escorting light cruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Breslau</arg></template><space/><link><target>Pursuit of Goeben and Breslau</target><part>evaded British and French ships on the outbreak of war</part></link>, and steamed to Constantinople (<link><target>Istanbul</target></link>) with two British battlecruisers in hot pursuit. The two German ships were handed over to the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Navy</target></link>, and this was instrumental in bringing the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>into the war as one of the<space/><link><target>Central Powers</target></link>.<space/><italics>Goeben</italics><space/>herself, renamed<space/><italics>Yavuz Sultan Selim</italics>, fought engagements against the<space/><link><target>Imperial Russian Navy</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Black Sea</target></link><space/>and against the British in the<space/><link><target>Aegean Sea</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Halpern, pp. 5358</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Staff, pp. 1820</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The original battlecruiser concept proved successful in December 1914 at the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Falkland Islands</target></link>. The British battlecruisers<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Inflexible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>did precisely the job for which they were intended when they chased down and annihilated the<space/><link><target>German East Asia Squadron</target></link>, centered on the armoured cruisers<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Scharnhorst</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Gneisenau</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, along with three light cruisers, commanded by Admiral<space/><link><target>Maximilian von Spee</target><part>Maximilian Graf Von Spee</part></link>, in the South Atlantic Ocean. Prior to the battle, the Australian battlecruiser<space/><template><target>HMAS</target><arg>Australia</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>had unsuccessfully searched for the German ships in the Pacific.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burr, pp. 2223</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:SMS Seydlitz2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>was heavily damaged in the Battle of Dogger Bank</part></link>During the<space/><link><target>Battle of Dogger Bank (1915)</target><part>Battle of Dogger Bank</part></link><space/>in 1915, the aftermost barbette of the German flagship<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>was struck by a British 13.5-inch shell from<space/><italics>HMS Lion</italics>. The shell did not penetrate the barbette, but it dislodged a piece of the barbette armour that allowed the flame from the shell's detonation to enter the barbette. The propellant charges being hoisted upwards were ignited, and the fireball flashed up into the turret and down into the<space/><link><target>magazine (artillery)</target><part>magazine</part></link>, setting fire to charges removed from their brass cartridge cases. The gun crew tried to escape into the next turret, which allowed the flash to spread into that turret as well, killing the crews of both turrets.<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>was saved from near-certain destruction only by emergency flooding of her after magazines, which had been effected by<space/><link><target>Wilhelm Heidkamp</target></link>. This near-disaster was due to the way that ammunition handling was arranged and was common to both German and British battleships and battlecruisers, but the lighter protection on the latter made them more vulnerable to the turret or barbette being penetrated. The Germans learned from investigating the damaged<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>and instituted measures to ensure that ammunition handling minimised any possible exposure to flash.<extension extension_name='ref'>Staff, pp. 2324, 43</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Apart from the<space/><link><target>cordite</target></link><space/>handling, the battle was mostly inconclusive, though both the British flagship<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>were severely damaged.<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>lost speed, causing her to fall behind the rest of the battleline, and Beatty was unable to effectively command his ships for the remainder of the engagement. A British signalling error allowed the German battlecruisers to withdraw, as most of Beatty's squadron mistakenly concentrated on the crippled armoured cruiser<space/><italics>Blcher</italics>, sinking her with great loss of life. The British blamed their failure to win a decisive victory on their poor gunnery and attempted to increase their rate of fire by stockpiling unprotected cordite charges in their ammunition hoists and barbettes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Staff, pp. 4344, Burr, pp. 24, 33</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Destruction of HMS Queen Mary.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Queen Mary'' blows up during the Battle of Jutland</part></link>At the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jutland</target></link><space/>on 31 May 1916, both British and German battlecruisers were employed as fleet units. The British battlecruisers became engaged with both their German counterparts, the battlecruisers, and then German battleships before the arrival of the battleships of the<space/><link><target>British Grand Fleet</target></link>. The result was a disaster for the Royal Navy's battlecruiser squadrons:<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>,<space/><italics>Queen Mary</italics>, and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>1909</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>exploded with the loss of all but a handful of their crews.<extension extension_name='ref'>Halpern, pp. 31821</extension><space/>The exact reason why the ships' magazines detonated is not known, but the plethora of exposed cordite charges stored in their turrets, ammunition hoists and working chambers in the quest to increase their rate of fire undoubtedly contributed to their loss.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lambert 1998, pp. 5455</extension><space/>Beatty's flagship<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>herself was almost lost in a similar manner, save for the heroic actions of<space/><link><target>Major</target></link><space/><link><target>Francis John William Harvey</target><part>Francis Harvey</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, p. 116</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The better-armoured German battlecruisers fared better, in part due to the poor performance of British fuzes (the British shells tended to explode or break up on impact with the German armour).<extension extension_name='ref'>Halpern, p. 328</extension><space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Lützow</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>the only German battlecruiser lost at Jutlandhad only 128 killed,<extension extension_name='ref'>Staff, pp. 4142</extension><space/>for instance, despite receiving more than thirty hits. The other German battlecruisers,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Moltke</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics>,<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Derfflinger</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, were all heavily damaged and required extensive repairs after the battle,<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>barely making it home, for they had been the focus of British fire for much of the battle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Halpern, pp. 31925</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Interwar period</heading><paragraph>In the years immediately after World War I, Britain, Japan and the USA all began design work on a new generation of ever more powerful battleships and battlecruisers. The new burst of shipbuilding that each nation's navy desired was politically controversial and potentially economically crippling. This nascent arms race was prevented by the<space/><link><target>Washington Naval Treaty</target></link><space/>of 1922, where the major naval powers agreed to limits on capital ship numbers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 6264, 7072</extension><space/>The German navy was not represented at the talks; under the terms of the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link>, Germany was not allowed any modern capital ships at all.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chesneau, p. 218</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Through the 1920s and 1930s only Britain and Japan retained battlecruisers, often modified and rebuilt from their original designs. The line between the battlecruiser and the modern fast battleship became blurred; indeed, the Japanese<space/><italics>Kong</italics>s were formally redesignated as battleships.<extension extension_name='ref' name="j5">Jentschura, Jung &amp; Mickel, p. 35</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Plans in the aftermath of World War I</heading><paragraph><italics>Hood</italics>, launched in 1918, was the last World War I battlecruiser to be completed. Owing to lessons from Jutland, the ship was modified during construction; the thickness of her belt armour was increased by an average of 50 percent and extended substantially, she was given heavier deck armour, and the protection of her magazines was improved to guard against the ignition of ammunition. This was hoped to be capable of resisting her own weaponsthe classic measure of a &quot;balanced&quot; battleship.<space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>was the largest ship in the Royal Navy when completed; thanks to her great displacement, in theory she combined the firepower and armour of a battleship with the speed of a battlecruiser, causing some to refer to her as a fast battleship. However her protection was markedly less than that of the British battleships built immediately after World War I, the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Nelson</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>4</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Breyer, p. 168"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Lexington class battlecruiser2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Lexington''-class battlecruiser (painting, c. 1919)</part></link>The navies of Japan and the United States, not being affected immediately by the war, had time to develop new heavy<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>16</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>guns for their latest designs and to refine their battlecruiser designs in light of combat experience in Europe. The Imperial Japanese Navy began four<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Amagi</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s. These vessels would have been of unprecedented size and power, as fast and well armoured as<space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>whilst carrying a main battery of ten 16-inch guns, the most powerful armament ever proposed for a battlecruiser. They were, for all intents and purposes, fast battleshipsthe only differences between them and the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Tosa</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s which were to precede them were<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="adj">off</arg></template><space/>less side armour and a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>.25</arg><arg>kn</arg></template><space/>increase in speed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 353</extension><space/>The United States Navy, which had worked on its battlecruiser designs since 1913 and watched the latest developments in this class with great care, responded with the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Lexington</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. If completed as planned, they would have been exceptionally fast and well armed with eight 16-inch guns, but carried armour little better than the<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>sthis after an<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>increase in protection following Jutland.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, p. 234</extension><space/>The final stage in the post-war battlecruiser race came with the British response to the<space/><italics>Amagi</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Lexington</italics><space/>types: four<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>48000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/><link><target>G3 battlecruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Royal Navy documents of the period often described any battleship with a speed of over about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>24</arg><arg>kn</arg></template><space/>as a battlecruiser, regardless of the amount of protective armour, although the G3 was considered by most to be a well-balanced fast battleship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, pp. 4142</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Washington Naval Treaty meant that none of these designs came to fruition. Ships that had been started were either broken up on the<space/><link><target>slipway</target></link><space/>or converted to aircraft carriers. In Japan,<space/><italics>Amagi</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese aircraft carrier</arg><arg>Akagi</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were selected for conversion.<space/><italics>Amagi</italics><space/>was damaged beyond repair by the<space/><link><target>1923 Great Kant earthquake</target></link><space/>and was broken up for<space/><link><target>ship breaking</target><part>scrap</part></link>; the hull of one of the proposed<space/><italics>Tosa</italics>-class battleships,<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese aircraft carrier</arg><arg>Kaga</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, was converted in her stead.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 235</extension><space/>The United States Navy also converted two battlecruiser hulls into aircraft carriers in the wake of the Washington Treaty:<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Lexington</arg><arg>CV-2</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Saratoga</arg><arg>CV-3</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, although this was only considered marginally preferable to scrapping the hulls outright (the remaining four:<space/><italics>Constellation</italics>,<space/><italics>Ranger</italics>,<space/><italics>Constitution</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>United States</italics><space/>were scrapped).<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 119</extension><space/>In Britain, Fisher's &quot;large light cruisers,&quot; were converted to carriers.<space/><italics>Furious</italics><space/>had already been partially converted during the war and<space/><italics>Glorious</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Courageous</italics><space/>were similarly converted.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner &amp; Gray, p. 40</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Rebuilding programmes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:HMS Repulse (1919) profile drawing.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>350px</part><part>''Repulse'' as she was in 1919</part></link><link><target>Image:HMS Renown (1939) profile drawing.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>350px</part><part>''Renown'', as reconstructed, in 1939</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In total, nine battlecruisers survived the Washington Naval Treaty, although HMS<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>later became a victim of the<space/><link><target>London Naval Conference</target></link><space/>of 1930 and was scrapped.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burt, p. 48</extension><space/>Because their high speed made them valuable surface units in spite of their weaknesses, most of these ships were significantly updated before World War II.<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Renown</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Repulse</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were modernized significantly in the 1920s and 1930s. Between 1934 and 1936,<space/><italics>Repulse</italics><space/>was partially modernized and had her<space/><link><target>bridge (nautical)</target><part>bridge</part></link><space/>modified, an aircraft<space/><link><target>hangar</target></link>,<space/><link><target>aircraft catapult</target><part>catapult</part></link><space/>and new gunnery equipment added and her anti-aircraft armament increased.<space/><italics>Renown</italics><space/>underwent a more thorough reconstruction between 1937 and 1939. Her deck armour was increased, new turbines and boilers were fitted, an aircraft hangar and catapult added and she was completely rearmed aside from the main guns which had their elevation increased to +30 degrees. The bridge structure was also removed and a large bridge similar to that used in the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>King George V</arg><arg>battleship (1939)</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>battleships installed in its place. While conversions of this kind generally added weight to the vessel,<space/><italics>Renown</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s tonnage actually decreased due to a substantially lighter power plant. Similar thorough rebuildings planned for<space/><italics>Repulse</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>were cancelled due to the advent of<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 15758, 172</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unable to build new ships, the Imperial Japanese Navy also chose to improve its existing battlecruisers of the<space/><italics>Kong</italics><space/>class (initially the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese battleship</arg><arg>Haruna</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese battleship</arg><arg>Kirishima</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese battleship</arg><arg>Kongō</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Japanese battleship</arg><arg>Hiei</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>only later as it had been disarmed under the terms of the Washington treaty) in two substantial reconstructions (one for<space/><italics>Hiei</italics>). During the first of these, elevation of their main guns was increased to +40 degrees, anti-torpedo bulges and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3800</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg></template><space/>of horizontal armour added, and a &quot;pagoda&quot; mast with additional command positions built up. This reduced the ships' speed to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25.9</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. The second reconstruction focused on speed as they had been selected as fast escorts for aircraft carrier task forces. Completely new main engines, a reduced number of boilers and an increase in hull length by<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>26</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>allowed them to reach up to 30 knots once again. They were reclassified as &quot;fast battleships,&quot; although their armour and guns still fell short compared to surviving World War Iera battleships in the American or the British navies, with dire consequences during the<space/><link><target>Pacific War</target></link>, when<space/><italics>Hiei</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics><space/>were easily crippled by US gunfire during actions off Guadalcanal, forcing their scuttling shortly afterwards.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breyer, pp. 33940</extension><space/>Perhaps most tellingly,<space/><italics>Hiei</italics><space/>was crippled by medium-caliber gunfire from heavy and light cruisers in a close-range night engagement.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stille, pp. 1920</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There were two exceptions: Turkey's<space/><italics>Yavuz Sultan Selim</italics><space/>and the Royal Navy's<space/><italics>Hood</italics>. The Turkish Navy made only minor improvements to the ship in the interwar period, which primarily focused on repairing wartime damage and the installation of new fire control systems and anti-aircraft batteries.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chesneau, p. 406</extension><space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>was in constant service with the fleet and could not be withdrawn for an extended reconstruction. She received minor improvements over the course of the 1930s, including modern fire control systems, increased numbers of anti-aircraft guns, and in March 1941, radar.<extension extension_name='ref'>Konstam, pp. 3334</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Naval rearmament</heading><paragraph>In the late 1930s navies began to build capital ships again, and during this period a number of large commerce raiders and small, fast battleships were built that are sometimes referred to as battlecruisers. Germany and Russia designed new battlecruisers during this period, though only the latter laid down two of the 35,000-ton<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kronshtadt</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>. They were still on the slipways when the Germans invaded in 1941 and construction was suspended. Both ships were scrapped after the war.<extension extension_name='ref'>McLaughlin 2004, pp. 112, 114</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Germans planned three battlecruisers of the<space/><template><target>sclass2-</target><arg>O</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>as part of the expansion of the<space/><link><target>Kriegsmarine</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Plan Z</target></link>). With six 15-inch guns, high speed, excellent range, but very thin armour, they were intended as commerce raiders. Only one was ordered shortly before World War II; no work was ever done on it. No names were assigned, and they were known by their contract names: 'O', 'P', and 'Q'. The new class was not universally welcomed in the Kriegsmarine. Their abnormally-light protection gained it the derogatory nickname<space/><italics>Ohne Panzer Quatsch</italics><space/>(without armour nonsense) within certain circles of the Navy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Garzke &amp; Dulin, pp. 35354, 363</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Grner, p. 68</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>World War II</heading><paragraph>The Royal Navy deployed some of its battlecruisers during the<space/><link><target>Norwegian Campaign</target></link><space/>in April 1940. The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>German battleship</arg><arg>Gneisenau</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>German battleship</arg><arg>Scharnhorst</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were engaged during the<space/><link><target>Action off Lofoten</target></link><space/>by<space/><italics>Renown</italics><space/>in very bad weather and disengaged after<space/><italics>Gneisenau</italics><space/>was damaged. One of<space/><italics>Renown</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s 15-inch shells passed through<space/><italics>Gneisenau</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s<space/><link><target>List of British ordnance terms#DCT</target><part>director-control tower</part></link><space/>without exploding, severing electrical and communication cables as it went and destroyed the<space/><link><target>rangefinders</target></link><space/>for the forward 150&amp;nbsp;mm (5.9&amp;nbsp;in) turrets. Main-battery fire control had to be shifted aft due to the loss of electrical power. Another shell from<space/><italics>Renown</italics><space/>knocked out<space/><italics>Gneisenau</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s aft turret.<extension extension_name='ref'>Garzke &amp; Dulin, pp. 13536</extension><space/>The British ship was struck twice by German shells that failed to inflict any significant damage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Burt, p. 243</extension><space/>She was the only modernized battlecruiser to survive the war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chesneau, pp. 9, 173</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the early years of the war various German ships had a measure of success hunting merchant ships in the<space/><link><target>Atlantic</target></link>. Allied battlecruisers such as<space/><italics>Renown</italics>,<space/><italics>Repulse</italics>, and the fast battleships<space/><italics>Dunkerque</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French battleship</arg><arg>Strasbourg</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were employed on operations to hunt down the commerce-raiding German ships, but they never got close to their targets. The one stand-up fight occurred when the battleship<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>German battleship</arg><arg>Bismarck</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and the<space/><link><target>heavy cruiser</target></link><space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>German cruiser</arg><arg>Prinz Eugen</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/><link><target>sortie</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>into the North Atlantic to attack British shipping and were intercepted by<space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>and the battleship<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Prince of Wales</arg><arg>53</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in May 1941 in the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Denmark Strait</target></link>. The elderly British battlecruiser was no match for the modern German battleship: within minutes, the<space/><italics>Bismarck</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s 15-inch shells caused a magazine explosion in<space/><italics>Hood</italics><space/>reminiscent of the Battle of Jutland. Only three men survived.<extension extension_name='ref'>Whitley 1998, p. 127</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first battlecruiser to see action in the Pacific War was<space/><italics>Repulse</italics><space/>when<space/><link><target>Sinking of Prince of Wales and Repulse</target><part>she was sunk</part></link><space/>by Japanese<space/><link><target>torpedo bomber</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>north of<space/><link><target>Singapore</target></link><space/>on 10 December 1941 whilst in company with<space/><italics>Prince of Wales</italics>. She was lightly damaged by a single<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>250</arg><arg>kg</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>bomb and near-missed by two others in the first Japanese attack. Her speed and agility enabled her to avoid the other attacks by level bombers and dodge 33 torpedoes. The last group of torpedo bombers attacked from multiple directions and<space/><italics>Repulse</italics><space/>was struck by five torpedoes. She quickly<space/><link><target>capsized</target></link><space/>with the loss of 27 officers and 486 crewmen; 42 officers and 754 enlisted men were rescued by the escorting destroyers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Shores, Cull &amp; Izawa, pp. 11621, 123</extension><space/>The loss of<space/><italics>Repulse</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Prince of Wales</italics><space/>conclusively proved the vulnerability of capital ships to aircraft without air cover of their own.<extension extension_name='ref'>Osborne, pp. 12728</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Japanese<space/><italics>Kong</italics>-class battlecruisers were extensively used as carrier escorts for most of their wartime career due to their high speed. Their World War I-era armament was weaker and their upgraded armour was still thin compared to contemporary battleships. On 13 November 1942, during the<space/><link><target>First Naval Battle of Guadalcanal</target></link>,<space/><italics>Hiei</italics><space/>stumbled across American cruisers and destroyers at<space/><link><target>point-blank range</target></link>. The ship was badly damaged in the encounter and had to be towed by her<space/><link><target>sister ship</target></link><space/><italics>Kirishima</italics>. Both were spotted by American aircraft the following morning and<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics><space/>was forced to cast off her tow because of repeated aerial attacks.<space/><italics>Hiei</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s captain ordered her crew to abandon ship after further damage and<space/><link><target>scuttled</target></link><space/><italics>Hiei</italics><space/>in the early evening of 14 November.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hiei"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.combinedfleet.com/hiei2.htm</arg><arg name="title">IJN Hiei: Tabular Record of Movement</arg><arg name="last1">Hackett</arg><arg name="first1">Bob</arg><arg name="last2">Kingsepp</arg><arg name="first2">Sander</arg><arg name="last3">Ahlberg</arg><arg name="first3">Lars</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Combinedfleet.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>On the night of 14/15 November during the<space/><link><target>Second Naval Battle of Guadalcanal</target></link>,<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics><space/>returned to<space/><link><target>Ironbottom Sound</target></link>, but encountered the American battleships<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>South Dakota</arg><arg>BB-57</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Washington</arg><arg>BB-56</arg><arg>2</arg></template>. While failing to detect<space/><italics>Washington</italics>,<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics><space/>engaged<space/><italics>South Dakota</italics><space/>with some effect.<space/><italics>Washington</italics><space/>opened fire a few minutes later at short range and badly damaged<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics>, knocking out her aft turrets, jamming her rudder, and hitting the ship below the waterline. The flooding proved to be uncontrollable and<space/><italics>Kirishima</italics><space/>capsized three and a half hours later.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kiri"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.combinedfleet.com/Kirishima.htm</arg><arg name="title">IJN Kirishima: Tabular Record of Movement</arg><arg name="last1">Hackett</arg><arg name="first1">Bob</arg><arg name="last2">Kingsepp</arg><arg name="first2">Sander</arg><arg name="last3">Ahlberg</arg><arg name="first3">Lars</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Combinedfleet.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Returning to Japan after the<space/><link><target>Battle of Leyte Gulf</target></link>,<space/><italics>Kong</italics><space/>was torpedoed and sunk by the American submarine<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Sealion II</arg><arg>SS-315</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>on 21 November 1944.<extension extension_name='ref' name="j5"></extension><space/><italics>Haruna</italics><space/>was moored at<space/><link><target>Kure, Hiroshima</target><part>Kure</part></link>, Japan when the<space/><link><target>Bombing of Kure (July 1945)</target><part>naval base was attacked</part></link><space/>by American carrier aircraft on 24 and 28 July. The ship was only lightly damaged by a single bomb hit on 24 July, but was hit a dozen more times on 28 July and sank at her<space/><link><target>pier</target></link>. She was refloated after the war and scrapped in early 1946.<extension extension_name='ref' name="har"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.combinedfleet.com/haruna.htm</arg><arg name="title">IJN Haruna: Tabular Record of Movement</arg><arg name="last1">Hackett</arg><arg name="first1">Bob</arg><arg name="last2">Kingsepp</arg><arg name="first2">Sander</arg><arg name="last3">Ahlberg</arg><arg name="first3">Lars</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Combinedfleet.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Large cruisers or &quot;cruiser killers&quot;</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Uss alaska cb.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>USS</target><arg>Alaska</arg><arg>CB-1</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, one of the<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target></link>'s two &quot;large cruisers&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Alaska-class cruiser</arg><arg>Design 1047 battlecruiser</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A late renaissance in popularity of ships between battleships and cruisers in size occurred on the eve of World War II. Described by some as battlecruisers, but never classified as capital ships, they were variously described as &quot;super cruisers&quot;, &quot;large cruisers&quot; or even &quot;unrestricted cruisers&quot;. The Dutch, American, and Japanese navies all planned these new classes specifically to counter the heavy cruisers, or their counterparts, being built by their naval rivals.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chesneau, p. 388; Garzke &amp; Dulin, p. 86; Friedman 1984, p. 288; McLaughlin 2006, pp. 104</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first such battlecruisers were the Dutch<space/><link><target>Design 1047 battlecruiser</target><part>Design 1047</part></link>, desired to protect their colonies in the<space/><link><target>Dutch East Indies</target><part>East Indies</part></link><space/>in the face of Japanese aggression. Never officially assigned names, these ships were designed with German and Italian assistance. While they broadly resembled the German<space/><italics>Scharnhorst</italics><space/>class and had the same main battery, they would have been more lightly armoured and only protected against eight-inch gunfire. Although the design was mostly completed, work on the vessels never commenced as the Germans overran the Netherlands in May 1940. The first ship would have been laid down in June of that year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Noot, pp. 243, 249, 268</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CB-1 Alaska Outboard Profile.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>350px</part><part>Drawing of the ''Alaska'' class</part></link>The only class of these late battlecruisers actually built were the United States Navy's<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Alaska</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>&quot;large cruisers&quot;. Two of them were completed,<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Alaska</arg><arg>CB-1</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Guam</arg><arg>CB-2</arg><arg>2</arg></template>; a third,<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Hawaii</arg><arg>CB-3</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, was cancelled while under construction and three others, to be named<space/><italics>Philippines</italics>,<space/><italics>Puerto Rico</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Samoa</italics>, were cancelled before they were laid down. They were classified as &quot;large cruisers&quot; instead of battlecruisers, and their status as non-capital ships evidenced by their being named for territories or protectorates. (Battleships, in contrast, were named after states and cruisers after cities). With a main armament of nine 12-inch guns in three triple turrets and a displacement of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>27000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg></template>, the<space/><italics>Alaska</italics>s were twice the size of<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Baltimore</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s and had guns some 50% larger in diameter. They lacked the thick armoured belt and intricate torpedo defence system of true capital ships. However, unlike most battlecruisers, they were considered a balanced design according to cruiser standards as their protection could withstand fire from their own caliber of gun, albeit only in a very narrow range band. They were designed to hunt down Japanese heavy cruisers, though by the time they entered service most Japanese cruisers had been sunk by American aircraft or submarines.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman 1984, pp. 28889, 296, 30102</extension><space/>Like the contemporary<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Iowa</arg><arg>battleship</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>fast battleships, their speed ultimately made them more useful as carrier escorts and bombardment ships than as the surface combatants they were developed to be.<extension extension_name='ref'>Whitley 1995, pp. 27879</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Japanese started designing the B64 class, which was similar to the<space/><italics>Alaska</italics><space/>but with<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>310</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>guns. News of the<space/><italics>Alaska</italics>s led them to upgrade the design, creating the B65. Armed with 356&amp;nbsp;mm guns, the B65's would have been the best armed of the new breed of battlecruisers, but they still would have had only sufficient protection to keep out eight-inch shells. Much like the Dutch, the Japanese got as far as completing the design for the B65s, but never laid them down. By the time the designs were ready the Japanese Navy recognized that they had little use for the vessels and that their priority for construction should lie with aircraft carriers. Like the<space/><italics>Alaska</italics>s, the Japanese did not call these ships battlecruisers, referring to them instead as super-heavy cruisers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jentschura, Jung &amp; Mickel, p. 40</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Garzke &amp; Dulin, pp. 8687</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Cold War-era designs</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Kirov-class battlecruiser.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>''Admiral Lazarev'', formerly ''Frunze'', the second ship of her class of ship</part></link>In spite of the fact that after World War II, most navies abandoned the battleship and battlecruiser concepts,<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target></link>'s fondness for big-gun-armed warships caused the Soviet Union to plan a large cruiser class in the late 1940s. In the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>they were termed &quot;heavy cruisers&quot; (<italics>tjazholyj krejser</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>McLaughlin 2006, p. 104</extension><space/>The fruits of this program were the<space/><link><target>Stalingrad-class battlecruiser</target><part>Project 82 (''Stalingrad'')</part></link><space/>cruisers, of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>36500</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>LT</arg></template><space/>standard load, nine 305&amp;nbsp;mm guns and a speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>35</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. Three ships were laid down in 195152, but they were cancelled in April 1953 after Stalin's death. Only the central armoured hull section of the first ship,<space/><italics>Stalingrad</italics>, was launched in 1954 and then used as a target.<extension extension_name='ref'>McLaughlin 2006, pp. 116, 12122</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Soviet<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kirov</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>is sometimes referenced as a battlecruiser.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gardiner, Chumbley &amp; Budzbon, p. 328</extension><space/>This classification arises from their over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>24000</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>displacement, which is roughly equal to that of a First World War battleship and more than twice the displacement of contemporary cruisers. The<space/><italics>Kirov</italics><space/>class lacks the armour that distinguishes battlecruisers from ordinary cruisers and they are classified as<space/><italics>Tyazholyy Atomnyy Raketny Kreyser</italics><space/>(Heavy Nuclear-powered Missile Cruiser) by Russia. Four members of the class were completed during the 1980s and 1990s, but due to budget constraints only the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian battlecruiser</arg><arg>Petr Velikiy</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>is operational with the<space/><link><target>Russian Navy</target></link>, though plans were announced in 2010 to return the other three ships to service. As of 2012 one ship was being refitted, but the other two ships are reportedly beyond economical repair.<extension extension_name='ref'>Saunders, p. 674</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Battleships</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of battlecruisers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of sunken battlecruisers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Protected cruiser</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armoured cruiser</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">Note</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">20em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bidlingmaier<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Gerhard<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Warship Profile 4<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Windsor, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Profile Publications<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>20229321<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>KM Admiral Graf Spee<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>73–96<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Breyer</arg><arg name="first1">Siegfried</arg><arg name="title">Battleships and Battle Cruisers 1905–1970</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="location">Garden City, New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Doubleday</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-385-07247-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Dreadnought Gunnery at the Battle of Jutland: The Question of Fire Control<space/></arg><arg name="last">Brooks</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge, Frank Cass Publishers</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7146-5702-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brown</arg><arg name="first">David K.</arg><arg name="title">The Grand Fleet: Warship Design and Development 1906–1922</arg><arg name="publisher">Caxton Editions</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="edition">reprint of the 1999</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84067-531-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brown</arg><arg name="first">David K.</arg><arg name="title">Warrior to Dreadnought: Warship Development 1860–1905</arg><arg name="edition">reprint of the 1997</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Caxton Editions</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84067-529-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Burr</arg><arg name="first">Lawrence</arg><arg name="title">British Battlecruisers 1914–1918</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-84603-008-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Burt</arg><arg name="first">R. A.</arg><arg name="title">British Battleships, 1919–1939</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59114-052-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1922–1946</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Chesneau</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Roger</arg><arg name="publisher">Conway Maritime Press</arg><arg name="location">Greenwich, UK</arg><arg name="year">1980</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85177-146-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Churchill</arg><arg name="first">Winston</arg><arg name="authorlink">Winston Churchill<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Second World War: The Gathering Storm</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton Mifflin Company</arg><arg name="location">Boston, Massachusetts</arg><arg name="isbn">0-395-41055-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Evans</arg><arg name="first">David C.</arg><arg name="first2">Mark R.</arg><arg name="last2">Peattie</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="title">Kaigun: Strategy, Tactics, and Technology in the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1887–1941</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87021-192-7</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Friedman</arg><arg name="first">Norman</arg><arg name="authorlink">Norman Friedman</arg><arg name="title">Naval Firepower: Battleship Guns and Gunnery in the Dreadnought Era</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="isbn">1-59114-555-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Friedman</arg><arg name="first">Norman</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Cruisers: An Illustrated Design History</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87021-718-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor">Gardiner, Robert</arg><arg name="title">The Eclipse of the Big Gun: The Warship 1906–45</arg><arg name="origyear">1992</arg><arg name="series">Conway's History of the Ship</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Chartwell Books</arg><arg name="location">Edison, New Jersey</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7858-1414-0</arg><arg name="oclc">51940554</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Gardiner</arg><arg name="first1">Robert</arg><arg name="last2">Chumbley</arg><arg name="first2">Stephen</arg><arg name="last3">Budzbon</arg><arg name="first3">Przemysław</arg><arg name="title">Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships 1947–1995</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="isbn">1-55750-132-7</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor1-last">Gardiner</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Robert</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Gray</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Randal</arg><arg name="title">Conway's All the World's Fighting Ships: 1906–1922</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87021-907-3</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Garzke</arg><arg name="first1">William H.</arg><arg name="last2">Dulin</arg><arg name="first2">Robert O.</arg><arg name="title">Battleships: Axis and Neutral Battleships in World War II</arg><arg name="year">1985</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87021-101-0</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gille</arg><arg name="first">Eric</arg><arg name="title">Cent ans de cuirassés français</arg><arg name="publisher">Marines</arg><arg name="location">Nantes</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="isbn">2-909675-50-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gröner</arg><arg name="first">Erich</arg><arg name="title">German Warships: 1815–1945</arg><arg name="year">1990</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87021-790-9</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Halpern</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul G.</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Naval History of World War I</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-55750-352-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hough<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard</arg><arg name="authorlink">Richard Hough</arg><arg name="title">Dreadnought: A History of the Modern Battleship</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>MacMillan</arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="year">1964</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-02-554420-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jentschura</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Hansgeorg</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Dieter<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Jung</arg><arg name="first3">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Mickel</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1977</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Warships of the Imperial Japanese Navy, 1869–1945</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>United States Naval Institute</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-87021-893-X</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Konstam</arg><arg name="first">Angus</arg><arg name="title">British Battlecruisers 1939–45</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey Books</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84176-633-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Koop</arg><arg name="first1">Gerhard</arg><arg name="last2">Schmolke</arg><arg name="first2">Klaus-Peter</arg><arg name="title">Battleship Scharnhorst</arg><arg name="publisher">Conway Maritime Press</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85177-772-4</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Lambert</arg><arg name="first">Nicholas A.</arg><arg name="date">January 1998</arg><arg name="title">"Our Bloody Ships" or "Our Bloody System"? Jutland and the Loss of the Battle Cruisers, 1916</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Military History</arg><arg name="publisher">Society for Military History</arg><arg name="volume">62</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">29–55</arg><arg name="jstor">120394</arg><arg name="issn">0899-3718</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lambert</arg><arg name="first">Nicholas</arg><arg name="title">Sir John Fisher's Naval Revolution</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">University of South Carolina Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-57003-492-3</arg><arg name="location">Columbia, South Carolina</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert K.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Robert Massie<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[Dreadnought (book)|Dreadnought: Britain, Germany and the Coming of the Great War]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-394-52833-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mackay</arg><arg name="first">Ruddock F.</arg><arg name="title">Fisher of Kilverstone</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="isbn">0198224095</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McLaughlin</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="chapter">Project 69: The Kronshtadt Class Battlecruisers</arg><arg name="editor">Preston, Anthony</arg><arg name="publisher">Conway's Maritime Press</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="title">Warship 2004</arg><arg name="pages">99–117</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85177-948-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">McLaughlin</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="chapter">Project 82: The Stalingrad Class</arg><arg name="editor">Jordan, John</arg><arg name="publisher">Conway</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="title">Warship 2006</arg><arg name="pages">102–123</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84486-030-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Noot<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lt. Jurrien S.<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1980<space/></arg><arg name="title">Battlecruiser: Design Studies for the Royal Netherlands Navy 1939–40<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Warship International<space/></arg><arg name="volume">XVII<space/></arg><arg name="pages">242–273<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[International Naval Research Organization]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Toledo, Ohio</arg><arg name="issn">0043-0374</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Osborne</arg><arg name="first">Eric F.</arg><arg name="title">Cruisers and Battle Cruisers: An Illustrated History of Their Impact</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC CLIO</arg><arg name="location">Santa Barbara, California</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85109-369-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Preston<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Antony<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The World's Worst Warships<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Conway Maritime Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-85177-754-6<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Roberts</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Battlecruisers</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Institute Press</arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="isbn">1-55750-068-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor">Saunders, Stephen</arg><arg name="title">Jane's Fighting Ships 2013–2014</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">IHS Jane's</arg><arg name="location">n.p.</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7106-3048-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Shores</arg><arg name="first1">Christopher</arg><arg name="last2">Cull</arg><arg name="first2">Brian</arg><arg name="last3">Izawa</arg><arg name="first3">Yasuho</arg><arg name="title">Bloody Shambles</arg><arg name="volume">I: The Drift to War to the Fall of Singapore</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">Grub Street</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-948817-50-X</arg><arg name="last-author-amp">y</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Staff</arg><arg name="first">Gary</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="title">German Battlecruisers: 1914–1918</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey Books</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84603-009-3</arg><arg name="oclc">64555761</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Stille</arg><arg name="first">Mark</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="title">Imperial Japanese Navy Battleship 1941–1945</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey Books</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84603-280-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Sondhaus</arg><arg name="first">Lawrence</arg><arg name="title">Naval Warfare, 1815–1914</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-21478-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Sumida</arg><arg name="first">Jon T.</arg><arg name="title">In Defense of Naval Supremacy: Financial Limitation, Technological Innovation and British Naval Policy, 1889–1914</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-04445-104-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Vandervat</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dan</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1988</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Atlantic Campaign</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Harper & Row</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-06-015967-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Whitley<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>M. J.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Battleships of World War Two<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="location">Annapolis, Maryland</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Naval Institute Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-55750-184-X<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Whitley</arg><arg name="first">M. J.</arg><arg name="title">Cruisers of World War Two: An International Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="publisher">Cassell</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">1-86019-874-0</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Battlecruisers</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.maritimequest.com/warship_directory/20th_century_battleship_overview.htm'>Maritimequest Battleships &amp; Battlecruisers of the 20th century</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.worldwar1.co.uk/battlecr.htm'>British and German Battlecruisers of the First World War</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.navsource.org/archives/04idx.htm'>Navsource Online</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Warship types of the 19th &amp; 20th centuries</target></template><template><target>Large cruisers</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Ship types</target></link><link><target>Category:Battlecruisers</target></link></paragraph></article>