<article title='Definable_real_number'><paragraph><template><target>Disputed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><template><target>Original research</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><template><target>Expert-subject</target><arg name="WikiProject">Mathematics</arg><arg name="talk"></arg><arg name="reason">See http://mathoverflow.net/a/44129</arg><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><template><target>No footnotes</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template>A<space/><link><target>real number</target></link><space/><italics>a</italics><space/>is<space/><bold>first-order definable in the language of set theory, without parameters</bold>, if there is a formula<space/><italics></italics><space/>in the language of<space/><link><target>set theory</target></link>, with one<space/><link><target>free variable</target></link>, such that<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>is the unique real number such that<space/><italics>(a)</italics><space/>holds in the standard model of set theory (see Kunen 1980:153).<space/></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>For the purposes of this article, such reals will be called simply<space/><bold><italics>definable numbers</italics></bold>. This should not be understood to be standard terminology.</paragraph><paragraph>Note that this definition cannot be expressed in the language of set theory itself.</paragraph><heading level='2'>General facts</heading><paragraph>Assuming they form a set, the definable numbers form a<space/><link><target>field (mathematics)</target><part>field</part></link><space/>containing all the familiar real numbers such as<space/><link><target>Zero</target><part>0</part></link>,<space/><link><target>One</target><part>1</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Pi</target><part><template><target>pi</target></template></part></link>,<space/><link><target>E_(mathematical_constant)</target><part>''e''</part></link>, et cetera. In particular, this field contains all the numbers named in the<space/><link><target>mathematical constant</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>article, and all<space/><link><target>algebraic number</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(and therefore all<space/><link><target>rational number</target><trail>s</trail></link>). However, most real numbers are not definable: the<space/><link><target>Set (mathematics)</target><part>set</part></link><space/>of all definable numbers is<space/><link><target>countably infinite</target></link><space/>(because the set of all logical formulas is) while the set of real numbers is<space/><link><target>uncountable set</target><part>uncountably infinite</part></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>Cantor's diagonal argument</target></link>). As a result,<space/><link><target>almost all</target><part>most</part></link><space/>real numbers have no description (in the same sense of &quot;most&quot; as 'most real numbers are not rational').</paragraph><paragraph>The field of definable numbers is not<space/><link><target>complete space</target><part>complete</part></link>; there exist<space/><link><target>Cauchy sequence</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of definable numbers whose<space/><link><target>limit of a sequence</target><part>limit</part></link><space/>is not definable (since every real number is the limit of a sequence of rational numbers). However, if the sequence itself is definable in the sense that we can specify a single formula for all its terms, then its limit will necessarily be a definable number.</paragraph><paragraph>While every<space/><link><target>computable number</target></link><space/>is definable, the converse is not true: the numeric representations of the<space/><link><target>Halting problem</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chaitin's constant</target></link>, the truth set of first order arithmetic, and<space/><link><target>Zero sharp</target><part>0<xhtml:sup><list type='numbered'><listitem></listitem></list></xhtml:sup></part></link><space/>are examples of numbers that are definable but not computable. Many other such numbers are known.</paragraph><paragraph>One may also wish to talk about definable<space/><link><target>complex number</target><trail>s</trail></link>: complex numbers which are uniquely defined by a logical formula. However, whether this is possible depends on how the field of complex numbers is derived in the first place: it may not be possible to distinguish a complex number from its conjugate (say, 3+i from 3-i), since it is impossible to find a property of one that is not also a property of the other, without falling back on the underlying set-theoretic definition. Assuming we can define at least one nonreal complex number, however, a<space/><link><target>complex number</target></link><space/>is definable if and only if both its real part and its imaginary part are definable. The definable complex numbers also form a field if they form a set.</paragraph><paragraph>The related concept of &quot;standard&quot; numbers, which can only be defined within a finite time and space, is used to motivate axiomatic<space/><link><target>internal set theory</target></link>, and provide a workable formulation for<space/><link><target>illimited number</target><part>illimited</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>infinitesimal number</target></link>. Definitions of the hyper-real line within<space/><link><target>non-standard analysis</target></link><space/>(the subject area dealing with such numbers) overwhelmingly include the usual, uncountable set of real numbers as a subset.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notion does not exhaust &quot;unambiguously described&quot; numbers</heading><paragraph>Not every number that we would informally say has been unambiguously described, is definable in the above sense. For example, if we can enumerate all such definable numbers by the<space/><link><target>Gdel number</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of their defining formulas then we can use<space/><link><target>Cantor's diagonal argument</target></link><space/>to find a particular real that is not first-order definable in the same language. The argument can be made as follows:</paragraph><paragraph>Suppose that in a mathematical language L, it is possible to enumerate all of the defined numbers in L. Let this enumeration be defined by the function G: W R, where G(n) is the real number described by the nth description in the sequence. Using the diagonal argument, it is possible to define a real number x, which is not equal to G(n) for any n. This means that there is a language L' that defines x, which is undefinable in L.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Other notions of definability</heading><paragraph>The notion of definability treated in this article has been chosen primarily for definiteness, not on the grounds that it's more useful or interesting than other notions. Here we treat a few others:</paragraph><heading level='3'>Definability in other languages or structures</heading><heading level='4'>Language of arithmetic</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>language of arithmetic</target></link><space/>has symbols for 0, 1, the successor operation, addition, and multiplication, intended to be interpreted in the usual way over the<space/><link><target>natural number</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Since no variables of this language range over the<space/><link><target>real number</target><trail>s</trail></link>, we cannot simply copy the earlier definition of definability. Rather, we say that a real<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>is<space/><bold><italics>definable in the language of arithmetic</italics></bold><space/>(or<space/><bold><italics><link><target>arithmetical hierarchy</target><part>arithmetical</part></link></italics></bold>) if its<space/><link><target>Dedekind cut</target></link><space/>can be defined as a<space/><link><target>Predicate (logic)</target><part>predicate</part></link><space/>in that language; that is, if there is a first-order formula<space/><italics></italics><space/>in the language of arithmetic, with two free variables, such that</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&lt;math&gt;\forall m \, \forall n \, (\varphi(n,m)\iff\frac{n}{m}&lt;a).&lt;/math&gt;</listitem></list><heading level='4'>2nd-order language of arithmetic</heading><paragraph>The second-order language of arithmetic is the same as the first-order language, except that variables and quantifiers are allowed to range over sets of naturals. A real that is second-order definable in the language of arithmetic is called<space/><bold><italics><link><target>analytical hierarchy</target><part>analytical</part></link></italics></bold>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Definability with ordinal parameters</heading><paragraph>Sometimes it is of interest to consider definability<space/><italics>with parameters</italics>; that is, to give a definition relative to another object that remains undefined. For example, a real<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>(or for that matter, any set<space/><italics>a</italics>) is called<space/><bold><italics>ordinal definable</italics></bold><space/>if there is a first-order formula<space/><italics></italics><space/>in the language of set theory, with<space/><italics>two</italics><space/>free variables, and an<space/><link><target>Ordinal number</target><part>ordinal</part></link><space/>, such that<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>is the unique object such that<space/><italics></italics>(<italics>a</italics>,) holds (in V).</paragraph><paragraph>The other sorts of definability thus far considered have only countably many defining formulas, and therefore allow only countably many definable reals. This is not true for ordinal definability, because an ordinal definable real is defined not only by the formula<space/><italics></italics>, but also by the ordinal . In fact it is consistent with<space/><link><target>ZFC</target></link><space/>that<space/><italics>all</italics><space/>reals are ordinal-definable, and therefore that there are uncountably many ordinal-definable reals. However it is also consistent with ZFC that there are only countably many ordinal-definable reals.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Berry paradox</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Computable number</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Constructible number</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Constructible universe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entscheidungsproblem</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Kunen<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Kenneth<space/></arg><arg name="author1-link">Kenneth Kunen<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[Set Theory: An Introduction to Independence Proofs]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">North-Holland<space/></arg><arg name="location">Amsterdam<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-444-85401-8<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>	<space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://rothkamm.com/download.cfm/turing/Turing.pdf'>Alan Turing, &quot;On Computable Numbers, With An Application to the Entscheidungsproblem&quot;, ''Proceedings of the London Mathematical Society'', 1936</link><space/>(<link><target>Alan Turing</target><part>Turing's</part></link><space/>original paper distinguishing computable and definable numbers)</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Set theory</target></link></paragraph></article>