<article title='Books_of_Samuel'><paragraph><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Nevi'im</arg><arg>historical</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The two<space/><bold>Books of Samuel</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-he</target><arg>''Sefer Shmuel'' ספר שמואל</arg></template>) are part of the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link>, a series of books (<link><target>Book of Joshua</target><part>Joshua</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link>, Samuel and<space/><link><target>Books of Kings</target><part>Kings</part></link>) in the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link>/<link><target>Old Testament</target></link><space/>that constitute a theological history of the<space/><link><target>Israelites</target></link><space/>which explains<space/><link><target>Torah</target><part>God's law for Israel</part></link><space/>under the guidance of the prophets.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gordon</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="p">18</arg></template><space/>According to Jewish tradition the book was written by Samuel, with additions by the prophets Gad and Nathan;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>1</arg><arg>Chronicles</arg><arg>29:29</arg><arg>9</arg></template></extension><space/>modern scholarly thinking is that the entire history (called the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link>) was composed in the period c.630540&amp;nbsp;BCE by combining a number of independent texts of various ages.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knight</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">62</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">197</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Samuel begins with the prophet<space/><link><target>Samuel</target></link>'s birth and<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target><part>God</part></link>'s call to him as a boy. The story of the<space/><link><target>Ark of the Covenant</target></link><space/>that follows tells of Israel's oppression by the<space/><link><target>Philistines</target></link>, which brought about Samuel's anointing of<space/><link><target>Saul</target></link><space/>as Israel's first king. But Saul proved unworthy and God's choice turned to<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, who defeated Israel's enemies and brought the Ark to Jerusalem. God then promised David and his successors an everlasting dynasty.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Spieckerman</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">348</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Naming conventions</heading><paragraph>What it is now commonly known as<space/><bold>1 Samuel</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>2 Samuel</bold><space/>are called by<space/><link><target>the Vulgate</target></link>, in imitation of the<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target></link>,<space/><bold>1 Kings</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>2 Kings</bold><space/>respectively.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>To avoid confusion, the designation "First and Second Books of Samuel" is adopted by Catholic writers when referring to the Hebrew text, otherwise "First and Second Books of Kings" is commonly used. The testimony of Origen, St. Jerome, etc., confirmed by the Massoretic summary appended to the second book, as well as by the Hebrew MSS., shows that the two books originally but one, entitled "Samuel". This title was chosen not only because Samuel is the principal figure in the first part, but probably also because, by having been instrumental in the establishment of the kingdom and in the selection of Saul and David as kings, he may be said to have been a determining factor in the history of the whole period comprised by the book. The division into two books was first introduced into the Septuagint, to conform to the shorter and more convenient size of scrolls in vogue among the Greeks. The Book of Kings was divided at the same time, and the four books, being considered as a consecutive history of the Kingdoms of Israel and Juda, were named "Books of the Kingdoms" (Basileiôn biblía). St. Jerome retained the division into four books, which from the Septuagint had passed into the Itala, or old Latin translation, but changed the name "Books of the Kingdoms" (Libri Regnorum) into "Books of the Kings" (Libri Regum). The Hebrew text of the Books of Samuel and of the Books of Kings was first divided in Bomberg's edition of the rabbinical Bible (Venice, 1516-17), the individual books being distinguished as I B. of Samuel and II B. of Samuel, I B. of Kings and II B. of Kings. This nomenclature was adopted in the subsequent editions of the Hebrew Bible and in the Protestant translations, and thus became current among nonCatholics.<ref>[Catholic Encyclopedia (1913) First and Second Books of Kings called in our days as First and Second of Samuel https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Catholic_Encyclopedia_%281913%29/First_and_Second_Books_of_Kings]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Then, what it is now commonly known as<space/><bold>1 Kings</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>2 Kings</bold><space/>would be<space/><bold>3 Kings</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>4 Kings</bold><space/>in old Bibles before the year 1516 such as the Vulgate and the Septuagint respectively.<extension extension_name='ref'>[Catholic Encyclopedia (1913) Third and Fourth Books of Kings called in our days as First and Second of Kings https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Catholic_Encyclopedia_%281913%29/Third_and_Fourth_Books_of_Kings]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It's from 1517 when is began using the division we know now today used by Protestant Bibles and adopted by Catholics. Some Bibles still preserve the old denomination, for example,<space/><link><target>Douay Rheims bible</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>[Douay Rheims bible http://www.drbo.org/]</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contents</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ernst Josephson. - David och Saul.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Ernst Josephson</target></link>, ''David and Saul'', 1878.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The childless<space/><link><target>Hannah (Bible)</target><part>Hannah</part></link><space/>vows to<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target><part>Yahweh of hosts</part></link><space/>that if she has a son, he will be dedicated to him.<space/><link><target>Eli (Bible)</target><part>Eli</part></link>, the priest of<space/><link><target>Shiloh (biblical city)</target><part>Shiloh</part></link><space/>(where the<space/><link><target>ark of the covenant</target></link><space/>is located), blesses her, and a child named<space/><link><target>Samuel (Bible)</target><part>Samuel</part></link><space/>is born. Samuel is dedicated to the Lord as a<space/><link><target>Nazirite</target></link><space/>- the only one beside<space/><link><target>Samson</target></link><space/>to be identified in the Bible. Eli's sons, Hophni and Phinehas, prove unworthy of the priesthood and are killed in battle, but the child Samuel grows up &quot;in the presence of the Lord.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>The Philistines capture the<space/><link><target>Ark of the Covenant</target></link><space/>from Shiloh and take it to the temple of their god<space/><link><target>Dagon</target></link>, who recognises the supremacy of Yahweh. The Philistines are afflicted with plagues and return the ark to the Israelites, but to the territory of the tribe of Benjamin rather than to Shiloh. The Philistines attack the Israelites gathered at<space/><link><target>Mizpah in Gilead (Judges)</target><part>Mizpah</part></link><space/>in Benjamin. Samuel appeals to Yahweh, the Philistines are decisively beaten, and the Israelites reclaim their lost territory.</paragraph><paragraph>In Samuel's old age, he appoints his sons as judges, but they are unworthy, and so the people clamour for a king. God reluctantly accedes and gives them<space/><link><target>Saul</target></link><space/>of the tribe of Benjamin. Saul defeats the enemies of the Israelites, but sins against Yahweh.</paragraph><paragraph>Yahweh tells Samuel to anoint<space/><link><target>David</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Bethlehem</target></link><space/>as king, and David enters Saul's court as his armour-bearer and harpist. Saul's son and heir Jonathan befriends David and recognises him as rightful king. Saul plots David's death, but David flees into the wilderness, where he becomes a champion of the Hebrews. David joins the Philistines, but continues secretly to champion his own people, until Saul and Jonathan are killed in battle. At this point, David offers a majestic eulogy, where he praises the bravery and magnificence of both his friend Jonathan and King Saul.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Samuel</arg><arg>1:17-27</arg><arg>9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The elders of Judah anoint David as king, but in the north Saul's son Ishbaal rules over the northern tribes. After a long war Ishbaal is murdered by two of his captains who hope for a reward from David; but David has them killed for killing God's anointed. David is then anointed King of all Israel. David captures Jerusalem and brings the Ark there. David wishes to build a temple, but<space/><link><target>Nathan (Prophet)</target><part>Nathan</part></link><space/>tells him that one of David's sons will be the one to build the temple. David defeats the enemies of Israel, slaughtering Philistines,<space/><link><target>Moab</target><trail>ites</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Edom</target><trail>ites</trail></link>, Syrians and<space/><link><target>Arameans</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>David commits adultery with<space/><link><target>Bathsheba</target></link><space/>and plots the death of her husband; for this<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link><space/>sends disasters against his house. The prophet Nathan tells David that the sword shall never depart from his house. For the remainder of his reign there are problems: one of his sons rapes one of his daughters, another son kills the first, his favourite son rebels and is killed, until finally only two contenders for the succession remain, one of them Bathsheba's son<space/><link><target>Solomon</target></link>.<space/><link><target>1 Kings</target></link><space/>then relates how, as David lies dying, Bathsheba and the prophet<space/><link><target>Nathan (prophet)</target><part>Nathan</part></link><space/>ensure Solomon's elevation to the throne.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:David and Bathsheba by Artemisia Gentileschi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>255px</part><part>''David and Bathsheba'', by<space/><link><target>Artemisia Gentileschi</target></link>. David is in the background, standing on a balcony.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Versions</heading><paragraph>1 and 2 Samuel were originally (and still are in some Jewish bibles) a single book, but<space/><link><target>Septuagint</target><part>the first Greek translation</part></link>, produced around the second century BCE, divided it into two; this was adopted by the Latin translation used in the early Christian church of the West, and finally introduced into Jewish bibles around the early 16th century.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gordon</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="p">19-20</arg></template><space/>The modern Hebrew text (called the<space/><link><target>Masoretic text</target></link>) differs considerably from the Greek, and scholars are still working at finding the best solutions to the many problems this presents.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bergen</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">25-27</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authorship and date of composition</heading><paragraph>According to passages 14b and 15a of the<space/><link><target>Bava Basra</target></link><space/>tractate of the<space/><link><target>Talmud</target></link>, the book was written by Samuel up until 1 Samuel 25, which notes the death of Samuel, and the remainder by the prophets Gad and Nathan. Critical scholars from the 19th century onward have rejected this idea.<space/><link><target>Martin Noth</target></link><space/>in 1943 theorized that Samuel was composed by a single author as part of a history of Israel: the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link>, made up of (<link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Joshua</target><part>Joshua</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Judges</target><part>Judges</part></link>, Samuel and<space/><link><target>Books of Kings</target><part>Kings</part></link>).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Klein</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">316</arg></template><space/>Although Noth's belief that the entire history was composed by a single individual has been largely abandoned, his theory in its broad outline has been adopted by most scholars.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Tsumura</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">15-19</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The most common view today is that an early version of the history was composed in the time of king<space/><link><target>Hezekiah</target></link><space/>(8th century BCE); the bulk of the first edition dates from his grandson<space/><link><target>Josiah</target></link><space/>at the end of the 7th, with further sections added during the<space/><link><target>Babylonian exile</target></link><space/>(6th century) and the work substantially complete by about 550 BCE.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walton</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">41-42</arg></template><space/>Further editing was apparently done even after then: for example, the silver quarter-shekel which Saul's servant offers to Samuel in 1 Samuel 9 almost certainly fixes the date of this story in the Persian or Hellenistic periods.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Auld</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">219</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The 6th century authors and editors responsible for the bulk of the history drew on many earlier sources, including (but not limited to) an &quot;ark narrative&quot; (1 Samuel 4:17:1 and perhaps part of 2 Samuel 6), a &quot;Saul cycle&quot; (parts of 1 Samuel 9-11 and 1314), the &quot;history of David's rise&quot; (1 Samuel 16:14-2 Samuel 5:10), and the &quot;succession narrative&quot; (2 Samuel 920 and 1 Kings 12).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knight</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">853</arg></template><space/>The oldest of these, the &quot;ark narrative,&quot; may even predate the Davidic era.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Tsumura</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sources</heading><paragraph>The sources used to construct 1 &amp; 2 Samuel are believed to include the following:<extension extension_name='ref'>Jones, pp.197199</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Call of Samuel</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>Youth of Samuel</italics><space/>(1 Samuel 17): From Samuel's birth his career as Judge and prophet over Israel. This source includes the<space/><italics>Eli narrative</italics><space/>and part of the ark narrative.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">210-211</arg></template></listitem><listitem><italics>Ark narrative</italics><space/>(1 Samuel 4:1b-7:1 and 2 Samuel 6:120): the ark's capture by the Philistines in the time of Eli and its transfer to Jerusalem by David opinion is divided over whether this is actually an independent unit.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Eynikel</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">88</arg></template></listitem><listitem><italics>Jerusalem source</italics>: a fairly brief source discussing David conquering Jerusalem from the<space/><link><target>Jebusite</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics>Republican source</italics>: a source with an anti-monarchial bias. This source first describes Samuel as decisively ridding the people of the Philistines, and begrudgingly appointing an individual chosen by God to be king, namely Saul. David is described as someone renowned for his skill at playing the harp, and consequently summoned to Saul's court to calm his moods. Saul's son Jonathan becomes friends with David, which<space/><link><target>David and Jonathan</target><part>some commentators view as romantic</part></link>, and later acts as his protector against Saul's more violent intentions. At a later point, having been deserted by God on the eve of battle, Saul consults a<space/><link><target>Mediumship</target><part>medium</part></link><space/>at Endor, only to be condemned for doing so by Samuel's ghost, and told he and his sons will be killed. David is heartbroken on discovering the death of Jonathan, tearing his clothes as a gesture of grief.</listitem><listitem><italics>Monarchial source</italics>: a source with a pro-monarchial bias and covering many of the same details as the<space/><italics>republican source</italics>. This source begins with the divinely appointed birth of Samuel. It then describes Saul as leading a war against the Ammonites, being chosen by the people to be king, and leading them against the Philistines. David is described as a shepherd boy arriving at the battlefield to aid his brothers, and is overheard by Saul, leading to David challenging Goliath and defeating the Philistines. David's warrior credentials lead to women falling in love with him, including Michal, Saul's daughter, who later acts to protect David against Saul. David eventually gains two new wives as a result of threatening to raid a village, and Michal is redistributed to another husband. At a later point, David finds himself seeking sanctuary amongst the Philistine army and facing the Israelites as an enemy. David is incensed that anyone should have killed Saul, even as an act of mercy, since Saul was anointed by Samuel, and has the individual responsible killed.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Court History of David</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics>Succession narrative</italics><space/>(2 Samuel 920 and 1 Kings 12): a &quot;historical novel&quot;, in<space/><link><target>Alberto Soggin</target></link>'s phrase, telling the story of David's reign from his affair with<space/><link><target>Bathsheba</target></link><space/>to his death. The theme is of retribution: David's sin against<space/><link><target>Uriah the Hittite</target></link><space/>is punished by God through the destruction of his own family,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">216-217</arg></template><space/>and its purpose is to serve as an apology for the coronation of Bathsheba's son<space/><link><target>Solomon</target></link><space/>instead of his older brother<space/><link><target>Adonijah</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Klein</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">316</arg></template><space/>Some textual critics have posited that given the intimacy and precision of certain narrative details, the Court Historian may have been an eyewitness to some of the events he describes, or at the very least enjoyed access to the archives and battle reports of the royal house of David.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirsch"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kirsch</arg><arg name="first">Jonathan</arg><arg name="title">King David: The Real Life of the Man Who Ruled Israel</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House LLC</arg><arg name="isbn">9780307567819</arg><arg name="pages">307–309</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem><italics>Redactions</italics>: additions by the redactor to harmonize the sources together; many of the uncertain passages may be part of this editing.</listitem><listitem><italics>Various</italics>: several short sources, none of which have much connection to each other, and are fairly independent of the rest of the text. Many are poems or pure lists.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hannah VICTORS, Jan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Hannah (Bible)</target><part>Hannah</part></link><space/>presenting<space/><link><target>Samuel (Biblical figure)</target><part>Samuel</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Eli (Bible)</target><part>Eli</part></link>, by<space/><link><target>Jan Victors</target></link>, 1645.</part></link>The Book of Samuel is a theological evaluation of kingship in general and of dynastic kingship and<space/><link><target>David</target></link><space/>in particular.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Klein</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">312</arg></template><space/>The main themes of the book are introduced in the opening poem (the &quot;<link><target>Song of Hannah</target></link>&quot;): (1), the sovereignty of<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, God of Israel; (2), the reversal of human fortunes; and (3), kingship.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Tsumura</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">68</arg></template><space/>These themes are played out in the stories of the three main characters,<space/><link><target>Samuel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saul</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Samuel</heading><paragraph>Samuel answers the description of the &quot;prophet like Moses&quot; predicted in Deuteronomy 18:1522: like Moses, he has direct contact with<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, the God of the<space/><link><target>Israelites</target></link>, acts as a judge, and is a perfect leader who never makes mistakes.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Beytenbrach</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">53-55</arg></template><space/>Samuel's successful defence of the Israelites against their enemies demonstrates that they have no need for a king (who will, moreover, introduce inequality), yet despite this the people demand a king. But the king they are given is Yahweh's gift, and Samuel explains that kingship can be a blessing rather than a curse if they remain faithful to their God. On the other hand, total destruction of both king and people will result if they turn to wickedness.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Klein</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">316</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Saul</heading><paragraph>Saul is the chosen one, a king appointed by Yahweh, and anointed by Samuel, Yahweh's prophet, and yet he is ultimately rejected.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hertzberg</arg><arg>1964</arg><arg name="p">19</arg></template><space/>Saul has two faults which make him unfit for the office of king: he carries out a sacrifice in place of Samuel (1 Samuel 13:814), and he fails to complete the genocide of the<space/><link><target>Amalekites</target></link><space/>as God has ordered (1 Samuel 15).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Klein</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">319</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>David</heading><paragraph>One of the main units within Samuel is the &quot;History of David's Rise&quot;, the purpose of which is to justify David as the legitimate successor to Saul.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Dick</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">3-4</arg></template><space/>The narrative stresses that he gained the throne lawfully, always respecting &quot;the Lord's anointed&quot; (i.e. Saul) and never taking any of his numerous chances to seize the throne by violence.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">198</arg></template><space/>As God's chosen king over Israel David is also the son of God (&quot;I will be a father to him, and he shall be a son to me...&quot; 2 Samuel 7:14).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">216, 229-233</arg></template><space/>God enters into an eternal covenant (treaty) with David and his line, promising divine protection of the dynasty and of Jerusalem through all time.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coogan</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">425</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>David and Jonathan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biblical judges</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Midrash Shmuel (aggadah)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Bible and history</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of ancient Israel and Judah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kingdom of Judah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kingdom of Israel (Samaria)</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>4</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><heading level='3'>Translations of 1 and 2 Samuel</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/quicksearch/?quicksearch=samuel&amp;amp;qs_version=31'>Samuel 1 and 2 at Bible Gateway</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Commentaries on Samuel</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/bible_cdo/aid/15830/showrashi/true'>Shmuel I Samuel I (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/bible_cdo/aid/15861/showrashi/true'>Shmuel II Samuel II (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Auld</arg><arg name="first">Graeme</arg><arg name="chapter">1 & 2 Samuel</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson</arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802837110</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Bergen</arg><arg name="first">David T.</arg><arg name="title">1, 2 Samuel</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="publisher">B&H Publishing Group</arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="isbn">9780805401073</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Gordon</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="title">I & II Samuel, A Commentary</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Paternoster Press</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="isbn">9780310230229</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Hertzberg</arg><arg name="first">Hans Wilhelm</arg><arg name="title">I & II Samuel, A Commentary</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1964</arg><arg name="edition">trans. from German 2nd edition 1960</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0664223182</arg><arg name="page">19</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Tsumura</arg><arg name="first">David Toshio</arg><arg name="title">The First book of Samuel</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802823595</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>General</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Breytenbach</arg><arg name="first">Andries</arg><arg name="title">Past, present, future: the Deuteronomistic history and the prophets</arg><arg name="publisher">Brill</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="chapter">Who Is Behind The Samuel Narrative?</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy</arg><arg name="isbn">9789004118713</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Coogan, Michael D. (2009)<space/><italics>A Brief Introduction to the Old Testament: the Hebrew Bible in its Context</italics><space/>Oxford University Press</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Dick</arg><arg name="first">Michael B</arg><arg name="chapter">The History of "David's Rise to Power" and the Neo-Babylonian Succession Apologies</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Bernard Frank Batto and Kathryn L. Roberts</arg><arg name="title">David and Zion: biblical studies in honor of J.J.M. Roberts</arg><arg name="publisher">Eisenbrauns</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">9781575060927</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Eynikel</arg><arg name="first">Erik</arg><arg name="title">Past, present, future: the Deuteronomistic history and the prophets</arg><arg name="publisher">Brill</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="chapter">The Relation Between the Eli Narrative and the Ark Narratives</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy</arg><arg name="isbn">9789004118713</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Halpern</arg><arg name="first">Baruch</arg><arg name="title">David's secret demons: messiah, murderer, traitor, king</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802827975</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Jones</arg><arg name="first">Gwilym H</arg><arg name="chapter">1 and 2 Samuel</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">John Barton and John Muddiman</arg><arg name="title">The Oxford Bible Commentary</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">9780198755005</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Klein</arg><arg name="first">R.W.</arg><arg name="chapter">Samuel, books of</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Bromiley, Geoffrey W</arg><arg name="title">The international standard Bible encyclopedia</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">9780802837844</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen and Kent Harold Richards</arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter 4 Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation</arg><arg name="publisher">T&T Clark</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">9780567292896</arg><arg name="page">62</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A</arg><arg name="chapter">Sources</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Watson E. Mills, Roger Aubrey Bullard</arg><arg name="title">Mercer Dictionary of the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Mercer University Press</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="isbn">9780865543737</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Schleffer</arg><arg name="first">Eben</arg><arg name="title">Past, present, future: the Deuteronomistic history and the prophets</arg><arg name="publisher">Brill</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="chapter">Saving Saul from the Deuteronomist</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Johannes Cornelis de Moor and H.F. Van Rooy</arg><arg name="isbn">9789004118713</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Soggin</arg><arg name="first">Alberto</arg><arg name="title">Introduction to the Old Testament</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9780664221560</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Spieckerman</arg><arg name="first">Hermann</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Leo G. Perdue</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell companion to the Hebrew Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">9780631210719</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Van Seters</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">In search of history: historiography in the ancient world and the origins of biblical history</arg><arg name="publisher">Eisenbrauns</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9781575060132</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Walton</arg><arg name="first">John H</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Andrew E. Hill, John H. Walton</arg><arg name="title">A Survey of the Old Testament</arg><arg name="publisher">Zondervan</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="isbn">9780631210719</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>1 Samuel</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>2 Samuel</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Books of Samuel</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>Masoretic Text</target></link></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt08a01.htm'><space/>''Shmuel Aleph'' Samuel A</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt08b01.htm'><space/>''Shmuel Bet'' Samuel B</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Jewish translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et08a01.htm'>1 Samuel at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society translation)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et08b01.htm'>2 Samuel at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society translation)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Related articles</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ibs.org/niv/studybible/1samuel.php'>Introduction to the book of 1 Samuel</link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>NIV Study Bible</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ibs.org/niv/studybible/2samuel.php'>Introduction to the book of 2 Samuel</link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>NIV Study Bible</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblestudytools.com/1-samuel/1.html'>1 Samuel</link><space/>at BibleStudyTools.com</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblestudytools.com/1-samuel/2.html'>2 Samuel</link><space/>at BibleStudyTools.com</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Nevi'im|History books]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Judges|Judges]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>1<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Books of Kings|Kings]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Ruth|Ruth]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>1<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Samuel, Books Of</target></template><link><target>Category:Nevi'im</target></link><link><target>Category:Year of work unknown</target></link><link><target>Category:Books of Samuel</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>