<article title='Albert%2C_Duke_of_Prussia'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Albert of Prussia</arg><arg>the 19th-century prince</arg><arg>Prince Albert of Prussia (1809–1872)</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="{{One source|date">February 2012}}
{{More footnotes|date</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>infobox royalty</target><arg name="name"><space/>Albert
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights<br />Duke of Prussia
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Lucas Cranach d.Ä. - Bildnis des Markgrafen Albrecht von Brandenburg-Ansbach (Herzog Anton Ulrich-Museum).jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Albert of Prussia, painting by [[Lucas Cranach the Elder]], dated 1528
</arg><arg name="succession1"><space/>[[Grand Masters of the Teutonic Knights|Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights]]
</arg><arg name="reign1"><space/>1510–1525
</arg><arg name="predecessor1"><space/>[[Duke Frederick of Saxony]]
</arg><arg name="successor1"><space/>[[Walter von Cronberg]]
</arg><arg name="succession2"><space/>[[Duke of Prussia]]
</arg><arg name="reign2"><space/>1525–1568
</arg><arg name="predecessor2"><space/>none (new creation)
</arg><arg name="successor2"><space/>[[Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia|Albert Frederick of Prussia]]
</arg><arg name="royal house"><space/>[[House of Hohenzollern]]
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Frederick I, Margrave of Brandenburg-Ansbach|Frederick I of Brandenburg-Ansbach]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>[[Sophia of Poland]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Dorothea of Denmark, Duchess of Prussia|Dorothea of Denmark]]<space/><br/><space/>[[Anna Marie of Brunswick-Lüneburg]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>[[Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia|Albert Frederick]]<space/><br/><space/>Others
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Roman Catholicism]], then [[Lutheranism]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1490|5|17|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Ansbach]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1568|3|20|1490|7|8|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>Tapiau Castle in Tapiau ([[Gvardeysk]])
</arg></template><bold>Albert of Prussia</bold><space/>(17 May 1490 20 March 1568) was the last<space/><link><target>Grand Masters of the Teutonic Knights</target><part>Grand Master</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Knights</target></link>, who after converting to<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target></link>, became the first monarch of the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Prussia</target></link>, the secularized state that emerged from the former<space/><link><target>Monastic State of the Teutonic Knights</target></link>. Albert was the first European ruler to establish Lutheranism, and thus<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target></link>, as the official<space/><link><target>state religion</target></link><space/>of his lands. He proved instrumental in the political spread of Protestantism in its early stage, ruling the Prussian lands for nearly six decades (15101568).</paragraph><paragraph>A member of the<space/><link><target>Principality of Ansbach</target><part>Brandenburg-Ansbach</part></link><space/>branch of the<space/><link><target>House of Hohenzollern</target></link>, Albert's election as Grand Master had brought about hopes of a reversal of the declining fortune of the Teutonic Knights. He was a skilled political administrator and leader, and did indeed reverse the decline of the Teutonic Order. However, Albert, who was sympathetic to the demands of<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link>, rebelled against the<space/><link><target>Catholic church</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target></link><space/>by converting the Teutonic state into a Protestant and hereditary realm, the Duchy of Prussia, for which he did homage to his uncle, the<space/><link><target>Sigismund I the Old</target><part>King of Poland</part></link>. The arrangement was confirmed by the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Krakw</target></link><space/>in 1525. Albert pledged a personal oath to the King and in return was invested with the duchy for himself and his heirs.</paragraph><paragraph>Albert's rule in Prussia was fairly prosperous. Although he had some trouble with the peasantry, the confiscation of the lands and treasures of the Catholic church enabled him to propitiate the nobles and provide for the expenses of the newly established Prussian court. He was active in imperial politics, joining the<space/><link><target>League of Torgau</target></link><space/>in 1526, and acted in unison with the Protestants in plotting to overthrow Emperor<space/><link><target>Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Charles V</part></link><space/>after the issue of the<space/><link><target>Augsburg Interim</target></link><space/>in May 1548. Albert established schools in every town and founded<space/><link><target>Knigsberg University</target></link><space/>in 1544. He promoted culture and arts, patronising the works of<space/><link><target>Erasmus Reinhold</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Caspar Hennenberger</target></link>. Albert's final years were clouded by peasant resentment of heavy taxes, a step he felt compelled to take due to there no longer being any church land available to confiscate in Prussia. The intrigues of court favourites,<space/><link><target>Johann Funck</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Paul Skali</target></link><space/>also caused various religious and political disputes. Albert spent his final years virtually deprived of power, and died at<space/><link><target>Tapiau</target></link><space/>on 20 March 1568. His son<space/><link><target>Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia</target><part>Albert Frederick</part></link><space/>succeeded him as Duke of Prussia.</paragraph><paragraph>Albert's dissolution of the Teutonic State caused the founding of the Duchy of Prussia, paving the way for the rise of the House of Hohenzollern. He is therefore often seen as the father of the Prussian nation, and even as indirectly responsible for the<space/><link><target>unification of Germany</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life</heading><paragraph>Albert was born in<space/><link><target>Ansbach</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Franconia</target></link><space/>as the third son of<space/><link><target>Frederick I, Margrave of Brandenburg-Ansbach</target></link>. His mother was<space/><link><target>Sophia of Poland</target><part>Sophia</part></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Casimir IV Jagiellon</target></link>, Grand Duke of<space/><link><target>Grand Duchy of Lithuania</target><part>Lithuania</part></link><space/>and King of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Poland (13851569)</target><part>Poland</part></link>, and his wife<space/><link><target>Elisabeth of Austria (d. 1505)</target><part>Elisabeth of Austria</part></link>. He was raised for a career in the<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target><part>Church</part></link><space/>and spent some time at the court of<space/><link><target>Hermann IV of Hesse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Electorate of Cologne</target><part>Elector of Cologne</part></link>, who appointed him canon of the<space/><link><target>Cologne Cathedral</target></link>.Not only was he quite religious, he was also interested in mathematics and science, and sometimes is claimed to have contradicted the teachings of the Church in favour of scientific theories. His career was forwarded by the Church however and institutions of the Catholic clerics supported his early advance.</paragraph><paragraph>Turning to a more active life, Albert accompanied Emperor<space/><link><target>Maximilian I, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Maximilian I</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>in 1508, and after his return spent some time in the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Hungary</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Grand Master</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Albrecht von Hohenzollern-Ansbach.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>As Grand Master of the Teutonic Order, Statue by<space/><link><target>Rudolf Siemering</target></link></part></link><link><target>Duke Frederick of Saxony</target></link>, Grand Master of the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Order</target></link>, died in December 1510. Albert was chosen as his successor early in 1511 in the hope that his relationship to his maternal uncle,<space/><link><target>Sigismund I the Old</target></link>, Grand Duke of Lithuania and King of Poland, would facilitate a settlement of the disputes over eastern<space/><link><target>Prussia (region)</target><part>Prussia</part></link>, which had been held by the Order under Polish<space/><link><target>suzerainty</target></link><space/>since the<space/><link><target>Second Peace of Thorn (1466)</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The new Grand Master, aware of his duties to the empire and to the papacy, refused to submit to the crown of Poland. As war over the Order's existence appeared inevitable, Albert made strenuous efforts to secure allies and carried on protracted negotiations with Emperor Maximilian I. The ill-feeling, influenced by the ravages of members of the Order in Poland, culminated in<space/><link><target>PolishTeutonic War (15191521)</target><part>a war</part></link><space/>which began in December 1519 and devastated Prussia. Albert was granted a four-year truce early in 1521.</paragraph><paragraph>The dispute was referred to Emperor<space/><link><target>Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Charles V</part></link><space/>and other princes, but as no settlement was reached Albert continued his efforts to obtain help in view of a renewal of the war. For this purpose he visited the<space/><link><target>Diet of Nuremberg</target></link><space/>in 1522, where he made the acquaintance of the<space/><link><target>Protestant Reformation</target><part>Reformer</part></link><space/><link><target>Andreas Osiander</target></link>, by whose influence Albert was won over to<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Grand Master then journeyed to<space/><link><target>Wittenberg</target></link>, where he was advised by<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link><space/>to abandon the rules of his Order, to marry, and to convert Prussia into a hereditary duchy for himself. This proposal, which was understandably appealing to Albert, had already been discussed by some of his relatives; but it was necessary to proceed cautiously, and he assured<space/><link><target>Pope Adrian VI</target></link><space/>that he was anxious to reform the Order and punish the knights who had adopted<space/><link><target>Lutheranism</target><part>Lutheran</part></link><space/>doctrines. Luther for his part did not stop at the suggestion, but in order to facilitate the change made special efforts to spread his teaching among the Prussians, while Albert's brother, Margrave<space/><link><target>George, Margrave of Brandenburg-Ansbach</target><part>George of Brandenburg-Ansbach</part></link>, laid the scheme before their uncle,<space/><link><target>Sigismund I the Old</target></link><space/>of Poland.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Duke in Prussia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Prussian Homage.jpg</target><part>350px</part><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>Prussian Homage (painting)</target><part>Prussian Homage</part></link>'': Albert and his brothers receive the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Prussia</target></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>fief</target></link><space/>from Polish King<space/><link><target>Sigismund I the Old</target></link>, 1525.<space/><link><target>History painting</target><part>Painting</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Jan Matejko</target><part>Matejko</part></link>, 1882.</part></link>After some delay Sigismund assented to the offer, with the provision that Prussia should be treated as a Polish fiefdom; and after this arrangement had been confirmed by a<space/><link><target>Treaty of Krakw</target><part>treaty concluded at Krakw</part></link>, Albert pledged a<space/><link><target>Prussian Homage</target><part>personal oath</part></link><space/>to Sigismund I and was invested with the duchy for himself and his heirs on 10 February 1525.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Estates of the realm</target><part>Estates</part></link><space/>of the land then met at<space/><link><target>Knigsberg</target></link><space/>and took the oath of allegiance to the new duke, who used his full powers to promote the doctrines of Luther. This transition did not, however, take place without protest. Summoned before the imperial court of justice, Albert refused to appear and was proscribed, while the Order elected a new Grand Master,<space/><link><target>Walter von Cronberg</target></link>, who received Prussia as a fief at the imperial<space/><link><target>Diet of Augsburg</target></link>. As the German princes were experiencing the tumult of the Reformation, the<space/><link><target>German Peasants' War</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Ottoman wars in Europe</target><part>wars against the Ottoman Turks</part></link>, they did not enforce the ban on the duke, and agitation against him soon died away.</paragraph><paragraph>In imperial politics Albert was fairly active. Joining the<space/><link><target>League of Torgau</target></link><space/>in 1526, he acted in unison with the Protestants, and was among the princes who banded and plotted together to overthrow Charles V after the issue of the<space/><link><target>Augsburg Interim</target></link><space/>in May 1548. For various reasons, however, poverty and personal inclination among others, he did not take a prominent part in the military operations of this period.<link><target>File:Albrecht von Brandenburg-Preuen Groschen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>One<space/><link><target>Groschen</target></link><space/>coin, 1534, ''<link><target>Epistle to the Galatians</target><part>Iustus ex fide vivit</part></link><space/>The Just lives on Faith''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The early years of Albert's rule in Prussia were fairly prosperous. Although he had some trouble with the peasantry, the lands and treasures of the church enabled him to propitiate the nobles and for a time to provide for the expenses of the court. He did something for the furtherance of learning by establishing schools in every town and by freeing serfs who adopted a scholastic life. In 1544, in spite of some opposition, he founded<space/><link><target>Knigsberg University</target></link>, where he appointed his friend Andreas Osiander to a professorship in 1549. Albert also paid for the printing of the Astronomical &quot;<link><target>Prutenic Tables</target></link>&quot; compiled by<space/><link><target>Erasmus Reinhold</target></link><space/>and the first maps of Prussia by<space/><link><target>Caspar Hennenberger</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>This step was the beginning of the troubles which clouded the closing years of Albert's reign. Osiander's divergence from Luther's doctrine of<space/><link><target>Justification (theology)</target><part>justification</part></link><space/>by faith involved him in a violent quarrel with<space/><link><target>Philip Melanchthon</target></link>, who had adherents in Knigsberg, and these theological disputes soon created an uproar in the town. The duke strenuously supported Osiander, and the area of the quarrel soon broadened. There were no longer church lands available with which to conciliate the nobles, the burden of taxation was heavy, and Albert's rule became unpopular.</paragraph><paragraph>After Osiander's death in 1552, Albert favoured a preacher named<space/><link><target>Johann Funck</target></link>, who, with an adventurer named<space/><link><target>Paul Skali</target></link>, exercised great influence over him and obtained considerable wealth at public expense. The state of turmoil caused by these religious and political disputes was increased by the possibility of Albert's early death and the need, should that happen, to appoint a<space/><link><target>regent</target></link>, as his only son,<space/><link><target>Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia</target><part>Albert Frederick</part></link><space/>was still a mere youth. The duke was forced to consent to a condemnation of the teaching of Osiander, and the climax came in 1566 when the<space/><link><target>Estates of the realm</target><part>Estates</part></link><space/>appealed to King<space/><link><target>Sigismund II Augustus</target></link><space/>of Poland, Albert's cousin, who sent a commission to Knigsberg. Skali saved his life by flight, but Funck was executed. The question of the regency was settled, and a form of Lutheranism was adopted and declared binding on all teachers and preachers.<link><target>File:Paulus Scalichius (Scaligius, c.1534-1575).png</target><part>thumb</part><part>170px</part><part>Portrait of<space/><link><target>Pavao Skali</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>encyclopedist</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Renaissance humanist</target></link><space/>and adventurer from<space/><link><target>Croatia</target></link>, who strongly influenced the Duke in the closing years of his reign</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Virtually deprived of power, the duke lived for two more years, and died at<space/><link><target>Gvardeysk</target><part>Tapiau</part></link><space/>on 20 March 1568 of the plague, along with his wife.<space/><link><target>Cornelis Floris de Vriendt</target></link><space/>designed his tomb within<space/><link><target>Knigsberg Cathedral</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mhlpfordt, p. 73</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Albert was a voluminous letter writer, and corresponded with many of the leading personages of the time.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dom Fuerstengruft.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Tomb of Albert by<space/><link><target>Cornelis Floris de Vriendt</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Knigsberg Cathedral</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Albertus-Schild.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;Albertus&quot; with sword from the<space/><link><target>Silberbibliothek</target></link></part></link>Although Albert has received relatively little recognition in German history,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>his dissolution of the Teutonic State caused the founding of the Duchy of Prussia, which would eventually become arguably the most powerful German state and instrumental in uniting the whole of Germany. Albert is therefore often seen as the father of the Prussian nation, and even as indirectly responsible for the<space/><link><target>unification of Germany</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>He was a skilled political administrator and leader, and effectively reversed the decline of the Teutonic Order, until he betrayed it by transforming the order's lands into his own duchy, secularizing it in the process.</paragraph><paragraph>Albert was the first German noble to support Luther's ideas and in 1544 founded the<space/><link><target>University of Knigsberg</target></link>, the Albertina, as a rival to the Roman Catholic<space/><link><target>Cracow Academy</target></link>. It was the second Lutheran university in the German states, after the<space/><link><target>University of Marburg</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>relief</target></link><space/>of Albert over the Renaissance-era portal of<space/><link><target>Knigsberg Castle</target></link>'s southern wing was created by Andreas Hess in 1551 according to plans by Christoph Rmer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="M90">Mhlpfordt, p. 90</extension><space/>Another relief by an unknown artist was included in the wall of the Albertina's original campus. This depiction, which showed the duke with his sword over his shoulder, was the popular &quot;Albertus&quot;, the symbol of the university. The original was moved to<space/><link><target>Knigsberg Public Library</target></link><space/>to protect it from the elements, while the sculptor<space/><link><target>Paul Kimritz</target></link><space/>created a duplicate for the wall.<extension extension_name='ref' name="M90"></extension><space/>Another version of the &quot;Albertus&quot; by Lothar Sauer was included at the entrance of the<space/><link><target>Knigsberg State and Royal Library</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="M90"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1880<space/><link><target>Friedrich Reusch</target></link><space/>created a sandstone bust of Albert at the Regierungsgebude, the administrative building for<space/><link><target>Regierungsbezirk Knigsberg</target></link>. On 19 May 1891 Reusch premiered a famous statue of Albert at<space/><link><target>Knigsberg Castle</target></link><space/>with the inscription: &quot;Albert of Brandenburg, Last Grand Master, First Duke in Prussia&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mhlpfordt, p. 82</extension><space/><link><target>Albert Wolff (sculptor)</target><part>Albert Wolff</part></link><space/>also designed an equestrian statue of Albert located at the new campus of the Albertina.<space/><link><target>King's Gate (Kaliningrad)</target><part>King's Gate</part></link><space/>contains a statue of Albert.</paragraph><paragraph>Albert was oft-honored in the quarter<space/><link><target>Maraunenhof</target></link><space/>in northern Knigsberg. Its main street was named Herzog-Albrecht-Allee in 1906. Its town square, Knig-Ottokar-Platz, was renamed Herzog-Albrecht-Platz in 1934 to match its church, the<space/><link><target>Herzog-Albrecht-Gedchtniskirche</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mhlpfordt, p. 133</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Spouse and issue</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dorothea of Denmark, Duchess of Prussia by Cornelis II Floris de Vriendt (Pushkin museum) by shakko 02.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part></part><part>Dorothea of Denmark, Duchess of Prussia by<space/><link><target>Cornelis Floris de Vriendt</target></link></part></link>Albert married first, to Princess<space/><link><target>Dorothea of Denmark, Duchess of Prussia</target><part>Dorothea</part></link><space/>(1 August 1504 11 April 1547), daughter of King<space/><link><target>Frederick I of Denmark</target></link>, in 1526. They had six children;</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Anna Sophia of Prussia</target><part>Anna Sophia</part></link><space/>(15271591)</listitem><listitem>Katharina (b. &amp; d. 1528)</listitem><listitem>Frederick Albert (15291530)</listitem><listitem>Lucia Dorothea (15311532)</listitem><listitem>Lucia (15371539)</listitem><listitem>Albert (15391539)</listitem></list><paragraph>He married secondly to<space/><link><target>Anna Marie of Brunswick-Lneburg</target><part>Anna Maria</part></link><space/>(153220 March 1568), daughter of<space/><link><target>Eric I, Duke of Brunswick-Lneburg</target><part>Eric I</part></link>, Duke of<space/><link><target>Brunswick-Lneburg</target></link>, in 1550. The couple had two children;</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Elisabeth (15511596)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia</target><part>Albert Frederick</part></link><space/>(15531618)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Ancestors</heading><paragraph><xhtml:center><template><target>ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Albert, Duke of Prussia ''' (1490–1568)
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. [[Frederick I, Margrave of Brandenburg-Ansbach]] (1460–1536)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. [[Zofia Jagiellonka]] (1464–1512)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[Albrecht III, Elector of Brandenburg]] (1414–1486)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. [[Anna of Saxony (d. 1512)|Anna of Saxony]] (1437–1512)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3"><space/>6. [[Casimir IV Jagiellon]] (1427–1492)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4"><space/>7. [[Elisabeth of Austria (d. 1505)|Elisabeth of Austria]] (1435–1505)
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[Frederick I, Elector of Brandenburg]] (1371–1440)
</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. [[Elisabeth of Bavaria-Landshut]] (1383–1442)
</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[Frederick II, Elector of Saxony]] (1412–1464)
</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. [[Margaret of Austria (1416–1486)|Margaret of Austria]] (1416–1486)
</arg><arg name="4"><space/>12. [[Jogaila]] (1362–1434)
</arg><arg name="5"><space/>13. [[Sophia of Halshany]] (1405–1461)
</arg><arg name="6"><space/>14. [[Albert II of Germany]] (1397–1439)
</arg><arg name="7"><space/>15. [[Elisabeth of Bohemia (1409–1442)|Elisabeth of Bohemia]] (1409–1442)
</arg><arg name="8"><space/>16. [[Frederick V, Burgrave of Nuremberg]] (1333–1398)
</arg><arg name="9"><space/>17. [[Elisabeth of Meissen]] (1329–1375)
</arg><arg name="10"><space/>18. [[Frederick, Duke of Bavaria-Landshut]] (1339–1393)
</arg><arg name="11"><space/>19. [[Maddalena Visconti]] (1366–1404)
</arg><arg name="12"><space/>20. [[Frederick I, Elector of Saxony]] (1370–1428)
</arg><arg name="13"><space/>21. [[Catherine of Brunswick-Lüneburg|Catherine of Brunswick]] ( -1442)
</arg><arg name="14"><space/>22. [[Ernest, Duke of Austria]] (1377–1424)
</arg><arg name="15"><space/>23. [[Cymburgis of Masovia]] (1394–1397)
</arg><arg name="16"><space/>24. [[Algirdas]] (1296–1377)
</arg><arg name="17"><space/>25. [[Uliana of Tver]] (1325–1392)
</arg><arg name="18"><space/>26. [[Andrew of Halshany]] (1365–1410)
</arg><arg name="19"><space/>27. [[Alexandra Drucka]] (1380–1426)
</arg><arg name="20"><space/>28. [[Albert IV, Duke of Austria]] (1377–1404)
</arg><arg name="21"><space/>29. [[Johanna Sophia of Bavaria]] (1373–1410)
</arg><arg name="22"><space/>30. [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor]] (1368–1437)
</arg><arg name="23"><space/>31. [[Barbara of Celje]] (1390–1451)
</arg><arg name="24"><space/>24. [[Algirdas]] (1296–1377)
</arg><arg name="25"><space/>25. [[Uliana of Tver]] (1325–1392)
</arg><arg name="26"><space/>26. [[Andrew of Halshany]] (1365–1410)
</arg><arg name="27"><space/>27. [[Alexandra Drucka]] (1380–1426)
</arg><arg name="28"><space/>28. [[Albert IV, Duke of Austria]] (1377–1404)
</arg><arg name="29"><space/>29. [[Johanna Sophia of Bavaria]] (1373–1410)
</arg><arg name="30"><space/>30. [[Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor]] (1368–1437)
</arg><arg name="31"><space/>31. [[Barbara of Celje]] (1390–1451)
</arg></template></xhtml:center></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Albert (grand master)</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Albinus</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="authorlink"></arg><arg name="title">Lexikon der Stadt Königsberg Pr. und Umgebung</arg><arg name="year">1985</arg><arg name="publisher">Verlag Gerhard Rautenberg</arg><arg name="location">Leer</arg><arg name="pages">371</arg><arg name="isbn">3-7921-0320-6</arg><arg name="language">de</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mühlpfordt</arg><arg name="first">Herbert Meinhard</arg><arg name="authorlink">Herbert Meinhard Mühlpfordt</arg><arg name="title">Welche Mitbürger hat Königsberg öffentlich geehrt?</arg><arg name="year">1963</arg><arg name="publisher">Holzner Verlag</arg><arg name="location">Würzburg</arg><arg name="pages"></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="language">de</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Albrecht von Preußen</arg><arg>Albert, Duke of Prussia</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>DNB portal</target><arg>118637673</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://google.com/search?q=cache:lqag5cL8YAAJ:department.monm.edu/history/urban/articles/State_of_the_grandmasters.htm+Casimir+IV+deutscher+orden'>William Urban on the situation in Prussia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://zs.thulb.uni-jena.de/receive/jportal_jparticle_00054867'>K. P. Faber: Briefe Luthers an Herzog Albrecht (1811)</link><space/>letters of<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link><space/>to Albrecht<space/><template><target>de icon</target></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Principality of Ansbach|House of Brandenburg-Ansbach]]<space/></arg><arg>16 May</arg><arg>1490</arg><arg>20 March</arg><arg>1568</arg><arg><space/>[[House of Hohenzollern]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-reg</target></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Duke Frederick of Saxony]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Grand Masters of the Teutonic Knights|Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights]]<space/></arg><arg name="years">1510–1525<space/></arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Walter von Cronberg]]<space/></arg></template>|-<template><target>S-new</target><arg><space/>creation</arg><arg name="reason">[[Secularisation]] of the [[Monastic state of the Teutonic Knights|Monastic<br>state of the Teutonic Knights]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Duke of Prussia]]<space/></arg><arg name="years">1525–1568</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Albert Frederick, Duke of Prussia|Albert Frederick]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Rulers of Prussia</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:1490 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1568 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Converts to Lutheranism from Roman Catholicism</target></link><link><target>Category:Dukes of Prussia</target></link><link><target>Category:German people of Lithuanian descent</target></link><link><target>Category:German people of Polish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:German Lutherans</target></link><link><target>Category:Grand Masters of the Teutonic Order</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Hohenzollern</target></link><link><target>Category:People excommunicated by the Roman Catholic Church</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Ansbach</target></link><link><target>Category:People from the Principality of Ansbach</target></link><link><target>Category:People from the Duchy of Prussia</target></link><link><target>Category:People of the PolishTeutonic War (151921) (German side)</target></link><link><target>Category:Protestant monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Protestant Reformation</target></link><link><target>Category:University of Knigsberg</target></link></paragraph></article>