<article title='David_Thompson_%28explorer%29'><paragraph><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="name"><space/>David Thompson
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>David Thompson (1770-1857).jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="caption">
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Westminster]], London, England
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Longueuil]], [[Canada East]]
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Explorer and [[Cartography|Map Maker]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Charlotte Small]]
</arg><arg name="parents"><space/>John and Sofia Thompson
</arg><arg name="children"><space/>Fanny (1801), Samuel (1804), Emma (1806), John (1808), Joshuah (1811), Henry (1813), Charlotte (1815), Elizabeth (1817), William (1819), Thomas (1822), George (1824), Mary (1827), Eliza (1829)
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>David Thompson signature.svg
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>David Thompson</bold><space/>(30 April 1770 10 February 1857) was a<space/><link><target>English Canadian</target><part>British-Canadian</part></link><space/><link><target>fur trader</target></link>,<space/><link><target>surveying</target><part>surveyor</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Cartography</target><part>map-maker</part></link>, known to some native peoples as &quot;Koo-Koo-Sint&quot; or &quot;the Stargazer.&quot; Over his career he mapped over 3.9&amp;nbsp;million square kilometres of North America and for this has been described as the &quot;greatest land geographer who ever lived.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="tyrell"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><paragraph>Thompson was born in<space/><link><target>Westminster</target></link><space/>to recent Welsh migrants, David and Ann Thompson. When Thompson was two, his father died and the financial hardship of this occurrence resulted in his and his brother's placement in the<space/><link><target>Grey Coat Hospital</target></link>, a school for the disadvantaged of Westminster.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.hbcheritage.ca/hbcheritage/history/people/explorers/david-thompson'>Hudson's Bay Company</link>. Retrieved 9 January 2013.</extension><space/>He eventually graduated to the Grey Coat mathematical school and was introduced to basic navigation skills which would form the basis of his future career. In 1784, at the age of 14, he entered a seven-year apprenticeship with the<space/><link><target>Hudson's Bay Company</target></link>. He set sail on 28 May of that year, and left England .<extension extension_name='ref' name="vanherk">Aritha Van Herk,<space/><italics>Travels with Charlotte</italics>, Canadian Geographic Magazine, July/August 2007</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Hudson's Bay Company (HBC)</heading><paragraph>He arrived in<space/><link><target>Churchill, Manitoba</target><part>Churchill</part></link><space/>(now in<space/><link><target>Manitoba</target></link>) and was put to work copying the personal papers of the governor of Fort Churchill,<space/><link><target>Samuel Hearne</target></link>. The next year he was transferred to nearby<space/><link><target>York Factory, Manitoba</target><part>York Factory</part></link>, and over the next few years spent time as a clerk at<space/><link><target>Cumberland House, Saskatchewan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South Branch House</target></link><space/>before arriving at<space/><link><target>Manchester House</target></link><space/>in 1787. On 23 December 1788, Thompson seriously fractured his leg, forcing him to spend the next two winters at Cumberland House convalescing. It was during this time he greatly refined and expanded his mathematical, astronomical and surveying skills under the tutelage of Hudson's Bay Company surveyor<space/><link><target>Philip Turnor</target></link>. It was also during this time that he lost sight in his right eye.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gottfred">J. &amp; A. Gottfred, &quot;Art. I. The Life of David Thompson&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1790 with his apprenticeship nearing its end, Thompson made the unusual request of a set of surveying tools in place of the typical parting gift of fine clothes offered by the company to those completing their indenture. He received both. He then entered the employ of the Hudson's Bay Company as a<space/><link><target>fur trader</target></link><space/>and in 1792 completed his first significant survey, mapping a route to<space/><link><target>Lake Athabasca</target></link><space/>(where today's<space/><link><target>Alberta</target></link>/<link><target>Saskatchewan</target></link><space/>border is located). In recognition of his map-making skills, the company promoted him to surveyor in 1794. Thompson continued working for the Hudson's Bay Company until 23 May 1797 when, frustrated with the Hudson's Bay Company's policies, he left and walked 80&amp;nbsp;miles in the snow to enter the employ of the competition, the<space/><link><target>North West Company</target></link><space/>where he continued to work as a<space/><link><target>fur trader</target></link><space/>and surveyor.</paragraph><heading level='3'>North West Company</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:David Thompson (explorer).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>An artist's impression of Thompson based on historical accounts</part><trail>Thompson</trail></link>'s decision to defect to the<space/><link><target>North West Company</target></link><space/>in 1797 without providing the customary one-year notice was not well received by his former employers. However, joining the North West Company allowed Thompson to pursue his interest in surveying and work on mapping the interior of what was to become Canada. In 1797, Thompson was sent south by his employers to survey part of the Canada-US boundary along the water routes from<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Lake of the Woods</target></link><space/>to satisfy unresolved questions of territory arising from the<space/><link><target>Jay Treaty</target></link><space/>between Great Britain and the United States. By 1798 Thompson had completed a survey of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6750</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>from<space/><link><target>Grand Portage</target></link>, through<space/><link><target>Lake Winnipeg</target></link>, to the<space/><link><target>River source</target><part>headwaters</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Assiniboine River</target><part>Assiniboine</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mississippi River</target><part>Mississippi</part></link><space/>Rivers, as well as two sides of<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vanherk"></extension><space/>In 1798, the company sent him to Red Deer Lake (Lac La Biche in present-day<space/><link><target>Alberta</target></link>) to establish a trading post. The English translation of<space/><link><target>Lac la Biche (Alberta)</target><part>Lac La Biche</part></link>-Red Deer Lake-first appeared on the Mackenzie map of 1793.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AlbertaAtlas"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://sunsite.ualberta.ca/Projects/Alberta-Lakes/view/?region</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Alberta</arg><arg name="location">Edmonton, Alberta</arg><arg name="title">Lac La Biche</arg><arg name="series">Atlas of Alberta Lakes</arg><arg name="year">2004-5</arg></template></extension><space/>Thompson spent the next few seasons trading based in Fort George (now in<space/><link><target>Alberta</target></link>), and during this time led several expeditions into the<space/><link><target>Rocky Mountains</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1804, at the annual meeting of the North West Company in<space/><link><target>Fort Kaministiquia</target><part>Kaministiquia</part></link>, Thompson was made a full partner of the company and spent the next few seasons based there managing the fur trading operations but still finding time to expand his surveys of the waterways around<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link>. However, a decision was made at the 1806 company meeting to send Thompson back out into the interior. Concern over the American-backed expedition of<space/><link><target>Lewis and Clark Expedition</target><part>Lewis and Clark</part></link><space/>prompted the North West Company to charge Thompson with the task of finding a route to the Pacific to open up the lucrative trading territories of the<space/><link><target>Pacific Northwest</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Columbia travels</heading><paragraph>After the general meeting in 1806, Thompson travelled to<space/><link><target>Rocky Mountain House</target></link><space/>and prepared for an expedition to follow the<space/><link><target>Columbia River</target></link><space/>to the Pacific. In June 1807 Thompson crossed the Rocky Mountains and spent the summer surveying the<space/><link><target>Columbia basin</target></link><space/>and continuing to survey the area over the next few seasons. Thompson mapped and established trading posts in Northwestern<space/><link><target>Montana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Idaho</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Washington (state)</target><part>Washington</part></link>, and Western Canada. Trading posts he founded included<space/><link><target>Kootenae House</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kullyspell House</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Saleesh House</target></link>; the latter two of which were the first trading posts west of the Rockies in Idaho and Montana, respectively.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gottfred"></extension><space/>These posts established by Thompson extended North West Company fur trading territory into the Columbia Basin drainage area. The maps he made of the Columbia River basin east of the<space/><link><target>Cascade Mountains</target></link><space/>were of such high quality and detail that they continued to be regarded as authoritative well into the mid-20th century.<space/><link><target>File:Columbiarivermap.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>David Thompson navigated the entire length of Columbia River in 1811. Map of Columbia and its tributaries showing modern political boundaries</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In early 1810, Thompson was returning eastward towards<space/><link><target>Montreal</target></link><space/>but while on route at<space/><link><target>Rainy Lake</target></link>, received orders to return to the Rocky Mountains and establish a route to the mouth of the Columbia. This was a response by the North West Company to the plans of<space/><link><target>John Jacob Astor</target></link><space/>to send a ship around the Americas to establish a fur trading post. During his return, Thompson was delayed by an angry group of<space/><link><target>Northern Peigan</target><part>Peigan</part></link><space/>natives at<space/><link><target>Howse Pass</target></link><space/>which ultimately forced him to seek a new route across the<space/><link><target>Rocky Mountains</target></link><space/>through the<space/><link><target>Athabasca Pass</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>David Thompson was the first European to navigate the full length of the Columbia River. During Thompson's 1811 voyage down the Columbia River he camped at the junction with the<space/><link><target>Snake River</target></link><space/>on 9 July 1811, and erected a pole and a notice claiming the country for Great Britain and stating the intention of the North West Company to build a<space/><link><target>trading post</target></link><space/>at the site. This notice was found later that year by Astorians looking to establish an inland fur post, contributing to their selection of a more northerly site at<space/><link><target>Fort Okanogan</target></link>. The North West Company's<space/><link><target>Fort Nez Percs</target></link><space/>was established near the Snake River junction several years later. Continuing down the Columbia, Thompson passed the barrier of<space/><link><target>The Dalles, Oregon</target><part>The Dalles</part></link><space/>with much less difficulty than experienced by<space/><link><target>Lewis and Clark Expedition</target><part>Lewis and Clark</part></link>, as high water obscured<space/><link><target>Celilo Falls</target></link><space/>and many of the rapids. On 14 July 1811, Thompson reached the partially constructed<space/><link><target>Fort Astoria</target></link><space/>at the mouth of the Columbia, arriving two months after the<space/><link><target>Pacific Fur Company</target></link>'s ship, the<space/><italics><link><target>Tonquin</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Meinig</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.W.</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>D.W. Meinig</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Great Columbia Plain</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Weyerhaeuser Environmental Classic</arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1968</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Washington Press</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-295-97485-9</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>37–38, 50<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Before returning upriver and across the mountains, Thompson hired<space/><link><target>Naukane</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Native Hawaiians</target><part>Native Hawaiian</part></link><space/>labourer brought to Fort Astoria by the Pacific Fur Company's ship<space/><italics><link><target>Tonquin</target></link></italics>. Naukane, known as Coxe to Thompson, accompanied Thompson across the continent to<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link><space/>before journeying on to England.</paragraph><paragraph>Thompson wintered at Saleesh House before beginning his final journey back to Montreal in 1812.</paragraph><paragraph>In his published journals, Thompson recorded seeing large footprints near what is now<space/><link><target>Jasper, Alberta</target></link>, in 1811. It has been suggested that these prints were similar to what has since been called the<space/><link><target>sasquatch</target></link>. However, Thompson noted that these tracks showed &quot;a small Nail at the end of each [toe]&quot;, and stated that these tracks &quot;very much resembles a large Bear's Track&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thompson, David.<space/><italics>Columbia Journals</italics>. Edited by Barbara Belyea. McGill-Queen's University Press, 1994, p. 135</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Appearance and personality</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:DavidThompson.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>David Thompson late in life</part></link>In 1820, the English geologist,<space/><link><target>John Jeremiah Bigsby</target></link>, attended a dinner party given by The Hon.<space/><link><target>William McGillivray</target></link><space/>at his home, Chateau St. Antoine, one of the early estates in<space/><link><target>Montreal</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Golden Square Mile</target></link>. He describes the party and some of the guests in his entertaining book<space/><italics>The Shoe and Canoe</italics>, giving an excellent description of David Thompson:</paragraph><paragraph><italics>I was well placed at table between one of the Miss McGillivray's and a singular-looking person of about fifty. He was plainly dressed, quiet, and observant. His figure was short and compact, and his black hair was worn long all round, and cut square, as if by one stroke of the shears, just above the eyebrows. His complexion was of the gardener's ruddy brown, while the expression of his deeply-furrowed features was friendly and intelligent, but his cut-short nose gave him an odd look. His speech betrayed the<space/><link><target>Wales</target><part>Welshman</part></link>, although he left his native hills when very young. I might have been spared this description of Mr David Thompson by saying he greatly resembled<space/><link><target>John Philpot Curran</target><part>Curran</part></link><space/>the Irish Orator...</italics></paragraph><paragraph><italics>I afterwards travelled much with him, and have now only to speak of him with great respect, or, I ought to say, with admiration... No living person possesses a<space/><link><target>tithe</target></link><space/>of his information respecting the<space/><link><target>Hudson's Bay Company</target><part>Hudson's Bay</part></link><space/>countries... Never mind his Bunyan-like face and cropped hair; he has a very powerful mind, and a singular faculty of picture-making. He can create a wilderness and people it with warring savages, or climb the<space/><link><target>Rocky Mountains</target></link><space/>with you in a snow-storm, so clearly and palpably, that only shut your eyes and you hear the crack of the rifle, or feel the snow-flakes melt on your cheeks as he talks.</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>John Jeremiah Bigsby</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The shoe and canoe: or pictures of travel in the Canadas ; with facts and opinions on emigration, state policy, and other points of public interest</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1850</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Chapman and Hall</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Marriage and children</heading><paragraph>On 10 June 1799 at<space/><link><target>le--la-Crosse, Saskatchewan</target><part>le--la-Crosse</part></link>, he married<space/><link><target>Charlotte Small</target></link>, a thirteen-year-old<space/><link><target>Mtis people (Canada)</target><part>Mtis</part></link><space/>child of a Scottish fur trader Patrick Small and a<space/><link><target>Cree</target></link><space/>mother.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="last">Thompson
<space/></arg><arg name="first">David
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dictionary of Canadian Biography
<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.biographi.ca/en/bio/thompson_david_1770_1857_8E.html
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-10-08</arg></template></extension><space/>Their marriage was formalised at the Scotch Presbyterian Church in<space/><link><target>Montreal</target></link><space/>on 30 October 1812. He and Charlotte had 13 children together; five of them were born before he left the fur trade. The family did not adjust easily to life in Eastern Canada and two of the children, John (aged 5) and Emma (aged 7) died of round worms, a common parasite.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vanherk"></extension><space/>Their marriage lasted 58 years, the longest Canadian pre-Confederation marriage known.<extension extension_name='ref' name="vanherk"></extension><link><target>File:1814ThompsonMap.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Map of the North-West Territory of the Province of Canada, stretching from the<space/><link><target>Fraser River</target></link><space/>on the west to<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link><space/>on the east. By David Thompson, 1814.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Later years</heading><paragraph>Upon his arrival back in<space/><link><target>Montreal</target></link>, Thompson retired with a generous pension from the<space/><link><target>North West Company</target></link>. He settled in nearby<space/><link><target>Terrebonne, Quebec</target><part>Terrebonne</part></link><space/>and worked on completing his great map, a summary of his lifetime of exploring and surveying the interior of North America. The map covered the wide area stretching from<space/><link><target>Lake Superior</target></link><space/>to the Pacific, and was given by Thompson to the North West Company. Thompson's 1814 map, his greatest achievement, was so accurate that 100 years later it was still the basis for many of the maps issued by the Canadian government. It now resides in the Archives of Ontario.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.archives.gov.on.ca/english/exhibits/thompson/records.htm'>David Thompson Records Held by the [[Archives of Ontario</link>]]</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1815, Thompson moved his family to<space/><link><target>Williamstown, Ontario</target><part>Williamstown, Upper Canada</part></link><space/>and a few years later was employed to survey the newly established borders with the United States from<space/><link><target>Lake of the Woods</target></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>Eastern Townships</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Quebec</target></link>, established by<space/><link><target>Treaty of Ghent</target></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link>. In 1843 Thompson completed his atlas of the region from<space/><link><target>Hudson Bay</target></link><space/>to the Pacific Ocean.</paragraph><paragraph>Afterwards, Thompson returned to a life as a land owner, but soon financial misfortune would ruin him. By 1831 he was so deeply in debt he was forced to take up a position as a surveyor for the British American Land Company to provide for his family. His luck continued to worsen and he was forced to move in with his daughter and son-in-law in 1845. He began work on a manuscript chronicling his life exploring the continent, but this project was left unfinished when his sight failed him completely in 1851.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Death and afterward</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Stamp-Thompson-1957.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Postage stamp commemorating David Thompson's life</part></link>The land mass mapped by Thompson amounted to 3.9&amp;nbsp;million square kilometres of wilderness (one-fifth of the continent). His contemporary, the great explorer<space/><link><target>Alexander Mackenzie (explorer)</target><part>Alexander Mackenzie</part></link>, remarked that Thompson did more in ten months than he would have thought possible in two years.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite these significant achievements, Thompson died in Montreal in near obscurity on 10 February 1857, his accomplishments almost unrecognised. He never finished the book of his 28 years in the fur trade, based on his 77 field notebooks, before he died. In the 1890s geologist<space/><link><target>Joseph Tyrrell</target><part>J.B. Tyrrell</part></link><space/>resurrected Thompson's notes and in 1916 published them as<space/><italics>David Thompson's Narrative</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rick Boychuk,<space/><italics>David Thompson's living legacy</italics>, Canadian Geographic Magazine, July/August 2007, p. 13</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:David Thompson Monument.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>200px</part><part>David Thompson Memorial, Verendrye, North Dakota</part></link>Thompson's body was interred in Montreal's<space/><link><target>Mount Royal Cemetery</target></link><space/>in an unmarked grave. It was not until 1926 that efforts by<space/><link><target>Joseph Tyrrell</target><part>J.B. Tyrell</part></link><space/>and the Canadian Historical Society resulted in the placing of a tombstone to mark his grave.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1957, one hundred years after his death, the Canadian government honoured him with his image on a<space/><link><target>List of people on stamps of Canada</target><part>Canadian postage stamp</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>David Thompson Highway</target></link><space/>in Alberta was named in his honour, along with David Thompson High School situated on the side of the highway near<space/><link><target>Leslieville, Alberta</target></link>. His prowess as a geographer is now well-recognized. He has been called &quot;the greatest land geographer who ever lived.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="tyrell"><italics><link type='external' href='http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;amp;lang=eng&amp;amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;amp;searchtype=Author&amp;amp;startrow=1&amp;amp;Limit=All'>David Thompson's narrative of his explorations in western America, 17841812</link></italics><space/>(edited by J.B. Tyrell)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="vanherk"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:LLB Thompson statue.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>David Thompson and two First Nations guides on the shore of<space/><link><target>Lac la Biche (Alberta)</target><part>Lac la Biche</part></link>, where he landed on 4 October 1798.</part></link>There is a monument dedicated to David Thompson (maintained by the state of<space/><link><target>North Dakota</target></link>) near the former town site of the ghost town,<space/><link><target>Verendrye, North Dakota</target></link>, located approximately two miles north and one mile west of<space/><link><target>Karlsruhe, North Dakota</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Thompson Falls, Montana</target></link><space/>and British Columbia's<space/><link><target>Thompson River</target></link><space/>are also named after the explorer.</paragraph><paragraph>The year 2007 marked the 150th year of Thompson's death and the 200th anniversary of his first crossing of the Rocky Mountains. Commemorative events and exhibits were planned across Canada and the United States from 2007 to 2011 as a celebration of his accomplishments.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.davidthompson200.org/'>David Thompson Bicentennials</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Thompson was the subject of a 1964<space/><link><target>National Film Board of Canada</target></link><space/>short film<space/><italics>David Thompson: The Great Mapmaker<space/></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nfb.ca/film/david_thompson_the_great_mapmaker/'>''David Thompson: The Great Mapmaker '', National Film Board of Canada</link></extension><space/>as well as the<space/><link><target>BBC2</target></link><space/>programme<space/><italics><link><target>Ray Mears' Northern Wilderness</target></link></italics><space/>(Episode 5), broadcast in November 2009.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/wales/8354658.stm'>BBC Wales news report</link>. Retrieved 25 November 2009.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Exploration of North America</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fur trade</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jack Nisbet</target></link><space/>(author of several books on David Thompson)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1814: Map of the North-West Territory of the Province of Canada</listitem><listitem>1897:<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.canadiana.org/ECO/ItemRecord?id=3de1bded3c9598b4'>New light on the early history of the greater Northwest: the manuscript journals of Alexander Henry, fur trader of the North West Company, and of David Thompson, official geographer and explorer of the same company, 17991814 : exploration and adventure among the Indians on the Red, Saskatchewan, Missouri and Columbia Rivers</link></italics><space/>(edited by Elliott Coues)</listitem><listitem>1916:<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;amp;lang=eng&amp;amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;amp;searchtype=Author&amp;amp;startrow=1&amp;amp;Limit=All'>David Thompson's narrative of his explorations in western America, 17841812</link></italics><space/>(edited by J.B. Tyrell)</listitem><listitem>1950:<space/><italics>David Thompson's journals relating to Montana and adjacent regions, 18081812</italics><space/>(edited by M. Catherine White)</listitem><listitem>1962:<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96867&amp;amp;lang=eng&amp;amp;query=9_96867&amp;amp;searchtype=Bibrecord&amp;amp;startrow=1&amp;amp;Limit=All'>David Thompson's narrative, 17841812</link></italics><space/>(edited by Richard Glover)</listitem><listitem>1974:<space/><italics>David Thompson's journal of the international boundary survey, 18171827 : western Lake Erie, AugustSeptember 1819</italics><space/>(edited by Clarke E. Leverette)</listitem><listitem>1993:<space/><italics>Columbia Journals</italics><space/>(edited by Barbara Belyea)</listitem><listitem>2006: &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/products.htm'>Moccasin Miles The Travels of Charlotte Small Thompson 17991812</link>&quot; Contemporary and Historical Maps: Charlotte Small (S. Leanne Playter/Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consulting)</listitem><listitem>2006/2007:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/products.htm'>&quot;David Thompson in Alberta 17871812&quot;; &quot;David Thompson on the Columbia River 18071812&quot;; &quot;The Explorations and Travels of David Thompson 17841812&quot;; &quot;Posts and Forts of the North American Fur Trade 16001870&quot;</link><space/>Contemporary and Historical Maps: David Thompson (Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consulting)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Thompson, David<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Library and Archives Canada<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.biographi.ca/009004-119.01-e.php?&id_nbr</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2 June 2007</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jenish</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D'Arcy</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Epic wanderer: David Thompson and the mapping of the Canadian West</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Doubleday Canada</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Toronto</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-385-65973-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Thompson</arg><arg name="first"><space/>David</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Columbia Journals</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGill-Queen's University Press</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Montreal</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7735-0989-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>David Thompson Canada's greatest Geographer<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>David Thompson Things<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>David Thompson Things<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.davidthompsonthings.com/geog1.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>23 June 2007</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite map</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Explorations and Travels of David Thompson 1784–1812<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Andreas N. Korsos</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Arcturus Consulting<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/shop.htm<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-9783707-2-5<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>2006: &quot;Moccasin Miles The Travels of Charlotte Small Thompson 17991812&quot; Contemporary and Historical Maps: Charlotte Small (S. Leanne Playter/Andreas N. Korsos|Publisher: Arcturus Consulting)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Flandrau, Grace</arg><arg name="title">Koo-koo-sint, the Star Man: a chronicle of David Thompson</arg><arg name="publisher">Great Northern Railway</arg><arg name="year">1925</arg></template><link type='external' href='http://www.secstate.wa.gov/history/publications_detail.aspx?p=86'>Available online through the Washington State Library's Classics in Washington History collection</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Haywood, Carl W.</arg><arg name="title">Sometime Only Horses to Eat: David Thompson; The Saleesh House Period 1807–1812: Tracking David Thompson Across Western North America</arg><arg name="publisher">Stonydale Press Publishing Co.</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jenish, D'Arcy</arg><arg name="title">Epic Wanderer: David Thompson and the Mapping of the Canadian West</arg><arg name="publisher">Doubleday Canada</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">McCart, Joyce and Peter</arg><arg name="title">On the Road with David Thompson</arg><arg name="publisher">Fifth House</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Nisbet, Jack</arg><arg name="title">Sources of the River: Tracking David Thompson Across Western North America</arg><arg name="publisher">Sasquatch Books</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Elle Andra-Warner,2010. David Thompson: A Life of Adventure and Discovery. Heritage House Publishing Co.Ltd.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>David Thompson's Narrative of His Explorations in Western America 17841812 Vol's I and II, Champlain Society 1916,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/download/davidthompsonsna00thom/davidthompsonsna00thom_bw.pdf'>PDF (B/W) 25.1 MB</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96855&amp;amp;lang=eng&amp;amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;amp;searchtype=Author&amp;amp;startrow=1&amp;amp;Limit=All'>Complete text of David Thompson's ''Narrative'' (Tyrrell edition)</link><space/>Champlain Society digital collection</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://link.library.utoronto.ca/champlain/item_record.cfm?Idno=9_96867&amp;amp;lang=eng&amp;amp;query=thompson%20AND%20david&amp;amp;searchtype=Author&amp;amp;startrow=1&amp;amp;Limit=All'>Complete text of David Thompson's ''Narrative'' (Glover edition)</link><space/>Champlain Society digital collection</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.arcturusconsulting.net/products.htm'>Contemporary and Historical Maps</link><space/>Maps depicting David Thompson's travels, Charlotte Small's travels, Posts and Forts of the Canadian Fur Trade 16001870, and other explorations</listitem><listitem><template><target>Oregon Encyclopedia</target><arg>thompson_david</arg><arg>David Thompson</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biographi.ca/009004-119.01-e.php?&amp;amp;id_nbr=4218'>Biography at the ''Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20060719085105/http://www.davidthompson200.org/cms/'>DavidThompson200</link>: bicentennial commemorations of Thompson's explorations</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.champlainsociety.ca'>The Writings of David Thompson</link><space/>edited by William E. Moreau. Three volumes. This edition of the works of Thompson has been in preparation for the past nine years, and is to be published by The Champlain Society with McGill-Queen's University Press and the University of Washington Press.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.library.utoronto.ca/fisher/collections/findaids/thompson_david.pdf'>David Thompson Papers, Thomas Fisher Rare Book Library</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.findagrave.com/cgi-bin/fg.cgi?page=gr&amp;amp;GRid=2662'>Find a Grave: David Thompson</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Thompson, David
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Canadian explorer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>30 April 1770
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Westminster, London, England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>10 February 1857
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Longueuil, Canada East
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Thompson, David</target></template><link><target>Category:Canadian people of Welsh descent</target></link><link><target>Category:English cartographers</target></link><link><target>Category:English explorers</target></link><link><target>Category:English surveyors</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian cartographers</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian canoeists</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian explorers</target></link><link><target>Category:Canadian surveyors</target></link><link><target>Category:English emigrants to pre-Confederation Canada</target></link><link><target>Category:Explorers of British Columbia</target></link><link><target>Category:North West Company people</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Westminster</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Montreal</target></link><link><target>Category:Pre-Confederation Quebec people</target></link><link><target>Category:Interior of British Columbia</target></link><link><target>Category:Hudson's Bay Company people</target></link><link><target>Category:1770 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1857 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:History of the Pacific Northwest</target></link><link><target>Category:Persons of National Historic Significance (Canada)</target></link><link><target>Category:Explorers of Washington (state)</target></link><link><target>Category:People educated at Grey Coat Hospital</target></link><link><target>Category:Explorers of North America</target></link></paragraph></article>