<article title='Casa_Batll%C3%B3'><paragraph><template><target>Expand Catalan</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg><arg>Casa Batlló</arg></template><template><target>Expand French</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg><arg>Casa Batlló</arg></template><template><target>coord</target><arg>41</arg><arg>23</arg><arg>30</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>09</arg><arg>54</arg><arg>E</arg><arg>region:ES-CT_scale:5000_type:landmark</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template><template><target>Infobox building</target><arg name="name"><space/>Casa Batlló
</arg><arg name="native_name"><space/>
</arg><arg name="native_name_lang"><space/>
</arg><arg name="former_names"><space/>
</arg><arg name="alternate_names"><space/>''Casa dels ossos'' (House of Bones)
</arg><arg name="status"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>File:CasaBatllo.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="map_type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="map_alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="map_caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="relief"><space/>
</arg><arg name="altitude"><space/>
</arg><arg name="building_type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="architectural_style"><space/>
</arg><arg name="structural_system"><space/>
</arg><arg name="material"><space/>
</arg><arg name="cost"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_cost"><space/>
</arg><arg name="client"><space/>
</arg><arg name="owner"><space/>
</arg><arg name="current_tenants"><space/>
</arg><arg name="landlord"><space/>
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>
</arg><arg name="address"><space/>
</arg><arg name="location_town"><space/>[[Barcelona]]
</arg><arg name="location_country"><space/>[[Spain]]
</arg><arg name="iso_region"><space/>
</arg><arg name="coordinates_display"><space/>
</arg><arg name="coordinates_format"><space/>
</arg><arg name="latitude"><space/>
</arg><arg name="longitude"><space/>
</arg><arg name="latd"><space/>
</arg><arg name="latm"><space/>
</arg><arg name="lats"><space/>
</arg><arg name="latNS"><space/>
</arg><arg name="longd"><space/>
</arg><arg name="longm"><space/>
</arg><arg name="longs"><space/>
</arg><arg name="longEW"><space/>
</arg><arg name="coordinates"><space/>
</arg><arg name="groundbreaking_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="start_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="completion_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="opened_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="inauguration_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="renovation_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="closing_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="height"><space/>
</arg><arg name="diameter"><space/>
</arg><arg name="circumference"><space/>
</arg><arg name="architectural"><space/>
</arg><arg name="tip"><space/>
</arg><arg name="antenna_spire"><space/>
</arg><arg name="roof"><space/>
</arg><arg name="top_floor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="observatory"><space/>
</arg><arg name="other_dimensions"><space/>
</arg><arg name="floor_count"><space/>
</arg><arg name="floor_area"><space/>
</arg><arg name="seating_type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="seating_capacity"><space/>
</arg><arg name="elevator_count"><space/>
</arg><arg name="grounds_area"><space/>
</arg><arg name="architect"><space/>
</arg><arg name="architecture_firm"><space/>
</arg><arg name="structural_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="services_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="civil_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="other_designers"><space/>
</arg><arg name="quantity_surveyor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="main_contractor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="awards"><space/>
</arg><arg name="designations"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_architect"><space/>[[Antoni Gaudí]]
</arg><arg name="ren_firm"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_str_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_serv_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_civ_engineer"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_oth_designers"><space/>[[Domènec Sugrañes i Gras]], Josep Canaleta, [[Joan Rubió]]
</arg><arg name="ren_qty_surveyor"><space/>
</arg><arg name="ren_awards"><space/>
</arg><arg name="rooms">
</arg><arg name="parking"><space/>
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>[http://www.casabatllo.cat casabatllo.cat]
</arg><arg name="embedded"><space/>
</arg><arg name="references"><space/>
</arg></template><bold>Casa Batll</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-ca</target><arg>ˈkazə βəˈʎːo</arg></template>) is a renowned building located in the center of<space/><link><target>Barcelona</target></link><space/>and is one of<space/><link><target>Antoni Gaud</target></link>s masterpieces. A remodel of a previously built house, it was redesigned in 1904 by Gaud and has been refurbished several times after that. Gaud's assistants<space/><link><target>Domnec Sugraes i Gras</target></link>, Josep Canaleta and<space/><link><target>Joan Rubi</target></link><space/>also contributed to the renovation project. The local name for the building is<space/><italics>Casa dels ossos</italics><space/>(House of Bones), as it has a<space/><link><target>viscera</target><trail>l</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>skeleton</target><part>skeletal</part></link><space/>organic quality.</paragraph><paragraph>Like everything Gaud designed, it is only identifiable as<space/><link><target>Modernisme</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Art Nouveau</target></link><space/>in the broadest sense. The ground floor, in particular, has unusual tracery, irregular oval windows and flowing sculpted stone work. There are few straight lines, and much of the<space/><link><target>faade</target></link><space/>is decorated with a colorful<space/><link><target>mosaic</target></link><space/>made of broken ceramic tiles (<link><target>trencads</target></link>). The roof is<space/><link><target>arch</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>and was likened to the back of a<space/><link><target>European dragon</target><part>dragon</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>dinosaur</target></link>. A common theory about the building is that the rounded feature to the left of centre, terminating at the top in a turret and cross, represents the lance of<space/><link><target>Saint George</target></link><space/>(patron saint of<space/><link><target>Catalonia</target></link>, Gaud's home), which has been plunged into the back of the dragon.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Initial construction (1877)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gaud%C3%AD_(1910).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part>Antoni Gaud in 1910</part></link>The building that is now Casa Batll was built in 1877 by Antoni Gaudi, commissioned by Llus Sala Snchez.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bassegoda i Nonell<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>La Casa Batlló<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.co.jp/books/about/La_Casa_Batll%C3%B3.html?id</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>March 8, 2012</arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Publicaciones de la Real Cátedra Gaudí<space/></arg><arg name="location">Barcelona<space/></arg><arg name="page">4<space/></arg><arg name="language">Spanish</arg></template></extension><space/>It was a classical building without remarkable characteristics within the<space/><link><target>eclecticism</target></link><space/>traditional by the end of the 19th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bassegoda i Nonell<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Los jardines de Gaudí<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.jp/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Edicions UPC<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9788483015384<space/></arg><arg name="page">75<space/></arg><arg name="language">Spanish</arg></template></extension><space/>The building had a basement, a ground floor, four other floors and a garden in the back.<extension extension_name='ref' name="workart"><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllo.es/en/history/casa-batllo/gaudi-work-art/'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Batll family</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Batllo-godo-per Napoleon.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>240px</part><part>The Batll family</part></link>The house was bought by Josep Batll in 1900. The design of the house made the home undesirable to buyers but the Batll family decided to buy the place due to its centralized location. It is located in the middle of<space/><link><target>Passeig de Gracia</target></link>, which in the early 20th century was known as a very prestigious and fashionable area. It was an area where the prestigious family could draw attention to themselves.<extension extension_name='ref' name="workart"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1906 Josep Batll still owned the home. The Batll family was very well known in Barcelona for its contribution to the textile industry in the city. Mr. Josep Batll I Casanovas was a textile industrialist who owned a few factories in the city. Mr. Batll married Amalia Godo Belaunzaran, from the family that founded the newspaper La Vanguardia. Josep wanted an architect that would design a house that was like no other and stood out as being audacious and creative. Both Josep and his wife were open to anything and they decided not to limit Gaud. Josep did not want his house to resemble any of the houses of the rest of the Batll family, such as Casa Pa, built by the Josep Vilaseca. He chose the architect who had designed<space/><link><target>Park Gell</target></link><space/>because he wanted him to come up with a risky plan. The family lived on the Noble Floor of Casa Batll until the middle of the 1950s.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllo.es/en/history/batllo-family/'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Renovation (1904-1906)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Casa Batll (Antoni Gaudi) (atrium,close up), 43, Passeig de Grcia, Eixample, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>240px</part><part>The atrium; Gaud convinced Batll to let him expand the central well of the building to let in light, instead of rebuilding.</part></link>In 1904 Josep Batll hired Gaud to design his home; at first his plans were to tear down the building and construct a completely new house. Gaud convinced Josep that a renovation was sufficient and was also able to submit the planning application the same year. The building was completed and refurbished in 1906. He completely changed the main apartment which became the residence for the Batll family. He expanded the central well in order to supply light to the whole building and also added new floors. In the same year the Barcelona City Council selected the house as a candidate for that years best building award. The award was given to another architect that year despite Gauds design.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Refurbishments</heading><paragraph>Josep Batll died in 1934 and the house was kept in order by the wife until her death in 1940 . After the death of the two parents the house was kept and managed by the children until 1954. In 1954 an insurance company named Seguros Iberia acquired Casa Batll and set up offices there. In 1970, the first refurbishment occurred mainly in several of the interior rooms of the house. In 1983, the exterior balconies were restored to their original colour and a year later the exterior faade was illuminated in the ceremony of<space/><link><target>La Merc</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Multiple uses</heading><paragraph>In 1993, the current owners of Casa Batll bought the home and continued refurbishments throughout the whole building. Two years later, in 1995, Casa Batll began to hire out its facilities for different events. More than 2,500 square meters of rooms within the building were rented out for many different functions. Due to the building's location and the beauty of the facilities being rented, the rooms of Casa Batll were in very high demand and hosted many important events for the city.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Design</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Casa Batll fireplace seat.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Casa Batll fireplace seat</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Overview</heading><paragraph>The local name for the building is<space/><italics>Casa dels ossos</italics><space/>(House of Bones), as it has a<space/><link><target>viscera</target><trail>l</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>skeleton</target><part>skeletal</part></link><space/>organic quality. The building looks very remarkable &amp;mdash; like everything Gaud designed, only identifiable as<space/><link><target>Modernisme</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Art Nouveau</target></link><space/>in the broadest sense. The ground floor, in particular, is rather astonishing with tracery, irregular oval windows and flowing sculpted stone work.</paragraph><paragraph>It seems that the goal of the designer was to avoid straight lines completely. Much of the<space/><link><target>faade</target></link><space/>is decorated with a<space/><link><target>mosaic</target></link><space/>made of broken ceramic tiles (<link><target>trencads</target></link>) that starts in shades of golden orange moving into greenish blues. The roof is<space/><link><target>arch</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/>and was likened to the back of a<space/><link><target>European dragon</target><part>dragon</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>dinosaur</target></link>. A common theory about the building is that the rounded feature to the left of centre, terminating at the top in a turret and cross, represents the lance of<space/><link><target>Saint George</target></link><space/>(patron saint of<space/><link><target>Catalonia</target></link>, Gaud's home), which has been plunged into the back of the dragon.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Loft</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Casa Batll Parabolic Arches.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part>The loft, originally a service area, has sixty<space/><link><target>Catenary</target></link><space/>arches</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The loft is considered to be one of the most unusual spaces. It was formerly a service area for the tenants of the different apartments in the building which contained laundry rooms and storage areas. It is known for its simplicity of shapes and its Mediterranean influence through the use of white on the walls. It contains a series of sixty<space/><link><target>Catenary</target></link><space/>arches that creates a space which represents the ribcage of an animal. Some people believe that the ribcage design of the arches is a ribcage for the dragons spine that is represented in the roof.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Noble floor and museum</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Casa Batll (Antoni Gaudi) (interior), 43, Passeig de Grcia, Eixample, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>240px</part><part>Interior of the Noble Floor, which currently houses a museum open to the public</part></link>The noble floor is larger than seven-hundred square meters, it is the main floor of the building. The noble floor is accessed through a private entrance hall that utilizes skylights resembling tortoise shells and vaulted walls in curving shapes. On the noble floor, there is a spacious landing with direct views to the blue tiling of the building well. On the Passeig de Gracia side is Mr. Batlls study, a festejador and a secluded spot for courting couples, decorated with a mushroom-shaped fireplace . The elaborate and animal-like dcor continues throughout the whole noble floor.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2002, the house opened its doors to the public and people were allowed to visit the noble floor. The building was opened to the public as part of the celebration of the International Year of Gaud. Casa Batll with very much unanticipated success and visitors became eager to see the rest of the house. Two years later, in celebration of the one hundredth anniversary of the beginning of work on Casa Batll the fifth floor was restored and the house extended its visit to the loft and the well. In 2005, Casa Batll became a<space/><link><target>Unesco World Heritage Site</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.worldsiteguides.com/europe/spain/barcelona/casa-batllo/'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Roof</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Jfader batto roof.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>240px</part><part>Four chimney stacks on the roof, with the dragon's spine roof arch behind</part></link>The roof terrace is one of the most popular features of the entire house due to its famous dragon back design. Gaud represents an animals spine by using tiles of different colors on one side. The roof is decorated with four chimney stacks, that are designed to prevent backdraughts.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllo.es/en/history/the-building/'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Exterior facade</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CasaBatllo 0170.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>The facade has three distinct sections.</part></link>The facade has three distinct sections which are harmoniously integrated. The lower ground floor with the main floor and two first-floor galleries are contained in a structure of<space/><link><target>Montjuc</target></link><space/>sandstone with undulating lines. The central part, which reaches the last floor, is a multicolored section with protruding balconies. The top of the building is a crown, like a huge gable, which is at the same level as the roof and helps to conceal the room where there used to be water tanks. This room is currently empty. The top displays a<space/><link><target>Molding (decorative)</target><part>trim</part></link><space/>with ceramic pieces that has attracted multiple interpretations.<space/></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Roof tiles</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:casa batllo roof.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>Roof architecture and ceramic tiles, with tower and bulb in the background</part></link>The roof's arched profile recalls the spine of a dragon with ceramic tiles for scales, and a small triangular window towards the right of the structure simulates the eye. Legend has it that it was once possible to see the Sagrada Familia through this window, which was being built simultaneously. The view of the<space/><link><target>Sagrada Familia</target></link><space/>is now blocked from this vantage point by newer buildings.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFCirici1956'>Circi 1956, pp. 161165</link></extension><space/>The tiles were given a metallic sheen to simulate the varying scales of the monster, with the color grading from green on the right side, where the head begins, to deep blue and violet in the center, to red and pink on the left side of the building.</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Tower and bulb</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>One of the highlights of the facade is a tower topped with a cross of four arms oriented to the cardinal directions. It is a bulbous, root-like structure that evokes plant life. There is a second bulb-shaped structure similarly reminiscent of a thalamus flower, which is represented by a cross with arms that are actually buds announcing the next flowering. The tower is decorated with monograms of Jesus (JHS), Maria (M with the ducal crown) and Joseph (JHP), made of ceramic pieces that stand out golden on the green background that covers the facade. These symbols show the deep religiosity of Gaudi, who was inspired by the contemporaneous construction of his basilica<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda1981'>Bassegoda 1981</link></extension><space/>to choose the theme of the holy family.</paragraph><paragraph>The bulb was broken when it was delivered, perhaps during transportation. Although the manufacturer committed to re-do the broken parts, Gaud liked the aesthetic of the broken masonry and asked that the pieces be stuck to the main structure with lime mortar and held in with a brass ring.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda_i_Nonell2001'>Bassegoda Nonell and 2001, p. 10.</link></extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Central section</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:Casa Batllo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>The central part of the facade evokes the surface of a lake with water lilies.</part></link>The central part of the facade evokes the surface of a lake with water lilies, reminiscent of<space/><link><target>Monet</target></link>'s Nymphas, with gentle ripples and reflections caused by the glass and ceramic mosaic.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda2001'>Bassegoda 2001, p. 75.</link></extension><space/>It is a great undulating surface covered with plaster fragments of colored glass discs combined with 330 rounds of polychrome pottery. The discs were designed by Gaud and Jujol between tests during their stay in Majorca, while working on the restoration of the Cathedral of Palma.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda1971'>Bassegoda 1971.</link></extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Balcony</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>Finally, above the central part of the facade is a smaller balcony, also iron, with a different exterior aesthetic, closer to a local type of lily. Two iron arms were installed here to support a pulley to raise and lower furniture.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFLahuerta2001'>Lahuerta 2001, p. 31.</link></extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Main floor</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>The facade of the main floor, made entirely in sandstone, and is supported by two columns. The design is complemented by joinery windows set with multicolored stained glass.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda_i_Nonell2001'>Bassegoda Nonell and 2001, p. 4.</link></extension><space/>In front of the large windows, as if they were pillars that support the complex stone structure, there are six fine columns that seem to simulate the bones of a limb, with an apparent central articulation; in fact, this is a floral decoration. The rounded shapes of the gaps and the lip-like edges carved into the stone surrounding them create a semblance of a fully open mouth, for which the Casa Batll has been nicknamed the &quot;house of yawns.&quot; The structure repeats on the first floor and in the design of two windows at the ends forming galleries, but on the large central window there are two balconies as described above.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://translate.googleusercontent.com/translate_c?rurl=translate.google.com&amp;amp;sl=ca&amp;amp;tl=en&amp;amp;twu=1&amp;amp;u=http://ca.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casa_Batll%25C3%25B3&amp;amp;usg=ALkJrhgeha9Kegk3qaXh9Yb8e30MUZpphA#CITEREFBassegoda_i_Nonell2001'>Bassegoda Nonell and 2001, p. 12.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Gaudi-Batllo-0279ret.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Facade of Casa Batll</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:CasaBatllo 0054.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Facade of Casa Batll</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image: Close up Casa Batlo.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Facade close-up</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:CasaBatllo 0096.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Interior of the Noble Floor</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Casa batllo chimney.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Close-up of a chimney</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image: staircase casa batllo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Unique design of the staircase and ceiling</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Casa Batll Fireplace.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Casa Batll fireplace</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Casa Batll Light Well.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Casa Batll central light well</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Casa Batll (Antoni Gaudi) (atrium), 43, Passeig de Grcia, Eixample, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Atrium of Casa Batll</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Casa Batll (Antoni Gaudi) (interior, ceiling close up), 43, Passeig de Grcia, Eixample, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Ceiling close-up</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Casa Batll (Antoni Gaudi) (interior, stained-glass window close up), 43, Passeig de Grcia, Eixample, Barcelona, Catalonia, Spain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Stained-glass window close-up</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Casa Batll chair.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Chair in oak, designed 1906</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Modernisme buildings in Barcelona</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>more references</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Official website</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllo.es/en'>Casa Batll</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllostore.com'>Casa Batll Store</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.casabatllo.es/en/virtual-tour/'>Official Virtual Tour</link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Unofficial websites</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.greatbuildings.com/buildings/Casa_Batllo.html'>Casa Batll on GreatBuildings.com</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.barcelona-tourist-guide.com/albums-en/gaudi-casa-batllo/index.html'>Casa Batll pictures</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.op.net/~jmeltzer/Gaudi/batllo.html'>Casa Batll description</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gaudidesigner.com/uk/casa-batllo.html'>Casa Batllo at Gaudidesigner.com</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://modernistespuntcom.blogspot.com/2010/04/casa-batllo.html'>Casa Batllo at Tot Passejant</link><space/><bold>(Spanish)</bold></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Barcelona landmarks</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Casa Batllo</target></template><link><target>Category:Visionary environments</target></link><link><target>Category:Modernisme architecture in Barcelona</target></link><link><target>Category:Antoni Gaud buildings</target></link><link><target>Category:Houses completed in 1877</target></link><link><target>Category:World Heritage Sites in Catalonia</target></link><link><target>Category:Visitor attractions in Barcelona</target></link><link><target>Category:Eixample</target></link><link><target>Category:Passeig de Grcia</target></link><link><target>Category:Art Nouveau houses</target></link><link><target>Category:Houses completed in 1904</target></link><link><target>Category:Houses in Catalonia</target></link></paragraph></article>