<article title='Agrarianism'><paragraph><bold>Agrarianism</bold><space/>has two common meanings. The first meaning refers to a<space/><link><target>social philosophy</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>political philosophy</target></link><space/>which values rural society as superior to urban society, the independent farmer as superior to the paid worker, and sees farming as a way of life that can shape the ideal social values.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thompson, Paul. 2010. Interview Eighteen in Sustainability Ethics: 5 Questions Ed. Ryne Raffaelle, Wade Robinson, and Evan Selinger. United States: Automatic Press</extension><space/>It stresses the superiority of a simpler rural life as opposed to the complexity of city life, with its banks and factories.</paragraph><paragraph>Secondly, the term &quot;agrarianism&quot; means political proposals for land redistribution, specifically the distribution of land from the rich to the poor or landless. This terminology is common in many countries, and originated from the &quot;Lex Sempronia Agraria&quot; or &quot;agrarian laws&quot; of Rome in 133 BC, imposed by<space/><link><target>Tiberius Gracchus</target></link>, that seized public land (<italics>ager publicus</italics>) used by the rich and distributed it to the poor.<extension extension_name='ref'>H. H. Scullard,<space/><italics>From the Gracchi to Nero: A History of Rome from 133 B.C. to A.D. 68</italics><space/>(1963) ch 2</extension><space/>This definition of agrarianism is commonly known as agrarian reform. In 18th- and 19th-century England and Ireland, the word identified any land reform movement that sought to redistribute farm lands more equally, especially to landless Irish families.<extension extension_name='ref' name="google1993"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Terry Mulhall</arg><arg name="title">The State and Agrarian Reform: The Case of Ireland 1800-1940</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">University of London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Philosophy</heading><paragraph><link><target>M. Thomas Inge</target></link><space/>defines agrarianism by the following basic tenets:<extension extension_name='ref'>M. Thomas Inge, ed.<space/><italics>Agrarianism in American Literature</italics><space/>(1969), introduction;<space/><link type='external' href='http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/HNS/Yoeman/agri1.html'>paraphrased</link></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Farming is the sole occupation that offers total independence and self-sufficiency.</listitem><listitem>Urban life, capitalism, and technology destroy independence and dignity and foster vice and weakness.</listitem><listitem>The agricultural community, with its fellowship of labor and co-operation, is the model society.</listitem><listitem>The farmer has a solid, stable position in the world order. He &quot;has a sense of identity, a sense of historical and religious tradition, a feeling of belonging to a concrete family, place, and region, which are psychologically and culturally beneficial.&quot; The harmony of his life checks the encroachments of a fragmented, alienated modern society.</listitem><listitem>Cultivation of the soil &quot;has within it a positive spiritual good&quot; and from it the cultivator acquires the virtues of &quot;honor, manliness, self-reliance, courage, moral integrity, and hospitality.&quot; They result from a direct contact with nature and, through nature, a closer relationship to God. The agrarian is blessed in that he follows the example of God in creating order out of chaos.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>History of agrarianism</arg></template>The philosophical roots of agrarianism include European and Chinese philosophers. The Chinese<space/><link><target>School of Agrarianism</target></link><space/>was a philosophy that advocated peasant utopian<space/><link><target>communalism</target></link><space/>and egalitarianism. In societies influenced by<space/><link><target>Confucianism</target></link>, the farmer was considered an esteemed productive member of society, but merchants who made money were looked down upon.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wp"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Deutsch<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eliot<space/></arg><arg name="author2"><space/>Ronald Bontekoei</arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>183</arg><arg name="title">A companion to world philosophies</arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley Blackwell</arg></template></extension><space/>That influenced European intellectuals like<space/><link><target>Franois Quesnay</target></link>, an avid<space/><link><target>Confucianism</target><part>Confucianist</part></link><space/>and advocate of China's agrarian policies, in form the French agrarian philosophy of<space/><link><target>Physiocracy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>L.A. Maverick, &quot;Chinese Influences upon the Physiocrats,&quot;<space/><italics>Economic History</italics>, 3:5467 (February 1938),</extension><space/>The Physiocrats, along with the ideas of<space/><link><target>John Locke</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Romantic Era</target></link>, formed the basis of modern European and American agrarianism.</paragraph><paragraph>United States president (1801-1809)<space/><link><target>Thomas Jefferson</target></link><space/>was a representative agrarian who built<space/><link><target>Jeffersonian Democracy</target></link><space/>around the notion that farmers are the most valuable citizens and the truest<space/><link><target>Republicanism in the United States</target><part>republicans</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas P. Govan, &quot;Agrarian and Agrarianism: A Study in the Use and Abuse of Words,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Southern History</italics>, Vol. 30#1 (Feb., 1964), pp. 3547<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2205372'>in JSTOR</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Agrarian parties</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of agrarian parties</arg></template>Peasant parties first appeared across Eastern Europe between 1860 and 1910, when commercialized agriculture and world market forces disrupted traditional rural society, and the railway and growing literacy facilitated the work of roving organizers. Agrarian parties advocated land reforms to redistribute land on large estates among those who work it. They also wanted village cooperatives to keep the profit from crop sales in local hands and credit institutions to underwrite needed improvements. Many peasant parties were also nationalist parties because peasants often worked their land for the benefit of landlords of different ethnicity.</paragraph><paragraph>Peasant parties rarely had any power before World War I but some became influential in the interwar era, especially in<space/><link><target>Bulgaria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Czechoslovakia</target></link>. For a while, in the 1920s and the 1930s, there was a<space/><bold>Green International</bold><space/>(<link><target>International Agrarian Bureau</target></link>) based on the peasant parties in Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia,<space/><link><target>Poland</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Serbia</target></link>. It functioned primarily as an information center that spread the ideas of agrarianism and combating socialism on the left and landlords on the right and never launched any significant activities.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bulgaria</heading><paragraph>In Bulgaria, the<space/><link><target>Bulgarian Agrarian National Union</target></link><space/>(BZNS) was organized in 1899 to resist taxes and build cooperatives. BZNS came to power in 1919 and introduced many economic, social, and legal reforms. However, conservative forces crushed BZNS in a 1923 coup and assassinated its leader,<space/><link><target>Aleksandar Stamboliyski</target></link><space/>(18791923). BZNS was made into a Communist puppet group until 1989, when it reorganized as a genuine party.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Czechoslovakia</heading><paragraph>In Czechoslovakia, the<space/><link><target>Republican Party of Agricultural and Smallholder People</target></link><space/>often shared power in parliament as a partner in the five-party ptka coalition. The party's leader,<space/><link><target>Antonin Svehla</target></link><space/>(18731933), was prime minister several times. It was consistently the strongest party, forming and dominating coalitions. It moved beyond its original agrarian base to reach middle-class voters.The party was banned by the<space/><link><target>National Front (Czechoslovakia)</target><part>National Front</part></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Second World War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sharon Werning Rivera, &quot;Historical cleavages or transition mode? Influences on the emerging party systems in Poland, Hungary and Czechoslovakia.&quot;<space/><italics>Party Politics</italics><space/>(1996) 2#2 : 177-208.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Romania</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Romania</target></link>, older parties from<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Moldavia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Wallachia</target></link><space/>merged to become the<space/><link><target>National Peasants' Party</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Iuliu Maniu</target></link><space/>(18731953) was a prime minister with an agrarian cabinet from 1928 to 1930, but the<space/><link><target>Great Depression</target></link><space/>made proposed reforms impossible. The communists dissolved the party in 1947, but it reformed in 1989 after they fell from power.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Serbia</heading><paragraph>In Serbia,<space/><link><target>Nikola Pai</target></link><space/>(18451926) and his<space/><link><target>People's Radical Party</target></link><space/>dominated Serbian politics after 1903. The party also monopolized power in Yugoslavia from 1918 to 1929. During the dictatorship of the 1930s, the prime minister was from that party.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tunisia</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Farmers' Voice Party</target></link><space/>won a seat in the district of<space/><link><target>Jendouba Governorate</target><part>Jendouba</part></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Tunisian parliamentary election, 2014</target><part>parliamentary election of 2014</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.isie.tn/documents/arrete-resultats-preliminaires.pdf in Arabic</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph>Historian F.K. Crowley finds that:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Australian farmers and their spokesman have always considered that life on the land is inherently more virtuous, as well as more healthy, more important and more productive, then life in the towns and cities....The farmers complained that something was wrong with an electoral system which produced parliamentarians who spent money beautifying vampire-cities instead of developing the interior.<extension extension_name='ref'>F.K. Crowley,<space/><italics>Modern Australia in Documents: 1901 1939</italics><space/>(1973) pp 77-78.</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>National Party of Australia</target><part>Country Party</part></link>, from the 1920s to the 1970s, promulgated its version of agrarianism, which it called &quot;<link><target>countrymindedness</target></link>&quot;. The goal was to enhance the status of the graziers (operators of big sheep ranches) and small farmers and justified subsidies for them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rae Wear, &quot;Countrymindedness Revisited,&quot; (Australian Political Science Association, 1990)<space/><link type='external' href='http://apsa2000.anu.edu.au/confpapers/wear.rtf'>online edition<space/></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>New Zealand</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>New Zealand Liberal Party</target></link><space/>aggressively promoted agrarianism in its heyday (18911912). The landed gentry and aristocracy ruled Britain at this time. New Zealand never had an aristocracy but it's wealthy landowners largely controlled politics before 1891. The Liberal Party set out to change that by a policy it called &quot;populism.&quot;<space/><link><target>Richard Seddon</target></link><space/>had proclaimed the goal as early as 1884: &quot;It is the rich and the poor; it is the wealthy and the landowners against the middle and labouring classes. That, Sir, shows the real political position of New Zealand.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Leslie Lipson</arg><arg name="title">The Politics of Equality: New Zealand's Adventures in Democracy</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1948</arg><arg name="publisher">U. of Chicago Press</arg></template></extension><space/>The Liberal strategy was to create a large class of small landowning farmers who supported Liberal ideals. The<space/><link><target>Liberal Government of New Zealand</target><part>Liberal government</part></link><space/>also established the basis of the later welfare state such as<space/><link><target>old age pensions</target></link><space/>and developed a system for settling industrial disputes, which was accepted by both employers and trade unions. In 1893, it<space/><link><target>women's suffrage in New Zealand</target><part>extended voting rights to women</part></link>, making New Zealand the first country in the world to<space/><link><target>women's suffrage</target><part>do so</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>To obtain land for farmers, the Liberal government from 1891 to 1911 purchased<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3,100,000</arg><arg>acres</arg><arg>ha</arg></template><space/>of Maori land. The government also purchased<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1,300,000</arg><arg>acres</arg><arg>ha</arg></template><space/>from large estate holders for subdivision and closer settlement by small farmers. The Advances to Settlers Act (1894) provided low-interest mortgages, and the Agriculture Department disseminated information on the best farming methods. The Liberals proclaimed success in forging an egalitarian, anti-monopoly land policy. The policy built up support for the Liberal party in rural North Island electorates. By 1903, the Liberals were so dominant that there was no longer an organized opposition in Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'>James Belich,<space/><italics>Paradise Reforged: A history of the New Zealanders</italics><space/>(2001) pp. 3946</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Tom Brooking, &quot;'Busting Up' the Greatest Estate of All: Liberal Maori Land Policy, 18911911,&quot;<space/><italics>New Zealand Journal of History</italics><space/>(1992) 26#1 pp. 7898<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nzjh.auckland.ac.nz/document.php?wid=802&amp;amp;action=null'>online</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Back-to-the-land movement</heading><paragraph>Agrarianism is similar to but not identical with the<space/><link><target>back-to-the-land movement</target></link>. Agrarianism concentrates on the fundamental goods of the earth, on communities of more limited economic and political scale than in modern society, and on simple living, even when the shift involves questioning the &quot;progressive&quot; character of some recent social and economic developments. Thus, agrarianism is not<space/><link><target>industrial farming</target></link>, with its specialization on products and industrial scale.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jeffrey Carl Jacob,<space/><italics>New Pioneers: The Back-to-the-Land Movement and the Search for a Sustainable Future</italics><space/>(Penn State University Press. 1997)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Agropedia</arg></template><template><target>div col</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Agrarian Justice</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Agrarian socialism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Agrarian society</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Agrarian system</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Physiocrats</target></link>, 18th-century French thinkers</listitem><listitem><link><target>International Agrarian Bureau</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nordic agrarian parties</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Yeoman</target></link>, English farmers</listitem><listitem><link><target>Permaculture</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><heading level='3'>Agrarian values</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Brass, Tom.<space/><italics>Peasants, Populism and Postmodernism: The Return of the Agrarian Myth</italics><space/>(2000)<space/></listitem><listitem>Brass, Tom.<space/><italics>Class, Culture and the Agrarian Myth</italics><space/>(2014)</listitem><listitem>Danbom, David B. &quot;Romantic Agrarianism in Twentieth-Century America,&quot;<space/><italics>Agricultural History</italics>, Vol. 65#4 (Autumn, 1991), pp.&amp;nbsp;112<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/3743942'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Grampp, William D. &quot;John Taylor: Economist of Southern Agrarianism,&quot;<space/><italics>Southern Economic Journal</italics>, Vol. 11#3 (Jan., 1945), pp.&amp;nbsp;255268<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1053268'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Hofstadter</target><part>Hofstadter, Richard</part></link>. &quot;Parrington and the Jeffersonian Tradition,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of the History of Ideas</italics>, Vol. 2, No. 4 (Oct., 1941), pp.&amp;nbsp;391400<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2707018'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Inge, M. Thomas.<space/><italics>Agrarianism in American Literature</italics><space/>(1969)</listitem><listitem>Kolodny, Annette.<space/><italics>The Land before Her: Fantasy and Experience of the American Frontiers, 16301860</italics><space/>(1984).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/library/book/the-land-before-her-fantasy-and-experience-of-the-american-frontiers-1630-1860-by-annette-kolodny.jsp'>onlin edition</link></listitem><listitem>Marx, Leo.<space/><italics>The Machine in the Garden: Technology and the Pastoral Ideal in America</italics><space/>(1964).</listitem><listitem>Murphy, Paul V.<space/><italics>The Rebuke of History: The Southern Agrarians and American Conservative Thought</italics><space/>(2000)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/parrington/'>Parrington, Vernon. ''Main Currents in American Thought'' (1927), 3-vol online</link></listitem><listitem>Quinn, Patrick F. &quot;Agrarianism and the Jeffersonian Philosophy,&quot;<space/><italics>Review of Politics</italics>, Vol. 2#1 (Jan., 1940), pp.&amp;nbsp;87104<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1404453'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Thompson, Paul, and Thomas C. Hilde, eds.<space/><italics>The Agrarian Roots of Pragmatism</italics><space/>(2000)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Sorokin, Pitirim A. et al., eds.<space/><italics>A Systematic Source Book in Rural Sociology</italics><space/>(3 vol. 1930) vol 1 pp.&amp;nbsp;1146 covers many major thinkers down to 1800</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Europe</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Batory, Agnes, and Nick Sitter. &quot;Cleavages, competition and coalition building: Agrarian parties and the European question in Western and East Central Europe&quot;<space/><italics>European Journal of Political Research,</italics><space/>(2004) Vol. 43, pp.&amp;nbsp;523546.<space/></listitem><listitem>Bell, John D.<space/><italics>Peasants in Power: Alexander Stamboliski and the Bulgarian Agrarian National Union, 18991923</italics>(1923)</listitem><listitem>Donnelly, James S.<space/><italics>Captain Rock: The Irish Agrarian Rebellion of 18211824</italics><space/>(2009)</listitem><listitem>Donnelly, James S.<space/><italics>Irish Agrarian Rebellion, 17601800</italics><space/>(2006)</listitem><listitem>Gross, Feliks, ed.<space/><italics>European Ideologies: A Survey of 20th Century Political Ideas</italics><space/>(1948) pp.&amp;nbsp;391481<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/read/8946552'>online edition</link>, on Russia and Bulgaria</listitem><listitem>Kubricht, Andrew Paul. &quot;The Czech Agrarian Party, 1899-1914: a study of national and economic agitation in the Habsburg monarchy&quot; (PhD thesis, Ohio State University Press, 1974)</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Merlan, Francesca<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tracking Rural Change: Community, Policy and Technology in Australia, New Zealand and Europe</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">ANU E Press</arg><arg name="page">60</arg><arg name="isbn">9781921536533</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Narkiewicz, Olga A.<space/><italics>The Green Flag: Polish Populist Politics, 18671970</italics><space/>(1976).</listitem><listitem>Oren, Nissan.<space/><italics>Revolution Administered: Agrarianism and Communism in Bulgaria</italics><space/>(1973), focus is post 1945</listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas Paine</target><part>Paine, Thomas</part></link>.<space/><italics>Agrarian Justice</italics><space/>(1794)</listitem><listitem>Patterson, James G.<space/><italics>In the Wake of the Great Rebellion: Republican, Agrarianism and Banditry in Ireland After 1798</italics><space/>(2008)</listitem><listitem>Roberts, Henry L.<space/><italics>Rumania: Political Problems of an Agrarian State</italics><space/>(1951).</listitem><listitem>Zagorin, Perez.<space/><italics>Rebels and Rulers, 15001660: Volume 1, Agrarian and Urban Rebellions : Society, States and Early Modern Revolution</italics><space/>(1982)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>North America</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Eisinger, Chester E. &quot;The Influence of Natural Rights and Physiocratic Doctrines on American Agrarian Thought during the Revolutionary Period,&quot;<space/><italics>Agricultural History</italics><space/>(1947) 21#1 pp.&amp;nbsp;1323<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/3739767'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Griswold, A. Whitney. &quot;The Agrarian Democracy of Thomas Jefferson,&quot;<space/><italics>American Political Science Review</italics><space/>(1946) 40#4 pp.&amp;nbsp;657681<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1950410'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Goodwyn, Lawrence.<space/><italics>The Populist Moment: A Short History of the Agrarian Revolt in America</italics><space/>(1978), 1880s and 1890s in U.S.</listitem><listitem>Hofstadter, Richard. &quot;Parrington and the Jeffersonian Tradition,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of the History of Ideas</italics><space/>(1941) 2#4 pp.&amp;nbsp;391400<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2707018'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Lipset, Seymour Martin.<space/><italics>Agrarian socialism: the Coperative Commonwealth Federation in Saskatchewan</italics><space/>(1950)</listitem><listitem>McConnell, Grant.<space/><italics>The decline of agrarian democracy</italics>(1953), 20th century U.S.</listitem><listitem>Mark, Irving.<space/><italics>Agrarian conflicts in colonial New York, 17111775</italics><space/>(1940)</listitem><listitem>Ochiai, Akiko.<space/><italics>Harvesting Freedom: African American Agrarianism in Civil War Era South Carolina</italics><space/>(2007)</listitem><listitem>Robison, Dan Merritt.<space/><italics>Bob Taylor and the agrarian revolt in Tennessee</italics><space/>(1935)</listitem><listitem>Stine, Harold E.<space/><italics>The agrarian revolt in South Carolina;: Ben Tillman and the Farmers' Alliance</italics><space/>(1974)</listitem><listitem>Summerhill, Thomas.<space/><italics>Harvest of Dissent: Agrarianism in Nineteenth-Century New York</italics><space/>(2005)</listitem><listitem>Szatmary, David P.<space/><italics>Shay's Rebellion: The Making of an Agrarian Insurrection</italics><space/>(1984), 1787 in Massachusetts</listitem><listitem>Woodward, C. Vann.<space/><italics><space/>Tom Watson: Agrarian Rebel</italics><space/>(1938)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/library/book/tom-watson-agrarian-rebel-by-c-vann-woodward.jsp'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Woodward, C. Vann. &quot;Tom Watson and the Negro in Agrarian Politics,&quot;<space/><italics>The Journal of Southern History,</italics><space/>(1938) 4#1 pp.&amp;nbsp;1433<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/pss/2191851'>in JSTOR</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Global South</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Brass, Tom (ed.).<space/><italics>New Farmers' Movements in India</italics><space/>(1995) 304 pages.</listitem><listitem>Brass, Tom (ed.).<space/><italics>Latin American Peasants</italics><space/>(2003) 432 pages.</listitem><listitem>Ginzberg, Eitan. &quot;State Agrarianism versus Democratic Agrarianism: Adalberto Tejeda's Experiment in Veracruz, 192832,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Latin American Studies</italics>, Vol. 30#2 (May, 1998), pp.&amp;nbsp;341372<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/158529'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Handy, Jim.<space/><italics>Revolution in the Countryside: Rural Conflict and Agrarian Reform in Guatemala, 19441954</italics><space/>(1994)</listitem><listitem>Jacoby, Erich H.<space/><italics>Agrarian unrest in Southeast Asia</italics><space/>(1949)</listitem><listitem>Newbury, David, and Catharine Newbury. &quot;Bringing the peasants back in: Agrarian themes in the construction and corrosion of statist historiography in Rwanda.&quot;<space/><italics>American Historical Review</italics><space/>(2000): 832-877.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2651812'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Paige, Jeffery M.<space/><italics><space/>Agrarian revolution: social movements and export agriculture in the underdeveloped world</italics><space/>(1978) 435 pages<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/Agrarian-Revolution-Jeffrey-M-Paige/dp/0029235502'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Sanderson, Steven E.<space/><italics><space/>Agrarian populism and the Mexican state: the struggle for land in Sonora</italics><space/>(1981)</listitem><listitem>Stokes, Eric.<space/><italics>The Peasant and the Raj: Studies in Agrarian Society and Peasant Rebellion in Colonial India</italics><space/>(1980)</listitem><listitem>Springer, S. (2012).<space/><link type='external' href='http://uvic.academia.edu/SimonSpringer/Papers/1564152/Illegal_evictions_Overwriting_possession_and_orality_with_laws_violence_in_Cambodia'>&quot;Illegal evictions? Overwriting possession and orality with laws violence in Cambodia.&quot;</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template><space/>Journal of Agrarian Change.</listitem><listitem>Tannenbaum, Frank.<space/><italics>The Mexican Agrarian Revolution</italics><space/>(1930)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thedeliberateagrarian.com/'>Writings of a Deliberate Agrarian</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newagrarian.com/'>The New Agrarian</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Simple living</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Agrarianism</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>