<article title='D%C3%A9j%C3%A0_vu'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Dj vu</bold>, (<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg name="audio">En-us-deja vu.ogg</arg><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>eɪ</arg><arg>ʒ</arg><arg>ɑː</arg><arg>_</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>v</arg><arg>uː</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>de.ʒa.vy</arg></template>) from<space/><link><target>French language</target><part>French</part></link>, literally &quot;already seen&quot;, is the<space/><link><target>phenomenon</target></link><space/>of having the strong sensation that an event or experience currently being experienced has already been experienced in the past,.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brown, A. S. (2003).<space/><italics>A Review of the Deja Vu Experience</italics>. Psychological Bulletin 129: 394-413.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>O'Connor, A. R; Moulin, C. J. A. (2010).<space/><italics>Recognition without identification, erroneous familiarity, and dj vu</italics>. Current Psychiatry Reports 12: 165-173.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Schnider, Armin. (2008).<space/><italics>The Confabulating Mind: How the Brain Creates Reality</italics>. Oxford University Press. pp. 167-168. ISBN 978-0-19-920675-9</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Blom, Jan Dirk. (2010).<space/><italics>A Dictionary of Hallucinations</italics>. Springer. pp. 132-134. ISBN 978-1-4419-1222-0</extension>Dj vu is caused by erroneous familiarity and dj vcu (the feeling of having &quot;already lived through&quot; something<extension extension_name='ref'>Ratliff, E. (02-06-2006). &quot;Dj Vu, Again and Again&quot;. The New York Times</extension>) by erroneous recollection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Illman, N. A., Butler, C. R., Souchay, C., and Moulin C. J. A. (2012). &quot;Dj Experiences in Temporal Lobe Epilepsy&quot;. doi:10.1155/2012/539567</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Scientific approaches reject the explanation of dj vu as &quot;<link><target>precognition</target></link>&quot; or &quot;<link><target>prophecy</target></link>&quot;, but rather explain it as an anomaly of memory, which creates a distinct impression that an experience is &quot;being recalled&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Meaning of Dj Vu&quot;, Eli Marcovitz, M.D. (1952).<space/><italics><link><target>Psychoanalytic Quarterly</target></link></italics>, vol. 21, pages: 481-489</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The dj vu experience</italics>, Alan S. Brown, Psychology Press, (2008), ISBN 0-203-48544-0, Introduction, page 1</extension><space/>This explanation is supported by the fact that the sense of &quot;recollection&quot; at the time is strong in most cases, but that the circumstances of the &quot;previous&quot; experience (when, where, and how the earlier experience occurred) are uncertain or believed to be impossible. Two types of dj vu are suggested to exist: the pathological type of dj vu usually associated with<space/><link><target>epilepsy</target></link><space/>and the non-pathological which is a characteristic of healthy people and psychological phenomenon.<extension extension_name='ref'>Warren-Gash, Charlotte, and Adam Zeman. (2003).<space/><italics>Deja vu</italics>. Practical Neurology 3: 106-109.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Nathan A. Illman, Chris R. Butler, Celine Souchay, and Chris J. A. Moulin. (2012).<space/><italics>Dj Experiences in Temporal Lobe Epilepsy</italics>. Epilepsy Research and Treatment 115.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Vlasov, P. N., A. V. Chervyakov, and V. V. Gnezditskii. (2013).<space/><italics>Dj vu phenomenon-related EEG pattern: Case report</italics>. Epilepsy &amp; Behavior Case Reports 1: 136-141.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Labate, Angelo; Cerasa, Antonio; Mumoli, Laura; Ferlazzo, Edoardo; Aguglia, Umberto; Quattrone, Aldo; Gambardella, Antonio. (2015).<space/><italics>Neuro-anatomical differences among epileptic and non-epileptic dj-vu</italics>. Cortex 64: 1-7.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 2004 survey concluded that approximately two-thirds of the population have had dj vu experiences.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Brown<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>A. S.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The déjà vu illusion<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Current Directions in Psychological Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>13<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>256–259<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.0963-7214.2004.00320.x</arg></template></extension><space/>Other studies confirm that dj vu is a common experience in healthy individuals, with between 31% and 96% of individuals reporting it. Dj vu experiences that are unusually prolonged or frequent, or in association with other symptoms such as hallucinations, may be an indicator of neurological or psychiatric illness.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wild-j-neurol-2005"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Wild</arg><arg name="first1">E</arg><arg name="title">Deja vu in neurology.</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of neurology</arg><arg name="date">Jan 2005</arg><arg name="volume">252</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">1–7</arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s00415-005-0677-3</arg><arg name="pmid">15654548</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Links with disorders</heading><paragraph>Early researchers tried to establish a link between dj vu and mental disorders such as<space/><link><target>anxiety</target></link>,<space/><link><target>dissociative identity disorder</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>schizophrenia</target></link><space/>but failed to find correlations of any diagnostic value.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brown2004"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brown<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alan S.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Déjà Vu Experience<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Psychology Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84169-075-9<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg></template></extension><space/>There does not seem to be a special association between dj vu and schizophrenia.<extension extension_name='ref'>T. Adachi, N. Adachi, Y. Takekawa, N. Akanuma, M. Ito, R. Matsubara, H. Ikeda, M. Kimura, H. Arai. (2006).<space/><italics>Dj Vu Experiences in Patients with Schizophrenia</italics>. Compr Psychiatry 47: 389-393.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Adachi, N., Adachi, T., Akanuma, N., Matsubara, R., Ito, M., Takekawa, Y., Ikeda, H., Arai, H. (2007).<space/><italics>Dj vu experiences in schizophrenia: relations with psychopathology and antipsychotic medication</italics>. Compr Psychiatry 48: 592-596.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The strongest pathological association of dj vu is with<space/><link><target>temporal lobe epilepsy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.neurologychannel.com/seizures/types.shtml'>Neurology Channel</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="pnoegm"><link type='external' href='http://people.howstuffworks.com/question657.htm'>Howstuffworks &quot;What is dj vu?&quot;</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Kovacs, N., Auer, T., Balas, I., Karadi, K., Zambo, K., Schwarcz, A., et al. (2009). Neuroimaging and cognitive changes during deja vu. Epilepsy and Behavior 14: 190-196.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Akgl S, ksz-Kanbur N, Turan G. (2013).<space/><italics>Persistent dj vu associated with temporal lobe epilepsy in an adolescent</italics>. Turk J Pediatr 55: 552-554.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Warren-Gash C, Zeman A. (2014).<space/><italics>Is there anything distinctive about epileptic dj vu?</italics>. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 85: 143-147.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wells CE, Moulin CJ, Ethridge P, Illman NA, Davies E, Zeman A (2014).<space/><italics>Persistent psychogenic dj vu: a case report</italics>. J Med Case Rep, 8: 414.</extension><space/>This correlation has led some researchers to speculate that the experience of dj vu is possibly a<space/><link><target>neurology</target><part>neurological</part></link><space/>anomaly related to improper electrical discharge in the brain. As most people suffer a mild (i.e. non-pathological)<space/><link><target>epileptic</target></link><space/>episode regularly (e.g. a<space/><link><target>hypnic jerk</target><part>hypnagogic jerk</part></link>, the sudden &quot;jolt&quot; that frequently, but not always, occurs just prior to falling asleep), it is conjectured that a similar (mild) neurological aberration occurs in the experience of dj vu, resulting in an erroneous sensation of memory. Scientists have even looked into genetics when considering dj vu. Although there is not currently a gene associated with dj vu, the LGII gene on<space/><link><target>chromosome 10</target></link><space/>is being studied for a possible link. Certain forms of the gene are associated with a mild form of epilepsy and, though by no means a certainty, dj vu occurs often enough during seizures that researchers have reason to suspect a link.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brynie</arg><arg name="first">Faith</arg><arg name="title">Brain Sense: The Science of the Senses and How We Process the World Around Us</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Amacom</arg><arg name="pages">195</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 2008 study found that dj vu experiences are unlikely to be pathological<space/><link><target>Dissociation (psychology)</target><part>dissociative experiences</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Adachi, N., Akanu, N., Adachi, T., Takekawa, Y., Adachi, Y., Ito, M. &amp; Ikeda, H. (2008).<space/><italics>Dj vu experiences are rarely associated with pathological dissociation</italics>. Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease, 196, 417419.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Pharmacology</heading><paragraph>Certain drugs increase the chances of dj vu occurring in the user. Some pharmaceutical drugs, when taken together, have also been implicated in the cause of dj vu. Taiminen and Jskelinen (2001)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Taiminen<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>T.<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>S.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Intense and recurrent déjà vu experiences related to amantadine and phenylpropanolamine in a healthy male
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Clinical Neuroscience
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>8
</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Jääskeläinen
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>460–462
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001
</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>11535020
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1054/jocn.2000.0810
</arg></template></extension><space/>reported the case of an otherwise healthy male who started experiencing intense and recurrent sensations of dj vu upon taking the drugs<space/><link><target>amantadine</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>phenylpropanolamine</target></link><space/>together to relieve flu symptoms. He found the experience so interesting that he completed the full course of his treatment and reported it to the psychologists to write up as a case study. Because of the<space/><link><target>dopaminergic</target></link><space/>action of the drugs and previous findings from electrode stimulation of the brain (e.g. Bancaud, Brunet-Bourgin, Chauvel, &amp; Halgren, 1994),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/brain/117.1.71
</arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>8149215
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994
</arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Bancaud<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J.
</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Brunet-Bourgin<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>F.
</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Chauvel<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>P.
</arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Halgren<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>E.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anatomical origin of déjà vu and vivid 'memories' in human temporal lobe epilepsy
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>117
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>71–90
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Brain : a journal of neurology
<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1
</arg></template></extension><space/>Taiminen and Jskelinen speculate that dj vu occurs as a result of hyperdopaminergic action in the mesial temporal areas of the brain.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Explanations</heading><heading level='3'>Memory-based explanations</heading><paragraph>Research has associated dj vu experiences with good memory function.<extension extension_name='ref'>Adachi, N., Adachi, T., Kimura, M., Akanuma, N., Takekawa, Y., Kato, M. (2003).<space/><italics>Demographic and psychological features of dj vu experiences in a nonclinical Japanese population</italics>. Journal of Nervous and Mental Disease 191: 242-247.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The similarity between a dj-vu-eliciting stimulus and an existing, but different, memory trace may lead to the sensation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brown2004"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Cleary2008"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Cleary, Anne M.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Recognition memory, familiarity and déjà vu experiences<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Current Directions in Psychological Science<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>17<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>353–357<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1467-8721.2008.00605.x<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5</arg></template></extension><space/>Thus, encountering something which evokes the implicit associations of an experience or sensation that cannot be remembered may lead to dj vu. In an effort to experimentally reproduce the sensation, Banister and Zangwill (1941)<extension extension_name='ref' name="Banister1941a"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Banister H, Zangwill OL<space/></arg><arg name="year">1941<space/></arg><arg name="title">Experimentally induced olfactory paramnesia<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[British Journal of Psychology]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">32<space/></arg><arg name="pages">155–175<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8295.1941.tb01018.x</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Banister1941b"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Banister H, Zangwill OL<space/></arg><arg name="year">1941<space/></arg><arg name="title">Experimentally induced visual paramnesias<space/></arg><arg name="journal">British Journal of Psychology<space/></arg><arg name="volume">32<space/></arg><arg name="pages">30–51<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.2044-8295.1941.tb01008.x</arg></template></extension><space/>used<space/><link><target>hypnosis</target></link><space/>to give participants posthypnotic amnesia for material they had already seen. When this was later re-encountered, the restricted activation caused thereafter by the posthypnotic amnesia resulted in three of the 10 participants reporting what the authors termed &quot;paramnesias&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Memory-based explanations may lead to the development of a number of non-invasive experimental methods by which a long sought-after analogue of dj vu can be reliably produced that would allow it to be tested under well-controlled experimental conditions. Cleary<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cleary2008"></extension><space/>suggests that dj vu may be a form of familiarity-based recognition (recognition that is based on a feeling of familiarity with a situation) and that laboratory methods of probing familiarity-based recognition hold promise for probing dj vu in laboratory settings.</paragraph><paragraph>A recent study that used virtual reality technology to study reported dj vu experiences supported this idea. This virtual reality investigation suggested that similarity between a new scene's spatial layout and the layout of a previously experienced scene in memory (but which fails to be recalled) may contribute to the dj vu experience.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cleary et al., 2012"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Cleary et al., 2012"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Cleary et al.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Familiarity from the configuration of objects in 3-dimensional space and its relation to déjà vu: A virtual reality investigation<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Consciousness and Cognition<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>21<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>969–975<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/j.concog.2011.12.010<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>22322010<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Brown<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>AS<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Sawyer<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>BD<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Nomi<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>JS<space/></arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Ajoku<space/></arg><arg name="first5"><space/>AC<space/></arg><arg name="last6"><space/>Ryals<space/></arg><arg name="first6"><space/>AJ</arg></template></extension><space/>When the previously experienced scene fails to come to mind in response to viewing the new scene, that previously experienced scene in memory can still exert an effectthat effect may be a feeling of familiarity with the new scene that is subjectively experienced as a feeling of dj vu, or of having been there before despite knowing otherwise.</paragraph><paragraph>Another possible explanation for the phenomenon of dj vu is the occurrence of &quot;<link><target>cryptomnesia</target></link>&quot;, which is where information learned is forgotten but nevertheless stored in the brain, and similar occurrences invoke the contained knowledge, leading to a feeling of familiarity because of the situation, event or emotional/vocal content, known as &quot;dj vu&quot;. Some experts suggest that memory is a process of reconstruction, rather than a recall of fixed, established events. This reconstruction comes from stored components, involving elaborations, distortions and omissions. Each successive recall of an event is merely a recall of the last reconstruction. The proposed sense of recognition (dj vu) involves achieving a good match' between the present experience and our stored data. This reconstruction however, may now differ so much from the original event that we know' we have never experienced it before, even though it seems similar.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Youngson</arg><arg name="first">R.</arg><arg name="title">Deja Vu</arg><arg name="url">http://www.credoreference.com/entry/rsmhealth/deja_vu</arg><arg name="work">The Royal Society of Medicine Health Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="publisher">Dr R.M. Youngson</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 October 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Robert Efron of Boston's Veterans Hospital in 1963 proposed that dj vu is caused by dual neurological processing caused by delayed signals in the brain. Efron found that the brain's sorting of incoming signals is done in the temporal lobe of the brain's left hemisphere. However, signals enter the temporal lobe<space/><italics>twice</italics><space/>before processing, once from each hemisphere of the brain, normally with a slight delay of milliseconds between them. Efron proposed that if the two signals were occasionally not synchronized properly then they would be processed as two separate experiences, with the second seeming to be a re-living of the first.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Robert<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Efron<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>TEMPORAL PERCEPTION, APHASIA AND DÉJÀ VU<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Brain<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>86<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>403–424<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/brain/86.3.403<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://science.howstuffworks.com/science-vs-myth/deja-vu4.htm'>How deja vu works by Lee Ann Obringer - How Stuff Works</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Dream-based explanation</heading><paragraph>One theory of dj vu attributes the feeling of having previously seen or experienced something to having dreamt about a similar situation or place, and forgetting about it until one seems to be mysteriously reminded of the situation or the place while awake.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Dream Directory: The Comprehensive Guide to Analysis and Interpretation<space/></arg><arg name="last">Lohff<space/></arg><arg name="first">David C.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Running Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7624-1962-8</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Related phenomena</heading><heading level='3'>Jamais vu</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Jamais vu<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jamais vu (from French, meaning &quot;never seen&quot;) is a term in psychology which is used to describe any familiar situation which is not recognized by the observer.</paragraph><paragraph>Often described as the opposite of dj vu, jamais vu involves a sense of eeriness and the observer's impression of seeing the situation for the first time, despite rationally knowing that he or she has been in the situation before. Jamais vu is more commonly explained as when a person momentarily does not recognize a word, person, or place that they already know. Jamais vu is sometimes associated with certain types of<space/><link><target>aphasia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>amnesia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>epilepsy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Theoretically, as seen below, a jamais vu feeling in a sufferer of a<space/><link><target>delirium</target><part>delirious</part></link><space/>disorder or intoxication could result in a delirious explanation of it, such as in the<space/><link><target>Capgras delusion</target></link>, in which the patient takes a person known by him or her for a false<space/><link><target>Body double</target><part>double</part></link><space/>or impostor. If the impostor is himself, the clinical setting would be the same as the one described as<space/><link><target>depersonalisation</target></link>, hence jamais vus of oneself or of the very &quot;reality of reality&quot;, are termed depersonalisation (or<space/><link><target>surreality</target></link>) feelings.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Times Online</italics><space/>reports (see<space/><link><target>semantic satiation</target></link>):<template><target>quotation</target><arg name="[[Chris Moulin]], of the [[University of Leeds]], asked 95 volunteers to write out "door" 30 times in 60 seconds. At the International Conference on Memory in Sydney last week he reported that 68 percent of the volunteers showed symptoms of jamais vu, such as beginning to doubt that "door" was a real word. Dr. Moulin believes that a similar brain fatigue underlies a phenomenon observed in some schizophrenia patients: that a familiar person has been replaced by an impostor. Dr. Moulin suggests they could be suffering from chronic jamais vu.<ref>{{cite news |url">http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,6-2282789,00.html |title</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Presque vu</heading><paragraph><link><target>Presque vu</target></link><space/>(from French, meaning &quot;almost seen&quot;) is the sensation of being on the brink of an<space/><link><target>epiphany (feeling)</target><part>epiphany</part></link>, such as when attempting to recall a word or name.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Dj entendu</heading><paragraph><bold>Dj entendu</bold>, (literally &quot;already heard&quot;) is the experience of feeling sure about already hearing something, even though the exact details are uncertain or were perhaps imagined.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://psychcentral.com/encyclopedia/2008/deja-entendu/
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Déjà Entendu
</arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Grinnel
</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Renée
</arg><arg name="work">
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="pages">
</arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>PsychCentral
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2011-04-10
</arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>{{inconsistent citations}}</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nevdgp.org.au/files/programsupport/mentalhealth/Mental%20State%20Exam%20-%20form.pdf?PHPSESSID=aebebbe47bf4cfb4119bc939249f47aa'>Mental Status Examination Rapid Record Form</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Capgras delusion</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Intuition (knowledge)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Psychological repression</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rapport congruency</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/ulterior-motives/201001/what-is-d-j-vu<space/></arg><arg name="title">What is déjà vu?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Psychology Today</arg><arg name="date">2010-01-05</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Draaisma<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Douwe<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Why life speeds up as you get older<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-521-69199-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="first"><space/>J.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Hughlinks-Jackson<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A particular variety of epilepsy "intellectual aura", one case with symptoms of organic brain disease<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Brain<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1888<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>11<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>179–207<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/11/2/179<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1093/brain/11.2.179<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2004/09/14/science/14deja.html?ex</arg><arg name="title">Déjà Vu: If It All Seems Familiar, There May Be a Reason<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">2004-09-14<space/></arg><arg name="first">Benedict<space/></arg><arg name="last">Carey<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-05-01</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2006/07/02/magazine/02dejavu.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Déjà Vu, Again and Again<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">2006-07-02<space/></arg><arg name="first">Evan<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ratliff<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-05-01</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.canada.com/ottawacitizen/news/story.html?id</arg><arg name="title">When déjà vu is more than just an odd feeling<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Ottawa Citizen<space/></arg><arg name="date">2006-02-20</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://serendip.brynmawr.edu/bb/neuro/neuro98/202s98-paper2/Johnson2.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">UGH! I Just Got the Creepiest Feeling That I Have Been Here Before: Déjà vu and the Brain, Consciousness and Self<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Neurobiology and Behavior<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://chronicle.com/free/v50/i46/46a01201.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Tease of Memory<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Chronicle of Higher Education<space/></arg><arg name="date">2004-07-23</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rebornspirit.com<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Psychology Of Deja Vu<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Science Daily<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-11-19</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.psychologicalscience.org/onlyhuman/2008/10/and-i-feel-like-ive-been-here-before.cfm<space/></arg><arg name="title">And I feel like I've been here before<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wray<space/></arg><arg name="last">Herbert<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Psychological Science<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-10-23</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>McHugh TJ<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dentate gyrus NMDA receptors mediate rapid pattern separation in the hippocampal network<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>317<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5834<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>94–9<space/></arg><arg name="date">July 2007<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>17556551<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1126/science.1140263<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="author2"><space/>Jones MW<space/></arg><arg name="author3"><space/>Quinn JJ<space/></arg><arg name="display-authors"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Balthasar<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>N.<space/></arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Coppari<space/></arg><arg name="first5"><space/>R.<space/></arg><arg name="last6"><space/>Elmquist<space/></arg><arg name="first6"><space/>J. K.<space/></arg><arg name="last7"><space/>Lowell<space/></arg><arg name="first7"><space/>B. B.<space/></arg><arg name="last8"><space/>Fanselow<space/></arg><arg name="first8"><space/>M. S.<space/></arg><arg name="last9"><space/>Wilson<space/></arg><arg name="first9"><space/>M. A.<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Neppe, Vernon. (1983).<space/><italics>The Psychology of Dj vu: Have We Been Here Before?</italics>. Witwatersrand University Press.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://medchrome.com/supernatural/deja-vu-scientifically-explained/'>Deja Vu: Scientifically Explained | Medchrome</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=67mD5nJ0cP4'>Anne Cleary discussing a virtual reality investigation of dj vu</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053810012000049'>Familiarity from the Configuration of Objects in 3-dimensional Space and Its Relation to Deja vu: A Virtual Reality Investigation</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.psychologytoday.com/blog/dream-factory/201410/dream-d-j-vu'>Dream Dj Vu</link><space/>-<space/><italics><link><target>Psychology Today</target></link></italics><space/></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cbc.ca/quirks/media/2005-2006/mp3/qq-2006-02-25d.mp3'>Chronic dj vu - quirks and quarks episode</link><space/>(mp3)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://skepdic.com/dejavu.html'>Dj vu<space/></link><space/>-<space/><italics><link><target>The Skeptic's Dictionary</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://science.howstuffworks.com/deja-vu.htm'>How Dj Vu Works</link><space/>&amp;mdash; a Howstuffworks article</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.deja-experience-research.org'>Dj Experience Research</link><space/>&amp;mdash; a website dedicated to providing dj experience information and research</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scientificamerican.com/article.cfm?id=braon-on-deja-vu&amp;amp;ref=rss'>Nikhil Swaminathan, ''Think You've Previously Read About This?''</link>,<space/><italics>Scientific American</italics>, June 8, 2007</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/2007/deja-vu-0607.html?tmpl=component&amp;amp;print=1'>Deberoh Halber, ''Research Deciphers Deju-Vu Brain Mechanics''</link>, MIT Report, June 7, 2007</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Deja Vu</target></template><link><target>Category:Memory processes</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of mind</target></link><link><target>Category:Perception</target></link><link><target>Category:Requests for audio pronunciation (English)</target></link></paragraph></article>