<article title='Communication'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>communication between living things</arg><arg>technological aspects</arg><arg>telecommunications</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Communicate</arg></template><template><target>Communication</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><bold>Communication</bold><space/>(from<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/><italics>commnicre</italics>, meaning &quot;to share&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>OEtymD</target><arg>communication</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-23</arg></template></extension>) is the<space/><link><target>Intention</target><part>purposeful</part></link><space/>activity of<space/><link><target>information</target></link><space/>exchange between two or more<space/><link><target>Open system (systems theory)</target><part>participants</part></link><space/>in order to convey or receive the intended<space/><link><target>meaning (linguistics)</target><part>meanings</part></link><space/>through a shared system of<space/><link><target>sign</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Semiosis</target><part>semiotic</part></link><space/>rules. The basic steps of communication are the forming of communicative intent, message composition, message encoding, transmission of signal, reception of signal, message decoding and finally interpretation of the message by the recipient.</preline></preblock><paragraph>Communication in general takes place inside and between three main subject categories: human beings, living organisms in general and communication-enabled devices (for example<space/><link><target>Wireless sensor network</target><part>sensor networks</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>control system</target><trail>s</trail></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.gwu.edu/~asc/cyber_definition.html</extension><space/>Communication in the category of living organisms (studied in the field of<space/><link><target>biosemiotics</target></link>) usually occurs through visual, auditory, or biochemical means. Human communication is unique for its extensive use of<space/><link><target>language</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Nonverbal communication</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Nonverbal communication</arg></template><link><target>Nonverbal communication</target></link><space/>describes the process of conveying meaning in the form of non-word messages. Examples of nonverbal communication include<space/><link><target>haptic communication</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chronemics</target><part>chronemic</part></link><space/>communication,<space/><link><target>gestures</target></link>,<space/><link><target>body language</target></link>,<space/><link><target>facial expression</target></link>,<space/><link><target>eye contact</target></link>, and how one dresses. Speech also contains nonverbal elements known as<space/><link><target>paralanguage</target></link>, e.g.<space/><link><target>rhythm (linguistics)</target><part>rhythm</part></link>,<space/><link><target>intonation (linguistics)</target><part>intonation</part></link>,<space/><link><target>tempo of speech</target><part>tempo</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Stress (linguistics)</target><part>stress</part></link>. Research has shown that up to 55% of human communication may occur through non verbal facial expressions, and a further 38% through paralanguage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mehrabian, A. (1972). Nonverbal communication. Transaction Publishers.</extension><space/>Likewise, written texts include nonverbal elements such as handwriting style, spatial arrangement of words and the use of<space/><link><target>emoticons</target></link><space/>to convey emotion.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of the reasons for Nonverbal communication are to complement and illustrate, to reinforce and emphasize, to replace and substitute, to control and regulate, to contradict. The Nonverbal communication contributes more percentage in human communication since they supplement the ideas/thoughts of the sender and also helps the receiver to decode it properly. Written texts include nonverbal elements such as handwriting style, spatial arrangement of words and the use of emoticons to convey emotion.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Verbal communication</heading><paragraph>Effective verbal or spoken communication is dependent on a number of factors and cannot be fully isolated from other important interpersonal skills such as non-verbal communication, listening skills and clarification.Human<space/><link><target>language</target></link><space/>can be defined as a<space/><link><target>system</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>symbol</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(sometimes known as<space/><link><target>lexeme</target><trail>s</trail></link>) and the<space/><link><target>grammar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(<link><target>wikt:rule</target><part>rules</part></link>) by which the symbols are manipulated. The word &quot;language&quot; also refers to common properties of languages.<space/><link><target>Language acquisition</target><part>Language learning</part></link><space/>normally occurs most intensively during human childhood. Most of the thousands of human languages use patterns of<space/><link><target>sound</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>gesture</target></link><space/>for symbols which enable communication with others around them. Languages tend to share certain properties, although there are exceptions. There is<space/><link><target>language or dialect</target><part>no defined line</part></link><space/>between a language and a<space/><link><target>dialect</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Constructed language</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Esperanto</target></link>,<space/><link><target>programming language</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and various mathematical formalism is not necessarily restricted to the properties shared by human languages. The communication is two way process instead of one way.</paragraph><paragraph>Effective Communication Process:</paragraph><paragraph><space/>Use standard terminology when communicatinginformation. Request and provide clarification when needed. Ensure statements are direct and unambiguous. Inform the appropriate individuals when the mission orplans change. Communicate all information needed by thoseindividuals or teams external to the team. Use nonverbal communication appropriately. Use proper order when communicating information.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Effective Communication.&quot;<space/><italics>Be Influenced, Figure 7-1 Presents a Communication Model. SHANNONS COMMUNICATIONS MODEL</italics>(n.d.): n. pag. Web.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Written communication and its historical development</heading><paragraph>Over time the forms of and ideas about communication have evolved through the continuing progression of technology. Advances include communications psychology and media psychology, an emerging field of study.</paragraph><paragraph>The progression of written communication can be divided into three &quot;information communication revolutions&quot;:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Xin Li</arg><arg name="title">Complexity Theory – the Holy Grail of 21st Century</arg><arg name="url">http://www.csee.wvu.edu/~xinl/complexity.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Lane Dept of CSEE, West Virginia University</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Written communication first emerged through the use of pictographs. The<space/><link><target>pictogram</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were made in stone, hence written communication was not yet mobile.</listitem><listitem>The next step occurred when writing began to appear on<space/><link><target>paper</target></link>, papyrus, clay, wax, etc. with common<space/><link><target>alphabet</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Communication became mobile.</listitem><listitem>The final stage is characterized by the transfer of information through controlled waves of<space/><link><target>electromagnetic radiation</target></link><space/>(i.e., radio, microwave, infrared) and other<space/><link><target>Signal (electrical engineering)</target><part>electronic signals</part></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Communication is thus a process by which meaning is assigned and conveyed in an attempt to create shared understanding. This process, which requires a vast repertoire of skills in<space/><link><target>interpersonal</target></link><space/>processing, listening, observing, speaking, questioning, analyzing, gestures, and evaluating enables<space/><link><target>collaboration</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cooperation</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">communication</arg><arg name="work">The office of superintendent of Public Instruction</arg><arg name="location">Washington</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Misunderstandings can be anticipated and solved through formulations, questions and answers, paraphrasing, examples, and stories of strategic talk. Written communication can be clarified by planning follow-up talks on critical written communication as part of the everyday way of doing business. A few minutes spent talking in the present will save valuable time later by avoiding misunderstandings in advance. A frequent method for this purpose is reiterating what one heard in one's own words and asking the other person if that really was what was meant.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heyman, Richard. Why Didn't You Say That in the First Place? How to Be Understood at Work.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Business communication</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Business communication</arg></template>Business communications is a term for a wide variety of activities including but not limited to: strategic communications planning, media relations, public relations (which can include social media, broadcast and written communications, and more), brand management, reputation management, speech-writing, customer-client relations, and internal/employee communications.</paragraph><paragraph>Companies with limited resources may only choose to engage in a few of these activities while larger organizations may employ a full spectrum of communications. Since it is difficult to develop such a broad range of skills, communications professionals often specialize in one or two of these areas but usually have at least a working knowledge of most of them. By far, the most important qualifications communications professionals can possess are excellent writing ability, good 'people' skills, and the capacity to think critically and strategically.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Barriers to effective human communication</heading><paragraph>Barriers to effective communication can retard or distort the message and intention of the message being conveyed which may result in failure of the communication process or an effect that is undesirable. These include filtering, selective perception, information overload, emotions, language, silence, communication apprehension, gender differences and political correctness<extension extension_name='ref'>Robbins, S., Judge, T., Millett, B., &amp; Boyle, M. (2011). Organisational Behaviour. 6th ed. Pearson, French's Forest, NSW p315-317.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>This also includes a lack of expressing &quot;knowledge-appropriate&quot; communication, which occurs when a person uses ambiguous or complex legal words, medical jargon, or descriptions of a situation or environment that is not understood by the recipient.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Physical barriers.</bold><space/>Physical barriers are often due to the nature of the environment. An example of this is the natural barrier which exists if staff are located in different buildings or on different sites. Likewise, poor or outdated equipment, particularly the failure of management to introduce new technology, may also cause problems. Staff shortages are another factor which frequently causes communication difficulties for an organization.</listitem><listitem><bold>System design.</bold><space/><link><target>System design</target></link><space/>faults refer to problems with the structures or systems in place in an organization. Examples might include an organizational structure which is unclear and therefore makes it confusing to know whom to communicate with. Other examples could be inefficient or inappropriate information systems, a lack of supervision or training, and a lack of clarity in roles and responsibilities which can lead to staff being uncertain about what is expected of them.</listitem><listitem><bold>Attitudinal barriers.</bold><space/>Attitudinal barriers come about as a result of problems with staff in an organization. These may be brought about, for example, by such factors as poor management, lack of consultation with employees, personality conflicts which can result in people delaying or refusing to communicate, the personal attitudes of individual employees which may be due to lack of motivation or dissatisfaction at work, brought about by insufficient training to enable them to carry out particular tasks, or simply resistance to change due to entrenched attitudes and ideas.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><bold>Ambiguity of words/phrases.</bold><space/>Words sounding the same but having different meaning can convey a different meaning altogether. Hence the communicator must ensure that the receiver receives the same meaning. It is better if such words are avoided by using alternatives whenever possible.</listitem><listitem><bold>Individual linguistic ability.</bold><space/>The use of<space/><link><target>jargon</target></link>, difficult or inappropriate words in communication can prevent the recipients from understanding the message. Poorly explained or misunderstood messages can also result in confusion. However, research in communication has shown that confusion can lend legitimacy to research when persuasion fails.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pmhut.com/what-should-be-included-in-a-project-plan'>What Should Be Included in a Project Plan</link><space/>- Retrieved December 18th, 2009</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://qbox.wharton.upenn.edu/documents/mktg/research/Bafflegab%20Pays.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bafflegab Pays<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>J. Scott Armstrong<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Psychology Today<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>12<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1980</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Physiological barriers.</bold><space/>These may result from individuals' personal discomfort, causedfor exampleby ill health, poor eyesight or hearing difficulties.</listitem><listitem><bold>Cultural differences.</bold><space/>These may result from the cultural differences of communities around the world, within an individual country (tribal/regional differences, dialects etc.), between religious groups and in organisations or at an organisational level - where companies, teams and units may have different expectations, norms and idiolects. Families and family groups may also experience the effect of cultural barriers to communication within and between different family members or groups. For example: words, colours and symbols have different meanings in different cultures. In most parts of the world, nodding your head means agreement, shaking your head means no, except in some parts of the world.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nageshwar Rao, Rajendra P.Das,<space/><italics>Communication skills,</italics><space/>Himalaya Publishing House, 9789350516669, p.48</extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Bypassing.</bold><space/>These happens when the communicators (sender and the receiver) do not attach the same symbolic meanings to their words. It is when the sender is expressing a thought or a word but the receiver take it in a different meaning. For example- ASAP, Rest room</listitem></list><paragraph>Fear of being criticized is a major factor that prevents good communication. If we exercise simple practices to improve our communication skill, we can become effective communicators. For example, read an article from the newspaper or collect some news from the television and present it in front of the mirror. This will not only boost your confidence, but also improve your language and vocabulary.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Communication with high achievers</heading><paragraph>In daily life we see people who are very good in our field and we want to discuss something but we hold our self back because of fear of getting neglected. We think that we are not good enough to discuss something with them. This kind of behavior mostly turns out to be harmful as we can get the knowledge that we dont have. Indeed not only the knowledge but also the connections with high profile peoples lead us to many opportunities.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Benefits of contacts with high achievers.</bold>In this era connection with high profile peoples is very important. Making connections with high profile peoples in our area is a great way to learn and grow. By communicating with high achievers one can know what is important and what is harmful to do in respective field. Also if someone talks to a leader or an achiever it provides a positive energy and inspires to be one of like them.</listitem><listitem><bold>How to interact with them?</bold><space/>Now, How to contact with high profile people is still a question? What and when we should ask them. Biggest thing that stops someone is fear. So when you are energized with their presentation is very good time to approach them. This positive energy helps to get past your fear. When a high profile person gives a talk he is also very energetic and involved with listeners, so it is a great time to contact them. Whenever we get a chance to communicate with a high achiever try not to waste their time, Ask them straight questions as they do not much time. Each time you connect to a leader try to end the conversation in a way that you can contact them again.</listitem><listitem><bold>What if they do not want any interaction?</bold><space/>What if he says no to you or do not want to talk to you. Well, in this case try to be positive instead of thinking that you are not important. May be he does not want to talk you because of his personal issues like he is busy in something or overwhelmed. Even we dont want to talk to anyone when we are focused. In the end they are also people like you and also want to communicate with others but in their own comfort.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Additional communication barriers</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Fear of reprisal for honest communication</listitem><listitem>Differing frames of reference among communicators</listitem><listitem>Lack of communication skills</listitem><listitem>Ego involvement</listitem><listitem>Turf wars</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Barriers to Interpersonal communication</heading><heading level='3'>Bypassing</heading><paragraph>It happens when the sender and the receiver do not match to the same symbolic meaning of their words. Eg: ASAP,Restroom.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Limited frame of reference</heading><paragraph>This frame of reference is a slow process of negotiation and which also takes more time to build the relationship.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Lack of knowledge skills</heading><paragraph>Inadequate vocabulary, poor expression.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Lack of listening skills</heading><paragraph>Non involvement, lack of quick reading/processing skills.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Emotional Interference</heading><paragraph>Focus-Content Vs Communicator</paragraph><paragraph>Process-Objective Vs Subjective</paragraph><heading level='3'>Physical Distractions</heading><paragraph>Faculty acoustics, noisy surroundings, wrong seating pattern.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Nonhuman communication</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Biocommunication (science)</arg><arg>Interspecies communication</arg><arg>Biosemiotics</arg></template>Every<space/><link><target>information exchange</target></link><space/>between living organisms&amp;nbsp; i.e. transmission of<space/><link><target>Signalling theory</target><part>signal</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that involve a living sender and<space/><link><target>Receiver (information theory)</target><part>receiver</part></link><space/>can be considered a form of communication; and even primitive creatures such as corals are competent to communicate. Nonhuman communication also include<space/><link><target>cell signaling</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cellular communication (biology)</target><part>cellular communication</part></link>, and chemical transmissions between primitive organisms like<space/><link><target>bacteria</target></link><space/>and within the<space/><link><target>plant</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fungi</target><part>fungal</part></link><space/>kingdoms.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Animals</heading><paragraph>The broad field of<space/><link><target>animal communication</target></link><space/>encompasses most of the issues in<space/><link><target>ethology</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Animal communication</target></link><space/>can be defined as any<space/><link><target>behavior</target></link><space/>of one animal that affects the current or future behavior of another animal. The study of animal communication, called<space/><italics>zoo semiotics</italics><space/>(distinguishable from<space/><link><target>anthroposemiotics</target></link>, the study of human communication) has played an important part in the development of<space/><link><target>ethology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sociobiology</target></link>, and the study of<space/><link><target>animal cognition</target></link>. Animal communication, and indeed the understanding of the animal world in general, is a rapidly growing field, and even in the 21st century so far, a great share of prior understanding related to diverse fields such as personal symbolic<space/><link><target>name</target></link><space/>use,<space/><link><target>emotion in animals</target><part>animal emotions</part></link>,<space/><link><target>animal culture</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>animal learning</target><part>learning</part></link>, and even<space/><link><target>animal sexuality</target><part>sexual conduct</part></link>, long thought to be well understood, has been revolutionized.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Plants and fungi</heading><paragraph>Communication is observed within the plant organism, i.e. within<space/><link><target>plant cells</target></link><space/>and between plant cells, between plants of the same or related species, and between plants and non-plant organisms, especially in the<space/><link><target>rhizosphere</target><part>root zone</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Plant root</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>communicate with<space/><link><target>rhizome</target></link><space/><link><target>bacteria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>fungi</target></link>, and insects within the<space/><link><target>soil</target></link>. These interactions are governed by syntactic, pragmatic, and semantic rules,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><space/>and are possible because of the decentralized &quot;nervous system&quot; of plants. The original meaning of the word &quot;neuron&quot; in Greek is &quot;vegetable fiber&quot; and recent research has shown that most of the microorganism plant communication processes are<space/><link><target>neuron</target></link>-like.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Baluska<space/></arg><arg name="first1">F.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Marcuso<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Stefano<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Volkmann<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Dieter<space/></arg><arg name="title">Communication in plants: neuronal aspects of plant life<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="page">19<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis US<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">3-540-28475-3<space/></arg><arg name="quote">...the emergence of plant neurobiology as the most recent area of plant sciences.</arg></template></extension><space/>Plants also communicate via<space/><link><target>volatile oil</target><part>volatile</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>when exposed to<space/><link><target>herbivory</target></link><space/>attack behavior, thus warning neighboring plants.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Rapid Changes in Tree Leaf Chemistry Induced by Damage: Evidence for Communication Between Plants<space/></arg><arg name="authors">Ian T. Baldwin, Jack C. Schultz<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Science<space/></arg><arg name="year">1983<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1126/science.221.4607.277<space/></arg><arg name="volume">221<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4607<space/></arg><arg name="pages">277–279<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In parallel they produce other volatiles to attract<space/><link><target>parasitism</target><part>parasites</part></link><space/>which attack these herbivores. In<space/><link><target>biotic stress</target><part>stress</part></link><space/>situations plants can overwrite the<space/><link><target>genomes</target></link><space/>they inherited from their parents and revert to that of their grand- or great-grandparents.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Fungi communicate to coordinate and organize their growth and development such as the formation of<space/><link><target>nobelium</target><part>Marcelia</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fruiting body</target><part>fruiting bodies</part></link>. Fungi communicate with their own and related species as well as with non fungal organisms in a great variety of symbiotic interactions, especially with bacteria,<space/><link><target>unicellular</target></link><space/>eukaryote, plants and insects through biochemicals of biotic origin. The biochemicals trigger the fungal organism to react in a specific manner, while if the same chemical molecules are not part of biotic messages, they do not trigger the fungal organism to react. This implies that fungal organisms can differentiate between molecules taking part in biotic messages and similar molecules being irrelevant in the situation. So far five different primary signalling molecules are known to coordinate different behavioral patterns such as<space/><link><target>filamentation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mating</target></link>, growth, and<space/><link><target>pathogenicity</target></link>. Behavioral coordination and production of signaling substances is achieved through interpretation processes that enables the organism to differ between self or non-self, a biotic indicator, biotic message from similar, related, or non-related species, and even filter out &quot;noise&quot;, i.e. similar molecules without biotic content.<extension extension_name='ref'>Witzany, G (ed) (2012). Biocommunication of Fungi. Springer. ISBN 978-94-007-4263-5</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bacteria quorum sensing</heading><paragraph>Communication is not a tool used only by humans, plants and animals, but it is also used by microorganisms like bacteria. The process is called<space/><link><target>quorum sensing</target></link>. Through quorum sensing, bacteria are able to sense the density of cells, and regulate gene expression accordingly. This can be seen in both gram positive and gram negative bacteria.This was first observed by Fuqua<space/><italics>et al.</italics><space/>in marine microorganisms like<space/><italics><link><target>Vibrio harveyi</target><part>V. harveyi</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Vibrio fischeri</target><part>V. fischeri</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Anand, Sandhya.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.biotecharticles.com/Biology-Article/Quorum-Sensing-Communication-Plan-For-Microbes-517.html'>Quorum Sensing- Communication Plan For Microbes</link></italics>. Article dated 2010-12-28, retrieved on 2012-04-03.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Models of communication</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Models of communication</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Communication shannon-weaver2.svg</target><part>Shannon and Weaver Model of Communication</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Communication emisor.jpg</target><part>Communication major dimensions scheme</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Interaction comm model.svg</target><part>Interactional Model of Communication</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Smcr.jpg</target><part>Berlo's Sender-Message-Channel-Receiver Model of Communication</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Transactional comm model.jpg</target><part>Transactional model of communication</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Encoding communication.jpg</target><part>Communication code scheme</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link><link><target>File:Linear comm model.svg</target><part>Linear Communication Model</part><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The first major model for communication was introduced by<space/><link><target>Claude Shannon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Warren Weaver</target></link><space/>for Bell Laboratories in 1949<extension extension_name='ref'>Shannon, C. E., &amp; Weaver, W. (1949).<space/><italics>The mathematical theory of communication</italics>. Urbana, Illinois:<space/><link><target>University of Illinois Press</target></link></extension><space/>The original model was designed to mirror the functioning of radio and telephone technologies. Their initial model consisted of three primary parts: sender, channel, and receiver. The sender was the part of a telephone a person spoke into, the channel was the telephone itself, and the receiver was the part of the phone where one could hear the other person. Shannon and Weaver also recognized that often there is static that interferes with one listening to a telephone<space/><link><target>conversation</target></link>, which they deemed noise.</paragraph><paragraph>In a simple model, often referred to as the transmission model or standard view of communication, information or content (e.g. a message in<space/><link><target>natural language</target></link>) is sent in some form (as<space/><link><target>spoken language</target></link>) from an emisor/ sender/<space/><link><target>encoder</target></link><space/>to a destination/ receiver/ decoder. This common conception of communication simply views communication as a means of sending and receiving information. The strengths of this model are simplicity, generality, and quantifiability. Claude Shannon and Warren Weaver structured this model based on the following elements:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>An information source, which produces a message.</listitem><listitem>A transmitter, which encodes the message into signals</listitem><listitem>A channel, to which signals are adapted for transmission</listitem><listitem>A noise source, which distorts the signal while it propagates through the channel</listitem><listitem>A receiver, which 'decodes' (reconstructs) the message from the signal.</listitem><listitem>A destination, where the message arrives.</listitem></list><paragraph>Shannon and Weaver argued that there were three levels of problems for communication within this theory.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The technical problem: how accurately can the message be transmitted?</listitem><listitem>The semantic problem: how precisely is the meaning 'conveyed'?</listitem><listitem>The effectiveness problem: how effectively does the received meaning affect behavior?</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Daniel Chandler</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Daniel Chandler</target></link>, &quot;The Transmission Model of Communication&quot;,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aber.ac.uk/media/Documents/short/trans.html'>Aber.ac.uk</link></extension><space/>critiques the transmission model by stating:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>It assumes communicators are isolated individuals.</listitem><listitem>No allowance for differing purposes.</listitem><listitem>No allowance for differing interpretations.</listitem><listitem>No allowance for unequal power relations.</listitem><listitem>No allowance for situational contexts.</listitem></list><paragraph>In 1960, David Berlo expanded on Shannon and Weaver's (1949) linear model of communication and created the SMCR Model of Communication.<extension extension_name='ref'>Berlo, D. K. (1960).<italics><space/>The process of communication</italics>. New York, New York: Holt, Rinehart, &amp; Winston.</extension><space/>The Sender-Message-Channel-Receiver Model of communication separated the model into clear parts and has been expanded upon by other scholars.</paragraph><paragraph>Communication is usually described along a few major dimensions: Message (what type of things are communicated), source / emisor / sender /<space/><link><target>encoder</target></link><space/>(by whom), form (in which form), channel (through which<space/><link><target>media (communication)</target><part>medium</part></link>), destination / receiver / target / decoder (to whom), and Receiver. Wilbur Schram (1954) also indicated that we should also examine the impact that a message has (both desired and undesired) on the target of the message.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schramm, W. (1954). How communication works. In W. Schramm (Ed.),<space/><italics>The process and effects of communication</italics><space/>(pp. 326). Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press.</extension><space/>Between parties, communication includes acts that confer knowledge and experiences, give advice and commands, and ask questions. These acts may take many forms, in one of the various manners of communication. The form depends on the abilities of the group communicating. Together, communication content and form make<space/><link><target>message</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that are sent towards a destination. The target can be oneself, another<space/><link><target>Interpersonal Communication</target><part>person</part></link><space/>or being, another entity (such as a corporation or group of beings).</paragraph><paragraph>Communication can be seen as processes of<space/><link><target>information transmission</target></link><space/>governed by three levels of<space/><link><target>semiotic</target></link><space/>rules:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><link><target>Pragmatics</target><part>Pragmatic</part></link><space/>(concerned with the relations between signs/expressions and their users)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Semantic</target></link><space/>(study of relationships between signs and symbols and what they represent) and</listitem><listitem><link><target>Syntactic</target></link><space/>(formal properties of signs and symbols).</listitem></list><paragraph>Therefore, communication is<space/><link><target>Interpersonal relationship</target><part>social interaction</part></link><space/>where at least two interacting agents share a common set of signs and a common set of<space/><link><target>semiotic</target></link><space/>rules. This commonly held rule in some sense ignores<space/><link><target>semiotics</target><part>autocommunication</part></link>, including<space/><link><target>intrapersonal communication</target></link><space/>via<space/><link><target>diary</target><part>diaries</part></link><space/>or self-talk, both secondary phenomena that followed the primary acquisition of communicative competences within social interactions.</paragraph><paragraph>In light of these weaknesses, Barnlund (2008) proposed a transactional model of communication.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barnlund, D. C. (2008). A transactional model of communication. In. C. D. Mortensen (Eds.),<space/><italics>Communication theory</italics><space/>(2nd ed., pp47-57). New Brunswick, New Jersey: Transaction.</extension><space/>The basic premise of the transactional model of communication is that individuals are simultaneously engaging in the sending and receiving of messages.</paragraph><paragraph>In a slightly more complex form a sender and a receiver are linked<space/><link><target>wikt:reciprocal</target><part>reciprocally</part></link>. This second attitude of communication, referred to as the constitutive model or constructionist view, focuses on how an individual communicates as the determining factor of the way the message will be interpreted. Communication is viewed as a conduit; a passage in which information travels from one individual to another and this information becomes separate from the communication itself. A particular instance of communication is called a<space/><link><target>speech act</target></link>. The sender's personal filters and the receiver's personal filters may vary depending upon different regional traditions, cultures, or gender; which may alter the intended meaning of message contents. In the presence of &quot;<link><target>noise</target><part>communication noise</part></link>&quot; on the transmission channel (air, in this case), reception and decoding of content may be faulty, and thus the speech act may not achieve the desired effect. One problem with this encode-transmit-receive-decode model is that the processes of encoding and decoding imply that the sender and receiver each possess something that functions as a<space/><link><target>codebook</target></link>, and that these two code books are, at the very least, similar if not identical. Although something like code books is implied by the model, they are nowhere represented in the model, which creates many conceptual difficulties.</paragraph><paragraph>Theories of<space/><link><target>coregulation</target></link><space/>describe communication as a creative and dynamic continuous process, rather than a discrete exchange of information. Canadian media scholar<space/><link><target>Harold Innis</target></link><space/>had the theory that people use different types of media to communicate and which one they choose to use will offer different possibilities for the shape and durability of society (Wark, McKenzie 1997). His famous example of this is using<space/><link><target>ancient Egypt</target></link><space/>and looking at the ways they built themselves out of media with very different properties stone and papyrus. Papyrus is what he called '<link><target>General semantics</target><part>Space Binding</part></link>'. it made possible the transmission of written orders across space, empires and enables the waging of distant military campaigns and colonial administration. The other is stone and '<link><target>General semantics</target><part>Time Binding</part></link>', through the construction of temples and the pyramids can sustain their authority generation to generation, through this media they can change and shape communication in their society (Wark, McKenzie 1997).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Noise</heading><paragraph>In any communication model, noise is interference with the decoding of messages sent over a channel by an encoder. There are many examples of noise:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Environmental noise.</bold><space/>Noise that physically disrupts communication, such as standing next to loud speakers at a party, or the noise from a construction site next to a classroom making it difficult to hear the professor.</listitem><listitem><bold>Physiological-impairment noise.</bold><space/>Physical maladies that prevent effective communication, such as actual<space/><link><target>deafness</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>blindness</target></link><space/>preventing messages from being received as they were intended.</listitem><listitem><bold>Semantic noise.</bold><space/>Different interpretations of the meanings of certain words. For example, the word &quot;weed&quot; can be interpreted as an undesirable plant in a yard, or as a euphemism for marijuana.</listitem><listitem><bold>Syntactical noise.</bold><space/>Mistakes in grammar can disrupt communication, such as abrupt changes in<space/><link><target>Grammatical tense</target><part>verb tense</part></link><space/>during a sentence.</listitem><listitem><bold>Organizational noise.</bold><space/>Poorly structured communication can prevent the receiver from accurate interpretation. For example, unclear and badly stated directions can make the receiver even more lost.</listitem><listitem><bold>Cultural noise.</bold><space/>Stereotypical assumptions can cause misunderstandings, such as unintentionally offending a non-Christian person by wishing them a &quot;Merry Christmas&quot;.</listitem><listitem><bold>Psychological noise.</bold><space/>Certain attitudes can also make communication difficult. For instance, great anger or sadness may cause someone to lose focus on the present moment. Disorders such as<space/><link><target>autism</target></link><space/>may also severely hamper effective communication.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roy M. Berko, et al., Communicating. 11th ed. (Boston, MA: Pearson Education, Inc., 2010) 9-12</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Communication as academic discipline</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Communication studies</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Media</arg><arg>Sociology</arg><arg>Technology</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Advice (opinion)</target><part>Advice</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Augmentative and alternative communication</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Communication rights</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Data communication</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human communication</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Inter Mirifica</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ishin-denshin</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sign system</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Small talk</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>SPEAKING</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Telecommunication</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Telepathy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Understanding</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template><template><target>Rahi Notes: Communication Skills, Shujaat Ali Rahi, Facebook</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Innis, Harold.<space/><italics>Empire and Communications</italics>. Rev. by Mary Q. Innis; foreword by Marshall McLuhan. Toronto, Ont.: University of Toronto Press, 1972. xii, 184 p.<space/><italics>N.B</italics>.: &quot;Here he [i.e. Innis] develops his theory that the history of empires is determined to a large extent by their means of communication.&quot;From the back cover of the book's pbk. ed. ISBN 0-8020-6119-2 pbk</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no
</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">no
</arg><arg name="others">no
</arg><arg name="about">yes
</arg><arg name="label">communication</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Communication</arg></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Human intelligence topics</target></template><template><target>Communication studies</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Rahi Notes: Communication Skills, Shujaat Ali Rahi, Faocebook</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Communication</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>