<article title='Digital_video'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>about</target><arg>digital techniques applied to video</arg><arg>the specific format</arg><arg>DV</arg></template><template><target>lead too short</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">January 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Digital video</bold><space/>is a representation of moving visual images in the form of encoded<space/><link><target>digital data</target></link>. This is in contrast to<space/><link><target>analog video</target></link>, which represents moving visual images with analog signals.</paragraph><paragraph>The terms<space/><italics><link><target>camera</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>video camera</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>camcorder</target></link></italics><space/>are used interchangeably in this article.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>Starting in the late 1970s to the early 1980s, several types of<space/><link><target>video production</target></link><space/>equipment that were digital in their internal workings were introduced, such as<space/><link><target>time base corrector</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(TBC) and<space/><link><target>digital video effects</target></link><space/>(DVE) units (one of the former being the<space/><link><target>Thomson-CSF</target></link><space/>9100 Digital Video Processor, an internally all-digital full-frame TBC introduced in 1980, and two of the latter being the<space/><link><target>Ampex</target></link><space/>ADO, and the<space/><link><target>Nippon Electric Corporation</target></link><space/>(NEC) DVE). They operated by taking a standard analog<space/><link><target>composite video</target></link><space/>input and digitizing it internally. This made it easier to either correct or enhance the video signal, as in the case of a TBC, or to manipulate and add effects to the video, in the case of a DVE unit. The digitized and processed<space/><link><target>video</target></link><space/>information that was output from these units would then be converted back to standard analog video.</paragraph><paragraph>Later on in the 1970s, manufacturers of professional video broadcast equipment, such as<space/><link><target>Robert Bosch GmbH</target><part>Bosch</part></link><space/>(through their<space/><link><target>Fernseh</target></link><space/>division),<space/><link><target>RCA</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Ampex</target></link><space/>developed prototype digital<space/><link><target>videotape recorder</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(VTR) in their<space/><link><target>research and development</target></link><space/>labs. Bosch's machine used a modified<space/><link><target>1 inch type B videotape</target><part>1&quot; Type B</part></link><space/>transport, and recorded an early form of<space/><link><target>CCIR 601</target></link><space/>digital video. Ampex's prototype digital video recorder used a modified<space/><link><target>Quadruplex videotape</target><part>2&quot; Quadruplex</part></link><space/>VTR (an Ampex AVR-3), but fitted with custom digital video electronics, and a special &quot;octaplex&quot; 8-head headwheel (regular analog 2&quot; Quad machines only used 4 heads). The audio on Ampex's prototype digital machine, nicknamed by its developers as &quot;Annie&quot;, still recorded the audio in analog as linear tracks on the tape, like 2&quot; Quad. None of these machines from these manufacturers were ever marketed commercially, however.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital video was first introduced commercially in 1986 with the Sony<space/><link><target>D1 (Sony)</target><part>D1</part></link><space/>format, which recorded an uncompressed<space/><link><target>standard definition</target></link><space/><link><target>component video</target></link><space/>signal in digital form instead of the high-band analog forms that had been commonplace until then. Due to its expense, and the requirement of component video connections using 3 cables (such as<space/><link><target>YPbPr</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Component video#RGB analog component video</target><part>RGB</part></link><space/>component video) to and from a D1 VTR that most<space/><link><target>television</target></link><space/>facilities were not wired for (composite NTSC or PAL video using one cable was the norm for most of them at that time), D1 was used primarily by large<space/><link><target>television network</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other component-video capable video studios.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1988, Sony and Ampex co-developed and released the<space/><link><target>D-2 (video)</target><part>D2</part></link><space/>digital videocassette format, which recorded video digitally without compression in<space/><link><target>ITU-601</target></link><space/>format, much like D1. But D2 had the major difference of encoding the video in composite form to the NTSC standard, thereby only requiring single-cable composite video connections to and from a D2 VCR, making it a perfect fit for the majority of television facilities at the time. This made D2 quite a successful format in the<space/><link><target>television broadcast</target></link><space/>industry throughout the late '80s and the '90s. D2 was also widely used in that era as the master tape format for mastering<space/><link><target>laserdiscs</target></link><space/>(prior to D2, most laserdiscs were mastered using analog<space/><link><target>1&quot; Type C videotape</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>D1 &amp; D2 would eventually be replaced by cheaper systems using<space/><link><target>video compression</target></link>, most notably Sony's<space/><link><target>Digital Betacam</target></link><space/>(still heavily used as an<space/><link><target>electronic field production</target></link><space/>(EFP) recording format by professional television producers) that were introduced into the network's<space/><link><target>television studio</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Other examples of digital video formats utilizing compression were Ampex's<space/><link><target>DCT (videocassette format)</target><part>DCT</part></link><space/>(the first to employ such when introduced in 1992), the industry-standard<space/><link><target>DV</target></link><space/>and MiniDV (and its professional variations, Sony's<space/><link><target>DVCAM</target></link><space/>and Panasonic's<space/><link><target>DVCPRO</target></link>), and<space/><link><target>Betacam SX</target></link>, a lower-cost variant of Digital Betacam using<space/><link><target>MPEG-2</target></link><space/>compression.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the first digital video products to run on personal computers was<space/><italics>PACo: The PICS Animation Compiler</italics><space/>from The Company of Science &amp; Art in Providence, RI, which was developed starting in 1990 and first shipped in May 1991.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>CoSA Lives: The Story of the Company Behind After Effects</italics>, http://www.motionworks.com.au/2009/11/cosa-lives/, retrieved 11/15/2009.</extension><space/>PACo could stream unlimited-length video with synchronized sound from a single file (with the &quot;.CAV&quot;<space/><link><target>file extension</target></link>) on CD-ROM. Creation required a Mac; playback was possible on Macs, PCs, and Sun Sparcstations. In 1992, Bernard Luskin, Philips Interactive Media, and Eric Doctorow, Paramount Worldwide Video, successfully put the first fifty videos in digital MPEG 1 on CD, developed the packaging and launched movies on CD, leading to advancing versions of MPEG, and to DVD.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>QuickTime</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Apple Computer</target></link>'s architecture for time-based and streaming data formats appeared in June, 1991. Initial consumer-level content creation tools were crude, requiring an analog video source to be digitized to a computer-readable format. While low-quality at first, consumer digital video increased rapidly in quality, first with the introduction of playback standards such as<space/><link><target>MPEG-1</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>MPEG-2</target></link><space/>(adopted for use in television transmission and<space/><link><target>DVD</target></link><space/>media), and then the introduction of the<space/><link><target>DV</target></link><space/>tape format allowing recordings in the format to be transferred direct to digital video files (containing the same video data recorded on the transferred DV tape) on an editing computer and simplifying the editing process, allowing<space/><link><target>non-linear editing system</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(NLE) to be deployed cheaply and widely on<space/><link><target>desktop computer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with no external playback/recording equipment needed, save for the computer simply requiring a<space/><link><target>FireWire</target></link><space/>port to interface to the DV-format camera or VCR. The widespread adoption of digital video has also drastically reduced the bandwidth needed for a<space/><link><target>high-definition video</target></link><space/>signal (with<space/><link><target>HDV</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>AVCHD</target></link>, as well as several commercial variants such as<space/><link><target>DVCPRO</target></link>-HD, all using less bandwidth than a standard definition analog signal) and<space/><link><target>tapeless camcorder</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>based on<space/><link><target>flash memory</target></link><space/>and often a variant of<space/><link><target>MPEG-4</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview of basic properties</heading><paragraph>Digital video comprises a series of orthogonal bitmap<space/><link><target>digital image</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>displayed in rapid succession at a constant rate. In the context of video these images are called<space/><bold><link><target>film frame</target><part>frames</part></link></bold>.<extension extension_name='ref'>In fact the still images correspond to frames only in the case of progressive scan video. In interlaced video they correspond to fields. See section about interlacing for clarification</extension><space/>We measure the rate at which frames are displayed in<space/><bold>frames per second (FPS)</bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>Since every frame is an orthogonal bitmap digital image it comprises a raster of<space/><bold><link><target>pixel</target><trail>s</trail></link></bold>. If it has a width of<space/><bold>W</bold><space/>pixels and a height of<space/><bold>H</bold><space/>pixels we say that the<space/><bold>frame size</bold><space/>is W<italics>x</italics>H.</paragraph><paragraph>Pixels have only one property, their color. The color of a pixel is represented by a fixed number of bits. The more bits the more subtle variations of colors can be reproduced. This is called the<space/><bold><link><target>color depth</target><part>color depth (CD)</part></link></bold><space/>of the video.</paragraph><paragraph>An example video can have a<space/><bold>duration (T)</bold><space/>of 1 hour (3600<italics>sec</italics>), a frame size of 640x480<space/><italics>(WxH)</italics><space/>at a color depth of 24<italics>bits</italics><space/>and a frame rate of 25<italics>fps</italics>. This example video has the following properties:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>pixels per frame</bold><space/>= 640 * 480 = 307,200</listitem><listitem><bold>bits per frame</bold><space/>= 307,200 * 24 = 7,372,800 = 7.37<italics>Mbits</italics></listitem><listitem><bold>bit rate (BR)</bold><space/>= 7.37 * 25 = 184.25<bold><italics>Mbits/sec</italics></bold></listitem><listitem><bold>video size (VS)</bold><extension extension_name='ref'>we use the term<space/><italics>video size</italics><space/>instead of just<space/><italics>size</italics><space/>in order to avoid confusion with the<space/><italics>frame size</italics></extension><space/>= 184<italics>Mbits/sec</italics><space/>* 3600<italics>sec</italics><space/>= 662,400<italics>Mbits</italics><space/>= 82,800<italics>Mbytes</italics><space/>= 82.8<bold><italics>Gbytes</italics></bold></listitem></list><paragraph>The most important properties are<space/><italics>bit rate</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>video size</italics>. The formulas relating those two with all other properties are:</paragraph><preblock><preline>BR = W * H * CD * FPS</preline><preline>VS = BR * T = W * H * CD * FPS * T</preline><preline>(units are: BR in bit/s, W and H in pixels, CD in bits, VS in bits, T in seconds)</preline></preblock><paragraph>while some secondary formulas are:</paragraph><preblock><preline><italics>pixels_per_frame</italics><space/>= W * H</preline><preline><italics>pixels_per_second</italics><space/>= W * H * FPS</preline><preline><italics>bits_per_frame</italics><space/>= W * H * CD</preline></preblock><heading level='3'>Regarding Interlacing</heading><paragraph>In interlaced video each<space/><italics>frame</italics><space/>is composed of two<space/><italics>halves of an image</italics>. The first half contains only the odd-numbered lines of a full frame. The second half contains only the even-numbered lines. Those halves are referred to individually as<space/><italics>fields</italics>. Two consecutive fields compose a full frame. If an interlaced video has a frame rate of 15 frames per second the field rate is 30 fields per second. All the properties and formulas discussed here apply equally to interlaced video but one should be careful not to confuse the fields per second rate with the frames per second rate.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Properties of compressed video</heading><paragraph>The above are accurate for<space/><link><target>uncompressed video</target></link>. Because of the relatively high bit rate of uncompressed video,<space/><link><target>video compression</target></link><space/>is extensively used. In the case of compressed video each frame requires a small percentage of the original bits. Assuming a<space/><link><target>compression algorithm</target></link><space/>that shrinks the input data by a factor of<space/><bold>CF</bold>, the bit rate and video size would equal to:</paragraph><preblock><preline>BR = W * H * CD * FPS / CF</preline><preline>VS = BR * T / CF</preline></preblock><paragraph>Please note that it is not necessary that all frames are equally compressed by a factor of CF. In practice they are not, so CF is the<space/><italics>average</italics><space/>factor of compression for<space/><italics>all</italics><space/>the frames taken together.</paragraph><paragraph>The above equation for the bit rate can be rewritten by combining the compression factor and the color depth like this:</paragraph><preblock><preline>BR = W * H * ( CD / CF ) * FPS</preline></preblock><paragraph>The value<space/><bold>(CD / CF)</bold><space/>represents the<space/><bold>average bits per pixel (BPP)</bold>. As an example, if we have a color depth of 12bits/pixel and an algorithm that compresses at 40x, then BPP equals 0.3 (12/40). So in the case of compressed video the formula for bit rate is:</paragraph><preblock><preline>BR = W * H * BPP * FPS</preline></preblock><paragraph>In fact the same formula is valid for uncompressed video because in that case one can assume that the &quot;compression&quot; factor is 1 and that the average bits per pixel equal the color depth.</paragraph><heading level='3'>More on bit rate and BPP</heading><paragraph>As is obvious by its definition<space/><link><target>bit rate</target></link><space/>is a measure of the rate of information content of the digital video stream. In the case of uncompressed video, bit rate corresponds directly to the quality of the video (remember that bit rate is proportional to every property that affects the<space/><link><target>video quality</target></link>). Bit rate is an important property when transmitting video because the transmission link must be capable of supporting that bit rate.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://animationants.com/explainer-videos-the-perfect-marketing-tool-for-all-businesses/</extension><space/>Bit rate is also important when dealing with the storage of video because, as shown above, the video size is proportional to the bit rate and the duration. Bit rate of uncompressed video is too high for most practical applications.<space/><link><target>Video compression</target></link><space/>is used to greatly reduce the bit rate.</paragraph><paragraph>BPP is a measure of the efficiency of compression. A true-color video with no compression at all may have a BPP of 24 bits/pixel.<space/><link><target>Chroma subsampling</target></link><space/>can reduce the BPP to 16 or 12 bits/pixel. Applying<space/><link><target>jpeg</target></link><space/>compression on every frame can reduce the BPP to 8 or even 1 bits/pixel. Applying video compression algorithms like<space/><link><target>MPEG1</target></link>,<space/><link><target>MPEG2</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>MPEG4</target></link><space/>allows for fractional BPP values.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Constant bit rate versus variable bit rate</heading><paragraph>As noted above BPP represents the<space/><italics>average</italics><space/>bits per pixel. There are compression algorithms that keep the BPP almost constant throughout the entire duration of the video. In this case we also get video output with a<space/><link><target>Constant bitrate</target><part>constant bit rate (CBR)</part></link>. This CBR video is suitable for real-time, non-buffered, fixed bandwidth video streaming (e.g. in videoconferencing).</paragraph><paragraph>Noting that not all frames can be compressed at the same level because quality is more severely impacted for scenes of high complexity some algorithms try to constantly adjust the BPP. They keep it high while compressing complex scenes and low for less demanding scenes. This way one gets the best quality at the smallest average bit rate (and the smallest file size accordingly). Of course when using this method the<space/><link><target>Variable Bit Rate</target><part>bit rate is variable</part></link><space/>because it tracks the variations of the BPP.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Technical overview</heading><paragraph>Standard<space/><link><target>film stock</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>16 mm</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>35 mm</target></link><space/>record at 24<space/><link><target>frame rate</target><part>frames per second</part></link>. For video, there are two frame rate standards:<space/><link><target>NTSC</target></link>, which shoot at 30/1.001 (about 29.97) frames per second or 59.94 fields per second, and<space/><link><target>PAL</target></link>, 25 frames per second or 50 fields per second.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital video cameras come in two different image capture formats:<space/><link><target>Interlaced video</target><part>interlace</part><trail>d</trail></link><space/>and deinterlaced /<space/><link><target>progressive scan</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Interlaced cameras record the image in alternating sets of lines: the odd-numbered lines are scanned, and then the even-numbered lines are scanned, then the odd-numbered lines are scanned again, and so on. One set of odd or even lines is referred to as a &quot;field&quot;, and a consecutive pairing of two fields of opposite parity is called a<space/><italics>frame</italics>. Deinterlaced cameras records each frame as distinct, with all scan lines being captured at the same moment in time. Thus, interlaced video captures samples the scene motion twice as often as progressive video does, for the same number of<space/><link><target>frame rate</target><part>frames per second</part></link>. Progressive-scan camcorders generally produce a slightly sharper image. However, motion may not be as smooth as interlaced video which uses 50 or 59.94 fields per second, particularly if they employ the 24 frames per second standard of film.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital video can be copied with no degradation in quality. No matter how many generations of a digital source is copied, it will still be as clear as the original first generation of digital footage. However a change in parameters like frame size as well as a change of the digital format can decrease the quality of the video due to new calculations that have to be made. Digital video can be manipulated and edited to follow an order or sequence on an NLE, or<space/><link><target>non-linear editing</target></link><space/>workstation, a computer-based device intended to edit video and<space/><link><target>sound recording</target><part>audio</part></link>. More and more, videos are edited on readily available, increasingly affordable consumer-grade computer hardware and software. However, such editing systems require ample disk space for video footage. The many video formats and parameters to be set make it quite impossible to come up with a specific number for how many minutes need how much time.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital video has a significantly lower cost than 35&amp;nbsp;mm film. The<space/><link><target>film stock</target></link><space/>itself is very inexpensive. Digital video also allows footage to be viewed on location without the expensive chemical processing required by film. Also physical deliveries of tapes and broadcasts do not apply anymore.<space/><link><target>Digital television</target></link><space/>(including higher quality<space/><link><target>High Definition Television</target><part>HDTV</part></link>) started to spread in most developed countries in early 2000s. Digital video is also used in modern<space/><link><target>mobile phones</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Video teleconference</target><part>video conferencing</part></link><space/>systems. Digital video is also used for<space/><link><target>Internet</target></link><space/>distribution of media, including<space/><link><target>streaming video</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>peer-to-peer</target></link><space/>movie distribution. However even within Europe are lots of TV-Stations not broadcasting in HD, due to restricted budgets for new equipment for processing HD.</paragraph><paragraph>Many types of<space/><link><target>video compression</target></link><space/>exist for serving digital video over the internet and on optical disks. The file sizes of digital video used for professional editing are generally not practical for these purposes, and the video requires further compression with codecs such as Sorenson, H.264 and more recently Apple ProRes especially for HD. Probably the most widely used formats for delivering video over the internet are MPEG4, Quicktime, Flash and Windows Media, while MPEG2 is used almost exclusively for DVDs, providing an exceptional image in minimal size but resulting in a high level of CPU consumption to decompress.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>As of</target><arg>2011</arg></template>, the highest resolution demonstrated for digital video generation is 35<space/><link><target>megapixel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(8192 x 4320). The highest speed is attained in industrial and scientific<space/><link><target>high speed camera</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that are capable of filming 1024x1024 video at up to 1 million frames per second for brief periods of recording.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Interfaces and cables</heading><paragraph>Many interfaces have been designed specifically to handle the requirements of uncompressed digital video (from roughly 400 Mbit/s to 10 Gbit/s):</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>HDMI</target><part>High-Definition Multimedia Interface</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Digital Visual Interface</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Serial Digital Interface</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>DisplayPort</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Digital component video</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Unified Display Interface</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>IEEE 1394</target><part>FireWire</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Universal Serial Bus</target><part>USB</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph>The following interface has been designed for carrying<space/><link><target>Moving Picture Experts Group</target><part>MPEG</part></link>-Transport compressed video:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Digital Video Broadcasting</target><part>DVB</part></link>-<link><target>Asynchronous serial communication</target><part>ASI</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Compressed video is also carried using<space/><link><target>User Datagram Protocol</target><part>UDP</part></link>-<link><target>Internet Protocol</target><part>IP</part></link><space/>over<space/><link><target>Ethernet</target></link>. Two approaches exist for this:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Using<space/><link><target>Real-time Transport Protocol</target><part>RTP</part></link><space/>as a wrapper for video packets</listitem><listitem>1-7<space/><link><target>MPEG transport stream</target><part>MPEG Transport Packets</part></link><space/>are placed directly in the<space/><link><target>User Datagram Protocol</target><part>UDP</part></link><space/>packet</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Storage formats</heading><heading level='3'>Encoding</heading><paragraph>All current formats, which are listed below, are<space/><link><target>Pulse-code modulation</target><part>PCM</part></link><space/>based.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>CCIR 601</target></link><space/>used for broadcast stations</listitem><listitem><link><target>MPEG-4</target></link><space/>good for online distribution of large videos and video recorded to<space/><link><target>flash memory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>MPEG-2</target></link><space/>used for DVDs, Super-VCDs, and many broadcast television formats</listitem><listitem><link><target>MPEG-1</target></link><space/>used for video CDs</listitem><listitem><link><target>H.261</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>H.263</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>H.264/MPEG-4 AVC</target><part>H.264</part></link><space/>also known as<space/><italics>MPEG-4 Part 10</italics>, or as<space/><italics>AVC</italics>, used for<space/><link><target>Blu-ray Disc</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and some broadcast television formats</listitem><listitem><link><target>Theora</target></link><space/>used for video on Wikipedia</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Tapes</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Video tape</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Betacam</target><part>Betacam SX</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Betacam IMX</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Digital Betacam</target></link>, or DigiBeta Commercial video systems by<space/><link><target>Sony</target></link>, based on original<space/><link><target>Betamax</target></link><space/>technology</listitem><listitem><link><target>D-VHS</target></link><space/>MPEG-2 format data recorded on a tape similar to<space/><link><target>S-VHS</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>D1 (Sony)</target><part>D1</part></link>,<space/><link><target>D2 (video format)</target><part>D2</part></link>,<space/><link><target>D3 (video)</target><part>D3</part></link>,<space/><link><target>D5 HD</target><part>D5</part></link>,<space/><link><target>D9 (video)</target><part>D9</part></link><space/>(also known as Digital-S) various<space/><link><target>SMPTE</target></link><space/>commercial digital video standards</listitem><listitem><link><target>Digital8</target></link><space/>DV-format data recorded on<space/><link><target>Hi8</target></link>-compatible cassettes; largely a consumer format</listitem><listitem><link><target>DV</target></link>,<space/><link><target>MiniDV</target></link><space/>used in most of today's videotape-based consumer camcorders; designed for high quality and easy editing; can also record high-definition data (<link><target>HDV</target></link>) in MPEG-2 format</listitem><listitem><link><target>DVCAM</target></link>,<space/><link><target>DVCPRO</target></link><space/>used in professional broadcast operations; similar to DV but generally considered more robust; though DV-compatible, these formats have better audio handling.</listitem><listitem><link><target>DVCPRO</target><part>DVCPRO50</part></link>,<space/><link><target>DVCPRO</target><trail>HD</trail></link><space/>support higher bandwidths as compared to Panasonic's DVCPRO.</listitem><listitem><link><target>HDCAM</target></link><space/>was introduced by Sony as a high-definition alternative to DigiBeta.</listitem><listitem><link><target>MicroMV</target></link><space/>MPEG-2-format data recorded on a very small, matchbook-sized cassette; obsolete</listitem><listitem><link><target>ProHD</target></link><space/>name used by JVC for its MPEG-2-based professional camcorders</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Discs</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Optical disc</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Blu-ray Disc</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>DVD</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>VCD</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target><arg></arg><arg>20em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Digital audio</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Digital cinematography</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of video topics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Video coding</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Video editing software</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Video hosting service</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Webcam</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.adamwilt.com/DV.html'>The DV, DVCAM, &amp; DVCPRO Formats -- tech details, FAQ, and links</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.equasys.de/videoformats.html'>Standard digital TV and video formats.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Digital systems</target></template><template><target>Video storage formats</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Digital Video</target></template><link><target>Category:Film and video technology</target></link><link><target>Category:Video signal</target></link><link><target>Category:Television terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:1986 introductions</target></link><link><target>Category:Film and video terminology</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>pl:Digital video</target></link><link><target>pt:Vdeo digital</target></link></paragraph></article>