<article title='Endocarditis'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox disease</target><arg name="Name"><space/>Endocarditis
</arg><arg name="Image"><space/>Blood_culture_negative_endocarditis.jpg
</arg><arg name="Caption"><space/>''Bartonella henselae'' bacilli in cardiac valve of a patient with blood culture-negative endocarditis. The bacilli appear as black granulations.
</arg><arg name="Field"><space/>[[Cardiology]], [[Infectious disease (medical specialty)|infectious disease]]
</arg><arg name="DiseasesDB"><space/>4224
</arg><arg name="ICD10"><space/>{{ICD10|I|33||i|30}}
</arg><arg name="ICD9"><space/>{{ICD9|421}}
</arg><arg name="ICDO">
</arg><arg name="OMIM">
</arg><arg name="MedlinePlus"><space/>001098
</arg><arg name="eMedicineSubj"><space/>emerg
</arg><arg name="eMedicineTopic"><space/>164
</arg><arg name="eMedicine_mult"><space/>{{eMedicine2|med|671}} {{eMedicine2|ped|2511}}
</arg><arg name="MeshID"><space/>D004696
</arg></template><bold>Endocarditis</bold><space/>is an<space/><link><target>inflammation</target></link><space/>of the inner layer of the<space/><link><target>heart</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>endocardium</target></link>. It usually involves the<space/><link><target>heart valve</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Other structures that may be involved include the<space/><link><target>interventricular septum</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>chordae tendineae</target></link>, the mural endocardium, or the surfaces of intracardiac devices. Endocarditis is characterized by lesions, known as<space/><italics><link><target>Vegetation (pathology)</target><part>vegetation</part><trail>s</trail></link></italics>, which is a mass of<space/><link><target>platelets</target></link>,<space/><link><target>fibrin</target></link>, microcolonies of microorganisms, and scant inammatory cells.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Harrison"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Kasper DL, Braunwald E, [[Anthony Fauci|Fauci AS]], Hauser S, Longo DL, Jameson JL</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Harrison's Principles of Internal Medicine]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[McGraw-Hill]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>731–40<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-07-139140-1<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>54501403 56437106 56801936 56967424<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In the<space/><link><target>subacute</target></link><space/>form of infective endocarditis, the vegetation may also include a center of<space/><link><target>granuloma</target><part>granulomatous tissue</part></link>, which may fibrose or calcify.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Mitchell RS, Kumar V, Robbins SL, Abbas AK, Fausto N<space/></arg><arg name="title">Robbins Basic Pathology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Saunders/Elsevier<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>8th<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="pages">406–8<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-4160-2973-7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are several ways to classify endocarditis. The simplest classification is based on cause: either<space/><italics>infective</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>non-infective</italics>, depending on whether a<space/><link><target>microorganism</target></link><space/>is the source of the inflammation or not. Regardless, the diagnosis of endocarditis is based on clinical features, investigations such as an<space/><link><target>echocardiogram</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>blood culture</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>demonstrating the presence of endocarditis-causing microorganisms. Signs and symptoms include: fever, chills, sweating, malaise, weakness, anorexia, weight loss,<space/><link><target>splenomegaly</target></link>, flu like feeling, cardiac murmur, heart failure,<space/><link><target>petechia</target></link><space/>of anterior trunk,<space/><link><target>Janeway_lesion</target><part>Janeway's lesions</part></link>, etc.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cause</heading><heading level='3'>Infective</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Infective endocarditis</arg></template>Since the valves of the heart do not receive any dedicated blood supply, defensive immune mechanisms (such as<space/><link><target>white blood cell</target><trail>s</trail></link>) cannot directly reach the valves via the bloodstream. If an organism (such as<space/><link><target>bacteria</target></link>) attaches to a valve surface and forms a vegetation, the host immune response is blunted. The lack of blood supply to the valves also has implications on treatment, since drugs also have difficulty reaching the infected valve.</paragraph><paragraph>Normally, blood flows smoothly past these valves. If they have been damaged (from<space/><link><target>rheumatic fever</target></link>, for example) the risk of bacteria attachment is increased.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Rheumatic fever</target></link><space/>is common worldwide and responsible for many cases of damaged<space/><link><target>heart valve</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Chronic<space/><link><target>rheumatic fever</target><part>rheumatic heart disease</part></link><space/>is characterized by repeated inflammation with fibrinous resolution. The cardinal anatomic changes of the valve include leaflet thickening, commissural fusion, and shortening and thickening of the tendinous cords.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RobbinsPath"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Cotran, Ramzi S.; Kumar, Vinay; Fausto, Nelson; Robbins, Stanley L.; Abbas, Abul K.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Robbins and Cotran pathologic basis of disease<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Elsevier Saunders<space/></arg><arg name="location">St. Louis, Mo<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7216-0187-1<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.robbinspathology.com/<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg></template></extension><space/>The recurrence of rheumatic fever is relatively common in the absence of maintenance of low dose antibiotics, especially during the first three to five years after the first episode. Heart complications may be long-term and severe, particularly if valves are involved. While rheumatic fever since the advent of routine penicillin administration for Strep throat has become less common in developed countries, in the older generation and in much of the less-developed world, valvular disease (including mitral valve prolapse, reinfection in the form of valvular endocarditis, and valve rupture) from undertreated rheumatic fever continues to be a problem.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nlm.nih.gov/medlineplus/ency/article/003940.htm'>NLM/NIH: Medline Plus Medical Encyclopedia: Rheumatic fever</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In an Indian hospital between 2004 and 2005, 4 of 24 endocarditis patients failed to demonstrate classic vegetation. All had rheumatic heart disease and presented with prolonged fever. All had severe eccentric mitral regurgitation. (One had severe aortic regurgitation also.) One had flail posterior mitral leaflet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">https://drsvenkatesan.wordpress.com/2009/04/10/can-we-diagnose-infective-endocarditis-without-vegetation/</arg><arg name="author">S Venkatesan</arg><arg name="title">Can we diagnose Infective endocarditis without vegetation ?<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Indian Heart Journal</arg><arg name="volume">59<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5<space/></arg><arg name="date">Sep–Oct 2007</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Non-infective</heading><paragraph><link><target>Nonbacterial thrombotic endocarditis</target></link><space/>(NBTE), also called<space/><bold>marantic endocarditis</bold><space/>is most commonly found on previously undamaged valves.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>As opposed to infective endocarditis, the vegetations in NBTE are small, sterile, and tend to aggregate along the edges of the valve or the cusps.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>Also unlike infective endocarditis, NBTE does not cause an inflammation response from the body.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>NBTE usually occurs during a hypercoagulable state such as system wide bacterial infection, or pregnancy, though it is also sometimes seen in patients with venous catheters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>NBTE may also occur in patients with cancers, particularly mucinous adenocarcinoma<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>where<space/><link><target>Trousseau syndrome</target></link><space/>can be encountered. Typically NBTE does not cause many problems on its own, but parts of the vegetations may break off and embolize to the heart or brain, or they may serve as a focus where bacteria can lodge, thus causing infective endocarditis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another form of sterile endocarditis, is termed<space/><link><target>Libman-Sacks endocarditis</target></link>; this form occurs more often in patients with<space/><link><target>lupus erythematosus</target></link><space/>and is thought to be due to the deposition of immune complexes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>Like NBTE, Libman-Sacks endocarditis involves small vegetations, while infective endocarditis is composed of large vegetations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension><space/>These immune complexes precipitate an inflammation reaction, which helps to differentiate it from NBTE. Also unlike NBTE, Libman-Sacks endocarditis does not seem to have a preferred location of deposition and may form on the undersurfaces of the valves or even on the endocardium.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robbins"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Diagnostics</heading><paragraph>Examination of suspected infective endocarditis includes a detailed examination of the patient, complete history taking, and especially careful cardiac auscultation, various blood tests, ECG, cardiac ultrasound (echocardiography). Analysis of blood helps reveal the typical signs of inflammation (increased erythrocyte sedimentation rate, leukocytosis). Two or more separate blood cultures are normally drawn. Negative blood cultures, however, do not exclude the diagnosis of infective endocarditis. Echocardiography (through the anterior chest wall or transesophageal), plays a decisive role in the diagnosis by reliably establishing the presence of microbial vegetation and the degree of valvular dysfunction affecting the pumping function of the heart.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://medusanews.com/diseases-and-conditions/cardiology/endocarditis.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Health/Conditions_and_Diseases/Cardiovascular_Disorders/Heart_Disease/Endocarditis/</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Circulatory system pathology</target></template><template><target>Inflammation</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Valvular heart disease</target></link><link><target>Category:Inflammations</target></link><link><target>Category:Rodent-carried diseases</target></link></paragraph></article>