<article title='American_Revolution'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>political and social developments, and the origins and aftermath of the war</arg><arg>military actions</arg><arg>American Revolutionary War</arg><arg>other uses</arg></template><template><target>hatnote</target><arg>In this article, inhabitants of the Thirteen Colonies who supported the American Revolution are primarily referred to as "Americans" or "[[Patriot (American Revolution)|Patriots]]," and sometimes as "Whigs," "Rebels" or "Revolutionaries." Colonists who supported the British side are called "[[Loyalists]]" or "[[Tories]]". In accordance with the policy of this encyclopedia, this article uses American English terminology; in British English these events are known as the "American War of Independence".</arg></template><template><target>pp-semi-indef</target></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Declaration independence.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part>alt=Founding Fathers listen to the draft of the Declaration of Independence</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>John Trumbull</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Trumbull's Declaration of Independence</target><part>Declaration of Independence</part></link></italics>, showing the<space/><link><target>Committee of Five</target></link><space/>presenting its work to Congress</xhtml:center></part></link></preline></preblock><paragraph>The<space/><bold>American Revolution</bold><space/>was a political upheaval that took place between 1765 and 1783 during which colonists in the<space/><link><target>Thirteen Colonies</target><part>Thirteen American Colonies</part></link><space/>rejected the British monarchy and aristocracy, overthrew the authority of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Great Britain</target><part>Great Britain</part></link>, and founded the<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>United States of America</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Starting in 1765, members of American colonial society<space/><link><target>No taxation without representation</target><part>rejected the authority</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Parliament of Great Britain</target><part>the British Parliament</part></link><space/>to tax them without colonial representatives in the government. During the following decade, protests by colonistsknown as Patriotscontinued to escalate, as in the<space/><link><target>Boston Tea Party</target></link><space/>in 1773 during which patriots destroyed a consignment of taxed tea from the Parliament-controlled and favored<space/><link><target>East India Company</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Smuggler Nation: How Illicit Trade Made America: Peter Andreas Page 4</extension><space/>The British responded by imposing punitive lawsthe<space/><link><target>Coercive Acts</target></link>on Massachusetts in 1774, following which Patriots in the other colonies rallied behind Massachusetts. In late 1774 the Patriots set up their own alternative government to better coordinate their resistance efforts against Great Britain, while other colonists, known as<space/><link><target>Loyalist (American Revolution)</target><part>Loyalists</part></link>, preferred to remain aligned to the British Crown.</paragraph><paragraph>Tensions escalated to the outbreak of fighting between Patriot militia and British regulars at<space/><link><target>Battles of Lexington and Concord</target><part>Lexington and Concord</part></link><space/>in April 1775. The conflict then evolved into a global war, during which the Patriots (and later their French, Spanish, and Dutch allies) fought the British and Loyalists in what became known as the<space/><link><target>American Revolutionary War</target></link><space/>(17751783). Patriots in each of the thirteen colonies formed a<space/><link><target>Provincial Congress</target></link><space/>that assumed power from the old colonial governments and suppressed Loyalism, and from there built a<space/><link><target>Continental Army</target></link><space/>under the leadership of General<space/><link><target>George Washington</target></link>. Claiming King George III's rule to be tyrannical and infringing the colonists' &quot;<link><target>Rights of Englishmen</target><part>rights as Englishmen</part></link>&quot;, the Continental Congress<space/><link><target>United States Declaration of Independence</target><part>declared the colonies free and independent states</part></link><space/>in July 1776. The Patriot leadership professed the political philosophies of<space/><link><target>Liberalism in the United States</target><part>liberalism</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Republicanism in the United States</target><part>republicanism</part></link><space/>to reject<space/><link><target>monarchy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>aristocracy</target></link>, and proclaimed that<space/><link><target>all men are created equal</target></link>. Congress rejected British proposals requiring allegiance to the monarchy and abandonment of independence.</paragraph><paragraph>The British were forced out of Boston in 1776, but then captured and held New York City for the duration of the war. The British blockaded the ports and captured other cities for brief periods, but failed to defeat Washington's forces. In early 1778, following a failed patriot invasion of Canada, a British army was captured at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Saratoga</target></link>, following which the French openly entered the war as allies of the United States. The war later turned to the American South, where the British captured an army at<space/><link><target>South Carolina</target></link>, but failed to enlist enough volunteers from Loyalist civilians to take effective control. A combined AmericanFrench force<space/><link><target>Siege of Yorktown</target><part>captured a second British army at Yorktown</part></link><space/>in 1781, effectively ending the war in the United States. The<space/><link><target>Treaty of Paris (1783)</target><part>Treaty of Paris</part></link><space/>in 1783 formally ended the conflict, confirming the new nation's complete separation from the British Empire. The United States took possession of nearly all the territory east of the<space/><link><target>Mississippi River</target></link><space/>and south of the<space/><link><target>Great Lakes</target></link>, with the British retaining control of Canada and Spain taking Florida.<extension extension_name='ref'>Liberty's Exiles: Maya Jasanoff.Pages 5-53</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Rough Crossings; Simon Schama Page 13-50</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Among the significant results of the revolution was the creation of a democratically-elected representative government<space/><link><target>Consent of the governed</target><part>responsible to the will of the people</part></link>, but which as a result of the '<link><target>Three-Fifths Compromise</target></link>' allowed the southern slaveholders to consolidate power and maintain slavery in America for another eighty years.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;We Hold These Truths to be Self-evident;&quot; An Interdisciplinary Analysis of the Roots of Racism &amp; slavery in America Kenneth N. Addison; Introduction P. xxii</extension><space/>The new Constitution established a relatively strong<space/><link><target>Federal government</target><part>federal</part></link><space/>national government that included an<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>executive</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United States Supreme Court</target><part>national judiciary</part></link>, a bicameral<space/><link><target>Congress of the United States</target><part>Congress</part></link><space/>that represented both states in the<space/><link><target>United States Senate</target><part>Senate</part></link><space/>and population in the<space/><link><target>United States House of Representatives</target><part>House of Representatives</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wood, 1992">Wood,<space/><italics>The Radicalism of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1992)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) chapter 70</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Map of territorial growth 1775.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part>alt=Eastern North America in 1775. The British Province of Quebec, the thirteen colonies on the Atlantic coast and the Indian reserve as defined by the Royal Proclamation of 1763. The 1763 Proclamation line is the border between the red and the pink areas, while the orange area represents the Spanish claim.</part><part><xhtml:center>Eastern North America in 1775. The<space/><link><target>Province of Quebec (17631791)</target><part>British Province of Quebec</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Thirteen Colonies</target></link><space/>on the Atlantic coast and the<space/><link><target>Indian Reserve (1763)</target><part>Indian Reserve</part></link><space/>as defined by the<space/><link><target>Royal Proclamation of 1763</target></link>. The 1763 &quot;Proclamation line&quot; comprises the border between the red and the pink areas, while the orange area represents the<space/><link><target>Spanish colonization of the Americas</target><part>Spanish claim</part></link>.</xhtml:center></part></link>Historians typically begin their histories of the American Revolution with the British victory in the<space/><link><target>French and Indian War</target></link><space/>in 1763, which removed France as a major player in North American affairs.<space/><link><target>Lawrence Henry Gipson</target></link>, the historian of the British Empire, states:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>It may be said as truly that the American Revolution was an aftermath of the Anglo-French conflict in the New World carried on between 1754 and 1763.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lawrence Henry Gipson, &quot;The American revolution as an aftermath of the Great War for the Empire, 1754-1763.&quot;<space/><italics>Political Science Quarterly</italics><space/>(1950): 86-104.<link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2144276'>in JSTOR</link></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>For the prior history see<space/><link><target>Thirteen Colonies</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>17641766: Taxes imposed and withdrawn</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Sugar Act</arg><arg>Currency Act</arg><arg>Quartering Acts</arg><arg>Stamp Act 1765</arg><arg>Declaratory Act</arg></template><template><target>Further</target><arg>No taxation without representation</arg><arg>Virtual representation</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Parliament Stamp Act1765.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Notice of Stamp Act of 1765 in newspaper</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1764 Parliament passed the Currency Act to restrain the use of paper money that British merchants saw as a means to evade debt payments.<template><target>or</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template><space/>Parliament also passed the Sugar Act imposing customs<space/><link><target>Duty (economics)</target><part>duties</part></link><space/>on a number of articles. That same year Prime Minister<space/><link><target>George Grenville</target></link><space/>proposed to impose direct taxes on the colonies to raise revenue, but delayed action to see if the colonies would propose some way to raise the revenue themselves.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template><space/>None did, and in March 1765 Parliament passed the Stamp Act which imposed direct taxes on the colonies for the first time. All official documents, newspapers, almanacs and pamphletseven decks of playing cardswere required to have the stamps.</paragraph><paragraph>The colonists objected chiefly on the grounds not that the taxes were high (they were low),<extension extension_name='ref'>Englishmen paid on average twenty-five shillings annually in taxes whereas Americans paid only sixpence. Miller,<space/><italics>Origins of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1943) p. 89</extension><space/>but because they had no representation in the Parliament.<space/><link><target>Benjamin Franklin</target></link><space/>testified in Parliament in 1766 that Americans already contributed heavily to the defense of the Empire. He said local governments had raised, outfitted and paid 25,000 soldiers to fight Franceas many as Britain itself sentand spent many millions from American treasuries doing so in the<space/><link><target>French and Indian War</target></link><space/>alone.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">James A. Henretta, ed.</arg><arg name="title">Documents for America's History, Volume 1: To 1877</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Bedford/St. Martin's</arg><arg name="page">110</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Walter Isaacson</arg><arg name="title">Benjamin Franklin: An American Life</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Simon and Schuster</arg><arg name="pages">229–30</arg></template></extension><space/>Stationing a<space/><link><target>standing army</target></link><space/>in Great Britain during peacetime was politically unacceptable. London had to deal with 1,500 politically well-connected British officers who became redundant; it would have to discharge them or station them in North America.<extension extension_name='ref'>Shy,<space/><italics>Toward Lexington</italics><space/>7378</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1765 the<space/><link><target>Sons of Liberty</target></link><space/>formed. They used public demonstrations,<space/><link><target>boycott</target></link>, violence and threats of violence to ensure that the British tax laws were unenforceable. While openly hostile to what they considered an oppressive Parliament acting illegally, colonists persisted in sending numerous petitions and pleas for intervention from a monarch to whom they still claimed loyalty. In Boston, the Sons of Liberty burned the records of the vice-admiralty court and looted the home of the chief justice,<space/><link><target>Thomas Hutchinson (governor)</target><part>Thomas Hutchinson</part></link>. Several legislatures called for united action, and nine colonies sent delegates to the<space/><link><target>Stamp Act Congress</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link><space/>in October 1765. Moderates led by<space/><link><target>John Dickinson (delegate)</target><part>John Dickinson</part></link><space/>drew up a &quot;<link><target>Declaration of Rights and Grievances</target></link>&quot; stating that taxes passed without representation violated their<space/><link><target>Rights of Englishmen</target><part>rights as Englishmen</part></link>. Colonists emphasized their determination by boycotting imports of British merchandise.<extension extension_name='ref'>T.H. Breen,<space/><italics>American Insurgents, American Patriots: The Revolution of the People</italics><space/>(2010) pp 81-82</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Parliament at Westminster saw itself as the supreme lawmaking authority throughout all British possessions and thus entitled to levy any tax without colonial approval.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlekauff p. 62</extension><space/>They argued that the colonies were legally British corporations that were completely subordinate to the British parliament and pointed to numerous instances where Parliament had made laws binding on the colonies in the past.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lecky, William Edward Hartpole 1882 pp. 297-298">Lecky, William Edward Hartpole,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyofengland03leck#page/297/mode/1up'>A History of England in the Eighteenth Century</link><space/>(1882) pp. 297-298</extension><space/>They did not see anything in the unwritten British constitution that made taxes special<extension extension_name='ref'>Lecky, William Edward Hartpole,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyofengland03leck#page/315/mode/1up'>A History of England in the Eighteenth Century</link><space/>(1882) pp. 315-316</extension><space/>and noted that Parliament had taxed American trade for decades. Parliament insisted that the colonies effectively enjoyed a &quot;<link><target>virtual representation</target></link>&quot; like most British people did, as only a small minority of the British population elected representatives to Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lecky, William Edward Hartpole,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyofengland03leck#page/173/mode/1up'>A History of England in the Eighteenth Century</link><space/>(1882) p. 173</extension><space/>Americans such as<space/><link><target>James Otis, Jr.</target><part>James Otis</part></link><space/>maintained the Americans were not in fact virtually represented.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bryan-Paul Frost and Jeffrey Sikkenga</arg><arg name="title">History of American Political Thought</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Lexington Books</arg><arg name="pages">55–56</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In London, the<space/><link><target>Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham</target><part>Rockingham</part></link><space/>government came to power (July 1765) and Parliament debated whether to repeal the stamp tax or to send an army to enforce it. Benjamin Franklin made the case for repeal, explaining the colonies had spent heavily in manpower, money, and blood in defense of the empire in a series of wars against the French and Indians, and that further taxes to pay for those wars were unjust and might bring about a rebellion. Parliament agreed and repealed the tax (February 21, 1766), but in the<space/><link><target>Declaratory Act</target></link><space/>of March 1766 insisted that parliament retained full power to make laws for the colonies &quot;in all cases whatsoever&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Miller</arg><arg name="title">Origins of the American Revolution
</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1943</arg><arg name="pages">181–</arg></template></extension><space/>The repeal nonetheless caused widespread celebrations in the colonies.</paragraph><paragraph>Briggs says unnamed modern American economic historians have challenged the view that Great Britain was placing a heavy burden on the North American colonies and have suggested the cost of defending them from the possibility of invasion by France or Spain was 400,000 five times the maximum income from them. Briggs rejects the analysis, saying that issue was not invoked at the time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Briggs, Asa<space/><italics>A Social History of England</italics><space/>(1994) p. 184</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>17671773: Townshend Acts and the Tea Act</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Townshend Acts</arg><arg>Tea Act</arg></template><template><target>Further</target><arg>Massachusetts Circular Letter</arg><arg>Boston Massacre</arg><arg>Boston Tea Party</arg></template><link><target>File:Gaspee Affair.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Burning of the Gaspee</part><part><xhtml:center>Burning of the<space/><italics><link><target>Gaspee Affair</target><part>Gaspee</part></link></italics></xhtml:center></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1767 the Parliament passed the<space/><link><target>Townshend Acts</target></link>, which placed duties on a number of essential goods including paper, glass, and tea and established a Board of Customs in Boston to more rigorously execute trade regulations. The new taxes were enacted on the belief that Americans only objected to internal taxes and not external taxes like custom duties. The Americans, however, argued against the constitutionality of the act because its purpose was to raise revenue and not regulate trade. Colonists responded by organizing new boycotts of British goods. These boycotts were less effective, however, as the Townshend goods were widely used.</paragraph><paragraph>In February 1768 the Assembly of Massachusetts Bay<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Circular Letter</target><part>issued a circular letter</part></link><space/>to the other colonies urging them to coordinate resistance. The governor dissolved the assembly when it refused to rescind the letter. Meanwhile, in June 1768 a riot broke out in Boston over the seizure of the sloop<space/><italics>Liberty</italics>, owned by<space/><link><target>John Hancock</target></link>, for alleged smuggling. Custom officials were forced to flee, prompting the British to deploy troops to Boston. A Boston town meeting declared no obedience was due to parliamentary laws and called for the convening of a convention. A convention assembled but only issued a mild protest before dissolving itself. In January 1769 Parliament responded to the unrest by reactivating the<space/><link><target>Treason Act 1543</target></link><space/>which permitted subjects outside the realm to face trials for treason in England. The governor of Massachusetts was instructed to collect evidence of said treason, and although the threat was not carried out it caused widespread outrage.</paragraph><paragraph>On March 5, 1770 a large mob gathered around a group of British soldiers. The mob grew more and more threatening, throwing snowballs, rocks and debris at the soldiers. One soldier was clubbed and fell.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hiller B. Zobel 1996">Hiller B. Zobel,<space/><italics>The Boston Massacre</italics><space/>(1996)</extension><space/>There was no order to fire but the soldiers fired into the crowd anyway. They hit 11 people; three civilians died at the scene of the shooting, and two died after the incident. The event quickly came to be called the<space/><link><target>Boston Massacre</target></link>. Although the soldiers were tried and acquitted (defended by<space/><link><target>John Adams</target></link>), the widespread descriptions soon became propaganda to turn colonial sentiment against the British. This in turn began a downward spiral in the relationship between Britain and the Province of Massachusetts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hiller B. Zobel 1996"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A new ministry under<space/><link><target>Lord North</target></link><space/>came to power in 1770 and Parliament withdrew all taxes except the tax on tea, giving up its efforts to raise revenue while maintaining the right to tax. This temporarily resolved the crisis and the boycott of British goods largely ceased, with only the more radical patriots such as<space/><link><target>Samuel Adams</target></link><space/>continuing to agitate.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Boston Tea Party Currier colored.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=Two ships in a harbor, one in the distance. On board, men stripped to the waist and wearing feathers in their hair are throwing crates into the water. A large crowd, mostly men, is standing on the dock, waving hats and cheering. A few people wave their hats from windows in a nearby building.</part><part><xhtml:center>This 1846<space/><link><target>Lithography</target><part>lithograph</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Nathaniel Currier</target></link><space/>was entitled &quot;The Destruction of Tea at Boston Harbor&quot;; the phrase &quot;<link><target>Boston Tea Party</target></link>&quot; had not yet become standard.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alfred F. Young,<space/><italics>The Shoemaker and the Tea Party: Memory and the American Revolution</italics><space/>(Boston: Beacon Press, 1999; ISBN 0-8070-5405-4; ISBN 978-0-8070-5405-5), 18385.</extension></xhtml:center></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In June 1772, in what became known as the<space/><link><target>Gaspee Affair</target><part>''Gaspee'' Affair</part></link>, American<space/><link><target>Patriot (American Revolution)</target><part>patriots</part></link><space/>including<space/><link><target>John Brown (Rhode Island)</target><part>John Brown</part></link><space/>burned a British warship that had been vigorously enforcing unpopular trade regulations. The affair was investigated for possible treason, but no action was taken.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1772 it became known that the Crown intended to pay fixed salaries to the governors and judges in Massachusetts. Samuel Adams in Boston set about creating new Committees of Correspondence, which linked Patriots in all 13 colonies and eventually provided the framework for a rebel government. In early 1773 Virginia, the largest colony, set up its Committee of Correspondence, on which Patrick Henry and Thomas Jefferson served.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) chapters 2224</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A total of about 7000 to 8000 Patriots served on &quot;Committees of Correspondence&quot; at the colonial and local levels, comprising most of the leadership in their communities Loyalists were excluded. The committees became the<space/><link><target>leadership</target><part>leaders</part></link><space/>of the American resistance to British actions, and largely determined the war effort at the state and local level. When the First Continental Congress decided to boycott British products, the colonial and local Committees took charge, examining merchant records and publishing the names of merchants who attempted to defy the boycott by importing British goods.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mary Beth Norton 2001 pp 144">Mary Beth Norton et al.,<space/><italics>A People and a Nation</italics><space/>(6th ed. 2001) vol 1 pp 144145</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1773<space/><link><target>Hutchinson Letters Affair</target><part>private letters were published</part></link><space/>where Massachusetts Governor Thomas Hutchinson claimed the colonists could not enjoy all English liberties, and Lieutenant Governor<space/><link><target>Andrew Oliver</target></link><space/>called for the direct payment of colonial officials. The letters, whose contents were used as evidence of a systematic plot against American rights, discredited Hutchinson in the eyes of the people the Assembly petitioned for his recall.<space/><link><target>Benjamin Franklin</target></link>, post-master general for the colonies, acknowledged that he leaked the letters which led to him being berated by British officials and fired from his job.</paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, Parliament passed the<space/><link><target>Tea Act</target></link><space/>to lower the price of taxed tea exported to the colonies in order to help the<space/><link><target>East India Company</target></link><space/>undersell smuggled Dutch tea. Special consignees were appointed to sell the tea in order to bypass colonial merchants. The act was opposed not only by those who resisted the taxes but also by smugglers who stood to lose business. In most instances the consignees were forced to resign and the tea was turned back, but Massachusetts governor Hutchinson refused to allow Boston merchants to give into pressure. A town meeting in Boston determined that the tea would not be landed, and ignored a demand from the governor to disperse. On December 16, 1773 a group of men, led by Samuel Adams and dressed to evoke American Indians, boarded the ships of the<space/><link><target>East India Company</target><part>British East India Company</part></link><space/>and dumped 10,000 worth of tea from their holds (approximately 636,000 in 2008) into Boston Harbor. Decades later this event became known as the<space/><link><target>Boston Tea Party</target></link><space/>and remains a significant part of American patriotic lore.<extension extension_name='ref'>Benjamin L. Carp,<space/><italics>Defiance of the Patriots: The Boston Tea Party and the Making of America</italics><space/>(2010)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>17741775: Intolerable Acts and the Quebec Act</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:RapeBoston.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=A 1774 etching from The London Magazine, copied by Paul Revere of Boston. Prime Minister Lord North, author of the Boston Port Act, forces the Intolerable Acts down the throat of America, whose arms are restrained by Lord Chief Justice Mansfield while the 4th Earl of Sandwich pins down her feet and peers up her skirt. Behind them, Mother Britannia weeps helplessly.</part><part><xhtml:center>A 1774 etching from<space/><italics><link><target>The London Magazine</target></link></italics>, copied by<space/><link><target>Paul Revere</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Frederick North, Lord North</target><part>Prime Minister Lord North</part></link>, author of the<space/><link><target>Boston Port Act</target></link>, forces the<space/><link><target>Intolerable Acts</target></link><space/>down the throat of America, whose arms are restrained by<space/><link><target>William Murray, 1st Earl of Mansfield</target><part>Lord Chief Justice Mansfield</part></link><space/>while<space/><link><target>John Montagu, 4th Earl of Sandwich</target><part>Lord Sandwich</part></link><space/>pins down her feet and peers up her robes. Behind them,<space/><link><target>Britannia</target><part>Mother Britannia</part></link><space/>weeps helplessly.</xhtml:center></part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Quebec Act</arg><arg>Intolerable Acts</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The British government responded by passing several Acts which came to be known as the<space/><link><target>Intolerable Acts</target></link>, which further darkened colonial opinion towards the British. They consisted of four laws enacted by the British parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miller (1943) pp. 35376</extension><space/>The first, the<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Government Act</target></link>, altered the Massachusetts charter and restricted town meetings. The second Act, the<space/><link><target>Administration of Justice Act 1774</target><part>Administration of Justice Act</part></link>, ordered that all British soldiers to be tried were to be arraigned in Britain, not in the colonies. The third Act was the<space/><link><target>Boston Port Act</target></link>, which closed the port of Boston until the British had been compensated for the tea lost in the Boston Tea Party. The fourth Act was the<space/><link><target>Quartering Acts</target><part>Quartering Act of 1774</part></link>, which allowed royal governors to house British troops in the homes of citizens without requiring permission of the owner.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carp,<space/><italics>Defiance of the Patriots: The Boston Tea Party and the Making of America</italics><space/>(2010) ch 9</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In response, Massachusetts patriots issued the<space/><link><target>Suffolk Resolves</target></link><space/>and formed an alternative shadow government known as the &quot;Provincial Congress&quot; which began training militia outside British-occupied Boston.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">John K. Alexander</arg><arg name="title">Samuel Adams: The Life of an American Revolutionary</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Rowman & Littlefield</arg><arg name="pages">187–94</arg></template></extension><space/>In September 1774, the<space/><link><target>First Continental Congress</target></link><space/>convened, consisting of representatives from each of the colonies, to serve as a vehicle for deliberation and collective action. During secret debates conservative<space/><link><target>Joseph Galloway</target></link><space/>proposed the creation of a colonial Parliament that would be able to approve or disapprove of acts of the British Parliament but his idea was not accepted. The Congress instead endorsed the proposal of John Adams that Americans would obey Parliament voluntarily but would resist all taxes in disguise. Congress called for a boycott beginning on 1 December 1774 of all British goods; it was enforced by new committees authorized by the Congress.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Mary Beth Norton</arg><arg name="title">A People and a Nation: A History of the United States</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Cengage Learning</arg><arg name="page">143</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Quebec Act</target></link><space/>of 1774 extended<space/><link><target>Quebec</target></link>'s boundaries to the<space/><link><target>Ohio River</target></link>, shutting out the claims of the 13 colonies. By then, however, the Americans had little regard for new laws from London; they were drilling militia and organizing for war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) chapter 15</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British retaliated by confining all trade of the New England colonies to Britain and excluding them from the Newfoundland fisheries.<space/><link><target>Frederick North, Lord North</target><part>Lord North</part></link><space/>advanced a compromise proposal in which Parliament would not tax so long as the colonies made fixed contributions for defense and to support civil government. This would also be rejected.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Creating new state constitutions</heading><paragraph>Following the<space/><link><target>Battle of Bunker Hill</target></link><space/>in June 1775, the Patriots had control of Massachusetts outside the Boston city limits; the Loyalists suddenly found themselves on the defensive with no protection from the British army. In all 13 colonies, Patriots had overthrown their existing governments, closing courts and driving British officials away. They had elected conventions and &quot;legislatures&quot; that existed outside any legal framework; new constitutions were drawn up in each state to supersede royal charters. They declared that they were states now, not colonies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pole-ch29">Nevins (1927); Greene and Pole (1994) chapter 29</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On January 5, 1776,<space/><link><target>Province of New Hampshire</target><part>New Hampshire</part></link><space/>ratified the first state constitution. In May 1776, Congress voted to suppress all forms of crown authority, to be replaced by locally created authority. Virginia,<space/><link><target>Province of South Carolina</target><part>South Carolina</part></link>, and New Jersey created their constitutions before July 4.<space/><link><target>Colony of Rhode Island and Providence Plantations</target><part>Rhode Island</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Connecticut Colony</target><part>Connecticut</part></link><space/>simply took their existing<space/><link><target>royal charter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and deleted all references to the crown.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nevins (1927)</extension><space/>The new states were all committed to republicanism, with no inherited offices. They decided not only what form of government to create, and also how to select those who would craft the constitutions and how the resulting document would be ratified. But there would be no universal suffrage and real power, including the right to elect the future President would still lay in the hands of a few selected elites for many years. On 26 May 1776<space/><link><target>John Adams</target></link><space/>wrote James Sullivan from Philadelphia;</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Depend upon it, sir, it is dangerous to open so fruitful a source of controversy and altercation, as would be opened by attempting to alter the qualifications of voters. There will be no end of it. New claims will arise. Women will demand a vote. Lads from twelve to twenty one will think their rights not enough attended to, and every man, who has not a farthing, will demand an equal voice with any other in all acts of state. It tends to confound and destroy all distinctions, and prostrate all ranks, to one common level&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Founding the Republic: A Documentary History; edited by John J. Patrick</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Reason, Religion, and Democracy: Dennis C. Muelle. Page 206</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In states where the wealthy exerted firm control over the process, such as<space/><link><target>Province of Maryland</target><part>Maryland</part></link>, Virginia,<space/><link><target>Delaware Colony</target><part>Delaware</part></link>, New York and<space/><link><target>Constitution of Massachusetts</target><part>Massachusetts</part></link><space/>the last-mentioned of these state's constitutions still being in force in the 21st century, continuously since its ratification on June 15, 1780 the results were constitutions that featured:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Substantial property qualifications for voting and even more substantial requirements for elected positions (though New York and Maryland lowered property qualifications);<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pole-ch29"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bicameral legislature</target><trail>s</trail></link>, with the upper house as a check on the lower;</listitem><listitem>Strong<space/><link><target>governor</target><trail>s</trail></link>, with veto power over the legislature and substantial appointment authority;</listitem><listitem>Few or no restraints on individuals holding multiple positions in government;</listitem><listitem>The continuation of<space/><link><target>Established church</target><part>state-established religion</part></link>.</listitem></list><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Benjamin Rush Painting by Peale 1783.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Benjamin Rush, 1783</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>Benjamin Rush</target></link>, 1783</xhtml:center></part></link></preline></preblock><paragraph>In states where the less affluent had organized sufficiently to have significant powerespecially Pennsylvania, New Jersey, and New Hampshirethe resulting constitutions embodied</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>universal white manhood suffrage, or minimal property requirements for voting or holding office (New Jersey enfranchised some property owning widows, a step that it retracted 25 years later);</listitem><listitem>strong,<space/><link><target>Unicameralism</target><part>unicameral legislatures</part></link>;</listitem><listitem>relatively weak governors, without veto powers, and little appointing authority;</listitem><listitem>prohibition against individuals holding multiple government posts;</listitem></list><paragraph>The radical provisions of Pennsylvania's constitution lasted only 14 years. In 1790, conservatives gained power in the state legislature, called a new constitutional convention, and rewrote the constitution. The new constitution substantially reduced universal white-male suffrage, gave the governor veto power and patronage appointment authority, and added an upper house with substantial wealth qualifications to the unicameral legislature. Thomas Paine called it a constitution unworthy of America.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wood, 1992"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Military hostilities begin</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Benjamin Franklin - Join or Die.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=&quot;Join, or Die&quot; by Benjamin Franklin was recycled to encourage the former colonies to unite against British rule</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>Join, or Die</target></link><space/>by Benjamin Franklin was recycled to encourage the former colonies to unite against British rule.</xhtml:center></part></link><template><target>Further</target><arg>Shot heard 'round the world</arg><arg>Boston campaign</arg><arg>Invasion of Canada (1775)</arg><arg>American Revolutionary War</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Massachusetts was declared in a state of rebellion in February 1775 and the British garrison received orders to disarm the rebels and arrest their leaders, leading to the<space/><link><target>Battles of Lexington and Concord</target></link><space/>on 19 April 1775. The Patriots set siege to Boston, expelled royal officials from all the colonies, and took control through the establishment of<space/><link><target>Provincial Congress</target><trail>es</trail></link>. The<space/><link><target>Battle of Bunker Hill</target></link><space/>followed on June 17, 1775. While a British victory, it was at a great cost; about 1,000 British casualties from a garrison of about 6,000, as compared to 500 American casualties from a much larger force.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harvey.<space/><italics>&quot;A few bloody noses&quot;</italics><space/>(2002) pp. 208210</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Urban p.74</extension><space/>First ostensibly loyal to the king and desiring to govern themselves while remaining in the empire, the repeated<space/><link><target>Olive Branch Petition</target><part>pleas</part></link><space/>by the First Continental Congress for royal intervention on their behalf with Parliament resulted in the<space/><link><target>Proclamation of Rebellion</target><part>declaration by the King</part></link><space/>that the states were &quot;in rebellion&quot;, and the members of Congress were traitors.</paragraph><paragraph>In the winter of 1775, the Americans<space/><link><target>Invasion of Canada (1775)</target><part>invaded Canada</part></link>. General<space/><link><target>Richard Montgomery</target></link><space/>captured<space/><link><target>Montreal</target></link><space/>but a joint<space/><link><target>Battle of Quebec (1775)</target><part>attack on Quebec</part></link><space/>was a total failure; many Americans were captured or died of smallpox.</paragraph><paragraph>In March 1776, with George Washington as the commander of the new army, the Continental Army forced the British to<space/><link><target>Evacuation Day (Massachusetts)</target><part>evacuate Boston</part></link>. The revolutionaries were now in full control of all 13 colonies and were ready to declare independence. While there still were many Loyalists, they were no longer in control anywhere by July 1776, and all of the Royal officials had fled.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miller (1948) p. 87</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Prisoners</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Prisoners of war in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template>In August 1775, George III declared Americans in arms against royal authority to be traitors to the Crown. Following their surrender at the<space/><link><target>Battles of Saratoga</target></link><space/>in October 1777, there were thousands of British and Hessian soldiers in American hands. Although Lord Germain took a hard line, the British generals on the scene never held treason trials; they treated captured enemy soldiers as<space/><link><target>prisoners of war</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alan Valentine,<space/><italics>Lord George Germain</italics><space/>(1962) pp&amp;nbsp;30910</extension><space/>The dilemma was that tens of thousands of Loyalists were under American control and American retaliation would have been easy. The British built much of their strategy around using these Loyalists.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Larry G. Bowman 1976">Larry G. Bowman,<space/><italics>Captive Americans: Prisoners During the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1976)</extension><space/>Therefore, no Americans were put on trial for treason. The British maltreated the prisoners they held, resulting in more deaths to American sailors and soldiers than from combat operations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Larry G. Bowman 1976"></extension><space/>At the end of the war, both sides released their surviving prisoners.<extension extension_name='ref'>John C. Miller,<space/><italics>Triumph of Freedom, 17751783</italics><space/>(1948) p. 166.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Independence and Union</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Johannes Adam Simon Oertel Pulling Down the Statue of King George III, N.Y.C. ca. 1859.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Johannes Adam Simon Oertel</target></link>. Pulling Down the Statue of King George III, N.Y.C., ca. 1859. The painting is a<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target><part>romanticized</part></link><space/>version of the<space/><link><target>Sons of Liberty</target></link><space/>destroying the symbol of monarchy following the reading of the<space/><link><target>United States Declaration of Independence</target></link><space/>to the Continental Army and residents on the New York City commons by George Washington, July 9th, 1776.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Lee Resolution</arg><arg>Articles of Confederation</arg><arg>Committee of Five</arg><arg>United States Declaration of Independence</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In April 1776 the<space/><link><target>North Carolina Provincial Congress</target></link><space/>issued the<space/><link><target>Halifax Resolves</target></link>, explicitly authorizing its delegates to vote for independence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jensen,<space/><italics>The Founding of a Nation</italics><space/>(1968) pp. 6789</extension><space/>In May Congress called on all the states to write constitutions, and eliminate the last remnants of royal rule.</paragraph><paragraph>By June nine colonies were ready for independence; one by one the last fourPennsylvania, Delaware, Maryland and New Yorkfell into line.<space/><link><target>Richard Henry Lee</target></link><space/>was instructed by the Virginia legislature to propose independence, and he did so on June 7, 1776. On the 11th a committee was created to draft a document explaining the justifications for separation from Britain. After securing enough votes for passage, independence was voted for on July 2. The<space/><link><target>United States Declaration of Independence</target><part>Declaration of Independence</part></link>, drafted largely by<space/><link><target>Thomas Jefferson</target></link><space/>and presented by the committee, was slightly revised and unanimously adopted by the entire Congress on July 4, marking the formation of a new sovereign nation, which called itself the<space/><link><target>United States of America</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Maier,<space/><italics>American Scripture</italics><space/>(1997) pp. 4146</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Second Continental Congress approved a new constitution, the &quot;Articles of Confederation,&quot; for ratification by the states on November 15, 1777, and immediately began operating under their terms. The Articles were formally ratified on March 1, 1781. At that point, the Continental Congress was dissolved and on the following day a new government of the<space/><link><target>Congress of the Confederation</target><part>United States in Congress Assembled</part></link><space/>took its place, with<space/><link><target>Samuel Huntington (statesman)</target><part>Samuel Huntington</part></link><space/>as presiding officer.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) chapter 30</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Klos,<space/><italics>President Who? Forgotten Founders</italics><space/>(2004)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Defending the Revolution</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>American Revolutionary War</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>British return: 17761777</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>New York and New Jersey campaign</arg><arg>Staten Island Peace Conference</arg><arg>Saratoga campaign</arg><arg>Philadelphia campaign</arg></template>According to British historian<space/><link><target>Jeremy Black (historian)</target><part>Jeremy Black</part></link>, the British had significant advantages including a highly trained army, the world's largest navy and a highly efficient system of public finance that could easily fund the war. However, the British were seriously handicapped by their misunderstanding of the depth of support for the Patriot position. Ignoring the advice of General Gage, they misinterpreted the situation as merely a large-scale riot. London decided that by sending a large military and naval force they could overawe the Americans and force them to be loyal again:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Convinced that the Revolution was the work of a full few miscreants who had rallied an armed rabble to their cause, they expected that the revolutionaries would be intimidated…. Then the vast majority of Americans, who were loyal but cowed by the terroristic tactics… would rise up, kick out the rebels, and restore loyal government in each colony.<ref>Jeremy Black, ''Crisis of Empire: Britain and America in the Eighteenth Century'' (2008) p 140</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>After Washington forced the British out of Boston in the spring of 1776, neither the British nor the Loyalists controlled any significant areas. The British, however, were massing forces at their naval base at<space/><link><target>Halifax Regional Municipality</target><part>Halifax, Nova Scotia</part></link>. They returned in force in July 1776, landing in New York and defeating Washington's Continental Army at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Long Island</target><part>Battle of Brooklyn</part></link><space/>in August. After winning the Battle of Brooklyn, the British requested a meeting with representatives from Congress to negotiate an end to hostilities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schecter, Barnet 2002">Schecter, Barnet.<space/><italics>The Battle for New York: The City at the Heart of the American Revolution</italics>. (2002)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McCullough, 1776 2005">McCullough,<space/><italics>1776</italics><space/>(2005)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A delegation including John Adams and Benjamin Franklin met Howe on<space/><link><target>Staten Island</target></link><space/>in New York Harbor on September 11, in what became known as the<space/><link><target>Staten Island Peace Conference</target></link>. Howe demanded a retraction of the Declaration of Independence, which was refused, and negotiations ended. The British then<space/><link><target>Battle of Kip's Bay</target><part>quickly seized New York City</part></link><space/>and nearly captured Washington's army. They made New York their main political and military base of operations in North America,<space/><link><target>Evacuation Day (New York)</target><part>holding it until November 1783</part></link>. The city became the destination for Loyalist refugees, and a focal point of Washington's<space/><link><target>Intelligence in the American Revolutionary War</target><part>intelligence network</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schecter, Barnet 2002"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McCullough, 1776 2005"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British also took New Jersey, pushing the Continental Army into Pennsylvania. In a surprise attack in late December 1776 Washington<space/><link><target>Washington's crossing of the Delaware</target><part>crossed the Delaware River</part></link><space/>back into New Jersey and defeated Hessian and British armies at<space/><link><target>Battle of Trenton</target><part>Trenton</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Princeton</target><part>Princeton</part></link>, thereby regaining control of most of New Jersey. The victories gave an important boost to Patriots at a time when morale was flagging, and have become iconic events of the war.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1777, as part of a grand strategy to end the war, the British sent an invasion force from Canada to seal off New England, which the British perceived as the primary source of agitators. In a major case of mis-coordination, the British army in New York City went to Philadelphia which it captured from Washington. The invasion army under<space/><link><target>John Burgoyne</target><part>Burgoyne</part></link><space/>waited in vain for reinforcements from New York, and became trapped in northern New York state. It surrendered after the<space/><link><target>Battle of Saratoga</target></link><space/>in October 1777. From early October 1777 until November 15 a pivotal<space/><link><target>siege</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Fort Mifflin</target></link>, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania distracted British troops and allowed Washington time to preserve the Continental Army by safely leading his troops to harsh winter quarters at<space/><link><target>Valley Forge</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>American alliances after 1778</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>France in the American Revolutionary War</arg><arg>Spain in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The capture of a British army at Saratoga encouraged the French to formally enter the war in support of Congress, as Benjamin Franklin negotiated a permanent military alliance in early 1778, significantly becoming the first country to officially recognize the Declaration of Independence. On February 6, 1778, a<space/><link><target>Treaty of Amity and Commerce (USAFrance)</target><part>Treaty of Amity and Commerce</part></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>Treaty of Alliance (1778)</target><part>Treaty of Alliance</part></link><space/>were signed between the United States and France.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hamilton, 1974 p. 28">Hamilton,<space/><italics>The Papers of Alexander Hamilton</italics><space/>(1974) p. 28</extension><space/><link><target>William Pitt, 1st Earl of Chatham</target><part>William Pitt</part></link><space/>spoke out in parliament urging Britain to make peace in America, and unite with America against France, while other British politicians who had previously sympathised with colonial grievances now turned against the American rebels for allying with Britain's international rival and enemy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanley Weintraub,<space/><italics>Iron Tears: America's Battle for Freedom, Britain's Quagmire, 17751783</italics><space/>(2005) p. 151</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Later Spain (in 1779) and the<space/><link><target>Dutch Republic</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/>(1780) became allies of the French, leaving the British Empire to fight a global war alone without major allies, and requiring it to slip through a combined blockade of the Atlantic. The American theater thus became only one front in Britain's war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mackesy,<space/><italics>The War for America</italics><space/>(1993) p. 568</extension><space/>The British were forced to withdraw troops from continental America to reinforce the valuable sugar-producing Caribbean colonies, which were considered more important.</paragraph><paragraph>Because of the alliance with France and the deteriorating military situation,<space/><link><target>Henry Clinton (American War of Independence)</target><part>Sir Henry Clinton</part></link>, the British commander, evacuated Philadelphia to reinforce New York City. General Washington attempted to intercept the retreating column, resulting in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Monmouth</target><part>Battle of Monmouth Court House</part></link>, the last major battle fought in the north. After an inconclusive engagement, the British successfully retreated to New York City. The northern war subsequently became a stalemate, as the focus of attention shifted to the smaller southern theater.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Higginbotham, 1983 p. 83">Higginbotham,<space/><italics>The War of American Independence</italics><space/>(1983) p. 83</extension><link><target>File:Us unabhaengigkeitskrieg.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>Hessian (soldiers)</target><part>Hessian</part></link><space/>troops hired out to the British by their German sovereigns</xhtml:center></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>The British move South, 17781783</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Southern theater of the American Revolutionary War</arg><arg>Naval operations in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The British strategy in America now concentrated on a campaign in the southern states. With fewer regular troops at their disposal, the British commanders saw the &quot;southern strategy&quot; as a more viable plan, as the south was perceived as being more strongly Loyalist, with a large population of recent immigrants as well as large numbers of slaves who might be captured or run away to join the British.<extension extension_name='ref'>Crow and Tise,<space/><italics>The Southern Experience in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1978) p.&amp;nbsp;1579</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Beginning in late December 1778, the British captured<space/><link><target>Savannah, Georgia</target><part>Savannah</part></link><space/>and controlled the<space/><link><target>Province of Georgia</target><part>Georgia</part></link><space/>coastline. In 1780 they launched a fresh invasion and<space/><link><target>Siege of Charleston</target><part>took Charleston</part></link><space/>as well. A significant victory at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Camden</target></link><space/>meant that royal forces soon controlled most of Georgia and South Carolina. The British set up a network of forts inland, hoping the Loyalists would rally to the flag.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Henry Lumpkin 2000">Henry Lumpkin,<space/><italics>From Savannah to Yorktown: The American Revolution in the South</italics><space/>(2000)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Not enough Loyalists turned out, however, and the British had to fight their way north into North Carolina and Virginia, with a severely weakened army. Behind them much of the territory they had already captured dissolved into a chaotic<space/><link><target>guerrilla war</target></link>, fought predominantly between bands of Loyalist and American militia, which negated many of the gains the British had previously made.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Henry Lumpkin 2000"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Surrender at Yorktown (1781)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Siege of Yorktown</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Yorktown80.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=The siege of Yorktown ended with the surrender of a second British army, paving the way for the end of the American Revolutionary War</part><part><xhtml:center>The<space/><link><target>siege of Yorktown</target></link><space/>ended with the surrender of a second British army, marking effective British defeat.</xhtml:center></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The British army under Cornwallis marched to<space/><link><target>Yorktown, Virginia</target></link><space/>where they expected to be rescued by a British fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brendan Morrissey,<space/><italics>Yorktown 1781: The World Turned Upside Down</italics><space/>(1997)</extension><space/>The fleet showed up but so did a larger French fleet, so the British fleet after the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Chesapeake</target></link><space/>returned to New York for reinforcements, leaving Cornwallis trapped. In October 1781 under a combined siege by the French and Continental armies under Washington, the British surrendered their second invading army of the war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harvey pp 493515</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The end of the war</heading><paragraph>Historians continue to debate whether the odds for American victory were long or short.<space/><link><target>John E. Ferling</target></link><space/>says the odds were so long that the American victory was &quot;Almost A Miracle.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>John Ferling,<space/><italics>Almost A Miracle: The American Victory in the War of Independence</italics><space/>(2009)</extension><space/>On the other hand,<space/><link><target>Joseph Ellis</target></link><space/>says the odds favored the Americans, and asks whether there ever was any realistic chance for the British to win. He argues that this opportunity came only once, in the summer of 1776 and the British failed that test. Admiral Howe and his brother General Howe, &quot;missed several opportunities to destroy the Continental Army....Chance, luck, and even the vagaries of the weather played crucial roles.&quot; Ellis's point is that the strategic and tactical decisions of the Howes were fatally flawed because they underestimated the challenges posed by the Patriots. Ellis concludes that once the Howe brothers failed, the opportunity for a British victory &quot;would never come again.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Joseph J. Ellis</arg><arg name="title">Revolutionary Summer: The Birth of American Independence</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="page">11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Support for the conflict had never been strong in Britain, where many sympathized with the rebels, but now it reached a new low.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harvey p.528</extension><space/>Although King George III personally wanted to fight on, his supporters lost control of Parliament, and no further major land offensives were launched in the American Theater.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Higginbotham, 1983 p. 83"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>A final naval battle was fought on March 10, 1783 by Captain<space/><link><target>John Barry (naval officer)</target><part>John Barry</part></link><space/>and the crew of the<space/><link><target>USS Alliance (1778)</target><part>USS ''Alliance''</part></link>, who defeated three British warships led by HMS<space/><italics>Sybille</italics>. Martin I. J. Griffin,<space/><italics>The Story of Commodore John Barry</italics><space/>(2010) pp 21823</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Washington could not know that after Yorktown the British would not reopen hostilities. They still had 26,000 troops occupying New York City, Charleston and Savannah, together with a powerful fleet. The French army and navy departed, so the Americans were on their own in 178283.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jonathan R. Dull,<space/><italics>The French Navy and American Independence</italics><space/>(1975) p. 248</extension><space/>The treasury was empty, and the unpaid soldiers were growing restive, almost to the point of mutiny or possible<space/><italics>coup d'tat</italics>. The unrest among officers of the<space/><link><target>Newburgh Conspiracy</target></link><space/>was personally dispelled by Washington in 1783, and Congress subsequently created the promise of a five years bonus for all officers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard H. Kohn,<space/><italics>Eagle and Sword: The Federalists and the Creation of the Military Establishment in America, 17831802</italics><space/>(1975) pp 1739</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Peace treaty</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Treaty of Paris (1783)</arg></template>During negotiations in Paris, the American delegation discovered that France would support independence, but no territorial gains. The new nation would be confined to the area east of the Appalachian Mountains. The American delegation opened direct secret negotiations with London, cutting the French out. British Prime Minister<space/><link><target>William Petty, 2nd Earl of Shelburne</target><part>Lord Shelburne</part></link><space/>was in full charge of the British negotiations. He now saw a chance make the United States a valuable economic partner.<extension extension_name='ref'>Charles R. Ritcheson, &quot;The Earl of Shelbourne and Peace with America, 17821783: Vision and Reality.&quot;<space/><italics>International History Review</italics><space/>5#3 (1983): 322-345.</extension><space/>The U.S. obtained all the land east of the Mississippi River, south of Canada, and north of Florida. It gained fishing rights off Canadian coasts, and agreed to allow British merchants and Loyalists to try to recover their property. It was a highly favorable treaty for the United States, and deliberately so from the British point of view. Prime Minister Shelburne foresaw highly profitable two-way trade between Britain and the rapidly growing United States, as indeed came to pass. Since the blockade was lifted and the old imperial restrictions were gone, American merchants were free to trade with any nation anywhere in the world, and their businesses flourished.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jonathan R. Dull</arg><arg name="title">A Diplomatic History of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="publisher">Yale up</arg><arg name="pages">144–151</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British largely abandoned the Indian allies living in the new nation. They were not a party to this treaty and did not recognize it until they were defeated militarily by the United States. However, the British did promise to support the Indians. They sold them munitions and maintained forts in American territory until the<space/><link><target>Jay Treaty</target></link><space/>of 1795.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">William Deverell, ed.</arg><arg name="title">A Companion to the American West</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="page">17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Impact on Britain</heading><paragraph>Losing the war and the 13 colonies was a shock to Britain. The war revealed the limitations of Britain's<space/><link><target>fiscal-military state</target></link><space/>when it discovered it suddenly faced powerful enemies, with no allies, and dependent on extended and vulnerable transatlantic lines of communication. The defeat heightened dissension and escalated political antagonism to the King's ministers. Inside parliament, the primary concern changed from fears of an over-mighty monarch to the issues of representation, parliamentary reform, and government retrenchment. Reformers sought to destroy what they saw as widespread institutional corruption.<extension extension_name='ref' name="William Hague 2004">William Hague,<space/><italics>William Pitt the Younger</italics><space/>(2004)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeremy Black 2006">Jeremy Black,<space/><italics>George III: America's Last King</italics>(2006)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The result was a powerful crisis, 17761783. The peace in 1783 left France financially prostrate, while the British economy boomed thanks to the return of American business. The crisis ended after 1784 thanks to the King's shrewdness in outwitting<space/><link><target>Charles James Fox</target></link><space/>(the leader of the<space/><link><target>Fox-North Coalition</target></link>), and renewed confidence in the system engendered by the leadership of the new Prime Minister,<space/><link><target>William Pitt the Younger</target><part>William Pitt</part></link>. Historians conclude that loss of the American colonies enabled Britain to deal with the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>with more unity and better organization than would otherwise have been the case.<extension extension_name='ref' name="William Hague 2004"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeremy Black 2006"></extension><space/>Britain turned towards Asia, the Pacific and later Africa with subsequent exploration leading to the rise of the<space/><link><target>Second British Empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#refOHBEv1</target><part>Canny</part></link>, p.&amp;nbsp;92.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Finance</heading><paragraph>Britain's war against the Americans, French and Spanish cost about 100 million. The Treasury borrowed 40% of the money it needed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul Kennedy,<space/><italics>The Rise and Fall of the Great Powers</italics><space/>(1987) pp. 81, 119</extension><space/>Heavy spending brought France to the<space/><link><target>Causes of the French Revolution#Economics and finances</target><part>verge of bankruptcy and revolution</part></link>, while the British had relatively little difficulty financing their war, keeping their suppliers and soldiers paid, and hiring tens of thousands of German soldiers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="John Brewer 1990 p 91">John Brewer,<space/><italics>The sinews of power: war, money, and the English state, 16881783</italics><space/>(1990) p 91</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Britain had a sophisticated financial system based on the wealth of thousands of landowners, who supported the government, together with banks and financiers in London. The efficient British tax system collected about 12 percent of the GDP in taxes during the 1770s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="John Brewer 1990 p 91"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In sharp contrast, Congress and the American states had no end of difficulty financing the war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Curtis P. Nettels,<space/><italics>The Emergence of a National Economy, 17751815</italics><space/>(1962) pp 2344</extension><space/>In 1775 there was at most 12 million dollars in gold in the colonies, not nearly enough to cover current transactions, let alone finance a major war. The British made the situation much worse by imposing a tight blockade on every American port, which cut off almost all imports and exports. One partial solution was to rely on volunteer support from militiamen, and donations from patriotic citizens.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Charles Rappleye 2010 pp 225">Charles Rappleye,<space/><italics>Robert Morris: Financier of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2010) pp 22552</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another was to delay actual payments, pay soldiers and suppliers in depreciated currency, and promise it would be made good after the war. Indeed, in 1783 the soldiers and officers were given land grants to cover the wages they had earned but had not been paid during the war. Not until 1781, when<space/><link><target>Robert Morris (financier)</target><part>Robert Morris</part></link><space/>was named<space/><link><target>Superintendent of Finance of the United States</target></link>, did the national government have a strong leader in financial matters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Charles Rappleye 2010 pp 225"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Morris used a French loan in 1782 to set up the private<space/><link><target>Bank of North America</target></link><space/>to finance the war. Seeking greater efficiency, Morris reduced the civil list, saved money by using competitive bidding for contracts, tightened accounting procedures, and demanded the national government's full share of money and supplies from the confederated states.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Charles Rappleye 2010 pp 225"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Congress used four main methods to cover the cost of the war, which cost about 66 million dollars in specie (gold and silver).<extension extension_name='ref'>Oliver Harry Chitwood,<space/><italics>A History of Colonial America</italics><space/>(1961) pp 586589</extension><space/>Congress made two issues of paper money, in 17751780, and in 178081. The first issue amounted to 242 million dollars. This paper money would supposedly be redeemed for state taxes, but the holders were eventually paid off in 1791 at the rate of one cent on the dollar. By 1780, the paper money was &quot;not worth a Continental&quot;, as people said.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Terry M. Mays</arg><arg name="title">Historical Dictionary of Revolutionary America</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Scarecrow Press</arg><arg name="pages">73–75</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The skyrocketing inflation was a hardship on the few people who had fixed incomesbut 90 percent of the people were farmers, and were not directly affected by that inflation. Debtors benefited by paying off their debts with depreciated paper.The greatest burden was borne by the soldiers of the Continental Army, whose wagesusually in arrearsdeclined in value every month, weakening their morale and adding to the hardships of their families.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ralph Volney Harlow, &quot;Aspects of Revolutionary Finance, 17751783,&quot;<space/><italics>American Historical Review</italics><space/>(1929) 35#1 pp. 4668<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1838471'>in JSTOR</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Beginning in 1777, Congress repeatedly asked the states to provide money. But the states had no system of taxation either, and were little help. By 1780 Congress was making requisitions for specific supplies of corn, beef, pork and other necessitiesan inefficient system that kept the army barely alive.<extension extension_name='ref'>Erna Risch,<space/><italics>Supplying Washington's Army</italics><space/>(1982)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>E. Wayne Carp,<space/><italics>To Starve the Army at Pleasure: Continental Army Administration and American Political Culture, 17751783</italics><space/>(1990)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Starting in 1776, the Congress sought to raise money by loans from wealthy individuals, promising to redeem the bonds after the war. The bonds were in fact redeemed in 1791 at face value, but the scheme raised little money because Americans had little specie, and many of the rich merchants were supporters of the Crown. Starting in 1776, the French secretly supplied the Americans with money, gunpowder, and munitions in order to weaken its arch enemy, Great Britain. When France officially entered the war in 1778, the subsidies continued, and the French government, as well as bankers in Paris and Amsterdam loaned large sums to the American war effort. These loans were repaid in full in the 1790s.<extension extension_name='ref'>E. James Ferguson,<space/><italics>The power of the purse: A history of American public finance, 17761790</italics><space/>(1961)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Concluding the Revolution</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Philadelphia Convention</arg><arg>United States Bill of Rights</arg></template><template><target>see also</target><arg>Annapolis Convention (1786)</arg><arg>The Federalist Papers</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Creating a &quot;more perfect union&quot; and guaranteeing rights</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Federalist Party</arg><arg>Annapolis Convention (1786)</arg><arg>United States Bill of Rights</arg></template>After the war finally ended in 1783, there was a period of prosperity. The national government, still operating under the Articles of Confederation, was able to settle the issue of the western territories, which were ceded by the states to Congress. American settlers moved rapidly into those areas, with Vermont, Kentucky and Tennessee becoming states in the 1790s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole, eds.<space/><italics>Companion to the American Revolution,</italics><space/>pp. 557624</extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, the national government had no money to pay either the war debts owed to European nations and the private banks, or to pay Americans who had been given millions of dollars of promissory notes for supplies during the war. Nationalists, led by Washington, Alexander Hamilton and other veterans, feared that the new nation was too fragile to withstand an international war, or even internal revolts such as the<space/><link><target>Shays' Rebellion</target></link><space/>of 1786 in Massachusetts.</paragraph><paragraph>Calling themselves &quot;Federalists,&quot; the nationalists convinced Congress to call the<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Convention</target></link><space/>in 1787.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard B. Morris,<space/><italics>The Forging of the Union: 17811789</italics><space/>(1987) pp 245266</extension><space/>It adopted a new<space/><link><target>Constitution of the United States</target><part>Constitution</part></link><space/>that provided for a much stronger federal government, including an effective executive in a<space/><link><target>Separation of powers</target><part>check-and-balance</part></link><space/>system with the judiciary and legislature.<extension extension_name='ref'>Morris,<space/><italics>The Forging of the Union: 17811789</italics><space/>pp 30013</extension><space/>After a fierce debate in the states over the nature of the proposed new government, the Constitution was ratified in 1788. The new government under President George Washington took office in New York in March 1789.<extension extension_name='ref'>Morris,<space/><italics>The Forging of the Union, 17811789</italics><space/>pp 30022</extension><space/>As assurances to those who were cautious about federal power, amendments to the Constitution guaranteeing many of the<space/><link><target>inalienable rights</target></link><space/>that formed a foundation for the revolution were spearheaded in Congress by<space/><link><target>James Madison</target></link>, and later ratified by the states in 1791.</paragraph><heading level='3'>National debt</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>United States public debt</arg><arg>Alexander Hamilton</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The national debt after the American Revolution fell into three categories. The first was the $12 million owed to foreignersmostly money borrowed from France. There was general agreement to pay the foreign debts at full value. The national government owed $40 million and state governments owed $25 million to Americans who had sold food, horses, and supplies to the revolutionary forces. There were also other debts that consisted of<space/><link><target>promissory note</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>issued during the Revolutionary War to soldiers, merchants, and farmers who accepted these payments on the premise that the new Constitution would create a government that would pay these debts eventually.</paragraph><paragraph>The war expenses of the individual states added up to $114 million compared to $37 million by the central government.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jensen,<space/><italics>The New Nation</italics><space/>(1950) p. 379</extension><space/>In 1790, at the recommendation of first Secretary of the Treasury, Alexander Hamilton, Congress combined the remaining state debts with the foreign and domestic debts into one national debt totaling $80 million. Everyone received face value for wartime certificates, so that the national honor would be sustained and the national credit established.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joseph J. Ellis,<space/><italics>His Excellency: George Washington</italics><space/>(2004) p 204</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ideology and factions</heading><paragraph>The population of the 13 Colonies was far from homogeneous, particularly in their political views and attitudes. Loyalties and allegiances varied widely not only within regions and communities, but also within families and sometimes shifted during the course of the Revolution.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ideology behind the Revolution</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>American Enlightenment</arg><arg>Liberalism in the United States</arg><arg>Republicanism in the United States</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The ideological movement known as the American Enlightenment was a critical precursor to the American Revolution. Chief among the ideas of the American Enlightenment were the concepts of liberalism, republicanism and fear of corruption. Collectively, the acceptance of these concepts by a growing number of American colonists began to foster an intellectual environment which would lead to a new sense of political and social identity.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Natural rights and republicanism</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>John Locke</arg><arg>Republicanism in the United States</arg></template><template><target>unbalanced</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><template><target>Republicanism sidebar</target></template><link><target>File:J S Copley - Samuel Adams.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>alt=A stern middle-aged man with gray hair is wearing a dark red suit. He is standing behind a table, holding a rolled up document in one hand, and pointing with the other hand to a large document on the table.</part><part><xhtml:center>In this<space/><template><target>circa</target><arg>1772</arg></template><space/>portrait by<space/><link><target>John Singleton Copley</target></link>, Samuel Adams points at the<space/><link><target>Explanatory charter</target><part>Massachusetts Charter</part></link>, which he viewed as a constitution that protected the people's rights.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alexander,<space/><italics>Revolutionary Politician</italics>, 103, 136; Maier,<space/><italics>Old Revolutionaries</italics>, 4142.</extension></xhtml:center></part></link><link><target>John Locke</target></link>'s (16321704) ideas on liberty greatly influenced the political thinking behind the revolution, especially through his indirect influence on English writers such as<space/><link><target>John Trenchard (writer)</target><part>John Trenchard</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Thomas Gordon (writer)</target><part>Thomas Gordon</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Benjamin Hoadly</target></link>, whose political ideas in turn had a strong influence on the American revolutionaries.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlekauff (2005), pp. 136-138</extension><space/>Locke is often referred to as &quot;the philosopher of the American Revolution&quot;, and is credited with leading Americans to the critical concepts of social contract, natural rights, and &quot;born free and equal.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jeffrey D. Schultz</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of Religion in American Politics</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="publisher">Greenwood</arg><arg name="page">148</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><space/>Locke's<space/><link><target>Two Treatises of Government</target></link>, published in 1689, were especially influential; Locke in turn was influenced by<space/><link><target>Protestantism</target><part>Protestant</part></link><space/>theology.<extension extension_name='ref'>Waldron (2002), p. 13</extension><space/>He argued that, as all humans were created equally free, governments needed the &quot;consent of the governed.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Waldron (2002), p. 136</extension><space/>Both Lockean concepts were central to the<space/><link><target>United States Declaration of Independence</target></link>, which deduced human equality, &quot;life, liberty, and the pursuit of happiness&quot; from the biblical belief in creation: &quot;All men are<space/><italics>created</italics><space/>equal,&amp;nbsp;... they are endowed by their<space/><italics>Creator</italics><space/>with certain unalienable Rights.&quot; In late eighteenth-century America, belief in &quot;equality by creation&quot; and &quot;rights by creation&quot; was still widespread.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thomas S. Kidd (2010):<space/><italics>God of Liberty: A Religious History of the American Revolution</italics>, New York, N.Y., pp. 6-7</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Declaration also referred to the &quot;Laws of Nature and of Nature's God&quot; as justification for the Americans' separation from the British monarchy. Most eighteenth-century Americans believed that nature, the entire universe, was God's creation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlekauff (2005), pp.&amp;nbsp;3-6</extension><space/>Therefore, he was &quot;Nature's God.&quot; Everything, including man, was part of the &quot;universal order of things&quot;, which began with God and was pervaded and directed by his providence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlekauff (2005), pp.&amp;nbsp;34</extension><space/>Accordingly, the signers of the Declaration professed their &quot;firm reliance on the Protection of divine Providence.&quot; And they appealed to &quot;the Supreme Judge [God] for the rectitude of [their] intentions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kidd (2010), p. 141</extension><space/>Like most of his countrymen,<space/><link><target>George Washington</target></link><space/>was firmly convinced that he was an instrument of providence, to the benefit not only of the American people but of all of humanity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Middlekauff (2005), p. 302</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The theory of the &quot;<link><target>social contract</target></link>&quot; influenced the belief among many of the Founders that among the &quot;natural rights&quot; of man was the<space/><link><target>Right of revolution</target><part>right of the people to overthrow their leaders</part></link>, should those leaders betray the historic<space/><link><target>rights of Englishmen</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Toth1989">Charles W. Toth,<space/><italics>Liberte, Egalite, Fraternite: The American Revolution and the European Response.</italics><space/>(1989) p. 26.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Cohen2008">page 101, Philosophical Tales, by Martin Cohen, (Blackwell 2008)</extension><space/>In terms of writing state and national constitutions, the Americans heavily used<space/><link><target>Charles de Secondat, baron de Montesquieu</target><part>Montesquieu</part></link>'s analysis of the wisdom of the &quot;balanced&quot; British Constitution (<link><target>mixed government</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>A motivating force behind the revolution was the American embrace of a political ideology called &quot;republicanism&quot;, which was dominant in the colonies by 1775, but of minor importance back in Great Britain. The republicanism was inspired by the &quot;<link><target>Whig (British political party)</target><part>country party</part></link>&quot; in Great Britain, whose critique of British government emphasized that<space/><link><target>political corruption</target><part>corruption</part></link><space/>was a terrible reality in Great Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weintraub2005">Stanley Weintraub,<space/><italics>Iron Tears: America's Battle for Freedom, Britain's Quagmire, 17751783</italics><space/>(2005) chapter 1</extension><space/>Americans feared the corruption was crossing the Atlantic; the commitment of most Americans to republican values and to their rights, energized the revolution, as Britain was increasingly seen as hopelessly corrupt and hostile to American interests. Britain seemed to threaten the established liberties that Americans enjoyed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bailyn,<space/><italics><space/>The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1992) pp. 12537</extension><space/>The greatest threat to liberty was depicted as corruptionnot just in<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>but at home as well. The colonists associated it with luxury and, especially, inherited aristocracy, which they condemned.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wood,<space/><italics>The Radicalism of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1992) pp. 35, 1745</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Founding Fathers were strong advocates of republican values, particularly<space/><link><target>Samuel Adams</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Patrick Henry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Adams</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Benjamin Franklin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thomas Jefferson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thomas Paine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>George Washington</target></link>,<space/><link><target>James Madison</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexander Hamilton</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Shalhope,<space/><italics>Toward a Republican Synthesis</italics><space/>(1972) pp.4980</extension><space/>which required men to put civic duty ahead of their personal desires. Men had a civic duty to be prepared and willing to fight for the rights and liberties of their countrymen and countrywomen. John Adams, writing to<space/><link><target>Mercy Otis Warren</target></link><space/>in 1776, agreed with some<space/><link><target>Classical antiquity</target><part>classical</part></link><space/>Greek and Roman thinkers in that &quot;Public Virtue cannot exist without private, and public Virtue is the only Foundation of Republics.&quot; He continued:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="There must be a positive Passion for the public good, the public Interest, Honour, Power, and Glory, established in the Minds of the People, or there can be no Republican Government, nor any real Liberty. And this public Passion must be Superior to all private Passions. Men must be ready, they must pride themselves, and be happy to sacrifice their private Pleasures, Passions, and Interests, nay their private Friendships and dearest connections, when they Stand in Competition with the Rights of society.<ref name">Rahe1994>Adams quoted in Paul A. Rahe, ''Republics Ancient and Modern: Classical Republicanism and the American Revolution. Volume: 2'' (1994) P. 23.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For women, &quot;<link><target>republican motherhood</target></link>&quot; became the ideal, exemplified by<space/><link><target>Abigail Adams</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mercy Otis Warren</target></link>; the first duty of the republican woman was to instill republican values in her children and to avoid luxury and ostentation.</paragraph><heading level='5'>Fusing republicanism and liberalism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:commonsense.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Thomas Paine's pamphlet Common Sense, published in 1776</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>Thomas Paine</target></link>'s pamphlet<space/><italics><link><target>Common Sense (pamphlet)</target><part>Common Sense</part></link></italics>, published in 1776</xhtml:center></part></link>While some republics had emerged throughout history, such as the<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target></link><space/>of the ancient world, one based on liberal principles had never existed. Thomas Paine's best-seller pamphlet<space/><italics><link><target>Common Sense (pamphlet)</target><part>Common Sense</part></link></italics><space/>appeared in January 1776, after the Revolution had started. It was widely distributed and loaned, and often read aloud in<space/><link><target>Tavern#North America</target><part>taverns</part></link>, contributing significantly to spreading the ideas of republicanism and liberalism together, bolstering enthusiasm for separation from Great Britain, and encouraging recruitment for the Continental Army.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferguson, 2000 pp. 465">Ferguson,<space/><italics>The Commonalities of Common Sense</italics><space/>(2000) pp. 465504</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Paine provided a new and widely accepted argument for independence, by advocating a complete break with history.<space/><italics>Common Sense</italics><space/>is oriented to the future in a way that compels the reader to make an immediate choice. It offered a solution for Americans disgusted and alarmed at the threat of tyranny.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ferguson, 2000 pp. 465"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Impact of Great Awakening</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>First Great Awakening</arg></template><link><target>Dissenter</target><part>Dissenting</part></link><space/>(i.e. Protestant, non-<link><target>Church of England</target></link>) churches of the day were the &quot;school of<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bonomi">Bonomi, p. 186, Chapter 7 &quot;Religion and the American Revolution</extension><space/>President<space/><link><target>John Witherspoon</target></link><space/>of the College of New Jersey (now<space/><link><target>Princeton University</target></link>) wrote widely circulated sermons linking the American Revolution to the teachings of the Hebrew Bible. Throughout the colonies, dissenting Protestant ministers (<link><target>Congregational church</target><part>Congregationalist</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Baptists</target><part>Baptist</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Presbyterianism</target><part>Presbyterian</part></link>) preached Revolutionary themes in their sermons, while most Church of England clergymen preached loyalty to the king, the<space/><link><target>Supreme Governor of the Church of England</target><part>titular head</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>State Church</target><part>state church</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nelson1961">William H. Nelson,<space/><italics>The American Tory</italics><space/>(1961) p. 186</extension><space/>Religious motivation for fighting tyranny reached across socioeconomic lines to encompass rich and poor, men and women, frontiersmen and townsmen, farmers and merchants.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bonomi"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>Bernard Bailyn</target></link><space/>argues that the evangelicalism of the era challenged traditional notions of natural hierarchy by preaching that the Bible taught all men are equal, so that the true value of a man lies in his moral behavior, not his class.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bailyn,<italics>The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1992) p. 303</extension><space/>Kidd argues that religious<space/><link><target>Disestablished</target><part>disestablishment</part></link>, belief in a God as the source of<space/><link><target>human rights</target></link>, and shared convictions about sin, virtue, and<space/><link><target>divine providence</target></link><space/>worked together to unite rationalists and evangelicals and thus encouraged American defiance of the Empire, whereas Bailyn denied that religion played such a critical role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Thomas S. Kidd 2010">Thomas S. Kidd,<space/><italics>God of Liberty: A Religious History of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2010)</extension><space/>Alan Heimert argued, however, that New Light antiauthoritarianism was essential to the further democratization of colonial American society, and set the stage for a confrontation with British monarchical and aristocratic rule.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alan Heimert,<space/><italics>Religion and the American Mind: From the Great Awakening to the Revolution</italics>. Cambridge: Harvard University Press, 1967.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Class and psychology of the factions</heading><paragraph>Looking back, John Adams concluded in 1818:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The Revolution was effected before the war commenced. The Revolution was in the minds and hearts of the people&nbsp;... This radical change in the principles, opinions, sentiments, and affections of the people was the real American Revolution.<ref>John Ferling, ''Setting the World Ablaze: Washington, Adams, Jefferson, and the American Revolution'' (2002) p. 281</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In terms of class, Loyalists tended to have longstanding social and economic connections to British merchants and government; for instance, prominent merchants in major port cities such as New York, Boston and Charleston tended to be Loyalists, as did men involved with the<space/><link><target>fur trade</target></link><space/>along the northern frontier.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><space/>In addition, officials of colonial government and their staffs, those who had established positions and status to maintain, favored maintaining relations with Great Britain. They often were linked to British families in England by marriage as well.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By contrast, Patriots by number tended to be<space/><link><target>Yeoman#United States</target><part>yeomen farmers</part></link>, especially in the frontier areas of New York and the backcountry of Pennsylvania, Virginia and down the Appalachian mountains.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><space/>They were craftsmen and small merchants. Leaders of both the Patriots and the Loyalists were men of educated, propertied classes. The Patriots included many prominent men of the<space/><link><target>planter (plantation owner)</target><part>planter</part></link><space/>class from Virginia and South Carolina, for instance, who became leaders during the Revolution, and formed the new government at the national and state levels.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>To understand the opposing groups, historians have assessed evidence of their hearts and minds. In the mid-20th century, historian<space/><link><target>Leonard Woods Labaree</target></link><space/>identified eight characteristics of the Loyalists that made them essentially conservative; traits to those characteristic of the Patriots.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Labaree, 1948 pp. 164-5">Labaree,<space/><italics>Conservatism in Early American History</italics><space/>(1948) pp. 1645</extension><space/>Older and better established men, Loyalists tended to resist innovation. They thought resistance to the Crownwhich they insisted was the only legitimate governmentwas morally wrong, while the Patriots thought morality was on their side.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hull 1978 pp. 344">Hull et al.,<space/><italics>Choosing Sides</italics><space/>(1978) pp. 34466</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallace, 1972 pp. 167">Burrows and Wallace,<space/><italics>The American Revolution</italics><space/>(1972) pp. 167305</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Loyalists were alienated when the Patriots resorted to violence, such as burning houses and<space/><link><target>tarring and feathering</target></link>. Loyalists wanted to take a centrist position and resisted the Patriots' demand to declare their opposition to the Crown. Many Loyalists, especially merchants in the port cities, had maintained strong and long-standing relations with Britain (often with business and family links to other parts of the British Empire).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hull 1978 pp. 344"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallace, 1972 pp. 167"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many Loyalists realized that independence was bound to come eventually, but they were fearful that revolution might lead to anarchy, tyranny or mob rule. In contrast, the prevailing attitude among Patriots, who made systematic efforts to use mob violence in a controlled manner, was a desire to seize the initiative.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hull 1978 pp. 344"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallace, 1972 pp. 167"></extension><space/>Labaree also wrote that Loyalists were pessimists who lacked the confidence in the future displayed by the Patriots.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Labaree, 1948 pp. 164-5"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historians in the early 20th century, such as<space/><link><target>J. Franklin Jameson</target></link>, examined the class composition of the Patriot cause, looking for evidence of a class war inside the revolution.<extension extension_name='ref'>J. Franklin Jameson,<space/><italics>The American Revolution Considered as a Social Movement</italics><space/>(1926); other historians pursuing the same line of thought included<space/><link><target>Charles A. Beard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carl L. Becker</target><part>Carl Becker</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arthur Schlesinger, Sr.</target></link>.</extension><space/>In the last 50&amp;nbsp;years, historians have largely abandoned that interpretation, emphasizing instead the high level of ideological unity.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wood,<space/><italics>Rhetoric and Reality in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1966) pp. 332</extension><space/>Just as there were rich and poor Loyalists, the Patriots were a 'mixed lot', with the richer and better educated more likely to become officers in the Army.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nash 2005">Nash (2005)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Resch 2006">Resch (2006)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ideological demands always came first: the Patriots viewed independence as a means to gain freedom from British oppression and taxation and, above all, to reassert what they considered to be their rights as English subjects. Most yeomen farmers, craftsmen, and small merchants joined the Patriot cause to demand more political equality. They were especially successful in Pennsylvania but less so in New England, where John Adams attacked Thomas Paine's<space/><italics>Common Sense</italics><space/>for the &quot;absurd democratical notions&quot; it proposed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nash 2005"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Resch 2006"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>King George III</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>George III of Great Britain</arg></template>The war became a personal issue for<space/><link><target>George III of the United Kingdom</target><part>the king</part></link>, fueled by his growing belief that British leniency would be taken as weakness by the Americans. The king also sincerely believed he was defending Britain's constitution against usurpers, rather than opposing patriots fighting for their natural rights.<extension extension_name='ref'>Andrew Jackson O'Shaughnessy, &quot;'If Others Will Not Be Active, I must Drive': George III and the American Revolution.&quot;<space/><italics>Early American Studies</italics><space/>2004 2(1): pp 146. P. D. G. Thomas, &quot;George III and the American Revolution.&quot;<space/><italics>History</italics><space/>1985 70(228): 1631, says the king played a minor role before 1775.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Patriots</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Patriot (American Revolution)</arg></template><template><target>Further</target><arg>Sons of Liberty</arg></template>At the time, revolutionaries were called &quot;Patriots&quot;, &quot;Whigs&quot;, &quot;Congress-men&quot;, or &quot;Americans&quot;. They included a full range of social and economic classes, but were unanimous regarding the need to defend the rights of Americans and uphold the principles of<space/><link><target>Republicanism in the United States</target><part>republicanism</part></link><space/>in terms of rejecting monarchy and aristocracy, while emphasizing civic virtue on the part of the citizens. Newspapers were strongholds of patriotism (although there were a few Loyalist papers), and printed many pamphlets, announcements, patriotic letters and pronouncements.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carol Sue Humphrey,<space/><italics>The American Revolution and the Press: The Promise of Independence</italics><space/>(Northwestern University Press; 2013)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to historian Robert Calhoon, the consensus of historians is that 4045% of the white population in the Thirteen Colonies supported the Patriots' cause, 1520% supported the Loyalists, and the remainder were neutral or kept a low profile.<extension extension_name='ref'>Robert M. Calhoon, &quot;Loyalism and neutrality&quot; in<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Jack P. Greene</arg><arg name="author2">J. R. Pole</arg><arg name="title">A Companion to the American Revolution</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley & Sons</arg><arg name="page">235</arg></template></extension><space/>Mark Lender explores why ordinary folk became insurgents against the British even though they were unfamiliar with the ideological rationales being offered. They held very strongly a sense of &quot;rights&quot; that they felt the British were violating rights that stressed local autonomy, fair dealing, and government by consent. They were highly sensitive to the issue of tyranny, which they saw manifested in the British response to the Boston Tea Party. The arrival in Boston of the British Army heightened their sense of violated rights, leading to rage and demands for revenge. They had faith that God was on their side.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mark Edward Lender, review of<space/><italics>American Insurgents, American Patriots: The Revolution of the People</italics><space/>(2010) by T. H. Breen, in<space/><italics>The Journal of Military History</italics><space/>(2012) 76#1 p. 2334</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Loyalists</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Loyalist (American Revolution)</arg></template><link><target>File:Mobbing the Tories - Project Gutenberg eText 16960.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><xhtml:center>Mobbing of a Loyalist by American Patriots in 177576</xhtml:center></part></link>The consensus of scholars is that about 1520% of the white population remained loyal to the British Crown.<extension extension_name='ref'>Calhoon, &quot;Loyalism and neutrality&quot; in Greene and Pole, eds.<space/><italics>A Companion to the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1980) at<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=xK1NuzpAcH8C&amp;amp;pg=PA235'>page 235</link></extension><space/>Those who actively supported the king were known at the time as &quot;Loyalists&quot;, &quot;Tories&quot;, or &quot;King's men&quot;. The Loyalists never controlled territory unless the British Army occupied it. Loyalists were typically older, less willing to break with old loyalties, often connected to the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link>, and included many established merchants with strong business connections across the Empire, as well as royal officials such as Thomas Hutchinson of Boston.<extension extension_name='ref'>Calhoon, &quot;Loyalism and neutrality&quot; in Greene and Pole, eds.<space/><italics>A Companion to the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1980) pp 235-47,</extension><space/>There were 500 to 1000<space/><link><target>Black Loyalist</target><part>black loyalists</part></link><space/>who were held as slaves by patriots, escaped to British lines and joined the British army. Most died of disease but Britain took the survivors to Canada as free men.</paragraph><paragraph>The revolution could divide families. The most dramatic example was when<space/><link><target>William Franklin</target></link>, son of Benjamin Franklin and royal governor of the<space/><link><target>Province of New Jersey</target></link>, remained loyal to the Crown throughout the war; they never spoke again.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sheila L. Skemp,<space/><italics>Benjamin and William Franklin: Father and Son, Patriot and Loyalist</italics><space/>(1994)</extension><space/>Recent immigrants who had not been fully Americanized were also inclined to support the King, such as recent Scottish settlers in the back country; among the more striking examples of this, see<space/><link><target>Flora MacDonald (Scottish Jacobite)</target><part>Flora MacDonald</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Joan Magee</arg><arg name="title">Loyalist Mosaic: A Multi-Ethnic Heritage</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="publisher">Dundurn</arg><arg name="page">137ff</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the war, the great majority of the 450,000500,000 Loyalists remained in America and resumed normal lives. Some, such as<space/><link><target>Samuel Seabury (17291796)</target><part>Samuel Seabury</part></link>, became prominent American leaders. Estimates vary, but about 62,000 Loyalists relocated to Canada, and others to Britain (7,000) or to Florida or the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link><space/>(9,000). The exiles represented approximately 2% of the total population of the colonies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pole 1994">Greene and Pole (1994) chapters 2022</extension><space/>Nearly all<space/><link><target>Black Loyalist</target><part>black loyalists</part></link><space/>left for Nova Scotia, Florida, or England, where they could remain free.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.blackloyalist.com/canadiandigitalcollection/story/exile/chaos.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chaos in New York<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-10-18<space/></arg><arg name="work">Black Loyalists: Our People, Our History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Canada's Digital Collections</arg></template></extension><space/>When Loyalists left the<space/><link><target>Southern United States</target><part>South</part></link><space/>in 1783, they took thousands of their slaves with them to be slaves in the British West Indies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pole 1994"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Neutrals</heading><paragraph>A minority of uncertain size tried to stay neutral in the war. Most kept a low profile, but the<space/><link><target>Religious Society of Friends</target><part>Quakers</part></link>, especially in Pennsylvania, were the most important group to speak out for neutrality. As Patriots declared independence, the Quakers, who continued to do business with the British, were attacked as supporters of British rule, &quot;contrivers and authors of seditious publications&quot; critical of the revolutionary cause.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gottlieb (2005)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Role of women</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Abigail Adams.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Abigail Adams</part><part><xhtml:center><link><target>Abigail Adams</target></link></xhtml:center></part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Women in the American Revolution</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Women contributed to the American Revolution in many ways, and were involved on both sides. While formal Revolutionary politics did not include women, ordinary domestic behaviors became charged with political significance as Patriot women confronted a war that permeated all aspects of political, civil, and domestic life. They participated by boycotting British goods, spying on the British, following armies as they marched, washing, cooking, and tending for soldiers, delivering secret messages, and in a few cases like<space/><link><target>Deborah Samson</target></link>, fighting disguised as men. Also,<space/><link><target>Mercy Otis Warren</target></link><space/>held meetings in her house and cleverly attacked Loyalists with her creative plays and histories.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Eileen K. Cheng</arg><arg name="title">The Plain and Noble Garb of Truth: Nationalism & Impartiality in American Historical Writing, 1784–1860</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Georgia Press</arg><arg name="page">210</arg></template></extension><space/>Above all, they continued the agricultural work at home to feed their families and the armies. They maintained their families during their husbands' absences and sometimes after their deaths.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Berkin, 2006 p. 59-60">Berkin,<space/><italics>Revolutionary Mothers</italics><space/>(2006) p.&amp;nbsp;5960</extension></paragraph><paragraph>American women were integral to the success of the boycott of British goods,<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) chapter 41</extension><space/>as the boycotted items were largely household items such as tea and cloth. Women had to return to knitting goods, and to spinning and weaving their own cloth skills that had fallen into disuse. In 1769, the women of Boston produced 40,000 skeins of yarn, and 180 women in<space/><link><target>Middleton, Massachusetts</target><part>Middletown, Massachusetts</part></link><space/>wove<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20522</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>of cloth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Berkin, 2006 p. 59-60"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A crisis of political loyalties could disrupt the fabric of colonial America women's social worlds: whether a man did or did not renounce his allegiance to the King could dissolve ties of class, family, and friendship, isolating women from former connections. A woman's loyalty to her husband, once a private commitment, could become a political act, especially for women in America committed to men who remained loyal to the King. Legal divorce, usually rare, was granted to Patriot women whose husbands supported the King.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kerber,<space/><italics>Women of the Republic</italics><space/>(1997) chapters 4 and 6</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Mary Beth Norton,<space/><italics>Liberty's Daughters: The Revolutionary Experience of American Women</italics><space/>(1980)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other participants</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Diplomacy in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>France in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template>In early 1776, France set up a major program of aid to the Americans, and the Spanish secretly added funds. Each country spent one million &quot;livres tournaises&quot; to buy munitions. A<space/><link><target>dummy corporation</target></link><space/>run by<space/><link><target>Pierre Beaumarchais</target></link><space/>concealed their activities. American rebels obtained some munitions through the<space/><link><target>Dutch Republic</target></link><space/>as well as French and Spanish ports in the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jonathan Dull,<space/><italics>A Diplomatic History of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1985) pp. 5765</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Spain</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Spain in the American Revolutionary War</arg></template>Spain did not officially recognize the U.S. but became an informal ally when it declared war on Britain on June 21, 1779.<space/><link><target>Bernardo de Glvez y Madrid</target></link>, general of the Spanish forces in<space/><link><target>New Spain</target></link>, also served as governor of Louisiana. He led an expedition of colonial troops to force the British out of Florida and keep open a vital conduit for supplies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Thompson, Buchanan Parker,<space/><italics>Spain: Forgotten Ally of the American Revolution</italics><space/>North Quincy, Mass.: Christopher Publishing House, 1976.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Native Americans</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Native Americans in the United States</arg></template><template><target>further</target><arg>Western theater of the American Revolutionary War</arg></template>Most Native Americans rejected pleas that they remain neutral and supported the British Crown, both because of trading relationships and Britain's effort to establish an Indian reserve and prohibit colonial settlement west of the Appalachian Mountains. The great majority of the 200,000 Native Americans east of the Mississippi distrusted the colonists and supported the British cause, hoping to forestall continued colonial encroachment on their territories.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (2004) chapters 19, 46 and 51; Colin G. Calloway,<space/><italics>The American Revolution in Indian Country: Crisis and Diversity in Native American Communities</italics><space/>(1995)</extension><space/>Those tribes that were more closely involved in colonial trade tended to side with the revolutionaries, although political factors were important as well.</paragraph><paragraph>Except for warriors and bands associated with four of the<space/><link><target>Iroquois</target></link><space/>nations in New York and Pennsylvania, which allied with the British, most Native Americans did not participate directly in the war. The British did have other allies especially in the upper Midwest. They provided Indians with funding and weapons to attack American outposts. Some Indians tried to remain neutral, seeing little value in joining a European conflict and fearing reprisals from whichever side they opposed. The<space/><link><target>Oneida tribe</target><part>Oneida</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Tuscarora people</target><part>Tuscarora</part></link>, among the Iroquois of central and western New York, supported the American cause.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joseph T. Glatthaar and James Kirby Martin,<space/><italics>Forgotten Allies: The Oneida Indians and the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2007)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British provided arms to Indians, who were led by<space/><link><target>Loyalists</target></link><space/>in war parties to raid frontier settlements from the<space/><link><target>Province of Carolina</target><part>Carolinas</part></link><space/>to New York. They killed many settlers on the frontier, especially in Pennsylvania and New York's Mohawk Valley.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1776<space/><link><target>Cherokee</target></link><space/>war parties attacked American colonists all along the southern frontier of the uplands throughout the<space/><link><target>Washington District, North Carolina</target></link><space/>(now Tennessee) and the Kentucky wilderness area.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tom Hatley,<space/><italics>The Dividing Paths: Cherokees and South Carolinians through the Era of Revolution</italics><space/>(1993); James H. O'Donnell, III,<space/><italics>Southern Indians in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1973)</extension><space/>While the Cherokee launched raids numbering a couple hundred warriors, as seen in the<space/><link><target>CherokeeAmerican wars</target></link>, they could not mobilize enough forces to fight a major invasion of colonial areas without the help of allies, most often the<space/><link><target>Muscogee (Creek)</target><part>Creek</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Chickamauga Cherokee</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Dragging Canoe</target></link><space/>allied themselves closely with the British, and fought on for an additional decade after the signing of the Treaty of Paris.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Joseph Brant</target></link><space/>of the powerful<space/><link><target>Mohawk nation</target></link>, part of the Iroquois Confederacy based in New York, was the most prominent Native American leader against the rebel forces. In 1778 and 1780, he led 300 Iroquois warriors and 100 white Loyalists in multiple attacks on small frontier settlements in New York and Pennsylvania, killing many settlers and destroying villages, crops and stores.<extension extension_name='ref'>see Barbara Graymont, &quot;Thayendanegea&quot;,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.biographi.ca/EN/ShowBio.asp?BioId=36808&amp;amp;query=joseph%20AND%20brant'>''Dictionary of Canadian Biography Online''</link></extension><space/>The Seneca, Onondaga and Cayuga of the Iroquois Confederacy also allied with the British against the Americans.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Colin G. Calloway 1995">Colin G. Calloway,<space/><italics>The American Revolution in Indian Country: Crisis and Diversity in Native American Communities</italics><space/>(1995)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1779 the Continentals retaliated with an American army under<space/><link><target>John Sullivan (general)</target><part>John Sullivan</part></link>, which raided and destroyed 40 empty Iroquois villages in central and western New York.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Colin G. Calloway 1995"></extension><space/>Sullivan's forces systematically burned the villages and destroyed about 160,000 bushels of corn that comprised the winter food supply. Facing starvation and homeless for the winter, the Iroquois fled to the Niagara Falls area and to Canada, mostly to what became Ontario. The British resettled them there after the war, providing land grants as compensation for some of their losses.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joseph R. Fischer,<space/><italics>A Well-Executed Failure: The Sullivan Campaign against the Iroquois, JulySeptember 1779</italics><space/>(1997).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the peace conference following the war, the British ceded lands which they did not really control, and did not consult their Indian allies. They &quot;transferred&quot; control to the United States of all the land east of the Mississippi and north of Florida. The historian Calloway concludes:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Burned villages and crops, murdered chiefs, divided councils and civil wars, migrations, towns and forts choked with refugees, economic disruption, breaking of ancient traditions, losses in battle and to disease and hunger, betrayal to their enemies, all made the American Revolution one of the darkest periods in American Indian history.<ref>Calloway (1995) p. 290</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The British did not give up their forts in the West (what is now the eastern Midwest, stretching from Ohio to Wisconsin) until 1796; they kept alive the dream of forming a satellite Indian nation there, which they called a Neutral Indian Zone. That goal was one of the causes of the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Smith</arg><arg name="first">Dwight L.</arg><arg name="year">1989</arg><arg name="title">A North American Neutral Indian Zone: Persistence of a British Idea</arg><arg name="journal">Northwest Ohio Quarterly</arg><arg name="volume">61</arg><arg name="issue">2–4</arg><arg name="pages">46–63</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Francis M. Carroll,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=1AjlS20Q5J8C&amp;amp;pg=PA24'>''A Good and Wise Measure: The Search for the Canadian-American Boundary, 17831842''</link><space/>(2001) p. 23</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>African Americans</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>African Americans in the Revolutionary War</arg></template>Free blacks in the North and South fought on both sides of the Revolution, but<space/><link><target>Military history of African Americans#Revolutionary War</target><part>most fought for the patriots</part></link>. Gary Nash reports that recent research concludes there were about 9000 black Patriot soldiers, counting the Continental Army and Navy, and state militia units, as well as privateers, wagoneers in the Army, servants to officers, and spies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gary B. Nash, &quot;The African Americans Revolution,&quot; in<space/><italics>Oxford Handbook of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2012) edited by Edward G Gray and Jane Kamensky pp 250-70, at p 254</extension><space/>Ray Raphael notes that while thousands did join the Loyalist cause, &quot;A far larger number, free as well as slave, tried to further their interests by siding with the patriots.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Ray Raphael,<space/><italics>A People's History of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2001) p 281</extension><space/><link><target>Crispus Attucks</target></link>, who was shot dead by British soldiers in the<space/><link><target>Boston Massacre</target></link><space/>in 1770, is an iconic martyr to Patriots. Both sides offered freedom and re-settlement to slaves who were willing to fight for them, recruiting slaves whose owners supported the opposing cause.</paragraph><paragraph>Many African-American slaves sided with the Loyalists. Tens of thousands in the South used the turmoil of war to escape, and the southern plantation economies of South Carolina and Georgia especially were disrupted. During the Revolution, the British tried to turn slavery against the Americans.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Revolutionary War: The Home Front"><link type='external' href='http://memory.loc.gov/learn/features/timeline/amrev/homefrnt/homefrnt.html'>Revolutionary War: The Home Front</link>, Library of Congress</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historian<space/><link><target>David Brion Davis</target></link><space/>explains the difficulties with a policy of wholesale arming of the slaves:<template><target>quote</target><arg>But England greatly feared the effects of any such move on its own [[West Indies]], where Americans had already aroused alarm over a possible threat to incite slave [[insurrection]]s. The British elites also understood that an all-out attack on one form of property could easily lead to an assault on all boundaries of privilege and social order, as envisioned by radical religious sects in Britain's seventeenth-century civil wars.<ref>Davis p. 148</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Davis underscored the British dilemma: &quot;Britain, when confronted by the rebellious American colonists, hoped to exploit their fear of<space/><link><target>Slave rebellion</target><part>slave revolts</part></link><space/>while also reassuring the large number of slave-holding Loyalists and wealthy Caribbean planters and merchants that their slave property would be secure&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Davis p. 149</extension><space/>The colonists accused the British of encouraging slave revolts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schama pp. 2830 p.&amp;nbsp;7890</extension></paragraph><paragraph>American advocates of independence were commonly lampooned in Britain for what was termed their hypocritical calls for freedom, at the same time that many of their leaders were planters who held hundreds of slaves.<space/><link><target>Samuel Johnson</target></link><space/>snapped, &quot;how is it we hear the loudest yelps for liberty among the [slave] drivers of the Negroes?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanley Weintraub,<space/><italics>Iron Tears: America's Battle for Freedom, Britain's Quagmire, 17751783</italics><space/>(2005) p. 7</extension><space/>Benjamin Franklin countered by criticizing the British self-congratulation about &quot;the freeing of one Negro&quot; (<link><target>Somersett's Case</target><part>Somersett</part></link>) while they continued to permit the<space/><link><target>Slave Trade</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schama, p. 75</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Phyllis Wheatley</target></link>, a black poet who popularized the image of<space/><link><target>Columbia (name)</target><part>Columbia</part></link><space/>to represent America, came to public attention when her<space/><italics>Poems on Various Subjects, Religious and Moral</italics><space/>appeared in 1773.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hochschild p.50-51">Hochschild p.&amp;nbsp;5051</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the war, slaves escaped from across New England and the mid-Atlantic area to British-occupied cities, such as New York. The effects of the war were more dramatic in the South. In Virginia the royal governor Lord<space/><link><target>John Murray, 4th Earl of Dunmore</target><part>Dunmore</part></link><space/>recruited black men into the British forces with the promise of freedom, protection for their families, and land grants. Tens of thousands of slaves escaped to British lines throughout the South, causing dramatic losses to slaveholders and disrupting cultivation and harvesting of crops. For instance,<space/><link><target>South Carolina</target></link><space/>was estimated to lose about 25,000 slaves, or one third of its slave population, to flight, migration or death. From 1770 to 1790, the black proportion of the population (mostly slaves) in South Carolina dropped from 60.5 percent to 43.8 percent; and in<space/><link><target>Georgia (U.S. state)</target><part>Georgia</part></link><space/>from 45.2 percent to 36.1 percent.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Kolchin,<space/><italics>American Slavery: 16191877</italics>, New York: Hill and Wang, 1993, p. 73</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When the British evacuated its forces from<space/><link><target>Savannah, Georgia</target><part>Savannah</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Charleston, South Carolina</target><part>Charleston</part></link>, it also gave transportation to 10,000 slaves, carrying through on its commitment to them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kolchin,<space/><italics>American Slavery</italics>, p. 73</extension><space/>They evacuated and resettled more than 3,000 &quot;<link><target>Black Loyalist</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; from New York to<space/><link><target>Nova Scotia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Upper Canada</target><part>Upper</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lower Canada</target></link>. Others sailed with the British to England or were resettled as freedmen in the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link><space/>of the Caribbean. But slaves who were carried to the Caribbean under control of Loyalist masters generally remained slaves until British abolition in its colonies in 1834. More than 1200 of the Black Loyalists of Nova Scotia later resettled in the British colony of<space/><link><target>History of Sierra Leone</target><part>Sierra Leone</part></link>, where they became leaders of the<space/><link><target>Sierra Leone Creole people</target><part>Krio</part></link><space/>ethnic group of Freetown and the later national government. Many of their descendants still live in Sierra Leone, as well as other African countries.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hill (2007), see also<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.blackloyalist.com/'>blackloyalist.com</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Effects of the Revolution</heading><heading level='3'>Loyalist expatriation</heading><paragraph>About 60,000 to 70,000 Loyalists left the newly founded republic; some migrated to Britain. The remainder, known as<space/><link><target>United Empire Loyalists</target></link>, received land and subsidies for resettlement in British colonies in North America, especially<space/><link><target>Province of Quebec (1763-1791)</target><part>Quebec</part></link><space/>(concentrating in the<space/><link><target>Eastern Townships</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Prince Edward Island</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Nova Scotia</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>W. Stewart Wallace,<space/><italics>The United Empire Loyalists: A Chronicle of the Great Migration</italics><space/>(Toronto, 1914)<space/><link type='external' href='http://infomotions.com/etexts/gutenberg/dirs/1/1/9/7/11977/11977.htm'>online edition</link></extension><space/>The new colonies of Upper Canada (now<space/><link><target>Ontario</target></link>) and<space/><link><target>New Brunswick</target></link><space/>were expressly created by Britain for their benefit, where the Crown awarded land to Loyalists as compensation for losses in the United States. Britain wanted to develop the frontier of Upper Canada on a British colonial model. But about 80% of the Loyalists stayed in the United States and became full, loyal citizens; some of the exiles later returned to the U.S.<extension extension_name='ref'>Van Tine,<space/><italics>American Loyalists</italics><space/>(1902) p 307</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Interpretations</heading><paragraph>Interpretations about the effect of the Revolution vary. Contemporary participants referred to the events as &quot;the revolution&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>David McCullough,<space/><italics>John Adams</italics><space/>(2001)</extension><space/>Greene argues that the events were not &quot;revolutionary&quot;, as the relationships and property rights of colonial society were not transformed: a distant government was simply replaced with a local one; the Revolution is still sometimes known outside the United States as the American War of Independence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene,<space/><italics>The American Revolution</italics><space/>(2000) pp. 93102</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historians such as<space/><link><target>Bernard Bailyn</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gordon S. Wood</target><part>Gordon Wood</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Edmund Morgan (historian)</target><part>Edmund Morgan</part></link><space/>accept the contemporary view of the participants that the American Revolution was a unique and radical event that produced deep changes and had a profound effect on world affairs, based on an increasing belief in the principles of the Enlightenment, as reflected in how liberalism was understood during the period, and republicanism. These were demonstrated by a leadership and government that espoused protection of natural rights, and a system of laws chosen by the people.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wood,<space/><italics>The American Revolution: A History</italics><space/>(2003)</extension><space/>However, what was then considered &quot;the people&quot; was still mostly restricted to free white males who were able to pass a property-qualification.<extension extension_name='ref' name="U.S. Voting Rights"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.infoplease.com/timelines/voting.html</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Voting Rights</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 July 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Such a restriction made a significant gain of the revolution in the short term irrelevant to women, African Americans and slaves, poor white men, youth, and Native Americans.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.history.org/foundation/journal/spring07/elections.cfm</arg><arg name="title">Voting in Early America</arg><arg name="last">Crews</arg><arg name="first">Ed</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 July 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>McCool, Daniel, Susan M. Olson, and Jennifer L. Robinson.<space/><italics>Native Vote,</italics><space/>Cambridge, England: Cambridge University Press, 2007.</extension><space/>Only with the development of the American system over the following centuries would &quot;a government by the people&quot;, promised by the revolution, be won for a greater proportion of the population.<extension extension_name='ref' name="U.S. Voting Rights"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Morgan has argued that in terms of long-term impact on American society and values:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>The Revolution did revolutionize social relations. It did displace the deference, the patronage, the social divisions that had determined the way people viewed one another for centuries and still view one another in much of the world. It did give to ordinary people a pride and power, not to say an arrogance, that have continued to shock visitors from less favored lands. It may have left standing a host of inequalities that have troubled us ever since. But it generated the egalitarian view of human society that makes them troubling and makes our world so different from the own in which the revolutionists had grown up.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Edmund S. Morgan</arg><arg name="title">The Genuine Article: A Historian Looks at Early America</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">W. W. Norton</arg><arg name="page">246</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Inspiring all colonies</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Atlantic Revolutions</arg></template>After the Revolution, genuinely democratic politics became possible in the former colonies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon Wood,<space/><italics>The Radicalism of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1992) pp. 2789</extension><space/>The rights of the people were incorporated into state constitutions. Concepts of liberty, individual rights, equality among men and hostility toward corruption became incorporated as core values of liberal republicanism. The greatest challenge to the old order in Europe was the challenge to inherited political power and the democratic idea that government rests on the<space/><link><target>consent of the governed</target></link>. The example of the first successful revolution against a European empire, and the first successful establishment of a republican form of democratically elected government, provided a model for many other colonial peoples who realized that they too could break away and become self-governing nations with directly elected representative government.<extension extension_name='ref'>Palmer, (1959)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Dutch Republic, also at war with Britain, was the next country to sign a treaty with the United States, on October 8, 1782.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hamilton, 1974 p. 28"></extension><space/>On April 3, 1783, Ambassador Extraordinary<space/><link><target>Gustaf Philip Creutz</target></link>, representing King<space/><link><target>Gustav III of Sweden</target></link>, and Benjamin Franklin, signed a<space/><link><target>Treaty of Amity and Commerce (USASweden)</target><part>Treaty of Amity and Commerce</part></link><space/>with the U.S.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hamilton, 1974 p. 28"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The American Revolution was the first wave of the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Revolutions</target></link>: the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Haitian Revolution</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Latin American wars of independence</target></link>. Aftershocks reached Ireland in the<space/><link><target>Irish Rebellion of 1798</target></link>, in the<space/><link><target>Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth</target></link>, and in the Netherlands.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole (1994) ch 5355</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wim Klooster,<space/><italics>Revolutions in the Atlantic World: A Comparative History</italics><space/>(2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Revolution had a strong, immediate influence in Great Britain, Ireland, the Netherlands, and France. Many British and Irish<space/><link><target>British Whig Party</target><part>Whigs</part></link><space/>spoke in favor of the American cause. In Ireland, there was a profound impact; the Protestants who controlled Ireland were demanding more and more self-rule. Under the leadership of<space/><link><target>Henry Grattan</target></link>, the so-called &quot;<link><target>Irish Patriot Party#Grattan's Patriots</target><part>Patriots</part></link>&quot; forced the reversal of mercantilist prohibitions against trade with other British colonies. The King and his cabinet in London could not risk another rebellion on the American model, and made a series of concessions to the Patriot faction in Dublin. Armed Protestant volunteer units were set up to protect against an invasion from France. As in America, so too in Ireland the King no longer had a monopoly of lethal force.<extension extension_name='ref'>R. B. McDowell,<space/><italics>Ireland in the age of imperialism and revolution, 17601801</italics><space/>(1979)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Revolution, along with the<space/><link><target>Dutch Revolt</target></link><space/>(end of the 16th century) and the 17th century<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link>, was among the examples of overthrowing an old regime for many Europeans who later were active during the era of the French Revolution, such as<space/><link><target>Marquis de Lafayette</target></link>. The American Declaration of Independence influenced the French<space/><link><target>Declaration of the Rights of Man and the Citizen</target></link><space/>of 1789.<extension extension_name='ref'>Palmer, (1959); Greene and Pole (1994) chapters 4952</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Center for History and New Media,<space/><italics>Liberty, equality, fraternity</italics><space/>(2010)</extension>The spirit of the Declaration of Independence led to laws ending slavery in all the Northern states and the Northwest Territory, with New Jersey the last in 1804long before the British Parliament acted in 1833 to abolish slavery in its colonies. States such as New Jersey and New York adopted gradual emancipation, which kept some people as slaves for more than two decades longer.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greene and Pole p. 409, 45354</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Status of American women</heading><paragraph>The democratic ideals of the Revolution inspired changes in the roles of women.<extension extension_name='ref'>Linda K. Kerber, et al. &quot;Beyond Roles, Beyond Spheres: Thinking about Gender in the Early Republic,&quot;<space/><italics>William and Mary Quarterly,</italics><space/>(1989), 46#3 56585<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1922356'>in JSTOR</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The concept of<space/><link><target>republican motherhood</target></link><space/>was inspired by this period and reflects the importance of<space/><link><target>revolutionary republicanism</target><part>Republicanism as the dominant American ideology</part></link>. It assumed that a successful republic rested upon the virtue of its citizens. Women were considered to have the essential role of instilling their children with values conducive to a healthy republic. During this period, the wife's relationship with her husband also became more liberal, as love and affection instead of obedience and subservience began to characterize the ideal marital relationship. In addition, many women contributed to the war effort through fundraising and running family businesses in the absence of husbands.</paragraph><paragraph>The traditional constraints gave way to more liberal conditions for women. Patriarchy faded as an ideal; young people had more freedom to choose their spouses and more often used birth control to regulate the size of their families. Society emphasized the role of mothers in child rearing, especially the patriotic goal of raising republican children rather than those locked into aristocratic value systems. There was more permissiveness in child-rearing. Patriot women married to Loyalists who left the state could get a divorce and obtain control of the ex-husband's property.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mary Beth Norton,<space/><italics>Liberty's Daughters: The Revolutionary Experience of American Women, 17501800</italics><space/>(3rd ed. 1996)</extension>Whatever gains they had made, however, women still found themselves subordinated, legally and socially, to their husbands, disfranchised and usually with only the role of mother open to them. But, some women earned livelihoods as midwives and in other roles in the community, which were not originally recognized as significant by men.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Abigail Adams</target></link><space/>expressed to her husband, the president, the desire of women to have a place in the new republic:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="I desire you would remember the Ladies, and be more generous and favourable to them than your ancestors. Do not put such unlimited power into the hands of the Husbands.<ref>{{cite book|author">Woody Holton|title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Zagarri in 2007 argued that the American Revolution created a continuing debate on the rights of woman and an environment favorable to women's participation in U.S. politics. She asserts that for a brief decade, a &quot;comprehensive transformation in women's rights, roles, and responsibilities seemed not only possible but perhaps inevitable.&quot; But, the changes also engendered a backlash that set back the cause of women's rights and led to a greater rigidity that marginalized women from political life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rosemarie Zagarri,<space/><italics>Revolutionary Backlash: Women and Politics in the Early American Republic</italics><space/>(2007). quote p 8</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Status of African Americans</heading><paragraph>In the first two decades after the American Revolution, state legislatures and individuals took actions to free numerous slaves, in part based on revolutionary ideals. Northern states passed new constitutions that contained language about equal rights or specifically abolished slavery; some states, such as New York and New Jersey, where slavery was more widespread, passed laws by the end of the 18th century to abolish slavery by a gradual method; in New York, the last slaves were freed in 1827.</paragraph><paragraph>While no southern state abolished slavery, for a period individual owners could free their slaves by personal decision, often providing for manumission in wills but sometimes filing deeds or court papers to free individuals. Numerous slaveholders who freed their slaves cited revolutionary ideals in their documents; others freed slaves as a reward for service. Records also suggest that some slaveholders were freeing their own<space/><link><target>mixed-race</target></link><space/>children, born into slavery to slave mothers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Memory</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>United States Bicentennial</arg></template><link><target>File:American revolution bicentennial.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part></link><link><target>File:Colonial Williamsburg Governors Palace Front Dscn7232.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Governor's Palace,<space/><link><target>Colonial Williamsburg</target></link>, a restored colonial city, Williamburg, Virginia</part></link>The American Revolution has a central place in the American memory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Kammen,<space/><italics>A Season of Youth: The American Revolution and the Historical Imagination</italics><space/>(1978); Kammen,<space/><italics>Mystic Chords of Memory: The Transformation of Tradition in American Culture</italics><space/>(1991)</extension><space/>As the founding story, it is covered in the schools, memorialized by a national holiday, and commemorated in innumerable monuments. Thus<space/><link><target>Independence Day (United States)</target><part>Independence Day</part></link><space/>(the &quot;Fourth of July&quot;) is a major national holiday celebrated annually. Besides local sites such as Bunker Hill, one of the first national pilgrimages for memorial tourists was<space/><link><target>Mount Vernon</target></link>, George Washington's estate (near<space/><link><target>Washington, D.C.</target><part>Washington City</part></link>), which attracted ten thousand visitors a year by the 1850s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jean B. Lee, &quot;Historical Memory, Sectional Strife, and the American Mecca: Mount Vernon, 1783-1853,&quot;<space/><italics>Virginia Magazine of History and Biography</italics><space/>(2001) 109#3 pp. 255-300<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/4249931'>in JSTOR</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Crider points out that in the 1850s, editors and orators both North and South claimed their region was the true custodian of the legacy of 1776, as they used the Revolution symbolically in their rhetoric.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jonathan B. Crider, &quot;De Bow's Revolution: The Memory of the American Revolution in the Politics of the Sectional Crisis, 1850-1861,&quot;<space/><italics>American Nineteenth Century History</italics><space/>(2009) 10#3 pp 317332</extension><space/>Ryan, noting that the Bicentennial was celebrated a year after the United States' humiliating 1975 withdrawal from Vietnam, says the Ford administration stressed the themes of renewal and rebirth based on a restoration of traditional values, and presented a nostalgic approach to 1776 that made it seem eternally young and fresh.<extension extension_name='ref'>David Ryan, &quot;Re-enacting Independence through Nostalgia - The 1976 US Bicentennial after the Vietnam War,&quot;<space/><italics>Forum for Inter-American Research</italics><space/>(2012) 5#3 pp 2648.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Albanese argues that the Revolution became the main source of the non-denominational &quot;<link><target>American civil religion</target></link>&quot; that has shaped patriotism, and the memory and meaning of the nation's birth ever since.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Catherine L. Albanese 1977">Catherine L. Albanese,<space/><italics>Sons of the Fathers: The Civil Religion of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1977)</extension><space/>She says that specific battles are not central (as they are for the Civil War) but rather certain events and people have been celebrated as icons of certain virtues (or vices). Thus she points out the Revolution produced a<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link>-like leader (George Washington),<extension extension_name='ref'>Robert P. Hay, &quot;George Washington: American Moses,&quot;<space/><italics>American Quarterly</italics><space/>(1969) 21#4 pp 780-91<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2711609'>in JSTOR</link></extension><space/>prophets (Thomas Jefferson, Tom Paine), disciples (Alexander Hamilton, James Madison) and martyrs (Boston Massacre, Nathan Hale), as well as devils (Benedict Arnold), sacred places (Valley Forge, Bunker Hill), rituals (Boston Tea Party), emblems (the new flag), sacred holidays (Independence Day), and a holy scripture whose every sentence is carefully studied and applied in current law cases (The Declaration of Independence, the Constitution and the Bill of Rights).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Catherine L. Albanese 1977"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bibliography of the American Revolutionary War</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of the American Revolution</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Diplomacy in the American Revolutionary War</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Founding Fathers of the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of plays and films about the American Revolution</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bailyn, Bernard</arg><arg name="authorlink">Bernard Bailyn</arg><arg name="title">The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="publisher">Belknap Press of Harvard University Press</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, Massachusetts</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-674-44302-0</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Becker, Carl</arg><arg name="authorlink">Carl L. Becker</arg><arg name="title">The Declaration of Independence: a Study in the History of Political Ideas</arg><arg name="publisher">Harcourt, Brace and Company</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1922</arg><arg name="url">http://files.libertyfund.org/files/1177/0034_Bk.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="isbn">0-394-70060-0</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20101012230827/http://files.libertyfund.org/files/1177/0034_Bk.pdf</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>12 October 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Berkin, Carol</arg><arg name="title">Revolutionary Mothers: Women in the Struggle for America's Independence</arg><arg name="publisher">Vintage Books</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4000-7532-4</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Revolutionary-Mothers-Struggle-Americas-Independence/dp/1400075327</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-03</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Boorstin</arg><arg name="first">Daniel J.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Daniel J. Boorstin</arg><arg name="title">The Genius of American Politics</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Chicago Press</arg><arg name="location">Chicago</arg><arg name="year">1953</arg><arg name="isbn">0-226-06491-3</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-03</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Brinkley, Douglas</arg><arg name="authorlink">Douglas Brinkley</arg><arg name="title">The Sparck of Rebellion</arg><arg name="journal">American Heritage Magazine</arg><arg name="volume">59</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="issn">0002-8738</arg><arg name="url">http://staging.americanheritage.com/articles/magazine/ah/2010/4/2010_4_33_print.shtml</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Burrows</arg><arg name="first">Edwin G.</arg><arg name="last2">Wallace</arg><arg name="first2">Michael</arg><arg name="authorlink">Edwin G. Burrows</arg><arg name="authorlink2">Mike Wallace (historian)</arg><arg name="title">The American Revolution: The Ideology and Psychology of National Liberation</arg><arg name="journal">Perspectives in American History</arg><arg name="volume">6</arg><arg name="pages">167–305</arg><arg name="year">1972</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Calhoon</arg><arg name="first">Robert M.</arg><arg name="editor-last">Greene</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jack P.</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Pole</arg><arg name="editor2-first">J.R.</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Encyclopedia of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="chapter">Loyalism and Neutrality</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons, Limited</arg><arg name="location">Hoboken, New Jersey</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-55786-244-0</arg><arg name="oclc">94003190</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Blackwell-Encyclopedia-American-Revolution-Greene/dp/1557862443</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20101103043546/http://www.amazon.com/Blackwell-Encyclopedia-American-Revolution-Greene/dp/1557862443</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>3 November 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="first">Nicholas</arg><arg name="last">Canny</arg><arg name="title">The Origins of Empire, The Oxford History of the British Empire Volume I</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-924676-9</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="ref">refOHBEv1</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 July 2009</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Center for History and New Media</arg><arg name="title">Liberty, equality, fraternity: exploring the French Revolution. Chapter 3: Enlightenment and human rights</arg><arg name="publisher">George Mason University</arg><arg name="location">Fairfax, Virginia</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="url">http://chnm.gmu.edu/revolution/chap3a.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-11</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20101115151015/http://chnm.gmu.edu/revolution/chap3a.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>15 November 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Chisick</arg><arg name="first">Harvey</arg><arg name="title">Historical Dictionary of the Enlightenment</arg><arg name="pages">313–4</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8108-5097-2</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-last">Crow</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jeffrey J.</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Tise</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Larry E.</arg><arg name="title">The Southern Experience in the American Revolution</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="publisher">The University of North Carolina Press</arg><arg name="location">Chapel Hill, North Carolina</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8078-1313-3</arg><arg name="url">http://www.questia.com/read/104464395</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Ferguson, Robert A.</arg><arg name="title">The Commonalities of Common Sense</arg><arg name="journal">The William and Mary Quarterly</arg><arg name="volume">57</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">465–504</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="issn">0043-5597</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2674263</arg><arg name="jstor">2674263</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Fifth Virginia Convention</arg><arg name="authorlink">Virginia Conventions</arg><arg name="title">Preamble and Resolution of the Virginia Convention, May 15, 1776</arg><arg name="publisher">Lillian Goldman Law Library</arg><arg name="location">New Haven, CT</arg><arg name="year">1776</arg><arg name="url">http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/const02.asp</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20100906044910/http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/const02.asp</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>6 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-last">Greene</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jack P.</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Pole</arg><arg name="editor2-first">J.R.</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Encyclopedia of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons, Limited</arg><arg name="location">Hoboken, New Jersey</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-55786-244-0</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Blackwell-Encyclopedia-American-Revolution-Greene/dp/1557862443</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20101103043546/http://www.amazon.com/Blackwell-Encyclopedia-American-Revolution-Greene/dp/1557862443</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>3 November 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-last">Greene</arg><arg name="editor-first">Jack P.</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Pole</arg><arg name="editor2-first">J.R.</arg><arg name="title">A Companion to the American Revolution</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley and Sons, Limited</arg><arg name="location">Hoboken, New Jersey</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4051-1674-9</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.2307/2652437</arg><arg name="last">Greene</arg><arg name="first">Jack P.</arg><arg name="title">The American Revolution</arg><arg name="journal">The American Historical Review</arg><arg name="volume">105</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">93–102</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="issn">1937-5239</arg><arg name="url">http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/105.1/ah000093.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="jstor">2652437</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Griffin</arg><arg name="first">Martin Ignatius Joseph</arg><arg name="title">Commodore John Barry: "the father of the American navy"</arg><arg name="year">1903</arg><arg name="publisher">self-published</arg><arg name="location">Philadelphia</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-04</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hamilton</arg><arg name="first">Alexander</arg><arg name="authorlink">Alexander Hamilton</arg><arg name="editor-last">Syrett</arg><arg name="editor-first">Harold C.</arg><arg name="title">The Papers of Alexander Hamilton</arg><arg name="volume">XX</arg><arg name="year">1974</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-231-08919-8</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-04</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Higginbotham</arg><arg name="first">Don</arg><arg name="authorlink">Don Higginbotham</arg><arg name="title">The War of American Independence: Military Attitudes, Policies, and Practice, 1763–1789</arg><arg name="year">1983</arg><arg name="publisher">Northeastern University Press</arg><arg name="location">Boston</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-02-551460-7</arg><arg name="url">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hull</arg><arg name="first">N.E.H.</arg><arg name="last2">Hoffer</arg><arg name="first2">Peter C.</arg><arg name="last3">Allen</arg><arg name="first3">Steven L.</arg><arg name="title">Choosing Sides: A Quantitative Study of the Personality Determinants of Loyalist and Revolutionary Political Affiliation in New York</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of American History</arg><arg name="volume">65</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">344–66</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="issn">0021-8723</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/1894084</arg><arg name="jstor">1894084</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jensen, Merrill</arg><arg name="authorlink">Merrill Jensen</arg><arg name="title">The Founding of a Nation: a History of the American Revolution, 1763–1776</arg><arg name="publisher">Hackett Publishing Company</arg><arg name="location">Indianapolis, Indiana</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">0-87220-706-4</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jensen, Merrill</arg><arg name="title">The New Nation: a History of the United States during the Confederation, 1781–1789</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House Inc.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1950</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-394-70527-9</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/New-Nation-History-Confederation-1781-1789/dp/0394705270</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kerber</arg><arg name="first">Linda K.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Linda K. Kerber</arg><arg name="title">Women of the Republic: Intellect and Ideology in Revolutionary America</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">The University of North Carolina Press</arg><arg name="location">Chapel Hill, North Carolina</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8078-4632-2</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Women-Republic-Intellect-Revolutionary-Institute/dp/0807846325</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Klos</arg><arg name="first">Stanley L.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Stanley L. Klos</arg><arg name="title">President Who? Forgotten Founders</arg><arg name="publisher">Evisum, Inc.</arg><arg name="location">Pittsburgh</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-9752627-5-7</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Labaree</arg><arg name="first">Leonard Woods</arg><arg name="authorlink">Leonard Woods Labaree</arg><arg name="title">Conservatism in Early American History (Anson G. Phelps lectureship on early American history)</arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell University Press</arg><arg name="location">Ithaca, New York</arg><arg name="year">1948</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Conservatism-American-history-Phelps-lectureship/dp/B0007EHCJ6</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Lee, Richard Henry</arg><arg name="authorlink">Richard Henry Lee</arg><arg name="title">Lee's Resolutions</arg><arg name="publisher">Lillian Goldman Law Library</arg><arg name="location">New Haven, CT</arg><arg name="year">1776</arg><arg name="url">http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/lee.asp</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20100906041406/http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/lee.asp</arg><arg name="archivedate">6 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mackesy</arg><arg name="first">Piers</arg><arg name="authorlink">Piers Mackesy</arg><arg name="title">The War for America: 1775–1783</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Nebraska Press</arg><arg name="location">Lincoln, Nebraska</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8032-8192-9</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/booksid</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Maier, Pauline</arg><arg name="authorlink">Pauline Maier</arg><arg name="title">American Scripture: Making the Declaration of Independence</arg><arg name="publisher">Alfred A. Knopf</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-679-45492-2</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Maier, Pauline</arg><arg name="title">From Resistance to Revolution: Colonial Radicals and the Development of American Opposition to Britain, 1765–1776</arg><arg name="publisher">W.W. Norton and Company, Inc.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-393-30825-9</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Shalhope, Robert E.</arg><arg name="title">Toward a Republican Synthesis</arg><arg name="journal">The William and Mary Quarterly</arg><arg name="volume">29</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">49–80</arg><arg name="year">1972</arg><arg name="issn">0043-5597</arg><arg name="url">http://www.littlejohnexplorers.com/republicanism/shalhope_1.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/1921327</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Shy, John</arg><arg name="title">Toward Lexington: The Role of the British Army in the Coming of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton University Press</arg><arg name="location">Princeton, New Jersey</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-59740-414-3</arg><arg name="url">http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Stephens</arg><arg name="first">Otis H.</arg><arg name="last2">Glenn</arg><arg name="first2">Richard A.</arg><arg name="title">Unreasonable Searches and Seizures: Rights and Liberties under the Law</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="location">Santa Barbara, California</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-85109-503-2</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-07</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Warren, Charles</arg><arg name="authorlink">Charles Warren (U.S. author)</arg><arg name="title">Fourth of July Myths</arg><arg name="journal">The William and Mary Quarterly</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">237–272</arg><arg name="year">1945</arg><arg name="issn">0043-5597</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/1921451</arg><arg name="jstor">1921451</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Wood, Gordon S.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Gordon S. Wood</arg><arg name="title">Rhetoric and Reality in the American Revolution</arg><arg name="journal">The William and Mary Quarterly</arg><arg name="volume">23</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">3–32</arg><arg name="year">1966</arg><arg name="issn">0043-5597</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2936154</arg><arg name="jstor">2936154</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wood</arg><arg name="first">Gordon S.</arg><arg name="title">The Radicalism of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="publisher">Vintage Books</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-679-73688-2</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Radicalism-American-Revolution-Gordon-Wood/dp/0679736883</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-04</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20100925060129/http://www.amazon.com/Radicalism-American-Revolution-Gordon-Wood/dp/0679736883</arg><arg name="archivedate">25 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wood</arg><arg name="first">Gordon S.</arg><arg name="title">The American Revolution: A History</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Modern Library</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8129-7041-8</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-02</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wraight</arg><arg name="first">Christopher D.</arg><arg name="title">Rousseau's The Social Contract: A Reader's Guide</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">Continuum Books</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8264-9860-1</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-10-04</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><heading level='3'>Reference works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Barnes, Ian, and<space/><link><target>Charles Royster</target></link>.<space/><italics>The Historical Atlas of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2000), maps and commentary<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0415922437/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Blanco</arg><arg name="first1">Richard L.</arg><arg name="last2">Sanborn</arg><arg name="first2">Paul J.</arg><arg name="title">The American Revolution, 1775–1783: An Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="publisher">Garland Publishing Inc.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8240-5623-0</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/American-Revolution-1775-1783-Encyclopedia-Humanities/dp/082405623X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Boatner</arg><arg name="first">Mark Mayo III</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of the American Revolution</arg><arg name="edition">2</arg><arg name="publisher">Charles Scribners and Sons</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1974</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-684-31513-3</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Encyclopedia-American-Revolution-Library-Military/dp/0684315130</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Cappon, Lester J.<space/><italics>Atlas of Early American History: The Revolutionary Era, 17601790</italics><space/>(1976)</listitem><listitem>Fremont-Barnes, Gregory, and Richard A. Ryerson, eds.<space/><italics>The Encyclopedia of the American Revolutionary War: A Political, Social, and Military History</italics><space/>(5 vol. 2006) 1000 entries by 150 experts, covering all topics</listitem><listitem>Gray, Edward G., and Jane Kamensky, eds.<space/><italics>The Oxford Handbook of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2013) 672 pp; 33 essays by scholars</listitem><listitem>Greene, Jack P. and J. R. Pole, eds.<space/><italics>A Companion to the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2004), 777pp an expanded edition of Greene and Pole, eds.<space/><italics>The Blackwell Encyclopedia of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1994); comprehensive coverage of political and social themes and international dimension; thin on military</listitem><listitem>Kennedy, Frances H.<space/><italics>The American Revolution: A Historical Guidebook</italics><space/>(2014) A guide to 150 famous historical sites.</listitem><listitem>Purcell, L. Edward.<space/><italics>Who Was Who in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1993); 1500 short biographies</listitem><listitem>Resch, John P., ed.<space/><italics>Americans at War: Society, Culture and the Homefront</italics><space/>vol 1 (2005), articles by scholars</listitem><listitem>Symonds, Craig L. and William J. Clipson.<space/><italics>A Battlefield Atlas of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1986) new diagrams of each battle</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Surveys of the era</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Allison, Robert.<space/><italics>The American Revolution: A Concise History</italics><space/>(2011) 128pp<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0195312953/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Axelrod, Alan.<space/><italics>The Real History of the American Revolution: A New Look at the Past</italics><space/>(2009), well-illustrated popular history</listitem><listitem><link><target>George Bancroft</target><part>Bancroft, George</part></link>.<space/><italics>History of the United States of America, from the discovery of the American continent.</italics><space/>(185478), vol 410<space/><link type='external' href='http://jrshelby.com/sc-links/bancroft.htm'>online edition</link>, classic 19th century narrative; highly detailed</listitem><listitem>Black, Jeremy.<space/><italics>War for America: The Fight for Independence 17751783</italics><space/>(2001) 266pp; by leading British scholar</listitem><listitem>Brown, Richard D., and Thomas Paterson, eds.<space/><italics>Major Problems in the Era of the American Revolution, 17601791: Documents and Essays</italics><space/>(2nd ed. 1999)</listitem><listitem>Christie, Ian R. and Benjamin W. Labaree.<space/><italics>Empire or Independence: 1760-1776</italics><space/>(1976)</listitem><listitem>Cogliano, Francis D.<space/><italics>Revolutionary America, 17631815; A Political History</italics><space/>(2nd ed. 2008), British textbook</listitem><listitem><link><target>Joseph J. Ellis</target><part>Ellis, Joseph J.</part></link><space/><italics>American Creation: Triumphs and Tragedies in the Founding of the Republic</italics><space/>(2008)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0307276457/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Don Higginbotham</target><part>Higginbotham, Don</part></link>.<space/><italics>The War of American Independence: Military Attitudes, Policies, and Practice, 17631789</italics><space/>(1983)<space/><link type='external' href='http://quod.lib.umich.edu/cgi/t/text/text-idx?c=acls;cc=acls;q1=don;q2=ACLS%20Humanities%20E-Book;op2=and;rgn=works;rgn1=author;rgn2=series;view=toc;idno=heb01365.0001.001'>Online in ACLS Humanities E-book Project</link>; comprehensive coverage of military and domestic aspects of the war.</listitem><listitem>Jensen, Merrill.<space/><italics>The Founding of a Nation: A History of the American Revolution 17631776.</italics><space/>(2004)</listitem><listitem>Knollenberg, Bernhard.<space/><italics>Growth of the American Revolution: 17661775</italics><space/>(2003)</listitem><listitem>Lecky, William Edward Hartpole.<space/><italics>The American Revolution, 17631783</italics><space/>(1898), older British perspective<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=Rb6RAAAAIAAJ'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Mackesy, Piers.<space/><italics>The War for America: 17751783</italics><space/>(1992), British military study<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=55002630'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Middlekauff</target><part>Middlekauff, Robert</part></link>.<space/><italics><space/>The Glorious Cause: The American Revolution, 17631789</italics><space/>(Oxford History of the United States, 2005).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=84633736'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Miller, John C.<space/><italics>Triumph of Freedom, 17751783</italics><space/>(1948)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=14559136'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Miller, John C.<space/><italics>Origins of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1943)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=493014'>online edition</link>, to 1775</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jack Rakove</target><part>Rakove, Jack N.</part></link><space/><italics>Revolutionaries: A New History of the Invention of America</italics><space/>(2010) interpretation by leading scholar<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0618267468/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stanley Weintraub</target><part>Weintraub, Stanley</part></link>.<space/><italics>Iron Tears: Rebellion in America 177583</italics><space/>(2005)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0743226879/'>excerpt and text search</link>, popular</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gordon S. Wood</target><part>Wood, Gordon S.</part></link><space/><italics>Revolutionary Characters: What Made the Founders Different</italics><space/>(2007)</listitem><listitem>Wrong, George M.<space/><italics>Washington and His Comrades in Arms: A Chronicle of the War of Independence</italics><space/>(1921) online short survey by Canadian scholar<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historycarper.com/resources/wahcia/contents.htm'>online</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Specialized studies</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bailyn, Bernard.<space/><italics>The Ideological Origins of the American Revolution.</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press, 1967). ISBN 0-674-44301-2</listitem><listitem>Becker, Carl.<space/><italics>The Declaration of Independence: A Study on the History of Political Ideas</italics><space/>(1922)<link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/Home3/Book.php?recordID=0034'>online edition</link>, famous classic</listitem><listitem>Becker, Frank:<space/><link type='external' href='http://nbn-resolving.de/urn:nbn:de:0159-2011081848'>The American Revolution as a European Media Event</link>,<space/><link><target>European History Online</target></link>, Mainz:<space/><link><target>Institute of European History</target></link>, 2011, retrieved: October 25, 2011.</listitem><listitem>Berkin, Carol.<italics>Revolutionary Mothers: Women in the Struggle for America's Independence</italics><space/>(2006)</listitem><listitem>Bonomi, Patricia U.,<space/><italics>Under the Cope of Heaven: Religion, Society, and Politics in Colonial America</italics><space/>(2003)</listitem><listitem>Breen, T. H.<space/><italics>The Marketplace of Revolution: How Consumer Politics Shaped American Independence</italics><space/>(2005)</listitem><listitem>Breen, T. H.<space/><italics>American Insurgents, American Patriots: The Revolution of the People</italics><space/>(2010) 337 pages; examines rebellions in 177476 including loosely organized militants took control before elected safety committees emerged.</listitem><listitem>Brunsman, Denver, and David J Silverman, eds.<space/><italics>The American Revolution Reader</italics><space/>(Routledge Readers in History, 2013) 472pp; essays by leading scholars</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ron Chernow</target><part>Chernow, Ron</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Washington: A Life</target></link></italics><space/>(2010) detailed biography; Pulitzer Prize</listitem><listitem>Crow, Jeffrey J. and Larry E. Tise, eds.<space/><italics>The Southern Experience in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1978)</listitem><listitem><link><target>David Hackett Fischer</target><part>Fischer, David Hackett</part></link>.<space/><italics>Paul Revere's Ride</italics><space/>(1995), Minutemen in 1775</listitem><listitem>Fischer, David Hackett.<space/><italics>Washington's Crossing</italics><space/>(2004). 1776 campaigns; Pulitzer prize. ISBN 0-19-517034-2</listitem><listitem><link><target>Douglas Southall Freeman</target><part>Freeman, Douglas Southall</part></link>.<space/><italics>Washington</italics><space/>(1968) Pulitzer Prize; abridged version of 7 vol biography</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gerald Horne</target><part>Horne, Gerald</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Counter-Revolution of 1776: Slave Resistance and the Origins of the United States of America.</italics><space/>(<link><target>New York University Press</target></link>, 2014). ISBN 1479893404</listitem><listitem>Kerber, Linda K.<space/><italics>Women of the Republic: Intellect and Ideology in Revolutionary America</italics><space/>(1979)</listitem><listitem>Kidd, Thomas S.<space/><italics>God of Liberty: A Religious History of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2010)</listitem><listitem><link><target>David McCullough</target><part>McCullough, David</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>1776 (book)</target><part>1776</part></link></italics><space/>(2005). ISBN 0-7432-2671-2; popular narrative of the year 1776</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pauline Maier</target><part>Maier, Pauline</part></link>.<space/><italics>American Scripture: Making the Declaration of Independence</italics><space/>(1998)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0679779086/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Nash, Gary B.<space/><italics>The Unknown American Revolution: The Unruly Birth of Democracy and the Struggle to Create America</italics>. (2005). ISBN 0-670-03420-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Allan Nevins</target><part>Nevins, Allan</part></link>;<space/><italics>The American States during and after the Revolution, 17751789</italics><space/>1927.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=82373566'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Norton, Mary Beth.<space/><italics>Liberty's Daughters: The Revolutionary Experience of American Women, 17501800</italics><space/>(1980)</listitem><listitem>O'Shaughnessy Andrew Jackson.<space/><italics>The Men Who Lost America: British Leadership, the American Revolution, and the Fate of the Empire</italics><space/>(Yale University Press; 2013) 466 pages; on top British leaders</listitem><listitem>Palmer, Robert R.<space/><italics>The Age of the Democratic Revolution: A Political History of Europe and America, 17601800.</italics><space/>vol 1 (1959)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=22790906'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Resch, John Phillips and Walter Sargent, eds.<space/><italics>War and Society in the American Revolution: Mobilization and Home Fronts</italics><space/>(2006)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Murray Rothbard</target><part>Rothbard, Murray</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Conceived in Liberty</target></link></italics><space/>(2000),<space/><italics>Volume III: Advance to Revolution, 17601775</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Volume IV: The Revolutionary War, 17751784</italics>. ISBN 0-945466-26-9,<space/><link><target>Libertarianism</target><part>libertarian</part></link><space/>perspective</listitem><listitem>Van Tyne, Claude Halstead.<space/><italics>American Loyalists: The Loyalists in the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1902)<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=mNtEAAAAIAAJ'>online edition</link></listitem><listitem>Volo, James M. and Dorothy Denneen Volo.<space/><italics>Daily Life during the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2003)</listitem><listitem>Wahlke, John C. ed.<space/><italics>The Causes of the American Revolution</italics><space/>(1967) readings</listitem><listitem>Wood, Gordon S.<space/><italics>American Revolution</italics><space/>(2005) [excerpt and text search] 208pp<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0753818078/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Wood, Gordon S.<space/><italics>The Radicalism of the American Revolution: How a Revolution Transformed a Monarchical Society into a Democratic One Unlike Any That Had Ever Existed</italics>. (1992), by a leading scholar</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Historiography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Breen, Timothy H. &quot;Ideology and nationalism on the eve of the American Revolution: Revisions once more in need of revising.&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of American History</italics><space/>(1997): 13-39.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2952733'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Schocket, Andrew M.<space/><italics>Fighting over the Founders: How We Remember the American Revolution</italics><space/>(2014), how politicians, screenwriters, activists, biographers, museum professionals, and reenactors portray the American Revolution.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/Fighting-over-Founders-Remember-Revolution/dp/0814708161/'>excerpt</link></listitem><listitem>Sehat, David.<space/><italics>The Jefferson Rule: How the Founding Fathers Became Infallible and Our Politics Inflexibl</italics><space/>(2015)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/The-Jefferson-Rule-Infallible-Inflexible/dp/1476779775/'>excerpt</link></listitem><listitem>Shalhope, Robert E. &quot;Toward a republican synthesis: the emergence of an understanding of republicanism in American historiography.&quot;<space/><italics>William and Mary Quarterly</italics><space/>(1972): 49-80.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1921327'>in JSTOR</link></listitem><listitem>Waldstreicher, David. &quot;The Revolutions of Revolution Historiography: Cold War Contradance, Neo-Imperial Waltz, or Jazz Standard?.&quot;<space/><italics>Reviews in American History</italics><space/>42.1 (2014): 23-35.<space/><link type='external' href='http://muse.jhu.edu/journals/reviews_in_american_history/v042/42.1.waldstreicher.html'>online</link></listitem><listitem>Wood, Gordon S. &quot;Rhetoric and Reality in the American Revolution.&quot;<space/><italics>William and Mary Quarterly</italics><space/>(1966): 4-32.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/2936154'>in JSTOR</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The American Revolution: Writings from the War of Independence</italics><space/>(2001), Library of America, 880pp</listitem><listitem><link><target>Henry Steele Commager</target><part>Commager, Henry Steele</part></link><space/>and Morris, Richard B., eds.<space/><italics>The Spirit of 'Seventy-Six: The Story of the American Revolution As Told by Participants</italics><space/>(1975) (ISBN 0-06-010834-7) short excerpts from hundreds of official and unofficial primary sources</listitem><listitem>Dann, John C., ed.<space/><italics>The Revolution Remembered: Eyewitness Accounts of the War for Independence</italics><space/>(1999)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0226136248/'>excerpt and text search</link>, recollections by ordinary soldiers</listitem><listitem>Humphrey, Carol Sue ed.<space/><italics>The Revolutionary Era: Primary Documents on Events from 1776 to 1800</italics><space/>(2003), 384pp; newspaper accounts<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/dp/0313320837/'>excerpt and text search</link></listitem><listitem>Jensen, Merill, ed.<space/><italics>Tracts of the American Revolution, 17631776</italics><space/>(1967). American pamphlets</listitem><listitem>Jensen, Merill, ed.<space/><italics>English Historical Documents: American Colonial Documents to 1776: Volume 9</italics><space/>(1955), 890pp; major collection of important documents</listitem><listitem><link><target>Samuel Eliot Morison</target><part>Morison, Samuel E.</part></link><space/>ed.<space/><italics>Sources and Documents Illustrating the American Revolution, 17641788, and the Formation of the Federal Constitution</italics><space/>(1923). 370 pp<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/library/book/sources-and-documents-illustrating-the-american-revolution-1764-1788-and-the-formation-of-the-federal-constitution-by-s-e-morison.jsp'>online version</link></listitem><listitem>Tansill, Charles C. ed.;<space/><italics>Documents Illustrative of the Formation of the Union of the American States.</italics><space/>Government Printing Office. (1927). 1124 pages<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=61951136'>online version</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/TheAmericanRevolutionThroughBritishEyes'>Martin Kallich and Andrew MacLeish, eds. ''The American Revolution through British eyes'' (1962)</link><space/>primary documents</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Contemporary sources: Annual Register</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=mXIEAAAAQAAJ'>''Annual Register'' 1773</link>, British compendium of speeches and reports</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=y3YEAAAAQAAJ'>1774</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=rHgEAAAAQAAJ'>1775</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=zbqTVDanXIgC'>1776</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=oMoHAAAAIAAJ'>1777</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=63IEAAAAQAAJ'>1778</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=osoHAAAAIAAJ'>1779</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=BscLAAAAYAAJ'>1780</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=-HAEAAAAQAAJ'>1781</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=Y88HAAAAIAAJ'>1782</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=IXEEAAAAQAAJ'>1783</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/revolution/home.html'>Library of Congress Guide to the American Revolution</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archives.gov/research/military/american-revolution/pictures/'>''Pictures of the Revolutionary War: Select Audiovisual Records''</link>, National Archives and Records Administration selection of images, including a number of non-military events and portraits</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://sandbox.nyhsdev.org/sites/default/files/curriculum_materials/revolution/Revolution-Teachers-Guide.zip'>Revolution! The Atlantic World Reborn</link>, Revolution! explores the enormous transformations in the world's politics that took place from 1763-1815, with particular attention to three globally influential revolutions in America, France, and Haiti. Linking the attack on monarchism and aristocracy to the struggle against slavery, Revolution!shows how freedom, equality, and the sovereignty of the people became universal goals.<link><target>New-York Historical Society</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/ktca/liberty/'>PBS Television Series</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chickasaw.tv/history-timeline/document/american-revolution'>Chickasaws Conflicted by the American Revolution</link><space/>- Chickasaw.TV</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.smithsonianeducation.org/educators/lesson%5Fplans/revolutionary%5Fmoney/'>Smithsonian study unit on Revolutionary Money</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nps.gov/revwar/index.html'>''The American Revolution: Lighting Freedom's Flame''</link>, US National Park Service website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nps.gov/revwar/educational_resources/teachers.html'>''Honored Places: The National Park Service Teacher's Guide to the American Revolution''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.haldimand-collection.ca'>Haldimand Collection</link><space/>Letters regarding the war to important generals. Fully indexed</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://tigger.uic.edu/~rjensen/am-rev.htm'>&quot;Military History of Revolution&quot;</link><space/>with links to documents, maps, URLs</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.independencemuseum.org/'>American Independence Museum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.blackloyalist.com/'>Black Loyalist Heritage Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ouramericanhistory.com/'>Spanish and Latin American contribution to the American Revolution</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://dig.lib.niu.edu/amarch/index.html/'>American Archives: Documents of the American Revolution</link><space/>at Northern Illinois University Libraries</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shmoop.com/american-revolution/'>American Revolution</link><space/>study guide and teacher resources</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theamericanrevolution.org'>AmericanRevolution.Org</link><space/>Resource for pre collegiate historical educational institutions</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.history.com/topics/american-revolution'>The American Revolution</link>, the History Channel (US cable television) website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://zinnedproject.org/materials/half-a-revolution/'>Gayle Olson-Ramer, &quot;Half a Revolution&quot;</link>, 16-page teaching guide for high school students, Zinn Education Project/Rethinking Schools</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.democracynow.org/2014/6/27/counter_revolution_of_1776_was_us'>&quot;Counter-Revolution of 1776&quot;: Was U.S. Independence War a Conservative Revolt in Favor of Slavery?</link><space/><italics><link><target>Democracy Now!</target></link></italics><space/>June 27, 2014.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>American Revolution origins</target></template><template><target>British law and the American Revolution</target></template><template><target>Historical American Documents</target></template><template><target>US history</target></template><template><target>United States topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:1770s conflicts</target></link><link><target>Category:1780s conflicts</target></link><link><target>Category:18th century in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century rebellions</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century revolutions</target></link><link><target>Category:American Revolution</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:History of the United States (177689)</target></link><link><target>Category:Legal history of the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Age of Enlightenment</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>pl:Wojna o niepodlego Stanw Zjednoczonych</target></link></paragraph></article>