<article title='A_Modest_Proposal'><paragraph><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg name="name"><space/>A Modest Proposal
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>File:A Modest Proposal 1729 Cover.jpg
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Jonathan Swift]]
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="subject">
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Satire|Satirical essay]]
</arg><arg name="pub_date"><space/>1729
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold><italics>A Modest Proposal for Preventing the Children of Poor People From Being a Burthen to Their Parents or Country, and for Making Them Beneficial to the Publick</italics></bold>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="gutenberg"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/1080/1080-h/1080-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Modest Proposal, by Dr. Jonathan Swift<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Project Gutenberg]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 July 2008<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 January 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>commonly referred to as<space/><bold><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics></bold>, is a<space/><link><target>Juvenal</target><part>Juvenalian</part></link><space/><link><target>Satire</target><part>satirical</part></link><space/><link><target>essay</target></link><space/>written and published anonymously by<space/><link><target>Jonathan Swift</target></link><space/>in 1729. Swift suggests that the impoverished Irish might ease their economic troubles by selling their children as food for rich gentlemen and ladies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.smh.com.au/entertainment/restaurants-and-bars/from-cradle-to-crock-pot-20101013-16imh.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">From cradle to crock pot<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Sydney Morning Herald]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 October 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 January 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>This satirical<space/><link><target>hyperbole</target></link><space/>mocks heartless attitudes towards the poor, as well as Irish policy in general.</paragraph><paragraph>In English writing, the phrase &quot;a modest proposal&quot; is now conventionally an allusion to this style of straight-faced satire.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Details</heading><paragraph>Swift goes to great lengths to support his argument, including a list of possible preparation styles for the children, and calculations showing the financial benefits of his suggestion. He uses methods of argument throughout his essay which lampoon the then-influential<space/><link><target>William Petty</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Social engineering (political science)</target><part>social engineering</part></link><space/>popular among followers of<space/><link><target>Francis Bacon</target></link>. These lampoons include<space/><link><target>appeal to authority</target><part>appealing to the authority</part></link><space/>of &quot;a very knowing American of my acquaintance in London&quot; and &quot;the famous<space/><link><target>George Psalmanazar</target><part>Psalmanazar</part></link>, a native of the island<space/><link><target>Taiwan</target><part>Formosa</part></link>&quot; (who had already confessed to<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>being from Formosa in 1706). This essay is widely held to be one of the greatest examples of sustained irony in the history of the English language. Much of its shock value derives from the fact that the first portion of the essay describes the plight of starving beggars in Ireland, so that the reader is unprepared for the surprise of Swift's solution when he states, &quot;A young healthy child well nursed, is, at a year old, a most delicious nourishing and wholesome food, whether stewed, roasted, baked, or boiled; and I make no doubt that it will equally serve in a<space/><link><target>fricassee</target></link>, or a<space/><link><target>ragout</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="gutenberg"></extension></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>In the tradition of Roman satire, Swift introduces the reforms he is actually suggesting by<space/><link><target>paralipsis</target></link>:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Therefore let no man talk to me of other expedients: Of taxing our absentees at five shillings a pound: Of using neither clothes, nor household furniture, except what is of our own growth and manufacture: Of utterly rejecting the materials and instruments that promote foreign luxury: Of curing the expensiveness of pride, vanity, idleness, and gaming in our women: Of introducing a vein of parsimony, prudence and temperance: Of learning to love our country, wherein we differ even from [[Sami people|Laplanders]], and the [[Tupi people|inhabitants of Topinamboo]]: Of quitting our animosities and factions, nor acting any longer like the Jews, who were [[Zealot Temple Siege|murdering one another]] at the very moment [[Siege of Jerusalem (70)|their city was taken]]: Of being a little cautious not to sell our country and consciences for nothing: Of teaching landlords to have at least one degree of mercy towards their tenants. Lastly, of putting a spirit of honesty, industry, and skill into our shop-keepers, who, if a resolution could now be taken to buy only our native goods, would immediately unite to cheat and exact upon us in the price, the measure, and the goodness, nor could ever yet be brought to make one fair proposal of just dealing, though often and earnestly invited to it.

Therefore I repeat, let no man talk to me of these and the like expedients, 'till he hath at least some glympse of hope, that there will ever be some hearty and sincere attempt to put them into practice.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Population solutions</heading><paragraph>George Wittkowsky argued that Swifts main target in<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>was not the conditions in Ireland, but rather the can-do spirit of the times that led people to devise a number of illogical schemes that would purportedly solve social and economic ills.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p76">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swifts Modest Proposal</italics>, p76</extension><space/>Swift was especially insulted by projects that tried to fix population and labour issues with a simple cure-all solution.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p85">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swifts Modest Proposal</italics>, p85</extension><space/>A memorable example of these sorts of schemes &quot;involved the idea of running the poor through a<space/><link><target>joint-stock company</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p85"></extension><space/>In response, Swift's<space/><italics>Modest Proposal</italics><space/>was &quot;a burlesque of projects concerning the poor&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsk_p88">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swift's Modest Proposal</italics>, p88</extension><space/>that were in vogue during the early 18th century.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>also targets the calculating way people perceived the poor in designing their projects. The pamphlet targets reformers who &quot;regard people as commodities&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p101">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swift's Modest Proposal</italics>, p101</extension><space/>In the piece, Swift adopts the &quot;technique of a political arithmetician&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p95">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swift's Modest Proposal</italics>, p95</extension><space/>to show the utter ridiculousness of trying to prove any proposal with dispassionate statistics.</paragraph><paragraph>Critics differ about Swift's intentions in using this faux-mathematical philosophy. Edmund Wilson argues that statistically &quot;the logic of the 'Modest proposal' can be compared with defense of crime (arrogated to Marx) in which he argues that crime takes care of the superfluous population&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p95"></extension><space/>Wittkowsky counters that Swift's satiric use of statistical analysis is an effort to enhance his satire that &quot;springs from a spirit of bitter mockery, not from the delight in calculations for their own sake&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wittkowsky_p98">Wittkowsky,<space/><italics>Swift's Modest Proposal</italics>, p98</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Rhetoric</heading><paragraph>Charles K. Smith argues that Swift's rhetorical style persuades the reader to detest the speaker and pity the Irish. Swift's specific strategy is twofold, using a &quot;trap&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p135">Smith,<space/><italics>Toward a Participatory Rhetoric</italics>, p. 135</extension><space/>to create sympathy for the Irish and a dislike of the narrator who, in the span of one sentence, &quot;details vividly and with rhetorical emphasis the grinding poverty&quot; but feels emotion solely for members of his own class.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p136">Smith,<space/><italics>Toward a Participatory Rhetoric</italics>, p. 136</extension><space/>Swift's use of gripping details of poverty and his narrator's cool approach towards them create &quot;two opposing points of view&quot; that &quot;alienate the reader, perhaps unconsciously, from a narrator who can view with 'melancholy' detachment a subject that Swift has directed us, rhetorically, to see in a much less detached way.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p136"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Swift has his proposer further degrade the Irish by using language ordinarily reserved for animals. Lewis argues that the speaker uses &quot;the vocabulary of animal husbandry&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p138">Smith,<space/><italics>Toward a Participatory Rhetoric</italics>, p. 138</extension><space/>to describe the Irish. Once the children have been commodified, Swift's rhetoric can easily turn &quot;people into animals, then meat, and from meat, logically, into tonnage worth a price per pound&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p138"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Swift uses the proposer's serious tone to highlight the absurdity of his proposal. In making his argument, the speaker uses the conventional, text book approved order of argument from Swift's time (which was derived from the Latin rhetorician<space/><link><target>Quintilian</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p139">Smith,<space/><italics>Toward a Participatory Rhetoric</italics>, p. 139</extension><space/>The contrast between the &quot;careful control against the almost inconceivable perversion of his scheme&quot; and &quot;the ridiculousness of the proposal&quot; create a situation in which the reader has &quot;to consider just what perverted values and assumptions would allow such a diligent, thoughtful, and conventional man to propose so perverse a plan&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith_p139"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Influences</heading><paragraph>Scholars have speculated about which earlier works Swift may have had in mind when he wrote<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tertullian's<space/><italics>Apology</italics></heading><paragraph>James Johnson argued that<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>was largely influenced and inspired by<space/><link><target>Tertullian</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Apologeticus</target><part>Apology</part></link></italics>: a satirical attack against early Roman persecution of Christianity. James William Johnson believes that Swift saw major similarities between the two situations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson_p563">Johnson,<space/><italics>Tertullian and A Modest Proposal</italics>, p563</extension><space/>Johnson notes Swift's obvious affinity for Tertullian and the bold stylistic and structural similarities between the works<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Apology</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson_p562">Johnson,<space/><italics>Tertullian and A Modest Proposal</italics>, p562</extension><space/>In structure, Johnson points out the same central theme, that of cannibalism and the eating of babies as well as the same final argument, that &quot;human depravity is such that men will attempt to justify their own cruelty by accusing their victims of being lower than human.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson_p563"></extension><space/>Stylistically, Swift and Tertullian share the same command of sarcasm and language.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson_p563"></extension><space/>In agreement with Johnson, Donald C. Baker points out the similarity between both authors' tones and use of irony. Baker notes the uncanny way that both authors imply an ironic &quot;justification by ownership&quot; over the subject of sacrificing childrenTertullian while attacking pagan parents, and Swift while attacking the English mistreatment of the Irish poor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker_p219">Baker,<space/><italics>Tertullian and Swift's A Modest Proposal</italics>, p219</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Defoe's<space/><italics>The Generous Projector</italics></heading><paragraph>It has also been argued that<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>was, at least in part, a response to the 1728 essay<space/><italics>The Generous Projector or, A Friendly Proposal to Prevent Murder and Other Enormous Abuses, By Erecting an Hospital for Foundlings and Bastard Children</italics><space/>by Swift's rival<space/><link><target>Daniel Defoe</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.montrealmirror.com/2009/021909/books1.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">A modest but failed proposal<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Montreal Mirror]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 February 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="last">Waters<space/></arg><arg name="first">Juliet</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Economic themes</heading><paragraph>Robert Phiddian's article &quot;Have you eaten yet? The Reader in A Modest Proposal&quot; focuses on two aspects of<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics>: the voice of Swift and the voice of the Proposer. Phiddian stresses that a reader of the pamphlet must learn to distinguish between the satiric voice of Jonathan Swift and the apparent economic projections of the Proposer. He reminds readers that &quot;there is a gap between the narrator's meaning and the text's, and that a moral-political argument is being carried out by means of parody&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Phiddian_p6">Phiddian,<space/><italics>Have You Eaten Yet?</italics>, p6</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While Swift's proposal is obviously not a serious economic proposal, George Wittkowsky, author of &quot;Swift's Modest Proposal: The Biography of an Early Georgian Pamphlet&quot;, argues that to understand the piece fully, it is important to understand the economics of Swifts time. Wittowsky argues that not enough critics have taken the time to focus directly on the mercantilism and theories of labour in 18th century England. &quot;[I]f one regards the<space/><italics>Modest Proposal</italics><space/>simply as a criticism of condition, about all one can say is that conditions were bad and that Swift's irony brilliantly underscored this fact&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Phiddian_p3">Phiddian,<space/><italics>Have You Eaten Yet?</italics>, p3</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;People are the riches of a nation&quot;</heading><paragraph>At the start of a new industrial age in the 18th century, it was believed that &quot;people are the riches of the nation&quot;, and there was a general faith in an economy that paid its workers low wages because high wages meant workers would work less.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Phiddian_p4">Phiddian,<space/><italics>Have You Eaten Yet?</italics>, p4</extension><space/>Furthermore, &quot;in the mercantilist view no child was too young to go into industry&quot;. In those times, the &quot;somewhat more humane attitudes of an earlier day had all but disappeared and the laborer had come to be regarded as a commodity&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Phiddian_p6"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Louis A. Landa presents Swift's<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>as a critique of the popular and unjustified maxim of mercantilism in the 18th century that &quot;people are the riches of a nation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landa_p161">Landa,<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal and Populousness</italics>, p161</extension><space/>Swift presents the dire state of Ireland and shows that mere population itself, in Ireland's case, did not always mean greater wealth and economy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landa_p165">Landa,<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal and Populousness</italics>, p165</extension><space/>The uncontrolled maxim fails to take into account that a person who does not produce in an economic or political way makes a country poorer, not richer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landa_p165"></extension><space/>Swift also recognises the implications of such a fact in making mercantilist philosophy a paradox: the wealth of a country is based on the poverty of the majority of its citizens.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landa_p165"></extension><space/>Swift however, Landa argues, is not merely criticising economic maxims but also addressing the fact that England was denying Irish citizens their natural rights and dehumanising them by viewing them as a mere commodity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landa_p165"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern usage</heading><paragraph><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>is included in many literature programs as an example of<space/><link><target>Satire#Early modern western satire</target><part>early modern western satire</part></link>. It also serves as an exceptional introduction to the concept and use of argumentative language, lending itself well to secondary and post-secondary essay courses. Outside of the realm of English studies,<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>is a relevant piece included in many comparative and global literature and history courses, as well as those of numerous other disciplines in the arts, humanities, and even the social sciences.</paragraph><paragraph>The essay has been emulated many times. In his book<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics><space/>(1984), evangelical author<space/><link><target>Frank Schaeffer</target></link><space/>emulated Swift's work in social conservative polemic against abortion and<space/><link><target>euthanasia</target></link><space/>in a future<space/><link><target>dystopia</target></link><space/>that advocated<space/><link><target>recycling</target></link><space/>of aborted<space/><link><target>embryos</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fetuses</target></link>, as well as some disabled infants with compound intellectual, physical and physiological difficulties. (Such<space/><link><target>Baby Doe Rules</target></link><space/>cases were then a major concern of the<space/><link><target>pro-life</target></link><space/>movement of the early 1980s, which viewed selective treatment of those infants as<space/><link><target>disability discrimination</target></link>.) In his book<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal for America</italics><space/>(2013), statistician<space/><link><target>Howard Friedman</target></link><space/>opens with a satirical reflection of the extreme drive to fiscal stability by ultra-conservatives.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Hunter S. Thompson</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Fear and Loathing in America</target><part>Fear and Loathing in America: The Brutal Odyssey of an Outlaw Journalist</part></link></italics>, which contains hundreds of private letters written by Thompson over the years, contains a letter in which he uses<space/><italics>A Modest Proposal</italics>'s satire technique against the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link>. Thompson writes a letter to a local<space/><link><target>Aspen, Colorado</target><part>Aspen</part></link><space/>newspaper informing them that, on Christmas Eve, he was going to use<space/><link><target>napalm</target></link><space/>to burn a number of dogs and hopefully any humans they find. This letter protests the burning of Vietnamese people occurring overseas.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baker<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Donald C
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tertullian and Swift's ''A Modest Proposal''
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The Classical Journal
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>52
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1957
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>219–220</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Johnson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>James William
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tertullian and ''A Modest Proposal''
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Modern Language and Notes
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>73
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1958
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>561–563
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/3043246
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>8
</arg><arg name="format">
</arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>3043246
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Johns Hopkins University Press<space/></arg></template><space/>(subscription needed)</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Landa<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Louis A
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>''A Modest Proposal'' and Populousness
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Modern Philology
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>40
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1942
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>161–170
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1086/388567</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Phiddian<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Have You Eaten Yet? The Reader in ''A Modest Proposal''
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Studies in English Literature, 1500–1900
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>603–621
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>36
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/450801
</arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>450801
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Rice University</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Smith<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles Kay
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Toward a Participatory Rhetoric: Teaching Swift's ''Modest Proposal''
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>College English
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>30
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1968
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>135–149
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/374449
</arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>374449
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>National Council of Teachers of English</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Wittkowsky<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>George
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Swift's ''Modest Proposal'': The Biography of an Early Georgian Pamphlet
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of the History of Ideas
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>4
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1943
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>75–104
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/2707237
</arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>2707237
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Pennsylvania Press</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource</target><arg>A Modest Proposal</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ucc.ie/celt/online/E700001-022'>''A Modest Proposal'' (CELT)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/etext/1080'>''A Modest Proposal'' (Gutenberg)</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>librivox book</target><arg name="title"><space/>A Modest Proposal<space/></arg><arg name="author">H. Jonathan Swift</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20090129.shtml'>''A Modest Proposal''</link><space/>BBC Radio 4<space/><italics><link><target>In Our Time (BBC Radio 4)</target><part>In Our Time</part></link></italics><space/>with<space/><link><target>Melvyn Bragg</target></link></listitem><listitem>'<link type='external' href='http://books.google.it/books?id=t1MJAAAAQAAJ'>''A modest proposal For preventing the children of poor people From being a Burthen to their Parents or the Country, And for making them Beneficial to the publick''</link>. The Third Edition, Dublin, Printed: And Reprinted at London, for Weaver Bickerton, in Devereux-Court near the Middle-Temple, 1730.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Jonathan Swift</target><arg name="state">expanded</arg></template><template><target>Population</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Modest Proposal, A</target></template><link><target>Category:Essays by Jonathan Swift</target></link><link><target>Category:Satirical works</target></link><link><target>Category:Pamphlets</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century essays</target></link><link><target>Category:Works published anonymously</target></link><link><target>Category:British satire</target></link><link><target>Category:1729 in Great Britain</target></link><link><target>Category:Cannibalism in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:1729 works</target></link></paragraph></article>