<article title='Epistle_to_the_Ephesians'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><template><target>Books of the New Testament</target></template>The<space/><bold>Epistle to the Ephesians</bold>, also called the<space/><bold>Letter to the Ephesians</bold><space/>and often shortened to<space/><bold>Ephesians</bold>, is the tenth book of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>. Its authorship has traditionally been credited to<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target></link><space/>but, starting in 1792, this has been challenged<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ephesians">Authenticity of<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bible-apologetics.com/history/ephesians.htm'>Ephesians</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Hoehner 2002"><link><target>Harold Hoehner</target><part>Hoehner, Harold</part></link>.<space/><italics>Ephesians: An Exegetical Commentary.</italics><space/>Baker Academic, 2002. ISBN 978-0-8010-2614-0</extension><space/>as<space/><link><target>Authorship of the Pauline epistles</target><part>Deutero-Pauline</part></link>, that is, written in Paul's name by a later author strongly influenced by Paul's thought.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hoehner surveys 279 commentators from 1519 to 2001, finding 54% favor Pauline authorship, 39% conclude against Pauline authorship, and 7% remained uncertain. See Harold W. Hoehner, Ephesians: An Exegetical Commentary (Grand Rapids: Baker, 2001), 6-20; isbn=0-8010-2614-8</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ehrman 2004 381384"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Ehrman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bart D.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Bart D. Ehrman<space/></arg><arg name="title">The New Testament: A Historical Introduction to the Early Christian Writings<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-515462-2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">381–384</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="nccbuscc.org"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="title">USCCB – NAB – Ephesians – Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-01-17<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nccbuscc.org/nab/bible/ephesians/intro.htm<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20090104184919/http://www.nccbuscc.org:80/nab/bible/ephesians/intro.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">4 January 2009<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="barth"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Perrin<space/></arg><arg name="first">Norman</arg><arg name="authorlink">Norman Perrin<space/></arg><arg name="title">The New Testament: An Introduction. Second Edition.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harcourt Brace Jovanovich<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-15-565726-7<space/></arg><arg name="pages">218–222</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>The main theme of Ephesians is the Church, the Body of Christ.<template><target>quote</target><arg>As a prisoner for the Lord, then, I urge you to live a life worthy of the calling you have received. Be completely humble and gentle; be patient, bearing with one another in love. Make every effort to keep the unity of the Spirit through the bond of peace.</arg><arg>{{bibleref2|Ephesians|4:1–3}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Church is to maintain the unity in practice which Christ has brought about positionally. According to New Testament scholar Daniel Wallace, the theme may be stated pragmatically as Christians, get along with each other! Maintain the unity practically which Christ has effected positionally by his death.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallace">Wallace, Daniel B. &quot;Ephesians:Introduction, Argument, and Outline.&quot; Web:<space/><link type='external' href='http://bible.org/seriespage/ephesians-introduction-argument-and-outline'></link><space/>1 January 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another major theme in Ephesians is the keeping of Christ's body (that is, the Church) pure and holy.<space/><template><target>quote</target><arg>Therefore be imitators of God, as beloved children. And walk in love, as Christ loved us and gave himself up for us, a fragrant offering and sacrifice to God.</arg><arg>{{bibleref2|Ephesians|5:1–2}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From Ephesians 4:176:20 the author of the Epistle to the Ephesians gives practical advice in how to live a holy, pure, and Christ-inspired lifestyle. Many devotional thoughts and sermons that are addressed to the practically minded individual have been drawn from this section of the New Testament, due to its nature as being good for application studies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph>According to tradition, the Apostle Paul wrote the letter while he was in prison in<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link><space/>(around AD 62). This would be about the same time as the<space/><link><target>Epistle to the Colossians</target></link><space/>(which in many points it resembles) and the<space/><link><target>Epistle to Philemon</target></link>. However many critical scholars have questioned the authorship of the letter and suggest that it may have been written between AD 80 and 100.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ehrman 2004 381384"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="nccbuscc.org"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="barth"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authenticity and Destination</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Authorship of the Pauline Epistles</arg></template>The first verse in the letter, according to the late manuscripts used in most English translations, reads, &quot;Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus by the will of God, To the saints in<space/><link><target>Ephesus</target></link>, the faithful in Christ Jesus.&quot; (<template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>1:1</arg></template><space/>NIV). Hence, the letter identifies Paul as its author, and these manuscripts designate the Ephesian church as its recipient. Ephesians is found in the two earliest canons, and many of the early<space/><link><target>Church Fathers</target></link><space/>(including<space/><link><target>Clement of Rome</target></link>, Ignatius, Hermas, and<space/><link><target>Polycarp</target></link>) support Paul's authorship.</paragraph><paragraph>There are four main theories in biblical scholarship that address the question of Pauline authorship.<extension extension_name='ref'>These four views all come from Markus Barth, Ephesians: Introduction, Translation, and Commentary on Chapters 13 (New York: Doubleday and Company Inc., 1974), 38</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The traditional view that the epistle is written by Paul is supported by scholars that include Frank Thielman,<space/><link><target>Ezra Abbot</target></link>, Asting, Gaugler, Grant,<space/><link><target>Adolf von Harnack</target><part>Harnack</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Erich Haupt</target><part>Haupt</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Fenton John Anthony Hort</target></link>, Klijn,<space/><link><target>Johann David Michaelis</target></link>, A. Robert, and Andr Feuillet,<space/><link><target>James A. Sanders</target><part>Sanders</part></link>, Schille,<space/><link><target>Brooke Foss Westcott</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Theodor Zahn</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ephesians"></extension><space/>For a defense of the Pauline authorship of Ephesians, see<space/><italics>Ephesians: An Exegetical Commentary</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Harold Hoehner</target></link>, pp 261.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hoehner 2002"></extension></listitem><listitem>A second position suggests that Ephesians was dictated by Paul with interpolations from another author. Some of the scholars that espouse this view include Albertz, Benoit, Cerfaux, Goguel, Harrison,<space/><link><target>H. J. Holtzmann</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jerome Murphy-O'Connor</target><part>Murphy-O'Connor</part></link>, and Wagenfuhrer.</listitem><listitem>Currently, most &quot;critical scholars&quot; think it improbable that Paul authored Ephesians. Among this group are Allan, Beare, Brandon, Bultmann, Conzelmann,<space/><link><target>Martin Dibelius</target><part>Dibelius</part></link>, Goodspeed, Kilsemann, J. Knox, W.L. Knox, Kmmel, K and S Lake, Marxsen, Masson, Mitton, Moffatt,<space/><link><target>Dennis Nineham</target><part>Nineham</part></link>, Pokorny, Schweizer, and J. Weiss.</listitem><listitem>Still other scholars suggest there is a lack of conclusive evidence. Some of this group are Cadbury, Julicher, McNeile, and Williams.</listitem></list><paragraph>There are some problems with Ephesus being the original destination, including:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The earliest and best known manuscripts omit the words &quot;in Ephesus&quot;, rendering the phrase simply as &quot;to the saints ... the faithful in Christ Jesus&quot; (NIV alternative translation).</listitem><listitem>The letter lacks any references to people in Ephesus, or any events Paul experienced there. There are no &quot;when I was with you&quot; statements, as there are in his writings to other churches which he did know personally. (1 Cor. 2:1-3, 2 Cor. 12:14, 13:1-2; Phil. 2:12; 1 Thess. 1:5-2:13)</listitem><listitem>Phrases such as &quot;since I heard about your faith&quot;<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>1:15</arg><arg></arg><arg>1:15 NIV</arg></template><space/>would seem to indicate that the writer has no firsthand knowledge of his audience. This presents a problem as the book of Acts records that Paul spent a significant amount of time with the church in Ephesus, and in fact was one of its founders. It could be argued, however, that &quot;faith&quot; in this verse is the start of a list of qualities displayed by the recipients of the letter, not a solitary statement about news of faith, full stop. Additionally, the author gives no indication that the report he &quot;heard&quot; was his introduction to the church in Ephesus. It could mean that he received word of the further development and growth of the church in Ephesus, and if Paulco-founder of that churchwrote the letter, this illuminates his follow-up: &quot;I do not cease to give thanks for you...&quot;<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>1:16</arg><arg></arg><arg>1:16 ESV</arg></template></listitem><listitem>On the other hand, there are several distinctive parallel statements in &quot;Ephesians&quot; with the epistle to the Colossians which is strongly associated with Laodicea and other churches which had not seen Paul &quot;in the flesh.&quot; (Col. 2:1) One of these parallels is the mention of Tychicus only in these two letters (Eph. 6:21-22, Col. 4:7-8) as being sent to them for this very purpose, to better inform them about Pauls circumstances and situation.</listitem></list><paragraph>The lack of any internal references to Ephesus in the early manuscripts may have led<space/><link><target>Marcion</target></link>, a second-century heretic<space/><link><target>Development of the New Testament canon#Marcion of Sinope</target><part>who created the first New Testament canon</part></link>, to believe that the letter was actually addressed to the church at Laodicea, for details see<space/><link><target>Epistle to the Laodiceans</target></link>. The view is not uncommon in later traditions either, considering that the content of the letter seems to suggest a similar socio-critical context to the Laodicean church mentioned in the Revelation of John.<template><target>quote</target><arg name="Most English translations indicate that the addressees are 'the saints who are in Ephesus' (1:1), but the words 'in Ephesus' are not found in the earliest and best Greek manuscripts of this letter. Most textual experts think that the words were not in the letter originally but were added by a scribe after it had already been in circulation for a time.<ref name">"Ehrman 2004 381–384"/></arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;This was probably a circular letter to be read in more than one place....Most likely, the author did not know the readers personally (see 1:15, 3:24, and 6:2324). According to Acts [20:31], Paul spent three years in Ephesus and was emotionally attached to the believers there. If this letter were to Ephesus, one would expect it to have more of the warmth evidenced in Philippians...We may safely assume the letter was a general letter to Gentile believers in southwestern Asia Minor and that it became identified with Ephesus as the most important city between Rome and Antioch.&quot; (NIV application commentary; Klyne Snodgrass; p.&amp;nbsp;21)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Place, date, and purpose of the writing of the letter</heading><paragraph>If Paul was the author of the letter, then it was probably written from Rome during Paul's first imprisonment (<template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>3:1</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>4:1</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>6:20</arg></template>), and probably soon after his arrival there in the year 62, four years after he had parted with the Ephesian elders at Miletus. However, scholars who dispute Paul's authorship date the letter to between 7080 AD.<extension extension_name='ref' name="barth"></extension><space/>In the latter case, the possible location of the authorship could have been within the church of Ephesus itself.<space/><link><target>Ignatius of Antioch</target></link><space/>himself seemed to be very well versed in the epistle to the Ephesians, and mirrors many of his own thoughts in his own epistle to the Ephesians.<extension extension_name='ref' name="barth">See Markus Barth, Ephesians: Introduction, Translation, and Commentary on Chapters 13 (New York: Doubleday and Company Inc., 1974), 5051</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The major theme of the letter is the unity and reconciliation of the whole of creation through the agency of the Church and, in particular, its foundation in Christ as part of the will of the Father.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Epistle to the Romans</target></link>, Paul writes from the point of view of the demonstration of the<space/><link><target>righteousness</target></link><space/>of God his covenant faithfulness and saving justice in the gospel; the author of Ephesians writes from the perspective of union with Christ, who is the head of the true church.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Outline</heading><paragraph>Ephesians contains:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>1:1,2</arg></template>.</bold><space/>The greeting</listitem><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>1:3–2:10</arg></template>.</bold><space/>A general account of the blessings that the<space/><link><target>gospel</target></link><space/>reveals. This includes the source of these blessings, the means by which they are attained, the reason why they are given, and their final result. The whole of the section<space/><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>1:3–23</arg></template><space/>consists in the original Greek of just two lengthy and complex sentences (<template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>1:3–14,15-23</arg></template>). It ends with a fervent<space/><link><target>prayer</target></link><space/>for the further spiritual enrichment of the Ephesians.</listitem><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>2:11–3:21</arg></template>.</bold><space/>A description of the change in the spiritual position of<space/><link><target>Gentile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as a result of the work of Christ. It ends with an account of how Paul was selected and qualified to be an<space/><link><target>Twelve Apostles#Other apostles</target><part>apostle</part></link><space/>to the Gentiles, in the hope that this will keep them from being dispirited and lead him to pray for them.</listitem><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>4:1–16</arg></template>.</bold><space/>A chapter on unity in the midst of the diversity of gifts among believers.</listitem><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>4:17–6:9</arg></template>.</bold><space/><link><target>Household code</target><part>Instructions about ordinary life and different relationships</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><bold><template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>6:10–24</arg></template>.</bold><space/>The imagery of<space/><link><target>spiritual warfare</target></link><space/>(including the metaphor of the<space/><link><target>Armor of God</target></link>), the mission of<space/><link><target>Tychicus</target></link>, and valedictory blessings.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Founding of the church at Ephesus</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Early centers of Christianity#Asia Minor</arg></template>Paul's first and hurried visit for the space of three months to<space/><link><target>Ephesus</target></link><space/>is recorded in<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>18:19–21</arg></template>. The work he began on this occasion was carried forward by<space/><link><target>Aquila (bible)</target><part>Aquila</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Priscilla (Christian)</target><part>Priscilla</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Apollos</target></link><template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Ac.</arg><arg>18:24–26</arg></template>. On his second visit early in the following year, he remained at Ephesus &quot;three years,&quot; for he found it was the key to the western provinces of<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target><part>Asia Minor</part></link>. Here &quot;a great door and effectual&quot; was opened to him,<template><target>Bibleref2c</target><arg>1Cor</arg><arg>16:9</arg><arg></arg><arg>1 Cor 16:9</arg></template><space/>and the church was established and strengthened by his diligent labours there.<template><target>Bibleref2c</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:20,31</arg></template><space/>From Ephesus the gospel spread abroad &quot;almost throughout all Asia.&quot;<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>19:26</arg></template><space/>The word &quot;mightily grew and prevailed&quot; despite all the opposition and persecution he encountered.</paragraph><paragraph>On his last journey to<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link>, the apostle landed at<space/><link><target>Miletus</target></link><space/>and, summoning together the elders of the church from Ephesus, delivered to them a farewell charge,<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:18–35</arg></template><space/>expecting to see them no more.</paragraph><paragraph>The following parallels between this epistle and the Milesian charge may be traced:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:19</arg></template><space/>=<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>4:2</arg></template>. The phrase &quot;lowliness of mind&quot;.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:27</arg></template><space/>=<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>1:11</arg></template>. The word &quot;counsel&quot;, denoting the divine plan.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:32</arg></template><space/>=<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>3:20</arg></template>. The divine ability.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:32</arg></template><space/>=<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>2:20</arg></template>. The building upon the foundation.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:32</arg></template><space/>=<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>1:14,18</arg></template><space/>&quot;The inheritance of the saints.&quot;</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Purpose</heading><paragraph>The purpose of the epistle, and to whom it was written, are matters of much speculation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bruce">Bruce, F.F.<space/><italics>The New International Commentary on the New Testament</italics>. Eerdmans, 1984, 1991. ISBN 0-8028-2401-3.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.229</arg></template><space/>It was regarded by<space/><link><target>C.H. Dodd</target></link><space/>as the &quot;crown of Paulinism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bruce"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.229</arg></template><space/>In general, it is born out of its particular socio-historical context and the situational context of both the author and the audience. Originating in the circumstance of a<space/><link><target>multicultural</target></link><space/>church (primarily<space/><link><target>Jewish</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hellenistic</target></link>), the author addressed issues appropriate to the diverse religious and cultural backgrounds present in the community.<link><target>File:Ein Herr Ein Glaube Eine Taufe.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>right</part><part>German inscription of the text, &quot;One Lord, One faith, One baptism,&quot; (Ephesians 4:5).</part></link>Paul exhorts the church repeatedly to embrace a specific view of salvation, which he then explicates. It seems most likely that Paul's Christology of sacrifice is the manner in which he intends to effect an environment of peace within the church. In short: &quot;If Christ was sacrificed for your sake, be like him and be in submission to one another.&quot; Paul addresses hostility, division, and self-interest more than any other topic in the letter, leading many scholars to believe that his primary concern was not doctrinal, but behavioral.</paragraph><paragraph>Some theologians, such as Frank Charles Thompson,<extension extension_name='ref'>Thompson, Frank C.<space/><italics>Thompson Chain Reference Study Bible (NIV).</italics><space/>Kirkbride Bible Company, 2000. ISBN 978-0-88707-009-9</extension><space/>agree the main theme of Ephesians is in response to the newly converted Jews who often separated themselves from their Gentile brethren. The unity of the church, especially between Jew and Gentile believers, is the keynote of the book. This is shown by the recurrence of such words and phrases as:</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Together:</bold><space/>made alive together;<template><target>Bibleref2c</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>2:5</arg></template><space/>raised up together, sitting together;<template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>2:6</arg></template><space/>built together.<template><target>Bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Eph.</arg><arg>2:22</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>One</bold>, indicating unity: one new man,<template><target>Bibleref2c</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>2:15</arg></template><space/>one body,<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>2:16</arg></template><space/>one Spirit,<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>2:18</arg></template><space/>one hope,<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>4:4</arg></template><space/>one Lord, one faith, one baptism, one God and Father of all.<template><target>Bibleref2c-nb</target><arg>Eph</arg><arg>4:5–6</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Pauline theme of unity based on a sacrificial Christology may also be noted in the epistle to the<space/><link><target>Philippians</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Interpretations</heading><paragraph>Ephesians is notable for its domestic code treatment in<space/><template><target>bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Ephesians</arg><arg>5:22–6:9</arg></template>, covering husband-wife, parent-child, and master-slave relationships. In<space/><template><target>bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Ephesians</arg><arg>5:22</arg></template>, wives are urged to submit to their husbands, and husbands to love their wives &quot;as Christ loved the Church.&quot;<space/><link><target>Christian egalitarianism</target><part>Christian Egalitarian theologians</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>Katharine Bushnell</target></link><space/>and Jesse Penn-Lewis, interpret these commands in the context of the preceding verse,<space/><template><target>bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Ephesians</arg><arg>5:21</arg></template><space/>for all Christians to &quot;submit to one another.&quot; Thus, it is two-way, mutual submission of both husbands to wives and wives to husbands. But according to<space/><link><target>Peter O'Brien (theologian)</target><part>Peter O'Brien</part></link>, Professor Emeritus at<space/><link><target>Moore Theological College</target></link>, this would be the only instance of this meaning of submission in the whole New Testament, indeed in any extant comparable Greek texts; by O'Brien's account, the word simply does not connote mutuality.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Peter O'Brien (theologian)</target><part>OBrien, Peter Thomas</part></link>. The Letter to the Ephesians. The Pillar New Testament Commentary. Grand Rapids, Mich.: W.B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., 1999.</extension><space/><link><target>Dallas Theological Seminary</target></link><space/>professor Daniel Wallace understands it to be an extension of<space/><template><target>bibleref2-nb</target><arg>Ephesians</arg><arg>5:15–21</arg></template><space/>on being filled by the Holy Spirit.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wallace"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the context leading up to the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link><space/>(186165),<space/><template><target>Bibleref2</target><arg>Ephesians</arg><arg>6:5</arg></template><space/>on master-slave relationships was one of the Bible verses used by<space/><link><target>Confederate States of America</target><part>Confederate</part></link><space/>slaveholders in support of a slaveholding position.<extension extension_name='ref'>E.N. Elliott, ed.<space/><italics>Cotton is king, and pro-slavery arguments comprising the writings of Hammond, Harper, Christy, Stringfellow, Hodge, Bledsoe, and Cartwright, on this important subject</italics>. Augusta, Ga. : Pritchard, Abbott &amp; Loomis, 1860.<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Cotton is King – Google Books</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-03-13</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="author1"><space/>Christy</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>David</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Bledsoe</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Albert Taylor</arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Stringfellow</arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Thornton</arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Harper</arg><arg name="first4"><space/>Robert Goodloe</arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Hammond</arg><arg name="first5"><space/>James Henry</arg><arg name="last6"><space/>Cartwright</arg><arg name="first6"><space/>Samuel Adolphus</arg><arg name="last7"><space/>Hodge</arg><arg name="first7"><space/>Charles</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1860</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Earlier Epistle to the Ephesians</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Ephesians</target><part>Textual variants in the Epistle to the Ephesians</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EBD</target><arg>Ephesians, Epistle to the</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource</target><arg>Ephesians (Bible)</arg><arg>Ephesians</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10628_id432549.pdf'>A Brief Introduction to Ephesians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tyndale.ca/seminary/mtsmodular/reading-rooms/newt/ephesians'>Ephesians Online Reading Room</link><space/>extensive collection of online resources for Ephesians; Tyndale Seminary</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ephesiansonline.com'>Ephesians Online</link><space/>a collection of resources on the Epistle to the Ephesians</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sermonsfortoday.org/browse_sermons/sermonsInSeries.php?series=Series%20on%20Ephesians'>Biblical Expository on Ephesians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.raystedman.org/new-testament/ephesians'>Ephesians: The Calling of the Saints</link><space/>Ephesians Messages, Audio &amp; Podcast by Ray Stedman</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite AmCyc</target><arg name="wstitle">Ephesians, Epistle to the</arg><arg name="author">[[A. J. Schem]]</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg>[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] Prison [[Epistles|Epistle]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Epistle to the Galatians|Galatians]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title"><small>[[New Testament]]</small><br>[[Books of the Bible]]</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Epistle to the Philippians|Philippians]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Epistle to the Ephesians</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Epistle to the Ephesians</target></template><link><target>Category:Canonical epistles</target><part>Ephesians</part></link><link><target>Category:Pauline-related books</target></link><link><target>Category:Prison writings</target></link><link><target>Category:New Testament books</target><part>Ephesians</part></link><link><target>Category:Epistle to the Ephesians</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>