<article title='Electromagnetic_radiation'><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:Onde electromagnetique.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>The electromagnetic waves that compose electromagnetic radiation can be imagined as a self-propagating<space/><link><target>Transverse wave</target><part>transverse oscillating wave</part></link><space/>of electric and magnetic fields. This diagram shows a plane linearly polarized EMR wave propagating from left to right. The electric field is in a vertical plane and the magnetic field in a horizontal plane. The electric and magnetic fields in EMR waves are always in phase and at 90 degrees to each other.</part></link><template><target>Electromagnetism</target><arg name="cTopic">Electrodynamics</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Electromagnetic radiation</bold><space/>(<bold>EM radiation</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>EMR</bold>) is the<space/><link><target>radiant energy</target></link><space/>released by certain<space/><link><target>electromagnetism</target><part>electromagnetic</part></link><space/>processes. Visible<space/><link><target>light</target></link><space/>is one type of electromagnetic radiation, other familiar forms are invisible electromagnetic radiations such as radio waves, infrared light and X rays.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Classical electromagnetism</target><part>Classically</part></link>, electromagnetic radiation consists of<space/><bold>electromagnetic waves</bold>, which are synchronized<space/><link><target>oscillation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>electric field</target><part>electric</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target><part>magnetic</part></link><space/>fields that propagate at the<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link><space/>through a vacuum. The oscillations of the two fields are perpendicular to each other and perpendicular to the direction of energy and<space/><link><target>wave propagation</target></link>, forming a<space/><link><target>transverse wave</target></link>. Electromagnetic waves can be characterized by either the<space/><link><target>frequency</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>wavelength</target></link><space/>of their oscillations to form the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic spectrum</target></link>, which includes, in order of increasing frequency and decreasing wavelength:<space/><link><target>radio wave</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>microwave</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>infrared radiation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>visible spectrum</target><part>visible light</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ultraviolet</target></link><space/>radiation,<space/><link><target>X-ray</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gamma ray</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Electromagnetic waves are produced whenever<space/><link><target>charged particle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are<space/><link><target>acceleration</target><part>accelerated</part></link>, and these waves can subsequently interact with any charged particles. EM waves carry<space/><link><target>energy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>momentum</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>angular momentum</target></link><space/>away from their source particle and can impart those quantities to<space/><link><target>matter</target></link><space/>with which they interact. Quanta of EM waves are called<space/><link><target>photon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are<space/><link><target>Massless particle</target><part>massless</part></link>, but they are still affected by<space/><link><target>General relativity#Light deflection and gravitational time delay</target><part>gravity</part></link>. Electromagnetic radiation is associated with those EM waves that are free to propagate themselves (&quot;radiate&quot;) without the continuing influence of the moving charges that produced them, because they have achieved sufficient distance from those charges. Thus, EMR is sometimes referred to as the<space/><link><target>Near and far field</target><part>far field</part></link>. In this jargon, the<space/><italics>near field</italics><space/>refers to EM fields near the charges and current that directly produced them, specifically,<space/><link><target>electromagnetic induction</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>static electricity</target><part>electrostatic induction</part></link><space/>phenomena.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Quantum electrodynamics</target><part>quantum theory of electromagnetism</part></link>, EMR consists of<space/><link><target>photon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>elementary particle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>responsible for all electromagnetic interactions. Quantum effects provide additional sources of EMR, such as the<space/><link><target>Atomic electron transition</target><part>transition of electrons</part></link><space/>to lower<space/><link><target>energy level</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in an atom and<space/><link><target>black-body radiation</target></link>. The energy of an individual photon is<space/><link><target>Quantization (physics)</target><part>quantized</part></link><space/>and is greater for photons of higher frequency. This relationship is given by<space/><link><target>PlanckEinstein relation</target><part>Planck's equation</part></link><space/>E=h, where E is the energy per photon, is the frequency of the photon, and h is<space/><link><target>Planck's constant</target></link>. A single gamma ray photon, for example, might carry ~100,000 times the energy of a single photon of visible light.</paragraph><paragraph>The effects of EMR upon biological systems (and also to many other chemical systems, under<space/><link><target>standard conditions for temperature and pressure</target><part>standard conditions</part></link>) depend both upon the radiation's<space/><link><target>Power (physics)</target><part>power</part></link><space/>and its frequency. For EMR of visible frequencies or lower (i.e., radio, microwave, infrared), the damage done to cells and other materials is determined mainly by power and caused primarily by heating effects from the combined energy transfer of many photons. By contrast, for ultraviolet and higher frequencies (i.e., X-rays and gamma rays), chemical materials and living cells can be further damaged beyond that done by simple heating, since individual photons of such high frequency have enough energy to cause direct<space/><link><target>Photodissociation</target><part>molecular damage</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Physics</heading><heading level='3'>Theory</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:VisibleEmrWavelengths.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Shows the relative wavelengths of the electromagnetic waves of three different colours of<space/><link><target>Visible light</target><part>light</part></link><space/>(blue, green, and red) with a distance scale in micrometers along the x-axis.</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Maxwell's equations</arg><arg>Near and far field</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Maxwells equations</heading><paragraph><link><target>James Clerk Maxwell</target></link><space/>first formally postulated<space/><italics>electromagnetic waves</italics>. These were subsequently confirmed by<space/><link><target>Heinrich Hertz</target></link>. Maxwell derived a<space/><link><target>Electromagnetic wave equation</target><part>wave form of the electric and magnetic equations</part></link>, thus uncovering the wave-like nature of electric and magnetic fields and their<space/><link><target>Symmetry (physics)</target><part>symmetry</part></link>. Because the speed of EM waves predicted by the wave equation coincided with the measured<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link>, Maxwell concluded that<space/><link><target>light</target></link><space/>itself is an EM wave.</paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link>, a spatially varying<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>is always associated with a<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target></link><space/>that changes over time. Likewise, a spatially varying magnetic field is associated with specific changes over time in the electric field. In an electromagnetic wave, the changes in the electric field are always accompanied by a wave in the magnetic field in one direction, and vice versa. This relationship between the two occurs without either type field causing the other; rather, they occur together in the same way that time and space changes occur together and are interlinked in<space/><link><target>special relativity</target></link>. In fact, magnetic fields may be viewed as relativistic distortions of electric fields, so the close relationship between space and time changes here is more than an analogy. Together, these fields form a propagating electromagnetic wave, which moves out into space and need never again affect the source. The distant EM field formed in this way by the acceleration of a charge carries energy with it that &quot;radiates&quot; away through space, hence the term.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Near and far fields</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Liénard–Wiechert potential</arg></template><link><target>File:FarNearFields-USP-4998112-1.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>In electromagnetic radiation (such as microwaves from an antenna, shown here) the term applies only to the parts of the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic field</target></link><space/>that radiate into infinite space and decrease in intensity by an<space/><link><target>inverse-square law</target></link><space/>of power, so that the total radiation energy that crosses through an imaginary spherical surface is the same, no matter how far away from the antenna the spherical surface is drawn. Electromagnetic radiation thus includes the<space/><link><target>near and far field</target><part>far field</part></link><space/>part of the electromagnetic field around a transmitter. A part of the &quot;near-field&quot; close to the transmitter, forms part of the changing<space/><link><target>electromagnetic field</target></link>, but does not count as electromagnetic radiation.</part></link>Maxwell's equations established that some charges and currents (&quot;sources&quot;) produce a local type of<space/><link><target>electromagnetic field</target></link><space/>near them that does<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>have the behaviour of EMR. Currents directly produce a magnetic field, but it is of a<space/><link><target>magnetic dipole</target></link><space/>type that dies out with distance from the current. In a similar manner, moving charges pushed apart in a conductor by a changing electrical potential (such as in an antenna) produce an<space/><link><target>electric dipole</target></link><space/>type electrical field, but this also declines with distance. These fields make up the<space/><link><target>near and far field</target><part>near-field</part></link><space/>near the EMR source. Neither of these behaviours are responsible for EM radiation. Instead, they cause electromagnetic field behaviour that only efficiently transfers power to a receiver very close to the source, such as the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic induction</target><part>magnetic induction</part></link><space/>inside a<space/><link><target>transformer</target></link>, or the feedback behaviour that happens close to the coil of a<space/><link><target>metal detector</target></link>. Typically, near-fields have a powerful effect on their own sources, causing an increased load (decreased<space/><link><target>electrical reactance</target></link>) in the source or transmitter, whenever energy is withdrawn from the EM field by a receiver. Otherwise, these fields do not propagate freely out into space, carrying their energy away without distance-limit, but rather oscillate, returning their energy to the transmitter if it is not received by a receiver.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By contrast, the EM far-field is composed of<space/><italics>radiation</italics><space/>that is free of the transmitter in the sense that (unlike the case in an electrical transformer) the transmitter requires the same power to send these changes in the fields out, whether the signal is immediately picked up or not. This distant part of the electromagnetic field<space/><italics>is</italics><space/>&quot;electromagnetic radiation&quot; (also called the far-field). The far-fields propagate (radiate) without allowing the transmitter to affect them. This causes them to be independent in the sense that their existence and their energy, after they have left the transmitter, is completely independent of both transmitter and receiver. Because such waves conserve the amount of energy they transmit through any spherical boundary surface drawn around their source, and because such surfaces have an area that is defined by the square of the distance from the source, the power of EM radiation always varies according to an<space/><link><target>inverse-square law</target></link>. This is in contrast to dipole parts of the EM field close to the source (the near-field), which varies in power according to an inverse cube power law, and thus does<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>transport a conserved amount of energy over distances, but instead fades with distance, with its energy (as noted) rapidly returning to the transmitter or absorbed by a nearby receiver (such as a transformer secondary coil).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The far-field (EMR) depends on a different mechanism for its production than the near-field, and upon different terms in Maxwells equations. Whereas the magnetic part of the near-field is due to currents in the source, the magnetic field in EMR is due only to the local change in the electric field. In a similar way, while the electric field in the near-field is due directly to the charges and charge-separation in the source, the electric field in EMR is due to a change in the local magnetic field. Both processes for producing electric and magnetic EMR fields have a different dependence on distance than do near-field dipole electric and magnetic fields. That is why the EMR type of EM field becomes dominant in power far from sources. The term far from sources refers to how far from the source (moving at the speed of light) any portion of the outward-moving EM field is located, by the time that source currents are changed by the varying source potential, and the source has therefore begun to generate an outwardly moving EM field of a different phase.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A more compact view of EMR is that the far-field that composes EMR is generally that part of the EM field that has traveled sufficient distance from the source, that it has become completely disconnected from any feedback to the charges and currents that were originally responsible for it. Now independent of the source charges, the EM field, as it moves farther away, is dependent only upon the accelerations of the charges that produced it. It no longer has a strong connection to the direct fields of the charges, or to the velocity of the charges (currents).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>LinardWiechert potential</target></link><space/>formulation of the electric and magnetic fields due to motion of a single particle (according to Maxwell's equations), the terms associated with acceleration of the particle are those that are responsible for the part of the field that is regarded as electromagnetic radiation. By contrast, the term associated with the changing static electric field of the particle and the magnetic term that results from the particle's uniform velocity, are both associated with the electromagnetic near-field, and do not comprise EM radiation.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Properties</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Electromagneticwave3Dfromside.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>Electromagnetic waves can be imagined as a self-propagating transverse oscillating wave of electric and magnetic fields. This 3D animation shows a plane linearly polarized wave propagating from left to right. Note that the electric and magnetic fields in such a wave are in-phase with each other, reaching minima and maxima together</part></link><link><target>File:Electromagneticwave3D.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>An alternate view of the wave shown above.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>physics</target></link><space/>of electromagnetic radiation is<space/><link><target>electrodynamics</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Electromagnetism</target></link><space/>is the physical phenomenon associated with the theory of electrodynamics. Electric and magnetic fields obey the properties of<space/><link><target>superposition principle</target><part>superposition</part></link>. Thus, a field due to any particular particle or time-varying electric or magnetic field contributes to the fields present in the same space due to other causes. Further, as they are<space/><link><target>Vector (geometric)</target><part>vector</part></link><space/>fields, all magnetic and electric field vectors add together according to<space/><link><target>vector addition</target></link>. For example, in optics two or more coherent lightwaves may interact and by constructive or destructive interference yield a resultant irradiance deviating from the sum of the component irradiances of the individual lightwaves.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Since light is an oscillation it is not affected by travelling through static electric or magnetic fields in a linear medium such as a vacuum. However, in nonlinear media, such as some<space/><link><target>crystal</target><trail>s</trail></link>, interactions can occur between light and static electric and magnetic fields these interactions include the<space/><link><target>Faraday effect</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Kerr effect</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>refraction</target></link>, a wave crossing from one medium to another of different<space/><link><target>density</target></link><space/>alters its<space/><link><target>Velocity</target><part>speed and direction</part></link><space/>upon entering the new medium. The ratio of the refractive indices of the media determines the degree of refraction, and is summarized by<space/><link><target>Snell's law</target></link>. Light of composite wavelengths (natural sunlight) disperses into a visible<space/><link><target>electromagnetic spectrum</target><part>spectrum</part></link><space/>passing through a prism, because of the wavelength-dependent<space/><link><target>refractive index</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>prism</target></link><space/>material (<link><target>Dispersion (optics)</target><part>dispersion</part></link>); that is, each component wave within the composite light is bent a different amount.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>EM radiation exhibits both wave properties and<space/><link><target>Subatomic particle</target><part>particle</part></link><space/>properties at the same time (see<space/><link><target>wave-particle duality</target></link>). Both wave and particle characteristics have been confirmed in many experiments. Wave characteristics are more apparent when EM radiation is measured over relatively large timescales and over large distances while particle characteristics are more evident when measuring small timescales and distances. For example, when electromagnetic radiation is absorbed by matter, particle-like properties will be more obvious when the average number of photons in the cube of the relevant wavelength is much smaller than 1. It is not too difficult to experimentally observe non-uniform deposition of energy when light is absorbed, however this alone is not evidence of &quot;particulate&quot; behavior. Rather, it reflects the quantum nature of<space/><italics>matter</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.qo.phy.auckland.ac.nz/talks/photoelectric.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Einstein and the Photoelectric Effect<space/></arg><arg name="first">H. J.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Carmichael<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Quantum Optics Theory Group, University of Auckland<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 December 2009</arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Demonstrating that the light itself is quantized, not merely its interaction with matter, is a more subtle affair.</paragraph><paragraph>Some experiments display both the wave and particle natures of electromagnetic waves, such as the self-interference of a single<space/><link><target>photon</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.1119/1.1737397</arg><arg name="url">http://people.whitman.edu/~beckmk/QM/grangier/Thorn_ajp.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Observing the quantum behavior of light in an undergraduate laboratory</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="last1">Thorn</arg><arg name="first1">J. J.</arg><arg name="last2">Neel</arg><arg name="first2">M. S.</arg><arg name="last3">Donato</arg><arg name="first3">V. W.</arg><arg name="last4">Bergreen</arg><arg name="first4">G. S.</arg><arg name="last5">Davies</arg><arg name="first5">R. E.</arg><arg name="last6">Beck</arg><arg name="first6">M.</arg><arg name="journal">American Journal of Physics</arg><arg name="volume">72</arg><arg name="issue">9</arg><arg name="pages">1210</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2004AmJPh..72.1210T<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>When a single photon is sent through an<space/><link><target>interferometer</target></link>, it passes through both paths, interfering with itself, as waves do, yet is detected by a<space/><link><target>photomultiplier</target></link><space/>or other sensitive detector only once.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>Quantum mechanics</target><part>quantum theory</part></link><space/>of the interaction between electromagnetic radiation and matter such as electrons is described by the theory of<space/><link><target>quantum electrodynamics</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Wave model</heading><paragraph>Electromagnetic radiation is a<space/><link><target>transverse wave</target></link>, meaning that its oscillations are perpendicular to the direction of energy transfer and travel. The electric and magnetic parts of the field stand in a fixed ratio of strengths in order to satisfy the two<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target><part>Maxwell equations</part></link><space/>that specify how one is produced from the other. These<space/><bold>E</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>B</bold><space/>fields are also in phase, with both reaching maxima and minima at the same points in space (see illustrations). A common misconception is that the<space/><bold>E</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>B</bold><space/>fields in electromagnetic radiation are out of phase because a change in one produces the other, and this would produce a phase difference between them as sinusoidal functions (as indeed happens in<space/><link><target>electromagnetic induction</target></link>, and in the<space/><link><target>near and far field</target><part>near-field</part></link><space/>close to antennas). However, in the far-field EM radiation which is described by the two source-free Maxwell<space/><link><target>curl (mathematics)</target><part>curl operator</part></link><space/>equations, a more correct description is that a time-change in one type of field is proportional to a space-change in the other. These derivatives require that the<space/><bold>E</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>B</bold><space/>fields in EMR are in-phase (see math section below).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An important aspect of light's nature is its<space/><link><target>frequency</target></link>. The frequency of a wave is its rate of oscillation and is measured in<space/><link><target>hertz</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>SI</target></link><space/>unit of frequency, where one hertz is equal to one oscillation per<space/><link><target>second</target></link>. Light usually has multiple frequencies that sum to form the resultant wave. Different frequencies undergo different angles of refraction, a phenomenon known as<space/><link><target>Dispersion relation</target><part>dispersion</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A wave consists of successive troughs and crests, and the distance between two adjacent crests or troughs is called the<space/><link><target>wavelength</target></link>. Waves of the electromagnetic spectrum vary in size, from very long radio waves the size of buildings to very short gamma rays smaller than atom nuclei. Frequency is inversely proportional to wavelength, according to the equation:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\displaystyle v=f\lambda</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><italics>v</italics><space/>is the speed of the wave (<italics><link><target>speed of light</target><part>c</part></link></italics><space/>in a vacuum, or less in other media),<space/><italics>f</italics><space/>is the frequency and is the wavelength. As waves cross boundaries between different media, their speeds change but their frequencies remain constant.</paragraph><paragraph>Electromagnetic waves in free space must be solutions of Maxwell's<space/><link><target>electromagnetic wave equation</target></link>. Two main classes of solutions are known, namely plane waves and spherical waves. The plane waves may be viewed as the limiting case of spherical waves at a very large (ideally infinite) distance from the source. Both types of waves can have a waveform which is an arbitrary time function (so long as it is sufficiently differentiable to conform to the wave equation). As with any time function, this can be decomposed by means of<space/><link><target>Fourier analysis</target></link><space/>into its<space/><link><target>frequency spectrum</target></link>, or individual sinusoidal components, each of which contains a single frequency, amplitude and phase. Such a component wave is said to be<space/><italics>monochromatic</italics>. A monochromatic electromagnetic wave can be characterized by its frequency or wavelength, its peak amplitude, its phase relative to some reference phase, its direction of propagation and its polarization.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Interference (wave propagation)</target><part>Interference</part></link><space/>is the superposition of two or more waves resulting in a new wave pattern. If the fields have components in the same direction, they constructively interfere, while opposite directions cause destructive<space/><link><target>interference</target></link>. An example of interference caused by EMR is<space/><link><target>electromagnetic interference</target></link><space/>(EMI) or as it is more commonly known as,<space/><link><target>Radio frequency interference</target><part>radio-frequency interference</part></link><space/>(RFI).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The energy in electromagnetic waves is sometimes called<space/><link><target>radiant energy</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Particle model and quantum theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Quantization (physics)</arg><arg>Quantum optics</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An anomaly arose in the late 19th century involving a contradiction between the wave theory of light and measurements of the electromagnetic spectra that were being emitted by thermal radiators known as<space/><link><target>black body</target><part>black bodies</part></link>. Physicists struggled with this problem, which later became known as the<space/><link><target>ultraviolet catastrophe</target></link>, unsuccessfully for many years. In 1900,<space/><link><target>Max Planck</target></link><space/>developed a new theory of<space/><link><target>Planck's law of black-body radiation</target><part>black-body radiation</part></link><space/>that explained the observed spectrum. Planck's theory was based on the idea that black bodies emit light (and other electromagnetic radiation) only as discrete bundles or packets of<space/><link><target>energy</target></link>. These packets were called<space/><link><target>quantum</target><part>quanta</part></link>. Later,<space/><link><target>Albert Einstein</target></link><space/>proposed that light quanta be regarded as real particles. Later the particle of light was given the name<space/><link><target>photon</target></link>, to correspond with other particles being described around this time, such as the<space/><link><target>electron</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>proton</target></link>. A photon has an energy,<space/><italics>E</italics>, proportional to its frequency,<space/><italics>f</italics>, by</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>E = hf = \frac{hc}{\lambda} \,\!<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><italics>h</italics><space/>is<space/><link><target>Planck's constant</target></link>,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\lambda</extension><space/>is the wavelength and<space/><italics>c</italics><space/>is the<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link>. This is sometimes known as the<space/><link><target>PlanckEinstein equation</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Physical Chemistry
<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Paul M. S. Monk
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Wiley and Sons
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-471-49180-4
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>435
<space/></arg><arg name="url">
<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In quantum theory (see<space/><link><target>first quantization</target></link>) the energy of the photons is thus directly proportional to the frequency of the EMR wave.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Weinberg<space/></arg><arg name="first">S.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Steven Weinberg
<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Quantum Theory of Fields
<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Cambridge University Press]]
<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-55001-7
<space/></arg><arg name="pages">15–17
<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Likewise, the momentum<space/><italics>p</italics><space/>of a photon is also proportional to its frequency and inversely proportional to its wavelength:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>p = { E \over c } = { hf \over c } = { h \over \lambda }.<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The source of Einstein's proposal that light was composed of particles (or could act as particles in some circumstances) was an experimental anomaly not explained by the wave theory: the<space/><link><target>photoelectric effect</target></link>, in which light striking a metal surface ejected electrons from the surface, causing an<space/><link><target>electric current</target></link><space/>to flow across an applied<space/><link><target>voltage</target></link>. Experimental measurements demonstrated that the energy of individual ejected electrons was proportional to the<space/><italics><link><target>frequency</target></link></italics>, rather than the<space/><italics><link><target>intensity (physics)</target><part>intensity</part></link></italics>, of the light. Furthermore, below a certain minimum frequency, which depended on the particular metal, no current would flow regardless of the intensity. These observations appeared to contradict the wave theory, and for years physicists tried in vain to find an explanation. In 1905, Einstein explained this puzzle by resurrecting the particle theory of light to explain the observed effect. Because of the preponderance of evidence in favor of the wave theory, however, Einstein's ideas were met initially with great skepticism among established physicists. Eventually Einstein's explanation was accepted as new particle-like behavior of light was observed, such as the<space/><link><target>Compton effect</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As a photon is absorbed by an<space/><link><target>atom</target></link>, it<space/><link><target>Excited state</target><part>excites</part></link><space/>the atom, elevating an<space/><link><target>electron</target></link><space/>to a higher<space/><link><target>energy level</target></link><space/>(one that is on average farther from the nucleus). When an electron in an excited molecule or atom descends to a lower energy level, it emits a photon of light at a frequency corresponding to the energy difference. Since the energy levels of electrons in atoms are discrete, each element and each molecule emits and absorbs its own characteristic frequencies. Immediate photon emission is called<space/><link><target>fluorescence</target></link>, a type of<space/><link><target>photoluminescence</target></link>. An example is visible light emitted from fluorescent paints, in response to ultraviolet (<link><target>blacklight</target></link>). Many other fluorescent emissions are known in spectral bands other than visible light. Delayed emission is called<space/><link><target>phosphorescence</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Waveparticle duality</heading><paragraph>The modern theory that explains the nature of light includes the notion of<space/><link><target>waveparticle duality</target></link>. More generally, the theory states that everything has both a particle nature and a wave nature, and various experiments can be done to bring out one or the other. The particle nature is more easily discerned using an object with a large mass. A bold proposition by<space/><link><target>Louis de Broglie</target></link><space/>in 1924 led the scientific community to realize that<space/><link><target>electrons</target></link><space/>also exhibited waveparticle duality.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Wave and particle effects of electromagnetic radiation</heading><paragraph>Together, wave and particle effects fully explain the emission and absorption spectra of EM radiation. The matter-composition of the medium through which the light travels determines the nature of the absorption and emission spectrum. These bands correspond to the allowed energy levels in the atoms. Dark bands in the<space/><link><target>absorption spectroscopy</target><part>absorption spectrum</part></link><space/>are due to the atoms in an intervening medium between source and observer. The atoms absorb certain frequencies of the light between emitter and detector/eye, then emit them in all directions. A dark band appears to the detector, due to the radiation scattered out of the beam. For instance, dark bands in the light emitted by a distant<space/><link><target>star</target></link><space/>are due to the atoms in the star's atmosphere. A similar phenomenon occurs for<space/><link><target>Emission (electromagnetic radiation)</target><part>emission</part></link>, which is seen when an emitting gas glows due to excitation of the atoms from any mechanism, including heat. As electrons descend to lower energy levels, a spectrum is emitted that represents the jumps between the energy levels of the electrons, but lines are seen because again emission happens only at particular energies after excitation. An example is the<space/><link><target>Emission (electromagnetic radiation)</target><part>emission</part></link><space/>spectrum of<space/><link><target>nebula</target><trail>e</trail></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><space/>Rapidly moving electrons are most sharply accelerated when they encounter a region of force, so they are responsible for producing much of the highest frequency electromagnetic radiation observed in nature.</paragraph><paragraph>These phenomena can aid various chemical determinations for the composition of gases lit from behind (absorption spectra) and for glowing gases (emission spectra). Spectroscopy (for example) determines what<space/><link><target>chemical element</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>comprise a particular star. Spectroscopy is also used in the determination of the distance of a star, using the<space/><link><target>red shift</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Propagation speed</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Speed of light</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Any electric charge that accelerates, or any changing magnetic field, produces electromagnetic radiation. Electromagnetic information about the charge travels at the speed of light. Accurate treatment thus incorporates a concept known as<space/><link><target>retarded time</target></link>, which adds to the expressions for the electrodynamic<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target></link>. These extra terms are responsible for electromagnetic radiation.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When any wire (or other conducting object such as an<space/><link><target>antenna (electronics)</target><part>antenna</part></link>) conducts<space/><link><target>alternating current</target></link>, electromagnetic radiation is propagated at the same frequency as the current. In many such situations it is possible to identify an electrical dipole moment that arises from separation of charges due to the exciting electrical potential, and this dipole moment oscillates in time, as the charges move back and forth. This oscillation at a given frequency gives rise to changing electric and magnetic fields, which then set the electromagnetic radiation in motion.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At the quantum level, electromagnetic radiation is produced when the wavepacket of a charged particle oscillates or otherwise accelerates. Charged particles in a<space/><link><target>stationary state</target></link><space/>do not move, but a superposition of such states may result in a transition state that has an<space/><link><target>electric dipole moment</target></link><space/>that oscillates in time. This oscillating dipole moment is responsible for the phenomenon of radiative transition between quantum states of a charged particle. Such states occur (for example) in atoms when photons are radiated as the atom shifts from one stationary state to another.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As a wave, light is characterized by a velocity (the<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link>),<space/><link><target>wavelength</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>frequency</target></link>. As particles, light is a stream of<space/><link><target>photon</target><part>photons.</part></link><space/>Each has an energy related to the frequency of the wave given by<space/><link><target>Max Planck</target><part>Planck's</part></link><space/>relation<space/><italics>E = hf</italics>, where<space/><italics>E</italics><space/>is the energy of the photon,<space/><italics>h</italics><space/>= 6.626 10<xhtml:sup>34</xhtml:sup><space/>Js is<space/><link><target>Planck's constant</target></link>, and<space/><italics>f</italics><space/>is the frequency of the wave.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>One rule is obeyed regardless of circumstances: EM radiation in a vacuum travels at the<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link>,<space/><italics>relative to the observer</italics>, regardless of the observer's velocity. (This observation led to Einstein's development of the theory of<space/><link><target>special relativity</target></link>.)<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In a medium (other than vacuum),<space/><link><target>velocity of propagation</target><part>velocity factor</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>refractive index</target></link><space/>are considered, depending on frequency and application. Both of these are ratios of the speed in a medium to speed in a vacuum.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Special theory of relativity</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Special theory of relativity</arg></template>By the late nineteenth century, various experimental anomalies could not be explained by the simple wave theory. One of these anomalies involved a controversy over the speed of light. The speed of light and other EMR predicted by Maxwell's equations did not appear unless the equations were modified in a way first suggested by<space/><link><target>George Francis FitzGerald</target><part>FitzGerald</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hendrik Lorentz</target><part>Lorentz</part></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>history of special relativity</target></link>), or else otherwise that speed would depend on the speed of observer relative to the &quot;medium&quot; (called<space/><link><target>luminiferous aether</target></link>) which supposedly &quot;carried&quot; the electromagnetic wave (in a manner analogous to the way air carries sound waves). Experiments failed to find any observer effect. In 1905, Einstein proposed that space and time appeared to be velocity-changeable entities for light propagation and all other processes and laws. These changes accounted for the constancy of the speed of light and all electromagnetic radiation, from the viewpoints of all observerseven those in relative motion.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History of discovery</heading><paragraph>Electromagnetic radiation of wavelengths other than those of visible light were discovered in the early 19th century. The discovery of<space/><link><target>infrared</target></link><space/>radiation is ascribed to astronomer<space/><link><target>William Herschel</target></link>, who published his results in 1800 before the<space/><link><target>Royal Society of London</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HerschelRSIR">Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, Vol. 90 (1800), pp. 284-292, http://www.jstor.org/stable/info/107057</extension><space/>Herschel used a glass<space/><link><target>Triangular prism (optics)</target><part>prism</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>refract</target></link><space/>light from the<space/><link><target>Sun</target></link><space/>and detected invisible rays that caused heating beyond the<space/><link><target>red</target></link><space/>part of the spectrum, through an increase in the temperature recorded with a<space/><link><target>thermometer</target></link>. These &quot;calorific rays&quot; were later termed infrared.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1801, German physicist<space/><link><target>Johann Wilhelm Ritter</target></link><space/>discovered<space/><link><target>ultraviolet</target></link><space/>in an experiment similar to Hershel's, using sunlight and a glass prism. Ritter noted that invisible rays near the violet edge of a solar spectrum dispersed by a triangular prism darkened<space/><link><target>silver chloride</target></link><space/>preparations more quickly than did the nearby violet light. Ritter's experiments were an early precursor to what would become photography. Ritter noted that the ultraviolet rays (which at first were called &quot;chemical rays&quot;) were capable of causing chemical reactions.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1862-4<space/><link><target>James Clerk Maxwell</target></link><space/>developed equations for the electromagnetic field which suggested that waves in the field would travel with a speed that was very close to the known speed of light. Maxwell therefore suggested that visible light (as well as invisible infrared and ultraviolet rays by inference) all consisted of propagating disturbances (or radiation) in the electromagnetic field. Radio waves were first produced deliberately by<space/><link><target>Heinrich Hertz</target></link><space/>in 1887, using electrical circuits calculated to produce oscillations at a much lower frequency than that of visible light, following recipes for producing oscillating charges and currents suggested by Maxwell's equations. Hertz also developed ways to detect these waves, and produced and characterized what were later termed<space/><link><target>radio wave</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>microwave</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeans"><link><target>James Jeans</target></link><space/>(1947)<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/growthofphysical029068mbp#page/n11/mode/2up'>The Growth of Physical Science</link>, link from<space/><link><target>Internet Archive</target></link></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>286,7</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Wilhelm Rntgen</target></link><space/>discovered and named<space/><link><target>X-rays</target></link>. After experimenting with high voltages applied to an evaccuated tube on 8 November 1895, he noticed a fluorescence on a nearby plate of coated glass. In one month, he discovered X-rays' main properties.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeans"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>307</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The last portion of the EM spectrum to be discovered was associated with<space/><link><target>radioactivity</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Henri Becquerel</target></link><space/>found that<space/><link><target>uranium</target></link><space/>salts caused fogging of an unexposed photographic plate through a covering paper in a manner similar to X-rays, and<space/><link><target>Marie Curie</target></link><space/>discovered that only certain elements gave off these rays of energy, soon discovering the intense radiation of<space/><link><target>radium</target></link>. The radiation from pitchblende was differentiated into alpha rays (<link><target>alpha particle</target><trail>s</trail></link>) and beta rays (<link><target>beta particle</target><trail>s</trail></link>) by<space/><link><target>Ernest Rutherford</target></link><space/>through simple experimentation in 1899, but these proved to be charged particulate types of radiation. However, in 1900 the French scientist<space/><link><target>Paul Villard</target></link><space/>discovered a third neutrally charged and especially penetrating type of radiation from radium, and after he described it, Rutherford realized it must be yet a third type of radiation, which in 1903 Rutherford named<space/><link><target>gamma ray</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In 1910 British physicist<space/><link><target>William Henry Bragg</target></link><space/>demonstrated that gamma rays are electromagnetic radiation, not particles, and in 1914 Rutherford and<space/><link><target>Edward Andrade</target></link><space/>measured their wavelengths, finding that they were similar to X-rays but with shorter wavelengths and higher frequency, although a 'cross-over' between X and gamma rays makes it possible to have X-rays with a higher energy (and hence shorter wavelength) than gamma rays and vice versa. The origin of the ray differentiates them, gamma rays tend to be a natural phenomena originating from the unstable nucleus of an atom and X-rays are electrically generated (and hence man-made) unless they are as a result of<space/><link><target>bremsstrahlung</target></link><space/>X-radiation caused by the interaction of fast moving particles (such as beta particles) colliding with certain materials, usually of higher atomic numbers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jeans"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>308,9</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Electromagnetic spectrum</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:EM spectrum.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>490px</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Electromagnetic spectrum</target></link><space/>with visible light highlighted</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Electromagnetic spectrum</arg></template>[[File:Light spectrum.svg|right|frame|<bold>Legend:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>=<space/><link><target>Gamma ray</target><trail>s</trail></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>HX = Hard<space/><link><target>X-ray</target><trail>s</trail></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>SX = Soft X-Rays<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>EUV = Extreme-<link><target>ultraviolet</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>NUV = Near-ultraviolet<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Visible light</target></link><space/>(colored bands)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>NIR = Near-<link><target>infrared</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>MIR = Mid-infrared<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>FIR = Far-infrared<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>EHF =<space/><link><target>Extremely high frequency</target></link><space/>(microwaves)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>SHF =<space/><link><target>Super-high frequency</target></link><space/>(microwaves)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>UHF =<space/><link><target>Ultrahigh frequency</target></link><space/>(radio waves)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>VHF =<space/><link><target>Very high frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>HF =<space/><link><target>High frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>MF =<space/><link><target>Medium frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>LF =<space/><link><target>Low frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>VLF =<space/><link><target>Very low frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>VF =<space/><link><target>Voice frequency</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>ULF =<space/><link><target>Ultra-low frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>SLF =<space/><link><target>Super-low frequency</target></link><space/>(radio)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>ELF =<space/><link><target>Extremely low frequency</target></link>(radio)]]</paragraph><paragraph>EM radiation (the designation 'radiation' excludes static electric and magnetic and<space/><link><target>near and far field</target><part>near fields</part></link>) is classified by wavelength into<space/><link><target>radio</target></link>,<space/><link><target>microwave</target></link>,<space/><link><target>infrared</target></link>,<space/><link><target>visible spectrum</target><part>visible</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ultraviolet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>X-ray</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gamma rays</target></link>. Arbitrary electromagnetic waves can be expressed by<space/><link><target>Fourier analysis</target></link><space/>in terms of<space/><link><target>sinusoidal</target></link><space/>monochromatic waves, which in turn can each be classified into these regions of the EMR spectrum.</paragraph><paragraph>For certain classes of EM waves, the waveform is most usefully treated as<space/><italics>random</italics>, and then spectral analysis must be done by slightly different mathematical techniques appropriate to random or<space/><link><target>stochastic process</target><trail>es</trail></link>. In such cases, the individual frequency components are represented in terms of their<space/><italics>power</italics><space/>content, and the phase information is not preserved. Such a representation is called the<space/><link><target>power spectral density</target></link><space/>of the random process. Random electromagnetic radiation requiring this kind of analysis is, for example, encountered in the interior of stars, and in certain other very wideband forms of radiation such as the<space/><link><target>Zero point field</target><part>Zero point wave field</part></link><space/>of the electromagnetic vacuum.</paragraph><paragraph>The behavior of EM radiation depends on its frequency. Lower frequencies have longer wavelengths, and higher frequencies have shorter wavelengths, and are associated with photons of higher energy. There is no fundamental limit known to these wavelengths or energies, at either end of the spectrum, although photons with energies near the<space/><link><target>Planck energy</target></link><space/>or exceeding it (far too high to have ever been observed) will require new physical theories to describe.</paragraph><paragraph>Soundwaves are not electromagnetic radiation<bold>.</bold><space/>At the lower end of the electromagnetic spectrum, about 20&amp;nbsp;Hz to about 20&amp;nbsp;kHz, are frequencies that might be considered in the audio range. However, electromagnetic waves cannot be directly perceived by human<space/><link><target>ears</target></link>. Sound waves are instead the oscillating compression of molecules. To be heard, electromagnetic radiation must be converted to pressure waves of the fluid in which the<space/><link><target>ear</target></link><space/>is located (whether the fluid is air, water or something else).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Interactions as a function of frequency</heading><paragraph>When EM radiation interacts with matter, its behavior changes qualitatively as its frequency changes.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Radio and microwave</heading><paragraph>At radio and microwave frequencies, EMR interacts with matter largely as a bulk collection of charges which are spread out over large numbers of affected atoms. In<space/><link><target>electrical conductor</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such induced bulk movement of charges (<link><target>electric currents</target></link>) results in absorption of the EMR, or else separations of charges that cause generation of new EMR (effective reflection of the EMR). An example is absorption or emission of radio waves by antennas, or absorption of microwaves by water or other molecules with an electric dipole moment, as for example inside a<space/><link><target>microwave oven</target></link>. These interactions produce either electric currents or heat, or both. Infrared EMR interacts with dipoles present in single molecules, which change as atoms vibrate at the ends of a single chemical bond. For this reason, infrared is reflected by metals (as is most EMR into the ultraviolet) but is absorbed by a wide range of substances, causing them to increase in temperature as the vibrations dissipate as<space/><link><target>heat</target></link>. In the same process, bulk substances radiate in the infrared spontaneously (see<space/><link><target>thermal radiation</target></link><space/>section below).</paragraph><heading level='4'>Visible light</heading><paragraph>As frequency increases into the visible range, photons of EMR have enough energy to change the bond structure of some individual molecules. It is not a coincidence that this happens in the &quot;visible range,&quot; as the<space/><link><target>Visual system</target><part>mechanism of vision</part></link><space/>involves the change in bonding of a single molecule (<link><target>retinal</target></link>) which absorbs light in the<space/><link><target>rhodopsin</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>retina</target></link><space/>of the human eye.<space/><link><target>Photosynthesis</target></link><space/>becomes possible in this range as well, for similar reasons, as a single molecule of<space/><link><target>chlorophyll</target></link><space/>is excited by a single photon. Animals that detect infrared make use of small packets of water that change temperature, in an essentially thermal process that involves many photons (see<space/><link><target>infrared sensing in snakes</target></link>). For this reason, infrared, microwaves and radio waves are thought to damage molecules and biological tissue only by bulk heating, not excitation from single photons of the radiation.</paragraph><paragraph>Visible light is able to affect a few molecules with single photons, but usually not in a permanent or damaging way, in the absence of power high enough to increase temperature to damaging levels. However, in plant tissues that conduct photosynthesis,<space/><link><target>carotenoids</target></link><space/>act to quench electronically excited chlorophyll produced by visible light in a process called<space/><link><target>non-photochemical quenching</target></link>, in order to prevent reactions that would otherwise interfere with photosynthesis at high light levels. Limited evidence indicate that some<space/><link><target>reactive oxygen species</target></link><space/>are created by visible light in skin, and that these may have some role in photoaging, in the same manner as<space/><link><target>ultraviolet A</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r1"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Liebel<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>F.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Kaur<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>S.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Ruvolo<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>E.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Kollias<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>N.<space/></arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Southall<space/></arg><arg name="first5"><space/>M. D.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Irradiation of Skin with Visible Light Induces Reactive Oxygen Species and Matrix-Degrading Enzymes<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1038/jid.2011.476<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Investigative Dermatology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>132<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>7<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1901–1907<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>22318388<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Ultraviolet</heading><paragraph>As frequency increases into the ultraviolet, photons now carry enough energy (about three<space/><link><target>electron volt</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or more) to excite certain doubly bonded molecules into permanent chemical rearrangement. In<space/><link><target>DNA</target></link>, this causes lasting damage. DNA is also indirectly damaged by reactive oxygen species produced by ultraviolet A (UVA), which has energy too low to damage DNA directly. This is why ultraviolet at all wavelengths can damage DNA, and is capable of causing cancer, and (for<space/><link><target>UVB</target></link>) skin burns (sunburn) that are far worse than would be produced by simple heating (temperature increase) effects. This property of causing molecular damage that is out of proportion to heating effects, is characteristic of all EMR with frequencies at the visible light range and above. These properties of high-frequency EMR are due to quantum effects that permanently damage materials and tissues at the molecular level.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At the higher end of the ultraviolet range, the energy of photons becomes large enough to impart enough energy to electrons to cause them to be liberated from the atom, in a process called<space/><link><target>photoionisation</target></link>. The energy required for this is always larger than about 10<space/><link><target>electron volt</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(eV) corresponding with wavelengths smaller than 124&amp;nbsp;nm (some sources suggest a more realistic cutoff of 33 eV, which is the energy required to ionize water). This high end of the ultraviolet spectrum with energies in the approximate ionization range, is sometimes called &quot;extreme UV.&quot; Ionizing UV is strongly filtered by the Earth's atmosphere).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>X-rays and gamma rays</heading><paragraph>Electromagnetic radiation composed of photons that carry minimum-ionization energy, or more, (which includes the entire spectrum with shorter wavelengths), is therefore termed<space/><link><target>ionizing radiation</target></link>. (Many other kinds of ionizing radiation are made of non-EM particles). Electromagnetic-type ionizing radiation extends from the extreme ultraviolet to all higher frequencies and shorter wavelengths, which means that all<space/><link><target>X-rays</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gamma rays</target></link><space/>qualify. These are capable of the most severe types of molecular damage, which can happen in biology to any type of biomolecule, including mutation and cancer, and often at great depths below the skin, since the higher end of the X-ray spectrum, and all of the gamma ray spectrum, penetrate matter. This type of damage causes these types of radiation to be especially carefully monitored, due to their hazard, even at comparatively low-energies, to all living organisms.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Atmosphere and magnetosphere</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>ozone layer</arg><arg>shortwave radio</arg><arg>skywave</arg><arg>ionosphere</arg></template><link><target>File:Atmospheric electromagnetic opacity.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>500px</part><part>Rough plot of Earth's atmospheric absorption and scattering (or<space/><link><target>opacity (optics)</target><part>opacity</part></link>) of various<space/><link><target>wavelength</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of electromagnetic radiation</part></link>Most UV and X-rays are blocked by absorption first from molecular<space/><link><target>nitrogen</target></link>, and then (for wavelengths in the upper UV) from the electronic excitation of<space/><link><target>dioxygen</target></link><space/>and finally<space/><link><target>ozone</target></link><space/>at the mid-range of UV. Only 30% of the Sun's ultraviolet light reaches the ground, and almost all of this is well transmitted.</paragraph><paragraph>Visible light is well transmitted in air, as it is not energetic enough to excite nitrogen, oxygen, or ozone, but too energetic to excite molecular vibrational frequencies of water vapor.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Absorption bands in the infrared are due to modes of vibrational excitation in water vapor. However, at energies too low to excite water vapor, the atmosphere becomes transparent again, allowing free transmission of most microwave and radio waves.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, at radio wavelengths longer than 10 meters or so (about 30&amp;nbsp;MHz), the air in the lower atmosphere remains transparent to radio, but plasma in certain layers of the<space/><link><target>ionosphere</target></link><space/>begins to interact with radio waves (see<space/><link><target>skywave</target></link>). This property allows some longer wavelengths (100 meters or 3&amp;nbsp;MHz) to be reflected and results in<space/><link><target>shortwave radio</target></link><space/>beyond line-of-sight. However,<space/><link><target>Ionosphere#D layer</target><part>certain ionospheric effects</part></link><space/>begin to block incoming radiowaves from space, when their frequency is less than about 10&amp;nbsp;MHz (wavelength longer than about 30 meters).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Types and sources, classed by spectral band</heading><paragraph>See<space/><link><target>electromagnetic spectrum</target></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Radio waves</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Radio waves</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When radio waves impinge upon a<space/><link><target>Electrical conductor</target><part>conductor</part></link>, they couple to the conductor, travel along it and<space/><link><target>radio frequency induction</target><part>induce</part></link><space/>an electric current on the conductor surface by moving the electrons of the conducting material in correlated bunches of charge. Such effects can cover macroscopic distances in conductors (including as radio antennas), since the wavelength of radiowaves is long.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Microwaves</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Microwaves</arg></template>Microwaves are a form of electromagnetic radiation with wavelengths ranging from as long as one meter to as short as one millimeter; with frequencies between 300&amp;nbsp;MHz (0.3&amp;nbsp;GHz) and 300&amp;nbsp;GHz.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Infrared</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Infrared</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Visible light</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Light</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Natural sources produce EM radiation across the spectrum. EM radiation with a<space/><link><target>wavelength</target></link><space/>between approximately 400<space/><link><target>nanometre</target><part>nm</part></link><space/>and 700&amp;nbsp;nm is directly detected by the<space/><link><target>human eye</target></link><space/>and perceived as visible<space/><link><target>light</target></link>. Other wavelengths, especially nearby infrared (longer than 700&amp;nbsp;nm) and ultraviolet (shorter than 400&amp;nbsp;nm) are also sometimes referred to as light.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ultraviolet</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Ultraviolet</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>X-rays</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>X-rays</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Gamma rays</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Gamma rays</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Thermal radiation and electromagnetic radiation as a form of heat</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Thermal radiation</arg><arg>Planck's law</arg></template>The basic structure of<space/><link><target>matter</target></link><space/>involves charged particles bound together. When electromagnetic radiation impinges on matter, it causes the charged particles to oscillate and gain energy. The ultimate fate of this energy depends on the context. It could be immediately re-radiated and appear as scattered, reflected, or transmitted radiation. It may get dissipated into other microscopic motions within the matter, coming to<space/><link><target>thermal equilibrium</target></link><space/>and manifesting itself as<space/><link><target>thermal energy</target></link><space/>in the material. With a few exceptions related to high-energy photons (such as<space/><link><target>fluorescence</target></link>,<space/><link><target>harmonic generation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>photochemical reaction</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the<space/><link><target>photovoltaic effect</target></link><space/>for ionizing radiations at far ultraviolet, X-ray and gamma radiation), absorbed electromagnetic radiation simply deposits its energy by<space/><link><target>heat</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>the material. This happens for infrared, microwave and radio wave radiation. Intense radio waves can thermally burn living tissue and can cook food. In addition to infrared<space/><link><target>laser</target><trail>s</trail></link>, sufficiently intense visible and ultraviolet lasers can easily set paper afire.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Ionizing radiation creates high-speed electrons in a material and breaks chemical bonds, but after these electrons collide many times with other atoms eventually most of the energy becomes thermal energy all in a tiny fraction of a second. This process makes ionizing radiation far more dangerous per unit of energy than non-ionizing radiation. This caveat also applies to UV, even though almost all of it is not ionizing, because UV can damage molecules due to electronic excitation, which is far greater per unit energy than heating effects.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Infrared radiation in the spectral distribution of a<space/><link><target>black body</target></link><space/>is usually considered a form of heat, since it has an equivalent temperature and is associated with an entropy change per unit of thermal energy. However, &quot;heat&quot; is a technical term in physics and thermodynamics and is often confused with thermal energy. Any type of electromagnetic energy can be transformed into thermal energy in interaction with matter. Thus,<space/><italics>any</italics><space/>electromagnetic radiation can &quot;heat&quot; (in the sense of increase the<space/><link><target>thermal energy</target></link><space/>termperature of) a material, when it is absorbed.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The inverse or time-reversed process of absorption is thermal radiation. Much of the thermal energy in matter consists of random motion of charged particles, and this energy can be radiated away from the matter. The resulting radiation may subsequently be absorbed by another piece of matter, with the deposited energy heating the material.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The electromagnetic radiation in an opaque cavity at thermal equilibrium is effectively a form of thermal energy, having maximum<space/><link><target>entropy</target><part>radiation entropy</part></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biological effects</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Electromagnetic radiation and health</arg><arg>Mobile phone radiation and health</arg></template><link><target>Bioelectromagnetics</target></link><space/>is the study of the interactions and effects of EM radiation on living organisms. The effects of electromagnetic radiation upon living cells, including those in humans, depends upon the radiation's power and frequency. For low-frequency radiation (radio waves to visible light) the best-understood effects are those due to radiation power alone, acting through heating when radiation is absorbed. For these thermal effects, frequency is important only as it affects penetration into the organism (for example, microwaves penetrate better than infrared). Initially, it was believed that low frequency fields that were too weak to cause significant heating could not possibly have any biological effect.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Binhi"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite this opinion among researchers, evidence has accumulated that supports the existence of complex biological effects of weaker<space/><italics>non-thermal</italics><space/>electromagnetic fields, (including weak ELF magnetic fields, although the latter does not strictly qualify as EM radiation<extension extension_name='ref' name="Binhi"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Delgado<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J. M.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Leal<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>J.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Monteagudo<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>J. L.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Gracia<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>M. G.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Embryological changes induced by weak, extremely low frequency electromagnetic fields<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of anatomy<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>134<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>Pt 3<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>533–551<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1982<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>7107514<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>1167891<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Harland<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J. D.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Liburdy<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>R. P.<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1002/(SICI)1521-186X(1997)18:8<555::AID-BEM4>3.0.CO;2-1<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Environmental magnetic fields inhibit the antiproliferative action of tamoxifen and melatonin in a human breast cancer cell line<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Bioelectromagnetics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>18<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>8<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>555–562<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>9383244<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension>), and modulated RF and microwave fields.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Aalto S, Haarala C, Brck A, Sipil H, Hmlinen H, Rinne JO 2006 88590"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Aalto<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>S.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Haarala<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>C.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Brück<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>A.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Sipilä<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>H.<space/></arg><arg name="last5"><space/>Hämäläinen<space/></arg><arg name="first5"><space/>H.<space/></arg><arg name="last6"><space/>Rinne<space/></arg><arg name="first6"><space/>J. O.<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1038/sj.jcbfm.9600279<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Mobile phone affects cerebral blood flow in humans<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Cerebral Blood Flow &#38; Metabolism<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>7<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>885–890<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>16495939<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1002/bem.2250110107<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Cleary<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>S. F.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Liu<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>L. M.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Merchant<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>R. E.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>In vitro lymphocyte proliferation induced by radio-frequency electromagnetic radiation under isothermal conditions<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Bioelectromagnetics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>11<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>47–56<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>2346507<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Ramchandani<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>P.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Prevalence of childhood psychiatric disorders may be underestimated<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Evidence-based mental health<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>7<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>59<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>15107355<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1136/ebmh.7.2.59<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Fundamental mechanisms of the interaction between biological material and electromagnetic fields at non-thermal levels are not fully understood.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Binhi"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Binhi</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Vladimir N</arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>Repiev, A & Edelev, M (translators from Russian)</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Magnetobiology: Underlying Physical Problems<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Academic Press</arg><arg name="location"><space/>San Diego</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1–16</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-12-100071-4</arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>49700531</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target></link><space/>has classified radio frequency electromagnetic radiation as<space/><link><target>List of IARC Group 2B carcinogens</target><part>Group 2B</part></link><space/>- possibly carcinogenic.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iarc.fr/en/media-centre/pr/2011/pdfs/pr208_E.pdf'>IARC classifies Radiofrequency Electromagnetic Fields as possibly carcinogenic to humans</link>. World Health Organization. 31 May 2011</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cbsnews.com/2100-503063_162-20068246.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">CBS News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Trouble with cell phone radiation standard</arg></template></extension><space/>This group contains possible carcinogens that have weaker evidence, at the same level as coffee and automobile exhaust. For example, epidemiological studies looking for a relationship between cell phone use and brain cancer development, have been largely inconclusive, save to demonstrate that the effect, if it exists, cannot be a large one.</paragraph><paragraph>At higher frequencies (visible and beyond), the effects of individual photons begin to become important, as these now have enough energy individually to directly or indirectly damage biological molecules.<extension extension_name='ref'>See PMID 22318388 for evidence of quantum damage from visible light via<space/><link><target>reactive oxygen species</target></link><space/>generated in skin. This happens also with UVA. With UVB, the damage to DNA becomes direct, with<space/><link><target>photochemistry</target><part>photochemical</part></link><space/>formation of<space/><link><target>pyrimidine dimers</target></link>.</extension><space/>All UV frequences have been classed as Group 1 carcinogens by the World Health Organization. Ultraviolet radiation from sun exposure is the primary cause of skin cancer.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Narayanan</arg><arg name="first">DL<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Saladi, RN<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Fox, JL</arg><arg name="title">Ultraviolet radiation and skin cancer</arg><arg name="journal">International Journal of Dermatology</arg><arg name="date">September 2010</arg><arg name="volume">49</arg><arg name="issue">9</arg><arg name="pages">978–86</arg><arg name="pmid">20883261</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1365-4632.2010.04474.x</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Review05"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Saladi</arg><arg name="first">RN</arg><arg name="author2">Persaud, AN</arg><arg name="title">The causes of skin cancer: a comprehensive review</arg><arg name="journal">Drugs of today (Barcelona, Spain : 1998)</arg><arg name="date">January 2005</arg><arg name="volume">41</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="pages">37–53</arg><arg name="pmid">15753968</arg><arg name="doi">10.1358/dot.2005.41.1.875777</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Thus, at UV frequencies and higher (and probably somewhat also in the visible range),<extension extension_name='ref' name="r1"></extension><space/>electromagnetic radiation does more damage to biological systems than simple heating predicts. This is most obvious in the &quot;far&quot; (or &quot;extreme&quot;) ultraviolet. UV, with X-ray and gamma radiation, are referred to as<space/><link><target>ionizing radiation</target></link><space/>due to the ability of photons of this radiation to produce<space/><link><target>ion</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>free radical</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in materials (including living tissue). Since such radiation can severely damage life at energy levels that produce little heating, it is considered far more dangerous (in terms of damage-produced per unit of energy, or power) than the rest of the electromagnetic spectrum.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Derivation from electromagnetic theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Electromagnetic wave equation</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Electromagnetic waves were predicted by the classical laws of<space/><link><target>electricity</target></link><space/>and magnetism, known as<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link>. Inspection of Maxwell's equations without sources (charges or currents) results in nontrivial solutions of changing electric and magnetic fields. Beginning with Maxwell's equations in<space/><link><target>vacuum</target><part>free space</part></link>:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} = 0 \qquad \qquad \qquad \ \ (1)</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \mathbf{E} = -\frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t} \qquad \qquad \ (2)</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \cdot \mathbf{B} = 0 \qquad \qquad \qquad \ \ (3)</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mu_0 \epsilon_0 \frac{\partial \mathbf{E}}{\partial t} \qquad \quad \ (4)</extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>where<list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla</extension><space/>is a vector differential operator (see<space/><link><target>Del</target></link>).</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>One solution,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E}=\mathbf{B}=\mathbf{0},</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>is trivial.</paragraph><paragraph>For a more useful solution, we utilize<space/><link><target>List of vector identities</target><part>vector identities</part></link>, which work for any vector, as follows:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \left( \nabla \times \mathbf{A} \right) = \nabla \left( \nabla \cdot \mathbf{A} \right) - \nabla^2 \mathbf{A}</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>The curl of equation (2):</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \left(\nabla \times \mathbf{E} \right) = \nabla \times \left(-\frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t} \right) \qquad \qquad \qquad \quad \ \ \ (5) \,</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Evaluating the left hand side:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\nabla \times \left(\nabla \times \mathbf{E} \right) = \nabla\left(\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} \right) - \nabla^2 \mathbf{E} = - \nabla^2 \mathbf{E} \qquad \ \ (6) \,</extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>simplifying the above by using equation (1).</listitem></list><paragraph>Evaluating the right hand side:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \left(-\frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t} \right) = -\frac{\partial}{\partial t} \left( \nabla \times \mathbf{B} \right) = -\mu_0 \epsilon_0 \frac{\partial^2 \mathbf{E}}{\partial t^2} \quad \ \ \ \ (7)</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Equations (6) and (7) are equal, so this results in a vector-valued<space/><link><target>differential equation</target></link><space/>for the electric field, namely</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><table cellpadding="2" style="border:2px solid #ccccff"><tablerow><tablecell><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla^2 \mathbf{E} = \mu_0 \epsilon_0 \frac{\partial^2 \mathbf{E}}{\partial t^2}</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table>Applying a similar pattern results in similar differential equation for the magnetic field:</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><table cellpadding="2" style="border:2px solid #ccccff"><tablerow><tablecell><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla^2 \mathbf{B} = \mu_0 \epsilon_0 \frac{\partial^2 \mathbf{B}}{\partial t^2}.</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table>These differential equations are equivalent to the<space/><link><target>wave equation</target></link>:</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla^2 f = \frac{1}{{c_0}^2} \frac{\partial^2 f}{\partial t^2} \,</extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>where<list type='ident'><listitem><italics>c</italics><xhtml:sub>0</xhtml:sub><space/>is the speed of the wave in free space and</listitem><listitem><italics>f</italics><space/>describes a displacement</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Or more simply:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Box f = 0</extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\Box</extension><space/>is<space/><link><target>d'Alembert operator</target><part>d'Alembertian</part></link>:<list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\Box = \nabla^2 - \frac{1}{{c_0}^2} \frac{\partial^2}{\partial t^2} = \frac{\partial^2}{\partial x^2} + \frac{\partial^2}{\partial y^2} + \frac{\partial^2}{\partial z^2} - \frac{1}{{c_0}^2} \frac{\partial^2}{\partial t^2} \ &lt;/math&gt;

In the case of the electric and magnetic fields, the speed is:

::&lt;math&gt;c_0 = \frac{1}{\sqrt{\mu_0 \epsilon_0}}&lt;/math&gt;

This is the [[speed of light]] in vacuum. Maxwell's equations unified the [[vacuum permittivity]] &lt;math&gt;\epsilon_0&lt;/math&gt;, the [[vacuum permeability]] &lt;math&gt;\mu_0&lt;/math&gt;, and the speed of light itself, ''c''&lt;sub&gt;0&lt;/sub&gt;. This relationship had been discovered by [[Wilhelm Eduard Weber]] and [[Rudolf Kohlrausch]] prior to the development of Maxwell's electrodynamics, however Maxwell was the first to produce a field theory consistent with waves traveling at the speed of light.

These are only two equations versus the original four, so more information pertains to these waves hidden within Maxwell's equations. A generic vector wave for the electric field.

:&lt;math&gt;\mathbf{E} = \mathbf{E}_0 f\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right)</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Here,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E}_0</extension><space/>is the constant amplitude,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>f</extension><space/>is any second differentiable function,<space/><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\hat{\mathbf{k}}</extension><space/>is a unit vector in the direction of propagation, and<space/><extension extension_name='math'><space/>{\mathbf{x}}<space/></extension>is a position vector.<space/><extension extension_name='math'>f\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right)</extension><space/>is a generic solution to the wave equation. In other words,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla^2 f\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right) = \frac{1}{{c_0}^2} \frac{\partial^2}{\partial t^2} f\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right),</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>for a generic wave traveling in the<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\hat{\mathbf{k}}</extension><space/>direction.</paragraph><paragraph>This form will satisfy the wave equation.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} = \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{E}_0 f'\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right) = 0</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E} \cdot \hat{\mathbf{k}} = 0</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The first of Maxwell's equations implies that the electric field is orthogonal to the direction the wave propagates.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \mathbf{E} = \hat{\mathbf{k}} \times \mathbf{E}_0 f'\left( \hat{\mathbf{k}} \cdot \mathbf{x} - c_0 t \right) = -\frac{\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t}</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{B} = \frac{1}{c_0} \hat{\mathbf{k}} \times \mathbf{E}</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The second of Maxwell's equations yields the magnetic field. The remaining equations will be satisfied by this choice of<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E},\mathbf{B}</extension>.</paragraph><paragraph>The electric and magnetic field waves in the far-field travel at the speed of light. They have a special restricted orientation and proportional magnitudes,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>E_0 = c_0 B_0</extension>, which can be seen immediately from the<space/><link><target>Poynting vector</target></link>. The electric field, magnetic field, and direction of wave propagation are all orthogonal, and the wave propagates in the same direction as<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E} \times \mathbf{B}</extension>. Also,<space/><bold>E</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>B</bold><space/>far-fields in free space, which as wave solutions depend primarily on these two Maxwell equations, are in-phase with each other. This is guaranteed since the generic wave solution is first order in both space and time, and the<space/><link><target>curl (mathematics)</target><part>curl operator</part></link><space/>on one side of these equations results in first-order spatial derivatives of the wave solution, while the time-derivative on the other side of the equations, which gives the other field, is first order in time, resulting in the same phase shift for both fields in each mathematical operation.</paragraph><paragraph>From the viewpoint of an electromagnetic wave traveling forward, the electric field might be oscillating up and down, while the magnetic field oscillates right and left. This picture can be rotated with the electric field oscillating right and left and the magnetic field oscillating down and up. This is a different solution that is traveling in the same direction. This arbitrariness in the orientation with respect to propagation direction is known as<space/><link><target>polarization (waves)</target><part>polarization</part></link>. On a quantum level, it is described as<space/><link><target>photon polarization</target></link>. The direction of the polarization is defined as the direction of the electric field.</paragraph><paragraph>More general forms of the second-order wave equations given above are available, allowing for both non-vacuum propagation media and sources. Many competing derivations exist, all with varying levels of approximation and intended applications. One very general example is a form of the electric field equation,<extension extension_name='ref' name="kinsler2010"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Kinsler, P.
</arg><arg name="year">2010
</arg><arg name="title">Optical pulse propagation with minimal approximations
</arg><arg name="journal">Phys. Rev. A
</arg><arg name="volume">81
</arg><arg name="page">013819
</arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/PhysRevA.81.013819
</arg><arg name="arxiv">0810.5689
</arg><arg name="bibcode"><space/>2010PhRvA..81a3819K<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>which was factorized into a pair of explicitly directional wave equations, and then efficiently reduced into a single uni-directional wave equation by means of a simple slow-evolution approximation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target><arg></arg><arg>25em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Antenna (radio)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Antenna measurement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bioelectromagnetism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bolometer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Control of electromagnetic radiation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic pulse</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic radiation and health</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic spectrum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic wave equation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Evanescent wave coupling</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Finite-difference time-domain method</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Helicon (physics)</target><part>Helicon</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Impedance of free space</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Light</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Near and far field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Radiant energy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Radiation reaction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Risks and benefits of sun exposure</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sinusoidal plane-wave solutions of the electromagnetic wave equation</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">35em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hecht<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eugene
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Optics
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>4th
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pearson Education
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8053-8566-5
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Serway<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Raymond A.
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Jewett, John W.
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Physics for Scientists and Engineers
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>6th
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Brooks Cole
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-534-40842-7
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Tipler<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Physics for Scientists and Engineers: Electricity, Magnetism, Light, and Elementary Modern Physics
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>5th
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>W. H. Freeman
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7167-0810-8
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Reitz<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Milford, Frederick<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Christy, Robert
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Foundations of Electromagnetic Theory
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>4th
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Addison Wesley
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-201-52624-7
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jackson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John David
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>John David Jackson (physicist)
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Classical Electrodynamics
<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>3rd
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Wiley & Sons
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1999
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-471-30932-X
<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">[[Allen Taflove]] and Susan C. Hagness
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Computational Electrodynamics: The Finite-Difference Time-Domain Method, 3rd ed
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Artech House Publishers
<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-58053-832-0
<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>QST/December 1915/Pictured Electromagnetic Waves</arg><arg>Pictured Electro-Magnetic Waves</arg></template><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no 
</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">no 
</arg><arg name="others">no 
</arg><arg name="about">yes 
</arg><arg name="label">Electromagnetic radiation</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lightandmatter.com/html_books/0sn/ch11/ch11.html'>Electromagnetism</link><space/>a chapter from an online textbook</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.physnet.org/modules/pdf_modules/m210.pdf'>'' Electromagnetic Waves from Maxwell's Equations ''</link><space/>on<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.physnet.org'>Project PHYSNET</link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hydrogenlab.de/elektronium/HTML/einleitung_hauptseite_uk.html'>Radiation of atoms? e-m wave, Polarisation, ...</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://scripts.mit.edu/~raskar/lightfields/index.php?title=An_Introduction_to_The_Wigner_Distribution_in_Geometric_Optics'>An Introduction to The Wigner Distribution in Geometric Optics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.astronoo.com/articles/electromagneticSpectrum-en.html'>The windows of the electromagnetic spectrum, on Astronoo</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.khanacademy.org/science/cosmology-and-astronomy/universe-scale-topic/light-fundamental-forces/v/introduction-to-light'>Introduction to light and electromagnetic radiation</link><space/>course video from the<space/><link><target>Khan Academy</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ocw.mit.edu/courses/physics/8-02sc-physics-ii-electricity-and-magnetism-fall-2010/electromagnetic-waves/'>Lectures on electromagnetic waves</link><space/>course video and notes from MIT Professor<space/><link><target>Walter Lewin</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/science/electromagnetic-radiation'>Encyclopedia Britannica Electromagnetic Radiation</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.learner.org/courses/physics/unit/text.html?unit=2&amp;amp;secNum=4'>Physics for the 21st Century Early Unification for Electromagnetism Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Radiation</target><arg name="state">uncollapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Electromagnetic Radiation</target></template><link><target>Category:Electromagnetic radiation</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Radiation</target></link></paragraph></article>