<article title='Stolen_base'><paragraph><link><target>Image:Baseball steal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The all-time stolen base leader,<space/><link><target>Rickey Henderson</target></link>, steals third base in 1988.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>baseball</target></link>, a<space/><bold>stolen base</bold><space/>occurs when a runner advances to a base to which he is not entitled and the official scorer rules that the advance should be credited to the action of the runner. The<space/><link><target>umpire</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>determine whether the runner is safe or out at the next base, but the official scorer rules on the question of credit or blame for the advance under Rule 10.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/downloads/y2008/official_rules/10_the_official_scorer.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">MLB Rule 10<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A stolen base most often occurs when a<space/><link><target>baserunner</target></link><space/>successfully advances to the next base while the<space/><link><target>pitcher</target></link><space/>is pitching the ball to<space/><link><target>home plate</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Successful base-stealing requires not only that the runner be fast but also have good baserunning instincts and timing.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph><link><target>Ned Cuthbert</target></link>, playing for the<space/><link><target>Philadelphia Keystones</target></link><space/>in either 1863 or 1865, was the first player to steal a base in a baseball game, although the term stolen base was not used until 1870.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://nymutuals.com/Mutual_Articles.html</arg><arg name="title">New York Mutual Articles</arg></template></extension><space/>For a time in the 19th century, stolen bases were credited when a baserunner reached an extra base on a base hit from another player.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bid"></extension><space/>For example, if a runner on<space/><link><target>First baseman</target><part>first base</part></link><space/>reached<space/><link><target>Third baseman</target><part>third base</part></link><space/>on a single, it counted as a steal. In 1887,<space/><link><target>Hugh Nicol</target></link><space/>set a still-standing Major League record with 138 stolen bases,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-reference.com/leaders/SB_season.shtml</arg><arg name="title">Single-Season Leaders for Stolen Bases</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-05-17</arg><arg name="publisher">Baseball-Reference.com</arg></template></extension><space/>many of which would not have counted under modern rules.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bid"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jockbio.com/Classic/McPhee/McPhee_bio.html</arg><arg name="title">JockBio: Bid McPhee</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-05-17</arg><arg name="publisher">JockBio.com</arg></template></extension><space/>Modern steal rules were fully implemented in 1898.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseballlibrary.com/baseballlibrary/excerpts/rules_chronology.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chronology of Baseball Rules</arg><arg name="publisher">BaseballLibrary.com</arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:MLB HR and SB rates.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Graph depicting the yearly number of home runs (blue line) and stolen bases (pink line) per MLB game. The two primary periods in which the stolen base was popular were before 1920 and again in the 1970s and 1980s.</part><part>500px</part></link>Base stealing was popular in the game's early decades, with speedsters such as<space/><link><target>Ty Cobb</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Clyde Milan</target></link><space/>stealing nearly 100 bases in a season. But the tactic fell into relative disuse after<space/><link><target>Babe Ruth</target></link><space/>introduced the era of the home run &amp;ndash; in 1955, for example, no one in baseball stole more than 25 bases, and<space/><link><target>Dom DiMaggio</target></link><space/>won the AL stolen base title in 1950 with just 15. However, in the late 1950s and early 1960s, base-stealing was brought back to prominence primarily by<space/><link><target>Luis Aparicio</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Maury Wills</target></link>, who broke Cobb's modern single-season record by stealing 104 bases in 1962. Wills' record was broken in turn by<space/><link><target>Lou Brock</target></link><space/>in 1974, and<space/><link><target>Rickey Henderson</target></link><space/>in 1982. The stolen base remained a popular tactic through the 1980s, perhaps best exemplified by<space/><link><target>Vince Coleman</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>St. Louis Cardinals</target></link>, but began to decline again in the 1990s as the frequency of<space/><link><target>home run</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>reached record heights and the steal-friendly<space/><link><target>artificial turf</target></link><space/>ballparks began to disappear.</paragraph><paragraph>Base stealing is an important characteristic of the &quot;<link><target>small ball</target></link>&quot; managing style (or &quot;manufacturing runs&quot;). Such managers emphasize &quot;doing the little things&quot; (including risky running plays like base-stealing) to advance runners and score runs, often relying on pitching and defense to keep games close. The<space/><link><target>Los Angeles Dodgers</target></link><space/>of the 1960s, led by pitcher<space/><link><target>Sandy Koufax</target></link><space/>and speedy shortstop<space/><link><target>Maury Wills</target></link>, were a successful example of this style. The antithesis of this is reliance on power hitting, exemplified by the<space/><link><target>Baltimore Orioles</target></link><space/>of the 1970s, which aspired to score most of its runs via home runs. Often the &quot;small ball&quot; model is associated with the<space/><link><target>National League</target></link>, while power hitting is associated with the<space/><link><target>American League</target></link>. However, some successful recent American League teams, including the<space/><link><target>2002 in baseball</target><part>2002</part></link><space/><link><target>Los Angeles Angels of Anaheim</target><part>Anaheim Angels</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>2001 in baseball</target><part>2001</part></link><space/><link><target>Seattle Mariners</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>2005 in baseball</target><part>2005</part></link><space/><link><target>Chicago White Sox</target></link><space/>have excelled at &quot;small ball.&quot; The<space/><link><target>Kansas City Royals</target></link><space/>have embodied this style recently, leading the league in stolen bases but finishing last in<space/><link><target>home run</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in 2013 and 2014. Successful teams often combine both styles, with a speedy runner or two complementing hitters with power, such as the 2005 White Sox, who despite playing &quot;small ball&quot;, still hit 200 home runs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Base-stealing technique</heading><paragraph>Baseball's Rule 8 (The Pitcher) specifies the pitching procedure in detail. For example, in the Set Position, the pitcher must &quot;com[e] to a complete stop&quot;; thereafter, &quot;any natural motion associated with his delivery of the ball to the batter commits him to the pitch without alteration or interruption.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>MLB Rule 8.01(b).</extension><space/>A runner intending to &quot;steal on the pitcher&quot; breaks for the next base the moment the pitcher commits to pitch to home plate. The pitcher cannot abort the pitch and try to put the runner out; this is a<space/><link><target>Balk (baseball)</target><part>balk</part></link><space/>under Rule 8.</paragraph><paragraph>If the runner breaks too soon (before the pitcher is obliged to complete a pitch), the pitcher may throw to a base rather than pitch, and the runner is usually<space/><italics>picked off</italics><space/>by being tagged out between the bases. Past this moment, any delay in the runner's break makes it more likely that the catcher, after receiving the pitch, will be able to throw the runner out at the destination base.</paragraph><paragraph>Before the pitch, the runner takes a<space/><italics>lead-off,</italics><space/>walking several steps away from the base as a<space/><link><target>Head start (positioning)</target><part>head start</part></link><space/>toward the next base. Even a runner who does not intend to steal takes a<space/><italics>secondary lead</italics><space/>of a few more steps, once the pitcher has legally committed to complete the pitch.</paragraph><paragraph>The pitcher may, without limit, throw the ball to the runner's base. The runner must return to that base or risk being tagged out; but the underlying strategy is thereby to dissuade the runner from too big a lead-off; that is, to<space/><italics>hold the runner on</italics><space/>his original base.</paragraph><paragraph>The more adept base stealers are proficient at<space/><italics>reading the pickoff</italics>, meaning that they can detect certain<space/><italics>tells</italics><space/>(tell-tale signs) in a pitchers pre-pitch movements or mannerisms that indicate the pickoff attempt is or is not imminent. For example, one experienced base stealer noted that careless pitchers dig the toes on their back foot into the ground when they are about to pitch in order to get a better push off, but when they intend to turn and throw a pickoff, they do not.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mahony1">Baseball Explained, by Phillip Mahony. McFarland Books, 2014. See<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.baseballexplained.com/'>www.baseballexplained.com</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>If a batted ball is caught on the fly, the runner must return to his original base. In this case, a runner trying to steal is more likely to be caught off his original base, resulting in a<space/><link><target>Double play</target><part>doubleplay</part></link>. This is a minor risk of a steal attempt. It is offset by the lower likelihood of a doubleplay on a ground ball.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plays involving baserunning</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><italics><link><target>hit and run (baseball)</target><part>hit-and-run play</part></link>,</italics><space/>coaches coordinate the actions of runner and batter. The runner tries to steal and the batter swings at almost any pitch, if only to distract the catcher. If the batter makes contact, the runner has a greater chance of reaching the next base; if the batter gets a base hit, the runner may be able to take an extra base. If the batter fails to hit the ball, the hit-and-run becomes a pure steal attempt.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>delayed steal,</italics><space/>the runner does not take advantage of the pitcher's duty to complete a pitch, but relies on surprise and takes advantage of any complacency by the fielders. The runner gives the impression he is not trying to steal, and does not break for the next base until the ball crosses the plate. It is rare for Major League defenses to be fooled, but the play is used effectively at the college level. The first delayed steal on record was performed by<space/><link><target>Miller Huggins</target></link><space/>in 1903.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cincy"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Huggins cornerstone to Yankees</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[The Cincinnati Post]]</arg><arg name="first">Lonnie</arg><arg name="last">Wheeler</arg><arg name="date">June 3, 2003</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 16, 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>The delayed steal was famously practiced by<space/><link><target>Eddie Stanky</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Brooklyn Dodgers</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Second base</target></link><space/>is the base most often stolen, because once a runner is on second base he is considered to be in<space/><italics>scoring position</italics>, meaning that he is expected to be able to run home and score on most routine singles hit into the outfield.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mahony1"></extension><space/>Second base is also the easiest to steal, as it is farthest from home plate and thus a longer throw from the catcher is required to prevent it.<space/><link><target>Third base</target></link><space/>is a shorter throw for the catcher, but the runner is able to take a longer lead off second base. A steal of<space/><link><target>home plate</target></link><space/>is the riskiest, as the catcher only needs to tag out the runner after receiving the ball from the pitcher. It is difficult for the runner to cover the distance between the bases before the ball arrives home.<space/><link><target>Ty Cobb</target></link><space/>holds the records for most steals of home in a single season (8) as well as for a career (54).<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBAlm"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-almanac.com/recbooks/rb_stbah.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stealing Home Base Records by Baseball Almanac<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Baseball-almanac.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension><space/>Steals of home are not officially recorded statistics, and must be researched through individual game accounts. Thus, Cobb's totals may be even greater than is recorded.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBAlm"></extension><space/><link><target>Jackie Robinson</target></link><space/>famously stole home in Game 1 of the<space/><link><target>1955 World Series</target></link>. The most recent player credited with a &quot;straight&quot; steal of home (that is, with no other runners moving to distract the pitcher) was<space/><link><target>Elvis Andrus</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Texas Rangers (baseball)</target><part>Texas Rangers</part></link><space/>who stole home against the<space/><link><target>San Diego Padres</target></link><space/>on September 1, 2015.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MLB.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://news.yahoo.com/watch-elvis-andrus-steal-home-123327729.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Watch Elvis Andrus Steal Home Plate Against an Oblivious Padres Pitcher<space/></arg><arg name="date">2015-09-02<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-09-02</arg></template></extension><space/>35 games have ended with a runner stealing home, but only 2 have occurred since 1980.<extension extension_name='ref'>Larson, J. &quot;Stolen Victories.&quot; Baseball Research Journal #36, p. 116-119. 2007.</extension><space/>In a variation on the steal of home, the batter is signaled to simultaneously execute a<space/><link><target>sacrifice bunt</target></link>, which results in the<space/><italics><link><target>Squeeze play (baseball)</target><part>squeeze play</part></link>.</italics><space/>The<space/><italics>suicide squeeze</italics><space/>is a squeeze in which the runner on third begins to steal home without seeing the outcome of the bunt; it is so named because if the batter fails to bunt, the runner will surely be out. In contrast, when the runner on third does not commit until seeing that the ball is bunted advantageously, it is called a<space/><italics>safety squeeze.</italics></paragraph><paragraph>In more recent years, most steals of home involve a<space/><italics>delayed double steal,</italics><space/>in which a runner on first attempts to steal second, while the runner on third breaks for home as soon as the catcher throws to second base. If it is important to prevent the run from scoring, the catcher may hold on to the ball (conceding the steal of second) or may throw to the pitcher; this may deceive the runner at third and the pitcher may throw back to the catcher for the out.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Statistics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Granderson-20th stolen base 2007.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Curtis Granderson</target></link><space/>steals a base.</part></link>In<space/><link><target>baseball statistics</target></link>, stolen bases are denoted by<space/><bold>SB</bold>. Attempts to steal that result in the baserunner being out are<space/><italics><link><target>caught stealing</target></link></italics><space/>(<bold>CS</bold>). The sum of these statistics is<space/><italics>steal attempts.</italics></paragraph><paragraph>The rule on stolen bases<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/official_scorer_10.jsp</arg><arg name="title">Official Rules: Rule 10.07(g)</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Major League Baseball]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-05-17</arg></template></extension><space/>states that:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Advances that are credited to some other play are not steal attempts. For example, on a wild pitch or a passed ball, the official scorer must notice whether the runner broke for the next base before the pitch got away.</listitem><listitem>As usual, statistics in the case of a defensive<space/><link><target>Error (baseball)</target><part>error</part></link><space/>are based on error-free play. If a runner would have been out, but for the error, it is scored as &quot;caught stealing, safe on the error.&quot; A catcher does not commit an error by throwing poorly to the destination base, but if any runner takes an extra base on the bad throw, it is &quot;stolen base plus error.&quot;</listitem><listitem>There is no steal attempt on a dead ball, whether the runner is sent back to the original base (as on a foul ball) or is awarded the next base (as on a hit batsman). On a base award when the ball is live (such as a walk), the runner could make a steal attempt beyond the base awarded.</listitem><listitem>Cases where the defense makes no attempt to put the baserunner out (for example, if the catcher doesn't even look his way) are scored as<space/><italics>defensive indifference</italics><space/>(also called<space/><italics>fielder's indifference</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="jackcurry"><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2009/09/23/sports/baseball/23score.html?ref=sports'>Curry, Jack. &quot;Safe at Second, but No Stolen Base to Show for It,&quot; ''The New York Times'', Wednesday, September 23, 2009.</link></extension><space/>This is generally only scored late in the game and when the team at bat is trailing by more than one run.</listitem></list><paragraph>Relative skill at stealing bases can be judged either by evaluating a player's total number of steals or the success rate (stolen bases as a percentage of steal attempts). Noted statistician<space/><link><target>Bill James</target></link><space/>has argued that unless a player can steal a high percentage of the time, then the stolen base may be detrimental to a team. A success rate of 67 to 70% or better is necessary to make stealing bases worthwhile.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-almanac.com/stats.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Baseball Almanac Stats<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Baseball-almanac.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Comparing skill against players from other eras is also problematic because the definition has not been constant. Caught stealing was not recorded regularly until the middle of the 20th century.<space/><link><target>Ty Cobb</target></link>, for example, was known as a great base-stealer, with 892 steals and a success rate of over 83%. However the data on Cobb's caught stealing is missing from 12 seasons, strongly suggesting he was unsuccessful many more times than his stats indicate.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-reference.com/c/cobbty01.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ty Cobb's stats at Baseball Reference<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Baseball-reference.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Carlos Beltrn</target></link>, with 286 steals, has the highest career success rate of all players with over 300 stolen base attempts, at 88.3%.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Evolution of rules and scoring</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Lastings Milledge and Luis Castillo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Lastings Milledge</target></link><space/>steals a base.</part></link>The first mention of the stolen base as a statistic was in the 1877 scoring rules adopted by the<space/><link><target>National League</target></link>, which noted credit toward a player's<space/><link><target>total bases</target></link><space/>when a base is stolen.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2413"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Scoring rules for 1877-- Batting</italics>, p. 2413</extension><space/>It was not until 1886 that the stolen base appeared as something to be tracked, but was only to &quot;appear in the summary of the game&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2414"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2414</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1887, the stolen base was given its own individual statistical column in the<space/><link><target>box score</target></link>, and was defined for purposes of scoring: &quot;...every base made after first base has been reached by a base runner, except for those made by reason of or with the aid of a battery error (<link><target>wild pitch</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>passed ball</target></link>), or by batting,<space/><link><target>balk</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or by being forced off. In short, shall include all bases made by a clean steal, or through a wild throw or muff of the ball by a fielder who is directly trying to put the base runner out while attempting to steal.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2415"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2415</extension><space/>The next year, it was clarified that any attempt to steal must be credited to the runner, and that fielders committing errors during this play must also be charged with an error. This rule also clarified that advancement of another base(s) beyond the one being stolen is not credited as a stolen base on the same play, and that an error is charged to the fielder who permitted the extra advancement. There was clarification that a runner is credited with a steal if the attempt began before a battery error. Finally, batters were credited with a stolen base if they were tagged out after over running the base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2415"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1892, a rule credited runners with stolen bases if a base runner advanced on a fly out, or if they advanced more than one base on any safe hit or attempted out, providing an attempt was made by the defense to put the runner out.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2415"></extension><space/>The rule was rescinded in 1897.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2415"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1898, stolen base scoring was narrowed to no longer include advancement in the event of a fielding error, or advancement caused by a hit batsman.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2416"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2416</extension></paragraph><paragraph>1904 saw an attempt to reduce the already wordy slew of rules governing stolen bases, with the stolen base now credited when &quot;...the<space/><template><target>sic</target><arg>base</arg><arg>runner</arg></template><space/>advances a base unaided by a base hit, a put out, (or) a fielding or batter error.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2417"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2417</extension></paragraph><paragraph>1910 saw the first addressing of the double and triple steal attempts. Under the new rule, when any runner is thrown out, and the other(s) are successful, the successful runners will not be credited with a stolen base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2417"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Without using the term, 1920 saw the first rule that would be referred to today as defensive indifference, as stolen bases would not be credited, unless an effort was made to stop the runner by the defense.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jackcurry"></extension><space/>This is usually called if such is attempted in the ninth inning while that player's team is trailing, unless the runner represents the potential tying run.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2418"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2418</extension></paragraph><paragraph>1931 saw a further narrowing of the criteria for awarding a stolen base. Power was given to the official scorer, in the event of a muff by the catcher in throwing, that in the judgment of the scorer the runner would have been out, to credit the catcher with an error, and not credit the runner with a stolen base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2419"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2419</extension><space/>Further, any successful steal on a play resulting in a wild pitch, passed ball, or balk would no longer be credited as a steal, even if the runner had started to steal before the play.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2419"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of the largest rewrites to the rules in history came in 1950.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2420-23"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, pp. 242023</extension><space/>The stolen base was specifically to be credited &quot;to a runner whenever he advances one base unaided by a base hit, a putout, a forceout, a<space/><link><target>fielder's choice</target></link>, a passed ball, a wild pitch, or a balk.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2423</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There were noted exceptions, such as denying a stolen base to an otherwise successful steal as a part of a double or triple steal, if one other runner was thrown out in the process.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>A stolen base would be awarded to runners who successfully stole second base as a part of a double steal with a man on third, if the other runner failed to steal home, but instead was able to return safely to third base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>Runners who are tagged out oversliding the base after an otherwise successful steal would not be credited with a stolen base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>Indifference was also credited as an exception.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>Runners would now be credited with stolen bases if they had begun the act of stealing, and the resulting pitch was wild, or a passed ball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>Finally, for 1950 only, runners would be credited with a stolen base if they were &quot;well advanced&quot; toward the base they were attempting to steal&quot;, and the pitcher is charged with a balk, with the further exception of a player attempting to steal, who would otherwise have been forced to advance on the balk by a runner behind them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension><space/>This rule was removed in 1951.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2423"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A clarification came in 1955 that awarded a stolen base to a runner even if he became involved in a<space/><link><target>rundown</target></link>, provided he evaded the rundown and advanced to the base he intended to steal.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2426"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2426</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The criteria for &quot;caught stealing&quot; were fine-tuned in 1979, with a runner being charged with being caught if he is put out while trying to steal, overslides a base (otherwise successfully stolen), or is picked off a base and tries to advance to the next base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2429"><italics>Total Baseball, 5th ed.</italics>, 1997, Viking Press, Thorn, John et al. ed,<space/><italics>Chronology of Scoring Rules 1878-1996</italics>, p. 2429</extension><space/>It is explicitly not caught stealing to be put out after a wild pitch or passed ball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Total Baseball2429"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>&quot;Stealing first&quot;</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Uncaught third strike</arg></template>While not recorded as a stolen base, the same dynamic between batter/runner and defense is on display in the case of an<space/><link><target>uncaught third strike</target></link>. The batter/runner can avoid an<space/><link><target>out (baseball)</target><part>out</part></link><space/>and become a baserunner by reaching first base ahead of the throw. This case is a<space/><link><target>strikeout</target></link><space/>that is not an out; the batter/runner's acquisition of first base is scored as a<space/><link><target>passed ball</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>wild pitch</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/runner_7.jsp'>Official Rules: 7.00 The Runner</link>: 7.08(i), MLB.com.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In baseball's earlier decades, a runner on second base could &quot;steal&quot; first base, perhaps with the intention of drawing a throw that might allow a runner on third to score (a tactic famously employed by<space/><link><target>Germany Schaefer</target></link>). However, such a tactic was not recorded as a stolen base. MLB rules now forbid running clockwise on the basepaths to &quot;confuse the defense or make a travesty of the game&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/official_info/official_rules/runner_7.jsp'>Official Rules: 7.09 The Runner</link>: 7.0, MLB.com. Retrieved on 2009-06-11.</extension><space/>Further, after the pitcher assumes the pitching position, runners cannot return to any previous base.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stark"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Stark</arg><arg name="first">Jayson</arg><arg name="title">Jean Segura should've been called out</arg><arg name="url">http://espn.go.com/mlb/blog/_/name/stark_jayson/id/9210491/the-final-ruling-jean-segura-baserunning-misadventures</arg><arg name="work">Jayson Stark Blog</arg><arg name="publisher">ESPN</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 August 2013</arg><arg name="date">2013-04-25</arg></template><space/>(citing MLB Rule 7.01)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a game on April 19, 2013,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://espn.go.com/mlb/playbyplay?gameId</arg><arg name="title">Chicago Cubs vs. Milwaukee Brewers - Play By Play - April 19, 2013 - ESPN<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Espn.go.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2013-04-19<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-04-22</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Milwaukee Brewers</target></link><space/>shortstop<space/><link><target>Jean Segura</target></link><space/>stole second base in the bottom of the eighth inning. After the batter up,<space/><link><target>Ryan Braun</target></link>, walked, Segura broke early for third base and the pitcher,<space/><link><target>Shawn Camp</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Chicago Cubs</target></link>, threw ahead of him. As Segura was chased back to second base, Braun advanced to second as well and was tagged out. Segura, thinking<space/><italics>he</italics><space/>was out, began to return to the home dugout behind first base, but first base coach<space/><link><target>Garth Iorg</target></link><space/>directed him to stand at first. Segura had not intentionally run the bases backwards as a deception or mockery, but no fielder tried to tag him out. Later in the inning, he attempted to steal second for the second time, but was thrown out by catcher<space/><link><target>Welington Castillo</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The expression &quot;You can't steal<space/><link><target>first base</target></link>&quot; is sometimes used in reference to a player who is fast but not very good at getting<space/><link><target>on-base percentage</target><part>on base</part></link><space/>in the first place.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.baseballprospectus.com/article.php?articleid</arg><arg name="title">Prospectus Q & A: Tim Raines</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-30</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Baseball Prospectus]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Former<space/><link><target>Pittsburgh Pirates</target></link><space/>manager<space/><link><target>Lloyd McClendon</target></link><space/>is jokingly referred to as having &quot;stolen first&quot; in a June 26, 2001 game after being<space/><link><target>ejection (sports)</target><part>ejected</part></link><space/>for disputing a call at first base, he yanked the base out of the ground and left the field with it, delaying the game.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Baseball</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lead off</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stolen base percentage</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball leaders in career stolen bases</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball stolen base champions</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Major League Baseball stolen base records</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Stealing (baseball)</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.baseball-almanac.com/hitting/hisb1.shtml'>Baseball-Almanac.com list of All-Time Career stolen bases leaders</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Baseball</target></template><template><target>Baseball statistics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Stolen Base</target></template><link><target>Category:Baserunning statistics</target></link><link><target>Category:Baseball terminology</target></link></paragraph></article>