<article title='North_American_B-25_Mitchell'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>B-25</arg><arg>the British Second World War-era fighter plane<space/></arg><arg>Blackburn Roc</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>B25 (disambiguation){{!}}B25</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><table><tablerow><tablecell>name= B-25 Mitchell</tablecell><tablecell>image= File:North American Aviation's B-25 medium bomber, Inglewood, Calif.jpg</tablecell><tablecell>caption= A B-25C Mitchell in 1942}}<template><target>Infobox aircraft type</target><arg name="type"><space/>[[Medium bomber]]
<space/></arg><arg name="manufacturer"><space/>[[North American Aviation]]
<space/></arg><arg name="national origin">United States
<space/></arg><arg name="designer"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="first flight"><space/>19 August 1940
<space/></arg><arg name="introduction"><space/>1941
<space/></arg><arg name="status">
<space/></arg><arg name="retired"><space/>1979 (Indonesia)
<space/></arg><arg name="primary user"><space/>[[United States Army Air Forces]]
<space/></arg><arg name="more users"><space/>[[Royal Air Force]]<space/><br /><space/>[[Soviet Air Force]]<br />[[United States Marine Corps]] 
<space/></arg><arg name="number built"><space/>9,816<ref name</arg><arg name="unit cost">
<space/></arg><arg name="developed from"><space/>[[North American XB-21]]
<space/></arg><arg name="variants with their own articles">
<space/></arg><arg name="developed into"><space/>[[North American XB-28 Dragon]]
</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>The<space/><bold>North American B-25 Mitchell</bold><space/>is an American twin-engine,<space/><link><target>medium bomber</target></link><space/>manufactured by<space/><link><target>North American Aviation</target></link>. It was named in honor of<space/><link><target>Billy Mitchell</target><part>Major General William &quot;Billy&quot; Mitchell</part></link>, a pioneer of U.S. military aviation. Used by many<space/><link><target>Allies of World War II</target><part>Allied</part></link><space/>air forces, the B-25 served in every theater of World War II and after the war ended many remained in service, operating across four decades. Produced in numerous variants, nearly 10,000 Mitchells rolled from NAA factories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="U.S. Air Force Factsheets: North American B-25B Mitchell"></extension><space/>These included a few limited models, such as the<space/><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target></link>' PBJ-1<space/><link><target>Maritime patrol aircraft</target><part>patrol bomber</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United States Army Air Forces</target></link>' F-10<space/><link><target>reconnaissance aircraft</target></link><space/>and AT-24 trainers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Design and development</heading><paragraph><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><link><target>File:B25-1 300.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Late war development B-25J2 Mitchell strafer bomber</part><part>alt=Black and white photo of an early bomber parked perpendicular to camera, facing left. Rearward of the wing is a star in front of horizontal stripes.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Air Corps issued a circular (Number 38-385) in March 1938 describing the performance they required from the next bombers&amp;nbsp; a payload of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1200</arg><arg>lb</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>with a range of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1200</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>at more than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baugher1">Baugher, Joe.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.joebaugher.com/usaf_bombers/b25_1.html'>&quot;North American NA-40.&quot;</link><space/><italics>American Military Aircraft: US Bomber Aircraft</italics>, 6 March 2000. Retrieved: 24 May 2015.</extension><space/>Those performance specifications led NAA to submit their NA-40 design. The NA-40 had benefited from the<space/><link><target>North American XB-21</target></link><space/>(NA-39) of 1936 which was the company's partly-successful design for an earlier medium bomber that had been initially accepted and ordered but then cancelled. However, the company's experience from the XB-21 contributed to the design and development of the NA-40. The single NA-40 built flew first at the end of January 1939. It went through several modifications to correct problems. These improvements included fitting 1,600&amp;nbsp;hp<space/><link><target>Wright R-2600</target></link><space/>&quot;Double Cyclone&quot;<space/><link><target>radial engine</target><trail>s</trail></link>, in March 1939 which solved the lack of power.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baugher1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In March 1939, North American delivered the substantially redesigned and improved NA-40 (as NA-40B) to the<space/><link><target>United States Army Air Corps</target></link><space/>for evaluation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baugher1"></extension><space/>It was in competition with other manufacturers' designs (Douglas 7B,<space/><link><target>Stearman X-100</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Martin Model 167F</target></link>)<extension extension_name='ref'>Baugher, Joe.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.joebaugher.com/usattack/a20_1.html'>&quot;Douglas Model 7B.&quot;</link><space/><italics>American Military Aircraft: US Bomber Aircraft</italics>, 2000. Retrieved: 28 May 2015.</extension><space/>but failed to win orders. The aircraft was originally intended to be an attack bomber for export to the United Kingdom and France, both of which had a pressing requirement for such aircraft in the early stages of World War II. However, the French had already opted for a revised<space/><link><target>Douglas Aircraft Company</target><part>Douglas</part></link><space/>7B (as the DB-7). Unfortunately, the NA-40B was destroyed in a<space/><link><target>List of accidents and incidents involving military aircraft (19351939)#1939</target><part>crash on 11 April 1939</part></link><space/>while undergoing testing. Although the crash was not considered due to a fault with the aircraft design, the Army ordered the DB-7 as the<space/><link><target>Douglas A-20 Havoc</target><part>A-20</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Air Corps issued a specification for a medium bomber in March 1939:<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2400</arg><arg>lb</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1200</arg><arg>miles</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>300</arg><arg>mph</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Baugher, Joe.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.joebaugher.com/usaf_bombers/b25_2.html'>&quot;North American B-25 Mitchell.&quot;</link><space/><italics>American Military Aircraft: US Bomber Aircraft</italics>, 6 March 2000. Retrieved: 24 May 2015.</extension><space/>NAA used the NA-40B design to develop the NA-62 which competed for the medium bomber contract. There was no YB-25 for prototype service tests. In September 1939, the Air Corps ordered the NA-62 into production as the B-25, along with the other new Air Corps medium bomber, the<space/><link><target>Martin B-26 Marauder</target></link><space/>&quot;off the drawing board&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Alfred T. Palmer - Assembling the North American B-25 Mitchell at Kansas City, Kansas (USA).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>North American B-25 Mitchell production in Kansas City in 1942</part><part>alt=Interior of huge aircraft factory where rows of bombers are being assembled.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The NA-40 lost out to the Douglas A-20 in the attack type competition, but NAA developed a more advanced design, the NA-40B, which in turn led to the NA-62, B-25 Mitchell bomber.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA">Parker 2013, pp. 77-79, 83, 88, 92.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated70">Borth 1945, pp. 70, 92, 244.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Early into B-25 production, NAA incorporated a significant redesign to the wing dihedral. The first nine aircraft had a constant-<link><target>dihedral (aircraft)</target><part>dihedral</part></link>, meaning the wing had a consistent, upward angle from the fuselage to the wingtip. This design caused stability problems. A slight anhedral on the outboard wing sections nullified the problem and gave the B-25 its<space/><link><target>gull wing</target></link><space/>configuration.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chor aero p74">Chorlton<space/><italics>Aeroplane</italics><space/>May 2013, p. 74.</extension><space/>Less noticeable changes during this period included an increase in the size of the tail fins and a decrease in their inward cant.</paragraph><paragraph>NAA continued design and development in 1940 and 1941. Both the B-25A and B-25B series entered AAF service. The B-25B was operational in 1942. Combat requirements lead to further developments. Before the year was over, NAA was producing the B-25C and B-25D series at different plants. Also in 1942, the manufacturer began design work on the cannon-armed B-25G series. The NA-100 of 1943 and 1944 was an interim armament development at the Kansas City complex known as the B-25D2. Similar armament upgrades by U.S-based commercial modification centers involved about half of the B-25G series. Further development led to the B-25H, B-25J and B-25J2. The gunship design concept dates to late 1942 and NAA sent a field technical representative to the SWPA. The factory produced B-25G entered production during the NA-96 order followed by the redesigned B-25H gunship. The B-25J reverted to the bomber role, but it, too, could be outfitted as a strafer (pictured above).</paragraph><paragraph>North American Aviation manufactured the greatest number of aircraft in World War II. It was the first time a company had produced trainers, bombers and fighters simultaneously (the AT-6/SNJ Texan, B-25 Mitchell, and the P-51 Mustang).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>It produced B-25s at both its Inglewood main plant and an additional 6,608 aircraft at its<space/><link><target>Kansas City, Kansas</target></link><space/>plant at<space/><link><target>Fairfax Airport</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated70"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Herman 2012, pp. 11, 88, 115, 140-143, 263, 297.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Postwar, the USAF placed a contract for the TB-25L trainer in 1952. This was a modification program by Hayes of<space/><link><target>Birmingham, Alabama</target></link>. Its primary role was reciprocal engine pilot training.</paragraph><paragraph>A development of the B-25 was the<space/><link><target>North American XB-28 Dragon</target><part>North American XB-28</part></link>, designed as a high-altitude bomber. Two prototypes were built with the second prototype, the XB-28A, evaluated as a photo-reconnaissance platform but the aircraft did not enter production.<extension extension_name='ref'>Norton 2012, p. 68.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Operational history</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><link><target>File:Lt. Preddy and crew of 3d Antisubmarine Squadron.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Crew and their B-25</part></link><link><target>File:USS Hornet flight deck April 1942.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Doolittle Raid</target></link><space/>B-25Bs aboard USS ''Hornet''</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Asia-Pacific</heading><paragraph>The majority of B-25s in American service were used in<space/><link><target>Pacific War</target><part>the war against Japan in Asia and the Pacific</part></link>. The Mitchell fought from the Northern Pacific to the South Pacific and the Far East. These areas included the campaigns in Aleutians,<space/><link><target>Papua New Guinea</target></link>, the Solomons,<space/><link><target>New Britain</target></link>, China, Burma and the<space/><link><target>island hopping campaign</target></link><space/>in the Central Pacific. The aircrafts potential as a ground-<link><target>attack aircraft</target></link><space/>emerged. The jungle environment reduced the usefulness of medium-level bombing, and made low-level attack the best tactic. Using similar mast height level tactics and skip bombing, the B-25 proved itself to be a capable anti-shipping weapon and sank many enemy sea vessels of various types. An ever-increasing number of forward firing guns made the B-25 a formidable strafing aircraft for island warfare. The strafer versions were the B-25C1/D1, the B-25J1 and with the NAA strafer nose, the J2 sub-series.</paragraph><paragraph>In Burma, the B-25 was often used to attack Japanese communication links, especially bridges in central Burma. It also helped supply the<space/><link><target>Battle of Imphal</target><part>besieged troops at Imphal</part></link><space/>in 1944. The China Air Task Force, the Chinese American Composite Wing, the First Air Commando Group, the 341st Bomb Group, and eventually, the relocated 12th Bomb Group, all operated the B-25 in the<space/><link><target>China Burma India Theater</target></link><space/>(CBI). Many of these missions involved battle field isolation, interdiction and close air support.</paragraph><paragraph>Later in the war, as the AAF acquired bases in other parts of the Pacific the Mitchell could strike targets in<space/><link><target>Indochina</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Formosa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kyushu</target></link>, increasing the usefulness of the B-25. Although it was also used in some of the shortest raids of the Pacific War striking from<space/><link><target>Saipan</target></link><space/>against<space/><link><target>Guam</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Tinian</target></link>. The 41st Bomb Group used it against Japanese-occupied islands that had been bypassed by the main campaign, such as happened in the<space/><link><target>Marshall Islands</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Middle East and Italy</heading><paragraph>The first B-25s arrived in Egypt and were carrying out independent operations by October 1942.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pace, 2002 p23</extension><space/>There operations against Axis airfields and motorized vehicle columns supported the ground actions of the<space/><link><target>Second Battle of El Alamein</target></link>. From there, the aircraft took part in the rest of the<space/><link><target>North Africa campaign</target><part>campaign in North Africa</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>invasion of Sicily</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Italian campaign (World War II)</target><part>advance up Italy</part></link>. In the Strait of Messina to the Aegean Sea the B-25 conducted sea sweeps as part of the coastal air forces. In Italy, the B-25 was used in the<space/><link><target>ground attack</target></link><space/>role, concentrating on attacks against road and rail links in Italy, Austria and the Balkans. The B-25 had a longer range than the<space/><link><target>Douglas A-20 Havoc</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Douglas A-26 Invader</target><trail>s</trail></link>, allowing it to reach further into occupied Europe. The five bombardment groups - 20 squadrons - of the Ninth and Twelfth Air Forces that used the B-25 in the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Theater of Operations</target></link><space/>were the only U.S. units to employ the B-25 in Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pace 2002, p. 6.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Europe</heading><paragraph>The RAF received nearly 900 Mitchells, using them to replace<space/><link><target>Douglas A-20 Havoc</target><part>Douglas Boston</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Lockheed Ventura</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vickers Wellington</target></link><space/>bombers. The Mitchell entered active RAF service on 22 January 1943. At first, it was used to bomb targets in occupied Europe. After the<space/><link><target>invasion of Normandy</target><part>Normandy</part></link><space/>invasion, the RAF and France used Mitchells in support of the Allies in Europe. Several squadrons moved to forward airbases on the continent. The AAF did not use the B-25 in combat in the ETO.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Military operators</heading><heading level='3'>USAAF</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Army B-25 (Doolittle Raid).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A B-25 Mitchell taking off from USS ''Hornet'' for the Doolittle Raid</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The B-25B first gained fame as the bomber used in the 18 April 1942<space/><link><target>Doolittle Raid</target></link>, in which 16 B-25Bs led by<space/><link><target>Lieutenant colonel (United States)</target><part>Lieutenant Colonel</part></link><space/><link><target>Jimmy Doolittle</target></link><space/>attacked mainland Japan, four months after the bombing of Pearl Harbor. The mission gave a much-needed lift in spirits to the Americans, and alarmed the Japanese, who had believed their home islands to be inviolable by enemy forces. Although the amount of actual damage done was relatively minor, it forced the Japanese to divert troops for home defense for the remainder of the war.</paragraph><paragraph>The raiders took off from the carrier<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Hornet</arg><arg>CV-8</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and successfully bombed Tokyo and four other Japanese cities without loss. Fifteen of the bombers subsequently crash-landed en route to recovery fields in eastern China. These losses were the result of the task force being spotted by a Japanese vessel, forcing the bombers to take off<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>170</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>early, fuel exhaustion, stormy nighttime conditions with zero visibility, and lack of electronic homing aids at the recovery bases. Only one B-25 bomber landed intact, in<space/><link><target>Siberia</target></link><space/>where its five-man crew was interned and the aircraft confiscated. Of the 80 aircrew, 69 survived their historic mission and eventually made it back to American lines.</paragraph><paragraph>Following a number of additional modifications, including the addition of<space/><link><target>Plexiglas</target></link><space/>dome for navigational sightings to replace the overhead window for the navigator and heavier nose armament,<space/><link><target>De-ice</target><part>de-icing</part></link><space/>and anti-icing equipment, the B-25C entered AAF operations. Through block 20 the B-25C and B-25D differed only in location of manufacture: C series at<space/><link><target>Inglewood, California</target></link>; D series at<space/><link><target>Kansas City, Kansas</target></link>. After block 20 some NA-96 began the transition to the G series while some NA-87 acquired interim modifications eventually produced as the B-25D2 and ordered as the NA-100. NAA built a total of 3,915 B-25Cs and Ds during World War II.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the B-25 was originally designed to bomb from medium altitudes in level flight, it was used frequently in the<space/><link><target>South West Pacific theatre of World War II</target><part>Southwest Pacific theatre</part></link><space/>in treetop-level<space/><link><target>strafing</target></link><space/>and missions with parachute-retarded fragmentation bombs against Japanese airfields in<space/><link><target>New Guinea</target></link><space/>and the Philippines. These heavily armed Mitchells were field-modified at<space/><link><target>Townsville</target></link>, Australia, under the diirection of Major<space/><link><target>Paul I. &quot;Pappy&quot; Gunn</target></link><space/>and North American tech rep Jack Fox, These &quot;commerce destroyers&quot; were also used on strafing and<space/><link><target>skip bombing</target></link><space/>missions against Japanese shipping trying to resupply their armies.</paragraph><paragraph>Under the leadership of<space/><link><target>Lieutenant General</target></link><space/><link><target>George C. Kenney</target></link>, Mitchells of the Far East Air Forces and its exising components, the<space/><link><target>Fifth Air Force</target><part>Fifth</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thirteenth Air Force</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>devastated Japanese targets in the Southwest Pacific Theater during 1944 to 1945. The USAAF played a significant role in pushing the Japanese back to their home islands. The type operated with great effect in the<space/><link><target>Pacific Ocean Areas (command)</target><part>Central Pacific</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of the Aleutian Islands</target><part>Alaska</part></link>,<space/><link><target>North African campaign</target><part>North Africa</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of the Mediterranean</target><part>Mediterranean</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South-East Asian theatre of World War II</target><part>China-Burma-India</part></link><space/>(CBI) theaters.</paragraph><paragraph>The AAF Antisubmarine Command made great use of the B-25 in 1942 and 1943. Some of the earliest B-25 Bomb Groups also flew the Mitchell on coastal patrols after the Pearl Harbor attack, prior to the AAFAC organization. Many of the two dozen or so Antisubmarine Squadrons flew the B-25C, D and G series in the American Theater Antisubmarine campaign, often in the distinctive, white sea search camouflage.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Combat developments</heading><heading level='5'>Use as a gunship</heading><preblock><preline><link><target>File:North American B-25 Mitchell.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A view of a B-25G shows the mid-ship location of dorsal turret continued.</part></link></preline></preblock><paragraph>In anti-shipping operations, the AAF had urgent need for hard-hitting aircraft, and North American responded with the B-25G. In this series the transparent nose and bombardier/navigator position was changed for a shorter, hatched nose with two fixed .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns and a<space/><link><target>75 mm Gun M2/M3/M6</target><part>75&amp;nbsp;mm (2.95&amp;nbsp;in) M4 cannon</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Merriam">Merriam, Ray, ed.<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/?id=R7GjzzNMpu4C&amp;amp;lpg=PA8&amp;amp;pg=PA8'>&quot;U. S. Warplanes of World War II.&quot;</link><space/><italics>World War II Journal, No. 15,</italics><space/>1 July 2000, p. 8.</extension><space/>one of the largest weapons fitted to an aircraft, similar to the experimental British<space/><link><target>Ordnance QF 6-pounder</target><part>57&amp;nbsp;mm gun</part></link>-armed<space/><link><target>de Havilland Mosquito</target><part>Mosquito Mk. XVIII</part></link><space/>and the German<space/><link><target>Junkers Ju 88</target><part>Ju 88P</part></link><space/>heavy cannon (up to a 75&amp;nbsp;mm long-barrel<space/><italics>Bordkanone BK 7,5</italics>). The shorter nose placed the cannon breech behind the pilot where it could be manually loaded and serviced by the navigator; his crew station relocated to just behind the pilot. The navigator signalled the pilot when the gun was ready and the pilot fired the weapon using a button on his control wheel.</paragraph><paragraph>The RAF, USN and USSR each conducted trials with this series but none adopted it. The G series comprised of one prototype, five pre-production C conversions, 58 C series modifications and 400 production aircraft for a total of 464 B-25G. In its final version, the G-12, an interim armament modification, eliminated the lower Bendix turret and added a starboard dual gun pack, waist guns and a canopy for the tail gunner to improve the view when firing the single tail gun. In April 1945 the air depots in Hawaii refurbished about two dozen of these and included the eight gun nose and rocket launchers in the upgrade.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The B-25H series continued the development of the gunship concept. NAA Inglewood produced 1000. The H had even more firepower. Most replaced the M4 gun with the lighter<space/><link><target>75 mm gun (US)#T13E1 / M5</target><part>T13E1</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Merriam"></extension><space/>designed specifically for the aircraft but 20-odd H-1 block aircraft completed by the<space/><link><target>Republic Aviation</target></link><space/>modification center at Evansville had the M4 and two machine gun nose armament. The 75&amp;nbsp;mm (2.95&amp;nbsp;in) gun fired at a muzzle velocity of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2,362</arg><arg>ft/s</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg><arg name="lk">on</arg></template>. Due to its low rate of fire (about four rounds could be fired in a single<space/><link><target>strafing</target></link><space/>run), relative ineffectiveness against ground targets, and the substantial recoil, the 75&amp;nbsp;mm gun was sometimes removed from both G and H models and replaced with two additional .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns as a field modification.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kinzey 1999, pp. 51, 53.</extension><space/>In the new FEAF these were re-designated the G1 and H1 series respectively.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:B-25H.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A restored B-25H &quot;Barbie III&quot; showing 75 mm M5 gun and four 0.50 Browning with belt feeds</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The H series normally came from the factory mounting four fixed, forward-firing .50&amp;nbsp; (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns in the nose; four more fixed guns in forward-firing, individual gun packages; two more in the manned dorsal turret, re-located forward to a position just behind the cockpit; one each in a pair of new waist positions, introduced simultaneously with the forward-relocated dorsal turret; and lastly, a pair of guns in a new tail gunner's position. Company promotional material bragged that the B-25H could &quot;bring to bear 10 machine guns coming and four going, in addition to the 75&amp;nbsp;mm cannon, eight<space/><link><target>unguided rocket</target><part>rockets</part></link><space/>and 3,000&amp;nbsp;lb (1,360&amp;nbsp;kg) of bombs.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Yenne 1989, p. 40.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The H had a modified cockpit with single flight controls operated by pilot. The co-pilot's station and controls were deleted, and instead had a smaller seat used by the navigator/cannoneer, The radio operator crew position was aft the bomb bay with access to the waist guns.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kinzey 1999, pp. 5253.</extension><space/>Factory production total were 405 B-25Gs and 1,000 B-25Hs with, 248 of the latter being used by the Navy as PBJ-1H.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Merriam"></extension><space/>Elimination of the co-pilot saved weight, moving the dorsal turret forward counterbalanced in part the waist guns and the manned rear turret.<extension extension_name='ref'>Baugher, Joe.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.joebaugher.com/usaf_bombers/b25_15.html'>North American B-25H Mitchell.&quot;</link><space/><italics>American Military Aircraft: US Bomber Aircraft</italics>, 11 March 2000. Retrieved: 28 May 2015.</extension></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='5'>Return to medium bomber</heading><paragraph>Following the two gunship series NAA again produced the medium bomber configuration with the B-25J series.. It optimized the mix of the interim NA-100 and the H series having both the bombardier's station and fixed guns of the D and the forward turret and refined armament of the H series. NAA also produced a strafer nose first shipped to air depots as kits, then introduced on the production line in alternating blocks with the bombardier nose. The solid-metal &quot;strafer&quot; nose housed eight centerline Browning M2 .50 calibre machine guns. The remainder of the armament was as in the H-5. NAA also supplied kits to mount eight underwing 5 &quot;high velocity airborne rockets&quot; (HVAR) just outside the propeller arcs. These were mounted on zero length launch rails, four to a wing.<link><target>File:Restored B-25J Take-off Time at an air show.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>The restored B-25J Mitchell ''Take-Off Time'' at the<space/><link><target>Mid-Atlantic Air Museum</target></link><space/>for World War II Weekend 2015 in<space/><link><target>Reading, Pennsylvania</target></link></part></link>The final, and the most built, series of the Mitchell, the<space/><bold>B-25J</bold>, looked less like earlier series apart from the well-glazed bombardier's nose of nearly-identical appearance to the earliest B-25 subtypes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Merriam"></extension><space/>Instead, the J followed the overall configuration of the H series from the cockpit aft. It had the forward dorsal turret and other armament and airframe advancements. All J models included four .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) light-barrel Browning AN/M2 guns in a pair of &quot;fuselage package&quot;, conformal<space/><link><target>gun pod</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>each flanking the lower cockpit, each pod containing two<space/><link><target>Browning M2</target><trail>s</trail></link>. By 1945, however, combat squadrons removed these. The J series restored the co-pilot's seat and dual flight controls. The factory made available kits to the Air Depot system to create the strafer-nose B-25J-2. This configuration carried a total of 18 .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) light-barrel AN/M2 Browning M2 machine guns: eight in the nose, four in the flank-mount conformal gun pod packages, two in the dorsal turret, one each in the pair of waist positions, and a pair in the tail with 14 of the guns either aimed directly forward, or aimed to fire directly forward for strafing missions. Some aircraft had eight<space/><link><target>5-Inch Forward Firing Aircraft Rocket</target><part>5 in (130 mm) high-velocity aircraft rockets (HVAR)</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Merriam"></extension><space/>NAA introduced the J-2 into production in alternating blocks at the J-22. Total J series production was 4,318.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Flight characteristics</heading><paragraph>The B-25 was a safe and forgiving aircraft to fly.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tallman 1973, pp. 216, 228.</extension><space/>With one engine out, 60 banking turns into the dead engine were possible, and control could be easily maintained down to 145&amp;nbsp;mph (230&amp;nbsp;km/h). The pilot had to remember to maintain engine-out directional control at low speeds after takeoff with rudder; if this maneuver was attempted with ailerons, the aircraft could snap out of control. The tricycle landing gear made for excellent visibility while taxiing. The only significant complaint about the B-25 was the extremely high noise level produced by its engines; as a result, many pilots eventually suffered from varying degrees of<space/><link><target>hearing loss</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dbvxho">Higham 1978</extension><template><target>page needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The high noise level was due to design and space restrictions in the engine cowlings which resulted in the exhaust &quot;stacks&quot; protruding directly from the cowling ring and partly covered by a small triangular fairing. This arrangement directed exhaust and noise directly at the pilot and crew compartments. Crew members and operators on the air show circuit frequently commented that &quot;the B-25 is the fastest way to turn aviation fuel directly into noise&quot;.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Durability</heading><paragraph>The Mitchell was an exceptionally sturdy aircraft that could withstand tremendous punishment. One B-25C of the<space/><link><target>321st Bombardment Group</target><part>321st Bomb Group</part></link><space/>was nicknamed &quot;Patches&quot; because its crew chief painted all the aircraft's<space/><link><target>flak</target></link><space/>hole patches with high-visibility<space/><link><target>zinc chromate</target></link><space/>primer. By the end of the war, this aircraft had completed over 300 missions, had been belly-landed six times and had over 400 patched holes. The airframe of &quot;Patches&quot; was so distorted from battle damage that straight-and-level flight required 8 of left<space/><link><target>aileron</target></link><space/>trim and 6 of right rudder, causing the aircraft to &quot;crab&quot; sideways across the sky.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.usaf.com/pastplanes/b-25.htm'>&quot;A Brief history of the B-25.&quot;</link><space/>USAF.com. Accessed: 25 May 2015.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Range</heading><paragraph>B-25 pilots could extend range by using one-quarter wing flap settings. Since the aircraft normally cruised in a slightly nose-high attitude, about 40&amp;nbsp;gal (150&amp;nbsp;l) of fuel was below the fuel pickup point and thus unavailable for use. The flaps-down setting gave the aircraft a more level flight attitude, which resulted in this fuel becoming available, thus slightly extending the aircraft's range.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Post war (USAF) use</heading><paragraph>In 1947 legislation created an independent<space/><link><target>United States Air Force</target></link><space/>and by that time the B-25 inventory numbered only a few hundred. Some B-25s continued in service into the 1950s in a variety of training, reconnaissance and support roles. The principal use during this period was undergraduate training of multi-engine aircraft pilots slated for reciprocating engine or turboprop cargo, aerial refuelling or reconnaissance aircraft. Others were assigned to units of the<space/><link><target>Air National Guard</target></link><space/>in training roles in support of<space/><link><target>Northrop F-89 Scorpion</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lockheed F-94 Starfire</target></link><space/>operations.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In its USAF tenure, many B-25s received the so-called &quot;Hayes modification&quot; and as a result, surviving B-25 often exhibit exhaust system with a semi-collector ring that splits emissions into two different systems. The upper seven cylinders are collected by a ring while the other cylinders remain directed to individual ports.</paragraph><paragraph>TB-25J-25-NC Mitchell,<space/><italics>44-30854</italics>, the last B-25 in the USAF inventory, assigned at<space/><link><target>March AFB</target></link>, California as of March 1960,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Doolittle Park Will Have AF B-25 Bomber&quot;.<space/><italics>Playground News</italics><space/>(Fort Walton Beach, Florida), Volume 15, Number 7, 10 March 1960, p. 10.</extension><space/>was flown to<space/><link><target>Eglin AFB</target></link>, Florida, from<space/><link><target>Turner Air Force Base</target></link>, Georgia, on 21 May 1960, the last flight by a USAF B-25, and presented by Brigadier General A. J. Russell, Commander of<space/><link><target>Strategic Air Command</target><part>SAC</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>822d Air Division</target></link><space/>at Turner AFB, to the Air Proving Ground Center Commander, Brigadier General Robert H. Warren, who in turn presented the bomber to<space/><link><target>Valparaiso, Florida</target></link><space/>Mayor Randall Roberts on behalf of the Niceville-Valparaiso Chamber of Commerce. Four of the original<space/><link><target>Doolittle Raid</target><part>Tokyo Raiders</part></link><space/>were present for the ceremony, Colonel<space/><link><target>David M. Jones</target><part>Davy Jones</part></link>, Colonel Jack Simms, Lieutenant Colonel Joseph Manske, and retired Master Sergeant Edwin W. Horton.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;B-25 Makes Last Flight During Ceremony at Eglin&quot;.<space/><italics>Playground News</italics><space/>(Fort Walton Beach, Florida), Volume 15, Number &quot;17&quot; (actually No. 18: Special), 26 May 1960, p. 2.</extension><space/>It was donated back to the<space/><link><target>Air Force Armament Museum</target></link><space/>c. 1974 and marked as Doolittle's<space/><italics>40-2344</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.warbirdregistry.org/b25registry/b25-4430854.html'>&quot;B-25 44-330854.&quot;</link><space/><italics>warbirdregistry.org</italics>. Retrieved: 30 December 2009.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>U.S. Navy and USMC</heading><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The U.S. Navy designation for the Mitchell as the PBJ-1 and apart from increased use of radar, it was configured like its Army counterparts series. The designation standing for Patrol (P) Bomber (B) built by North American Aviation (J), first variant (-1) under the<space/><link><target>1922 United States Navy aircraft designation system</target><part>existing American naval aircraft designation system of the era</part></link>. The PBJ had its origin in an inter-service agreement of mid-1942 between the Navy and the USAAF exchanging the Boeing Renton plant for the Kansas plant for B-29 production. The<space/><link><target>Boeing XPBB Sea Ranger</target></link><space/>flying boat competing for B-29 engines, was cancelled in exchange for part of the Kansas City Mitchell production. Other terms included the inter-service transfer of 50 B-25C and 152 B-25D to the Navy. The bombers carried Navy<space/><link><target>bureau number</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(BuNos), beginning with BuNo 34998. The first PBJ-1 arrived in February 1943 and nearly all reached Marine Corps squadrons, beginning with Marine Bombing Squadron 413 (VMB-413). Following the AAFAC format, the Marine Mitchells had search<space/><link><target>radar</target></link><space/>in a retractable radome replacing the ventral turret. Later D and J series had nose mounted APS-3 radar; and later still, J and H series mounted radar in the starboard wingtip. The large quantities of B-25H and J series became known as PBJ-1H and PBJ-1J respectively. These aircraft often operated along with earlier PBJ series in Marine squadrons.</paragraph><paragraph>The PBJs were operated almost exclusively by the Marine Corps as land-based bombers. To operate them, the<space/><link><target>U.S. Marine Corps</target></link><space/>established a number of Marine bomber squadrons (VMB), beginning with VMB-413, in March 1943 at<space/><link><target>MCAS Cherry Point</target></link>, North Carolina. Eight VMB squadrons were flying PBJs by the end of 1943, forming the initial Marine medium bombardment group. Four more squadrons were in the process of formation in late 1945, but had not yet deployed by the time the war ended.</paragraph><paragraph>Operational use of the Marine Corps PBJ-1s began in March 1944. The Marine PBJs operated from the Philippines, Saipan,<space/><link><target>Iwo Jima</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Okinawa</target></link><space/>during the last few months of the Pacific war. Their primary mission was the long range<space/><link><target>interdiction</target></link><space/>of enemy shipping trying to run the blockade which was strangling Japan. The weapon of choice during these missions was usually the five-inch HVAR rocket, eight of which could be carried. Some VMB-612 intruder PBJ-1D and J series flew without top turrets to save weight and increase range on night patrols, especially towards the end of the war when air superiority existed.</paragraph><paragraph>During the war the Navy tested the cannon-armed G series and conducted carrier trial with an H equipped with arresting gear. After World War II, some PBJs stationed at the Navy's rocket laboratory in<space/><link><target>Inyokern, California</target></link>, the present-day<space/><link><target>Naval Air Weapons Station China Lake</target></link>, tested various air-to-ground rockets and arrangements. One arrangement was a twin-barrel nose arrangement that could fire 10 spin-stabilized five-inch rockets in one salvo.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=O-ADAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA113&amp;amp;source=gbs_ge_summary_r&amp;amp;cad=0#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>&quot;Smash Hits.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Popular Mechanics</italics>, March 1947, p. 113.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Royal Air Force</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Royal Air Force</target></link><space/>(RAF) was an early customer for the B-25 via<space/><link><target>Lend-Lease</target></link>. The first Mitchells were given the service name Mitchell I by the RAF and were delivered in August 1941, to No. 111 Operational Training Unit based in<space/><link><target>the Bahamas</target></link>. These bombers were used exclusively for training and familiarization and never achieved operational status. The B-25Cs and Ds were designated Mitchell II. Altogether, 167 B-25Cs and 371 B-25Ds were delivered to the RAF. The RAF tested the cannon-armed G series but did not adopt the series nor the follow on H series.</paragraph><paragraph>By the end of 1942 the RAF had taken delivery of a total of 93 Mitchell marks I and II. Some served with squadrons of<space/><link><target>No. 2 Group RAF</target></link>, the RAF's tactical medium bomber force. The first RAF operation with the Mitchell II took place on 22 January 1943, when six aircraft from<space/><link><target>No. 180 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>attacked oil installations at<space/><link><target>Ghent</target></link>. After the invasion of Europe (by which point 2 Group was part of<space/><link><target>Second Tactical Air Force</target></link>), all four Mitchell squadrons moved to bases in France and Belgium (Melsbroek) to support Allied ground forces. The British Mitchell squadrons were joined by<space/><link><target>No. 342 Squadron RAF</target><part>No. 342 (Lorraine) Squadron</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>French Air Force</target></link><space/>in April 1945.</paragraph><paragraph>As part of its move from Bomber Command,<space/><link><target>No. 305 Polish Bomber Squadron</target><part>No 305 (Polish) Squadron</part></link><space/>flew Mitchell IIs from September to December 1943 before converting to the<space/><link><target>de Havilland Mosquito</target></link>. In addition to No. 2 Group, the B-25 was used by various second-line RAF units in the UK and abroad. In the Far East, No. 3 PRU, which consisted of<space/><link><target>No. 681 Squadron RAF</target><part>Nos. 681</part></link><space/>and 684 Squadrons, flew the Mitchell (primarily Mk IIs) on photographic reconnaissance sorties.</paragraph><paragraph>The RAF was allocated 316 B-25J which entered service as the Mitchell III. Deliveries took place between August 1944 and August 1945. However, only about 240 of these bombers actually reached Britain, with some being diverted to No. 111<space/><link><target>Operational training unit</target><part>OTU</part></link><space/>in the Bahamas, some crashing during delivery and some being retained in the United States.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Royal Canadian Air Force</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Royal Canadian Air Force</target></link><space/>(RCAF) used the B-25 Mitchell for training during the war. Post-war use saw continued operations with most of 162 Mitchells received. The first B-25s had originally been diverted to Canada from RAF orders. These included one Mitchell I, 42 Mitchell IIs, and 19 Mitchell IIIs. No 13 (P) Squadron was formed unofficially at<space/><link><target>Ottawa/Rockcliffe Airport</target><part>RCAF Rockcliffe</part></link><space/>in May 1944 and used Mitchell IIs on high-altitude aerial photography sorties. No. 5 OTU (Operational Training Unit) at Boundary Bay, British Columbia and Abbotsford, British Columbia, operated the B-25D Mitchell in the training role together with B-24 Liberators for Heavy Conversion as part of the BCATP. The RCAF retained the Mitchell until October 1963.<extension extension_name='ref'>Skaarup 2009, pp. 333334.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>No 418 (Auxiliary) Squadron received its first Mitchell IIs in January 1947. It was followed by No 406 (auxiliary), which flew Mitchell IIs and IIIs from April 1947 to June 1958. No 418 Operated a mix of IIs and IIIs until March 1958. No 12 Squadron of Air Transport Command also flew Mitchell IIIs along with other types from September 1956 to November 1960. In 1951, the RCAF received an additional 75 B-25Js from USAF stocks to make up for attrition and to equip various second-line units.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walker, R.W.R.<space/><link type='external' href='http://rwrwalker.ca/RCAF_5200_5249_detailed.html'>&quot;RCAF 5200 to 5249, Detailed List.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Canadian Military Aircraft Serial Numbers</italics>, 25 May 2013. Retrieved: 25 May 2015.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Royal Australian Air Force</heading><paragraph>The Australians received Mitchells by the spring of 1944. The joint Australian-Dutch<space/><link><target>No. 18 (Netherlands East Indies) Squadron RAAF</target></link><space/>had more than enough Mitchells for one squadron, so the surplus went to re-equip the RAAF's<space/><link><target>No. 2 Squadron RAAF</target><part>No. 2 Squadron</part></link>, replacing their Beauforts.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Dutch Air Force</heading><paragraph>During World War II, the Mitchell served in fairly large numbers with the Air Force of the Dutch government-in-exile. They participated in combat in the East Indies as well as on the European front. On 30 June 1941, the Netherlands Purchasing Commission, acting on behalf of the Dutch government-in-exile in London, signed a contract with North American Aviation for 162 B-25C aircraft. The bombers were to be delivered to the<space/><link><target>Netherlands East Indies</target></link><space/>to help deter any Japanese aggression into the region.</paragraph><paragraph>In February 1942, the<space/><link><target>British Overseas Airways Corporation</target></link><space/>(BOAC) agreed to ferry 20 Dutch B-25s from Florida to Australia travelling via Africa and India, and an additional ten via the South Pacific route from California. During March, five of the bombers on the Dutch order had reached<space/><link><target>Bangalore</target></link>, India and 12 had reached Archerfield in Australia. It was agreed that the B-25s in Australia would be used as the nucleus of a new squadron, designated No. 18. This squadron was staffed jointly by Australian and Dutch aircrews plus a smattering of aircrews from other nations, and operated - at least initially - under Royal Australian Air Force command.</paragraph><paragraph>The B-25s of No. 18 Squadron were painted with the Dutch national insignia (at this time a rectangular Netherlands flag) and carried NEIAF serials. Discounting the ten &quot;temporary&quot; B-25s delivered to 18 Squadron in early 1942, a total of 150 Mitchells were taken on strength by the NEIAF, 19 in 1942, 16 in 1943, 87 in 1944, and 28 in 1945. They flew bombing raids against Japanese targets in the East Indies. In 1944, the more capable B-25J Mitchell replaced most of the earlier C and D models.</paragraph><paragraph>In June 1940,<space/><link><target>No. 320 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>had been formed from personnel formerly serving with the<space/><link><target>Netherlands Naval Aviation Service</target><part>Royal Dutch Naval Air Service</part></link><space/>who had escaped to England after the German occupation of the Netherlands. Equipped with various British aircraft, No. 320 Squadron flew anti-submarine patrols, convoy escort missions, and performed air-sea rescue duties. They acquired the Mitchell II in September 1943, performing operations over Europe against gun emplacements, railway yards, bridges, troops and other tactical targets. They moved to Belgium in October 1944, and transitioned to the Mitchell III in 1945. No. 320 Squadron was disbanded in August 1945. Following the war, B-25s were used in Indonesia.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Soviet Air Force</heading><paragraph>The U.S. supplied 862 B-25s (B, D, G, and J types) to the Soviet Union under<space/><link><target>Lend-Lease</target></link><space/>during World War II via the AlaskaSiberia<space/><link><target>ALSIB</target></link><space/>ferry route.</paragraph><paragraph>Other damaged aircraft arrived or crashed in the Far East of Russia, and one Doolittle Raid aircraft landed there short of fuel after attacking Japan. The lone airworthy aircraft to reach the Soviet Union was lost in a hangar fire in the early 50s while undergoing routine maintenance. In general, the B-25 was operated as a ground-support and tactical daylight bomber (as similar Douglas A-20 Havocs were used). It saw action in fights from Stalingrad (with B/D models) to the German surrender during May 1945 (with G/J types).</paragraph><paragraph>B-25s that remained in Soviet Air Force service after the war were assigned the<space/><link><target>NATO reporting name</target></link><space/>&quot;<bold>Bank</bold>&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>China</heading><paragraph>Well over 100 B-25Cs and Ds were supplied to the Nationalist Chinese during the<space/><link><target>Second Sino-Japanese War</target></link>. In addition, a total of 131 B-25Js were supplied to China under Lend-Lease.</paragraph><paragraph>The four squadrons of the 1st BG (1st, 2nd, 3rd, and 4th) of the 1st Medium Bomber Group were formed during the war. They formerly operated Russian-built<space/><link><target>Tupolev SB</target><part>Tupolev SB bombers</part></link>, then transferred to the B-25. The 1st BG was under the command of CACW (Chinese-American Composite Wing) while operating B-25s. Following the end of the war in the Pacific, these four bombardment squadrons were established to fight against the Communist insurgency that was rapidly spreading throughout the country. During the<space/><link><target>Chinese Civil War</target></link>, Chinese Mitchells fought alongside de Havilland Mosquitos.</paragraph><paragraph>In December 1948, the Nationalists were forced to retreat to the island of Taiwan, taking many of their Mitchells with them. However, some B-25s were left behind and were impressed into service with the air force of the new People's Republic of China.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Brazilian Air Force</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:B-25J Mitchell - s-n 44-30069 - at Museu Aerospacial in Campos dos Afonsos Air Force Base - Rio de Janeiro.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>B-25J Mitchell ''44-30069'' at ''Museu Aerospacial'' in ''Campos dos Afonsos Air Force Base'', Rio de Janeiro</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>During the war, the Fora Area Brasileira (<link><target>Brazilian Air Force</target><part>FAB</part></link>) received a few B-25s under Lend-Lease. Brazil declared war against the Axis powers in August 1942 and participated in the war against the U-boats in the southern Atlantic. The last Brazilian B-25 was finally declared surplus in 1970.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Free French</heading><paragraph>The Royal Air Force issued at least 21 Mitchell IIIs to No 342 Squadron, which was made up primarily of Free French aircrews. Following the liberation of France, this squadron transferred to the newly formed French Air Force (<italics>Arme de l'Air</italics>) as GB I/20 Lorraine. The aircraft continued in operation after the war, with some being converted into fast VIP transports. They were struck off charge in June 1947.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Variants</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:North American B-25C Mitchell (00910460 178).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>B-25C Mitchell</part></link><link><target>File:77BS B-25.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>USAAF B-25C/D. Note the early radar with<space/><link><target>Yagi antenna</target></link><space/>fitted to the nose</part></link><link><target>File:North American B-25J (00910460 117).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>B-25J</part></link></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>NA-40</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Twin-engined five-seat bomber to meet 1938 USAAF requirement for attack bomber. Powered by two 1,100&amp;nbsp;hp (825&amp;nbsp;kW)<space/><link><target>Pratt &amp; Whitney R-1830</target></link>-56C3G radials. Wingspan 66&amp;nbsp;ft (20.12 m), length 48&amp;nbsp;ft 3&amp;nbsp;in (14.71 m) length. First flew on 29 January 1939 but proved to be underpowered and unstable.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WoF3 p124">Dorr<space/><italics>Wings of Fame</italics><space/>Volume 3, p. 124.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="aerofiles"><link type='external' href='http://aerofiles.com/_noram.html'>&quot;North American&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Aerofiles</italics>, 2009. Retrieved: 12 December 2011.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>NA-40B</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>The NA-40B (also known as the NA-40-2) was a modification of the NA-40 prototype with two 1,600&amp;nbsp;hp (1,200&amp;nbsp;kW) Wright R-2600-A71-3 radials and numerous minor changes. First flew in revised form on 1 March 1939. Crashed: 11 April 1940.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WoF3 p124"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Initial production version of B-25, powered by 1,350&amp;nbsp;hp (1,012&amp;nbsp;kW) R-2600-9 engines. Up to 3,600 lb (1,600 kg) bombs and defensive armament of three .30 machine guns in nose, waist and ventral positions, with one .50 machine gun in the tail. The first nine aircraft were built with constant<space/><link><target>dihedral (aircraft)</target><part>dihedral</part></link><space/>angle. Due to low stability, the wing was redesigned so that the dihedral was eliminated on the outboard section. (Number made: 24.)<extension extension_name='ref' name="WoF3 p124"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="fact b25"><link type='external' href='http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2509'>&quot;Factsheets: North American B-25.&quot;</link><space/><italics>National Museum of the United States Air Force</italics>, 26 June 2009. Retrieved: 13 December 2011.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25A</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Version of the B-25 modified to make it combat ready; additions included<space/><link><target>self-sealing fuel tank</target><trail>s</trail></link>, crew armor, and an improved tail gunner station. No changes were made in the armament. Re-designated obsolete (<italics>RB-25A</italics>) in 1942. (Number made: 40.)<extension extension_name='ref' name="fact b25a"><link type='external' href='http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2510'>&quot;Factsheets: North American B-25A&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>National Museum of the U.S. Air Force</italics>, 26 June 2009. Retrieved: 13 December 2011.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25B</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Tail and gun position removed and replaced by manned dorsal turret on rear fuselage and retractable, remotely operated ventral turret, each with a pair of .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns. A total of 120 were built (this version was used in the<space/><link><target>Doolittle Raid</target></link>). A total of 23 were supplied to the Royal Air Force as the<space/><bold>Mitchell Mk I</bold>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WoF3 p125-6">Dorr<space/><italics>Wings of Fame</italics><space/>Volume 3, pp. 125126.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="fact b25b"><link type='external' href='http://www.nationalmuseum.af.mil/factsheets/factsheet.asp?id=2511'>&quot;Factsheets: North American B-25B.&quot;</link><space/><italics>National Museum of the U.S. Air Force</italics>, 26 June 2009. Retrieved: 26 April 2013.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25C</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Improved version of the B-25B: powerplants upgraded from<space/><link><target>Wright R-2600</target></link>-9 radials to R-2600-13s; de-icing and anti-icing equipment added; the navigator received a sighting blister; nose armament was increased to two .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns, one fixed and one flexible. The B-25C model was the first mass-produced B-25 version; it was also used in the United Kingdom (as the Mitchell II), in Canada, China, the Netherlands and the Soviet Union. (Number made: 1,625.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>ZB-25C</defkey></listitem><listitem><defkey>B-25D</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Through block 20 the series was near identical to the B-25C. The series designation differentiated that the B-25D was made in<space/><link><target>Kansas City, Kansas</target></link>, whereas the B-25C was made in<space/><link><target>Inglewood, California</target></link>. Later blocks with interim armament upgrades were the D2. First flew on 3 January 1942. (Number made: 2,290.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>F-10[[File</defkey><defval>North American F-10 Mitchell.jpg|thumb|right|A F-10 reconnaissance aircraft]]</defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>The F-10 designation distinguished 45 B-25D modified for photographic reconnaissance. All armament, armor and bombing equipment was stripped. Three K.17 cameras were installed, one pointing down and two more mounted at oblique angles within blisters on each side of the nose. Optionally, a second downward-pointing camera could also be installed in the aft fuselage. Although designed for combat operations these aircraft were mainly used for ground mapping.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25D Weather reconnaissance variant</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>In 1944, four B-25Ds were converted for weather reconnaissance. One later user was the<space/><link><target>53d Weather Reconnaissance Squadron</target></link>, originally called the Army Hurricane Reconnaissance Unit, now called the &quot;Hurricane Hunters&quot;. Weather reconnaissance first started in 1943 with the<space/><link><target>1st Weather Reconnaissance Squadron</target><part>First Weather Reconnaissance Squadron</part></link>, with flights on the North Atlantic ferry routes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Robison, Tom.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.awra.us/The%20B-29%20in%20Weather%20Reconnaissance%20by%20Tom%20Robison.htm'>&quot;B-29 in Weather Reconnaissance.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Aerial Weather Reconnaissance Association: Hurricane Hunters.</italics><space/>Retrieved: 2 October 2010.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Gibbins, Scott and Jeffrey Long.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hurricanehunters.com/history.htm'>&quot;The History of the Hurricane Hunters.&quot;</link><space/><italics>Hurricane Hunters Association.</italics><space/>Retrieved: 2 October 2010.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>ZB-25D</defkey></listitem><listitem><defkey>XB-25E</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Single B-25C modified to test de-icing and anti-icing equipment that circulated exhaust from the engines in chambers in the leading and trailing edges and empennage. The aircraft was tested for almost two years, beginning in 1942; while the system proved extremely effective, no production models were built that used it prior to the end of World War II. Many surviving<space/><link><target>warbird</target></link>-flown B-25 aircraft today use the de-icing system from the XB-25E. (Number made: 1, converted.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>ZXB-25E</defkey></listitem><listitem><defkey>XB-25F-A</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Modified B-25C with insulated electrical coils mounted inside the wing and empennage leading edges to test the effectiveness as a de-icing system. The hot air de-icing system tested on the XB-25E was determined to be the more practical of the two. (Number made: 1, converted.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>XB-25G</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Modified B-25C in which the transparent nose was replaced to create a short nosed gunship carrying two fixed .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns and a 75&amp;nbsp;mm (2.95&amp;nbsp;in) M4 cannon, then the largest weapon ever carried on an American bomber. (Number made: 1, converted.)</listitem><listitem>The B-25G followed the success of the prototype XB-25G and production was a continuation of the NA96. The production model featured increased armor and a greater fuel supply than the XB-25G. One B-25G was passed to the British, who gave it the name<space/><bold>Mitchell II</bold><space/>that had been used for the B-25C. The USSR also tested the G. (Number made: 463; 5 converted Cs; 58 modified Cs; 400 production.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25H</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:B-25 At Centennial.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>B-25H ''Barbie III'' taxiing at<space/><link><target>Centennial Airport</target></link>, Colorado</part></link></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>An improved version of the B-25G. This version relocated the manned dorsal turret to a more forward location on the fuselage just aft of the flight deck. It also featured two additional fixed .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine guns in the nose and in the H-5 onward, four in fuselage-mounted pods. the T13E1 light weight cannon replaced the heavy M4 cannon 75&amp;nbsp;mm (2.95&amp;nbsp;in). Single controls from factory with navigator in right seat. (Number made: 1000; two airworthy<space/><template><target>As of</target><arg>2015</arg><arg name="lc">yes</arg></template>)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>B-25J-NC</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Follow-on production at Kansas city, the B-25J, could be called a cross between the B-25D and the B-25H. It had a transparent nose, but many of the delivered aircraft were modified to have a strafer nose (J2). Most of its 1418 machine guns were forward-facing for strafing missions, including the two guns of the forward-located dorsal turret. The RAF received 316 aircraft, which were known as the<space/><bold>Mitchell III</bold>. The J series was the last factory series production of the B-25. (Number made: 4,318.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>CB-25J</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Utility transport version.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>VB-25J</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>A number of B-25s were converted for use as staff and VIP transports.<space/><link><target>Henry H. Arnold</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dwight D. Eisenhower</target></link><space/>both used converted B-25Js as their personal transports. The last VB-25J in active service was retired in May 1960 at the<space/><link><target>Eglin Air Force Base</target></link><space/>in Florida.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drucker, Graham.<link type='external' href='http://www.fleetairarmarchive.net/Aircraft/Mitchell.htm'>&quot;North American B-25 Mitchell.&quot;</link><space/><italics>fleetairarmarchive.net</italics>. Retrieved: 31 March 2013.</extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Trainer variants</heading><paragraph>Most models of the B-25 were used at some point as training aircraft.</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25D</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Originally designated<space/><bold>AT-24A</bold><space/>(Advanced Trainer, Model 24, Version A). Trainer modification of B-25D often with the dorsal turret omitted. In total, 60 AT-24s were built.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25G</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Originally designated<space/><bold>AT-24B</bold>. Trainer modification of B-25G.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25C</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Originally designated<space/><bold>AT-24C</bold>. Trainer modification of B-25C.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25J</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Originally designated<space/><bold>AT-24D</bold>. Trainer modification of B-25J. Another 600 B-25Js were modified after the war.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25K</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Hughes E1 fire-control radar trainer (Hughes). (Number made: 117.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25L</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Hayes pilot-trainer conversion. (Number made: 90.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25M</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Hughes E5 fire-control radar trainer. (Number made: 40.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>TB-25N</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Hayes navigator-trainer conversion. (Number made: 47.)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>U.S. Navy / U.S. Marine Corps variants</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:PBJ-1H VMB-613 open bomb bay.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A PBJ-1H of VMB-613.</part></link><link><target>File:PBJ Philippine guerillas 1945.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Two PBJ-1Ds on Mindanao,1945.</part></link></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>PBJ-1C</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Similar to the B-25C for the U.S. Navy; often fitted with airborne search radar and used in the anti-submarine role.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>PBJ-1D</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Similar to the B-25D for the U.S. Navy and U.S. Marine Corps. Differed in having a single .50&amp;nbsp;in (12.7&amp;nbsp;mm) machine gun in the tail turret and waist gun positions similar to the B-25H. Often fitted with airborne search radar and used in the anti-submarine role.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>PBJ-1G</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>U.S. Navy/U.S. Marine Corps designation for the B-25G. Trials only.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>PBJ-1H</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>U.S. Navy/U.S. Marine Corps designation for the B-25H*</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>PBJ-1J</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>U.S. Navy designation for the B-25J-NC (Blocks 1 through 35) with improvements in radio and other equipment. Beside the standar armament package, the Marines often fitted with 5&quot; underwing rockets and search radar for the anti-shipping/anti-submarine role.</listitem></list><paragraph>The large &quot;Tiny Tim&quot; rocket powered warhead saw use in 1945.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>One PBJ-1H was modified with carrier takeoff and landing equipment and successfully tested on the<space/><link><target>USS Shangri-La</target><part>USS ''Shangri-La''</part></link>, but the Navy did not continue development.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Operators</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:18 sqn (AWM P01818.011).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>B-25 Mitchell bombers from<space/><link><target>No. 18 (Netherlands East Indies) Squadron RAAF</target><part>No. 18 (NEI) Squadron RAAF</part></link><space/>on a training flight near<space/><link><target>Canberra</target></link><space/>in 1942</part></link></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>AUS</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Royal Australian Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 50 aircraft<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>No. 2 Squadron RAAF</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="choir aero p85">Chorlton<space/><italics>Aeroplane</italics><space/>May 2013, p. 85.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>Flag</target><arg>Biafra</arg></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Biafran Air Force</target></link><space/>operated two aircraft.<extension extension_name='ref' name="choir aero p86">Chorlton<space/><italics>Aeroplane</italics><space/>May 2013, p. 86.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>BOL</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:B-25 en Cochabamba Bolivia 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bolivian North American B-25J Mitchell</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fuerza Area Boliviana</target></link><space/>operated 13 aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>BRA</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Brazilian Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 75 aircraft including B-25B, B-25C, B-25J)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>Flag</target><arg>Canada</arg><arg>1921</arg></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Royal Canadian Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 164 aircraft in bomber, light transport, trainer and &quot;special&quot; mission roles<list type='bullet'><listitem>13 Squadron (Mitchell II)</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>ROC</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Republic of China Air Force</target></link><space/>operated more than 180 aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>PRC</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>People's Liberation Army Air Force</target></link><space/>operated captured Nationalist Chinese aircraft.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>CHL</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fuerza Area de Chile</target></link><space/>operated 12 aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>COL</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fuerza Area Colombiana</target></link><space/>operated three aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>CUB</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cuban Army Air Force</target><part>Fuerza Area Revolucionaria</part></link><space/>operated six aircraft</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuban Army Air Force</target><part>Fuerza Area del Ejrcito de Cuba</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuban Army Air Force</target><part>Cuerpo de Aviacin del Ejrcito de Cuba</part></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>DOM</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dominican Air Force</target></link><space/>operated five aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>FRA</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>French Air Force</target><part>Arme de l'Air</part></link><space/>operated 11 aircraft</listitem><listitem><link><target>Free French Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 18 aircraft</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>IDN</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Indonesian Air Force</target></link><space/>received some B-25 Mitchells from Netherlands, the last example retired in 1979.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>MEX</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mexican Air Force</target></link><space/>received three B-25Js in December 1945, which remained in use until at least 1950.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hag AE pt1 p53-4">Hagedorn<space/><italics>Air Enthusiast</italics><space/>May/June 2003, pp. 5354.</extension></listitem><listitem>Eight Mexican civil registrations were allocated to B-25s, including one aircraft registered to the Bank of Mexico but used by the<space/><link><target>President of Mexico</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hag AE pt1 p55">Hagedorn<space/><italics>Air Enthusiast</italics><space/>May/June 2003, p. 55.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>NLD</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Royal Netherlands Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 62 aircraft<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>No. 18 (Netherlands East Indies) Squadron RAAF</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 119 (Netherlands East Indies) Squadron RAAF</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 320 Squadron RAF</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dutch Naval Aviation Service</target></link><space/>operated 107 aircraft<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>No. 320 Squadron RAF</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Netherlands East Indies Army Air Force</target></link><space/>operated 149 aircraft, including many postwar</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>PER</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Peru Air Force</target><part>Cuerpo Aeronutico del Per</part></link><space/>received 8 B-25Js in 1947, which formed Bomber Squadron N 21 at<space/><link><target>Talara</target></link>.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>POL</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Polish Air Forces in France and Great Britain</target><part>Polish Air Forces on exile in Great Britain</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>No. 305 Polish Bomber Squadron</target></link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>flag</target><arg>Spain</arg><arg>1938</arg></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ejrcito del Aire</target></link><space/>operated 1 ex-USAAF example interned in 1944 and operated between 1948 and 1956.<extension extension_name='ref'>Leeuw, Ruud.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ruudleeuw.com/cuatro_vientos04.htm'>&quot;Cuatro Vientos Madrid.&quot;</link><space/><italics>ruudleeuw.com.</italics><space/>Retrieved: 25 August 2010.</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>USSR</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Soviet Air Force</target></link><space/>(<italics>Voyenno-Vozdushnye Sily</italics><space/>or VVS) received a total of 866 B-25s of the C, D, G* &amp; J series.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hardesty 1991, p. 253.</extension><space/>* trials only (5).</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>UK</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Royal Air Force</target></link><space/>received just over 700 aircraft.<template><target>efn</target><arg>The maximum on RAF strength was 517 in December 1944</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="ab">&quot;Mitchells: The North American Mitchell in Royal Air Force service.&quot;<space/><italics>Aeromilitaria</italics><space/>(<link><target>Air-Britain</target></link><space/>Historians), Issue 2, 1978, pp. 4148.</extension><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>No. 98 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- September 1942 - November 1945 (converted to the Mosquito<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 180 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- September 1942 - September 1945 (converted to the Mosquito)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 226 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- May 1943 - September 1945 (disbanded)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 305 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- September 1943 - December 1943 (converted to the Mosquito)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 320 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- March 1943 - August 1945 (transferred to Netherlands)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 342 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- March 1945 - December 1945 (transferred to France)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 681 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- January 1943 - December 1943 (Mitchell withdrawn)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 684 Squadron RAF</target></link><space/>- September 1943 - April 1944 (Replaced by Mosquito)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>No. 111 Operational Training Unit RAF</target></link><space/>August 1942 - August 1945 (disbanded)<extension extension_name='ref' name="ab"></extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/><link><target>Fleet Air Arm</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem>operated 1 aircraft for evaluation<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>US</target></template></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United States Army Air Forces</target></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>see<space/><link><target>B-25 Mitchell units of the United States Army Air Forces</target></link></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United States Navy</target></link><space/>received 706 aircraft, most of which were then transferred to the USMC.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>URU</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fuerza Area Uruguaya</target></link><space/>operated 15 examples</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><template><target>VEN</target></template><space/></defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Venezuelan Air Force</target><part>Fuerza Area Venezolana</part></link><space/>operated 24 examples</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Survivors</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:B-25J Mitchell high bank 80th.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Mitchell III, in RAF configuration with<space/><link><target>invasion stripes</target></link>, of the<space/><link><target>Canadian Warplane Heritage Museum</target></link><space/>during the Brantford Air Show at<space/><link><target>Brantford, Ontario</target></link>, Canada</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of surviving B-25 Mitchells</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Today, many B-25s are kept in airworthy condition by air museums and collectors.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Specifications (B-25H)</heading><paragraph><template><target>aircraft specifications</target><arg name="plane or copter?">plane
</arg><arg name="jet or prop?">prop
</arg><arg name="ref">United States Military Aircraft since 1909<ref name</arg><arg name="crew">6 (one pilot, one co-pilot, navigator/bombardier, turret gunner/engineer, radio operator/waist gunner, tail gunner)
</arg><arg name="length main">52 ft 11 in
</arg><arg name="length alt">16.13 m
</arg><arg name="span main">67 ft 7 in
</arg><arg name="span alt">20.60 m
</arg><arg name="height main">16 ft 4 in
</arg><arg name="height alt">4.98 m
</arg><arg name="area main">610 sq&nbsp;ft
</arg><arg name="area alt">56.7 m
</arg><arg name="empty weight main">19,480 lb
</arg><arg name="empty weight alt">8,855 kg
</arg><arg name="loaded weight main">
</arg><arg name="loaded weight alt">
</arg><arg name="max takeoff weight main">35,000 lb
</arg><arg name="max takeoff weight alt">15,910 kg
</arg><arg name="engine (prop)">[[Wright R-2600]]-92 ''Twin Cyclone''
</arg><arg name="type of prop">14-cylinder air-cooled [[radial engine]]
</arg><arg name="number of props">2
</arg><arg name="power main">1,700 hp
</arg><arg name="power alt">1,267 kW
</arg><arg name="max speed main">272 mph
</arg><arg name="max speed alt">237 kn, 438 km/h
</arg><arg name="max speed more"><space/>at 13,000 ft (3,960 m)
</arg><arg name="cruise speed main">230 mph
</arg><arg name="cruise speed alt">200 knots, 370 km/h
</arg><arg name="range main">1,350 mi
</arg><arg name="range alt">1,174 nmi, 2,174 km
</arg><arg name="ceiling main">24,200 ft
</arg><arg name="ceiling alt">7,378 m
</arg><arg name="climb rate main">
</arg><arg name="climb rate alt">
</arg><arg name="guns">1218  .50 in (12.7 mm) [[Browning M2|machine gun]]s and 75 mm (2.95 in) T13E1 cannon
</arg><arg name="bombs">3,000 lb (1,360 kg) bombs 
</arg><arg name="hardpoints">2,000 lb (900 kg) ventral shackles to hold one external [[Mark 13 torpedo]]<ref>Caiden 1957, p. 176.</ref>
</arg><arg name="rockets">racks for eight {{convert|5|in|mm|0|abbr</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Accidents and incidents</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Empire State Building crash</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>B-25 Empire State Building crash</arg></template>At 9:40 on Saturday, 28 July 1945, a USAAF B-25D crashed in thick fog into the north side of the<space/><link><target>Empire State Building</target></link><space/>between the 79th and 80th floors. Fourteen people died&amp;nbsp; 11 in the building and the three occupants of the aircraft, including the pilot, Colonel William F. Smith.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roberts, William.&quot;ESB News.&quot;<space/><italics>Elevator World, March 1996.</italics></extension><space/>Betty Lou Oliver, an elevator attendant, survived the impact and a subsequent uncontrolled descent in the elevator.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kingwell 2007, p. 12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On Friday, 1 August 1947, a B-25 crashed on Maury Creek near Kelso, Washington with two members of the crew reportedly killed. This crash has been controversially linked by conspiracy theorists with the<space/><link><target>Maury Island Incident</target></link>, a UFO-related<space/><link><target>hoax</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Aircraft in fiction#B-25 Mitchell</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Thirty Seconds Over Tokyo</target></link></italics><space/>(1944) - The B-25 played a major role in this retelling of the 1942 Doolittle Raid</listitem><listitem><italics>Catch 22</italics>- The B-25 featured prominently in the novel<space/><italics><link><target>Catch-22</target></link></italics><space/>by Joseph Heller and<space/><link><target>Catch-22 (film)</target><part>film adaption of the same name</part></link>. In the story, people who were crazy were not obliged to fly missions; but anyone who applied to stop flying was showing a rational concern for their safety, and was sane. This circular paradox that made flying inescapable was known to air force personnel in the story as Catch 22.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Military of the United States</arg><arg>United States Air Force</arg><arg>Aviation</arg></template><template><target>aircontent</target><arg name="related">
*[[North American XB-21]]
*[[North American XB-28]]
</arg><arg name="similar aircraft">
* [[de Havilland Mosquito]]
* [[Martin B-26 Marauder]]
</arg><arg name="see also">
*[[GT-1 (missile)]]
</arg><arg name="lists">
* [[List of aircraft of World War II]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>notelist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Borth, Christy.<space/><italics>Masters of Mass Production</italics>. Indianapolis, Indiana: Bobbs-Merrill Co., 1945.</listitem><listitem>Bridgman, Leonard, ed. &quot;The North American Mitchell.&quot;<space/><italics>Jane's Fighting Aircraft of World War II</italics>. London: Studio, 1946. ISBN 1-85170-493-0.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Martin Caidin</target><part>Caidin, Martin</part></link>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=bT1tfRMvD3IC&amp;amp;pg=PA176'>''Air Force.''</link><space/>New York: Arno Press, 1957.</listitem><listitem>Chorlton, Martyn. &quot;Database: North American B-25 Mitchell&quot;.<space/><italics><link><target>Aeroplane Monthly</target><part>Aeroplane</part></link></italics>, Vol. 41, No. 5, May 2013. pp.&amp;nbsp;6986.</listitem><listitem>Dorr, Robert F. &quot;North American B-25 Variant Briefing&quot;.<space/><italics>Wings of Fame</italics>, Volume 3, 1996. London: Aerospace Publishing. ISBN 1-874023-70-0. ISSN 1361-2034. pp.&amp;nbsp;118141.</listitem><listitem>Green, William.<space/><italics>Famous Bombers of the Second World War</italics>. New York: Doubleday &amp; Company, 1975. ISBN 0-385-12467-8.</listitem><listitem>Hagedorn, Dan. &quot;Latin Mitchells: North American B-25s in South America, Part One&quot;.<space/><italics><link><target>Air Enthusiast</target></link></italics>, No. 105, May/June 2003. pp.&amp;nbsp;5255.</listitem><listitem>Hardesty, Von.<space/><italics>Red Phoenix: The Rise of Soviet Air Power 19411945</italics>. Washington, D.C.: Smithsonian Institution, 1991, first edition 1982. ISBN 0-87474-510-1.</listitem><listitem>Heller, Joseph.<space/><italics>Catch 22</italics>. New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1961. ISBN 0-684-83339-5.</listitem><listitem>Herman, Arthur.<space/><italics>Freedom's Forge: How American Business Produced Victory in World War II,</italics><space/>New York: Random House, 2012. ISBN 978-1-4000-6964-4.</listitem><listitem>Higham, Roy and Carol Williams, eds.<space/><italics>Flying Combat Aircraft of USAAF-USAF (Vol. 1)</italics>. Andrews AFB, Maryland: Air Force Historical Foundation, 1975. ISBN 0-8138-0325-X.</listitem><listitem>Higham, Roy and Carol Williams, eds.<space/><italics>Flying Combat Aircraft of USAAF-USAF (Vol. 2)</italics>. Andrews AFB, Maryland: Air Force Historical Foundation, 1978. ISBN 0-8138-0375-6.</listitem><listitem>Johnsen, Frederick A.<space/><italics>North American B-25 Mitchell</italics>. Stillwater, Minnesota: Voyageur Press, 1997. ISBN 0-933424-77-9.</listitem><listitem>Kingwell, Mark.<space/><italics>Nearest Thing to Heaven: The Empire State Building and American Dreams</italics>. New Haven, Connecticut: Yale University Press, 2007. ISBN 978-03-001-2612-9.</listitem><listitem>Kinzey, Bert.<space/><italics>B-25 Mitchell In Detail</italics>. Carrollton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications Inc., 1999. ISBN 1-888974-13-3.</listitem><listitem>Kit, Mister and Jean-Pierre De Cock.<space/><italics>North American B-25 Mitchell</italics><space/>(in French). Paris, France: ditions Atlas, 1980.</listitem><listitem>McDowell, Ernest R.<space/><italics>B-25 Mitchell in Action (Aircraft number 34)</italics>. Carrollton, Texas: Squadron/Signal Publications Inc., 1978. ISBN 0-89747-033-8.</listitem><listitem>McDowell, Ernest R.<space/><italics>North American B-25A/J Mitchell</italics><space/>(Aircam No.22). Canterbury, Kent, UK: Osprey Publications Ltd., 1971. ISBN 0-85045-027-6.</listitem><listitem>Mizrahi, J.V.<space/><italics>North American B-25: The Full Story of World War II's Classic Medium</italics>. Hollywood, California: Challenge Publications Inc., 1965.</listitem><listitem>Norton, Bill.<space/><italics>American Bomber Aircraft Development in World War 2.</italics><space/>Hersham, Surrey, UK: Midland Publishing, 2012. ISBN 978-1-85780-330-3.</listitem><listitem>Pace, Steve.<space/><italics>B-25 Mitchell Units in the MTO</italics>. Oxford, UK: Osprey Publishing, 2002. ISBN 978-1-8417-6284-5.<space/></listitem><listitem>Pace, Steve.<space/><italics>Warbird History: B-25 Mitchell</italics>. St. Paul, Minnesota: Motorbooks International, 1994. ISBN 0-87938-939-7.</listitem><listitem>Parker, Dana T.<space/><italics>Building Victory: Aircraft Manufacturing in the Los Angeles Area in World War II</italics>. Cypress, California: Dana Parker Enterprises, 2013. ISBN 978-0-9897906-0-4.</listitem><listitem>Scutts, Jerry.<space/><italics>B-25 Mitchell at War</italics>. London: Ian Allan Ltd., 1983. ISBN 0-7110-1219-9.</listitem><listitem>Scutts, Jerry.<space/><italics>North American B-25 Mitchell</italics>. Ramsbury, Marlborough, Wiltshire, UK: Crowood Press, 2001. ISBN 1-86126-394-5.</listitem><listitem>Skaarup, Harold A.<space/><italics>Canadian Warplanes</italics>. Bloomington, Indiana: IUniverse, 2009. ISBN 978-1-4401-6758-4.</listitem><listitem>Swanborough, F.G. and<space/><link><target>Peter M. Bowers</target></link>.<space/><italics>United States Military Aircraft since 1909</italics>. London: Putnam, 1963.</listitem><listitem>Swanborough, Gordon.<space/><italics>North American, An Aircraft Album No. 6</italics>. New York: Arco Publishing Company Inc., 1973. ISBN 0-668-03318-5.</listitem><listitem>Tallman, Frank.<space/><italics>Flying the Old Planes</italics>. New York: Doubleday and Company, 1973. ISBN 978-0-3850-9157-2.</listitem><listitem>Wolf, William.<space/><italics>North American B-25 Mitchell, The Ultimate Look: from Drawing Board to Flying Arsenal</italics>. Atglen, Pennsylvania: Schiffer Publishing, 2008. ISBN 978-0-7643-2930-2.</listitem><listitem>Yenne, Bill.<space/><italics>Rockwell: The Heritage of North American</italics>. New York: Crescent Books, 1989. ISBN 0-517-67252-9.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>B-25 Mitchell</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.joebaugher.com/usaf_bombers/b25.html'>North American B-25 Mitchell Joe Baugher, ''American Military Aircraft: US Bomber Aircraft''</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>YouTube</target><arg name="id">-YQmkjpP6q8</arg><arg name="title">"How to Fly the North American B-25 "Mitchell" Medium Bomber (1944)"</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.popsci.com/archive-viewer?id=oiUDAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=70&amp;amp;query=Vol.+144'>I Fly Mitchell's, February 1944</link><space/><link><target>Popular Science</target></link><space/>article on B-25s in North Africa Theater</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.popsci.com/archive-viewer?id=oiUDAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=105&amp;amp;query=Vol.+144'>Flying Big Gun, February 1944, [[Popular Science</link>] article on 75mm cannon mount.]</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=pCcDAAAAMBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA119&amp;amp;dq=popular+science+june+1941&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=3_GWTNmZMYKnnQfh5d3OCA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=6&amp;amp;ved=0CDwQ6AEwBTge#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=true'>Early B-25 model's tail gun position, extremely rare photo</link></listitem><listitem>A collection photos of the Marine VMB-613 post in the Kwajalein Island at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://digital.lib.uh.edu/cdm4/about_collection.php?CISOROOT=/p15195coll10'>University of Houston Digital Library</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://i-ota.net/BarbieIII/'>Hi-res spherical panoramas; B-25H: A look inside &amp; out &quot;Barbie III&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scribd.com/doc/76131949'>(1943) Report No. NA-5785 Temporary Handbook of Erection and Maintenance Instructions for the B-25 H-1-NA Medium Bombardment Airplanes</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://lend-lease.airforce.ru/english/articles/akvilyanov/index.htm'>&quot;The B-25 Mitchell in the USSR&quot;, an account of the service history of the Mitchell in the Soviet Union's VVS during World War II</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.airspacemag.com/history-of-flight/lake-murrays-mitchell-14033140/?no-ist'>Lake Murray's Mitchell<space/></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>North American Aviation aircraft</target></template><template><target>USAF bomber aircraft</target></template><template><target>US reconnaissance aircraft</target></template><template><target>USAF trainer aircraft</target></template><template><target>USN patrol aircraft</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Gull-wing aircraft</target></link><link><target>Category:United States bomber aircraft 19401949</target></link><link><target>Category:North American Aviation aircraft</target><part>B-25</part></link><link><target>Category:World War II bombers of the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:1941 introductions</target></link></paragraph></article>