<article title='Epistle_to_Philemon'><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template><template><target>Books of the New Testament</target></template><template><target>Bible chapter</target><arg name="letname"><space/>Epistle to Philemon<space/></arg><arg name="previouslink"><space/>Titus 3<space/></arg><arg name="previousletter"><space/>Titus 3<space/></arg><arg name="nextlink"><space/>Hebrews 1<space/></arg><arg name="nextletter"><space/>Hebrews 1<space/></arg><arg name="book"><space/>Epistle to Philemon<space/></arg><arg name="biblepart">[[New Testament]]<space/></arg><arg name="booknum"><space/>18<space/></arg><arg name="category"><space/>[[Pauline epistles]]<space/></arg><arg name="filename"><space/>Fragmento filemon.jpg<space/></arg><arg name="size">250px<space/></arg><arg name="name">Papyrus 87, 200 CE</arg><arg name="caption"><div style</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Epistle of Paul to Philemon</bold>, known simply as<space/><bold>Philemon</bold>, is one of the books of the<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>. It is a<space/><link><target>Prison literature</target><part>prison letter</part></link>, co-authored by<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Saint Timothy</target><part>Timothy</part></link>, to<space/><link><target>Philemon (New Testament person)</target><part>Philemon</part></link>, a leader in the<space/><link><target>Epistle to the Colossians</target><part>Colossian church</part></link>. It deals with the themes of<space/><link><target>forgiveness</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Reconciliation (theology)</target><part>reconciliation</part></link>. Paul does not identify himself as an apostle with authority, but as &quot;a prisoner of Jesus Christ&quot;, calling Timothy &quot;our brother&quot;, and addressing Philemon as &quot;fellowlabourer&quot; and &quot;brother&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Philemon</arg><arg>1:1;1:7;1:20</arg><arg>9</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Onesimus</target></link>, a slave that had departed from his master Philemon, was returning with this epistle wherein Paul asked Philemon to receive him as a &quot;brother beloved&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>verse 1:16 in<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Philemon</arg><arg>1:9–17</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Philemon 1:9–17</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Philemon was a wealthy Christian, possibly a bishop<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Apostolic constitution</target><part>Const. Apost.</part></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/fathers/07157.htm'>VII, 46</link></extension><space/>of the<space/><link><target>house church</target></link><space/>that met in his home (<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Philemon</arg><arg>1:1–2</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Philemon 1:1–2</arg></template>) in<space/><link><target>Colosse</target></link>. This letter is now generally regarded as one of the<space/><link><target>Authorship of the Pauline epistles#undisputed</target><part>undisputed works of Paul</part></link>. It is the shortest of Paul's extant letters, consisting of only 445&amp;nbsp;words and 25&amp;nbsp;verses in the Bible.<extension extension_name='ref'>445 words in Authorized Version text, including 7 italicized words, not counting words in the Title or subscription. Note: Compound words like &quot;fellowlabourer&quot; (from a single Greek compound word), are counted as single words. Other editions, versions and counting methods may vary.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Content and commentary</heading><paragraph>Paul, who was then a prisoner (in either<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Ephesus</target></link>), and Timothy wrote to a fellow saint named Philemon and two of his associates: a woman named Apphia, sometimes assumed to be his wife, and a fellow worker named<space/><link><target>Archippus</target></link>, who is assumed by some to have been Philemon's son<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph>F. F. Bruce, &quot;Philemon,&quot;<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=oza_DbyQS2IC&amp;amp;pg=PA206#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Archippus&amp;amp;f=false'>The Epistles to the Colossians, to Philemon, and to the Ephesians</link></italics>, (New International Commentary on the New Testament), Grand Rapids, MI: William B. Eerdmans, 1984, p.206, ISBN 978-0-8028-2510-0</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>also<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=oza_DbyQS2IC&amp;amp;pg=PA185#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Archippus&amp;amp;f=false'>page 185</link></listitem></list></extension><space/>and who also appears to have had special standing in the church that met in Philemon's house (see<space/><template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Colossians</arg><arg>4:17</arg><arg>9</arg></template>). Since Onesimus was<space/><italics>one</italics><space/>of the Colossians (see Col.4:9 quote below), it can be assumed, though not expressly stated, that Philemon lived in<space/><link><target>Colossae</target></link>. It is supposed that he was wealthy by the standards of the early church; this is supported by noting his house was large enough to accommodate the church that met in his house. Paul wrote on behalf of Onesimus, a former slave of Philemon who had left him. Beyond that, it is not self-evident what has transpired. Onesimus is described as having &quot;departed&quot; from Philemon, once having been &quot;useless&quot; to him (a<space/><link><target>pun</target></link><space/>on Onesimus's name, which means &quot;useful&quot;), and having done him wrong.</paragraph><paragraph>The traditional interpretation is that Onesimus was a runaway slave who became a Christian believer. Paul sent him back to face his aggrieved master, and sought in this letter to effect reconciliation between these two Christians. What is problematic is how Onesimus came to be with Paul. Various suggestions have been given: Onesimus being imprisoned with Paul; Onesimus being brought to Paul by others; Onesimus coming to Paul by chance (or in some Christian understandings, by divine providence); or Onesimus deliberately seeking Paul out, as a friend of his master's, in order to be reconciled.</paragraph><paragraph>However, Onesimus' status as a runaway slave was challenged by Allen Dwight Callahan in an article published in the<space/><italics>Harvard Theological Review</italics>. In this article Callahan notes that the weight of proving Onesimus' servile identity falls on verse 16; beyond this &quot;nothing in the text conclusively indicates that Onesimus was ever the chattel of the letter's chief addressee. Moreover, the expectations fostered by the traditional fugitive slave hypothesis go unrealized in the letter. Modern commentators, even those committed to the prevailing interpretation, have tacitly admitted as much.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Callahan,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/1509909'>&quot;Paul's Epistle to Philemon: Toward an Alternative Argumentum&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The Harvard Theological Review</italics>,<space/><bold>86</bold><space/>(1993), p. 362</extension><space/>Callahan points out that the earliest commentators on this work the homily of<space/><link><target>Origen</target></link><space/>and the Anti-Marcion Preface are silent about Onesimus' possible servile status, and traces the origins of this interpretation to its first documented advocate,<space/><link><target>John Chrysostom</target></link>, who proposed it in his<space/><italics>Homiliae in epistolam ad Philemonem</italics>, during his ministry in<space/><link><target>Antioch</target></link>, circa 386398.<extension extension_name='ref'>Callahan, &quot;Paul's Epistle&quot;, p. 366</extension><space/>In place of the traditional interpretation, Callahan suggests that Onesimus and Philemon are brothers both by blood and religion, but who have become estranged, and the intent of this letter was to reconcile the two men.<extension extension_name='ref'>Callahan, &quot;Paul's Epistle&quot;, pp. 369ff</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The only extant information about Onesimus apart from this letter is found in Paul's epistle to the Colossians 4:79, where Onesimus is called &quot;a faithful and beloved brother&quot;:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>All my state shall Tychicus declare unto you, ''who is'' a beloved brother, and a faithful minister and fellowservant in the Lord:<space/><sup>8</sup>&nbsp;Whom I have sent unto you for the same purpose, that he might know your estate, and comfort your hearts;<space/><sup>9</sup><space/>With Onesimus, a faithful and beloved brother, who is ''one'' of you. They shall make known unto you all things which ''are done'' here.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>Paul uses slavery vs. freedom language often in his writings as a metaphor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Foster, Paul. &quot;Philippians And Philemon: Sacra Pagina Commentary.&quot; p.174</extension><space/>At this time slavery was common, and can be seen as a theme in the book of Philemon. Slavery was most commonly found in households. This letter, seemingly, provided alleviation of suffering of some slaves due to the fact that Paul placed pastoral focus on the issue.<extension extension_name='ref'>Foster, Paul. &quot;Philippians And Philemon: Sacra Pagina Commentary.&quot; p.176</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Although it is a main theme, Paul does not label slavery as negative or positive. Some scholars see it as unthinkable in the times to even question ending slavery. Because slavery was so ingrained into society that the abolitionist would have been at the same time an insurrectionist, and the political effects of such a movement would have been unthinkable.<extension extension_name='ref'><preblock><preline>Gaventa, Beverly Roberts, and David L. Petersen. The New Interpreter's Bible: One-Volume Commentary. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010. p.894</preline></preblock></extension><space/>Paul doesnt question it in this epistle. Paul may have envisioned slavery as a fixed institution. He was not questioning the rightness or wrongness of it. Paul did however view slavery as a human institution, and believed that all human institutions were about to fade away.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaventa, Beverly Roberts, and David L. Petersen. The New Interpreter's Bible: One-Volume Commentary. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010. p.894</extension><space/>This may be because Paul had the perspective that Jesus would return soon. Paul viewed his present world as something that was swiftly passing away.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaventa, Beverly Roberts, and David L. Petersen. The New Interpreter's Bible: One-Volume Commentary. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010. p.895</extension><space/>This is a part of<space/><link><target>Pauline Christianity</target></link><space/>and theology.</paragraph><paragraph>When it comes to Onesimus and his circumstance as a slave, Paul felt that Onesimus should return to Philemon but not as a slave, but under a bond of familial love. Paul also was not suggesting that Onesimus be punished, but Roman law allowed the owner of a runaway slave nearly unlimited privileges of punishment, even execution.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaventa, Beverly Roberts, and David L. Petersen. The New Interpreter's Bible: One-Volume Commentary. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010. p.895</extension><space/>This is a concern of Paul and a reason he is writing to Philemon, asking that Philemon accept Onesimus back in a bond of friendship, forgiveness, and reconciliation. Paul is trying to break through the social barriers dividing people.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaventa, Beverly Roberts, and David L. Petersen. The New Interpreter's Bible: One-Volume Commentary. Nashville: Abingdon, 2010. p.895</extension><space/>We see this in many of Pauls other epistles, including his letters to the Corinthians, delivering the message of unity with others and unity with Christ - a change of identity. As written in Sacra Pagina Philippians and Philemon, the move from slave to freedman has to do with a shift in standing under the lordship of Jesus Christ. So in short, Onesimus honor and obedience is not claimed by Philemon, but by Christ.</paragraph><paragraph>Verses 13-14 suggest that Paul wants Philemon to send Onesimus back to Paul (possibly freeing him for the purpose). Marshall, Travis and Paul write, &quot;Paul hoped that it might be possible for [Onesimus] to spend some time with him as a missionary colleague.... If that is not a request for Onesimus to join Pauls circle, I do not know what more would need to be said&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Marshall</arg><arg name="first1">I. Howard</arg><arg name="last2">Travis</arg><arg name="first2">Stephen</arg><arg name="last3">Paul</arg><arg name="first3">Ian</arg><arg name="title">Exploring the New Testament. Vol. 2: A Guide to the Letters and Revelation</arg><arg name="date">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">InterVarsity Press</arg><arg name="location">Downers Grove, Illinois</arg><arg name="isbn">9780830869404</arg><arg name="page">155</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Significance</heading><paragraph>Paul's tactful address to Philemon was labelled &quot;holy flattery&quot; by<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link>. He saw a parallel between Paul and Christ in their work of<space/><link><target>reconciliation (theology)</target><part>reconciliation</part></link>, which is also contained within the concept of Christian<space/><link><target>Grace (Christianity)</target><part>grace</part></link>. Still, Luther insisted that the letter upheld the social<space/><italics><link><target>status quo</target></link></italics>: though not explicit, the text could be interpreted to indicate that Paul did nothing to change Onesimus's legal position as a servant and that Paul was complying with Roman law in returning him to Philemon. However, the text could<space/><template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template><space/>also be interpreted as indicating that Paul was demanding the legal freedom of Onesimus and, as an act of both trust and reconciliation, holding Philemon accountable in the higher court of God to accomplish this change himself.</paragraph><paragraph>Sarah Ruden, in her<space/><italics>Paul Among the People</italics><space/>(2010), argues that in the letter to Philemon Paul created the Western conception of the individual human being, &quot;unconditionally precious to God and therefore entitled to the consideration of other human beings.&quot; Before Paul, Ruden argues, a slave was considered subhuman, and entitled to no more consideration than an animal.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sarah Ruden,<space/><italics>Paul Among the People</italics><space/>(2010), p. xix.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Diarmaid MacCulloch</target></link>, in his<space/><italics>A History of Christianity</italics>, described the epistle as &quot;a Christian foundation document in the justification of slavery&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Diarmaid MacCulloch</target></link>,<space/><italics>A History of Christianity</italics>, 2009 (Penguin 2010, p. 115), ISBN 978-0-14-102189-8</extension><space/>Due to its ambiguity, the letter was a cause of debate during the British and later American struggles over the<space/><link><target>Abolitionism</target><part>abolition of slavery</part></link>. Both sides cited Philemon for support.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to Philemon</target><part>Textual variants in the Epistle to Philemon</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Christian views on slavery</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EBD</target><arg>Philemon, Epistle to</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>J. M. G. Barclay,<space/><italics>Colossians and Philemon</italics>, Sheffield Academic Press, 1997 ISBN 1-85075-818-2</listitem><listitem><link><target>N. T. Wright</target></link>,<space/><italics>Colossians and Philemon</italics>, Tyndale IVP, 1986 ISBN 0-8028-0309-1</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Wikisource-inline</target><arg>Bible_(King_James)/Philemon</arg><arg>Philemon</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><small>[[Pastoral epistles|Pastoral]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]<br>to</small><space/>[[Epistle to Titus|Titus]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><small>[[New Testament]]</small><br>[[Books of the Bible]]</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Epistle to Hebrews|<small>Epistle to<br>the</small><space/>Hebrews]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Epistle To Philemon</target></template><link><target>Category:New Testament books</target><part>Philemon</part></link><link><target>Category:Pauline-related books</target></link><link><target>Category:Prison writings</target></link><link><target>Category:Canonical epistles</target><part>Philemon</part></link><link><target>Category:1st-century Christianity</target></link><link><target>Category:Slavery in ancient Rome</target></link></paragraph></article>