<article title='Baroque_dance'><paragraph><link><target>File:Baroquedance.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Final plate from Kellom Tomlinson's dancing manual ''The Art of Dancing Explained'' (London, 1735).<space/><template><target>audio</target><arg>The Art of Dancing Explained-The conclusion or presenting of both arms.mid</arg><arg>Play notation</arg></template></part></link><bold>Baroque dance</bold><space/>is<space/><link><target>dance</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Baroque</target></link><space/>era (roughly 16001750), closely linked with<space/><link><target>Baroque music</target></link>, theatre and opera.</paragraph><heading level='2'>English country dance</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>English Country Dance</arg></template>The majority of surviving choreographies from the period are<space/><link><target>English country dance</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as those in the many editions of<space/><link><target>John Playford</target><part>Playford's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>The Dancing Master</target></link></italics>. Playford only gives the floor patterns of the dances, with no indication of the steps. However other sources of the period, such as the writings of the French dancing-masters<space/><link><target>Raoul Auger Feuillet</target><part>Feuillet</part></link><space/>and Lorin, indicate that steps more complicated than simple walking were used at least some of the time.</paragraph><paragraph>English country dance survived well beyond the Baroque era and eventually spread in various forms across Europe and its colonies, and to all levels of society. See the article on<space/><link><target>English country dance</target></link><space/>for more information.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The French Noble style</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>French ballet</arg></template><link><target>Image:Ballet de la nuit 1653.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>A costume design for Louis XIV as The Rising Sun, from the final entre of ''<link><target>Ballet de la Nuit</target><part>Le Ballet de la Nuit</part></link>'' (1653).</part></link>The great innovations in dance in the 17th century originated at the French court under<space/><link><target>Louis XIV of France</target><part>Louis XIV</part></link>, and it is here that we see the first clear stylistic ancestor of<space/><link><target>classical ballet</target></link>. The same basic technique was used both at social events, and as theatrical dance in court ballets and at public theaters. The style of dance is commonly known to modern scholars as the<space/><italics>French noble style</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>belle danse</italics><space/>(French, literally &quot;beautiful dance&quot;), however it is often referred to casually as<space/><italics>baroque dance</italics><space/>in spite of the existence of other theatrical and social dance styles during the baroque era.</paragraph><paragraph>Primary sources include more than three hundred choreographies in<space/><link><target>Beauchamp-Feuillet notation</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Little, Meredith Ellis and Marsh, Carol G.<space/><italics>La Danse Noble, An Inventory of Dances and Sources</italics>, (Broude Brothers Ltd, 1992) ISBN 0-8450-0092-6</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lancelot, Francine,<space/><italics>La Belle Dance: Catalogue Raisonn</italics>, (Van Dieren Editeur, 1996) ISBN 2-911087-02-X</extension><space/>as well as manuals by<space/><link><target>Raoul Handsome Auger Feuillet</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pierre Rameau</target></link><space/>in France,<space/><link><target>Kellom Tomlinson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Weaver (dancer)</target><part>John Weaver</part></link><space/>in England, and<space/><link><target>Gottfried Taubert</target></link><space/>in Germany. This wealth of evidence has allowed modern scholars and dancers to recreate the style, although areas of controversy still exist. The standard modern introduction is Hilton.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hilton, Wendy,<space/><italics>Dance and Music of Court and Theater: Selected Writings of Wendy Hilton</italics><space/>(Pendragon Press, 1997) ISBN 0-945193-98-X</extension></paragraph><paragraph>French dance types include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Allemande</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bourre</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Canarie (dance)</target><part>Canarie</part></link><space/>(canary)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chaconne</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Courante</target><part>(French) courante</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Entre grave</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Forlane</target></link><space/>(forlana)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gavotte</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gigue</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Loure</target></link><space/>(slow gigue)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Minuet</target><part>Menuet</part></link><space/>(minuet)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bal-musette</target><part>Musette</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Passacaglia</target><part>Passacaille</part></link><space/>(passacaglia)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Passepied</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rigaudon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sarabande</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tambourin</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>The English, working in the French style, added their own<space/><link><target>hornpipe</target></link><space/>to this list.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of these dance types are familiar from<space/><link><target>European classical music</target><part>baroque music</part></link>, perhaps most spectacularly in the stylized<space/><link><target>suite (music)</target><part>suite</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Johann Sebastian Bach</target><part>J. S. Bach</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Little, Meredith and Jenne, Natalie.<space/><italics>Dance and the Music of J.S. Bach</italics><space/>(Indiana University Press, 1991, 2001) ISBN 0-253-21464-5</extension><space/>Note however, that the<space/><link><target>allemande</target><trail>s</trail></link>, that occur in these suites do not correspond to a French dance from the same period.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Theatrical dance</heading><paragraph>The French noble style was danced both at social events and by professional dancers in theatrical productions such as opera-ballets and court entertainments. However, 18th century theatrical dance had at least two other styles: comic or grotesque, and semi-serious.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fairfax, Edmund.<space/><italics>The Styles of Eighteenth-Century Ballet</italics><space/>(Scarecrow Press, 2003) ISBN 0-8108-4698-5</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Harris-Warrick, Rebecca and Brown, Bruce Alan, editors.<space/><italics>The Grotesque Dancer on the Eighteenth Century Stage</italics><space/>(The University of Wisconsin Press, 2005) ISBN 0-299-20354-9</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other social dance styles</heading><paragraph>Other dance styles, such as the Italian and Spanish dances of the period are much less well studied than either English country dance or the French style. The general picture seems to be that during most of the 17th century, a style of late<space/><link><target>Renaissance dance</target></link><space/>was widespread, but as time progressed, French ballroom dances such as the minuet were widely adopted at fashionable courts. Beyond this, the evolution and cross-fertilisation of dance styles is an area of ongoing research.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern reconstructions</heading><paragraph>The revival of baroque music in the 1960s and '70s sparked renewed interest in 17th and 18th century dance styles. While some 300 of these dances had been preserved in<space/><link><target>Beauchamp-Feuillet notation</target></link>, it wasn't until the mid-20th century that serious scholarship commenced in deciphering the notation and reconstructing the dances.</paragraph><paragraph>Perhaps best known among these pioneers was Britain's Melusine Wood, who published several books on historical dancing in the 1950s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wood, Melusine,<space/><italics>More Historical Dances</italics>, (Imperial Soc. Dancing, 1956) ISBN 0-900484-12-8</extension><space/>Miss Wood passed her research on to her student Belinda Quirey, and also to Pavlova Company ballerina &amp; choreographer Mary Skeaping (19021984). The latter became well known for her reconstructions of baroque ballets for London's &quot;Ballet for All&quot; company in the 1960s.</paragraph><paragraph>The leading figures of the second generation of historical dance research include Shirley Wynne and her Baroque Dance Ensemble which was founded at Ohio State University in the early 1970s and Wendy Hilton (19312002), a student of Belinda Quirey who supplemented the work of Melusine Wood with her own research into original sources.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hilton, Wendy,<space/><italics>Dance of Court and Theater: The French Noble Style 1690-1725</italics><space/>(Princeton Book Company, 1981) ISBN 0-916622-09-6</extension>A native of Britain, Hilton arrived in the U.S. in 1969 joining the faculty of the<space/><link><target>Juilliard School</target></link><space/>in 1972 and establishing her own baroque dance workshop at<space/><link><target>Stanford University</target></link><space/>in 1974 which endured for more than 25 years.</paragraph><paragraph>Catherine Turocy (b. circa 1950) began her studies in Baroque dance in 1971 as a student of dance historian Shirley Wynne. She founded The New York Baroque Dance Company (http://www.nybaroquedance.org/) in 1976 with Ann Jacoby, and the company has since toured internationally. In 1982/83 as part of the French national celebration of Jean Philippe Rameau's 300th birthday, Turocy choreographed the first production of<space/><link><target>Jean-Philippe Rameau</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Les Borades</italics><space/>- it was never performed during the composer's lifetime. This French supported production with John Eliot Gardiner, conductor, and his Orchestra was directed by Jean Louis Martinoty. Ms. Turocy has been decorated as Chevalier in the<space/><link><target>Ordre des Arts et des Lettres</target></link><space/>by the French government.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In 1973, French dance historian<space/><link><target>Francine Lancelot</target></link><space/>(19292003) began her formal studies in ethnomusicology which later lead her to researching French traditional dance forms and eventually Renaissance and Baroque dances. In 1980, at the invitation of the French Minister of Culture, she founded the baroque dance company &quot;Ris et Danceries&quot;. Her work in choreographing the landmark 1986 production of<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Lully</target><part>Lully</part></link>'s 1676 tragedie-lyrique<space/><italics><link><target>Atys (Lully)</target><part>Atys</part></link></italics><space/>was part of the national celebration of the 300th anniversary of Lully's death. This production propelled the career of<space/><link><target>William Christie (musician)</target><part>William Christie</part></link><space/>and his ensemble<space/><link><target>Les Arts Florissants (ensemble)</target><part>Les Arts Florissants</part></link>. Since the Ris et Danseries company was disbanded circa 1993, choreographers from the company have continued with their own work. Batrice Massin with her &quot;Compagnie Fetes Galantes&quot;, along with Marie Genevieve Mass and her company &quot;L'Eventail&quot; are among the most prominent. In 1995 Francine Lancelot's<space/><link><target>catalogue raisonn</target></link><space/>of baroque dance, entitled &quot;La Belle Dance&quot; was published.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Dance</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://baroquedance.info/'>BaroqueDance.info</link><space/>background information, period dancing manuals, and a large collection of links.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.early-dance.de/en/'>The Calendar of Early Dance</link><space/>information about upcoming baroque events, choreographies and photos galleries</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Baroque dance</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Baroque Dance</target></template><link><target>Category:History of dance</target></link><link><target>Category:Baroque music</target><part>Dance</part></link><link><target>Category:European court festivities</target></link><link><target>Category:Baroque dance</target></link></paragraph></article>