<article title='Concept'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template>A<space/><bold>concept</bold><space/>is an abstraction or generalization from experience or the result of a transformation of existing ideas. The concept is<space/><link><target>wikt:instantiate#Verb</target><part>instantiated (reified)</part></link><space/>by all of its actual or potential instances, whether these are things in the real world or other<space/><link><target>idea</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Concepts are treated in many if not most disciplines both explicitly, such as in<space/><link><target>psychology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link>, etc., and implicitly, such as in<space/><link><target>mathematics</target></link>,<space/><link><target>physics</target></link>, etc.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Generalization process using trees PNG version.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>alt=Diagram</part><part>When the mind makes a generalization such as the concept of ''tree'', it extracts similarities from numerous examples; the simplification enables<space/><link><target>Hierarchy (thinking)</target><part>higher-level thinking</part></link>.</part></link>In<space/><link><target>metaphysics</target></link>, and especially<space/><link><target>ontology</target></link>, a concept is a fundamental<space/><link><target>category of being</target><part>category of existence</part></link>. In<space/><link><target>contemporary philosophy</target></link>, there are at least three prevailing ways to understand what a concept is:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Concepts</arg><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/concepts/</arg><arg name="work">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</arg><arg name="publisher">Metaphysics Research Lab at Stanford University</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 November 2012</arg><arg name="author">Eric Margolis</arg><arg name="author2">Stephen Lawrence</arg></template></extension><template><target>fix</target><arg name="text">See talk page</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Concepts as<space/><link><target>mental representation</target><trail>s</trail></link>, where concepts are entities that exist in the brain,</listitem><listitem>Concepts as<space/><link><target>skill</target><part>abilities</part></link>, where concepts are abilities peculiar to cognitive agents, and</listitem><listitem>Concepts as<space/><link><target>abstract object</target><trail>s</trail></link>, where objects are the constituents of propositions that mediate between thought, language, and referents.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;concept&quot; is traced back to 155460 (Latin<space/><italics><link><target>Wikt:conceptus</target><part>conceptum</part></link></italics><space/>&quot;something conceived&quot;),<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.bartleby.com/61/49/C0544900.html|The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language: Fourth Edition.</extension><space/>but what is today termed &quot;the classical theory of concepts&quot; is the theory of<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>on the definition of terms.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2008</arg></template><space/>The meaning of &quot;concept&quot; is explored in mainstream<space/><link><target>information science</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Stock, W.G. (2010).<space/><link type='external' href='http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/asi.21382/abstract'>Concepts and semantic relations in information science</link>. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 61(10), 19511969.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Hjrland, B. (2009). Concept Theory. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 60(8), 15191536</extension><space/><link><target>cognitive science</target></link>,<space/><link><target>metaphysics</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>philosophy of mind</target></link>. In computer and information science contexts, especially, the term 'concept' is often used in unclear or inconsistent ways.<extension extension_name='ref'>Smith, B. (2004).<space/><link type='external' href='http://ontology.buffalo.edu/bfo/Beyond_Concepts.pdf'>Beyond Concepts, or: Ontology as Reality Representation</link>, Formal Ontology and Information Systems. Proceedings of the Third International Conference (FOIS 2004), Amsterdam: IOS Press, 2004, 7384.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Abstract objects</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Abstract object</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In a<space/><link><target>Platonism</target><part>platonist</part></link><space/>theory of mind, concepts are construed as abstract objects.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Concepts and Cognitive Science</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="publisher">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</arg><arg name="location">in Concepts: Core Readings</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-262-13353-1</arg><arg name="pages">3–83</arg><arg name="author">Stephen Lawrence</arg><arg name="author2">Eric Margolis</arg></template></extension><space/>This debate concerns the<space/><link><target>ontology</target><part>ontological</part></link><space/>status of concepts what they are really like.</paragraph><paragraph>There is debate as to the relationship between concepts and<space/><link><target>natural language</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>However, it is necessary at least to begin by understanding that the concept &quot;dog&quot; is philosophically distinct from the things in the world grouped by this concept or the reference class or<space/><link><target>Extension (semantics)</target><part>extension</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Origin of Concepts"></extension><space/>Concepts that can be equated to a single word are called &quot;lexical concepts&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Study of concepts and conceptual structure falls into the disciplines of<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>psychology</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>cognitive science</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the simplest terms, a concept is a name or label that regards or treats an abstraction as if it had concrete or material existence, such as a person, a place, or a thing. It may represent a natural object that exists in the real world like a tree, an animal, a stone, etc. It may also name an artificial (man-made) object like a chair, computer, house, etc. Abstract ideas and knowledge domains such as freedom, equality, science, happiness, etc., are also symbolized by concepts. It is important to realize that a concept is merely a symbol, a representation of the abstraction. The word is not to be mistaken for the thing. For example, the word &quot;moon&quot; (a concept) is not the large, bright, shape-changing object up in the sky, but only<space/><italics>represents</italics><space/>that celestial object. Concepts are created (named) to describe, explain and capture reality as it is known and understood.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Issues in concept theory</heading><heading level='3'>A priori concepts</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>A priori and a posteriori</arg><arg>Category (Kant)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link><space/>declared that human minds possess pure or<space/><italics><link><target>a priori and a posteriori</target><part>a priori</part></link></italics><space/>concepts. Instead of being abstracted from individual perceptions, like empirical concepts, they originate in the mind itself. He called these concepts<space/><link><target>category (Kant)</target><part>categories</part></link>, in the sense of the word that means<space/><link><target>predicate (grammar)</target><part>predicate</part></link>, attribute, characteristic, or<space/><link><target>quality (philosophy)</target><part>quality</part></link>. But these pure categories are predicates of things<space/><italics>in general</italics>, not of a particular thing. According to Kant, there are 12 categories that constitute the understanding of phenomenal objects. Each category is that one predicate which is common to multiple empirical concepts. In order to explain how an<space/><italics>a priori</italics><space/>concept can relate to individual phenomena, in a manner analogous to an<space/><italics><link><target>Empirical evidence</target><part>a posteriori</part></link></italics><space/>concept, Kant employed the technical concept of the<space/><link><target>schema (Kant)</target><part>schema</part></link>. He held that the account of the concept as an abstraction of experience is only partly correct. He called those concepts that result from abstraction &quot;a posteriori concepts&quot; (meaning concepts that arise out of experience). An empirical or an<space/><italics>a posteriori</italics><space/>concept is a general representation (<italics>Vorstellung</italics>) or non-specific thought of that which is common to several specific perceived objects (<link><target>Logic</target></link>, I, 1., 1, Note 1)</paragraph><paragraph>A concept is a common feature or characteristic. Kant investigated the way that empirical<space/><italics>a posteriori</italics><space/>concepts are created.<template><target>Quotation</target><arg>The logical acts of the understanding by which concepts are generated as to their form are:

# ''comparison'', i.e., the likening of mental images to one another in relation to the unity of consciousness;
# ''reflection'', i.e., the going back over different mental images, how they can be comprehended in one consciousness; and finally
# ''abstraction'' or the segregation of everything else by which the mental images differ ...

In order to make our mental images into concepts, one must thus be able to compare, reflect, and abstract, for these three logical operations of the understanding are essential and general conditions of generating any concept whatever. For example, I see a fir, a willow, and a linden. In firstly comparing these objects, I notice that they are different from one another in respect of trunk, branches, leaves, and the like; further, however, I reflect only on what they have in common, the trunk, the branches, the leaves themselves, and abstract from their size, shape, and so forth; thus I gain a concept of a tree.</arg><arg>Logic, §6</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Embodied content</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Embodied cognition</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>cognitive linguistics</target></link>, abstract concepts are transformations of concrete concepts derived from embodied experience. The mechanism of transformation is structural mapping, in which properties of two or more source domains are selectively mapped onto a blended space (Fauconnier &amp; Turner, 1995; see<space/><link><target>conceptual blending</target></link>). A common class of blends are<space/><link><target>metaphors</target></link>. This theory contrasts with the rationalist view that concepts are perceptions (or<space/><italics>recollections</italics>, in<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link>'s term) of an independently existing world of ideas, in that it denies the existence of any such realm. It also contrasts with the empiricist view that concepts are abstract generalizations of individual experiences, because the contingent and bodily experience is preserved in a concept, and not abstracted away. While the perspective is compatible with Jamesian pragmatism, the notion of the transformation of embodied concepts through structural mapping makes a distinct contribution to the problem of concept formation.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ontology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Ontology</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Plato</target></link><space/>was the starkest proponent of the realist thesis of universal concepts. By his view, concepts (and ideas in general) are innate ideas that were instantiations of a transcendental world of pure forms that lay behind the veil of the physical world. In this way, universals were explained as transcendent objects. Needless to say this form of realism was tied deeply with Plato's ontological projects. This remark on Plato is not of merely historical interest. For example, the view that numbers are Platonic objects was revived by<space/><link><target>Kurt Gdel</target></link><space/>as a result of certain puzzles that he took to arise from the phenomenological accounts.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Godel's Rationalism',<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/goedel/#GodRat'>Standford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gottlob Frege</target></link>, founder of the analytic tradition in philosophy, famously argued for the analysis of language in terms of sense and reference. For him, the sense of an expression in language describes a certain state of affairs in the world, namely, the way that some object is presented. Since many commentators view the notion of sense as identical to the notion of concept, and Frege regards senses as the linguistic representations of states of affairs in the world, it seems to follow that we may understand concepts as the manner in which we grasp the world. Accordingly, concepts (as senses) have an ontological status (Morgolis:7)</paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Carl Benjamin Boyer</target></link>, in the introduction to his<space/><italics>The History of the Calculus and its Conceptual Development</italics>, concepts in calculus do not refer to perceptions. As long as the concepts are useful and mutually compatible, they are accepted on their own. For example, the concepts of the<space/><link><target>derivative</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>integral</target></link><space/>are not considered to refer to spatial or temporal perceptions of the external world of experience. Neither are they related in any way to mysterious<space/><link><target>limit (mathematics)</target><part>limits</part></link><space/>in which quantities are on the verge of nascence or evanescence, that is, coming into or going out of existence. The abstract concepts are now considered to be totally autonomous, even though they originated from the process of abstracting or taking away qualities from perceptions until only the common, essential attributes remained.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Mental representations</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Mental representation</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In a<space/><link><target>physicalism</target><part>physicalist</part></link><space/><link><target>philosophy of mind</target><part>theory of mind</part></link>, a concept is a mental representation, which the brain uses to denote a class of things in the world. This is to say that it is literally, a symbol or group of symbols together made from the physical material of the brain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Origin of Concepts"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Carey</arg><arg name="first">Susan</arg><arg name="title">The Origin of Concepts</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-536763-8</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Murphy</arg><arg name="first">Gregory</arg><arg name="title">The Big Book of Concepts</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="publisher">Massachusetts Institute of Technology</arg><arg name="isbn">0-262-13409-8</arg></template></extension><space/>Concepts are mental representations that allow us to draw appropriate inferences about the type of entities we encounter in our everyday lives.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>Concepts do not encompass all mental representations, but are merely a subset of them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Origin of Concepts"></extension><space/>The use of concepts is necessary to cognitive processes such as<space/><link><target>categorization</target></link>,<space/><link><target>memory</target></link>,<space/><link><target>decision making</target></link>,<space/><link><target>learning</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>inference</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notable theories on the structure of concepts</heading><heading level='3'>Classical theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Definitionism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The classical theory of concepts, also referred to as the empiricist theory of concepts,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Origin of Concepts"></extension><space/>is the oldest theory about the structure of concepts (it can be traced back to Aristotle<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension>), and was prominently held until the 1970s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>The classical theory of concepts says that concepts have a definitional structure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>Adequate definitions of the kind required by this theory usually take the form of a list of features. These features must have two important qualities to provide a comprehensive definition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>Features entailed by the definition of a concept must be both<space/><italics><link><target>necessity and sufficiency</target><part>necessary</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>necessity and sufficiency</target><part>sufficient</part></link></italics><space/>for membership in the class of things covered by a particular concept.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>A feature is considered necessary if every member of the denoted class has that feature. A feature is considered sufficient if something has all the parts required by the definition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>For example, the classic example<space/><italics><link><target>bachelor</target></link></italics><space/>is said to be defined by<space/><italics>unmarried</italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>man</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>An entity is a bachelor (by this definition) if and only if it is both unmarried and a man. To check whether something is a member of the class, you compare its qualities to the features in the definition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Origin of Concepts"></extension><space/>Another key part of this theory is that it obeys the<space/><italics><link><target>law of the excluded middle</target></link></italics>, which means that there are no partial members of a class, you are either in or out.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The classical theory persisted for so long unquestioned because it seemed intuitively correct and has great explanatory power. It can explain how concepts would be acquired, how we use them to categorize and how we use the structure of a concept to determine its referent class.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>In fact, for many years it was one of the major activities in<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/><link><target>formal concept analysis</target><part>concept analysis</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>Concept analysis is the act of trying to articulate the necessary and sufficient conditions for the membership in the referent class of a concept.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='4'>Arguments against the classical theory</heading><paragraph>Given that most later theories of concepts were born out of the rejection of some or all of the classical theory,<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>it seems appropriate to give an account of what might be wrong with this theory. In the 20th century, philosophers such as Rosch and Wittgenstein argued against the classical theory. There are six primary arguments<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>summarized as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>It seems that there simply are no definitions especially those based in sensory primitive concepts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>It seems as though there can be cases where our ignorance or error about a class means that we either don't know the definition of a concept, or have incorrect notions about what a definition of a particular concept might entail.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Willard Van Orman Quine</target><part>Quine</part></link>'s argument against analyticity in<space/><link><target>Two Dogmas of Empiricism</target></link><space/>also holds as an argument against definitions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>Some concepts have fuzzy membership. There are items for which it is vague whether or not they fall into (or out of) a particular referent class. This is not possible in the classical theory as everything has equal and full membership.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Eleanor Rosch</target><part>Rosch</part></link><space/>found typicality effects which cannot be explained by the classical theory of concepts, these sparked the prototype theory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>See below.</listitem><listitem>Psychological experiments show no evidence for our using concepts as strict definitions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Prototype theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Prototype theory</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Prototype theory came out of problems with the classical view of conceptual structure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>Prototype theory says that concepts specify properties that members of a class tend to possess, rather than must possess.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target><part>Wittgenstein</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Eleanor Rosch</target><part>Rosch</part></link>, Mervis,<space/><link><target>Brent Berlin</target><part>Berlin</part></link>, Anglin, and<space/><link><target>Michael Posner (psychologist)</target><part>Posner</part></link><space/>are a few of the key proponents and creators of this theory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="new paradigm"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brown</arg><arg name="first">Roger</arg><arg name="title">A New Paradigm of Reference</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="publisher">Academic Press Inc</arg><arg name="isbn">0-12-497750-2</arg><arg name="pages">159–166</arg></template></extension><space/>Wittgenstein describes the relationship between members of a class as<space/><italics>family resemblances</italics>. There are not necessarily any necessary conditions for membership, a dog can still be a dog with only three legs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>This view is particularly supported by psychological experimental evidence for prototypicality effects.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>Participants willingly and consistently rate objects in categories like 'vegetable' or 'furniture' as more or less typical of that class.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="new paradigm"></extension><space/>It seems that our categories are fuzzy psychologically, and so this structure has explanatory power.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>We can judge an item's membership to the referent class of a concept by comparing it to the typical member the most central member of the concept. If it is similar enough in the relevant ways, it will be cognitively admitted as a member of the relevant class of entities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>Rosch suggests that every category is represented by a central exemplar which embodies all or the maximum possible number of features of a given category.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theory-theory</heading><paragraph>Theory-theory is a reaction to the previous two theories and develops them further.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>This theory postulates that categorization by concepts is something like scientific theorizing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stanford Encycl"></extension><space/>Concepts are not learned in isolation, but rather are learned as a part of our experiences with the world around us.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Big Book"></extension><space/>In this sense, concepts' structure relies on their relationships to other concepts as mandated by a particular mental theory about the state of the world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>How this is supposed to work is a little less clear than in the previous two theories, but is still a prominent and notable theory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>This is supposed to explain some of the issues of ignorance and error that come up in prototype and classical theories as concepts that are structured around each other seem to account for errors such as whale as a fish (this misconception came from an incorrect theory about what a whale is like, combining with our theory of what a fish is).<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension><space/>When we learn that a whale is not a fish, we are recognizing that whales don't in fact fit the theory we had about what makes something a fish. In this sense, the Theory-Theory of concepts is responding to some of the issues of prototype theory and classic theory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="concepts core readings"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ideasthesia</heading><paragraph>According to the theory of<space/><link><target>ideasthesia</target></link><space/>(or &quot;sensing concepts&quot;), activation of a concept may be the main mechanism responsible for creation of phenomenal experiences. Therefore, understanding how the brain processes concepts may be central to solving the mystery of how conscious experiences (or<space/><link><target>qualia</target></link>) emerge within a physical system e.g., the sourness of the sour taste of lemon.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MroczkoNikolic2014">Mroczko-Wsowicz, A., Nikoli D. (2014) Semantic mechanisms may be responsible for developing synesthesia.<space/><italics>Frontiers in Human Neuroscience</italics><space/>8:509. doi: 10.3389/fnhum.2014.00509</extension><space/>This question is also known as the<space/><link><target>hard problem of consciousness</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stevan Harnad (1995). Why and How We Are Not Zombies.<space/><italics>Journal of Consciousness Studies</italics><space/>1: 164167.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>David Chalmers (1995). Facing Up to the Problem of Consciousness.<space/><italics>Journal of Consciousness Studies</italics><space/>2 (3): 200219.</extension><space/>Research on ideasthesia emerged from research on<space/><link><target>synesthesia</target></link><space/>where it was noted that a synesthetic experience requires first an activation of a concept of the inducer.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nikoli, D. (2009) Is synaesthesia actually ideaesthesia? An inquiry into the nature of the phenomenon. Proceedings of the Third International Congress on Synaesthesia, Science &amp; Art, Granada, Spain, April 2629, 2009.</extension><space/>Later research expanded these results into everyday perception.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gomez2013">Gmez Miln, E., Iborra, O., de Crdoba, M.J., Jurez-Ramos V., Rodrguez Artacho, M.A., Rubio, J.L. (2013) The Kiki-Bouba effect: A case of personification and ideaesthesia.<space/><italics>The Journal of Consciousness Studies.</italics><space/>20(12): pp. 84102.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target><arg></arg><arg>18em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Abstraction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Categorization</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Class (philosophy)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Concept and object</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Concept learning</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Concept map</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual art</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual blending</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual clustering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual framework</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual history</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual model</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conversation theory</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conveyed concept</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Definitionism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Formal concept analysis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fuzzy concept</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hypostatic abstraction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Idea</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ideasthesia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Notion (philosophy)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Object (philosophy)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Philosophy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Recept</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Schema (Kant)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Social construction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Symbol grounding</target><part>Symbol grounding problem</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Armstrong, S. L., Gleitman, L. R., &amp; Gleitman, H. (1999). what some concepts might not be. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, Concepts (pp.&amp;nbsp;225261). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Carey, S. (1999). knowledge acquisition: enrichment or conceptual change? In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;459489). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Fodor, J. A., Garrett, M. F., Walker, E. C., &amp; Parkes, C. H. (1999). against definitions. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;491513). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Fodor, J., &amp; LePore, E. (1996). the pet fish and the red Herring: why concept still can't be prototypes. cognition, 253270.</listitem><listitem>Hume, D. (1739). book one part one: of the understanding of ideas, their origin, composition, connexion, abstraction etc. In D. Hume, a treatise of human nature. England.</listitem><listitem>Murphy, G. (2004). Chapter 2. In G. Murphy, a big book of concepts (pp.&amp;nbsp;11 41). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Murphy, G., &amp; Medin, D. (1999). the role of theories in conceptual coherence. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;425459). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Prinz, J. J. (2002). Desiderata on a Theory of Concepts. In J. J. Prinz, Furnishing the Mind: Concepts and their Perceptual Basis (pp.&amp;nbsp;123). Massechusettes: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Putnam, H. (1999). is semantics possible? In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;177189). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Quine, W. (1999). two dogmas of empiricism. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;153171). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem>Rey, G. (1999). Concepts and Stereotypes. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Laurence (Eds.), Concepts: Core Readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;279301). Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press.</listitem><listitem>Rosch, E. (1977). Classification of real-world objects: Origins and representations in cognition. In P. Johnson-Laird, &amp; P. Wason, Thinking: Readings in Cognitive Science (pp.&amp;nbsp;212223). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press.</listitem><listitem>Rosch, E. (1999). Principles of Categorization. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Laurence (Eds.), Concepts: Core Readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;189206). Cambridge, Massachusetts: MIT Press.</listitem><listitem>Schneider, S. (2011). Concepts: A Pragmatist Theory. In S.Schneider, The Language of Thought: a New Direction. Mass.: MIT Press.</listitem><listitem>Wittgenstein, L. (1999). philosophical investigations: sections 6578. In E. Margolis, &amp; S. Lawrence, concepts: core readings (pp.&amp;nbsp;171175). Massachusetts: MIT press.</listitem><listitem><italics>The History of Calculus and its Conceptual Development</italics>,<space/><link><target>Carl Benjamin Boyer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dover Publications</target></link>, ISBN 0-486-60509-4</listitem><listitem><italics>The Writings of William James</italics>,<space/><link><target>University of Chicago Press</target></link>, ISBN 0-226-39188-4</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Logic</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, Dover Publications, ISBN 0-486-25650-2</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>A System of Logic</target></link></italics>, John Stuart Mill, University Press of the Pacific, ISBN 1-4102-0252-6</listitem><listitem><italics>Parerga and Paralipomena</italics>, Arthur Schopenhauer, Volume I,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>, ISBN 0-19-824508-4</listitem><listitem><italics>Kant's Metaphysic of Experience</italics>, H. J. Paton, London: Allen &amp; Unwin, 1936</listitem><listitem><italics>Conceptual Integration Networks.</italics><space/>Gilles Fauconnier and Mark Turner, 1998.<space/><italics>Cognitive Science.</italics><space/>Volume 22, number 2 (AprilJune 1998), pages 133187.</listitem><listitem><italics>The Portable Nietzsche</italics>, Penguin Books, 1982, ISBN 0-14-015062-5</listitem><listitem>Stephen Laurence and Eric Margolis<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.philosophy.dept.shef.ac.uk/papers/CCS.pdf'>&quot;Concepts and Cognitive Science&quot;</link>. In<space/><italics>Concepts: Core Readings</italics>,<space/><link><target>MIT Press</target></link><space/>pp.&amp;nbsp;381, 1999.</listitem><listitem>Birger Hjrland. (2009). Concept Theory. Journal of the American Society for Information Science and Technology, 60(8), 15191536</listitem><listitem>Georgij Yu. Somov (2010). Concepts and Senses in Visual Art: Through the example of analysis of some works by<space/><link><target>Pieter Bruegel the Elder</target><part>Bruegel the Elder</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Semiotica</target></link></italics><space/>182 (1/4), 475506.</listitem><listitem>Daltrozzo J, Vion-Dury J, Schn D. (2010).<space/><link type='external' href='http://daltrozzo.net78.net/papers/Daltrozzo_et_al_2011.pdf'>Music and Concepts</link>. Horizons in Neuroscience Research 4: 157167.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wiktionary</target></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>Concepts</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>SEP</target><arg>concepts</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>InPho</target><arg>idea</arg><arg>1734</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>concepts</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>th-th-co</arg><arg>Theory-Theory of Concepts</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>conc-cl</arg><arg>Classical Theory of Concepts</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://markturner.org/blending.html'>Blending and Conceptual Integration</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.virtuescience.com/conceptualscience.html'>Conceptual Science and Mathematical Permutations</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.conceptmobiles.com/'>Concept Mobiles</link><space/>Latest concepts</listitem><listitem><link><target>v:Conceptualize: A Wikiversity Learning Project</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.free-dictionary-translation.com/Concept.html'>Concept simultaneously translated in several languages and meanings</link></listitem><listitem>TED-Ed<space/><link type='external' href='http://ed.ted.com/lessons/ideasthesia-how-do-ideas-feel-danko-nikolic'>Lesson</link><space/>on ideasthesia (sensing concepts)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://zcomm.org/wp-content/uploads/zinstructionals/htdocs/RTInstruc/id7.htm'>What is a concept?</link>--&quot;It is an assumption.&quot;, sometimes.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>philosophy of language</target></template><template><target>philosophy of mind</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Cognitive science</target></link><link><target>Category:Concepts</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Abstraction</target></link><link><target>Category:Mental content</target></link><link><target>Category:Ontology</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of language</target></link><link><target>Category:Semantics</target></link><link><target>Category:Units of information (cognitive processes)</target></link></paragraph></article>