<article title='Ethical_egoism'><paragraph><template><target>For</target><arg>other forms of egoism</arg><arg>Egoism (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Individualism sidebar</target></template><bold>Ethical egoism</bold><space/>is the<space/><link><target>normative ethics</target><part>normative ethical</part></link><space/>position that<space/><link><target>Moral agency</target><part>moral agent</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>ought to do what is in their own<space/><link><target>self-interest</target></link>. It differs from<space/><link><target>psychological egoism</target></link>, which claims that<space/><link><target>people</target></link><space/>can only act in their self-interest. Ethical egoism also differs from<space/><link><target>rational egoism</target></link>, which holds that it is<space/><link><target>rationality</target><part>rational</part></link><space/>to act in one's self-interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sanders, Steven M. Is egoism morally defensible? Philosophia. Springer Netherlands. Volume 18, Numbers 23 / July 1988</extension>Ethical egoism holds that actions whose consequences will benefit the doer can be considered ethical.</paragraph><paragraph>Ethical egoism contrasts with ethical<space/><link><target>altruism (ethics)</target><part>altruism</part></link>, which holds that moral agents have an<space/><link><target>moral obligation</target><part>obligation</part></link><space/>to help others. Egoism and altruism both contrast with ethical<space/><link><target>utilitarianism</target></link>, which holds that a moral agent should treat one's<space/><link><target>Philosophy of self</target><part>self</part></link><space/>(also known as<space/><link><target>subject (philosophy)</target><part>the subject</part></link>) with no higher regard than one has for others (as egoism does, by elevating self-interests and &quot;the self&quot; to a status not granted to others). But it also holds that one should not (as altruism does) sacrifice one's own interests to help others' interests, so long as one's own interests (i.e. one's own<space/><link><target>desire (philosophy)</target><part>desires</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Quality of life</target><part>well-being</part></link>) are substantially equivalent to the others' interests and well-being. Egoism, utilitarianism, and altruism are all forms of<space/><link><target>consequentialism</target></link>, but egoism and altruism contrast with utilitarianism, in that egoism and altruism are both<space/><link><target>Consequentialism#Agent-focused or agent-neutral</target><part>agent-focused</part></link><space/>forms of consequentialism (i.e. subject-focused or<space/><link><target>Subjectivity</target><part>subjective</part></link>). However, utilitarianism is held to be agent-neutral (i.e.<space/><link><target>Objectivity (philosophy)</target><part>objective</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Impartiality</target><part>impartial</part></link>): it does not treat the subject's (i.e. the self's, i.e. the moral &quot;agent's&quot;) own interests as being more or less important than the interests, desires, or well-being of others.</paragraph><paragraph>Ethical egoism does not, however, require moral agents to harm the interests and well-being of others when making moral deliberation; e.g. what is in an agent's self-interest may be incidentally detrimental, beneficial, or neutral in its effect on others.<space/><link><target>Individualism</target></link><space/>allows for others' interest and well-being to be disregarded or not, as long as what is chosen is efficacious in satisfying the self-interest of the agent. Nor does ethical egoism necessarily entail that, in pursuing self-interest, one ought always to do what one wants to do; e.g. in the long term, the fulfillment of short-term desires may prove detrimental to<space/><link><target>self (philosophy)</target><part>the self</part></link>. Fleeting pleasure, then, takes a back seat to protracted<space/><link><target>eudaimonia</target></link>. In the words of<space/><link><target>James Rachels</target></link>, &quot;Ethical egoism [...] endorses selfishness, but it doesn't endorse foolishness.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rachels 2008, p. 534">Rachels 2008, p. 534.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ethical egoism is often used as the philosophical basis for support of<space/><link><target>right-libertarianism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>individualist anarchism</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ridgely"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ridgely
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.A.
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Selfishness, Egoism and Altruistic Libertarianism
<space/></arg><arg name="work">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>August 24, 2008
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.positiveliberty.com/2008/08/selfishness-egoism-and-altruistic-libertarianism.html
<space/></arg><arg name="doi">
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2008-08-24</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></extension><space/>These are political positions based partly on a belief that individuals should not coercively prevent others from exercising freedom of action.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Forms of ethical egoism</heading><paragraph>Ethical egoism can be broadly divided into three categories: individual, personal, and universal. An<space/><italics>individual ethical egoist</italics><space/>would hold that all people should do whatever benefits &quot;my&quot; (<italics>the individual</italics>)<italics><space/></italics>self-interest; a<space/><italics>personal ethical egoist</italics><space/>would hold that he or she should act in<space/><italics>his or her</italics><space/>self-interest, but would make no claims about what anyone else ought to do; a<space/><italics>universal ethical egoist</italics><space/>would argue that everyone should act in ways that are in their self-interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Waller (2005), p. 81.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Waller (2005), p. 83.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>Ethical egoism was introduced by the philosopher<space/><link><target>Henry Sidgwick</target></link><space/>in his book<space/><italics><link><target>The Methods of Ethics</target></link></italics>, written in 1874. Sidgwick compared egoism to the philosophy of<space/><link><target>utilitarianism</target></link>, writing that whereas utilitarianism sought to maximize overall pleasure, egoism focused only on maximizing individual pleasure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="routledge"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Egoism and Altruism<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Floridi<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Luciano<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Craig<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Edward<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780415187091</arg><arg name="pages">246–247</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Philosophers before Sidgwick have also retroactively been identified as ethical egoists. One ancient example is the philosophy of<space/><link><target>Yang Zhu</target></link><space/>(4th century B.C.),<space/><link><target>Yangism</target></link>, who views<space/><italics>wei wo</italics>, or &quot;everything for myself&quot;, as the only virtue necessary for self-cultivation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="senghaas"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The clash within civilizations: coming to terms with cultural conflicts<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="last">Senghaas<space/></arg><arg name="first">Dieter<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Psychology Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-415-26228-6</arg><arg name="page">33</arg></template></extension><space/>Ancient Greek philosophers like Plato, Aristotle and the Stoics were exponents of<space/><link><target>virtue ethics</target></link>, and &quot;did not accept the formal principle that whatever the good is, we should seek only our own good, or prefer it to the good of others.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="routledge"></extension><space/>However, the beliefs of the<space/><link><target>Cyrenaics</target></link><space/>have been referred to as a &quot;form of egoistic hedonism&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/cyren/'>Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Cyrenaics</link></extension><space/>and while some refer to Epicurus' hedonism as a form of<space/><link><target>virtue ethics</target></link>, others argue his ethics are more properly described as ethical egoism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Evans"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Evans<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Matthew<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Can Epicureans be friends?<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Ancient Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>24<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>407–424<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2004</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Justifications</heading><paragraph>Philosopher<space/><link><target>James Rachels</target></link>, in an essay that takes as its title the theory's name, outlines the three arguments most commonly touted in its favor:<extension extension_name='ref'>He notes, however, that &quot;the theory is asserted more often than it is argued for. Many of its supporters apparently think its truth is self-evident, so that arguments are not needed.&quot; (Rachels 2008, p. 534.)</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;The first argument,&quot; writes Rachels, &quot;has several variations, each suggesting the same general point:<extension extension_name='ref'>That is, that regarding and pursuing the interests of others is a self-defeating policy. Rachels quotes Alexander Pope in support of this: &quot;Thus God and nature formed the general frame/And bade self-love and social be the same.&quot;</extension><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Each of us is intimately familiar with our own individual wants and needs. Moreover, each of us is uniquely placed to pursue those wants and needs effectively. At the same time, we know the desires and needs of others only imperfectly, and we are not well situated to pursue them. Therefore, it is reasonable to believe that if we set out to be 'our brother's keeper,' we would often bungle the job and end up doing more mischief than good.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rachels 2008, p. 534"></extension></listitem><listitem>To pursue actively the interests of others is to be officious. We should mind our own business and allow others to mind theirs.</listitem><listitem>To give charity to someone is to degrade him, implying as it does that he is reliant on such munificence and quite unable to look out for himself. &quot;That,&quot; reckons Rachels, &quot;is why the recipients of 'charity' are so often resentful rather than appreciative.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rachels 2008, p. 534, where it is pointed out that, in the strictest egoistic terms, this is an inconsequential argument. Ethical egoism does not bother itself with how others receive charity, irrespective of how degraded it makes them feel. The same reasoning applies to the previous two bullets, which use self-interest as a means to the end of beneficence, rather than for its own purposes, as the theory would dictate.</extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Altruism, ultimately, denies an individual value and is therefore destructive both to society and its individual components, viewing life merely as a thing to be sacrificed. Novelist<space/><link><target>Ayn Rand</target></link><space/>is quoted as writing that, &quot;[i]f a man accepts the ethics of altruism, his first concern is not how to live his life but how to sacrifice it.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rachels 2008, p. 535, where this argument is attributed to<space/><link><target>Ayn Rand</target></link>, &quot;a writer little heeded by professional philosophers but who nevertheless was enormously popular on college campuses in the 1960s and 1970s&quot;.</extension><space/>Moreover, &quot;[t]he basic principle of altruism is that man has no right to exist for his own sake, that service to others is the only justification for his existence, and that self-sacrifice is his highest moral duty, virtue or value.&quot; Rather, she writes, &quot;[t]he purpose of morality is to teach you, not to suffer and die, but to enjoy yourself and live.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rand, Ayn, &quot;Faith and Force: Destroyers of the Modern World,&quot;<space/><italics>Philosophy: Who Needs It</italics>, p. 74;<space/><italics><link><target>Atlas Shrugged</target></link></italics>, 1957, Random House, p.1014; &quot;Faith and Force,&quot; p. 74.</extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>All of our commonly accepted moral duties, from doing no harm unto others to speaking always the truth to keeping promises, are rooted in the one fundamental principle of self-interest.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>It has been observed, however, that the very act of eating (especially, when there are others starving in the world) is such an act of self-interested discrimination. Ethical egoists such as Rand who readily acknowledge the (conditional) value of others to an individual, and who readily endorse empathy for others, have argued the exact reverse from Rachels, that it is altruism which discriminates: &quot;If the sensation of eating a cake is a value, then why is it an immoral indulgence in your stomach, but a moral goal for you to achieve in the stomach of others?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rand, Ayn,<space/><italics>Atlas Shrugged</italics>, 1957, Random House.</extension><space/>It is therefore altruism which is an arbitrary position, according to Rand.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notable proponents</heading><paragraph>The term<space/><italics>ethical egoism</italics><space/>has been applied retroactively to philosophers such as<space/><link><target>Bernard de Mandeville</target></link><space/>and to many other<space/><link><target>Dialectical materialism</target><part>materialist</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of his generation, although none of them declared themselves to be egoists. Note that materialism does not necessarily imply egoism, as indicated by<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link>, and the many other<space/><link><target>materialist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who espoused forms of<space/><link><target>collectivism</target></link>. It has been argued that ethical egoism can lend itself to<space/><link><target>individualist anarchism</target></link><space/>such as that of<space/><link><target>Benjamin Tucker</target></link>, or the combined<space/><link><target>anarcho-communism</target></link><space/>and egoism of<space/><link><target>Emma Goldman</target></link>, both of whom were proponents of many egoist ideas put forward by<space/><link><target>Max Stirner</target></link>. In this context, egoism is another way of describing the sense that the common good should be enjoyed by all. However, most notable anarchists in history have been less radical, retaining altruism and a sense of the importance of the individual that is appreciable but does not go as far as egoism. Recent trends to greater appreciation of egoism within<space/><link><target>anarchism</target></link><space/>tend to come from less classical directions such as<space/><link><target>post-left anarchy</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Situationism</target></link><space/>(e.g.<space/><link><target>Raoul Vaneigem</target></link>). Egoism has also been referenced by<space/><link><target>Anarcho-capitalism</target><part>anarcho-capitalists</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>Murray Rothbard</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Philosopher<space/><link><target>Max Stirner</target></link>, in his book<space/><italics><link><target>The Ego and Its Own</target></link></italics>, was the first philosopher to call himself an egoist, though his writing makes clear that he desired not a new idea of morality (ethical egoism), but rather a rejection of morality (<link><target>amoralism</target></link>), as a nonexistent and limiting spook; for this, Stirner has been described as the first<space/><link><target>Individualist anarchism</target><part>individualist anarchist</part></link>. Other philosophers, such as<space/><link><target>Thomas Hobbes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David Gauthier</target></link>, have argued that the conflicts which arise when people each pursue their own ends can be resolved for the best of each individual only if they all voluntarily forgo some of their aims that is, one's self-interest is often best pursued by allowing others to pursue their self-interest as well so that liberty is equal among individuals. Sacrificing one's short-term self-interest to maximize one's long-term self-interest is one form of &quot;<link><target>Rational selfishness</target><part>rational self-interest</part></link>&quot; which is the idea behind most philosophers' advocacy of ethical egoism. Egoists have also argued that one's actual interests are not immediately obvious, and that the pursuit of self-interest involves more than merely the acquisition of some good, but the<space/><italics>maximizing</italics><space/>of one's chances of survival and/or happiness.</paragraph><paragraph>Philosopher<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link><space/>suggested that egoistic or &quot;life-affirming&quot; behavior stimulates jealousy or &quot;<link><target>ressentiment</target></link>&quot; in others, and that this is the psychological motive for the altruism in<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>. Sociologist<space/><link><target>Helmut Schoeck</target></link><space/>similarly considered<space/><link><target>envy</target></link><space/>the motive of collective efforts by society to reduce the disproportionate gains of successful individuals through moral or legal constraints, with altruism being primary among these.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Helmut Schoeck</target><part>Schoeck, Helmut</part></link>,<space/><italics>Der Neid. Eine Theorie der Gesellschaft</italics><space/>(<italics>Envy. A Theory of Social Behaviour</italics>), 1966, 1st English ed. 1969.</extension><space/>In addition, Nietzsche (in<space/><italics><link><target>Beyond Good and Evil</target></link></italics>) and<space/><link><target>Alasdair MacIntyre</target></link><space/>(in<space/><italics><link><target>After Virtue</target></link></italics>) have pointed out that the<space/><link><target>ancient Greeks</target></link><space/>did not associate<space/><link><target>morality</target></link><space/>with altruism in the way that post-Christian<space/><link><target>Western culture</target><part>Western civilization</part></link><space/>has done.<link><target>Aristotle</target></link>'s view is that we have duties to ourselves as well as to other people (e.g. friends) and to the<space/><italics><link><target>polis</target></link></italics><space/>as a whole. The same is true for<space/><link><target>Thomas Aquinas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Christian Wolff (philosopher)</target><part>Christian Wolff</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, who claim that there are duties to ourselves as Aristotle did, although it has been argued that, for Aristotle, the duty to one's self is primary.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wheeler, Jack, &quot;Rand and Aristotle,&quot; in Den Uyl and Rasmussen,<space/><italics><link><target>The Philosophic Thought of Ayn Rand</target></link></italics>, 1986.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Ayn Rand</target></link><space/>argued that there is a positive harmony of interests among free, rational humans, such that no moral agent can rationally coerce another person consistently with his own long-term self-interest. Rand argued that other people are an enormous value to an individual's well-being (through education, trade and affection), but also that this value could be fully realized only under conditions of political and economic freedom. According to Rand, voluntary trade alone can assure that human interaction is<space/><italics>mutually</italics><space/>beneficial.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rand, Ayn,<space/><italics><link><target>The Virtue of Selfishness</target></link></italics>(1964).</extension><space/>Rand's student,<space/><link><target>Leonard Peikoff</target></link><space/>has argued that the identification of one's interests itself is impossible absent the use of principles, and that self-interest cannot be consistently pursued absent a consistent adherence to certain ethical principles.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peikoff, Leonard, &quot;Why Should One Act on Principle?,&quot;<space/><italics>The Objectivist Forum</italics>, 1988, originally delivered at the<space/><link><target>Ford Hall Forum</target></link>.</extension><space/>Recently, Rand's position has also been defended by such writers as<space/><link><target>Tara Smith (philosopher)</target><part>Tara Smith</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Tibor Machan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Allan Gotthelf</target></link>,<space/><link><target>David Kelley</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Douglas Rasmussen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nathaniel Branden</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Harry Binswanger</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andrew Bernstein</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Craig Biddle</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Philosopher<space/><link><target>David L. Norton</target></link><space/>identified himself an &quot;ethical individualist,&quot; and, like Rand, saw a harmony between an individual's fidelity to his own self-actualization, or &quot;personal destiny,&quot; and the achievement of society's well being.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>David L. Norton</target><part>Norton, David</part></link>,<space/><italics>Personal Destinies: A Philosophy of Ethical Individualism</italics>, 1976,<space/><link><target>Princeton University Press</target></link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticisms</heading><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>amoralism</target></link>, there is nothing wrong with egoism, but there is also nothing ethical about it; one can adopt<space/><link><target>rational egoism</target></link><space/>and drop morality as a superfluous attribute of the egoism.</paragraph><paragraph>Ethical egoism has been alleged as the basis for<space/><link><target>immorality</target></link>. Egoism has also been alleged as being outside the scope of moral philosophy.<space/><link><target>Thomas Jefferson</target></link><space/>writes in an 1814 letter to Thomas Law:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Self-interest, or rather [[self-love]], or egoism, has been more plausibly substituted as the basis of morality. But I consider our relations with others as constituting the boundaries of morality. With ourselves, we stand on the ground of identity, not of relation, which last, requiring two subjects, excludes self-love confined to a single one. To ourselves, in strict language, we can owe no duties, obligation requiring also two parties. Self-love, therefore, is no part of morality. Indeed, it is exactly its counterpart.<ref>Jefferson, Thomas. June 13, 1814. ''The Moral Sense''. Teaching American History (accessed 3 August 2007) [http://www.teachingamericanhistory.org/library/index.asp?document">1506]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast, Rand saw ethics as a necessity for human survival and well-being, and argued that the &quot;social&quot; implications of morality, including natural rights, were simply a subset of the wider field of ethics. Thus, for Rand, &quot;virtue&quot; included productiveness, honesty with oneself, and scrupulousness of thought. Although she greatly admired Jefferson, she also wrote:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>[To those who say] that morality is social and that man would need no morality on a desert island—it is on a desert island that he would need it most. Let him try to claim, when there are no victims to pay for it, that a rock is a house, that sand is clothing, that food will drop into his mouth without cause or effort, that he will collect a harvest tomorrow by devouring his stock seed today—and reality will wipe him out, as he deserves; reality will show him that life is a value to be bought and that thinking is the only coin noble enough to buy it.<ref>Rand, Ayn, ''Atlas Shrugged'', 1957, Random House, p. 1018.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>The Moral Point of View</italics>,<space/><link><target>Kurt Baier</target></link><space/>objects that ethical egoism provides no moral basis for the resolution of conflicts of interest, which, in his opinion, form the only vindication for a moral code. Were this an ideal world, one in which interests and purposes never jarred, its inhabitants would have no need of a specified set of ethics, according to Baier. This, however, is not an &quot;ideal world.&quot; Baier believes that ethical egoism fails to provide the moral guidance and arbitration that it necessitates. Far from resolving conflicts of interest, claimed Baier, ethical egoism all too often spawns them. To this, as Rachels has shown, the ethical egoist may object that he cannot admit a construct of morality whose aim is merely to forestall conflicts of interest. &quot;On his view,&quot; he writes, &quot;the moralist is not like a courtroom judge, who resolves disputes. Instead, he is like the Commissioner of Boxing, who urges each fighter to do his best.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rachels 2008, p. 538.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Baiers is also part of a team of philosophers who hold that ethical egoism is paradoxical, implying that to do what is in one's best interests can be both wrong and right in ethical terms. Although a successful pursuit of self-interest may be viewed as a moral victory, it could also be dubbed immoral if it prevents another person from executing what is in<space/><italics>his</italics><space/>best interests. Again, however, the ethical egoists have responded by assuming the guise of the Commissioner of Boxing. His philosophy precludes empathy for the interests of others, so forestalling them is perfectly acceptable. &quot;Regardless of whether we think this is a correct view,&quot; adds Rachels, &quot;it is, at the very least, a<space/><italics>consistent</italics><space/>view, and so this attempt to convict the egoist of self-contradiction fails.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rachels 2008, p. 539.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, it has been averred that ethical egoism is no better than<space/><link><target>bigotry</target></link><space/>in that, like<space/><link><target>racism</target></link>, it divides people into two types themselves and others and discriminates against one type on the basis of some arbitrary disparity. This, to Rachels's mind, is probably the best objection to ethical egoism, for it provides the soundest reason why the interests of others ought to concern the interests of the self. &quot;What,&quot; he asks, &quot;is the difference between myself and others that justifies placing myself in this special category? Am I more<space/><link><target>intelligence</target><part>intelligent</part></link>? Do I enjoy my life more? Are my accomplishments greater? Do I have needs or abilities that are so different from the needs and abilities of others?<space/><italics>What is it that makes me so special</italics>? Failing an answer, it turns out that Ethical Egoism is an arbitrary doctrine, in the same way that racism is arbitrary. [...] We should care about the interests of other people<space/><italics>for the very same reason we care about our own interests</italics>; for their needs and desires are comparable to our own.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rachels 2008, pp. 539540.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Adam Smith</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>invisible hand</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Baruch Spinoza</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Epicurus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas Hobbes</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Behavioral economics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Crvka</target></link>, an egoistic Indian philosophy</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hedonism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Helping behavior</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Objectivism (Ayn Rand)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Profit motive</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rational expectations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Yangism</target></link>, an egoistic Chinese philosophy</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Nicomachean Ethics</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Eudemian Ethics</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Evans<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Matthew<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Can Epicureans be friends?<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Ancient Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>24<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>407–424<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2004</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kurt Baier</target><part>Baier, Kurt</part></link>, 1990, &quot;Egoism&quot; in<space/><italics>A Companion to Ethics</italics>,<space/><link><target>Peter Singer</target></link><space/>(ed.), Blackwell: Oxford. ISBN 978-0-631-18785-1</listitem><listitem>Biddle, Craig,<space/><italics>Loving Life: The Morality of Self-Interest and the Facts that Support It</italics>, 2002, Glen Allen.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Nathaniel Branden</target><part>Branden, Nathaniel</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Psychology of Self-Esteem</target></link></italics>, 1969, Nash.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas Hobbes</target><part>Hobbes, Thomas</part></link>, 1968,<space/><italics>Leviathan</italics>,<space/><link><target>C. B. Macpherson</target></link><space/>(ed.), Harmondsworth: Penguin. ISBN 978-0-14-043195-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tibor Machan</target><part>Machan, Tibor</part></link>,<space/><italics>Classical Individualism: The Supreme Importance of Each Human Being</italics>, 1998, Routledge.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target><part>Nietzsche, Friedrich</part></link>, 1886,<space/><italics><link><target>Beyond Good and Evil</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>David L. Norton</target><part>Norton, David</part></link>,<space/><italics>Personal Destinies: A Philosophy of Ethical Individualism</italics>, 1976,<space/><link><target>Princeton University Press</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Paul, E. &amp; F. Miller &amp; J. Paul (1997).<space/><italics>Self-Interest</italics>. Cambridge University Press</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leonard Peikoff</target><part>Peikoff, Leonard</part></link>, &quot;Why Should One Act on Principle?,&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>The Objectivist Forum</target></link></italics>, 1988.</listitem><listitem><link><target>James Rachels</target><part>Rachels, James</part></link>. &quot;Ethical Egoism.&quot; In<space/><italics>Reason &amp; Responsibility: Readings in Some Basic Problems of Philosophy</italics>, edited by<space/><link><target>Joel Feinberg</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Russ Shafer-Landau</target></link>, 532540.<space/><link><target>California</target></link>:<space/><link><target>The Thomson Corporation</target><part>Thomson Wadsworth</part></link>,<space/><link><target>2008 in literature</target><part>2008</part></link>. ISBN 978-0-495-50069-8.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ayn Rand</target><part>Rand, Ayn</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Atlas Shrugged</target></link></italics>, 1957,<space/><link><target>Random House</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ayn Rand</target><part>Rand, Ayn</part></link>, 1964,<space/><italics><link><target>The Virtue of Selfishness</target></link></italics>. Signet. ISBN 978-0-451-16393-6</listitem><listitem>Rosenstand, Nina. 2000. 'Chapter 3: Myself or Others?'. In<space/><italics>The Moral of the Story</italics>. (3rd Edition). Mountain View, Calif: Mayfield Publishing: 127167. ISBN 978-0-07-296335-9</listitem><listitem><link><target>Helmut Schoeck</target><part>Schoeck, Helmut</part></link>,<space/><italics>Der Neid. Eine Theorie der Gesellschaft</italics><space/>(<italics>Envy: A Theory of Social Behaviour</italics>), 1966, 1st English ed. 1969.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tara Smith (philosopher)</target><part>Smith, Tara</part></link>,<space/><italics>Viable Values: A Study of Life as the Root and Reward of Morality</italics>, 2000,<space/><link><target>Rowman &amp; Littlefield</target></link>. ISBN 0-8476-9760-6.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tara Smith (philosopher)</target><part>Smith, Tara</part></link>,<space/><italics>The Virtuous Egoist: Ayn Rand's Normative Ethics</italics>, 2006,<space/><link><target>Cambridge University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-521-86050-4.</listitem><listitem>Waller, Bruce, N. 2005. &quot;Egoism.&quot; In<space/><italics>Consider Ethics: Theory, Readings, and Contemporary Issues</italics>. New York: Pearson Longman: 7983. ISBN 978-0-321-20280-2</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>egoism</arg><arg>Egoism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>egoism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.m-w.com/cgi-bin/dictionary?book=Dictionary&amp;amp;va=egoism+'>Merriam-Webster Dictionary entry for ''egoism''</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ethical Egoism</target></template><link><target>Category:Egoism</target></link><link><target>Category:Normative ethics</target></link><link><target>Category:Anarchist theory</target></link><link><target>Category:Individualism</target></link><link><target>Category:Consequentialism</target></link><link><target>Category:Ethical theories</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of life</target></link></paragraph></article>