<article title='Barrister'><paragraph><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>Barista</arg></template><template><target>Infobox Occupation</target><arg name="name">Barrister
</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Advokat, Engelsk advokatdräkt, Nordisk familjebok.png|200px|Artist's rendition of an early 20th-century English barrister]]
</arg><arg name="caption">Illustration of an early 20th-century English barrister
</arg><arg name="official_names">
</arg><arg name="type">[[Profession]]
</arg><arg name="activity_sector">[[Law]]<space/><br /><space/>[[Jurisprudence]]<space/><br /><space/>[[Justice]]<space/><br /><space/>[[Intellectual property]] 
</arg><arg name="competencies"><space/>Advocacy and interpersonal skills, analytical mind, critical thinking, commercial sense
</arg><arg name="formation">[[Bar Professional Training Course]] (and possibly [[Common Professional Examination]])
</arg><arg name="employment_field">[[Chambers (law)|Barristers' chambers]], government, [[Sole proprietorship|sole trader]]
</arg><arg name="related_occupation">[[Pupillage|Pupil barrister]], [[advocate]], [[judge]], [[lawyer]], [[attorney at law|attorney]]
</arg></template>A<space/><bold>barrister</bold><space/>(also known as<space/><bold>barrister-at-law</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Bar-at-law</bold>) is a type of<space/><link><target>lawyer</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>common law</target></link><space/><link><target>jurisdiction (area)</target><part>jurisdictions</part></link><space/>with a<space/><bold>split legal profession</bold>. Barristers specialise in courtroom<space/><link><target>advocacy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>litigation</target></link>. Their tasks include taking cases in large<space/><link><target>tribunal</target><trail>s</trail></link>, drafting legal<space/><link><target>pleading</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and giving expert legal opinions. Often, barristers are also recognised as<space/><italics><link><target>jurist</target><part>legal scholars</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Barristers are distinguished from<space/><link><target>solicitor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Attorney at law</target><part>attorneys</part></link>, who have more direct access to clients, and may do transactional-type legal work. Barristers are rarely hired by clients directly but instead are retained (or instructed) by solicitors to act on behalf of clients. In some legal systems, including those of<space/><link><target>Scots law</target><part>Scotland</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Anglo-Dutch law</target><part>South Africa</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Stockholm Institute for Scandinavian Law#Scandinavian Law</target><part>Scandinavia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Law of Pakistan</target><part>Pakistan</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Law of India</target><part>India</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Law of Bangladesh</target><part>Bangladesh</part></link>, the British Crown dependencies of<space/><link><target>Law of Jersey</target><part>Jersey</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Guernsey#Politics</target><part>Guernsey</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Manx Law</target><part>Isle of Man</part></link>, barrister is regarded as an<space/><italics><link><target>honorific</target></link><space/>title</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In a few jurisdictions, barristers are usually forbidden from &quot;conducting&quot;<space/><link><target>litigation</target></link>, and can only act on the instructions of a solicitor who performs tasks such as corresponding with parties and the court, and<space/><link><target>legal writing</target><part>drafting</part></link><space/>court documents. In England and Wales, barristers may seek authorisation from the<space/><link><target>Bar Standards Board</target></link><space/>to conduct litigation. This allows the barrister to practise in a 'dual capacity', fulfilling the role of both barrister and solicitor.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.shensmithbarristers.co.uk/videos/direct-access-interview-with-isabelle-parasram-shensmith-barristers/</arg><arg name="title">Interview with an employment barrister</arg><arg name="publisher">ShenSmith Barristers</arg><arg name="author">Isabelle Parasram</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In some countries with common law legal systems, like<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link><space/>and some states of<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lawyer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are entitled to practise both as barristers and solicitors, but it remains a separate system of qualification to practise exclusively as a barrister.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Differences between barristers and other lawyers</heading><heading level='3'>Differences</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Scottish Court wigs (2013).JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>190px</part><part>A barrister's wigs, Parliament Hall, Edinburgh</part></link>A barrister, who can be considered as a jurist, is a lawyer who represents a litigant as advocate before a court of appropriate jurisdiction. A barrister speaks in court and presents the case before a judge or jury. In some jurisdictions, a barrister receives additional training in evidence law, ethics, and court practice and procedure. In contrast, a solicitor generally meets with clients, does preparatory and administrative work and provides legal advice. In this role, he or she may draft and review legal documents, interact with the client as necessary, prepare evidence, and generally manage the day-to-day administration of a lawsuit. A solicitor can provide a crucial support role to a barrister when in court, such as managing large volumes of documents in the case or even negotiating a settlement outside the courtroom while the trial continues inside.</paragraph><paragraph>There are other essential differences. A barrister will usually have<space/><link><target>rights of audience</target></link><space/>in the higher courts, whereas other legal professionals will often have more limited access, or will need to acquire additional qualifications to have such access. In countries where there is a split between the roles of barrister and solicitor; whereas, the barrister in<space/><link><target>Civil law (legal system)</target><part>civil law</part></link><space/>jurisdictions is responsible for appearing in trials or pleading cases before the courts.</paragraph><paragraph>Barristers usually have particular knowledge of case law, precedent, and the skills to &quot;build&quot; a case. When a solicitor in general practice is confronted with an unusual point of law, they may seek the &quot;opinion of counsel&quot; on the issue.<extension extension_name='ref'>In<space/><link><target>insurance</target></link><space/>contracts there is often the requirement to seek the expert opinion of counsel where the policy contains what is known as &quot;a<space/><link><target>QC clause</target></link>&quot;.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In most countries, barristers operate as sole practitioners, and are prohibited from forming partnerships or from working as a barrister as part of a corporation. (In 2009, the Clementi Report recommended the abolition of this restriction in England and Wales.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.legal-services-review.org.uk/content/report/index.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Clementi report<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Legal-services-review.org.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-11-06<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-12</arg></template></extension>) However, barristers normally band together into &quot;<link><target>Chambers (law)</target><part>chambers</part></link>&quot; to share clerks (administrators) and operating expenses.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.shensmithbarristers.co.uk/</arg><arg name="title">Client Access to Barristers</arg><arg name="author">Sunil Rupasinha, road traffic barrister</arg><arg name="publisher">ShenSmith Barristers</arg></template></extension><space/>Some chambers grow to be large and sophisticated, and have a distinctly corporate feel. In some jurisdictions, barristers may be employed by firms of solicitors, banks, or corporations as in-house legal advisers.</paragraph><paragraph>In contrast, solicitors and attorneys work directly with the clients and are responsible for engaging a barrister with the appropriate expertise for the case. Barristers generally have little or no direct contact with their 'lay clients', particularly without the presence or involvement of the solicitor. All correspondence, inquiries, invoices, and so on, will be addressed to the solicitor, who is primarily responsible for the barrister's fees.</paragraph><paragraph>In court, barristers are often visibly distinguished from solicitors by their apparel. For example, in Ireland, England, and Wales, a barrister usually wears a horsehair wig, stiff collar,<space/><link><target>Bands (neckwear)</target><part>bands</part></link>, and a gown. Since January 2008,<space/><link><target>solicitor advocate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have also been entitled to wear wigs, but wear different gowns.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.judiciary.gov.uk/Resources/JCO/Documents/Practice%20Directions/prac_dir_court_dress.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Practice Direction<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-12</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In many countries the traditional divisions between barristers and solicitors are breaking down. Barristers once enjoyed a monopoly on appearances before the higher courts, but in<space/><link><target>Great Britain</target></link><space/>this has now been abolished, and solicitor advocates can generally appear for clients at trial. Increasingly, firms of solicitors are keeping even the most advanced advisory and litigation work in-house for economic and client relationship reasons. Similarly, the prohibition on barristers taking instructions directly from the public has also been widely abolished. But, in practice, direct instruction is still a rarity in most jurisdictions, partly because barristers with narrow specializations, or who are only really trained for advocacy, are not prepared to provide general advice to members of the public.</paragraph><paragraph>Historically, barristers have had a major role in trial preparation, including drafting<space/><link><target>pleading</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and reviewing evidence. In some areas of law, that is still the case. In other areas, it is relatively common for the barrister to receive the brief from the instructing solicitor to represent a client at trial only a day or two before the proceeding. Part of the reason for this is cost. A barrister is entitled to a 'brief fee' when a brief is delivered, and this represents the bulk of her/his fee in relation to any trial. They are then usually entitled to a 'refresher' for each day of the trial after the first. But if a case is settled before the trial, the barrister is not needed and the brief fee would be wasted. Some solicitors avoid this by delaying delivery of the brief until it is certain the case will go to trial.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Justification for a split profession</heading><paragraph>Some benefits of maintaining the split include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Having an independent barrister reviewing a course of action gives the client a fresh and independent opinion from an expert in the field distinct from solicitors who may maintain ongoing and long-term relationships with the client.<extension extension_name='ref'>This view was expressed by Sir Owen Dixon, Chief Justice of Australia,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nswbar.asn.au/docs/about/what_is/dixon.php'>on his swearing in as Chief Justice</link></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>In many jurisdictions, judges are appointed from the bar. Since barristers do not have long-term client relationships, and are further removed from clients than solicitors, judicial appointees are more independent.<space/></listitem><listitem>Having recourse to all of the specialist barristers at the bar can enable smaller firms, who could not maintain large specialist departments, to compete with larger firms.</listitem><listitem>A barrister acts as a check on the solicitor conducting the trial; if it becomes apparent that the claim or defence has not been properly conducted by the solicitor prior to trial, the barrister can (and usually has a duty to) advise the client of a separate possible claim against the solicitor.</listitem><listitem>Expertise in conducting trials, owing to the fact that barristers are specialist advocates.<space/></listitem><listitem>In many jurisdictions, barristers must follow the<space/><link><target>cab-rank rule</target></link>, which obliges them to accept a brief if it is in their area of expertise and if they are available, facilitating access to justice for the unpopular.</listitem></list><paragraph>Some disadvantages of the split include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A multiplicity of legal advisers can lead to less efficiency and higher costs, a concern to Sir<space/><link><target>David Clementi</target></link><space/>in his review of the English legal profession.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aiga.it/old/pdf/doc-57-871.pdf'>''Review of the Regulatory Framework for Legal Services in England and Wales'', Sir Davuid Clementi, December 2004</link></extension></listitem><listitem>Because they are further removed from the client, barristers can be less familiar with the client's needs.</listitem></list><paragraph>A detailed examination of the justifications for a split legal profession and of the arguments in favour of a fused profession can be found in English solicitor Peter Reeves 1986 book,<space/><italics>Are Two Legal Professions Necessary?</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>London: Waterlow Publishers Limited, 1986 (foreword by Sir David Napley)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Regulation</heading><paragraph>Barristers are regulated by the<space/><link><target>Bar association</target><part>Bar</part></link><space/>for the jurisdiction where they practise, and in some countries, by the<space/><link><target>Inns of Court</target><part>Inn of Court</part></link><space/>to which they belong. In some countries, there is external regulation.</paragraph><paragraph>Inns of Court, where they exist, regulate admission to the profession. Inns of Court are independent societies that are titularly responsible for the training, admission (calling), and discipline of barristers. Where they exist, a person may only be called to the Bar by an Inn, of which they must first be a member. In fact, historically, call to and success at the Bar, to a large degree, depended upon social connections made early in life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Daniel Duman,<space/><italics>The English and Colonial Bars in the 19th Century</italics><space/>(Routledge: London, 1983) ISBN 0-85664-468-4, ISBN 978-0-85664-468-9</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A Bar collectively describes all members of the profession of barrister within a given jurisdiction. While as a minimum the Bar is an association embracing all its members, it is usually the case, either<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>de jure</italics>, that the Bar is invested with regulatory powers over the manner in which barristers practise.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Barristers around the world</heading><paragraph>In the common law tradition, the respective roles of a lawyer that is as legal adviser and advocate were formally split into two separate, regulated sub-professions, the other being the office of solicitor. Historically, the distinction was absolute, but in the modern legal age, some countries that had a split legal profession now have a<space/><link><target>fused profession</target></link><space/>anyone entitled to practise as a barrister may also practise as a solicitor, and vice versa. In practice, the distinction may be non-existent, minor, or marked, depending on the jurisdiction. In some jurisdictions, such Australia, Scotland and Ireland, there is little overlap.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:M Battye.jpg</target><part><link><target>Margaret Battye</target></link>, 1930s Australian court dress</part><part>thumb</part></link>In the Australian states of<space/><link><target>New South Wales</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Queensland</target></link>, there is a split profession. Nevertheless, subject to conditions, barristers can accept direct access work from clients. Each state Bar Association regulates the profession and essentially has the functions of the English Inns of Court. In the states of<space/><link><target>South Australia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Victoria (Australia)</target><part>Victoria</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Western Australia</target></link>, as well as the<space/><link><target>Australian Capital Territory</target></link>, the professions of barrister and solicitor are fused, but an independent bar nonetheless exists, regulated by the Legal Practice Board of the state or territory. In<space/><link><target>Tasmania</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Northern Territory</target></link>, the profession is fused, although a very small number of practitioners operate as an independent bar.</paragraph><paragraph>Generally counsel dress in the traditional English manner (wig, gown, and<space/><link><target>jabot (neckwear)</target><part>jabot</part></link>) before superior courts, although they no longer robe for appearances in lower jurisdictions. Wigs are no longer worn in the highest civil court in New South Wales, the Court of Appeal. Wigs are still worn in the Supreme Court, while only robes without wigs are worn in the District Courts in civil matters. Robes and wigs are worn in all criminal cases.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nswbar.asn.au/docs/professional/attire_state.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">NSWbar.asn.au<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">NSWbar.asn.au<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-12</arg></template></extension><space/>In Western Australia, wigs are no longer worn in any court.</paragraph><paragraph>Each year, the Bar Association appoints certain barristers of seniority and eminence to the rank of &quot;Senior Counsel&quot; (in most States and Territories) or &quot;Queen's Counsel&quot; (in the Northern Territory, Queensland, and Victoria). Such barristers carry the title &quot;SC&quot; or &quot;QC&quot; after their name. The appointments are made after a process of consultation with members of the profession and the judiciary. Senior Counsel appear in particularly complex or difficult cases. They make up about 14 per cent of the bar in New South Wales.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph>In Canada (except<space/><link><target>Quebec</target></link>), the professions of barrister and solicitor are fused, and many lawyers refer to themselves with both names, even if they do not practise in both areas.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stephen Waddams,<space/><italics>Introduction to the Study of Law</italics>, 7th ed (Toronto: Carswell, 2010) at 128.</extension><space/>In colloquial parlance within the Canadian legal profession, lawyers often term themselves as &quot;litigators&quot; (or &quot;barristers&quot;), or as &quot;solicitors&quot;, depending on the nature of their law practice though some may in effect practise as both litigators and solicitors. However, &quot;litigators&quot; would generally perform all litigation functions traditionally performed by barristers and solicitors; in contrast, those terming themselves &quot;solicitors&quot; would generally limit themselves to legal work not involving practice before the courts (not even in a preparatory manner as performed by solicitors in England), though some might practise before chambers judges. As is the practice in many other Commonwealth jurisdictions such as Australia, Canadian litigators are &quot;gowned&quot;, but without a wig, when appearing before courts of &quot;superior jurisdiction&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The situation is somewhat different in Quebec as a result of its<space/><link><target>civil law (legal system)</target><part>civil law</part></link><space/>tradition. The profession of solicitor, or<space/><italics>avou</italics>, never took hold in colonial Quebec, so attorneys<extension extension_name='ref'>Here the term<space/><italics>attorney</italics><space/>may be preferable as an<space/><italics>avocat</italics><space/>is very much like an American attorney in that he/she may be both a trial and case lawyer.</extension><space/>(<italics>avocats</italics>) have traditionally been a fused profession, arguing and preparing cases in contentious matters, whereas Quebec's other type of lawyer,<space/><link><target>civil law notary</target><part>civil-law notaries</part></link><space/>(<italics>notaires</italics>), handle out-of-court non-contentious matters. However, a number of areas of non-contentious<space/><link><target>private law</target></link><space/>are not monopolized by notaries so that attorneys often specialise in handling either trials, cases, advising, or non-trial matters. The only disadvantage is that attorneys cannot draw up<space/><link><target>public instrument</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that have the same force of law as<space/><link><target>act (document)</target><part>notarial acts</part></link>. Most large law firms in Quebec offer the full range of legal services of law firms in common-law provinces. Intending Quebec attorneys must earn a bachelor's degree in civil law, pass the provincial bar examination, and successfully complete a legal internship to be admitted to practice. Attorneys are regulated by the Quebec Law Society (<italics>Barreau du Qubec</italics>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>In France,<space/><italics>avocates</italics>, or attorneys, were, until the 20th century, the equivalent of barristers. The profession included several grades ranked by seniority:<space/><italics>stagiaire</italics><space/>(pupil, student-at-law),<space/><italics>plaignant</italics><space/>(junior barrister), and<space/><italics>consultant</italics><space/>(senior barrister). Since the 14th century and during the course of the 19th in particular, French barristers competed in territorial battles over respective areas of legal practice against the<space/><italics>conseil juridique</italics><space/>(chamber-counselor) and<space/><italics>avou</italics><space/>(solicitor), and expanded to become the generalist legal practitioner. After the 1971 and 1990 legal reforms, the<space/><italics>avocat</italics><space/>was fused with the solicitor and chamber-counselor, making the<space/><italics>avocat</italics><space/>(or, if female,<space/><italics>avocate</italics>) an all-purpose lawyer for matters of contentious jurisdiction, analogous to an American attorney. French attorneys may specialize as litigators (trial lawyers) and legal consultants (advising lawyers), known respectively as<space/><italics>avocat plaidant</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>avocat-conseil</italics>. All intending attorneys must pass a legal practice examination and two-year traineeship to be admitted to general practice and enrolled, but to have rights of audience at a given court, an attorney must join that court's bar (<italics>barreau</italics>) by passing its specific bar examination. Each bar is regulated by a Bar Council (<italics>Ordre du barreau</italics>).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Germany</heading><paragraph>In Germany, no distinction is made and lawyers may plead at all courts with the exception of the Federal Court of Justice (<italics>Bundesgerichtshof</italics>) to which fewer than fifty lawyers are admitted<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><space/>78 of the<space/><italics>Zivilprozessordnung</italics>.</extension><space/>as of 25 September 2007. See the list of lawyers admitted to the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bundesgerichtshof.de/DE/BGH/Rechtsanwaelte/rechtsanwaelte_node.html'>''Bundesgerichtshof''</link>. Those lawyers may not plead at other courts, almost only deal with litigation, and are usually instructed by a lawyer who represented the client in the lower courts. However, these restrictions do not apply to criminal cases, nor to pleadings at courts of the other court systems (labour, administrative, taxation, and social courts, as well as the EU court system).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hong Kong</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Hong Kong Bar Association</arg></template>The legal profession in Hong Kong is also divided into two branches: barristers and solicitors.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://acelawtutor.com/routes-to-professional-qualification/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>High Court (Hong Kong)</target><part>High Court</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Court of Final Appeal (Hong Kong)</target><part>Court of Final Appeal</part></link>, as a general rule, only barristers and<space/><link><target>solicitor-advocate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are allowed to speak on behalf of any party in open court. This means that solicitors are restricted from doing so. In these two courts, barristers dress in the traditional English manner, as do the judges and other lawyers.</paragraph><paragraph>In Hong Kong, the rank of Queen's Counsel was granted prior to the<space/><link><target>transfer of the sovereignty of Hong Kong</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>People's Republic of China</target><part>China</part></link><space/>in 1997. After the handover, the rank has been replaced by<space/><link><target>Senior Counsel</target></link><space/><link><target>post-nominal letters</target></link>: SC. Senior Counsels may still, however, style themselves as silks, like their British counterparts.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ireland</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Republic of Ireland</target></link>, admission to the Bar by the Chief Justice of Ireland is restricted to those on whom a Barrister-at-Law degree (B.L.) has first been conferred.<space/><link><target>King's Inns</target><part>The Honorable Society of King's Inns</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Note: the historical spelling variant<space/><italics>Honorable</italics>, not the contemporary Honourable</extension><space/>is the only educational establishment which runs vocational courses for barristers in the Republic and degrees of Barrister-at-Law can only be conferred by King's Inns. King's Inns are also the only body with the capacity to call individuals to the bar and to disbar them.</paragraph><paragraph>Most Irish barristers choose to be governed thereafter by the<space/><link><target>Bar Council of Ireland</target></link>, a quasi-private entity. Senior members of the profession may be selected for elevation to the Inner Bar, when they may describe themselves as Senior Counsel (&quot;S.C.&quot;). Admission to the Inner Bar is made by declaration before the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Ireland</target><part>Supreme Court</part></link>,<space/><link><target>patent of precedence</target><part>patents of precedence</part></link><space/>having been granted by the<space/><link><target>Government of Ireland</target><part>Government</part></link>. Irish barristers are sole practitioners and may not form chambers or partnerships if they wish to remain members of the Bar Council's Law Library.</paragraph><paragraph>To practise under the Bar Council of Ireland's rules, a newly qualified barrister is apprenticed to an experienced barrister of at least seven years' experience. This apprenticeship is known as<space/><link><target>pupillage</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>devilling</target></link>. Devilling is compulsory for those barristers who wish to be members of the Law Library and lasts for one legal year. It is common to devil for a second year in a less formal arrangement but this is not compulsory.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Israel</heading><paragraph>In Israel there is no distinction between barristers and solicitors, even though the judicial system is based mostly on English common law, from when Britain administered what was then<space/><link><target>Mandatory Palestine</target></link><space/>from 1920 to 1948.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Japan</heading><paragraph>Japan adopts a unified system. However, there are certain classes of qualified professionals who are allowed to practise in certain limited areas of law, such as scriveners (<italics>&quot;shiho shoshi&quot;</italics>, qualified to handle title registration, deposit, and certain petite court proceedings with additional certification), tax accountants (<italics>&quot;zeirishi&quot;</italics>, qualified to prepare tax returns, provide advice on tax computation and represent a client in administrative tax appeals) and patent agents (<italics>&quot;benrishi&quot;</italics>, qualified to practise patent registration and represent a client in administrative patent appeals). Only the lawyers (<italics>&quot;bengoshi&quot;</italics>) can appear before court and are qualified to practise in any areas of law, including, but not limited to, areas that those qualified law-related professionals above are allowed to practise. Most attorneys still focus primarily on court practice and still a very small number of attorneys give sophisticated and expertised legal advice on a day-to-day basis to large corporations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Netherlands</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link><space/>used to have a semi-separated legal profession comprising the lawyer and the<space/><italics>procureur</italics>, the latter resembling, to some extent, the profession of barrister. Under that system, lawyers were entitled to represent their clients in law, but were only able to file cases before the court at which they were registered. Cases falling under the jurisdiction of another court had to be filed by a<space/><italics>procureur</italics><space/>registered at that court, in practice often another lawyer exercising both functions. Questions were raised on the necessity of the separation, given the fact that its main purpose the preservation of the quality of the legal profession and observance of local court rules and customs had become obsolete. For that reason, the<space/><italics>procureur</italics><space/>as a separate profession was abolished and its functions merged with the legal profession in 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.advocatenorde.nl/2118/consumenten/Nieuws/afschaffing-procuraat-per-1-september-2008-definitief.html</arg><arg name="title">Afschaffing procuraat per 1 September 2008 definitief</arg><arg name="publisher">Nederlandse Orde van Advocaten</arg><arg name="date">22 August 2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-04</arg></template></extension><space/>Currently, lawyers can file cases before any court, regardless of where they are registered. The only notable exception concerns cases brought before the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the Netherlands</target><part>Supreme Court</part></link>, which have to be handled by lawyers registered in the district of<space/><link><target>South Holland</target></link>, mainly for qualitative reasons.</paragraph><heading level='3'>New Zealand</heading><paragraph>In New Zealand, the professions are not formally fused but practitioners are enrolled in the High Court as &quot;Barristers and Solicitors&quot;. They may choose, however, to practise as barristers sole. About 15% practise solely as barristers, mainly in the larger cities and usually in &quot;chambers&quot; (following the British terminology). They receive &quot;instructions&quot; from other practitioners, at least nominally. They usually conduct the proceedings in their entirety.</paragraph><paragraph>Any lawyer may apply to become a<space/><link><target>Queen's Counsel</target></link><space/>(QC) to recognize long standing contribution to the legal profession but this status is only conferred on those practising as solicitors in exceptional circumstances. This step, referred to as &quot;being called to the inner bar&quot; or &quot;taking silk&quot;, is considered highly prestigious and has been a step in the career of many New Zealand judges.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nigeria</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>, there is no formal distinction between barristers and solicitors. All students who pass the bar examinations offered exclusively by the<space/><link><target>Nigerian Law School</target></link><space/>are called to the Nigerian bar, by the Body of Benchers. Lawyers may argue in any Federal trial or appellate court as well as any of the courts in Nigeria's 36 states and the Federal Capital Territory. The Legal Practitioner's Act, refers to Nigerian lawyers as Legal Practitioners, and following their<space/><link><target>call to the Bar</target></link>, Nigerian lawyers enter their names in the register or Roll of Legal Practitioners kept at the Supreme Court. Perhaps for this reason, a Nigerian lawyer is also often referred to as a Barrister and Solicitor of the Supreme Court of Nigeria, and many Nigerian lawyers term themselves Barrister-at-Law complete with the postnominal initials &quot;B.L.&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The vast majority of Nigerian lawyers combine contentious and non-contentious work, although there is a growing tendency for practitioners in the bigger practices to specialise in one or the other. In colloquial parlance within the Nigerian legal profession, lawyers may for this reason be referred to as &quot;litigators&quot; or as &quot;solicitors&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Consistent with the practice in England and elsewhere in the Commonwealth, senior members of the profession may be selected for elevation to the Inner Bar by conferment of the rank of<space/><link><target>Senior Advocate of Nigeria</target></link><space/>(SAN).</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Asia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pic iqbal 001.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>3000px</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Muhammad Iqbal</target><part>Dr Allamah Muhammad Iqbal</part></link><space/>is regarded as one of the greatest South Asian barristers.</part></link>In<space/><link><target>Law of India</target><part>India</part></link>, the law relating to the Barrister is the Advocates Act, 1961 introduced and thought up by<space/><link><target>Ashoke Kumar Sen</target></link>, the then law minister of India, which is a law passed by the Parliament and is administered and enforced by the<space/><link><target>Bar Council of India</target></link>. Under the Act, the Bar Council of India is the supreme regulatory body to regulate the legal profession in India and also to ensure the compliance of the laws and maintenance of professional standards by the legal profession in the country. For this purpose, the Bar Council of India is authorized to pass regulations and make orders in individual cases and also generally.</paragraph><paragraph>Each State has a Bar Council of its own whose function is to enroll the Barristers willing to practise predominately within the territorial confines of that State and to perform the functions of the Bar Council of India within the territory assigned to them. Therefore, each law degree holder must be enrolled with a (single) State Bar Council to practise in India. However, enrollment with any State Bar Council does not restrict the Barrister from appearing before any court in India, even though it is beyond the territorial jurisdiction of the State Bar Council which he is enrolled in.The advantage with having the State Bar Councils is that the work load of the Bar Council of India can be divided into these various State Bar Councils and also that matters can be dealt with locally and in an expedited manner. However, for all practical and legal purposes, the Bar Council of India retains with it, the final power to take decisions in any and all matters related to the legal profession on the whole or with respect to any The process for being entitled to practise in India is twofold. First, the applicant must be a holder of a law degree from a recognized institution in India (or from one of the four recognised Universities in the United Kingdom) and second, must pass the enrollment qualifications of the Bar Council of the state where he/she seeks to be enrolled. For this purpose, the Bar Council of India has an internal Committee whose function is to supervise and examine the various institutions conferring law degrees and to grant recognition to these institutions once they meet the required standards. In this manner the Bar Council of India also ensures the standard of education required for practising in India are met with. As regards the qualification for enrollment with the State Bar Council, while the actual formalities may vary from one State to another, yet predominately they ensure that the application has not been a bankrupt /criminal and is generally fit to practise before courts of India.Enrollment with a Bar Council also means that the law degree holder is recognized as a Barrister and is required to maintain a standards of conduct and professional demeanor at all times, both on and off the profession. The Bar Council of India also prescribes &quot;Rules of Conduct&quot; to be observed by the Barristers in the courts, while interacting with clients and even otherwise.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Law of Pakistan</target><part>Pakistan</part></link><space/>a graduated can qualify as a Barrister after completion of a<space/><link><target>Master of Laws</target></link><space/>degree, six months pupillage under a senior Barrister in his chambers and afterwards to go for Bar admission test, the Bar Council of the relevant province examine him that he is fit or not to become as an Barrister and is not convicted. After passing the multiple choice question examination and interview conducted by provincial Bar Council, the Bar Council will issue him the license for appearing before the Courts.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Law of Bangladesh</target><part>Bangladesh</part></link>, graduate lawyers have to seat for and pass the Bar Council Exam to become professional Barristers.By passing the Bar Council Exam, barristers are eligible to practise in the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Bangladesh</target></link><space/>and other courts. In Bangladesh there is an association called<space/><link><target>Barristers' Association of Bangladesh</target></link><space/>that represents the barrister.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Become Barrister from Bangladesh</arg><arg name="url">http://iamastudent.net/become-barrister-bangladesh/</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>A license is obtained after successful completion of two year's practice in the lower courts by applicant, which is reviewed by a body of the relevant provincial Bar Council. Most applications after successful completion of the requirement, are accepted.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Students lock Bar Council</arg><arg name="url">http://bdnews24.com/bangladesh/2013/09/04/students-lock-bar-council</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 February 2015</arg><arg name="work">[[bdnews24.com]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Africa</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Advocate#Advocates_in_South_Africa</arg></template>In<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link><space/>the employment and practise of advocates (as barristers are known in South Africa) is consistent with the rest of the Commonwealth. Advocates carry the rank of Junior or Senior Counsel (SC), and are mostly briefed and paid by solicitors (known as<space/><link><target>Attorneys in South Africa</target><part>attorneys</part></link>). They are usually employed in the higher courts, particularly in the Appeal Courts where they often appear as specialist counsel. South African solicitors (attorneys) follow a practice of referring cases to Counsel for an opinion before proceeding with a case, when Counsel in question practises as a specialist in the case law at stake. Aspiring advocates currently spend one year in pupillage (formerly only six months) before being admitted to the bar in their respective provincial or judicial jurisdictions. The term 'Advocate' is sometimes used in South Africa as a title, e. g. 'Advocate John Doe, SC' ('Advokaat' in Afrikaans) in the same fashion as 'Dr. John Doe' for a medical doctor.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph>There is no distinction between two branches. A person who passed the national bar exam, after 2 years of national education, would be able to become a judge, a prosecutor or a &quot;lawyer&quot; in accordance of their grades upon graduation. However, Korea has accommodated Law School System either. Now, there are two(2) ways to be a lawyer, the traditional but time limited way until 2017 and the other way to take a course on a law school and passing the bar exam. Under the current legal system, to be a judge or a prosecutor, lawyers need to practise their legal knowledge. A &quot;lawyer&quot; does not have any limitation of practice.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spain</heading><paragraph>Spain has a division that somewhat corresponds to the division in Britain between barristers/advocates and solicitors.<space/><italics>Procuradores</italics><space/>represent the litigant procedurally in court, generally under the authority of a power of attorney executed by a civil law notary, while<space/><italics>abogados</italics><space/>represent the substantive claims of the litigant through trial advocacy. Essentially, Procuradores are court agents and their practice is confined to the locality of the court to which they are admitted. Procuradores are regulated by Royal Decree 2046 of 1982, which approved the General Statute of the Procuradores, and the Organic Law no.6 of 1985. The General Statute regulates the qualifications and conduct of the procuradores. Thus, obligations to act<space/><italics>pro bono</italics><space/>are laid down by Article 13.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph>The United States does not draw a distinction between lawyers as pleaders (barristers) and lawyers as agents (or solicitors). All lawyers who have passed a<space/><link><target>bar examination</target></link><space/>and have been admitted to practice may prosecute or defend in the courts of the state where they are admitted. Historically, a distinction was made, and a separate label for barristers (called &quot;counselors,&quot; hence the expression &quot;attorney<space/><italics>and</italics><space/>counselor at law&quot;) existed in certain states, though both professions have long since been fused into the all-purpose attorney.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2012</arg></template><space/>Attorneys specializing in court procedure, combining advocacy and case preparation, are called trial attorneys or litigators.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>South Carolina</target></link><space/>still requires attorneys to be licensed separately to plead in a courtroom. Additionally, some state appellate courts require attorneys to obtain a separate certificate of admission to plead and practise in the appellate court. Federal courts require specific admission to that court's bar to practise before it. At the state appellate level and in Federal courts, there is generally no separate examination process, although some U.S. district courts require an examination on practices and procedures in their specific courts. Unless an examination is required, admission is usually granted as a matter of course to any licensed attorney in the state where the court is located. Some federal courts will grant admission to any attorney licensed in any U.S. jurisdiction.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><heading level='4'>England and Wales</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Barristers in England and Wales</arg></template><link><target>Image:Gray's inn zzz.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Gray's Inn</target></link>,<space/><link><target>London</target></link></part></link>Although with somewhat different laws,<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wales</target></link><space/>are considered within the United Kingdom<space/><link><target>England and Wales</target><part>a single united and unified legal jurisdiction</part></link><space/>for the purposes of both civil and criminal law, alongside Scotland and Northern Ireland, the other two legal jurisdictions within the United Kingdom. England and Wales are covered by a common bar (an organisation of barristers) and a single law society (an organisation of solicitors).</paragraph><paragraph>The profession of barrister in England and Wales is a separate profession from that of solicitor. It is, however, possible to hold the qualification of both barrister and solicitor at the same time. It is not necessary to leave the bar to qualify as a solicitor.</paragraph><paragraph>Barristers are regulated by the<space/><link><target>Bar Standards Board</target></link>, a division of the<space/><link><target>General Council of the Bar</target></link>. A barrister must be a member of one of the<space/><link><target>Inns of Court</target></link>, which traditionally educated and regulated barristers. There are four Inns of Court:<space/><link><target>Lincoln's Inn</target><part>The Honourable Society of Lincoln's Inn</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Gray's Inn</target><part>The Honourable Society of Gray's Inn</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Middle Temple</target><part>The Honourable Society of the Middle Temple</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Inner Temple</target><part>The Honourable Society of the Inner Temple</part></link>. All are situated in central London, near the<space/><link><target>Royal Courts of Justice</target></link>. They perform scholastic and social roles, and in all cases, provide financial aid to student barristers (subject to merit) through scholarships. It is the Inns that actually &quot;call&quot; the student to the Bar at a ceremony similar to a graduation. Social functions include dining with other members and guests and hosting other events.</paragraph><paragraph>Student barristers must take the<space/><link><target>Bar Professional Training Course</target></link><space/>(BPTC - previously Bar Vocational Course or BVC) at one of the institutions authorised by the Bar Council to offer the BPTC.<extension extension_name='ref'>Qualification details of English Bar,<space/><link type='external' href='http://thepupillagepages.com/'>thepupillagepages.com</link></extension><space/>On successful completion of the BPTC student barristers are &quot;called&quot; to the bar by their respective inns and are elevated to the degree of &quot;Barrister&quot;. However, before they can practise independently they must first undertake 12 months of<space/><link><target>pupillage</target></link>. The first six months of this period is spent shadowing more senior practitioners, after which pupil barristers may begin to undertake some court work of their own. Following successful completion of this stage, most barristers then join a set of Chambers, a group of counsel who share the costs of premises and support staff whilst remaining individually self-employed.</paragraph><paragraph>In December 2014 there were just over 15,500 barristers in independent practice, of whom about ten percent are<space/><link><target>Queen's Counsel</target></link><space/>and the remainder are<space/><link><target>junior barrister</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Many barristers (about 2,800) are employed in companies as 'in-house' counsel, or by local or national government or in academic institutions.</paragraph><paragraph>Certain barristers in England and Wales are now instructed directly by members of the public.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.barcouncil.org.uk/about/find-a-barrister/public-access-directory/'>Public Access Directory of The Bar Council</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.barcouncil.org.uk/about/find-a-barrister/public-access-directory/<space/></arg><arg name="date">20111229171106<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Members of the public may engage the services of the barrister directly within the framework of the<space/><link><target>Public Access Scheme</target></link>; a solicitor is not involved at any stage. Barristers undertaking public access work can provide legal advice and representation in court in almost all areas of law (see the Public Access Information on the Bar Council website)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.barcouncil.org.uk/guidance/publicaccessinformationforlayclients/'>Barcouncil.org.uk</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.barcouncil.org.uk/guidance/publicaccessinformationforlayclients/<space/></arg><arg name="date">20100322204941<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and are entitled to represent clients in any court or tribunal in England and Wales. Once instructions from a client are accepted, it is the barrister (rather than the solicitor) who advises and guides the client through the relevant legal procedure or litigation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.shensmithbarristers.co.uk/legal-practice-areas/employment-law-barrister/</arg><arg name="title">Employment Law Barrister</arg><arg name="author">Isabelle Parasram</arg><arg name="publisher">ShenSmith Barristers</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Before a barrister can undertake Public Access work, he must have completed a special course. At present, about one in 20 barristers has so qualified. There is also a separate scheme called 'Licensed Access', available to certain nominated classes of professional client; it is not open to the general public. Public access work is experiencing a huge surge at the bar, with barristers taking advantage of the new opportunity for the bar to make profit in the face of legal aid cuts elsewhere in the profession.</paragraph><paragraph>The ability of barristers to accept such instructions is a recent development; it results from a change in the rules set down by the General Council of the Bar in July 2004. The Public Access Scheme has been introduced as part of the drive to open up the legal system to the public and to make it easier and cheaper to obtain access to legal advice. It further reduces the distinction between solicitors and barristers. The distinction remains however because there are certain aspects of a solicitor's role that a barrister is not able to undertake.</paragraph><paragraph>Some honorific suffixes to signify notable barristers may be<space/><italics><link><target>Esquire</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">British English: Esquire</arg><arg name="url">http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/english/esquire?showCookiePolicy</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2014</arg><arg name="date">n.d.</arg><arg name="publisher">Collins Dictionary</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.collinsdictionary.com/dictionary/american/esquire?showCookiePolicy</arg><arg name="publisher">Collins Dictionary</arg><arg name="title">American English: Esquire</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2014</arg><arg name="date">n.d.</arg></template></extension><template><target>Failed verification</target><arg name="reason">these sources do not state that the term Esquire is used specifically for 'notable' barristers</arg><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template><space/>Even though the term &quot;barrister-at-law&quot; is sometimes seen, and was once very common, it has never been formally correct in England and Wales. Barrister is the only correct nomenclature.<extension extension_name='ref'>This was confirmed by the Professional Conduct Committee of the Bar Council when it changed its rules on the usage of the description by individuals in 1970, Annual Statement of the Bar Council, 1969/70.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Northern Ireland</heading><paragraph>In April 2003 there were 554 barristers in independent practice in<space/><link><target>Northern Ireland</target></link>. 66 were<space/><link><target>Queen's Counsel</target></link><space/>(QCs), barristers who have earned a high reputation and are appointed by the Queen on the recommendation of the Lord Chancellor as senior advocates and advisers.</paragraph><paragraph>Those barristers who are not QCs are called Junior Counsel and are styled &quot;BL&quot; or &quot;Barrister-at-Law&quot;. The term &quot;junior&quot; is often misleading since many members of the Junior Bar are experienced barristers with considerable expertise.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Bencher</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are, and have been for centuries, the governing bodies of the four<space/><link><target>Inns of Court</target></link><space/>in London and<space/><link><target>King's Inns</target></link>, Dublin. The Benchers of the<space/><link><target>Inn of Court of Northern Ireland</target></link><space/>governed the Inn until the enactment of the Constitution of the Inn in 1983, which provides that the government of the Inn is shared between the Benchers, the Executive Council of the Inn and members of the Inn assembled in General Meeting.</paragraph><paragraph>The Executive Council (through its Education Committee) is responsible for considering Memorials submitted by applicants for admission as students of the Inn and by Bar students of the Inn for admission to the degree of Barrister-at-Law and making recommendations to the Benchers. The final decisions on these Memorials are taken by the Benchers. The Benchers also have the exclusive power of expelling or suspending a Bar student and of disbarring a barrister or suspending a barrister from practice.</paragraph><paragraph>The Executive Council is also involved with: education; fees of students; calling counsel to the Bar, although call to the Bar is performed by the<space/><link><target>Lord Chief Justice of Northern Ireland</target></link><space/>on the invitation of the Benchers; administration of the Bar Library (to which all practising members of the Bar belong); and liaising with corresponding bodies in other countries.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bar Council is responsible for the maintenance of the standards, honour and independence of the Bar and, through its Professional Conduct Committee, receives and investigates complaints against members of the Bar in their professional capacity.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Scotland</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Advocate</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In Scotland, an<space/><link><target>advocate</target></link><space/>is, in all respects except name, a barrister, but there are significant differences in professional practice.</paragraph><paragraph>In Scotland, admission to and the conduct of the profession is regulated by the<space/><link><target>Faculty of Advocates</target></link><space/>(as opposed to an Inn).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Crown dependencies &amp; UK Overseas Territories</heading><heading level='4'>Isle of Man, Jersey and Guernsey</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Bailiwick of Jersey</target></link>, there are solicitors (called<space/><italics>ecrivains</italics>) and advocates (French<space/><italics>avocat</italics>). In the Bailiwicks of Jersey and<space/><link><target>Guernsey</target></link><space/>and on the<space/><link><target>Isle of Man</target></link>, Advocates perform the combined functions of both solicitors and barristers.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Gibraltar</heading><paragraph><link><target>Gibraltar</target></link><space/>is a British Overseas Territory boasting a legal profession based on the common law. The legal profession includes both barristers and solicitors with most barristers also acting as solicitors. Admission and Disciplinary matters in Gibraltar are dealt with by the Bar Council of Gibraltar and the Supreme Court of Gibraltar. In order for Barristers and/or Solicitors to be admitted as a practising lawyer in Gibraltar they must comply with the Supreme Court Act 1930 as amended by the Supreme Court Amendment Act 2015 which requires, amongst other things, for all newly admitted lawyers as of the 1 July 2015 to undertake a year's course in Gibraltar Law at the University of Gibraltar. Solicitors also have right of audience in Gibraltar's courts.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Popular culture</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Rumpole of the Bailey</target></link></italics><space/>(UK) - Classic court room series</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Kavanagh Q.C.</target></link></italics><space/>(19952001) (UK)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>North Square</target></link></italics><space/>(2000) (UK) -<space/><link><target>Channel 4</target></link><space/>court drama series contains interactions between barristers and solicitors</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Silk (TV series)</target><part>Silk</part></link></italics><space/>(20112014) (UK) -<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>court drama series</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Rake (Australian TV series)</target><part>Rake</part></link></italics><space/>(2010-2014) - Australian TV series based on the story of a colourful barrister</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sydney Carton</target></link><space/>- central character, a barrister, in Charles Dickens's<space/><italics><link><target>A Tale of Two Cities</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Witness for the Prosecution (1957 film)</target><part>Witness for the Prosecution</part></link></italics>, in which the central character is the barrister Sir Wilfred Robards, QC</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Legal professions in England and Wales</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electoral registration in the United Kingdom#Registration process from 1832</target><part>Revising Barrister</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Special Pleader</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Serjeant-at-law</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Abel, Richard L.<space/><italics>The Making of the English Legal Profession: 1800-1988</italics><space/>(1998), 576pp<space/></listitem><listitem>Lemmings, David.<space/><italics>Gentlemen and Barristers: The Inns of Court and the English Bar, 1680-1730</italics><space/>(Oxford 1990)</listitem><listitem>Levack, Brian.<space/><italics>The civil lawyers</italics><space/>(Oxford 1973)</listitem><listitem>Prest, Wilfrid.<space/><italics>The Inns of Court</italics><space/>(1972)</listitem><listitem>Prest, Wilfrid.<space/><italics>The Rise of the Barristers</italics><space/>(1986)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wiktionary</target><arg>barrister</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hkba.org/'>Hong Kong Bar Association (barristers in Hong Kong)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hklawsoc.org.hk/'>Law Society of Hong Kong (solicitors in Hong Kong)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cba.org/'>Canadian Bar Association</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.austbar.asn.au/'>Australian Bar Association (barristers in the Commonwealth of Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nswbar.asn.au/'>Bar Association of New South Wales (Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vicbar.com.au/'>The Victorian Bar (Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.qldbar.asn.au/'>Queensland Bar Association (Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sabar.org.au/'>South Australian Bar Association (Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wabar.asn.au/'>Western Australian Bar Association (Australia)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ntba.asn.au/'>The Northern Territory Bar Association (Australia)</link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>UK and Ireland</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.barristermagazine.com/'>The Barrister magazine</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.innertemple.org.uk/'>The Inner Temple</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.barcouncil.org.uk/'>Bar Council (barristers in England and Wales)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.barlibrary.com/'>Bar Library of Northern Ireland</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.advocates.org.uk'>Faculty of Advocates in Scotland</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lawlibrary.ie/'>Irish Bar Council (barristers in the Republic of Ireland)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://irishbarrister.com/FAQs.html'>The difference between barristers and solicitors</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.legal-research.co.uk/'>Open source legal search tool free access</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://thepupillagepages.com'>Advice on structure and training for the Bar</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://barristerdirect.co.uk/pages/barristers-and-qcs-2'>Barrister vs QC</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Barristers and advocates</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Common law</target></link><link><target>Category:Law in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Legal professions</target></link></paragraph></article>