<article title='A_Little_Night_Music'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg></arg><arg>the Mozart serenade</arg><arg>Eine kleine Nachtmusik</arg><arg>the film</arg><arg>A Little Night Music (film)</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>A Little Night Music (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Infobox musical</target><arg name="name"><space/>A Little Night Music
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Pnight.jpeg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>original Broadway production poster
</arg><arg name="music"><space/>[[Stephen Sondheim]]
</arg><arg name="lyrics"><space/>[[Stephen Sondheim]]
</arg><arg name="book"><space/>[[Hugh Wheeler]]
</arg><arg name="basis"><space/>1955 [[Ingmar Bergman]] film<br />''[[Smiles of a Summer Night]]''
</arg><arg name="productions"><space/>1973 [[Broadway theatre|Broadway]]<br />1975 [[West End theatre|West End]]<br />1977 [[A Little Night Music (1977 film)|Film]]<br />1989 [[West End theatre|West End]] [[revival (theatre)|revival]]<br />1990 [[New York City Opera]]<br />1995 [[Royal National Theatre]]<space/><br><space/>2000 Barcelona<space/><br />2002 [[Kennedy Center]]<br />2003 NYCO revival<br />2008 London revival<space/><br />2009 Broadway revival<br />International productions
</arg><arg name="awards"><space/>[[Tony Award for Best Musical]]<br />[[Tony Award for Best Book]]<space/><br><space/>Tony Award for Best Original Score<space/><br><br>[[Drama Desk Awards]], Outstanding Book of a Musical, Outstanding Music, Outstanding Lyrics 
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold><italics>A Little Night Music</italics></bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Musical theatre</target><part>musical</part></link><space/>with music and lyrics by<space/><link><target>Stephen Sondheim</target></link><space/>and book by<space/><link><target>Hugh Wheeler</target></link>. Inspired by the<space/><link><target>Ingmar Bergman</target></link><space/>film<space/><italics><link><target>Smiles of a Summer Night</target></link></italics>, it involves the romantic lives of several couples. Its title is a literal English translation of the German name for<space/><link><target>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</target><part>Mozart</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Eine kleine Nachtmusik</target><part>Serenade No. 13 for strings in G major</part></link>,<space/><italics>Eine kleine Nachtmusik</italics>. The musical includes the popular song &quot;<link><target>Send in the Clowns</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Since its original 1973<space/><link><target>Broadway theatre</target><part>Broadway</part></link><space/>production, the musical has enjoyed professional productions in the<space/><link><target>West End theatre</target><part>West End</part></link>, by opera companies, in a 2009 Broadway revival, and elsewhere, and it is a popular choice for regional groups. It was<space/><link><target>A Little Night Music (1977 film)</target><part>adapted for film in 1977</part></link>, with<space/><link><target>Harold Prince</target></link><space/>directing and<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Taylor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Len Cariou</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lesley-Anne Down</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Diana Rigg</target></link><space/>starring.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Synopsis</heading><heading level='3'>Act One</heading><paragraph>The setting is Sweden, around the year 1900. One by one, the Quintet five singers who comment like a<space/><link><target>Greek chorus</target></link><space/>throughout the show enter, tuning up. Gradually, their vocalizing becomes an overture blending fragments of &quot;Remember,&quot; &quot;Soon,&quot; and &quot;The Glamorous Life,&quot; leading into the first &quot;Night Waltz&quot;. The other characters enter<space/><link><target>waltz</target><trail>ing</trail></link>, each uncomfortable with their particular partner. After they drift back off, the aging and severe Madame Armfeldt and her solemn granddaughter, Fredrika, enter. Madame Armfeldt tells the child that the summer night &quot;smiles&quot; three times: first on the young, second on fools, and third on the old. Fredrika vows to watch the smiles occur. Middle aged Fredrik Egerman is a successful lawyer. He has recently married an 18-year-old<space/><link><target>trophy wife</target></link>, Anne, a vain girl who is in love with Fredrik, but too immature to grasp the concept of marriage. The two have been married for eleven months, but Anne still protects her<space/><link><target>virginity</target></link>. Fredrik laments his inability to<space/><link><target>sexual intercourse</target><part>make love</part></link><space/>to his wife (&quot;Now&quot;). Meanwhile, his son Henrik, a year older than his stepmother, is feeling extremely frustrated. He is a<space/><link><target>seminary</target></link><space/>student and everyone is always teasing him, never taking him seriously or letting him talk (&quot;Later&quot;). Anne is intrigued by him, but fails to understand his real meaning. Anne promises her husband that she will consent to have sex shortly (&quot;Soon&quot;). Anne's<space/><link><target>maidservant</target></link><space/>Petra, an experienced and forthright girl, slightly older than the teen herself, offers her worldly but crass advice.</paragraph><paragraph>Desiree Armfeldt is a prominent and glamorous actress who is now reduced to touring in small towns. Madame Armfeldt, Desiree's mother, has taken over the care of Desiree's daughter Fredrika. Fredrika misses her mother, but Desiree continually puts off going to see her, preferring, somewhat ironically, &quot;The Glamorous Life&quot;. She is performing near Fredrik's home, and he brings Anne to see the play. While there, Desiree notices Fredrik; the two were lovers years before. Anne, suspicious and annoyed because of Desiree's amorous glances, demands that Fredrik take her home immediately. Meanwhile, Petra has been trying to seduce Henrik.</paragraph><paragraph>That night, as Fredrik remembers his past with Desiree, he sneaks out to see her; the two share a happy but strained reunion, as they &quot;Remember&quot;. They reflect on their new lives, and Fredrik tries to explain how much he loves Anne (&quot;You Must Meet My Wife&quot;). Desiree responds sarcastically, boasting of her own adultery, as she has been seeing the married<space/><link><target>dragoon</target></link>, Count Carl-Magnus Malcolm. Upon learning that Fredrik has gone for eleven months without sex, she agrees to accommodate him as a favor for an old friend.</paragraph><paragraph>Madame Armfeldt offers advice to young Fredrika. The elderly woman reflects poignantly on her own checkered past, and wonders what happened to her refined &quot;Liaisons&quot;. Back in Desiree's apartment, Count Carl-Magnus Malcolm proclaims his unannounced arrival in his typical booming voice. Fredrik and Desiree fool the gullible Count into believing that their disheveled appearance was entirely innocent, but he is still suspicious. He instantly dislikes Fredrik and returns to his wife, Countess Charlotte. Charlotte is quite aware of her husband's infidelity, but Carl-Magnus is too absorbed in his suspicions of Desiree to talk to her (&quot;In Praise of Women&quot;). When she persuades him to blurt out the whole story, a twist is revealed&amp;mdash;Charlotte's little sister is a school friend of Anne's.</paragraph><paragraph>Charlotte visits Anne, who is talking with Petra. Charlotte describes Fredrik's meeting with Desiree; Anne reacts with shock and horror. The older woman explains to Anne that such is the lot of a wife, and that marriage brings pain (&quot;Every Day A Little Death&quot;). Meanwhile, Desiree asks Madame Armfeldt to host a party for Fredrik, Anne, and Henrik. Though reluctant, Madame Armfeldt agrees. She sends out a personal invitation; its receipt sends the women into a frenzy, imagining &quot;A Weekend in the Country&quot;. Anne does not want to accept the invitation, but Charlotte convinces her to do so to heighten the contrast between the older woman and the young teenager. Meanwhile, the Count has plans of his own as a birthday present to his wife, the pair will attend the party uninvited. Carl-Magnus plans to challenge Fredrik to a<space/><link><target>duel</target></link>, while Charlotte hopes to seduce the lawyer to make her husband jealous and end his philandering. The day of the party dawns.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Act Two</heading><paragraph>Armfeldt's country estate is bathed in the golden glow of perpetual summer sunset at this high latitude (&quot;Night Waltz One and Two&quot;). Everyone arrives, each carrying their own amorous purposes and desires&amp;mdash;even Petra, who catches the eye of Armfeldt's fetching<space/><link><target>manservant</target></link>, Frid. The women begin to act against each other. Fredrik is astonished to learn the name of Desiree's daughter. Henrik meets Fredrika, and confesses his deep love for Anne to her. Meanwhile, in the garden, Fredrik and Carl-Magnus reflect on how difficult it is to be annoyed with Desiree, agreeing &quot;It Would Have Been Wonderful&quot; had she not been quite so wonderful. Dinner is served, and the characters' &quot;Perpetual Anticipation&quot; enlivens that meal.</paragraph><paragraph>At dinner, Charlotte attempts to flirt with Fredrik, while Anne and Desiree trade insults. Soon, everyone is shouting and scolding everyone else, except for Henrik, who finally stands up for himself. He shrieks at them for being completely<space/><link><target>amorality</target><part>amoral</part></link>, and flees the scene. Stunned, everyone reflects on the situation and wanders away. Fredrika tells Anne of Henrik's secret love, and the two dash off searching for him. Meanwhile, Desiree meets Fredrik and asks if he still wants to be &quot;rescued&quot; from his life. Fredrik answers honestly that he loves Desiree, but only as a dream. Hurt and bitter, Desiree can only reflect on the nature of her life (&quot;Send in the Clowns&quot;). Anne finds Henrik, who is attempting to commit suicide. The clumsy boy cannot complete the task, and Anne tells him that she has feelings for him, too. The pair begins to kiss, which leads to Anne's first sexual encounter. Meanwhile, not far away, Frid sleeps in Petra's lap. The maid thinks of the joy and freedom that she longs for before becoming trapped in marriage (&quot;The Miller's Son&quot;). Henrik and Anne, happy together, run away to start their new life. However, Carl-Magnus is enraged by this and attempts to shoot the lovers, but Desiree and Charlotte prevent him, while lamenting both the pains of marriage and the strange behavior of married people (&quot;The World Won't End/Every Day a Little Death (reprise)&quot;). With Carl-Magnus calmed, Charlotte confesses her plan to Fredrik, and the two commiserate on a bench. Carl-Magnus, preparing to romance Desiree, sees this and challenges Fredrik to<space/><link><target>Russian Roulette</target></link>, at which a nervous Fredrik misfires and simply grazes his own ear. Victorious, Carl-Magnus begins to romance Charlotte, granting her wish at last.</paragraph><paragraph>After the Count and Countess leave, Fredrika and Madame Armfeldt discuss the chaos of the recent turns-of-events. The elderly woman then asks Fredrika a surprising question: &quot;What is it all for?&quot; Fredrika thinks about this, and decides that it &quot;must be worth it&quot;. Madame Armfeldt is surprised, ruefully noting that she rejected love for material wealth at Fredrika's age. She praises her granddaughter and remembers true love's fleeting nature.</paragraph><paragraph>Fredrik finally confesses his love for Desiree, acknowledges that Fredrika is his daughter, and the two promise to start a new life together (&quot;Finale&quot;). Armfeldt sits alone with Fredrika. Fredrika tells her grandmother that she has watched carefully, but still has not seen the night smile. Armfeldt laughs and points out that the night has indeed smiled twice: first on Henrik and Anne, the young, and second on Desiree and Fredrik, the fools. As the two wait for the &quot;third smile... on the old&quot;, it happens: Madame Armfeldt closes her eyes, and dies peacefully with Fredrika beside her.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Musical numbers</heading><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Act I</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Overture Mr. Lindquist, Mrs. Nordstrom, Mrs. Anderssen, Mr. Erlanson and Mrs. Segstrom (the &quot;Quintet&quot;)</listitem><listitem>&quot;Night Waltz&quot; Company</listitem><listitem>&quot;Now&quot; Fredrik Egerman</listitem><listitem>&quot;Later&quot; Henrik Egerman</listitem><listitem>&quot;Soon&quot; Anne Egerman, Fredrik and Henrik</listitem><listitem>&quot;The Glamorous Life&quot; Fredrika Armfeldt, Desiree Armfeldt, Madame Armfeldt and Quintet</listitem><listitem>&quot;Remember?&quot; Quintet</listitem><listitem>&quot;You Must Meet My Wife&quot; Desiree and Fredrik</listitem><listitem>&quot;Liaisons&quot; Madame Armfeldt</listitem><listitem>&quot;In Praise of Women&quot; Count Carl-Magnus Malcolm</listitem><listitem>&quot;Every Day a Little Death&quot; Countess Charlotte Malcolm and Anne</listitem><listitem>&quot;Weekend in the Country&quot; Company</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-2</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Act II</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Entr'acte Orchestra</listitem><listitem>&quot;Night Waltz I (The Sun Won't Set)&quot; Quintet</listitem><listitem>&quot;Night Waltz II (The Sun Sits Low)&quot; Quintet</listitem><listitem>&quot;It Would Have Been Wonderful&quot; Fredrik and Carl-Magnus</listitem><listitem>&quot;Perpetual Anticipation&quot; Mrs. Nordstrom, Mrs. Segstrom and Mrs. Anderssen</listitem><listitem>&quot;Dinner Table Scene&quot; Orchestra</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link><target>Send in the Clowns</target></link>&quot; Desiree</listitem><listitem>&quot;The Miller's Son&quot; Petra</listitem><listitem>&quot;The World Won't End/Every Day a Little Death (reprise)&quot; Desiree and Charlotte<space/></listitem><listitem>Reprises<space/><xhtml:small>(&quot;Soon&quot;, &quot;You Must Meet My Wife&quot;, &quot;A Weekend in the Country&quot; and &quot;Every Day a Little Death&quot;)</xhtml:small><space/>Quintet</listitem><listitem>&quot;Send in the Clowns&quot; (Reprise) Desiree and Fredrik</listitem><listitem>&quot;Last Waltz&quot; Orchestra</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Additional musical numbers</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Stage:</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Two Fairy Tales&quot; Henrik and Anne<space/><xhtml:small>(cut for time)</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem>&quot;Silly People&quot; Frid<space/><xhtml:small>(cut for time)</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem>&quot;Bang!&quot; Carl-Magnus<space/><xhtml:small>(replaced by &quot;In Praise of Women&quot;)</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem>&quot;My Husband the Pig&quot; Charlotte<space/><xhtml:small>(replaced by the second half of &quot;In Praise of Women&quot;)</xhtml:small></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Screen:</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Love Takes Time&quot; Company<space/><xhtml:small>(lyrics added to Night Waltz)</xhtml:small></listitem><listitem>&quot;The Glamorous Life&quot; Fredrika<space/><xhtml:small>(solo version)</xhtml:small></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Characters</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Fredrik Egerman</bold>: A successful widowed middle-aged lawyer. He is married to the 18-year-old Anne and has one son from his previous marriage, Henrik.</listitem><listitem><bold>Anne Egerman</bold>: Fredrik's new, naive wife.</listitem><listitem><bold>Henrik Egerman</bold>: Fredrik's son, 20 years old and Anne's stepson. He is serious but confused, as he reads the works of philosophers and theologians as he studies for the Lutheran priesthood.</listitem><listitem><bold>Petra</bold>: Anne's maid and closest confidante.</listitem><listitem><bold>Desiree Armfeldt</bold>: Self-absorbed, once-successful actress, now touring the country-side in what is clearly not the &quot;glamorous life&quot;.</listitem><listitem><bold>Fredrika Armfeldt</bold>: Desiree's thirteen-year-old daughter, who may or may not be the product (unbeknownst to Fredrik) of the actress's and Fredrik's affair.</listitem><listitem><bold>Madame Armfeldt</bold>: Desiree's mother, who has had &quot;liaisons&quot; with royalty.</listitem><listitem><bold>Count Carl-Magnus Malcolm</bold>: A military dragoon who is Desiree's latest lover.</listitem><listitem><bold>Charlotte Malcolm</bold>: Carl-Magnus' wife.</listitem><listitem><bold>Frid</bold>: Madame Armfeldt's manservant.</listitem><listitem><bold>The Quintet</bold>: Mr. Lindquist, Mrs. Nordstrom, Mrs. Anderssen, Mr. Erlanson and Mrs. Segstrom. A group of five singers that act as a<space/><link><target>Greek chorus</target></link>. Sometimes referred to as the Liebeslieder Singers although Sondheim and Wheeler did not script them to have that title, using Quintet instead. The first usage of Liebeslieders for the Quintet came during the 1990 New York Opera production. Prince said that these characters represent &quot;people in the show who aren't wasting time ... the play is about wasting time.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Gussow, Mel, &quot;Prince Revels in 'A Little Night Music'&quot;,<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, p. 54, March 27, 1973</extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Malla</bold>: Desiree's maid, with her constantly, silent part</listitem><listitem><bold>Osa</bold>: Maid at Madame Armfeldt's manse, silent part</listitem><listitem><bold>Bertrand</bold>: Page at Madame Armfeldt's manse, silent part</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Productions</heading><heading level='3'>Original Broadway production</heading><paragraph><italics>A Little Night Music</italics><space/>opened on<space/><link><target>Broadway theatre</target><part>Broadway</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Shubert Theatre (Broadway)</target><part>Shubert Theatre</part></link><space/>on February 25, 1973, and closed on August 3, 1974, after 601 performances and 12 previews. It moved to the<space/><link><target>Majestic Theatre (Broadway)</target><part>Majestic Theatre</part></link><space/>on September 17, 1973, where it completed its run. It was directed by<space/><link><target>Harold Prince</target></link><space/>with choreography by<space/><link><target>Patricia Birch</target></link><space/>and design by<space/><link><target>Boris Aronson</target></link>. The cast included<space/><link><target>Glynis Johns</target></link><space/>(Desiree Armfeldt),<space/><link><target>Len Cariou</target></link><space/>(Fredrik Egerman),<space/><link><target>Hermione Gingold</target></link><space/>(Madame Armfeldt),<space/><link><target>Victoria Mallory</target></link><space/>(Anne Egerman),<space/><link><target>Judith Kahan</target></link><space/>(Fredrika Armfeldt),<space/><link><target>Mark Lambert (American actor)</target><part>Mark Lambert</part></link><space/>(Henrik Egerman),<space/><link><target>Laurence Guittard</target></link><space/>(Carl-Magnus Malcolm),<space/><link><target>Patricia Elliott</target></link><space/>(Charlotte Malcolm),<space/><link><target>George Lee Andrews</target></link><space/>(Frid), and D. Jamin Bartlett (Petra). It won the<space/><link><target>New York Drama Critics' Circle</target></link><space/>Award and the<space/><link><target>Tony Award</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Tony Award for Best Musical</target><part>Best Musical</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States tour</heading><paragraph>A US national tour began on February 26, 1974, at the Forrest Theatre, Philadelphia, and ended on February 13, 1975, at the Shubert Theatre, Boston.<space/><link><target>Jean Simmons</target></link><space/>as Desiree Armfeldt, George Lee Andrews as Fredrik Egerman and<space/><link><target>Margaret Hamilton (actress)</target><part>Margaret Hamilton</part></link><space/>as Madame Armfeldt headed the cast.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sondheimguide.com/night.html#BWP'>&quot;'A Little Night Music' tour, 1974&quot;</link><space/>sondheimguide.com, accessed March 13, 2011</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>West End premiere</heading><paragraph>The musical premiered in the<space/><link><target>West End theatre</target><part>West End</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Adelphi Theatre</target></link><space/>on April 15, 1975, and starred Jean Simmons,<space/><link><target>Joss Ackland</target></link>, David Kernan,<space/><link><target>Liz Robertson</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Diane Langton</target></link>, with Hermione Gingold reprising her role as Madame Armfeldt. It ran for 406 performances. During the run,<space/><link><target>Angela Baddeley</target></link><space/>replaced Gingold, and<space/><link><target>Virginia McKenna</target></link><space/>replaced Simmons.</paragraph><heading level='3'>1989 West End revival</heading><paragraph>A revival opened in the West End on October 6, 1989, at the<space/><link><target>Piccadilly Theatre</target></link>, directed by Ian Judge, designed by Mark Thompson, and choreographed by<space/><link><target>Anthony Van Laast</target></link>. It starred<space/><link><target>Lila Kedrova</target></link><space/>as Madame Armfeldt,<space/><link><target>Dorothy Tutin</target></link><space/>as Desiree Armfeldt,<space/><link><target>Peter McEnery</target></link><space/>as Fredrick, and<space/><link><target>Susan Hampshire</target></link>. The production ran for 144 performances, closing on February 17, 1990.</paragraph><heading level='3'>1995 London revival</heading><paragraph>A revival by the<space/><link><target>Royal National Theatre</target></link><space/>opened at the Olivier Theatre on September 26, 1995. It was directed by<space/><link><target>Sean Mathias</target></link>, with set design by Stephen Brimson Lewis, costumes by<space/><link><target>Nicky Gillibrand</target></link>, lighting by Mark Henderson and choreography by<space/><link><target>Wayne McGregor</target></link>. It starred<space/><link><target>Judi Dench</target></link><space/>(Desiree),<space/><link><target>Sin Phillips</target></link><space/>(Madame Armfeldt),<space/><link><target>Joanna Riding</target></link><space/>(Anne Egerman),<space/><link><target>Laurence Guittard</target></link><space/>(Fredrik Egerman),<space/><link><target>Patricia Hodge</target></link><space/>(Countess Charlotte) and<space/><link><target>Issy van Randwyck</target></link><space/>(Petra). The production closed on August 31, 1996. Dench received the<space/><link><target>Olivier Award</target></link><space/>for Best Actress in a Musical.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.officiallondontheatre.co.uk/olivier_awards/past_winners/view/item98530/Olivier-Winners-1996/'>&quot;Olivier Winners 1996&quot;</link><space/>officiallondontheatre.co.uk, retrieved June 14, 2010<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.officiallondontheatre.co.uk/olivier_awards/past_winners/view/item98530/Olivier-Winners-1996/<space/></arg><arg name="date">20120213150059<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>2008 London revival</heading><paragraph>The third London revival ran at the<space/><link><target>Menier Chocolate Factory</target></link><space/>from November 22, 2008 until March 8, 2009. The production was directed by<space/><link><target>Trevor Nunn</target></link>, with choreography by Lynne Page, sets and costumes by David Farley and new orchestrations by Jason Carr. The cast included<space/><link><target>Hannah Waddingham</target></link><space/>as Desiree,<space/><link><target>Alexander Hanson (actor)</target><part>Alexander Hanson</part></link><space/>as Frederik,<space/><link><target>Jessie Buckley</target></link><space/>(Anne),<space/><link><target>Maureen Lipman</target></link><space/>(Mme. Armfeldt), Alistair Robins (the Count), Gabriel Vick (Henrik), Grace Link and Holly Hallam (shared role Fredrika) and Kasia Hammarlund (Petra).<extension extension_name='ref'>Benedict, David.<link type='external' href='http://www.variety.com/article/VR1117993701.html?categoryid=15&amp;amp;cs=1'>&quot;Waddingham to star in 'Night Music'&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Variety</italics>, October 10, 2008</extension><space/>This critically acclaimed<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nightmusiclondon.com/news_and_reviews/'></link><space/>nightmusiclondon.com<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.nightmusiclondon.com/news_and_reviews/<space/></arg><arg name="date">20120307175938<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="night">Nightingale, Benedict.<link type='external' href='http://entertainment.timesonline.co.uk/tol/arts_and_entertainment/stage/theatre/article5289255.ece'>&quot;'A Little Night Music' at the Menier Chocolate Factory, London SE1&quot;</link><space/>December 5, 2008</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="telegraph">Spencer, Charles.<link type='external' href='http://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/theatre/drama/3687085/A-Little-Night-Music-at-the-Menier-Chocolate-Factory.html'>&quot;'A Little Night Music' at the Menier Chocolate Factory&quot;</link><italics>The Telegraph</italics>, December 4, 2008</extension><space/>production transferred to the<space/><link><target>Garrick Theatre</target></link><space/>in the West End for a limited season, opening on March 28, 2009 running until July 25, 2009.<extension extension_name='ref'>Shenton, Mark.<link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/127812.html'>&quot;Isn't It Rich?: Menier 'A Little Night Music' Arrives in the West End March 28&quot;</link>, playbill.com, March 28, 2009</extension><space/>This production then transferred to Broadway with a new cast.</paragraph><heading level='3'>2009 Broadway revival</heading><paragraph>The 2008<space/><link><target>Menier Chocolate Factory</target></link><space/>production opened on Broadway at the<space/><link><target>Walter Kerr Theatre</target></link><space/>in previews November 24, 2009 and officially December 13, 2009, with the same creative team. The cast starred<space/><link><target>Angela Lansbury</target></link><space/>as Madame Armfeldt and, in her Broadway debut,<space/><link><target>Catherine Zeta-Jones</target></link><space/>as Desiree. Also featured were Alexander Hanson as Frederik,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hernandez, Ernio and Gans, Andrew.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/134767-A-Little-Night-Music-With-Zeta-Jones-and-Lansbury-Begins-on-Broadway'>&quot;A Little Night Music, With Zeta-Jones and Lansbury, Begins on Broadway&quot;</link>. Playbill.com, November 24, 2009<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.playbill.com/news/article/134767-A-Little-Night-Music-With-Zeta-Jones-and-Lansbury-Begins-on-Broadway<space/></arg><arg name="date">20150221072347<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Ramona Mallory (the daughter of original Broadway cast members<space/><link><target>Victoria Mallory</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mark Lambert (American actor)</target><part>Mark Lambert</part></link>) as Anne, Hunter Ryan Herdlicka as Henrik,<space/><link><target>Leigh Ann Larkin</target></link><space/>as Petra,<space/><link><target>Erin Davie</target></link><space/>as the Countess,<space/><link><target>Aaron Lazar</target></link><space/>as the Count, and<space/><link><target>Bradley Dean</target></link><space/>as Frid. Zeta-Jones was recognized as<space/><link><target>Tony Award for Best Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Leading Actress in a Musical</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>64th Tony Awards</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tony1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tonyawards.com/en_US/nominees/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tony Award nominees, 2009-2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 13, 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When the contracts of Zeta-Jones and Lansbury ended the production temporarily closed on June 20, 2010 and resumed on July 13, with new stars<space/><link><target>Bernadette Peters</target></link><space/>as Desiree Armfeldt and<space/><link><target>Elaine Stritch</target></link><space/>as Madame Armfeldt.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gans, Andrew.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/141676-Isnt-It-Bliss-Bernadette-Peters-and-Elaine-Stritch-Open-in-Night-Music-Revival-Aug-1'>&quot;'Isn't It Bliss?' Bernadette Peters and Elaine Stritch Open in Night Music Revival Aug. 1</link>. Playbill, August 1, 2010</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>McBride, Walter.<link type='external' href='http://www.broadwayworld.com/article/Photo_Coverage_Bernadette_Peters_and_Elaine_Stritch_Open_in_A_LITTLE_NIGHT_MUSIC_20100714'>&quot;Photo Coverage: Bernadette Peters and Elaine Stritch Open in 'A Little Night Music'&quot;</link>. Broadwayworld.com, July 14, 2010</extension><space/>In an interview, Peters said that Sondheim had &quot;proposed the idea to her this spring and urged the producers of the revival to cast her.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Healy, Patrick.<space/><link type='external' href='http://artsbeat.blogs.nytimes.com/2010/06/07/peters-stritch-to-join-night-music-cast/'>&quot;Peters, Stritch To Join Night Music Cast&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, June 7, 2010</extension><space/>Trevor Nunn directed rehearsals with the two new stars, and the rest of the original cast remained.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rizzo, Frank.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.courant.com/features/hc-rizzo-ticker-0610-20100610,0,1197922.column'>&quot;Elaine Stritch: She's Still Here in West Hartford&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>The Hartford Courant</italics>, June 10, 2010<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.courant.com/features/hc-rizzo-ticker-0610-20100610,0,1197922.column<space/></arg><arg name="date">20121210091135<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.broadway.com/shows/little-night-music/buzz/153809/a-little-night-music-sets-closing-date-peters-and-stritch-extend/'>&quot;A Little Night Music Sets Closing Date; Peters and Stritch Extend&quot;</link>. Broadway.com</extension><space/>Peters and Stritch extended their contracts until January 9, 2011, when the production closed with 20 previews and 425 regular performances.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gans, Andrew.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/143644-Bernadette-Peters-and-Elaine-Stritch-Extend-Run-in-Broadways-A-Little-Night-Music'>&quot;Bernadette Peters and Elaine Stritch Extend Run in Broadway's A Little Night Music&quot;</link>. Playbill.com, October 5, 2010</extension><space/>Before the production closed it recouped its initial investment.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gans, Andrew.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/146428-Broadways-A-Little-Night-Music-with-Bernadette-Peters-and-Elaine-Stritch-Recoups'>Broadway's A Little Night Music, with Bernadette Peters and Elaine Stritch, Recoups&quot;</link>. Playbill, January 6, 2011</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Europe</heading><paragraph><link><target>Zarah Leander</target></link><space/>played Madame Armfeldt in the original Austrian staging (in 1975) as well as in the original Swedish staging in<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>in 1978 (here with<space/><link><target>Jan Malmsj</target></link><space/>as Fredrik Egerman), performing<space/><italics>Send In The Clowns</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Liaisons</italics><space/>in both stagings. The successful Stockholm-staging was directed by<space/><link><target>Stig Olin</target></link>. In 2010 the musical was scheduled to return to<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>and the Stockholm Stadsteater. The cast included<space/><link><target>Pia Johansson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dan Ekborg</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Yvonne Lombard</target></link><space/>and Threse Andersson.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Thtre du Chtelet</target></link>, Paris production ran from February 15, 2010 through February 20, 2010. Lee Blakeley directed and Andrew George was the choreographer.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gans, Andrew and Jones, Kenneth.<link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/130840-Kristin_Scott_Thomas_and_Leslie_Caron_to_Star_in_A_Little_Night_Music_in_France'>&quot;Kristin Scott Thomas and Leslie Caron to Star in 'A Little Night Music' in France&quot;</link><space/>playbill.com, July 6, 2009</extension><space/>Italian-born actress<space/><link><target>Greta Scacchi</target></link><space/>played Dsire, and<space/><link><target>Leslie Caron</target></link><space/>played Madame Armfeldt.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hetrick, Adam.<link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/136884-Scacchi-and-Caron-Sing-A-Little-Night-Music-in-Paris-Beginning-Feb-15'>&quot;Scacchi and Caron Sing 'A Little Night Music' in Paris Beginning Feb. 15&quot;</link><space/>playbill.com, February 15, 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Turun kaupunginteatteri</target><part>Turku City Theatre</part></link><space/>staged the musical in 2011 with<space/><link><target>Kirsi Tarvainen</target></link><space/>in the role as Dsire.<space/><link><target>Tuomas Parkkinen</target></link><space/>directed and<space/><link><target>Jussi Vahvaselk</target></link><space/>was musical director.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Opera companies</heading><paragraph>The musical has also become part of the repertoire of a few opera companies.<space/><link><target>Michigan Opera Theatre</target></link><space/>was the first major American opera company to present the work in 1983, and again in November 2009. Light Opera Works (Evanston, IL) produced the work in August 1983.<space/><link><target>New York City Opera</target></link><space/>staged it in 1990, 1991 and 2003, the<space/><link><target>Houston Grand Opera</target></link><space/>in 1999, the<space/><link><target>Los Angeles Opera</target></link><space/>in 2004, and Hartford Opera Theater in 2014. New York City Opera's production in August 1990 and July 1991 (total of 18 performances) won the 1990<space/><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Revival</target></link><space/>and was telecast on the<space/><link><target>Public Broadcasting Service</target><part>PBS</part></link><space/>show &quot;Live at Lincoln Center&quot; on November 7, 1990.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0359610/?ref_=rvi_tt</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension><space/>The cast included both stage performers:<space/><link><target>Sally Ann Howes</target></link><space/>and George Lee Andrews as Desiree and Frederick and opera regular<space/><link><target>Regina Resnik</target></link><space/>as Madame Armfeldt (in 1991).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sondheimguide.com/night.html#1990NYCO'>1990 New York City Opera Production</link><space/>sondheimguide.com, accessed October 21, 2012</extension><space/>The 2003 production featured a young<space/><link><target>Anna Kendrick</target></link><space/>as Fredrika Armfeldt, alongside<space/><link><target>Jeremy Irons</target></link><space/>as Frederick and<space/><link><target>Marc Kudisch</target></link><space/>as Carl-Magnus.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sondheimguide.com/night.html#2003NYCO'>2003 New York City Opera Production</link><space/>sondheimguide.com, accessed October 21, 2012</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Opera Australia</target></link><space/>presented the piece in Melbourne in May 2009, starring<space/><link><target>Sigrid Thornton</target></link><space/>as Desiree Armfeldt and Nacye Hayes as Madame Armfeldt. The production returned in 2010 at the Sydney Opera House with<space/><link><target>Anthony Warlow</target></link><space/>taking on the role of Fredrik Egerman. The production was directed by Stuart Maunder, designed by Roger Kirk, and conducted by Andrew Greene.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.opera-australia.org.au/scripts/nc.dll?OPRA:PRODUCTION:0:pc=PC_90107'>''A Little Night Music''</link>,<space/><link><target>Opera Australia</target></link></extension><space/><link><target>Opera Theatre of Saint Louis</target></link><space/>performed the musical in June 2010. Designer<space/><link><target>Isaac Mizrahi</target></link><space/>directed and designed the production, with a cast that starred<space/><link><target>Amy Irving</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sin Phillips</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Ron Raines</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hetrick, Adam.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/140075-Mizrahi-Helmed-Night-Music-with-Irving-Phillips-and-Raines-Opens-in-St-Louis'>&quot;Mizrahi-Helmed 'Night Music', with Irving, Phillips and Raines, Opens in St. Louis&quot;</link>. Playbill.com, June 6, 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The piece has also become a popular choice for amateur musical theatre and light opera companies.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Film adaptation</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>A Little Night Music (film)</arg></template>In 1977, a film version of<space/><italics><link><target>A Little Night Music (1977 film)</target><part>A Little Night Music</part></link></italics><space/>was released, starring<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Taylor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lesley-Anne Down</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Diana Rigg</target></link>, with<space/><link><target>Len Cariou</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hermione Gingold</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Laurence Guittard</target></link><space/>reprising their Broadway roles. The setting for the film was moved from Sweden to Austria.<space/><link><target>Stephen Sondheim</target></link><space/>wrote lyrics for the &quot;Night Waltz&quot; theme (&quot;Love Takes Time&quot;) and wrote an entirely new version of &quot;The Glamorous Life&quot;, which has been incorporated into several subsequent productions of the stage musical. However, other songs, including &quot;In Praise of Women&quot;, &quot;The Miller's Son&quot; and &quot;Liaisons&quot;, were cut and remain heard only as background orchestrations. The film marked Broadway director<space/><link><target>Hal Prince</target></link>'s second time as a motion picture director. Critical reaction to the film was mostly negative, with much being made of Taylor's wildly fluctuating weight from scene to scene.<extension extension_name='ref'>Canby, Vincent.<space/><link type='external' href='http://movies.nytimes.com/movie/review?res=9E0CEEDA1F3EE632A2575BC0A9659C946990D6CF'>&quot;Review: A Little Night Music (1977)&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, March 8, 1978</extension><space/>Some critics talked more positively of the film, with<space/><italics><link><target>Variety (magazine)</target><part>Variety</part></link></italics><space/>calling it &quot;an elegant looking, period romantic charade&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117792646.html?categoryid=31&amp;amp;cs=1'></link><space/>variety.com</extension><space/>There was praise for Diana Rigg's performance, and orchestrator<space/><link><target>Jonathan Tunick</target></link><space/>received an<space/><link><target>Academy Award</target><part>Oscar</part></link><space/>for his work on the score. A soundtrack recording was released on LP, and a DVD release was issued in June 2007.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>IMDb title</target><arg name="id">0076319</arg><arg name="title">A Little Night Music</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Music analysis</heading><paragraph>The score for<space/><italics>A Little Night Music</italics><space/>has elements not often found in musical theater, presenting challenges for performers, with complex meters, pitch changes, polyphony, and high notes for both males and females. The difficulty is heightened when songs merge, as in &quot;Now&quot;/&quot;Later&quot;/&quot;Soon&quot;, because all three have to be performed in the same key, limiting the ability to pick a comfortable key for each singer. Critic<space/><link><target>Rex Reed</target></link><space/>noted that &quot;The score of 'Night Music' ...contains patter songs, contrapuntal duets and trios, a quartet, and even a dramatic double quintet to puzzle through. All this has been gorgeously orchestrated by Jonathan Tunick; there is no rhythm section, only strings and woodwinds to carry the melodies and harmonies aloft.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Deutsch, Didier C.<link type='external' href='http://www.masterworksbroadway.com/music/a-little-night-music'>&quot;'A Little Night Music' Liner Notes, Song List and Synopsis&quot;</link><space/>masterworksbroadway.com, retrieved June 9, 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sondheim's engagement with threes extends to his lyrics. He organizes trios with the singers separated, while his duets are sung together, about a third person.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tunick"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The work is performed as an<space/><link><target>operetta</target></link><space/>in many professional opera companies. For example, it was added to the<space/><link><target>New York City Opera</target></link><space/>Company repertoire in 1990.<extension extension_name='ref'>Green, Kay. &quot;Broadway Musicals, Show By Show&quot; (1996). Hal Leonard Corporation. ISBN 0-7935-7750-0, p. 237</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>3/4 time</heading><paragraph>Virtually all of the music in the show is written in<space/><link><target>waltz time</target></link><space/>(3/4). Some parts adopt<space/><link><target>Compound meter (music)</target><part>compound meter</part></link>, with a<space/><link><target>time signature</target></link><space/>such as 12/8.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tunick"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">A Little Night Music (Libretto)
</arg><arg name="last1">Sondheim<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Stephen
</arg><arg name="last2">Prince<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Hal
</arg><arg name="last3">Tunick<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Neal
</arg><arg name="date">November 30, 1973
</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 2009
</arg></template></extension><space/>Passages in &quot;Overture&quot;, &quot;Glamorous Life&quot;, &quot;Liaisons&quot;, and &quot;The Miller's Son&quot; are in<space/><link><target>duple meter</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Citron, p. 204</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Counterpoint and polyphony</heading><paragraph>At several points, Sondheim has multiple performers each sing a different song simultaneously. This use of<space/><link><target>counterpoint</target></link><space/>maintains coherence even as it extends the notion of a<space/><link><target>round (music)</target><part>round</part></link>, familiar in songs such as the traditional &quot;<link><target>Frre Jacques</target></link>&quot;, into something more complex. Sondheim said: &quot;As for the three songs... going together well, I might as well confess. In those days I was just getting into contrapuntal and choral writing...and I wanted to develop my technique by writing a trio. What I didn't want to do is the<space/><link><target>quodlibet</target></link><space/>method...wouldn't it be nice to have three songs you don't think are going to go together, and they do go together... The trick was the little<space/><link><target>vamp (music)</target><part>vamp</part></link><space/>on &quot;Soon&quot; which has five-and six-note chords.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="swayne">Swayne, Steve.<space/><italics>How Sondheim Found His Sound</italics>, University of Michigan Press, 2007, ISBN 0-472-03229-1, p. 251</extension><space/>Steve Swayne comments that the &quot;contrapuntal episodes in the extended ensembles... stand as testament to his interest in Counterpoint.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="swayne"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Send In The Clowns&quot;</heading><paragraph>The show's best-known and Sondheim's biggest hit song was almost an afterthought, written several days before the start of out of town tryouts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Citron, p. 207</extension><space/>Sondheim initially conceived Desiree as a role for a more-or-less non-singing actress. When he discovered that the original Desiree,<space/><link><target>Glynis Johns</target></link>, was able to sing (she had a &quot;small, silvery voice&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="secrest">Secrest, Meryle. &quot;Stephen Sondheim: A Life&quot; (1998). Dell Publishing. ISBN 0-385-33412-5, pp. 251-252</extension>) but could not &quot;sustain a phrase&quot;, he devised the song &quot;<link><target>Send in the Clowns</target></link>&quot; for her in a way that would work around her vocal weakness, e.g., by ending lines with consonants that made for a short cut-off.<extension extension_name='ref' name="secrest"></extension><space/>&quot;It is written in short phrases in order to be acted rather than sung...tailor-made for Glynis Johns, who lacks the vocal power to sustain long phrases.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Sondheim, S., Shevelove, B., Gelbart, L., Wheeler, H., and Lapine, J. &quot;Four by Sondheim, Wheeler, Lapine, Shevelove and Gelbart&quot; (2000). Hal Leonard Corporation. ISBN 1-55783-407-5, p. 170</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In analyzing the text of the song,<space/><link><target>Max Cryer</target></link><space/>wrote that it &quot;is not intended to be sung by the young in love, but by a mature performer who has seen it all before. The song remains an anthem to regret for unwise decisions in the past and recognition that there's no need to send in the clowns-they're already here.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Cryer, Max. ''Love Me Tender: The Stories Behind the World's Best-loved Frances Lincoln Ltd, 2008, ISBN 0-7112-2911-2, p. 171</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Graham Wolfe has argued, &quot;What Desire is referring to in the famous song is a conventional device to cover over a moment when something has gone wrong on stage. Midway through the second Act she has deviated from her usual script by suggesting to Fredrik the possibility of being together seriously and permanently, and, having been rejected, she falters<space/><italics>as</italics><space/>a show-person, finds herself bereft of the capacity to improvise and wittily cover. If Desire could perform at this moment revert to the innuendos, one-liners and blithe self-referential humour that constitutes her normal character all would be well. She cannot, and what follows is an exemplary manifestation of Sondheims musico-dramatic complexity, his inclination to write music that performs drama. That is, what needs to be covered over (by the clowns sung about in the song) is the very intensity, ragged emotion and utter vulnerability that comes forward through the music and singing itself, a display protracted to six minutes, wrought with exposed silences, a shocked Fredrik sitting so uncomfortably before Desire while something much too real emerges in a realm where he and his audience felt assured of performance.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wolfe, Graham. &quot;Sondheim's<space/><italics>A Little Night Music</italics>: Reconciling the Comic and the Sublime.&quot;<space/><italics>Studies in Musical Theatre</italics><space/>8.2 (2014): 143-157.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Influences</heading><paragraph>There is a<space/><link><target>Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart</target><part>Mozart</part></link><space/>reference in the title&amp;mdash;<italics>A Little Night Music</italics><space/>is an occasionally used translation of<space/><italics><link><target>Eine kleine Nachtmusik</target></link></italics>, the nickname of Mozart's<space/><link><target>Serenade No. 13 (Mozart)</target><part>Serenade No. 13 for strings in G major</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kchel catalogue</target><part>K.</part></link><space/>525. The elegant,<space/><link><target>harmony</target><part>harmonically</part></link>-advanced music in this musical pays indirect homage to the compositions of<space/><link><target>Maurice Ravel</target></link>, especially his<space/><italics><link><target>Valses nobles et sentimentales (Ravel)</target><part>Valses nobles et sentimentales</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Citron, Stephen. pp. 200, 203</extension><space/>(whose opening chord is borrowed for the opening chord of the song &quot;Liaisons&quot;); part of this effect stems from the style of orchestration that<space/><link><target>Jonathan Tunick</target></link><space/>used.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cast recordings</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Nightrnt.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Cast recording of 1995 National Theatre revival starring Judi Dench</part></link>In addition to the original Broadway and London cast recordings, and the motion picture soundtrack (no longer available), there are recordings of the 1990 studio cast, the 1995<space/><link><target>Royal National Theatre</target></link><space/>revival (starring<space/><link><target>Judi Dench</target></link>), and the 2001 Barcelona cast recording sung in<space/><link><target>Catalan language</target><part>Catalan</part></link>. In 1997 an all-jazz version of the score was recorded by<space/><link><target>Terry Trotter</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sondheimguide.com/nightrecs.html'>&quot;Recordings, 'A Little Night Music'&quot;</link><space/>sondheimguide.com, retrieved June 8, 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 2009 Broadway revival with Catherine Zeta-Jones and Angela Lansbury recorded a cast album on January 4, 2010 which was released on April 6.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hetrick, Adam and Jones, Kenneth.<link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/138450-A-Little-Night-Music-CD-Released-April-6-Sondheim-and-Co-Host-Signing'>&quot;'A Little Night Music' CD Released April 6; Sondheim and Co. Host Signing&quot;</link><space/>playbill.com, April 6, 2010</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Critical response</heading><paragraph>In his review of the original 1973 Broadway production,<space/><link><target>Clive Barnes</target></link><space/>in the<space/><italics><link><target>New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>called the musical &quot;heady, civilized, sophisticated and enchanting.&quot; He noted that &quot;the real triumph belongs to Stephen Sondheim...the music is a celebration of 3/4 time, an orgy of plaintively memorable waltzes, all talking of past loves and lost worlds...There is a peasant touch here.&quot; He commented that the lyrics are &quot;breathtaking&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barnes, Clive, &quot;The Theater:'A Little Night Music&quot;,<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, February 26, 1973, p. 26</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In its review of the 1989 London revival, the reviewer for<space/><italics>The Guardian</italics><space/>wrote that the &quot;production also strikes me as infinitely superior to Harold Prince's 1975 version at the Adelphi. Mr Judge's great innovation is to transform the Liebeslieder Singers from the evening-dressed, after-dinner line-up into 18th century ghosts weaving in and out of the action...But Mr Judge's other great realisation is that, in Sondheim, the lyrics are not an adornment to a song but their very essence: understand them and the show will flow. Thus Dorothy Tutin as Desiree, the touring thesp eventually reunited with her quondam lover, is not the melting romantic of previous productions but a working mother with the sharpness of a hat-pin.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Billington, Michael. &quot;Arts: Night of the short memories - 'A Little Night Music'&quot;,<space/><italics>The Guardian</italics><space/>(London)., October 23, 1989 (no page number)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Independent</italics><space/>review of the 1995 National Theatre revival praised the production, writing &quot;For three hours of gloriously barbed bliss and bewitchment, Sean Mathias's production establishes the show as a minor miracle of astringent worldly wisdom and one that is haunted by less earthy intimations.&quot; The review went on to state that &quot;The heart of the production, in both senses, is Judi Dench's superb Desiree Armfeldt...Her husky-voiced rendering of &quot;Send in the Clowns&quot; is the most moving I've ever heard.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor, Paul and Seckerson, Edward.<link type='external' href='http://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/double-take-reviews-a-little-night-music-1603205.html'>&quot;Double Take: Reviews: 'A Little Night Music'&quot;</link>''Independent', September 1995</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In reviewing the 2008 Menier Chocolate Factory production,<space/><italics>The Telegraph</italics><space/>reviewer wrote that &quot;Sondheim's lyrics are often superbly witty, his music here, mostly in haunting waltz-time, far more accessible than is sometimes the case. The score positively throbs with love, regret and desire.&quot; But of the specific production, the reviewer went on to note: &quot;But Nunn's production, on one of those hermetic sets largely consisting of doors and tarnished mirrors that have become such a clich in recent years, never penetrates the work's subtly erotic heart. And as is often the case with this director's work, the pace is so slow and the mood so reverent, that initial enchantment gives way to bored fidgeting.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="telegraph"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In his<space/><italics><link><target>New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>review of the 2009 Broadway production,<space/><link><target>Ben Brantley</target></link><space/>noted that &quot;the expression that hovers over Trevor Nunn's revival...feels dangerously close to a smirk...It is a smirk shrouded in shadows. An elegiac darkness infuses this production.&quot; The production is &quot;sparing on furniture and heavy on shadows&quot;, with &quot;a scaled-down orchestra at lugubriously slowed-down tempos...&quot; He goes on to write that &quot;this somber, less-is-more approach could be effective were the ensemble plugged into the same rueful sensibility. But there is only one moment in this production when all its elements cohere perfectly. That moment, halfway through the first act, belongs to Ms. Lansbury, who has hitherto been perfectly entertaining, playing Madame Armfeldt with the overripe aristocratic condescension of a Lady Bracknell. Then comes her one solo, &quot;Liaisons&quot;, in which her character thinks back on the art of love as a profession in a gilded age, when sex 'was but a pleasurable means to a measurable end.' Her face, with its glamour-gorgon makeup, softens, as Madame Armfeldt seems to melt into memory itself, and the wan stage light briefly appears to borrow radiance from her. It's a lovely example of the past reaching out to the present...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Brantley, Ben.<link type='external' href='http://theater.nytimes.com/2009/12/14/theater/reviews/14little.htm'>&quot;A Weekend in the Country With Eros and Thanatos&quot;</link><space/><italics>The New York Times</italics>, December 14, 2009<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://theater.nytimes.com/2009/12/14/theater/reviews/14little.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">20150402204405<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Steven Suskin, reviewing the new Broadway cast for<space/><italics><link><target>Variety (magazine)</target><part>Variety</part></link></italics>, wrote &quot;What a difference a diva makes. Bernadette Peters steps into the six-month-old revival of 'A Little Night Music' with a transfixing performance, playing it as if she realizes her character's onstage billing -- &quot;the one and only Desiree Armfeldt&quot;is cliched hyperbole. By figuratively rolling her eyes at the hype, Peters gives us a rich, warm and comedically human Desiree, which reaches full impact when she pierces the facade with a nakedly honest, tears-on-cheek 'Send in the Clowns.'&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Suskin, Steven. &quot;'A Little Night Music' Review&quot;,<space/><italics>Variety</italics>, August 2, 2010</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Awards and nominations</heading><heading level='3'>Original Broadway production</heading><table class="wikitable" style="width:95%;"><tablerow><tablehead style="width:5%;">Year</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Award Ceremony</tablehead><tablehead style="width:45%;">Category</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Nominee</tablehead><tablehead style="width:10%;">Result</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="23" style="text-align:center;">1973</tablecell><tablecell rowspan="7"><link><target>Drama Desk Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Book of a Musical</target><part>Outstanding Book of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Hugh Wheeler</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Music</target><part>Outstanding Music</part></link></tablecell><tablecell rowspan="2"><link><target>Stephen Sondheim</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Lyrics</target><part>Outstanding Lyrics</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="2"><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Actress in a Musical</target><part>Outstanding Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Glynis Johns</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Patricia Elliott</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Director</target><part>Outstanding Director</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Harold Prince</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award</target><part>Most Promising Performer</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>D'Jamin Bartlett</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Grammy Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Grammy Award for Best Musical Show Album</target><part>Best Musical Show Album</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="3" colspan="2"><link><target>Theatre World Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Guittard</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Patricia Elliott</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>D'Jamin Bartlett</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="12"><link><target>Tony Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Tony Award for Best Musical</target><part>Best Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Book of a Musical</target><part>Best Book of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Hugh Wheeler</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Original Score</target><part>Best Original Score</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Stephen Sondheim</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Leading Actor in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Len Cariou</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Glynis Johns</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Featured Actor in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Guittard</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="2"><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Patricia Elliott</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Hermione Gingold</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Costume Design</target><part>Best Costume Design</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Florence Klotz</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Scenic Design</target><part>Best Scenic Design</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Boris Aronson</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Lighting Design</target><part>Best Lighting Design</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tharon Musser</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Direction of a Musical</target><part>Best Direction of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Harold Prince</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>1995 London revival</heading><table class="wikitable" style="width:95%;"><tablerow><tablehead style="width:5%;">Year</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Award Ceremony</tablehead><tablehead style="width:45%;">Category</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Nominee</tablehead><tablehead style="width:10%;">Result</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="4" style="text-align:center;">1995</tablecell><tablecell rowspan="4"><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Judi Dench</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Performance in a Supporting Role in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance in a Supporting Role in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Sin Phillips</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Theatre Choreographer</target><part>Best Theatre Choreographer</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Wayne McGregor</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Costume Design</target><part>Best Costume Design</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Nicky Gillibrand</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>2009 London Revival</heading><table class="wikitable" width="95%"><tablerow><tablehead width="5%">Year</tablehead><tablehead width="20%">Award Ceremony</tablehead><tablehead width="45%">Category</tablehead><tablehead width="20%">Nominee</tablehead><tablehead width="10%">Result</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="5">2010</tablecell><tablecell rowspan="5"><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Musical Revival</target><part>Best Revival of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Hannah Waddingham</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Actor in a Musical</target><part>Best Actor in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Alexander Hanson (actor)</target><part>Alexander Hanson</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Performance in a Supporting Role in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance in a Supporting role in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Maureen Lipman</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Laurence Olivier Award for Best Performance in a Supporting Role in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance in a Supporting role in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Kelly Price</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>2009 Broadway revival</heading><table class="wikitable" style="width:95%;"><tablerow><tablehead style="width:5%;">Year</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Award Ceremony</tablehead><tablehead style="width:45%;">Category</tablehead><tablehead style="width:20%;">Nominee</tablehead><tablehead style="width:10%;">Result</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="10" style="text-align:center;">2010</tablecell><tablecell rowspan="3"><link><target>Drama Desk Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Revival of a Musical</target><part>Outstanding Revival of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Actress in a Musical</target><part>Outstanding Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Catherine Zeta-Jones</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Drama Desk Award for Outstanding Featured Actress in a Musical</target><part>Outstanding Featured Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Angela Lansbury</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="3"><link><target>Outer Critics Circle Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2">Outstanding Revival of a Musical</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Outstanding Actress in a Musical</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Catherine Zeta-Jones</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Outstanding Featured Actress in a Musical</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Angela Lansbury</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell rowspan="4"><link><target>Tony Award</target></link></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Tony Award for Best Revival of a Musical</target><part>Best Revival of a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Leading Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Catherine Zeta-Jones</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>won</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical</target><part>Best Performance by a Featured Actress in a Musical</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Angela Lansbury</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Tony Award for Best Sound Design</target><part>Best Sound Design</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Dan Moses Schreier</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Gareth Owen (sound designer)</target><part>Gareth Owen</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell style="text-align:center;">2011</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Grammy Award</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Gans, Andrew.<link type='external' href='http://www.playbill.com/news/article/145450-Idiot-Fela-Night-Music-Promises-and-Sondheim-Are-Grammy-Nominated'>&quot;Idiot, Fela!, Night Music, Promises and Sondheim Are Grammy-Nominated&quot;</link><space/>playbill.com, December 1, 2010</extension></tablecell><tablecell colspan="2"><link><target>Grammy Award for Best Musical Show Album</target><part>Best Musical Show Album</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>nom</target></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Citron, Stephen. &quot;Sondheim and Lloyd-Webber: The New Musical&quot; (2001). Oxford University Press US. ISBN 0-19-509601-0</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>ibdb show</target><arg>1162</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sondheimguide.com/night.html'>''A Little Night Music'' on The Stephen Sondheim Reference Guide</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mtishows.com/show_detail.asp?showid=000048'>''A Little Night Music''</link><space/>at the Music Theatre International website</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://stageagent.com/Shows/View/735'>A Little Night Music info page on StageAgent.com</link><space/>- A Little Night Music plot summary &amp; character descriptions</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nightmusiconbroadway.com/'>''A Little Night Music''<space/></link><space/>- A Little Night Music Broadway Revival</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ingentaconnect.com/content/intellect/smt/2014/00000008/00000002/art00004'>&quot;Sondheim's ''A Little Night Music'': Reconciling the Comic and the Sublime&quot; by Graham Wolfe</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DramaDesk MusicalRevival 19882000</target></template><template><target>TonyAwardBestMusical 1947-1975</target></template><template><target>TonyAward MusicalScore 1947-1975</target></template><template><target>TonyAward MusicalBook 1947-1975</target></template><template><target>Stephen Sondheim</target></template><template><target>Smiles of a Summer Night</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Little Night Music, A</target></template><link><target>Category:1973 musicals</target></link><link><target>Category:Broadway musicals</target></link><link><target>Category:West End musicals</target></link><link><target>Category:Musicals based on films</target></link><link><target>Category:Musicals by Stephen Sondheim</target></link><link><target>Category:Best Original Music Score Academy Award winners</target></link><link><target>Category:Adaptations of works by Ingmar Bergman</target></link><link><target>Category:Plays adapted into films</target></link><link><target>Category:Tony Award for Best Musical</target></link></paragraph></article>