<article title='Dracula'><paragraph><template><target>Two other uses</target><arg>the novel</arg><arg>the eponymous character</arg><arg>Count Dracula</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg name="name"><space/>Dracula
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Dracula1st.jpeg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>The cover of the first edition
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Bram Stoker]]
</arg><arg name="cover_artist"><space/>
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United Kingdom
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Horror fiction|Horror]], [[Gothic fiction|Gothic]]
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Constable & Robinson|Archibald Constable and Company (UK)]]
</arg><arg name="release_date"><space/>26 May [[1897 in literature|1897]]
</arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>1447002
</arg></template><bold><italics>Dracula</italics></bold><space/>is an 1897 Gothic horror novel by Irish author<space/><link><target>Bram Stoker</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>First published as a hardcover in 1897 by Archibald Constable and Co. See http://www.bramstoker.org/novels.html Bibliography of Stoker's novels at Bram Stoker Online.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Famous for introducing the character of the<space/><link><target>vampire</target></link><space/><link><target>Count Dracula</target></link>, the novel tells the story of Dracula's attempt to move from<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link><space/>to England so he may find new blood and spread the undead curse, and the battle between Dracula and a small group of men and women led by Professor<space/><link><target>Abraham Van Helsing</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>has been assigned to many<space/><link><target>literary genre</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>including<space/><link><target>vampire literature</target></link>,<space/><link><target>horror fiction</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>gothic fiction</target><part>gothic novel</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>invasion literature</target></link>. Although Stoker did not invent the vampire, he defined its modern form, and the novel has spawned numerous theatrical, film and television interpretations.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot summary</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Stoker Dracula Notes Personal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Stoker's handwritten notes on the personnel of the novel</part></link>The story is told in<space/><link><target>Epistolary novel</target><part>epistolary</part></link><space/>format, as a series of letters,<space/><link><target>diary</target></link><space/>entries, and ships' log entries, whose narrators are the novel's protagonists, and occasionally supplemented with newspaper clippings relating events not directly witnessed. The events portrayed in the novel take place chronologically and largely in England and<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link><space/>during the 1890s and all transpire within the same year between the 3rd of May and the 6th of November. A short note is located at the end of the final chapter written 7 years after the events outlined in the novel.</paragraph><paragraph>The tale begins with<space/><link><target>Jonathan Harker</target></link>, a newly qualified English<space/><link><target>solicitor</target></link>, visiting<space/><link><target>Count Dracula</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Carpathian Mountains</target></link><space/>on the border of<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bukovina</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Moldavia</target></link>, to provide legal support for a<space/><link><target>real estate</target></link><space/>transaction overseen by Harker's employer. At first enticed by Dracula's gracious manners, Harker soon realizes that he is Dracula's prisoner. Wandering the Count's castle against Dracula's admonition, Harker encounters three female vampires, called &quot;<link><target>Brides of Dracula</target><part>the sisters</part></link>&quot;, from whom he is rescued by Dracula. After the preparations are made, Dracula leaves Transylvania and abandons Harker to the sisters. Harker barely escapes from the castle with his life.</paragraph><paragraph>Not long afterward, a Russian ship, the<space/><italics>Demeter</italics>, having weighed anchor at<space/><link><target>Varna</target></link>, runs aground on the shores of<space/><link><target>Whitby</target></link>. The captain's<space/><link><target>Logbook</target><part>log</part></link><space/>narrates the gradual disappearance of the entire crew, until the captain alone remained, himself bound to the helm to maintain course. An animal resembling &quot;a large dog&quot; is seen leaping ashore. The ship's cargo is described as silver sand and boxes of &quot;mould&quot;, or earth, from Transylvania.</paragraph><paragraph>Soon Dracula is tracking Harker's fiance,<space/><link><target>Mina Harker</target><part>Wilhelmina &quot;Mina&quot; Murray</part></link>, and her friend,<space/><link><target>Lucy Westenra</target></link>, who begins to sleepwalk nightly. Lucy receives three marriage proposals from Dr.<space/><link><target>John Seward</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Quincey Morris</target></link>, and the Hon.<space/><link><target>Arthur Holmwood</target></link><space/>(later Lord Godalming). Lucy accepts Holmwood's proposal while turning down Seward and Morris, but all remain friends. Dracula communicates with Seward's patient<space/><link><target>Renfield</target></link>, an insane man who wishes to consume insects, spiders, birds, and rats to absorb their &quot;life force&quot;, and therefore assimilate to Dracula himself. Renfield is able to detect Dracula's presence and supplies clues accordingly.</paragraph><paragraph>When Lucy begins to waste away suspiciously, Seward invites his old teacher,<space/><link><target>Abraham Van Helsing</target></link>, who immediately determines the cause of Lucy's condition but refuses to disclose it. She has obviously lost an enormous quantity of blood, and though she receives<space/><link><target>blood transfusions</target></link><space/>from all of her three quondam lovers, and Van Helsing to boot, which quantity Morris notes &quot;her body could not hold&quot;, she continues to waste away - appearing to lose blood every night. While both doctors are absent, Lucy and her mother are attacked by a<space/><link><target>wolf</target></link>; Mrs. Westenra, who has a heart condition, dies of fright. Van Helsing attempts to protect her with<space/><link><target>Garlic#Spiritual and religious uses</target><part>garlic</part></link><space/>but fate thwarts him each night, whether Lucy's mother removes the garlic from her room, or Lucy herself does so in her restless sleep. The doctors have found two small puncture marks about her neck, which Dr Seward is at a loss to understand. Following Lucy's death soon after, the newspapers report children being stalked in the night by, in their words, a &quot;bloofer lady&quot; (i.e., &quot;beautiful lady&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Leonard Wolf</target></link><space/>(2004).<space/><italics>The Essential Dracula</italics>, Chapter 13, Note 31. &quot;Bloofer lady&quot; is explained as baby-talk for &quot;beautiful lady&quot;.</extension><space/>Van Helsing, knowing Lucy has become a vampire, confides in Seward, Lord Godalming, and Morris. The suitors and Van Helsing track her down and, after a confrontation with her, stake her heart,<space/><link><target>behead</target></link><space/>her, and fill her mouth with<space/><link><target>garlic</target></link>. Around the same time, Jonathan Harker arrives from<space/><link><target>Budapest</target></link>, where Mina marries him after his escape, and he and Mina join the coalition against Dracula.</paragraph><paragraph>After Dracula learns of Van Helsing's plot against him, he attacks Mina on three occasions, and feeds Mina his own blood to control her. Under his influence, Mina oscillates from consciousness to a semi-trance during which she perceives Dracula's surroundings and actions. After the protagonists sterilize all of his lairs in London by putting pieces of consecrated host in each box of Transylvanian earth, Dracula flees to Transylvania, pursued by Van Helsing and the others under the guidance of Mina. In Transylvania, Van Helsing repulses and later destroys the vampire &quot;sisters&quot;. Upon discovering Dracula being transported by<space/><link><target>Romani people</target><part>Gypsies</part></link>, Harker shears Dracula through the throat with a<space/><link><target>kukri</target></link><space/>while the mortally wounded Quincey stabs the Count in the heart with a<space/><link><target>Bowie knife</target></link>. Dracula crumbles to dust, and Mina is restored to health.</paragraph><paragraph>The book closes with a note on Mina's and Jonathan's married life and the birth of their son, whom they name after all four members of the party, but address as &quot;Quincey&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Deleted ending</heading><paragraph>Three paragraphs from the original final chapter were removed, in which Dracula's castle falls apart as he dies, hiding the fact that vampires were ever there.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">listverse.com</arg><arg name="url">http://listverse.com/2013/01/14/deleted-book-chapters/</arg><arg name="date">14 January 2013</arg><arg name="title">10 Deleted Chapters that Transformed Famous Books</arg><arg name="author">Symon, Evan V.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Dracula's Guest&quot;</heading><paragraph>In 1914, two years after Stoker's death, the short story &quot;<link><target>Dracula's Guest</target></link>&quot; was posthumously published. It was, according to most contemporary critics, the deleted first (or second) chapter from the original manuscript<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?vid</arg><arg name="author">James Craig Holte<space/></arg><arg name="page">27<space/></arg><arg name="title">''Dracula Film Adaptations''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 June 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>and the one which gave the volume its name,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Belford2002"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?vid</arg><arg name="author">Barbara Belford<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bram Stoker and the Man Who Was Dracula<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-306-81098-0<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 June 2010</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>325</arg></template><space/>but which the original publishers deemed unnecessary to the overall story.</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Dracula's Guest&quot; follows an unnamed Englishman traveller as he wanders around<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link><space/>before leaving for Transylvania. It is<space/><link><target>Walpurgis Night</target></link>, and in spite of the coachman's warnings, the young Englishman foolishly leaves his hotel and wanders through a dense forest alone. Along the way he feels he is being watched by a tall and thin stranger (possibly Count Dracula).</paragraph><paragraph>The short story climaxes in an old graveyard, where in a marble tomb (with a large iron stake driven into it), the Englishman encounters a sleeping female vampire called<space/><italics>Countess Dolingen</italics>. This malevolent and beautiful vampire awakens from her marble<space/><link><target>bier</target></link><space/>to conjure a snowstorm before being struck by lightning and returning to her eternal prison. However, the Englishman's troubles are not quite over, as he is dragged away by an unseen force and rendered unconscious. He awakes to find a &quot;gigantic&quot; wolf lying on his chest and licking at his throat; however, the wolf merely keeps him warm and protects him until help arrives.</paragraph><paragraph>When the Englishman is finally taken back to his hotel, a telegram awaits him from his expectant host Dracula, with a warning about &quot;dangers from snow and wolves and night&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Characters</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Jonathan Harker</target></link>: A solicitor sent to do business with Count Dracula; Mina's fianc and prisoner in Dracula's castle.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Count Dracula</target></link>: A Transylvanian noble who has purchased a house in London.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mina Harker</target><part>Wilhelmina &quot;Mina&quot; Harker</part></link><space/>(ne Murray): A schoolteacher and Jonathan Harker's fiance.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lucy Westenra</target></link>: A 19-year-old aristocrat; Mina's best friend; Arthur's fiance and Dracula's first victim.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Arthur Holmwood</target></link>: Lucy's suitor and later fianc.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>John Seward</target></link>: A doctor; one of Lucy's suitors and a former student of Van Helsing.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Abraham Van Helsing</target></link>: A Dutch doctor and professor; John Seward's teacher; and, a vampire hunter.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quincey Morris</target></link>: An American cowboy and explorer; and one of Lucy's suitors.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Renfield</target></link>: A lawyer who has lost his wits after meeting Dracula.<space/></listitem><listitem>&quot;Weird Sisters&quot;: Three siren-like vampire women who serve Dracula. In some of the plays, films etc. that came after the novel they are referred to as the<space/><link><target>Brides of Dracula</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph>Between 1879 and 1898, Stoker was a business manager for the world-famous<space/><link><target>Lyceum Theatre, London</target><part>Lyceum Theatre</part></link><space/>in London, where he supplemented his income by writing a large number of sensational novels, his most famous being the vampire tale<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>published on 26 May 1897.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Belford2002"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>269</arg></template><space/>Parts of it are set around the town of<space/><link><target>Whitby</target></link>, where he spent summer holidays. Throughout the 1880s and 1890s, authors such as<space/><link><target>Henry Rider Haggard</target><part>H. Rider Haggard</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Rudyard Kipling</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Robert Louis Stevenson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>H. G. Wells</target></link><space/>wrote many tales in which fantastic creatures threatened the British Empire.<space/><link><target>Invasion literature</target></link><space/>was at a peak, and Stoker's formula of an invasion of England by continental European influences was by 1897 very familiar to readers of fantastic adventure stories. Victorian readers enjoyed it as a good adventure story like many others, but it would not reach its iconic legendary status until later in the 20th century when film versions began to appear.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Nina Auerbach</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David Skal</target></link>, editors.<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>. Norton Critical Edition. 1997. ISBN 0-393-97012-4. Preface, first paragraph.</extension><space/></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>File:Henry Irving portrait.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>175px</part><part>Shakespearean actor and friend of Stoker's,<space/><link><target>Henry Irving</target><part>Sir Henry Irving</part></link><space/>was a possible real-life inspiration for the character of Dracula. The role was tailor-made to his dramatic presence, gentlemanly mannerisms and affinity for playing villain roles. Irving, however, never agreed to play the part on stage.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Before writing<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>, Stoker spent seven years researching European folklore and stories of vampires, being most influenced by<space/><link><target>Emily Gerard</target></link>'s 1885 essay, &quot;Transylvania Superstitions&quot;. Later he would also claim that he had a nightmare, caused by eating too much crab meat covered with mayonnaise sauce, about a &quot;vampire king&quot; rising from his grave.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite being the most widely known vampire novel,<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>was not the first. It was preceded and partly inspired by<space/><link><target>Sheridan Le Fanu</target></link>'s 1871 &quot;<link><target>Carmilla</target></link>&quot;, about a<space/><link><target>lesbian vampire</target></link><space/>who preys on a lonely young woman, and by<space/><italics><link><target>Varney the Vampire</target></link></italics>, a lengthy<space/><link><target>penny dreadful</target></link><space/>serial from the mid-Victorian period by<space/><link><target>James Malcolm Rymer</target></link>. The image of a vampire portrayed as an aristocratic man, like the character of Dracula, was created by<space/><link><target>John Polidori</target></link><space/>in &quot;<link><target>The Vampyre</target></link>&quot; (1819), during the summer spent with<space/><italics><link><target>Frankenstein</target></link></italics><space/>creator<space/><link><target>Mary Shelley</target></link>, her husband, the poet<space/><link><target>Percy Bysshe Shelley</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lord Byron</target></link><space/>in 1816. The Lyceum Theatre, where Stoker worked between 1878 and 1898, was headed by the actor-manager<space/><link><target>Henry Irving</target></link>, who was Stoker's real-life inspiration for Dracula's mannerisms and who Stoker hoped would play Dracula in a stage version.<extension extension_name='ref' name="warren">Lewis S Warren,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/107.4/ah0402001124.html'>''Buffalo Bill Meets Dracula: William F. Cody, Bram Stoker, and the Frontiers of Racial Decay''</link>,<space/><link><target>American Historical Review</target></link>, Vol. 107, No. 4, October 2002, paragraph 18<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="df">yes</arg><arg name="url">http://www.historycooperative.org/journals/ahr/107.4/ah0402001124.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20130506083906<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Although Irving never did agree to do a stage version, Dracula's dramatic sweeping gestures and gentlemanly mannerisms drew their living embodiment from Irving.<extension extension_name='ref' name="warren"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>The Dead Un-Dead</italics><space/>was one of Stoker's original titles for<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>, and up until a few weeks before publication, the manuscript was titled simply<space/><italics>The Un-Dead</italics>. Stoker's notes for<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>show that the name of the count was originally &quot;Count Wampyr&quot;, but while doing research, Stoker became intrigued by the name &quot;Dracula&quot;, after reading<space/><link><target>William Wilkinson (diplomat)</target><part>William Wilkinson</part></link>'s book<space/><italics>Account of the Principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia with Political Observations Relative to Them</italics><space/>(London 1820),<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=RogMAQAAMAAJ'>An account of the principalities of Wallachia and Moldavia</link><space/>- William Wilkinson, Longman, 1820 (Google Free eBook)</extension><space/>which he found in the Whitby Library, and consulted a number of times during visits to Whitby in the 1890s.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Radu R. Florescu</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Raymond T. McNally</target></link><space/><italics>Dracula, Prince of Many Faces</italics>. Little Brown. 1989. ISBN 0316286567. pp. 229&amp;ndash;31.</extension><space/>The name Dracula was the<space/><link><target>Patronymic</target><part>patronym</part></link><space/>(<italics>Drculea</italics>) of the descendants of<space/><link><target>Vlad II Dracul</target><part>Vlad II</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Wallachia</target></link>, who took the name &quot;Dracul&quot; after being invested in the<space/><link><target>Order of the Dragon</target></link><space/>in 1431. In the Romanian language, the word<space/><italics>dracul</italics><space/>(Romanian<space/><italics>drac</italics><space/>&quot;dragon&quot; +<space/><italics>-ul</italics><space/>&quot;the&quot;) can mean either &quot;the dragon&quot; or, especially in the present day, &quot;the devil&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Raymond T. McNally</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Radu R. Florescu</target></link><space/><italics>In Search of Dracula, The History of Dracula and Vampires (Completely Revised)</italics>. Houghton Mifflin. 1994. ISBN 0-395-65783-0. pp. 8-9.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The novel has been in the<space/><link><target>public domain</target></link><space/>in the United States since its original publication because Stoker failed to follow proper copyright procedure. In the United Kingdom and other countries following the<space/><link><target>Berne Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works</target><part>Berne Convention</part></link><space/>on copyrights, however, the novel was under copyright until April 1962, fifty years after Stoker's death.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Lugosi v. Universal Pictures</italics>, 70 Cal.App.3d 552 (1977), note 4.</extension><space/>When<space/><link><target>F. W. Murnau</target></link>'s unauthorized film adaptation<space/><italics><link><target>Nosferatu</target></link></italics><space/>was released in 1922, the popularity of the novel increased considerably, owing to the controversy caused when Stoker's widow tried to have the film removed from public circulation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Stoker<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bram<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/vampires/classicstory/dracula_p1.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">—Article at the BBC Cult website<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reaction and scholarly criticism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dracamer99.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>1899 first American edition, Doubleday &amp; McClure, New York.</part></link>When it was first published, in 1897,<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>was not an immediate<space/><link><target>bestseller</target></link>, although reviewers were unstinting in their praise. The contemporary<space/><italics><link><target>Daily Mail</target></link></italics><space/>ranked Stoker's powers above those of<space/><link><target>Mary Shelley</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target></link><space/>as well as<space/><link><target>Emily Bront</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Wuthering Heights</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cited in Paul Murray's &quot;From the Shadow of Dracula: A Life of Bram Stoker&quot; 2004. pp. 363-4.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to literary historians<space/><link><target>Nina Auerbach</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David J. Skal</target></link><space/>in the Norton Critical Edition, the novel has become more significant for modern readers than it was for contemporary Victorian readers, most of whom enjoyed it just as a good adventure story; it reached its broad iconic legendary classic status only later in the 20th century when the movie versions appeared.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nina Auerbach and David Skal, editors.<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>. Norton Critical Edition. 1997. ISBN 0-393-97012-4. Preface, first paragraph.</extension><space/>It did not make much money for Stoker; the last year of his life he was so poor that he had to petition for a compassionate grant from the Royal Literary Fund,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.todayinliterature.com/stories.asp?Event_Date</arg><arg name="title">Bram Stoker - Stoker, Irving & Count Vlad<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Today in Literature<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 April 1912<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>and in 1913 his widow was forced to sell his notes and outlines of the novel at a<space/><link><target>Sotheby's</target></link><space/>auction, where they were purchased for a little over 2 pounds.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://irishphiladelphia.com/2011/06/bram-stokers-dracula-by-gothic-candlelight/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bram Stoker's "Dracula" by Gothic Candlelight<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Irishphiladelphia.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 June 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>But when F. W. Murnau's unauthorized adaptation of the story in the form of<space/><italics><link><target>Nosferatu</target></link></italics><space/>was released in theatres in 1922, Stoker's widow took affront, and during the legal battle that followed, the novel's popularity started to grow.<space/><italics>Nosferatu</italics><space/>was followed by a highly successful stage adaptation, touring the UK for three years before arriving in the US where Stoker's creation caught Hollywood's attention, and after the American 1931 movie version was released, the book has never been out of print.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Stoker<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bram<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/cult/vampires/classicstory/dracula_p1.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cult Vampires - Extract from Dracula by Bram Stoker<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>However, some Victorian fans were ahead of the time, describing it as &quot;the sensation of the season&quot; and &quot;the most blood-curdling novel of the paralysed century&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Dalby &quot;Bram Stoker&quot;, in Jack Sullivan (ed)<space/><italics>The Penguin Encyclopedia of Horror and the Supernatural</italics>, 1986, Viking, pp. 404-6, 405.</extension><space/><link><target>Sherlock Holmes</target></link><space/>author<space/><link><target>Sir Arthur Conan Doyle</target></link><space/>wrote to Stoker in a letter, &quot;I write to tell you how very much I have enjoyed reading<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>. I think it is the very best story of diablerie which I have read for many years.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Klinger, page xxxii</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Daily Mail</italics><space/>review of 1 June 1897 proclaimed it a classic of<space/><link><target>Gothic horror</target></link>, &quot;In seeking a parallel to this weird, powerful, and horrorful story our mind reverts to such tales as<space/><italics><link><target>The Mysteries of Udolpho</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Frankenstein</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Fall of the House of Usher</target></link></italics><space/>... but Dracula is even more appalling in its gloomy fascination than any one of these.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Cited in Nina Auerbach and David Skal, editors,<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>, Norton Critical Edition, 1997, pp. 363-4.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Similarly good reviews appeared when the book was published in the U.S. in 1899. The first American edition was published by<space/><link><target>Doubleday (publisher)</target><part>Doubleday &amp; McClure</part></link><space/>in New York.</paragraph><paragraph>In the last several decades, literary and cultural scholars have offered diverse analyses of Stoker's novel and the character of Count Dracula. C.F. Bentley reads Dracula as an embodiment of the<space/><link><target>Freudian</target></link><space/><link><target>Id, ego and super-ego#Id</target><part>id</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>C.F. Bentleys.<space/><italics>The Monster in the Bedroom: Sexual Symbolism in Bram Stokers Dracula</italics></extension><space/>Carol A. Senf reads the novel as a response to the powerful New Woman,<extension extension_name='ref'>Senf, Carol A.<space/><italics>The Vampire in Nineteenth-Century English Literature</italics>. Bowling Green: Popular Press,</extension><space/>while Christopher Craft sees Dracula as embodying latent homosexuality.<extension extension_name='ref'>Christopher Craft (1984).<space/><italics>&quot;Kiss Me with Those Red Lips&quot;: Gender and Inversion in Bram Stoker's Dracula</italics></extension><space/>Stephen D. Arata interprets the events of the novel as anxiety over<space/><link><target>colonialism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>racial mixing</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Arata, Stephen D.<space/><italics>The Occidental Tourist: Dracula and the Anxiety of Reverse Colonization</italics>, Victorian Studies 33.4 (1990).</extension><space/>and Talia Schaffer construes the novel as an indictment of<space/><link><target>Oscar Wilde</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schaffer, Talia (1994).<space/><italics>A Wilde Desire Took Me: the Homoerotic History of Dracula</italics></extension><space/><link><target>Franco Moretti</target></link><space/>reads Dracula as a figure of<space/><link><target>monopoly</target></link><space/><link><target>capitalism</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Franco Moretti, The Dialectic of Fear, New Left Review 136 (1982): 67-85</extension><space/>though<space/><link><target>Hollis Robbins</target></link><space/>suggests that Dracula's inability to participate in social conventions and to forge business partnerships undermines his power.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Killing Time 2014">&quot;Killing Time: Dracula and Social Discoordination&quot; in<space/><italics>Economics of the Undead</italics><space/>Eds. Glen Whitman and James Dow (Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 2014), chapter 23</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Bram Stoker's Notes for Dracula: A Facsimile Edition</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Robert Eighteen-Bisang</target></link><space/>&amp;<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Miller (academic)</target><part>Elizabeth Miller</part></link><space/>(McFarland, 2008)</extension><space/>Richard Noll reads<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>within the context of 19th century<space/><link><target>Psychiatry</target><part>alienism</part></link><space/>(<link><target>psychiatry</target></link>) and<space/><link><target>History of psychiatric institutions</target><part>asylum</part></link><space/>medicine.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Noll<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://www.academia.edu/6793535/Vampires_Werewolves_and_Demons_Twentieth_Century_Case_Reports_in_the_Psychiatric_Literature_1991_<space/></arg><arg name="title">Vampires Werewolves and Demons: Twentieth Century Case Reports in the Psychiatric Literature (1991) &#124; Richard Noll<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Academia.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>D. Bruno Starrs understands the novel to be a pro-<link><target>Catholic</target></link><space/>pamphlet promoting<space/><link><target>proselytization</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Starrs, D. Bruno. &quot;Keeping the faith: Catholicism in Dracula and its adaptations,&quot; Journal of Dracula Studies 6 (2004). http://blooferland.com/drc/index.php?title=Journal_of_Dracula_Studies#Number_6_.282004.29</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical and geographical references</heading><paragraph>Although<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>is a work of fiction, it does contain some historical references. The historical connections with the novel and how much Stoker knew about the history are a matter of conjecture and debate.</paragraph><paragraph>Following the publication of<space/><italics>In Search of Dracula</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Radu Florescu</target></link><space/>and Raymond McNally in 1972, the supposed connections between the historical<space/><link><target>Transylvania</target><trail>n</trail></link>-born<space/><link><target>Vlad the Impaler</target><part>Vlad III Dracula</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Wallachia</target></link><space/>and Bram Stoker's fictional Dracula attracted popular attention. During his main reign (14561462), &quot;Vlad the Impaler&quot; is said to have killed from 40,000 to 100,000 European civilians (political rivals, criminals, and anyone he considered &quot;useless to humanity&quot;), mainly by impaling. The sources depicting these events are records by<space/><link><target>Transylvanian Saxons</target><part>Saxon</part></link><space/>settlers in neighbouring Transylvania, who had frequent clashes with Vlad III. Vlad III is revered as a folk hero by<space/><link><target>Romanians</target></link><space/>for driving off the invading<space/><link><target>Ottoman Turks</target></link>, of which his<space/><link><target>impalement</target><part>impaled</part></link><space/>victims are said to have included as many as 100,000.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Andreescu"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Vlad the Impaler (Dracula)</arg><arg name="author"><space/>Andreescu, Stefan</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1999</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Romanian Cultural Foundation Publishing House</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>973-577-197-7</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Vlad Tepes 002.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part><link><target>Vlad the Impaler</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Historically, the name &quot;Dracula&quot; is derived from a<space/><link><target>Chivalric order</target></link><space/>called the<space/><link><target>Order of the Dragon</target></link>, founded by<space/><link><target>Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Sigismund of Luxembourg</part></link><space/>(then king of<space/><link><target>Hungary</target></link>) to uphold<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link><space/>and defend the Empire against the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target><part>Ottoman Turks</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Vlad II Dracul</target></link>, father of Vlad III, was admitted to the order around 1431, after which Vlad II wore the emblem of the order and later, as ruler of Wallachia, his<space/><link><target>coin</target><trail>age</trail></link><space/>bore the dragon symbol, from which the name &quot;Dracula&quot; is derived. People of Wallachia only knew<space/><italics>voievod</italics><space/>(king) Vlad III as Vlad epe (the Impaler). The name &quot;Dracula&quot; became popular in Romania after publication of Stoker's book. Contrary to popular belief, the name Dracula does not translate to &quot;son of the devil&quot; in<space/><link><target>Romanian language</target><part>Romanian</part></link>, which would be &quot;<italics>pui de drac</italics>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Stoker came across the name Dracula in his reading on<space/><link><target>History of Romania</target><part>Romanian history</part></link>, and chose this to replace the name (<italics>Count Wampyr</italics>) originally intended for his villain. Some Dracula scholars, led by<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Miller (academic)</target><part>Elizabeth Miller</part></link>, argue that Stoker knew little of the historic Vlad III except for the name &quot;Dracula&quot;, whereas in the novel, Stoker mentions the Dracula who fought against the Turks, and was later betrayed by his brother, historical facts which unequivocally point to Vlad III:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Who was it but one of my own race who as Voivode crossed the Danube and beat the Turk on his own ground? This was a Dracula indeed! Woe was it that his own unworthy brother, when he had fallen, sold his people to the Turk and brought the shame of slavery on them! Was it not this Dracula, indeed, who inspired that other of his race who in a later age again and again brought his forces over the great river into Turkey-land; who, when he was beaten back, came again, and again, though he had to come alone from the bloody field where his troops were being slaughtered, since he knew that he alone could ultimately triumph! (Chapter 3, pp 19)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Count's identity is later speculated on by Professor Van Helsing:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>He must, indeed, have been that Voivode Dracula who won his name against the Turk, over the great river on the very frontier of Turkey-land. (Chapter 18, p 145)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many of Stoker's biographers and literary critics have found strong similarities to the earlier Irish writer<space/><link><target>Sheridan Le Fanu</target></link>'s classic of the vampire genre,<space/><italics><link><target>Carmilla</target></link></italics>. In writing<space/><italics>Dracula</italics>, Stoker may also have drawn on stories about the<space/><link><target>Aos S</target><part>sdhe</part></link>,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template><space/>some of which feature blood-drinking women. The folkloric figure of<space/><link><target>Abhartach</target></link><space/>has also been suggested as a source.<extension extension_name='ref' name="curran"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Curran<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bob<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Was Dracula an Irishman?<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>History Ireland<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>8<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>Summer 2000<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1983, McNally additionally suggested that Stoker was influenced by the history of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Hungary</target><part>Hungarian</part></link><space/>Countess<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Bathory</target></link>, who tortured and killed between 36 and 700 young women.<extension extension_name='ref'>McNally, Raymund.<space/><italics>Dracula was a Woman</italics>. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1983</extension><space/>It was later commonly believed that she committed these crimes to bathe in their blood, believing that this preserved her youth.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Dennis Bathory-Kitsz<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://bathory.org/miller02.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Báthory Erzsébet - Elizabeth Bathory: Bram Stoker, Elizabeth Bathory, and Dracula (Elizabeth Miller)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bathory.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In her book<space/><italics>The Essential Dracula</italics>, Clare Haword-Maden opined the castle of Count Dracula was inspired by<space/><link><target>New Slains Castle</target><part>Slains Castle</part></link>, at which Bram Stoker was a guest of the 19th<space/><link><target>Earl of Erroll</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Haword-Maden, Clare.<space/><italics>The Essential Dracula</italics>. London: Bison Books, 1992</extension><space/>According to Miller, he first visited Cruden Bay in 1893, three years after work on<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>had begun. Haining and Tremaine maintain that during this visit, Stoker was especially impressed by Slains Castle's interior and the surrounding landscape. Miller and Leatherdale question the stringency of this connection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Haining, Peter and Tremayne, Peter. The Un-Dead: The Legend of Bram Stoker and Dracila. London: Constable 1997, quoted by Miller, Elizabeth. Dracula - Sense &amp; Nonsense, 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, p. 19. See also Leatherdale, Clive. Dracula Unearthed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 1998, p. 13</extension><space/>Possibly, Stoker was not inspired by a real edifice at all, but by<space/><link><target>Jules Verne</target></link>'s novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Carpathian Castle</target></link></italics><space/>(1892) or<space/><link><target>Anne Radcliffe</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Mysteries of Udolpho</target></link></italics><space/>(1794).<extension extension_name='ref'>Elizabeth Miller,<space/><italics>Dracula: Sense &amp; Nonsense</italics>. 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, p. 141</extension><space/>A third possibility is that he copied information about a castle at<space/><link><target>Brncoveneti, Mure</target><part>Vcs</part></link><space/>from one of his sources on Transylvania, the book by Major E.C. Johnson.<extension extension_name='ref'>Major E.C. Johnson,<space/><italics>On the Track of the Crescent: Erratic Notes from the Piraeus to Pesth.</italics><space/>London: Hurst and Blackett, 1885. p. 256-257, quoted by Marius Crian,<space/><italics>The Models for Castle Dracula in Stokers Sources on Transylvania</italics>, Journal of Dracula Studies Nr 10 (2008); also referred to by Miller, 2006, p. 141</extension><space/>A further option is that Stoker saw an illustration of Castle Bran (Trzburg) in the book on Transylvania by<space/><link><target>Charles Boner</target></link>, or read about it in the books by Mazuchelli or Crosse.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Charles Boner</target></link>,<space/><italics>Transylvania: Its Products and Its People.</italics><space/>London: Longmans, 1865. Referred to by Marius Crian,<space/><italics>The Models for Castle Dracula in Stokers Sources on Transylvania</italics>, Journal of Dracula Studies Nr 10 (2008). As indicated by Crian, Crosse's book .<space/><italics>Round About the Carpathians</italics><space/>and Mazuchelli's<space/><italics>Magyarland</italics><space/>describe Trzburg as well.</extension><space/>Many of the scenes in<space/><link><target>Whitby</target></link><space/>and London are based on real places that Stoker frequently visited, although in some cases he distorts the geography for the sake of the story. One scholar has suggested that Stoker chose<space/><link><target>Whitby</target></link><space/>as the site of Dracula's first appearance in England because of the<space/><link><target>Synod of Whitby</target></link>, given the novel's preoccupation with timekeeping and calendar disputes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Killing Time 2014"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Daniel Farson, Leonard Wolf, and Peter Haining have suggested that Stoker received much historical information from<space/><link><target>rmin Vmbry</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Hungary</target><part>Hungarian</part></link><space/>professor he met at least twice. Miller argues &quot;there is nothing to indicate that the conversation included Vlad, vampires, or even Transylvania&quot; and that, &quot;furthermore, there is no record of any other correspondence between Stoker and Vmbry, nor is Vmbry mentioned in Stoker's notes for Dracula.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Elizabeth Miller,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.blooferland.com/drc/images/Divorce.rtf'>Filing for Divorce Count Dracula vs Vlad Tepes</link><space/>Dracula: The Shade and the Shadow, ed. Elizabeth Miller (Westcliff-on-Sea: Desert Island Books, 1998; cf. Miller, Elizabeth. Dracula - Sense &amp; Nonsense, 2nd ed. Westcliff-on-Sea, UK: Desert Island Books, 2006, p. 25-27)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Adaptations</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>details</target><arg>Dracula in popular culture</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>File:Bela Lugosi as Dracula, anonymous photograph from 1931, Universal Studios.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bela Lugosi</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Dracula (1931 English-language film)</target><part>Dracula</part></link><space/>(1931)</part></link>The story of<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>has been the basis for numerous films and plays. Stoker himself wrote the first theatrical adaptation, which was presented at the Lyceum Theatre under the title<space/><italics>Dracula, or The Undead</italics><space/>shortly before the novel's publication and performed only once. Popular films include<space/><italics><link><target>Dracula (1931 English-language film)</target><part>Dracula</part></link></italics><space/>(1931),<space/><italics><link><target>Dracula (1958 film)</target><part>Dracula</part></link></italics><space/>(alternative title:<space/><italics>The Horror of Dracula</italics>) (1958), and<space/><italics><link><target>Dracula (1992 film)</target><part>Dracula</part></link></italics><space/>(also known as<space/><italics>Bram Stoker's Dracula</italics>) (1992).<space/><italics>Dracula</italics><space/>was also adapted as<space/><italics><link><target>Nosferatu</target></link></italics><space/>(1922), a film directed by the German director<space/><link><target>F. W. Murnau</target></link>, without permission from Stoker's widow; the filmmakers attempted to avoid copyright problems by altering many of the details, including changing the name of the villain to &quot;<link><target>Count Orlok</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The character of Count Dracula has remained popular over the years, and many films have used the character as a villain, while others have named him in their titles, including<space/><italics><link><target>Dracula's Daughter</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Brides of Dracula</target></link></italics>. As of 2009, an estimated 217 films feature Dracula in a major role,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>imdb character</target><arg>0002561</arg><arg>Count Dracula</arg></template></extension><space/>a number second only to<space/><link><target>Sherlock Holmes</target></link><space/>(223 films).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>imdb character</target><arg>0026631</arg><arg>Sherlock Holmes</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most adaptations do not include all the major characters from the novel. The Count is always present, and<space/><link><target>Jonathan Harker</target><part>Jonathan</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mina Harker</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Seward</target><part>Dr. Seward</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Abraham Van Helsing</target><part>Dr. Van Helsing</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Renfield</target></link><space/>usually appear as well. The characters of Mina and Lucy are often combined into a single female role. Jonathan Harker and Renfield are also sometimes reversed or combined.<space/><link><target>Quincey Morris</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Arthur Holmwood</target></link><space/>are usually omitted entirely (<italics><link><target>Dracula (1992 film)</target><part>Bram Stoker's Dracula</part></link></italics><space/>being a notable exception).</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Vampire literature</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Church of Saint Mary, Whitby</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of contemporary epistolary novels</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bloodline (Cary novel)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Book of Renfield</target></link>: A Gospel of Dracula</listitem><listitem><link><target>Clinical vampirism</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Dalby, Richard and Hughes, William.<space/><italics>Bram Stoker: A Bibliography</italics><space/>(Westcliff-on-Sea: Desert Island Books, 2005)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Christopher Frayling</target><part>Frayling, Christopher</part></link>.<space/><italics>Vampyres: Lord Byron to Count Dracula</italics><space/>(1992) ISBN 0-571-16792-6</listitem><listitem>Eighteen-Bisang, Robert and Miller, Elizabeth.<space/><italics>Bram Stoker's Notes for Dracula: A Facsimile Edition</italics><space/>Toronto: McFarland, 2008, ISBN 978-0-7864-3410-7</listitem><listitem>Hughes, William.<space/><italics>Beyond Dracula: Bram Stoker's Fiction and its Cultural Contexts</italics><space/>(Basingstoke: Macmillan, 2000)</listitem><listitem>McNally, Raymond T. &amp; Florescu, Radu.<space/><italics>In Search of Dracula</italics>. Houghton Mifflin Company, 1994. ISBN 0-395-65783-0</listitem><listitem>Miller, Elizabeth.<space/><italics>Dracula: Sense &amp; Nonsense</italics>. 2nd ed. Desert Island Books, 2006. ISBN 1-905328-15-X</listitem><listitem>Schaffer, Talia.<space/><italics>A Wilde Desire Took Me: the Homoerotic History of Dracula</italics>, in: ELH - Volume 61, Number 2 (1994), pp.&amp;nbsp;381425.</listitem><listitem>Senf, Carol.<space/><italics>Science and Social Science in Bram Stoker's Fiction</italics><space/>(Greenwood, 2002).</listitem><listitem>Senf, Carol.<space/><italics>Dracula: Between Tradition and Modernism</italics><space/>(Twayne, 1998).</listitem><listitem>Spencer, Kathleen.<space/><italics>Purity and Danger: Dracula, the Urban Gothic, and the Late Victorian Degeneracy Crisis</italics>, in: ELH - Volume 59, Number 1 (1992), pp.&amp;nbsp;197225.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leonard Wolf</target><part>Wolf, Leonard</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Essential Dracula</italics>. ibooks, inc., 2004. ISBN 0-7434-9803-8</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leslie S. Klinger</target><part>Klinger, Leslie S.</part></link><space/><italics>The New Annotated Dracula</italics>. W.W. Norton &amp; Co., 2008. ISBN 0-393-06450-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>Colin Waters.</target><part>Waters, Colin</part></link><space/><italics>Gothic Whitby</italics><space/>. History Press, 2009 - ISBN 0-7524-5291-6</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>gutenberg</target><arg name="no">345</arg><arg name="name">Dracula</arg></template>, text version of 1897 edition.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/E890000-001/'>''Dracula''</link><space/>from the<space/><link type='external' href='http://celt.ucc.e/'>CELT Project</link>, HTML version of 1897 edition.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucc.ie/celt/texts/xml/E890000-001.xml'>TEI/XML</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/draculabr00stokuoft'>''Dracula''</link>, New York: Grosset &amp; Dunlap, 1897. Scanned first edition from<space/><link><target>Internet Archive</target></link>.<space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>librivox book</target><arg name="title">Dracula<space/></arg><arg name="author">Bram Stoker</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/local/york/hi/people_and_places/arts_and_culture/newsid_8121000/8121579.stm'>Bram Stoker, Dracula and Whitby BBC article</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.themythoftransylvania.ro/'>''The Myth of Transylvania''</link>, Romanian Website dealing with the Dracula myth and the Western perception of Romania.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://dractravel.com/drc/'>''Journal of Dracula Studies''</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Dracula</target></template><template><target>Bram Stoker</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Dracula</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1897 novels</target></link><link><target>Category:British novels adapted into films</target></link><link><target>Category:Dracula in written fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:England in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:Epistolary novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Gothic novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Horror novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Hungary in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:Invasion literature</target></link><link><target>Category:Irish novels adapted into films</target></link><link><target>Category:Mind control in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:North Yorkshire</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels by Bram Stoker</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels set in London</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels set in Romania</target></link><link><target>Category:Romania in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:Transylvania in fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:Vampire novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Victorian novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Constable &amp; Co. books</target></link></paragraph></article>