<article title='Geography_of_Chad'><paragraph><link><target>File:Un-chad.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>550px</part><part>A map of Chad</part></link><link><target>File:LocationChad.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Location of Chad</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Chad</target></link></bold><space/>is one of the 48 land-locked countries in the world and is located in North Central<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link>, measuring<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1284000</arg><arg>km2</arg><arg>sqmi</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>, nearly twice the size of<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>and slightly more than three times the size of<space/><link><target>California</target></link>. Most of its ethnically and linguistically diverse population lives in the south, with densities ranging from 54 persons per square kilometer in the Logone River basin to 0.1 persons in the northern B.E.T. (Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti) desert region, which itself is larger than France. The capital city of<space/><link><target>N'Djamna</target></link>, situated at the confluence of the<space/><link><target>Chari River</target><part>Chari</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Logone River</target><trail>s</trail></link>, is cosmopolitan in nature, with a current population in excess of 700,000 people.</paragraph><paragraph>Chad has four bioclimatic zones. The northernmost<space/><link><target>Sahara</target><part>Saharan</part></link><space/>zone averages less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of rainfall annually. The sparse human population is largely nomadic, with some livestock, mostly small ruminants and camels. The central Sahelian zone receives between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>600</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>rainfall and has vegetation ranging from grass/shrub<space/><link><target>steppe</target></link><space/>to thorny, open savanna. The southern zone, often referred to as the Sudanian zone, receives between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>600</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>1000</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, with woodland<space/><link><target>savanna</target></link><space/>and deciduous forests for vegetation. Rainfall in the Guinea zone, located in Chad's southwestern tip, ranges between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1000</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>1200</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>The country's topography is generally flat, with the elevation gradually rising as one moves north and east away from<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link>. The highest point in Chad is<space/><link><target>Emi Koussi</target></link>, a mountain that rises<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3100</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in the northern<space/><link><target>Tibesti Mountains</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Ennedi Plateau</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Ouadda highlands</target></link><space/>in the east complete the image of a gradually sloping basin, which descends towards Lake Chad. There are also central highlands in the Guera region rising to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1500</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link><space/>is the second largest lake in west Africa and is one of the most important wetlands on the continent.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/6261447.stm'>BBC News - Lake Chad fishermen pack up their nets</link></extension><space/>Home to 120 species of fish and at least that many species of birds, the lake has shrunk dramatically in the last four decades due to increased water usage from an<space/><link><target>Human overpopulation</target><part>expanding population</part></link><space/>and low rainfall. Bordered by Chad,<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link>, Lake Chad currently covers only 1350 square kilometers, down from 25,000 square kilometers in 1963. The Chari and Logone Rivers, both of which originate in the Central African Republic and flow northward, provide most of the surface water entering Lake Chad.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Geographical setting</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chad sat.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>A satellite image of Chad.</part></link><link><target>File:Chad nasa satellite.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>A satellite image of Chad.</part></link><link><target>File:Chad Topography.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>A topographic map of Chad.</part></link>Located in north-central Africa, Chad stretches for about 1,800 kilometers from its northernmost point to its southern boundary. Except in the far northwest and south, where its borders converge, Chad's average width is about 800 kilometers. Its area of 1,284,000 square kilometers is roughly equal to the combined areas of<space/><link><target>Idaho</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wyoming</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Utah</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nevada</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Arizona</target></link>. Chad's neighbors include<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>to the north,<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>to the west,<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>to the east,<space/><link><target>Central African Republic</target></link><space/>to the south, and<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link><space/>to the southwest.</paragraph><paragraph>Chad exhibits two striking geographical characteristics. First, the country is landlocked.<space/><link><target>N'Djamena</target></link>, the capital, is located more than 1,100 kilometers northeast of the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target></link>;<space/><link><target>Abch</target></link>, a major city in the east, lies 2,650 kilometers from the<space/><link><target>Red Sea</target></link>; and<space/><link><target>Faya-Largeau</target></link>, a much smaller but strategically important center in the north, is in the middle of the<space/><link><target>Sahara Desert</target></link>, 1,550 kilometers from the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Sea</target></link>. These vast distances from the sea have had a profound impact on Chad's historical and contemporary development.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The second noteworthy characteristic is that the country borders on very different parts of the African continent:<space/><link><target>North Africa</target></link>, with its<space/><link><target>Islamic culture</target></link><space/>and economic orientation toward the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Basin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>West Africa</target></link>, with its diverse religions and cultures and its history of highly developed states and regional economies;<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Chad also borders<space/><link><target>Horn of Africa</target><part>Northeast Africa</part></link>, oriented toward the<space/><link><target>Nile</target><part>Nile Valley</part></link><space/>and the Red Sea region - and Central or Equatorial Africa, some of whose people have retained classical African religions while others have adopted<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>, and whose economies were part of the great<space/><link><target>Congo River</target></link><space/>system. Although much of Chad's distinctiveness comes from this diversity of influences, since independence the diversity has also been an obstacle to the creation of a national identity.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Land</heading><paragraph>Although Chadian society is economically, socially, and culturally fragmented, the country's geography is unified by the<space/><link><target>Lake Chad Basin</target></link>. Once a huge inland sea (the Pale-Chadian Sea) whose only remnant is shallow Lake Chad, this vast depression extends west into Nigeria and Niger. The larger, northern portion of the basin is bounded within Chad by the Tibesti Mountains in the northwest, the Ennedi Plateau in the northeast, the Ouadda Highlands in the east along the border with Sudan, the Gura Massif in central Chad, and the Mandara Mountains along Chad's southwestern border with Cameroon. The smaller, southern part of the basin falls almost exclusively in Chad. It is delimited in the north by the Gura Massif, in the south by highlands 250 kilometers south of the border with Central African Republic, and in the southwest by the Mandara Mountains.</paragraph><paragraph>Lake Chad, located in the southwestern part of the basin at an altitude of 282 meters, surprisingly does not mark the basin's lowest point; instead, this is found in the<space/><link><target>Bodele</target></link><space/>and Djourab regions in the north-central and northeastern parts of the country, respectively. This oddity arises because the great stationary dunes (ergs) of the Kanem region create a dam, preventing lake waters from flowing to the basin's lowest point. At various times in the past, and as late as the 1870s, the Bahr el Ghazal Depression, which extends from the northeastern part of the lake to the Djourab, acted as an overflow canal; since independence, climatic conditions have made overflows impossible.</paragraph><paragraph>North and northeast of Lake Chad, the basin extends for more than 800 kilometers, passing through regions characterized by great rolling dunes separated by very deep depressions. Although vegetation holds the dunes in place in the Kanem region, farther north they are bare and have a fluid, rippling character. From its low point in the Djourab, the basin then rises to the plateaus and peaks of the Tibesti Mountains in the north. The summit of this formationas well as the highest point in the Sahara Desertis Emi Koussi, a dormant volcano that reaches 3,414 meters above sea level.</paragraph><paragraph>The basin's northeastern limit is the Ennedi Plateau, whose limestone bed rises in steps etched by erosion. East of the lake, the basin rises gradually to the Ouadda Highlands, which mark Chad's eastern border and also divide the Chad and Nile watersheds. These highland areas are part of the<space/><link><target>East Saharan montane xeric woodlands</target></link><space/><link><target>ecoregion</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Southeast of Lake Chad, the regular contours of the terrain are broken by the Gura Massif, which divides the basin into its northern and southern parts. South of the lake lie the floodplains of the Chari and Logone rivers, much of which are inundated during the rainy season. Farther south, the basin floor slopes upward, forming a series of low sand and clay plateaus, called koros, which eventually climb to 615 meters above sea level. South of the Chadian border, the koros divide the Lake Chad Basin from the Ubangi-Zaire river system.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Water systems</heading><paragraph><template><target>See</target><arg>List of rivers of Chad</arg><arg>List of lakes of Chad</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Permanent streams do not exist in northern or central Chad. Following infrequent rains in the Ennedi Plateau and Ouadda Highlands, water may flow through depressions called enneris and wadis. Often the result of flash floods, such streams usually dry out within a few days as the remaining puddles seep into the sandy clay soil. The most important of these streams is the Batha, which in the rainy season carries water west from the Ouadda Highlands and the Gura Massif to Lake Fitri.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Chari River.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>240px</part><part>right</part><part>Chari River</part><trail>Chad</trail></link>'s major rivers are the<space/><link><target>Chari River</target><part>Chari</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Logone River</target><part>Logone</part></link><space/>and their tributaries, which flow from the southeast into Lake Chad. Both river systems rise in the highlands of Central African Republic and Cameroon, regions that receive more than 1,250 millimeters of rainfall annually. Fed by rivers of Central African Republic, as well as by the Bahr Salamat,<space/><link><target>Bahr Aouk</target></link>, and Bahr Sara rivers of southeastern Chad, the Chari River is about 1,200 kilometers long. From its origins near the city of Sarh, the middle course of the Chari makes its way through swampy terrain; the lower Chari is joined by the Logone River near N'Djamena. The Chari's volume varies greatly, from 17 cubic meters per second during the dry season to 340 cubic meters per second during the wettest part of the year.</paragraph><paragraph>The Logone River is formed by tributaries flowing from Cameroon and Central African Republic. Both shorter and smaller in volume than the Chari, it flows northeast for 960 kilometers; its volume ranges from five to eighty-five cubic meters per second. At N'Djamena the Logone empties into the Chari, and the combined rivers flow together for thirty kilometers through a large delta and into Lake Chad. At the end of the rainy season in the fall, the river overflows its banks and creates a huge floodplain in the delta.</paragraph><paragraph>The seventh largest lake in the world (and the fourth largest in Africa),<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link><space/>is located in the sahelian zone, a region just south of the Sahara Desert. The Chari River contributes 95 percent of Lake Chad's water, an average annual volume of 40 billion cubic meters, 95% of which is lost to evaporation. The size of the lake is determined by rains in the southern highlands bordering the basin and by temperatures in the Sahel. Fluctuations in both cause the lake to change dramatically in size, from 9,800 square kilometers in the dry season to 25,500 at the end of the rainy season.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Lake Chad also changes greatly in size from one year to another. In 1870 its maximum area was 28,000 square kilometers. The measurement dropped to 12,700 in 1908. In the 1940s and 1950s, the lake remained small, but it grew again to 26,000 square kilometers in 1963. The droughts of the late 1960s, early 1970s, and mid-1980s caused Lake Chad to shrink once again, however. The only other lakes of importance in Chad are Lake Fitri, in Batha Prefecture, and Lake Iro, in the marshy southeast.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Climate</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Chad#Climate</arg><arg name="l1">Climate</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The Lake Chad Basin embraces a great range of tropical climates from north to south, although most of these climates tend to be dry. Apart from the far north, most regions are characterized by a cycle of alternating rainy and dry seasons. In any given year, the duration of each season is determined largely by the positions of two great air massesa maritime mass over the Atlantic Ocean to the southwest and a much drier continental mass.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>During the rainy season, winds from the southwest push the moister maritime system north over the African continent where it meets and slips under the continental mass along a front called the &quot;intertropical convergence zone&quot;. At the height of the rainy season, the front may reach as far as Kanem Prefecture. By the middle of the dry season, the intertropical convergence zone moves south of Chad, taking the rain with it. This weather system contributes to the formation of three major regions of climate and vegetation.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Saharan region</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sand strom Chad.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>A sandstorm at Abch airport, Chad (2005).</part></link>The Saharan region covers roughly the northern half of the country, including Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti Prefecture along with the northern parts of Kanem, Batha, and Biltine prefectures. Much of this area receives only traces of rain during the entire year; at Faya Largeau, for example, annual rainfall averages less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>30</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>2</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>. Scattered small oases and occasional wells provide water for a few date palms or small plots of millet and garden crops.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In much of the north, the average daily maximum temperature is about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>32</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>during January, the coolest month of the year, and about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>45</arg><arg>°C</arg></template><space/>during May, the hottest month. On occasion, strong winds from the northeast produce violent sandstorms. In northern Biltine Prefecture, a region called the Mortcha plays a major role in animal husbandry. Dry for nine months of the year, it receives<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>350</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>or more of rain, mostly during July and August.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>A carpet of green springs from the desert during this brief wet season, attracting herders from throughout the region who come to pasture their cattle and camels. Because very few wells and springs have water throughout the year, the herders leave with the end of the rains, turning over the land to the antelopes, gazelles, and ostriches that can survive with little groundwater. Northern Chad averages over 3500 hours of sunlight per year, the south somewhat less.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sahelian region</heading><paragraph>The semiarid sahelian zone, or Sahel, forms a belt about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>500</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>wide that runs from Lac and Chari-Baguirmi prefectures eastward through Gura, Ouadda, and northern Salamat prefectures to the Sudanese frontier. The climate in this transition zone between the desert and the southern soudanian zone is divided into a rainy season (from June to early September) and a dry period (from October to May).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In the northern Sahel, thorny shrubs and acacia trees grow wild, while date palms, cereals, and garden crops are raised in scattered oases. Outside these settlements, nomads tend their flocks during the rainy season, moving southward as forage and surface water disappear with the onset of the dry part of the year. The central Sahel is characterized by drought-resistant grasses and small woods. Rainfall is more abundant there than in the Saharan region. For example, N'Djamena records a maximum annual average rainfall of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>580</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>, while Ouadda Prefecture receives just a bit less.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>During the hot season, in April and May, maximum temperatures frequently rise above<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>°C</arg></template>. In the southern part of the Sahel, rainfall is sufficient to permit crop production on unirrigated land, and millet and sorghum are grown. Agriculture is also common in the marshlands east of Lake Chad and near swamps or wells. Many farmers in the region combine subsistence agriculture with the raising of cattle, sheep, goats, and poultry.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Soudanian region</heading><paragraph>The humid<space/><italics>soudanian</italics><space/>zone includes the southern prefectures of Mayo-Kebbi, Tandjil, Logone Occidental, Logone Oriental, Moyen-Chari, and southern Salamat. Between April and October, the rainy season brings between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>750</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>1250</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>of precipitation. Temperatures are high throughout the year. Daytime readings in Moundou, the major city in the southwest, range from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>27</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>in the middle of the cool season in January to about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>°C</arg></template><space/>in the hot months of March, April, and May.</paragraph><paragraph>The soudanian region is predominantly<space/><link><target>East Sudanian savanna</target></link>, or plains covered with a mixture of tropical or subtropical grasses and woodlands. The growth is lush during the rainy season but turns brown and dormant during the five-month dry season between November and March. Over a large part of the region, however, natural vegetation has yielded to agriculture.</paragraph><heading level='3'>2010 drought</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>2010 Sahel drought</arg></template><space/>On 22 June, the temperature reached<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>47.6</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>°F</arg></template><space/>in Faya, breaking a record set in 1961 at the same location. Similar temperature rises were also reported in<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link>, which began to enter a famine situation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MastersNOAA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Masters</arg><arg name="first">Jeff</arg><arg name="title">NOAA: June 2010 the globe's 4th consecutive warmest month on record</arg><arg name="url">http://www.wunderground.com/blog/JeffMasters/comment.html?entrynum</arg><arg name="work">Weather Underground</arg><arg name="publisher">Jeff Masters' WunderBlog</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 July 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 26 July the heat reached near-record levels over<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wunderground.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wunderground.com/blog/JeffMasters/comment.html?entrynum</arg><arg name="title">Wunder Blog : Weather Underground<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wunderground.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-07-28</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Area</heading><paragraph><bold>Area:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>total:</italics>1.284 million km<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>land:</italics>1,259,200&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>water:</italics>24,800&amp;nbsp;km</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Area - comparative:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Canada: smaller than the<space/><link><target>Northwest Territories</target></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>US: slightly more than three times the size of<space/><link><target>California</target></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Boundaries</heading><paragraph><bold>Land boundaries:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>total:</italics>6,406&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>border countries:</italics><link><target>Cameroon</target></link><space/>1,116&amp;nbsp;km,<space/><link><target>Central African Republic</target></link><space/>1,556&amp;nbsp;km, Libya 1,050&amp;nbsp;km,<space/><link><target>Niger</target></link><space/>1,196&amp;nbsp;km,<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>85&amp;nbsp;km,<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>1,403&amp;nbsp;km</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Coastline:</bold>0&amp;nbsp;km (landlocked)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Maritime claims:</bold>none (landlocked)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Elevation extremes:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>lowest point:</italics><link><target>Djourab Depression</target></link><space/>160 m<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>''highest point:'<link><target>Emi Koussi</target></link><space/>3,415 m</paragraph><heading level='2'>Land use and resources</heading><paragraph><bold>Natural resources:</bold><link><target>petroleum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>uranium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>natron</target></link>,<space/><link><target>kaolin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>fish</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Chari River</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Logone River</target></link>),<space/><link><target>gold</target></link>,<space/><link><target>limestone</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sand</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gravel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>salt</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Land use:</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>arable land:</italics>3.89%<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>permanent crops:</italics>0.03%<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>other:</italics>96.08% (2012)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Irrigated land:</bold>302.7&amp;nbsp;km (2003)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Total renewable water resources:</bold>43&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup><space/>(2011)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Freshwater withdrawal (domestic/industrial/agricultural):</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>total:</italics>0.88 km<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup>/yr (12%/12%/76%)<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>per capita:</italics>84.81 m<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup>/yr (2005)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Environmental issues</heading><paragraph><bold>Natural hazards:</bold>hot, dry, dusty<space/><link><target>Harmattan</target></link><space/>winds occur in north; periodic droughts;<space/><link><target>locust</target></link><space/>plagues</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Environment - current issues:</bold>inadequate supplies of potable water; improper waste disposal in rural areas contributes to soil and<space/><link><target>water pollution</target></link>;<space/><link><target>desertification</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>Also see-<space/><link><target>2010 Sahel drought</target></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Extreme points</heading><paragraph>This is a list of the extreme points of<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link>, the points that are farther north, south, east or west than any other location.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Northernmost point - an unnamed location on the border with<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti Region</target><part>Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti region</part></link></listitem><listitem>Easternmost point - the northern section of the Chad-Sudan<space/><link><target>border</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti Region</target><part>Borkou-Ennedi-Tibesti region</part></link><space/>*</listitem><listitem>Southernmost point - unnamed location on the border with<space/><link><target>Central Africa Republic</target></link><space/>at a confluence in the<space/><link><target>Lb river</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Logone Oriental Region</target><part>Logone Oriental region</part></link></listitem><listitem>Westernmost point - unnamed location west of the town of<space/><link><target>Kanirom</target></link><space/>and immediately north of<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lac Region</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><italics>*Note: technically Chad does not have an easternmost point, the northern section of the border being formed by the 24 of longitude</italics></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>loc</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>CIA World Factbook</target></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>coord</target><arg>15</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>19</arg><arg>E</arg><arg name="display">inline,title</arg></template><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template><space/>Geo-links for Geography of Chad</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.izf.net/izf/documentation/cartes/Pays/supercartes/tchad.htm'>Detailed map of Chad from www.izf.net</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Chad topics</target></template><template><target>Geography of Africa</target></template><template><target>Africa topic</target><arg>Climate of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Chad</target></template><link><target>Category:Geography of Chad</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Geography of Central Africa</target><part>Chad</part></link></paragraph></article>