<article title='Bulletin_board_system'><paragraph>A<space/><bold>bulletin board system</bold>, or<space/><bold>BBS</bold>, is a<space/><link><target>host (network)</target><part>computer server</part></link><space/>running<space/><link><target>list of BBS software</target><part>custom software</part></link><space/>that allows users to connect to the system using a<space/><link><target>terminal program</target></link>. Once logged in, the user can perform functions such as<space/><link><target>upload</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>download</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>software and data, reading news and bulletins, and exchanging messages with other users through<space/><link><target>email</target></link>, public<space/><link><target>Internet forum</target><part>message boards</part></link>, and sometimes via direct<space/><link><target>synchronous conferencing</target><part>chatting</part></link>. Many BBSes also offer<space/><link><target>BBS door</target><part>on-line games</part></link>, in which users can compete with each other, and BBSes with multiple phone lines often provide<space/><link><target>chat room</target><trail>s</trail></link>, allowing users to interact with each other. Bulletin board systems were in many ways a precursor to the modern form of the<space/><link><target>World Wide Web</target></link>,<space/><link><target>social network service</target><part>social networks</part></link><space/>and other aspects of the<space/><link><target>Internet</target></link>. Low-cost, high-performance modems drove online use through the early 1990s, both<space/><link><target>online service</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and BBSes.<space/><italics><link><target>Infoworld</target></link></italics><space/>estimated there were 60,000 BBS systems serving 17 million users in the US alone in 1994, a collective market much larger than the major online services like<space/><link><target>CompuServe</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The introduction of inexpensive<space/><link><target>Dial-up Internet access</target><part>dial-up internet service</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Mosaic (web browser)</target><part>Mosaic web browser</part></link><space/>offered ease-of use and global access that BBS and online systems did not provide, and led to a rapid crash in the market starting in 1994. Over the next year, many of the<space/><link><target>List of BBS software</target><part>leading BBS software providers</part></link><space/>went<space/><link><target>bankrupt</target></link><space/>and tens of thousands of BBSes disappeared. Today, BBSing survives largely as a nostalgic hobby in most parts of the world, but it is still an extremely popular form of communication for Taiwanese youth (see<space/><link><target>PTT Bulletin Board System</target></link>) and in China.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://thinkingchinese.com/chinese-bbs-the-social-activity-that-never-grows-old</extension><space/>Most BBSes are now accessible over<space/><link><target>Telnet</target></link><space/>and typically offer free email accounts, FTP services,<space/><link><target>Internet Relay Chat</target><part>IRC</part></link><space/>and all of the<space/><link><target>Communications protocol</target><part>protocols</part></link><space/>commonly used on the Internet. Some offer access through<space/><link><target>packet switched network</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or<space/><link><target>packet radio</target></link><space/>connections.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Precursors</heading><paragraph>A precursor to the public bulletin board system was<space/><link><target>Community Memory</target></link>, started in August 1973 in<space/><link><target>Berkeley, California</target></link>. Useful<space/><link><target>microcomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>did not exist at that time, and modems were both expensive and slow. Community Memory therefore ran on a<space/><link><target>mainframe computer</target></link><space/>and was accessed through terminals located in several<space/><link><target>San Francisco Bay Area</target></link><space/>neighborhoods.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Crosby</arg><arg name="first">Kip</arg><arg name="date">November 1995</arg><arg name="title">Convivial Cybernetic Devices</arg><arg name="journal">The Analytical Engine</arg><arg name="publisher">Computer History Association of California</arg><arg name="volume">3</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="issn">1071-6351</arg><arg name="url">http://www.opencollector.org/history/homebrew/engv3n1.html</arg></template></extension><space/>The poor quality of the original modem connecting the terminals to the mainframe prompted a user to invent the<space/><link><target>Pennywhistle modem</target></link>, whose design was highly influential in the mid-1970s.</paragraph><paragraph>Community Memory allowed the user to type messages into a<space/><link><target>computer terminal</target></link><space/>after inserting a coin, and offered a &quot;pure&quot; bulletin board experience with public messages only (no email or other features). It did offer the ability to tag messages with keywords, which the user could use in searches. The system acted primarily in the form of a buy and sell system with the tags taking the place of the more traditional<space/><link><target>Classified advertising</target><part>classifications</part></link>. But users found ways to express themselves outside these bounds, and the system spontaneously created stories, poetry and other forms of communications. Unfortunately, the system was expensive to operate, and when their host machine became unavailable and a new one could not be found, the system closed in January 1975.</paragraph><paragraph>Similar functionality was available to most mainframe users, which might be considered a sort of ultra-local BBS when used in this fashion. Commercial systems, expressly intended to offer these features to the public, became available in the late 1970s and formed the<space/><link><target>online service</target></link><space/>market that lasted into the 1990s. One particularly influential example was<space/><link><target>PLATO (computer system)</target><part>PLATO</part></link>, which had thousands of users by the late 1970s, many of whom used the messaging and<space/><link><target>chat room</target></link><space/>features of the system in the same way that would become common on BBSes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The first BBSes</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Ward Christensen and the First BBS.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part>Ward Christensen holds an expansion card from the original CBBS S-100 host machine.</part></link>Early modems were generally very simple devices using<space/><link><target>acoustic coupler</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to handle telephone operation. The user would first pick up the phone, dial a number, then press the handset into rubber cups on the top of the modem. Disconnecting at the end of a call required the user to pick up the handset and return it to the phone. Examples of direct-connecting modems did exist, and these often allowed the host computer to send it commands to answer or hang up calls, but these were very expensive devices used by large banks and similar companies.</paragraph><paragraph>With the introduction of<space/><link><target>microcomputer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with expansion slots, like the<space/><link><target>S-100 bus</target></link><space/>machines and<space/><link><target>Apple II</target></link>, it became possible for the modem to communicate instructions and data on separate lines. A number of modems of this sort were available by the late 1970s. This made the BBS possible for the first time, as it allowed software on the computer to pick up an incoming call, communicate with the user, and then hang up the call when the user logged off.</paragraph><paragraph>The first public<space/><link><target>dial-up</target></link><space/>BBS was developed by<space/><link><target>Ward Christensen</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Randy Suess</target></link>. According to an early interview, when Chicago was snowed under during the<space/><link><target>Great Blizzard of 1978</target></link>, the two began preliminary work on the<space/><link><target>Computerized Bulletin Board System</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>CBBS</target></link>. The system came into existence largely through a fortuitous combination of Christensen having a spare S-100 bus computer and an early Hayes internal modem, and Suess's insistence that the machine be placed at his house in<space/><link><target>Chicago</target></link><space/>where it would be a local phone call to millions of users. Christensen patterned the system after the<space/><link><target>cork board</target></link><space/>his local computer club used to post information like &quot;need a ride&quot;. CBBS officially went online on 16 February 1978.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ward"><link type='external' href='http://www.bbsdocumentary.com/software/AAA/AAA/CBBS/memories.txt'>Collection of Memories of writing and running the first BBS by Ward Christensen (Circa 1992)</link>,<space/><italics>BBSDocumentary.com</italics>, retrieved June 30, 2007</extension><space/>CBBS, which kept a count of callers, reportedly connected 253,301 callers before it was finally retired.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Smartmodem</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hayes 300 Baud Smartmodem 02.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part>The 300 baud Smartmodem led to an initial wave of early BBS systems.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A key innovation required for the popularization of the BBS was the<space/><link><target>Hayes Microcomputer Products#The Smartmodem</target><part>Hayes Smartmodem</part></link>. Internal modems like the ones used by CBBS and similar early systems were usable, but generally expensive due to the manufacturer having to make a different modem for every computer platform they wanted to target. They were also limited to those computers with internal expansion, and could not be used with other useful platforms like<space/><link><target>video terminal</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Hayes' solution to the problem was to use a small<space/><link><target>microcontroller</target></link><space/>to implement a system that examined the data flowing into the modem from the host computer, watching for certain command strings. This allowed commands to be sent to and from the modem using the same data pins as all the rest of the data, meaning it would work on any system that could support even the most basic modems. The Smartmodem could pick up the phone, dial numbers, and hang up again, all without any operator intervention. The Smartmodem was not necessary for BBS use, but made overall operation dramatically simpler. It also improved usability for the caller, as most terminal software allowed different phone numbers to be stored and dialled on command, allowing the user to easily connect to a series of systems.</paragraph><paragraph>The introduction of the Smartmodem led to the first real wave of BBS systems. Limited in both speed and storage capacity, these systems were normally dedicated solely to messaging, both private email and public &quot;forums&quot;. File transfers were painfully slow at these speeds, and file libraries were typically limited to text files containing lists of other BBS systems. These systems attracted a particular type of user who used the BBS as a unique type of communications medium, and when these local systems were crowded from the market in the 1990s, their loss was lamented for many years.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Higher speeds, commercialization</heading><paragraph>Speed improved with the introduction of 1200<space/><link><target>Bits per second</target><part>bit/s</part></link><space/>modems in the<space/><link><target>Modem#Increasing speeds</target><part>early 1980s</part></link>, giving way to 2400 bit/s fairly rapidly. The improved performance led to a substantial increase in BBS popularity. Most of the information was displayed using ordinary<space/><link><target>ASCII</target></link><space/>text or<space/><link><target>ANSI art</target></link>, but a number of systems attempted character-based<space/><link><target>graphical user interface</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which began to be practical at 2400 bit/s.</paragraph><paragraph>There was a lengthy delay before 2400 bit/s gave way and 9600&amp;nbsp;bit/s models began to appear on the market. 9600&amp;nbsp;bit/s was not even established as a strong standard before<space/><link><target>V.32bis</target></link><space/>at 14.4&amp;nbsp;kbit/s took over in the early 1990s. This period also saw the rapid rise in capacity and dramatic drop in price of<space/><link><target>hard drive</target><trail>s</trail></link>. By the late 1980s most BBS systems had relatively significant file libraries, and this gave rise to the &quot;leech&quot;, users who called BBSes solely for their files. These users would tie up the modem for some time, leaving less time for other users, crowding them out. The resulting upheaval eliminated many of the pioneering message-centric systems.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.oldgamemags.com/multi-format/non-gaming-magazines/chips-bits/'>&quot;File Sponges, the BBS nightmare&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Chips 'n Bits</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>This also gave rise to a new class of BBS systems, dedicated solely to file downloads, often a euphemism for pornographic images in<space/><link><target>GIF</target></link><space/>format. These systems charged for access, typically a flat monthly fee, compared to the per-hour fees charged by most online services. A host of 3rd party services sprang up to support these systems, offering simple credit card<space/><link><target>merchant account</target></link><space/>gateways for the payment of monthly fees, and entire file libraries on<space/><link><target>compact disk</target></link><space/>that made initial setup very easy. Early 1990s editions of<space/><italics>Boardwatch</italics><space/>were filled with ads for single-click install solutions dedicated to these new sysops. While this gave the market a bad reputation, it also led to its greatest success; during the early 1990s there were a number of mid-sized software companies dedicated to BBS software, and the number of BBSes in service reached its peak.</paragraph><paragraph>Towards the early 1990s, the BBS industry became so popular that it spawned three monthly magazines,<space/><italics><link><target>Boardwatch</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>BBS Magazine</target></link></italics>, and in Asia and Australia,<space/><italics><link><target>Chips 'n Bits Magazine</target></link></italics><space/>which devoted extensive coverage of the software and technology innovations and people behind them, and listings to US and worldwide BBSes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ChipsnBits"><link type='external' href='http://catalogue.nla.gov.au/Record/54469'>Chips 'n' Bits : the Northern Territory Computer Users' newsletter</link>,<space/><italics>catalogue.nla.gov.au</italics>, retrieved March 15, 2009</extension><space/>In addition, in the USA, a major monthly magazine,<space/><italics><link><target>Computer Shopper (US magazine)</target><part>Computer Shopper</part></link></italics>, carried a list of BBSes along with a brief abstract of each of their offerings.</paragraph><heading level='3'>GUIs</heading><paragraph>Through the late 1980s and early 1990s there was considerable experimentation with ways to improve the BBS experience from its<space/><link><target>command line interface</target></link><space/>roots. Almost every popular system improved matters somewhat by adding ANSI-based color menus to make reading easier, and most also allowed cursor commands to offer command-line recall and similar features. Another common feature was the use of<space/><link><target>autocomplete</target></link><space/>to make menu navigation simpler, a feature that would not re-appear on the web until decades later.</paragraph><paragraph>A number of systems also made forays into GUI-based interfaces, either using character graphics sent from the host, or using custom GUI-based terminal systems. The later initially appeared, unsurprisingly, on the<space/><link><target>Macintosh</target></link><space/>platform, where<space/><link><target>TeleFinder</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>FirstClass</target></link><space/>became very popular. FirstClass offered a host of features that would be difficult or impossible under a terminal-based solution, including bi-directional information flow and non-blocking operation that allowed the user to exchange files in both directions while continuing to use the message system and chat, all in separate windows.</paragraph><paragraph>On the PC, efforts were more oriented to extensions of the original terminal concept, with the GUI being described in the information on the host. One example was the<space/><link><target>Remote Imaging Protocol</target></link>, essentially a picture description system, which remained relatively obscure. Probably the ultimate development of this style of operation was the dynamic page implementation of the<space/><link><target>University of Southern California</target></link><space/>BBS (USCBBS) by Susan Biddlecomb, which predated the implementation of the<space/><link><target>HTML</target></link><space/><link><target>Dynamic web page</target></link>. A complete Dynamic web page implementation was accomplished using<space/><link><target>The Bread Board System</target><part>TBBS</part></link><space/>with a<space/><link><target>TDBS</target></link><space/>add-on presenting a complete menu system individually customized for each user.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Rise of the Internet and decline of BBS</heading><paragraph>The demand for complex ANSI and ASCII screens and larger file transfers taxed available<space/><link><target>channel capacity</target></link>, which in turn propelled demand for faster modems. 14.4 kbit/s modems were standard for a number of years while various companies attempted to introduce non-standard systems with higher performance, normally about 19.2 kbit/s. Another delay followed due to a long<space/><link><target>List of ITU-T V-Series Recommendations</target><part>V.34</part></link><space/>standards process before 28.8&amp;nbsp;kbit/s was released, only to be quickly replaced by 33.6&amp;nbsp;kbit/s, and then 56&amp;nbsp;kbit/s.</paragraph><paragraph>These increasing speeds had the side effect of dramatically reducing the noticeable effects of channel efficiency. When modems were slow, considerable effort was put into developing the most efficient protocols and display systems possible. Running a general-purpose protocol like<space/><link><target>TCP/IP</target></link><space/>over a 1200 bit/s modem was a painful experience. With<space/><link><target>56 kbit/s modem</target><trail>s</trail></link>, however, the overhead was so greatly reduced as to be unnoticeable. Dial-up internet service became widely available in 1994, and a must-have option for any general-use<space/><link><target>operating system</target></link><space/>by 1995.</paragraph><paragraph>What resulted was a<space/><link><target>perfect storm</target></link><space/>that almost completely destroyed the BBS market through 1995. Technically, internet service offered an enormous advantage over BBS systems, as a single connection to the user's<space/><link><target>internet service provider</target></link><space/>allowed them to contact services around the world. In comparison, BBS systems relied on a direct point-to-point connection, so even dialing multiple local systems required multiple phone calls. Moreover, internet protocols allowed that same single connection to be used to contact multiple services at the same time, say download files from an<space/><link><target>ftp</target></link><space/>library while checking the weather on a local news web site. In comparison, a connection to a BBS allowed access only to the information on that system.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Estimating numbers</heading><paragraph>According to the<space/><link><target>FidoNet</target></link><space/>Nodelist, BBSes reached their peak usage around 1996, which was the same period that the<space/><link><target>World Wide Web</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>AOL</target></link><space/>suddenly became mainstream. BBSes rapidly declined in popularity thereafter, and were replaced by systems using the internet for connectivity. Some of the larger commercial BBSes, such as MaxMegabyte and<space/><link><target>ExecPC BBS</target></link>, evolved into<space/><link><target>Internet Service Providers</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The website<space/><italics><link><target>textfiles.com</target></link></italics><space/>serves as an archive that documents the history of the BBS. The<space/><link type='external' href='http://bbslist.textfiles.com/'>historical BBS list</link><space/>on<space/><italics>textfiles.com</italics><space/>contains over 105,000 BBSes that have existed over a span of 20 years in North America alone. The owner of<space/><italics>textfiles.com</italics>,<space/><link><target>Jason Scott Sadofsky</target><part>Jason Scott</part></link>, also produced<space/><italics><link><target>BBS: The Documentary</target></link></italics>, a<space/><link><target>DVD</target></link><space/>film that chronicles the history of the BBS and features interviews with well-known people (mostly from the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>) from the heyday BBS era.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Software and hardware</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Amiga3000UX.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Amiga 3000 running a two-line BBS</part></link>Unlike modern websites and<space/><link><target>online services</target></link><space/>that are typically hosted by third-party companies in commercial<space/><link><target>data center</target><trail>s</trail></link>, BBS computers (especially for smaller boards) were typically operated from the SysOp's home. As such, access could be unreliable, and in many cases only one user could be on the system at a time. Only larger BBSes with multiple phone lines using specialized hardware, multitasking software, or a<space/><link><target>LAN</target></link><space/>connecting multiple computers, could host multiple simultaneous users.</paragraph><paragraph>The first BBSes used homebrew software,<extension extension_name='ref' group="nb">CBBS Chicago (which<space/><link><target>Ward Christensen</target></link><space/>programmed) was about 20,000 lines of 8080 assembler.</extension><space/>quite often written or customized by the SysOps themselves, running on early<space/><link><target>S-100 bus</target></link><space/><link><target>microcomputer</target></link><space/>systems such as the<space/><link><target>Altair 8800</target></link>,<space/><link><target>IMSAI 8080</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cromemco</target></link><space/>under the<space/><link><target>CP/M</target></link><space/>operating system. Soon after, BBS software was being written for all of the major<space/><link><target>home computer</target></link><space/>systems of the late 1970s era - the<space/><link><target>Apple II</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Atari 8-bit family</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Commodore International</target><part>Commodore</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>TRS-80</target></link><space/>being some of the most popular.</paragraph><paragraph>A few years later, in 1981, IBM introduced the first<space/><link><target>DOS</target></link><space/>based<space/><link><target>IBM personal computer</target><part>IBM PC</part></link>, and due to the overwhelming popularity of PCs and their<space/><link><target>IBM PC Compatible</target><part>clones</part></link>, DOS soon became the operating system on which the majority of BBS programs were run.<space/><link><target>RBBS-PC</target></link>,<space/><link><target>porting</target><part>ported</part></link><space/>over from the CP/M world, and<space/><italics>Fido</italics><space/>BBS, created by<space/><link><target>Tom Jennings</target></link><space/>(who later founded<space/><link><target>FidoNet</target></link>) were the first notable DOS BBS programs. Many successful commercial BBS programs were developed for DOS, such as<space/><link><target>PCBoard</target></link><space/>BBS,<space/><link><target>RemoteAccess</target></link><space/>BBS, and<space/><link><target>Wildcat! BBS</target></link>. Some popular<space/><link><target>freeware</target></link><space/>BBS programs for DOS included<space/><link><target>Telegard</target></link><space/>BBS and<space/><link><target>Renegade (BBS)</target><part>Renegade BBS</part></link>, which both had early origins from leaked<space/><link><target>WWIV</target></link><space/>BBS source code. There were several dozen other BBS programs developed over the DOS era, and many were released under the<space/><link><target>shareware</target></link><space/>concept, while some were released as<space/><link><target>freeware</target></link><space/>including iniquity.</paragraph><paragraph>BBS systems on other systems remained popular, especially<space/><link><target>home computer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, largely because they catered to the audience of users running those machines. The ubiquitous<space/><link><target>Commodore 64</target></link><space/>(introduced in 1982) was a common platform in the 1980s. Popular commercial BBS programs were<space/><link><target>Blue Board (software)</target><part>Blue Board</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Ivory BBS</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Color64</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>C-Net DS2</target><part>CNet 64</part></link>. In the early 1990s a small number of BBSes were also running on the Commodore<space/><link><target>Amiga</target></link>. Popular BBS software for the Amiga were ABBS,<space/><link><target>Amiexpress</target></link>, C-Net, StormforceBBS,<space/><link><target>Infinity (software)</target><part>Infinity</part></link><space/>and Tempest. There was also a small faction of devoted Atari BBSes that used the<space/><link><target>Atari 8-bit family</target><part>Atari 800</part></link>, then the 800XL, and eventually the 1040ST. The earlier machines generally lacked<space/><link><target>hard drive</target></link><space/>capabilities, which limited them primarily to messaging.</paragraph><paragraph>MS-DOS continued to be the most popular operating system for BBS use up until the mid-1990s, and in the early years most multi-node BBSes were running under a DOS based multitasker such as<space/><link><target>DESQview</target></link><space/>or consisted of multiple computers connected via a<space/><link><target>LAN</target></link>. In the late 1980s, a handful of BBS developers implemented multitasking communications routines inside their software, allowing multiple phone lines and users to connect to the same BBS computer. These included Galacticomm's<space/><link><target>MajorBBS</target></link><space/>(later WorldGroup), eSoft<space/><link><target>The Bread Board System</target></link><space/>(TBBS), and<space/><link><target>Falken</target></link>. Though most BBS software had been written in<space/><link><target>BASIC</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Pascal (programming language)</target><part>Pascal</part></link><space/>(with some low-level routines written in<space/><link><target>assembly language</target></link>), the<space/><link><target>C (language)</target><part>C</part></link><space/>language was starting to gain popularity.</paragraph><paragraph>By 1995, many of the DOS-based BBSes had begun switching to modern<space/><link><target>Computer multitasking</target><part>multitasking</part></link><space/>operating systems, such as<space/><link><target>OS/2</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Windows 95</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Linux</target></link>. TCP/IP networking allowed most of the remaining BBSes to evolve and include Internet hosting capabilities. Recent BBS software, such as<space/><link><target>Synchronet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mystic BBS</target></link>, EleBBS,<space/><link><target>Dave's own version of Citadel</target><part>DOC</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Wildcat! BBS</target></link><space/>provide access using the<space/><link><target>Telnet</target></link><space/>protocol rather than dialup, or by using legacy DOS based BBS software with a<space/><link><target>FOSSIL</target></link>-to-Telnet redirector such as<space/><link><target>NetFoss</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Presentation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Neon2.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Welcome screen of Neon#2 BBS (Tornado)</part></link>BBSes were generally text-based, rather than<space/><link><target>Graphical User Interface</target><part>GUI</part></link>-based, and early BBSes conversed using the simple<space/><link><target>ASCII</target></link><space/>character set. However, some home computer manufacturers extended the ASCII character set to take advantage of the advanced color and graphics capabilities of their systems. BBS software authors included these extended character sets in their software, and terminal program authors included the ability to display them when a compatible system was called. Atari's native character set was known as<space/><link><target>ATASCII</target></link>, while most Commodore BBSes supported<space/><link><target>PETSCII</target></link>. PETSCII was also supported by the nationwide online service<space/><link><target>Quantum Link</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' group="nb">Quantum Link and parts of<space/><link><target>AppleLink</target></link><space/>went on to become<space/><link><target>America Online</target></link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The use of these custom character sets was generally incompatible between manufacturers. Unless a caller was using terminal emulation software written for, and running on, the same type of system as the BBS, the session would simply fall back to simple ASCII output. For example, a Commodore 64 user calling an Atari BBS would use ASCII rather than the machine's native character set. As time progressed, most terminal programs began using the<space/><link><target>ANSI X3.64</target><part>ANSI</part></link><space/>standard, but could use their native character set if it was available.</paragraph><paragraph>COCONET, a BBS system made by Coconut Computing, Inc., was released in 1988 and only supported a GUI (no text interface was initially available but eventually became available around 1990), and worked in EGA/VGA graphics mode, which made it stand out from the text-based BBS systems. COCONET's bitmap and vector graphics and support for multiple type fonts were inspired by the<space/><link><target>PLATO system</target></link>, and the graphics capabilities were based on what was available in the Borland BGI graphics library. A competing approach called<space/><link><target>Remote Imaging Protocol</target></link><space/>(RIP) emerged and was promoted by Telegrafix in the early to mid-1990s but it never became widespread. An industry standard technology called<space/><link><target>NAPLPS</target></link><space/>was also considered, and although it became the underlying graphics technology behind the<space/><link><target>Prodigy (online service)</target><part>Prodigy service</part></link>, it never gained popularity in the BBS market. There were several GUI-based BBSes on the<space/><link><target>Apple Macintosh</target></link><space/>platform, including<space/><link><target>TeleFinder</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>FirstClass</target></link>, but these remained widely used only in the Mac market.</paragraph><paragraph>In the UK, the<space/><link><target>BBC Micro</target></link><space/>based OBBS software, available from<space/><link><target>Pace Micro Technology</target><part>Pace</part></link><space/>for use with their modems, optionally allowed for color and graphics using the<space/><link><target>Teletext</target></link><space/>based graphics mode available on that platform. Other systems used the<space/><link><target>Viewdata</target></link><space/>protocols made popular in the UK by<space/><link><target>British Telecom</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Prestel</target></link><space/>service, and the on-line magazine<space/><link><target>Micronet800</target><part>Micronet 800</part></link><space/>whom were busy giving away modems with their subscriptions.</paragraph><paragraph>The most popular form of online graphics was<space/><link><target>ANSI art</target></link>, which combined the<space/><link><target>Extended ASCII</target><part>IBM Extended ASCII</part></link><space/>character set's blocks and symbols with<space/><link><target>ANSI X3.64</target><part>ANSI</part></link><space/><link><target>escape sequence</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to allow changing colors on demand, provide cursor control and screen formatting, and even basic musical tones. During the late 1980s and early 1990s, most BBSes used ANSI to make elaborate welcome screens, and colorized menus, and thus, ANSI support was a sought-after feature in terminal client programs. The development of ANSI art became so popular that it spawned an entire BBS &quot;<link><target>artscene</target></link>&quot;<space/><link><target>subculture</target></link><space/>devoted to it.<link><target>File:Koala Country BBS Login Screen.jpg</target><part>400px</part><part>thumb</part><part>BBS ANSI Login Screen example</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Amiga</target></link><space/><italics>Skyline BBS</italics><space/>software was the first in 1987 featuring a script<space/><link><target>markup language</target></link><space/>communication protocol called<space/><link><target>Skypix</target></link><space/>which was capable of giving the user a complete graphical interface, featuring rich graphic content, changeable fonts, mouse-controlled actions, animations and sound.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Skyline"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>BBSDocumentary, An Overview of BBS Programs<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bbsdocumentary.com/software/expanded.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Jason Scott Sadofsky|Jason Scott]] for [[Wired (magazine)|Wired]] Magazine (?)<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Scott Lee<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2005</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Today, most BBS software that is still actively supported, such as Worldgroup,<space/><link><target>Wildcat! BBS</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Citadel/UX</target></link>, is Web-enabled, and the traditional text interface has been replaced (or operates concurrently) with a Web-based user interface. For those more nostalgic for the true BBS experience, one can use NetSerial (Windows) or<space/><link><target>DOSBox</target></link><space/>(Windows/*nix) to redirect DOS COM port software to telnet, allowing them to connect to Telnet BBSes using 1980s and 1990s era modem<space/><link><target>terminal emulator</target><part>terminal emulation</part></link><space/>software, like<space/><link><target>Telix</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Terminate (software)</target><part>Terminate</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Qmodem</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Procomm Plus</target></link>. Modern 32-bit terminal emulators such as mTelnet and<space/><link><target>Synchronet#SyncTerm</target><part>SyncTerm</part></link><space/>include native telnet support.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Content and access</heading><paragraph>Since most early BBSes were run by computer hobbyists, they were typically technical in topic, with user communities revolving around hardware and software discussions.</paragraph><paragraph>As the BBS phenomenon grew, so did the popularity of special interest boards. Bulletin Board Systems could be found for almost every hobby and interest. Popular interests included politics, religion, music,<space/><link><target>matchmaker.com</target><part>dating</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>alternative lifestyle</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Many SysOps also adopted a<space/><link><target>Theme (computing)</target><part>theme</part></link><space/>in which they customized their entire BBS (welcome screens, prompts, menus, and so on) to reflect that theme. Common themes were based on<space/><link><target>fantasy</target></link>, or were intended to give the user the illusion of being somewhere else, such as in a<space/><link><target>sanatorium</target></link>, wizard's castle, or on a<space/><link><target>pirate ship</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the early days, the file download library consisted of files that the SysOps obtained themselves from other BBSes and friends. Many BBSes inspected every file uploaded to their public file download library to ensure that the material did not violate copyright law. As time went on,<space/><link><target>shareware</target></link><space/>CD-ROMs were sold with up to thousands of files on each<space/><link><target>CD-ROM</target></link>. Small BBSes copied each file individually to their hard drive. Some systems used a CD-ROM drive to make the files available. Advanced BBSes used Multiple CD-ROM disc changer units that switched 6 CD-ROM disks on demand for the caller(s). Large systems used all 26 DOS drive letters with multi-disk changers housing tens of thousands of copyright-free shareware or freeware files available to all callers. These BBSes were generally more family friendly, avoiding the seedier side of BBSes. Access to these systems varied from single to multiple modem lines with some requiring little or no confirmed registration.</paragraph><paragraph>Some BBSes, called elite, WaReZ or pirate boards, were exclusively used for distributing<space/><link><target>pirated software</target></link>,<space/><link><target>phreaking</target></link>, and other questionable or unlawful content. These BBSes often had multiple modems and phone lines, allowing several users to upload and download files at once. Most elite BBSes used some form of new user verification, where new users would have to apply for membership and attempt to prove that they were not a law enforcement officer or a<space/><italics><link><target>lamer</target></link>.</italics><space/>The largest elite boards accepted users by invitation only. Elite boards also spawned their own subculture and gave rise to the<space/><link><target>slang</target></link><space/>known today as<space/><link><target>leet</target><trail>speak</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Another common type of board was the &quot;support BBS&quot; run by a manufacturer of computer products or software. These boards were dedicated to supporting users of the company's products with question and answer forums, news and updates, and downloads. Most of them were not a free call. Today, these services have moved to the web.</paragraph><paragraph>Some general purpose Bulletin Board Systems had special levels of access that were given to those who paid extra money, uploaded useful files or knew the SysOp personally. These specialty and pay BBSes usually had something special to offer their users such as large file libraries,<space/><link><target>warez</target></link>,<space/><link><target>pornography</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chat room</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Internet</target></link><space/>access.</paragraph><paragraph>Pay BBSes such as The<space/><link><target>WELL (virtual community)</target><part>WELL</part></link><space/>and Echo NYC (now Internet forums rather than dial-up),<space/><link><target>ExecPC BBS</target><part>ExecPC</part></link>, PsudNetwork and<space/><link><target>MindVox</target></link><space/>(which folded in 1996) were admired for their tight-knit communities and quality discussion forums. However, many &quot;free&quot; BBSes also maintained close knit communities, and some even had annual or bi-annual events where users would travel great distances to meet face-to-face with their on-line friends. These events were especially popular with BBSes that offered<space/><link><target>chat room</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of the BBSes that provided access to illegal content did wind up in trouble. On July 12, 1985, in conjunction with a<space/><link><target>credit card fraud</target></link><space/>investigation, the<space/><link><target>Middlesex County, New Jersey</target><part>Middlesex County, NJ</part></link><space/>Sheriff's department raided and seized The Private Sector BBS, which was the official BBS for<space/><link><target>grey hat</target></link><space/>hacker quarterly<space/><link><target>2600 Magazine</target></link><space/>at the time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Psector"><link type='external' href='http://thegreatgeekmanual.com/blog/this-day-in-geek-history-july-12'>This Day in Geek History: July12</link>,<space/><italics>thegreatgeekmanual.com</italics>, retrieved March 26, 2009</extension><space/>The notorious<space/><link><target>Rusty n Edie's BBS</target></link>, in<space/><link><target>Boardman, Ohio</target></link>, was raided by the FBI in January 1993 for software piracy, and later sued by<space/><link><target>Playboy</target></link><space/>for copyright infringement in November 1997. In<space/><link><target>Flint, Michigan</target></link>, a 21-year-old man was charged with distributing<space/><link><target>child pornography</target></link><space/>through his BBS in March 1996.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flintj"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Man Says Kiddie Porno Made Computer Site Popular</arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Flint Journal]]</arg><arg name="date">1996-03-20</arg><arg name="author">Doran, Tim</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Networks</heading><paragraph>Most early BBSes operated as individual systems. Information contained on that BBS never left the system, and users would only interact with the information and user community on that BBS alone. However, as BBSes became more widespread, there evolved a desire to connect systems together to share messages and files with distant systems and users. The largest such network was<space/><link><target>FidoNet</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>As is it was prohibitively expensive for the hobbyist SysOp to have a dedicated connection to another system, FidoNet was developed as a<space/><link><target>store and forward</target></link><space/>network. Private email (Netmail), public message boards (Echomail) and eventually even file attachments on a FidoNet-capable BBS would be bundled into one or more archive files over a set time interval. These archive files were then compressed with<space/><link><target>ARC (file format)</target><part>ARC</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>ZIP (file format)</target><part>ZIP</part></link><space/>and forwarded to (or polled by) another nearby node or hub via a dialup<space/><link><target>Xmodem</target></link><space/>session. Messages would be relayed around various FidoNet hubs until they were eventually delivered to their destination. The hierarchy of FidoNet BBS nodes, hubs, and zones was maintained in a routing table called a Nodelist. Some larger BBSes or regional FidoNet hubs would make several transfers per day, some even to multiple nodes or hubs, and as such, transfers usually occurred at night or early morning when toll rates were lowest. In Fido's heyday, sending a Netmail message to a user on a distant FidoNet node, or participating in an Echomail discussion could take days, especially if any FidoNet nodes or hubs in the message's route only made one transfer call per day.</paragraph><paragraph>FidoNet was platform-independent and would work with any BBS that was written to use it. BBSes that did not have integrated FidoNet capability could usually add it using an external FidoNet<space/><link><target>front end processor (program)</target><part>front-end</part></link><space/>mailer such as<space/><link><target>FrontDoor</target></link>, BinkleyTerm, InterMail or D'Bridge, and a mail processor such as<space/><link><target>FastEcho</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Squish (FidoNet)</target><part>Squish</part></link>. The front-end mailer would conduct the periodic FidoNet transfers, while the mail processor would usually run just before and just after the mailer ran. This program would scan for and pack up new outgoing messages, and then unpack, sort and &quot;toss&quot; the incoming messages into a BBS user's local email box or into the BBS's local message bases reserved for Echomail. As such, these mail processors were commonly called &quot;scanner/tosser/packers.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Many other BBS networks followed the example of FidoNet, using the same standards and the same software. These were called FidoNet Technology Networks (FTNs). They were usually smaller and targeted at selected audiences. Some networks used<space/><link><target>QWK (file format)</target><part>QWK</part></link><space/>doors, and others such as<space/><link><target>RelayNet</target></link><space/>(RIME) and<space/><link><target>WWIVnet</target></link><space/>used non-Fido software and standards.</paragraph><paragraph>Before commercial Internet access became common, these<space/><link><target>computer network</target><part>networks</part></link><space/>of BBSes provided regional and international<space/><link><target>e-mail</target></link><space/>and message bases. Some even provided<space/><link><target>Gateway (computer networking)</target><part>gateways</part></link>, such as UFGATE, by which members could send/receive e-mail to/from the<space/><link><target>Internet</target></link><space/>via<space/><link><target>UUCP</target></link>, and many FidoNet discussion groups were shared via gateway to<space/><link><target>Usenet</target></link>. Elaborate schemes allowed users to download binary files, search<space/><link><target>Gopher (protocol)</target><part>gopherspace</part></link>, and interact with distant<space/><link><target>Computer program</target><part>programs</part></link>, all using plain text e-mail.</paragraph><paragraph>As the volume of FidoNet Mail increased and newsgroups from the early days of the Internet became available, satellite data downstream services became viable for larger systems. The satellite service provided access to FidoNet and Usenet newsgroups in large volumes at a reasonable fee. By connecting a small dish &amp; receiver, a constant downstream of thousands of FidoNet and Usenet newsgroups could be received. The local BBS only needed to upload new outgoing messages via the modem network back to the satellite service. This method drastically reduced phone data transfers while dramatically increasing the number of message forums.</paragraph><paragraph>FidoNet is still in use today, though in a much smaller form, and many Echomail groups are still shared with Usenet via FidoNet to Usenet gateways. Widespread abuse of Usenet with<space/><link><target>spam (electronic)</target><part>spam</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pornography</target></link><space/>has led to many of these FidoNet gateways to cease operation completely.</paragraph><paragraph>Boston had a service in the 1990s called TIAC (The Internet Access Company).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Shareware and freeware</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Shareware</arg></template>Much of the<space/><link><target>shareware</target></link><space/>movement was started via user distribution of software through BBSes. A notable example was<space/><link><target>Phil Katz</target></link>'s PKARC (and later<space/><link><target>PKZIP</target></link>, using the same &quot;.zip&quot;<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>that<space/><link><target>WinZip</target></link><space/>and other popular archivers now use); also other concepts of software distribution like<space/><link><target>freeware</target></link>,<space/><link><target>postcardware</target></link><space/>like<space/><link><target>JPEGview</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>donationware</target></link><space/>like<space/><link><target>Red Ryder (software)</target><part>Red Ryder</part></link><space/>for the Macintosh first appeared on BBS sites.<space/><link><target>Doom (video game)</target><part>Doom</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>id Software</target></link><space/>and nearly all<space/><link><target>3D Realms</target><part>Apogee Software</part></link><space/>games were distributed as shareware (Apogee is, in fact, credited for adding an order form to a shareware demo) .<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>The Internet has largely erased the distinction of shareware - most users now download the software directly from the developer's website rather than receiving it from another BBS user 'sharing' it. Today shareware is commonly used to mean electronically distributed software from a small developer.</paragraph><paragraph>Many commercial BBS software companies that continue to support their old BBS software products switched to the shareware model or made it entirely free. Some companies were able to make the move to the Internet and provide commercial products with BBS capabilities.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Features</heading><paragraph>A classic BBS had:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A<space/><link><target>computer</target></link></listitem><listitem>One or more<space/><link><target>modem</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem>One or more phone lines, with more allowing for increased concurrent users</listitem><listitem>A<space/><link><target>List of BBS software</target><part>BBS software package</part></link></listitem><listitem>A<space/><link><target>sysop</target></link><space/>- system operator</listitem><listitem>A user community</listitem></list><paragraph>The BBS software usually provides:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Menu Systems</listitem><listitem>One or more<space/><link><target>Message board</target><part>message base</part><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem>File areas</listitem><listitem>SysOp side, live viewing of all caller activity</listitem><listitem>Voting - opinion booths</listitem><listitem>Statistics on message posters, top uploaders / downloaders</listitem><listitem><link><target>Online game</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(usually single<space/><link><target>Player (game)</target><part>player</part></link><space/>or only a single active player at a given time)</listitem><listitem>A<space/><link><target>BBS door</target><part>doorway</part></link><space/>to third-party online games</listitem><listitem>Usage auditing capabilities</listitem><listitem>Multi-user chat (only possible on multi-line BBSes)</listitem><listitem>Internet email (more common in later Internet-connected BBSes)</listitem><listitem>Networked message boards</listitem><listitem>Most modern BBSes allow<space/><link><target>telnet</target></link><space/>access over the Internet using a telnet server and a virtual<space/><link><target>FOSSIL</target></link><space/>driver.</listitem><listitem>A &quot;yell for SysOp&quot; page caller side menu item that sounded an audible alarm to the SysOp. If chosen, the SysOp could then initiate a text-to-text chat with the caller.</listitem><listitem>Primitive social networking features, such as leaving messages on a user's profile</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Internet</arg></template><template><target>Multicol</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>ANSI art</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>BBS: The Documentary</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>free shell</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Imageboard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Internet forum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Internet Relay Chat</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>KOM (BBS)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of BBS software</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-break</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of bulletin board systems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Minitel</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>PODSnet</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Terminal emulator</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Textboard</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>UGC</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Usenet</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Warez</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Col-break</target></template><template><target>Col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="group">"nb"</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sources</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Encyclopedia of New Media: An Essential Reference to Communication and Technology<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7619-2382-9<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Columbia Reader on Lesbians and Gay Men in Media, Society, and Politics<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-231-10446-4<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Modems for Dummies<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-56884-001-2<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Going On-Line with Your Micro<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Tab Books<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1984<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Lou<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Haas<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8306-0746-3<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Compute<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Compute! Publications<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>October 1989  September 1994<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>University of Michigan<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Computer Phone Book<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mike<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Cane<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1986<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New American Library<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Christians in a .Com World: Getting Connected Without Being Consumed<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-58134-218-7<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Beam Me Up Scottie<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Patrick<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Pippen<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-4116-0987-5<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Bulletin board systems</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://thebbs.org/'>The BBS organization (longest running bbs services site)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://textfiles.com/'>Textfiles.com</link><space/>- Collection of historical BBS documents, files and history</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://archives.thebbs.org/'>The BBS Archives</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbsdocumentary.com/'>The BBS Documentary</link><space/>-<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/bbs_documentary/'>(Video Collection)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbscorner.com/'>The BBS Corner</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bbses.info/'>BBSes.info BBS services EST. 2006</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bbs-scene.org/'>BBS-Scene.org</link><space/>- BBS related services</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.telnetbbsguide.com/'>The Telnet BBS Guide</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbsfinder.net/'>BBSfinder real time BBS lister</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bbsmates.com/'>BBSmates community and resource site</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bbsnews.org/'>BBS News site established 1996 (domain est 2004)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.hackcanada.com/hackcanada/oldsite/bbs/index.html/'>Hack Canada BBS List (Canadian BBS Services)</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Computers/Bulletin_Board_Systems/</arg><arg>Bulletin Board Systems</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:American inventions</target></link><link><target>Category:Bulletin board systems</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Online chat</target></link><link><target>Category:PreWorld Wide Web online services</target></link></paragraph></article>