<article title='Emancipation_Proclamation'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>American history</arg><arg>emancipation proclamations in other countries</arg><arg>Abolition of slavery timeline</arg></template><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template><link><target>File:Stephens-reading-proclamation-1863.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Henry Louis Stephens</target></link>, untitled watercolor (<template><target>circa</target></template><space/>1863) of a black man reading a newspaper with headline &quot;Presidential Proclamation/Slavery&quot;.</part></link><link><target>File:Brooklyn Museum - Abraham Lincoln - overall.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Abraham Lincoln,<space/><link><target>Brooklyn Museum</target></link></part></link>The<space/><bold>Emancipation Proclamation</bold><space/>was a<space/><link><target>presidential proclamation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>executive order</target></link><space/>issued by President<space/><link><target>Abraham Lincoln</target></link><space/>on January 1, 1863. In a single stroke, it changed the federal legal status of more than 3 million<space/><link><target>Slavery in the United States</target><part>enslaved persons</part></link><space/>in the designated areas of the South from &quot;slave&quot; to &quot;free&quot;. It had the practical effect that as soon as a slave escaped the control of the Confederate government, by running away or through advances of federal troops, the slave became legally free. Eventually it reached and liberated all of the designated slaves. It was issued as a war measure during the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link>, directed to all of the areas in rebellion and all segments of the<space/><link><target>Executive branch of the United States</target><part>executive branch</part></link><space/>(including the Army and Navy) of the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'>Political scientist Brian R. Dirck states: &quot;The Emancipation Proclamation was an executive order, itself a rather unusual thing in those days. Executive orders are simply presidential directives issued to agents of the executive department by its boss.&quot;<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Brian R. Dirck</arg><arg name="title">The Executive Branch of Federal Government: People, Process, and Politics</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="page">102</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It proclaimed the freedom of slaves in the ten states that were still in rebellion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Emancipation Proclamation</arg><arg name="url">http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/featured_documents/emancipation_proclamation/</arg><arg name="publisher">National Archives and Records Administration<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-27</arg></template></extension><space/>Because it was issued under the President's war powers, it necessarily excluded areas not in rebellion - it applied to more than 3 million of the 4 million slaves in the U.S. at the time. The Proclamation was based on the president's constitutional authority as commander in chief of the armed forces;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Emancipation Proclamation: Freedom's first steps</arg><arg name="url">http://edsitement.neh.gov/lesson-plan/emancipation-proclamation-freedoms-first-steps</arg><arg name="publisher">National Endowment for the Humanities<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-27</arg></template></extension><space/>it was not a law passed by Congress. The Proclamation also ordered that suitable persons among those freed could be enrolled into the paid service of United States' forces, and ordered the Union Army (and all segments of the Executive branch) to &quot;recognize and maintain the freedom of&quot; the ex-slaves. The Proclamation did not compensate the owners, did not outlaw slavery, and did not grant citizenship to the ex-slaves (called<space/><link><target>Freedman</target><part>freedmen</part></link>). It made the eradication of<space/><link><target>Slavery in the United States</target><part>slavery</part></link><space/>an explicit war goal, in addition to the goal of reuniting the Union.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Foner</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="pp">239–42</arg></template></extension>Around 20,000 to 50,000 slaves in regions where rebellion had already been subdued were immediately emancipated. It could not be enforced in areas still under rebellion, but as the Union army took control of Confederate regions, the Proclamation provided the legal framework for freeing more than 3 million slaves in those regions. Prior to the Proclamation, in accordance with the<space/><link><target>Fugitive Slave Act of 1850</target></link>, escaped slaves were either returned to their masters or held in camps as<space/><link><target>Contraband (American Civil War)</target><part>contraband</part></link><space/>for later return. The Proclamation applied only to slaves in Confederate-held lands; it did not apply to those in the<space/><link><target>Border states (American Civil War)</target><part>four slave states</part></link><space/>that were not in rebellion (Kentucky, Maryland, Delaware, and Missouri, which were unnamed), nor to Tennessee (unnamed but occupied by Union troops since 1862) and lower Louisiana (also under occupation), and specifically excluded those counties of Virginia soon to form the state of West Virginia. Also specifically excluded (by name) were some regions already controlled by the Union army. Emancipation in those places would come after separate state actions and/or the December 1865 ratification of the<space/><link><target>Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>Thirteenth Amendment</part></link>, which made slavery and indentured servitude, except for those duly convicted of a crime, illegal everywhere subject to United States jurisdiction.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution_amendments_11-27.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Amendments to the U.S. Constitution<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-26</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On September 22, 1862, Lincoln had issued a preliminary proclamation warning that he would order the emancipation of all slaves in any state that did not end its rebellion against the Union by January 1, 1863. None of the Confederate states restored themselves to the Union, and Lincoln's order, signed and issued January 1, 1863, took effect. The Emancipation Proclamation outraged white Southerners (and their sympathizers) who envisioned a race war, angered some Northern Democrats, energized anti-slavery forces, and undermined forces in Europe that wanted to intervene to help the Confederacy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Allan Nevins,<space/><italics>Ordeal of the Union: vol 6. War Becomes Revolution, 18621863</italics><space/>(1960) pp. 23141, 273</extension><space/>The Proclamation lifted the spirits of<space/><link><target>African American</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>both free and slave. It led many slaves to escape from their masters and get to Union lines to obtain their freedom.</paragraph><paragraph>The Emancipation Proclamation broadened the goals of the Civil War. While slavery had been a major issue that led to the war, Lincoln's only mission at the start of the war was to maintain the Union. The Proclamation made freeing the slaves an explicit goal of the Union war effort. Establishing the abolition of slavery as one of the two primary war goals served to deter intervention by Britain and France.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Howard Jones 1999"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Jones</arg><arg name="first">Howard</arg><arg name="title">Abraham Lincoln and a New Birth of Freedom: The Union and Slavery in the Diplomacy of the Civil War</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="publisher">U of Nebraska Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8032-2582-2</arg></template></extension><space/>The Emancipation Proclamation was never challenged in court. To ensure the abolition of slavery in all of the U.S., Lincoln pushed for passage of the<space/><link><target>Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>Thirteenth Amendment</part></link>. Congress passed it by the necessary two-thirds vote on January 31, 1865, and it was ratified by the states on December 6, 1865.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">13th Amendment to the U.S. Constitution</arg><arg name="url">http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/13thamendment.html</arg><arg name="publisher">The Library of Congress</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-27</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Authority</heading><paragraph><template><target>Slavery</target></template><template><target>LincolnSeries</target></template><template><target>Further</target><arg>Slave and free states</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target></link><space/>of 1787 did not use the word &quot;slavery&quot; but included several provisions about unfree persons. The<space/><link><target>Three-Fifths Compromise</target></link><space/>(in Article I, Section 2) allocated Congressional representation based &quot;on the whole Number of free Persons&quot; and &quot;three fifths of all other Persons&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jean Allain</arg><arg name="title">The Legal Understanding of Slavery: From the Historical to the Contemporary</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="page">117</arg><arg name="isbn">9780199660469</arg></template></extension><space/>Under the<space/><link><target>Fugitive Slave Clause</target></link><space/>(Article IV, Section 2), &quot;[n]o person held to service or labour in one state&quot; would be freed by escaping to another.<space/><link><target>Article One of the United States Constitution#Section 9: Limits on Congress</target><part>Article I, Section 9</part></link><space/>allowed Congress to pass legislation to outlaw the &quot;Importation of Persons&quot;, but not until 1808.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Foner201016"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Foner</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">16</arg></template></extension><space/>However, for purposes of the<space/><link><target>Fifth Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>Fifth Amendment</part></link>which states that, &quot;No person shall ... be deprived of life, liberty, or property, without due process of law&quot;slaves were understood as property.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Jean Allain</arg><arg name="title">The Legal Understanding of Slavery: From the Historical to the Contemporary</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="pages">119–120</arg><arg name="isbn">9780199660469</arg></template></extension><space/>Although abolitionists used the Fifth Amendment to argue against slavery, it became part of the legal basis for treating slaves as property with<space/><italics><link><target>Dred Scott v. Sandford</target></link></italics><space/>(1857).<extension extension_name='ref'>Tsesis,<space/><italics>The Thirteenth Amendment and American Freedom</italics><space/>(2004), p. 14. &quot;Nineteenth century apologists for the expansion of slavery developed a political philosophy that placed property at the pinnacle of personal interests and regarded its protection to be the government's chief purpose. The Fifth Amendment's Just Compensation clause provided the proslavery camp with a bastion for fortifying the peculiar institution against congressional restrictions to its spread westward. Based on this property-rights centered argument, Chief Justice Roger B. Taney, in<space/><italics>Dred Scott v. Sanford</italics><space/>(1857), found the Missouri Compromise unconstitutionally violated due process.&quot;</extension><space/>Socially, slavery was also supported in law and in practice by a pervasive culture of<space/><link><target>white supremacy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tsesis,<space/><italics>The Thirteenth Amendment and American Freedom</italics><space/>(2004), pp. 1823. &quot;Constitutional protections of slavery coexisted with an entire culture of oppression. The peculiar institution reached many private aspects of human life, for both whites and blacks. [...] Even free Southern blacks lived in a world so legally constricted by racial domination that it offered only a deceptive shadow of freedom.&quot;</extension><space/>Nonetheless, between 1777 and 1804, every Northern state provided for the immediate or gradual abolition of slavery. No Southern state did so, and the slave population of the South continued to grow, peaking at almost 4 million people at the beginning of the American Civil War, in which most slave states sought to break away from the United States.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Foner201014&amp;amp;ndash;16"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Foner</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="pp">14–16</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lincoln understood that the Federal government's power to end slavery in peacetime was limited by the Constitution which before 1865, committed the issue to individual<space/><link><target>US States</target><part>states</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mackubin"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nationalreview.com/books/owens200403251139.asp</arg><arg name="title">The Liberator</arg><arg name="first">Thomas Owens</arg><arg name="last">Mackubin</arg><arg name="date">March 25, 2004</arg><arg name="work">National Review</arg><arg name="publisher">National Review</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/62a7fJ9hj</arg><arg name="archivedate">2011-10-20</arg></template></extension><space/>Against the background of the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link>, however, Lincoln issued the Proclamation under his authority as &quot;<link><target>Commander-in-chief</target><part>Commander in Chief</part></link><space/>of the Army and Navy&quot; under<space/><link><target>Article Two of the United States Constitution#Section 2</target><part>Article II, section 2</part></link><space/>of the United States Constitution.<extension extension_name='ref'>Crowther p. 651</extension><space/>As such, he claimed to have the martial power to free persons held as slaves in those states that were in rebellion &quot;as a fit and necessary war measure for suppressing said rebellion&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Numerous slaves were being commanded to perform tasks to support the Confederate war effort, including making weapons.</extension><space/>He did not have Commander-in-Chief authority over the four<space/><link><target>Slave and free states</target><part>slave-holding states</part></link><space/>that were not in rebellion:<space/><link><target>Missouri</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kentucky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Delaware</target></link>, and so those states were not named in the Proclamation.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="The fourth paragraph of the proclamation explains that Lincoln issued it, "by virtue of the power in me vested as Commander-in-Chief, of the Army and Navy of the United States in time of actual armed rebellion against the authority and government of the United States, and as a fit and necessary war measure for suppressing said rebellion".<ref>{{cite web|url">http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/featured_documents/emancipation_proclamation/transcript.html|title</arg></template><space/>The fifth border jurisdiction,<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link>, where slavery remained legal but was in the process of being abolished, was, in January 1863, still part of the legally recognized<space/><link><target>Restored Government of Virginia</target><part>&quot;reorganized&quot; state of Virginia</part></link>, based in Alexandria, which was in the Union (as opposed to the Confederate state of Virginia, based in Richmond).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Coverage</heading><paragraph>The Proclamation applied in the ten states that were still in rebellion in 1863, and thus did not cover the nearly 500,000 slaves in the slave-holding<space/><link><target>border states (American Civil War)</target><part>border states</part></link><space/>(Missouri, Kentucky, Maryland or Delaware) which were Union states. Those slaves were freed by later separate state and federal actions.</paragraph><paragraph>The state of<space/><link><target>Tennessee</target></link><space/>had already mostly returned to Union control, under a recognized Union government, so it was not named and was exempted.<space/><link><target>Virginia</target></link><space/>was named, but exemptions were specified for the 48 counties then in the process of forming the new state of<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link>, and seven additional counties and two cities in the Union-controlled<space/><link><target>Tidewater region of Virginia</target><part>Tidewater region</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Freedmen and Southern Society Project</arg><arg name="title">Freedom: a documentary history of emancipation 1861–1867 : selected from the holdings of the National Archives of the United States. The destruction of slavery</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1982</arg><arg name="publisher">CUP Archive</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-22979-1</arg><arg name="pages">[http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>Also specifically exempted were<space/><link><target>New Orleans</target></link><space/>and 13 named parishes of<space/><link><target>Louisiana</target></link>, which were mostly under federal control at the time of the Proclamation. These exemptions left unemancipated an additional 300,000 slaves.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Foner</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="pp">241–242</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Emancipation Proclamation has been ridiculed, notably in an influential passage by<space/><link><target>Richard Hofstadter</target></link><space/>for &quot;freeing&quot; only the slaves over which the Union had no power.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Striner</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Father Abraham: Lincoln's Relentless Struggle to End Slavery<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="page">192 (citing Hofstadter's 1948 essay, in which he relates, in part, a sardonic remark by [[William H. Seward|William Seward]])</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-518306-1</arg></template></extension><space/>These slaves were freed due to Lincoln's &quot;war powers&quot;. This act cleared up the issue of<space/><link><target>contraband</target></link><space/>slaves.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Heidler</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Encyclopedia of the American Civil War</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="page">652</arg></template></extension><space/>It automatically clarified the status of over 100,000 now-former slaves. Some 20,000 to 50,000 slaves were freed the day it went into effect<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIFBEP"></extension><space/>in parts of nine of the ten states to which it applied (Texas being the exception).<extension extension_name='ref' name="AEPLRES">William C. Harris, &quot;After the Emancipation Proclamation: Lincoln's Role in the Ending of Slavery&quot;, North &amp; South vol. 5 no. 1 (December 2001), map on p.&amp;nbsp;49</extension><space/>In every Confederate state (except Tennessee and Texas), the Proclamation went into immediate effect in Union-occupied areas and at least 20,000 slaves<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIFBEP"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="AEPLRES"></extension><space/>were freed at once on January 1, 1863.<link><target>File:Am Arch Sculpt 4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The moment portrayed by<space/><link><target>Lee Lawrie</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Lincoln, Nebraska</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Additionally, the Proclamation provided the legal framework for the emancipation of nearly all four million slaves as the Union armies advanced, and committed the Union to ending slavery, which was a controversial decision even in the North. Hearing of the Proclamation, more slaves quickly escaped to Union lines as the Army units moved South. As the Union armies advanced through the Confederacy, thousands of slaves were freed each day until nearly all (approximately 3.9 million, according to the 1860 Census)<extension extension_name='ref' name="1860Census"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sonofthesouth.net/slavery/slave-maps/slave-census.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Census, Son of the South<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="year">1860</arg><arg name="publisher">sonofthesouth.net<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>were freed by July 1865.</paragraph><paragraph>While the Proclamation had freed most slaves as a war measure, it had not made slavery illegal. Of the states that were exempted from the Proclamation, Maryland,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.msa.md.gov/msa/speccol/sc2600/sc2685/html/conv1864.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Archives of Maryland Historical List: Constitutional Convention, 1864<space/></arg><arg name="date">November 1, 1864</arg></template></extension><space/>Missouri,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.civilwaronthewesternborder.org/event/missouri-abolishes-slavery<space/></arg><arg name="title">Missouri abolishes slavery<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 11, 1865</arg></template></extension><space/>Tennessee,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1865/01/15/news/tennessee-state-convention-slavery-declared-forever-abolished-parson-brownlow.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tennessee State Convention: Slavery Declared Forever Abolished<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 14, 1865</arg></template></extension><space/>and West Virginia<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wvculture.org/history/thisdayinwvhistory/february.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">On this day: 1865-FEB-03</arg></template></extension><space/>prohibited slavery before the war ended. In 1863, President Lincoln proposed a moderate plan for the Reconstruction of the captured Confederate State of Louisiana.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stauffer (2008),<space/><italics>Giants</italics>, p. 279</extension><space/>Only 10% of the state's electorate had to take the loyalty oath. The state was also required to abolish slavery in its new constitution. Identical Reconstruction plans would be adopted in Arkansas and Tennessee. By December 1864, the Lincoln plan abolishing slavery had been enacted in Louisiana.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peterson 1995 pp. 3841">Peterson (1995)<space/><italics>Lincoln in American Memory</italics>, pp. 3841</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McCarthy 1901 p. 76">McCarthy (1901),<space/><italics>Lincoln's plan of Reconstruction</italics>, p. 76</extension><space/>However, in Delaware<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.slavenorth.com/delaware.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Slavery in Delaware</arg></template></extension><space/>and Kentucky,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">A new history of Kentucky<space/></arg><arg name="author">Lowell Hayes Harrison and James C. Klotter<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="page">180</arg><arg name="isbn">0813126215<space/></arg></template><space/>In 1866, Kentucky refused to ratify the 13th Amendment. It did ratify it in 1976.</extension><space/>slavery continued to be legal until December 18, 1865, when the Thirteenth Amendment went into effect.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph><template><target>Emancipation Proclamation draft</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Military action prior to emancipation</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Fugitive Slave Act of 1850</target></link><space/>required individuals to return runaway slaves to their owners. During the war, Union generals such as<space/><link><target>Benjamin Franklin Butler (politician)</target><part>Benjamin Butler</part></link><space/>declared that slaves in occupied areas were<space/><link><target>contraband (American Civil War)</target><part>contraband of war</part></link><space/>and accordingly refused to return them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT_20110411"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/04/03/magazine/mag-03CivilWar-t.html</arg><arg name="date">April 1, 2011</arg><arg name="title">How Slavery Really Ended in America</arg><arg name="author">Adam Goodheart</arg><arg name="work">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-04-03</arg></template></extension><space/>This decision was controversial because it implied recognition of the Confederacy as a separate nation under international law, a notion that Lincoln steadfastly denied. As a result, he did not promote the contraband designation. In addition, as contraband, these people were legally designated as &quot;property&quot; when they crossed Union lines and their ultimate status was uncertain.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nps.gov/cwdw/historyculture/living-contraband-former-slaves-in-the-capital-during-and-after-the-civil-war.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Living Contraband - Former Slaves in the Nation's Capital During the Civil War<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">National Park Service<space/></arg><arg name="work">Civil War Defenses of Washington<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-29</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Governmental action towards emancipation</heading><paragraph>In December 1861, Lincoln sent his first annual message to Congress (the<space/><link><target>State of the Union Address</target></link>, but then typically given in writing and not referred to as such). In it he praised the free labor system, as respecting human rights over property rights; he endorsed legislation to address the status of contraband slaves and slaves in loyal states, possibly through buying their freedom with federal taxes, and also the funding of strictly voluntary colonization efforts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Striner</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Father Abraham: Lincoln's Relentless Struggle to End Slavery<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="pages">147–148</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-518306-1</arg></template></extension><space/>In January 1862,<space/><link><target>Thaddeus Stevens</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>History of the United States Republican Party</target><part>Republican</part></link><space/>leader in the<space/><link><target>United States House of Representatives</target><part>House</part></link>, called for total war against the rebellion to include emancipation of slaves, arguing that emancipation, by forcing the loss of enslaved labor, would ruin the rebel economy. On March 13, 1862, Congress approved a &quot;Law Enacting an Additional Article of War&quot;, which stated that from that point onward it was forbidden for Union Army officers to return fugitive slaves to their owners.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">U.S., Statutes at Large, Treaties, and Proclamations of the United States of America<space/></arg><arg name="volume">12<space/></arg><arg name="location">Boston<space/></arg><arg name="year">1863<space/></arg><arg name="page">354.</arg></template></extension><space/>On April 10, 1862, Congress declared that the federal government would compensate slave owners who freed their slaves. Slaves in the<space/><link><target>Geography of Washington, D.C.</target><part>District of Columbia</part></link><space/>were freed on April 16, 1862, and their owners were compensated.</paragraph><paragraph>On June 19, 1862, Congress prohibited slavery in all current and future<space/><link><target>Organized incorporated territories of the United States#List of organized incorporated territories</target><part>United States territories</part></link><space/>(though not in the states), and President Lincoln quickly signed the legislation. By this act, they repudiated the 1857 opinion of the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target></link><space/>in the<space/><italics><link><target>Dred Scott v. Sandford</target><part>Dred Scott Case</part></link></italics><space/>that Congress was powerless to regulate slavery in U.S. territories.<extension extension_name='ref'>Guminski, Arnold.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=5uFS7SOBHd8C&amp;amp;pg=PA241&amp;amp;dq=%22June+19,+1862%22+slavery+Lincoln&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=_HzHTbzOLaHj0QGa5riUCA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=3&amp;amp;ved=0CDMQ6AEwAjg8#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22June%2019%2C%201862%22%20slavery%20Lincoln&amp;amp;f=false'>The Constitutional Rights, Privileges, and Immunities of the American People</link></italics>, page 241 (2009).</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson, Theresa and Johanningmeir, Erwin.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=K_7Tba0v3ogC&amp;amp;pg=PA129&amp;amp;dq=%22June+19,+1862%22+slavery+Lincoln&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=s3jHTYnxBc2cgQeIldHLBA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=7&amp;amp;ved=0CEcQ6AEwBjge#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22June%2019%2C%201862%22%20slavery%20Lincoln&amp;amp;f=false'>Race, ethnicity, and education</link></italics>, page 129 (IAP 2003).</extension>This joint action by Congress and President Lincoln also rejected the notion of<space/><link><target>popular sovereignty</target></link><space/>that had been advanced by<space/><link><target>Stephen A. Douglas</target></link><space/>as a solution to the slavery controversy, while completing the effort first legislatively proposed by<space/><link><target>Thomas Jefferson</target></link><space/>in 1784 to confine slavery within the borders of existing states.<extension extension_name='ref'>Montgomery, David.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=A24AAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA428&amp;amp;dq=%22June+19,+1862%22+slavery+Lincoln&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=s3jHTYnxBc2cgQeIldHLBA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=4&amp;amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAzge#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22June%2019%2C%201862%22%20slavery%20Lincoln&amp;amp;f=false'>The student's American history</link></italics>, page 428 (Ginn &amp; Co. 1897).</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Keifer, Joseph.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=GBq0gjrfxRgC&amp;amp;pg=PA109&amp;amp;dq=%22June+19,+1862%22+slavery+Lincoln&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=s3jHTYnxBc2cgQeIldHLBA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=6&amp;amp;ved=0CEIQ6AEwBTge#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=%22June%2019%2C%201862%22%20slavery%20Lincoln&amp;amp;f=false'>Slavery and Four Years of War</link></italics>, p. 109 (Echo Library 2009).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July 1862, Congress passed and Lincoln signed the<space/><link><target>Second Confiscation Act</target></link>, containing provisions for court proceedings to liberate slaves held by convicted &quot;rebels&quot;, or of slaves of rebels that had escaped to Union lines.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.history.umd.edu/Freedmen/conact2.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Second Confiscation Act, July 17, 1862<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">History.umd.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-05-29</arg></template></extension><space/>The Act applied in cases of criminal convictions and to those who were slaves of &quot;disloyal&quot; masters. However, Lincoln's position continued to be that Congress lacked power to free all slaves within the borders of rebel held states, but Lincoln as commander in chief could do so if he deemed it a proper military measure,<extension extension_name='ref'>Donald, David.<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=fuTY3mxs9awC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=%22David+Herbert+Donald%22+and+Lincoln&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;src=bmrr&amp;amp;ei=_f3ITd34C8Hb0QH6xOTpCA&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=book-preview-link&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CEEQuwUwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Second%20Confiscation%20Act&amp;amp;f=false'>Lincoln</link></italics>, page 365 (Simon and Schuster 1996)</extension><space/>and that Lincoln had already drafted plans to do.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Public opinion of emancipation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gordon, scourged back, NPG, 1863.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Medical examination photo of<space/><link><target>Gordon (slave)</target><part>Gordon</part></link>, widely distributed by Abolitionists to expose the brutality of slavery.</part></link><link><target>Abolitionism in the United States</target><part>Abolitionists</part></link><space/>had long been urging Lincoln to free all slaves. In the summer of 1862, Republican editor<space/><link><target>Horace Greeley</target></link><space/>of the highly influential<space/><link><target>New York Tribune</target></link><space/>wrote a famous editorial entitled &quot;The Prayer of Twenty Millions&quot; demanding a more aggressive attack on the Confederacy and faster emancipation of the slaves: &quot;On the face of this wide earth, Mr. President, there is not one ... intelligent champion of the Union cause who does not feel ... that the rebellion, if crushed tomorrow, would be renewed if slavery were left in full vigor ... and that every hour of deference to slavery is an hour of added and deepened peril to the Union.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Harold Holzer,<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=tA4lXY3W8hkC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;hl=de#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>Dear Mr. Lincoln: Letters to the President</link></italics>, Southern Illinois University Press, 2006, p. 160161</extension><space/>Lincoln responded in his<space/><link><target>q:AbrahamLincoln#Letter to Horace Greeley (1862)</target><part>Letter To Horace Greeley</part></link><space/>from August 22, 1862, in terms of the limits imposed by his duty as president to save the Union:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>If there be those who would not save the Union, unless they could at the same time save slavery, I do not agree with them. If there be those who would not save the Union unless they could at the same time destroy slavery, I do not agree with them. My paramount object in this struggle is to save the Union, and is not either to save or to destroy slavery. If I could save the Union without freeing any slave I would do it, and if I could save it by freeing all the slaves I would do it; and if I could save it by freeing some and leaving others alone I would also do that. What I do about slavery, and the colored race, I do because I believe it helps to save the Union; and what I forbear, I forbear because I do not believe it would help to save the Union.... I have here stated my purpose according to my view of official duty; and I intend no modification of my oft-expressed personal wish that all men everywhere could be free.<ref>''The Collected Works of Abraham Lincoln'' edited by Roy P. Basler, Volume V, p. 388–389</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lincoln scholar<space/><link><target>Harold Holzer</target></link><space/>wrote in this context about Lincoln's letter: &quot;Unknown to Greeley, Lincoln composed this after he had already drafted a preliminary Emancipation Proclamation, which he had determined to issue after the next Union military victory. Therefore, this letter, was in truth, an attempt to position the impending announcement in terms of saving the Union, not freeing slaves as a humanitarian gesture. It was one of Lincoln's most skillful public relations efforts, even if it has cast longstanding doubt on his sincerity as a liberator.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Harold Holzer,<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=tA4lXY3W8hkC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;hl=de#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>Dear Mr. Lincoln: Letters to the President</link></italics>, Southern Illinois University Press, 2006, p. 162</extension><space/>Historian Richard Striner argues that &quot;for years&quot; Lincoln's letter has been misread as &quot;Lincoln only wanted to save the Union.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Striner"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Striner</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Father Abraham: Lincoln's Relentless Struggle to End Slavery<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="page">176</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-518306-1</arg></template></extension><space/>However, within the context of Lincoln's entire career and pronouncements on slavery this interpretation is wrong, according to Striner. Rather, Lincoln was softening the strong Northern white supremacist opposition to his imminent emancipation by tying it to the cause of the Union. This opposition would fight for the Union but not to end slavery, so Lincoln gave them the means and motivation to do both, at the same time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Striner"></extension><space/>In his 2014 book,<space/><italics><link><target>Lincoln's Gamble</target></link></italics>, journalist and historian<space/><link><target>Todd Brewster</target></link><space/>asserted that Lincoln's desire to reassert the saving of the Union as his sole war goal was in fact crucial to his claim of legal authority for emancipation. Since slavery was protected by the Constitution, the only way that he could free the slaves was as a tactic of warnot as the mission itself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brewster"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brewster</arg><arg name="first">Todd</arg><arg name="title">Lincoln's Gamble: The Tumultuous Six Months that Gave America the Emancipation Proclamation and Changed the Course of the Civil War</arg><arg name="year">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Scribner</arg><arg name="page">59</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1451693867</arg></template></extension><space/>But that carried the risk that when the war ended, so would the justification for freeing the slaves. Late in 1862, Lincoln asked his Attorney General,<space/><link><target>Edward Bates</target></link>, for an opinion as to whether slaves freed through a war-related proclamation of emancipation could be re-enslaved once the war was over. Bates had to work through the language of the Dred Scott decision to arrive at an answer, but he finally concluded that they could indeed remain free. Still, a complete end to slavery would require a constitutional amendment.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Brewster</arg><arg name="first">Todd</arg><arg name="title">Lincoln's Gamble: The Tumultuous Six Months that Gave America the Emancipation Proclamation and Changed the Course of the Civil War</arg><arg name="year">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Scribner</arg><arg name="page">236</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1451693867</arg></template></extension><space/>Conflicting advice, to free all slaves, or not free them at all, was presented to Lincoln in public and private.<space/><link><target>Thomas Nast</target></link>, a cartoon artist during the Civil War and the late 1800s considered &quot;Father of the American Cartoon&quot;, composed many works including a two-sided spread that showed the transition from slavery into civilization after President Lincoln signed the Proclamation. Nast believed in equal opportunity and equality for all people, including enslaved Africans or free blacks.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Thomas Nast</target></link></extension><space/>A mass rally in Chicago on September 7, 1862, demanded an immediate and universal emancipation of slaves. A delegation headed by<space/><link><target>William W. Patton</target></link><space/>met the President at the<space/><link><target>White House</target></link><space/>on September 13. Lincoln had declared in peacetime that he had no constitutional authority to free the slaves. Even used as a war power, emancipation was a risky political act. Public opinion as a whole was against it.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Guelzo</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">[http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>There would be strong opposition among<space/><link><target>Copperheads (politics)</target><part>Copperhead</part></link><space/>Democrats and an uncertain reaction from loyal border states. Delaware and Maryland already had a high percentage of free blacks: 91.2% and 49.7%, respectively, in 1860.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Kolchin,<space/><italics>American Slavery: 16191877</italics>, New York: Hill and Wang, 1994, p. 82</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Drafting and issuance of the proclamation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Eastman Johnson - A Ride for Liberty -- The Fugitive Slaves - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>right</part><part>'''<link><target>Eastman Johnson</target></link>''' (American, 1824-1906). ''A Ride for Liberty -- The Fugitive Slaves (recto)'', ca. 1862. Oil on paperboard.<space/><link><target>Brooklyn Museum</target></link></part></link>Lincoln first discussed the proclamation with his cabinet in July 1862. He drafted his &quot;preliminary proclamation&quot; and read it to Secretary of State William Seward, and Secretary of Navy Gideon Welles, on July 13. Seward and Welles were at first speechless, then Seward referred to possible anarchy throughout the South and resulting foreign intervention; Welles apparently said nothing. On July 22, Lincoln presented it to his entire cabinet as something he had determined to do and he asked their opinion on wording.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/alhtml/almintr.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Emancipation Proclamation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Library of Congress and Knox College<space/></arg><arg name="work">Lincoln Papers<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-28</arg></template></extension><space/>Although Secretary of War Edwin Stanton supported it, Seward advised Lincoln to issue the proclamation after a major Union victory, or else it would appear as if the Union was giving &quot;its last shriek of retreat&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Goodwin</arg><arg name="first">Doris</arg><arg name="title">Team of Rivals</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Blithedale Productions</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In September 1862, the<space/><link><target>Battle of Antietam</target></link><space/>gave Lincoln the victory he needed to issue the Emancipation. In the battle, though<space/><link><target>General McClellan</target></link><space/>allowed the escape of<space/><link><target>Robert E. Lee</target></link>'s retreating troops, Union forces turned back a Confederate invasion of Maryland. On September 22, 1862, five days after Antietam occurred, Lincoln called his cabinet into session and issued the Preliminary Emancipation Proclamation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/american_originals_iv/sections/preliminary_emancipation_proclamation.html#'>U.S. National Archives and Records Administration, Preliminary Emancipation Proclamation, 1862</link></extension><space/>According to Civil War historian<space/><link><target>James M. McPherson</target></link>, Lincoln told Cabinet members that he had made a covenant with God, that if the Union drove the Confederacy out of Maryland, he would issue the Emancipation Proclamation.<extension extension_name='ref'>McPherson, James M.<space/><italics>Battle Cry of Freedom</italics>, (1988), p. 557</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="first">Frank B<space/></arg><arg name="last">Carpenter<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Francis Bicknell Carpenter<space/></arg><arg name="title">Six Months at the White House<space/></arg><arg name="year">1866<space/></arg><arg name="page">90<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-02-20<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4290-1527-1</arg></template><space/>as reported by Secretary of the Treasury, Salmon Portland Chase, September 22, 1862. Others present used the word<space/><italics>resolution</italics><space/>instead of<space/><italics>vow to God</italics>.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Gideon Welles</target></link>,<space/><italics>Diary of Gideon Welles, Secretary of the Navy Under Lincoln and Johnson</italics><space/>(Boston, New York: Houghton Mifflin Company, 1911), 1:143, reported that Lincoln made a covenant with God that if God would change the tide of the war, Lincoln would change his policy toward slavery. See also Nicolas Parrillo, &quot;Lincoln's Calvinist Transformation: Emancipation and War&quot;,<space/><italics>Civil War History</italics><space/>(September 1, 2000).</extension><space/>Lincoln had first shown an early draft of the proclamation to Vice President<space/><link><target>Hannibal Hamlin</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://bangorinfo.com/Focus/focus_hannibal_hamlin.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bangor In Focus: Hannibal Hamlin<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bangorinfo.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-05-29</arg></template></extension><space/>an ardent abolitionist, who was more often kept in the dark on presidential decisions. The final proclamation was issued January 1, 1863. Although implicitly granted authority by Congress, Lincoln used his powers as Commander-in-Chief of the Army and Navy, &quot;as a necessary war measure&quot; as the basis of the proclamation, rather than the equivalent of a statute enacted by Congress or a constitutional amendment. Some days after issuing the final Proclamation, Lincoln wrote to Major General<space/><link><target>John McClernand</target></link>: &quot;After the commencement of hostilities I struggled nearly a year and a half to get along without touching the &quot;institution&quot;; and when finally I conditionally determined to touch it, I gave a hundred days fair notice of my purpose, to all the States and people, within which time they could have turned it wholly aside, by simply again becoming good citizens of the United States. They chose to disregard it, and I made the peremptory proclamation on what appeared to me to be a military necessity. And being made, it must stand.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://quod.lib.umich.edu/l/lincoln/lincoln6/1:84.1?rgn=div2;view=fulltext;q1=broken+eggs'>&quot;The Collected Works of Abraham Lincoln</link>&quot; edited by Roy P. Basler, Volume 6, p. 4849</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:EmancipationProclamation.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Reproduction of the Emancipation Proclamation at the<space/><link><target>National Underground Railroad Freedom Center</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cincinnati</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ohio</target></link>. ('''''<link type='external' href='http://toolserver.org/~dschwen/iip/wip.php?f=EmancipationProclamation.jpg'>Zoom</link>''''')</part></link>Initially, the Emancipation Proclamation effectively freed only a small percentage of the slaves, those who were behind Union lines in areas not exempted. Most slaves were still behind Confederate lines or in exempted Union-occupied areas. Secretary of State<space/><link><target>William H. Seward</target></link><space/>commented, &quot;We show our sympathy with slavery by emancipating slaves where we cannot reach them and holding them in bondage where we can set them free.&quot; Had any slave state ended its secession attempt before January 1, 1863, it could have kept slavery, at least temporarily. The Proclamation only gave the Lincoln Administration the legal basis to free the slaves in the areas of the South that were still in rebellion on January 1, 1863. It effectively destroyed slavery as the Union armies advanced south and conquered the entire Confederacy.</paragraph><paragraph>The Emancipation Proclamation also allowed for the enrollment of freed slaves into the United States military. During the war nearly 200,000 blacks, most of them ex-slaves, joined the Union Army.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archives.gov/education/lessons/blacks-civil-war/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Teaching With Documents: The Fight for Equal Rights: Black Soldiers in the Civil War</arg><arg name="work">[[National Archives and Records Administration|U.S. National Archives and Records Administration]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Their contributions gave the North additional manpower that was significant in winning the war. The Confederacy did not allow slaves in their army as soldiers until the last month before its defeat.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.history.umd.edu/Freedmen/csenlist.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Confederate Law Authorizing the Enlistment of Black Soldiers, as Promulgated in a Military Order<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 23, 1865</arg><arg name="work">CSA General Orders, No. 14</arg><arg name="publisher">Department of History, University of Maryland</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Though the counties of Virginia that were soon to form<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link><space/>were specifically exempted from the Proclamation (Jefferson County being the only exception), a condition of the state's<space/><link><target>admittance to the Union</target></link><space/>was that its constitution provide for the gradual abolition of slavery (an immediate emancipation of all slaves was also adopted there in early 1865). Slaves in the border states of<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Missouri</target></link><space/>were also emancipated by separate state action before the Civil War ended. In Maryland, a new state constitution abolishing slavery in the state went into effect on November 1, 1864. The Union-occupied counties of eastern Virginia and parishes of Louisiana, which had been exempted from the Proclamation, both adopted state constitutions that abolished slavery in April 1864.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.encyclopediavirginia.org/Virginia_Convention_of_1864</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.historylearningsite.co.uk/april-1864-civil-war.htm</extension><space/>In early 1865, Tennessee adopted an amendment to its constitution prohibiting slavery.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.history.umd.edu/Freedmen/chronol.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Freedmen and Southern Society Project: Chronology of Emancipation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">History.umd.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-12-08<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-05-29</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.tn.us/tsla/exhibits/blackhistory/timelines/timeline_1861-1865.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">TSLA: This Honorable Body: African American Legislators in 19th Century Tennessee<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">State.tn.us<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-05-29</arg></template></extension><space/>Slaves in<space/><link><target>Kentucky</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Delaware</target></link><space/>were not emancipated until the Thirteenth Amendment was ratified.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Implementation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emancipation Proclamation.PNG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Areas covered by the Emancipation Proclamation are in red. Slave holding areas not covered are in blue.</part></link><template><target>further</target><arg>Slave and free states</arg></template>The Proclamation was issued in two parts. The first part, issued on September 22, 1862, was a preliminary announcement outlining the intent of the second part, which officially went into effect 100 days later on January 1, 1863, during the second year of the Civil War. It was Abraham Lincoln's declaration that all slaves would be permanently freed in all areas of the Confederacy that had not already returned to federal control by January 1863. The ten affected states were individually named in the second part (South Carolina, Mississippi, Florida, Alabama, Georgia, Louisiana, Texas, Virginia, Arkansas, North Carolina). Not included were the<space/><link><target>Union (American Civil War)</target><part>Union</part></link><space/><link><target>slave state</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Delaware</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Missouri</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kentucky</target></link>. Also not named was the state of<space/><link><target>Tennessee</target></link>, in which a Union-controlled military government had already been set up, based in the capital, Nashville. Specific exemptions were stated for areas also under Union control on January 1, 1863, namely 48 counties that would soon become<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link>, seven other named counties of<space/><link><target>Virginia</target></link><space/>including Berkeley and Hampshire counties, which were soon added to West Virginia,<space/><link><target>New Orleans</target></link><space/>and 13 named parishes nearby.</paragraph><paragraph>Union-occupied areas of the Confederate states where the proclamation was put into immediate effect by local commanders included Winchester, Virginia,<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Duncan, Beleaguered Winchester: A Virginia Community at War (Baton Rouge, LA: LSU Press, 2007), pp. 13940</extension><space/>Corinth, Mississippi,<extension extension_name='ref'>Ira Berlin et al., eds, Freedom: A Documentary History of Emancipation 18611867, Vol. 1: The Destruction of Slavery (Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press, 1985), p. 260</extension><space/>the Sea Islands along the coasts of the Carolinas and Georgia,<extension extension_name='ref'>William Klingaman, Abraham Lincoln and the Road to Emancipation, 18611865 (NY: Viking Press, 2001), p. 234</extension><space/>Key West, Florida,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Important From Key West&quot;,<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics><space/>February 4, 1863, p. 1</extension><space/>and Port Royal, South Carolina.<extension extension_name='ref' name="New York Times January 9, 1863, p. 2"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1863/01/09/news/interesting-port-royal-jubliee-among-negroes-first-president-s-emancipation.html?scp</arg><arg name="title">Interesting from Port Royal<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 9, 1863<space/></arg><arg name="page">2<space/></arg><arg name="first">Our<space/></arg><arg name="last">Own</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Immediate impact</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:SlaveChildrenUnknown.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>A circa 1870 photograph of two children who were likely recently emancipated.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>It has been inaccurately claimed that the Emancipation Proclamation did not free a single slave;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">James M. Paradis</arg><arg name="title">African Americans and the Gettysburg Campaign</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Scarecrow Press</arg><arg name="page">90</arg></template></extension><space/>black author<space/><link><target>Lerone Bennett, Jr.</target></link><space/>alleged that the proclamation was a hoax deliberately designed not to free any slaves.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Kenneth L. Deutsch</arg><arg name="author2">Joseph Fornieri</arg><arg name="title">Lincoln's American Dream: Clashing Political Perspectives</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Potomac Books</arg><arg name="page">35</arg></template></extension><space/>However, as a result of the Proclamation, many slaves were freed during the course of the war, beginning with the day it took effect; eyewitness accounts at places such as Hilton Head, South Carolina,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;News from South Carolina: Negro Jubilee at Hilton Head&quot;,<space/><italics>New York Herald</italics>, January 7, 1863, p. 5</extension><space/>and Port Royal, South Carolina<extension extension_name='ref' name="New York Times January 9, 1863, p. 2"></extension><space/>record celebrations on January 1 as thousands of blacks were informed of their new legal status of freedom. Estimates of how many thousands of slaves were freed immediately by the Emancipation Proclamation are varied. One contemporary estimate put the 'contraband' population of Union-occupied North Carolina at 10,000, and the Sea Islands of South Carolina also had a substantial population. Those 20,000 slaves were freed immediately by the Emancipation Proclamation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIFBEP">Poulter, Keith &quot;Slaves Immediately Freed by the Emancipation Proclamation&quot;,<space/><italics>North &amp; South</italics><space/>vol. 5 no. 1 (December 2001), p. 48</extension><space/>This Union-occupied zone where freedom began at once included parts of eastern North Carolina, the Mississippi Valley, northern Alabama, the Shenandoah Valley of Virginia, a large part of Arkansas, and the Sea Islands of Georgia and South Carolina.<extension extension_name='ref'>Harris, &quot;After the Emancipation Proclamation&quot;, p. 45</extension><space/>Although some counties of Union-occupied Virginia were exempted from the Proclamation, the lower Shenandoah Valley, and the area around Alexandria were covered.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SIFBEP"></extension><space/>Emancipation was immediately enforced as Union soldiers advanced into the Confederacy. Slaves fled their masters and were often assisted by Union soldiers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Allen C. Guelzo</arg><arg name="title">Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation: The End of Slavery in America</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Simon & Schuster</arg><arg name="pages">107–8</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Booker T. Washington</target></link>, as a boy of 9 in Virginia, remembered the day in early 1865:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Booker T. Washington</arg><arg name="title">Up From Slavery: an autobiography</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1907</arg><arg name="publisher">Doubleday, Page</arg><arg name="pages">19–21</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>As the great day drew nearer, there was more singing in the slave quarters than usual. It was bolder, had more ring, and lasted later into the night. Most of the verses of the plantation songs had some reference to freedom. ... Some man who seemed to be a stranger (a United States officer, I presume) made a little speech and then read a rather long paper—the Emancipation Proclamation, I think. After the reading we were told that we were all free, and could go when and where we pleased. My mother, who was standing by my side, leaned over and kissed her children, while tears of joy ran down her cheeks. She explained to us what it all meant, that this was the day for which she had been so long praying, but fearing that she would never live to see.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Emancipation took place without violence by masters or ex-slaves. The Proclamation represented a shift in the war objectives of the Northreuniting the nation was no longer the only goal. It represented a major step toward the ultimate abolition of<space/><link><target>slavery in the United States</target></link><space/>and a &quot;new birth of freedom&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Runaway slaves who had escaped to Union lines had previously been held by the Union Army as &quot;contraband of war&quot; under the<space/><link><target>Confiscation Acts</target></link>; when the proclamation took effect, they were told at midnight that they were free to leave. The<space/><link><target>Sea Islands</target></link><space/>off the coast of<space/><link><target>Georgia (U.S. state)</target><part>Georgia</part></link><space/>had been occupied by the Union Navy earlier in the war. The whites had fled to the mainland while the blacks stayed. An early program of<space/><link><target>Reconstruction Era of the United States</target><part>Reconstruction</part></link><space/>was set up for the former slaves, including schools and training. Naval officers read the proclamation and told them they were free.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:A Visit from the Old Mistress.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>Winslow Homer's 1876 &quot;A Visit from the Old Mistress&quot; depicts a tense meeting between a group of newly freed slaves and their former slaveholder.<space/><link><target>Smithsonian Museum of American Art</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Slaves had been part of the &quot;engine of war&quot; for the Confederacy. They produced and prepared food; sewed uniforms; repaired railways; worked on farms and in factories, shipping yards, and mines; built fortifications; and served as hospital workers and common laborers. News of the Proclamation spread rapidly by word of mouth, arousing hopes of freedom, creating general confusion, and encouraging thousands to escape to Union lines.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Goodheart</arg><arg name="first">Adam</arg><arg name="title">1861: The Civil War Awakening</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Knopf Doubleday Publishing Group</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg></template></extension><space/>George Washington Albright, a teenage slave in<space/><link><target>Mississippi</target></link>, recalled that like many of his fellow slaves, his father escaped to join Union forces. According to Albright, plantation owners tried to keep the Proclamation from slaves but news of it came through the &quot;grapevine&quot;. The young slave became a &quot;runner&quot; for an informal group they called the<space/><italics>4Ls</italics><space/>(&quot;Lincoln's Legal Loyal League&quot;) bringing news of the proclamation to secret slave meetings at plantations throughout the region.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jenkins, Sally, and John Stauffer.<space/><italics>The State of Jones</italics>. New York: Anchor Books edition/Random House, c. 2009 (2010). ISBN 978-0-7679-2946-2, p. 42</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Robert E. Lee</target></link><space/>saw the Emancipation Proclamation as a way for the Union to bolster the number of soldiers it could place on the field, making it imperative for the Confederacy to increase their own numbers.</paragraph><paragraph>Writing on the matter after the sack of Fredericksburg, Lee wrote &quot;In view of the vast increase of the forces of the enemy, of the savage and brutal policy he has proclaimed, which leaves us no alternative but success or degradation worse than death, if we would save the honor of our families from pollution, our social system from destruction, let every effort be made, every means be employed, to fill and maintain the ranks of our armies, until God, in his mercy, shall bless us with the establishment of our independence.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Civil War, a Narrative: Fredericksburg to Meridian</arg><arg name="author">Shelby Foote</arg><arg name="volume">Volume 2</arg><arg name="year">1963</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg></template></extension><space/>Lee's request for a drastic increase of troops would go unfulfilled.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Political impact</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:TRUMP.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>&quot;Abe Lincoln's Last Card; Or, Rouge-et-Noir (Red and Black)&quot;; ''Punch'', Volume 43, October 18, 1862, p.&amp;nbsp;161. a cartoon by the Englishman<space/><link><target>John Tenniel</target></link>, after the ''London Times'' stated that Lincoln had played his &quot;last card&quot; in issuing the Proclamation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.millikensbend.org/articles-docs/london-times/lt-01-003.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">London Times Editorial<space/></arg><arg name="date">Oct 6, 1862<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-28</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.mrlincolnandfreedom.org/inside.asp?ID</arg><arg name="title">International Reaction</arg></template></extension><space/>Lincoln's hair is in points, suggesting horns. The cartoon was often reprinted in the<space/><link><target>Copperheads (politics)</target><part>Copperhead</part></link><space/>press.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.arthist.umn.edu/aict/Tennielweb/punch/621018.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Abe Lincoln's Last Card</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">Abraham Lincoln, a press portrait: his life and times from the original newspaper documents of the Union, the Confederacy, and Europe<space/></arg><arg name="first">Herbert<space/></arg><arg name="last">Mitgang<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fordham Univ Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8232-2062-5</arg></template></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Proclamation was immediately denounced by<space/><link><target>Copperheads (politics)</target><part>Copperhead Democrats</part></link><space/>who opposed the war and advocated restoring the union by allowing slavery.<space/><link><target>Horatio Seymour</target></link>, while running for the governorship of New York, cast the Emancipation Proclamation as a call for slaves to commit extreme acts of violence on all white southerners, saying it was &quot;a proposal for the butchery of women and children, for scenes of lust and rapine, and of arson and murder, which would invoke the interference of civilized Europe&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Copperheads: the rise and fall of Lincoln's opponents in the North</arg><arg name="last">Weber</arg><arg name="first">Jennifer L.</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York, New York</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension><space/>The Copperheads also saw the Proclamation as an unconstitutional abuse of Presidential power. Editor Henry A. Reeves wrote in Greenport's<space/><italics>Republican Watchman</italics><space/>that &quot;In the name of freedom of Negroes, [the proclamation] imperils the liberty of white men; to test a utopian theory of equality of races which Nature, History and Experience alike condemn as monstrous, it overturns the Constitution and Civil Laws and sets up Military Usurpation in their Stead.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Racism remained pervasive on both sides of the conflict and many in the North supported the war only as an effort to force the South to stay in the Union. The promises of many Republican politicians that the war was to restore the Union and not about black rights or ending slavery, were now declared lies by their opponents citing the Proclamation. Copperhead David Allen spoke to a rally in Columbiana, Ohio, stating &quot;I have told you that this war is carried on for the Negro. There is the proclamation of the President of the United States. Now fellow Democrats I ask you if you are going to be forced into a war against your Brithren of the Southern States for the Negro. I answer No!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">[http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The Copperheads saw the Proclamation as irrefutable proof of their position and the beginning of a political rise for their members; in Connecticut, H. B. Whiting wrote that the truth was now plain even to &quot;those stupid thick-headed persons who persisted in thinking that the President was a conservative man and that the war was for the restoration of the Union under the Constitution&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>War Democrats</target></link><space/>who rejected the Copperhead position within their party, found themselves in a quandary. While throughout the war they had continued to espouse the racist positions of their party and their disdain of the concerns of slaves, they did see the Proclamation as a viable military tool against the South, and worried that opposing it might demoralize troops in the Union army. The question would continue to trouble them and eventually lead to a split within their party as the war progressed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lincoln further alienated many in the Union two days after issuing the preliminary copy of the Emancipation Proclamation by<space/><link><target>Habeas corpus in the United States#Suspension during the Civil War</target><part>suspending habeas corpus</part></link>. His opponents linked these two actions in their claims that he was becoming a despot. In light of this and a lack of military success for the Union armies, many War Democrat voters who had previously supported Lincoln turned against him and joined the Copperheads in the off-year elections held in October and November.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>United States House of Representatives elections, 1862</target><part>1862 elections</part></link>, the Democrats gained 28 seats in the House as well as the governorship of<space/><link><target>New York</target></link>. Lincoln's friend Orville Hickman Browning told the President that the Proclamation and the suspension of habeas corpus had been &quot;disastrous&quot; for his party by handing the Democrats so many weapons. Lincoln made no response. Copperhead William Javis of Connecticut pronounced the election the &quot;beginning of the end of the utter downfall of<space/><link><target>Abolitionism in the United States</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Historians James M. McPherson and Allan Nevins state that though the results looked very troubling, they could be seen favorably by Lincoln; his opponents did well only in their historic strongholds and &quot;at the national level their gains in the House were the smallest of any minority party's in an off-year election in nearly a generation. Michigan, California, and Iowa all went Republican.... Moreover, the Republicans picked up five seats in the Senate.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension><space/>McPherson states &quot;If the election was in any sense a referendum on emancipation and on Lincoln's conduct of the war, a majority of Northern voters endorsed these policies.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weber"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The initial Confederate response was one of expected outrage. The Proclamation was seen as vindication for the rebellion, and proof that Lincoln would have abolished slavery even if the states had remained in the Union.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Rebel Message: What Jefferson Davis Has to Say</arg><arg name="url">http://infoweb.newsbank.com/iw-search/we/HistArchive/?p_product</arg><arg name="work">New York Herald</arg><arg name="publisher">America's Historical Newspapers</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>International impact</heading><paragraph>As Lincoln had hoped, the Proclamation turned foreign popular opinion in favor of the Union by gaining the support of anti-slavery countries and countries that had already abolished slavery (especially the developed countries in Europe). This shift ended the Confederacy's hopes of gaining official recognition.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Robert E. May</arg><arg name="title">The Union, the Confederacy, and the Atlantic rim</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Purdue University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-55753-061-5</arg><arg name="pages">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="chapter">History and Mythology : The Crisis over British Intervention in the Civil War</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since the Emancipation Proclamation made the eradication of slavery an explicit Union war goal, it linked support for the South to support for slavery. Public opinion in Britain would not tolerate direct support for slavery. British companies, however, continued to build and operate<space/><link><target>Blockade runners of the American Civil War</target><part>blockade runners</part></link><space/>for the South. As<space/><link><target>Henry Adams</target></link><space/>noted, &quot;The Emancipation Proclamation has done more for us than all our former victories and all our diplomacy.&quot; In Italy,<space/><link><target>Giuseppe Garibaldi</target></link><space/>hailed Lincoln as &quot;the heir of the aspirations of<space/><link><target>John Brown (abolitionist)</target><part>John Brown</part></link>&quot;. On August 6, 1863, Garibaldi wrote to Lincoln:<space/><italics>Posterity will call you the great emancipator, a more enviable title than any crown could be, and greater than any merely mundane treasure</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mack Smith, p. 72</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Alan Van Dyke, a representative for workers from<space/><link><target>Manchester</target></link>, England, wrote to Lincoln saying, &quot;We joyfully honor you for many decisive steps toward practically exemplifying your belief in the words of your great founders: 'All men are created free and equal.'&quot; The Emancipation Proclamation served to ease tensions with Europe over the North's conduct of the war, and combined with the recent failed Southern offensive at<space/><link><target>Battle of Antietam</target><part>Antietam</part></link>, to cut off any practical chance for the Confederacy to receive international support in the war.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Gettysburg Address</heading><paragraph>Lincoln's<space/><link><target>Gettysburg Address</target></link><space/>in November 1863 made indirect reference to the Proclamation and the ending of slavery as a war goal with the phrase &quot;new birth of freedom&quot;. The Proclamation solidified Lincoln's support among the rapidly growing abolitionist element of the Republican Party and ensured they would not block his re-nomination in 1864.<extension extension_name='ref'>Allan Nevins,<space/><italics>Ordeal of the Union: vol 6. War Becomes Revolution, 18621863</italics><space/>(1960)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Postbellum</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:EMANCI4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Emancipation from Freedmen's viewpoint; illustration from ''<link><target>Harper's Weekly</target></link>'' 1865</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Near the end of the war, abolitionists were concerned that the Emancipation Proclamation would be construed solely as a war measure, Lincoln's original intent, and would no longer apply once fighting ended. They were also increasingly anxious to secure the freedom of all slaves, not just those freed by the Emancipation Proclamation. Thus pressed, Lincoln staked a large part of his 1864 presidential campaign on a constitutional amendment to abolish slavery uniformly throughout the United States. Lincoln's campaign was bolstered by separate votes in both Maryland and Missouri to abolish slavery in those states. Maryland's new constitution abolishing slavery took effect in November 1864. Slavery in Missouri was ended by executive proclamation of its governor, Thomas C. Fletcher, on January 11, 1865.</paragraph><paragraph>Winning re-election, Lincoln pressed the<space/><link><target>lame duck (politics)</target><part>lame duck</part></link><space/><link><target>38th United States Congress</target><part>38th Congress</part></link><space/>to pass the proposed amendment immediately rather than wait for the incoming<space/><link><target>39th United States Congress</target><part>39th Congress</part></link><space/>to convene. In January 1865, Congress sent to the state legislatures for ratification what became the<space/><link><target>Thirteenth Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>Thirteenth Amendment</part></link>, banning slavery in all<space/><link><target>U.S. state</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and territories. The amendment was ratified by the legislatures of enough states by December 6, 1865, and proclaimed 12 days later. There were about 40,000 slaves in Kentucky and 1,000 in Delaware who were liberated then.<extension extension_name='ref' name="1860Census"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Critiques</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Abraham Lincoln and slavery</arg></template>As the years went on and American life continued to be deeply unfair towards blacks, cynicism towards Lincoln and the Emancipation Proclamation increased. Perhaps the strongest attack was<space/><link><target>Lerone Bennett, Jr.</target><part>Lerone Bennett's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Forced into Glory: Abraham Lincoln's White Dream</target></link></italics><space/>(2000), which claimed that Lincoln was a white supremacist who issued the Emancipation Proclamation in lieu of the real racial reforms for which radical abolitionists pushed. In his<space/><italics>Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation</italics>,<space/><link><target>Allen C. Guelzo</target></link><space/>noted the professional historians' lack of substantial respect for the document, since it has been the subject of few major scholarly studies. He argued that Lincoln was America's &quot;last<space/><link><target>Age of Enlightenment</target><part>Enlightenment</part></link><space/><link><target>politician</target></link>&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Guelzo</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">[http://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and as such was dedicated to removing slavery strictly within the bounds of law.</paragraph><paragraph>Other historians have given more credit to Lincoln for what he accomplished within the tensions of his cabinet and a society at war, for his own growth in political and moral stature, and for the promise he held out to the slaves.<extension extension_name='ref'>Doris Kearns Goodwin,<space/><italics>A Team of Rivals</italics>, New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 2005</extension><space/>More might have been accomplished if he had not been assassinated. As<space/><link><target>Eric Foner</target></link><space/>wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Lincoln was not an abolitionist or Radical Republican, a point Bennett reiterates innumerable times. He did not favor immediate abolition before the war, and held racist views typical of his time. But he was also a man of deep convictions when it came to slavery, and during the Civil War displayed a remarkable capacity for moral and political growth.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ericfoner.com/reviews/040900latimes.html<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20041027065400/http://www.ericfoner.com/reviews/040900latimes.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2004-10-27<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no<space/></arg><arg name="title">review of ''Forced into Glory: Abraham Lincoln's White Dream'' by Lerone Bennett, Jr.<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eric<space/></arg><arg name="last">Foner<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Los Angeles Times Book Review<space/></arg><arg name="date">April 9, 2000<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-23</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Kal Ashraf wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Perhaps in rejecting the critical dualismLincoln as individual emancipator pitted against collective self-emancipatorsthere is an opportunity to recognise the greater persuasiveness of the combination. In a sense, yes: a racist, flawed Lincoln did something heroic, and not in lieu of collective participation, but next to, and enabled, by it. To venerate a singular Great Emancipator' may be as reductive as dismissing the significance of Lincoln's actions. Who he was as a man, no one of us can ever really know. So it is that the version of Lincoln we keep is also the version we make.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.baas.ac.uk/resources/american-studies-in-britain-the-baas-newsletter/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Editorial in American Studies in Britain (108: Spring 2013) iSSN 1465-9956<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kal<space/></arg><arg name="last">Ashraf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">British Association for American Studies<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 2013<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-03-28</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy in the Civil Rights Era</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:President Barack Obama views the Emancipation Proclamation in the Oval Office 2010-01-18.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>President<space/><link><target>Barack Obama</target></link><space/>views the Emancipation Proclamation in the Oval Office next to a bust of Martin Luther King, Jr.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</heading><paragraph><link><target>Martin Luther King Jr.</target><part>Dr. Martin Luther King Jr.</part></link><space/>made many references to the Emancipation Proclamation during the<space/><link><target>African-American Civil Rights Movement (195568)</target><part>Civil Rights Movement</part></link>. These include a speech made at an observance of the hundredth anniversary of the issuing of the Proclamation made in New York City on September 12, 1962 where he placed it alongside the Declaration of Independence as an &quot;imperishable&quot; contribution to civilization, and &quot;All tyrants, past, present and future, are powerless to bury the truths in these declarations&quot;. He lamented that despite a history where America &quot;proudly professed the basic principles inherent in both documents&quot;, it &quot;sadly practiced the antithesis of these principles&quot;. He concluded &quot;There is but one way to commemorate the Emancipation Proclamation. That is to make its declarations of freedom real; to reach back to the origins of our nation when our message of equality electrified an unfree world, and reaffirm democracy by deeds as bold and daring as the issuance of the Emancipation Proclamation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nps.gov/anti/historyculture/mlk-ep.htm</arg><arg name="title">Dr. Martin Luther King on the Emancipation Proclamation</arg><arg name="publisher">National Park Service</arg><arg name="author">Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>King's most famous invocation of the Emancipation Proclamation was in a speech from the steps of the Lincoln Memorial at the 1963<space/><link><target>March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom</target></link><space/>(often referred to as the &quot;<link><target>I Have a Dream</target></link>&quot; speech). King began the speech saying &quot;Five score years ago, a great American, in whose symbolic shadow we stand, signed the Emancipation Proclamation. This momentous decree came as a great beacon light of hope to millions of Negro slaves who had been seared in the flames of withering injustice. It came as a joyous daybreak to end the long night of captivity. But one hundred years later, we must face the tragic fact that the Negro is still not free. One hundred years later, the life of the Negro is still sadly crippled by the manacles of segregation and the chains of discrimination.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thekingcenter.org/archive/document/i-have-dream</arg><arg name="title">I Have A Dream</arg><arg name="publisher">The King Center</arg><arg name="date">August 28, 1963</arg><arg name="author">Dr. Marin Luther King, Jr.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>The &quot;Second Emancipation Proclamation&quot;</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Second Emancipation Proclamation</arg></template>In the early 1960s Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and his associates developed a strategy to call on President<space/><link><target>John F. Kennedy</target></link><space/>to bypass a Southern segregationist opposition in the Congress by issuing an<space/><link><target>Executive Order</target></link><space/>to put an end to segregation. This envisioned document was referred to as the &quot;Second Emancipation Proclamation&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>President John F. Kennedy</heading><paragraph>On June 11, 1963, President Kennedy appeared on national television to address the issue of civil rights. Kennedy, who had been routinely criticized as timid by some of the leaders of the civil rights movement, told Americans that<space/><link><target>Stand in the Schoolhouse Door</target><part>two black students had been peacefully enrolled</part></link><space/>in the University of Alabama with the aid the National Guard despite the opposition of Governor<space/><link><target>George Wallace</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>John Kennedy called it a &quot;moral issue&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peniel"></extension><space/>Invoking the centennial of the Emancipation Proclamation he said &quot;One hundred years of delay have passed since President Lincoln freed the slaves, yet their heirs, their grandsons, are not fully free. They are not yet freed from the bonds of injustice. They are not yet freed from social and economic oppression. And this Nation, for all its hopes and all its boasts, will not be fully free until all its citizens are free. We preach freedom around the world, and we mean it, and we cherish our freedom here at home, but are we to say to the world, and much more importantly, to each other that this is a land of the free except for the Negroes; that we have no second-class citizens except Negroes; that we have no class or caste system, no ghettoes, no master race except with respect to Negroes? Now the time has come for this Nation to fulfill its promise. The<space/><link><target>Birmingham campaign</target><part>events in Birmingham</part></link><space/>and elsewhere have so increased the cries for equality that no city or State or legislative body can prudently choose to ignore them.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">237 - Radio and Television Report to the American People on Civil Rights</arg><arg name="date">June 11, 1963</arg><arg name="author">John F. Kennedy</arg><arg name="url">http://www.presidency.ucsb.edu/ws/index.php?pid</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the same speech Kennedy announced he would introduce comprehensive civil rights legislation to the United States Congress which he did a week later (he continued to push for its passage until his assassination in November 1963). Historian Peniel E. Joseph holds Lyndon Johnson's ability to get that bill, the<space/><link><target>Civil Rights Act of 1964</target></link>, passed on July 2, 1964 was aided by &quot;the moral forcefulness of the June 11 speech&quot; which turned &quot;the narrative of civil rights from a regional issue into a national story promoting racial equality and democratic renewal&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Peniel"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Kennedy's Finest Moment<space/></arg><arg name="author">Peniel E. Joseph<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 10, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2013/06/11/opinion/kennedys-civil-rights-triumph.html?hp<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">The New York Times</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>President Lyndon B. Johnson</heading><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>African-American Civil Rights Movement (19551968)</target><part>American Civil Rights movement of the 1960s</part></link><space/><link><target>Lyndon B. Johnson</target></link><space/>invoked the Emancipation Proclamation holding it up as a promise yet to be fully implemented.</paragraph><paragraph>As Vice President while speaking from Gettysburg on May 30, 1963 (Memorial Day), at the centennial of the Emancipation Proclamation, Johnson connected it directly with the ongoing Civil Rights struggles of the time saying &quot;One hundred years ago, the slave was freed. One hundred years later, the Negro remains in bondage to the color of his skin.... In this hour, it is not our respective races which are at stakeit is our nation. Let those who care for their country come forward, North and South, white and Negro, to lead the way through this moment of challenge and decision.... Until justice is blind to color, until education is unaware of race, until opportunity is unconcerned with color of men's skins, emancipation will be a proclamation but not a fact. To the extent that the proclamation of emancipation is not fulfilled in fact, to that extent we shall have fallen short of assuring freedom to the free.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Remarks of Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson</arg><arg name="date">May 30, 1963</arg><arg name="url">http://www.lbjlib.utexas.edu/johnson/archives.hom/speeches.hom/630530.asp</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As President, Johnson again invoked the proclamation in a speech presenting the<space/><link><target>Voting Rights Act</target></link><space/>at a joint session of Congress on Monday, March 15, 1965. This was one week after violence had been inflicted on peaceful civil rights marchers during the<space/><link><target>Selma to Montgomery marches</target></link>. Johnson said &quot;... it's not just Negroes, but really it's all of us, who must overcome the crippling legacy of bigotry and injustice. And<space/><link><target>We Shall Overcome#Use in the 1960s civil rights and other protest movements</target><part>we shall overcome</part></link>. As a man whose roots go deeply into Southern soil, I know how agonizing racial feelings are. I know how difficult it is to reshape the attitudes and the structure of our society. But a century has passedmore than 100 yearssince the Negro was freed. And he is not fully free tonight. It was more than 100 years ago that Abraham Lincolna great President of another partysigned the Emancipation Proclamation. But emancipation is a proclamation and not a fact. A century has passedmore than 100 yearssince equality was promised, and yet the Negro is not equal. A century has passed since the day of promise, and the promise is unkept. The time of justice has now come, and I tell you that I believe sincerely that no force can hold it back. It is right in the eyes of man and God that it should come, and when it does, I think that day will brighten the lives of every American.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">We Shall Overcome</arg><arg name="author">Lyndon B. Johnson</arg><arg name="date">March 15, 1965</arg><arg name="url">http://www.historyplace.com/speeches/johnson.htm</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emancipation Proclamation 1963 U.S. stamp.1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>210px</part><part>U.S. commemorative, 1963<extension extension_name='ref' name="Emancipation Proclamation Issue">&quot;<link type='external' href='http://arago.si.edu/flash/?tid=2027477'>|s1=1 Emancipation Proclamation Issue</link>&quot;, Arago: people, postage &amp; the post, Smithsonian National Postal Museum, viewed September 28, 2014</extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>List of The Andy Griffith Show episodes#Season Four (1963-64)</target><part>episode 86</part></link><space/>of<space/><italics><link><target>The Andy Griffith Show</target></link></italics>, Andy asks<space/><link><target>Barney Fife</target><part>Barney</part></link><space/>to explain the Emancipation Proclamation to<space/><link><target>Opie Taylor</target><part>Opie</part></link><space/>who is struggling with history at school.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tvland.com/shows/andy-griffith-show/episode-guide/season-3</arg><arg name="title">Episode Guide</arg><arg name="work">[http://www.tvland.com/shows/andy-griffith-show/ The Andy Griffith Show]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[TV Land]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Barney brags about his history expertise, yet it is apparent he cannot answer Andy's question. He finally becomes frustrated and explains it is a proclamation for certain people who wanted emancipation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="title">Barney Fife Explains The Emancipation Proclamation</arg><arg name="work">Episode clip, The Andy Griffith Show</arg><arg name="publisher">[[YouTube]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Emancipation Proclamation is celebrated around the world including on stamps of nations &lt;/ref&gt; The United States commemorative was issued on August 16, 1963, the opening day of the Century of Negro Progress Exposition in Chicago, Illinois. Designed by Georg Olden, an initial printing of 120 million stamps was authorized.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Emancipation Proclamation Issue"></extension><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Tall image</target><arg>Emancipation_Proclamation_in_the_National_Republican,_9-23-1862.png</arg><arg>350</arg><arg>150</arg><arg>Preliminary Emancipation Proclamation - printed in the September 23, 1862, National Republican, Washington D.C.</arg><arg>right</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Abolition of slavery timeline</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Act Prohibiting the Return of Slaves</target></link><space/>1862 statute</listitem><listitem><link><target>African-American Civil Rights Movement (195468)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>District of Columbia Compensated Emancipation Act</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of slavery in Kentucky</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of slavery in Missouri</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Slavery Abolition Act 1833</target></link><space/>an act passed by the British parliament abolishing slavery in British colonies with compensation to the owners</listitem><listitem><link><target>Slave Trade Act</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of the African-American Civil Rights Movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>War Governors' Conference</target></link><space/>gave Lincoln the much needed political support to issue the Proclamation</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Belz, Herman.<space/><italics>Emancipation and Equal Rights: Politics and Constitutionalism in the Civil War Era</italics><space/>(1978)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=103250477'>online</link></listitem><listitem>Biddle, Daniel R., and Murray Dubin. &quot;'God Is Settling the Account': African American Reaction to Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation&quot;,<space/><italics>Pennsylvania Magazine of History and Biography</italics><space/>(Jan. 2013) 137#1 5778.</listitem><listitem>Crowther, Edward R. &quot;Emancipation Proclamation&quot;. in<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of the American Civil War.</italics><space/>Heidler, David S. and Heidler, Jeanne T. (2000) ISBN 0-393-04758-X</listitem><listitem>Chambers Jr, Henry L. &quot;Lincoln, the Emancipation Proclamation, and Executive Power.&quot;<space/><italics>Maryland Law Review</italics><space/>73 (2013): 100+<space/><link type='external' href='http://digitalcommons.law.umaryland.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=3599&amp;amp;context=mlr'>online</link></listitem><listitem>Ewan, Christopher. &quot;The Emancipation Proclamation and British Public Opinion&quot;<space/><italics>The Historian</italics>, Vol. 67, 2005</listitem><listitem>Franklin, John Hope.<space/><italics>The Emancipation Proclamation</italics><space/>(1963)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=10793158'>online</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikicite</target><arg name="reference">Foner, Eric. ''The Fiery Trial: Abraham Lincoln and American Slavery'' (W.W. Norton, 2010)</arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Foner|2010}}</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Guelzo</arg><arg name="first">Allen C.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation: The End of Slavery in America</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Simon and Schuster</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-7432-9965-7</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Guelzo, Allen C. &quot;How Abe Lincoln Lost the Black Vote: Lincoln and Emancipation in the African American Mind&quot;,<space/><italics>Journal of the Abraham Lincoln Association</italics><space/>(2004) 25#1</listitem><listitem><link><target>Harold Holzer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Edna Greene Medford</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Frank J. Williams</target></link>.<space/><italics>The Emancipation Proclamation: Three Views</italics><space/>(2006)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=6928200'>Howard Jones, ''Abraham Lincoln and a New Birth of Freedom: The Union and Slavery in the Diplomacy of the Civil War'' (1999)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=105216005'>Mitch Kachun, ''Festivals of Freedom: Memory and Meaning in African American Emancipation Celebrations, 18081915'' (2003)</link></listitem><listitem>Kolchin, Peter, &quot;Reexamining Southern Emancipation in Comparative Perspective,&quot;<space/><italics>Journal of Southern History</italics>, 81#1 (Feb. 2015), 7-40.</listitem><listitem>Litwack, Leon F.<space/><italics>Been in the Storm So Long: The Aftermath of Slavery</italics><space/>(1979), social history of the end of slavery in the Confederacy</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Denis</arg><arg name="last">Mack Smith</arg><arg name="title">Garibaldi (Great Lives Observed)</arg><arg name="publisher">Prentice Hall</arg><arg name="location">Englewood Cliffs, N.J.</arg><arg name="year">1969</arg></template></listitem><listitem>McPherson, James M.<space/><italics>Ordeal by Fire: the Civil War and Reconstruction</italics><space/>(2001 [3rd ed.]), esp. pp.&amp;nbsp;316321.</listitem><listitem>Masur, Louis P.<space/><italics>Lincoln's Hundred Days: The Emancipation Proclamation and the War for the Union</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press; 2012)</listitem><listitem>Nevins, Allan.<space/><italics>Ordeal of the Union: vol 6. War Becomes Revolution, 18621863</italics><space/>(1960)</listitem><listitem>Siddali, Silvana R.<space/><italics>From Property To Person: Slavery And The Confiscation Acts, 18611862</italics><space/>(2005)</listitem><listitem>Syrett, John.<space/><italics>Civil War Confiscation Acts: Failing to Reconstruct the South</italics><space/>(2005)</listitem><listitem>Tsesis, Alexander.<space/><italics>We Shall Overcome: A History of Civil Rights and the Law</italics><space/>(2008)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=105900244'>* Vorenberg, Michael. ''Final Freedom: The Civil War, the Abolition of Slavery, and the Thirteenth Amendment'' (2001)</link></listitem><listitem>Vorenberg, Michael, ed.<space/><italics>The Emancipation Proclamation: A Brief History with Documents</italics><space/>(2010), primary and secondary sources</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.questia.com/PM.qst?a=o&amp;amp;d=37435583'>C. Peter Ripley, Roy E. Finkenbine, Michael F. Hembree, Donald Yacovone, ''Witness for Freedom: African American Voices on Race, Slavery, and Emancipation'' (1993)</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>The Emancipation Proclamation</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bl.uk/manuscripts/Viewer.aspx?ref=C.160.c.4.(1)_f001r'>A zoomable image of the Leland-Boker authorized edition of the Emancipation Proclamation held by the British Library</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://edsitement.neh.gov/view_lesson_plan.asp?id=290'>Lesson plan on Emancipation Proclamation from EDSITEment NEH</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/american_originals_iv/sections/emancipation_proclamation.html'>Text and images of the Emancipation Proclamation from the National Archives</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.abrahamlincoln200.org/for-kids/lincoln-coloring-book.aspx'>Online Lincoln Coloring Book for Teachers and Students</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/program/bib/ourdocs/EmanProc.html'>Emancipation Proclamation and related resources at the Library of Congress</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.articlemyriad.com/85.htm'>Scholarly article on rhetoric and the Emancipation Proclamation</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mrlincolnandfreedom.org/inside.asp?ID=39&amp;amp;subjectID=3'>Mr. Lincoln and Freedom: Emancipation Proclamation</link></listitem><listitem>First Edition<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sonofthesouth.net/leefoundation/civil-war/1862/october/emancipation-proclamation.htm'>Emancipation Proclamation</link><space/>in 1862 Harper's Weekly</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.history.umd.edu/Freedmen/chronol.htm'>Chronology of Emancipation during the Civil War</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.anti-slaverysociety.addr.com/hus-emancproc.htm'>&quot;Lincoln's Emancipation Proclamation&quot;</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nysl.nysed.gov/ep/'>Preliminary Emancipation Proclamation at the New York State Library</link><space/>Images and transcript of Lincoln's original manuscript of the preliminary proclamation.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://humorinamerica.wordpress.com/2013/02/21/in-the-archives-lincoln-diversion-1862/'>The role of humor in presenting the Proclamation to Lincoln's Cabinet.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/1865/06/16/news/emancipation-proclamation-interesting-sketch-its-history-artist-carpenter.html?scp=32&amp;amp;sq=emancipation+proclamation&amp;amp;st=p&amp;amp;pagewanted=all'>1865 NY Times article</link><space/>Sketch of its History by Lincoln's portrait artist</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite NIE</target><arg name="wstitle">Emancipation, Proclamation of</arg><arg name="year">1905<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pritzkermilitarylibrary.org/Home/James-McPherson-2012.aspx'>Webcast Discussion</link><space/>with Pulitzer Prize-winning author<space/><link><target>James Alan McPherson</target><part>James McPherson</part></link><space/>and James Cornelius, Curator of the Lincoln Collection in the<space/><link><target>Abraham Lincoln Presidential Library and Museum</target></link><space/>about the 150th anniversary of the Emancipation Proclamation</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Abraham Lincoln</target></template><template><target>American Civil War</target><arg name="expanded">Origins</arg></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Emancipation Proclamation</target></template><link><target>Category:1863 in law</target></link><link><target>Category:1863 works</target></link><link><target>Category:Abolitionism in the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:African Americans in the Civil War</target></link><link><target>Category:American Civil War documents</target></link><link><target>Category:History of the United States (184965)</target></link><link><target>Category:Human rights instruments</target></link><link><target>Category:Presidency of Abraham Lincoln</target></link><link><target>Category:Proclamations</target><part>Emancipation</part></link><link><target>Category:Works about American slavery</target></link></paragraph></article>