<article title='Amplitude_modulation'><paragraph><template><target>Modulation techniques</target></template><bold>Amplitude modulation</bold><space/>(<bold>AM</bold>) is a<space/><link><target>modulation</target></link><space/>technique used in electronic communication, most commonly for transmitting information via a<space/><link><target>radio</target></link><space/><link><target>carrier wave</target></link>. In amplitude modulation, the<space/><link><target>amplitude</target></link><space/>(signal strength) of the carrier wave is varied in proportion to the waveform being transmitted. That waveform may, for instance, correspond to the sounds to be reproduced by a<space/><link><target>loudspeaker</target></link>, or the light intensity of television pixels. This technique contrasts with<space/><link><target>frequency modulation</target></link>, in which the<space/><link><target>frequency</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>carrier signal</target></link><space/>is varied, and<space/><link><target>phase modulation</target></link>, in which its<space/><link><target>Phase (waves)</target><part>phase</part></link><space/>is varied.</paragraph><paragraph>AM was the earliest modulation method used to transmit voice by radio. It was developed during the first two decades of the 20th century beginning with Roberto Landell De Moura and<space/><link><target>Reginald Fessenden</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>radiotelephone</target></link><space/>experiments in 1900.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.aminharadio.com/radio/files/Artigo-Revista-PCP-USA.pdf</extension><space/>It remains in use today in many forms of communication; for example it is used in portable<space/><link><target>two way radio</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Airband</target><part>VHF aircraft radio</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Citizen's Band Radio</target></link><space/>and in computer<space/><link><target>modem</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template><space/>&quot;AM&quot; is often used to refer to<space/><link><target>mediumwave</target></link><space/><link><target>AM broadcasting</target><part>AM radio broadcasting</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Amfm3-en-de.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Fig 1: An audio signal (top) may be carried by a carrier frequency using AM or FM methods.</part><part>alt=Animation of audio, AM and FM modulated carriers.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>Forms of amplitude modulation</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template>In<space/><link><target>electronics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>telecommunications</target></link>,<space/><link><target>modulation</target></link><space/>means varying some aspect of a higher frequency<space/><link><target>continuous wave</target></link><space/><link><target>carrier signal</target></link><space/>with an information-bearing modulation waveform, such as an<space/><link><target>audio signal</target></link><space/>which represents sound, or a<space/><link><target>video signal</target></link><space/>which represents images, so the carrier will &quot;carry&quot; the information. When it reaches its destination, the information signal is extracted from the modulated carrier by<space/><link><target>demodulation</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In amplitude modulation, the<space/><link><target>amplitude</target></link><space/>or &quot;strength&quot; of the carrier oscillations is what is varied. For example, in AM radio communication, a<space/><link><target>continuous wave</target></link><space/>radio-frequency signal (a<space/><link><target>Sine wave</target><part>sinusoid</part><trail>al</trail></link><space/><link><target>carrier wave</target></link>) has its<space/><link><target>amplitude</target></link><space/><link><target>modulation</target><part>modulated</part></link><space/>by an audio waveform before transmission. The audio waveform modifies the amplitude of the carrier wave and determines the<space/><italics><link><target>Envelope (waves)</target><part>envelope</part></link></italics><space/>of the waveform. In the<space/><link><target>frequency domain</target></link>, amplitude modulation produces a signal with power concentrated at the carrier frequency and two adjacent<space/><link><target>sideband</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Each sideband is equal in<space/><link><target>bandwidth (signal processing)</target><part>bandwidth</part></link><space/>to that of the modulating signal, and is a mirror image of the other. Standard AM is thus sometimes called &quot;double-sideband amplitude modulation&quot; (DSB-AM) to distinguish it from more sophisticated modulation methods also based on AM.</paragraph><paragraph>One disadvantage of all amplitude modulation techniques (not only standard AM) is that the receiver amplifies and detects<space/><link><target>Noise (radio)</target><part>noise</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>electromagnetic interference</target></link><space/>in equal proportion to the signal. Increasing the received<space/><link><target>signal to noise ratio</target></link>, say, by a factor of 10 (a 10<space/><link><target>decibel</target></link><space/>improvement), thus would require increasing the transmitter power by a factor of 10. This is in contrast to<space/><link><target>frequency modulation</target></link><space/>(FM) and<space/><link><target>digital radio</target></link><space/>where the effect of such noise following<space/><link><target>demodulation</target></link><space/>is strongly reduced so long as the received signal is well above the threshold for reception. For this reason AM broadcast is not favored for music and<space/><link><target>high fidelity</target></link><space/>broadcasting, but rather for voice communications and broadcasts (sports, news,<space/><link><target>talk radio</target></link><space/>etc.).</paragraph><paragraph>Another disadvantage of AM is that it is inefficient in power usage; at least two-thirds of the power is concentrated in the carrier signal. The carrier signal contains none of the original information being transmitted (voice, video, data, etc.). However its presence provides a simple means of demodulation using<space/><link><target>envelope detector</target><part>envelope detection</part></link>, providing a frequency and phase reference to extract the modulation from the sidebands. In some modulation systems based on AM, a lower transmitter power is required through partial or total elimination of the carrier component, however receivers for these signals are more complex and costly. The receiver may regenerate a copy of the carrier frequency (usually as shifted to the<space/><link><target>intermediate frequency</target></link>) from a greatly reduced &quot;pilot&quot; carrier (in<space/><link><target>reduced-carrier transmission</target></link><space/>or DSB-RC) to use in the demodulation process. Even with the carrier totally eliminated in<space/><link><target>double-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target></link>, carrier regeneration is possible using a<space/><link><target>Costas loop</target><part>Costas phase-locked loop</part></link>. This doesn't work however for<space/><link><target>single-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target></link><space/>(SSB-SC), leading to the characteristic &quot;Donald Duck&quot; sound from such receivers when slightly detuned. Single sideband is nevertheless used widely in<space/><link><target>amateur radio</target></link><space/>and other voice communications both due to its power efficiency and bandwidth efficiency (cutting the RF bandwidth in half compared to standard AM). On the other hand, in<space/><link><target>medium wave</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>short wave</target></link><space/>broadcasting, standard AM with the full carrier allows for reception using inexpensive receivers. The broadcaster absorbs the extra power cost to greatly increase potential audience.</paragraph><paragraph>An additional function provided by the carrier in standard AM, but which is lost in either single or double-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission, is that it provides an amplitude reference. In the receiver, the<space/><link><target>automatic gain control</target></link><space/>(AGC) responds to the carrier so that the reproduced audio level stays in a fixed proportion to the original modulation. On the other hand, with suppressed-carrier transmissions there is<space/><italics>no</italics><space/>transmitted power during pauses in the modulation, so the AGC must respond to peaks of the transmitted power during peaks in the modulation. This typically involves a so-called<space/><italics>fast attack, slow decay</italics><space/>circuit which holds the AGC level for a second or more following such peaks, in between syllables or short pauses in the program. This is very acceptable for communications radios, where<space/><link><target>Dynamic range compression</target><part>compression</part></link><space/>of the audio aids intelligibility. However it is absolutely undesired for music or normal broadcast programming, where a faithful reproduction of the original program, including its varying modulation levels, is expected.</paragraph><paragraph>A trivial form of AM which can be used for transmitting<space/><link><target>Digital data</target><part>binary data</part></link><space/>is<space/><link><target>on-off keying</target></link>, the simplest form of<space/><italics><link><target>amplitude-shift keying</target></link></italics>, in which<space/><link><target>Binary numeral system</target><part>ones and zeros</part></link><space/>are represented by the presence or absence of a carrier. On-off keying is likewise used by radio amateurs to transmit<space/><link><target>Morse code</target></link><space/>where it is known as<space/><link><target>continuous wave</target></link><space/>(CW) operation, even though the transmission is not strictly &quot;continuous.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>ITU designations</heading><paragraph>In 1982, the<space/><link><target>International Telecommunication Union</target></link><space/>(ITU) designated the types of amplitude modulation:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Designation</tablehead><tablehead>Description</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>A3E</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>double sideband</target><part>double-sideband</part></link><space/>a full-carrier - the basic Amplitude modulation scheme</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>R3E</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Single-sideband modulation</target><part>single-sideband</part></link><space/><link><target>Reduced-carrier transmission</target><part>reduced-carrier</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>H3E</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Single-sideband modulation</target><part>single-sideband</part></link><space/>full-carrier</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>J3E</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Single-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target><part>single-sideband suppressed-carrier</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>B8E</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>independent sideband</target><part>independent-sideband</part></link><space/>emission</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>C3F</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>vestigal sideband</target><part>vestigial-sideband</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Lincompex</tablecell><tablecell>linked<space/><link><target>compander</target><part>compressor and expander</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Telefunken arc radiotelephone.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>One of the crude pre-vacuum tube AM transmitters, a Telefunken<space/><link><target>arc converter</target><part>arc transmitter</part></link><space/>from 1906. The carrier wave is generated by 6 electric arcs in the vertical tubes, connected to a<space/><link><target>tuned circuit</target></link>. Modulation is done by the large carbon microphone ''(cone shape)'' in the antenna lead.</part></link><link><target>Image:Meissner radiotelephone transmitter.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>One of the first<space/><link><target>vacuum tube</target></link><space/>AM radio transmitters, built by Meissner in 1913 with an early triode tube by Robert von Lieben. He used it in a historic 36 km (24 mi) voice transmission from Berlin to Nauen, Germany. Compare its small size with above transmitter.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Although AM was used in a few crude experiments in multiplex telegraph and telephone transmission in the late 1800s,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bray"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bray
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John 
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Innovation and the Communications Revolution: From the Victorian Pioneers to Broadband Internet
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Inst. of Electrical Engineers
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>59, 61–62
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/>
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0852962185</arg></template></extension><space/>the practical development of amplitude modulation is synonymous with the development between 1900 and 1920 of &quot;<link><target>radiotelephone</target></link>&quot; transmission, that is, the effort to send sound (audio) by radio waves. The first radio transmitters, called<space/><link><target>spark gap transmitter</target><trail>s</trail></link>, transmitted information by<space/><link><target>wireless telegraphy</target></link>, using different length pulses of carrier wave to spell out text messages in<space/><link><target>Morse code</target></link>. They couldn't transmit audio because the carrier consisted of strings of<space/><link><target>damped wave</target><trail>s</trail></link>, pulses of radio waves that declined to zero, that sounded like a buzz in receivers. In effect they were already amplitude modulated.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Continuous waves</heading><paragraph>The first AM transmission was made by Canadian researcher<space/><link><target>Reginald Fessenden</target></link><space/>on 23 December 1900 using a<space/><link><target>spark gap transmitter</target></link><space/>with a specially designed high frequency 10&amp;nbsp;kHz<space/><link><target>induction coil</target><part>interrupter</part></link>, over a distance of 1 mile (1.6&amp;nbsp;km) at Cobb Island, Maryland, USA. His first transmitted words were, &quot;Hello. One, two, three, four. Is it snowing where you are, Mr. Thiessen?&quot;. The words were barely intelligible above the background buzz of the spark.</paragraph><paragraph>Fessenden was a significant figure in the development of AM radio. He was one of the first researchers to realize, from experiments like the above, that the existing technology for producing radio waves, the spark transmitter, was not usable for amplitude modulation, and that a new kind of transmitter, one that produced<space/><link><target>sinusoidal</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>continuous wave</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics>, was needed. This was a radical idea at the time, because experts believed the impulsive spark was necessary to produce radio frequency waves, and Fessenden was ridiculed. He invented and helped develop one of the first continuous wave transmitters - the<space/><link><target>Alexanderson alternator</target></link>, with which he made what is considered the first AM public entertainment broadcast on Christmas Eve, 1906. He also discovered the principle on which AM modulation is based,<space/><link><target>heterodyne</target><part>heterodyning</part></link>, and invented one of the first<space/><link><target>detector (radio)</target><part>detector</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>able to<space/><link><target>rectifier</target><part>rectify</part></link><space/>and receive AM, the electrolytic detector or &quot;liquid baretter&quot;, in 1902. Other radio detectors invented for wireless telegraphy, such as the<space/><link><target>Fleming valve</target></link><space/>(1904) and the<space/><link><target>crystal detector</target></link><space/>(1906) also proved able to rectify AM signals, so the technological hurdle was generating AM waves; receiving them was not a problem.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early technologies</heading><paragraph>Early experiments in AM radio transmission, conducted by Fessenden, Valdamar Poulsen, Ernst Ruhmer,<space/><link><target>Quirino Majorana</target></link>, Charles Harrold, and<space/><link><target>Lee De Forest</target></link>, were hampered by the lack of a technology for<space/><link><target>amplifier</target><part>amplification</part></link>. The first practical continuous wave AM<space/><link><target>transmitter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were based on either the huge, expensive<space/><link><target>Alexanderson alternator</target></link>, developed 1906-1910, or versions of the<space/><link><target>Poulsen arc</target></link><space/>transmitter (arc converter), invented in 1903. The modifications necessary to transmit AM were clumsy and resulted in very low quality audio. Modulation was usually accomplished by a carbon<space/><link><target>microphone</target></link><space/>inserted directly in the antenna or ground wire; its varying resistance varied the current to the antenna. The limited power handling ability of the microphone severely limited the power of the first radiotelephones; many of the microphones were water-cooled.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Vacuum tubes</heading><paragraph>The discovery in 1912 of the amplifying ability of the<space/><link><target>Audion</target></link><space/><link><target>vacuum tube</target></link>, invented in 1906 by<space/><link><target>Lee De Forest</target></link>, solved these problems. The vacuum tube<space/><link><target>electronic oscillator</target><part>feedback oscillator</part></link>, invented in 1912 by<space/><link><target>Edwin Armstrong</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexander Meissner</target></link>, was a cheap source of<space/><link><target>continuous wave</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and could be easily<space/><link><target>modulation</target><part>modulated</part></link><space/>to make an AM transmitter. Modulation did not have to be done at the output but could be applied to the signal before the final amplifier tube, so the microphone or other audio source didn't have to handle high power. Wartime research greatly advanced the art of AM modulation, and after the war the availability of cheap tubes sparked a great increase in the number of radio stations experimenting with AM transmission of news or music. The vacuum tube was responsible for the rise of<space/><link><target>AM broadcasting</target><part>AM radio broadcasting</part></link><space/>around 1920, the first electronic<space/><link><target>mass communication</target><part>mass entertainment</part></link><space/>medium. Amplitude modulation was virtually the only type used for<space/><link><target>radio broadcasting</target></link><space/>until<space/><link><target>FM broadcasting</target></link><space/>began after World War 2.</paragraph><paragraph>At the same time as AM radio began,<space/><link><target>telephone company</target><part>telephone companies</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>AT&amp;T</target></link><space/>were developing the other large application for AM: sending multiple telephone calls through a single wire by modulating them on separate<space/><link><target>carrier signal</target><part>carrier</part></link><space/>frequencies, called<space/><italics><link><target>frequency division multiplexing</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bray"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Single-sideband</heading><paragraph>John Renshaw Carson in 1915 did the first mathematical analysis of amplitude modulation, showing that a signal and carrier frequency combined in a nonlinear device would create two sidebands on either side of the carrier frequency, and passing the modulated signal through another nonlinear device would extract the original baseband signal.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bray"></extension><space/>His analysis also showed only one sideband was necessary to transmit the audio signal, and Carson patented<space/><link><target>single-sideband modulation</target></link><space/>(SSB) on 1 December 1915.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bray"></extension><space/>This more advanced variant of amplitude modulation was adopted by AT&amp;T for<space/><link><target>longwave</target></link><space/>transatlantic telephone service beginning 7 January 1927. After WW2 it was developed by the military for aircraft communication.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Simplified analysis of standard AM</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Illustration of Amplitude Modulation.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>391x391px</part><part>Illustration of Amplitude Modulation</part></link>Consider a carrier wave (sine wave) of frequency<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>and amplitude<space/><italics>A</italics><space/>given by:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>c(t) = A\cdot \sin(2 \pi f_c t)\,</extension>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Let<space/><italics>m</italics>(<italics>t</italics>) represent the modulation waveform. For this example we shall take the modulation to be simply a sine wave of a frequency<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>m</xhtml:sub></italics>, a much lower frequency (such as an audio frequency) than<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub></italics>:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>m(t) = M\cdot \cos(2 \pi f_m t + \phi)\,</extension>,</listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>is the amplitude of the modulation. We shall insist that<space/><italics>M</italics>&lt;1 so that<space/><italics>(1+m(t))</italics><space/>is always positive. If<space/><italics>M</italics>&gt;1 then overmodulation occurs and reconstruction of message signal from the transmitted signal would lead in loss of original signal. Amplitude modulation results when the carrier<space/><italics>c(t)</italics><space/>is multiplied by the positive quantity<space/><italics>(1+m(t))</italics>:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><table><tablerow><tablecell><extension extension_name='math'>y(t)\,</extension></tablecell><tablecell><extension extension_name='math'>= [1 + m(t)]\cdot c(t) \,</extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell><extension extension_name='math'>= [1 + M\cdot \cos(2 \pi f_m t + \phi)] \cdot A \cdot \sin(2 \pi f_c t)</extension></tablecell></tablerow></table>In this simple case<space/><italics>M</italics><space/>is identical to the<space/><link><target>#Modulation index</target><part>modulation index</part></link>, discussed below. With<space/><italics>M</italics>=0.5 the amplitude modulated signal<space/><italics>y</italics>(<italics>t</italics>) thus corresponds to the top graph (labelled &quot;50% Modulation&quot;) in Figure 4.</listitem></list><paragraph>Using<space/><link><target>Prosthaphaeresis#The identities</target><part>prosthaphaeresis identities</part></link>,<space/><italics>y</italics>(<italics>t</italics>) can be shown to be the sum of three sine waves:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>y(t) = A\cdot \sin(2 \pi f_c t) + \begin{matrix}\frac{AM}{2} \end{matrix} \left[\sin(2 \pi (f_c + f_m) t + \phi) + \sin(2 \pi (f_c - f_m) t - \phi)\right].\,</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Therefore, the modulated signal has three components: the carrier wave<space/><italics>c(t)</italics><space/>which is unchanged, and two pure sine waves (known as<space/><link><target>sideband</target><trail>s</trail></link>) with frequencies slightly above and below the carrier frequency<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Spectrum</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:AM spectrum.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>Fig 2: Double-sided spectra of baseband and AM signals.</part><part>alt=Diagrams of an AM signal, with formulas</part></link>Of course a useful modulation signal<space/><italics>m(t)</italics><space/>will generally not consist of a single sine wave, as treated above. However, by the principle of<space/><link><target>Fourier decomposition</target></link>,<space/><italics>m(t)</italics><space/>can be expressed as the sum of a number of sine waves of various frequencies, amplitudes, and phases. Carrying out the multiplication of<space/><italics>1+m(t)</italics><space/>with<space/><italics>c(t)</italics><space/>as above then yields a result consisting of a sum of sine waves. Again the carrier<space/><italics>c(t)</italics><space/>is present unchanged, but for each frequency component of<space/><italics>m</italics><space/>at<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>i</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>there are two sidebands at frequencies<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub><space/>+ f<xhtml:sub>i</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>and<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub><space/>- f<xhtml:sub>i</xhtml:sub></italics>. The collection of the former frequencies above the carrier frequency is known as the upper sideband, and those below constitute the lower sideband. In a slightly different way of looking at it, we can consider the modulation<space/><italics>m(t)</italics><space/>to consist of an equal mix of positive and negative frequency components (as results from a formal<space/><link><target>Fourier transform</target></link><space/>of a real valued quantity) as shown in the top of Fig. 2. Then one can view the sidebands as that modulation<space/><italics>m(t)</italics><space/>having simply been shifted in frequency by<space/><italics>f<xhtml:sub>c</xhtml:sub></italics><space/>as depicted at the bottom right of Fig. 2 (formally, the modulated signal also contains identical components at negative frequencies, shown at the bottom left of Fig. 2 for completeness).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:AM signal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>Fig 3: The<space/><link><target>spectrogram</target></link><space/>of an AM voice broadcast shows the two sidebands (green) on either side of the carrier (red) with time proceeding in the vertical direction.</part><part>alt=Sonogram of an AM signal, showing the carrier and both sidebands vertically</part></link>If we just look at the short-term spectrum of modulation, changing as it would for a human voice for instance, then we can plot the frequency content (horizontal axis) as a function of time (vertical axis) as in Fig. 3. It can again be seen that as the modulation frequency content varies, at any point in time there is an upper sideband generated according to those frequencies shifted<space/><italics>above</italics><space/>the carrier frequency, and the same content mirror-imaged in the lower sideband below the carrier frequency. At all times, the carrier itself remains constant, and of greater power than the total sideband power.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Power and spectrum efficiency</heading><paragraph>The RF bandwidth of an AM transmission (refer to Figure 2, but only considering positive frequencies) is twice the bandwidth of the modulating (or &quot;<link><target>baseband</target></link>&quot;) signal, since the upper and lower sidebands around the carrier frequency each have a bandwidth as wide as the highest modulating frequency. Although the bandwidth of an AM signal is narrower than one using<space/><link><target>frequency modulation</target></link><space/>(FM), it is twice as wide as<space/><link><target>single-sideband</target></link><space/>techniques; it thus may be viewed as spectrally inefficient. Within a frequency band, only half as many transmissions (or &quot;channels&quot;) can thus be accommodated. For this reason television employs a variant of single-sideband (known as<space/><link><target>vestigial sideband</target></link>, somewhat of a compromise in terms of bandwidth) in order to reduce the required channel spacing.</paragraph><paragraph>Another improvement over standard AM is obtained through reduction or suppression of the carrier component of the modulated spectrum. In Figure 2 this is the spike in between the sidebands; even with full (100%) sine wave modulation, the power in the carrier component is twice that in the sidebands, yet it carries no unique information. Thus there is a great advantage in efficiency in reducing or totally suppressing the carrier, either in conjunction with elimination of one sideband (<link><target>single-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target></link>) or with both sidebands remaining (<link><target>double sideband suppressed carrier</target></link>). While these suppressed carrier transmissions are efficient in terms of transmitter power, they require more sophisticated receivers employing<space/><link><target>Product detector</target><part>synchronous detection</part></link><space/>and regeneration of the carrier frequency. For that reason, standard AM continues to be widely used, especially in broadcast transmission, to allow for the use of inexpensive receivers using<space/><link><target>envelope detector</target><part>envelope detection</part></link>. Even (analog) television, with a (largely) suppressed lower sideband, includes sufficient carrier power for use of envelope detection. But for communications systems where both transmitters and receivers can be optimized, suppression of both one sideband and the carrier represent a net advantage and are frequently employed.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modulation index</heading><paragraph>The AM modulation index is a measure based on the ratio of the modulation excursions of the RF signal to the level of the unmodulated carrier. It is thus defined as:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>h = \frac{\mathrm{peak\ value\ of\ } m(t)}{A} = \frac{M}{A}<space/></extension><space/></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>M\,</extension><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>A\,</extension><space/>are the modulation amplitude and carrier amplitude, respectively; the modulation amplitude is the peak (positive or negative) change in the RF amplitude from its unmodulated value. Modulation index is normally expressed as a percentage, and may be displayed on a meter connected to an AM transmitter.</paragraph><paragraph>So if<space/><extension extension_name='math'>h=0.5</extension>, carrier amplitude varies by 50% above (and below) its unmodulated level, as is shown in the first waveform, below. For<space/><extension extension_name='math'>h=1.0</extension>, it varies by 100% as shown in the illustration below it. With 100% modulation the wave amplitude sometimes reaches zero, and this represents full modulation using standard AM and is often a target (in order to obtain the highest possible<space/><link><target>signal to noise ratio</target></link>) but mustn't be exceeded. Increasing the modulating signal beyond that point, known as<space/><link><target>overmodulation</target></link>, causes a standard AM modulator (see below) to fail, as the negative excursions of the wave envelope cannot become less than zero, resulting in<space/><link><target>distortion</target></link><space/>(&quot;clipping&quot;) of the received modulation. Transmitters typically incorporate a<space/><link><target>limiter</target></link><space/>circuit to avoid overmodulation, and/or a<space/><link><target>Dynamic range compression</target><part>compressor</part></link><space/>circuit (especially for voice communications) in order to still approach 100% modulation for maximum intelligibility above the noise. Such circuits are sometimes referred to as a<space/><link><target>vogad</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>However it is possible to talk about a modulation index exceeding 100%, without introducing distortion, in the case of<space/><link><target>double-sideband reduced-carrier transmission</target></link>. In that case, negative excursions beyond zero entail a reversal of the carrier phase, as shown in the third waveform below. This cannot be produced using the efficient high-level (output stage) modulation techniques (see below) which are widely used especially in high power<space/><link><target>broadcast</target></link><space/>transmitters. Rather, a special modulator produces such a waveform at a low level followed by a<space/><link><target>linear amplifier</target></link>. What's more, a standard AM receiver using an<space/><link><target>envelope detector</target></link><space/>is incapable of properly demodulating such a signal. Rather, synchronous detection is required. Thus double-sideband transmission is generally<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>referred to as &quot;AM&quot; even though it generates an identical RF waveform as standard AM as long as the modulation index is below 100%. Such systems more often attempt a radical reduction of the carrier level compared to the sidebands (where the useful information is present) to the point of<space/><link><target>double-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target></link><space/>where the carrier is (ideally) reduced to zero. In all such cases the term &quot;modulation index&quot; loses its value as it refers to the ratio of the modulation amplitude to a rather small (or zero) remaining carrier amplitude.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Amplitude Modulated Wave-hm-64.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>center</part><part>Fig 4: Modulation depth. In the diagram, the unmodulated carrier has an amplitude of 1.</part><part>alt=Graphs illustrating how signal intelligibility increases with modulation index, but only up to 100% using standard AM.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>AM modulation methods</arg></template>Modulation methods</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:ammodstage.png</target><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Anode (plate) modulation. A tetrode's plate and screen grid voltage is modulated via an audio transformer. The resistor R1 sets the grid bias; both the input and output are tuned circuits with inductive coupling.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Modulation circuit designs may be classified as low- or high-level (depending on whether they modulate in a low-power domainfollowed by amplification for transmissionor in the high-power domain of the transmitted signal).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Communication Engineering
<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>A.P.Godse and U.A.Bakshi
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Technical Publications
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-81-8431-089-4
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>36
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Low-level generation</heading><paragraph>In modern radio systems, modulated signals are generated via<space/><link><target>digital signal processing</target></link><space/>(DSP). With DSP many types of AM are possible with software control (including DSB with carrier, SSB suppressed-carrier and independent sideband, or ISB). Calculated digital samples are converted to voltages with a<space/><link><target>digital to analog converter</target></link>, typically at a frequency less than the desired RF-output frequency. The analog signal must then be shifted in frequency and<space/><link><target>linear amplifier</target><part>linearly amplified</part></link><space/>to the desired frequency and power level (linear amplification must be used to prevent modulation distortion).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>American Radio Relay League
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The ARRL Handbook for Radio Communications
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Silver<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Ward
</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Eighty-eighth
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Ch. 15 DSP and Software Radio Design
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-87259-096-0</arg></template></extension>This low-level method for AM is used in many Amateur Radio transceivers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>American Radio Relay League
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The ARRL Handbook for Radio Communications
</arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Silver<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Ward
</arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Eighty-eighth
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Ch. 14 Transceivers
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-87259-096-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>AM may also be generated at a low level, using analog methods described in the next section.</paragraph><heading level='3'>High-level generation</heading><paragraph>High-power AM<space/><link><target>transmitter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(such as those used for<space/><link><target>AM broadcasting</target></link>) are based on high-efficiency<space/><link><target>Class-D amplifier</target><part>class-D</part></link><space/>and class-E<space/><link><target>Electronic amplifier</target><part>power amplifier</part></link><space/>stages, modulated by varying the supply voltage.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author"><space/>Frederick H. Raab
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>RF and Microwave Power Amplifier and Transmitter Technologies - Part 2
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>High Frequency Design
</arg><arg name="date">May 2003
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>p. 22ff
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.scribd.com/doc/8616046/RF-Power-Amplifier-and-Transmitter-Technologies-Part2
</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Older designs (for broadcast and amateur radio) also generate AM by controlling the gain of the transmitters final amplifier (generally class-C, for efficiency). The following types are for vacuum tube transmitters (but similar options are available with transistors):<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Laurence Gray and Richard Graham
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Radio Transmitters
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGraw-Hill
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1961
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>141ff
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Plate modulation:</bold><space/>In plate modulation, the plate voltage of the RF amplifier is modulated with the audio signal. The audio power requirement is 50 percent of the RF-carrier power.</listitem><listitem><bold>Heising (constant-current) modulation:</bold><space/>RF amplifier plate voltage is fed through a<space/><link><target>Choke (electronics)</target><part>choke</part></link><space/>(high-value inductor). The AM modulation tube plate is fed through the same inductor, so the modulator tube diverts current from the RF amplifier. The choke acts as a constant current source in the audio range. This system has a low power efficiency.</listitem><listitem><bold>Control grid modulation:</bold><space/>The operating bias and gain of the final RF amplifier can be controlled by varying the voltage of the control grid. This method requires little audio power, but care must be taken to reduce distortion.</listitem><listitem><bold>Clamp tube (screen grid) modulation:</bold><space/>The screen-grid bias may be controlled through a clamp tube, which reduces voltage according to the modulation signal. It is difficult to approach 100-percent modulation while maintaining low distortion with this system.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Doherty amplifier</target><part>Doherty modulation:</part></link></bold><space/>One tube provides the power under carrier conditions and another operates only for positive modulation peaks. Overall efficiency is good, and distortion is low.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Ampliphase</target><part>Outphasing modulation:</part></link></bold><space/>Two tubes are operated in parallel, but partially out of phase with each other. As they are differentially phase modulated their combined amplitude is greater or smaller. Efficiency is good and distortion low when properly adjusted.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>Pulse-width modulation</target><part>Pulse width modulation (PWM) or Pulse duration modulation (PDM):</part></link></bold><space/>A highly efficient high voltage power supply is applied to the tube plate. The output voltage of this supply is varied at an audio rate to follow the program. This system was pioneered by<space/><link><target>Hilmer Swanson</target></link><space/>and has a number of variations, all of which achieve high efficiency and sound quality.</listitem></list><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>AM demodulation methods</arg></template>Demodulation methods</heading><paragraph>The simplest form of AM demodulator consists of a diode which is configured to act as<space/><link><target>envelope detector</target></link>. Another type of demodulator, the<space/><link><target>product detector</target></link>, can provide better-quality demodulation with additional circuit complexity.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>AM broadcasting</target><part>AM radio</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>AM stereo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mediumwave</target></link><space/>band used for AM broadcast radio</listitem><listitem><link><target>Longwave</target></link><space/>band used for AM broadcast radio</listitem><listitem><link><target>Frequency modulation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Shortwave radio</target></link><space/>almost universally uses AM, narrow FM occurring above 25&amp;nbsp;MHz.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Modulation</target></link>, for a list of other modulation techniques</listitem><listitem><link><target>Amplitude modulation signalling system</target></link><space/>(AMSS), a digital system for adding low bitrate information to an AM signal.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sideband</target></link>, for some explanation of what this is.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Types of radio emissions</target></link>, for the emission types designated by the<space/><link><target>ITU</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Airband</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Citizen's Band Radio</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quadrature amplitude modulation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Double-sideband suppressed-carrier transmission</target><part>DSB-SC</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Notes</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Newkirk, David and Karlquist, Rick (2004). Mixers, modulators and demodulators. In D. G. Reed (ed.),<space/><italics>The ARRL Handbook for Radio Communications</italics><space/>(81st ed.), pp.&amp;nbsp;15.1&amp;ndash;15.36. Newington: ARRL. ISBN 0-87259-196-4.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link type='external' href='http://demonstrations.wolfram.com/AmplitudeModulation/'>Amplitude Modulation</link></italics><space/>by Jakub Serych,<space/><link><target>Wolfram Demonstrations Project</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://robotics.eecs.berkeley.edu/~sastry/ee20/modulation/node3.html'>Amplitude Modulation</link>, by S Sastry.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fas.org/man/dod-101/navy/docs/es310/AM.htm'>Amplitude Modulation</link>, an introduction by<space/><link><target>Federation of American Scientists</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://afrotechmods.com/tutorials/2011/11/28/amplitude-modulation-tutorial-am-radio-transmitter-circuit/'>Amplitude Modulation tutorial video with example transmitter circuit.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Telecommunications</target></template><template><target>Audio broadcasting</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Amplitude Modulation</target></template><link><target>Category:Radio modulation modes</target></link></paragraph></article>