<article title='Chastity'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">April 2009</arg></template><link><target>Image:Hans-Memling-allegory-chastity.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part><link><target>Allegory</target></link><space/>of chastity by<space/><link><target>Hans Memling</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Chastity</bold><space/>is<space/><link><target>Human sexual activity</target><part>sexual behavior</part></link><space/>of a man or woman that is acceptable to the<space/><link><target>morals</target><part>moral</part></link><space/>standards and guidelines of their culture, civilization or<space/><link><target>religion</target></link>. In the Western world, the term has become closely associated (and is often used interchangeably) with<space/><link><target>sexual abstinence</target></link>, especially<space/><link><target>Premarital sex</target><part>before marriage</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Chastity<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chastity &#124; Define Chastity at Dictionary.com<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Dictionary.reference.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-10-01</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The words &quot;chaste&quot; and &quot;chastity&quot; stem from the<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>adjective<space/><italics>castus</italics><space/>meaning &quot;pure&quot;. The words entered the English language around the middle of the 13th century; at that time they meant slightly different things. &quot;Chaste&quot; meant &quot;virtuous or pure from unlawful sexual intercourse&quot; (referring to<space/><link><target>extramarital sex</target></link>),<extension extension_name='ref' name="etymonlineChaste"><link type='external' href='http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=chaste'>Chaste at etymonline.com</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="podDictEtym"><link type='external' href='http://podictionary.com/?p=605'>podictionary.com</link></extension>while &quot;chastity&quot; meant &quot;virginity&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="podDictEtym"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?search=chastity'>Chastity at etymonline.com</link></extension><space/>It was not until the late 16th century that the two words came to have the same basic meaning as a related adjective and noun.<extension extension_name='ref' name="etymonlineChaste"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="podDictEtym"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In Abrahamic religions</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">August 2008</arg></template>For Muslims and many Christians, acts of sexual nature are<space/><link><target>fornication</target><part>restricted to marriage</part></link>. For unmarried persons, chastity is identified with<space/><link><target>sexual abstinence</target></link>. Sexual acts outside or apart from marriage, such as<space/><link><target>adultery</target></link>,<space/><link><target>fornication</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>prostitution</target></link>, are considered<space/><link><target>sin</target><trail>ful</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Christianity</heading><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Vow of chastity</arg><arg>vows of Catholic Religious</arg><arg>Evangelical counsels</arg><arg>vows of chastity in other Christian Churches</arg><arg>Religious vows</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In many<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/>traditions, chastity is synonymous with sexual purity. Chastity means not having any sexual relations before marriage. It also means fidelity to husband or wife during marriage. In<space/><link><target>Catholicism</target><part>Catholic</part></link><space/>morality, chastity is placed opposite the<space/><link><target>Seven deadly sins</target><part>deadly sin</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>lust</target></link>, and is classified as one of<space/><link><target>seven virtues</target></link>. The moderation of sexual desires is required to be virtuous. Reason, will and desire can harmoniously work together to do what is good.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>marriage</target></link>, the spouses commit to a lifelong relationship which excludes sexual intimacy with other persons. Within marriage, various Abrahamic religions consider several practices to be considered unchaste, such as sexual intimacy during or shortly after<space/><link><target>menstrual cycle</target><part>menstruation</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>childbirth</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Leviticus</target></link><space/>12:2, 15:24, 20:18.</extension><space/>After marriage, a third form of chastity, often called &quot;vidual chastity&quot;, is expected of a woman while she is in mourning for her late husband. For example,<space/><link><target>Jeremy Taylor</target></link><space/>defined 5 rules in<space/><italics>Holy Living</italics><space/>(1650), including abstaining from marrying &quot;so long as she is with child by her former husband&quot; and &quot;within the year of mourning&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Holy Living<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Chapter II, Section III, Of Chastity<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Jeremy Taylor]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1650<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.anglicanlibrary.org/taylor/holyliving/index.htm<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The particular ethical system may not prescribe each of these. For example, Roman Catholics view sex within marriage as chaste, but prohibit the use of artificial contraception as an offense against chastity, seeing contraception as unnatural, contrary to God's will and design of human sexuality. Many<space/><link><target>Anglicanism</target><part>Anglican</part></link><space/>communities allow for artificial contraception, seeing the restriction of family size as possibly not contrary to God's will. A stricter view is held by the<space/><link><target>Shakers</target></link>, who prohibit marriage (and<space/><link><target>sexual intercourse</target></link><space/>under any circumstances) as a violation of chastity. The<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>has set up various rules regarding<space/><link><target>clerical celibacy</target></link>, while most Protestant communities allow clergy to marry.</paragraph><paragraph>Celibacy is required of<space/><link><target>Monasticism</target><part>monastic</part><trail>s</trail></link>monks, nuns and friarseven in a rare system of<space/><link><target>double cloister</target><trail>s</trail></link>, in which husbands could enter the (men's) monastery while their wives entered a (women's) sister monastery. Required celibacy among the clergy is a relatively recent practice: it became Church policy at the<space/><link><target>Second Lateran Council</target></link><space/>in 1139. It was not uniformly enforced among the clergy until 200 years later.<extension extension_name='ref'>Diarmaid MacCulloch, 'Reformation', Penguin Books, 2003, pg 28</extension><space/>Certain Latin-Rite Catholic priests may receive a dispensation to be married before ordination, and Eastern Catholic priests in many countries are also permitted to be married, provided they are so before ordination.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Vows of chastity</italics><space/>can also be taken by laypersons, either as part of an organised religious life (such as Roman Catholic<space/><link><target>Beguines and Beghards</target></link><space/>in the past) or on an individual basis: as a voluntary act of devotion, or as part of an ascetic lifestyle (often devoted to<space/><link><target>contemplation</target></link>), or both.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The voluntary aspect has led it to being included among the main<space/><link><target>counsels of perfection</target></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Chastity is a central and pivotal concept in Roman Catholic<space/><link><target>Christian theological praxis</target><part>praxis</part></link>. Chastity's importance in traditional Roman Catholic teaching stems from the fact that it is regarded as essential in maintaining and cultivating the unity of body with spirit and thus the integrity of the human being.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catechism of the Catholic Church, 1999, Geoffrey Chapman, p.500</extension><space/>It is also regarded as fundamental to the practise of the Catholic life because it involves an<space/><italics>apprenticeship in self-mastery</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>ibid</italics><space/>p.501</extension><space/>By attaining mastery over one's passions, reason, will and desire can harmoniously work together to do what is good.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Islam</heading><paragraph>Chastity, on the other hand is mandatory in Islam. Sex outside legitimacy is prohibited, for both men and women whether married or unmarried.</paragraph><paragraph>The most famous personal example of chastity in the Quran is Virgin Mary (Miriam) mother of Jesus:</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;And remember her, who guarded her chastity, We breathed into her of Our spirit and We made her and her son a sign for all peoples.&quot; (21 :91)</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;She screened herself away from them (her people) then We sent to her Our angel, and he appeared before her as a man in all respects. She said: I seek refuge from you to God, Most Gracious (come not near) if you do fear God. He said I am only a messenger from your Lord (to announce) to you the gift of a holy son-She said: How shall I have a son, seeing that no man has touched me and I am not unchaste?&quot; (19:17-20)</paragraph><paragraph>Extramarital sex is forbidden and the Quran says:</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Nor come near to adultery. ..for it is a shameful deed and an evil road (to other evils).&quot; (17:32)</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Those who invoke not with God any other god, nor slay such life as God has made sacred except for just cause, nor commit fornication: and any that does this (not only) meets punishment, but the penalty on the Day of Judgement will be doubled to.him, and he will dwell therein in ignominy. Unless he repents, believes and works righteous deeds, for God will change the evil of such persons into good, and God is Oft-Forgiving Most-Merciful.&quot; (25:68-70)</paragraph><paragraph>The injunctions and forbiddings in Islam apply equally to men and women. The legal punishment for adultery is equal for men and women. Social hypocrisy in many societies over history had lead to a double standard when considering sin committed by men versus sin committed by women. Society tended to be more lenient and permissive towards men forgiving men for sins not forgivable when women do them. At the root of the contemporary wave of free sex for both sexes was appa-rently to establish equality and remove discrimination between man and woman. Instead of calling for equal cleanliness the call was for equal dirt. Not so in Islam. and in a list of commendable deeds the Quran says:</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;For muslim men and women,for believing men and women.for men and women who are patient and constant.for men and women who give in charity , for men and women who observe fasting,FOR MEN AND WOMEN WHO GUARD THEIR CHASTITYand for men and women who engage much in God's praise.for them has God prepared forgiveness and great reward&quot;. (33:35)</paragraph><paragraph>Because the sex desire is usually attained before a man is financially capable of marriage, the love to God and mindfulness of Him should be sufficient motive for chastity:</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Let those who find not the wherewithal for marriage keep themselves chaste, until God gives them means out of His grace.&quot; (24:33) The prophet's prescription to the youth was:</paragraph><paragraph>Those of you who own the means should marry for this should keep their eyes uncraving and their chastity secure. Those who don't, may practise fasting for it curbs desire. &quot; (Ibn Massoud)</paragraph><paragraph>Chastity is an attitude and a way of life. In Islam it is both a personal and a social value. A Muslim society should not condone relations entailing or conducive to sexual license. Social patterns and practices bent on flaring up the sexual desire are frowned upon by Islam be the means permissive ideologies, pruritic art or neglect of moral upbringing. Personal freedoms should never be taught as the freedom to challenge God's injunctions or trespass over the limits He drew.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In Eastern religions</heading><heading level='3'>Hinduism</heading><paragraph><link><target>Hinduism</target></link>'s view on premarital sex is rooted in its concept of the stages of<space/><link><target>life</target></link>. The first of these stages, known as<space/><italics><link><target>Brahmacharya</target></link>,</italics><space/>roughly translates as chastity. Celibacy is considered the appropriate behavior for both<space/><link><target>male</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>female</target></link><space/><link><target>students</target></link><space/>during this stage, which precedes the stage of the married householder. Many<space/><link><target>Sadhus</target></link><space/>(Hindu monks) are also celibate as part of their<space/><link><target>asceticism</target><part>ascetic</part></link><space/>discipline.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sikhism</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Sikhism</target></link>, premarital or extra-marital sex is strictly forbidden. However, it is encouraged to marry and live as a family unit to provide and nurture children for the perpetual benefit of creation (as opposed to sannyasa or living as a monk, which was, and remains, a common spiritual practice in India). A Sikh is encouraged not to live as a recluse, beggar, monk, nun, celibate, or in any similar vein.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Jainism</heading><paragraph>Celibacy is a must for all<space/><link><target>Jain monasticism</target><part>Jain monks and nuns</part></link>. Chastity (Bhramacharya) is one of the five major vows of<space/><link><target>Jainism</target></link>. The general Jain code of<space/><link><target>ethics</target></link><space/>requires that one do no harm to any living being in thought, action, or word. Adultery is clearly a violation of a moral agreement with one's spouse, and therefore forbidden, and fornication too is seen as a violation of the state of chastity.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Buddhism</heading><paragraph>The teachings of<space/><link><target>Buddhism</target></link><space/>include the<space/><link><target>Noble Eightfold Path</target></link>, comprising a division called<space/><link><target>Noble Eightfold Path#Right action</target><part>right action</part></link>. Under the<space/><link><target>Five Precepts</target></link><space/>ethical code,<space/><link><target>Upsaka and Upsik</target></link><space/>lay followers should abstain from sexual misconduct, while<space/><link><target>Bhikkhu</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bhikkhuni</target></link><space/>monastics should practice strict chastity.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Daoism</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Five Precepts (Taoism)</target><part>Five Precepts</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Daoist</target></link><space/>religion include No Sexual Misconduct, which is interpreted as prohibiting extramarital sex for lay practitioners and marriage or sexual intercourse for monks and nuns.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Fornication</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chastity belt</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chastity belt (BDSM)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Law of chastity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Seven deadly sins</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Seven virtues</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ten Commandments</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Theology of the body</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>wiktionary</target><arg>chastity</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/archive/catechism/p3s2c2a6.htm'>Catechism of the Catholic Church (III.2.I)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.passtheword.org/SHAKER-MANUSCRIPTS/Abstinence/shaker-abst-x1.htm'>Early Shaker Writings Relating to Sexual Abstinence</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03637d.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia: Chastity</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Christian terminology</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of love</target></link><link><target>Category:Sexual abstinence</target></link><link><target>Category:Virtue</target></link><link><target>Category:Seven virtues</target></link></paragraph></article>