<article title='Bubble_tea'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox prepared food</target><arg name="name"><space/>Boba
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Bubble tea by Chill Bubble Tea.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Bubble tea
</arg><arg name="alternate_name"><space/>Pearl milk tea<br>Boba milk tea
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>[[Taiwan]]
</arg><arg name="region">
</arg><arg name="course"><space/>Drink
</arg><arg name="served">
</arg><arg name="main_ingredient"><space/>[[Tapioca]], milk/creamer, brewed tea, sugar, water
</arg><arg name="variations">
</arg><arg name="calories">
</arg><arg name="other">
</arg><arg name="cookbook"><space/>Bubble Tea
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bubble tea</bold><space/>(also known as<space/><bold>pearl milk tea</bold>, or<space/><bold>boba-milk tea</bold>) (Traditional Chinese:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>zh-tw</arg><arg>珍珠奶茶</arg></template>, Simplified Chinese:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>zh-cn</arg><arg>珍珠奶茶</arg></template>) is a Taiwanese tea-based drink invented in<space/><link><target>Taichung</target></link><space/>in the 1980s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Martin 2007 219"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Martin</arg><arg name="first">Laura C.</arg><arg name="title">Tea: The drink that changed the world</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Tuttle Publishing</arg><arg name="location">Rutland</arg><arg name="isbn">9780804837248</arg><arg name="page">219</arg></template></extension><space/>Most bubble tea recipes contain a tea base mixed/shaken with fruit or milk, to which chewy<space/><link><target>tapioca</target></link><space/>balls or fruit jellies are often added. The &quot;bubble&quot; refers to the foam created by shaking the tea, which itself is called &quot;pom&quot; () tea, meaning &quot;frothy/foamy&quot; tea. Ice-blended versions are usually mixed with fruit or syrup, resulting in a slushy consistency.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Chang</arg><arg name="first">Derrick</arg><arg name="title">Is this the inventor of bubble tea?</arg><arg name="url">http://travel.cnn.com/explorations/drink/inventor-bubble-tea-885732</arg><arg name="publisher">CNN<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>International Edition<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 June 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There are many variants of the drinks, and many kinds of ingredients may be added. The most popular bubble drinks are bubble milk tea with tapioca and bubble milk green tea with tapioca.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Description</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferencedsection</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><link><target>File:BubbleTeaHoneydewMapleStreet20July2008.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Honeydew-flavored bubble tea</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Bubble teas are typically of two distinct types: fruit-flavored teas and<space/><link><target>milk tea</target><trail>s</trail></link>. However, some shops offer hybrid &quot;fruit milk teas&quot;. Most milk teas include powdered dairy or<space/><link><target>non-dairy creamer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, but some shops also offer fresh milk as an alternative. Other varieties are 100% crushed-fruit smoothies with tapioca pearls and signature ice cream shakes made from local ice cream sources. Many American bubble tea vendors sell &quot;milk smoothies&quot;, which are similar to bubble tea but do not contain any tea ingredients. Some small cafs offer sweetener substitutes, such as honey,<space/><link><target>agave</target></link>,<space/><link><target>stevia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>aspartame</target></link>, upon special request.</paragraph><paragraph>The oldest known bubble tea consisted of a mixture of hot<space/><link><target>Taiwanese cuisine</target><part>Taiwanese</part></link><space/><link><target>black tea</target></link>, small<space/><link><target>tapioca</target><part>tapioca pearls</part></link><space/>(),<space/><link><target>condensed milk</target></link>, and syrup () or honey. Many variations were created, the most common of which is served cold rather than hot. The tea type is frequently replaced. First was bubble green tea, which uses jasmine-infused<space/><link><target>green tea</target></link><space/>() instead of black tea. Big tapioca pearls (/) were adapted and quickly replaced the small pearls.<extension extension_name='ref'></extension><space/>Peach or plum flavoring appeared, then more fruit flavors were added until, in some variations, the tea was removed entirely in favor of real fruit. These fruit versions sometimes contain colored pearls (and/or &quot;jelly cubes&quot; as in the related drink<space/><link><target>taho</target></link>), the color chosen to match whatever fruit juice is used. Flavors may be added in the form of powder, fruit juice, pulp, or syrup to hot black or green tea, which is then shaken in a<space/><link><target>cocktail shaker</target></link><space/>or mixed with ice in a<space/><link><target>blender (device)</target><part>blender</part></link>. Cooked tapioca pearls and other mix-ins (such as vanilla extract, honey, syrup, and sugar) are added at the end.</paragraph><paragraph>Today, one can find shops entirely devoted to bubble tea, similar to the<space/><link><target>juice bar</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the early 1990s. Some cafs use plastic dome-shaped lids, while other bubble tea bars serve it using a machine to seal the top of the cup with plastic cellophane. The latter method allows the tea to be shaken in the serving cup and makes it spill-free until one is ready to drink it. The cellophane is then pierced with an oversized straw large enough to allow the pearls to pass through. Today, in Taiwan, it's more common for people to refer to the drink as &quot;pearl milk tea&quot; (&quot;zhn zh ni ch&quot;, or &quot;zhn ni&quot; for short). &quot;Pearl milk tea&quot; is also used by English speakers and overseas Chinese and Taiwanese speakers, but it is usually called &quot;bubble tea&quot; or &quot;boba tea&quot; by English speakers, with the former seemingly more common in locations with less Chinese influence.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Variants</heading><paragraph>Each of the ingredients of bubble tea can have many variations depending on the tea store. Typically, different types of black tea,<space/><link><target>green tea</target></link>, or even coffee form the basis of this beverage. The most common black tea varieties are oolong and Earl Grey, while jasmine green tea is a mainstay at almost all tea stores. Another variation called<space/><link><target>Yuanyang (drink)</target><part>yuanyang</part></link><space/>(, named after the<space/><link><target>Mandarin duck</target></link>) originated in Hong Kong and consists of half black tea and half coffee. Some people add milk to the drink. Decaffeinated versions of teas are sometimes available when the tea house freshly brews the tea base.</paragraph><paragraph>The milk in bubble tea is optional, though many tea stores use it. Some cafs use a non-dairy creamer<space/><link><target>milk substitute</target></link><space/>instead of milk because many East Asians are<space/><link><target>lactose intolerance</target><part>lactose intolerant</part></link><space/>and because it is cheaper and easier to store and use than perishable milk.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Chao<space/></arg><arg name="first">Julie<space/></arg><arg name="title">Taiwan tapioca tea on tap<space/></arg><arg name="work">San Francisco Examiner<space/></arg><arg name="date">12 December 1999<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f</arg></template></extension><space/>In Western countries, soy milk options are widely available for those who avoid dairy products. This adds a distinct flavor and consistency to the drink.<link><target>File:Bubble Tea Drinks.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Four Bubble Tea drinks of different flavors.</part><part>Four different bubble teas: mango green tea, lychee green tea, strawberry green tea with strawberry jelly, and a coconut cream blend with tapioca.</part></link>Different flavorings can be added to bubble tea. Some widely available fruit flavors include<space/><link><target>Garden strawberry</target><part>strawberry</part></link>,<space/><link><target>green apple</target></link>,<space/><link><target>passion fruit</target></link>,<space/><link><target>mango</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lemon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>watermelon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>grape</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lychee</target></link>,<space/><link><target>peach</target></link>,<space/><link><target>pineapple</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cantaloupe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>honeydew (melon)</target><part>honeydew</part></link>,<space/><link><target>banana</target></link>,<space/><link><target>avocado</target></link>,<space/><link><target>coconut</target></link>,<space/><link><target>kiwifruit</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>jackfruit</target></link>. Other popular non-fruit flavors include<space/><link><target>taro</target></link>,<space/><link><target>pudding</target></link>,<space/><link><target>chocolate</target></link>,<space/><link><target>coffee</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cafe mocha</target><part>mocha</part></link>,<space/><link><target>barley</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sesame</target></link>,<space/><link><target>almond</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ginger</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lavender</target></link>,<space/><link><target>rose</target></link>,<space/><link><target>caramel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>viola (plant)</target><part>violet</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Thai tea</target></link>. Some of the sour fruit flavors are available in bubble tea without milk only as the acidity tends to curdle the milk.</paragraph><paragraph>Other varieties of the bubble tea drink can include blended drinks. Many stores in the US provide a list of choices to choose from. Some may include coffee-blended drinks or even smoothies.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Tapioca</target></link><space/>balls (boba) are the prevailing chewy tidbits in bubble tea, but a wide range of other options can be used to add similar texture to the drink. Green pearls have a small hint of green tea flavor and are chewier than the traditional tapioca balls. Jelly is also used in small cubes, stars, or rectangular strips, with flavors such as<space/><link><target>nata de coco</target><part>coconut jelly</part></link>,<space/><link><target>konjac</target></link>,<space/><link><target>lychee</target></link>,<space/><link><target>grass jelly</target><part>grass</part></link>,<space/><link><target>mango</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>green tea</target></link><space/>often available at some shops. Rainbow, a fruit mix of konjac, has a pliant, almost crispy consistency.<space/><link><target>Azuki bean</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>mung bean</target></link><space/>paste, also typical toppings for Taiwanese shaved ice desserts, give the drinks an added subtle flavor as well as texture.<space/><link><target>Aloe</target></link>, egg pudding (<link><target>custard pudding</target></link>),<space/><link><target>sago</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>taro</target></link><space/>balls can also be found in most tea houses.</paragraph><paragraph>Due to its popularity, single-serving packets of black tea (with powdered milk and sugar included) are available as &quot;Instant Boba Milk Tea&quot; in some places.</paragraph><paragraph>Bubble tea cafs will also frequently serve drinks without coffee or tea in them. The base for these drinks is flavoring blended with ice, often called Snow Bubble. All mix-ins that can be added to the bubble tea can also be added to these<space/><link><target>slushie</target></link>-like drinks. One drawback to them is that the coldness of the iced drink may cause the tapioca balls to harden, making them difficult to suck up through a straw and chew. To prevent this from happening, these slushies must be consumed more quickly than bubble tea.</paragraph><paragraph>Occasionally,<space/><link><target>nata de coco</target></link><space/>is used in mass-produced bubble tea drinks as a healthier alternative to tapioca starch.<space/><italics>Nata de coco</italics><space/>is high in dietary fiber and low in<space/><link><target>cholesterol</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fat</target></link>. The<space/><italics>nata de coco</italics><space/>is sliced into thin strips to make it easier to pass through a straw.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fivebyfifty.com/2009/03/17/healthier-bubble-tea<space/></arg><arg name="title">Healthier Bubble Tea</arg><arg name="publisher">Five by Fifty - Asian Consumer Intelligence</arg><arg name="date">17 March 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bubble Tea.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>Milk-tea-flavored bubble tea</part></link>The most accredited story about the creation of bubble tea is the Chun Shui Tang Teahouse in<space/><link><target>Taichung</target></link>, Taiwan. The founder of the teahouse, Liu Han-Chieh,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Martin 2007 219"></extension><space/>observed how the Japanese served cold coffee while on a visit in the 1980s, and applied this method to tea.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"></extension><space/>The new style of serving tea propelled his business, and multiple chains were established. This expansion would be the stepping stone for the rapid expansion of bubble tea.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"></extension><space/>The actual creator of bubble tea is Lin Hsiu Hui, the teahouse's product development manager, who poured a sweetened pudding with tapioca balls into the iced tea drink during a meeting in 1988.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"></extension><space/>The beverage was well received by the people at the meeting, leading to its inclusion on the menu. It ultimately became the franchise's top-selling product.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chang12"></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>An alternative origin is the Hanlin teahouse in<space/><link><target>Tainan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Taiwan</target></link>, owned by Tu Tsong-he. He made tea using traditional white tapioca, which has the appearance of pearls, supposedly resulting in the so-called &quot;pearl tea&quot;. Shortly after, Hanlin changed the white tapioca balls to the black version that is seen most today.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The drink became popular in most parts of<space/><link><target>East Asia</target><part>East</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia</target></link><space/>during the 1990s.<extension extension_name='ref'></extension><space/>Famous chain-stores that sell boba teas are Gong Cha, ShareTea, and Coco<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.gong-cha.com/en/home.php, http://www.shareteaus.com/,http://www.coco-tea.com/bin/home.php?Lang=en</extension><space/>The drink is well received by global consumers from Canada and USA, specifically around areas with high Asian demographics.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Types</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="p">pàomò hóngchá</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): &quot;foam red tea&quot;, by direct translation, is the drink that is more appropriate for the more literal name of &quot;bubble tea&quot;; however, the English name, foam tea, is not used much throughout Asia. Consequently, in non-Chinese-speaking Asian countries, &quot;bubble tea&quot; is commonly used to refer to this drink.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yes411.com/chcanada/listing.php?id</arg><arg name="title">Yes411 全球華人首選生活資訊網 - 加拿大黃頁<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yes411.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 November 2010<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>There is no tapioca in this particular drink. To create this, vendors mix hot or warm tea (in this case,<space/><link><target>Tea#Black tea</target><part>black tea</part></link>) with syrup or sugar and ice cubes into a cocktail shaker. Then they would shake the shaker either by hand or by machine before it is served. The resulting tea would be covered by a layer of foam or froth and the tea would have a light foamy feel to the taste.</listitem><listitem><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="p">pàomò nǎichá</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): &quot;foam milk tea&quot;. One of the many variants that is prepared the same way as the &quot;foam red tea&quot;, well-shaken before serving.</listitem><listitem><space/>or for short) (<template><target>zh</target><arg name="hp">zhēnzhū nǎichá</arg></template>): &quot;pearl milk tea&quot;, or more commonly referred to as bubble tea by most<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>English</part></link><space/>speakers and overseas Chinese speakers. The &quot;pearl&quot; name originally referred to the small 1/12&quot; tapioca pearls added to the drink. Though most modern vendors serve only the bigger 1/4&quot; pearls, they still use &quot;pearl tea&quot; as the name.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://crystalpalace.poempalace.org/cn/pearl009.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">珍珠奶茶的製作方法(pearls)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Crystalpalace.poempalace.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 July 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="hp">bōbà nǎichá</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): &quot;bubble milk tea&quot; and also commonly referred to as boba tea by English speakers and Asian Americans. The name refers to the variant with the bigger, 1/4&quot; tapioca pearls.<extension extension_name='ref'></extension></listitem><listitem><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="hp">hēi zhēnzhū nǎichá</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): &quot;black pearl milk tea&quot;. Since the bigger 1/4&quot; tapioca pearls are separately sold as &quot;black pearls&quot; () in markets, this name was the logical first choice and is more popular with the consumers of the drink. &quot;Boba&quot; () is an alternative name that is less commonly used these days.</listitem><listitem>() (<template><target>zh</target><arg name="hp">(nǎi) chá zhēnzhū</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): &quot;(milk) tea pearl&quot; (less common).</listitem><listitem><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="hp"><space/>pào pào chá</arg><arg name="links">no</arg></template>): used interchangeably with to refer to &quot;bubble tea&quot; in Singapore.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Health concerns</heading><paragraph>Tapioca pearls, milk powder, and juice syrups have in the past been found to contain banned chemical additives. In May 2011,<space/><link><target>2011 Taiwan food scandal</target><part>a food scandal</part></link><space/>broke out in Taiwan where<space/><link><target>Bis(2-ethylhexyl) phthalate</target><part>DEHP</part></link><space/>(a chemical plasticizer and potential carcinogen used to make plastic) was found as a stabilizer in drinks and juice syrups. Some of these products may have been exported and used in bubble tea shops around the world. DEHP can affect hormone balances.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Juan<space/></arg><arg name="last">Yi-yu<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Wei<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Yi-chia<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Hung<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Su-ching<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2011/05/29/2003504450<space/></arg><arg name="title">FOOD SCARE WIDENS:Tainted additives used for two decades: manufacturer<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taipei Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">29 May 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://focustaiwan.tw/ShowNews/WebNews_Detail.aspx?Type</arg><arg name="title">167 food ingredient suppliers affected by toxic contamination: DOH<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Focus Taiwan News Channel<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 May 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>In June 2011, the Health Minister of Malaysia,<space/><link><target>Liow Tiong Lai</target></link>, instructed companies selling &quot;Strawberry Syrup&quot;, a material used in some bubble teas, to stop selling them after chemical tests showed they were tainted with a carcinogen identified as DEHP.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Lee Yen Mun<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://thestar.com.my/news/story.asp?file</arg><arg name="title">Taiwanese syrup used in bubble tea found to be DEHP contaminated<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Star<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 June 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In August 2012, scientists from the<space/><link><target>RWTH Aachen University</target><part>Technical University of Aachen (RWTH)</part></link><space/>in Germany analyzed bubble tea samples within a research project to look for allergenic substances. The result indicated that the products contain styrene, acetophenone and brominated substances.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thelocal.de/sci-tech/20120822-44503.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bubble tea 'contains all sorts of crap'<space/></arg><arg name="date">22 August 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Local</arg></template></extension><space/>The report was published by German newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Rheinische Post</target></link></italics><space/>and caused Taiwan's representative office in Germany to issue a statement, saying food items in Taiwan are monitored.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title">Tests rebut claims about carcinogenic German bubble tea<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/taiwan/archives/2012/09/11/2003542499<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 September 2012<space/></arg><arg name="work">Taipei Times</arg></template></extension><space/>Taiwan's Food and Drug Administration confirmed in September that in a second round of tests conducted by German authorities, Taiwanese bubble tea was found to be free of cancer-causing chemicals. The products were also found to contain no excessive levels of heavy-metal contaminants or other health-threatening agents.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="title">'Reckless' report has hurt Taiwanese bubble tea industry: supplier<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://focustaiwan.tw/ShowNews/WebNews_Detail.aspx?Type</arg><arg name="publisher">Central News Agency<space/></arg><arg name="date">28 September 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In May 2013 the Taiwan Food and Drug Administration issued an alert on the detection of<space/><link><target>maleic acid</target></link>, an unapproved food additive, in some food products, including tapioca pearls.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Taiwan recalls food products due to unapproved food additive</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ava.gov.sg/NR/rdonlyres/9253E7B2-E57D-4992-982C-1304E73748D6/26031/foodalert_Taiwanrecallsfoodproductsduetounapproved.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">Agri-Food & Veterinary Authority of Singapore</arg></template></extension><space/>The Agri-Food &amp; Veterinary Authority of Singapore conducted its own tests and found additional brands of tapioca pearls and some other starch-based products sold in Singapore were similarly affected.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Recall of starch-based products from Taiwan due to maleic acid</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ava.gov.sg/NR/rdonlyres/9253E7B2-E57D-4992-982C-1304E73748D6/26074/Pressrelease_RecallofstarchbasedproductsfromTaiwan.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">Agri-Food & Veterinary Authority of Singapore</arg><arg name="accessdate">28 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In April 2015 investigation for cleaning a pitcher containing the alleged poisonous milk tea at the store namely ErgoCHA in<space/><link><target>Sampaloc, Manila</target></link><space/><link><target>Philippines</target></link><space/>denied the allegation of their helper that he brought a chemical to the store the night before the alleged poisoning happened. However, preliminary findings of the<space/><link><target>Department of Health (Philippines)</target><part>Department of Health</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Food and Drug Administration (Philippines)</target><part>Food and Drug Administration</part></link><space/>did not find any toxic substance in the sample milk tea. The DOH and FDA are still conducting further tests to determine what caused the deaths. In a news report, ABS-CBN News told that the pitcher containing the alleged poisonous milk tea might be containing a<space/><link><target>cyanide</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>As of May 10, 2015, ABS-CBN's news program<space/><link><target>TV Patrol</target></link><space/>reported that the victims of the milk tea poisoning at ErgoCha in<space/><link><target>Sampaloc, Manila</target></link><space/>was contaminated by a cleaning agent,<space/><link><target>oxalic acid</target></link>. Although, investigation is still on-going for further information about the said incident.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Drink</arg></template><template><target>div col</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Taiwanese inventions and discoveries</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cendol</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chatime</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuisine of Taiwan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>EasyWay</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Falooda</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quickly</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taho</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taiwanese tea culture</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>GongCha</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>commons category-inline</target><arg>Bubble tea</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Teas</target></template><template><target>Taiwanese cuisine</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Bubble Tea</target></template><link><target>Category:Taiwanese beverages</target></link><link><target>Category:Taiwanese tea</target></link><link><target>Category:Taiwanese inventions</target></link><link><target>Category:Tea culture</target></link></paragraph></article>