<article title='Wikipedia%3AEditing_policy'><paragraph><template><target>redirects here</target><arg>Wikipedia:Editing guidelines</arg><arg>editing guidelines that are not part of this policy</arg><arg>Wikipedia:List of guidelines#Editing</arg></template><template><target>redirects here</target><arg>WP:EP</arg><arg>the education program</arg><arg>Wikipedia:Education program</arg></template><template><target>pp-semi</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><template><target>policy</target><arg>WP:EP</arg><arg>WP:EDIT</arg><arg>WP:EDITING</arg></template><space/><template><target>policy in a nutshell</target><arg>Improve pages wherever you can, and do not worry about leaving them imperfect. Preserve the value that others add, even if they "did it wrong" (try to fix it rather than [[WP:Deletion|delete it]]).</arg></template><template><target>notice</target><arg>For help on editing, see [[Wikipedia:How to edit a page]].</arg></template><template><target>Conduct policy list</target></template><link><target>Wikipedia:About</target><part>Wikipedia</part></link><space/>is the product of thousands of<space/><bold>editors' contributions</bold>, each one bringing something different to the table, whether it be: researching skills, technical expertise, writing prowess or tidbits of information, but most importantly a willingness to help. Even the<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Featured articles</target><part>best</part></link><space/>articles should not be considered complete, as each new editor can offer new insights on how to enhance the content in it at any time.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Adding information to Wikipedia</heading><paragraph>Wikipedia is here to provide information to people; generally speaking, the more information it can provide (subject to certain defined<space/><link><target>WP:NOT</target><part>limitations</part></link><space/>on its scope), the better it is. Please<space/><link><target>WP:BOLD</target><part>boldly</part></link><space/>add information to Wikipedia, either by creating new articles or adding to existing articles, and exercise particular caution when considering removing information. However, it is Wikipedia policy that information in Wikipedia should be<space/><link><target>WP:V</target><part>verifiable</part></link><space/>and must not be<space/><link><target>WP:NOR</target><part>original research</part></link>. You are invited to show that information is verifiable by referencing<space/><link><target>WP:RS</target><part>reliable sources</part></link>. Unsourced information may be challenged and<space/><link><target>WP:BURDEN</target><part>removed</part></link>, because on Wikipedia a lack of information is better than misleading or false informationWikipedia's reputation as an encyclopedia depends on the information in articles being verifiable and reliable. To avoid such challenges, the best practice is to provide an &quot;<link><target>WP:IC</target><part>inline citation</part></link>&quot; at the time the information is added (see:<space/><link><target>WP:Citing sources</target></link><space/>for instructions on how to do this, or ask for assistance on the article talk page).</paragraph><paragraph>Although reliable sources are required, when developing articles on the basis of sources,<space/><link><target>WP:COPYPASTE</target><part>avoid copying</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>WP:PARAPHRASE</target><part>closely paraphrasing</part></link><space/>a copyrighted source. Wikipedia respects others' copyright. You should read the source, understand it, and then express what it says in your own words.</paragraph><paragraph>Another way editors can improve an article is by finding a source for existing unsourced material. This is especially true if you come across statements that are potentially controversial. You do not need to be the person who added the information to add a source and citation for it.</paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Perfection is not required</arg></template><space/>Wikipedia is a work in progress: perfection is not required</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:IMPERFECT</arg><arg>WP:PERFECTION</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><italics>Perfection is not required</italics>:<space/><link><target>WP:WIP</target><part>Wikipedia is a work in progress</part></link>. Collaborative editing means that incomplete or poorly written first drafts can evolve over time into excellent articles. Even poor articles, if they can be improved, are welcome. For instance, one person may start an article with an overview of a subject or a few random facts. Another may help standardize the article's formatting, or have additional facts and figures or a graphic to add. Yet another may bring better<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Neutral point of view#Due and undue weight</target><part>balance</part></link><space/>to the views represented in the article, and perform fact-checking and<space/><link><target>WP:CITE</target><part>sourcing</part></link><space/>to existing content. At any point during this process, the article may become disorganized or contain substandard writing.</paragraph><paragraph>Although perfection is not required in an article, any contentious material about living persons (or<space/><link><target>Recent Deaths</target><part>recently deceased</part></link>) in any article, that is unsourced or poorly sourcedwhether the material is negative, positive, neutral, or just questionableshould be removed immediately and without waiting for discussion (see the Wikipedia policy<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Biographies of living persons</target><part>biographies of living persons</part></link><space/>for more on this issue). If contentious material about a living person (or a recently deceased person) is verified with one or more reliable sources, the material must be presented in a<space/><link><target>WP:NPOV</target><part>neutral manner</part></link><space/>without<space/><link><target>WP:UNDUE</target><part>undue weight</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Try to fix problems: preserve information</arg><arg>Preserve content</arg></template><space/>Try to fix problems</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>How to handle problematic material</arg><arg>Handling problematic material</arg><arg>Fix problems: preserve information</arg><arg>Remove libel, nonsense, and copyright violations</arg><arg>Handling material that violates policy</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:PRESERVE</arg><arg>WP:HANDLE</arg><arg>WP:FIXTHEPROBLEM</arg></template><italics>Fix problems if you can, flag or remove them if you can't.</italics><space/>Preserve appropriate content. As long as any facts or ideas would belong in an encyclopedia, they should be retained in Wikipedia.<space/><italics><link><target>Wikipedia:Five pillars</target><part>Wikipedia is an encyclopedia.</part></link></italics></paragraph><paragraph>Likewise, as long as any of the facts or ideas added to an article<space/><link><target>WP:ONUS</target><part>would belong</part></link><space/>in the &quot;finished&quot; article, they should be retained if they meet the three article content retention policies:<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Neutral point of view</target><part>Neutral point of view</part></link><space/>(which does not mean<space/><link><target>WP:YESPOV</target><part>No point of view</part></link>),<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Verifiability</target><part>Verifiability</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:No original research</target><part>No original research</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Instead of removing article content that is poorly presented, consider cleaning up the writing, formatting or sourcing on the spot, or<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Template messages/Cleanup</target><part>tagging</part></link><space/>it as necessary. If you think an article needs to be rewritten or changed substantially,<space/><link><target>WP:BOLD</target><part>go ahead and do so</part></link>, but it is best to<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Talk page guidelines#How to use article talk pages</target><part>leave a comment</part></link><space/>about why you made the changes on the article's talk page. The<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:How to edit a page</target><part>editing process</part></link><space/>tends to guide articles through ever-higher<space/><link><target>WP:ASSESS</target><part>levels of quality</part></link><space/>over time.<space/><italics>Great Wikipedia articles can come from a succession of editors' efforts.</italics></paragraph><paragraph>Instead of removing content from an article, consider:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Rephrasing or copy-editing to improve grammar or more accurately represent the sources</listitem><listitem>Correcting<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Accuracy dispute</target><part>inaccuracies</part></link>, while keeping the rest of the content intact</listitem><listitem>Moving the content to a more relevant existing article, or<space/><link><target>WP:SS</target><part>splitting</part></link><space/>the content to<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Your first article</target><part>an entirely new article</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>WP:YESPOV</target><part>Adding other points of views</part></link><space/>to the existing points of view to make the article more balanced</listitem><listitem>Requesting a citation by adding the<space/><template><target>tl</target><arg>citation needed</arg></template><space/>tag, or adding any other<space/><link><target>Template:Inline tags</target></link><space/>as appropriate</listitem><listitem>Doing a quick<space/><link><target>Template:Findsources3</target><part>search for sources</part></link><space/>and adding a citation yourself</listitem><listitem>Adding<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Template messages/Cleanup</target><part>appropriate cleanup tags</part></link><space/>to sections you cannot fix yourself</listitem><listitem><link><target>WP:DEADREF</target><part>Repair a dead link</part></link><space/>if a new<space/><link><target>URL</target></link><space/>for the page or an<space/><link><target>archive site</target><part>archive</part></link><space/>of the old one can be located</listitem><listitem>Merging the entire article into another article with the original article turned into a<space/><link><target>WP:redirect</target><part>redirect</part></link><space/>as described at<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:MERGETEXT</target><part>performing a merge</part></link></listitem><listitem>Fixing errors in wikitext code or formatting</listitem></list><paragraph>Otherwise, if you think the content could provide the seed of a new subarticle, or if you are just unsure about removing it from<space/><link><target>WP:5P</target><part>the project</part></link><space/>entirely, consider copying the information to the article's talk page for further discussion. If you think the content might find a better home elsewhere, consider moving the content to a talk page of any article you think might be more relevant, so that editors there can decide how it might be properly included in our encyclopedia.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Problems that may justify removal</heading><paragraph><template><target>Policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:CANTFIX</arg><arg>WP:WONTWORK</arg></template><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>REMOVE</arg></template>Several of our core policies discuss situations when it<space/><italics>might</italics><space/>be more appropriate to remove information from an article rather than preserve it.<space/><link><target>WP:Verifiability</target></link><space/>discusses handling unsourced and contentious material;<space/><link><target>WP:No original research</target></link><space/>discusses the need to remove original research;<space/><link><target>WP:NOT</target><part>What Wikipedia is not</part></link><space/>describes material that is fundamentally inappropriate for Wikipedia; and<space/><link><target>WP:UNDUE</target></link><space/>discusses how to balance material that gives undue weight to a particular viewpoint, which might include removal of trivia, tiny minority viewpoints, or material that cannot be supported with high-quality sources. Also, redundancy within an article should be kept to a minimum (excepting the<space/><link><target>WP:LEAD</target><part>lead</part></link>, which is meant to be a summary of the entire article, and so is intentionally duplicative).</paragraph><paragraph>Libel, nonsense, hoaxes, and vandalism should be completely removed, as should material that<space/><link><target>WP:COPYVIO</target><part>violates copyright</part></link><space/>and material for which no reliable source that supports it has ever been<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Published</target><part>published</part></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Special care needs to be taken with biographies of living people, especially when it comes to handling unsourced or poorly sourced claims about the subject. Editors working on such articles need to know and understand the extra restrictions that are laid out at<space/><link><target>WP:Biographies of living people</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Talking and editing</heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>Wikipedia:Be bold in updating pages</target><part>Be bold in updating articles</part></link>, especially for minor changes and fixing problems</italics>. Previous authors do not need to be consulted before making changes.<space/><link><target>WP:OWN</target><part>Nobody owns articles</part></link>. If you see a problem that you can fix, do so. Discussion is, however, called for if you think the edit might be controversial or if someone indicates disagreement with your edit (either by reverting your edit and/or raising an issue on the talk page). The<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:BOLD, revert, discuss cycle</target><part>&quot;BOLD, revert, discuss cycle&quot; (BRD)</part></link><space/>is often used when changes might be contentious.</paragraph><paragraph>Boldness should not mean trying to impose edits against<space/><link><target>WP:CONSENSUS</target><part>existing consensus</part></link><space/>or in violation of core policies, such as<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Neutral point of view</target><part>Neutral point of view</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Verifiability</target><part>Verifiability</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Fait accompli</target><part>''Fait accompli''</part></link><space/>actions, where actions are justified by their having already been carried out, are inappropriate.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Be helpful: explain</heading><paragraph><template><target>policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:UNRESPONSIVE</arg></template><italics>Be helpful: explain your changes</italics>. When you edit an article, the more radical or controversial the change, the greater the need to explain it. Be sure to leave a comment about<space/><italics>why</italics><space/>you made the change. Try to use an appropriate<space/><link><target>Help:Edit summary</target><part>edit summary</part></link>. For larger or more significant changes, the edit summary may not give you enough space to fully explain the edit; in this case, you may leave a note on the<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Talk page</target><part>article's talk page</part></link><space/>as well. Remember too that notes on the talk page are more visible, make misunderstandings less likely and encourage discussion rather than<space/><link><target>WP:EW</target><part>edit warring</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Be cautious with major changes: discuss</heading><paragraph><template><target>policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:CAUTIOUS</arg></template><italics>Be cautious about making a major change to an article.</italics><space/>Prevent<space/><link><target>WP:EW</target><part>edit warring</part></link><space/>by discussing such edits first on the article's talk page. One editor's idea of an improvement may be another editor's idea of a desecration. If you choose to be<space/><link><target>WP:BOLD</target><part>bold</part></link>, try to justify your change in detail on the article talk page, so as to avoid an edit war. Before making a major change, consider first creating a new draft on a<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:User_pages#SUB</target><part>subpage of your own user page</part></link><space/>and then link to it on the article's talk page so as to facilitate a new discussion.</paragraph><heading level='3'>But&amp;nbsp; Wikipedia is not a discussion forum</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>WP:NOTFORUM</arg></template>Whether you decide to edit very boldly or discuss carefully on the talk page first, please bear in mind that Wikipedia is not a discussion forum. Wikipedia can be a very energetic place, and it is best for the project as a whole if we concentrate our energies on improving articles rather than debating our personal ideas and beliefs. This is discussed further at<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Etiquette</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Edits to policies and guidelines</heading><paragraph><template><target>seemain</target><arg>Wikipedia:Policies and guidelines#Content changes</arg></template><template><target>policy shortcut</target><arg>WP:WPEDIT</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Policies and guidelines are supposed to state what most Wikipedians agree upon, and should be phrased to reflect the present consensus on a subject. In general, more caution should be exercised in editing policies and guidelines than in editing articles. Minor edits to existing pages, such as formatting changes, grammatical improvement and uncontentious clarification, may be made by any editor at any time. However, changes that would alter the substance of policy or guidelines should normally be announced on the appropriate talk page first. The change may be implemented if no objection is made to it or if discussion shows that there is consensus for the change. Major changes should also be publicized to the community in general, as should proposals for new policy pages (see also<space/><link><target>Wikipedia:Policies and guidelines#Proposals</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Editing and refactoring talk pages</heading><paragraph>For guidance on how to edit talk pages see:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:Talk page</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:Archiving talk pages</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:Refactoring talk pages</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:Contributing to Wikipedia</target><part>Contributing to Wikipedia</part></link><space/>- explains how and where you can help Wikipedia.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Help:Edit conflict</target><part>Edit conflicts</part></link><space/>- explains how to deal with an edit conflict.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:There is no deadline</target><part>There is no deadline</part></link><space/>- various points of view on what this lack of a deadline means.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wikipedia:What Wikipedia is not</target><part>What Wikipedia is not</part></link><space/>- there are certain things that Wikipedia is not.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Wikipedia principles</target></template><template><target>Wikipedia policies and guidelines</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Wikipedia conduct policies</target></link><link><target>Category:Wikipedia editing</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>ml::</target></link></paragraph></article>