<article title='Ballroom_dance'><paragraph><link><target>File:Michael Foskett &amp; Nika Vlasenko 2.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>WDC World Youth (Under 21) Champions 2013, Michael Foskett &amp; Nika Vlasenko</part></link><bold>Ballroom dance</bold><space/>is a set of<space/><link><target>partner dance</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are enjoyed both<space/><link><target>social dance</target><part>socially</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ballroom dance#Competitive dancing</target><part>competitively</part></link><space/>around the world. Because of its<space/><link><target>performance dance</target><part>performance</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>entertainment</target></link><space/>aspects, ballroom dance is also widely enjoyed on<space/><link><target>Stage (theatre)</target><part>stage</part></link>,<space/><link><target>film</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>television</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Ballroom dance</italics><space/>may refer, at its widest definition, to almost any type of partner dancing as recreation. However, with the emergence of<space/><link><target>dancesport</target></link><space/>in modern times, the term has become narrower in scope, and traditionally refers to the five International Standard and five International Latin style dances (see dance<space/><link><target>Ballroom dance#Dances</target><part>categories</part></link><space/>below). The two styles, while differing in technique, rhythm and costumes, exemplify core elements of ballroom dancing such as control and cohesiveness. Developed in England,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Franks">Franks A.H. 1963.<space/><italics>Social dance: a short history</italics>. Routledge &amp; Kegan Paul, London.</extension><space/>the two styles are now regulated by the<space/><link><target>World Dance Council</target></link><space/>(WDC) and the world dancesport federation. (Wdsf). In the United States, two additional variations are popular:<space/><italics><link><target>American Smooth</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>American Rhythm</target></link></italics>, which combine elements of both traditional Latin and Ballroom dances.</paragraph><paragraph>There are also a number of historical dances, and local or national dances, which may be danced in ballrooms or salons. Sequence dancing, in pairs or other formations, is still a popular style of ballroom dance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Silvester, Victor 1980.<space/><italics>Old Time and sequence dancing</italics>. Barrie and Jenkins, London.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Definitions and history</heading><paragraph>The term 'ballroom dancing' is derived from the word<space/><italics>ball</italics><space/>which in turn originates from the Latin word<space/><italics>ballare</italics><space/>which means 'to dance' (a ball-room being a large room specially designed for such dances). In times past, ballroom dancing was<space/><link><target>Social dance</target><part>social dancing</part></link><space/>for the privileged, leaving<space/><link><target>folk dancing</target></link><space/>for the lower classes. These boundaries have since become blurred, and it should be noted even in times long gone, many ballroom dances were really elevated folk dances. The definition of ballroom dance also depends on the era: balls have featured popular dances of the day such as the<space/><link><target>Minuet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Quadrille</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Polonaise</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Polka</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mazurka</target></link>, and others, which are now considered to be<space/><link><target>historical dance</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early Modern Age</heading><paragraph>The first authoritative knowledge of the earliest ballroom dances was recorded toward the end of the 16th century, when Jehan Tabourot, under the pen name &quot;<link><target>Thoinot Arbeau</target><part>Thoinot-Arbeau</part></link>&quot;, published in 1588 his<space/><italics>Orchsographie</italics>, a study of late 16th-century French renaissance social dance. Among the dances described were the solemn<space/><link><target>basse danse</target></link>, the livelier<space/><link><target>branle</target></link>,<space/><link><target>pavane</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>galliarde</target></link><space/>which<space/><link><target>Shakespeare</target></link><space/>called the &quot;cinq pace&quot; as it was made of five steps.<extension extension_name='ref' name="silvester">Silvester, Victor 1993.<space/><italics>Modern Ballroom Dancing</italics>. Tralfalgar Square, London.</extension><link><target>File:Galliard.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>130px</part><part>Galliard in<space/><link><target>Siena</target></link>, Italy, 15th century</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1650 the<space/><link><target>Minuet</target></link>, originally a peasant dance of<space/><link><target>Poitou</target></link>, was introduced into Paris and set to music by<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Lully</target></link><space/>and danced by the King<space/><link><target>Louis XIV</target></link><space/>in public, and would continue to dominate ballroom from that time until the close of the 18th century.</paragraph><paragraph>Toward the latter half of the 17th century, Louis XIV founded his '<link><target>Acadmie Royale de Musique</target><part>Acadmie Royale de Musique et de Danse</part></link>', where specific rules for the execution of every dance and the &quot;<link><target>Positions of the feet in ballet</target><part>five positions</part></link>&quot; of the feet were formulated for the first time by members of the Acadmie. Eventually, the first definite cleavage between ballet and ballroom came when professional dancers appeared in the ballets, and the ballets left the Court and went to the stage. Ballet technique such as the<space/><link><target>Turnout (ballet)</target><part>turned out</part></link><space/>positions of the feet, however, lingered for over two centuries and past the end of the Victoria era.<extension extension_name='ref' name="silvester"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>19th century</heading><paragraph>The waltz with its modern hold took root in England in about 1812; in 1819<space/><link><target>Carl Maria von Weber</target></link><space/>wrote<space/><italics><link><target>Invitation to the Dance (Weber)</target><part>Invitation to the Dance</part></link></italics>, which marked the adoption of the waltz form into the sphere of absolute music. The dance was initially met with tremendous opposition due to the semblance of impropriety associated with the closed hold, though the stance gradually softened.<extension extension_name='ref' name="silvester">Silvester, Victor 1993.<space/><italics>Modern Ballroom Dancing</italics>; rev. ed. London: Stanley Paul. (1st edition: London: H. Jenkins, 1927)</extension><space/>In the 1840s several new dances made their appearance in the ballroom, including the<space/><link><target>Polka</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mazurka</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Schottische</target></link>. In the meantime a strong tendency emerged to drop all 'decorative' steps such as<space/><italics>entrechats</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>ronds de jambes</italics><space/>that had found a place in the Quadrilles and other dances.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early 20th century</heading><paragraph>Modern ballroom dance has its roots early in the 20th century, when several different things happened more or less at the same time. The first was a movement away from the sequence dances towards dances where the couples moved independently. This had been pre-figured by the waltz, which had already made this transition. The second was a wave of popular music, such as<space/><link><target>jazz</target></link>, much of which was based on the ideas of black musicians in the USA. Since dance is to a large extent tied to music, this led to a burst of newly invented dances. There were many dance crazes in the period 19101930.<link><target>File:Vernon and Irene Castle2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part><link><target>Vernon and Irene Castle</target></link>, early ballroom dance pioneers, c. 191018</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The third event was a concerted effort to transform some of the dance crazes into dances which could be taught to a wider dance public in the US and Europe. Here<space/><link><target>Vernon and Irene Castle</target></link><space/>were important, and so was a generation of English dancers in the 1920s, including<space/><link><target>Josephine Bradley</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Victor Silvester</target></link>. These professionals analysed, codified, published and taught a number of standard dances. It was essential, if popular dance was to flourish, for dancers to have some basic movements they could confidently perform with any partner they might meet. Here the huge<space/><link><target>Arthur Murray</target></link><space/>organisation in America, and the dance societies in England, such as the<space/><link><target>Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing</target></link>, were highly influential. Finally, much of this happened during and after a period of World War, and the effect of such a conflict in dissolving older social customs was considerable.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Franks"><xhtml:sup>Chapter 7</xhtml:sup></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Richardson P.J S. 1948.<space/><italics>The history of English ballroom dancing (19001945)</italics>. London: Jenkins</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Later, in the 1930s, the on-screen dance pairing of<space/><link><target>Fred Astaire</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ginger Rogers</target></link><space/>influenced all forms of dance in the USA and elsewhere. Although both actors had separate careers, their filmed dance sequences together, which included portrayals of the Castles, have reached iconic status.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.musicals101.com/1930film3.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">History of Musical Film, by John Kenrick<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-05-29<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Musicals101.com</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080511172708/http://www.musicals101.com/1930film3.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>11 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension><space/>Much of Astaire and Rogers' work portrayed social dancing, although the performances were highly choreographed (often by Astaire or<space/><link><target>Hermes Pan (choreographer)</target><part>Hermes Pan</part></link>), and meticulously staged and rehearsed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID</arg><arg name="title">Review of "Swing Time" (1936)<space/></arg><arg name="date">1998-02-15<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-05-29<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Roger Ebert|rogerebert.com]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Competitive dancing</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Dancesport</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ballroom dance competition cha cha 3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Young couple dancing<space/><link><target>Cha-cha-cha (dance)</target><part>cha-cha-cha</part></link><space/>at a junior Latin dance competition in the<space/><link><target>Czech Republic</target></link>.</part></link>Competitions, sometimes referred to as<space/><link><target>Dancesport</target></link>, range from world championships, regulated by the<space/><link><target>World Dance Council</target></link><space/>(WDC), to less advanced dancers at various proficiency levels. Most competitions are divided into professional and amateur, though in the USA<space/><link><target>pro-am</target></link><space/>competitions typically accompany professional competitions.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.unitedstatesdancechampionships.com/'>USDC</link></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>International Olympic Committee</target></link><space/>now recognizes<space/><link><target>competitive dance</target><part>competitive</part></link><space/>ballroom dance.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.idsf.net/index.tpl?id=30'>Certificate of Olympic recognition of WDSF</link></extension><space/>It has recognized another body, the<space/><link><target>World DanceSport Federation</target></link><space/>(WDSF), as the sole representative body for dancesport in the<space/><link><target>Olympic Games</target></link>. However, it seems doubtful that dance will be included in the Olympic Games, especially in light of efforts to reduce the number of participating sports.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Ballroom dance competitions are regulated by each country in its own way. There are about 30 countries which compete regularly in international competitions. There are another 20 or so countries which have membership of the WDC and/or the WDSF, but whose dancers rarely appear in international competitions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Complete listings of affiliations are given in the programmes of the major competitions.</extension><space/>In Britain there is the<space/><link><target>British Dance Council</target></link>, which grants national and regional championship titles, such as the British Ballroom Championships, the<space/><link><target>British Sequence Championships</target></link><space/>and the United Kingdom Championships. In the United States, amateur dance proficiency levels are defined by<space/><link><target>USA Dance</target></link><space/>(formerly United States Amateur Ballroom Dance Association, USABDA).</paragraph><paragraph>Ballroom dancing competitions in the former USSR also included the<space/><link><target>Soviet Ballroom dances</target></link>, or<space/><italics>Soviet Programme</italics>. Australian<space/><link><target>New Vogue (dance)</target><part>New Vogue</part></link><space/>is danced both competitively and socially. In competition there are 15 recognised New Vogue dances, which are performed by the competitors in sequence. These dance forms are not recognised internationally, neither are the US variations such as American Smooth, and Rhythm. Such variations in dance and competition methods are attempts to meets perceived needs in the local market-place.</paragraph><paragraph>Internationally, the<space/><link><target>Blackpool Dance Festival</target></link>, hosted annually at<space/><link><target>Blackpool</target></link>, England, is considered the most prestigious event a dancesport competitor can attend.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Formation dance</target></link><space/>is another style of competitive dance recognised by the IDSF. In this style, multiple dancers (usually in couples and typically up to 16 dancers at one time) compete on the same team, moving in and out of various formations while dancing.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Elements of competition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:MIT 2006 Latin Intermediate.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Intermediate level international style Latin dancing at the 2006<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</target><part>MIT</part></link><space/>ballroom dance competition. A judge stands in the foreground.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In competition ballroom, dancers are judged by diverse criteria such as poise, the hold or frame, posture, musicality and expression, timing, body alignment and shape, floor craft, foot and leg action, and presentation. Judging in a performance-oriented sport is inevitably subjective in nature, and controversy and complaints by competitors over judging placements are not uncommon. The scorekeeperscalled scrutineerswill tally the total number recalls accumulated by each couple through each round until the finals, when the<space/><link><target>Skating system</target></link><space/>is used to place each couple by ordinals, typically 16, though the number of couples in the final may vary. Sometimes, up to 7 couples may be present on the floor during the finals.and bronze the lowest. In these levels, moves are restricted to those written in syllabus, and illegal moves can lead to disqualification. Each level, bronze, silver, and gold, has different moves on their syllabus, increasing in difficulty. At these levels, the elaborate costumes are not allowed, as there are very strict clothing restrictions. Jewels on costumes or hair can lead to disqualification.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://usadance.org/dancesport/competition-guides/for-the-competitor/</extension><space/>Open levels are reserved for higher-skilled dancers, usually taking time to get to that caliber of dancing. There are three levels in the open category; novice, pre-champ, and champ in increasing order of skill. At those levels, dancers no longer have restrictions on clothing, so gowns covered in jewels for example, are allowed in the smooth and standard dances, and fringe dresses with huge cutouts and elaborate designs are now allowed in the rhythm and Latin categories. Women also tend to wear extremely intricate hairstyles and bright makeup, often with jewels glued on in patterns.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Medal tests</heading><paragraph>Medal examinations for amateurs enable dancers' individual abilities to be recognized according to conventional standards. In medal exams, which are run by bodies such as the<space/><link><target>Imperial Society of Teachers of Dancing</target></link><space/>(ISTD) and the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom Alliance (UKA)</target></link>, each dancer performs two or more dances in a certain genre in front of a judge. Genres such as Modern Ballroom or Latin are the most popular. Societies such as the ISTD and UKA also offer medal tests on other dance styles (such as Country &amp; Western, Rock 'n Roll or Tap). In some North American examinations, levels include Newcomer, Bronze, Silver, Gold, Novice, Pre-championship, and Championship; each level may be further subdivided into either two or four separate sections.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Collegiate Ballroom</heading><paragraph>There is a part of the ballroom world dedicated to college students. These chapters are typically clubs or teams that have an interest in ballroom dancing. Teams hold fundraisers, social events, and ballroom dance lessons. Ballroom dance teams goals are to have fun and learn to dance well. There is a strong focus on finding a compatible dance partner and bonding with teammates. There is also a competitive side to collegiate ballroom.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Ballroom 101</arg><arg name="url">http://usadance.org/college/ballroom-101/</arg><arg name="publisher">USA Dance, Inc.</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 April 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In competitive collegiate ballroom, competitors go to competitions at different schools or events, such as Arnold Dancesport Classic and MIT Open Ballroom Dance Competition. Dancers can compete in four different categories. The categories are American Rhythm, International Latin, American Smooth, and International Standard. Competitors dance at different level based on their abilities. The levels of dance, in order of difficultly, are newcomer, bronze, silver, gold, novice, pre-championship, and championship. Bronze through gold is considered syllabus. Novice through Championship is considered open. Individuals and teams as a whole compete against each other.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dances</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tango ballroom standard.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>180px</part><part>Victor Fung and Anna Mikhed dancing a<space/><link><target>Tango (ballroom)</target><part>tango</part></link><space/>in 2006. The couple, dancing for the USA, came third in the Professional<space/><link><target>World Ballroom Dance Championship</target><part>World Championship</part></link><space/>2009.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Ballroom dance&quot; refers most often to the ten dances of<space/><bold>International Ballroom</bold><space/>(or Standard) and<space/><bold>International Latin</bold>, though the term is also often used interchangeably with the five International Ballroom dances.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://linus.socs.uts.edu.au/%7Edon/pubs/modern.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">History of Modern Ballroom Dancing</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-02-20</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20070226125005/http://linus.socs.uts.edu.au/~don/pubs/modern.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>26 February 2007<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template>.</extension><space/><link><target>Sequence dancing</target></link>, which is danced predominantly in the United Kingdom, and its development<space/><link><target>New Vogue (dance)</target><part>New Vogue</part></link><space/>in Australia and New Zealand, are also sometimes included as a type of Ballroom dancing.</paragraph><paragraph>In the United States and Canada, the<space/><bold>American Style</bold><space/>(<bold>American Smooth</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>American Rhythm</bold>) also exists. The dance technique used for both International and American styles is similar, but International Ballroom allows only<space/><link><target>Ballroom glossary#Closed position</target><part>closed dance positions</part></link>, whereas American Smooth allows closed, open and separated dance movements. In addition, different sets of dance figures are usually taught for the two styles. International Latin and American Rhythm have different styling, and have different dance figures in their respective syllabi.</paragraph><paragraph>Other dances sometimes placed under the umbrella &quot;ballroom dance&quot; include Nightclub Dances such as<space/><link><target>Lindy Hop</target></link>,<space/><link><target>West Coast Swing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nightclub Two Step</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hustle (dance)</target><part>Hustle</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Salsa (dance)</target><part>Salsa</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>merengue (dance)</target><part>Merengue</part></link>.The categorization of dances as &quot;ballroom dances&quot; has always been fluid, with new dances or folk dances being added to or removed from the ballroom repertoire from time to time, so no list of subcategories or dances is any more than a description of current practices. There are other dances historically accepted as ballroom dances, and are revived via the<space/><link><target>Vintage dance</target></link><space/>movement.</paragraph><paragraph>In Europe, Latin Swing dances include<space/><link><target>Argentine Tango</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mambo (dance)</target><part>Mambo</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lindy Hop</target></link>, Swing Boogie (sometimes also known as Nostalgic Boogie), and<space/><link><target>Disco Fox</target></link>. One example of this is the subcategory of<space/><link><target>Cajun dance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that originated in<space/><link><target>Acadiana</target></link>, with branches reaching both coasts of the United States.</paragraph><paragraph>Ballroom/Smooth dances are normally danced to Western music (often from the mid-twentieth century), and couples dance counter-clockwise around a rectangular floor following the<space/><link><target>Ballroom glossary#Line of dance</target><part>line of dance</part></link>. In competitions, competitors are costumed as would be appropriate for a<space/><link><target>white tie</target></link><space/>affair, with full gowns for the ladies and<space/><link><target>bow tie</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>tail coat</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for the men; though in American Smooth it is now conventional for the men to abandon the tailsuit in favor of shorter<space/><link><target>tuxedo (clothing)</target><part>tuxedo</part><trail>s</trail></link>, vests, and other creative outfits.</paragraph><paragraph>Latin/Rhythm dances are commonly danced to contemporary Latin American music and (in case of Jive) Western music. With the exception of a few traveling dances like<space/><link><target>Samba (ballroom)</target><part>Samba</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paso Doble</target></link>, couples do not follow the line of dance but perform their routines more or less in one spot. In competitions, the women are often dressed in short-skirted<space/><link><target>latin</target></link><space/>outfits while the men are outfitted in tight-fitting shirts and pants, the goal being to emphasize the dancers' leg action and body movements.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dance style classification</heading><heading level='3'><link><target>World Dance Council</target><part>WDC</part></link>-defined Competition Dances<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.dancewdc.org/downloads/WDC%20Competition%20Rules%20current%20June%202015.pdf</extension></heading><paragraph><bold><link><target>Waltz (International Standard)</target><part>Waltz</part></link></bold>:28 beats per minute, 3/4 time, also known as<space/><italics>Slow Waltz</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>English Waltz</italics><space/>depending on locality</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Tango (ballroom)</target><part>Tango</part></link></bold>:32 beats per minute, 2/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Viennese Waltz</target></link></bold>:60 beats per minute, 3/4 timeIn some countries (for example, Austria) Viennese is known as the Waltz, while<space/><link><target>Waltz</target></link><space/>is recognized as<space/><italics>Slow Waltz</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Foxtrot (dance)</target><part>Foxtrot</part></link></bold>:28 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Quickstep</target></link></bold>:50 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Samba (ballroom)</target><part>Samba</part></link></bold>:48 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Cha-cha-cha (dance)</target><part>Cha-cha-cha</part></link></bold>:30 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Rhumba</target><part>Rumba</part></link></bold>:24 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Paso Doble</target></link></bold>:56 beats per minute, 2/4 time</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Jive (dance)</target><part>Jive</part></link></bold>:42 beats per minute, 4/4 time</paragraph><heading level='3'>American Style Competition Dances (only in the U.S. &amp; Canada)</heading><paragraph><bold><link><target>Waltz</target></link></bold>:2830 bars per minute3032 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Tango (ballroom)</target><part>Tango</part></link></bold>:30 bars per minute3032 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Foxtrot (dance)</target><part>Foxtrot</part></link></bold>:30 bars per minute3234 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Viennese Waltz</target></link></bold>:5354 bars per minute54 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Cha-cha-cha (dance)</target><part>Cha Cha</part></link></bold>:30 bars per minute</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Rhumba</target><part>Rumba</part></link></bold>:3032 bars per minute3236 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>East Coast Swing</target></link></bold>:36 bars per minute3436 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Bolero</target></link></bold>:24 bars per minute2426 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Mambo dance</target><part>Mambo</part></link></bold>:47 bars per minute4851 bars per minute for Bronze</paragraph><heading level='3'>Others</heading><paragraph>Historical/Vintage Ballroom dance:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><link><target>Waltz</target></link><space/><link><target>Polka</target></link><space/><link><target>Schottische</target></link><space/><link><target>Tango (dance)</target><part>Tango</part></link><space/><link><target>One-Step</target></link><space/><link><target>Foxtrot (dance)</target><part>Foxtrot</part></link><space/><link><target>Peabody (dance)</target><part>Peabody</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Other dances occasionally categorized as ballroom:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><bold>Nightclub</bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nightclub Two-step</target></link><space/><link><target>Hustle (dance)</target><part>Hustle</part></link><space/><link><target>Modern Jive</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>LeRoc</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>Ceroc</target></link><space/>and the whole swing variety:<space/><link><target>West Coast Swing</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>East Coast Swing</target></link>/<space/><link><target>Lindy Hop</target></link><space/>(always included in the &quot;Rhythm-Swing&quot; category) /<space/><link><target>Carolina Shag</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>Collegiate Shag</target></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>Balboa (dance)</target><part>Balboa</part></link><space/>/<space/><link><target>Blues</target></link><space/><link><target>Fusion dance</target><part>Fusion</part></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold>Latin nightclub</bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Salsa (dance)</target><part>Salsa</part></link><space/><link><target>Cumbia</target></link><space/><link><target>Mambo (dance)</target><part>Mambo</part></link><space/><link><target>Merengue (dance)</target><part>Merengue</part></link><space/><link><target>Porro</target></link><space/><link><target>Cha-cha-cha (dance)</target><part>Cha cha</part></link><space/><link><target>Bachata (dance)</target><part>Bachata</part></link><space/><link><target>Kizomba</target></link><space/><link><target>Semba</target></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold>Brazilian Dances</bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Forr</target></link><space/><link><target>Pagode</target></link><space/><link><target>Samba de Gafieira</target></link><space/><link><target>Lambada</target></link><space/>-<space/><link><target>Zouk-Lambada</target><part>Zouk</part></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold><link><target>Country-western dance</target><part>Country/Western</part></link></bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>C/W Polka</target></link><space/><link><target>C/W Cha-cha</target></link><space/><link><target>Country-western two-step</target><part>C/W Two-step</part></link><space/><link><target>C/W Waltz</target></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold>Cajun dances</bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cajun One Step</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Cajun Jig</target></link><space/><link><target>Two-step (dance move)</target><part>Cajun Two Step</part></link><space/><link><target>Zydeco (dance)</target><part>Zydeco</part></link><space/><link><target>Cajun Waltz</target></link><space/><link><target>Cajun Jitterbug</target></link></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold><link><target>Bal-musette</target><part>Musette dances</part></link></bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Java (dance)</target><part>Java</part></link><space/>musette-waltz musette-tango musette-paso-doble</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><bold>Other</bold></listitem><listitem><link><target>Argentine tango</target></link><space/><link><target>New Vogue (dance)</target><part>New Vogue</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dance in Canada</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sport in Austria#DanceSport in Austria</target><part>Dance sport in Austria</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Australian Dance Awards</target><part>Australian Dance</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dancesport at the Asian Games</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tdcomsa.com/niche_site/ballroom-dancing/'>'''Ballroom Dancing Judging Criteria'''<space/></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Ballroom dance</arg></template><template><target>Dance</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ballroom Dance</target></template><link><target>Category:Ballroom dance</target><part>*</part></link></paragraph></article>