<article title='Battle_of_Pharsalus'><paragraph><template><target>For</target><arg>other battles that took place at Pharsalus</arg><arg>Battle of Pharsalus (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>more footnotes</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="conflict">Battle of Pharsalus
</arg><arg name="partof">[[Caesar's Civil War]]
</arg><arg name="image">[[File:Battle of Pharsalus, 48 BC.gif|300px]]
</arg><arg name="caption">
</arg><arg name="date">9 August 48 BC</arg><arg>
</arg><arg name="place">[[Farsala|Palaeopharsalos]] (Greece)
</arg><arg name="result">Decisive Caesarian victory
</arg><arg name="combatant1">Forces of [[Julius Caesar]], including representatives of the [[Populares]]
</arg><arg name="combatant2">Forces of [[Pompey]], including many of the [[Optimates]]
</arg><arg name="commander1">[[Julius Caesar|Gaius Julius Caesar]]<br />[[Mark Antony]]
</arg><arg name="commander2">[[Pompey|Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus]]
</arg><arg name="strength1">Approximately 22,000 [[Legionary|legionaries]] (elements of 9 legions), 5,000–10,000 [[Auxiliaries (Roman military)|auxiliaries]] and allies, and allied cavalry of 1,800
</arg><arg name="strength2">Approximately 40,000–45,000 [[Legionary|legionaries]] (12 legions), 4,200 [[Auxiliaries (Roman military)|auxiliaries]] and allies, and allied cavalry of 5,000–8,000
</arg><arg name="casualties1">~230 (according to Caesar)
</arg><arg name="casualties2">6,000-15,000<ref>http://www.ancient.eu/article/697/</ref></arg></template><template><target>Campaignbox Caesar's Civil War</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Battle of Pharsalus</bold><space/>was a decisive battle of<space/><link><target>Caesar's Civil War</target></link>. On 9 August 48 BC at<space/><link><target>Pharsalus</target></link><space/>in central Greece,<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target><part>Gaius Julius Caesar</part></link><space/>and his allies formed up opposite the army of the<space/><link><target>Roman Republic</target><part>republic</part></link><space/>under the command of<space/><link><target>Pompey</target><part>Gnaeus Pompeius Magnus</part></link><space/>(&quot;Pompey the Great&quot;). Pompey had the backing of a majority of the<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target><part>senators</part></link>, of whom many were<space/><link><target>optimate</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and his army significantly outnumbered the veteran Caesarian legions.</paragraph><paragraph>The two armies confronted each other over several months of uncertainty, Caesar being in a much weaker position than Pompey.The former found himself isolated in a hostile country with only 22,000 men and short of provisions, while on the other side of the river he was faced by Pompey with an army about twice as large in number. Pompey wanted to delay, knowing the enemy would eventually surrender from hunger and exhaustion. Pressured by the senators present and by his officers, he reluctantly engaged in battle and suffered an overwhelming defeat, ultimately fleeing the camp and his men, disguised as an ordinary citizen.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Prelude</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>A dispute between Caesar and the<space/><italics>optimates</italics><space/>faction in the Senate of Rome culminated in Caesar marching his army on Rome and forcing Pompey, accompanied by much of the<space/><link><target>Roman Senate</target></link>, to flee from Italy to Greece in 49 BC where he could better conscript an army to face his former ally. Caesar, lacking a fleet to immediately give chase, solidified his control over the western Mediterranean Spain specifically before assembling ships to follow Pompey.<space/><link><target>Marcus Calpurnius Bibulus</target></link>, whom Pompey had appointed to command his 600-ship fleet, set up a massive blockade to prevent Caesar from crossing to Greece and to prevent any aid to Italy. Caesar, defying convention, chose to cross the Adriatic during the winter, with only half his fleet at a time. This move surprised Bibulus and the first wave of ships managed to run the blockade easily. Now prepared, Bibulus managed to prevent any further ships from crossing, but died soon afterwards.</paragraph><paragraph>Caesar was now in a precarious position, holding a beachhead at<space/><link><target>Epirus</target></link><space/>with only half his army, no ability to supply his troops by sea, and limited local support, as the Greek cities were mostly loyal to Pompey. Caesar's only choice was to fortify his position, forage what supplies he could, and wait on his remaining army to attempt another crossing. Pompey by now had a massive international army; however, his troops were mostly untested raw recruits, while Caesar's troops were hardened veterans. Realizing Caesar's difficulty in keeping his troops supplied, Pompey decided to simply mirror Caesar's forces and let hunger do the fighting for him. Caesar began to despair and used every channel he could think of to pursue peace with Pompey. When this was rebuffed he made an attempt to cross back to Italy to collect his missing troops but was turned back by a storm. Finally, Marc Antony rallied the remaining forces in Italy, fought through the blockade and made the crossing, reinforcing Caesar's forces in both men and spirit. Now at full strength Caesar felt confident to take the fight to Pompey.</paragraph><paragraph>Pompey was camped in a strong position just south of<space/><link><target>Battle of Dyrrhachium (48 BC)</target><part>Dyrrhachium</part></link><space/>with the sea to his back and surrounded by hills, making a direct assault impossible. Caesar ordered a wall to be built around Pompey's position in order to cut off water and pasture land for his horses. Pompey built a parallel wall and in between a kind of no man's land was created, with fighting comparable to the trench warfare of<space/><link><target>World War&amp;nbsp;I</target></link>. Finally the standoff was broken by a traitor in Caesar's army, who informed Pompey of a weakness in Caesar's wall. Pompey immediately exploited this information and forced Caesar's army into a full retreat, but ordered his army not to pursue, fearing Caesar's reputation for setting elaborate traps. This caused Caesar to remark, &quot;Today the victory had been the enemy's, had there been any one among them to gain it.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Plutarch</target></link><space/><italics>Pompey</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A2008.01.0058%3Achapter%3D65%3Asection%3D5'>65.5</link>, Dryden translation:<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=QScSAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA465&amp;amp;lpg=PA465'>p. 465</link>.</extension><space/>Pompey continued his strategy of mirroring Caesar's forces and avoiding any direct engagements. After trapping Caesar in<space/><link><target>Thessaly</target></link>, the prominent senators in Pompey's camp began to argue loudly for a more decisive victory. Although Pompey was strongly against ithe wanted to surround and starve Caesar's army insteadhe eventually gave in and accepted battle from Caesar on a field near Pharsalus.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Date and location</heading><paragraph>The date of the actual decisive battle is given as 9 August 48 BC according to the republican calendar.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>According to the Julian calendar however, the date was either 29 June (according to Le Verrier's chronological reconstruction) or possibly 7 June (according to Drumann/Groebe).<template><target>where?</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>As Pompey was assassinated on 3 September 48 BC, the battle must have taken place in the true month of August, when the harvest was becoming ripe (or Pompey's strategy of starving Caesar would not be plausible).<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The location of the battlefield was long a subject of controversy among scholars. Caesar himself, in his<space/><link><target>Commentarii de Bello Civili</target></link>, mentions few place-names;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Bellum Civile</italics><space/>3.8198</extension><space/>and although the battle is called after Pharsalos, four ancient writers the author of the<space/><italics>Bellum Alexandrinum</italics><space/>(48.1),<space/><link><target>Frontinus</target></link><space/>(<italics>Strategemata</italics><space/>2.3.22),<space/><link><target>Eutropius (historian)</target><part>Eutropius</part></link><space/>(20), and<space/><link><target>Orosius</target></link><space/>(6.15.27) place it specifically at<space/><italics>Palae</italics>pharsalos.<space/><link><target>Strabo</target></link><space/>in his<space/><italics>Geographica</italics><space/>(<italics></italics>) mentions both old and new Pharsaloi, and notes that the Thetideion, the temple to<space/><link><target>Thetis</target></link><space/>south of Scotoussa, was near both. In 198 BC in the<space/><link><target>Second Macedonian War</target></link><space/><link><target>Philip V of Macedon</target></link><space/>sacked Palaepharsalos (<link><target>Livy</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Ab Urbe Condita Libri (Livy)</target><part>Ab Urbe Condita</part></link></italics><space/>32.13.9), but left new Pharsalos untouched. These two details perhaps imply that the two cities were not close neighbours. Until the early 20th century, unsure of the site of Palaepharsalos, scholars followed<space/><link><target>Appian</target></link><space/>(2.75) and located the battle of 48 BC south of the Enipeus or close to Pharsalos (today's<space/><link><target>Pharsala</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Map with conjectured locations,<space/><italics>Annual of the British School at Athens</italics>, No. XXIV, 1921<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/30102514?seq=21'></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The north-bank thesis of<space/><link><target>F. L. Lucas</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>F. L. Lucas, 'The Battlefield of Pharsalos',<space/><italics>Annual of the British School at Athens</italics>, No. XXIV, 191921, pp.3453</extension><space/>based on his 1921 solo field-trip to Thessaly, is now, however, broadly accepted by historians.<extension extension_name='ref'>Holmes, T. Rice,<space/><italics>The Roman Republic and the Founder of the Empire</italics><space/>(Oxford, 1923); Fuller, J. F. C,<space/><italics>Julius Caesar: Man, Soldier and Tyrant</italics><space/>(London, 1965); Sheppard, Simon,<space/><italics>Pharsalus 48 B.C.: Caesar and Pompey Clash of the Titans</italics><space/>(Oxford, 2006)</extension><space/>A visit to the ground has only confirmed me, Lucas wrote in 1921; and it was interesting to find that Mr. Apostolides, son of the large local landowner, the hospitality of whose farm at Teks I enjoyed, was convinced too that the [battle-]site was by Driskole [now Krini], for the very sound reason that neither the hills nor the river further east suit Caesars description. John D. Morgan in his definitive Palae-pharsalus the Battle and the Town,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The American Journal of Archaeology</italics>, Vol. 87, No. 1, Jan. 1983</extension><space/>arguing for a site closer still to Krini, where he places Palaepharsalos, writes: My reconstruction is similar to Lucass, and in fact I borrow one of his alternatives for the line of the Pompeian retreat. Lucass theory has been subjected to many criticisms, but has remained essentially unshaken.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The opposing armies</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="section">yes</arg><arg name="{{expand section|date">November 2013}}
{{refimprove section|date</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Caesarian army</heading><paragraph>Caesar had the following legions with him:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Legions of veterans from the<space/><link><target>Gallic Wars</target></link><space/>Caesar's favourite legion,<space/><link><target>Legio X Equestris</target><part>X ''Equestris''</part></link>, and those later known with the names of<space/><link><target>Legio VIII Augusta</target><part>VIII ''Augusta''</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Legio IX Hispana</target><part>IX ''Hispana''</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Legio XII Fulminata</target><part>XII ''Fulminata''</part></link></listitem><listitem>Legions levied for the civil war legions later known as<space/><link><target>Legio I Germanica</target><part>I ''Germanica''</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Legio III Gallica</target><part>III ''Gallica''</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Legio IV Macedonica</target><part>IV ''Macedonica''</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph>However, all of these legions were understrength. Some only had about a thousand men at the time of Pharsalus, due partly to losses at Dyrrhachium and partly to Caesar's wish to rapidly advance with a picked body as opposed to a ponderous movement with a large army.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://militaryhistory.about.com/od/battleswarsto1000/p/pharsalus.htm</arg><arg name="title">Battle of Pharsalus<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">militaryhistory.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-06-18</arg></template></extension><space/>According to his accounts, he had 80 cohorts on the battlefield, about 22,000 men.<extension extension_name='ref'>Julius Caesar, Commentarii de Bello Civili,III 89,2</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Pompeian army</heading><paragraph>In total, Caesar counted 110 complete cohorts in the Pompeian army, 11 legions consisting of about 45,000 men, although<space/><link><target>Orosius</target></link>, following<space/><link><target>Livy</target></link><space/>and Pollio, only counted 88 cohorts,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>and Hans Delbrck suggests that Caesar's count includes detachments at Dyrrachium and elsewhere, leaving only 88 cohorts in the Pompeian army.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hans Delbrck,<space/><italics>Warfare in Antiquity</italics>, p. 545.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Battle</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Battle of Pharsalus.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>400px</part><part>Battle formations as described by Plutarch in his Life of Caesar c. 44</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Deployment</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>Pompey had every tactical advantage an army could hope for; he held the higher ground, had superiority of numbers, and was better supplied from his many allies in Greece. This caused him to act conservatively. Pompey deployed his army in the traditional formation of three lines with a depth of ten men. Again according to convention he posted his most experienced legions on the flanks (the first and the third legion on his left with Pompey himself commanding, the Syrian legions in the center with Scipio, the Cilician legion and the Spanish cohorts on the right with Afranius), dispersing his new recruits along the center. Pompey's right was protected by the<space/><link><target>Enipefs</target><part>River Enipeus</part></link>, therefore he massed all his cavalry on Caesar's right. He had given command of the cavalry to<space/><link><target>Labienus</target></link>, the former commander of Caesar's favourite X legion. He deployed the rest of the army on his left together with his auxiliary troops. Pompey's plan was to allow Caesar's infantry to advance, have his cavalry attack and push back the numerically inferior Julian horses, and then attack Caesar's infantry from behind.</paragraph><paragraph>Caesar knew this would be his last stand as his army had run out of supplies, and with no lines of retreat they would be at Pompey's mercy and likely to be slaughtered if they lost the battle. This &quot;nothing to lose&quot; mentality was played up by Caesar to his men as he explained that defeat meant nothing less than death. Caesar also deployed in three lines but could only set them to six men deep if he was to match the length of Pompey's line. Like Pompey he was protected by the river on his left allowing him to position all his cavalry to the right as a counter. As was typical of Caesar he gambled and began discreetly thinning his already depleted ranks of men then repositioned them as a fourth line to support his cavalry against the inevitable assault by the much larger Pompeian cavalry. Caesar himself commanded the cavalry, he posted the renowned tenth legion on his right under<space/><link><target>Publius Cornelius Sulla</target><part>Sulla</part></link>, with the undermanned eighth and possibly the ninth on his left under<space/><link><target>Antonius</target><part>Marc Antony</part></link>. In the center he designated<space/><link><target>Gnaeus Domitius Calvinus</target><part>Domitius</part></link><space/>as the commanding officer.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Progress of the battle</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>There was significant distance between the two armies, according to Caesar.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III 92,1.</extension><space/>Pompey ordered his men not to charge, but to wait until Caesar's legions came into close quarters; Pompey's adviser<space/><link><target>Caius Triarius</target></link><space/>believed that Caesar's infantry would be fatigued and fall into disorder if they were forced to cover twice the expected distance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III, 92,2.</extension><space/>But seeing that Pompey's army was not advancing, Caesar's men, without orders, stopped to rest and regroup before continuing the charge;<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III, 93,1.</extension><space/>Caesar, in his history of the war, would praise his own men's discipline and experience, and questioned Pompey's decision not to charge.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III, 92,3.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The heavy infantry then engaged. Pompey's legions could take the attack due to their deep formations.<space/><link><target>Labienus</target></link><space/>then ordered the Pompeian cavalry to attack; as expected they successfully pushed back Caesar's cavalry until his hidden fourth line joined in, using their<space/><link><target>Pilum</target><part>pila</part></link><space/>to thrust at Pompey's cavalry and turn them to flight.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>After this, Caesar threw in his last line of reserves<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III, 93,4</extension><space/>a move which at this point meant that the battle was more or less decided.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>Pompey could see this; after observing his cavalry routed, Pompey retreated to his camp and left his troops to their own devices, ordering the garrison to defend camp as he gathered his family, loaded up gold, and threw off his general's cloak and fled.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Caesar urged his men to end the day by capturing the enemy camp. They complied with his wishes, furiously attacking the walls. The Thracians and the other auxiliaries who were left in the camp, in total seven cohorts, defended bravely, but were not able to fend off the assault.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Caesar had won his greatest victory, claiming to have only lost about 200 soldiers and 30 centurions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Caesar, BC III 99,1.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template>Pompey fled from Pharsalus to<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>, where he was assassinated on the order of<space/><link><target>Pharaoh</target></link><space/><link><target>Ptolemy XIII</target></link>. Ptolemy XIII sent Pompey's head to Caesar in an effort to win his favor, but instead secured him as a furious enemy. Ptolemy, advised by his regent, the eunuch<space/><link><target>Pothinus</target></link>, and his rhetoric tutor<space/><link><target>Theodotus of Chios</target></link>, had failed to take into account that Caesar was granting amnesty to a great number of those of the<space/><link><target>Optimates</target><part>senatorial</part></link><space/>faction in their defeat. Even men who had been bitter enemies were allowed not only to return to Rome but to assume their previous positions in Roman society.</paragraph><paragraph>Pompey's assassination had deprived Caesar of his ultimate public relations moment pardoning his most ardent rival. The Battle of Pharsalus ended the wars of the<space/><link><target>First Triumvirate</target></link>. The Roman Civil War, however, was not ended. Pompey's two sons,<space/><link><target>Gnaeus Pompeius</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sextus Pompey</target></link>, and the Pompeian faction, led now by Metellus Scipio and Cato, survived and fought for their cause in the name of Pompey the Great. Caesar spent the next few years 'mopping up' remnants of the<space/><link><target>Optimates</target><part>senatorial faction</part></link>. After seemingly destroying all his enemies and bringing peace to Rome he was assassinated by friends in a conspiracy organized by<space/><link><target>Marcus Junius Brutus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Gaius Cassius Longinus</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Importance</heading><paragraph>Paul K. Davis wrote that &quot;Caesar's victory took him to the pinnacle of power, effectively ending the Republic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Paul K. Davis,<space/><italics>100 Decisive Battles from Ancient Times to the Present: The Worlds Major Battles and How They Shaped History</italics><space/>(Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1999), 59.</extension><space/>The battle itself did not end the civil war but it was decisive and gave Caesar a much needed boost in legitimacy. Until then much of the Roman world outside Italy supported Pompey and his allies due to the extensive list of clients he held in all corners of the Republic. After Pompey's defeat former allies began to align themselves with Caesar as some came to believe the gods favored him, while for others it was simple self-preservation. The ancients took great stock in success as a sign of favoritism by the gods.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template><space/>This is especially true of success in the face of almost certain defeat as Caesar experienced at Pharsalus. This allowed Caesar to parlay this single victory into a huge network of willing clients to better secure his hold over power and force the Optimates into near exile in search for allies to continue the fight against Caesar.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph>The battle gives its name to the following artistic, geographical, and business concerns:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Pharsalia</target></link></italics>, a poem by<space/><link><target>Marcus Annaeus Lucanus</target><part>Lucan</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pharsalia, New York</target></link>, U.S.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pharsalia Technologies</target></link>, Inc.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/pha-phd/pharsalus/battle.html'>Caesar's account of the battle</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/30102514?seq=1'>Frank Laurence Lucas, 'The Battlefield of Pharsalos', ''Annual of the British School at Athens'', No. XXIV, 191921</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/4434412'>Michel Rambaud, 'Le Soleil de Pharsale', ''Historia: Zeitschrift fr Alte Geschichte '', Vol.3, No.4, 1955</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/283876'>William E. Gwatkin, Jr., 'Some Reflections on the Battle of Pharsalus', ''Transactions and Proceedings of the American Philological Association'', Vol. 87, 1956</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/stable/504663?seq=1'>John D. Morgan, 'Palae-pharsalus the Battle and the Town', ''The American Journal of Archaeology'', Vol. 87, No. 1, Jan. 1983</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Pharsalus</target></template><link><target>Category:Battles involving the Roman Republic</target><part>Pharsalus</part></link><link><target>Category:Julius Caesar</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Thessaly</target></link><link><target>Category:Battles in ancient Thessaly</target><part>Pharsalus</part></link><link><target>Category:Battles of Caesar's Civil War</target></link><link><target>Category:1st century BC in Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:48 BC in Europe</target></link></paragraph></article>