<article title='Economy_of_Equatorial_Guinea'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox economy</target><arg name="country"><space/>Equatorial Guinea
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Old Equatorial Guinean 1000 pesetas banknote, 1969.jpg
</arg><arg name="width"><space/>270
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Old Banknote of [[Equatorial Guinea]]
</arg><arg name="currency"><space/>[[CFA franc|Communaute Financiere Africaine franc]] (XAF)
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>calendar year
</arg><arg name="organs"><space/>[[Economic Community of Central African States|UDEAC]], [[Economic Community of Central African States|ECCAS]]
</arg><arg name="gdp rank"><space/>[[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|113th]] (nominal) / [[List of countries by GDP (PPP)|128th]] (PPP)
</arg><arg name="gdp"><space/>$10.41 billion (2009)<ref name</arg><arg name="growth"><space/>18.6% (2005){{Citation needed|date</arg><arg name="per capita"><space/>$15,401 (2009)<ref name</arg><arg name="sectors"><space/>''agriculture'': 4.6%, ''industry'': 87.3%, ''services'': 8.1% (2013 est.)
</arg><arg name="inflation"><space/>6.4% (2013)<ref>[http://www.worldbank.org/en/country/equatorialguinea Equatorial Guinea Home]</ref>
</arg><arg name="edbr"><space/>155th<ref name</arg><arg name="unemployment"><space/>22.3% (2009)<ref name</arg><arg name="industries"><space/>petroleum, fishing, saw-milling, natural gas<ref name</arg><arg name="exports"><space/>$15.44 billion (2013 est.)<ref name</arg><arg name="export-partners"><space/>{{flag|Japan}} 18.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|France}} 16.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|China}} 11.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|United States}} 11.3%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Spain}} 7.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Netherlands}} 7.1%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Italy}} 5.1% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="imports"><space/>$7.943 billion (2013 est.)
</arg><arg name="import-partners"><space/>{{flag|Spain}} 18.0%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|China}} 17.0%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|United States}} 10.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|France}} 7.9%<space/><br>{{flag|Côte d'Ivoire}} 6.7%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Italy}} 5.8%<space/><br><space/>{{flag|Brazil}} 4.3% (2012 est.)<ref>{{cite web|url</arg><arg name="debt"><space/>''external'': $289 million (2006)
</arg><arg name="revenue"><space/>$2.752 billion (2006)
</arg><arg name="expenses"><space/>$1.424 billion (2006)
</arg><arg name="aid"><space/>none
</arg><arg name="cianame"><space/>ek
</arg><arg name="spelling"><space/>US
</arg></template><link><target>Equatorial Guinea</target></link><space/>is a small country at the west coast of<space/><link><target>Central Africa</target></link>. Despite a per capita GDP (PPP) of more than US$30,000<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2005/02/data/dbcoutm.cfm?SD=2004&amp;amp;ED=2004&amp;amp;R1=1&amp;amp;R2=1&amp;amp;CS=3&amp;amp;SS=2&amp;amp;OS=C&amp;amp;DD=0&amp;amp;OUT=1&amp;amp;C=512-941-914-446-612-666-614-672-311-946-213-137-911-962-193-674-122-676-912-548-313-556-419-678-513-181-316-682-913-684-124-273-339-921-638-948-514-686-218-688-963-518-616-728-223-558-516-138-918-353-748-196-618-278-522-692-622-694-156-142-624-449-626-564-628-283-228-853-924-288-233-293-632-566-636-964-634-182-238-453-662-968-960-922-423-714-935-862-128-716-611-456-321-722-243-965-248-718-469-724-253-576-642-936-643-961-939-813-644-199-819-184-172-524-132-361-646-362-648-364-915-732-134-366-652-734-174-144-328-146-258-463-656-528-654-923-336-738-263-578-268-537-532-742-944-866-176-369-534-744-536-186-429-925-178-746-436-926-136-466-343-112-158-111-439-298-916-927-664-846-826-299-542-582-443-474-917-754-544-698&amp;amp;S=PPPPC&amp;amp;CMP=0&amp;amp;x=18&amp;amp;y=9IMF'>World Economic Outlook IMF Database, September 2005</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2005/02/data/dbcoutm.cfm?SD</arg><arg name="date">20150219212346<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>which is as of 2008 the<space/><link><target>List of countries by GDP (PPP) per capita</target><part>twentieth highest</part></link><space/>in the world, Equatorial Guinea ranks 121st out of 177 countries on the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/><link><target>Human Development Index</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Economy overview</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Equatorial Guinea Exports Treemap (2009).jpg</target><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part>Equatorial Guinea Exports Treemap (2009)</part></link><link><target>File:Rent Equatorial Guinea.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Comparison of GDP per capita of Equatorial Guinea and Spain, the former colonial power in the Area, basend on A. Maddieson (<link type='external' href='http://www.ggdc.net/MADDISON/Historical_Statistics/horizontal-file_02-2010.xls'>World Population, GDP and Per Capita GDP, 1-2010 AD</link>).</part></link>Pre-independence Equatorial Guinea counted on<space/><link><target>Cocoa bean</target><part>cocoa</part></link><space/>production for hard currency earnings. In 1959 it had the highest<space/><link><target>per capita income</target></link><space/>of Africa which it still has.</paragraph><paragraph>The discovery of large<space/><link><target>oil reserves</target></link><space/>in 1996 and its subsequent exploitation have contributed to a dramatic increase in government revenue. As of 2004,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/articles/A1101-2004Sep6.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Washington Post<space/></arg><arg name="title">U.S. Oil Firms Entwined in Equatorial Guinea Deals<space/></arg><arg name="first">Justin<space/></arg><arg name="last">Blum<space/></arg><arg name="date">2004-09-07</arg></template></extension><space/>Equatorial Guinea is the third-largest oil producer in<space/><link><target>Sub-Saharan Africa</target></link>. Its oil production has risen to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>360000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template>, up from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>220000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>only two years earlier.</paragraph><paragraph>Forestry,<space/><link><target>agriculture</target><part>farming</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>fishing</target></link><space/>are also major components of GDP. Subsistence farming predominates. Although pre-independence Equatorial Guinea counted on cocoa production for hard currency earnings, the neglect of the rural economy under successive regimes has diminished potential for agriculture-led growth. However, the government has stated its intention to reinvest some<space/><link><target>petroleum</target><part>oil</part></link><space/>revenue into agriculture. A number of aid programs sponsored by the World Bank and the IMF have been cut off since 1993 because of corruption and mismanagement. No longer eligible for concessional financing because of large oil revenues, the government has been unsuccessfully trying to agree on a &quot;shadow&quot; fiscal management program with the<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target><part>IMF</part></link>. Businesses, for the most part, are owned by government officials and their family members. Undeveloped natural resources include<space/><link><target>titanium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>iron ore</target></link>,<space/><link><target>manganese</target></link>,<space/><link><target>uranium</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>alluvium</target><part>alluvial</part></link><space/><link><target>gold</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Mining industry of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>Mining in Equatorial Guinea</part></link>). Growth remained strong in 2005 and 2006, led by oil.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In greater depth</heading><paragraph>Oil and gas exports have increased substantially (in 2003<space/><link><target>Equatorial Guinea</target></link><space/>was ranked third among<space/><link><target>Africa</target><part>Sub-Sahara African</part></link><space/>producers behind<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Angola</target></link>) and will drive the economy for years to come. The GDP increased by 105.2% in 1997, and real GDP growth reached 23% in 1999, and initial estimates suggested growth of about 15% in 2001, according to IMF 2001 forecast. Per capita income grew from about $1,000 in 1998 to about $2,000 in 2000. The energy export sector is responsible for this rapid growth. Oil production has increased from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>81000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>210000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>between 1998 and early 2001. There is ongoing additional development of existing commercially viable oil and gas deposits as well as new exploration in other offshore concessions.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea has other largely unexploited human and natural resources, including a tropical climate, fertile soils, rich expanses of water, deepwater ports, and an untapped, if unskilled, source of labor. Following independence in 1968, the country suffered under a repressive dictatorship for 11 years, which devastated the economy. The agricultural sector, which historically was known for cocoa of the highest quality, has never fully recovered. In 1969 Equatorial Guinea produced 36,161 tons of highly bid cocoa, but production dropped to 4,800 tons in 2000. Coffee production also dropped sharply during this period to bounce back to 100,000 metric tons in 2000. Timber is the main source of foreign exchange after oil, accounting for about 12.4% of total export earnings in 1996-99. Timber production increased steadily during the 1990s; wood exports reached a record 789,000 cubic meters in 1999 as demand in Asia (mainly China) gathered pace after the 1998 economic crisis. Most of the production (mainly Okoume) goes to exports, and only 3% is processed locally. Environmentalists fear that exploitation at this level is unsustainable and point out to the permanent damage already inflicted on the forestry reserves on Bioko.</paragraph><paragraph>Consumer price inflation has declined from the 38.8% experienced in 1994 following the CFA franc devaluation, to 7.8% in 1998, and 1.0% in 1999, according to BEAC data. Consumer prices rose about 6% in 2000, according to initial estimates, and there was anecdotal evidence that price inflation was accelerating in 2001.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea's policies, as defined by law, comprise an open investment regime. Qualitative restrictions on imports, non-tariff protection, and many import licensing requirements were lifted when in 1992 the government adopted a public investment program endorsed by the World Bank. The Government of the Republic of Equatorial Guinea has sold some state enterprises. It is attempting to create a more favourable investment climate, and its investment code contains numerous incentives for job creation, training, promotion of non-traditional exports, support of development projects and indigenous capital participation, freedom for repatriation of profits, exemption from certain taxes and capital, and other benefits. Trade regulations have been further liberalized since implementation in 1994 of the ICN<space/><link><target>turnover tax</target></link>, in conformity with Central African tax and custom reform codes. The reform included elimination of quota restrictions and reductions in the range and amounts of tariffs. The CEMAC countries agreed to replace the ICN with a value added tax (VAT) in 1999.</paragraph><paragraph>While business laws promote a liberalized economy, the business climate remains difficult. Application of the laws remains selective. Corruption among officials is widespread, and many business deals are concluded under non-transparent circumstances.</paragraph><paragraph>There is little industry in the country, and the local market for industrial products is small. The government seeks to expand the role of free enterprise and to promote foreign investment but has had little success in creating an atmosphere conducive to investor interest.</paragraph><paragraph>The Equato-Guinean budget has grown enormously in the past 3 years as royalties and taxes on foreign company oil and gas production have provided new resources to a once poor government. The 2001 budget foresaw revenues of about 154<space/><link><target>1000000000 (number)</target><part>billion</part></link><space/>CFA francs (154 GCFAF) (about U.S.$200 million), up about 50% from 2000 levels. Oil revenues account for about two-thirds of government revenue, and VAT and trade taxes are the other large revenue sources.</paragraph><paragraph>Year 2001 government expenditures were planned to reach 158 billion CFA francs, up about 50% from 2000 levels. New investment projects represented about 40% of the budget, and personnel and internal and external debt payments represented about one-third of planned expenditures.</paragraph><paragraph>The Equato-Guinean Government has undertaken a number of reforms since 1991 to reduce its predominant role in the economy and promote private sector development. Its role is a diminishing one, although many government interactions with the private sector are at times capricious. Beginning in early 1997, the government initiated efforts to attract significant private sector involvement through a Corporate Council on Africa visit and numerous ministerial efforts. In 1998, the government privatized distribution of petroleum products. There are now Total and Mobil stations in the country. The government has expressed interest in privatizing the outmoded electricity utility. A French company operates cellular telephone service in cooperation with a state enterprise. The government is anxious for greater U.S. investment, and President Obiang visited the U.S. three times between 1999 and 2001 to encourage greater U.S. corporate interest. Investment in agriculture, fishing, livestock, and tourism are among sectors the government would like targeted.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea's balance-of-payments situation has improved substantially since the mid-1990s because of new oil and gas production and favorable world energy prices. Exports totaled about francs CFA 915 billion in 2000 (1.25 G$US), up from CFA 437 billion (700 M$US) in 1999. Crude oil exports accounted for more than 90% of export earnings in 2000. Timber exports, by contrast, represented only about 5% of export revenues in 2000. Additional oil production coming on line in 2001, combined with methanol gas exports from the new CMS-Nomeco plant, should increase export earnings substantially.</paragraph><paragraph>Imports into Equatorial Guinea also are growing very quickly. Imports totaled francs CFA 380 billion (530 M$US), up from franc CFA 261 million (420 M$US) in 1999. Imports of equipment used for the oil and gas sector accounted for about three-quarters of imports in 2000. Imports of capital equipment for public investment projects reached francs CFA 30 billion in 2000, up 40% from 1999 levels.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea's foreign debt stock was approximately francs CFA 69 billion (100 M$US) in 2000, slightly less than the debt stock in 1999, according to BEAC data. Equatorial Guinea's<space/><link><target>debt service ratio</target></link><space/>fell from 20% of GDP in 1994 to only 1% in 2000. Foreign exchange reserves were increasing slightly, although they were relatively low in terms of import coverage. According to the terms of the franc CFA zone, some of these reserves are kept in an account with the French Ministry of Finance.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea in the 1980s and 1990s received foreign assistance from numerous bilateral and multilateral donors, including European countries, the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link>. Many of these aid programs have ceased altogether or have diminished.<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>continue to provide some project assistance, as do<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cuba</target></link>. The government also has discussed working with World Bank assistance to develop government administrative capacity.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea operated under an<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target><part>IMF</part></link>-negotiated<space/><link><target>Enhanced structural adjustment facility</target><part>Enhanced Structural Adjustment Facility</part></link><space/>(ESAF) until 1996. Since then, there have been no formal agreements or arrangements. The International monetary Fund held Article IV consultations (periodic country evaluations) in 1996, 1997, and in August 1999. After the 1999 consultations, IMF directors stressed the need for Equatorial Guinea to establish greater fiscal discipline, accountability, and more transparent management of public sector resources, especially energy sector revenue. IMF officials also have emphasized the need for economic data. In 1999, the Equato-Guinean Government began attempting to meet IMF-imposed requirements, maintaining contact with IMF and the World Bank representatives. However, the newfound oil wealth allowed the government to avoid improving fiscal discipline, transparency and accountability.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Infrastructure</heading><paragraph>Infrastructure is generally old and in poor condition. Surface transport is extremely limited at present, with little more than 700 kilometres of paved roads. The African Development Bank is helping to improve the paved roads from Malabo to Luba and Riaba; the Chinese are undertaking a project to link Mongomo to Bata on the mainland, and the European Union is financing an inter-states road network linking Equatorial Guinea to Cameroon and Gabon. Road maintenance is often inadequate.</paragraph><paragraph>Electricity is available in Equatorial Guinea's larger towns thanks to three small overworked hydropower facilities and a number of aged generators. In 1999, national production was about 13 MWh. In Malabo, the American company, CMS-Nomeco, built a 10 megawatt electricity plant financed by the government, which came in line in mid-2000, and plans to double capacity are advancing. This plant provides improved service to the capital, although there are still occasional outages. On the mainland the largest city, Bata, still has regular blackouts.</paragraph><paragraph>Water is only available in the major towns and is not always reliable because of poor maintenance and mismanagement. Some villages and rural areas are equipped with generators and water pumps, usually owned by private individuals.</paragraph><paragraph>Parastatal Getesa, a joint venture with a minority ownership stake held by a French subsidiary of<space/><link><target>Orange S.A.</target><part>Orange</part></link>, provides telephone service in the major cities. The regular system is overextended, but Orange has introduced a popular GSM system, which is generally reliable in Malabo and Bata.</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea has two of the deepest Atlantic seaports of the region, including the main business and commercial port city of Bata. The ports of both Malabo and Bata are severely overextended and require extensive rehabilitation and reconditioning. The British company, Incat, has an ongoing project with the government to renovate and expand Luba, the country's third-largest port which is located on Bioko Island. The government hopes Luba will become a major transportation hub for offshore oil and gas companies operating in the Gulf of Guinea. Luba is located some 50 kilometres from Malabo and had been virtually inactive except for minor fishing activities and occasional use to ease congestion in Malabo. A new jetty is also being built at km 5 on the way from Malabo to the airport. It is a project mainly supposed to service the oil industry, but can also relieve the congested Malabo Port due to its closeness.The Oil Jetty at km 5 was supposed to open the end of March 2003. Riaba is the other port of any scale on Bioko but is less active. The continental ports of Mbini and Cogo have deteriorated as well and are now used primarily for timber activities.</paragraph><paragraph>There are both air and sea connections between the two cities of Malabo and Bata. A few aging Soviet-built aircraft operated by several small carriers, one state-owned, and the others private, constitute the national aircraft fleet. The runway at Malabo (3,200 m) is equipped with lights and can service equipment similar to DC 10s and Cl3Os. The one at Bata (2,400 m) does not operate at night but can accommodate aircraft as large as B737s. Their primary users are the national airline (EGA) and a private company (GEASA). Two minor airstrips (800 m) are located at Mongomo and Annobon. There are international connections out of Malabo to Madrid and Zurich in Europe and to Cotonou, Douala and Libreville in West Africa.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Energy developments</heading><paragraph>After a slow start, Equatorial Guinea has recently<template><target>when</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template><space/>emerged as a major oil producer in the Gulf of Guinea, one of the most promising<space/><link><target>hydrocarbon</target></link><space/>regions in the world. The main<space/><link><target>oil field</target><trail>s</trail></link>, Zafiro and Alba, both lie located offshore of Bioko island. In 1999 oil production was about five times its 1996 level;<space/><link><target>Zafiro Field</target></link>, operated by<space/><link><target>Exxon Mobil</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ocean Energy</target></link>, produced about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template>, and<space/><link><target>CMS Nomeco</target></link><space/>extracted approximately<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>6700</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template>. Aggressive field development and promising exploration activities may raise production to nearly<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>300000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>within 2 to 3 years (slightly above the current estimated production of Gabon) according to the official sources.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1995 Mobil (now Exxon Mobil) discovered the large Zafiro field,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="date"><space/>1996-09-02
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Oil & Gas Journal]]
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>94
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>36
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>38
<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0030-1388
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2013-08-29
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Partners discovered the Zafiro oil accumulation in March 1995 and declared the field commercial in October 1995.
</arg></template></extension>with estimated reserves of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>400000000</arg><arg>oilbbl</arg></template>. Production began in 1996. The company announced a 3-year U.S.$1bn rapid-development program to boost output to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>130000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>by early 2001. Progress was delayed due to a contractual dispute with the government and by unexpectedly difficult geology. The difference with the government was eventually resolved.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1998 a more liberal regulatory and profit-sharing arrangement for<space/><link><target>hydrocarbon exploration</target></link><space/>and production activities was introduced. It revised and updated the production-sharing contract, which, until then, had favoured Western operators heavily. As a result, domestic oil receipts rose from 13% to 20% of oil export revenue. However, the government's share remains relatively poor by international standards.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1997 CMS Nomeco moved to expand its operation with a U.S.$300m methanol plant. The plant entered production in 2000 and helped boost<space/><link><target>natural gas condensate</target></link><space/>output from Alba field.</paragraph><paragraph>In August 1999 the government closed bidding on a new petroleum-licensing round for 53 unexplored deepwater blocks and seven shallow-water blocks. The response was small due to a combination of factors, including falling oil-prices, restructuring within the oil industry, and uncertainty over an undemarcated maritime border with Nigeria (which was not resolved until 2000).</paragraph><paragraph>In late 1999<space/><link><target>Triton Energy</target></link>, a U.S. independent, discovered La Ceiba in block G in an entirely new area offshore the mainland of the country. Triton expects a U.S.$200m development program to enable La Ceiba and associated fields to produce<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100000</arg><arg>oilbbl/d</arg></template><space/>by late 2001, despite disappointments and technical problems at the beginning of the year.</paragraph><paragraph>With an upturn in oil prices, exploration intensified in 2000. In April 2000 U.S.-based Vanco Energy signed a production-sharing contract for the offshore block of Corisco Deep. In May 2000,<space/><link><target>Chevron Corporation</target><part>Chevron</part></link><space/>was granted block L, offshore<space/><link><target>Rio Muni</target></link>, and a further three production-sharing contracts (for blocks J, I, and H) were signed with<space/><link><target>Atlas Petroleum</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Nigerian</target></link><space/>company.</paragraph><paragraph>In early 2001 the government announced plans to establish a national oil company, to allow Equatorial Guinea to take a greater stake in the sector and to facilitate the more rapid transfer of skills. However, critics<template><target>who</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template><space/>fear that such a company may become a vehicle for opaque accounting and inertia of the sort that has hindered development in neighbouring countries including<space/><link><target>Angola</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Since 2001 the government has created<space/><link><target>GEPetrol</target></link>, a national oil company; and<space/><link><target>Sonagas</target></link>, a national natural-gas company. The company<space/><link><target>EG LNG</target></link><space/>has been created to construct and operate the Bioko Island<space/><link><target>LNG</target></link><space/>plant and terminal. The plant began to operate in May 2007 and a second plant is now<template><target>when</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template><space/>under development.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://lnglicensing.conocophillips.com/EN/news/documents/FirstLNGCargoFromEquatorialGuinea.pdf'></link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://lnglicensing.conocophillips.com/EN/news/documents/FirstLNGCargoFromEquatorialGuinea.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="date">20130516013344<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Animal Husbandry</heading><paragraph>Cattle and poultry production is rapidly reaching its pre-independence levels of self-sufficiency with the financial help of the<space/><link><target>African Development Bank</target></link>. However, production of domesticated animals is hindered by the presence of<space/><link><target>trypanosomiasis</target></link><space/>and other tropical deterrents. In 2005 there were 37,600 sheep, 9,000 goats, 6,100 hogs, and 5,000 cattle.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Fishing</heading><paragraph>The fishing industry gained strength through the 1980s and is now almost entirely modernized; a<space/><link><target>tuna</target></link><space/>processing plant went into operation in 1990.<space/><link><target>Annobn</target></link><space/>subsists almost entirely on fishing and retains its traditional preeminence in off shore<space/><link><target>whaling</target></link><space/>and turtle gathering. Bioko is also a major fishing center, the chief catches being<space/><link><target>Perch (disambiguation)</target><part>perch</part></link>, tuna,<space/><link><target>mackerel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cod</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Esox</target><part>pike</part></link>,<space/><link><target>shark</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>crayfish</target></link>. The countrys own catch was about 3,500 tons in 2003.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Forestry</heading><paragraph>Timber from Ro Muni is Equatorial Guineas leading export. Forests cover over 62 percent of the land area. The Ro Muni area on the mainland produces okoum and akoga from rain forests of considerable age. Even though the government has given permission to foreign firms, exploitation is difficult due to infrastructural problems. The government enacted a new forestry action plan in 1990 in an effort to strengthen the sectors development. In 2004, roundwood production was estimated at 811,000 cubic metres. In 2004, exports of forest products amounted to $97 million:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>$24 billion (2009 est.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Investment (gross fixed)</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>46.3% (2005 est.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Industries</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Petroleum, fishing, sawmilling, natural gas</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Industrial production growth rate</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>30% (2002 est.)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Electricity - production</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>29.43 GWh (2005)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Electricity - consumption</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>27.37 GWh (2005)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Agriculture - products</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><link><target>Coffee</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cocoa bean</target><part>cocoa</part></link>,<space/><link><target>rice</target></link>,<space/><link><target>yam (vegetable)</target><part>yams</part></link>,<space/><link><target>cassava</target></link><space/>(<link><target>tapioca</target></link>),<space/><link><target>banana</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>palm oil</target></link><space/>nuts; livestock; timber</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Exchange rates</defkey><defval></defval></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Communaut financire africaine francs (CFAF) per US$1 - 480.56 (2005), 528.29 (2004), 581.2 (2003), 696.99 (2002), 733.04 (2001)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Equatorial Guinea</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>reflist</target></template></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Regional/Africa/Equatorial_Guinea/Business_and_Economy/Economic_Development</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.trademap.org/open_access/Index.aspx?proceed=true&amp;amp;reporter=226'>Equatorial Guinea latest trade data on ITC Trade Map</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.equatorialoil.com/'>Equatorial Oil</link>- Government source on economics, run by the Ministry of Mines, Industry and Energy</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Economy of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>'''</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Economy Of Equatorial Guinea</target></template><link><target>Category:African Union member economies</target><part>Equatorial Guinea</part></link><link><target>Category:Economy of Equatorial Guinea</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>