<article title='Foreign_policy_of_the_United_States'><paragraph><template><target>Use American English</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/><template><target>Use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><template><target>Politics of the United States</target></template>The<space/><bold>foreign policy of the United States</bold><space/>is the way in which it interacts with foreign nations and sets standards of interaction for its organizations, corporations and individual citizens.</paragraph><paragraph>The officially stated goals of the foreign policy of the United States, including all the Bureaus and Offices in the<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/rls/dos/1718.htm</extension><space/>as mentioned in the<space/><italics>Foreign Policy Agenda</italics><space/>of the Department of State, are &quot;to build and sustain a more democratic, secure, and prosperous world for the benefit of the American people and the international community.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/s/d/rm/index.htm#mission</arg><arg name="title">Bureau of Budget and Planning</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>In addition, the<space/><link><target>United States House Committee on Foreign Affairs</target></link><space/>states as some of its jurisdictional goals: &quot;export controls, including nonproliferation of nuclear technology and nuclear hardware; measures to foster commercial interaction with foreign nations and to safeguard American business abroad; international commodity agreements; international education; and protection of American citizens abroad and expatriation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.internationalrelations.house.gov/about.asp?nav</arg><arg name="title">About the Committee</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>US foreign policy and<space/><link><target>United States foreign aid</target><part>foreign aid</part></link><space/>have been the subject of much debate, praise and<space/><link><target>Criticism of the United States government</target><part>criticism</part></link>, both domestically and abroad.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Powers of the President and Congress</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Foreign policy US government structure.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>400px</part><part>The US Constitution gives much of the foreign policy decision-making to the presidency, but the Senate has a role in ratifying treaties, and the Supreme Court interprets treaties when cases are presented to it.</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Treaty Clause</arg><arg>War Powers Clause</arg><arg>Appointments Clause</arg><arg>Commerce Clause</arg><arg name="l4">Foreign Commerce Clause</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Subject to the advice and consent role of the<space/><link><target>U.S. Senate</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target></link><space/>negotiates treaties with foreign nations, but treaties enter into force if ratified by two-thirds of the Senate. The President is also<space/><link><target>Commander in Chief</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>United States Armed Forces</target></link>, and as such has broad authority over the armed forces; however only Congress has authority to declare war, and the civilian and military budget is written by the Congress. The<space/><link><target>United States Secretary of State</target></link><space/>is the<space/><link><target>foreign minister</target></link><space/>of the United States and is the primary conductor of state-to-state diplomacy. Both the Secretary of State and ambassadors are appointed by the President, with the advice and consent of the Senate. Congress also has power to regulate commerce with foreign nations.<extension extension_name='ref'>James M. McCormick,<space/><italics>American Foreign Policy and Process</italics><space/>(2009) ch 7-8</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical overview</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of U.S. foreign policy</arg><arg>Timeline of United States diplomatic history</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Jay-treaty.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Jay Treaty</target></link><space/>of 1795 aligned the U.S. more with Britain and less with France, leading to political polarization at home</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The main trend regarding the history of U.S. foreign policy since the American Revolution is the shift from<space/><link><target>non-interventionism</target></link><space/>before and after<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, to its growth as a world power and global<space/><link><target>hegemony</target></link><space/>during and since World War II and the end of the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>in the 20th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>George C. Herring,<space/><italics>From Colony to Superpower: U.S. Foreign Relations Since 1776</italics><space/>(2008)</extension><space/>Since the 19th century, US foreign policy also has been characterized by a shift from the<space/><link><target>Political realism</target><part>realist school</part></link><space/>to the idealistic or<space/><link><target>Wilsonian</target></link><space/>school of international relations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Russell, &quot;American Diplomatic Realism: A Tradition Practised and Preached by George F. Kennan,&quot;<space/><italics>Diplomacy and Statecraft</italics>, Nov 2000, Vol. 11 Issue 3, pp&amp;nbsp;15983</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Foreign policy themes were expressed considerably in<space/><link><target>George Washington</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>George Washington's Farewell Address</target><part>farewell address</part></link>; these included among other things, observing good faith and justice towards all nations and cultivating peace and harmony with all, excluding both &quot;inveterate antipathies against particular nations, and passionate attachments for others&quot;, &quot;steer[ing] clear of permanent alliances with any portion of the foreign world&quot;, and advocating trade with all nations. These policies became the basis of the<space/><link><target>Federalist Party</target></link><space/>in the 1790s. But the rival<space/><link><target>Jeffersonian Democracy</target><part>Jeffersonians</part></link><space/>feared Britain and favored France in the 1790s, declaring the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link><space/>on Britain. After the 1778 alliance with France, the U.S. did not sign another permanent treaty until the<space/><link><target>North Atlantic Treaty</target></link><space/>in 1949. Over time, other themes, key goals, attitudes, or stances have been variously expressed by<space/><link><target>United States Presidential doctrines</target><part>Presidential 'doctrines'</part></link>, named for them. Initially these were uncommon events, but since WWII, these have been made by most presidents.</paragraph><paragraph>In general, the United States followed an<space/><link><target>isolationist</target></link><space/>foreign policy until attacks against U.S. shipping by<space/><link><target>Barbary corsairs</target></link><space/>spurred the country into developing a naval force projection capability, resulting in the<space/><link><target>First Barbary War</target></link><space/>in 1801.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Oren</arg><arg name="first">Michael B.</arg><arg name="title">The Middle East and the Making of the United States, 1776 to 1815</arg><arg name="date">2005-11-03</arg><arg name="url">http://www.columbia.edu/cu/news/05/11/michaelOren.html</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite occasional entanglements with European Powers such as the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link><space/>and the 1898<space/><link><target>SpanishAmerican War</target></link>, U.S. foreign policy was marked by steady expansion of its foreign trade and scope during the 19th century, and it maintained its policy of avoiding wars with and between European powers. Concerning its domestic borders, the 1803<space/><link><target>Louisiana Purchase</target></link><space/>doubled the nation's geographical area; Spain ceded the territory of<space/><link><target>Florida</target></link><space/>in 1819; annexation brought Texas in 1845; a war with Mexico in 1848 added California, Arizona and New Mexico. The U.S. bought<space/><link><target>Alaska Purchase</target><part>Alaska</part></link><space/>from the Russian Empire in 1867, and it annexed the Republic of Hawaii in 1898. Victory over Spain in 1898 brought the<space/><link><target>Philippines</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Puerto Rico</target></link>, as well as oversight of Cuba. The short experiment in imperialism ended by 1908, as the U.S. turned its attention to the Panama Canal and the stabilization of regions to its south, including Mexico.</paragraph><heading level='3'>20th century</heading><heading level='4'>World War I</heading><paragraph>The 20th century was marked by two world wars in which the United States, along with allied powers, defeated its enemies and increased its international reputation. President<space/><link><target>Woodrow Wilson</target><part>Wilson</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Fourteen Points</target></link><space/>was developed from his idealistic<space/><link><target>Wilsonianism</target></link><space/>program of spreading democracy and fighting militarism so as to end wars. It became the basis of the German Armistice (really a surrender) and the 1919<space/><link><target>Paris Peace Conference, 1919</target><part>Paris Peace Conference</part></link>. The resulting<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link>, due to European allies' punitive and territorial designs, showed insufficient conformity with these points and the U.S. signed separate treaties with each of its adversaries; due to Senate objections also, the U.S. never joined the<space/><link><target>League of Nations</target></link>, which was established as a result of Wilson's initiative. In the 1920s, the United States followed an independent course, and succeeded in a program of<space/><link><target>Washington Naval Conference</target><part>naval disarmament</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Dawes Plan</target><part>refunding the German economy</part></link>. New York became the financial capital of the world, but the downside was that the<space/><link><target>Wall Street Crash of 1929</target></link><space/>hurled the entire world into the<space/><link><target>Great Depression</target></link>. American trade policy relied on high tariffs under the Republicans, and reciprocal trade agreements under the Democrats, but in any case exports were at very low levels in the 1930s.</paragraph><heading level='4'>World War II</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Diplomatic history of World War II#United States</arg></template><link><target>File:Yalta Conference cropped.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Allies of World War II</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Yalta Conference</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franklin D. Roosevelt</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target></link>.</part></link>The United States adopted a non-interventionist foreign policy from 1932 to 1938, but then President<space/><link><target>Franklin D. Roosevelt</target></link><space/>moved toward strong support of the Allies in their wars against Germany and Japan. As a result of intense internal debate, the national policy was one of becoming the<space/><link><target>Arsenal of Democracy</target></link>, that is financing and equipping the Allied armies without sending American combat soldiers. Roosevelt mentioned four fundamental freedoms, which ought to be enjoyed by people &quot;everywhere in the world&quot;; these included the freedom of speech and religion, as well as freedom from want and fear. Roosevelt helped establish terms for a post-war world among potential allies at the<space/><link><target>Atlantic Charter</target><part>Atlantic Conference</part></link>;<space/><link><target>Atlantic Charter#Content and analysis</target><part>specific points</part></link><space/>were included to correct earlier failures, which became a step toward the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>. American policy was to threaten Japan, to force it out of China, and to prevent its attacking the Soviet Union. However, Japan reacted by an attack on Pearl Harbor in December 1941, and the United States was at war with Japan, Germany, and Italy. Instead of the loans given to allies in World War I, the United States provided Lend-Lease grants of $50,000,000,000. Working closely with<space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link><space/>of Britain, and Joseph Stalin of the Soviet Union, Roosevelt sent his forces into the Pacific against Japan, then into North Africa against Italy and Germany, and finally into Europe starting with France and Italy in 1944 against the Germans. The American economy roared forward, doubling industrial production, and building vast quantities of airplanes, ships, tanks, munitions, and, finally, the atomic bomb. Much of the American war effort went to strategic bombers, which flattened the cities of Japan and Germany.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Cold War</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>History of the Cold War</arg></template><link><target>File:President Nixon meets with China's Communist Party Leader, Mao Tse- Tung, 02-29-1972 - NARA - 194759.tif</target><part>thumb</part><part>Chinese Communist Party Chairman<space/><link><target>Mao Zedong</target></link><space/>meets with U.S. President<space/><link><target>Richard Nixon</target></link>, 1972</part></link>After the war, the U.S. rose to become the dominant non-colonial economic power with broad influence in much of the world, with the key policies of the<space/><link><target>Marshall Plan</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Truman Doctrine</target></link>. Almost immediately however, the world witnessed division into broad two camps during the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>; one side was led by the U.S., and the other by the Soviet Union, but this situation also led to the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Non-Aligned Movement</target></link>. This period lasted until almost the end of the 20th century, and is thought to be both an ideological and power struggle between the two superpowers. A policy of<space/><link><target>containment</target></link><space/>was adopted to limit Soviet expansion, and a series of proxy wars were fought with mixed results. In 1991, the Soviet Union dissolved into separate nations, and the Cold War formally ended as the United States gave separate diplomatic recognition to the Russian Federation and other former Soviet states. With these changes to forty-five years of established diplomacy and military confrontation, new challenges confronted U.S. policymakers. American foreign policy is characterized by the protection of its national interests.</paragraph><heading level='3'>21st century</heading><paragraph>In the 21st century, U.S. influence remains strong but, in relative terms, is declining in terms of economic output compared to rising nations such as China, India, Russia, Brazil, and the newly consolidated<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link>. Substantial problems remain, such as<space/><link><target>climate change</target></link>,<space/><link><target>nuclear proliferation</target></link>, and the specter of<space/><link><target>nuclear terrorism</target></link>. Foreign policy analysts Hachigian and Sutphen in their book<space/><italics>The Next American Century</italics><space/>suggest all six powers have similar vested interests in stability and terrorism prevention and trade; if they can find common ground, then the next decades may be marked by peaceful growth and prosperity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws13jans3w2"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Nikolas K. Gvosdev<space/></arg><arg name="title">FDR's Children<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Hachigian&nbsp;... and Sutphen&nbsp;... recognize that the global balance of power is changing; that despite America's continued predominance, the other pivotal powers "do challenge American dominance and impinge on the freedom of action the U.S. has come to enjoy and expect." Rather than focusing on the negatives, however, they believe that these six powers have the same vested interests: All are dependent on the free flow of goods around the world and all require global stability in order to ensure continued economic growth (and the prosperity it engenders).<space/></arg><arg name="work">National Interest<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-01-02<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://nationalinterest.org/bookreview/fdrs-children-1931<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-01-13<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20100826001356/http://nationalinterest.org:80/bookreview/fdrs-children-1931<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">26 August 2010<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Law</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Treaty</arg><arg>Treaty Clause</arg></template>In the United States, there are three types of treaty-related law:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Executive agreement</target><trail>s</trail></link></bold><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Congressional-executive agreements</bold><space/>are made by the<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>president</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>United States Congress</target><part>Congress</part></link>. A majority of both houses makes it binding much like regular legislation after it is signed by the president. The constitution does not expressly state that these agreements are allowed, and constitutional scholars such as<space/><link><target>Laurence Tribe</target></link><space/>think they are unconstitutional.<extension extension_name='ref'>Laurence H. Tribe, &quot;Taking Text and Structure Seriously: Reflections on Free-Form Method in Constitutional Interpretation,&quot; 108 Harv. L. Rev.1221, 1227 (1995).</extension><space/>However, the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target><part>U.S. Supreme Court</part></link><space/>has upheld their validity.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template></listitem><listitem><bold>Sole executive agreements</bold><space/>are made by the<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>president</part></link><space/>alone.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>Treaties</bold><space/>are formal written agreements specified by the<space/><link><target>Treaty Clause</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target><part>Constitution</part></link>. The president makes a treaty with foreign powers, but then the proposed treaty must be ratified by a two-thirds vote in the<space/><link><target>United States Senate</target><part>Senate</part></link>. For example, President<space/><link><target>Woodrow Wilson</target><part>Wilson</part></link><space/>proposed the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link><space/>after World War I after consulting with allied powers, but this treaty was rejected by the<space/><link><target>United States Senate</target><part>U.S. Senate</part></link>; as a result, the U.S. subsequently made separate agreements with different nations. While most international law has a broader interpretation of the term<space/><italics><link><target>treaty</target></link></italics>, the U.S. sense of the term is more restricted. In<space/><italics><link><target>Missouri v. Holland</target></link></italics>, the Supreme Court ruled that the power to make treaties under the U.S. Constitution is a power separate from the other enumerated powers of the federal government, and hence the federal government can use treaties to legislate in areas which would otherwise fall within the exclusive authority of the states.</listitem></list><paragraph>International law in most nations considers all three of the above agreements as<space/><italics><link><target>Treaty</target><part>treaties</part></link></italics>. In most nations, treaty laws supersede domestic law. So if there is a conflict between a treaty obligation and a domestic law, then the treaty usually prevails.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast to most other nations, the United States considers the three types of agreements as distinct. Further, the United States incorporates treaty law into the body of U.S. federal law. As a result,<space/><link><target>United States Congress</target><part>Congress</part></link><space/>can modify or repeal treaties afterwards. It can overrule an agreed-upon treaty obligation even if this is seen as a violation of the treaty under international law. Several U.S. court rulings confirmed this understanding, including the 1900<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target><part>Supreme Court</part></link><space/>decision in<space/><italics><link><target>The Paquete Habana</target><part>Paquete Habana</part></link></italics>, a late 1950s decision in<space/><italics><link><target>Reid v. Covert</target></link></italics>, and a lower court ruling in 1986 in<space/><italics><link><target>Garcia-Mir v. Meese</target></link></italics>. Further, the Supreme Court has declared itself as having the power to rule a treaty as void by declaring it &quot;unconstitutional&quot;, although as of 2011, it has never exercised this power.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target><part>State Department</part></link><space/>has taken the position that the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on the Law of Treaties</target></link><space/>represents established law. Generally when the U.S. signs a treaty, it is binding. However, because of the<space/><italics><link><target>Reid v. Covert</target></link></italics><space/>decision, the U.S. adds a<space/><link><target>Reservation (law)</target><part>reservation</part></link><space/>to the text of every treaty that says, in effect, that the U.S. intends to abide by the treaty, but if the treaty is found to be in violation of the<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target><part>Constitution</part></link>, then the U.S. legally can't abide by the treaty since the U.S. signature would be<space/><italics><link><target>ultra vires</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Alliances</heading><heading level='3'>NATO</heading><paragraph>[[Image:USA military relations 2007.png|thumb|A map of allies of the United States<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><template><target>legend</target><arg>#3300CC</arg><arg>[[NATO]] member states, including their colonies and overseas possessions</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>#6666FF</arg><arg>[[Major non-NATO ally|Major non-NATO allies]], plus [[Taiwan|Republic of China (Taiwan)]]</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>#66B2FF</arg><arg>Signatories of [[Partnership for Peace]] with NATO</arg></template>]]The United States is a founding member of<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>, the world's largest military alliance. The 28-nation alliance consists of Canada and much of Europe, including the nation with NATO's second largest military, the United Kingdom. Under the NATO charter, the United States is compelled to defend any NATO state that is attacked by a foreign power. NATO is restricted to within the North American and European areas. In 1989, the United States also granted five nations the<space/><link><target>major non-NATO ally</target></link><space/>status (MNNA); this number was increased in the late 1990s and following the<space/><link><target>September 11 attacks</target></link>; it currently includes 28 nations. Each such state has a unique relationship with the United States, involving various military and economic partnerships and alliances.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Geography</heading><paragraph><template><target>globalize</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>United Kingdom–United States relations</arg></template><template><target>Further</target><arg>Special Relationship</arg><arg>Anglosphere</arg></template><link><target>File:Barack &amp; Michelle Obama meet Queen Elizabeth II at Buckingham Palace 4-1-09.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>225px</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Elizabeth II</target><part>Queen Elizabeth II</part></link><space/>welcomes President Obama and First Lady Michelle Obama to<space/><link><target>Buckingham Palace</target></link><space/>on April 1, 2009.</part></link>United States foreign policy affirms its alliance with the United Kingdom as its most important<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/><link><target>bilateral relationship</target></link><space/>in the world, evidenced by aligned political affairs between the<space/><link><target>White House</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>10 Downing Street</target></link>, as well as joint military operations carried out between the two nations. While both the United States and the United Kingdom maintain close relationships with many other nations around the world, the level of cooperation in military planning, execution of military operations, nuclear weapons technology, and intelligence sharing with each other has been described as &quot;unparalleled&quot; among major powers throughout the 20th and early 21st century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wither"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last">James<space/></arg><arg name="first">Wither<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">An Endangered Partnership: The Anglo-American Defence Relationship in the Early Twenty-first Century<space/></arg><arg name="journal">European Security<space/></arg><arg name="volume">15<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">47–65<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/09662830600776694<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-01-09<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0966-2839</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The United States and Britain share the world's largest foreign direct investment partnership. American investment in the United Kingdom reached $255.4 billion in 2002, while British direct investment in the United States totaled $283.3 billion.<extension extension_name='ref'>US Department of State, Background Note on the United Kingdom</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Barack Obama meets Stephen Harper.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Prime Minister of Canada</target><part>Canadian Prime Minister</part></link><space/><link><target>Stephen Harper</target></link><space/>(right) and President Obama (left) meet in Ottawa in February 2009</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Canada–United States relations</arg></template>The bilateral relationship between Canada and the United States is of notable importance to both countries. About 7585% of Canadian trade is with the United States, and Canada is the United States' largest trading partner and chief supplier of oil. While there are disputed issues between the two nations, relations are close and the two countries share the &quot;<link><target>Canada United States border</target><part>world's longest undefended border</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>John Herd Thompson, and Stephen J. Randall,<space/><italics>Canada and the United States: Ambivalent Allies</italics><space/>(4th ed. McGill-Queen's University Press, 2008) is the standard scholarly survey</extension><space/>The border was demilitarized after the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link><space/>and, apart from minor raids<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template>, has remained peaceful. Military collaboration began during World War II and continued throughout the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>on both a bilateral basis and a multilateral relationship through<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>. A high volume of trade and migration between the United States and Canada since the 1850s has generated closer ties, despite continued Canadian fears of being culturally overwhelmed by its neighbor, which is nine times larger in terms of population and eleven times larger in terms of economy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsG37"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>5. Report for Selected Countries and Subjects<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>''International Monetary Fund''<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/>15,064 billions (figure for 2011) 313 million persons<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2011-11-09<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2011/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2011-11-09</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="imf2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.imf.org/external/pubs/ft/weo/2011/02/weodata/weorept.aspx?sy</arg><arg name="title">Canada</arg><arg name="publisher">International Monetary Fund</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-11-05</arg></template></extension><space/>The two economies have increasingly merged since the<space/><link><target>North American Free Trade Agreement</target></link><space/>(NAFTA) of 1994, which also includes Mexico.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mexico</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Mexico–United States relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The United States shares a unique and often complex relationship with Mexico. A history of armed conflict goes back to the<space/><link><target>Texas Revolution</target></link><space/>in the 1830s, the<space/><link><target>MexicanAmerican War</target></link><space/>in the 1840s, and an American invasion in the 1910s. Important treaties include the<space/><link><target>Gadsden Purchase</target></link>, and multilaterally with Canada, the<space/><link><target>North American Free Trade Agreement</target></link>. The central issue in recent years has been illegal immigration, followed by illegal gun sales (from the U.S.), drug smuggling (to the U.S.) and escalating drug cartel violence just south of the U.S.-Mexico border.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tim Padgett, &quot;Mexico's Caldern Needs to Listen, Not Just Lecture U.S.&quot;<space/><italics>TIME</italics><space/>May 19, 2010<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.time.com/time/world/article/0,8599,1990176,00.html'>online</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Burton Kirkwood,<space/><italics>The History of Mexico</italics><space/>(2010) pp&amp;nbsp;9799, 138-52, 216</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Australia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Australia–United States relations</arg></template><link><target>Image:Barack Obama &amp; Kevin Rudd in the Oval Office 3-24-09.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Former<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of Australia</target><part>Australian Prime Minister</part></link><space/><link><target>Kevin Rudd</target></link><space/>talks with United States President Barack Obama in Washington</part></link>The United States' relationship with Australia is a very close one, with<space/><link><target>United States Secretary of State</target><part>Secretary of State</part></link><space/><link><target>Hillary Clinton</target></link><space/>stating that &quot;America doesn't have a better friend in the world than Australia&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Lyndal Curtis for The World Today<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/news/stories/2009/03/25/2525854.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rudd's warm Washington welcome - ABC News (Australian Broadcasting Corporation)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abc.net.au<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-03-25<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><space/>The relationship is formalized by the<space/><link><target>ANZUS</target><part>ANZUS treaty</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>AustraliaUnited States Free Trade Agreement</target></link>.The two countries have a shared history, both have previously been British Colonies and many Americans flocked to the<space/><link><target>Australian gold rushes</target><part>Australian goldfields</part></link><space/>in the 19th century. At a strategic level, the relationship really came to prominence in World War II, when the two nations worked extremely closely in the<space/><link><target>Pacific War</target></link><space/>against Japan, with General<space/><link><target>Douglas MacArthur</target></link><space/>undertaking his role as Supreme Allied Commander based in Australia, effectively having Australian troops and resources under his command. During this period, the cultural interaction between Australia and the U.S. were elevated to a higher level as over 1 million U.S. military personnel moved through Australia during the course of the war. The relationship continued to evolve throughout the second half of the 20th Century, and today now involves strong relationships at the executive and mid levels of government and the military, leading<space/><link><target>Assistant Secretary of State for East Asian and Pacific Affairs</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kurt M. Campbell</target></link><space/>to declare that &quot;in the last ten years, [Australia] has ascended to one of the closest one or two allies [of the U.S.] on the planet&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TVNZ_3065958"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://tvnz.co.nz/q-and-a-news/q-guyon-espiner-interviews-kurt-campbell-3065958<space/></arg><arg name="title">Q+A: Guyon Espiner interviews Kurt Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 11, 2009<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Television New Zealand]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">September 30, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Middle East</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>United States foreign policy in the Middle East</arg></template>The United States has many important allies in the<space/><link><target>Greater Middle East</target></link><space/>region. These allies are<space/><link><target>Turkey-United States relations</target><part>Turkey</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Saudi ArabiaUnited States relations</target><part>Saudi Arabia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>MoroccoUnited States relations</target><part>Morocco</part></link>,<space/><link><target>JordanUnited States relations</target><part>Jordan</part></link>,<space/><link><target>AfghanistanUnited States relations</target><part>Afghanistan</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IsraelUnited States relations</target><part>Israel</part></link>,<space/><link><target>EgyptUnited States relations</target><part>Egypt</part></link>,<space/><link><target>KuwaitUnited States relations</target><part>Kuwait</part></link>,<space/><link><target>BahrainUnited States relations</target><part>Bahrain</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>QatarUnited States relations</target><part>Qatar</part></link>. Israel and Egypt are leading recipients of United States foreign aid, receiving $2.775 billion<extension extension_name='ref' name="jewishvirtuallibrary.org">https://www.jewishvirtuallibrary.org/jsource/US-Israel/aid2010.html Congress Approves FY2010 Aid to Israel</extension><space/>and 1.75 billion<extension extension_name='ref' name="smh"></extension><space/>in 2010. Turkey is an ally of the United States through its membership in<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>, while all of the other countries except Saudi Arabia and Qatar are<space/><link><target>major non-NATO allies</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The United States toppled the government of<space/><link><target>Saddam Hussein</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>2003 invasion of Iraq</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://fas.org/sgp/crs/natsec/RL33110.pdf The Cost of Iraq, Afghanistan, and other Global War on Terror Operations since 9/11</extension><space/><link><target>Turkey</target></link><space/>is host to approximately 90<space/><link><target>B61 nuclear bomb</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Incirlik Air Base</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.todayszaman.com/tz-web/news-206266-report-us-considers-withdrawing-nuclear-bombs-from-turkey.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Report: US considers withdrawing nuclear bombs from Turkey<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Todayszaman.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-04-03<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><space/>Other allies include<space/><link><target>Qatar</target></link>, where 3,500 U.S. troops are based,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Sciutto<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jim<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://abcnews.go.com/WNT/story?id</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Troops Preparing for War in Qatar - ABC News<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abcnews.go.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bahrain</target></link>, where the<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target></link><space/>maintains<space/><link><target>Naval Support Activity Bahrain</target><part>NSA Bahrain</part></link>, home of<space/><link><target>United States Naval Forces Central Command</target><part>NAVCENT</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United States Fifth Fleet</target><part>Fifth Fleet</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Japan</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Japan–United States relations</arg></template>The relationship began in the 1850s as the U.S. was a major factor in forcing Japan to resume contacts with the outer world beyond a very restricted role. In the late 19th century the Japanese sent many delegations to Europe, and some to the U.S., to discover and copy the latest technology and thereby modernize Japan very rapidly and allow it to build its own empire. There was some friction over control of Hawaii and the Philippines, but Japan stood aside as the U.S. annexed those lands in 1898. Likewise the U.S. did not object when Japan took control of Korea. The two nations cooperated with the European powers in suppressing the<space/><link><target>Boxer Rebellion</target></link><space/>in China in 1900, but the U.S. was increasingly troubled about Japan's denial of the<space/><link><target>Open Door Policy</target></link><space/>that would ensure that all nations could do business with China on an equal basis.<extension extension_name='ref'>Foster Rhea Dulles,<space/><italics>Yankees and Samurai: America's Role in the Emergence of Modern Japan, 17911900</italics><space/>(1965)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>President Theodore Roosevelt admired Japan's strength as it defeated a major European power, Russia. He brokered an end to the war between Russia and Japan in 19056. Anti-Japanese sentiment (especially on the West Coast) soured relations in the 190724 era. In the 1930s the U.S. protested vehemently against Japan's seizure of Manchuria (1931), its war against China (193745), and its seizure of Indochina (Vietnam) 194041. American sympathies were with China and Japan rejected increasingly angry American demands that Japan pull out of China. The two nations fought an all-out war 194145; the U.S. won a total victory, with heavy bombing (including two atomic bombs on Hiroshima and Nagasaki) that devastated Japan's 50 largest industrial cities. The American army under<space/><link><target>Douglas MacArthur</target></link><space/>occupied and ruled Japan, 194551, with the successful goal of sponsoring a peaceful, prosperous and democratic nation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walter LaFeber,<space/><italics>The Clash: A History of USJapan Relations</italics><space/>(W.W. Norton, 1997)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1951, the U.S. and Japan signed<space/><link><target>Treaty of San Francisco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Security Treaty Between the United States and Japan</target></link>, subsequently revised as<space/><link><target>Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security between the United States and Japan</target></link><space/>in 1960, relations since then have been excellent. The United States considers Japan to be one of its closest allies, and it is both a Major Non-NATO ally and NATO contact country. The United States has several military bases in Japan including<space/><link><target>Yokosuka, Kanagawa</target><part>Yokosuka</part></link>, which harbors the<space/><link><target>United States Seventh Fleet</target><part>U.S. 7th Fleet</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Japan Self-Defense Forces</target><part>JSDF</part></link>, or Japanese Self Defense Force, cross train with the U.S. Military, often providing auxiliary security and conducting war games. When the U.S.President Barack Obama met with Japanese Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Taro Aso</target></link><space/>in 2009, he said the relationship with Japan as the &quot;cornerstone of security in East Asia&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Japanese Prime Minister Meets With Obama, Says Economy Complicates North Korea Talks</arg><arg name="work">Washington Post</arg><arg name="date">2009-02-25</arg><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/02/24/AR2009022403404.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-01-24</arg><arg name="first">Glenn</arg><arg name="last">Kessler</arg></template></extension><space/>After the several years of critical moment during<space/><link><target>Democratic Party of Japan</target><part>Japan's Democratic Party</part></link><space/>administration, President Obama and Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Shinzo Abe</target></link><space/>reconfirmed the importance of its alliance and currently the U.S. and Japan negotiating to participate<space/><link><target>Trans-Pacific Strategic Economic Partnership</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Japan and United States Reaffirm Their Close Ties</arg><arg name="work">New York Times</arg><arg name="date">2013-02-22</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2013/02/23/world/asia/japan-and-united-states-reaffirm-their-close-ties.html?pagewanted</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-02-23</arg><arg name="first">Jackie</arg><arg name="last">Calmes</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.whitehouse.gov/the-press-office/2013/02/22/joint-statement-united-states-and-japan'>Joint Statement by the United States and Japan</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>South Korea</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>South Korea–United States relations</arg></template><link><target>South Korea</target></link>United States relations have been most extensive since 1945, when the United States helped establish capitalism in South Korea and led the UN-sponsored<space/><link><target>Korean War</target></link><space/>against North Korea and China (19501953).<extension extension_name='ref'>Jae Ho Chung,<space/><italics>Between Ally and Partner: Korea-China Relations and the United States</italics><space/>(2008)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.amazon.com/gp/reader/0231139071/'>excerpt and text search</link></extension><space/>Stimulated by heavy American aid<template><target>by whom</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template>, South Korea's rapid economic growth, democratization and modernization greatly reduced its U.S. dependency. Large numbers of U.S. forces remain in Korea. At the 2009 G-20 London summit, U.S. President Barack Obama called South Korea &quot;one of America's closest allies and greatest friends.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Republic of Korea Embassy in the United States"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://seoul.usembassy.gov/rok_040209.html<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20090704211009/http://seoul.usembassy.gov/rok_040209.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-07-04<space/></arg><arg name="title">President Obama Vows Strengthened U.S.-South Korea Ties</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>China</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Sino-American relations</arg></template><link><target>File:Chinadialogue speaking CK-0038.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>President<space/><link><target>Barack Obama</target></link><space/>addresses the opening session of the first U.S.China Strategic and Economic Dialogue.</part></link>American relations with the<space/><link><target>China</target><part>People's Republic of China</part></link><space/>are quite strong, yet complex. A great amount of trade between the two countries necessitates positive political relations, although occasional disagreements over tariffs, currency exchange rates and the<space/><link><target>Political status of Taiwan</target></link><space/>do occur. Nevertheless, the United States and China have an extremely extensive partnership. The U.S. criticizes China on human rights issues and in recent years, China has criticized the United States on human rights in return.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Taiwan</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Republic of China–United States relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Taiwan</target></link><space/>(officially the Republic of China), does not have official<space/><link><target>diplomacy</target><part>diplomatic relations</part></link><space/>with America and no longer receives<space/><link><target>diplomatic recognition</target></link><space/>from the State Department of the United States, but it conducts unofficial diplomatic relations through its<space/><link><target>de facto</target></link><space/>embassy, commonly known as the &quot;<link><target>American Institute in Taiwan</target></link><space/>(AIT)&quot;, and is considered to be a strong Asian ally and supporter of the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nancy Bernkopf Tucker, ed.,<space/><italics>Dangerous Strait: The U.S.-Taiwan-China Crisis</italics><space/>(2005)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>ASEAN</heading><paragraph><link><target>Association of Southeast Asian Nations</target></link><space/>(ASEAN) is an important partner for United States in both economic and geostrategic aspects. ASEAN's geostrategic importance stems from many factors, including: the strategic location of member countries, the large shares of global trade that pass through regional waters, and the alliances and partnerships which the United States shares with ASEAN member states. In July 2009, the United States signed ASEAN's Treaty of Amity and Cooperation, which establishes guiding principles intended to build confidence among its signatories with the aim of maintaining regional peace and stability.<extension extension_name='ref'>Daniel Seah, &quot;The Treaty of Amity and Cooperation in Southeast Asia: The Issue of Non-Intervention and its Accession by Australia and the USA,&quot;<space/><italics><space/>Chinese Journal of international Law and</italics><space/>(2012) 11#4 pp 785 - 822<space/><link type='external' href='http://chinesejil.oxfordjournals.org/content/11/4/785.short'>online</link></extension><space/>Trade flows are robust and increasing between America and the ASEAN region.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Indonesia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Indonesia–United States relations</arg></template>As the largest ASEAN member,<space/><link><target>Indonesia</target></link><space/>has played an active and prominent role in developing the organization.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thejakartapost.com/news/2011/07/20/editorial-the-asean-cage.html</arg><arg name="title">Editorial: The ASEAN cage ''Jakarta Post''7 July 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>For United States, Indonesia is important for dealing with certain issues; such as terrorism,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdi.org/terrorism/priority.cfm'>U.S.-Indonesia Military Relations in The Anti-Terror War</link></extension><space/>democracy, and how United States project its relations with Islamic world, since Indonesia has the world's largest Islamic population, and one that honors and respects religious diversity.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.trumanproject.org/posts/2011/02/indonesia-important-focus-point-world-security'>Indonesia: An Important Focus Point for World Security</link></extension><space/>US eyes Indonesia as potential strategic allies in Southeast Asia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="asean.org"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.asean.org/afp/111.htm</arg><arg name="title">404</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>During his stately visit to Indonesia, U.S. President<space/><link><target>Barack Obama</target></link><space/>has held up Indonesia as an example of how a developing nation can embrace democracy and diversity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-pacific-11723650</arg><arg name="title">BBC News - Obama hails Indonesia as example for world</arg><arg name="work">BBC News</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg><arg name="date">November 10, 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://projects.washingtonpost.com/obama-speeches/speech/486/'>Obama delivers a speech in the University of Indonesia</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Malaysia</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Malaysia–United States relations</arg></template>Despite increasingly strained relations under the<space/><link><target>Mahathir Mohamad</target></link><space/>government, ties have been thawed under<space/><link><target>Najib Razak</target></link>'s administration. Economic ties are particularly robust, with the United States being Malaysia's largest trading partner and Malaysia is the tenth-largest trading partner of the U.S. Annual two-way trade amounts to $49 billion. The United States and Malaysia launched negotiations for a bilateral free trade agreement (FTA) in June 2006.</paragraph><paragraph>The United States and Malaysia enjoy strong security cooperation. Malaysia hosts the Southeast Asia Regional Center for Counterterrorism (SEARCCT), where over 2000 officials from various countries have received training. The United States is among the foreign countries that has collaborated with the center in conducting capacity building programmes. The U.S. and Malaysia share a strong military-to-military relationship with numerous exchanges, training, joint exercises, and visits.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Myanmar</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Burma–United States relations</arg></template>Bilateral ties have generally been strained but are slowly improving. The United States has placed broad sanctions on Burma because of the<space/><link><target>8888 Uprising</target><part>military crackdown in 1988</part></link><space/>and the military regime's refusal to honour the<space/><link><target>Burmese general election, 1990</target><part>election results of the 1990</part></link><space/>People's Assembly election. Similarly, the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>has placed embargoes on Burma, including an arms embargo, cessation of trade preferences, and suspension of all aid with the exception of<space/><link><target>humanitarian aid</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EU"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/comm/external_relations/myanmar/intro/index.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The EU's relations with Burma / Myanmar<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-07-13<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[European Union]]</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20060725000750/http%3A//ec.europa.eu/comm/external_relations/myanmar/intro/index.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>25 July 2006</arg><arg name="deadurl">yes</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>US and European government sanctions against the military government, alongside boycotts and other types direct pressure on corporations by western supporters of the Burmese democracy movement, have resulted in the withdrawal from Burma of most U.S. and many European companies. However, several Western companies remain due to loopholes in the sanctions.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.foreignpolicy.com/story/cms.php?story_id=3986'>The List: Burma's Economic Lifelines</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Foreign Policy</target></link></italics>. October 2007</extension><space/>Asian corporations have generally remained willing to continue investing in Myanmar and to initiate new investments, particularly in<space/><link><target>natural resource</target></link><space/>extraction.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>201112 Burmese political reforms</target><part>Ongoing reforms</part></link><space/>have improved relations between Burma and the United States.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Philippines</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Philippines–United States relations</arg></template>The United States ruled the Philippines from 1898 to 1946. The Spanish government ceded the Philippines to the United States in the<space/><link><target>1898 Treaty of Paris</target></link><space/>that ended the SpanishAmerican War. The United States finally recognized Philippine independence on July 4, 1946 in the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Manila (1946)</target><part>Treaty of Manila</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://untreaty.un.org/unts/1_60000/1/6/00000254.pdf</arg><arg name="format">pdf</arg><arg name="title">TREATY OF GENERAL RELATIONS BETWEEN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA AND THE REPUBLIC OF THE PHILIPPINES. SIGNED AT MANILA, ON 4 JULY 1946</arg><arg name="publisher">United Nations</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-12-10</arg></template></extension><space/>July 4 was observed in the Philippines as<space/><italics>Independence Day</italics><space/>until August 4, 1964 when, upon the advice of historians and the urging of nationalists, President<space/><link><target>Diosdado Macapagal</target></link><space/>signed into law Republic Act No. 4166 designating June 12 as the country's<space/><italics>Independence Day</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.chanrobles.com/republicacts/republicactno4166.html</arg><arg name="title">REPUBLIC ACT NO. 4166 - AN ACT CHANGING THE DATE OF PHILIPPINE INDEPENDENCE DAY FROM JULY FOUR TO JUNE TWELVE, AND DECLARING JULY FOUR AS PHILIPPINE REPUBLIC DAY, FURTHER AMENDING FOR THE PURPOSE SECTION TWENTY-NINE OF THE REVISED ADMINISTRATIVE CODE</arg><arg name="date">August 4, 1964</arg><arg name="publisher">Chanrobles law library</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-11</arg></template></extension><space/>Since 2003 the U.S. has designated the<space/><link><target>Philippines</target></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>Major non-NATO ally</target><part>Major Non-NATO Ally</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Thailand</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Thailand–United States relations</arg></template>Thailand and the US are both former<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia Treaty Organization</target></link><space/>(SEATO) members, being close partners throughout the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>, and are still close allies. Since 2003, the U.S. has designated<space/><link><target>Thailand</target></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>major non-NATO ally</target><part>Major Non-NATO Ally</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Vietnam</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>United States–Vietnam relations</arg></template>United States involved in<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link><space/>in 1955 to 1975. In 1995,<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>President</part></link><space/><link><target>Bill Clinton</target></link><space/>announced the formal normalization of diplomatic relations with<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>. Today US eyes Vietnam as a potential strategic ally in Southeast Asia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="asean.org"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Eastern Europe</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:President Barack Obama talks with Prime Minister Arseniy Yatsenyuk of Ukraine at the conclusion of their bilateral meeting in the Oval Office, March 12, 2014. (Official White House Photo by Pete Souza)1 of 7.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Left</part><part>President<space/><link><target>Barack Obama</target></link><space/>talks with Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Arseniy Yatsenyuk</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ukraine</target></link><space/>at the conclusion of their bilateral meeting in the<space/><link><target>Oval Office</target></link>, March 12, 2014.</part></link><link><target>File:Defense.gov News Photo 990625-M-5696S-008.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>U.S. Marines greet local Albanian boys in<space/><link><target>Kosovo</target></link><space/>on June 25, 1999</part></link>American relations with Eastern Europe are influenced by the legacy of the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>. Since the collapse of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>, former Communist-bloc states in Europe have gradually transitioned to democracy and capitalism. Many have also joined the<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>, strengthening economic ties with the broader Western world and gaining the military protection of the United States via the<space/><link><target>North Atlantic Treaty</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Kosovo</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Kosovo–United States relations</arg></template>The UN Security Council divided on the question of<space/><link><target>2008 Kosovo declaration of independence</target><part>Kosovo's declaration of independence</part></link>. Kosovo declared its independence on February 17, 2008, whilst Serbia objected that Kosovo is part of its territory. Of the five members with veto power in the UN Security Council, the USA, UK, and France<space/><link><target>International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence</target><part>recognized</part></link><space/>the declaration of independence, and<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>has expressed concern, while Russia considers it<space/><link><target>International reaction to the 2008 Kosovo declaration of independence</target><part>illegal</part></link>. &quot;In its declaration of independence,<space/><link><target>Kosovo</target></link><space/>committed itself to the highest standards of democracy, including freedom and tolerance and justice for citizens of all ethnic backgrounds&quot;, President<space/><link><target>George W Bush</target></link><space/>said on February 19, 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.america.gov/st/peacesec-english/2008/February/20080219131902idybeekcm0.4052851.html'>Bush Hails Kosovo Independence</link>, U.S. Department of State's Bureau of International Information Programs</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2007/jun/11/balkans.usa'>Bush insists Kosovo must be independent and receives hero's welcome in Albania</link>, The Guardian</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hub and spoke vs multilateral</heading><paragraph>While America's relationships with Europe have tended to be in terms of multilateral frameworks, such as NATO, America's relations with Asia have tended to be based on a &quot;hub and spoke&quot; model using a series of bilateral relationships where states coordinate with the United States and do not collaborate with each other.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Hufbauer</arg><arg name="first1">Gary Clyde</arg><arg name="last2">Schott</arg><arg name="first2">Jeffrey J.</arg><arg name="title">Western Hemisphere Economic Integration</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="publisher">Peterson Institute</arg><arg name="pages">132–22</arg></template></extension><space/>On May 30, 2009, at the<space/><link><target>Shangri-La Dialogue</target></link><space/>Defense Secretary Robert M. Gates urged the nations of Asia to build on this hub and spoke model as they established and grew multilateral institutions such as<space/><link><target>ASEAN</target></link>,<space/><link><target>APEC</target></link><space/>and the ad hoc arrangements in the area.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/news/2009/05/mil-090530-afps03.htm</arg><arg name="title">Gates Delivers Keynote Address to Open Asia Security Conference</arg><arg name="author">John Pike</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>However, in 2011 Gates said that the United States must serve as the &quot;indispensable nation,&quot; for building multilateral cooperation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Shanker, Tom.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/03/world/asia/03Gates.html'>&quot;Gates Talks of Boosting Asian Security Despite Budget Cuts.&quot;</link><space/><italics>New York Times</italics>, 1 June 2011.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Oil</heading><heading level='3'>Persian Gulf</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Energy policy of the United States</arg><arg>Petroleum politics</arg></template><link><target>File:US Navy 030402-N-5362A-004 U.S. Army Sgt. Mark Phiffer stands guard duty near a burning oil well in the Rumaylah Oil Fields in Southern Iraq.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A U.S. soldier stands guard duty near a burning oil well in the<space/><link><target>Rumaila oil field</target></link>, Iraq, April 2003</part></link>As of 2014, the U.S. currently produces about 66% of the<space/><link><target>Petroleum</target><part>oil</part></link><space/>that it consumes.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.eia.gov/countries/country-data.cfm?fips=US</extension><space/>While its imports have exceeded domestic production since the early 1990s, new<space/><link><target>hydraulic fracturing</target></link><space/>techniques and discovery of shale oil deposits in Canada and the American Dakotas offer the potential for increased energy independence from oil exporting countries such as<space/><link><target>OPEC</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.eia.doe.gov/pub/oil_gas/petroleum/data_publications/company_level_imports/current/import.html'>Crude Oil and Total Petroleum Imports Top 15 Countries</link></extension><space/>Former U.S. President<space/><link><target>George W. Bush</target></link><space/>identified dependence on imported oil as an urgent<space/><italics>&quot;national security concern&quot;.</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bloomberg.com/apps/news?pid=10000087&amp;amp;sid=ar4D7HVGikXo&amp;amp;refer=top_world_news'>Bush Leverage With Russia, Iran, China Falls as Oil Prices Rise</link>, Bloomberg.com</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Two-thirds of the world's proven<space/><link><target>oil reserves</target></link><space/>are estimated to be found in the<link><target>Persian Gulf</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9E02E4D6123AF93AA15752C0A9649C8B63'>Shrinking Our Presence in Saudi Arabia</link>, New York Times</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://science.nationalgeographic.com/science/environment/alternative-energy/end-cheap-oil.html'>The End of Cheap Oil</link>, National Geographic</extension><space/>Despite its distance, the Persian Gulf region was first proclaimed to be of national interest to the United States during World War II.<space/><link><target>Petroleum</target></link><space/>is of central importance to modern armies, and the United Statesas the world's leading oil producer at that timesupplied most of the oil for the<space/><link><target>Allies of World War II</target><part>Allied</part></link><space/>armies. Many U.S. strategists were concerned that the war would dangerously reduce the U.S. oil supply, and so they sought to establish good relations with<space/><link><target>Saudi Arabia</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Monarchy</target><part>kingdom</part></link><space/>with large oil reserves.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.globalpolicy.org/security/oil/2005/crudedesigns.htm</arg><arg name="title">Crude Designs:</arg><arg name="author">James Paul - Global Policy Forum</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Persian Gulf region continued to be regarded as an area of vital importance to the United States during the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>. Three Cold War<space/><link><target>United States Presidential doctrines</target></link>the<space/><link><target>Truman Doctrine</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Eisenhower Doctrine</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Nixon Doctrine</target></link>played roles in the formulation of the<space/><link><target>Carter Doctrine</target></link>, which stated that the United States would use military force if necessary to defend its &quot;<link><target>national interest</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; in the<space/><link><target>Persian Gulf</target></link><space/>region.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/20874331/'>The war is about oil but it's not that simple</link>, msnbc.com</extension><space/>Carter's successor, President<space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link>, extended the policy in October 1981 with what is sometimes called the<space/><italics>&quot;Reagan Corollary to the Carter Doctrine&quot;</italics>, which proclaimed that the United States would intervene to protect Saudi Arabia, whose security was threatened after the outbreak of the<space/><link><target>IranIraq War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.history.navy.mil/wars/dstorm/sword-shield.htm'>The United States Navy and the Persian Gulf</link></extension><space/>Some analysts have argued that the implementation of the Carter Doctrine and the Reagan Corollary also played a role in the outbreak of the<space/><link><target>Iraq War</target><part>2003 Iraq War</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.haaretz.com/hasen/spages/996605.html'>What if the Chinese were to apply the Carter Doctrine?</link>, Haaretz - Israel News</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,921819,00.html'>Selling the Carter Doctrine</link>, TIME</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article2461214.ece'>Alan Greenspan claims Iraq war was really for oil</link>, Times Online</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2008/jun/20/iraq.oil'>Oil giants to sign contracts with Iraq</link>, The Guardian</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph>Almost all of Canada's energy exports go to the United States, making it the largest foreign source of U.S. energy imports: Canada is consistently among the top sources for U.S. oil imports, and it is the largest source of U.S. natural gas and electricity imports.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Energy Information Administration,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.eia.doe.gov/emeu/cabs/Canada/Background.html'>&quot;Canada&quot; (2009 report)</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Africa</heading><paragraph>In 2007 the U.S. was<space/><link><target>Sub-Saharan Africa</target></link>'s largest single export market accounting for 28.4% of exports (second in total to the EU at 31.4%). 81% of U.S. imports from this region were petroleum products.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.agoa.gov/resources/US_African_Trade_Profile_2009.pdf</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Foreign aid</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>United States foreign aid</arg><arg>United States Agency for International Development</arg></template>Foreign assistance is a core component of the State Department's international affairs budget, which is $49 billion in all for 2014.<extension extension_name='ref' name="appropriations.house.gov">See<space/><link type='external' href='http://appropriations.house.gov/uploadedfiles/01.13.14_fy_2014_omnibus_-_state_foreign_operations_-_summary.pdf'>&quot;FY 2014 Omnibus State and Foreign Operations Appropriations&quot; (Jan 2014)</link></extension><space/>Aid is considered an essential instrument of U.S. foreign policy. There are four major categories of non-military foreign assistance: bilateral development aid, economic assistance supporting U.S. political and security goals, humanitarian aid, and multilateral economic contributions (for example, contributions to the World Bank and International Monetary Fund).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://fpc.state.gov/documents/organization/31987.pdf'>Foreign Aid: An Introductory Overview of U.S. Programs and Policy</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In absolute dollar terms, the United States government is the largest international aid donor ($23 billion in 2014).<extension extension_name='ref' name="appropriations.house.gov"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>USAID</target><part>U.S. Agency for International Development</part></link><space/>(USAID) manages the bulk of bilateral economic assistance; the Treasury Department handles most multilateral aid. In addition many private agencies, churches and philanthropies provide aid.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the United States is the largest donor in absolute dollar terms, it is actually ranked 19 out of 27 countries on the<space/><link><target>Commitment to Development Index</target></link>. The CDI ranks the 27 richest donor countries on their policies that affect the developing world. In the aid component the United States is penalized for low net aid volume as a share of the economy, a large share of<space/><link><target>tied aid</target><part>tied</part></link><space/>or partially tied aid, and a large share of aid given to less poor and relatively undemocratic governments.</paragraph><paragraph>Foreign aid is a highly partisan issue in the United States, with liberals, on average, supporting foreign aid much more than conservatives do.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sup.org/books/title/?id</arg><arg name="title">The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs - Peter Hays Gries</arg><arg name="author">Stanford University Press</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Military</heading><paragraph>The United States has fought wars and intervened militarily on many occasions. See,<space/><link><target>Timeline of United States military operations</target></link>. The U.S. also operates a vast network of military bases around the world. See,<space/><link><target>List of United States military bases</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In recent years, the U.S. has used its military superiority as sole superpower to lead a number of wars, including, most recently, the invasion of<space/><link><target>Iraq</target></link><space/>in March 2003 as part of its global &quot;War on Terror.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aid</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>United States military aid</arg><arg>United States Foreign Military Financing</arg><arg>Foreign Military Sales</arg></template><link><target>File:Flickr - The U.S. Army - Humanitarian aid in Rajan Kala, Afghanistan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>U.S. Soldiers unload humanitarian aid for distribution to the town of Rajan Kala,<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, December 2009</part></link>The<space/><link><target>United States military aid</target><part>U.S. provides military aid</part></link><space/>through many different channels. Counting the items that appear in the budget as '<link><target>United States Foreign Military Financing</target><part>Foreign Military Financing</part></link>' and '<link><target>Plan Colombia</target></link>', the U.S. spent approximately $4.5 billion in military aid in 2001, of which $2 billion went to<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, $1.3 billion went to<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>, and $1 billion went to<space/><link><target>Colombia</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.amnestyusa.org/all-countries/colombia/us-military-aid-to-colombia/page.do?id</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Policy in Colombia &#124; Amnesty International USA<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Amnestyusa.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><space/>Since<space/><link><target>9/11</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link><space/>has received approximately $11.5 billion in direct military aid.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.thenews.com.pk/daily_detail.asp?id</arg><arg name="title">The News International: Latest, Breaking, Pakistan, Sports and Video News</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As of 2004, according to Fox News, the U.S. had more than 700 military bases in 130 different countries.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fox News, 1 November 2004<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.globalsecurity.org/org/news/2004/041101-iraq-basing.htm'>Analysts Ponder U.S. Basing in Iraq</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Estimated US foreign military financing and aid by recipient for 2010:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Recipient</tablehead><tablehead>Military aid (USD Billions)</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Iraq</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>6.50</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Afghanistan</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>5.60<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://fas.org/sgp/crs/row/R40699.pdf'>Afghanistan: US foreign assistance</link></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Israel</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>2.75<extension extension_name='ref' name="jewishvirtuallibrary.org"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Egypt</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>1.75<extension extension_name='ref' name="smh">http://www.smh.com.au/world/us-aid-tied-to-purchase-of-arms-20100101-llsb.html US aid tied to purchase of arms</extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Pakistan</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>1.60<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://belfercenter.ksg.harvard.edu/files/Final_DP_2009_06_08092009.pdf'>Aid to Pakistan</link></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Colombia</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>.834<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.ciponline.org/facts/below_the_radar_eng.pdf</extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Jordan</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>.300<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://fas.org/sgp/crs/mideast/RL33546.pdf'>Jordan: Background and U.S relations</link></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Palestinian Authority</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>.100<extension extension_name='ref' name="smh"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>flag</target><arg>Yemen</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>.070</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Missile defense</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>National missile defense</arg><arg>Strategic Defense Initiative</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>Strategic Defense Initiative</target></link><space/>(SDI) was a proposal by U.S. President<space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link><space/>on March 23, 1983<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Federation of American Scientists</target></link>.<space/><link type='external' href='https://fas.org/spp/starwars/program/milestone.htm'>Missile Defense Milestones</link>. Accessed March 10, 2006.</extension><space/>to use ground and space-based systems to protect the United States from attack by strategic<space/><link><target>nuclear weapon</target><part>nuclear</part></link><space/><link><target>ballistic missile</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.independent.co.uk/opinion/commentators/johann-hari/johann-hari-obamas-chance-to-end-the--fantasy-that-is-star-wars-1015509.html'>Johann Hari: Obama's chance to end the fantasy that is Star Wars</link>, The Independent, November 13, 2008</extension><space/>later dubbed<space/><italics>&quot;Star Wars&quot;</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cnn.com/SPECIALS/cold.war/episodes/22/documents/starwars.speech/'>Historical Documents: Reagan's 'Star Wars' speech</link>, CNN Cold War</extension><space/>The initiative focused on strategic defense rather than the prior strategic offense doctrine of<space/><link><target>mutual assured destruction</target></link><space/>(MAD). Though it was never fully developed or deployed, the research and technologies of SDI paved the way for some<space/><link><target>anti-ballistic missile</target></link><space/>systems of today.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://science.howstuffworks.com/missile-defense3.htm</arg><arg name="title">Son of "Star Wars" - How Missile Defense Systems Will Work</arg><arg name="work">HowStuffWorks</arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In February 2007, the U.S. started formal negotiations with Poland and<space/><link><target>Czech Republic</target></link><space/>concerning construction of missile shield installations in those countries for a<space/><link><target>Ground-Based Midcourse Defense</target></link><space/>system<extension extension_name='ref' name="news.yahoo.com"><link type='external' href='http://news.yahoo.com/s/ap/20080823/ap_on_go_co/us_russia_missile_defense'>Missile defense backers now cite Russia threat</link></extension><space/>(in April 2007, 57% of<space/><link><target>Poles</target></link><space/>opposed the plan).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/04/24/AR2007042400871.html'>U.S. Might Negotiate on Missile Defense</link>, washingtonpost.com</extension><space/>According to press reports the government of the Czech Republic agreed (while 67% Czechs disagree)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cvvm.cas.cz/upl/zpravy/100761s_pm80306.pdf'>Citizens on U.S. Anti-Missile Radar Base in Czech Republic</link></extension><space/>to host a<space/><link><target>missile defense</target></link><space/>radar on its territory while a base of missile interceptors is supposed to be built in Poland.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/europe/6704669.stm'>Europe diary: Missile defence</link>, BBC News</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.rand.org/commentary/032907IHT.html</arg><arg name="title">Missile Defense: Avoiding a Crisis in Europe</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Russia threatened to place short-range<space/><link><target>nuclear missiles</target></link><space/>on the Russia's border with<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link><space/>if the United States refuses to abandon plans to deploy 10 interceptor missiles and a radar in Poland and the Czech Republic.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/1569495/Russia-piles-pressure-on-EU-over-missile-shield.html'>Russia piles pressure on EU over missile shield</link>, Telegraph</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iht.com/articles/ap/2008/05/23/asia/AS-GEN-China-Russia.php'>China, Russia sign nuclear deal, condemn U.S. missile defense plans</link>, International Herald Tribune</extension><space/>In April 2007, Putin warned of a new<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>if the Americans deployed the shield in Central Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2007/apr/11/usa.topstories3'>Russia threatening new cold war over missile defence</link>, The Guardian</extension><space/>Putin also said that Russia is prepared to abandon its obligations under an<space/><link><target>Intermediate-Range Nuclear Forces Treaty</target></link><space/>of 1987 with the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-10-12-us-russia_N.htm'>U.S., Russia no closer on missile defense</link>, USATODAY.com</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On August 14, 2008, The United States and Poland announced a deal to implement the<space/><link><target>U.S. missile defense complex in Poland</target><part>missile defense system in Polish territory</part></link>, with a tracking system placed in the Czech Republic.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/15/world/europe/16poland.html?hp'>Russia Lashes Out on Missile Deal</link>, The New York Times, August 15, 2008</extension><space/>&quot;The fact that this was signed in a period of very difficult crisis in the relations between Russia and the United States over the situation in<space/><link><target>Georgia (country)</target><part>Georgia</part></link><space/>shows that, of course, the missile defense system will be deployed not against<space/><link><target>Iran</target></link><space/>but against the strategic potential of Russia&quot;, Dmitry Rogozin, Russia's<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link><space/>envoy, said.<extension extension_name='ref' name="news.yahoo.com"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://english.aljazeera.net/news/europe/2008/08/200881514010734640.html'>Russia angry over U.S. missile shield</link>, Al Jazeera English, August 15, 2008</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Exporting democracy</heading><preblock><preline><space/><template><target>See also</target><arg>American democracy promotion in the Middle East and North Africa</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>history, critics have charged that<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>presidents</part></link><space/>have used<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link><space/>to justify<space/><link><target>List of United States military history events</target><part>military intervention</part></link><space/>abroad.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Why"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Bruce Bueno de
</arg><arg name="last">Mesquita
</arg><arg name="date">Spring 2004
</arg><arg name="title">Why Gun-Barrel Democracy Doesn't Work
</arg><arg name="journal">Hoover Digest
</arg><arg name="volume">2
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.hooverdigest.org/042/bdm.html
</arg></template><space/>Also see<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/travbailey/why.html&amp;amp;date=2009-10-25+23:16:02'>this page</link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Meernik 1996 391"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">James
</arg><arg name="last">Meernik
</arg><arg name="year">1996
</arg><arg name="title">United States Military Intervention and the Promotion of Democracy
</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Peace Research
</arg><arg name="volume">33
</arg><arg name="issue">4
</arg><arg name="pages">391–402
</arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/0022343396033004002
</arg></template></extension><space/>Critics have also charged that the U.S. helped local militaries overthrow democratically elected governments in<space/><link><target>Operation Ajax</target><part>Iran</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Operation PBSUCCESS</target><part>Guatemala</part></link>, and in<space/><link><target>Covert U.S. Regime Change Actions</target><part>other instances</part></link>. Studies have been devoted to the historical success rate of the U.S. in exporting democracy abroad. Some studies of American intervention have been pessimistic about the overall effectiveness of U.S. efforts to encourage democracy in foreign nations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="operation"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">John A.
</arg><arg name="last">Tures
</arg><arg name="title">Operation Exporting Freedom: The Quest for Democratization via United States Military Operations
</arg><arg name="journal">[[Whitehead Journal of Diplomacy and International Relations]]
</arg><arg name="url">http://blogs.shu.edu/diplomacy/files/archives/09_tures.pdf
</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg></template>PDF file.</extension><space/>Until recently, scholars have generally agreed with international relations professor Abraham Lowenthal that U.S. attempts to export democracy have been &quot;negligible, often counterproductive, and only occasionally positive.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Abraham"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lowenthal
</arg><arg name="first">Abraham
</arg><arg name="title">The United States and Latin American Democracy: Learning from History
</arg><arg name="year">1991
</arg><arg name="publisher">''Johns Hopkins University Press''
</arg><arg name="pages">243–265
</arg><arg name="location">Baltimore
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="mark7"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Peceny
</arg><arg name="first">Mark
</arg><arg name="year">1999
</arg><arg name="title">Democracy at the Point of Bayonets
</arg><arg name="publisher">University Park: Pennsylvania State University Press
</arg><arg name="page">183
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-271-01883-6
</arg></template></extension><space/>Other studies find<space/><link><target>List of United States military history events</target><part>U.S. intervention</part></link><space/>has had mixed results,<extension extension_name='ref' name="operation"></extension><space/>and another by Hermann and Kegley has found that military interventions have improved democracy in other countries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="promote"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Margaret G.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Hermann<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="title">The U.S. Use of Military Intervention to Promote Democracy: Evaluating the Record<space/></arg><arg name="journal">International Interactions<space/></arg><arg name="volume">24<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">91–114<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/03050629808434922<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Kegley<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Charles</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Opinion that U.S. intervention does not export democracy</heading><paragraph>Professor Paul W. Drake argued that the U.S. first attempted to export<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Latin America</target></link><space/>through intervention from 1912 to 1932. Drake argued that this was contradictory because international law defines<space/><link><target>invasion</target><part>intervention</part></link><space/>as &quot;dictatorial interference in the affairs of another state for the purpose of altering the condition of things.&quot; The study suggested that efforts to promote democracy failed because democracy needs to develop out of internal conditions, and can not be forcibly imposed. There was disagreement about what constituted<space/><italics><link><target>democracy</target></link></italics>; Drake suggested American leaders sometimes defined democracy in a narrow sense of a nation having elections; Drake suggested a broader understanding was needed. Further, there was disagreement about what constituted a &quot;rebellion&quot;; Drake saw a pattern in which the<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target><part>U.S. State Department</part></link><space/>disapproved of any type of rebellion, even so-called &quot;revolutions&quot;, and in some instances rebellions against dictatorships.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LA"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lowenthal<space/></arg><arg name="first">Abraham F.<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 1, 1991<space/></arg><arg name="title">Exporting Democracy : The United States and Latin America<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1, 4, 5</arg><arg name="publisher">The Johns Hopkins University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-8018-4132-1</arg></template></extension><space/>Historian<space/><link><target>Walter LaFeber</target></link><space/>stated, &quot;The world's leading revolutionary nation (the U.S.) in the eighteenth century became the leading protector of the status quo in the twentieth century.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Walter"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Lafeber<space/></arg><arg name="first">Walter<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="title">Inevitable Revolutions: The United States in Central America<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">W. W. Norton & Company<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-393-30964-9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Bruce Bueno de Mesquita</target><part>Mesquita</part></link><space/>and Downs evaluated 35 U.S. interventions from 1945 to 2004 and concluded that in only one case,<space/><link><target>Colombia</target></link>, did a &quot;full fledged, stable democracy&quot; develop within ten years following the intervention.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Why2">Factors included limits on<space/><link><target>executive power</target></link>, clear rules for the transition of power,<space/><link><target>Universal suffrage</target><part>universal adult suffrage</part></link>, andcompetitive elections.</extension><space/>Samia Amin Pei argued that nation building in developed countries usually unravelled four to six years after American intervention ended. Pei, based on study of a database on worldwide democracies called<space/><italics><link><target>Polity</target></link></italics>, agreed with Mesquita and Downs that U.S. intervention efforts usually don't produce real democracies, and that most cases result in greater authoritarianism after ten years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Samia Amin
</arg><arg name="last">Pei
</arg><arg name="date">March 17, 2004
</arg><arg name="title">Why Nation-Building Fails in Mid-Course
</arg><arg name="journal">International Herald Tribune
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.carnegieendowment.org/publications/index.cfm?fa</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Professor<space/><link><target>Joshua Muravchik</target></link><space/>argued U.S. occupation was critical for<space/><link><target>Axis Powers</target><part>Axis power</part></link><space/>democratization after<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, but America's failure to encourage democracy in the<space/><link><target>third world</target></link><space/>&quot;prove&amp;nbsp;... that U.S. military occupation is not a sufficient condition to make a country democratic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mark4">Peceny, p. 186.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="joshua"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Muravchik
</arg><arg name="first">Joshua
</arg><arg name="year">1991
</arg><arg name="title">Exporting Democracy: Fulfilling America's Destiny
</arg><arg name="publisher">American Enterprise Institute Press
</arg><arg name="pages">91–118
</arg><arg name="location">Washington, DC
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8447-3734-8
</arg></template></extension><space/>The success of democracy in former Axis countries such as<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>were seen as a result of high national per-capita income, although U.S. protection was seen as a key to stabilization and important for encouraging the transition to democracy. Steven Krasner agreed that there was a link between wealth and democracy; when per-capita incomes of $6,000 were achieved in a democracy, there was little chance of that country ever reverting to an<space/><link><target>autocracy</target></link>, according to an analysis of his research in the<space/><italics><link><target>Los Angeles Times</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LA"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Stephen D.
</arg><arg name="last">Krasner
</arg><arg name="date">November 26, 2003
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>We Don't Know How To Build Democracy
</arg><arg name="journal">Los Angeles Times
</arg><arg name="url">http://cddrl.stanford.edu/news/krasner_opinion_piece_in_la_times_asserts_we_dont_know_how_to_build_democracy_20031117/
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Opinion that U.S. intervention has mixed results</heading><paragraph>Tures examined 228 cases of American intervention from 1973 to 2005, using<space/><link><target>Freedom House</target></link><space/>data. A plurality of interventions, 96, caused no change in the country's democracy. In 69 instances the country became less democratic after the intervention. In the remaining 63 cases, a country became more democratic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="operation"></extension><space/>However this does not take into account the direction the country would have gone with no US intervention.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Opinion that U.S. intervention effectively exports democracy</heading><paragraph>Hermann and Kegley found that American military interventions designed to protect or promote democracy increased freedom in those countries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="promote"></extension><space/>Peceny argued that the democracies created after military intervention are still closer to an<space/><link><target>autocracy</target></link><space/>than a<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link>, quoting Przeworski &quot;while some democracies are more democratic than others, unless offices are contested, no regime should be considered democratic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Adam
</arg><arg name="last">Przeworski
</arg><arg name="authorlink">
</arg><arg name="year">1996
</arg><arg name="title">What Makes Democracy Endure
</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Democracy
</arg><arg name="volume">7
</arg><arg name="issue">1
</arg><arg name="pages">39–55
</arg><arg name="url">http://muse.jhu.edu/cgi-bin/access.cgi?uri</arg><arg name="doi">10.1353/jod.1996.0016
</arg><arg name="format">–<space/><sup>[http://scholar.google.co.uk/scholar?hl</arg><arg name="last2">Przeworski
</arg><arg name="first2">Adam
</arg><arg name="last3">Limongi Neto
</arg><arg name="first3">Fernando Papaterra
</arg><arg name="last4">Alvarez
</arg><arg name="first4">Michael M.
</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">June 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>Therefore, Peceny concludes, it is difficult to know from the Hermann and Kegley study whether U.S. intervention has only produced less repressive autocratic governments or genuine democracies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peceny, p. 193</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Peceny stated that the United States attempted to export democracy in 33 of its 93 20th-century military interventions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mark6">Peceny, p. 2</extension><space/>Peceny argued that proliberal policies after military intervention had a positive impact on democracy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Review:<space/><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Michael
</arg><arg name="last">Shifter
</arg><arg name="date">Winter 2001
</arg><arg name="title">Democracy at the Point of Bayonets
</arg><arg name="journal">Latin American Politics and Society
</arg><arg name="volume">43
</arg><arg name="issue">4
</arg><arg name="page">150
</arg><arg name="url">http://www.findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_qa4000/is_200101/ai_n8943833
</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3177036
</arg><arg name="last2">Peceny
</arg><arg name="first2">Mark
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Global Opinion</heading><paragraph>A global survey done by Pewglobal indicated that at (as of 2014) least 33 surveyed countries have a positive view (50% or above) of the United States. With the top ten most positive countries being Philippines (92%), Israel (84%), South Korea (82%), Kenya (80%), El Salvador (80%), Italy (78%), Ghana (77%), Vietnam (76%), Bangladesh (76%), and Tanzania (75%). While 10 surveyed countries have the most negative view (Below 50%) of the United States. With the countries being Egypt (10%), Jordan (12%), Pakistan (14%), Turkey (19%), Russia (23%), Palestinian Territories (30%), Greece (34%), Argentina (36%), Lebanon (41%), Tunisia (42%). American's own view of the United States was viewed at 84%.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Global opinion"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">http://www.pewglobal.org/database/indicator/1/survey/16/</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2015</arg><arg name="work">Pew Research Center</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Covert actions</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Covert United States foreign regime change actions</arg><arg>Reagan Doctrine</arg></template>United States foreign policy also includes covert actions to topple foreign governments that have been opposed to the United States. In 1953 the CIA, working with the British government, initiated<space/><italics><link><target>Operation Ajax</target></link></italics><space/>against the democratically elected<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of Iran</target></link><space/><link><target>Mohammad Mossadegh</target></link><space/>who had attempted to<space/><link><target>nationalize</target></link><space/>Iran's oil, threatening the interests of the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Persian Oil Company</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYTsr2000"><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="work">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="title">Special Report: Secret History of the CIA in Iran</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/library/world/mideast/041600iran-cia-index.html</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A year later, in<space/><link><target>1954 Guatemalan coup d'tat</target><part>''Operation PBSUCCESS''</part></link>, the United States government and the CIA toppled the democratically elected left-wing government of<space/><link><target>Jacobo rbenz</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link><space/>and installed the military dictator<space/><link><target>Carlos Castillo Armas</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>United Fruit Company</target></link><space/>lobbied for rbenz overthrow as his<space/><link><target>Decree 900</target><part>land reforms</part></link><space/>jeopardized their land holdings in Guatemala, and painted these reforms as a communist threat. The coup triggered a decades long<space/><link><target>Guatemalan Civil War</target><part>civil war</part></link><space/>which claimed the lives of 200,000 people.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Stephen Schlesinger</target></link><space/>(3 June 2011).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2011/06/04/opinion/04schlesinger.html?_r=0'>Ghosts of Guatemala's Past</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link>.</italics><space/>Retrieved 5 July 2014.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Indonesian killings of 196566</target><part>massacre of alleged communists</part></link><space/>in 1960s Indonesia, the U.S. government provided assistance to the Indonesian military that, according to Bradley Simpson, Director of the Indonesia/East Timor Documentation Project at the<space/><link><target>National Security Archive</target></link>, helped facilitate the mass killings.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brad Simpson (Winter 2013).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.jstor.org/discover/10.1525/fq.2014.67.2.10?uid=3739896&amp;amp;uid=2&amp;amp;uid=4&amp;amp;uid=3739256&amp;amp;sid=21104133052663'>''The Act of Killing'' and the Dilemmas of History</link>.<space/><italics>Film Quarterly.</italics><space/>Vol. 67, No. 2, pp. 10-13. Published by:<space/><link><target>University of California Press</target></link>. Retrieved 9 May 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://thejakartaglobe.com/news/historian-claims-west-backed-post-coup-mass-killings-in-65/312844'>Historian Claims West Backed Post-Coup Mass Killings in '65</link>. The Jakarta Globe. Retrieved on 1 March 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Simpson, Bradley (2010).<space/><italics>Economists with Guns: Authoritarian Development and U.S.-Indonesian Relations, 19601968.</italics><space/><link><target>Stanford University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-8047-7182-0</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.abc.net.au/radionational/programs/hindsight/accomplices-in-atrocity-the-indonesian-killings-of/3182630#transcript'>Accomplices in Atrocity. The Indonesian killings of 1965 (transcript)</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Australian Broadcasting Corporation</target></link>,</italics><space/>7 September 2008</extension><space/>This included the U.S. Embassy in Jakarta supplying Indonesian forces with lists of up to 5,000 names of suspected<space/><link><target>Communist Party of Indonesia</target><part>PKI</part></link><space/>members, who were subsequently killed in the massacres.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bellamy, Alex J. (2012).<space/><italics>Massacres and Morality: Mass Atrocities in an Age of Civilian Immunity.</italics><space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-19-928842-9.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=EK8eK2xPCycC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA210#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 210.</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BlumenthalMcCormack">David A. Blumenthal and Timothy L. H. McCormack (2007).<space/><italics>The Legacy of Nuremberg: Civilising Influence or Institutionalised Vengeance? (International Humanitarian Law).</italics><space/><link><target>Martinus Nijhoff Publishers</target></link>. ISBN 90-04-15691-7<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=dg0hWswKgTIC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA81#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>pp.&amp;nbsp;8081</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Vickers, Adrian (2005).<space/><italics>A History of Modern Indonesia.</italics><space/><link><target>Cambridge University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-521-54262-6 p. 157</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Friend, Theodore (2003).<space/><italics>Indonesian Destinies.</italics><space/><link><target>Harvard University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-674-01137-6 p. 117</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1970, the<space/><link><target>United States intervention in Chile#Track II</target><part>CIA worked with coup-plotters</part></link><space/>in Chile in the attempted kidnapping of General<space/><link><target>Ren Schneider</target></link>, who was targeted for refusing to participate in a military coup upon the election of<space/><link><target>Salvador Allende</target></link>. Schneider was shot in the botched attempt and died three days later. The CIA later paid the group $35,000 for the failed kidnapping.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://abcnews.go.com/International/story?id=82588'>CIA Admits Involvement in Chile</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>ABC News</target></link>.</italics><space/>September 20</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>John Dinges</target></link>.<space/><italics>The Condor Years: How Pinochet And His Allies Brought Terrorism To Three Continents.</italics><space/><link><target>The New Press</target></link>, 2005.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=3JjtHROah_YC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA20#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 20</link>. ISBN 1565849779</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Human Rights</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of authoritarian regimes supported by the United States</arg><arg>United States and state-sponsored terrorism</arg></template>The inclusion of Human Rights in U.S. foreign policy had a controversial start. For one thing, human rights driven foreign policy did not originate in the Executive branch but was instead enforced upon it by Congress, starting in the 1970s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crabb &amp; Holt"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Crabb</arg><arg name="first">Cecil V.</arg><arg name="title">Invitation to Struggle: Congress, the President and Foreign Policy</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">Congressional Quarterly</arg><arg name="location">Michigan</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87187-622-5</arg><arg name="pages">187–211</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="author2">Pat Holt</arg></template></extension><space/>Following the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target></link>, the feeling that U.S. foreign policy had grown apart from traditional American values was seized upon by<space/><link><target>Donald M. Fraser</target><part>Senator Donald M. Fraser (D, MI)</part></link>, leading the Subcommittee on International Organizations and Movements, in criticizing Republican Foreign Policy under<space/><link><target>Richard Nixon#Presidency</target><part>the Nixon administration</part></link>. In the early 1970s, Congress concluded the Vietnam War and passed the<space/><link><target>War Powers Resolution</target><part>War Powers Act</part></link>. As &quot;part of a growing assertiveness by Congress about many aspects of Foreign Policy,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Forsythe"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Forsythe</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Human Rights and U.S. Foreign Policy: Congress Reconsidered</arg><arg name="year">1988</arg><arg name="publisher">University Press of Florida</arg><arg name="location">Gainesville</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8130-0885-1</arg><arg name="pages">1–23</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><space/>Human Rights concerns became a battleground between the Legislative and the Executive branches in the formulation of foreign policy. David Forsythe points to three specific, early examples of Congress interjecting its own thoughts on foreign policy:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Subsection (a) of the International Financial Assistance Act of 1977: ensured assistance through international financial institutions would be limited to countries &quot;other than those whose governments engage in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Forsythe"></extension></listitem><listitem>Section 116 of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended in 1984: reads in part, &quot;No assistance may be provided under this part to the government of any country which engages in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Forsythe"></extension></listitem><listitem>Section 502B of the Foreign Assistance Act of 1961, as amended in 1978: &quot;No security assistance may be provided to any country the government of which engages in a consistent pattern of gross violations of internationally recognized human rights.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Forsythe"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>These measures were repeatedly used by Congress, with varying success, to affect U.S. foreign policy towards the inclusion of Human Rights concerns. Specific examples include<space/><link><target>El Salvador</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nicaragua</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>. The Executive (from Nixon to Reagan) argued that the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>required placing regional security in favor of US interests over any behavioral concerns of national allies. Congress argued the opposite, in favor of distancing the United States from oppressive regimes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crabb &amp; Holt"></extension><space/>Nevertheless, according to historian<space/><link><target>Daniel Goldhagen</target></link>, during the last two decades of the Cold War, the number of American client states practicing mass murder outnumbered those of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><paragraph><link><target>Daniel Goldhagen</target></link><space/>(2009).<space/><italics>Worse Than War.</italics><space/><link><target>PublicAffairs</target></link>. ISBN 1-58648-769-8 p.537</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;During the 1970s and 1980s, the number of American client states practicing mass-murderous politics exceeded those of the Soviets.&quot;</listitem></list></extension><space/><link><target>John Henry Coatsworth</target></link>, a historian of Latin America and the provost of Columbia University, suggests the number of repression victims in Latin America alone far surpassed that of the USSR and its East European satellites during the period 1960 to 1990.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.scribd.com/doc/109666536/The-Cold-War-in-Central-America-1975-1991-John-H-Coatsworth-Ch-10'>&quot;The Cold War in Central America, 1975-1991&quot;</link><space/>John H. Coatsworth, Ch 10</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Noam Chomsky and Edward Herman (2014).<space/><italics><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=vXtHBgAAQBAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PR18#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>The Washington Connection and Third World Fascism: The Political Economy of Human Rights: Volume I</link>.</italics><space/><link><target>Haymarket Books</target></link>. p. xviii. ISBN 1608464067</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On December 6, 2011, Obama instructed agencies to consider<space/><link><target>LGBT rights by country or territory</target><part>LGBT rights</part></link><space/>when issuing financial aid to foreign countries.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">McVeigh</arg><arg name="first">Karen</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/dec/07/gay-rights-us-aid-criteria</arg><arg name="title">Gay rights must be criterion for US aid allocations, instructs Obama</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Guardian</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="date">December 6, 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 4, 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>He also criticized Russia's law discriminating against gays,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Adomanis</arg><arg name="first">Mark</arg><arg name="url">http://www.forbes.com/sites/markadomanis/2013/12/19/barack-obama-is-right-to-promote-gay-rights-in-russia-now-he-should-be-consistent/</arg><arg name="title">Barack Obama Is Right To Promote Gay Rights In Russia, Now He Should Be Consistent</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Forbes]]</arg><arg name="date">December 19, 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 25, 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>joining other western leaders in the<space/><link><target>boycott</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>2014 Winter Olympics</target></link><space/>in Russia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Bershidsky</arg><arg name="first">Leonid</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bloomberg.com/news/2013-12-19/putin-plays-games-to-salvage-olympics.html</arg><arg name="title">Putin Plays Games to Salvage Olympics</arg><arg name="publisher">Bloomberg.com</arg><arg name="date">December 19, 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 25, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In June 2014, a Chilean court ruled that the United States played a key role in the murders of<space/><link><target>Charles Horman</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Frank Teruggi</target></link>, both American citizens, shortly after the<space/><link><target>1973 Chilean coup d'tat</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pascale Bonnefoy (30 June 2014).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2014/07/01/world/americas/chilean-court-rules-us-had-role-in-murders.html?_r=0'>Chilean Court Rules U.S. Had Role in Murders</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link>.</italics><space/>Retrieved 4 July 2014.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>War on Drugs</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>War on Drugs</arg></template>United States foreign policy is influenced by the efforts of the U.S. government to control imports of illicit<space/><link><target>illegal drug trade</target><part>drugs</part></link>, including<space/><link><target>cocaine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>heroin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>methamphetamine</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Cannabis (drug)</target><part>cannabis</part></link>. This is especially true in Latin America, a focus for the U.S.<space/><link><target>War on Drugs</target></link>. Those efforts date back to at least 1880, when the U.S. and China completed an agreement that<space/><link><target>Prohibition (drugs)</target><part>prohibited</part></link><space/>the shipment of<space/><link><target>opium</target></link><space/>between the two countries.</paragraph><paragraph>Over a century later, the Foreign Relations Authorization Act requires the President to identify the major drug transit or major illicit drug-producing countries. In September 2005,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://georgewbush-whitehouse.archives.gov/news/releases/2005/09/20050915-2.html</arg><arg name="title">Memorandum for the Secretary of State</arg><arg name="date">15 September 2005</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>the following countries were identified:<space/><link><target>Bahamas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bolivia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Brazil</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Burma</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Colombia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dominican Republic</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ecuador</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Haiti</target></link>, India,<space/><link><target>Jamaica</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Laos</target></link>, Mexico,<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link>, Pakistan,<space/><link><target>Panama</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paraguay</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Peru</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Venezuela</target></link>. Two of these, Burma and Venezuela are countries that the U.S. considers to have failed to adhere to their obligations under international counternarcotics agreements during the previous 12 months. Notably absent from the 2005 list were<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>People's Republic of China</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>; Canada was also omitted in spite of evidence that criminal groups there are increasingly involved in the production of<space/><link><target>MDMA</target></link><space/>destined for the United States and that large-scale cross-border trafficking of Canadian-grown cannabis continues. The U.S. believes that the Netherlands are successfully countering the production and flow of MDMA to the U.S.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Criticism of American foreign policy</arg></template><link><target>File:DigiGes PRISM Yes we scan - Demo am Checkpoint Charlie June 2013.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Demonstration at<space/><link><target>Checkpoint Charlie</target></link><space/>in Berlin against the<space/><link><target>National Security Agency</target><part>NSA</part></link><space/>surveillance program<space/><link><target>PRISM (surveillance program)</target><part>PRISM</part></link>, June 2013</part></link>Critics from the left cite episodes that undercut leftist governments or showed support for Israel. Others cite human rights abuses and violations of international law. Critics have charged that the<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>U.S. presidents</part></link><space/>have used<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link><space/>to justify<space/><link><target>List of United States military history events</target><part>military intervention</part></link><space/>abroad.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Why"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Meernik 1996 391"></extension><space/>It was also noted that the U.S. overthrew democratically elected governments in<space/><link><target>Operation Ajax</target><part>Iran</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Operation PBSUCCESS</target><part>Guatemala</part></link>, and in<space/><link><target>Covert U.S. Regime Change Actions</target><part>other instances</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Noam Chomsky</target></link>, a vociferous critic of U.S. foreign policy, argues that &quot;in both cases the consequences reach to the present&quot; and that Guatemala in particular &quot;remains one of the world's worst horror chambers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Noam Chomsky</target></link><space/>(July 3, 2014).<space/><link type='external' href='http://billmoyers.com/2014/07/03/whose-security-how-washington-protects-itself-and-the-corporate-sector/'>Whose Security? How Washington Protects Itself and the Corporate Sector</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Moyers &amp; Company</target></link>.</italics><space/>Retrieved July 10, 2014.</extension><space/>Critics also point to declassified records which indicate that the CIA under<space/><link><target>Allen Dulles</target></link><space/>and the FBI under<space/><link><target>J. Edgar Hoover</target></link><space/>aggressively recruited more than 1,000 Nazis, including those responsible for war crimes, to use as spies and informants against the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>in the Cold War.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eric Lichtblau (October 26, 2014).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/27/us/in-cold-war-us-spy-agencies-used-1000-nazis.html'>In Cold War, U.S. Spy Agencies Used 1,000 Nazis</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link>.</italics><space/>Retrieved November 10, 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.democracynow.org/2014/10/31/the_nazis_next_door_eric_lichtblau'>The Nazis Next Door: Eric Lichtblau on How the CIA &amp; FBI Secretly Sheltered Nazi War Criminals</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Democracy Now!</target></link></italics><space/>October 31, 2014.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The U.S. has faced criticism for<space/><link><target>List of authoritarian regimes supported by the United States</target><part>backing right-wing dictators</part></link><space/>that systematically violated human rights, such as<space/><link><target>Augusto Pinochet</target></link><space/>of Chile,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Peter Kornbluh</target></link><space/>(September 11, 2013).<space/><italics><link><target>The Pinochet File: A Declassified Dossier on Atrocity and Accountability</target></link>.</italics><space/><link><target>The New Press</target></link>. ISBN 1595589120<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=WHYRBAAAQBAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PR18#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. xviii</link></extension><space/><link><target>Alfredo Stroessner</target></link><space/>of Paraguay,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hixson">Walter L. Hixson (2009).<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://yalepress.yale.edu/book.asp?isbn=9780300119121'>The Myth of American Diplomacy: National Identity and U.S. Foreign Policy</link>.</italics><space/><link><target>Yale University Press</target></link>.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=DNId6HxkzQwC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA223#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 223</link>. ISBN 0300151314</extension><space/><link><target>Efran Ros Montt</target></link><space/>of Guatemala,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/roomfordebate/2013/05/19/what-guilt-does-the-us-bear-in-guatemala'>What Guilt Does the U.S. Bear in Guatemala?</link><space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link>,</italics><space/>May 19, 2013. Retrieved July 1, 2014.</extension><space/><link><target>Jorge Rafael Videla</target></link><space/>of Argentina,<extension extension_name='ref'>Duncan Campbell (December 5, 2003).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theguardian.com/world/2003/dec/06/argentina.usa'>Kissinger approved Argentinian 'dirty war'</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link>.</italics><space/>Retrieved August 29, 2015.</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Suharto</target></link><space/>of Indonesia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BlumenthalMcCormack"></extension><space/>Critics have also accused the United States of supporting<space/><link><target>Operation Condor</target><part>Operation ''Condor''</part></link>, an international campaign of political assassination and state terror organized by right-wing military dictatorships in the<space/><link><target>Southern Cone</target></link><space/>of South America.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hixson"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Greg Grandin</target></link><space/>(2011).<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.press.uchicago.edu/ucp/books/book/chicago/L/bo11643711.html'>The Last Colonial Massacre: Latin America in the Cold War</link>.</italics><space/><link><target>University of Chicago Press</target></link>.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=6FivSpNY2fkC&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA75#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 75</link>. ISBN 9780226306902</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Tracking the Origins of a State Terror Network: Operation Condor<space/></arg><arg name="author">[[J. Patrice McSherry]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Latin American Perspectives<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>29<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>36–60</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1177/0094582X0202900103</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Studies have been devoted to the historical success rate of the U.S. in exporting democracy abroad. Some studies of American intervention have been pessimistic about the overall effectiveness of U.S. efforts to encourage democracy in foreign nations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="operation"></extension><space/>Some scholars have generally agreed with international relations professor Abraham Lowenthal that U.S. attempts to export democracy have been &quot;negligible, often counterproductive, and only occasionally positive.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Abraham"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="mark7"></extension><space/>Other studies find<space/><link><target>List of United States military history events</target><part>U.S. intervention</part></link><space/>has had mixed results,<extension extension_name='ref' name="operation"></extension><space/>and another by Hermann and Kegley has found that military interventions have improved democracy in other countries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="promote"></extension><space/>A 2013 global poll in 68 countries with 66,000 respondents by Win/Gallup found that the U.S. is perceived as the biggest threat to world peace.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Goodenough<space/></arg><arg name="first">Patrick<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://cnsnews.com/news/article/patrick-goodenough/and-country-posing-greatest-threat-peace-2013-ends<space/></arg><arg name="title">And The Country Posing The Greatest Threat to Peace as 2013 Ends is …<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">CNS News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://rt.com/news/us-biggest-threat-peace-079/<space/></arg><arg name="title">US the biggest threat to world peace in 2013 – poll — RT News<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Rt.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Editorial<space/></arg><arg name="first">Post<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://nypost.com/2014/01/05/us-is-the-greatest-threat-to-world-peace-poll/<space/></arg><arg name="title">US is the greatest threat to world peace: poll &#124; New York Post<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Nypost.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2014-01-05<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-08-18</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Support</heading><paragraph>Regarding support for certain anti-Communist dictatorships during the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link>, a response is that they were seen as a necessary evil, with the alternatives even worse Communist or fundamentalist dictatorships. David Schmitz says this policy did not serve U.S. interests. Friendly tyrants resisted necessary reforms and destroyed the political center (though not in South Korea), while the '<link><target>Political realism</target><part>realist</part></link>' policy of coddling dictators brought a backlash among foreign populations with long memories.<extension extension_name='ref'>The United States and Right-Wing Dictatorships, 19651989. David F. Schmitz. 2006.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"><link type='external' href='http://www.telegraph.co.uk/opinion/main.jhtml?xml=/opinion/2005/12/11/do1102.xml&amp;amp;sSheet=/opinion/2005/12/11/ixopinion.html'>Do the sums, then compare U.S. and Communist crimes from the Cold War</link><space/>Telegraph, 11 December 2005, Niall Ferguson</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Many democracies have voluntary military ties with United States. See<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ANZUS</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Treaty of Mutual Cooperation and Security between the United States and Japan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mutual Defense Treaty</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Major non-NATO ally</target></link>. Those nations with military alliances with the U.S. can spend less on the military since they can count on U.S. protection. This may give a false impression that the U.S. is less peaceful than those nations.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.economist.com/world/international/displaystory.cfm?story_id=9266967'>Give peace a rating</link><space/>May 31, 2007, from<space/><italics>The Economist</italics><space/>print edition</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.japantoday.com/jp/news/407850/all'>Japan ranked as world's 5th most peaceful nation: report</link><space/>Japan Today, May 31, 2007</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Research on the<space/><link><target>democratic peace theory</target></link><space/>has generally found that democracies, including the United States, have not made war on one another. There have been U.S. support for coups against some democracies, but for example<space/><link><target>Spencer R. Weart</target></link><space/>argues that part of the explanation was the perception, correct or not, that these states were turning into Communist dictatorships. Also important was the role of rarely transparent United States government agencies, who sometimes mislead or did not fully implement the decisions of elected civilian leaders.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Weart</arg><arg name="first">Spencer R.</arg><arg name="title">Never at War</arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">0-300-07017-9</arg></template><space/>pp. 221224, 314.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Empirical studies (see<space/><link><target>democide</target></link>) have found that democracies, including the United States, have killed much fewer civilians than dictatorships.<extension extension_name='ref'>DEATH BY GOVERNMENT By R.J. Rummel New Brunswick, N.J.: Transaction Publishers, 1994. Online links:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/NOTE1.HTM'></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/SOD.FIG23.4.GIF'></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hawaii.edu/powerkills/POWER.FIG2.GIF'></link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.cidcm.umd.edu/inscr/genocide/'>No Lessons Learned from the Holocaust?</link></italics>, Barbara Harff, 2003.</extension><space/>Media may be biased against the U.S. regarding reporting human rights violations. Studies have found that<space/><italics>The New York Times</italics><space/>coverage of worldwide human rights violations predominantly focuses on the human rights violations in nations where there is clear U.S. involvement, while having relatively little coverage of the human rights violations in other nations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Caliendo1999"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Caliendo, S.M.</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="title">All the News That's Fit to Print? New York Times Coverage of Human-Rights Violations</arg><arg name="journal">The Harvard International Journal of Press Politics</arg><arg name="volume">4</arg><arg name="pages">48–69</arg><arg name="url">http://muse.jhu.edu/login?uri</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-02</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Caliendo, Stephen. and Gibney, Mark.</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="title">American Print Media Coverage of Human Rights Violations</arg><arg name="url">http://www.allacademic.com/meta/p152798_index.html?type</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-02</arg></template></extension><space/>For example, the bloodiest war in recent time, involving eight nations and killing millions of civilians, was the<space/><link><target>Second Congo War</target></link>, which was almost completely ignored by the media.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Niall Ferguson</target></link><space/>argues that the U.S. is incorrectly blamed for all the human rights violations in nations they have supported. He writes that it is generally agreed that Guatemala was the worst of the US-backed regimes during the Cold War. However, the U.S. cannot credibly be blamed for all the 200,000 deaths during the long<space/><link><target>Guatemalan Civil War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension><space/>The U.S. Intelligence Oversight Board writes that military aid was cut for long periods because of such violations, that the U.S. helped stop a coup in 1993, and that efforts were made to improve the conduct of the security services.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ciponline.org/iob.htm'>Report on the Guatemala Review</link><space/>Intelligence Oversight Board. June 28, 1996.</extension><space/>However, W. John Green contends that the United States was an &quot;essential enabler&quot; of &quot;Latin America's political murder habit, bringing out and allowing to flourish some of the region's worst tendencies.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>W. John Green (June 1, 2015).<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.sunypress.edu/p-6060-a-history-of-political-murder-i.aspx'>A History of Political Murder in Latin America: Killing the Messengers of Change</link>.</italics><space/><link><target>SUNY Press</target></link>.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=NyezCAAAQBAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PP1&amp;amp;pg=PA147#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 147</link>. ISBN 1438456638</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Abdulredha Buhmaid on floor.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bahrain</target><trail>i</trail></link><space/>pro-democracy protesters killed by the U.S.-allied regime, February 2011</part></link>Today the U.S. states that democratic nations best support U.S. national interests. According to the U.S. State Department, &quot;Democracy is the one national interest that helps to secure all the others. Democratically governed nations are more likely to secure the peace, deter aggression, expand open markets, promote economic development, protect American citizens, combat international terrorism and crime, uphold human and worker rights, avoid humanitarian crises and refugee flows, improve the global environment, and protect human health.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/g/drl/democ/</arg><arg name="title">Democracy</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>According to former U.S. President<space/><link><target>Bill Clinton</target></link>, &quot;Ultimately, the best strategy to ensure our security and to build a durable peace is to support the advance of democracy elsewhere. Democracies don't attack each other.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="author">Clinton, Bill</arg><arg name="title">1994 State Of The Union Address</arg><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/politics/special/states/docs/sou94.htm</arg><arg name="accessdate">2006-01-22</arg><arg name="work">The Washington Post</arg><arg name="date">January 28, 2000</arg></template></extension><space/>In one view mentioned by the U.S. State Department, democracy is also good for business. Countries that embrace political reforms are also more likely to pursue economic reforms that improve the productivity of businesses. Accordingly, since the mid-1980s, under President<space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link>, there has been an increase in levels of foreign direct investment going to emerging market democracies relative to countries that have not undertaken political reforms.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://usinfo.state.gov/usinfo/USINFO/Products/Webchats/bohn_27_mar_2007.html'></link></extension><space/>Leaked cables in 2010 suggested that the &quot;dark shadow of terrorism still dominates the United States' relations with the world&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twsDecZ16af"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first1">Scott</arg><arg name="last1">Shane</arg><arg name="first2">Andrew W.</arg><arg name="last2">Lehren</arg><arg name="title">Leaked Cables Offer Raw Look at U.S. Diplomacy</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="quote">The cables show that nearly a decade after the attacks of Sept. 11, 2001, the dark shadow of terrorism still dominates the United States' relations with the world.&nbsp;...<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010-11-28</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2010/11/29/world/29cables.html?_r</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-12-26</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The United States officially maintains that it supports democracy and human rights through several tools<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/g/drl/</arg><arg name="title">Bureau of Democracy, Human Rights, and Labor</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Examples of these tools are as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A published yearly report by the State Department entitled &quot;Advancing Freedom and Democracy&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/j/drl/rls/afdr/index.htm'>Advancing Freedom and Democracy</link></extension><space/>issued in compliance with ADVANCE Democracy Act of 2007 (earlier the report was known as &quot;Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record&quot; and was issued in compliance with a 2002 law.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/shrd/</arg><arg name="title">Supporting Human Rights and Democracy: The U.S. Record</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>A yearly published &quot;<link><target>Country Reports on Human Rights Practices</target></link>.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/hrrpt/</arg><arg name="title">Human Rights Reports</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 February 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In 2006 (under President<space/><link><target>George W. Bush</target></link>), the United States created a &quot;Human Rights Defenders Fund&quot; and &quot;Freedom Awards.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c20063.htm'></link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The &quot;Human Rights and Democracy Achievement Award&quot; recognizes the exceptional achievement of officers of foreign affairs agencies posted abroad.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/g/drl/rls/77769.htm'></link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The &quot;Ambassadorial Roundtable Series&quot;, created in 2006, are informal discussions between newly confirmed U.S.<space/><link><target>Ambassador</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and human rights and democracy non-governmental organizations.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/g/drl/hr/c18970.htm'></link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>National Endowment for Democracy</target></link>, a private non-profit created by Congress in 1983 (and signed into law by President<space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link>, which is mostly funded by the U.S. Government and gives cash grants to strengthen democratic institutions around the world</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>History of U.S. foreign policy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>International relations of the Great Powers (18141919)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of United States diplomatic history</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-break</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Constitutional and international law</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Advice and consent</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of United States treaties</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Missouri v. Holland</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Treaty Clause</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Diplomacy</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Council on Foreign Relations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cowboy diplomacy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of diplomatic missions of the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>George Washington's Farewell Address</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States and the United Nations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Agency for International Development</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of diplomatic missions in the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States foreign aid</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Washington Diplomat</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Intelligence</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Covert United States foreign regime change actions</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Extraordinary rendition</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Special Activities Division</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Torture and the United States</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-break</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Military</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>2003 invasion of Iraq</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>NATO</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States Foreign Military Financing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States involvement in regime change</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States military aid</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Policy and doctrine</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United States and state terrorism</target></link><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States and state-sponsored terrorism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Anti-Americanism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>American imperialism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>American exceptionalism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bush Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Carter Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>China containment policy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Containment</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Dtente</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Foreign policy of the Barack Obama administration</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human rights in the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kirkpatrick Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Human Rights Record of the United States</target></link></italics><space/>(Chinese publication)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Monroe Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nixon Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Powell Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Reagan Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Roosevelt Corollary</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Special Relationship</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Truman Doctrine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Criticism of American foreign policy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>United States foreign policy in the Middle East</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-break</target></template><template><target>American Empire</target></template><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bailey, Thomas.<space/><italics>A Diplomatic History of the American People</italics><space/>(10th ed. Prentice Hall, 1980)</listitem><listitem><link><target>William Blum</target><part>Blum, William</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Killing Hope</target><part>Killing Hope: U.S. Military and C.I.A. Interventions since World War II</part></link></italics><space/>(Common Courage Press, 2003)<space/></listitem><listitem>Borgwardt, Elizabeth. &quot;A New Deal for the World&quot; (Harvard UP, 2005)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Noam Chomsky</target><part>Chomsky, Noam</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Hegemony or Survival</target><part>Hegemony or Survival: America's Quest for Global Dominance</part></link></italics><space/>(Metropolitan Books, 2003)</listitem><listitem>Cohen, Warren I.<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 4, America in the Age of Soviet Power, 19451991</italics><space/>(Cambridge UP, 1995)</listitem><listitem>Fawcett, Louise, ed.<space/><italics>International Relations of the Middle East</italics><space/>(3rd ed. Oxford U.P. 2013)</listitem><listitem>Freedman, Lawrence.<space/><italics>A Choice of Enemies: America Confronts the Middle East</italics><space/>(PublicAffairs, 2009)</listitem><listitem>Gries, Peter Hays.<space/><italics>The Politics of American Foreign Policy: How Ideology Divides Liberals and Conservatives over Foreign Affairs</italics><space/>(Stanford University Press, 2014)</listitem><listitem>Hastedt, Glenn P.<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of American Foreign Policy</italics><space/>(Facts on File, 2004)</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="first">Margaret G.
</arg><arg name="last">Hermann
</arg><arg name="authorlink">
</arg><arg name="year">1998
</arg><arg name="title">The U.S. Use of Military Intervention to Promote Democracy: Evaluating the Record
</arg><arg name="journal">International Interactions
</arg><arg name="volume">24
</arg><arg name="issue">2
</arg><arg name="pages">91–114
</arg><arg name="id">
</arg><arg name="url">
</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/03050629808434922
</arg><arg name="last2">Kegley
</arg><arg name="first2">Charles
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Herring, George C.<space/><italics>From Colony to Superpower: U.S. Foreign Relations Since 1776</italics><space/>(Oxford History of the United States) (2008)</listitem><listitem>Hixson, Walter L.<space/><italics>The Myth of American Diplomacy: National Identity and U.S. Foreign Policy.</italics><space/><link><target>Yale University Press</target></link>, 2009. ISBN 0300151314</listitem><listitem>Hook, Steven W. and<space/><link><target>John Spanier</target></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>American Foreign Policy Since WWII</target></link></italics><space/>(19th ed. 2012)</listitem><listitem>Ikenberry, G. John, ed.<space/><italics>American Foreign Policy: Theoretical Essays</italics><space/>(6th ed. Wadsworth, 2010), 640pp; essays by scholars</listitem><listitem>Iriye, Akira.<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 3, The Globalizing of America, 19131945</italics><space/>(Cambridge UP, 1995)</listitem><listitem>Jentleson, Bruce W.<space/><italics>American Foreign Policy: The Dynamics of Choice in the 21st Century</italics><space/>(4th ed. W. W. Norton, 2010)</listitem><listitem>Jentleson, Bruce W. and Thomas G. Paterson, eds.<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of U.S. Foreign Relations</italics><space/>(4 vol 1997), long historical articles by scholars</listitem><listitem>LaFeber, Walter.<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: The American Search for Opportunity, 18651913, vol. 2</italics><space/>(Cambridge UP, 1995)</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Lowenthal
</arg><arg name="first">Abraham F.
</arg><arg name="authorlink">
</arg><arg name="date">March 1, 1991
</arg><arg name="title">Exporting Democracy : The United States and Latin America
</arg><arg name="publisher">The Johns Hopkins University Press
</arg><arg name="location">
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8018-4132-1
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>McCormick, James M. et al.<space/><italics><space/>The Domestic Sources of American Foreign Policy: Insights and Evidence</italics><space/>(2012)</listitem><listitem>McDougall, Walter. &quot;Promised Land, Crusader State&quot; (2004)</listitem><listitem>Mead, Walter Russell, and Richard C. Leone.<space/><italics>Special Providence: American Foreign Policy and How It Changed the World</italics><space/>(2002)</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="first">James
</arg><arg name="last">Meernik
</arg><arg name="authorlink">
</arg><arg name="year">1996
</arg><arg name="title">United States Military Intervention and the Promotion of Democracy
</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Peace Research
</arg><arg name="volume">33
</arg><arg name="issue">4
</arg><arg name="pages">391–402
</arg><arg name="id">
</arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/0022343396033004002
</arg><arg name="jstor">424565
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Nichols, Christopher McKnight. &quot;Promise and Peril: America at the Dawn of a Global Age&quot; (2011)</listitem><listitem>Paterson, Thomas G. and others.<space/><italics>American Foreign Relations</italics><space/>(6th ed. 2 vol, Wadsworth, 2004), a detailed history</listitem><listitem>Perkins, Bradford.<space/><italics>The Cambridge History of American Foreign Relations: Volume 1, The Creation of a Republican Empire, 17761865</italics><space/>(Cambridge UP, 1995)</listitem><listitem>Sergent, Daniel J.<space/><italics>A Superpower Transformed: The Remaking of American Foreign Relations in the 1970s</italics><space/>(2015)</listitem><listitem>Schulzinger, Robert.<space/><italics><space/>A Companion to American Foreign Relations</italics><space/>(Wiley Blackwell Companions to American History) (2006). 26 essays by scholars; emphasis on historiography</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Smith
</arg><arg name="first">Tony
</arg><arg name="authorlink">
</arg><arg name="author2">Richard C. Leone
</arg><arg name="year">1995
</arg><arg name="title">America's Mission: The United States and the Worldwide Struggle for Democracy in the Twentieth Century
</arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton University Press
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-691-04466-X
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Watry, David M.<space/><italics>Diplomacy at the Brink: Eisenhower, Churchill, and Eden in the Cold War.</italics><space/>Baton Rouge: Louisiana State University Press, 2014.</listitem><listitem>Wittkopf, Eugene R. et al.<space/><italics>American Foreign Policy: Pattern and Process</italics><space/>(2007)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://history.state.gov/countries/'>History of the United States' relations with the countries of the world</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://history.state.gov/milestones/'>Milestones of U.S. diplomatic history</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://history.state.gov/historicaldocuments/'>Foreign Relations of the United States (FRUS): Official Documentary History of U.S. Foreign Relations</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ucblibraries.colorado.edu/govpubs/us/foraffrs.htm'>Foreign Relations and International Aid</link><space/>from ''UCB Libraries G</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cfr.org/publication/9488/'>U.S. Political Parties and Foreign Policy</link>, a background Q&amp;A by<space/><link><target>Council on Foreign Relations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digital.library.wisc.edu/1711.dl/FRUS'>Foreign Relations of the United States</link><space/>18611960 (full text from the University of Wisconsin-Madison Libraries)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.publicagenda.org/citizen/researchstudies/foreign-policy'>Confidence in U.S. Foreign Policy Index</link><space/>Tracking survey of American public attitudes on foreign policy, conducted by Public Agenda with<space/><link><target>Foreign Affairs</target></link><space/>magazine.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.historyisaweapon.com/defcon2/world.html'>An interactive map of some examples of a sampling of U.S. Foreign Policy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://papers.ssrn.com/sol3/papers.cfm?abstract_id=708243'>Analysis of Congressional-Executive Agreements (Article by Steve Charnovitz from the American Journal of International Law)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.au.af.mil/au/awc/awcgate/congress/treaties_senate_role.pdf'>A PDF file of the Congressional Research Service report, Library of Congress, ''Treaties and other International Agreements: the Role of the United States Senate''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://hdl.handle.net/10822/552551'>Rethinking U.S. Aid</link><space/>from the<space/><link type='external' href='https://repository.library.georgetown.edu/handle/10822/552494'>Dean Peter Krogh Foreign Affairs Digital Archives</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/PeterGowanInterview2009'>Peter Gowan interview on U.S. foreign policy since 1945</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>United States policy</target></template><template><target>Foreign relations of the United States</target><arg name="expanded">DPC</arg></template><template><target>United States topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Foreign Policy Of The United States</target></template><link><target>Category:Foreign relations of the United States</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:United States law</target></link><link><target>Category:Foreign policy</target></link><link><target>Category:United States foreign policy</target><part>*</part></link></paragraph></article>