<article title='Cluster_sampling'><paragraph><bold>Cluster sampling</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>sampling (statistics)</target><part>sampling</part></link><space/>technique used when &quot;natural&quot; but relatively homogeneous groupings are evident in a<space/><link><target>statistical population</target></link>. It is often used in<space/><link><target>marketing research</target></link>. In this technique, the total population is divided into these groups (or clusters) and a<space/><link><target>simple random sample</target></link><space/>of the groups is selected. Then the required information is collected from a simple random sample of the elements within each selected group. This may be done for every element in these groups or a subsample of elements may be selected within each of these groups. A common motivation for cluster sampling is to reduce the total number of interviews and costs given the desired accuracy. Assuming a fixed sample size, the technique gives more accurate results when most of the variation in the population is within the groups, not between them.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cluster elements</heading><paragraph>The population within a cluster should ideally be as heterogeneous as possible, but there should be homogeneity between cluster<space/><link><target>mean</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Each cluster should be a small-scale representation of the total population. The clusters should be mutually exclusive and collectively exhaustive. A random sampling technique is then used on any relevant clusters to choose which clusters to include in the study. In single-stage cluster sampling, all the elements from each of the selected clusters are used. In two-stage cluster sampling, a random sampling technique is applied to the elements from each of the selected clusters...</paragraph><paragraph>The main difference between cluster sampling and<space/><link><target>stratified sampling</target></link><space/>is that in cluster sampling the cluster is treated as the sampling unit so analysis is done on a population of clusters (at least in the first stage). In stratified sampling, the analysis is done on elements within strata. In stratified sampling, a random sample is drawn from each of the strata, whereas in cluster sampling only the selected clusters are studied. The main objective of cluster sampling is to reduce costs by increasing sampling efficiency. This contrasts with stratified sampling where the main objective is to increase precision.</paragraph><paragraph>There also exists<space/><link><target>multistage sampling</target></link>, here more than two steps are taken in selecting clusters from clusters.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Aspects of cluster sampling</heading><paragraph>One version of cluster sampling is<space/><link><target>area sampling</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>geographical cluster sampling</target></link>. Clusters consist of geographical areas. Because a geographically dispersed population can be expensive to survey, greater economy than simple random sampling can be achieved by treating several respondents within a local area as a cluster. It is usually necessary to increase the total sample size to achieve equivalent precision in the<space/><link><target>estimator</target><trail>s</trail></link>, but cost savings may make that feasible.</paragraph><paragraph>In some situations,<space/><link><target>cluster analysis</target></link><space/>is only appropriate when the clusters are approximately the same size. This can be achieved by combining clusters. If this is not possible,<space/><link><target>sampling (statistics)#Probability-proportional-to-size sampling</target><part>probability proportionate to size sampling</part></link><space/>is used. In this method, the probability of selecting any cluster varies with the size of the cluster, giving larger clusters a greater probability of selection and smaller clusters a lower probability. However, if clusters are selected with probability proportionate to size, the same number of interviews should be carried out in each sampled cluster so that each unit sampled has the same probability of selection.</paragraph><paragraph>Cluster sampling is used to estimate high mortalities in cases such as<space/><link><target>war</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>famine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>natural disaster</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>David Brown,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2006/10/10/AR2006101001442.html'>Study Claims Iraq's 'Excess' Death Toll Has Reached 655,000</link>,<space/><italics>Washington Post</italics>, Wednesday, October 11, 2006. Retrieved September 14, 2010.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Advantage</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Can be cheaper than other methods e.g. fewer travel expenses, administration costs.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Feasibility: This method takes large populations into account. Since these groups are so large, deploying any other technique would be very difficult task. It is feasible only when you are dealing with large population.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Economy: The regular two major concerns of expenditure, i.e., traveling and listing, are greatly reduced in this method. For example: Compiling research information about every house hold in city would be a very difficult, whereas compiling information about various blocks of the city will be easier. Here, traveling as well as listing efforts will be greatly reduced.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Reduced variability: When estimates are being considered by any other method, reduced variability in results are observed. This may not be an ideal situation every time.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Disadvantage</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Higher<space/><link><target>sampling error</target></link>, which can be expressed in the so-called &quot;design effect&quot;, the ratio between the number of subjects in the cluster study and the number of subjects in an equally reliable, randomly sampled unclustered study.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kerry and Bland (1998).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bmj.com/cgi/content/full/316/7142/1455'>Statistics notes: The intracluster correlation coefficient in cluster randomization</link>.<space/><italics>British Medical Journal</italics>, 316, 14551460.</extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Biased samples: If the group in population that is chosen as a sample has a biased opinion, then the entire population is inferred to have the same opinion. This may not be the actual case.</listitem></list><paragraph>Errors: The other probabilistic methods give fewer errors than this method. For this reason, it is discouraged for beginners.</paragraph><heading level='2'>More on cluster sampling</heading><heading level='3'>Two-stage cluster sampling</heading><paragraph>Two-stage cluster sampling, a simple case of<space/><link><target>multistage sampling</target></link>, is obtained by selecting cluster samples in the first stage and then selecting sample of elements from every sampled cluster. Consider a population of<space/><italics>N</italics><space/>clusters in total. In the first stage,<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>clusters are selected using ordinary cluster sampling method. In the second stage,<space/><link><target>simple random sampling</target></link><space/>is usually used.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ahmed</arg><arg name="first">Saifuddin</arg><arg name="title">Methods in Sample Surveys</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">The Johns Hopkins University and Saifuddin Ahmed</arg><arg name="url">http://ocw.jhsph.edu/courses/statmethodsforsamplesurveys/PDFs/Lecture5.pdf</arg></template></extension><space/>It is used separately in every cluster and the numbers of elements selected from different clusters are not necessarily equal. The total number of clusters<space/><italics>N</italics>, number of clusters selected<space/><italics>n</italics>, and numbers of elements from selected clusters need to be pre-determined by the survey designer. Two-stage cluster sampling aims at minimizing survey costs and at the same time controlling the uncertainty related to estimates of interest.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"><space/>Daniel Pfeffermann</arg><arg name="author2">C. Radhakrishna Rao</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Handbook of Statistics Vol.29A Sample Surveys: Theory, Methods and Infernece</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Elsevier B.V.</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-444-53124-7<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>This method can be used in health and social sciences. For instance, researchers used two-stage cluster sampling to generate a representative sample of the Iraqi population to conduct mortality surveys.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">LP Galway<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Nathaniel Bell<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Al S SAE<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Amy Hagopian<space/></arg><arg name="author5">Gilbert Burnham<space/></arg><arg name="author6">Abraham Flaxman<space/></arg><arg name="author7">Wiliam M Weiss<space/></arg><arg name="author8">Julie Rajaratnam<space/></arg><arg name="author9">Tim K Takaro</arg><arg name="title">A two-stage cluster sampling method using gridded population data, a GIS, and Google EarthTM imagery in a population-based mortality survey in Iraq</arg><arg name="journal">International Journal of Health Geographics</arg><arg name="date">27 April 2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ij-healthgeographics.com/content/11/1/12</arg></template></extension><space/>Sampling in this method can be quicker and more reliable than other methods, which is why this method is now used frequently.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>multistage sampling</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>sampling (statistics)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>simple random sampling</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>stratified sampling</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Statistics</target><arg>collection</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cluster Sampling</target></template><link><target>Category:Sampling techniques</target></link><link><target>Category:Market research</target></link></paragraph></article>