<article title='Elegiac_couplet'><paragraph>The<space/><bold>elegiac couplet</bold><space/>is a poetic form used by Greek lyric poets for a variety of themes usually of smaller scale than the<space/><link><target>Epic poetry</target><part>epic</part></link>. Roman poets, particularly<space/><link><target>Ovid</target></link>, adopted the same form in Latin many years later. As with the English<space/><link><target>heroic couplet</target><part>heroic</part></link>, each couplet usually makes sense on its own, while forming part of a larger work.</paragraph><paragraph>Each couplet consist of a<space/><link><target>dactylic hexameter</target><part>hexameter</part></link><space/>verse followed by a<space/><link><target>dactylic pentameter</target><part>pentameter</part></link><space/>verse. The following is a graphic representation of its<space/><link><target>scansion</target></link>. Note that - is a long syllable, u a short syllable, and U is either one long syllable or two short syllables:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>- U | - U | - U | - U | - u u | - -</listitem><listitem>- U | - U | - || - u u | - u u | -</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>The form was felt by the ancients to contrast the rising action of the first verse with a falling quality in the second. The sentiment is summarized in a line from Ovid's<space/><link><target>Amores (Ovid)</target><part>''Amores''</part></link><space/>I.1.27<space/><italics>Sex mihi surgat opus numeris, in quinque residat</italics><space/>- &quot;Let my work rise in six steps, fall back in five.&quot; The effect is illustrated by<space/><link><target>Samuel Taylor Coleridge</target><part>Coleridge</part></link><space/>as:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>In the hexameter rises the fountain's silvery column,</listitem><listitem>In the pentameter aye falling in melody back.</listitem></list><paragraph>translating<space/><link><target>Friedrich_Schiller</target><part>Schiller</part></link>,</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Im Hexameter steigt des Springquells silberne Sule,</listitem><listitem>Im Pentameter drauf fllt sie melodisch herab.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Coleridge</arg><arg name="first">Samuel Taylor</arg><arg name="title">The Collected Works of Samuel Taylor Coleridge</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Princeton University Press</arg><arg name="page">532</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Greek origins</heading><paragraph><bold>The elegiac couplet</bold><space/>is presumed to be the oldest Greek form of<space/><link><target>epodic poetry</target></link><space/>(a form where a later verse is sung in response or comment to a previous one). Scholars, who even in the past did not know who created it,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Horace</target></link>,<space/><italics>Epistulae</italics>, II, 3, 77-78.</extension><space/>theorize the form was originally used in Ionian dirges, with the name &quot;elegy&quot; derived from the Greek<space/><italics>, ,<space/></italics><space/>- &quot;Woe, cry woe, cry!&quot; Hence, the form was used initially for funeral songs, typically accompanied by an<space/><link><target>aulos</target></link>, a double-reed instrument.<space/><link><target>Archilochus</target></link><space/>expanded use of the form to treat other themes, such as war, travel, or homespun philosophy. Between Archilochus and other imitators, the verse form became a common poetic vehicle for conveying any strong emotion.</paragraph><paragraph>At the end of the 7th century BCE,<space/><link><target>Mimnermus</target></link><space/>of Colophon struck on the innovation of using the verse for erotic poetry. He composed several elegies celebrating his love for the flute girl Nanno, and though fragmentary today his poetry was clearly influential in the later Roman development of the form.<space/><link><target>Propertius</target></link>, to cite one example, notes<space/><italics>Plus in amore valet Mimnermi versus Homero</italics><space/>- &quot;The verse of Mimnermus is stronger in love than Homer&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The form continued to be popular throughout the Greek period and treated a number of different themes.<space/><link><target>Tyrtaeus</target></link><space/>composed elegies on a war theme, apparently for a Spartan audience.<space/><link><target>Theognis of Megara</target></link><space/>vented himself in couplets as an embittered aristocrat in a time of social change. Popular leaders were writers of elegy<link><target>Solon</target></link><space/>the lawgiver of Athens composed on political and ethical subjectsand even<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>dabbled with the meter.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>By the<space/><link><target>Hellenistic period</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Alexandrian_school#Literature</target><part>Alexandrian school</part></link><space/>made elegy its favorite and most highly developed form. They preferred the briefer style associated with elegy in contrast to the lengthier epic forms, and made it the singular medium for short epigrams. The founder of this school was<space/><link><target>Philitas of Cos</target></link>. He was eclipsed only by the school's most admired exponent,<space/><link><target>Callimachus</target></link>; their learned character and intricate art would have a heavy influence on the Romans.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="chapter"><space/>Hellenistic poetry<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>A. W. Bulloch<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>[[P.E. Easterling]]; [[Bernard M.W. Knox]] (eds.)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Hellenistic Period and the Empire<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>The Cambridge History of Classical Literature<space/></arg><arg name="year">1985<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-521-35984-8<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1–81<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/CHOL9780521210423.019</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Roman elegy</heading><paragraph>Like all Greek forms, elegy was adapted by the Romans for their own literature. The fragments of<space/><link><target>Ennius</target></link><space/>contain a few couplets, and scattered verses attributed to Roman public figures like<space/><link><target>Cicero</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link><space/>also survive.</paragraph><paragraph>But it is the elegists of the mid-to-late first century BCE who are most commonly associated with the distinctive Roman form of the elegiac couplet.<space/><link><target>Catullus</target></link>, the first of these, is an invaluable link between the Alexandrine school and the subsequent elegies of<space/><link><target>Tibullus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Propertius</target></link><space/>a generation later. His collection, for example, shows a familiarity with the usual Alexandrine style of terse epigram and a wealth of mythological learning, while his 66th poem is a direct translation of Callimachus'<space/><italics>Coma Berenices</italics>. Arguably the most famous elegiac couplet in Latin is his two-line 85th poem<space/><italics><link><target>Odi et amo</target><part>Odi et Amo</part></link></italics>:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>Odi et amo. Quare id faciam, fortasse requiris?</listitem><listitem>Nescio, sed fieri sentio et excrucior.</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>'I hate and I love. Why I do this, perhaps you ask.</listitem><listitem>I don't know, but I feel it happening and I'm tormented.'</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Many people, particularly students of Latin, who read this poem aloud often miss the metre because of the high amount of elision in this poem.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>- u u/ - - / - u u / - - / - u u / - x</listitem><listitem>Od'et am/o. Qua/r'id faci/am, for/tasse req/uiris?</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>- u u / - u u / - // - u u / - u u / -</listitem><listitem>Nescio / sed fier/i // senti'et / excruci/or.</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Cornelius Gallus</target></link><space/>is another important statesman/writer of this period, one who was generally regarded by the ancients as the greatest of the elegists. Other than a few scant lines, all of his work has been lost.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Elegy in the Augustan Age</heading><paragraph>The form reached its zenith with the collections of<space/><link><target>Tibullus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Propertius</target></link>, and several collections of<space/><link><target>Ovid</target></link><space/>(the<space/><italics><link><target>Amores (Ovid)</target><part>Amores</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Heroides</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tristia</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Epistulae ex Ponto</target></link></italics>). The vogue of elegy during this time is seen in the so-called 3rd and 4th book of Tibullus. Many poems in these books were clearly not written by Tibullus but by others, perhaps part of a circle under Tibullus' patron Mesalla. Notable in this collection are the poems of<space/><link><target>Sulpicia</target></link>, the only surviving Latin literature written by a woman.</paragraph><paragraph>Through these poetsand in comparison with the earlier Catullusit is possible to trace specific characteristics and evolutionary patterns in the Roman form of the verse:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The Roman authors often write about their own love affairs. In contrast to their Greek originals, these poets are characters in his own stories, and write about love in a highly subjective way.</listitem><listitem>The form began to be applied to new themes beyond the traditional love, loss, and other &quot;strong emotion&quot; verse. Propertius uses it to relate aetiological or &quot;origin&quot; myths such as the origins of Rome (IV.1) and the Temple of Apollo on the Palatine Hill (IV.6). Ovid's<space/><italics><link><target>Heroides</target></link></italics>though at first glance fictitious love lettersare described by Ovid himself as a new literary form, and can be read as character studies of famous heroines from mythology. There is also Ovid's<space/><italics><link><target>Fasti (poem)</target><part>Fasti</part></link></italics>, a lengthy elegiac poem on the first six months of the Roman calendar.</listitem><listitem>The Romans adopted the Alexandrine habit of concealing the name of their beloved in the poem with a pseudonym. Catullus' vexing<space/><link><target>Lesbia</target></link><space/>is notorious as the pseudonym of the teasing Clodia. But as the form developed, this habit becomes more artificial; Tibullus' Delia and Propertius' Cynthia, while likely real people, lack something of the specificity seen in Lesbia, while Ovid's Corinna is often considered a mere literary device.</listitem><listitem>The poets become extremely careful in forming the distinctive pentameter line of their verses. Examples:<list type='bullet'><listitem>A trend toward the clear separation of the pentameter halves. Catullus, for example, allows an elision across the<space/><link><target>caesura</target></link><space/>in 18 cases, a rare flaw in the later poets (Ovid, for example, never does this).</listitem><listitem>The pentameter begins to show a semi-regular &quot;leonine&quot; rhyme between the two halves of the verse, e.g. Tib. I.12, where the<space/><italics>culti</italics><space/>ending the first half of the pentameter rhymes with the<space/><italics>soli</italics><space/>closing the verse:</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>Divitias alius fulvo sibi congerat auro</listitem><listitem>Et teneat culti iugera multa soli,</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem>While Catullus shows this rhyme in about 1 in 5 couplets, the later elegists use it more frequently. Propertius II.34, for example, has the rhyme in nearly half its pentameters. Rhyming between adjacent lines and even in the two halves of the hexameter is also observed, more than would be expected by chance alone.</listitem><listitem>Unlike Catullus, later poets show a definite trend toward ending the pentameter with a two-syllable word. Propertius is especially interesting; in his first two books, he ignores this rule about as frequently as Catullus and Tibullus, but in the last two books endings other than a disyllabic word are very rare. Ovid has no exceptions to the disyllable in his<space/><link><target>Amores (Ovid)</target><part>Amores</part></link>, and only a few proper names occur as polysyllabic endings in his later work.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>The hexameter follows the usual rhetorical trends of the<space/><link><target>dactylic hexameter</target></link><space/>in this age. If anything, the elegists are even more interested in verbal effects like alliteration and assonance.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Post-Augustan writers</heading><paragraph>Although no classical poet wrote collections of love elegies after Ovid, the verse retained its popularity as a vehicle for popular<space/><link><target>occasional poetry</target></link>. Elegiac verses appear, for example, in<space/><link><target>Petronius</target></link>'<space/><italics>Satyricon</italics>, and<space/><link><target>Martial</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Epigrams</target></link><space/>uses it for many witty stand-alone couplets and for longer pieces. The trend continues through the remainder of the empire; short elegies appear in<space/><link><target>Apuleius</target></link>'s story<space/><italics>Psyche and Cupid</italics><space/>and the minor writings of<space/><link><target>Ausonius</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Medieval elegy</heading><paragraph>After the fall of the empire, one writer who produced elegiac verse was<space/><link><target>Maximianus (poet)</target><part>Maximianus</part></link>. Various Christian writers also adopted the form;<space/><link><target>Venantius Fortunatus</target></link><space/>wrote some of his hymns in the meter, while later<space/><link><target>Alcuin</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Venerable Bede</target></link><space/>dabbled in the verse. The form also remained popular among the educated classes for gravestone epitaphs; many such epitaphs can be found in European cathedrals.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>De tribus puellis</target></link></italics><space/>is an example of a Latin<space/><italics><link><target>fabliau</target></link></italics>, a genre of<space/><link><target>comedy</target></link><space/>which employed elegiac couplets in imitation of Ovid. The medieval theorist<space/><link><target>John of Garland</target></link><space/>wrote that &quot;all comedy is elegy, but the reverse is not true.&quot;<space/><link><target>Medieval Latin</target></link><space/>had a developed comedic genre known as<space/><link><target>elegiac comedy</target></link>. Sometimes narrative, sometimes<space/><link><target>drama</target><trail>tic</trail></link>, it deviated from ancient practice because, as Ian Thompson writes, &quot;no ancient drama would ever have been written in elegiacs.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Renaissance and modern period</heading><paragraph>With the Renaissance, more skilled writers interested in the revival of Roman culture took on the form in a way which attempted to recapture the spirit of the Augustan writers. The Dutch Latinist<space/><link><target>Johannes Secundus</target></link>, for example, included Catullus-inspired love elegies in his<space/><italics>Liber Basiorum</italics>, while the English poet<space/><link><target>John Milton</target></link><space/>wrote several lengthy elegies throughout his career. This trend continued down through the<space/><link><target>Recent Latin</target></link><space/>writers, whose close study of their Augustan counterparts reflects their general attempts to apply the cultural and literary forms of the ancient world to contemporary themes.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Prosody (Latin)</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.users.globalnet.co.uk/~loxias/latinverse.htm'>Reading Latin Verse Aloud: Metre and Scansion</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20080119132354/http://classics.rutgers.edu/Lat327/def.html'>What is Elegy? (Archive.org)</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Poetic form</target></link></paragraph></article>