<article title='Amphipolis'><paragraph><link><target>File:Amphipolis location.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Amphipolis</part></link><bold>Amphipolis</bold><space/>(aka Amfpolis,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.geographic.org/geographic_names/name.php?uni</arg><arg name="title">Amfípolis: Greece, name, administrative division, geographic coordinates and map<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/></arg><arg name="work">Geographical Names<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-10-22</arg></template></extension><space/><template><target>lang-ell</target><arg>Αμφίπολη</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>lang-grc</target><arg>Ἀμφίπολις</arg></template>) is a municipality in the<space/><link><target>Serres (regional unit)</target><part>Serres regional unit</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link>. The seat of the municipality is<space/><link><target>Rodolivos</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kallikratis"><link type='external' href='http://www.kedke.gr/uploads2010/FEKB129211082010_kallikratis.pdf'>Kallikratis law</link><space/>Greece Ministry of Interior<space/><template><target>el icon</target></template></extension><space/>Amphipolis was a rich<space/><link><target>Polis</target><part>city (polis)</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Macedon</target><part>ancient Macedonia</part></link>. It was famous for events such as the battle of the Spartans and Athenians in 424BC, and as the place where<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link><space/>prepared for campaigns leading to his invasion of Asia.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Amphipolis&quot;, Ministry of Culture: ISBN 960-214-126-3</extension><space/>Alexander's three finest admirals, Nearchos, Androsthenes and Laomedon, resided here and after Alexander's death, his wife<space/><link><target>Roxana</target><part>Roxane</part></link><space/>and their small son<space/><link><target>Alexander IV of Macedon</target><part>Alexander IV</part></link><space/>were exiled and later murdered here.</paragraph><paragraph>The unique and beautiful &quot;Lion of Amphipolis&quot; monument nearby is a well-known destination for visitors. Partial excavations in the city have so far revealed important ancient walls, buildings and tombs. At the nearby vast<space/><link><target>Kasta Tomb</target><part>Kasta burial mound</part></link>, an important ancient Macedonian<space/><link><target>tomb</target></link><space/>has recently been revealed.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Kasta tumulus and Lion of Amphipolis location map en.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Amphipolis location map</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Origins</heading><paragraph>Throughout the 5th century BC,<space/><link><target>Delian League</target><part>Athens</part></link><space/>sought to consolidate its control over Thrace, which was strategically important because of its primary materials (the gold and silver of the<space/><link><target>Pangaion hills</target></link><space/>and the dense forests essential for naval construction), and the sea routes vital for Athens' supply of grain from<space/><link><target>Scythia</target></link>. After a first unsuccessful attempt at colonisation in 497&amp;nbsp;BC by the<space/><link><target>Miletus</target><part>Milesian</part></link><space/><link><target>Tyrant</target></link><space/><link><target>Histiaeus</target></link>, the Athenians founded a first colony at Ennea-Hodoi (Nine Ways) in 465, but these first ten thousand colonists were massacred by the<space/><link><target>Thracians</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Thucydides</target></link><space/>I, 100, 3</extension><space/>A second attempt took place in 437&amp;nbsp;BC on the same site under the guidance of<space/><link><target>Hagnon</target></link>, son of<space/><link><target>Nicias</target></link>, which was successful. The city and its first walls date from this time.<link><target>File:Plan Amphipolis-en.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Map of Amphipolis.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The new settlement took the name of Amphipolis (literally, &quot;around the city&quot;), a name which is the subject of much debate about<space/><link><target>lexicography</target></link>. Thucydides claims the name comes from the fact that the Strymon flows &quot;around the city&quot; on two sides;<extension extension_name='ref'>http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0200&amp;layout=&amp;loc=4.102.3</extension><space/>however a note in the<space/><link><target>Suda</target></link><space/>(also given in the lexicon of<space/><link><target>Patriarch Photios I of Constantinople</target><part>Photius</part></link>) offers a different explanation apparently given by<space/><link><target>Marsyas</target></link>, son of<space/><link><target>Periander</target></link>: that a large proportion of the population lived &quot;around the city&quot;. However, a more probable explanation is the one given by<space/><link><target>Julius Pollux</target></link>: that the name indicates the vicinity of an<space/><link><target>isthmus</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Amphipolis became the main power base of the Athenians in Thrace and, consequently, a target of choice for their<space/><link><target>Sparta</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>adversaries. The Athenian population remained very much in the minority in the city.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0200;query=chapter%3D%23471;layout=;loc=4.105.1</extension><space/>For this reason Amphipolis remained an independent city and an ally of the Athenians, rather than a colony or member of the confederacy. However, in 424 BC the Spartan general<space/><link><target>Brasidas</target></link><space/>easily took control of the city.</paragraph><paragraph>A rescue expedition led by the Athenian general, and later historian, Thucydides had to settle for securing<space/><link><target>Eion</target></link><space/>and could not retake Amphipolis, a failure for which Thucydides was sentenced to exile. A new Athenian force under the command of<space/><link><target>Cleon</target></link><space/>failed once more in 422&amp;nbsp;BC during a<space/><link><target>Battle of Amphipolis</target><part>battle</part></link><space/>at which both Cleon and Brasidas lost their lives. Brasidas survived long enough to hear of the defeat of the Athenians and was buried at Amphipolis with impressive pomp. From then on he was regarded as the founder of the city<extension extension_name='ref'>http://perseus.mpiwg-berlin.mpg.de/cgi-bin/ptext?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.01.0200;query=chapter%3D%23511;layout=;loc=5.10.1</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Koukouli-Chrysanthaki Ch., &quot;Excavating Classical Amphipoli&quot;, In (eds) Stamatopoulou M., and M., Yeroulanou &lt;Excavating Classical Culture&gt;, BAR International Series 1031, 2002:57-73</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Agelarakis A., Physical anthropological report on the cremated human remains of an individual retrieved from the Amphipolis agora, In Excvating Classical Amphipolis by Koukouli-Chrysantkai Ch., &lt;Excavating Classical Culture&gt; (eds.) Stamatopoulou M., and M., Yeroulanou, BAR International Series 1031, 2002: 72-73.</extension>and honoured with yearly games and sacrifices.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Macedonian rule</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Amphipolis fortifications.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Fortification</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and bridge of Amphipolis.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The city itself kept its independence until the reign of king<space/><link><target>Philip II of Macedon</target><part>Philip II</part></link><space/>(r. 359336 BC) despite several Athenian attacks, notably because of the government of<space/><link><target>Callistratus of Aphidnae</target></link>. In 357&amp;nbsp;BC, Philip succeeded where the Athenians had failed and conquered the city, thereby removing the obstacle which Amphipolis presented to Macedonian control over Thrace. According the historian<space/><link><target>Theopompus</target></link>, this conquest came to be the object of a secret accord between Athens and Philip II, who would return the city in exchange for the fortified town of<space/><link><target>Pydna</target></link>, but the Macedonian king betrayed the accord, refusing to cede Amphipolis and laying siege to Pydna as well.</paragraph><paragraph>The city was not immediately incorporated into the Macedonian kingdom, and for some time preserved its institutions and a certain degree of autonomy. The border of Macedonia was not moved further east; however, Philip sent a number of Macedonian governors to Amphipolis, and in many respects the city was effectively &quot;Macedonianized&quot;. Nomenclature, the calendar and the currency (the<space/><link><target>Stater</target><part>gold stater</part></link>, created by Philip to capitalise on the gold reserves of the Pangaion hills, replaced the Amphipolitan<space/><link><target>drachma</target></link>) were all replaced by Macedonian equivalents. In the reign of<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link>, Amphipolis was an important naval base, and the birthplace of three of the most famous Macedonian admirals:<space/><link><target>Nearchus</target></link>, Androsthenes<extension extension_name='ref'>http://books.google.com/books?um=1&amp;q=Androsthenes+Thasos&amp;btnG=Search+Books</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Laomedon of Mytilene</target><part>Laomedon</part></link>, whose burial place is most likely marked by the famous lion of Amphipolis.<link><target>File:Amphipolis Lion.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The &quot;<link><target>Lion of Amphipolis</target><part>Amphipolis lion</part></link>&quot;.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The importance of the city in this period is shown by Alexander the Great's decision that it was one of the six cities at which large luxurious temples costing 1500 talents were built. Alexander prepared for campaigns here against Thrace in 335BC and the his army and fleet assembled near the port before the invasion of Asia. The port was also used as naval base during his campaigns in Asia. After Alexander's death, his wife Roxane and their small son Alexander IV were exiled by<space/><link><target>Cassander</target></link><space/>and later murdered here.</paragraph><paragraph>Throughout Macedonian sovereignty Amphipolis was a strong fortress of great strategic and economic importance, as shown by inscriptions. Amphipolis became one of the main stops on the Macedonian royal road (as testified by a border stone found between<space/><link><target>Philippi</target></link><space/>and Amphipolis giving the distance to the latter), and later on the<space/><italics><link><target>Via Egnatia</target></link></italics>, the principal<space/><link><target>Roman roads</target><part>Roman road</part></link><space/>which crossed the southern Balkans. Apart from the ramparts of the lower town, the<space/><link><target>Gymnasium (ancient Greece)</target><part>gymnasium</part></link><space/>and a set of well-preserved frescoes from a wealthy villa are the only artifacts from this period that remain visible. Though little is known of the layout of the town, modern knowledge of its institutions is in considerably better shape thanks to a rich epigraphic documentation, including a military ordinance of<space/><link><target>Philip V of Macedon</target><part>Philip V</part></link><space/>and an<space/><link><target>Ephebos</target><part>ephebarchic</part></link><space/>law from the gymnasium.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Conquest by the Romans</heading><paragraph>After the final victory of<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target><part>Rome</part></link><space/>over Macedonia in a<space/><link><target>Battle of Pydna</target><part>battle</part></link><space/>in 168&amp;nbsp;BC, Amphipolis became the capital one of the four mini-republics, or<space/><italics>merides</italics>, which were created by the Romans out of the kingdom of the<space/><link><target>Antigonid Dynasty</target><part>Antigonids</part></link><space/>which<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great#Legacy and division of the empire</target><part>succeeded</part></link><space/>Alexanders empire in Macedon. These<space/><italics>merides</italics><space/>were gradually incorporated into the Roman client state, and later province, of<space/><link><target>Thracia</target></link>. According to the<space/><link><target>Acts of the Apostles</target></link>, the apostles<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target><part>Paul</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Silas</target></link><space/>passed through Amphipolis in the early 50s AD, on their<space/><link><target>Missionary journeys of Paul</target><part>journey</part></link><space/>between<space/><link><target>Philippi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thessalonica</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Acts</arg><arg>17:1</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Revival in Late Antiquity</heading><paragraph>During the period of<space/><link><target>Late Antiquity</target></link>, Amphipolis benefited from the increasing economic prosperity of Macedonia, as is evidenced by the large number of<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian churches</part></link><space/>that were built. Significantly however, these churches were built within a restricted area of the town, sheltered by the walls of the<space/><link><target>acropolis</target></link>. This has been taken as evidence that the large fortified perimeter of the ancient town was no longer defendable, and that the population of the city had considerably diminished.</paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, the number, size and quality of the churches constructed between the fifth and sixth centuries are impressive. Four<space/><link><target>basilica</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>adorned with rich<space/><link><target>mosaic</target></link><space/>floors and elaborate architectural sculptures (such as the ram-headed<space/><link><target>column</target></link><space/>capitals - see picture) have been excavated, as well as a church with a hexagonal central plan which evokes that of the<space/><link><target>Basilica of San Vitale</target><part>basilica</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Saint Vitalis of Milan</target><part>St. Vitalis</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Ravenna</target></link>. It is difficult to find reasons for such municipal extravagance in such a small town. One possible explanation provided by the historian<space/><link><target>Andr Boulanger</target></link><space/>is that an increasing willingness on the part of the wealthy upper classes in the late Roman period to spend money on local<space/><link><target>gentrification</target></link><space/>projects (which he terms<space/><italics><link><target>euergetism</target></link></italics>, from the Greek verb , (meaning 'I do good') was exploited by the local church to its advantage, which led to a mass gentrification of the urban centre and of the agricultural riches of the citys territory. Amphipolis was also a<space/><link><target>diocese</target></link><space/>under the<space/><link><target>metropolitan see</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Thessalonica</target></link><space/>- the Bishop of Amphipolis is first mentioned in 533. The bishopric is today listed by the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>titular see</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Annuario Pontificio 2013</italics><space/>(Libreria Editrice Vaticana 2013 ISBN 978-88-209-9070-1), p. 831</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Final decline of the city</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>South Slavs#Interaction with the Balkan population</target><part>Slavic invasions</part></link><space/>of the late 6th century gradually encroached on the back-country Amphipolitan lifestyle and led to the decline of the town, during which period its inhabitants retreated to the area around the acropolis. The ramparts were maintained to a certain extent, thanks to materials plundered from the monuments of the lower city, and the large unused cisterns of the upper city were occupied by small houses and the workshops of artisans. Around the middle of the 7th century AD, a further reduction of the inhabited area of the city was followed by an increase in the fortification of the town, with the construction of a new rampart with pentagonal towers cutting through the middle of the remaining monuments. The acropolis, the<space/><link><target>Thermae</target><part>Roman baths</part></link>, and especially the episcopal basilica were crossed by this wall.</paragraph><paragraph>The city was probably abandoned in the eighth century, as the last bishop was attested in 787. Its inhabitants probably moved to the neighbouring site of ancient Eion, port of Amphipolis, which had been rebuilt and refortified in the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target><part>Byzantine period</part></link><space/>under the name Chrysopolis. This small port continued to enjoy some prosperity, before being abandoned during the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target><part>Ottoman period</part></link>. The last recorded sign of activity in the region of Amphipolis was the construction of a fortified tower to the north in 1367 by the<space/><italics><link><target>megas primikerios</target></link></italics><space/>John and the<space/><italics><link><target>stratopedarches</target></link></italics><space/>Alexios to protect the land that they had given to the<space/><link><target>Pantokratoros monastery</target><part>monastery of Pantokrator</part></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Mount Athos</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Archaeology</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Amphipolis frescoes.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Fresco</target></link><space/>from a house (Hellenistic period).</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The site was discovered and described by many travellers and archaeologists during the 19th century, including E. Cousinry (1831) (engraver), L. Heuzey (1861), and P. Perdrizet (18941899). However, excavations did not truly begin until after the Second World War. The<space/><link><target>Archaeological Society of Athens</target><part>Greek Archaeological Society</part></link><space/>under D. Lazaridis excavated in 1972 and 1985, uncovering a necropolis, the city wall (see photograph), the basilicas, and the acropolis.Further excavations have since uncovered the river bridge, the gymnasium, greek and roman villas and numerous tombs etc.</paragraph><paragraph>Parts of the lion monument and tombs were discovered during World War I by Bulgarian and British troops whilst digging trenches in the area. In 1934, M. Feyel, of the<space/><link><target>cole franaise d'Athnes</target></link>, led an<space/><link><target>epigraphy</target><part>epigraphical mission</part></link><space/>to the site and uncovered further remains of the lion monument (a reconstruction was given in the<space/><italics>Bulletin de Correspondance Hellnique</italics>, a publication of the EfA which is available on line).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://cefael.efa.gr/detail.php?site_id=1&amp;amp;actionID=page&amp;amp;prevpos=0&amp;amp;serie_id=BCH&amp;amp;volume_number=59&amp;amp;issue_number=0&amp;amp;startpos=289'>Bulletin de Correspondance Hellnique</link><space/><template><target>fr icon</target></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The silver ossuary containing the cremated remains of Brasidas<extension extension_name='ref'>A. Agelarakis, Physical anthropological report on the cremated human remains of an individual retrieved from the Amphipolis agora, In Excvating Classical Amphipolis by Ch. Koukouli-Chrysantkai, &lt;Excavating Classical Culture&gt; (eds.) Stamatopoulou M., and M., Yeroulanou, BAR International Series 1031, 2002: 72-73</extension><space/>and a gold crown (see image) was found in a tomb in pride of place under the Agora.<link><target>File:Silver ossuary and gold crown of Brasidas.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Silver ossuary and gold crown of Brasidas</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Tomb of Amphipolis</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Kasta Tomb</arg></template><link><target>File:The Abduction of Persephone by Pluto, Amphipolis.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Abduction of<space/><link><target>Persephone</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Pluto (mythology)</target><part>Pluto</part></link>, Amphipolis</part></link>In 2012<extension extension_name='ref' name="telegraph 1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/worldnews/europe/greece/11080463/Marble-female-figurines-unearthed-in-vast-Alexander-the-Great-era-Greek-tomb.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Marble female figurines unearthed in vast Alexander the Great-era Greek tomb<space/></arg><arg name="author">Andrew Marszal<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 September 2014<space/></arg><arg name="website">www.telegraph.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Daily Telegraph]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">10 September 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Greek archaeologists unearthed a large tomb within the<space/><link><target>Kasta Tomb</target><part>Kasta Hill</part></link>, the biggest burial mound in Greece, northeast of Amphipolis. The large size of the tumulus indicates the prominence of the burials made there. The perimeter wall of the tumulus is 497 meters long, and is made of limestone covered with marble.</paragraph><paragraph>The tomb comprises three chambers separated by walls. There are two<space/><link><target>sphinxes</target></link><space/>just outside the entrance to the tomb. Two of the columns supporting the roof in the first section are in the form of<space/><link><target>Caryatid</target><trail>s</trail></link>, in the 4th century BC style. The excavation revealed a pebble mosaic showing the abduction of<space/><link><target>Persephone</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Hades</target></link><space/>directly behind the Caryatids and in front of the Macedonian marble door leading to the &quot;third&quot; chamber. Hades' chariot is drawn by two white horses and led to the underworld by<space/><link><target>Hermes</target></link>. The mosaic verifies the Macedonian character of the tomb. As the head of one of the sphinxes was found inside the tomb behind the broken door, it is clear that there were intruders, probably in antiquity.</paragraph><paragraph>The identity of the burial remains unknown and the excavation is continuing.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.com/news/world-europe-28758920</arg><arg name="title">Greek tomb at Amphipolis is 'important discovery'</arg><arg name="date">12 August 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 August 2014</arg></template></extension>Dr.<space/><link><target>Katerina Peristeri</target></link>, the archaeologist heading the excavation of the tomb, dates the tomb to the 4th Century BC, the period after the death of<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link><space/>(323&amp;nbsp;BC).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Amphipolitans</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Demetrius of Amphipolis</target></link>, student of Plato's</listitem><listitem><link><target>Zoilus</target></link><space/>(400&amp;nbsp;BC-320&amp;nbsp;BC), grammarian, cynic philosopher</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pamphilus (painter)</target></link>, head of<space/><link><target>Sicyon</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>school and teacher of<space/><link><target>Apelles</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Aetion</target></link>, sculptor</listitem><listitem><link><target>Philippus of Amphipolis</target></link>, historian</listitem><listitem><link><target>Nearchus</target></link>, admiral</listitem><listitem><link><target>Erigyius</target></link>, general</listitem><listitem><link><target>Damasias of Amphipolis</target></link><space/>320&amp;nbsp;BC<space/><link><target>Stadion (running race)</target><part>Stadion</part></link><space/>Olympics</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hermagoras of Amphipolis</target></link><space/>(c. 225&amp;nbsp;BC), stoic philosopher, follower of<space/><link><target>Persaeus</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph>The fictional character<space/><link><target>Xena</target></link>, of the show<space/><italics><link><target>Xena: Warrior Princess</target></link></italics>, was from the city of Amphipolis.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Amfipolis+.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Coins from Amphipolis.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Amphipolis capitol.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Ram-headed capital of a column from a pre-Christian temple.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Amphipolis skulls 1916 British Shropshire Light Infantry.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>British soldiers of the 2nd<space/><link><target>King's Shropshire Light Infantry</target></link><space/>with skulls excavated during the construction of trenches and dugouts at site of Amphipolis during<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, 1916.</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Lion of Amphipolis early excavations.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Amphipolis Lion - early excavations.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Macedonian Museums-25-Arx Amphipolis-126.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Amphipolis archaeological museum.</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Archaeological Museum of Amphipolis</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Amphipolis</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://amphipolis.gr/en/'>Official site about Amphipolis</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gtp.gr/LocPage.asp?id=7646'>Demographic Information from Greek Travel Pages</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/am-ao/amphipolis/amphipolis.html'>Livius.org: Amphipolis</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theamphipolistomb.com'>The tomb of Amphipolis</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Greek Macedonia</target></template><template><target>Kallikratis-Central Macedonia</target></template><template><target>Amfipoli div</target></template><template><target>Second Journey of Paul of Tarsus</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Archaeological sites in Macedonia (Greece)</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Amphipolis</target></link><link><target>Category:437 BC</target></link><link><target>Category:Populated places established in the 5th century BC</target></link><link><target>Category:Populated places in Serres (regional unit)</target></link><link><target>Category:Municipalities of Central Macedonia</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Greek archaeological sites in Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:Populated places in Ancient Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:Former populated places in Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman sites in Greece</target></link><link><target>Category:New Testament places</target></link><link><target>Category:5th-century BC establishments</target></link></paragraph></article>