<article title='Chapterhouse%3A_Dune'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg><space/>
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Chapterhouse: Dune
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>FrankHerbert ChapterhouseDune 1st.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>US 1st edition cover
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Frank Herbert]] 
</arg><arg name="cover_artist"><space/>[[Bruce Pennington]]
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United States
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>[[Dune (franchise)|''Dune'' series]]
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Science fiction novel]]
</arg><arg name="published"><space/>1985
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[G. P. Putnam's Sons|Putnam]]
</arg><arg name="media_type"><space/>Print ([[hardcover]] & [[paperback]])
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>464 pp
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-399-13027-6
</arg><arg name="dewey"><space/>813/.54 19
</arg><arg name="congress"><space/>PS3558.E63 C48 1985
</arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>11133684
</arg><arg name="preceded_by"><space/>[[Heretics of Dune]]
</arg><arg name="followed_by"><space/>[[Hunters of Dune]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold><italics>Chapterhouse: Dune</italics></bold><space/>is a 1985<space/><link><target>science fiction novel</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Frank Herbert</target></link>, the last in his<space/><link><target>Dune (franchise)</target><part>''Dune'' series</part></link><space/>of six novels. It rose to #2 on<space/><link><target>The New York Times Best Seller list</target><part>''The New York Times'' Best Seller list</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYTBS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1985/05/19/books/best-sellers.html?scp</arg><arg name="title">Best Sellers</arg><arg name="date">May 19, 1985</arg><arg name="work">[[The New York Times]]</arg><arg name="publisher">NYTimes.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 20, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A direct followup to<space/><italics><link><target>Heretics of Dune</target></link></italics>, the novel chronicles the continued struggles of the<space/><link><target>Bene Gesserit</target></link><space/>Sisterhood against the violent<space/><link><target>Honored Matres</target></link>, who are succeeding in their bid to seize control of the universe and destroy the factions and planets that oppose them.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Chapterhouse: Dune</italics><space/>ends with a<space/><link><target>cliffhanger</target></link>, and Herbert's subsequent death in 1986 left some overarching plotlines of the series unresolved.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT 2006"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://web.archive.org/web/20131127220957/http://www.nytimes.com/2006/09/24/books/review/Itzkoff.t.html?scp</arg><arg name="title">Across the Universe: Dune Babies<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 24, 2006<space/></arg><arg name="last">Itzkoff<space/></arg><arg name="first">Dave<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''[[The New York Times]]''<space/></arg><arg name="website">NYTimes.com (Internet Archive)<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">November 27, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 27, 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="SFD 2007-08"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://web.archive.org/web/20080513064723/http://www.scifidimensions.com/Aug07/sandwormsofdune.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Audiobook Review: ''Sandworms of Dune'' by Brian Herbert & Kevin J Anderson<space/></arg><arg name="last">Snider<space/></arg><arg name="first">John C.<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SciFiDimensions.com (Internet Archive)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 20, 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Two decades later, Herbert's son<space/><link><target>Brian Herbert</target></link>, along with<space/><link><target>Kevin J. Anderson</target></link>, published two<space/><link><target>sequel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>&amp;ndash;<space/><italics><link><target>Hunters of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2006) and<space/><italics><link><target>Sandworms of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2007) &amp;ndash; based in part on notes left behind by Frank Herbert for what he referred to as<space/><italics>Dune 7</italics>, his own planned seventh novel in the<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>series.<template><target>Herbert notes</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot introduction</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Bene Gesserit</target></link><space/>still find themselves questioning the<space/><link><target>Golden Path (Dune)</target><part>Golden Path</part></link><space/>of humanity set by the<space/><link><target>Leto II Atreides</target><part>God Emperor Leto II</part></link>. Now they must survive the<space/><link><target>Honored Matres</target></link>, whose reckless conquest of the<space/><link><target>Old Empire (Dune)</target><part>Old Empire</part></link><space/>threatens Bene Gesserit survival. The Sisters must reassess their timeless methods: does ultimate survival go beyond calculated manipulation? Is there greater purpose to life than consolidating power?</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot summary</heading><paragraph>The situation is desperate for the Bene Gesserit as they find themselves the targets of the Honored Matres, whose conquest of the Old Empire is almost complete. The Matres are seeking to assimilate the technology and developed methods of the Bene Gesserit and exterminate the Sisterhood itself. Now in command of the Bene Gesserit, Mother Superior<space/><link><target>Darwi Odrade</target></link><space/>continues to develop her drastic, secret plan to overcome the Honored Matres. The Bene Gesserit are also terraforming the planet<space/><link><target>Chapterhouse (Dune)</target><part>Chapterhouse</part></link><space/>to accommodate the all-important<space/><link><target>Sandworm (Dune)</target><part>sandworm</part><trail>s</trail></link>, whose native planet<space/><link><target>Arrakis</target><part>Dune</part></link><space/>had been destroyed by the Matres.<space/><link><target>Sheeana</target></link>, in charge of the project, expects sandworms to appear soon. The Honored Matres have also destroyed the entire<space/><link><target>Bene Tleilax</target></link><space/>civilization, with Tleilaxu Master<space/><link><target>Scytale (Dune)</target><part>Scytale</part></link><space/>the only one of his kind left alive. In Bene Gesserit captivity, Scytale possesses the Tleilaxu secret of<space/><link><target>ghola</target></link><space/>production, which he has reluctantly traded for the Sisterhood's protection. The first ghola produced is that of their recently deceased military genius,<space/><link><target>Miles Teg</target></link>. The Bene Gesserit have two other prisoners on Chapterhouse: the latest<space/><link><target>Duncan Idaho</target></link><space/>ghola, and former Honored Matre<space/><link><target>Murbella</target></link>, whom they have accepted as a novice despite their suspicion that she intends to escape back to the Honored Matres.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Lampadas</target></link>, a center for Bene Gesserit education, has been destroyed by the Honored Matres. The planet's Chancellor,<space/><link><target>Reverend Mother (Dune)</target><part>Reverend Mother</part></link><space/><link><target>Lucilla (Dune)</target><part>Lucilla</part></link>, manages to escape carrying the shared-minds of millions of Reverend Mothers. Lucilla is forced to land on<space/><link><target>Giedi Prime</target><part>Gammu</part></link><space/>where she seeks refuge with an underground group of<space/><link><target>Jews</target></link>. The Rabbi gives Lucilla sanctuary, but to save his organization he must deliver her to the Matres. Before doing so, he reveals<space/><link><target>Rebecca (Dune)</target><part>Rebecca</part></link>, a &quot;wild&quot; Reverend Mother who has gained her<space/><link><target>Other Memory</target></link><space/>without Bene Gesserit training. Lucilla shares minds with Rebecca, who promises to take the memories of Lampadas safely back to the Sisterhood. Lucilla is then &quot;betrayed&quot;, and taken before the<space/><link><target>Great Honored Matre</target></link><space/><link><target>Dama (Dune)</target><part>Dama</part></link>, who tries to persuade her to join the Honored Matres, preserving her life in exchange for Bene Gesserit secrets. Lucilla refuses, and Dama ultimately kills her.</paragraph><paragraph>Back on Chapterhouse, Odrade confronts Duncan and forces him to admit that he is a<space/><link><target>Mentat</target></link>, proving that he retains the memories of his many ghola lives. He does not reveal his mysterious visions of two people. Meanwhile, Murbella collapses under the pressure of Bene Gesserit training, giving in to &quot;word weapons&quot; that the Bene Gesserit had planted to undermine her earlier Honored Matre identity. Murbella realizes that she wants to be Bene Gesserit. Odrade believes that the Bene Gesserit made a mistake in fearing emotion, and that in order to evolve, the Bene Gesserit must learn to accept emotions. Odrade permits Duncan to watch Murbella undergo the<space/><link><target>spice agony</target></link>, making him the first man ever to do so. Murbella survives the ordeal and becomes a Reverend Mother.</paragraph><paragraph>Odrade then confronts Sheeana, discovering that Duncan and Sheeana have been allied together for some time. Sheeana does not reveal that they have been considering the option of reawakening Teg's memory through<space/><link><target>Imprinting (psychology)</target><part>Imprinting</part></link>, nor does Odrade discover that Sheeana has the keys to Duncan's no-ship prison. Odrade continues molding Scytale, with Sheeana showing him a baby sandworm, the Bene Gesserit's own long term supply of spice, and destroying Scytale's main bargaining card. Finally, Teg is awakened by Sheeana using imprinting techniques. Odrade appoints him again as<space/><link><target>Bashar (Dune)</target><part>Bashar</part></link><space/>of the military forces of the Sisterhood for the assault on the Honored Matres.</paragraph><paragraph>Odrade next calls a meeting of all the Bene Gesserit, announcing her plan to attack the Honored Matres. She tells them that this attack will be led by Teg. She also announces candidates to succeed her as Mother Superior; she will share her memories with Murbella and Sheeana before she leaves. Odrade then goes to meet the Great Honored Matre. Under cover of Odrade's diplomacy, the Bene Gesserit forces under Teg attack Gammu with tremendous force. Teg uses his secret ability to see no-ships to secure control of the system. Survivors of the attack flee to Junction, and Teg follows them there and carries all with him. Victory for the Bene Gesserit seems inevitable. In the midst of this battle, the Jews (including Rebecca with her precious memories) take refuge with the Bene Gesserit fleet.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Logno</target></link><space/>&amp;mdash; chief advisor to Dama &amp;mdash; assassinates Dama with poison and assumes control of the Honored Matres. Her first act surprises Odrade greatly. Too late Odrade and Teg realize they have fallen into a trap, and the Honored Matres use a mysterious weapon to turn defeat into victory, as well as capturing Odrade. Murbella saves as much of the Bene Gesserit force as she can and they begin to withdraw to Chapterhouse. Odrade, however, had planned for the possible failure of the Bene Gesserit attack and left Murbella instructions for a last desperate gamble. Murbella pilots a small craft down to the surface, announcing herself as an Honored Matre who, in the confusion, has managed to escape the Bene Gesserit with all their secrets. She arrives on the planet and is taken to the Great Honored Matre. Unable to control her anger, Logno attacks but is killed by Murbella. Awed by her physical prowess, the remaining Honored Matres are forced to accept her as their new leader. Odrade is also killed in the melee and Murbella shares memories with her, thereby also becoming Reverend Mother Superior.</paragraph><paragraph>Murbella's ascension to leadership is not accepted as victory by all the Bene Gesserit. Some flee Chapterhouse, notably Sheeana, who has a vision of her own, and arranges to have some of the new worms that have emerged in the Chapterhouse desert brought aboard the no-ship. Sheeana is joined by Duncan. The two escape in the giant no-ship, with Scytale, Teg and the Jews. Murbella recognizes their plan at the last minute, but is powerless to stop them. Watching this escape with interest are<space/><link><target>Daniel and Marty</target></link>, the observers Duncan had been having visions of. The story ends on a cliffhanger with several questions left unanswered regarding the merging of the Honored Matres and Bene Gesserit, the fates of those on the escaped no-ship (including the role of Scytale, the development of Idaho and Teg, and the role of the Jews), the identity of the god-like characters in the book's final chapter and the ultimate mystery of what chased the Honored Matres back into the Old Empire.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Reception</heading><paragraph><italics>Chapterhouse: Dune</italics><space/>debuted at #5 and rose to #2 on<space/><link><target>The New York Times Best Seller list</target><part>''The New York Times'' Best Seller list</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYTBS"></extension><space/>Gerald Jonas of<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>noted that &quot;Against all odds, the universe of<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>keeps getting richer in texture, more challenging in its moral dilemmas.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT 1985"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1985/06/16/books/science-fiction.html?scp</arg><arg name="title">Science Fiction (Review)</arg><arg name="last">Jonas</arg><arg name="first">Gerald</arg><arg name="date">June 16, 1985</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="publisher">NYTimes.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">July 20, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sequels</heading><paragraph>Two decades after Frank Herbert's death, his son<space/><link><target>Brian Herbert</target></link>, along with<space/><link><target>Kevin J. Anderson</target></link>, published two<space/><link><target>sequel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>&amp;ndash;<space/><italics><link><target>Hunters of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2006) and<space/><italics><link><target>Sandworms of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2007) &amp;ndash; based on notes left behind by Frank Herbert for what he referred to as<space/><italics>Dune 7</italics>, his own planned seventh novel in the<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>series.<template><target>Herbert notes</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Dune franchise</target></template><template><target>Frank Herbert</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:1985 novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels by Frank Herbert</target></link><link><target>Category:Dune novels</target></link><link><target>Category:G. P. Putnam's Sons books</target></link></paragraph></article>