<article title='Controlled_Substances_Act'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox U.S. legislation</target><arg name="shorttitle"><space/>Controlled Substances Act
</arg><arg name="longtitle"><space/>An Act to amend the Public Health Service Act and other laws to provide increased research into, and prevention of, drug abuse and drug dependence; to provide for treatment and rehabilitation of drug abusers and drug dependent persons; and to strengthen existing law enforcement authority in the field of drug abuse.
</arg><arg name="colloquialacronym"><space/>CSA
</arg><arg name="enacted by"><space/>91st
</arg><arg name="effective date"><space/>October 27, 1970
</arg><arg name="public law url"><space/>http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/STATUTE-84/pdf/STATUTE-84-Pg1236.pdf
</arg><arg name="cite public law"><space/>91-513
</arg><arg name="cite statutes at large"><space/>{{usstat|84|1236}} ''a.k.a.'' 84 Stat. 1242
</arg><arg name="acts amended">
</arg><arg name="title amended"><space/>[[Title 21 of the United States Code|21 U.S.C.: Food and Drugs]]
</arg><arg name="sections created"><space/>{{Usc-title-chap|21|13}} § 801 et seq.
</arg><arg name="sections amended"><space/>
</arg><arg name="leghisturl"><space/>
</arg><arg name="introducedin"><space/>House
</arg><arg name="introducedbill"><space/>{{USBill|91|H.R.|18583}}
</arg><arg name="introducedby"><space/>[[Harley O. Staggers]] ([[Democratic Party (United States)|D]]–[[West Virginia|WV]])
</arg><arg name="introduceddate"><space/>September 10, 1970
</arg><arg name="committees"><space/>[[United States House Committee on Energy and Commerce|Interstate and Foreign Commerce Committee]] and [[United States Senate Committee on the Judiciary|Senate Judiciary Committee]]
</arg><arg name="passedbody1"><space/>House
</arg><arg name="passeddate1"><space/>September 24, 1970
</arg><arg name="passedvote1"><space/>[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/91-1970/h355 342-7]
</arg><arg name="passedbody2"><space/>Senate
</arg><arg name="passedas2"><space/>
</arg><arg name="passeddate2"><space/>October 7, 1970
</arg><arg name="passedvote2"><space/>[http://www.govtrack.us/congress/votes/91-1970/s584 54-0]
</arg><arg name="conferencedate"><space/>October 13, 1970
</arg><arg name="passedbody3"><space/>House
</arg><arg name="passeddate3"><space/>October 14, 1970
</arg><arg name="passedvote3"><space/>passed
</arg><arg name="agreedbody3"><space/>
</arg><arg name="agreeddate3"><space/>
</arg><arg name="agreedvote3"><space/>
</arg><arg name="agreedbody4"><space/>
</arg><arg name="agreeddate4"><space/>
</arg><arg name="agreedvote4"><space/>
</arg><arg name="passedbody4"><space/>Senate
</arg><arg name="passeddate4"><space/>October 14, 1970
</arg><arg name="passedvote4"><space/>passed
</arg><arg name="signedpresident"><space/>[[Richard Nixon]]
</arg><arg name="signeddate"><space/>October 27, 1970
</arg><arg name="amendments"><space/>[[Hillory J. Farias and Samantha Reid Date-Rape Prevention Act of 2000]]
</arg><arg name="SCOTUS cases"><space/>[[Gonzales v. Raich]]<br>[[United States v. Oakland Cannabis Buyers' Cooperative]]
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Controlled Substances Act</bold><space/>(<bold>CSA</bold>) is the statute prescribing<space/><link><target>federal government of the United States</target><part>federal</part></link><space/><link><target>drug policy of the United States</target><part>U.S. drug policy</part></link><space/>under which the manufacture, importation, possession, use and distribution of certain substances is regulated. It was passed by the<space/><link><target>91st United States Congress</target></link><space/>as Title II of the<space/><link><target>Comprehensive Drug Abuse Prevention and Control Act of 1970</target></link><space/>and signed into law by<space/><link><target>Presidency of Richard Nixon</target><part>President Richard Nixon</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>USStatute</target><arg>91</arg><arg>513</arg><arg>84</arg><arg>1236</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg>10</arg><arg>27</arg></template>, codified at<space/><template><target>usc</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801</arg></template><space/>et. seq.</extension><space/>The Act also served as the national implementing legislation for the<space/><link><target>Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The legislation created five Schedules (classifications), with varying qualifications for a substance to be included in each. Two federal agencies, the<space/><link><target>Drug Enforcement Administration</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Food and Drug Administration</target></link>, determine which substances are added to or removed from the various schedules, although the statute passed by Congress created the initial listing. Congress has sometimes scheduled other substances through legislation such as the Hillory J. Farias and<space/><link><target>Samantha Reid</target></link><space/>Date-Rape Prevention Act of 2000, which placed<space/><link><target>gamma hydroxybutyrate</target></link><space/>in Schedule I. Classification decisions are required to be made on criteria including potential for abuse (an undefined term),<extension extension_name='ref' name="regulations.gov"><link type='external' href='http://www.regulations.gov/#!docketDetail;D=DEA-2009-0013'></link><space/>Docket ID: DEA-2009-0013 in<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.regulations.gov/#!documentDetail;D=DEA-2009-0013-0003'></link><space/>DEA-2009-0013-0003 HHS recommendation document. Enclosure: BASIS FOR THE RECOMMENDATION TO CONTROL 5-METHOXY-DIMETHYLTRYPTAMINE (5-MeO-DMT) IN SCHEDULE I OF THE CONTROLLED SUBSTANCES ACT, (B.) (1.) The term &quot;abuse&quot; is not defined in the CSA.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Drug Abuse 1973 p.13">&quot;[D]rug abuse may refer to any type of drug or chemical without regard to its pharmacologic actions. It is an eclectic concept having only one uniform connotation: societal disapproval. ... The Commission believes that the term drug abuse must be deleted from official pronouncements and public policy dialogue. The term has no functional utility and has become no more than an arbitrary codeword for that drug use which is presently considered wrong.&quot; Second Report of the National Commission on Marihuana and Drug Abuse; Drug Use In America: Problem In Perspective (March 1973), p.13</extension><space/>currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States, and international treaties.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Regulation of therapeutic goods in the United States</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The nation first outlawed addictive drugs in the early 1900s and the<space/><link><target>International Opium Convention</target></link><space/>helped lead international agreements regulating trade.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.deamuseum.org/museum_ida.html'>Illegal Drugs in America: A Modern History</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/library/studies/canadasenate/vol3/chapter19_hague.htm'>The 1912 Hague International Opium Convention</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.druglibrary.org/schaffer/history/ophs.htm'>History of Legislative Control Over Opium, Cocaine, and Their Derivatives</link></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Food and Drugs Act of 1906</target></link><space/>was the beginning of over 200 laws concerning public health and consumer protections. Others were the<space/><link><target>Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act</target></link><space/>(1938), and the<space/><link><target>Kefauver Harris Amendment</target></link><space/>of 1962.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://rx-wiki.org/index.php?title=Medical_Device_Amendments'></link>- Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1969,<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>President</part></link><space/><link><target>Richard Nixon</target></link><space/>announced that the<space/><link><target>United States Attorney General</target><part>Attorney General</part></link>,<space/><link><target>John N. Mitchell</target></link>, was preparing a comprehensive new measure to more effectively meet the narcotic and dangerous drug problems at the federal level by combining all existing federal laws into a single new statute. The CSA did not only combine existing federal drug laws but it also changed the nature of federal drug law policies, expanded the scope of federal drug laws and expanded<space/><link><target>Federal law enforcement in the United States</target><part>Federal law enforcement</part></link><space/>as pertaining to controlled substances.</paragraph><paragraph>Part F of the Comprehensive Drug Abuse Prevention and Control Act of 1970 established the<space/><link><target>National Commission on Marijuana and Drug Abuse</target></link>known as the Shafer Commission after its chairman,<space/><link><target>Raymond P. Shafer</target></link>to study<space/><link><target>cannabis (drug)</target><part>cannabis</part></link><space/>abuse in the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'>Part F is printed on the inside cover of<space/><italics>Drug Use In America: Problem In Perspective, Second Report of the National Commission on Marihuana and Drug Abuse</italics>, March 1973</extension><space/>During his presentation of the commission's First Report to Congress, Shafer recommended the<space/><link><target>decriminalization</target></link><space/>of marijuana in small amounts, saying,<template><target>quote</target><arg>[T]he criminal law is too harsh a tool to apply to personal possession even in the effort to discourage use. It implies an overwhelming indictment of the behavior which we believe is not appropriate. The actual and potential harm of use of the drug is not great enough to justify intrusion by the criminal law into private behavior, a step which our society takes only with the greatest reluctance.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Rufus King notes that this stratagem was similar to that used by<space/><link><target>Harry Anslinger</target></link><space/>when he consolidated the previous anti-drug treaties into the Single Convention and took the opportunity to add new provisions that otherwise might have been unpalatable to the international community.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dontsit"><link type='external' href='http://www.druglibrary.net/special/king/dhu/dhu28.htm'>The 1970 Act: Don't Sit There, Amend Something</link></extension><space/>According to David T. Courtwright, &quot;the Act was part of an omnibus reform package designed to rationalize, and in some respects to liberalize, American drug policy.&quot; (Courtwright noted that the Act became, not<space/><link><target>Libertarianism</target><part>libertarian</part></link>, but instead repressionistic to the point of tyrannical, in its intent.) It eliminated mandatory minimum sentences and provided support for drug treatment and research.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob</arg><arg name="title">The Controlled Substances Act: how a "big tent" reform became a punitive drug law</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-02-12</arg><arg name="last">Courtwright</arg><arg name="first">David T.</arg><arg name="date">2004-10-05</arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2004.04.012</arg></template></extension><space/>King notes that the rehabilitation clauses were added as a compromise to Senator Jim Hughes, who favored a moderate approach. The bill, as introduced by Senator<space/><link><target>Everett Dirksen</target></link>, ran to 91 pages. While it was being drafted, the<space/><link><target>Uniform Controlled Substances Act</target></link>, to be passed by state legislatures, was also being drafted by the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Justice</target><part>Department of Justice</part></link>; its wording closely mirrored the Controlled Substances Act.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dontsit"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since its enactment in 1970, the Act has been amended several times:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fda.gov/RegulatoryInformation/Legislation/default.htm'>Legislation reform</link>- Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Medical Device Amendments</target></link><space/>of 1976.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Psychotropic Substances Act (United States)</target><part>Psychotropic Substances Act</part></link><space/>of 1978 added provisions implementing the<space/><link><target>Convention on Psychotropic Substances</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Controlled Substances Penalties Amendments Act of 1984</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Chemical Diversion and Trafficking Act</target></link><space/>of 1988 (implemented August 1, 1989 as Article 12) added provisions implementing the<space/><link><target>United Nations Convention Against Illicit Traffic in Narcotic Drugs and Psychotropic Substances</target></link><space/>that went into force on November 11, 1990.</listitem><listitem>The Anabolic Steroids Act, passed as part of the<space/><link><target>Crime Control Act of 1990</target></link>, which placed<space/><link><target>anabolic steroids</target></link><space/>into Schedule III<extension extension_name='ref'>Steven B. Karch. Pathology, Toxicogenetics, and Criminalistics of Drug Abuse. CRC Press, 2007 ISBN 9781420054569</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>30</arg></template></listitem><listitem>The Domestic Chemical Diversion and Control Act of 1993 (effective on April 16, 1994) in response to the methamphetamine trafficking.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Federal Analog Act</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Ryan Haight Online Pharmacy Consumer Protection Act of 2008</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>s:Ryan Haight Online Pharmacy Consumer Protection Act of 2008</target><part>Ryan Haight Act</part></link>- Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension></listitem><listitem>The Electronic Prescriptions for Controlled Substances (EPCS) 2010.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Content</heading><paragraph>The Controlled Substances Act consists of 2 subchapters. Subchapter I defines Schedules I-V, lists chemicals used in the manufacture of controlled substances, and differentiates lawful and unlawful manufacturing, distribution, and possession of controlled substances, including possession of Schedule I drugs for personal use; this subchapter also specifies the dollar amounts of fines and durations of prison terms for violations. Subchapter II describes the laws for exportation and importation of controlled substances, again specifying fines and prison terms for violations.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/21cfr/21usc/</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Enforcement authority</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Drug Enforcement Administration</target></link><space/>was established in 1973, combining the Bureau of Narcotics and Dangerous Drugs (BNDD) and Customs drug agents.<extension extension_name='ref'>.<link type='external' href='http://www.justice.gov/dea/ops/taskforces.shtml'>DEA</link>- Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension><space/>Proceedings to add, delete, or change the schedule of a drug or other substance may be initiated by the DEA, the<space/><link><target>Department of Health and Human Services</target></link><space/>(HHS), or by petition from any interested party, including the manufacturer of a drug, a medical society or association, a pharmacy association, a public interest group concerned with drug abuse, a state or local government agency, or an individual citizen. When a petition is received by the DEA, the agency begins its own investigation of the drug.</paragraph><paragraph>The DEA also may begin an investigation of a drug at any time based upon information received from laboratories, state and local law enforcement and regulatory agencies, or other sources of information. Once the DEA has collected the necessary data, the Deputy Administrator of DEA,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Federal Register</target></link></italics>: August 21, 2009 (Volume 74, Number 161), Page 42220 &quot;Under the authority vested in the<space/><link><target>Attorney General</target></link><space/>by section 201(a) of the CSA (21 USC 811(a)), and delegated to the Administrator of DEA by Department of Justice regulations (28 CFR 0.100), and redelegated to the Deputy Administrator pursuant to 28 CFR 0.104...&quot;</extension><space/>requests from HHS a scientific and medical evaluation and recommendation as to whether the drug or other substance should be controlled or removed from control. This request is sent to the Assistant Secretary of Health of HHS. Then, HHS solicits information from the Commissioner of the<space/><link><target>Food and Drug Administration</target></link><space/>and evaluations and recommendations from the<space/><link><target>National Institute on Drug Abuse</target></link><space/>and, on occasion, from the scientific and medical community at large. The Assistant Secretary, by authority of the Secretary, compiles the information and transmits back to the DEA a medical and scientific evaluation regarding the drug or other substance, a recommendation as to whether the drug should be controlled, and in what schedule it should be placed.</paragraph><paragraph>The HHS recommendation on scheduling is binding to the extent that if HHS recommends, based on its medical and scientific evaluation, that the substance not be controlled, then the DEA may not control the substance. Once the DEA has received the scientific and medical evaluation from HHS, the DEA Administrator evaluates all available data and makes a final decision whether to propose that a drug or other substance be controlled and into which schedule it should be placed. Under certain circumstances, the Government may temporarily schedule<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/fed_regs/rules/2011/fr0301.htm'>Temporary drug scheduling</link>-Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension><space/>a drug without following the normal procedure. An example is when international treaties require control of a substance. In addition,<space/><template><target>uscsub</target><arg>21</arg><arg>811</arg><arg>h</arg></template><space/>allows the Attorney General to temporarily place a substance in Schedule I &quot;to avoid an imminent hazard to the public safety&quot;. Thirty days' notice is required before the order can be issued, and the scheduling expires after a year; however, the period may be extended six months if rulemaking proceedings to permanently schedule the drug are in progress. In any case, once these proceedings are complete, the temporary order is automatically vacated. Unlike ordinary scheduling proceedings, such temporary orders are not subject to<space/><link><target>judicial review</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The CSA also creates a closed system of distribution<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=c9gp80lkqXMC&amp;amp;pg=PA184&amp;amp;lpg=PA184&amp;amp;dq=closed+system+of+distribution+of+controlled+substances&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=mbnQ9KPZee&amp;amp;sig=vGXCeCVAxNwtA2kZMoopqAfo2js&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=ZYzgUNiOHOiE2QXui4DYDA&amp;amp;ved=0CC8Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=closed%20system%20of%20distribution%20of%20controlled%20substances&amp;amp;f=false'>Pharmacy Practice and the Law</link>(Book, p 184); By Richard R. Abood -Retrieved 2012-12-30</extension><space/>for those authorized to handle controlled substances. The cornerstone of this system is the registration of all those authorized by the DEA to handle controlled substances. All individuals and firms that are registered are required to maintain complete and accurate inventories and records of all transactions involving controlled substances, as well as security for the storage of controlled substances.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Treaty obligations</heading><paragraph>The Congressional findings in<space/><link><target>21 USC</target></link><space/><template><target>USCSub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801</arg><arg>7</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>USCSub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801a</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and<space/><template><target>USCSub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801a</arg><arg>3</arg></template><space/>state that a major purpose of the CSA is to &quot;enable the United States to meet all of its obligations&quot; under international<space/><link><target>treaty</target><part>treaties</part></link>. The CSA bears many resemblances to these Conventions. Both the CSA and the treaties set out a system for classifying controlled substances in several Schedules in accordance with the binding scientific and medical findings of a public health authority. Under<space/><template><target>usc</target><arg>21</arg><arg>811</arg></template><space/>of the CSA, that authority is the<space/><link><target>Secretary of Health and Human Services</target></link><space/>(HHS). Under Article 3 of the Single Convention and Article 2 of the Convention on Psychotropic Substances, the<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target></link><space/>is that authority.</paragraph><paragraph>The domestic and international legal nature of these treaty obligations must be considered in light of the supremacy of the<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target></link><space/>over treaties or acts and the equality of treaties and Congressional acts. In<space/><italics><link><target>Reid v. Covert</target></link></italics><space/>the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target></link><space/>addressed both these issues directly and clearly holding:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>[N]o agreement with a foreign nation can confer power on the Congress, or on any other branch of Government, which is free from the restraints of the Constitution.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem><link><target>Article Six of the United States Constitution</target><part>Article VI</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Supremacy Clause</target></link><space/>of the Constitution, declares:</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;This Constitution, and the Laws of the United States which shall be made in Pursuance thereof, and all Treaties made, or which shall be made, under the Authority of the United States, shall be the supreme Law of the Land; . . .&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>There is nothing in this language which intimates that treaties and laws enacted pursuant to them do not have to comply with the provisions of the Constitution. Nor is there anything in the debates which accompanied the drafting and ratification of the Constitution which even suggests such a result. These debates, as well as the history that surrounds the adoption of the treaty provision in Article VI, make it clear that the reason treaties were not limited to those made in &quot;pursuance&quot; of the Constitution was so that agreements made by the United States under the Articles of Confederation, including the important peace treaties which concluded the Revolutionary War, would remain in effect. It would be manifestly contrary to the objectives of those who created the Constitution, as well as those who were responsible for the Bill of Rightslet alone alien to our entire constitutional history and traditionto construe Article VI as permitting the United States to exercise power under an international agreement without observing constitutional prohibitions. In effect, such construction would permit amendment of that document in a manner not sanctioned by Article V. The prohibitions of the Constitution were designed to apply to all branches of the National Government, and they cannot be nullified by the Executive or by the Executive and the Senate combined.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>There is nothing new or unique about what we say here. This Court has regularly and uniformly recognized the supremacy of the Constitution over a treaty. For example, in<space/><italics>Geofroy v. Riggs</italics>, 133 U. S. 258, 133 U. S. 267, it declared:</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;The treaty power, as expressed in the Constitution, is in terms unlimited except by those restraints which are found in that instrument against the action of the government or of its departments, and those arising from the nature of the government itself and of that of the States. It would not be contended that it extends so far as to authorize what the Constitution forbids, or a change in the character of the government, or in that of one of the States, or a cession of any portion of the territory of the latter, without its consent.&quot;</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='ident'><listitem>This Court has repeatedly taken the position that an Act of Congress, which must comply with the Constitution, is on a full parity with a treaty, and that, when a statute which is subsequent in time is inconsistent with a treaty, the statute to the extent of conflict renders the treaty null. It would be completely anomalous to say that a treaty need not comply with the Constitution when such an agreement can be overridden by a statute that must conform to that instrument.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://supreme.justia.com/us/354/1/case.html</arg><arg name="title">Reid v. Covert, 354 U. S. 1 at pp 17–19</arg><arg name="work">Justia Law</arg><arg name="accessdate">30 October 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>According to the Cato Institute, these treaties only bind (legally obligate) the United States to comply with them as long as that nation agrees to remain a state party to these treaties. The<space/><link><target>Congress of the United States</target><part>U.S. Congress</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target></link><space/>have the absolute<space/><link><target>Sovereignty</target><part>sovereign</part></link><space/>right to withdraw from or abrogate at any time these two instruments, in accordance with said nation's<space/><link><target>Constitution of the United States</target><part>Constitution</part></link>, at which point these treaties will cease to bind that nation in any way, shape, or form.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cato.org"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="chapterurl">http://www.cato.org/pubs/handbook/hb108/hb108-17.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cato Handbook for Congress: Policy Recommendations for the 108th Congress<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">The War on Drugs<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="pages">171–178<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cato Institute<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-10-20</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A provision for automatic compliance with treaty obligations is found at<space/><template><target>uscsub</target><arg>21</arg><arg>811</arg><arg>d</arg><arg></arg></template>, which also establishes mechanisms for amending international drug control regulations to correspond with HHS findings on scientific and medical issues. If control of a substance is mandated by the Single Convention, the Attorney General is required to &quot;issue an order controlling such drug under the schedule he deems most appropriate to carry out such obligations,&quot; without regard to the normal scheduling procedure or the findings of the HHS Secretary. However, the Secretary has great influence over any drug scheduling proposal under the Single Convention, because<space/><template><target>uscsub</target><arg>21</arg><arg>811</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>B</arg></template><space/>requires the Secretary the power to &quot;evaluate the proposal and furnish a recommendation to the Secretary of State which shall be binding on the representative of the United States in discussions and negotiations relating to the proposal.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Similarly, if the United Nations<space/><link><target>Commission on Narcotic Drugs</target></link><space/>adds or transfers a substance to a Schedule established by the Convention on Psychotropic Substances, so that current U.S. regulations on the drug do not meet the treaty's requirements, the Secretary is required to issue a recommendation on how the substance should be scheduled under the CSA. If the Secretary agrees with the Commission's scheduling decision, he can recommend that the Attorney General initiate proceedings to reschedule the drug accordingly. If the HHS Secretary disagrees with the UN controls, however, the Attorney General must temporarily place the drug in Schedule IV or V (whichever meets the minimum requirements of the treaty) and exclude the substance from any regulations not mandated by the treaty, while the Secretary is required to request that the<space/><link><target>United States Secretary of State</target><part>Secretary of State</part></link><space/>take action, through the Commission or the<space/><link><target>UN Economic and Social Council</target></link>, to remove the drug from international control or transfer it to a different Schedule under the Convention. The temporary scheduling expires as soon as control is no longer needed to meet international treaty obligations.</paragraph><paragraph>This provision was invoked in 1984 to place Rohypnol (<link><target>flunitrazepam</target></link>) in Schedule IV. The drug did not then meet the Controlled Substances Act's criteria for scheduling; however, control was required by the Convention on Psychotropic Substances. In 1999, an FDA official explained to Congress:<template><target>quote</target><arg>Rohypnol is not approved or available for medical use in the United States, but it is temporarily controlled in Schedule IV pursuant to a treaty obligation under the 1971 Convention on Psychotropic Substances. At the time flunitrazepam was placed temporarily in Schedule IV (November 5, 1984), there was no evidence of abuse or trafficking of the drug in the United States.<ref>[http://www.hhs.gov/asl/testify/t990311b.html "Date Rape" Drugs]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Cato Institute</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Handbook for Congress</italics><space/>calls for repealing the CSA, an action that would likely bring the United States into conflict with<space/><link><target>international law</target></link>, were the United States not to exercise its sovereign right to withdraw from and/or abrogate the<space/><link><target>Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs</target></link><space/>and/or the 1971<space/><link><target>Convention on Psychotropic Substances</target></link><space/>prior to repealing the Controlled Substances Act.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cato.org"></extension><space/>The exception would be if the U.S. were to claim that the treaty obligations violate the<space/><link><target>United States Constitution</target></link>. Many articles in these treatiessuch as Article 35 and Article 36 of the Single Conventionare prefaced with phrases such as &quot;Having due regard to their constitutional, legal and administrative systems, the Parties shall . . .&quot; or &quot;Subject to its constitutional limitations, each Party shall . . .&quot; According to former<space/><link><target>United Nations Drug Control Programme</target></link><space/>Chief of Demand Reduction<space/><link><target>Cindy Fazey</target></link>, &quot;This has been used by the USA not to implement part of article 3 of the 1988 Convention, which prevents inciting others to use narcotic or psychotropic drugs, on the basis that this would be in contravention of<space/><link><target>First Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>their constitutional amendment guaranteeing freedom of speech</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fuoriluogo.it/arretrati/2003/apr_17_en.htm'>fuoriluogo.it aprile 2003</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Schedules of controlled substances</heading><paragraph>Placing a drug or other substance in a certain Schedule or removing it from a certain Schedule is primarily based on<space/><link><target>21 USC</target></link><space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>801a</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>802</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>811</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>812</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>813</arg></template>, and<space/><template><target>uscsub2</target><arg>21</arg><arg>814</arg></template>. Every schedule otherwise requires finding and specifying the &quot;potential for abuse&quot; before a substance can be placed in that schedule.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www4.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode21/usc_sup_01_21_10_13.html'>21 USC Chapter 13 DRUG ABUSE PREVENTION AND CONTROL | LII / Legal Information Institute</link></extension><space/>The specific classification of any given drug or other substance is usually a source of controversy, as is the purpose and effectiveness of the entire regulatory scheme.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'><paragraph>The term &quot;controlled substance&quot; means a drug or other substance, or immediate precursor, included in schedule I, II, III, IV, or V of part B of this subchapter. The term does not include distilled spirits, wine, malt beverages, or tobacco, as those terms are defined or used in subtitle E of the Internal Revenue Code of 1986.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>uscsub</target><arg>21</arg><arg>802</arg><arg>6</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www4.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode21/usc_sec_21_00000802----000-.html'>21 USC 802 Definitions | LII / Legal Information Institute</link></extension></listitem></list></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some have argued that this is an important exemption, since alcohol and tobacco are the two most widely used drugs in the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.drugabusestatistics.samhsa.gov/Dependence/appendixc.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Appendix C: Measurement of Dependence, Abuse, Treatment, and Treatment Need – 2000 NHSDA – Substance Dependence, Abuse, and Treatment</arg><arg name="publisher">SAMHSA, Office of Applied Studies</arg><arg name="work">National Household Survey on Drug Abuse</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.drugabuse.gov/Infofacts/Tobacco.html</arg><arg name="title">InfoFacts – Cigarettes and Other Tobacco Products</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Also of significance, the exclusion of alcohol includes<space/><link><target>sacramental wine</target><part>wine which is sacramentally used</part></link><space/>by many major religious denominations in the United States.</paragraph><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Schedule I drugs</arg></template>Schedule I controlled substances</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Schedule I drugs (US)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>Schedule I substances are those that have the following findings:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="1">
{{ordered list|type</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>No prescriptions are allowed to be written for Schedule I substances, and such substances are subject to<space/><link><target>production quota</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which the DEA imposes. Moreover, it is illegal, and indeed a Class 1 federal felony, even to conduct any<space/><bold><italics>otherwise legitimate scientific research</italics></bold><space/>of<space/><bold><italics>any</italics></bold><space/>kind on Schedule I substances.</paragraph><paragraph>Under the DEA's interpretation of the CSA, a drug does not necessarily have to have the same &quot;high potential for abuse&quot; as heroin, for example, to merit placement in Schedule I:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="[W]hen it comes to a drug that is currently listed in schedule I, if it is undisputed that such drug has no currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States and a lack of accepted safety for use under medical supervision, and it is further undisputed that the drug has ''at least some potential for abuse sufficient to warrant control under the CSA'', the drug must remain in schedule I. In such circumstances, placement of the drug in schedules II through V would conflict with the CSA since such drug would not meet the criterion of "a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States." 21 USC 812(b). (emphasis added)<ref name">donnie>{{cite journal|last</arg><arg>[[Drug Enforcement Administration]]</arg><arg>Notice of denial of petition to reschedule marijuana (2001)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Sentences for first-time, non-violent offenders convicted of trafficking in Schedule I drugs can easily turn into<space/><italics><link><target>de facto</target></link></italics><space/><link><target>life sentence</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>when multiple sales are prosecuted in one proceeding.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Angelos">See<space/><italics>United States v. Angelos</italics>, 433 F.3d 738 (<link><target>United States Court of Appeals for the Tenth Circuit</target><part>10th Cir.</part></link><space/>2006) (55 years for three sales of marijuana).</extension><space/>Sentences for violent offenders are much higher<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Drugs in this schedule include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>alpha-Methyltryptamine</target><part>MT</part></link><space/>(alpha-methyltryptamine), an anti-depressant from the<space/><link><target>tryptamine</target></link><space/>family; first developed in the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>and marketed under the brand name Indopan.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Benzylpiperazine</target><part>BZP</part></link><space/>(benzylpiperazine), a synthetic stimulant once sold as a<space/><link><target>designer drug</target></link>. It has been shown to be associated with an increase in seizures if taken alone.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Gee<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Paul<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Mark<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Gilbert<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Sandra<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Richardson<space/></arg><arg name="first4">Grant<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first5">Sharon<space/></arg><arg name="last5">Paterson<space/></arg><arg name="first6">Patrick<space/></arg><arg name="last6">Graham<space/></arg><arg name="title">Toxicity from the Recreational Use of 1-benzylpiperazine<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Clinical Toxicology<space/></arg><arg name="volume">46<space/></arg><arg name="issue">9<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="pages">802–07<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/15563650802307602<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">18821145</arg></template></extension><space/>Although the effects of BZP are not as potent as MDMA, it can produce neuroadaptions that can cause an increase in the potential for abuse of this drug.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Brennan<space/></arg><arg name="first1">K.<space/></arg><arg name="first2">A.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Johnstone<space/></arg><arg name="first3">P.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Fitzmaurice<space/></arg><arg name="first4">R.<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Lea<space/></arg><arg name="first5">S.<space/></arg><arg name="last5">Schenk<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chronic Benzylpiperazine (BZP) Exposure Produces Behavioral Sensitization and Cross-sensitization to Methamphetamine (MA)<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Drug and Alcohol Dependence<space/></arg><arg name="volume">88<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2–3<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="pages">204–13<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.drugalcdep.2006.10.016<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">17125936</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cathinone</target></link>, an amphetamine-like stimulant found in the shrub<space/><italics><link><target>Catha edulis</target></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>khat</target></link>).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dimethyltryptamine</target><part>DMT</part></link><space/>(dimethyltryptamine), a naturally-occurring<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target></link><space/>that is widespread throughout the plant kingdom and endogenous to the human body. DMT is the main psychoactive constituent in the<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target><part>psychedelic</part></link><space/>South American brew,<space/><link><target>ayahuasca</target></link>, for which the<space/><link><target>Unio do Vegetal</target><part>UDV</part></link><space/>are granted exemption from DMT's schedule I status on the grounds of religious freedom.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Etorphine</target></link>, a semi-synthetic opioid possessing an analgesic potency approximately 1,0003,000 times that of morphine.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gamma-hydroxybutyric acid</target><part>GHB</part></link>, a general anaesthetic and treatment for<space/><link><target>narcolepsy</target></link>-cataplexy and alcohol withdrawal with minimal side-effects<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Tunnicliff<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>G.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sites of action of gamma hydroxybutyrate (GHB)--A neuroactive drug with abuse potential<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Clinical Toxicology<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>35<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>6</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>581–590<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.3109/15563659709001236<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and controlled action but a limited safe dosage range. It was placed in Schedule I in March 2000 after widespread recreational use led to increased<space/><link><target>emergency room</target></link><space/>visits, hospitalizations, and deaths.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Okun<space/></arg><arg name="first1">M. S.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Boothy<space/></arg><arg name="first2">L. A.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Bartfield<space/></arg><arg name="first3">R. B.<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Doering<space/></arg><arg name="first4">P. L.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">GHB: An important pharmacologic and clinical update<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Pharmacy and Pharmacological Science<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4</arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages">167–175</arg></template></extension><space/>This drug is also listed in Schedule III for limited uses, under the trademark<space/><link><target>Xyrem</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Heroin</target></link><space/>(diacetylmorphine), which is used in some European countries as a potent pain reliever in terminal cancer patients, and as second option, after<space/><link><target>morphine</target></link><space/>(it is about twice as potent, by weight, as morphine).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lysergic acid diethylamide</target><part>LSD</part></link><space/>(lysergic acid diethylamide), a<space/><link><target>semi-synthetic</target></link><space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target></link><space/>famous for its involvement in the<space/><link><target>counterculture of the 1960s</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cannabis (drug)</target><part>Marijuana</part></link><space/>and its<space/><link><target>cannabinoid</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Pure ()-trans-9-tetrahydrocannabinol is also listed in Schedule III for limited uses, under the trademark<space/><link><target>Marinol</target></link>. Ballot measures in several states such as<space/><link><target>Colorado</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Washington (state)</target><part>Washington</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link><space/>and others have made allowances for recreational and medical use of marijuana and/or have decriminalized possession of small amounts of marijuana such measures operate only on state laws, and have no effect on Federal law. Despite such ballot measures, and multiple studies showing medicinal benefits, marijuana nevertheless remains on Schedule I, effective across all U.S. states and territories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="donnie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Angelos"></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>MDMA</target></link><space/>(&quot;ecstasy&quot;), a<space/><link><target>stimulant</target></link>,<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target><part>psychedelic</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Empathogen-entactogen</target><part>entactogen</part><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>drug which initially garnered attention in<space/><link><target>psychedelic therapy</target></link><space/>as a treatment for<space/><link><target>post-traumatic stress disorder</target></link><space/>(PTSD). The medical community originally agreed upon placing it as a Schedule III substance, but the government denied this suggestion, despite two court rulings by the DEA's administrative law judge that placing MDMA in Schedule I was illegal. It was temporarily unscheduled after the first administrative hearing from December 22, 1987 July 1, 1988.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://maps.org/dea-mdma/</arg><arg name="title">MAPS Legal History of MDMA</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 October 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mescaline</target></link>, a naturally-occurring<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target></link><space/>and the main psychoactive constituent of<space/><link><target>peyote</target></link><space/>(<italics>Lophophora williamsii</italics>),<space/><link><target>Echinopsis pachanoi</target><part>San Pedro cactus</part></link><space/>(<italics>Echinopsis pachanoi</italics>), and<space/><link><target>Echinopsis peruviana</target><part>Peruvian torch cactus</part></link><space/>(<italics>Echinopsis peruviana</italics>).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Methaqualone</target></link><space/>(Quaalude, Sopor, Mandrax), a sedative that was previously used for similar purposes as barbiturates, until it was rescheduled.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peyote</target></link><space/>(<italics>Lophophora williamsii</italics>), a cactus growing in nature primarily in northeastern Mexico; one of the few plants specifically scheduled, with a narrow exception to its legal status for religious use by members of the<space/><link><target>Native American Church</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Psilocybin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>psilocin</target></link>, naturally-occurring<space/><link><target>psychedelic drug</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and the main psychoactive constituents of<space/><link><target>psilocybin mushroom</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem>Controlled substance analogs intended for human consumption (as defined by the<space/><link><target>Federal Analog Act</target></link>)</listitem></list><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Schedule II drugs</arg></template>Schedule II controlled substances</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Schedule II drugs (US)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>Schedule II substances are those that have the following findings:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="1">
{{ordered list|type</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Except when dispensed directly by a practitioner, other than a pharmacist, to an ultimate user, no controlled substance in Schedule II, which is a prescription drug as determined under the Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act (21 USC 301<space/><italics>et seq.</italics>), may be dispensed without the written prescription of a practitioner, except that in emergency situations, as prescribed by the Secretary by regulation after consultation with the Attorney General, such drug may be dispensed upon oral prescription in accordance with section 503(b) of that Act (21 USC 353 (b)). With exceptions, an original prescription is always required even though faxing in a prescription in advance to a pharmacy by a prescriber is allowed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="deadiversion.usdoj.gov"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Manuals - Practitioner's Manual - SECTION V</arg><arg name="url">http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/pubs/manuals/pract/section5.htm</arg></template><space/>Retrieved 2014-01-07</extension><space/>Prescriptions shall be retained in conformity with the requirements of section 827 of this title. No prescription for a controlled substance in schedule II may be refilled.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell2"><link type='external' href='http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode21/usc_sec_21_00000829----000-.html'>21 USC 829 Prescriptions | LII / Legal Information Institute</link></extension><space/>Notably no emergency situation provisions exist outside the Controlled Substances Act's &quot;closed system&quot; although this closed system may be unavailable or nonfunctioning in the event of accidents in remote areas or disasters such as hurricanes and earthquakes. Acts which would widely be considered morally imperative remain offenses subject to heavy penalties.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/html/uscode21/usc_sup_01_21_10_13_20_I_30_D.html'>21 USC Part D Offenses and Penalties | LII / Legal Information Institute</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>These drugs vary in potency: for example<space/><link><target>fentanyl</target></link><space/>is about 80 times as potent as<space/><link><target>morphine</target></link><space/>(<link><target>heroin</target></link><space/>is roughly four times as potent). More significantly, they vary in nature. Pharmacology and CSA scheduling have a weak relationship.</paragraph><paragraph>Because refills of prescriptions for Schedule II substances are not allowed, it can be burdensome to both the practitioner and the patient if the substances are to be used on a long-term basis. To provide relief, in 2007,<space/><template><target>CodeFedReg</target><arg>21</arg><arg>1306.12</arg></template><space/>was amended (at<space/><template><target>Federal Register</target><arg>72</arg><arg>64921</arg></template>) to allow practitioners to write up to three prescriptions at once, to provide up to a 90-day supply, specifying on each the earliest date on which it may be filled.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Issuance of Multiple Prescriptions for Schedule II Controlled Substances<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/faq/mult_rx_faq.htm<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[United States Drug Enforcement Administration|U.S. DEA]], [[United States Department of Justice|U.S. DOJ]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 September 2014<space/></arg><arg name="date">November 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Drugs in this schedule include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Cocaine</target></link><space/>(used as a<space/><link><target>topical anesthetic</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Amphetamine</target></link><space/>(originally placed in Schedule III, but moved to Schedule II in 1971),<space/><link><target>Adderall</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dextroamphetamine</target></link><space/>(Dexedrine),<space/><link><target>Lisdexamfetamine</target></link><space/>(Vyvanse): treatment of<space/><link><target>ADHD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>narcolepsy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Methylphenidate</target></link><space/>(Ritalin, Concerta),<space/><link><target>Dexmethylphenidate</target></link><space/>(Focalin): treatment of<space/><link><target>ADHD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>narcolepsy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Methamphetamine</target></link>: treatment of<space/><link><target>ADHD</target></link>, severe<space/><link><target>obesity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Opium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>opium tincture</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Laudanum</target></link>): treatment as a potent<space/><link><target>antidiarrheal</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fentanyl</target></link><space/>and most other strong pure opioid agonists,<space/><italics>i.e.</italics><space/><link><target>levorphanol</target></link>,<space/><link><target>opium</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Methadone</target></link>: treatment of<space/><link><target>heroin</target></link><space/>addiction, extreme chronic pain</listitem><listitem><link><target>Oxycodone</target></link><space/>(semi-synthetic opioid; active ingredient in<space/><link><target>Percocet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>OxyContin</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Percodan</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Oxymorphone</target></link><space/>(semi-synthetic opioid; active ingredient in Opana)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Morphine</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hydromorphone</target></link><space/>(semi-synthetic opioid; active ingredient in<space/><link><target>Dilaudid</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Palladone</target></link>)</listitem><listitem>Pure<space/><link><target>codeine</target></link><space/>and any drug for non-<link><target>wikt:parenteral</target><part>parenteral</part></link><space/>administration containing the equivalent of more than 90&amp;nbsp;mg of codeine per dosage unit;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hydrocodone</target></link><space/>In<space/><bold>ANY</bold><space/>formulation as of October 2014 (Examples include Vicodin, Norco, Tussionex). Prior to October 2014, formulations containing hydrocodone and over-the-counter<space/><link><target>NSAID</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as Acetaminophen and Ibuprofen were Schedule III.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Secobarbital</target></link><space/>(Seconal)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pethidine</target></link><space/>(<link><target>United States Adopted Name</target><part>USAN</part></link>: Meperidine; Demerol)</listitem><listitem>Pure<space/><link><target>diphenoxylate</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Phencyclidine</target></link><space/>(PCP)</listitem><listitem>Short-acting<space/><link><target>barbiturates</target></link>, such as<space/><link><target>pentobarbital</target></link><space/>and Nembutal</listitem><listitem><link><target>Nabilone</target></link><space/>(Cesamet) A synthetic<space/><link><target>cannabinoid</target></link>. An analogue to<space/><link><target>dronabinol</target></link><space/>(Marinol) which is a Schedule III drug.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tapentadol</target></link><space/>(Nucynta) A drug with mixed opioid agonist and norepinephrine re-uptake inhibitor activity.</listitem></list><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Schedule III drugs</arg></template>Schedule III controlled substances</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Schedule III drugs (US)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>Schedule III substances are those that have the following findings:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>ordered list</target><arg name="type">A
<space/></arg><arg>The drug or other substance has a potential for abuse less than the drugs or other substances in schedules I and II.
<space/></arg><arg>The drug or other substance has a currently accepted medical use in treatment in the United States.
<space/></arg><arg name="Abuse of the drug or other substance may lead to moderate or low physical dependence or high psychological dependence.<ref name">"cornell1"/>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Except when dispensed directly by a practitioner, other than a pharmacist, to an ultimate user, no controlled substance in schedule III or IV, which is a prescription drug as determined under the<space/><link><target>Federal Food, Drug, and Cosmetic Act</target></link><space/>(21 USC 301<space/><italics>et seq.</italics>), may be dispensed without a written or oral prescription in conformity with section 503(b) of that Act (21 USC 353 (b)). Such prescriptions may not be filled or refilled more than six months after the date thereof or be refilled more than five times after the date of the prescription unless renewed by the practitioner.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell2"></extension><space/>A prescription for controlled substances in Schedules III, IV, and V issued by a practitioner, may be communicated either orally, in writing, or by facsimile to the pharmacist, and may be refilled if so authorized on the prescription or by call-in.<extension extension_name='ref' name="deadiversion.usdoj.gov"></extension><space/>Control of wholesale distribution is somewhat less stringent than Schedule II drugs. Provisions for emergency situations are less restrictive within the &quot;closed system&quot; of the Controlled Substances Act than for Schedule II though no schedule has provisions to address circumstances where the closed system is unavailable, nonfunctioning or otherwise inadequate.</paragraph><paragraph>Drugs in this schedule include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Anabolic steroid</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(including<space/><link><target>prohormone</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as androstenedione); the specific end molecule testosterone in many of its forms (Androderm, AndroGel,Testosterone Cypionate and Testosterone Enanthate)are labeled as scheduled III while low-dose testosterone when compounded with estrogen derivatives have been exempted (from scheduling) by the FDA<extension extension_name='ref'>Exempt Anabolic Steroids (21 CFR 1308.33 and 21 CFR 1308.34) 05 February 2015 Drug Enforcement Administration Office of Diversion Control Drug and Chemical Evaluation Section</extension></listitem><listitem>Intermediate-acting<space/><link><target>barbiturate</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as<space/><link><target>talbutal</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>butalbital</target></link>;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Buprenorphine</target></link><space/>(semi-synthetic opioid; active in<space/><link><target>Suboxone</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Subutex</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Dihydrocodeine</target></link><space/>when compounded with other substances, to a certain dosage and concentration.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ketamine</target></link>, a drug originally developed as a safer, shorter-acting replacement for<space/><link><target>Phencyclidine</target><part>PCP</part></link><space/>(mainly for use as a human anesthetic) but has since become popular as a veterinary and pediatric anesthetic;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Xyrem</target></link>, a preparation of<space/><link><target>gamma-Hydroxybutyric acid</target><part>GHB</part></link><space/>used to treat<space/><link><target>narcolepsy</target></link>. Xyrem is in Schedule III but with a restricted distribution system. All other forms of GHB are in Schedule I;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tetrahydrocannabinol</target><part>Marinol</part></link>, synthetically prepared<space/><link><target>tetrahydrocannabinol</target></link><space/>(officially referred to by its<space/><link><target>International Nonproprietary Name</target><part>INN</part></link>,<space/><link><target>tetrahydrocannabinol</target><part>dronabinol</part></link>) used to treat<space/><link><target>nausea</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>vomiting</target></link><space/>caused by<space/><link><target>chemotherapy</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>Appetite</target><part>appetite loss</part></link><space/>caused by<space/><link><target>AIDS</target></link>;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Paregoric</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>antidiarrheal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>anti-tussive</target></link>, which contains<space/><link><target>opium</target></link><space/>combined with<space/><link><target>camphor</target></link><space/>(which makes it less addiction-prone than<space/><link><target>laudanum</target></link>, which is in Schedule II);</listitem><listitem>Phendimetrazine Tartrate, a stimulant synthesized for use as an anorexiant;</listitem><listitem><link><target>Benzphetamine</target></link><space/>HCl (Didrex), a stimulant designed for use as an anorexiant;</listitem><listitem>Fast-acting barbiturates such as secobarbital (Seconal) and pentobarbital (Nembutal), when combined with one or more additional active ingredient(s) not in Schedule II (e.g., Carbrital (no longer marketed), a combination of pentobarbital and carbromal).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ergine</target></link><space/>(lysergic acid amide), listed as a sedative but considered by some to be psychedelic.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Halpern<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J.H.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Hallucinogens and dissociative agents naturally growing in the United States<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Pharmacology & Therapeutics<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>102<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>131–138<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2004.03.003</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Schultes, R.E. and Hofmann, A., 1980.<space/><italics>The botany and chemistry of hallucinogens,</italics><space/>Charles C. Thomas, Springfield, IL.</extension><space/>An inefficient precursor to its<space/><italics>N</italics>,<italics>N</italics>-diethyl analogue,<space/><link><target>Lysergic acid diethylamide</target><part>LSD</part></link>, ergine occurs naturally in the seeds of the common garden flowers<space/><italics><link><target>Turbina corymbosa</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Ipomoea tricolor</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Argyreia nervosa</target></link></italics>.</listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Schedule IV drugs</arg></template>Schedule IV controlled substances</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Schedule IV drugs (US)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>&quot;Placement on schedules; findings requiredSchedule IV substances are those that have the following findings:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="1">
{{ordered list|type</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Control measures are similar to Schedule III. Prescriptions for Schedule IV drugs may be refilled up to five times within a six-month period. A prescription for controlled substances in Schedules III, IV, and V issued by a practitioner, may be communicated either orally, in writing, or by facsimile to the pharmacist, and may be refilled if so authorized on the prescription or by call-in.<extension extension_name='ref' name="deadiversion.usdoj.gov"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Drugs in this schedule include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Benzodiazepine</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as<space/><link><target>alprazolam</target></link><space/>(Xanax),<space/><link><target>chlordiazepoxide</target></link><space/>(Librium),<space/><link><target>clonazepam</target></link><space/>(Klonopin),<space/><link><target>diazepam</target></link><space/>(Valium);<space/><link><target>Lorazepam</target></link><space/>(Ativan):<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>temazepam</target></link><space/>(Restoril) (note that some states require specially coded prescriptions for<space/><link><target>temazepam</target></link>);</listitem><listitem><link><target>flunitrazepam</target></link><space/>(Rohypnol) (note that flunitrazepam is not used medically in the United States);</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Nonbenzodiazepine</target><part>benzodiazepine-like</part></link><space/><link><target>Z-drug</target><trail>s</trail></link>:<space/><link><target>zolpidem</target></link><space/>(Ambien),<space/><link><target>zopiclone</target></link><space/>(Imovane),<space/><link><target>eszopiclone</target></link><space/>(Lunesta), and<space/><link><target>zaleplon</target></link><space/>(Sonata) (zopiclone is not commercially available in the U.S.);</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chloral hydrate</target></link>, a sedative-hypnotic;</listitem><listitem>Long-acting<space/><link><target>barbiturates</target></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>phenobarbital</target></link>;</listitem><listitem>Some partial<space/><link><target>agonist</target></link><space/>opioid analgesics, such as<space/><link><target>pentazocine</target></link><space/>(Talwin);</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Stimulant</target><part>stimulant-like drug</part></link><space/><link><target>modafinil</target></link><space/>(sold in the U.S. as Provigil) as well as its<space/><italics>(R)</italics>-enantiomer<space/><link><target>armodafinil</target></link><space/>(sold in the U.S. as Nuvigil);</listitem><listitem><link><target>Difenoxin</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>antidiarrheal</target></link><space/>drug, such as when combined with atropine (Motofen) (difenoxin is 23 times more potent than<space/><link><target>diphenoxylate</target></link>, the active ingredient in<space/><link><target>Lomotil</target></link>, which is in Schedule V);</listitem><listitem><link><target>Tramadol</target></link><space/>(Ultram);</listitem><listitem><link><target>Carisoprodol</target></link><space/>(Soma) has become a Schedule IV medication as of 11 January 2012<extension extension_name='ref'>[Federal Register Volume 76, Number 238 (Monday, December 12, 2011)][Rules and Regulations] [Pages 77330-77360]</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Schedule V drugs</arg></template>Schedule V controlled substances</heading><preblock><preline><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of Schedule V drugs (US)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph>Schedule V substances are those that have the following findings:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="1">
{{ordered list|type</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>No controlled substance in schedule V which is a drug may be distributed or dispensed other than for a medical purpose.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cornell2"></extension><space/>A prescription for controlled substances in Schedules III, IV, and V issued by a practitioner, may be communicated either orally, in writing, or by facsimile to the pharmacist, and may be refilled if so authorized on the prescription or by call-in.<extension extension_name='ref' name="deadiversion.usdoj.gov"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Drugs in this schedule include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Cough suppressants containing small amounts of codeine (e.g.,<space/><link><target>promethazine</target></link>+codeine);</listitem><listitem>Preparations containing small amounts of opium or<space/><link><target>diphenoxylate</target></link><space/>(used to treat diarrhea);</listitem><listitem>Some anticonvulsants, such as<space/><link><target>pregabalin</target></link><space/>(Lyrica),<space/><link><target>lacosamide</target></link><space/>(Vimpat) and<space/><link><target>retigabine</target></link><space/>(<link><target>ezogabine</target></link>) (Potiga/Trobalt);</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pyrovalerone</target></link><space/>(used to treat<space/><link><target>chronic fatigue syndrome</target><part>chronic fatigue</part></link><space/>and as an<space/><link><target>appetite suppressant</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>weight loss</target></link>);</listitem><listitem>Some centrally-acting antidiarrheals, such as<space/><link><target>diphenoxylate</target></link><space/>(Lomotil) when mixed with<space/><link><target>atropine</target></link><space/>(to make it unpleasant for people to grind up, cook, and inject).<space/><link><target>Difenoxin</target></link><space/>with atropine (Motofen) has been moved to Schedule IV. Without atropine, these drugs are in Schedule II.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Federal regulation of pseudoephedrine and ephedrine</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also2</target><arg>[[Pseudoephedrine]] → [[Pseudoephedrine#National legislation|National Legislation]] → [[Pseudoephedrine#United States|United States]]</arg></template>Due to<space/><link><target>pseudoephedrine</target></link><space/>(PSE) and<space/><link><target>ephedrine</target></link><space/>being widely used in the manufacture of<space/><link><target>methamphetamine</target></link>, the U.S. Congress passed the<space/><link><target>Methamphetamine Precursor Control Act</target></link><space/>which places restrictions on the sale of any medicine containing pseudoephedrine. That bill was then superseded by the<space/><link><target>Combat Methamphetamine Epidemic Act of 2005</target></link>, which was passed as an amendment to the<space/><link><target>Patriot Act</target></link><space/>renewal and included wider and more comprehensive restrictions on the sale of PSE-containing products. This law requires<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.doh.state.fl.us/mqa/pharmacy/info_federallaw.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Federal Pseudoephedrine Law<space/></arg><arg name="work">doh.state.fl.us<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Florida Department of Health, Division of Medical Quality Assurance<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 5, 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-10-20</arg></template></extension><space/>customer signature of a &quot;log-book&quot; and presentation of valid photo ID in order to purchase PSE-containing products from all retailers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/meth/cma2005.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">General Information Regarding the Combat Methamphetamine Epidemic Act 2005<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Drug Enforcement Administration, Office of Diversion Control<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">October 20, 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Additionally, the law restricts an individual to the retail purchase of no more than three packages or 3.6 grams of such product per day per purchase and no more than 9 grams in a single month. A violation of this statute constitutes a misdemeanor. Retailers now commonly require PSE-containing products to be sold behind the pharmacy or service counter. This affects many preparations which were previously available over-the-counter without restriction, such as<space/><link><target>Actifed</target></link><space/>and its generic equivalents.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Alternatives to scheduling</heading><paragraph>The UK Science and Technology Select Committee<space/><link><target>Drug classification: making a hash of it?</target><part>published a 2006 report</part></link><space/>which suggested that the current system of recreational drug classification in the UK was arbitrary and unscientific and that a more scientific measure of harm should be used for classifying drugs. The new classification system suggested that<space/><link><target>heroin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cocaine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ethanol</target><part>alcohol</part></link>,<space/><link><target>benzodiazepines</target></link>,<space/><link><target>methamphetamine</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>tobacco</target></link><space/>have a high or a very high risk of harm or abuse potential, whilst<space/><link><target>Cannabis (drug)</target><part>cannabis</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lysergic acid diethylamide</target><part>LSD</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>MDMA</target><part>Ecstasy</part></link><space/>were all below the two legal drugs in harm or abuse potential.<extension extension_name='ref'>Science and Technology committee 2006, p. 176.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2007,<space/><italics><link><target>The Lancet</target></link></italics><space/>published a journal about researchers having introduced an alternative method for drug classification.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140673607604644/fulltext
</arg><arg name="title">Development of a rational scale to assess the harm of drugs of potential misuse
</arg><arg name="work">[[The Lancet]]
</arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)60464-4
</arg><arg name="pmid">17382831
</arg></template><template><target>subscription required</target></template></extension><space/>This new system uses a &quot;nine category matrix of harm, with an expert Delphic procedure, to assess the harms of a range of illicit drugs in an evidence-based fashion.&quot; The new classification system suggested that<space/><link><target>Ethanol</target><part>alcohol</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>tobacco</target></link><space/>were in the mid-range of harm, while<space/><link><target>Cannabis (drug)</target><part>cannabis</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Lysergic acid diethylamide</target><part>LSD</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>MDMA</target></link><space/>were all less harmful than the two legal drugs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="first1">David</arg><arg name="last1">Nutt
</arg><arg name="first2">Leslie A.</arg><arg name="last2">King
</arg><arg name="first3">William</arg><arg name="last3">Saulsbury
</arg><arg name="first4">Colin</arg><arg name="last4">Blakemore
</arg><arg name="work">[[The Lancet]]
</arg><arg name="date">24 March 2007
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism</heading><paragraph>There has been criticism against the schedule classifications of the listed drugs and substances in the CSA, citing undefined terms.<extension extension_name='ref' name="regulations.gov"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Drug Abuse 1973 p.13"></extension>Some criticism has arisen due to research that has found several substances on the list of Schedule I substances to have actual accepted medical uses and low abuse potential, despite the requirement for a Schedule I listing mandating that any substance so scheduled have both a high potential for abuse and<space/><bold><italics>no</italics></bold><space/>accepted medical use.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nutt, David J, King, Leslie A, &amp; Phillips, Lawrence D. (2010). Drug harms in the UK: A multicriteria decision analysis. The Lancet, 376(9752), 1558-1565.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.drugabuse.gov/publications/drugfacts/marijuana-medicine</extension><space/>One such example is the legalization of medical marijuana in over 20 states.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Government of the United States</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Convention on Psychotropic Substances</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Drug-Free Workplace Act of 1988</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fair Sentencing Act</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Gonzales v. Raich</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Legality of the War on Drugs</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of pharmaceutical companies</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Medical amnesty policy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Regulation of therapeutic goods</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Removal of cannabis from Schedule I of the Controlled Substances Act</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs</target></link><space/>(1961)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Treaty Clause</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Head Money Cases</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>United States v. Oakland Cannabis Buyers' Cooperative</target></link></italics></listitem></list><paragraph>Similar legislation outside of the United States:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Controlled Drugs and Substances Act</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Canada</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Misuse of Drugs Act 1971</target></link><space/>(<link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.deadiversion.usdoj.gov/21cfr/21usc/'>Full text of Controlled Substances Act</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Drug control laws</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Controlled Substances Act</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Drug Enforcement Administration</target></link><link><target>Category:History of drug control</target></link><link><target>Category:1970 in American politics</target></link><link><target>Category:United States federal criminal legislation</target></link></paragraph></article>