<article title='Military_engineering_vehicle'><paragraph><template><target>lead too short</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template><link><target>Image:20060714 defile blindes p1040887.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The EBG combat engineering vehicle, based on the<space/><link><target>AMX 30</target></link><space/>tank, is used by the engineers of the<space/><link><target>French Army</target></link><space/>for a variety of missions.</part></link><link><target>File:Bat-m.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>BAT-M engineering vehicle of<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link><space/>and the former<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>military engineering vehicle</bold><space/>is a vehicle built for the construction work or for the transportation of<space/><link><target>combat engineering</target><part>combat engineer</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on the battlefield. These vehicles may be modified civilian equipment or purpose-built<space/><link><target>military vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Types of military engineering vehicles</heading><heading level='3'>Civilian and militarized heavy equipment</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:D9-us pic28m.jpg</target><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part>USMC<space/><link><target>Caterpillar D9</target></link><space/><link><target>armored bulldozer</target></link>. The civilian tractor is fitted with an armor kit, produced by<space/><link><target>Israel Military Industries</target></link>.</part></link>Military engineering can employ a wide variety of<space/><link><target>Heavy equipment (construction)</target><part>heavy equipment</part></link><space/>in the same or similar ways to how this equipment is used outside the military.<space/><link><target>Bulldozer</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>crane (machine)</target><part>crane</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>grader</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>excavator</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>dump truck</target><trail>s</trail></link>, loaders, and backhoes all see extensive use by military engineers.</paragraph><paragraph>Military engineers may also use civilian heavy equipment which was modified for military applications. Typically, this involves adding armour for protection from battlefield hazards such as artillery, unexploded ordnance, mines, and small arms fire. Often this protection is provided by<space/><link><target>armour plate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and steel jackets. Some examples of armoured civilian heavy equipment are the<space/><link><target>IDF Caterpillar D9</target></link>, American D7 TPK, Canadian D6<space/><link><target>Armored bulldozer</target><part>armoured bulldozer</part></link>, cranes, graders, excavators, and<space/><link><target>M35 2-1/2 ton cargo truck</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Militarized heavy equipment may also take on the form of traditional civilian equipment designed and built to unique military specifications. These vehicles typically sacrifice some depth of capability from civilian models in order to gain greater speed and independence from prime movers. Examples of this type of vehicle include high speed backhoes such as the Australian Army's High Mobility Engineering Vehicle (HMEV) from Thales or the Canadian Army's Multi-Purpose Engineer Vehicle (MPEV) from Arva.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>The main article for civilian heavy equipment is:</italics><space/><link><target>Heavy equipment (construction)</target></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Armoured engineering vehicle</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pionierpanzer Dachs (2008).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''PiPz Dachs'' AEV of the<space/><link><target>German Army</target></link><space/>(2008)</part></link><link><target>File:MID Polish.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Polish Army<space/><link><target>PT-91 Twardy#MID Bizon-S</target><part>MID Bizon-S</part></link></part></link>Typically based on the platform of a main battle tank, these vehicles go by different names depending upon the country of use or manufacture. In the US the term &quot;combat engineer vehicle (CEV)&quot; is used, in the UK the term &quot;<link><target>Armoured Vehicle Royal Engineers</target></link><space/>(AVRE)&quot; is used, while in Canada and other commonwealth nations the term &quot;armoured engineer vehicle (AEV)&quot; is used. There is no set template for what such a vehicle will look like, yet likely features include a large dozer blade or mine ploughs, a large calibre demolition cannon, augers, winches, excavator arms and cranes or lifting booms.</paragraph><paragraph>These vehicles are designed to directly conduct obstacle breaching operations and to conduct other earth-moving and engineering work on the battlefield.</paragraph><paragraph>Good examples of this type of vehicle include the UK<space/><link><target>Trojan Armoured Vehicle Royal Engineers</target><part>Trojan AVRE</part></link>, the Russian IMR, and the US<space/><link><target>M728 Combat Engineer Vehicle</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>It should be noted that while the term &quot;armoured engineer vehicle&quot; is used specifically to describe these multi-purpose tank based engineering vehicles, that term is also used more generically in British and Commonwealth militaries to describe all heavy tank based engineering vehicles used in the support of mechanized forces. Thus, &quot;armoured engineer vehicle&quot; used generically would refer to AEV, AVLB, Assault Breachers, and so on.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Armoured earth mover</heading><paragraph>Lighter and less multi-functional than the AEVs described above, these vehicles are designed to conduct earth-moving work on the battlefield. These vehicles have greater high speed mobility than traditional heavy equipment and are protected against the effects of blast and fragmentation. Good examples are the American<space/><link><target>M9 ACE</target></link><space/>and the UK<space/><link><target>FV180 Combat Engineer Tractor</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Breaching vehicle</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:M1 Assault Breacher Vehicle.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Marines with 2nd Combat Engineer Battalion launch a<space/><link><target>M58 MICLIC</target></link><space/>from an<space/><link><target>Assault Breacher Vehicle</target></link>.</part></link>These vehicles are equipped with mechanical or other means for the breaching of man made obstacles. Common types of breaching vehicles include mechanical<space/><link><target>Mine flail</target><part>flails</part></link>, mine plough vehicles, and mine roller vehicles. In some cases, these vehicles will also mount<space/><link><target>Mine-clearing line charge</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Breaching vehicles may be either converted armoured fighting vehicles or purpose built vehicles. In larger militaries, converted AFV are likely to be used as<space/><italics>assault breachers</italics><space/>while the breached obstacle is still covered by enemy observation and fire, and then purpose built breaching vehicles will create additional lanes for following forces.</paragraph><paragraph>Good examples of breaching vehicles include the USMC M1<space/><link><target>Assault Breacher Vehicle</target></link>, the UK<space/><link><target>Aardvark JSFU</target></link>, and the Singaporean Trailblazer.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bridging vehicles</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:M104 HAB.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>U.S Army<space/><link><target>M104 Wolverine</target></link><space/>Heavy Assault Bridge</part></link>Several types of military bridging vehicles have been developed. An<space/><link><target>armoured vehicle-launched bridge</target></link><space/>(AVLB) is typically a modified tank hull converted to carry a bridge into battle in order to support crossing ditches, small waterways, or other gap obstacles.</paragraph><paragraph>Another type of bridging vehicle is the truck launched bridge. The Soviet TMM bridging truck could carry and launch a 10-meter bridge that could be daisy-chained with other TMM bridges to cross larger obstacles. More recent developments have seen the conversion of AVLB and truck launched bridge with launching systems that can be mounted on either tank or truck for bridges that are capable of supporting heavy main battle tanks.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.armedforces-int.com/article/leguan-system.html</arg><arg name="title">The LEGUAN System</arg><arg name="work">armedforces-int.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 April 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Earlier examples of bridging vehicles include a type in which a converted tank hull is the bridge. On these vehicles, the hull deck comprises the main portion of the tread way while ramps extend from the front and rear of the vehicle to allow other vehicles to climb over the bridging vehicle and cross obstacles. An example of this type of armoured bridging vehicle was the<space/><link><target>Churchill Ark</target></link><space/>used in the Second World War.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Combat engineer section carriers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Stryker ESV front q.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>M1132 Engineer Squad Vehicle</target></link><space/>(ESV) issued to combat engineer squads in the US Army<space/><link><target>Stryker Brigade Combat Team</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</part></link>Another type of CEVs are armoured fighting vehicles which are used to transport<space/><link><target>sapper</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(<link><target>combat engineer</target><trail>s</trail></link>) and can be fitted with a<space/><link><target>bulldozer</target></link>'s blade and other mine-breaching devices. They are often used as APCs because of their carrying ability and heavy protection. They are usually armed with<space/><link><target>machine gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and grenade launchers and usually tracked to provide enough tractive force to push blades and rakes. Some examples are the U.S.<space/><link><target>M113 Armored Personnel Carrier</target><part>M113 APC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IDF Puma</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nagmachon</target></link>, Husky, and U.S.<space/><link><target>M1132 Engineer Support Vehicle</target><part>M1132 ESV</part></link><space/>(a<space/><link><target>Stryker</target></link><space/>variant).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Military ferries and amphibious crossing vehicles</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:French army EFA DSC00859.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>This field-deployable apparatus, known as<space/><link><target>EFA (mobile bridge)</target><part>EFA</part></link>, used by the engineers of the<space/><link><target>French Army</target></link>, may either be used as a<space/><link><target>bridge</target></link><space/>(deployed in a series), or as a<space/><link><target>ferry</target></link></part></link>One of the major tasks of military engineering is crossing major rivers. Several military engineering vehicles have been developed in various nations to achieve this task. One of the more common types is the amphibious<space/><link><target>ferry</target></link><space/>such as the<space/><link><target>M3 Amphibious Rig</target></link>. These vehicles are self-propelled on land, they can transform into raft type ferries when in the water, and often multiple vehicles can connect to form larger rafts or<space/><link><target>pontoon bridge</target><part>floating bridge</part><trail>s</trail></link>. Other types of military ferries, such as the Soviet<space/><italics><link><target>PTS (amphibious vehicle)</target><part>Plavayushij Transportyor - Srednyj</part></link></italics>, are able to load while still on land and transport other vehicles cross country and over water.</paragraph><paragraph>In addition to amphibious crossing vehicles, military engineers may also employ several types of boats. Military assault boats are small boats propelled by oars or an outboard motor and used to ferry dismounted infantry across water.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Tank based combat engineering vehicles</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:AVRE-Bobbin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Churchill &quot;Bobbin&quot;, a rolled roadsurface (like a chespaling mat) that could be laid for following vehicles to cross loose sand. The raised boxes at the rear of the vehicle are radiator extensions to allow deep wading</part></link><space/>Most CEVs are<space/><link><target>armoured fighting vehicle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that may be based on a<space/><link><target>tank</target></link><space/><link><target>chassis</target></link><space/>and have special attachments in order to breach obstacles. Such attachments may include dozer blades,<space/><link><target>land mine</target><part>mine</part></link><space/>rollers, cranes etc. An example of an engineering vehicle of this kind is a bridgelaying tank, which replaces the turret with a segmented hydraulic<space/><link><target>bridge</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Hobart's Funnies</target></link><space/>of the Second World War were a wide variety of armoured vehicles for combat engineering tasks. They were allocated to the initial beachhead assaults by the British and Commonwealth forces in the D-Day landings</paragraph><heading level='3'>Churchill tank</heading><paragraph>The British<space/><link><target>Churchill tank</target></link><space/>because of its good cross-country performance and capacious interior with side hatches became the most adapted with modifications, the base unit being the AVRE carrying a large demolition gun.</paragraph><heading level='3'>M4 Sherman</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:M4A3-Sherman-105mm-Dozer-latrun-1.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>M4 with 105 mm howitzer and a dozer blade.</part></link><space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Dozer</bold>: The bulldozer blade was a valuable battlefield tool on the WWII<space/><link><target>M4 Sherman tank</target></link>. A 1943 field modification added the hydraulic dozer blade from a<space/><link><target>Caterpillar D8</target></link><space/>to a Sherman. The later M1 dozer blade was standardized to fit any Sherman with VVSS suspension and the M1A1 would fit the wider HVSS. Some M4s made for the Engineer Corps had the blades fitted permanently and the turrets removed. In the early stages of the 1944<space/><link><target>Invasion of Normandy</target><part>Battle of Normandy</part></link><space/>before the<space/><link><target>Rhino_tank</target><part>Culin Cutter</part></link>, breaking through the<space/><link><target>Bocage</target></link><space/>hedgerows relied heavily on Sherman dozers.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>M4 Doozit</bold>: Engineer Corps' Sherman dozer with demolition charge on wooden platform and T40<space/><italics>Whizbang</italics><space/>rocket launcher (the<space/><italics>Doozit</italics><space/>did not see combat but the<space/><italics><link><target>Rocket artillery</target><part>Whizbang</part></link></italics><space/>did).</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Bridgelayer</bold>: The US field-converted a few M4 in Italy with A-frame-supported bridge and heavy rear counter-weight to make the Mobile Assault Bridge. British developments for Shermans included the<space/><link><target>fascine</target></link><space/>(used by<space/><link><target>79th Armoured Division</target></link>), Crib, Twaby Ark, Octopus, Plymouth (<link><target>Bailey Bridge</target></link>), and AVRE (<link><target>Small Box Girder</target><part>SBG</part></link><space/>bridge).</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Mine-Clearing</bold>: British conversions included the<space/><link><target>Sherman Crab</target></link>. The US developed an extensive array of experimental types:<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>T15/E1/E2</bold>: Series of mine resistant Shermans based on the T14 kit. Cancelled at war's end.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E1 Roller</bold><space/>(<italics>Earthworm</italics>): Three sets of 6 discs made from armor plate.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E2 Roller</bold>: Two forward units with 7 discs only. Experimental.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E3/M1 Roller</bold><space/>(<italics>Aunt Jemima</italics>): Two forward units with five 10' discs. Most widely used T1 variant, adopted as the M1. (<link type='external' href='http://www.ww2incolor.com/gallery/us_army/mine_clearing_sherman'>picture</link>)</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E4 Roller</bold>: 16 discs.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E5 Roller</bold>: T1E3/M1 w/ smaller wheels. Experimental.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T1E6 Roller</bold>: T1E3/M1 w/ serrated edged discs. Experimental</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T2 Flail</bold>: British Crab I mine flail.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T3 Flail</bold>: Based on British Scorpion flail. Development stopped in 1943.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T3E1 Flail</bold>: T3 w/ longer arms and sand filled rotor. Cancelled.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T3E2 Flail</bold>: E1 variant, rotor replaced with steel drum of larger diameter. Development terminated at war's end.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T4</bold>: British Crab II mine flail.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T7</bold>: Frame with small rollers with two discs each. Abandoned.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T8</bold><space/>(<italics>Johnny Walker</italics>): Steel plungers on a pivot frame designed to pound on the ground. Vehicle steering was adversely affected.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T9</bold>: 6' Roller. Difficult to maneuver.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T9E1</bold>: Lightened version, but proved unsatisfactory because it failed to explode all mines.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T10</bold>: Remote control unit designed to be controlled by the following tank. Cancelled.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T11</bold>: Six forward firing mortars to set off mines. Experimental.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T12</bold>: 23 forward firing mortars. Apparently effective, but cancelled.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Exploder T14</bold>: Direct modification to a Sherman tank, upgraded belly armor and reinforced tracks. Cancelled.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Excavator T4</bold>: Plough device. Developed during 1942, but abandoned.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Excavator T5/E1/E2</bold>: T4 variant w/ v-shaped plough. E1/E2 was a further improvement.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Excavator T5E3</bold>: T5E1/E2 rigged to the hydraulic lift mechanism from the M1 dozer kit to control depth.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Excavator T6</bold>: Based on the v-shape/T5, unable to control depth.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mine Excavator T2/E1/E2</bold>: Based on the T4/T5's, but rigged to the hydraulic lift mechanism from the M1 dozer kit to control depth.</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>M60</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:M60-panther-mcgovern-base.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A remotely controlled Panther armored mine clearing vehicle leads a column down a road in<space/><link><target>Bosnia and Herzegovina</target></link>, May 16, 1996.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>M60A1 Armored Vehicle Launched Bridge (AVLB)</target><part>M60A1 AVLB</part></link></bold><space/>- Armored Vehicle Launched Bridge,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template><space/>scissors bridge on M60A1 chassis.</listitem><listitem><bold>M60 AVLM</bold><space/>- Armored Vehicle Launched MICLIC (Mine-Clearing Line Charge), modified M60 AVLB with up to 2 MICLIC mounted over the rear of the vehicle.</listitem><listitem><bold>M60 Panther</bold><space/>- M60 modified into a remotely controlled mine clearing tank. The turret is removed with the turret ring sealed, and the front of the vehicle is fitted with mine rollers.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>M728 Combat Engineer Vehicle</target><part>M728 CEV</part></link></bold><space/>- M60A1-based Combat Engineer Vehicle fitted with a folding A-frame crane and winch attached to the front of the turret, and an M135 165mm demolition gun. Commonly fitted with the D7 bulldozer blade, or a mine-clearing equipment.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>M728A1</bold><space/>- Upgraded version of the M728 CEV.</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>M1</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:M1 Grizzly 2.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Grizzly Combat Mobility Vehicle (CMV)</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>M1 Grizzly Combat Mobility Vehicle (CMV)<link type='external' href='http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ground/grizzly.htm'></link></listitem><listitem>M1 Panther II Remote Controlled Mine Clearing Vehicle<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ground/panther.htm'></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>M104 Wolverine</target></link><space/>Heavy Assault Bridge<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/systems/ground/wolverine.htm'></link></listitem><listitem>M1<space/><link><target>Assault Breacher Vehicle</target></link><space/>(USMC)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Leopard 1</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Biber (Beaver) armoured vehicle-launched bridge</listitem><listitem>Pionierpanzer 1</listitem><listitem>Pionierpanzer 2 Dachs (Badger) armoured engineer vehicle</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Leopard 2</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Panzerschnellbrcke 2 (Bridge layer)</listitem><listitem>Pionierpanzer 3 Kodiak</listitem></list><heading level='3'>T-55/54</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:MTU bridgelayer spb.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>MTU-12 bridgelayer</part></link><link><target>Image:MTU-20-latrun-2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>MTU-20 bridgelayer</part></link><link><target>File:IMR combat engineering vehicle in Odesa.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>IMR combat engineering vehicle</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>T-54 Dozer</bold><space/>- T-54 fitted with bulldozer blades for clearing soil, obstacles and snow.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.inetres.com/gp/military/cv/tank/T-54.html</arg><arg name="title">T-54/T-55 Main Battle Tank</arg><arg name="work">inetres.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 April 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>ALT-55</bold><space/>- Bulldozer version of the T-55 with large flat-plate superstructure, angular concave dozer blade on front and prominent hydraulic rams for dozer blade.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"><link type='external' href='http://www.jedsite.info/tanks-tango/tango-numbers-su/t-62_series/t62-series.html'>&quot;JED The Military Equipment Directory&quot;</link><template><target>Verify credibility</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template><template><target>Registration required</target></template></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>T-55</bold><space/>hull fitted with an excavator body and armoured cab.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>T-55 MARRS</bold><space/>- Fitted with a Vickers armoured recovery vehicle kit. It has a large flat-plate turret with slightly chamfered sides, vertical rear and very chmfered front and a large A-frame crane on the front of the turret. The crane has cylindrical winch rope feer between legs of crane. A dozer blade is fitted to the hull front.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>MT-55</target></link></bold><space/>or<space/><bold>MTU-55</bold><space/>(<italics>Tankoviy Mostoukladchik</italics>) - Soviet designator for Czechoslovakian MT-55A bridge-layer tank with scissors bridge.</listitem><listitem><bold>MTU-12</bold><space/>(<italics>Tankoviy Mostoukladchik</italics>)<extension extension_name='ref' name="OBT1">Karpenko, A.V.<italics>Obozreniye Bronetankovoj Tekhniki</italics><space/>(19051995 gg.) Bastion Nevskij 455-56</extension>- Bridge-layer tank with 12 m single-span bridge that can carry 50 tonnes. The system entered service in 1955; today only a very small number remains in service. Combat weight: 34 tonnes.</listitem><listitem><bold>MTU-20 (Ob'yekt 602)</bold><space/>(<italics>Tankoviy Mostoukladchik</italics>)<extension extension_name='ref' name="OBT1"></extension><space/>- The MTU-20 consists of a twin-treadway superstructure mounted on a modified T-54 tank chassis. Each treadway is made up of a box-type aluminum girder with a folding ramp attached to both ends to save space in the travel position. Because of that the vehicle with the bridge on board is only 11.6 m long, but the overall span length is 20 m. This is an increase of about 62% over that of the older MTU-1. The bridge is launched by the cantilever method. First the ramps are lowered and fully extended before the treadways are forward with the full load of the bridge resting on the forward support plate during launch. The span is moved out over the launching girder until the far end reaches the far bank. Next the near end is lowered onto the near bank. This method of launching gives the bridgelayer a low silhouette which makes it less vulnerable to detection and destruction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>MTU-20</bold><space/>based on the T-55 chassis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>BTS-1</bold><space/>(<italics>Bronetankoviy Tyagach Sredniy</italics><space/>- Medium Armoured Tractor) - This is basically a turretless T-54A with a stowage basket.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="softland.com.pl"><link type='external' href='http://softland.com.pl/aerojac/aaa/wzt-1/wzt1.htm'>softland.com.pl</link></extension><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>BTS-1M</bold><space/>- improved or remanufactured BTS-1.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>BTS-2 (Ob'yekt 9)</bold><space/>(<italics>Bronetankoviy Tyagach Sredniy</italics><space/>- Medium Armoured Tractor) - BTS-1 upgraded with a hoist and a small folding crane with a capacity of 3,000&amp;nbsp;kg. It was developed on the T-54 hull in 1951; series production started in 1955. The prototype Ob.9 had a commander's cupola with<space/><link><target>DShK</target><part>DShK 1938/46</part></link><space/>machine gun, but the production model has a square commander's hatch, opening to the right. Combat weight: 32 tons. Only a very small number remains in service.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OBT1"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>BTS-3</bold><space/>(<italics>Bronetankoviy Tyagach Sredniy</italics><space/>- Medium Armoured Tractor) - JVBT-55A in service with the Soviet Army.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>BTS-4</bold><space/>(<italics>Bronetankoviy Tyagach Sredniy</italics><space/>- Medium Armoured Tractor) - Similar to BTS-2 but with snorkel. In the West generally known as<space/><bold>T-54T</bold>. There are many different models, based on the T-44, T-54, T-55 and<space/><link><target>T-62</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OBT2">Karpenko, A.V.<italics>Obozreniye Bronetankovoj Tekhniki</italics><space/>(19051995 gg.) Bastion Nevskij 461-62</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Pancerni"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.pancerni.abajt.pl/index.php?option</arg><arg name="title">T-55 [ZSRR] - Pancerni.net</arg><arg name="author">Administrator</arg><arg name="work">abajt.pl</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 April 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>BTS-4B</bold><space/>- Dozer blade equipped armoured recovery vehicle converted from the early -odd-shaped turret versions of the T-54.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>BTS-4BM</bold><space/>- Experimental version of the BTS-4B with the capacity to winch over the front of the vehicle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>IMR (Ob'yekt 616)</bold><space/>(<italics>Inzhenernaya Mashina Razgrazhdeniya</italics>) - Combat engineer vehicle. It's a T-55 that had its turret replaced with a hydraulically operated 2t crane. The crane can also be fitted with a small bucket or a pair of pincer type grabs for removing trees and other obstacles. A hydraulically operated dozer blade mounts to the front of the hull; it can be used in a straight or V-configuration only. The IMR was developed in 1969 and entered service five years later.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gary's Combat Vehicle Reference Guide"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>SPK-12G</bold><space/>(<italics>Samokhodniy Podyomniy Kran</italics>) - Heavy crane mounted on T-55 chassis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><space/>Only two were built.</listitem><listitem><bold>BMR-2</bold><space/>(<italics>Boyevaya Mashina Razminirovaniya</italics>) - Mine clearing tank based on T-55 chassis. This vehicle has no turret but a fixed superstructure, armed with an NSVT machine gun. It is fitted with a KMT-7 mine clearing set and entered service around 1987 during the war in Afghanistan.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><list type='bullet'><listitem>Improved version of BMR-2 that has been seen fitted with a wide variety of mine roller designs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>T-64</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>BAT-2</target></link></bold><space/>Fast<space/><link><target>combat engineering vehicle</target></link><space/>with the engine, lower hull and &quot;small roadwheels&quot; suspension of the T-64.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.morozov.com.ua/eng/body/traktors/mt-tbas.php'></link><space/>The 40-ton tractor sports a very large, all axis adjustable V-shaped hydraulic dozer blade at the front, a single soil ripper spike at the rear and a 2-ton crane on the top. The crew compartment holds 8 persons (driver, commander, radio operators plus a five-man<space/><link><target>sapper</target></link><space/>squad for dismounted tasks). The highly capable BAT-2 was designed to replace the old<space/><link><target>T-54</target></link>/AT-T based<space/><link><target>BAT-M</target></link>, but<space/><link><target>Warsaw Pact</target></link><space/>allies received only small numbers due to its high price and the old and new vehicles served alongside during ar.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>T-72</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>IMR-2</target></link></bold><space/>(<italics>Inzhenernaya Mashina Razgrashdeniya</italics>) -<space/><link><target>Combat engineering vehicle</target></link><space/>(CEV). It has a telescoping crane arm which can lift between 5 and 11 metric tons and utilizes a pincers for uprooting trees. Pivoted at the front of the vehicle is a dozer blade that can be used in a V-configuration or as a straight dozer blade. When not required it is raised clear of the ground.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension><space/>On the vehicle's rear, a mine-clearing system is mounted.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>IMR-2</target><part>IMR-2M1</part></link></bold><space/>- Simplified model without the mine-clearing system. Entered service in 1987.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>IMR-2</target><part>IMR-2M2</part></link></bold><space/>- Improved version that is better suited for operations in dangerous situations, for example in contaminated areas. It entered service in 1990 and has a modified crane arm with bucket instead off the pincers.</listitem><listitem><bold><link><target>IMR-2</target><part>IMR-2MA</part></link></bold><space/>- Latest version with bigger operator's cabin armed with a 12.7&amp;nbsp;mm machine gun NSV.<list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Klin-1</bold><space/>- Remote controlled IMR-2.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><bold>MTU-72 (Ob'yekt 632)</bold><space/>(<italics>Tankovyj Mostoukladchik</italics>) - bridge layer based on T-72 chassis. The overall layout and operating method of the system are similar to those of the MTU-20 and MTU bridgelayers. The bridge, when laid, has an overall length of 20 meters. The bridge has a maximum capacity of 50,000&amp;nbsp;kg, is 3.3 meters wide, and can span a gap of 18 m. By itself, the bridge weighs 6400&amp;nbsp;kg. The time required to lay the bridge is 3 minutes, and 8 minutes for retrieval.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JED The Military Equipment Directory"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>BLP 72</bold><space/>(<italics>Brckenlegepanzer</italics>) - The East-German army had plans to develop a new bridgelayer tank that should have been ready for series production from 1987 but after several difficulties the project was canceled.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.militaertechnik-der-nva.de/Waffensysteme/BLP72/BLP72.html</arg><arg name="title">BLP72</arg><arg name="work">militaertechnik-der-nva.de</arg><arg name="accessdate">11 April 2015</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Combat engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>AM 50</target></link><space/>automatically launched assault bridge<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armored bulldozer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armoured recovery vehicle</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Armoured Vehicle Royal Engineers</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hobart's funnies</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sapper</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bulldozer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Caterpillar D9</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Terrier vehicle</target><part>Terrier armoured combat engineer vehicle</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>More footnotes</target><arg name="date">June 2008</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Military engineering vehicles</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.militaryphotos.net/forums/viewtopic.php?t=4663'>Combat Engineering Vehicles' pictures from around the world</link><space/>(www.militaryphotos.net forums)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.defence.gov.au/opslipper/images/gallery/20070309/index.htm'>Australian Provincial Reconstruction Team - Afghanistan</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.army-technology.com/projects/kodiak-vehicle/'>Kodiak Armoured Engineer Vehicle</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Military Engineering Vehicles</target></template><link><target>Category:Military engineering vehicles</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>