<article title='Khmer_architecture'><paragraph><link><target>File:Angkor Wat.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>380px</part><part>right</part><part>The 12th-century temple of<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>is the masterpiece of Angkorian architecture. Constructed under the direction of the<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Suryavarman II</target></link>, it was to serve as the monarch's personal mausoleum and as a temple to the<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>god<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>. Based on Dravidian architecture, it was designed as a pyramid representing the structure of the universe: the highest level at the center of the temple represented<space/><link><target>Mount Meru</target></link>, the home of the Hindu gods, with the five towers on the highest level representing the five peaks of the mountain. The broad moat around the complex represented the oceans that surround the world.</part></link><template><target>Culture of Cambodia</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The period of<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link><space/>is the period from approximately the latter half of the 8th century AD to the first half of the 15th century. If precise dates are required, the beginning may be set in 802 AD, when the founder of the<space/><link><target>Khmer Empire</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jayavarman II</target></link><space/>pronounced himself universal monarch (chakravartin) and declared independence from Java, and the end may be set in 1431 AD, when<space/><link><target>Thai people</target><part>Thai</part></link><space/>invaders from the kingdom of<space/><link><target>Ayutthaya Kingdom</target><part>Ayutthaya</part></link><space/>sacked Angkor and caused the<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link><space/>elite to migrate to<space/><link><target>Phnom Penh</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In any study of Angkorian architecture, the emphasis is necessarily on religious architecture, since all the remaining Angkorian buildings are religious in nature. During the period of Angkor, only temples and other religious buildings were constructed of stone. Non-religious buildings such as dwellings were constructed of perishable materials such as wood, and so have not survived.</paragraph><paragraph>The religious architecture of<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link><space/>has characteristic structures, elements, and motifs, which are identified in the glossary below. Since a number of different architectural styles succeeded one another during the Angkorean period, not all of these features were equally in evidence throughout the period. Indeed, scholars have referred to the presence or absence of such features as one source of evidence for dating the remains.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Periodization</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chan Chhaya Pavilion.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>380px</part><part>right</part><part>Khmer style architecture.</part></link>Scholars have worked to develop a periodization of Angkorian architectural styles. The following periods and styles may be distinguished. Each is named for a particular temple regarded as paradigmatic for the style.<extension extension_name='ref'>The periodization of Angkorian architecture presented here is based on that of Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, pp.30-31.</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Preah Ko</target></link><space/>Style (877-886 AD):<space/><link><target>Hariharalaya</target></link><space/>was the first capital city of the<space/><link><target>Khmer empire</target></link><space/>located in the area of Angkor; its ruins are in the area now called<space/><link><target>Roluos</target></link><space/>some fifteen kilometers southeast of the modern city of<space/><link><target>Siem Reap</target></link>. The earliest surviving temple of<space/><link><target>Hariharalaya</target></link><space/>is Preah Ko; the others are<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lolei</target></link>. The temples of the Preah Ko style are known for their small brick towers and for the great beauty and delicacy of their lintels.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Phnom Bakheng</target><part>Bakheng</part></link><space/>Style (889-923): Bakheng was the first temple mountain constructed in the area of Angkor proper north of Siem Reap. It was the state temple of King<space/><link><target>Yasovarman I</target><part>Yasovarman</part></link>, who built his capital of Yasodharapura around it. Located on a hill (phnom), it is currently one of the most endangered of the monuments, having become a favorite perch for tourists eager to witness a glorious sundown at Angkor.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Koh Ker</target></link><space/>Style (921-944)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pre Rup</target></link><space/>Style (944-968): Under King<space/><link><target>Rajendravarman</target></link>, the Angkorian Khmer built the temples of<space/><link><target>Pre Rup</target></link>,<space/><link><target>East Mebon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Phimeanakas</target></link>. Their common style is named after the state temple mountain of Pre Rup.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>Style (967-1000): Banteay Srei is the only major Angkorian temple constructed not by a monarch, but by a courtier. It is known for its small scale and the extreme refinement of its decorative carvings, including several famous narrative bas-reliefs dealing with scenes from Indian mythology.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Khleang</target></link><space/>Style (968-1010)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Baphuon</target></link><space/>Style (10501080): Baphuon, the massive temple mountain of King<space/><link><target>Udayadityavarman II</target></link><space/>was apparently the temple that most impressed the Chinese traveller<space/><link><target>Zhou Daguan</target></link>, who visited Angkor toward the end of the 13th century. Its unique relief carvings have a naive dynamic quality that contrast with the rigidity of the figures typical of some other periods. As of 2008, Baphuon is under restoration and cannot currently be appreciated in its full magnificence.</listitem><listitem>Classical or<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>Style (10801175): Angkor Wat, the temple and perhaps the mausoleum of King<space/><link><target>Suryavarman II</target></link>, is the greatest of the Angkorian temples and defines what has come to be known as the classical style of Angkorian architecture. Other temples in this style are<space/><link><target>Banteay Samre</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thommanon</target></link><space/>in the area of<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Phimai</target></link><space/>in modern<space/><link><target>Thailand</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Baroque or<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link><space/>Style (11811243): In the final quarter of the 12th century, King<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link><space/>freed the country of Angkor from occupation by an invasionary force from<space/><link><target>Champa</target></link>. Thereafter, he began a massive program of monumental construction, paradigmatic for which was the state temple called the Bayon. The king's other foundations participated in the style of the Bayon, and included<space/><link><target>Ta Prohm</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Banteay Chmar</target></link>. Though grandiose in plan and elaborately decorated, the temples exhibit a hurriedness of construction that contrasts with the perfection of Angkor Wat.</listitem><listitem>Post<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link><space/>Style (12431431): Following the period of frantic construction under Jayavarman VII, Angkorian architecture entered the period of its decline. The 13th century<space/><link><target>Terrace of the Leper King</target></link><space/>is known for its dynamic relief sculptures of demon kings, dancers, and<space/><link><target>nga</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Materials</heading><paragraph>Angkorian builders used<space/><link><target>brick</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sandstone</target></link>,<space/><link><target>laterite</target></link><space/>and wood as their materials. The ruins that remain are of brick, sandstone and laterite, the wood elements having been lost to decay and other destructive processes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Brick</heading><paragraph>The earliest Angkorian temples were made mainly of brick. Good examples are the temple towers of<space/><link><target>Preah Ko</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lolei</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Hariharalaya</target></link>. Decorations were usually carved into a stucco applied to the brick, rather than into the brick itself.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.27.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Angkor's neighbor state of<space/><link><target>Champa</target></link><space/>was also the home to numerous brick temples that are similar in style to those of Angkor. The most extensive ruins are at<space/><link><target>M Sn</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Vietnam</target></link>. A Cham story tells of the time that the two countries settled an armed conflict by means of a tower-building contest proposed by the Cham King<space/><link><target>Po klaung garai</target><part>Po Klaung Garai</part></link>. While the Khmer built a standard brick tower, Po Klaung Garai directed his people to build an impressive replica of paper and wood. In the end, the Cham replica was more impressive than the real brick tower of the Khmer, and the Cham won the contest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ng Vn Doanh,<space/><italics>Champa: Ancient Towers</italics>, p.232.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sandstone</heading><paragraph>The only stone used by Angkorian builders was sandstone, obtained from the<space/><link><target>Phnom Kulen</target><part>Kulen mountains</part></link>. Since its obtainment was considerably more expensive than that of brick, sandstone only gradually came into use, and at first was used for particular elements such as door frames. The 10th-century temple of<space/><link><target>Ta Keo</target></link><space/>is the first Angkorian temple to be constructed more or less entirely from Sandstone.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.26.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Laterite</heading><paragraph>Angkorian builders used laterite, a clay that is soft when taken from the ground but that hardens when exposed to the sun, for foundations and other hidden parts of buildings. Because the surface of laterite is uneven, it was not suitable for decorative carvings, unless first dressed with stucco. Laterite was more commonly used in the Khmer provinces than at Angkor itself.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.29.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structures</heading><heading level='3'>Central sanctuary</heading><paragraph>The central sanctuary of an Angkorian temple was home to the temple's primary deity, the one to whom the site was dedicated: typically<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link><space/>in the case of a<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>temple,<space/><link><target>Gautama Buddha</target><part>Buddha</part></link><space/>or a<space/><link><target>bodhisattva</target></link><space/>in the case of a<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target></link><space/>temple. The deity was represented by a statue (or in the case of<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link>, most commonly by a<space/><link><target>linga</target></link>). Since the temple was not considered a place of worship for use by the population at large, but rather a home for the deity, the sanctuary needed only to be large enough to hold the statue or linga; it was never more than a few metres across.<extension extension_name='ref'>Coeds,<space/><italics>Pour mieux comprendre Angkor</italics>, p.91.</extension><space/>Its importance was instead conveyed by the height of the tower (<italics>prasat</italics>) rising above it, by its location at the centre of the temple, and by the greater decoration on its walls. Symbolically, the sanctuary represented<space/><link><target>Mount Meru</target></link>, the legendary home of the<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>gods.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, pp.26 ff.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Prang</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Prang (architecture)</target><part>prang</part></link><space/>is the tall finger-like spire, usually richly carved, common to much Khmer religious architecture.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Enclosure</heading><paragraph>Khmer temples were typically enclosed by a concentric series of walls, with the central sanctuary in the middle; this arrangement represented the mountain ranges surrounding<space/><link><target>Mount Meru</target></link>, the mythical home of the gods. Enclosures are the spaces between these walls, and between the innermost wall and the temple itself. By modern convention, enclosures are numbered from the centre outwards. The walls defining the enclosures of Khmer temples are frequently lined by galleries, while passage through the walls is by way of gopuras located at the cardinal points.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.27.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Angkor Wat, Camboya, 2013-08-15, DD 038.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A cruciform gallery separates the courtyards at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>.</part></link>A gallery is a passageway running along the wall of an enclosure or along the axis of a temple, often open to one or both sides. Historically, the form of the gallery evolved during the 10th century from the increasingly long hallways which had earlier been used to surround the central sanctuary of a temple. During the period of<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>in the first half of the 12th century, additional half galleries on one side were introduced to<space/><link><target>buttress</target></link><space/>the structure of the temple.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Gopura</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ta Phrom, Angkor, Camboya, 2013-08-16, DD 01.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A gopura leads into the 12th-century temple compound at<space/><link><target>Ta Prohm</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Puerta Sur, Angkor Thom, Camboya, 2013-08-16, DD 09.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Many of the gopuras constructed under<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link><space/>toward the end of the 12th century, such as this one at<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>, are adorned with gigantic stone faces of<space/><link><target>Avalokiteshvara</target></link>.</part></link>A<space/><link><target>gopura</target></link><space/>is an entrance building. At<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link>, passage through the enclosure walls surrounding a temple compound is frequently accomplished by means of an impressive gopura, rather than just an aperture in the wall or a doorway. Enclosures surrounding a temple are often constructed with a gopura at each of the four<space/><link><target>cardinal point</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In plan, gopuras are usually cross-shaped and elongated along the axis of the enclosure wall; if the wall is constructed with an accompanying gallery, the gallery is sometimes connected to the arms of the gopura. Many Angkorian gopuras have a tower at the centre of the cross. The<space/><link><target>lintel (architecture)</target><part>lintels</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pediment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are often decorated, and guardian figures (<link><target>dvarapala</target><trail>s</trail></link>) are often placed or carved on either side of the doorways.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Hall of Dancers</heading><paragraph>A Hall of Dancers is a structure of a type found in certain late 12th-century temples constructed under King<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Ta Prohm</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Banteay Kdei</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Banteay Chhmar</target></link>. It is a rectangular building elongated along the temple's east axis and divided into four courtyards by galleries. Formerly it had a roof made of perishable materials; now only the stone walls remain. The pillars of the galleries are decorated with carved designs of dancing<space/><link><target>apsaras</target></link>; hence scholars have suggested that the hall itself may have been used for dancing.</paragraph><heading level='3'>House of Fire</heading><paragraph>House of Fire, or<space/><italics>Dharmasala</italics>, is the name given to a type of building found only in temples constructed during the reign of late 12th-century monarch<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ta Prohm</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Banteay Chhmar</target></link>. A House of Fire has thick walls, a tower at the west end and south-facing windows.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.172.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Scholars theorize that the House of Fire functioned as a &quot;rest house with fire&quot; for travellers. An inscription at<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link><space/>tells of 121 such rest houses lining the highways into<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link>. The Chinese traveller<space/><link><target>Zhou Daguan</target></link><space/>expressed his admiration for these rest houses when he visited Angkor in 1296 AD.<extension extension_name='ref'>Coeds,<space/><italics>Pour mieux comprendre Angkor</italics>, p.197f.</extension><space/>Another theory is that the House of Fire had a religious function as the repository the sacred flame used in sacred ceremonies.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Libraryangkorwat.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Unusually, the libraries at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>open to both the East and the West.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Library</heading><paragraph>Structures conventionally known as &quot;libraries&quot; are a common feature of Khmer temple architecture, but their true purpose remains unknown. Most likely they functioned broadly as religious shrines rather than strictly as repositories of manuscripts. Freestanding buildings, they were normally placed in pairs on either side of the entrance to an enclosure, opening to the west.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.30.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Srah and baray</heading><paragraph>Srahs and barays were<space/><link><target>reservoir (water)</target><part>reservoirs</part></link>, generally created by excavation and embankment respectively. It is not clear whether the significance of these reservoirs was religious, agricultural, or a combination of the two.</paragraph><paragraph>The two largest reservoirs at Angkor were the<space/><link><target>West Baray</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>East Baray</target></link>, located on either side of<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>. The East Baray is now dry. The<space/><link><target>West Mebon</target></link><space/>is an 11th-century temple standing at the center of the West Baray; the<space/><link><target>East Mebon</target></link><space/>a 10th-century temple standing at the center of the East Baray.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.161, 188.</extension><space/>The baray associated with<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link><space/>is the Jayataka, in the middle of which stands the 12th-century temple of<space/><link><target>Neak Pean</target></link>. Scholars have speculated that the Jayataka represents the Himalayan lake of Anavatapta, known for its miraculous healing powers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.178.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Temple mountain</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bakong.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link><space/>is the earliest surviving Temple Mountain at Angkor.</part></link>The dominant scheme for the construction of state temples in the Angkorian period was that of the Temple Mountain, an architectural representation of<space/><link><target>Mount Meru</target></link>, the home of the gods in<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target><part>Hindu</part></link><space/>mythology.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>The Monuments of Angkor</italics>, p.24.</extension><space/>The style was influenced by<space/><link><target>Indian architecture#Hindu architecture</target><part>Indian temple architecture</part></link>. Enclosures represented the mountain chains surrounding Mount Meru, while a moat represented the ocean. The temple itself took shape as a pyramid of several levels, and the home of the gods was represented by the elevated sanctuary at the center of the temple. The first great Temple Mountain was the<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link>, a five-level pyramid dedicated in 881 AD by King<space/><link><target>Indravarman I</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jessup,<space/><italics>Art &amp; Architecture of Cambodia</italics>, pp.73 ff.</extension><space/>Other Khmer Temple Mountains include<space/><link><target>Baphuon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pre Rup</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ta Keo</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Koh Ker</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Phimeanakas</target></link>, and most notably the<space/><link><target>Phnom Bakheng</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Coedes"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Coedès</arg><arg name="first"><space/>George</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>George Coedès</arg><arg name="editor"><space/>Walter F. Vella</arg><arg name="others"><space/>trans.Susan Brown Cowing</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Indianized States of Southeast Asia</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1968</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Hawaii Press</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8248-0368-1</arg></template></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>103,119</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Charles Higham (archaeologist)</target><part>Higham</part></link>, &quot;A temple was built for the worship of the ruler, whose essence, if a<space/><link><target>Saivite</target></link>, was embodied in a<space/><link><target>linga</target></link>...housed in the central sanctuary which served as a temple-mausoleum for the ruler after his death...these central temples also contained shrines dedicated to the royal ancestors and thus became centres of ancestor worship.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Higham">Higham, C., 2014, Early Mainland Southeast Asia, Bangkok: River Books Co., Ltd., ISBN 9786167339443</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>351</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Elements</heading><heading level='3'>Bas-relief</heading><paragraph><link><target>Bas-reliefs</target></link><space/>are individual figures, groups of figures, or entire scenes cut into stone walls, not as drawings but as sculpted images projecting from a background. Sculpture in bas-relief is distinguished from sculpture in haut-relief, in that the latter projects farther from the background, in some cases almost detaching itself from it. The Angkorian<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link><space/>preferred to work in bas-relief, while their neighbors the<space/><link><target>Art of Champa</target><part>Cham</part></link><space/>were partial to haut-relief.</paragraph><paragraph>Narrative bas-reliefs are bas-reliefs depicting stories from mythology or history. Until about the 11th century AD, the Angkorian Khmer confined their narrative bas-reliefs to the space on the<space/><link><target>tympanum (architecture)</target><part>tympana</part></link><space/>above doorways. The most famous early narrative bas-reliefs are those on the tympana at the 10th-century temple of<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link>, depicting scenes from<space/><link><target>Hindu mythology</target></link><space/>as well as scenes from the great works of Indian literature, the<space/><link><target>Ramayana</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link>. By the 12th century, however, the Angkorian artists were covering entire walls with narrative scenes in bas-relief. At<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>, the external gallery wall is covered with some 12,000 or 13,000 square meters of such scenes, some of them historical, some mythological. Similarly, the outer gallery at the<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link><space/>contains extensive bas-reliefs documenting the everyday life of the medieval Khmer as well as historical events from the reign of King<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.36.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Indraforestped01.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A bas-relief in a<space/><link><target>tympanum (architecture)</target><part>tympanum</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>shows<space/><link><target>Indra</target></link><space/>releasing the rains in an attempt to extinguish the fire created by<space/><link><target>Agni</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Angkor Wat, wall details.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The Battle of<space/><link><target>Kurukshetra</target></link><space/>is the subject of this bas-relief at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Bayonmarket01.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>This scene from the outer gallery at the Bayon shows Chinese expats negotiating with Khmer merchants at an Angkorean market.</part></link>The following is a listing of the motifs illustrated in some of the more famous Angkorian narrative bas-reliefs:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>bas-reliefs in the tympana at<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>(10th century)<list type='bullet'><listitem>the duel of the monkey princes<space/><link><target>Vali (Ramayana)</target><part>Vali</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sugriva</target></link>, and the intervention of the human hero<space/><link><target>Rama</target></link><space/>on behalf of the latter</listitem><listitem>the duel of<space/><link><target>Bhima</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Duryodhana</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Kurukshetra</target></link></listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>Rakshasa</target></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Ravana</target></link><space/>shaking Mount Kailasa, upon which sit<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link><space/>and his<space/><link><target>shakti</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kamadeva</target><part>Kama</part></link><space/>firing an arrow at<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link><space/>as the latter sits on Mount Kailasa</listitem><listitem>the burning of Khandava Forest by<space/><link><target>Agni</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Indra</target></link>'s attempt to extinguish the flames</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>bas-reliefs on the walls of the outer gallery at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>(mid-12th century)<list type='bullet'><listitem>the Battle of<space/><link><target>Lanka</target></link><space/>between the<space/><link><target>Rakshasas</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>vanaras</target></link><space/>or monkeys</listitem><listitem>the court and procession of King<space/><link><target>Suryavarman II</target></link>, the builder of Angkor Wat</listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>Battle of Kurukshetra</target></link><space/>between<space/><link><target>Pandavas</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kauravas</target></link></listitem><listitem>the judgment of<space/><link><target>Yama</target></link><space/>and the tortures of Hell</listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>samudra manthan</target><part>Churning of the Ocean of Milk</part></link></listitem><listitem>a battle between<space/><link><target>Deva (Hinduism)</target><part>devas</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>asuras</target></link></listitem><listitem>a battle between<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link><space/>and a force of<space/><link><target>asuras</target></link></listitem><listitem>the conflict between<space/><link><target>Krishna</target></link><space/>and the asura Bana</listitem><listitem>the story of the monkey princes<space/><link><target>Vali (Ramayana)</target><part>Vali</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sugriva</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>bas-reliefs on the walls of the outer and inner galleries at the<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link><space/>(late 12th century)<list type='bullet'><listitem>battles on land and sea between<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cham (Asia)</target><part>Cham</part></link><space/>troops</listitem><listitem>scenes from the everyday life of<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link></listitem><listitem>civil strife among the<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link></listitem><listitem>the legend of the Leper King</listitem><listitem>the worship of<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link></listitem><listitem>groups of dancing<space/><link><target>apsara</target><trail>s</trail></link></listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>File:Colonettesbanteaysrei.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>This blind door at<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>is flanked by colonettes. Above the door is a<space/><link><target>lintel</target></link>, above which is a tympanum with a scene from the<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Blind door and window</heading><paragraph>Angkorean shrines frequently opened in only one direction, typically to the East. The other three sides featured fake or blind doors to maintain symmetry. Blind windows were often used along otherwise blank walls.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.40.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Colonette</heading><paragraph>Colonettes were narrow decorative columns that served as supports for the beams and<space/><link><target>lintel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>above doorways or windows. Depending on the period, they were round, rectangular, or octagonal in shape. Colonettes were often circled with molded rings and decorated with carved leaves.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.38.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Corbelling</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Corbelangkorthomsouth.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>100px</part><part>left</part><part>Corbelled arch at the south gate of<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Ta-Prom IntrieurGalerie.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>100px</part><part>right</part><part>Corbelled hallway at<space/><link><target>Ta Prohm</target></link>.</part></link>Angkorian engineers tended to use the<space/><link><target>corbel arch</target></link><space/>in order to construct rooms, passageways and openings in buildings. A corbel arch is constructed by adding layers of stones to the walls on either side of an opening, with each successive layer projecting further towards the centre than the one supporting it from below, until the two sides meet in the middle. The corbel arch is structurally weaker than the true arch. The use of corbelling prevented the Angkorian engineers from constructing large openings or spaces in buildings roofed with stone, and made such buildings particularly prone to collapse once they were no longer maintained. These difficulties did not, of course, exist for buildings constructed with stone walls surmounted by a light wooden roof. The problem of preventing the collapse of corbelled structures at Angkor remains a serious one for modern conservation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="rlirmh">Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.32.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Lintel, pediment, and tympanum</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>lintel</target></link><space/>is a horizontal beam connecting two vertical columns between which runs a door or passageway. Because the Angkorean Khmer lacked the ability to construct a true<space/><link><target>arch</target></link>, they constructed their passageways using lintels or<space/><link><target>corbelling</target></link>. A<space/><link><target>pediment</target></link><space/>is a roughly triangular structure above a lintel. A tympanum is the decorated surface of a pediment.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Pedlintelsrei.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>lintel (architecture)</target><part>Lintel</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pediment</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link>; the motif on the pediment is<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link><space/><link><target>Nataraja</target></link>.</part></link>The styles employed by Angkorean artists in the decoration of lintels evolved over time, as a result, the study of lintels has proven a useful guide to the dating of temples. Some scholars have endeavored to develop a periodization of lintel styles.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, pp.32-35.</extension><space/>The most beautiful Angkorean lintels are thought to be those of the<space/><link><target>Preah Ko</target></link><space/>style from the late 9th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, pp.32-33.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Common motifs in the decoration of lintels include the<space/><link><target>kla (time)</target><part>kala</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Naga (mythology)</target><part>nga</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>makara (Hindu mythology)</target><part>makara</part></link>, as well as various forms of vegetation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>The Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.40.</extension><space/>Also frequently depicted are the<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>gods associated with the four cardinal directions, with the identity of the god depicted on a given lintel or pediment depending on the direction faced by that element.<space/><link><target>Indra</target></link>, the god of the sky, is associated with East;<space/><link><target>Yama</target></link>, the god of judgment and Hell, with South;<space/><link><target>Varuna</target></link>, the god of the ocean, with West; and<space/><link><target>Kubera</target></link>, god of wealth, with North.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freeman and Jacques,<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>, p.20.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Stairs</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Angkor Wat, Camboya, 2013-08-15, DD 054.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The stairs leading to the inner enclosure at<space/><link><target>Ankor Wat</target></link><space/>are daunting.</part></link>Angkorean<space/><link><target>stairs</target></link><space/>are notoriously steep. Frequently, the length of the<space/><link><target>Stair riser</target><part>riser</part></link><space/>exceeds that of the<space/><link><target>tread</target></link>, producing an angle of ascent somewhere between 45 and 70 degrees. The reasons for this peculiarity appear to be both religious and monumental. From the religious perspective, a steep stairway can be interpreted as a &quot;stairway to heaven,&quot; the realm of the gods. &quot;From the monumental point of view,&quot; according to Angkor-scholar<space/><link><target>Maurice Glaize</target></link>, &quot;the advantage is clear - the square of the base not having to spread in surface area, the entire building rises to its zenith with a particular thrust.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="rlirmh"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Motifs</heading><heading level='3'>Apsara and devata</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Apsarasdevatakdei01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>'''Apsaras''' (left) and a '''devata''' (right) grace the walls at<space/><link><target>Banteay Kdei</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Bayon, Angkor Thom, Camboya, 2013-08-16, DD 04.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Two '''<link><target>apsara</target><trail>s</trail></link>''' appear on this pillar at the 12th-century Buddhist temple the<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>Apsaras</target></link>, divine nymphs or celestial dancing girls, are characters from Indian mythology. Their origin is explained in the story of the churning of the<space/><link><target>Ocean of Milk</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>samudra manthan</target></link>, found in the<space/><link><target>Vishnu Purana</target></link>. Other stories in the Mahabharata detail the exploits of individual apsaras, who were often used by the gods as agents to persuade or seduce mythological demons, heroes and ascetics. The widespread use of apsaras as a motif for decorating the walls and pillars of temples and other religious buildings, however, was a<space/><link><target>Khmer people</target><part>Khmer</part></link><space/>innovation. In modern descriptions of Angkorian temples, the term &quot;apsara&quot; is sometimes used to refer not only to dancers but also to other minor female deities, though minor female deities who are depicted standing about rather than dancing are more commonly called &quot;<link><target>devatas</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Roveda.<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.200ff.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Apsaras and devatas are ubiquitous at<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link>, but are most common in the foundations of the 12th century. Depictions of true (dancing) apsaras are found, for example, in the<space/><link><target>Architecture of Cambodia#Hall of Dancers</target><part>Hall of Dancers</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link>, in the pillars that line the passageways through the outer gallery of the<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link>, and in the famous bas-relief of<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>depicting the churning of the Ocean of Milk. The largest population of devatas (around 2,000) is at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>, where they appear individually and in groups.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.37.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Dvarapala</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Banteay Kdei, Angkor, Camboya, 2013-08-16, DD 15.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>This '''dvarapala''' stands guard at<space/><link><target>Banteay Kdei</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>Dvarapala</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are human or demonic temple guardians, generally armed with lances and clubs. They are presented either as a stone statues or as relief carvings in the walls of temples and other buildings, generally close to entrances or passageways. Their function is to protect the temples. Dvarapalas may be seen, for example, at<space/><link><target>Preah Ko</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lolei</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Banteay Kdei</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.37.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Gajasimha and Reachisey</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>gajasimha</target></link><space/>is a mythical animal with the body of a lion and the head of an elephant. At Angkor, it is portrayed as a guardian of temples and as a mount for some warriors. The gajasimha may be found at<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>and at the temples belonging to the<space/><link><target>Hariharalaya</target><part>Roluos</part></link><space/>group.</paragraph><paragraph>The reachisey is another mythical animal, similar to the gajasimha, with the head of a lion, a short elephantine trunk, and the scaly body of a dragon. It occurs at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>in the epic bas reliefs of the outer gallery.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, pp.211-212.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Garuda</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Linteau Muse Guimet 25972.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>In this 9th century lintel now on display at the<space/><link><target>Muse Guimet</target></link>, '''Garuda''' bears Vishnu on his shoulders.</part></link><link><target>Garuda</target></link><space/>is a divine being that is part man and part bird. He is the lord of birds, the mythologial enemy of<space/><link><target>nga</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and the battle steed of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>. Depictions of Garuda at Angkor number in the thousands, and though Indian in inspiration exhibit a style that is uniquely Khmer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ukougg">Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.177.</extension><space/>They may be classified as follows:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>As part of a narrative bas relief, Garuda is shown as the battle steed of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Krishna</target></link>, bearing the god on his shoulders, and simultaneously fighting against the god's enemies. Numerous such images of Garuda may be observed in the outer gallery of<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Garuda serves as an<space/><link><target>Atlas (architecture)</target><part>atlas</part></link><space/>supporting a superstructure, as in the bas relief at Angkor Wat that depicts heaven and hell. Garudas and stylized mythological lions are the most common atlas figures at Angkor.</listitem><listitem>Garuda is depicted in the pose of a victor, often dominating a nga, as in the gigantic relief sculptures on the outer wall of<space/><link><target>Preah Khan</target></link>. In this context, Garuda symblizes the military power of the Khmer kings and their victories over their enemies. Not coincidentally, the city of Preah Khan was built on the site of King<space/><link><target>Jayavarman VII</target></link>'s victory over invaders from<space/><link><target>Champa</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>In free-standing nga sculptures, such as in nga bridges and balustrades, Garuda is often depicted in relief against the fan of nga heads. The relationship between Garuda and the nga heads is ambiguous in these sculptures: it may be one of cooperation, or it may again be one of domination of the nga by Garuda.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ukougg"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Indra</heading><paragraph>In the ancient religion of the<space/><link><target>Vedas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Indra</target></link><space/>the sky-god reigned supreme. In the medieval<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target></link><space/>of Angkor, however, he had no religious status, and served only as a decorative motif in architecture. Indra is associated with the East; since Angkorian temples typically open to the East, his image is sometimes encountered on lintels and pediments facing that direction. Typically, he is mounted on the three-headed elephant<space/><link><target>Airavata</target></link><space/>and holds his trusty weapon, the thunderbolt or<space/><link><target>vajra</target></link>. The numerous adventures of Indra documented in Hindu epic<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link><space/>are not depicted at Angkor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ukougg"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Kala</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Banteay Srei Kala.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A '''kala''' serves as the base for a deity at the 10th-century Hindu temple<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link>.</part></link>The kala is a ferocious monster symbolic of time in its all-devouring aspect and associated with the destructive side of the god<space/><link><target>Shiva</target><part>Siva</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.39.</extension><space/>In Khmer temple architecture, the kala serves as a common decorative element on lintels, tympana and walls, where it is depicted as a monstrous head with a large upper jaw lined by large carnivorous teeth, but with no lower jaw. Some kalas are shown disgorging vine-like plants, and some serve as the base for other figures.</paragraph><paragraph>Scholars have speculated that the origin of the kala as a decorative element in Khmer temple architecture may be found in an earlier period when the skulls of human victims were incorporated into buildings as a kind of protective magic or<space/><link><target>apotropaism</target></link>. Such skulls tended to lose their lower jaws when the ligaments holding them together dried out. Thus, the kalas of Angkor may represent the Khmer civilization's adoption into its decorative iconography of elements derived from long forgotten primitive antecedents.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.209.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Krishna</heading><paragraph>Scenes from the life of<space/><link><target>Krishna</target></link>, a hero and<space/><link><target>Avatar</target></link><space/>of the god<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>, are common in the relief carvings decorating Angkorian temples, and unknown in Angkorian sculpture in the round. The literary sources for these scenes are the<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Harivamsa</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Bhagavata Purana</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, pp.76 ff.</extension><space/>The following are some of the most important Angkorian depictions of the life of Krishna:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A series of bas reliefs at the 11th-century temple pyramid called<space/><link><target>Baphuon</target></link><space/>depicts scenes of the birth and childhood of Krishna.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.76.</extension></listitem><listitem>Numerous bas reliefs in various temples show Krishna subduing the<space/><link><target>nga</target></link><space/><link><target>Kaliya</target></link>. In Angkorian depictions, Krishna is shown effortlessly stepping on and pushing down his opponent's multiple heads.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rovedo,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.79</extension></listitem><listitem>Also common is the depiction of Krishna as he lifts Mount<space/><link><target>Govardhana</target></link><space/>with one hand in order to provide the cowherds with shelter from the deluge caused by<space/><link><target>Indra</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.80.</extension></listitem><listitem>Krishna is frequently depicted killing or subduing various demons, including his evil uncle<space/><link><target>Kamsa</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roveda,<space/><italics>Images of the Gods</italics>, p.91.</extension><space/>An extensive bas relief in the outer gallery of<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>depicts Krishna's battle with the<space/><link><target>asura</target></link><space/>Bana. In battle, Krishna is shown riding on the shoulders of<space/><link><target>Garuda</target></link>, the traditional mount of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>In some scenes, Krishna is depicted in his role as charioteer, advisor and protector of<space/><link><target>Arjuna</target></link>, the hero of the<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link>. A well-known bas relief from the 10th-century temple of<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>depicts the Krishna and Arjuna helping<space/><link><target>Agni</target></link><space/>to burn down Khandava forest.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Linga</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Linga Muse Guimet 2597.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>This segmented '''linga''' from 10th century Angkor has a square base, an octagonal middle, and a round tip.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>linga</target></link><space/>is a phallic post or cylinder symbolic of the god<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link><space/>and of creative power.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.16.</extension><space/>As a religious symbol, the function of the linga is primarily that of worship and ritual, and only secondarily that of decoration. In the<space/><link><target>Khmer empire</target></link>, certain lingas were erected as symbols of the king himself, and were housed in royal temples in order to express the king's consubstantiality with Siva.<extension extension_name='ref'>Coeds,<space/><italics>Pour mieux comprendre Angkor</italics>, p.60.</extension><space/>The lingas that survive from the Angkorean period are generally made of polished stone.</paragraph><paragraph>The lingas of the Angkorian period are of several different types.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Some lingas are implanted in a flat square base called a<space/><link><target>yoni</target></link>, symbolic of the womb.</listitem><listitem>On the surface of some lingas is engraved the face of Siva. Such lingas are called<space/><link><target>mukhalinga</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem>Some lingas are segmented into three parts: a square base symbolic of<space/><link><target>Brahma</target></link>, an octagonal middle section symbolic of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>, and a round tip symbolic of<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Makara</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Lintel corner with makara rider 1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The corner of a lintel on one of the brick towers at<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link><space/>shows a man riding on the back of a '''makara''' that in turn disgorges another monster.</part></link>A<space/><link><target>makara (Hindu mythology)</target><part>makara</part></link><space/>is a mythical sea monster with the body of a serpent, the trunk of an elephant, and a head that can have features reminiscent of a lion, a crocodile, or a dragon. In Khmer temple architecture, the motif of the makara is generally part of a decorative carving on a lintel, tympanum, or wall. Often the makara is depicted with some other creature, such as a lion or serpent, emerging from its gaping maw. The makara is a central motif in the design of the famously beautiful lintels of the<space/><link><target>Hariharalaya</target><part>Roluos</part></link><space/>group of temples:<space/><link><target>Preah Ko</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bakong</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lolei</target></link>. At<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link>, carvings of makaras disgorging other monsters may be observed on many of the corners of the buildings.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nga</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Buddha shielded by Naga.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Mucalinda</target></link>, the '''nga''' king who shielded<space/><link><target>Gautama Buddha</target><part>Buddha</part></link><space/>as he sat in meditation, was a favorite motif for Cambodian Buddhist sculptors from the 11th century. This statue is dated between 1150 and 1175 A.D.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Mythical serpents, or<space/><link><target>Naga (mythology)</target><part>nga</part><trail>s</trail></link>, represent an important motif in Khmer architecture as well as in free-standing sculpture. They are frequently depicted as having multiple heads, always uneven in number, arranged in a fan. Each head has a flared hood, in the manner of a cobra.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Linteau Muse Guimet 25973.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>This multi-headed '''nga''' is part of a decorative lintel from the end of the 9th century.</part></link>Ngas are frequently depicted in Angkorian<space/><link><target>lintel</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The composition of such lintels characteristically consists in a dominant image at the center of a rectangle, from which issue swirling elements that reach to the far ends of the rectangle. These swirling elements may take shape as either vinelike vegetation or as the bodies of ngas. Some such ngas are depicted wearing crowns, and others are depicted serving as mounts for human riders.</paragraph><paragraph>To the Angkorian Khmer, ngas were symbols of water and figured in the myths of origin for the Khmer people, who were said to be descended from the union of an Indian<space/><link><target>Brahman</target></link><space/>and a serpent princess from Cambodia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>The Monuments of Angkor</italics>, p.1.</extension><space/>Ngas were also characters in other well-known legends and stories depicted in Khmer art, such as the churning of the<space/><link><target>Ocean of Milk</target></link>, the legend of the Leper King as depicted in the bas-reliefs of the<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link>, and the story of<space/><link><target>Mucalinda</target></link>, the serpent king who protected the Buddha from the elements.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glaize,<space/><italics>The Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>, p.43.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nga Bridge</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Statues over a bridge-angkor.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Stone<space/><link><target>Asuras</target></link><space/>hold the '''nga'''<space/><link><target>Vasuki</target></link><space/>on a bridge leading into the 12th century city of<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>.</part></link>Nga bridges are causeways or true bridges lined by stone<space/><link><target>balustrade</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>shaped as ngas.</paragraph><paragraph>In some Angkorian nga-bridges, as for example those located at the entrances to 12th century city of<space/><link><target>Angkor Thom</target></link>, the nga-shaped balustrades are supported not by simple posts but by stone statues of gigantic warriors. These giants are the<space/><link><target>Deva (Hinduism)</target><part>devas</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>asuras</target></link><space/>who used the nga king<space/><link><target>Vasuki</target></link><space/>in order to the churn the Ocean of Milk in quest of the<space/><link><target>amrita</target></link><space/>or elixir of immortality. The story of the Churning of the Ocean of Milk or<space/><link><target>samudra manthan</target></link><space/>has its source in Indian mythology.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Quincunx</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Quincunxlingakbalspean01.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A '''linga''' in the form of a '''quincunx''', set inside a<space/><link><target>yoni</target></link>, is carved into the riverbed at<space/><link><target>Kbal Spean</target></link>.</part></link>A<space/><link><target>quincunx</target></link><space/>is a spatial arrangement of five elements, with four elements placed as the corners of a square and the fifth placed in the center. The five peaks of<space/><link><target>Mount Meru</target></link><space/>were taken to exhibit this arrangement, and Khmer temples was arranged accordingly in order to convey a symbolic identification with the sacred mountain. The five brick towers of the 10th-century temple known as<space/><link><target>East Mebon</target></link>, for example, are arranged in the shape of a quincunx. The quincunx also appears elsewhere in designs of the Angkorian period, as in the riverbed carvings of<space/><link><target>Kbal Spean</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Shiva</heading><paragraph>Most temples at<space/><link><target>Angkor</target></link><space/>are dedicated to<space/><link><target>Shiva</target></link>. In general, the Angkorian Khmer represented and worshipped Shiva in the form of a<space/><link><target>lingam</target></link>, though they also fashioned anthropomorphic statues of the god. Anthropomorphic representations are also found in Angkorian bas reliefs. A famous tympanum from<space/><link><target>Banteay Srei</target></link><space/>depicts Shiva sitting on Mount Kailasa with his consort, while the demon king<space/><link><target>Ravana</target></link><space/>shakes the mountain from below. At<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bayon</target></link>, Shiva is depicted as a bearded ascetic. His attributes include the mystical eye in the middle of his forehead, the trident, and the rosary. His<space/><link><target>vahana</target></link><space/>or mount is the bull<space/><link><target>Nandi (bull)</target><part>Nandi</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Vishnu</heading><paragraph>Angkorian representations of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link><space/>include anthropomorphic representations of the god himself, as well as representations of his incarnations or<space/><link><target>Avatar</target><trail>s</trail></link>, especially<space/><link><target>Krishna</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rama</target></link>. Depictions of Vishnu are prominent at<space/><link><target>Angkor Wat</target></link>, the 12th-century temple that was originally dedicated to Vishnu. Bas reliefs depict Vishna battling with against<space/><link><target>asura</target></link><space/>opponents, or riding on the shoulders of his<space/><link><target>vahana</target></link><space/>or mount, the gigantic bird-man<space/><link><target>Garuda</target></link>. Vishnu's attributes include the discus, the conch shell, the baton, and the orb.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ordinary housing</heading><paragraph>The nuclear family, in rural Cambodia, typically lives in a rectangular house that may vary in size from four by six meters to six by ten meters. It is constructed of a wooden frame with gabled thatch roof and walls of woven bamboo.<space/><link><target>Rural Khmer house</target><part>Khmer houses</part></link><space/>typically are raised on stilts as much as three meters for protection from annual floods. Two ladders or wooden staircases provide access to the house. The steep thatch roof overhanging the house walls protects the interior from rain. Typically a house contains three rooms separated by partitions of woven bamboo. The front room serves as a living room used to receive visitors, the next room is the parents' bedroom, and the third is for unmarried daughters. Sons sleep anywhere they can find space. Family members and neighbors work together to build the house, and a house-raising ceremony is held upon its completion. The houses of poorer persons may contain only a single large room. Food is prepared in a separate kitchen located near the house but usually behind it. Toilet facilities consist of simple pits in the ground, located away from the house, that are covered up when filled. Any livestock is kept below the house.<extension extension_name='ref' name="country"><link><target>Federal Research Division</target></link>. Russell R. Ross, ed. &quot;Housing&quot;.<space/><link type='external' href='http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/khtoc.html'>''Cambodia: A Country Study.''</link><space/>Research completed December 1987.<space/><italics>This article incorporates text from this source, which is in the public domain.</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Chinese and Vietnamese houses in Cambodian town and villages typically are built directly on the ground and have earthen, cement, or tile floors, depending upon the economic status of the owner. Urban housing and commercial buildings may be of brick, masonry, or wood.<extension extension_name='ref' name="country"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Khmer architecture</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Angkor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rural Khmer house</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.imdb.com/title/tt772159//'>&quot;Churning the Sea of Time&quot; Film</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Coeds, George.<space/><italics>Pour mieux comprendre Angkor</italics>. Hanoi: Imprimerie d'Extrme-Orient, 1943.</listitem><listitem>Forbes, Andrew; Henley, David (2011).<space/><italics>Angkor, Eighth Wonder of the World</italics>. Chiang Mai: Cognoscenti Books. ASIN: B0085RYW0O</listitem><listitem>Freeman, Michael and Jacques, Claude.<space/><italics>Ancient Angkor</italics>. Bangkok: River Books, 1999. ISBN 0-8348-0426-3.</listitem><listitem>Glaize, Maurice.<space/><italics>The Monuments of the Angkor Group</italics>. 1944. A translation from the original French into English is available online at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theangkorguide.com'>theangkorguide.com</link>.</listitem><listitem>Jessup, Helen Ibbitson.<space/><italics>Art &amp; Architecture of Cambodia</italics>. London: Thames &amp; Hudson, 2004.</listitem><listitem>Ng Vn Doanh,<space/><italics>Champa:Ancient Towers</italics>. Hanoi: The Gioi Publishers, 2006.</listitem><listitem>Roveda, Vittorio.<space/><italics>Images of the Gods: Khmer Mythology in Cambodia, Laos &amp; Thailand</italics>. Bangkok: River Books, 2005.</listitem><listitem><italics>Sthapatyakam. The Architecture of Cambodia</italics>. Phnom Penh: Department of Media and Communication, Royal University of Phnom Penh, 2012. Available online at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dmc-cci.edu.kh/userfiles/file/SthaPatyakam-1.pdf'></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Footnotes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Asia in topic</target><arg>Architecture of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Khmer Architecture</target></template><link><target>Category:Khmer</target></link><link><target>Category:Cambodian architecture</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Hindu temple architecture</target></link><link><target>Category:Buddhist temples</target></link><link><target>Category:Archaeological sites in Cambodia</target></link></paragraph></article>