<article title='The_Evil_Dead'><preblock><preline></preline><preline></preline><preline></preline><preline><template><target>about</target><arg>the 1981 film</arg><arg>all other uses, including the franchise as a whole</arg><arg>The Evil Dead (disambiguation)</arg></template></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Infobox film</target><arg name="name"><space/>The Evil Dead
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Evil dead ver1.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>220px
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Original theatrical release poster
</arg><arg name="director"><space/>[[Sam Raimi]]
</arg><arg name="producer"><space/>[[Robert Tapert]]
</arg><arg name="writer"><space/>Sam Raimi
</arg><arg name="starring"><space/>[[Bruce Campbell]]<br />[[Ellen Sandweiss]]<br />Hal Delrich<br />[[Betsy Baker]]<br />Sarah York
</arg><arg name="music"><space/>[[Joseph LoDuca]]
</arg><arg name="cinematography"><space/>Tim Philo
</arg><arg name="editing"><space/>Edna Ruth Paul
</arg><arg name="studio"><space/>[[Renaissance Pictures]]
</arg><arg name="distributor"><space/>[[New Line Cinema]]
</arg><arg name="released"><space/>{{Film date|1981|10|15|premiere|1983|01|17|United Kingdom}}
</arg><arg name="runtime"><space/>85 minutes<ref>{{cite web|title</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United States
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="budget"><space/>$350,000–400,000<ref>{{cite news|url</arg><arg name="gross"><space/>$2.6 million<ref>http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id</arg></template><bold><italics>The Evil Dead</italics></bold><space/>is a 1981 American<space/><link><target>horror film</target></link><space/>written and directed by<space/><link><target>Sam Raimi</target></link><space/>and executive produced by Raimi and<space/><link><target>Bruce Campbell</target></link>, who also stars alongside<space/><link><target>Ellen Sandweiss</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Betsy Baker</target></link>.<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>focuses on five college students vacationing in an isolated cabin in a remote wooded area. After they find an audiotape that releases a legion of<space/><link><target>demon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>spirit</target><trail>s</trail></link>, members of the group suffer from<space/><link><target>demonic possession</target></link>, leading to increasingly gory mayhem. Raimi and the cast produced the short film<space/><italics><link><target>Within the Woods</target></link></italics><space/>as a &quot;prototype&quot; to build the interest of potential investors, which secured Raimi US$90,000 to produce<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>. The film was shot on location in a remote cabin located in<space/><link><target>Morristown, Tennessee</target></link>, in a difficult filming process that proved extremely uncomfortable for the majority of the cast and crew.</paragraph><paragraph>The low-budget horror film attracted the interest of producer<space/><link><target>Irvin Shapiro</target></link>, who helped screen the film at the<space/><link><target>1982 Cannes Film Festival</target></link>. Horror author<space/><link><target>Stephen King</target></link><space/>gave a rave review of the film, which helped convince<space/><link><target>New Line Cinema</target></link><space/>to serve as its distributor. Though a meager commercial success in the United States, the film made its budget back through worldwide distribution, and grossed $2.4 million during its theatrical run. Both early and later critical reception were both universally positive and in the years since its release,<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>has developed a reputation as one of the largest<space/><link><target>cult film</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and has been cited among the greatest horror films of all time.<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>launched the careers of Campbell and Raimi, who would collaborate on several films together throughout the years, including Raimi's<space/><link><target>Spider-Man in film</target><part>''Spider-Man'' trilogy</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The film has spawned a<space/><link><target>Evil Dead (franchise)</target><part>media franchise</part></link>, beginning with two sequels written and directed by Raimi,<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead II</target></link></italics><space/>(1987) and<space/><italics><link><target>Army of Darkness</target></link></italics><space/>(1992), as well as video games and<space/><link><target>Army of Darkness (comics)</target><part>comic books</part></link>. The film's protagonist<space/><link><target>Ash Williams</target></link><space/>(Campbell) is regarded as a cult icon. The fourth film, serving as both a reboot and a remake, was titled<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead (2013 film)</target><part>Evil Dead</part></link></italics><space/>and was released in 2013. Raimi co-produced the film alongside Campbell and the franchise producer,<space/><link><target>Robert Tapert</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot</heading><paragraph>Five<space/><link><target>Michigan State University</target></link><space/>students,<space/><link><target>Ash Williams</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Bruce Campbell</target></link>) and his girlfriend Linda (<link><target>Betsy Baker</target></link>), accompanied by Ash's sister Cheryl (<link><target>Ellen Sandweiss</target></link>), their friend Scotty, and his girlfriend Shelly , venture into the<space/><link><target>Tennessee</target></link><space/>hills to vacation in an isolated cabin for their<space/><link><target>spring break</target></link>. They soon run into trouble, first narrowly avoiding another motorist, then having a sudden scare as the bridge near the cabin begins to collapse as they cross. That night, while Cheryl is making a drawing of a clock, her hand becomes violently possessed by a mysterious entity, causing her to draw a picture that looks like a deformed, evil face. She fails to mention the incident to the others, dismissing it as her imagination.</paragraph><paragraph>When the trapdoor to the cellar mysteriously flies open during dinner, Ash and Scotty go down to investigate and find the<space/><italics><link><target>Necronomicon#In popular culture</target><part>Naturom Demonto</part></link></italics>, a<space/><link><target>Sumer</target><trail>ian</trail></link><space/>version of the<space/><italics><link><target>Book of the Dead</target></link></italics>, along with a<space/><link><target>Tape recorder</target><part>tape recording</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>incantation</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which, when played, unleashes evil<space/><link><target>demon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>spirit</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The group is unaware of this, but Cheryl becomes hysterical when a tree crashes through the window, and she retires to her room. Later, hearing voices, she goes outside to investigate. Alone and far from the safety of the cabin, she is attacked and raped by<space/><link><target>Demonic possession</target><part>demonically possessed</part></link><space/>trees but manages to escape. The others do not believe her story, but Ash agrees to drive her to town where she can find a place to stay for the night. However, they find that the only bridge connecting the cabin to the rest of the world has been destroyed. Back at the cabin, while the girls play cards, Cheryl becomes demonically possessed, telling them that the demons will kill them. She then stabs Linda in the ankle with a pencil, and Scotty locks her in the cellar.</paragraph><paragraph>Shelly is the next to become possessed; she attacks Scotty, who eventually dismembers her with an axe. They bury her, and Scotty, emotionally shaken by her death, leaves to find an alternate trail through the woods.</paragraph><paragraph>Checking on Linda, Ash discovers that she, too, has become possessed, although she makes no attempt to attack him. Scotty returns, suffering from grave injuries caused by the possessed trees. Before losing consciousness, he tells Ash that an alternate trail does exist. Linda and Cheryl unsuccessfully attempt to deceive Ash into believing they are no longer possessed, only to attack him again. He locks Linda outside the cabin and tends to Scotty's injuries, but she sneaks in through the back-door and attacks Ash with a dagger, which he uses to impale her. Taking her body to the woodshed, Ash tries to force himself to dismember her with a chainsaw, but finds himself unable to do it and buries her instead. She rises from the grave and attacks him, forcing him to decapitate her with a shovel.</paragraph><paragraph>Returning to the cabin, Ash finds that Cheryl has escaped from the cellar. Arming himself with a shotgun, he finds her hiding outside and shoots her in the shoulder. He then descends into the cellar to search for more shotgun shells after barricading the doors. While there, he hears voices and sees blood seeping from numerous crevices and openings in the walls.</paragraph><paragraph>A demonically possessed Scotty tries to kill Ash as Cheryl breaks through the door. During their fight, Ash sees that the<space/><italics>Book of the Dead</italics><space/>has fallen near the fireplace and is starting to burn, as are Cheryl and Scotty. As Cheryl raises a fireplace poker to impale him, Ash snatches the book and throws it into the fire. With the book burnt, Cheryl and Scotty fall apart and die as the sun rises.</paragraph><paragraph>As Ash heads outside, an unseen evil speeds through the forest, breaks through the doors of the cabin and descends upon him. He turns around and screams in terror before the film cuts to the end credits.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Production</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sam Raimi by Gage Skidmore.jpg</target><part>alt=A man sitting next to a microphone placed on a table.</part><part><link><target>Sam Raimi</target></link><space/>directed the short film ''<link><target>Within the Woods</target></link>'' to generate the interest of investors for ''The Evil Dead''.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Background and writing</heading><paragraph>Director Raimi had grown up with Campbell, and the two formed a friendship at a very young age.<extension extension_name='ref' name="early2"><link><target>#Winston Dixon</target><part>Winston Dixon (2010)</part></link>, p. 161</extension><space/>The duo directed several low-budget<space/><link><target>Super 8 mm film</target></link><space/>projects together.<extension extension_name='ref' name="early"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 65</extension><space/>Several were comedies, including<space/><italics><link><target>Clockwork (film)</target><part>Clockwork</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>It's Murder!</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="def"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 16</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="writing"></extension><space/>Shooting a suspense scene in<space/><italics>It's Murder!</italics><space/>inspired Raimi to approach a career in the horror genre, and after researching horror cinema at<space/><link><target>drive-in theater</target><trail>s</trail></link>, Raimi was set on directing a horror film. The idea was to shoot a short film first, which would attract the interest of producers, and then use the money gained from that to shoot a full-length project.<extension extension_name='ref' name="writing"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 66</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="becker"><link><target>#Becker</target><part>Becker (2002)</part></link>, p. 64</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>short film</target></link><space/>that Raimi created was called<space/><italics><link><target>Within the Woods</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="proto"><link><target>#Lamberson</target><part>Lamberson (2008)</part></link>, p. 84</extension><space/>It was produced for $1,600, but for<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>, Raimi needed over $100,000.<extension extension_name='ref' name="money"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;8588</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To generate funds for the film, Raimi approached Phil Gillis, a lawyer to one of his friends.<extension extension_name='ref' name="money"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced"></extension><space/>Raimi showed him<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics>, and although Gillis was not impressed by the short film, he offered Raimi legal advice on how to produce<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>. With his advice in mind, Raimi asked a variety of people for donations, and even eventually &quot;begged&quot; some.<extension extension_name='ref' name="money"></extension><space/>Campbell had to ask several of his own family members, and Raimi asked every individual he thought could be interested.<extension extension_name='ref' name="money"></extension><space/>He eventually raised enough money to produce a full-length film, though not the full amount he originally wanted.<extension extension_name='ref' name="money"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>With enough money to produce the film, Raimi and Campbell set out to make what was then titled<space/><italics>Book of the Dead</italics>, a name inspired by Raimi's interest in the writer<space/><link><target>H. P. Lovecraft</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="writing"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="thingstoknow"></extension><space/>The film was supposed to be a remake of<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics>, with higher production values and a full-length running time. Raimi turned twenty just before shooting began, and he considered the project his &quot;<link><target>rite of passage</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ninety five"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 95</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pre-production and casting</heading><table class="infobox" style="font-size:100%;"><tablerow><tablehead>Actor</tablehead><tablehead class="unsortable"></tablehead><tablehead>Role</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>sortname</target><arg>Bruce<space/></arg><arg>Campbell</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>...</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Ash Williams</target><part>Ash</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>sortname</target><arg>Ellen</arg><arg>Sandweiss</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>...</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>List of The Evil Dead characters#Cheryl Williams</target><part>Cheryl</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>imdbname:nm0217822</target><part>Hal Delrich</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>...</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>List of The Evil Dead characters#Scotty</target><part>Scotty</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><template><target>sortname</target><arg>Betsy<space/></arg><arg>Baker</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>...</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>List of The Evil Dead characters#Linda</target><part>Linda</part></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>imdbname:nm0863462</target><part>Sarah York</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>...</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>List of The Evil Dead characters#Shelly</target><part>Shelly</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Raimi asked for help and assistance from several of his friends and past collaborators to make<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ninety five"></extension><space/>Campbell was cast as<space/><link><target>Ash Williams</target></link>, the main character.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EVIL2"><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;2324</extension><space/>To acquire more actors for the project, an ad in<space/><italics><link><target>The Detroit News</target></link></italics><space/>was placed.<space/><link><target>Betsy Baker</target></link><space/>was one of the actresses who responded, and<space/><link><target>Ellen Sandweiss</target></link>, who appeared in<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics>, was also cast.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ninety five"></extension><space/>The crew consisted almost entirely of Raimi and Campbell's friends and family. The make-up adviser for<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics>, Tom Sullivan, was brought on to compose the effects after expressing a positive reaction to working with Raimi.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EVIL2"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Without any formal assistance from location scouts, the cast had to find filming locations on their own. The crew initially attempted to shoot the film in Raimi's hometown of<space/><link><target>Royal Oak, Michigan</target></link>, but instead chose<space/><link><target>Morristown, Tennessee</target></link>, as Tennessee was the only state that expressed enthusiasm for the project. The crew quickly found a remote cabin located several miles away from any other buildings. During pre-production, the thirteen crew members had to stay at the cabin, leading to several people sleeping in the same room. The living conditions were notoriously difficult, with several arguments breaking out between crew members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cabin"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Steve Frankel was the only carpenter on set, which made him the art direction's sole contributor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weird"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;9394</extension><space/>For exterior shots, Frankel had to produce several elaborate props with a circular saw. Otherwise, the cabin mostly remained the way it was found during production. The cabin had no plumbing, but phone lines were connected to it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cabin"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;9698</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 14</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Filming</heading><paragraph>Because of the crew's inexperience, filming was a &quot;comedy of errors&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="errors"></extension><space/>The first day of filming led to the crew getting lost in the woods during a scene shot on a bridge.<extension extension_name='ref' name="errors"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 101</extension><space/>Several crew members became injured during the shoot, and because of the cabin's remoteness, securing medical assistance was difficult.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced2"><link><target>#Konow</target><part>Konow (2012)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;419422</extension><space/>One notably gruesome moment on set involved ripping off Baker's eyelashes during removal of her face-mask.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weird"></extension><space/>Because of the low budget, contact lenses as thick as glass had to be applied to the actors to achieve the &quot;demonic eyes&quot; effect.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weird"></extension><space/>The lenses took ten minutes to apply, and could only be left on for about fifteen minutes because eyes could not &quot;breathe&quot; with them applied.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weird"></extension><space/>Campbell later commented that to get the effect of wearing these lenses, they had to put &quot;<link><target>Tupperware</target></link>&quot; over their eyes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="weird"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Raimi developed a sense of<space/><italics><link><target>mise en scne</target></link></italics>, coming up with ideas for scenes at a fast rate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced"></extension><space/>He had drawn several crude illustrations to help him break down the flow of scenes. The crew was surprised when Raimi began using<space/><link><target>dutch angle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>during shots to build atmosphere during scenes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="raimi"></extension><space/>To accommodate Raimi's style of direction, several elaborate, low-budget rigs had to be built, since the crew could not afford a<space/><link><target>camera dolly</target></link>. One involved the &quot;vas-o-cam&quot;, which relied on a mounted camera that was slid down long wood platforms to create a more fluid sense of motion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="raimi"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ted Raimi by David Shankbone.jpg</target><part>alt=A man standing with a woman at a film premiere.</part><part>Sam Raimi's brother<space/><link><target>Ted Raimi</target></link><space/>''(pictured right)'' was the &quot;<link><target>fake shemp</target></link>&quot; in several scenes.</part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A camera trick used to emulate a<space/><link><target>Steadicam</target></link><space/>inexpensively was the &quot;<link><target>shaky camera</target><part>shaky cam</part></link>&quot;, which involved mounting the camera to a piece of wood and having two camera operators sprint around the swamp.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tested.com/art/movies/454928-low-budget-camera-tech-sam-raimis-evil-dead/</arg><arg name="title">The Low Budget Camera Tech of Sam Raimi’s Evil Dead</arg><arg name="author">Konow, David</arg><arg name="date">2013-04-18</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-05-07</arg></template></extension><space/>During scenes involving the unseen force in the woods watching the characters, Raimi had to run through the woods with the makeshift rig, jumping over logs and stones.<extension extension_name='ref' name="raimi"></extension><space/>This often proved difficult due to mist in the swamp.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 309</extension><space/>The film's final scene was shot with the camera mounted to a bike, while it was quickly driven through the cabin to create a seamless<space/><link><target>long take</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="raimi"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p.&amp;nbsp;102103</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Raimi had been a big fan of the<space/><italics><link><target>The Three Stooges</target></link></italics><space/>franchise during his youth, and it inspired him to use &quot;<link><target>fake shemp</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; during production.<extension extension_name='ref' name="def"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced"><link><target>#Konow</target><part>Konow (2012)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;412413</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 115</extension><space/>In any scene that required a background shot of a character, he would use another actor as a substitute to save time if the original actor was preoccupied.<extension extension_name='ref' name="shemp"></extension><space/>During a<space/><link><target>close-up</target></link><space/>involving Richard DeManicor's hand opening a curtain, Raimi used his own hand in the scene since it was more convenient. His brother<space/><link><target>Ted Raimi</target></link><space/>was used as a substitute in many scenes when the original actor was either busy or preoccupied.<extension extension_name='ref' name="shemp"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p.&amp;nbsp;111112</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Raimi famously enjoyed &quot;torturing&quot; his actors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ouch"><template><target>cite video</target><arg name="title">One by One We Will Take You: The Untold Saga of The Evil Dead</arg><arg name="type">documentary</arg><arg name="location">''The Evil Dead'' Ultimate Edition DVD</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Anchor Bay Entertainment</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir2</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2007)</part></link>, p. 507</extension><space/>Raimi believed that to capture pain and anger in his actors, he had to abuse them a little at times, saying, &quot;if everyone was in extreme pain and misery, that would translate into a horror.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ouch"></extension><space/>Producer<space/><link><target>Robert Tapert</target></link><space/>agreed with Raimi, commenting that he &quot;enjoyed when an actor bleeds.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ouch"></extension><space/>While shooting a scene with Campbell running down a hill, Campbell tripped and injured his leg.<extension extension_name='ref' name="torture"></extension><space/>Raimi enjoyed poking Campbell's injury with a stick he found in the woods. Because of the copious amounts of blood in the film, the crew produced gallons of fake blood with<space/><link><target>Associated British Foods</target><part>karo syrup</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced2"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="torture"></extension><space/>It took Campbell hours to remove the sticky substance from himself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="torture"></extension><space/>Several actors had inadvertently been stabbed or thrown into objects during production.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ouch"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="torture"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On the last few days on set, the conditions had become so poor that the crew began burning furniture to stay warm. Since only exterior shots needed to be filmed at that point, they burned nearly every piece of furniture left.<extension extension_name='ref' name="furniture"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;116117</extension><space/>Several actors went days without showering, and because of the freezing conditions, several caught colds and other illnesses. Campbell later described the filming process as nearly &quot;twelve weeks of mirthless exercise in agony&quot;, though he allowed that he did manage to have fun while on set.<extension extension_name='ref' name="torture"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;107109</extension><space/>On January 23, 1980, filming was finished and almost every crew member left the set to return home, with Campbell staying with Raimi.<extension extension_name='ref' name="furniture"></extension><space/>While looking over the footage that had been shot, Raimi discovered that a few<space/><link><target>Pick-up (filmmaking)</target><part>pick-ups</part></link><space/>were required to fill in missing shots. Four days of re-shoots were then done to complete the film.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reshot"></extension><space/>The final moment involved Campbell having &quot;monster-guts&quot; splattered on him in the basement.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reshot"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 128</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Editing</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:COEN Brothers (cannesPH).jpg</target><part>alt=Two men in button-up shirts smiling.</part><part>Joel Coen ''(pictured right'') of the<space/><link><target>Coen brothers</target></link><space/>was one of the staff members who edited the film.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part></link>After the extensive filming process, Raimi had a &quot;mountain of footage&quot; that he had to put together.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced2"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><space/>He chose a Detroit editing association, where he met Edna Paul, to cut the film. Paul's assistant was Joel Coen of the<space/><link><target>Coen brothers</target></link>, who helped with the film's editing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;129132</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="eddie"><link><target>#Eddie</target><part>Eddie (2010)</part></link>, p. 15</extension><space/>Paul edited a majority of the film, although Coen notably edited the shed sequence. Coen had been inspired by Raimi's<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics><space/>and liked the idea of producing a prototype film to help build the interest of investors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eddie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="pool"></extension><space/>Joel used the concept to help make<space/><italics><link><target>Blood Simple</target></link></italics><space/>with his brother Ethan, and he and Raimi became friends following the editing process.<extension extension_name='ref' name="thingstoknow"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">AMC staff</arg><arg name="date">2008-10-28</arg><arg name="url">http://blogs.amctv.com/movie-blog/2010/10/evil-dead-facts.php</arg><arg name="title">Ten Things You Might Not Know About the Evil Dead Trilogy</arg><arg name="publisher">[[AMC (TV channel)|Filmcritic.com]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="pool"><link><target>#Pooley</target><part>Pooley (1987)</part></link>, p. 44</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The film's first cut ran at around 117 minutes, which Campbell called an impressive achievement in light of the 65-minute length of the screenplay. It was then edited down to a more marketable 85 minutes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><space/>Raimi was inspired by the fact that<space/><link><target>Brian De Palma</target></link><space/>was editing his own film<space/><italics><link><target>Blow Out</target></link></italics><space/>with<space/><link><target>John Travolta</target></link><space/>at the same sound facility.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><space/>One of the most intricate moments during editing was the<space/><link><target>stop-motion</target></link><space/>sequence where the corpses &quot;melted&quot;, which took hours to cut properly.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><space/>The film had unique sounds that required extensive recording from the crew.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="kawin"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 17</extension><space/>Several sounds were not recorded properly during shooting, which meant the effects had to be redone in the editing rooms. Dead chickens were stabbed to replicate the sounds of mutilated flesh, and Campbell had to scream into a microphone for several hours.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Much like<space/><italics>Within the Woods</italics>,<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>needed to be blown up to 35mm, then the industry standard, to be played at movie theaters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension><space/>The relatively large budget made this a much simpler process with<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>than it had been with the short film.<extension extension_name='ref' name="editing"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Promotion and distribution</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:RedfordTheatreMarquee.jpg</target><part>alt=View of a movie theater marquee.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''The Evil Dead'' premiered at the<space/><link><target>Redford Theatre</target></link><space/>because Bruce Campbell watched films there as a child.</part></link>With the film completed, Raimi and the crew decided to celebrate with a &quot;big premiere&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="premiere"></extension><space/>They chose to screen the film at Detroit's<space/><link><target>Redford Theatre</target></link>, which Campbell had often visited as a child.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced2"></extension><space/>Raimi opted to have the most theatrical premiere possible, using custom tickets and wind tracks set in the theater, and ordering ambulances outside the theater to build atmosphere.<extension extension_name='ref' name="premiere"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#F. Kawin</target><part>F. Kawin (2012)</part></link>, p. 13</extension><space/>The premiere setup was inspired by horror director<space/><link><target>William Castle</target></link>, who would often attempt to scare his audiences by using gimmicks. Local turnout for the premiere exceeded the cast's expectations, with a thousand patrons showing up. The audiences responded enthusiastically to the premiere, which led to Raimi's idea of &quot;touring&quot; the film to build hype.<extension extension_name='ref' name="premiere"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;125126</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Raimi showed the film to anyone willing to watch it, booking meetings with distribution agents and anyone with experience in the film industry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="casa"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;136137</extension><space/>Eventually Raimi came across<space/><link><target>Irvin Shapiro</target></link>, the man who was responsible for the distribution of<space/><link><target>George A. Romero</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Night of the Living Dead</target></link></italics><space/>and other famous horror films.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced3"><link><target>#Konow</target><part>Konow (2012)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;422425</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Warren</target><part>Warren (2000)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;125126</extension><space/>Upon first viewing the film, he joked that while it &quot;wasn't<space/><italics><link><target>Gone with the Wind (film)</target><part>Gone with the Wind</part></link></italics>&quot;, it had commercial potential, and he expressed an interest in distributing it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="casa"></extension><space/>It was his idea not to use the then-title<space/><italics>Book of the Dead</italics>, because it made the film sound boring. Raimi brainstormed several ideas, eventually going with<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>, deemed the &quot;least worst&quot; title.<extension extension_name='ref' name="casa"></extension><space/>Shapiro also advised distributing the film worldwide to garner a larger income, though it required a further financial investment by Raimi, who managed to scrape together what little money he had.<extension extension_name='ref' name="casa"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Stephen King, Comicon.jpg</target><part>alt=Close-up of a man wearing glasses.</part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Stephen King</target></link><space/>cited ''The Evil Dead'' as one of his favorite films, which brought the interest of<space/><link><target>New Line Cinema</target></link>.</part></link>Shapiro was a founder of the<space/><link><target>Cannes Film Festival</target></link>, and allowed Raimi to screen the film at the<space/><link><target>1982 Cannes Film Festival</target><part>1982 festival</part></link><space/>out of competition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fuckyeah"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 24</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cannes"></extension><space/><link><target>Stephen King</target></link><space/>was present at its screening and gave the film a rave review.<space/><italics><link><target>USA Today</target></link></italics><space/>released an article about King's favorite horror films; the author cited<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>as his fifth favorite film of the genre.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cannes"><link><target>#R. Collings</target><part>R. Collings (2008)</part></link>, p. 26</extension><space/>The film severely affected King, who commented that while watching the film at Cannes, he was &quot;registering things [he] had never seen in a movie before&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gyu"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 20</extension><space/>He became one of the film's largest supporters during the early efforts to find a distributor, eventually describing it as the &quot;most ferociously original film of the year&quot;, a quote used in the film's promotional pieces.<extension extension_name='ref' name="thingstoknow"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#R. Collings</target><part>R. Collings (2007)</part></link>, p. 157</extension><space/>King's comments attracted the interest of critics, who otherwise would likely have dismissed the low-budget thriller.<extension extension_name='ref' name="gyu"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="LATIMES"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;151152</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The film's press attracted the attention of British film distribution agent<space/><link><target>Stephen Woolley</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Finney</target><part>Finney (1997)</part></link>, p. 58</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="bannedyo"><link><target>#Chibnall</target><part>Chibnall (2001)</part></link>, p. 184</extension><space/>Though he considered the film a big risk, Woolley decided to take on the job of releasing the film in the United Kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Finney</target><part>Finney (1997)</part></link>, p. 55</extension><space/>The film was promoted in an unconventional manner for a film of its budget, receiving marketing on par with that of larger budget films.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LATIMES"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="charming"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 19</extension><space/>Dozens of promotional pieces, including film posters and trailers, were showcased in the UK, heavy promotion rarely expended on such a low-budget film.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 27</extension><space/>Woolley was impressed by Raimi, whom he called &quot;charming&quot;, and was an admirer of the film, which led to his taking more risks with the film's promotion than he normally would have.<extension extension_name='ref' name="charming"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Newman</target><part>Newman (2011)</part></link>, p. 38</extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Fangoria</target></link></italics><space/>started covering the film in late 1982, writing several articles about the film's long production history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twentyone"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 21</extension><space/>Early critical reception at the time was very positive, and along with<space/><italics>Fangoria</italics>, King, and Shapiro's approval, the film generated an impressive amount of interest before its commercial premiere.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LATIMES"></extension><space/><link><target>New Line Cinema</target></link>, one of the distributors interested in the film, negotiated an agreement to distribute it domestically.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced3"></extension><space/>The film had several &quot;sneak previews&quot; before its commercial release, including screenings in New York and Detroit. Audience reception at both screenings was widely enthusiastic, and interest was built for the film to such an extent that wider distribution was planned. New Line Cinema wrote Raimi a check large enough to pay off all the investors, and decided to release the film in a unique manner:<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced3"></extension><space/>simultaneously into both cinemas and onto<space/><link><target>VHS</target></link>, with substantial domestic promotion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fuckyeah"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Commercial release</heading><paragraph>Because of its large promotional campaign, the film performed above expectations at the box office.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fuckyeah"></extension><space/>It grossed a total of $2,400,000 worldwide, nearly eight times its production budget.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BOM"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Evil Dead</arg><arg name="url">http://boxofficemojo.com/movies/?id</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Box Office Mojo]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-05-19</arg></template></extension><space/>The initial domestic gross was described as &quot;disappointing.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><space/>It opened in 15 theaters and grossed $108,000 in its opening weekend.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><space/>Word of mouth later spread, and the film became a &quot;<link><target>sleeper hit</target></link>&quot;, making over $600,000 domestically and nearly $2,000,000 overseas.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><space/>In its first week of release in 1983 two years later, the film made 100,000 in the UK and quickly became that week's best-selling video release. It became the best-selling video in the country that year, out-grossing large-budget horror releases such as<space/><italics><link><target>The Shining (film)</target><part>The Shining</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LATIMES"></extension><space/>Its impressive European performance was chalked up to its heavy promotion there and the more open-minded nature of audiences.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;2628</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The film's release was met with controversy. Raimi made the film as gruesome as possible with neither interest in nor fear of censorship, which led to the film's receiving an<space/><link><target>X rating</target></link><space/>and being named a &quot;<link><target>video nasty</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nasty"></extension><space/>Films with this label were quite violent and disturbing, and the title was often held by<space/><link><target>pornographic film</target><part>pornographic</part></link><space/>and other X-rated films.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nasty"><link><target>#Hantke</target><part>Hantke (2004)</part></link><space/>p. 160</extension><space/>While<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>was not pornographic in nature, it was considered one of the most violent films of its time, and censors had issues with the film's content, which impacted some of its commercial potential.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kerekes</target><part>Kerekes (2000)</part></link></extension><space/>The film was called the &quot;number one nasty&quot; in a nod to its status as both a nasty and the year's best-selling video release.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bannedyo"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Hantke</target><part>Hantke (2004)</part></link><space/>p. 162</extension><space/>Writer Bruce Kawin described<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>as one of the most notorious<space/><link><target>splatter film</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of its day, along with<space/><italics><link><target>Cannibal Holocaust</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>I Spit on Your Grave</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kawin"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Staiger</target><part>Staiger (2005)</part></link>, p. 125</extension><space/>The film was<space/><link><target>List of banned films</target><part>banned</part></link><space/>either theatrically or on video in some countries.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Davis, Laura</arg><arg name="title">BANNED: The most controversial films</arg><arg name="url">http://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/films/features/banned-the-most-controversial-films-1768299.html?action</arg><arg name="date">2010-10-05</arg><arg name="work">The Independent</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-11</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Xavier</target><part>Xavier (2004)</part></link>, p. 195</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Home video release</heading><paragraph>The first VHS release of<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>was by<space/><link><target>Thorn EMI</target></link><space/>in 1983, and Thorn's successor company<space/><link><target>HBO</target></link><space/><xhtml:small>(<link><target>Time Warner</target></link>)</xhtml:small>/<link><target>Cannon Films</target><part>Cannon</part></link><xhtml:small>(<link><target>MGM</target></link>)</xhtml:small><space/>Video later repackaged the film. Congress Video, a company notable for<space/><link><target>public domain</target></link><space/>films, issued their version in 1989.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The gorehound's guide to splatter films of the 1980s</arg><arg name="author">Stine, Scott Aaron</arg><arg name="publisher">McFarland</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="page">114</arg><arg name="isbn">0786415320</arg><arg name="quote">The Evil Dead (ABE; 85m); The Evil Dead (CNG; 89(85)m); The Evil Dead (EMI; 85m)</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Bowker's Complete Video Directory 1994</arg><arg name="publisher">[[R.R. Bowker]]</arg><arg name="page">266</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8352-3391-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The resurgence of<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>in the home-video market came through two companies that restored the film from its negatives and issued special editions in 1998:<space/><link><target>Anchor Bay Entertainment</target></link><space/>on VHS, and Elite Entertainment on<space/><link><target>laserdisc</target></link>. Anchor Bay was responsible for the film's first<space/><link><target>DVD</target></link><space/>release in 1999, and between them, Elite and Anchor Bay have released six different DVD versions of<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>, most notably a 2002 &quot;Book Of The Dead&quot; edition, packaged in a latex replica of the<space/><italics>Necronomicon</italics><space/>sculpted by Tom Sullivan.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 52-3</extension><space/>The film's high-definition debut was in a 2010<space/><link><target>Blu-ray</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ign.com/articles/2010/09/03/the-evil-dead-blu-ray-review</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead Blu-ray Review</arg><arg name="publisher">[[IGN]]</arg><arg name="author">White, Cindy</arg><arg name="date">2010-09-03</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-05-07</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reception</heading><heading level='3'>Early reception</heading><paragraph>Upon its release, contemporary critical opinion was mostly positive.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced3"></extension><space/>Bob Martin, editor of<space/><italics>Fangoria</italics>, reviewed the film before its formal premiere and proclaimed that it &quot;might be the exception to the usual run of low-budget horror films&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="twentyone"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Los Angeles Times</target></link></italics><space/>called the film an &quot;instant classic&quot;, proclaiming it as &quot;probably the grisliest well-made movie ever.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="LATIMES"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>In a 1982 review, staff from the<space/><link><target>trade magazine</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Variety (magazine)</target><part>Variety</part></link></italics><space/>wrote that the film &quot;emerges as the nec plus ultra of low-budget gore and shock effect&quot;, commenting that the &quot;powerful&quot; and inventive camerawork was key to creating a sense of dread.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Variety Staff</arg><arg name="url">http://www.variety.com/review/VE1117790757?refcatid</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead</arg><arg name="work">[[Variety (magazine)|Variety]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Reed Business Information|RBI]]</arg><arg name="date">1982-12-31</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-31</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>British press for the film was positive; Kim Newman of<space/><italics><link><target>Monthly Film Bulletin</target></link></italics>, Richard Cook of<space/><italics><link><target>NME</target></link></italics>, and Julian Petley of<space/><italics>Film and Filming</italics><space/>all gave the film good reviews during its early release.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"><link><target>#Egan</target><part>Egan (2011)</part></link>, p. 22</extension><space/>Petley and Cook compared the film to other contemporary horror films, writing that the film expressed more imagination and &quot;youthful enthusiasm&quot; than an average horror film.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>Cook described the camera work by Raimi as &quot;audacious&quot;, stating that the film's visceral nature was greatly helped by the style of direction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>Woolley, Newman, and several critics complimented the film for its unexpected use of<space/><link><target>black comedy</target></link>, which elevated the film above its genre's potential trappings.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>All three critics compared the film to the surrealistic work of<space/><link><target>Georges Franju</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jean Cocteau</target></link>, noting the cinephilic references to Cocteau's film<space/><italics><link><target>Orpheus (film)</target><part>Orpheus</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>Writer Lynn Schofield Clark in his novel<space/><italics>From Angels to Aliens</italics><space/>compared the film to better-known horror films such as<space/><italics><link><target>The Exorcist (film)</target><part>The Exorcist</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Omen</target></link></italics>, citing it as a key supernatural thriller.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Schofield Clark</target><part>Schofield Clark (2005)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;2628</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Later reception</heading><paragraph>The film continues to receive universal acclaim from modern critics. The<space/><link><target>review aggregator</target></link><space/>website<space/><link><target>Rotten Tomatoes</target></link><space/>reported a 96% approval rating with an average rating of 8.1/10, based on an aggregation of 53 reviews. It summarized the film: &quot;This classic low budget horror film combines just the right amount of gore and black humor, giving<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>an equal amount of thrills and laughs.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="RottenTomatoes"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rottentomatoes.com/m/the-evil-dead/<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Rotten Tomatoes]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-05-07</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>Empire (film magazine)</target><part>Empire</part></link></italics><space/>magazine stated the film's &quot;reputation was deserved&quot;, writing that the film was impressive considering its low budget and the cast's inexperienced nature. He commented that the film successfully blended the &quot;bizarre&quot; combination of<space/><italics>Night of the Living Dead</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Texas Chain Saw Massacre</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics>The Three Stooges</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Empire Staff</arg><arg name="url">http://www.empireonline.com/reviews/reviewcomplete.asp?DVDID</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead</arg><arg name="work">[[Empire (film magazine)|Empire]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Bauer Media Group]]</arg><arg name="date">2007-09-24</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-31</arg></template></extension><space/>A reviewer for<space/><link><target>Film4</target></link><space/>rated<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>four-and-a-half stars out of five, musing that the film was &quot;energetic, original and icky&quot; and concluding that Raimi's &quot;splat-stick debut is a tight little horror classic that deserves its cult reputation, despite the best efforts of the censors.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.film4.com/reviews/1983/the-evil-dead<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead review<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[Film4]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Channel Four Television Corporation]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-10-11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Slant Magazine</target></link>'s Ed Gonzales compared the film to<space/><link><target>Dario Argento</target></link>'s work, citing Raimi's &quot;unnerving wide angle work&quot; as an important factor to the film's atmosphere. He mused that Raimi possessed an &quot;almost unreal ability to suggest the presence of intangible evil&quot;, which was what prevented the movie from being &quot;B-movie schlock&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gonzales, Ed (2002-03-06).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.slantmagazine.com/film/review/the-evil-dead/112'>Review: ''The Evil Dead''</link>.<space/><link><target>Slant Magazine</target></link>. Retrieved on 2010-11-20.</extension><space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>critic Martyn Glanville awarded the film four stars out of five, writing that for Raimi, it served as a better debut film than Tobe Hooper's<space/><italics>The Texas Chainsaw Massacre</italics><space/>or<space/><link><target>Wes Craven</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Last House on the Left (1972 film)</target><part>The Last House on the Left</part></link></italics>. Glanville noted that other than the &quot;ill-advised trees-that-rape scene&quot;, the film is &quot;one of the great modern horror films, an even more impressive when one considers its modest production values.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Glanville</arg><arg name="first">Martyn</arg><arg name="date">2001-03-05</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2001/03/02/the_evil_dead_1982_review.shtml</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20010305142803/http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2001/03/02/the_evil_dead_1982_review.shtml</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead (1982)</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC]]</arg><arg name="archivedate">2001-03-05</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>AMC (TV channel)</target><part>Filmcritic.com</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Christopher Null</target></link><space/>gave the film the same rating as Glanville, writing that &quot;Raimi's biggest grossout is schlock horror done the right way&quot; and comparing it to Romero's<space/><italics>Night of the Living Dead</italics><space/>in its ability to create stark atmosphere.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Null</arg><arg name="first">Christopher</arg><arg name="date">2001-01-01</arg><arg name="url">http://movies.amctv.com/movie/1983/The+Evil+Dead</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead (1983)</arg><arg name="publisher">[[AMC (TV channel)|Filmcritic.com]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>Chicago Reader</target></link></italics><space/>writer Pat Graham commented that the film featured several &quot;clever&quot; turns on the standard horror formula, adding that Raimi's &quot;anything-for-an-effect enthusiasm pays off in lots of formally inventive bits.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Graham</arg><arg name="first">Pat</arg><arg name="date">2001-01-01</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chicagoreader.com/chicago/the-evil-dead/Film?oid</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead</arg><arg name="publisher">Wrapports</arg><arg name="work">[[Chicago Reader]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>The make-up effects in one of the final scenes was called &quot;amazing&quot; by<space/><italics><link><target>Time Out (magazine)</target><part>Time Out</part></link></italics><space/>critic Stephen Garrett, who commented that although the film was light on character development, the &quot;relentless&quot; barrage of violent imagery made for an entertaining film.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Graham</arg><arg name="first">Pat</arg><arg name="date">2005-01-26</arg><arg name="url">http://www.timeout.com/film/reviews/64080/the_evil_dead.html</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead (1981)</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Time Out (company)|Time Out]]</arg><arg name="work">''[[Time Out (magazine)|Time Out]]''<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>The same site later cited the film as the 41st greatest horror movie ever made.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Staff</arg><arg name="url">http://www.timeout.com/london/feature/2420/100-best-horror-films-the-list/6</arg><arg name="title">The 100 best horror films</arg><arg name="publisher">Time Out</arg><arg name="work">Time Out<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>Phelim O'Neill of<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics><space/>combined<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>and its sequel<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead II</target></link></italics><space/>and listed them as the 23rd best horror film ever made, announcing that the former film &quot;stands above its mostly forgotten peers in the 80s horror boom.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>O'Neill, Phelim (2010-10-22).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/film/2010/oct/22/evil-dead-raimi-horror'>The Evil Dead/Evil Dead II: No 23 best horror film of all time</link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics>. Retrieved on 2010-11-19.</extension><space/><italics><link><target>Complex Magazine</target></link></italics><space/>composed a list of the twenty-five best horror movies available on<space/><link><target>Netflix</target></link>, listing<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>at No. 21.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Complex"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Barone, Matt</arg><arg name="title">The 25 Best Horror Movies Streaming On Netflix Right Now</arg><arg name="url">http://www.complex.com/pop-culture/2012/06/the-25-best-horror-movies-streaming-on-netflix-right-now/the-evil-dead</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Complex Magazine]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-12-30</arg><arg name="date">2012-06-22</arg></template></extension><space/>Don Summer, in his book<space/><italics>Horror Movie Freak</italics>, and writer Kate Egan have both cited the film as a horror classic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="extra"><link><target>#Summer</target><part>Summer (2007)</part></link>, p. 165</extension></paragraph><paragraph>J.C. Maek III of<space/><italics><link><target>PopMatters</target></link></italics><space/>said, &quot;What is unquestionable is that the Raimis and their pals created a monster in<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>. It started as a disastrous failure to obtain a big break with a too long, too perilous shoot (note Campbells changing hairstyle in the various scenes of the one-day plot). The film went through name changes and bannings only to survive as not only 'the ultimate experience in grueling horror' but as an oft-imitated and cashed-in-on classic, with 30 years of positive reviews to prove it.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="PM"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bruce Campbell .jpg</target><part>alt=A man sitting at a table with a VHS on the table.</part><part><link><target>Bruce Campbell</target></link><space/>at a fan convention, signing a<space/><link><target>VHS</target></link><space/>copy of ''The Evil Dead''.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part></link>While<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>received a favorable critical opinion back when it was initially released, it failed to be established as a cultural standing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bloody"></extension><space/>It was, however, a box-office success, which led to Campbell and Raimi teaming up again for the release of another movie.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;161163</extension><space/>Joel Coen and his brother Ethan had collaborated as directors and released the film<space/><italics>Blood Simple</italics>, to critical acclaim.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#iek</target><part>iek (2000)</part></link>, p. 111</extension><space/>According to Campbell, Ethan, then an accountant, expressed surprise when the duo succeeded.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop"></extension><space/>The Coen brothers and Raimi collaborated on a screenplay, which was released shortly after<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>. The film,<space/><italics><link><target>Crimewave</target></link></italics>, was a box-office failure.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop"></extension><space/>The film's production was a &quot;disaster&quot; according to Campbell, who stated that &quot;missteps&quot; like<space/><italics>Crimewave</italics><space/>usually lead to the end of a director's career.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop2"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 171</extension><space/>Other people involved with the film expressed similar disappointment with the project.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Paul</target><part>Paul (2007)</part></link>, p. 121</extension><space/>Fortunately, Raimi had the studio support to make a sequel to<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>, which he initially decided to make out of desperation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="flop2"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics><link><target>Evil Dead II</target></link></italics><space/>was filmed and released in 1987, and was also a box-office success.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 101</extension><space/>A second, and currently final, sequel was released in 1993,<space/><italics><link><target>Army of Darkness</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 152</extension><space/>Campbell returned as the lead character Ash Williams in both films.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sequel"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced4"></extension><space/>At that time, Raimi had become a successful director, attracting Hollywood's interest.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sequel"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 207</extension><space/>His 1990<space/><link><target>superhero film</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Darkman</target></link></italics><space/>was another box-office success, which led to an increased budget for<space/><italics>Army of Darkness</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced4"><link><target>#Konow</target><part>Konow (2012)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;429434</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Harris</target><part>Harris (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;5152</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 138</extension><space/><italics>Army of Darkness</italics><space/>had 22.8 times the budget of the original<space/><italics>Evil Dead</italics>, though it was not considered to be a box-office success like its two predecessors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sequel"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;217218</extension><space/><italics>Evil Dead II</italics><space/>received general acclaim from critics and is often considered to be better than the original, and<space/><italics>Army of Darkness</italics><space/>received mostly positive reviews.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced4"></extension><space/>The series has often attracted attention because each sequel featured more comedic qualities than the last, progressing into &quot;weirder&quot; territory with each film.<extension extension_name='ref' name="reinforced4"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unofficial sequels were also made in Italywhere the film was known as<space/><italics>La Casa</italics><space/>(&quot;The House&quot;)by<space/><link><target>Joe D'Amato</target></link>'s Filmirage. In 1988, D'Amato produced two films labeled as sequels to<space/><italics>Evil Dead II</italics>,<space/><link><target>Umberto Lenzi</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Ghosthouse</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>La Casa 3</italics>), and<space/><italics><link><target>Witchery (film)</target><part>Witchery</part></link></italics><space/>(<italics>La Casa 4</italics>), starring<space/><link><target>Linda Blair</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>David Hasselhoff</target></link>. In 1990, D'Amato produced his final<space/><italics>La Casa</italics><space/>film,<space/><italics><link><target>Beyond Darkness</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>La Casa 5</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="PM"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Erotismo, orrore e pornografia secondo Joe D'Amato</arg><arg name="language">Italian</arg><arg name="page">168</arg><arg name="first">Gordiano</arg><arg name="last">Lupi</arg><arg name="publisher">Mondo Ignoto</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">88-89084-49-9</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>House II: The Second Story</target><part>House II</part></link></italics><space/>was reissued in Italy as<space/><italics>La Casa 6</italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>The Horror Show</target></link></italics><space/>was then released in Italy as<space/><italics>La Casa 7</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PM"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work">[[PopMatters]]</arg><arg name="title">Books of the Dead: The Followers and Clones of 'The Evil Dead'</arg><arg name="first">J.C.</arg><arg name="last">Maçek III</arg><arg name="date">2013-04-26</arg><arg name="url">http://www.popmatters.com/pm/column/170551-books-of-the-dead-the-followers-and-clones-of-the-evil-dead/</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>and its sequels have become one of the largest<space/><link><target>cult film</target></link><space/><link><target>Film trilogy</target><part>trilogies</part></link><space/>in history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 319</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cult"></extension><space/>David Lavery, in his book<space/><italics>The Essential Cult TV Reader</italics>, surmised that Campbell's &quot;career is a practical guide to becoming a cult idol&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cult"><link><target>#Lavery</target><part>Lavery (2009)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;217218</extension><space/>The film launched the careers of Raimi and Campbell, who have since collaborated frequently.<extension extension_name='ref' name="spiderman"></extension><space/>Raimi has worked with Campbell in virtually all of his films since, and Campbell has appeared in cameo roles in all three of Raimi's<space/><link><target>Spider-Man in film</target><part>''Spider-Man'' films</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="spiderman"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, p. 337</extension><space/>which have become some of the highest-grossing films in history.<extension extension_name='ref' name="spiderman"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BOMINT"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.boxofficemojo.com/movies/?page</arg><arg name="title">Spider-Man (2002) - International Box Office Results<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Box Office Mojo]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-08<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Though it has often been considered an odd choice for Raimia director known for his violent horror filmsto direct a family-friendly franchise, the hiring was mostly inspired by Raimi's passion for the comic books as a kid.<extension extension_name='ref' name="spiderman"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="HBO"><template><target>cite video</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[HBO]] Making-Of ''[[Spider-Man (2002 film)|Spider-Man]]''<space/></arg><arg name="medium"><space/>DVD<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sony<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2002</arg></template></extension><space/>Raimi returned to the horror-comedy genre in 2009 with<space/><italics><link><target>Drag Me to Hell</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ebert</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Roger</arg><arg name="title"><space/>'Drag Me to Hell' Review</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://rogerebert.suntimes.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2009-06-03</arg><arg name="work"><space/>[[Chicago Sun Times]]</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-06-28</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Critics have often compared Campbell's later performances to his role in<space/><italics>Evil Dead</italics>, which has been called his defining role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EVIL"><link><target>#Kenneth Muir</target><part>Kenneth Muir (2004)</part></link>, p. 112</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BLEND"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Wharton, David<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cinemablend.com/dvdnews/FlixWorthy-Celebrates-Ash-Wednesday-With-Best-Streaming-Bruce-Campbell-30581.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">FlixWorthy Celebrates Ash Wednesday With The Best Of Streaming Bruce Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="work">Cinema Blend</arg><arg name="publisher">Joshua Tyler<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-03-09</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-11-28</arg></template></extension><space/>Campbell's performance as Ash has been compared to roles ranging from his performance of<space/><link><target>Elvis Presley</target></link><space/>in the film<space/><italics><link><target>Bubba Ho-tep</target></link></italics><space/>to the bigamous demon in the<space/><italics><link><target>The X-Files</target></link></italics><space/>episode &quot;<link><target>Terms of Endearment (The X-Files)</target><part>Terms of Endearment</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sixth"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Seghers, Christine<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ca.ign.com/articles/2008/07/18/top-10-x-files-guest-stars?page</arg><arg name="title">Top 10 X-Files Guest Stars<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[IGN]]</arg><arg name="publisher">[[News Corporation]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-07-17</arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-08-11</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Russell</arg><arg name="first">Jamie</arg><arg name="date">2001-10-04</arg><arg name="title">Bubba Ho-Tep (2004)</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/films/2004/09/20/bubba_ho_tep_2004_review.shtml</arg></template></extension><space/>Campbell's fan base gradually developed after the release of<space/><italics>Evil Dead II</italics><space/>and his short-lived series<space/><italics><link><target>The Adventures of Brisco County, Jr.</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fan"></extension><space/>He is a regular favorite at most fan conventions and often draws sold-out auditoriums at his public appearances.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Lowry</target><part>Lowry (1995)</part></link>, pp.1921</extension><space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>developed a substantial cult following throughout the years, and has often been cited as a defining cult classic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="stacks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="fan"><link><target>#Campbell</target><part>Campbell (2002)</part></link>, pp.&amp;nbsp;245248</extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>The Evil Dead</italics><space/>has spawned a media franchise. A video game adaptation<space/><link><target>The Evil Dead (video game)</target><part>of the same name</part></link><space/>was for the<space/><link><target>Commodore 64</target></link><space/>in 1984, as was a trilogy of<space/><link><target>PlayStation (console)</target><part>PlayStation</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>PlayStation 2</target></link><space/>games in the 1990s:<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead: Hail to the King</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead: A Fistful of Boomstick</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead: Regeneration</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="retro"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Horror Movie Licenses<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Retro Gamer]]<space/></arg><arg name="author">Staff<space/></arg><arg name="page">71<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2004</arg></template></extension><space/>Ted Raimi did voices for the trilogy, and Campbell returned as the voice of Ash. The character Ash became the main character of a<space/><link><target>Army of Darkness (comics)</target><part>comic book franchise</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="what"><link type='external' href='http://forum.newsarama.com/showthread.php?t=125014'>WW: Chicago - ''Freddy vs. Jason vs. Ash'' Coming in November</link>, 2007-08-12,<space/><link><target>Newsarama</target></link></extension><space/>Ash has fought both<space/><link><target>Freddy Krueger</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jason Voorhees</target></link><space/>in the<space/><italics><link><target>Freddy vs. Jason vs. Ash</target></link></italics><space/>series,<space/><link><target>Herbert West</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics>Army of Darkness vs. Re-Animator</italics>, zombie versions of the<space/><link><target>Marvel Comics</target></link><space/>superhero team<space/><italics><link><target>Avengers (comics)</target><part>Avengers</part></link></italics><space/>in<space/><italics>Marvel Zombies vs. The Army of Darkness</italics>, and has even saved the life of a<space/><link><target>Barack Obama in comics</target><part>fictional</part></link><space/><link><target>Barack Obama</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>Army of Darkness (comics)#Army of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama (#1-4)</target><part>Army of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="first">Kiel<space/></arg><arg name="last">Phegley</arg><arg name="date">2009-05-27</arg><arg name="url">http://splashpage.mtv.com/2009/05/27/army-of-darkness-ash-saves-obama-artist-todd-nauck-on-spider-man-barack-celebrity-team-ups/</arg><arg name="title">'Army Of Darkness: Ash Saves Obama' Artist Todd Nauck On Spider-Man, Barack & Celebrity Team-Ups</arg><arg name="publisher">[[MTV]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="date">2007-03-27</arg><arg name="url">http://marvel.com/news/story/922/marvel_zombies_vs_army_of_darkness_1_goes_back_to_press</arg><arg name="title">Marvel Zombies vs. Army of Darkness #1 Goes Back to Press</arg><arg name="publisher">Marvel.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>In January 2008,<space/><link><target>Dark Horse Comics</target></link><space/>began releasing a four-part monthly comic book<space/><link><target>Limited series</target><part>mini-series</part></link>, written by<space/><link><target>Mark Verheiden</target></link><space/>and drawn by<space/><link><target>John Bolton (comics)</target><part>John Bolton</part></link>, based on<space/><italics>The Evil Dead</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.heroesassemble.com/the-evil-dead-1-movie-adaptation-dark-horse-comics-1606-p.asp</arg><arg name="title">The Evil Dead #1 Movie Adaptation Dark Horse Comics</arg><arg name="publisher">Hero Assemble</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-07-12</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In addition, the film has inspired a<space/><link><target>Broadway musical</target><part>stage musical</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Evil Dead: The Musical</target></link></italics>, which was produced with the permission of Raimi and Campbell. The musical has run on and off since its inception in 2003.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HoboTrashCan"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Murphy</arg><arg name="first">Joel</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Hanging Around&nbsp;... Evil Dead: The Musical</arg><arg name="work"></arg><arg name="publisher">Hobo Trash</arg><arg name="date">November 2006</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.hobotrashcan.com/hangingaround/evildead.php</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2007-07-18</arg></template></extension><space/>A<space/><link><target>Evil Dead (2013 film)</target><part>remake</part></link><space/>of the film was released in 2013, directed by Fede Alvarez and produced by Raimi and Campbell. It features actress<space/><link><target>Jane Levy</target></link><space/>as the main character, with Ash not appearing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="evil"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Barton</arg><arg name="first">Steve</arg><arg name="title">Jane Levy Talks Evil Dead Remake<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.dreadcentral.com/news/54953/jane-levy-talks-evil-dead-remake</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-04-24</arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>[[Dread Central]]</arg><arg name="date">2012-04-24</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Fleming<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mike<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.deadline.com/2012/02/jane-levy-is-new-star-of-evil-dead-remake/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jane Levy Is New Star Of 'Evil Dead' Remake<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Deadline.com]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">2012-02-03<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-19</arg></template></extension><space/>Campbell does make a brief, uncredited<space/><link><target>cameo appearance</target></link><space/>at the end of the film in a short<space/><link><target>post-credits scene</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://insidemovies.ew.com/2013/03/09/evil-dead-sequel/</arg><arg name="date">2013-03-09</arg><arg name="title">'Evil Dead' director reveals sequel plans</arg><arg name="work">Entertainment Weekly</arg><arg name="first">James</arg><arg name="last">Hibberd</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-04-28</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2002
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Campbell
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bruce
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>If Chins Could Kill: Confessions of a B Movie Actor
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>L.A. Weekly Books
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-312-29145-7
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Campbell</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lamberson
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Gregory
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cheap Scares!: Low Budget Horror Filmmakers Share Their Secrets
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McFarland
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7864-3706-1
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Lamberson</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2010
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Winston Dixon
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Wheeler
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A History of Horror 
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Rutgers University Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8135-4796-1
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Lamberson</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Becker
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Josh
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Complete Guide to Low-Budget Feature Filmmaking
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Point Blank
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8095-5690-8
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Becker</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2004
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>John
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Kenneth Muir
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Unseen Force: the Films of Sam Raimi
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Applause Theatre & Cinema Books
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-55783-607-6
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Kenneth Muir</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2010
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robson
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Eddie
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Coen Brothers (Virgin Film)
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Virgin Books
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7535-1268-5
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Eddie</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>John
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Kenneth Muir
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Horror Films of the 1980s
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Virgin Books
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7864-2821-2
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Kenneth Muir2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>1987
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eric
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Pooley
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Warped in America: The Dark Visions of Joel and Ethan Coen
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[New York Magazine]] 
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7864-2821-2
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Pooley</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2000
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bill
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Warren
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Evil Dead Companion
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Titan Books
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-84023-187-4
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Warren</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>R. Collings
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Films of Stephen King: From Carrie to Secret Window
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Palgrave Macmillan
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-230-60131-4
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>R. Collings</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kate 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Egan
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Evil Dead
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wallflower Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-906660-34-5
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Egan</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>R Collings
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Scaring Us to Death: The Impact of Stephen King on Popular Culture
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Borgo Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-930261-37-5
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>R Collings</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2000
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>David
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Kerekes
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>See No Evil: Banned Films and Video Controversy
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Critical Vision
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-900486-10-1
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Kerekes</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2004
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Steffen 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Hantke
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>University Press of Mississippi
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Critical Vision
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-57806-692-6
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Hantke</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2004
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mendik 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Xavier
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alternative Europe: Eurotrash and Exploitation Cinema Since 1945
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wallflower Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-903364-93-2
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Hantke</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2012
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bruce
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>F. Kawin
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Horror and the Horror Film (New Perspectives on World Cinema)
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Anthem Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-85728-450-1
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Hantke</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2005
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Janet
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Staiger
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Media Reception Studies 
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[NYU Press]]
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8147-8135-7
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Staiger</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>1997
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Angus
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Finney
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Egos Have Landed: Rise and Fall of Palace Pictures
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Arrow Books Ltd
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7493-1946-5
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Finney</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2001
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Steve
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Chibnall
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>British Horror Cinema
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-415-23004-9
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Chibnall</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2011
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kim
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Newman
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nightmare Movies: Horror on Screen Since the 1960s
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Bloomsbury Publishing
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-4088-0503-9
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Newman</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2005
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Lynn
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Schofield Clark
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>From Angels to Aliens: Teenagers, the Media, and the Supernatural
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Oxford University Press]]
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-530023-9
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Schofield Clark</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Don
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Summer
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Horror Movie Freak
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Unknown Binding
</arg><arg name="asin"><space/>B004434G7M
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Summer</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2000
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Slavoj
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Žižek
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Ticklish Subject: The Absent Centre of Political Ontology
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Verso
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-85984-291-1
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Žižek</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2007
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Louis 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Paul
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tales from the Cult Film Trenches: Interviews with 36 Actors from Horror, Science Fiction and Exploitation Cinema
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McFarland & Company
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-7864-2994-3
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Paul</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2002
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>J. P. Harris
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Harris
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Time Capsule: Reviews of horror, science fiction and fantasy films and TV shows from 1987 to 1991
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>iUniverse
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-595-21336-8
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Harris</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2009
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>David 
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lavery
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Essential Cult TV Reader (Essential Readers in Contemporary Media)
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The University Press of Kentucky
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-8131-2568-8
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Lavery</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>1995
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Brian
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Lowry
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Truth is Out There: The Official Guide to the X-Files
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Harper Prism 5
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-06-105330-6
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Lowry</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Glenn
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Kay
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Zombie Movies: The Ultimate Guide
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Chicago Review Press
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-55652-770-8
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Kay</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2008
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>David Konow
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Konow
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Reel Terror: The Scary, Bloody, Gory, Hundred-Year History of Classic Horror Films
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[St. Martin's Press]]
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-312-66883-X
</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>Kay</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.deadites.net/the-evil-dead-films/the-evil-dead/'>The Evil Dead</link></italics><space/>at Deadites Online.</listitem><listitem><template><target>IMDb title</target><arg>0083907</arg><arg>The Evil Dead</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>mojo title</target><arg>evildead</arg><arg>The Evil Dead</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Rotten Tomatoes</target><arg>the-evil-dead</arg><arg>The Evil Dead</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Evil Dead</target></template><template><target>Sam Raimi</target></template><template><target>Bruce Campbell</target></template><template><target>Renaissance Pictures</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Good article</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Evil Dead</target></template><link><target>Category:The Evil Dead (franchise) films</target><part>1 1981</part></link><link><target>Category:1981 films</target></link><link><target>Category:1981 horror films</target></link><link><target>Category:American films</target></link><link><target>Category:American horror films</target></link><link><target>Category:English-language films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films directed by Sam Raimi</target></link><link><target>Category:Directorial debut films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films shot in Michigan</target></link><link><target>Category:Films shot in Tennessee</target></link><link><target>Category:Films set in Tennessee</target></link><link><target>Category:Haunted house films</target></link><link><target>Category:Splatter films</target></link><link><target>Category:Films using stop-motion animation</target></link><link><target>Category:Supernatural horror films</target></link><link><target>Category:Renaissance Pictures productions</target></link><link><target>Category:New Line Cinema films</target></link><link><target>Category:Demons in film</target></link><link><target>Category:Features based on short films</target></link></paragraph></article>