<article title='Politics_of_Equatorial_Guinea'><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template><template><target>Politics of Equatorial Guinea</target></template>The<space/><bold>politics of<space/><link><target>Equatorial Guinea</target></link></bold><space/>take place in a framework of a<space/><link><target>presidential system</target><part>presidential</part></link><space/><link><target>republic</target></link>, whereby the<space/><link><target>President of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>President</part></link><space/>is both the<space/><link><target>head of state</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>head of government</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Executive power</target></link><space/>is exercised by the government.<space/><link><target>Legislative power</target></link><space/>is vested in both the government and the<space/><link><target>Chamber of People's Representatives</target></link><space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ek.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">CIA World Factbook: Equatorial Guinea - Government<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Central Intelligence Agency]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-03-20<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-12</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Book of Rule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Dorling Kindersley]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>282</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political conditions</heading><paragraph>In the period following Spain's grant of local<space/><link><target>autonomy</target></link><space/>to Equatorial Guinea in 1963, there was a great deal of political party activity.<space/><link><target>Bubi people</target><part>Bubi</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Fernandino peoples</target><part>Fernandino</part></link><space/>parties on the island preferred separation from<space/><link><target>Ro Muni</target></link><space/>or a loose federation. Ethnically based parties in Ro Muni favored independence for a united country comprising Bioko and Ro Muni, an approach that ultimately won out. (The<space/><link><target>Movement for the Self-Determination of Bioko Island</target></link><space/>(MAIB) which advocates independence for the island under Bubi control, is one of the offshoots of the era immediately preceding independence).</paragraph><paragraph>Equatorial Guinea became officially independent from Spain on October 12, 1968. Since then, the country has had<space/><link><target>Heads of State of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>two presidents</part></link>:<space/><link><target>Francisco Macas Nguema</target></link>, the former mayor of<space/><link><target>Mongomo</target></link><space/>under the Spanish colonial government, and<space/><link><target>Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo</target></link><space/>(Macas's nephew), who has ruled since 1979 when he staged a military<space/><link><target>coup d'tat</target></link><space/>and executed Macas.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1982 constitution of Equatorial Guinea gives Obiang extensive powers, including naming and dismissing members of the cabinet, making laws by decree, dissolving the Chamber of Representatives, negotiating and ratifying treaties and calling legislative elections. Obiang retains his role as<space/><link><target>commander-in-chief</target></link><space/>of the armed forces and minister of defense, and he maintains close supervision of the military activity. The Prime Minister is appointed by the President and operates under powers designated by the President. The Prime Minister coordinates government activities in areas other than foreign affairs, national defense and security.</paragraph><paragraph>After the accession of Macas to power, political activity largely ceased in Equatorial Guinea. Opposition figures who lived among the exile communities in Spain and elsewhere agitated for reforms; some of them had been employed in the Macas and Obiang governments. After political activities in Equatorial Guinea were legalized in the early 1990s, some opposition leaders returned to test the waters, but repressive actions have continued sporadically.</paragraph><paragraph>With the prodding of the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link>, and other donor countries, the government undertook an electoral census in 1995. Freely contested municipal elections, the country's first, were held in September. Most observers agree that the elections themselves were relatively free and transparent and that the opposition parties garnered between two-thirds and three-quarters of the total vote. The government delayed announcement of the results and then claimed a highly dubious 52% victory overall and the capture of 19 of 27 municipal councils. Malabo's council went to the opposition. In early January 1996 Obiang called presidential elections to be held in six weeks. The campaign was marred by allegations of fraud, and most of the other candidates withdrew in the final week. Obiang claimed re-election with 98% of the vote. International observers agreed the election was not free or fair. In an attempt to molify his critics, Obiang announced his new cabinet, giving minor portfolios to some people identified by the government as being opposition figures.</paragraph><paragraph>Since independence, the two Presidents (Macas and Obiang) have been the dominant political forces in Equatorial Guinea. Since 1979, President Obiang has been constrained only by a need to maintain a consensus among his advisers and political supporters, most of whom are drawn from the Nguema family in Mongomo, in the eastern part of Ro Muni. The Nguema family is part of the Esangui subclan of the Fang. Alleged coup attempts in 1981 and 1983 raised little sympathy among the populace.</paragraph><paragraph>President Obiang's rule, during which schools were permitted to reopen and primary education expanded, and public utilities and roads restored, compares favorably with Macas' tyranny and terror. It has been criticized for not implementing genuine democratic reforms. Corruption and a dysfunctional judicial system disrupt the development of Equatorial Guinea's economy and society. In March 2001 the President appointed a new Prime Minister, Cndido Muatetema Rivas, and replaced several ministers perceived to be especially corrupt. However, the government budget still does not include all revenues and expenditures. The United Nations Development Programme has proposed a broad governance reform program, but the Equatorial Guinean Government has not moved rapidly to implement it.</paragraph><paragraph>Although Equatorial Guinea lacks a well-established democratic tradition comparable to the developed democracies of the West, it has progressed toward developing a participatory political system out of the anarchic, chaotic, and repressive conditions of the Macias years. In power since 1979, the Obiang government has made little progress in stimulating the economy. Extremely serious health and sanitary conditions persist, and the educational system remains in desperate condition. Although the abuses and atrocities that characterized the Macias years have been eliminated, effective rule of law does not exist. Religious freedom is tolerated.</paragraph><paragraph>On December 15, 2002,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://allafrica.com/stories/200212160112.html'>allAfrica.com: Equatorial Guinea: Obiang Sure to Win As Opposition Quits Poll (Page 1 of 1)</link></extension><space/>Equatorial Guinea's four main opposition parties withdrew from the country's presidential election. Obiang won an election widely considered fraudulent by members of the western press.</paragraph><paragraph>According to a March 2004<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>profile,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/3516588.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Profile: Equatorial Guinea's great survivor<space/></arg><arg name="date">2004-03-17<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-05-22<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="last">Shaxson</arg></template></extension><space/>politics within the country are currently dominated by tensions between Obiang's son Teodoro (known by the nickname<space/><italics>Teodorn</italics>, meaning Little Teodoro), and other close relatives with powerful positions in the security forces. The tension may be rooted in a power shift arising from the dramatic increase since 1997 in oil production.</paragraph><paragraph>A November 2004 report<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.theguardian.com/uk/mark-thatcher?page</arg><arg name="title">Mark Thatcher</arg><arg name="work">The Guardian</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 May 2014<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>named<space/><link><target>Mark Thatcher</target></link><space/>as a financial backer of a March 2004 attempt to topple Obiang organized by<space/><link><target>Simon Mann</target></link>. Various accounts also name the UK's<space/><link><target>MI6</target></link>, the US<space/><link><target>Central Intelligence Agency</target></link>, and Spain as having been tacit supporters of the coup attempt.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/8830120/MI6-knew-about-Equatorial-Guinea-coup-plot-leader-claims.html</arg><arg name="title">MI6 knew about Equatorial Guinea coup plot, leader claims</arg><arg name="work">The Telegraph</arg><arg name="first">Martin<space/></arg><arg name="last">Evans</arg><arg name="date">16 October 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Nevertheless, an Amnesty International report on the ensuing trial highlights the government's failure to demonstrate in court that the alleged coup attempt had ever actually taken place.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.amnesty.org.uk/press-releases/equatorial-guinea-new-report-shows-trial-alleged-mercenary-coup-plotters-unfair</arg><arg name="title">Equatorial Guinea: New report shows trial of alleged 'mercenary coup plotters' unfair<space/></arg><arg name="work">Amnesty International</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 May 2014</arg><arg name="date">7 June 2005</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Executive branch</heading><paragraph><template><target>office-table</target></template>|<link><target>Heads of state of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>President</part></link>|<link><target>Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo</target></link>|<link><target>Democratic Party of Equatorial Guinea</target></link>|3 August 1979|-|<link><target>Heads of government of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>Prime Minister</part></link>|<link><target>Vicente Ehate Tomi</target></link>|<link><target>Democratic Party of Equatorial Guinea</target></link>|21 May 2012|}The 1982 constitution of Equatorial Guinea gives the President extensive powers, including naming and dismissing members of the cabinet, making laws by decree, dissolving the Chamber of Representatives, negotiating and ratifying treaties and calling legislative elections. The President retains his role as commander in chief of the armed forces and minister of defense, and he maintains close supervision of the military activity. The Prime Minister is appointed by the President and operates under powers designated by the President. The Prime Minister coordinates government activities in areas other than foreign affairs, national defense and security.<link><target>Teodoro Obiang Nguema Mbasogo</target></link><space/>seized power in a military coup. He is elected by popular vote to a seven-year term.</paragraph><paragraph>Another official branch of the government is the State Council. The State Council's main function is to serve as caretaker in case of death or physical incapacity of the President. It comprises the following ex officio members: the President of the Republic, the Prime Minister, the Minister of Defense, the President of the National Assembly and the Chairman of the Social and Economic Council.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Legislative branch</heading><paragraph><template><target>Unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template>The<space/><link><target>House of People's Representatives of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>Chamber of People's Representatives</part></link><space/>(<italics>Cmara de Representantes del Pueblo</italics>) has 100 members, elected for a five-year term by<space/><link><target>proportional representation</target></link><space/>in multi-member<space/><link><target>constituency</target><part>constituencies</part></link>. Equatorial Guinea is a<space/><link><target>One party dominant state</target></link>. This means that only one political party, the<space/><link><target>Democratic Party of Equatorial Guinea</target></link>, is in fact allowed to hold effective power. Although minor<space/><link><target>political parties</target><part>parties</part></link><space/>are allowed, they are de facto required to accept the leadership of the dominant party.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Political parties and elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>elect</target><arg>List of political parties in Equatorial Guinea</arg><arg>Elections in Equatorial Guinea</arg></template><template><target>Equatorial Guinean presidential election, 2002</target></template><template><target>Equatorial Guinean parliamentary election, 2004</target></template><template><target>Equatorial Guinean elections</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Judicial branch</heading><paragraph><template><target>Unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">December 2008</arg></template>The judicial system follows similar administrative levels. At the top are the President and his judicial advisors (the Supreme Court). In descending rank are the appeals courts, chief judges for the divisions, and local magistrates. Tribal laws and customs are honored in the formal court system when not in conflict with national law. The court system, which often uses customary law, is a combination of traditional, civil, and military justice, and it operates in an ad hoc manner for lack of established procedures and experienced judicial personnel.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Administrative divisions</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:EquatorialGuineaConsHouston.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A politician's image appears in the entrance to the<space/><link><target>Diplomatic missions of Equatorial Guinea</target><part>Consulate-General of Equatorial Guinea in Houston</part></link>, a diplomatic complex in an office building in<space/><link><target>Houston</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United States</target></link></part></link>Equatorial Guinea is divided in seven provinces (provincias, singular - provincia); Annobon, Bioko Norte, Bioko Sur, Centro Sur, Kie-Ntem, Litoral, Wele-Nzas.The President appoints the governors of the seven provinces. Each province is divided administratively into districts and municipalities. The internal administrative system falls under the Ministry of Territorial Administration; several other ministries are represented at the provincial and district levels.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Membership in international organizations</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>ACCT,<space/><link><target>Agency for the French-Speaking Community</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ACP,<space/><link><target>African, Caribbean, and Pacific Group of States</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>AfDB,<space/><link><target>African Development Bank</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>BDEAC,<space/><link><target>Central African States Development Bank</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>CEEAC,<space/><link><target>Economic Community of Central African States</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ECA,<space/><link><target>Economic Commission for Africa</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>FAO,<space/><link><target>Food and Agriculture Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>FZ,<space/><link><target>Franc Zone</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>G-77,<space/><link><target>Group of 77</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IBRD,<space/><link><target>International Bank for Reconstruction and Development</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ICAO,<space/><link><target>International Civil Aviation Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ICRM,<space/><link><target>International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IDA,<space/><link><target>International Development Association</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IFAD,<space/><link><target>International Fund for Agricultural Development</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IFC,<space/><link><target>International Finance Corporation</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IFRCS,<space/><link><target>International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ILO,<space/><link><target>International Labour Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IMF,<space/><link><target>International Monetary Fund</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IMO,<space/><link><target>International Maritime Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>Intelsat,<space/><link><target>International Telecommunications Satellite Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>Interpol,<space/><link><target>International Criminal Police Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>IOC,<space/><link><target>International Olympic Committee</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>ITU,<space/><link><target>International Telecommunication Union</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>NAM,<space/><link><target>Non-Aligned Movement</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>OAS; (observer),<space/><link><target>Organization of American States</target></link></listitem><listitem>OAU,<space/><link><target>Organization of African Unity</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>OPCW,<space/><link><target>Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>UDEAC,<space/><link><target>Central African Customs and Economic Union</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>UN,<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>UNCTAD,<space/><link><target>United Nations Conference on Trade and Development</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>UNESCO,<space/><link><target>UNESCO</target><part>United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization</part></link>,</listitem><listitem>UNIDO,<space/><link><target>United Nations Industrial Development Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>UPU,<space/><link><target>Universal Postal Union</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>WHO,<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>WIPO,<space/><link><target>World Intellectual Property Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>WToO,<space/><link><target>World Tourism Organization</target></link>,</listitem><listitem>WTrO;(applicant),<space/><link><target>World Trade Organization</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.guinea-ecuatorial.org/'>Gobierno en el Exilio de Guinea Ecuatorial</link><space/>Official website of the Equatorial Guinea Government in Exile<space/><template><target>es icon</target></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further viewing</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Once Upon a Coup</italics>,<space/><link><target>PBS</target></link><space/>Documentary, August 2009,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wnet/wideangle/episodes/once-upon-a-coup/full-episode/?p=5496'></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Politics of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Equatorial Guinea</target></template><link><target>Category:Politics of Equatorial Guinea</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>