<article title='Art'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the general concept of art</arg><arg>the group of creative disciplines</arg><arg>The arts</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Art (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>pp-semi-indef</target></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:Art-portrait-collage 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.5</part><part>Clockwise from upper left: a<space/><link><target>self-portrait</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Vincent van Gogh</target></link>; a female ancestor figure by a<space/><link><target>Chokwe people</target><part>Chokwe</part></link><space/>artist; detail from the ''<link><target>The Birth of Venus (Botticelli)</target><part>Birth of Venus</part></link>'' by<space/><link><target>Sandro Botticelli</target></link>; and an Okinawan<space/><link><target>Shisa</target><part>Shisa lion</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Art</bold><space/>is a diverse range of<space/><link><target>human behavior</target><part>human activities</part></link><space/>and the products of those activities, usually involving imaginative or technical skill. In their most general form these activities include the production of works of art, the criticism of art, the study of the history of art, and the aesthetic dissemination of art. This article focuses primarily on the<space/><link><target>visual arts</target></link>, which includes the creation of images or objects in fields including painting, sculpture,<space/><link><target>printmaking</target></link>, photography, and other visual media. Architecture is often included as one of the visual arts; however, like the<space/><link><target>decorative arts</target></link>, it involves the creation of objects where the practical considerations of use are essentialin a way that they usually are not in a painting, for example. Music, theatre, film, dance, and other<space/><link><target>performing arts</target></link>, as well as literature and other media such as<space/><link><target>interactive media</target></link>, are included in a broader definition of art or<space/><link><target>the arts</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Art, n. 1&quot;. OED Online. December 2011. Oxford University Press. http://www.oed.com. (Accessed 26 February 2012.);<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/art</arg><arg name="title">Definition of art</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford Dictionaries</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 January 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Until the 17th century,<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>referred to any skill or mastery and was not differentiated from<space/><link><target>craft</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>sciences</target></link>. In modern usage after the 17th century, where aesthetic considerations are paramount, the fine arts are separated and distinguished from acquired skills in general, such as the decorative or<space/><link><target>applied arts</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Art may be characterized in terms of<space/><link><target>mimesis</target></link><space/>(its representation of reality), expression, communication of emotion, or other qualities. During the<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target><part>Romantic period</part></link>, art came to be seen as &quot;a special faculty of the human mind to be classified with religion and science&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Gombrich, Ernst.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.gombrich.co.uk/showdoc.php?id</arg><arg name="title">Press statement on The Story of Art<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">18 November 2008<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Gombrich Archive</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20081006212330/http://www.gombrich.co.uk/showdoc.php?id</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>6 October 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Though the definition of what constitutes art is disputed<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Definition of Art<space/></arg><arg name="author">Stephen Davies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8014-9794-0</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Artworks: Definition, Meaning, Value<space/></arg><arg name="author">Robert Stecker<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pennsylvania State University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-271-01596-5</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Theories of Art Today<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Noël Carroll<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Wisconsin Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-299-16354-9</arg></template></extension><space/>and has changed over time, general descriptions mention an idea of imaginative or technical skill stemming from<space/><link><target>Agency (philosophy)</target><part>human agency</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ubc.ca/okanagan/creative/links/arthistory/What_is_Art_.html'>What Is Art?</link><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>and creation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="britannica.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/630806/art</arg><arg name="title">art</arg><arg name="work">Encyclopedia Britannica</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The nature of art, and related concepts such as<space/><link><target>creativity</target></link><space/>and interpretation, are explored in a branch of philosophy known as<space/><link><target>aesthetics</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kennick, William ed,<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><space/>and W. E. Kennick,<space/><italics>Art and philosophy : readings in aesthetics</italics><space/>New York: St. Martin's Press, 1979, pp. xixiii. ISBN 0-312-05391-6.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Creative art and fine art</heading><paragraph><template><target>wide image</target><arg>Wang Ximeng - A Thousand Li of River (Bridge).jpg</arg><arg>1250px</arg><arg>Works of art can tell stories or simply express an aesthetic truth or feeling. Panorama of a section of ''A Thousand Li of Mountains and Rivers'', a 12th-century painting by Song dynasty artist [[Wang Ximeng]].</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the perspective of the history of art,<extension extension_name='ref' name="britannica.com"></extension><space/>artistic works have existed for almost as long as humankind: from early<space/><link><target>pre-historic art</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>contemporary art</target></link>; however, some theories restrict the concept of &quot;artistic works&quot; to modern Western societies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Elkins, James &quot;Art History and Images That Are Not Art&quot;,<space/><italics>The Art Bulletin</italics>, Vol. 47, No. 4 (Dec. 1995), with previous bibliography. &quot;Non-Western images are not well described in terms of art, and neither are medieval paintings that were made in the absence of humanist ideas of artistic value&quot;. 553</extension><space/>One early sense of the definition of<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>is closely related to the older Latin meaning, which roughly translates to &quot;skill&quot; or &quot;craft,&quot; as associated with words such as &quot;artisan.&quot; English words derived from this meaning include<space/><italics>artifact</italics>,<space/><italics>artificial</italics>,<space/><italics>artifice</italics>,<space/><italics>medical arts</italics>, and<space/><italics>military arts</italics>. However, there are many other colloquial uses of the word, all with some relation to its<space/><link><target>etymology</target></link>.<link><target>File:Teke bottle.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>20th-century Rwandan bottle. Artistic works may serve practical functions, in addition to their decorative value.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Few modern scholars have been more divided than Plato and Aristotle on the question concerning the importance of art, with Aristotle strongly supporting art in general and Plato generally being opposed to its relative importance. Several dialogues in Plato tackle questions about art: Socrates says that poetry is inspired by the<space/><link><target>muses</target></link>, and is not rational. He speaks approvingly of this, and other forms of divine madness (drunkenness, eroticism, and dreaming) in the<space/><italics><link><target>Phaedrus (Plato)</target><part>Phaedrus</part></link><space/></italics>(265ac), and yet in the<space/><italics><link><target>Republic (Plato)</target><part>''Republic''</part></link></italics><space/>wants to outlaw Homer's great poetic art, and laughter as well. In<space/><italics><link><target>Ion (dialogue)</target><part>Ion</part></link></italics>, Socrates gives no hint of the disapproval of Homer that he expresses in the<space/><italics>Republic</italics>. The dialogue<space/><italics>Ion</italics><space/>suggests that<space/><link><target>Homer</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Iliad</target></link></italics><space/>functioned in the ancient Greek world as the Bible does today in the modern Christian world: as divinely inspired literary art that can provide moral guidance, if only it can be properly interpreted. With regards to the literary art and the musical arts, Aristotle considered<space/><link><target>epic poetry</target></link>, tragedy, comedy,<space/><link><target>Dithyramb</target><part>dithyrambic poetry</part></link><space/>and music to be<space/><link><target>Mimesis</target><part>mimetic</part></link><space/>or imitative art, each varying in imitation by medium, object, and manner.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle,<space/><italics>Poetics</italics><space/>I 1447a</extension><space/>For example, music imitates with the media of rhythm and harmony, whereas dance imitates with rhythm alone, and poetry with language. The forms also differ in their object of imitation. Comedy, for instance, is a dramatic imitation of men worse than average; whereas tragedy imitates men slightly better than average. Lastly, the forms differ in their manner of imitation through narrative or character, through change or no change, and through drama or no drama.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle,<space/><italics>Poetics</italics><space/>III</extension><space/>Aristotle believed that imitation is natural to mankind and constitutes one of mankind's advantages over animals.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle,<space/><italics>Poetics</italics><space/>IV</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second, and more recent, sense of the word<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>as an abbreviation for<space/><italics>creative art</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>fine art</italics><space/>emerged in the early 17th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Shorter Oxford English Dictionary</target><part>The New Shorter Oxford English Dictionary</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link></italics>, Oxford 1993, p.&amp;nbsp;120</extension><space/>Fine art refers to a skill used to express the artist's creativity, or to engage the audience's aesthetic sensibilities, or to draw the audience towards consideration of more refined or<space/><italics>finer</italics><space/>work of art.</paragraph><paragraph>Within this latter sense, the word<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>may refer to several things: (i) a study of a creative skill, (ii) a process of using the creative skill, (iii) a product of the creative skill, or (iv) the audience's experience with the creative skill. The creative arts (<italics>art</italics><space/>as discipline) are a collection of disciplines which produce<space/><italics>artworks</italics><space/>(<italics>art</italics><space/>as objects) that are compelled by a personal drive (art as activity) and convey a message, mood, or symbolism for the perceiver to interpret (art as experience). Art is something that stimulates an individual's thoughts, emotions, beliefs, or ideas through the senses. Works of art can be explicitly made for this purpose or interpreted on the basis of images or objects. For some scholars, such as<space/><link><target>Kant</target></link>, the sciences and the arts could be distinguished by taking science as representing the domain of knowledge and the arts as representing the domain of the freedom of artistic expression.</paragraph><paragraph>Often, if the skill is being used in a common or practical way, people will consider it a craft instead of art. Likewise, if the skill is being used in a commercial or industrial way, it may be considered<space/><link><target>commercial art</target></link><space/>instead of fine art. On the other hand, crafts and design are sometimes considered<space/><link><target>applied art</target></link>. Some art followers have argued that the difference between fine art and applied art has more to do with value judgments made about the art than any clear definitional difference.<extension extension_name='ref'>David Novitz, &quot;The Boundaries of Art&quot;, 1992</extension><space/>However, even fine art often has goals beyond pure creativity and self-expression. The purpose of works of art may be to communicate ideas, such as in politically, spiritually, or philosophically motivated art; to create a sense of beauty (see<space/><link><target>aesthetics</target></link>); to explore the nature of perception; for pleasure; or to generate strong<space/><link><target>emotion</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The purpose may also be seemingly nonexistent.</paragraph><paragraph>The nature of art has been described by philosopher<space/><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link><space/>as &quot;one of the most elusive of the traditional problems of human culture&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Wollheim,<space/><italics>Art and its objects</italics>, p.1, 2nd edn, 1980, Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-29706-0</extension><space/>Art has been defined as a vehicle for the expression or communication of emotions and ideas, a means for exploring and appreciating<space/><link><target>Formalism (art)</target><part>formal elements</part></link><space/>for their own sake, and as<space/><italics><link><target>mimesis</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><link><target>Representation (arts)</target><part>representation</part></link>. Art as mimesis has deep roots in the philosophy of<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Levinson5"></extension><space/><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link><space/>identified art as a use of indirect means to communicate from one person to another.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Levinson5">Jerrold Levinson,<space/><italics>The Oxford Handbook of Aesthetics</italics>, Oxford university Press, 2003, p5. ISBN 0-19-927945-4</extension><space/><link><target>Benedetto Croce</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>R.G. Collingwood</target></link><space/>advanced the<space/><link><target>Idealism</target><part>idealist</part></link><space/>view that art expresses emotions, and that the work of art therefore essentially exists in the mind of the creator.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jerrold Levinson,<space/><italics>The Oxford Handbook of Aesthetics</italics>, Oxford university Press, 2003, p16. ISBN 0-19-927945-4</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>R.G. Collingwood's view, expressed in<space/><italics>The Principles of Art</italics>, is considered in Wollheim, op. cit. 1980 pp 3643</extension><space/>The theory of art as form has its roots in the philosophy of<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, and was developed in the early twentieth century by<space/><link><target>Roger Fry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Clive Bell</target></link>. More recently, thinkers influenced by<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link><space/>have interpreted art as the means by which a community develops for itself a medium for self-expression and interpretation.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link>, &quot;The Origin of the Work of Art&quot;, in<space/><italics>Poetry, Language, Thought</italics>, (Harper Perennial, 2001). See also<space/><link><target>Maurice Merleau-Ponty</target></link>, &quot;Czanne's Doubt&quot; in<space/><italics>The Merleau-Ponty Aesthetics Reader</italics>, Galen Johnson and Michael Smith (eds), (Northwestern University Press, 1994) and<space/><link><target>John Russon</target></link>,<space/><italics>Bearing Witness to Epiphany</italics>, (State University of New York Press, 2009).</extension><space/><link><target>George Dickie (philosopher)</target><part>George Dickie</part></link><space/>has offered an<space/><link><target>institutional theory of art</target></link><space/>that defines a work of art as any artifact upon which a qualified person or persons acting on behalf of the social institution commonly referred to as &quot;the<space/><link><target>art world</target></link>&quot; has conferred &quot;the status of candidate for appreciation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kennick, William ed, and W. E. Kennick,<space/><italics>Art and philosophy: readings in aesthetics</italics><space/>New York: St. Martin's Press, 1979, p. 89. ISBN 0-312-05391-6</extension><space/>Larry Shiner has described fine art as &quot;not an essence or a fate but something we have made. Art as we have generally understood it is a European invention barely two hundred years old.<extension extension_name='ref'>Shiner 2003.<space/><italics><link><target>The Invention of Art: A Cultural History</target></link></italics>Chicago: University of Chicago Press. p. 3. ISBN 978-0-226-75342-3</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of art</arg></template><link><target>File:Venus of Willendorf frontview retouched 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Venus of Willendorf</target></link>, ''circa'' 24,00022,000&amp;nbsp;<link><target>Before Present</target><part>BP</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Sculptures,<space/><link><target>cave paintings</target></link>, rock paintings and<space/><link><target>petroglyphs</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Upper Paleolithic</target></link><space/>dating to roughly 40,000 years ago have been found,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>World's oldest art found in Indonesian cave<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nature.com/news/world-s-oldest-art-found-in-indonesian-cave-1.16100<space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/>nature.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>8 October 2014<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>12 October 2014<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>but the precise meaning of such art is often disputed because so little is known about the cultures that produced them. The oldest art objects in the worlda series of tiny, drilled snail shells about 75,000 years oldwere discovered in a South African cave.<extension extension_name='ref'>Radford, Tim. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://education.guardian.co.uk/higher/artsandhumanities/story/0,12241,1193237,00.html'>World's Oldest Jewellery Found in Cave</link>&quot;.<space/><italics>Guardian Unlimited</italics>, 16 April 2004. Retrieved on 18 January 2008.</extension><space/>Containers that may have been used to hold paints have been found dating as far back as 100,000 years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2011/10/14/science/14paint.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="title">African Cave Yields Evidence of a Prehistoric Paint Factory<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 October 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Etched shells by<space/><italics><link><target>Homo erectus</target></link></italics><space/>from 430,000 and 540,000 years ago were discovered in 2014.<extension extension_name='ref' name="homoerectus"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg22429983.200-shell-art-made-300000-years-before-humans-evolved.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Shell 'Art' Made 300,000 Years Before Humans Evolved<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 3, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[New Scientist]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Reed Business Information]] Ltd</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:lascaux2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Cave painting</target></link><space/>of a horse from the<space/><link><target>Lascaux</target></link><space/>caves, ''circa'' 16,000&amp;nbsp;BP</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Many great traditions in art have a foundation in the art of one of the great ancient civilizations:<space/><link><target>Ancient Egypt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mesopotamia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>History of Iran</target><part>Persia</part></link>, India, China, Ancient Greece, Rome, as well as<space/><link><target>Inca</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target><part>Maya</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Olmec</target></link>. Each of these centers of early civilization developed a unique and characteristic style in its art. Because of the size and duration of these civilizations, more of their art works have survived and more of their influence has been transmitted to other cultures and later times. Some also have provided the first records of how artists worked. For example, this period of Greek art saw a veneration of the human physical form and the development of equivalent skills to show musculature, poise, beauty, and anatomically correct proportions.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Byzantine art</target><part>Byzantine</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Medieval art</target></link><space/>of the Western Middle Ages, much art focused on the expression of subjects about Biblical and religious culture, and used styles that showed the higher glory of a heavenly world, such as the use of gold in the background of paintings, or glass in mosaics or windows, which also presented figures in idealized, patterned (flat) forms. Nevertheless, a classical realist tradition persisted in small Byzantine works, and realism steadily grew in the art of Catholic Europe.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Renaissance art</target></link><space/>had a greatly increased emphasis on the realistic depiction of the material world, and the place of humans in it, reflected in the corporeality of the human body, and development of a systematic method of<space/><link><target>graphical perspective</target></link><space/>to depict recession in a three-dimensional picture space.<link><target>File:Tugra Mahmuds II.gif</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>The stylized signature of<space/><link><target>Sultan</target></link><space/><link><target>Mahmud II</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>was written in<space/><link><target>Arabic calligraphy</target></link>. It reads ''Mahmud Khan son of Abdulhamid is forever victorious''.</part></link><link><target>File:Great Mosque of Kairouan Panorama - Grande Mosque de Kairouan Panorama.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Mosque of Uqba</target><part>Great Mosque of Kairouan</part></link><space/>in Tunisia, also called the Mosque of Uqba, is one of the finest, most significant and best preserved artistic and architectural examples of early great mosques. Dated in its present state from the 9th century, it is the ancestor and model of all the mosques in the western Islamic lands.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=IaM9AAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA104&amp;amp;dq=oleg+grabar+kairouan+mosque&amp;amp;cd=3#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=oleg%20grabar%20kairouan%20mosque&amp;amp;f=false'>John Stothoff Badeau and John Richard Hayes, ''The Genius of Arab civilization: source of Renaissance''. Taylor &amp; Francis. 1983. p. 104</link></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the east,<space/><link><target>Islamic art</target></link>'s rejection of<space/><link><target>iconography</target></link><space/>led to emphasis on geometric patterns,<space/><link><target>Islamic calligraphy</target><part>calligraphy</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Islamic architecture</target><part>architecture</part></link>. Further east, religion dominated artistic styles and forms too. India and Tibet saw emphasis on painted sculptures and dance, while religious painting borrowed many conventions from sculpture and tended to bright contrasting colors with emphasis on outlines. China saw the flourishing of many art forms: jade carving, bronzework, pottery (including the stunning<space/><link><target>terracotta army</target></link><space/>of Emperor Qin), poetry, calligraphy, music, painting, drama, fiction, etc. Chinese styles vary greatly from era to era and each one is traditionally named after the ruling dynasty. So, for example,<space/><link><target>Tang dynasty</target></link><space/>paintings are monochromatic and sparse, emphasizing idealized landscapes, but<space/><link><target>Ming Dynasty</target></link><space/>paintings are busy and colorful, and focus on telling stories via setting and composition. Japan names its styles after imperial dynasties too, and also saw much interplay between the styles of calligraphy and painting.<space/><link><target>Woodblock printing</target></link><space/>became important in Japan after the 17th century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ma Lin Guests.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Painting by<space/><link><target>Song dynasty</target></link><space/>artist Ma Lin, ''circa'' 1250. 24,8&amp;nbsp; 25,2&amp;nbsp;cm</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The western<space/><link><target>Age of Enlightenment</target></link><space/>in the 18th century saw artistic depictions of physical and rational certainties of the clockwork universe, as well as politically revolutionary visions of a post-monarchist world, such as<space/><link><target>William Blake</target><part>Blake</part></link>'s portrayal of Newton as a divine geometer, or<space/><link><target>Jacques-Louis David</target><part>David</part></link>'s propagandistic paintings. This led to<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target><part>Romantic</part></link><space/>rejections of this in favor of pictures of the emotional side and individuality of humans, exemplified in the novels of<space/><link><target>Goethe</target></link>. The late 19th century then saw a host of artistic movements, such as<space/><link><target>academic art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Symbolism (arts)</target><part>Symbolism</part></link>,<space/><link><target>impressionism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fauvism</target></link><space/>among others.</paragraph><paragraph>The history of twentieth-century art is a narrative of endless possibilities and the search for new standards, each being torn down in succession by the next. Thus the parameters of<space/><link><target>Impressionism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Expressionism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Fauvism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cubism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Dadaism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Surrealism</target></link>, etc. cannot be maintained very much beyond the time of their invention. Increasing<space/><link><target>globalization</target><part>global</part></link><space/>interaction during this time saw an equivalent influence of other cultures into Western art. Thus, Japanese woodblock prints (themselves influenced by Western Renaissance draftsmanship) had an immense influence on Impressionism and subsequent development. Later,<space/><link><target>African art</target><part>African sculptures</part></link><space/>were taken up by Picasso and to some extent by<space/><link><target>Matisse</target></link>. Similarly, in the 19th and 20th centuries the West has had huge impacts on Eastern art with originally western ideas like<space/><link><target>Communism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Post-Modernism</target></link><space/>exerting a powerful influence.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Modernism</target></link>, the idealistic search for truth, gave way in the latter half of the 20th century to a realization of its unattainability.<space/><link><target>Theodor W. Adorno</target></link><space/>said in 1970, &quot;It is now taken for granted that nothing which concerns art can be taken for granted any more: neither art itself, nor art in relationship to the whole, nor even the right of art to exist.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Adorno, Theodor W.,<space/><italics>Aesthetic Theory</italics>, (1970 in German)</extension><space/><link><target>Relativism</target></link><space/>was accepted as an unavoidable truth, which led to the period of<space/><link><target>contemporary art</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>List of postmodern critics</target><part>postmodern criticism</part></link>, where cultures of the world and of history are seen as changing forms, which can be appreciated and drawn from only with<space/><link><target>skepticism</target></link><space/>and irony. Furthermore, the separation of cultures is increasingly blurred and some argue it is now more appropriate to think in terms of a global culture, rather than of regional ones.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Forms, genres, media, and styles</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>The arts</arg></template><link><target>File:MonaLisa sfumato.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Detail of<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Mona Lisa</target></link>, showing the painting technique of ''<link><target>sfumato</target></link>''</part></link>The creative arts are often divided into more specific categories, each related to its technique, or<space/><link><target>Media (arts)</target><part>medium</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>decorative art</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>plastic arts</target></link>,<space/><link><target>performing arts</target></link>, or literature. Unlike scientific fields, art is one of the few subjects that are academically organized according to technique. An artistic<space/><link><target>recording medium</target><part>medium</part></link><space/>is the substance or material the artistic work is made from, and may also refer to the technique used. For example, paint is a medium used in painting, and paper is a medium used in drawing.</paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><bold><italics>art form</italics></bold><space/>is the specific<space/><italics>shape</italics>, or quality an artistic expression takes. The media used often influence the form. For example, the<space/><link><target>shape</target><part>form</part></link><space/>of a sculpture must exist in space in three dimensions, and respond to gravity. The constraints and limitations of a particular medium are thus called its<space/><bold><italics>formal qualities</italics></bold>. To give another example, the formal qualities of painting are the canvas texture, color, and brush texture. The formal qualities of video games are non-linearity, interactivity and virtual presence.The<space/><italics>form</italics><space/>of a particular work of art is determined by the formal qualities of the media, and is not related to the intentions of the artist or the reactions of the audience in any way whatsoever as these properties are related to content rather than form.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SaylorIntroPDF"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">www.sbctc.edu (adapted)</arg><arg name="title">Module 1: Introduction and Definitions</arg><arg name="url">http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/Module-1.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">Saylor.org</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 April 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold><italics>genre</italics></bold><space/>is a set of conventions and styles within a particular medium. For instance, well recognized genres in film are<space/><link><target>Western (genre)</target><part>western</part></link>,<space/><link><target>horror (genre)</target><part>horror</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>romantic comedy film</target><part>romantic comedy</part></link>. Genres in music include<space/><link><target>death metal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>trip hop</target></link>. Genres in painting include<space/><link><target>still life</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Landscape art</target><part>pastoral landscape</part></link>. A particular work of art may bend or combine genres but each genre has a recognizable group of conventions, clichs and tropes. (One note: the word<space/><italics>genre</italics><space/>has a second older meaning within painting;<space/><italics><link><target>genre painting</target></link></italics><space/>was a phrase used in the 17th to 19th centuries to refer specifically to paintings of scenes of everyday life and is still used in this way.)</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Great Wave off Kanagawa2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>The Great Wave off Kanagawa</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Hokusai</target></link><space/>(Japanese, 17601849), colored woodcut print</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold><italics>style</italics></bold><space/>of an artwork, artist, or movement is the distinctive method and form followed by the respective art. Any loose brushy, dripped or poured abstract painting is called<space/><italics>expressionistic</italics>. Often a style is linked with a particular historical period, set of ideas, and particular artistic movement. So<space/><link><target>Jackson Pollock</target></link><space/>is called an<space/><link><target>Abstract Expressionist</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A particular style may have specific cultural meanings. For example,<space/><link><target>Roy Lichtenstein</target></link>a painter associated with the American<space/><link><target>Pop art</target></link><space/>movement of the 1960swas not a<space/><link><target>Pointillism</target><part>pointillist</part></link>, despite his use of dots. Lichtenstein used evenly spaced<space/><link><target>Ben-Day dots</target></link><space/>(the type used to reproduce color in comic strips) as a style to question the &quot;high&quot; art of painting with the &quot;low&quot; art of comics, thus commenting on class distinctions in culture. Pointillism, a technique in late Impressionism (1880s) developed especially by the artist<space/><link><target>Georges Seurat</target></link>, employs dots to create variation in color and depth in an attempt to approximate the way people really see color. Both artists use dots, but the particular style and technique relate to the artistic movement adopted by each artist.</paragraph><paragraph>These are all ways of beginning to define a work of art, to narrow it down.<template><target>quote</target><arg>Imagine you are an art critic whose mission is to compare the meanings you find in a wide range of individual artworks. How would you proceed with your task? One way to begin is to examine the materials each artist selected in making an object, image video, or event. The decision to cast a sculpture in bronze, for instance, inevitably effects its meaning; the work becomes something different from how it might be if it had been cast in gold or plastic or chocolate, even if everything else about the artwork remains the same. Next, you might examine how the materials in each artwork have become an arrangement of shapes, colors, textures, and lines. These, in turn, are organized into various patterns and compositional structures. In your interpretation, you would comment on how salient features of the form contribute to the overall meaning of the finished artwork. [But in the end] the meaning of most artworks... is not exhausted by a discussion of materials, techniques, and form. Most interpretations also include a discussion of the ideas and feelings the artwork engenders.<ref>Robertson, Jean and Craig McDaniel: Themes of Contemporary Art, Visual Art after 1980, page 4. Oxford University Press, 2005.</ref></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Skill and craft</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Michelangelo, Creation of Adam 03.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Adam</target></link>. Detail from<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link>'s fresco in the ''<link><target>Cappella Sistina</target></link>'' (1511)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Conceptual art#Conceptual Art and Artistic Skill</arg><arg name="l1">Conceptual Art and Artistic Skill</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Art can connote a sense of trained ability or mastery of a<space/><link><target>Media (arts)</target><part>medium</part></link>. Art can also simply refer to the developed and efficient use of a<space/><link><target>language</target></link><space/>to convey meaning with immediacy and or depth. Art is an act of expressing feelings, thoughts, and observations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Breskin, Vladimir,<space/><link type='external' href='http://vip.iva.dk/signs/Articles_Signs_International_Section/2010/Breskin_(2010)_Signs_Triad_eng_final_rev_2010.pdf'>Triad: Method for studying the core of the semiotic parity of language and art</link>, Signs International Journal of Semiotics 3, pp.128, 2010. ISSN: 1902-8822</extension>There is an understanding that is reached with the material as a result of handling it, which facilitates one's thought processes.A common view is that the<space/><link><target>Wikt:epithet</target><part>epithet</part></link><space/>&quot;art&quot;, particular in its elevated sense, requires a certain level of creative expertise by the artist, whether this be a demonstration of technical ability, an originality in stylistic approach, or a combination of these two. Traditionally skill of execution was viewed as a quality inseparable from art and thus necessary for its success; for<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link>, art, neither more nor less than his other endeavors, was a manifestation of skill.<space/><link><target>Rembrandt</target></link>'s work, now praised for its ephemeral virtues, was most admired by his contemporaries for its virtuosity. At the turn of the 20th century, the adroit performances of<space/><link><target>John Singer Sargent</target></link><space/>were alternately admired and viewed with skepticism for their manual fluency, yet at nearly the same time the artist who would become the era's most recognized and peripatetic iconoclast,<space/><link><target>Pablo Picasso</target></link>, was completing a traditional academic training at which he excelled.</paragraph><paragraph>A common contemporary criticism of some<space/><link><target>modern art</target></link><space/>occurs along the lines of objecting to the apparent lack of skill or ability required in the production of the artistic object. In conceptual art,<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Fountain (Duchamp)</target><part>Fountain</part></link>&quot; is among the first examples of pieces wherein the artist used found objects (&quot;ready-made&quot;) and exercised no traditionally recognised set of skills.<space/><link><target>Tracey Emin</target></link>'s<space/><italics>My Bed</italics>, or<space/><link><target>Damien Hirst</target></link>'s<space/><italics>The Physical Impossibility of Death in the Mind of Someone Living</italics><space/>follow this example and also manipulate the mass media. Emin slept (and engaged in other activities) in her bed before placing the result in a gallery as work of art. Hirst came up with the conceptual design for the artwork but has left most of the eventual creation of many works to employed artisans. Hirst's celebrity is founded entirely on his ability to produce shocking concepts. The actual production in many conceptual and contemporary works of art is a matter of assembly of found objects. However, there are many modernist and contemporary artists who continue to excel in the skills of drawing and painting and in creating<space/><italics>hands-on</italics><space/>works of art.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Purpose of art</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Transition 1880.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A<space/><link><target>Navajo rug</target></link><space/>made ''circa'' 1880</part></link><link><target>File:B Escorial 93v.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Mozarabic art</target><part>Mozarabic</part></link><space/><link><target>Commentary on the Apocalypse</target><part>Beatus</part></link><space/><link><target>miniature (illuminated manuscript)</target><part>miniature</part></link>. Spain, late 10th century</part></link>Art has had a great number of different functions throughout its history, making its purpose difficult to abstract or quantify to any single concept. This does not imply that the purpose of Art is &quot;vague&quot;, but that it has had many unique, different reasons for being created. Some of these functions of Art are provided in the following outline. The different purposes of art may be grouped according to those that are non-motivated, and those that are motivated (Lvi-Strauss).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Non-motivated functions of art</heading><paragraph>The non-motivated purposes of art are those that are integral to being human, transcend the individual, or do not fulfill a specific external purpose. In this sense, Art, as creativity, is something humans must do by their very nature (i.e.,&amp;nbsp;no other species creates art), and is therefore beyond utility.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><italics><link><target>fine arts</target><part>Basic human instinct for harmony, balance, rhythm</part></link>.</italics><space/>Art at this level is not an action or an object, but an internal appreciation of balance and harmony (beauty), and therefore an aspect of being human beyond utility.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;Imitation, then, is one instinct of our nature. Next, there is the instinct for 'harmony' and rhythm, meters being manifestly sections of rhythm. Persons, therefore, starting with this natural gift developed by degrees their special aptitudes, till their rude improvisations gave birth to Poetry.&quot; -Aristotle<extension extension_name='ref'>Aristotle. The Poetics, Republic. Note: Although speaking mostly of poetry here, the Ancient Greeks often speak of the arts collectively. http://www.authorama.com/the-poetics-2.html</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Experience of the mysterious.</italics><space/>Art provides a way to experience one's self in relation to the universe. This experience may often come unmotivated, as one appreciates art, music or poetry.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;The most beautiful thing we can experience is the mysterious. It is the source of all true art and science.&quot; -Albert Einstein<extension extension_name='ref'>Einstein, Albert. The World as I See It. http://www.aip.org/history/einstein/essay.htm</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Expression of the imagination.</italics><space/>Art provides a means to express the imagination in non-grammatic ways that are not tied to the formality of spoken or written language. Unlike words, which come in sequences and each of which have a definite meaning, art provides a range of forms, symbols and ideas with meanings that are malleable.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;Jupiter's eagle [as an example of art] is not, like logical (aesthetic) attributes of an object, the concept of the sublimity and majesty of creation, but rather something else something that gives the imagination an incentive to spread its flight over a whole host of kindred representations that provoke more thought than admits of expression in a concept determined by words. They furnish an aesthetic idea, which serves the above rational idea as a substitute for logical presentation, but with the proper function, however, of animating the mind by opening out for it a prospect into a field of kindred representations stretching beyond its ken.&quot; -Immanuel Kant<extension extension_name='ref'>Immanuel Kant, Critique of Aesthetic Judgement (1790).</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Ritualistic and symbolic functions.</italics><space/>In many cultures, art is used in rituals, performances and dances as a decoration or symbol. While these often have no specific utilitarian (motivated) purpose, anthropologists know that they often serve a purpose at the level of meaning within a particular culture. This meaning is not furnished by any one individual, but is often the result of many generations of change, and of a cosmological relationship within the culture.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;Most scholars who deal with rock paintings or objects recovered from prehistoric contexts that cannot be explained in utilitarian terms and are thus categorized as decorative, ritual or symbolic, are aware of the trap posed by the term 'art'.&quot; -Silva Tomaskova<extension extension_name='ref'>Silvia Tomaskova, &quot;Places of Art: Art and Archaeology in Context&quot;: (1997)</extension></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Motivated functions of art</heading><paragraph>Motivated purposes of art refer to intentional, conscious actions on the part of the artists or creator. These may be to bring about political change, to comment on an aspect of society, to convey a specific emotion or mood, to address personal psychology, to illustrate another discipline, to (with commercial arts) to sell a product, or simply as a form of communication.</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem><italics>Communication.</italics><space/>Art, at its simplest, is a form of communication. As most forms of communication have an intent or goal directed toward another individual, this is a motivated purpose. Illustrative arts, such as scientific illustration, are a form of art as communication. Maps are another example. However, the content need not be scientific. Emotions, moods and feelings are also communicated through art.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;[Art is a set of] artefacts or images with symbolic meanings as a means of communication.&quot; -Steve Mithen<extension extension_name='ref'>Steve Mithen. The Prehistory of the Mind: The Cognitive Origins of Art, Religion and Science. 1999</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Art as entertainment</italics>. Art may seek to bring about a particular emotion or mood, for the purpose of relaxing or entertaining the viewer. This is often the function of the art industries of Motion Pictures and Video Games.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><italics>The Avante-Garde. Art for political change.</italics><space/>One of the defining functions of early twentieth-century art has been to use visual images to bring about political change. Art movements that had this goal<link><target>Dadaism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Surrealism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Russian constructivism</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Abstract Expressionism</target></link>, among othersare collectively referred to as the<space/><italics>avante-garde</italics><space/>arts.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;By contrast, the realistic attitude, inspired by positivism, from Saint Thomas Aquinas to Anatole France, clearly seems to me to be hostile to any intellectual or moral advancement. I loathe it, for it is made up of mediocrity, hate, and dull conceit. It is this attitude which today gives birth to these ridiculous books, these insulting plays. It constantly feeds on and derives strength from the newspapers and stultifies both science and art by assiduously flattering the lowest of tastes; clarity bordering on stupidity, a dog's life.&quot; -Andr Breton (Surrealism)<extension extension_name='ref'>Andr Breton, Surrealist Manifesto (1924)</extension></extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Art as a &quot;free zone&quot;</italics>, removed from the action of the social censure. Unlike the<space/><link><target>avant-garde</target></link><space/>movements, which wanted to erase cultural differences in order to produce new universal values,<space/><link><target>contemporary art</target></link><space/>has enhanced its tolerance towards cultural differences as well as its critical and liberating functions (social inquiry, activism, subversion, deconstruction...), becoming a more open place for research and experimentation.<extension extension_name='ref'>According to<space/><link><target>Maurizio Bolognini</target></link><space/>this is not only associated with the<space/><link><target>postmodern art</target><part>postmodern</part></link><space/>rejection of all canons but with a process of secularization of art, which is finally considered as &quot;a mere (albeit essential) convention, sustained and reproduced by the art system (artists, galleries, critics, collectors), providing a free zone, that is, a more open place for experimentation, removed from the constraints of the practical sphere.&quot;: see<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Postdigitale
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bolognini.org/bolognini_PDIG.htm
</arg><arg name="year">2008
</arg><arg name="author">Maurizio Bolognini
</arg><arg name="publisher">Carocci
</arg><arg name="location">Rome
</arg><arg name="isbn">978-88-430-4739-0
</arg><arg name="postscript">{{inconsistent citations}}
</arg></template>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bolognini.org/bolognini_PDIG.htm#ch3b'>chap. 3</link>.</extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Art for social inquiry, subversion and/or anarchy.</italics><space/>While similar to art for political change, subversive or deconstructivist art may seek to question aspects of society without any specific political goal. In this case, the function of art may be simply to criticize some aspect of society.<link><target>File:Graffiti Panorama rome.jpg</target><part>700px</part><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part><link><target>Aerosol paint</target><part>Spray-paint</part></link><space/><link><target>graffiti</target></link><space/>on a wall in Rome</part></link><space/><link><target>Graffiti#Uses</target><part>Graffiti art</part></link><space/>and other types of<space/><link><target>street art</target></link><space/>are graphics and images that are<space/><link><target>Spray painting</target><part>spray-painted</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>stencil</target><trail>led</trail></link><space/>on publicly viewable walls, buildings, buses, trains, and bridges, usually without permission. Certain art forms, such as graffiti, may also be illegal when they break laws (in this case vandalism).</listitem><listitem><italics>Art for social causes.</italics><space/>Art can be used to raise awareness for a large variety of causes. A number of art activities were aimed at raising awareness of<space/><link><target>autism</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Trotter<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jeramia<space/></arg><arg name="title">RiverKings raising autism awareness with art<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://southaven-hornlake.wmctv.com/news/arts-culture/riverkings-raising-autism-awareness-art/52165<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">WMC tv<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 February 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20110222053732/http://southaven-hornlake.wmctv.com:80/news/arts-culture/riverkings-raising-autism-awareness-art/52165<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">22 February 2011<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Art exhibit aims to raise awareness of autism</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newsminer.com/article_1a9b7e33-6ca0-56a5-89f3-c9c0798815a2.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Daily News-Miner</arg><arg name="date">4 April 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Anchorage art exhibit to raise awareness about autism</arg><arg name="url">http://dhss.alaska.gov/News/Documents/press/2011/Anchorage_art_exhibit_autism_PR033111.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">Alaska Department of Health and Social Services</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>cancer,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Ruhl</arg><arg name="first">Ashleigh</arg><arg name="title">Photographer Seeks Subjects To Help Raise Cancer Awareness</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gazettes.com/lifestyle/arts_and_entertainment/photographer-seeks-subjects-to-help-raise-cancer-awareness/article_10291db8-7614-11e2-be53-0019bb2963f4.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Gazettes</arg><arg name="date">18 February 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Bra art raising awareness for breast cancer</arg><arg name="url">http://www.palmbeachpost.com/videos/news/national/bra-art-raising-awareness-for-breast-cancer/vgBSm/</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 January 2015</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Palm Beach Post</arg><arg name="date">n.d.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Flynn</arg><arg name="first">Marella</arg><arg name="title">October art walk aims to raise money, awareness for breast cancer</arg><arg name="url">http://gargoyle.flagler.edu/2007/10/october-art-walk-aims-to-raise-money-awareness-for-breast-cancer/</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">Flagler College Gargoyle</arg><arg name="date">10 January 2007</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>human trafficking</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Students get creative in the fight against human trafficking<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wdtn.com/dpp/news/local/montgomery/ud-students-use-art-to-raise-awareness#.USb6vFeIqAg<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">WDTN Channel 2 News<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 November 2012<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20150122224159/http://www.wdtn.com/dpp/news/local/montgomery/ud-students-use-art-to-raise-awareness<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">22 January 2015<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Looking to raise awareness at ArtPrize<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wwmt.com/shared/newsroom/top-stories/stories/wwmt_looking-raise-awareness-at-artprize-4625.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">WWMT, Newschannel 3<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20121006075346/http://www.wwmt.com:80/shared/newsroom/top-stories/stories/wwmt_looking-raise-awareness-at-artprize-4625.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">6 October 2012<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and a variety of other topics, such as ocean conservation,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">SciCafe – Art/Sci Collision: Raising Ocean Conservation Awareness</arg><arg name="url">http://www.amnh.org/calendar/scicafe-art-sci-collision-raising-ocean-conservation-awareness</arg><arg name="publisher">American Museum of Natural History</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>human rights in<space/><link><target>Darfur</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">SMU students raise awareness with 'Art for Darfur'</arg><arg name="url">http://smu.edu/newsinfo/releases/07138c.asp</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2003</arg><arg name="newspaper">SMU News Release</arg><arg name="date">4 March 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>murdered and missing Aboriginal women,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Donnelly<space/></arg><arg name="first">Greg<space/></arg><arg name="title">Red dress art project to raise awareness of murdered and missing Aboriginal women<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.globaltvedmonton.com/red+dress+art+project+to+raise+awareness+of+murdered+and+missing+aboriginal+women/6442594504/story.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">Global Edmonton<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 May 2012<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20150122230836/http://www.globaltvedmonton.com/red+dress+art+project+to+raise+awareness+of+murdered+and+missing+aboriginal+women/6442594504/story.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">22 January 2015<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>elder abuse,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Raising elder abuse awareness through intergenerational art</arg><arg name="url">http://www.hrsdc.gc.ca/eng/success_stories/seniors/40/index.shtml</arg><arg name="publisher">Human Resources and Skills Development Canada</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>and pollution.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Mathema</arg><arg name="first">Paavan</arg><arg name="title">Trash to treasure: Turning Mt. Everest waste into art</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cnn.com/2013/01/15/world/asia/everest-trash-art/</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 February 2013</arg><arg name="newspaper">CNN</arg><arg name="date">16 January 2013</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Trashion</target></link>, using trash to make fashion, practiced by artists such as<space/><link><target>Marina DeBris</target></link><space/>is one example of using art to raise awareness about pollution.</listitem><listitem><italics>Art for psychological and healing purposes.</italics><space/>Art is also used by art therapists, psychotherapists and clinical psychologists as<space/><link><target>art therapy</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Art therapy#The Diagnostic Drawing Series (DDS)</target><part>Diagnostic Drawing Series</part></link>, for example, is used to determine the personality and emotional functioning of a patient. The end product is not the principal goal in this case, but rather a process of healing, through creative acts, is sought. The resultant piece of artwork may also offer insight into the troubles experienced by the subject and may suggest suitable approaches to be used in more conventional forms of psychiatric therapy.</listitem><listitem><italics>Art for propaganda, or commercialism.</italics><space/>Art is often utilized as a form of propaganda, and thus can be used to subtly influence popular conceptions or mood. In a similar way, art that tries to sell a product also influences mood and emotion. In both cases, the purpose of art here is to subtly manipulate the viewer into a particular emotional or psychological response toward a particular idea or object.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Roland Barthes</target></link>, Mythologies</extension></listitem><listitem><italics>Art as a fitness indicator.</italics><space/>It has been argued that the ability of the human brain by far exceeds what was needed for survival in the ancestral environment. One<space/><link><target>evolutionary psychology</target></link><space/>explanation for this is that the human brain and associated traits (such as artistic ability and creativity) are the human equivalent of the<space/><link><target>peacock</target></link>'s tail. The purpose of the male peacock's extravagant tail has been argued to be to attract females (see also<space/><link><target>Fisherian runaway</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>handicap principle</target></link>). According to this theory superior execution of art was evolutionary important because it attracted mates.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dutton">Dutton, Denis. 2003. 'Aesthetics and Evolutionary Psychology' in &quot;The Oxford Handbook for Aesthetics&quot;. Oxford University Press.</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The functions of art described above are not mutually exclusive, as many of them may overlap. For example, art for the purpose of entertainment may also seek to sell a product, i.e. the movie or video game.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Public access</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chateau-de-versailles-cour.jpg</target><part>upright=2</part><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Versailles:<space/><link><target>Louis Le Vau</target></link><space/>opened up the interior court to create the expansive entrance ''<link><target>cour d'honneur</target></link>'', later copied all over Europe.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Since ancient times, much of the finest art has represented a deliberate display of wealth or power, often achieved by using massive scale and expensive materials. Much art has been commissioned by rulers or religious establishments, with more modest versions only available to the most wealthy in society. Nevertheless, there have been many periods where art of very high quality was available, in terms of ownership, across large parts of society, above all in cheap media such as pottery, which persists in the ground, and perishable media such as textiles and wood. In many different cultures, the<space/><link><target>ceramics of indigenous peoples of the Americas</target></link><space/>are found in such a wide range of graves that they were clearly not restricted to a<space/><link><target>social elite</target></link>, though other forms of art may have been. Reproductive methods such as<space/><link><target>Molding (process)</target><part>moulds</part></link><space/>made mass-production easier, and were used to bring high-quality<space/><link><target>Ancient Roman pottery</target></link><space/>and Greek<space/><link><target>Tanagra figurine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to a very wide market.<space/><link><target>Cylinder seal</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were both artistic and practical, and very widely used by what can be loosely called the middle class in the<space/><link><target>Ancient Near East</target></link>. Once<space/><link><target>coin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were widely used these also became an art form that reached the widest range of society. Another important innovation came in the 15th century in Europe, when<space/><link><target>printmaking</target></link><space/>began with small<space/><link><target>woodcut</target><trail>s</trail></link>, mostly religious, that were often very small and hand-colored, and affordable even by<space/><link><target>peasant</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who glued them to the walls of their homes. Printed books were initially very expensive, but fell steadily in price until by the 19th century even the poorest could afford some with printed illustrations.<space/><link><target>Popular prints</target></link><space/>of many different sorts have decorated homes and other places for centuries.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Public art</target><part>Public buildings and monuments</part></link>, secular and religious, by their nature normally address the whole of society, and visitors as viewers, and display to the general public has long been an important factor in their design.<space/><link><target>Egyptian temple</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are typical in that the most largest and most lavish decoration was placed on the parts that could be seen by the general public, rather than the areas seen only by the priests. Many areas of royal palaces, castles and the houses of the social elite were often generally accessible, and large parts of the art collections of such people could often be seen, either by anybody, or by those able to pay a small price, or those wearing the correct clothes, regardless of who they were, as at the<space/><link><target>Palace of Versailles</target></link>, where the appropriate extra accessories (silver shoe buckles and a sword) could be hired from shops outside.</paragraph><paragraph>Special arrangements were made to allow the public to see many royal or private collections placed in galleries, as with the<space/><link><target>Orleans Collection#Collection in Paris</target><part>Orleans Collection</part></link><space/>mostly housed in a wing of the<space/><link><target>Palais Royal</target></link><space/>in Paris, which could be visited for most of the 18th century. In Italy the art tourism of the<space/><link><target>Grand Tour</target></link><space/>became a major industry from the Renaissance onwards, and governments and cities made efforts to make their key works accessible. The British<space/><link><target>Royal Collection</target></link><space/>remains distinct, but large donations such as the<space/><link><target>Old Royal Library</target></link><space/>were made from it to the<space/><link><target>British Museum</target></link>, established in 1753. The<space/><link><target>Uffizi</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link><space/>opened entirely as a gallery in 1765, though this function had been gradually taking the building over from the original civil servants' offices for a long time before. The building now occupied by the<space/><link><target>Prado</target></link><space/>in Madrid was built before the French Revolution for the public display of parts of the royal art collection, and similar royal galleries open to the public existed in<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>, Munich and other capitals. The opening of the<space/><link><target>Muse du Louvre</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>(in 1793) as a public museum for much of the former French royal collection certainly marked an important stage in the development of public access to art, transferring ownership to a republican state, but was a continuation of trends already well established.</paragraph><paragraph>Most modern public museums and art education programs for children in schools can be traced back to this impulse to have art available to everyone. Museums in the United States tend to be gifts from the very rich to the masses (<link><target>The Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link><space/>in New York City, for example, was created by<space/><link><target>John Taylor Johnston</target></link>, a railroad executive whose personal art collection seeded the museum.) But despite all this, at least one of the important functions of art in the 21st century remains as a marker of wealth and social status.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:BeuysAchberg78.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Performance by<space/><link><target>Joseph Beuys</target></link>, 1978: ''Everyone an artist On the way to the libertarian form of the social organism''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There have been attempts by artists to create art that can not be bought by the wealthy as a status object. One of the prime original motivators of much of the art of the late 1960s and 1970s was to create art that could not be bought and sold. It is &quot;necessary to present something more than mere objects&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">An Interview with Joseph Beuys</arg><arg name="journal">ArtForum</arg><arg name="date">December 1969</arg><arg name="first">Willoughby</arg><arg name="last">Sharp</arg><arg name="volume">8</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="page">45</arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="url"></arg></template></extension><space/>said the major post war German artist Joseph Beuys. This time period saw the rise of such things as<space/><link><target>performance art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>video art</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>conceptual art</target></link>. The idea was that if the artwork was a performance that would leave nothing behind, or was simply an idea, it could not be bought and sold. &quot;Democratic precepts revolving around the idea that a work of art is a commodity impelled the aesthetic innovation which germinated in the mid-1960s and was reaped throughout the 1970s. Artists broadly identified under the heading of Conceptual art... substituting performance and publishing activities for engagement with both the material and materialistic concerns of painted or sculptural form... [have] endeavored to undermine the art object qua object.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rorimer, Anne: New Art in the 60s and 70s Redefining Reality, page 35. Thames and Hudson, 2001.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the decades since, these ideas have been somewhat lost as the art market has learned to sell limited edition DVDs of video works,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first">Mia<space/></arg><arg name="last">Fineman<space/></arg><arg name="title">YouTube for ArtistsThe best places to find video art online.<space/></arg><arg name="date">21 March 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.slate.com/id/2162382/<space/></arg><arg name="work">Slate<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>3 August 2007<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>invitations to exclusive performance art pieces, and the objects left over from conceptual pieces. Many of these performances create works that are only understood by the elite who have been educated as to why an idea or video or piece of apparent garbage may be considered art. The marker of status becomes understanding the work instead of necessarily owning it, and the artwork remains an upper-class activity. &quot;With the widespread use of DVD recording technology in the early 2000s, artists, and the gallery system that derives its profits from the sale of artworks, gained an important means of controlling the sale of video and computer artworks in limited editions to collectors.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Robertson, Jean and Craig McDaniel: Themes of Contemporary Art, Visual Art after 1980, page 16. Oxford University Press, 2005.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Controversies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:JEAN LOUIS THODORE GRICAULT - La Balsa de la Medusa (Museo del Louvre, 1818-19).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright=1.5</part><part><link><target>Thodore Gricault</target></link>'s ''<link><target>The Raft of the Medusa</target><part>Raft of the Medusa</part></link>'', ''circa'' 1820</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Art has long been controversial, that is to say disliked by some viewers, for a wide variety of reasons, though most pre-modern controversies are dimly recorded, or completely lost to a modern view.<space/><link><target>Iconoclasm</target></link><space/>is the destruction of art that is disliked for a variety of reasons, including religious ones.<space/><link><target>Aniconism</target></link><space/>is a general dislike of either all figurative images, or often just religious ones, and has been a thread in many major religions. It has been a crucial factor in the history of<space/><link><target>Islamic art</target></link>, where<space/><link><target>depictions of Muhammad</target></link><space/>remain especially controversial. Much art has been disliked purely because it depicted or otherwise stood for unpopular rulers, parties or other groups. Artistic conventions have often been conservative and taken very seriously by<space/><link><target>art critic</target><trail>s</trail></link>, though often much less so by a wider public. The<space/><link><target>iconography</target><part>iconographic</part></link><space/>content of art could cause controversy, as with late medieval depictions of the new motif of the<space/><link><target>Swoon of the Virgin</target></link><space/>in scenes of the<space/><link><target>Crucifixion of Jesus</target></link>.<space/><link><target>The Last Judgment (Michelangelo)</target><part>The ''Last Judgment''</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link><space/>was controversial for various reasons, including breaches of<space/><link><target>decorum</target></link><space/>through nudity and the<space/><link><target>Apollo</target></link>-like pose of Christ.</paragraph><paragraph>The content of much formal art through history was dictated by the patron or commissioner rather than just the artist, but with the advent of<space/><link><target>Romanticism</target></link>, and econonomic changes in the production of art, the artists' vision became the usual determinant of the content of his art, increasing the incidence of controversies, though often reducing their significance. Strong incentives for perceived originality and publicity also encouraged artists to court controversy.<space/><link><target>Thodore Gricault</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Raft of the Medusa</target><part>Raft of the Medusa</part></link></italics><space/>(c. 1820), was in part a political commentary on a recent event.<space/><link><target>douard Manet</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Luncheon on the Grass</target><part>Le Djeuner sur l'Herbe</part></link></italics><space/>(1863), was considered scandalous not because of the<space/><link><target>nude</target></link><space/>woman, but because she is seated next to men fully dressed in the clothing of the time, rather than in robes of the antique world.<space/><link><target>John Singer Sargent</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Portrait of Madame X</target><part>Madame Pierre Gautreau (Madam&amp;nbsp;X)</part></link></italics><space/>(1884), caused a controversy over the reddish pink used to color the woman's ear lobe, considered far too suggestive and supposedly ruining the high-society model's reputation.</paragraph><paragraph>The gradual abandonment of naturalism and the depiction of realistic representations of the visual appearance of subjects in the 19th and 20th centuries led to a rolling controversy lasting for over a century. In the twentieth century,<space/><link><target>Pablo Picasso</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Guernica (painting)</target><part>Guernica</part></link></italics><space/>(1937) used arresting<space/><link><target>cubism</target><part>cubist</part></link><space/>techniques and stark<space/><link><target>Monochrome painting</target><part>monochromatic oils</part></link>, to depict the harrowing consequences of a contemporary bombing of a small, ancient Basque town.<space/><link><target>Leon Golub</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Interrogation III</italics><space/>(1981), depicts a female nude, hooded detainee strapped to a chair, her legs open to reveal her sexual organs, surrounded by two tormentors dressed in everyday clothing.<space/><link><target>Andres Serrano</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Piss Christ</target></link></italics><space/>(1989) is a photograph of a crucifix, sacred to the Christian religion and representing<space/><link><target>Jesus Christ</target><part>Christ</part></link>'s sacrifice and final suffering, submerged in a glass of the artist's own urine. The resulting uproar led to comments in the United States Senate about public funding of the arts.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Theory</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Aesthetics</arg></template>In the nineteenth century, artists were primarily concerned with ideas of<space/><italics>truth</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>beauty</italics>. The aesthetic theorist<space/><link><target>John Ruskin</target></link>, who championed what he saw as the naturalism of<space/><link><target>J. M. W. Turner</target><part>J.&amp;nbsp;M.&amp;nbsp;W. Turner</part></link>, saw art's role as the communication by artifice of an essential truth that could only be found in nature.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;go to nature in all<space/><link><target>singleness of heart</target></link>, rejecting nothing and selecting nothing, and scorning nothing, believing all things are right and good, and rejoicing always in the truth.&quot;<space/><link><target>John Ruskin</target><part>Ruskin, John</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Modern Painters</target></link>, Volume I, 1843. London: Smith, Elder and Co.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The definition and evaluation of art has become especially problematic since the 20th century.<space/><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link><space/>distinguishes three approaches to assessing the aesthetic value of art: the<space/><link><target>Aesthetic realism</target><part>Realist</part></link>, whereby aesthetic quality is an absolute value independent of any human view; the<space/><link><target>Objectivity (philosophy)</target><part>Objectivist</part></link>, whereby it is also an absolute value, but is dependent on general human experience; and the<space/><link><target>Relativist</target></link><space/><link><target>Aesthetic relativism</target><part>position</part></link>, whereby it is not an absolute value, but depends on, and varies with, the human experience of different humans.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollheim 1980, Essay VI. pp. 23139.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Arrival of Modernism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Piet Mondriaan, 1930 - Mondrian Composition II in Red, Blue, and Yellow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Composition II in Red, Blue, and Yellow'' (1930) by<space/><link><target>Piet Mondrian</target></link><space/>(Dutch, 18721944)</part></link>The arrival of<space/><link><target>Modernism</target></link><space/>in the late nineteenth century lead to a radical break in the conception of the function of art,<extension extension_name='ref'>Griselda Pollock,<space/><italics>Differencing the Canon</italics>. Routledge, London &amp; N.Y.,1999. ISBN 0-415-06700-6</extension><space/>and then again in the late twentieth century with the advent of<space/><link><target>Postmodern art</target><part>postmodernism</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Clement Greenberg</target></link>'s 1960 article &quot;Modernist Painting&quot; defines modern art as &quot;the use of characteristic methods of a discipline to criticize the discipline itself&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Frascina">Modern Art and Modernism: A Critical Anthology. ed. Francis Frascina and Charles Harrison, 1982.</extension><space/>Greenberg originally applied this idea to the Abstract Expressionist movement and used it as a way to understand and justify flat (non-illusionistic) abstract painting:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="Realistic, naturalistic art had dissembled the medium, using art to conceal art; modernism used art to call attention to art. The limitations that constitute the medium of painting—the flat surface, the shape of the support, the properties of the pigment—were treated by the Old Masters as negative factors that could be acknowledged only implicitly or indirectly. Under Modernism these same limitations came to be regarded as positive factors, and were acknowledged openly.<ref name"><space/>"Frascina" /></arg></template><space/>After Greenberg, several important art theorists emerged, such as<space/><link><target>Michael Fried</target></link>,<space/><link><target>T. J. Clark (historian)</target><part>T.&amp;nbsp;J.&amp;nbsp;Clark</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Rosalind Krauss</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Linda Nochlin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Griselda Pollock</target></link><space/>among others. Though only originally intended as a way of understanding a specific set of artists, Greenberg's definition of modern art is important to many of the ideas of art within the various art movements of the 20th century and early 21st century.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pop art</target><trail>ists</trail></link><space/>like<space/><link><target>Andy Warhol</target></link><space/>became both noteworthy and influential through work including and possibly critiquing popular culture, as well as the<space/><link><target>art world</target></link>. Artists of the 1980s, 1990s, and 2000s expanded this technique of self-criticism beyond<space/><italics>high art</italics><space/>to all cultural image-making, including fashion images, comics, billboards and pornography.</paragraph><paragraph>Duchamp once proposed that art is any activity of any kind- everything. However, the way that only certain activities are classified today as art is a social construction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Duchamp Interview Clip"><template><target>YouTube</target><arg>haon2DXWvLk</arg><arg>Duchamp Two Statements</arg></template></extension><space/>There is evidence that there may be an element of truth to this.<space/><link><target>The Invention of Art: A Cultural History</target></link><space/>is an art history book which examines the construction of the modern system of the arts i.e.<space/><link><target>Fine Art</target></link>. Shiner finds evidence that the older system of the arts before our modern system (fine art) held art to be any skilled human activity i.e. Ancient Greek society did not possess the term art but<space/><link><target>techne</target></link>. Techne can be understood neither as art or craft, the reason being that the distinctions of art and<space/><link><target>craft</target></link><space/>are historical products that came later on in human history. Techne included painting, sculpting and music but also; cooking, medicine,<space/><link><target>horsemanship</target></link>,<space/><link><target>geometry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>carpentry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>prophecy</target></link><space/>and farming etc.</paragraph><heading level='3'>New Criticism and the &quot;Intentional Fallacy&quot;</heading><paragraph>Following Duchamp during the first half of the twentieth century, a significant shift to general aesthetic theory took place which attempted to apply aesthetic theory between various forms of art, including the literary arts and the visual arts, to each other. This resulted in the rise of the<space/><link><target>New Criticism</target></link><space/>school and debate concerning<space/><italics>the intentional fallacy</italics>. At issue was the question of whether the aesthetic intentions of the artist in creating the work of art, whatever its specific form, should be associated with the criticism and evaluation of the final product of the work of art, or, if the work of art should be evaluated on its own merits independent of the intentions of the artist.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1946,<space/><link><target>W. K. Wimsatt</target><part>William K. Wimsatt</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Monroe Beardsley</target></link><space/>published a classic and controversial New Critical essay entitled &quot;<link><target>Intentional Fallacy</target><part>The Intentional Fallacy</part></link>&quot;, in which they argued strongly against the relevance of an<space/><link><target>Authorial intentionality</target><part>author's intention</part></link>, or &quot;intended meaning&quot; in the analysis of a literary work. For Wimsatt and Beardsley, the words on the page were all that mattered; importation of meanings from outside the text was considered irrelevant, and potentially distracting.</paragraph><paragraph>In another essay, &quot;<link><target>Affective fallacy</target><part>The Affective Fallacy</part></link>,&quot; which served as a kind of sister essay to &quot;The Intentional Fallacy&quot; Wimsatt and Beardsley also discounted the reader's personal/emotional reaction to a literary work as a valid means of analyzing a text. This fallacy would later be repudiated by theorists from the<space/><link><target>reader-response</target></link><space/>school of literary theory. Ironically, one of the leading theorists from this school,<space/><link><target>Stanley Fish</target></link>, was himself trained by New Critics. Fish criticizes Wimsatt and Beardsley in his essay &quot;Literature in the Reader&quot; (1970).<extension extension_name='ref'>Leitch, Vincent B. , et al., eds.<space/><italics>The Norton Anthology of Theory and Criticism</italics>. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2001.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As summarized by Gaut and Livingston in their essay &quot;The Creation of Art&quot;: &quot;Structuralist and post-structuralists theorists and critics were sharply critical of many aspects of New Criticism, beginning with the emphasis on aesthetic appreciation and the so-called autonomy of art, but they reiterated the attack on biographical criticisms's assumption that the artist's activities and experience were a privileged critical topic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaut and Livingston, &quot;The Creation of Art&quot;, p.3.</extension><space/>These authors contend that: &quot;Anti-intentionalists, such as formalists, hold that the intentions involved in the making of art are irrelevant or peripheral to correctly interpreting art. So details of the act of creating a work, though possibly of interest in themselves, have no bearing on the correct interpretation of the work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gaut and Livingston, p.6">Gaut and Livingston, p.6.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gaut and Livingston define the intentionalists as distinct from formalists stating that: &quot;Intentionalists, unlike formalists, hold that reference to intentions is essential in fixing the correct interpretation of works.&quot; They quote<space/><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link><space/>as stating that, &quot;The task of criticism is the reconstruction of the creative process, where the creative process must in turn be thought of as something not stopping short of, but terminating on, the work of art itself.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gaut and Livingston, p.6"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Linguistic turn&quot; and its debate</heading><paragraph>The end of the 20th century fostered an extensive debate known as the linguistic turn controversy, or the &quot;innocent eye debate&quot;, and generally referred to as the structuralism-<link><target>poststructuralism</target></link><space/>debate in the philosophy of art. This debate discussed the encounter of the work of art as being determined by the relative extent to which the conceptual encounter with the work of art dominates over the perceptual encounter with the work of art.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Philosophy for Architecture</italics>, Branco Mitrovic, 2012.</extension><space/>Decisive for the linguistic turn debate in art history and the humanities were the works of yet another tradition, namely the<space/><link><target>structuralism</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ferdinand de Saussure</target></link><space/>and the ensuing movement of<space/><link><target>poststructuralism</target></link>. In 1981, the artist<space/><link><target>Mark Tansey</target></link><space/>created a work of art titled &quot;The Innocent Eye&quot; as a criticism of the prevailing climate of disagreement in the philosophy of art during the closing decades of the 20th century. Influential theorists include<space/><link><target>Judith Butler</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Luce Irigaray</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Julia Kristeva</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jacques Derrida</target></link>. The power of language, more specifically of certain rhetorical tropes, in art history and historical discourse was explored by<space/><link><target>Hayden White</target></link>. The fact that language is<space/><italics>not</italics><space/>a transparent medium of thought had been stressed by a very different form of<space/><link><target>philosophy of language</target></link><space/>which originated in the works of<space/><link><target>Johann Georg Hamann</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wilhelm von Humboldt</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Introduction to Structuralism, Michael Lane, Basic Books University of Michigan, 1970.</extension><space/><link><target>Ernst Gombrich</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nelson Goodman</target></link><space/>in his book<space/><italics><link><target>Languages of Art</target><part>Languages of Art: An Approach to a Theory of Symbols</part></link></italics><space/>came to hold that the conceptual encounter with the work of art predominated exclusively over the perceptual and visual encounter with the work of art during the 1960s and 1970s.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Languages of Art</target><part>Languages of Art: An Approach to a Theory of Symbols</part></link></italics>. Indianapolis: Bobbs-Merrill, 1968. 2nd ed. Indianapolis: Hackett, 1976. Based on his 1960-61<space/><link><target>John Locke lectures</target></link>.</extension><space/>He was challenged on the basis of research done by the Nobel prize winning psychologist<space/><link><target>Roger Sperry</target></link><space/>who maintained that the human visual encounter was not limited to concepts represented in language alone (the linguistic turn) and that other forms of psychological representations of the work of art were equally defensible and demonstrable. Sperry's view eventually prevailed by the end of the 20th century with aesthetic philosophers such as Nick Zangwill strongly defending a return to moderate aesthetic formalism among other alternatives.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nick Zangwill, &quot;Feasible Aesthetic Formalism&quot;,<space/><italics>Nous</italics>, December 1999, pp. 610-629.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Classification disputes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Classificatory disputes about art</arg></template><link><target>Image:Duchamp Fountaine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The original ''<link><target>Fountain (Duchamp)</target><part>Fountain</part></link>'' by<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link>, 1917, photographed by<space/><link><target>Alfred Stieglitz</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Little Galleries of the Photo-Secession</target><part>291</part></link><space/>after the 1917<space/><link><target>Society of Independent Artists</target></link><space/>exhibit. Stieglitz used a backdrop of ''The Warriors'' by<space/><link><target>Marsden Hartley</target></link><space/>to photograph the urinal. The exhibition entry tag can be clearly seen.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tomkins, p. 186">Tomkins,<space/><italics>Duchamp: A Biography</italics>, p. 186.</extension></part></link>Disputes as to whether or not to classify something as a work of art are referred to as classificatory disputes about art.</paragraph><paragraph>Classificatory disputes in the 20th century have included<space/><link><target>cubist</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>impressionist</target></link><space/>paintings,<space/><link><target>Duchamp</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Fountain (Duchamp)</target><part>Fountain</part></link></italics>, the movies, superlative imitations of<space/><link><target>J. S. G. Boggs</target><part>banknotes</part></link>,<space/><link><target>conceptual art</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>video games</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Deborah Solomon, &quot;2003: the 3rd Annual Year in Ideas: Video Game Art&quot;, New York Times, Magazine Section, 14 December 2003</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Philosopher David Novitz has argued that disagreement about the definition of art are rarely the heart of the problem. Rather, &quot;the passionate concerns and interests that humans vest in their social life&quot; are &quot;so much a part of all classificatory disputes about art&quot; (Novitz, 1996). According to Novitz, classificatory disputes are more often disputes about societal values and where society is trying to go than they are about theory proper. For example, when the<space/><link><target>Daily Mail</target></link><space/>criticized<space/><link><target>Damien Hirst</target><part>Hirst</part></link>'s and<space/><link><target>Tracey Emin</target><part>Emin</part></link>'s work by arguing &quot;For 1,000 years art has been one of our great civilising forces. Today, pickled sheep and soiled beds threaten to make barbarians of us all&quot; they are not advancing a definition or theory about art, but questioning the value of Hirst's and Emin's work.<extension extension_name='ref'>Painter, Colin. &quot;Contemporary Art and the Home&quot;. Berg Publishers, 2002. p. 12. ISBN 1-85973-661-0</extension><space/>In 1998,<space/><link><target>Arthur Danto</target></link>, suggested a thought experiment showing that &quot;the status of an artifact as work of art results from the ideas a culture applies to it, rather than its inherent physical or perceptible qualities. Cultural interpretation (an art theory of some kind) is therefore constitutive of an object's arthood.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Dutton, Denis<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.denisdutton.com/tribal_art.htm'>Tribal Art</link></italics><space/>in ''<link><target>Encyclopedia of Aesthetics</target></link>, edited by Michael Kelly (New York: Oxford University Press, 1998).</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Danto, Arthur. &quot;Artifact and Art.&quot; In Art/Artifact, edited by Susan Vogel. New York, 1988.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Anti-art</target></link><space/>is a label for art that intentionally challenges the established parameters and values of art;<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"></extension><space/>it is term associated with<space/><link><target>Dada</target><trail>ism</trail></link><space/>and attributed to<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link><space/>just before World War I,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"><link type='external' href='http://www.tate.org.uk/collections/glossary/definition.jsp?entryId=571'>&quot;Glossary: Anti-art&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>Tate</target></link>. Retrieved 23 January 2010.</extension><space/>when he was making art from<space/><link><target>found art</target><part>found objects</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"></extension><space/>One of these,<space/><italics><link><target>Fountain (Duchamp)</target><part>Fountain</part></link></italics><space/>(1917), an ordinary urinal, has achieved considerable prominence and influence on art.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"></extension><space/>Anti-art is a feature of work by<space/><link><target>Situationist International</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Schneider, Caroline.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-78637292.html'>&quot;Asger Jorn&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Artforum</target></link></italics>, 1 September 2001. Retrieved from encyclopedia.com, 24 January 2010.<space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://www.encyclopedia.com/doc/1G1-78637292.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20110513081709<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>the lo-fi Mail art movement, and the<space/><link><target>Young British Artists</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"></extension><space/>though it is a form still rejected by the<space/><link><target>Stuckism</target><part>Stuckists</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="tate"></extension><space/>who describe themselves as<space/><link><target>anti-anti-art</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ferguson, Euan.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/artanddesign/2003/apr/20/thesaatchigallery.art2'>&quot;In bed with Tracey, Sarah ... and Ron&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Observer</target></link></italics>, 20 April 2003. Retrieved on 2 May 2009.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.artnet.com/Magazine/news/artnetnews/artnetnews10-27-00.asp'>&quot;Stuck on the Turner Prize&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>artnet</target></link>, 27 October 2000. Retrieved on 2 May 2009.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Value judgment</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Aboriginal hollow log tomb.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Aboriginal hollow log tombs. National Gallery,<space/><link><target>Canberra</target></link>, Australia</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Somewhat in relation to the above, the word<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>is also used to apply judgments of value, as in such expressions as &quot;that meal was a work of art&quot; (the cook is an artist), or &quot;the art of deception&quot;, (the highly attained level of skill of the deceiver is praised). It is this use of the word as a measure of high quality and high value that gives the term its flavor of subjectivity.</paragraph><paragraph>Making judgments of value requires a basis for criticism. At the simplest level, a way to determine whether the impact of the object on the senses meets the criteria to be considered<space/><italics>art</italics><space/>is whether it is perceived to be attractive or repulsive. Though perception is always colored by experience, and is necessarily subjective, it is commonly understood that what is not somehow aesthetically satisfying cannot be art. However, &quot;good&quot; art is not always or even regularly aesthetically appealing to a majority of viewers. In other words, an artist's prime motivation need not be the pursuit of the aesthetic. Also, art often depicts terrible images made for social, moral, or thought-provoking reasons. For example,<space/><link><target>Francisco Goya</target></link>'s painting depicting the Spanish shootings of 3rd&amp;nbsp;of May 1808 is a graphic depiction of a firing squad executing several pleading civilians. Yet at the same time, the horrific imagery demonstrates Goya's keen artistic ability in composition and execution and produces fitting social and political outrage. Thus, the debate continues as to what mode of aesthetic satisfaction, if any, is required to define 'art'.</paragraph><paragraph>The assumption of new values or the rebellion against accepted notions of what is aesthetically superior need not occur concurrently with a complete abandonment of the pursuit of what is aesthetically appealing. Indeed, the reverse is often true, that the revision of what is popularly conceived of as being aesthetically appealing allows for a re-invigoration of aesthetic sensibility, and a new appreciation for the standards of art itself. Countless schools have proposed their own ways to define quality, yet they all seem to agree in at least one point: once their aesthetic choices are accepted, the value of the work of art is determined by its capacity to transcend the limits of its chosen medium to strike some universal chord by the rarity of the skill of the artist or in its accurate reflection in what is termed the<space/><italics><link><target>zeitgeist</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Art is often intended to appeal to and connect with human emotion. It can arouse<space/><link><target>aesthetic</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>morality</target><part>moral</part></link><space/>feelings, and can be understood as a way of communicating these feelings. Artists express something so that their audience is aroused to some extent, but they do not have to do so consciously. Art may be considered an exploration of the<space/><link><target>human condition</target></link>; that is, what it is to be human.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Graham<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Gordon<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Philosophy of the arts: an introduction to aesthetics<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Arts</arg><arg>Visual arts</arg></template><template><target>Wikipedia books</target><arg>Art</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Art movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Artist in residence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Formal analysis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of artistic media</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Outline of the visual arts</target></link><space/>guide to the subject of art presented as a<space/><link><target>tree structure</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>list of its subtopics.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Shiner, Larry. &quot;<link><target>The Invention of Art: A Cultural History</target></link>&quot;. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2003. ISBN 978-0-226-75342-3</listitem><listitem><link><target>Arthur Danto</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Abuse of Beauty: Aesthetics and the Concept of Art.</italics><space/>2003</listitem><listitem>Dana Arnold and Margaret Iverson (eds.)<space/><italics>Art and Thought</italics>. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 2003</listitem><listitem>Michael Ann Holly and Keith Moxey (eds.)<space/><italics>Art History Aesthetics Visual Studies</italics>. New Haven: Yale University Press, 2002. ISBN 0300097891</listitem><listitem>John Whitehead.<space/><italics>Grasping for the Wind</italics>, 2001</listitem><listitem>Noel Carroll,<space/><italics>Theories of Art Today</italics>, 2000</listitem><listitem>Evelyn Hatcher, ed.<space/><italics>Art as Culture: An Introduction to the Anthropology of Art</italics>, 1999</listitem><listitem><link><target>Catherine de Zegher</target></link><space/>(ed.).<space/><italics>Inside the Visible</italics>. MIT Press, 1996</listitem><listitem>Nina, Felshin, ed.<space/><italics>But is it Art?</italics><space/>1995</listitem><listitem>Stephen Davies,<space/><italics>Definitions of Art</italics>, 1991</listitem><listitem>Oscar Wilde, &quot;Intentions&quot;.</listitem><listitem>Jean Robertson and Craig McDaniel, &quot;Themes of Contemporary Art, Visual Art after 1980&quot;, 2005</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Art</arg></template><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no
</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">no
</arg><arg name="others">no
</arg><arg name="about">yes
</arg><arg name="label">Art<space/></arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Shiner, Larry.<space/><italics>The Invention of Art: A Cultural History</italics>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2003. ISBN 978-0-226-75342-3</listitem><listitem>Augros, Robert M., Stanciu, George N.<space/><italics>The New Story of Science: mind and the universe</italics>, Lake Bluff, Ill.: Regnery Gateway, 1984. ISBN 0-89526-833-7 (this book has significant material on art and science)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link>,<space/><italics>Art and its Objects: An introduction to aesthetics</italics>. New York: Harper &amp; Row, 1968.<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>1077405</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Carl Jung</target></link>,<space/><italics>Man and His Symbols</italics>. London: Pan Books, 1978. ISBN 0330253212</listitem><listitem><link><target>Benedetto Croce</target></link>.<space/><italics>Aesthetic as Science of Expression and General Linguistic</italics>, 2002</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wadysaw Tatarkiewicz</target></link>,<space/><italics>A History of Six Ideas: an Essay in Aesthetics</italics>, translated from the Polish by<space/><link><target>Christopher Kasparek</target></link>, The Hague, Martinus Nijhoff, 1980</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link>, &quot;<link><target>What Is Art?</target></link>&quot;, 1897</listitem><listitem>Kleiner, Gardner, Mamiya and Tansey.<space/><italics>Art Through the Ages, Twelfth Edition (2 volumes)</italics><space/>Wadsworth, 2004. ISBN 0-534-64095-8 (vol 1) and ISBN 0-534-64091-5 (vol 2)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kristine Stiles</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Peter Selz</target></link>, eds.<space/><italics>Theories and Documents of Contemporary Art</italics>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1986</listitem><listitem>Florian Dombois, Ute Meta Bauer, Claudia Mareis and Michael Schwab, eds.<space/><italics>Intellectual Birdhouse. Artistic Practice as Research</italics>. London: Koening Books, 2012. ISBN 978-3863351182</listitem><listitem>Dana Arnold and Margaret Iverson, eds.<space/><italics>Art and Thought</italics>. London: Blackwell, 2003. ISBN 0631227156</listitem><listitem>Antony Briant and<space/><link><target>Griselda Pollock</target></link>, eds.<space/><italics>Digital and Other Virtualities: Renegotiating the image</italics>. London and NY: I.B.Tauris, 2010. ISBN 978-1441676313</listitem><listitem>Carol Armstrong and Catherine de Zegher, eds.<space/><italics>Women Artists at the Millennium</italics>. Massachusetts: October Books/The MIT Press, 2006. ISBN 026201226X</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Sisterlinks</target><arg>art</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline>*<space/><link type='external' href='http://xtf.lib.virginia.edu/xtf/view?docId=DicHist/uvaBook/tei/DicHist1.xml;chunk.id=dv1-17;toc.depth=1;toc.id=dv1-17;brand=default;query=Dictionary%20of%20the%20History%20of%20Ideas#1'>''Art and Play'' from the Dictionary of the History of ideas</link></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://witcombe.sbc.edu/ARTHLinks.html'>In-depth directory of art</link></listitem><listitem><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.sil.si.edu/digitalcollections/art-design/artandartistfiles/'>Art and Artist Files in the Smithsonian Libraries Collection</link></italics><space/>(2005) Smithsonian Digital Libraries</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ahds.ac.uk/'>Visual Arts Data Service (VADS)</link><space/>online collections from UK museums, galleries, universities</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.RevolutionArtMagazine.com/'>RevolutionArt Art magazines with worldwide exhibitions, callings and competitions</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>sep entry</target><arg>art-definition</arg><arg>The Definition of Art</arg><arg>Thomas Adajian</arg></template></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>aesthetics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Aesthetics</target></link><link><target>Category:Arts</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Visual arts</target></link></paragraph></article>