<article title='Antonio_Vivaldi'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Vivaldi</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Antonio Vivaldi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Antonio Vivaldi (engraving by<space/><template><target>ill</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>François Morellon de La Cave</arg></template>, from Michel-Charles Le Cne's edition of Vivaldi's Op. 8)</part></link></preline></preblock><paragraph><bold>Antonio Lucio Vivaldi</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>anˈtɔːnjo ˈluːtʃo viˈvaldi</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>; 4 March 1678&amp;nbsp; 28 July 1741) was an Italian<space/><link><target>Baroque music</target><part>Baroque</part></link><space/>composer,<space/><link><target>virtuoso</target></link><space/>violinist, teacher and<space/><link><target>Clergy</target><part>cleric</part></link>. Born in<space/><link><target>Venice</target></link>, he is recognized as one of the greatest Baroque composers, and his influence during his lifetime was widespread across Europe. He is known mainly for composing many instrumental<space/><link><target>concerto</target><trail>s</trail></link>, for the violin and a variety of other instruments, as well as sacred choral works and more than forty<space/><link><target>opera</target><trail>s</trail></link>. His best-known work is a series of<space/><link><target>violin concerto</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>known as<space/><italics><link><target>The Four Seasons (Vivaldi)</target><part>The Four Seasons</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Many of his compositions were written for the female music ensemble of the<space/><italics><link><target>Ospedale della Piet</target></link></italics>, a home for abandoned children where Vivaldi (who had been ordained as a<space/><link><target>Priesthood (Catholic Church)</target><part>Catholic priest</part></link>) was employed from 1703 to 1715 and from 1723 to 1740. Vivaldi also had some success with expensive stagings of his operas in<space/><link><target>Venice</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mantua</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>. After meeting the<space/><link><target>Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Emperor Charles VI</part></link>, Vivaldi moved to Vienna, hoping for preferment. However, the Emperor died soon after Vivaldi's arrival, and Vivaldi himself died less than a year later in poverty.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Life</heading><heading level='3'>Childhood</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chiesa di San Giovanni in Bragora - Venezia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Church where Vivaldi was baptised: San Giovanni Battista in Bragora,<space/><link><target>Castello, Venice</target><part>Sestiere di Castello</part></link>, Venice</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Antonio Lucio Vivaldi was born in 1678 in Venice,<extension extension_name='ref' name="TalbotGrove"></extension><space/>then the capital of the<space/><link><target>Republic of Venice</target></link>. He was<space/><link><target>Baptism</target><part>baptized</part></link><space/>immediately after his birth at his home by the midwife, which led to a belief that his life was somehow in danger. Though not known for certain, the child's immediate baptism was most likely due either to his poor health or to an<space/><link><target>earthquake</target></link><space/>that shook the city that day. In the trauma of the earthquake, Vivaldi's mother may have dedicated him to the priesthood.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walter Kolneder,<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: Documents of his life and works</italics><space/>(Amsterdam: Heinrichshofen's Verlag, Wilhelmshaven, Locarno, 1982), 46.</extension><space/>Vivaldi's official church baptism took place two months later.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated5">Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd., 1978), 39.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Vivaldi's parents were Giovanni Battista Vivaldi and Camilla Calicchio, as recorded in the register of San Giovanni in Bragora.<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 15</extension><space/>Vivaldi had five siblings: Margarita Gabriela, Cecilia Maria, Bonaventura Tomaso, Zanetta Anna, and Francesco Gaetano.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 37.</extension><space/>Giovanni Battista, who was a barber before becoming a professional violinist, taught Antonio to play the violin and then toured Venice playing the violin with his young son. Antonio was probably taught at an early age, judging by the extensive musical knowledge he had acquired by the age of 24, when he started working at the Ospedale della Piet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 41</extension><space/>Giovanni Battista was one of the founders of the<space/><italics>Sovvegno dei musicisti di Santa Cecilia</italics>, an association of musicians.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd., 1978), 36.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The president of the<space/><italics>Sovvegno</italics><space/>was<space/><link><target>Giovanni Legrenzi</target></link>, an early Baroque composer and the<space/><italics>maestro di cappella</italics><space/>at<space/><link><target>St Mark's Basilica</target></link>. It is possible that Legrenzi gave the young Antonio his first lessons in composition. The Luxembourg scholar Walter Kolneder has discerned the influence of Legrenzi's style in Vivaldi's early liturgical work<space/><italics>Laetatus sum</italics><space/>(<link><target>Ryom-Verzeichnis</target><part>RV</part></link><space/>Anh 31), written in 1691 at the age of thirteen. Vivaldi's father may have been a composer himself: in 1689, an opera titled<space/><italics>La Fedelt sfortunata</italics><space/>was composed by a Giovanni Battista Rossi the name under which Vivaldi's father had joined the Sovvegno di Santa Cecilia.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, P. 40</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Vivaldi's health was problematic. His symptoms,<space/><italics>strettezza di petto</italics><space/>(&quot;tightness of the chest&quot;), have been interpreted as a form of<space/><link><target>asthma</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated5"></extension><space/>This did not prevent him from learning to play the violin, composing or taking part in musical activities,<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated5"></extension><space/>although it did stop him from playing wind instruments. In 1693, at the age of fifteen, he began studying to become a<space/><link><target>Priesthood (Catholic Church)</target><part>priest</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 16</extension><space/>He was ordained in 1703, aged 25, and was soon nicknamed<space/><italics>il Prete Rosso</italics>, &quot;The Red Priest&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Pincherle,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics><space/>(Paris: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 1957), 16</extension><space/>(<italics><link><target>Wikt:rosso</target><part>Rosso</part></link></italics><space/>is Italian for &quot;red&quot;, and would have referred to the color of his hair, a family trait.)</paragraph><paragraph>Not long after his ordination, in 1704, he was given a dispensation from celebrating<space/><link><target>Mass (liturgy)</target><part>Mass</part></link><space/>because of his ill health. Vivaldi only said Mass as a priest a few times and appeared to have withdrawn from priestly duties, though he remained a priest.</paragraph><heading level='3'>At the<space/><italics>Conservatorio dell'Ospedale della Piet</italics></heading><paragraph>In September 1703, Vivaldi became<space/><italics>maestro di violino</italics><space/>(master of violin) at an<space/><link><target>orphanage</target></link><space/>called the Pio<space/><link><target>Ospedale della Piet</target></link><space/>(Devout Hospital of Mercy) in Venice.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TalbotGrove">Michael Talbot, &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.oxfordmusiconline.com/subscriber/article/grove/music/40120'>Vivaldi, Antonio</link>&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Grove Music Online</target></link></italics><space/><template><target>Subscription required</target></template></extension><space/>While Vivaldi is most famous as a composer, he was regarded as an exceptional technical violinist as well. The German architect Johann Friedrich Armand von Uffenbach referred to Vivaldi as &quot;the famous composer and violinist&quot; and said that &quot;Vivaldi played a solo accompaniment excellently, and at the conclusion he added a free fantasy [an improvised cadenza] which absolutely astounded me, for it is hardly possible that anyone has ever played, or ever will play, in such a fashion.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 49</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:8106 - Venezia - Calle della Piet - Lapide Vivaldi - Foto Giovanni Dall'Orto 8-Aug-2007.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>300 px</part><part>Commemorative plaque beside the Ospedale della Piet.</part></link>Vivaldi was only 25 when he started working at the Ospedale della Piet. Over the next thirty years he composed most of his major works while working there.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 51</extension><space/>There were four similar institutions in Venice; their purpose was to give shelter and education to children who were abandoned or orphaned, or whose families could not support them. They were financed by funds provided by the Republic.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Pincherle,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics><space/>(Paris: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 1957), 18.</extension><space/>The boys learned a trade and had to leave when they reached 15. The girls received a musical education, and the most talented stayed and became members of the Ospedale's renowned orchestra and choir.</paragraph><paragraph>Shortly after Vivaldi's appointment, the orphans began to gain appreciation and esteem abroad, too. Vivaldi wrote concertos, cantatas and sacred vocal music for them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 77</extension><space/>These sacred works, which number over 60, are varied: they included solo motets and large-scale choral works for soloists, double chorus, and orchestra.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 78</extension><space/>In 1704, the position of teacher of<space/><italics><link><target>lyra viol</target><part>viola all'inglese</part></link></italics><space/>was added to his duties as violin instructor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landon26">Landon, p. 26</extension><space/>The position of<space/><italics>maestro di coro</italics>, which was at one time filled by Vivaldi, required a lot of time and work. He had to compose an oratorio or concerto at every feast and teach the orphans both music theory and how to play certain instruments.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Pincherle,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics><space/>(Paris: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 1957), 24.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>His relationship with the board of directors of the Ospedale was often strained. The board had to take a vote every year on whether to keep a teacher. The vote on Vivaldi was seldom unanimous, and went 7 to 6 against him in 1709.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated3">Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 48.</extension><space/>After a year as a freelance musician, he was recalled by the Ospedale with a unanimous vote in 1711; clearly during his year's absence the board realized the importance of his role.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated3"></extension><space/>He became responsible for all of the musical activity of the institution<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 54.</extension><space/>when he was promoted to<space/><italics>maestro de' concerti</italics><space/>(music director) in 1716.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 59.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1705, the first collection (<italics>Connor Cassara</italics>) of his works was published by Giuseppe Sala:<extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Pincherle,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics><space/>(Paris: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 1957), 38.</extension><space/>his Opus 1 is a collection of 12<space/><link><target>sonata</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for two violins and basso continuo, in a conventional style.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Landon26"></extension><space/>In 1709, a second collection of 12 sonatas for violin and basso continuo appeared, his Opus 2.<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 31</extension><space/>A real breakthrough as a composer came with his first collection of 12 concerti for one, two, and four violins with strings,<space/><italics><link><target>L'estro Armonico</target><part>L'estro armonico</part></link></italics><space/>Opus 3, which was published in<space/><link><target>Amsterdam</target></link><space/>in 1711 by<space/><link><target>Estienne Roger</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 42</extension><space/>dedicated to<space/><link><target>Ferdinando (III) de' Medici</target><part>Grand Prince Ferdinand of Tuscany</part></link>. The prince sponsored many musicians including<space/><link><target>Alessandro Scarlatti</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>George Frideric Handel</target></link>. He was a musician himself, and Vivaldi probably met him in Venice.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1">Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 54.</extension><space/><italics>L'estro armonico</italics><space/>was a resounding success all over Europe. It was followed in 1714 by<space/><italics><link><target>La stravaganza</target></link></italics><space/>Opus 4, a collection of concerti for solo violin and strings,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Michael Talbot 1978">Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 58.</extension><space/>dedicated to an old violin student of Vivaldi's, the Venetian noble Vettor Dolfin.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot, Vivaldi (London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 71.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In February 1711, Vivaldi and his father traveled to<space/><link><target>Brescia</target></link>, where his setting of the<space/><link><target>Stabat Mater</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Stabat Mater (Vivaldi)</target><part>RV 621</part></link>) was played as part of a religious festival. The work seems to have been written in haste: the string parts are simple, the music of the first three movements is repeated in the next three, and not all the text is set. Nevertheless, perhaps in part because of the forced essentiality of the music, the work is one of his early masterpieces.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite his frequent travels from 1718, the Piet paid him 2<space/><link><target>sequin (coin)</target><part>sequins</part></link><space/>to write two concerti a month for the orchestra and to rehearse with them at least five times when in Venice. The Piet's records show that he was paid for 140 concerti between 1723 and 1733.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Opera impresario</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Vivaldis first edition of Juditha triumphnas.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>First edition of ''Juditha triumphans''<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baroque music"><link type='external' href='http://www.baroquemusic.org/bqxvivaldi.html'>Baroque Music</link><space/><italics>As far as his theatrical activities were concerned, the end of 1716 was a high point for Vivaldi. In November, he managed to have the Ospedale della Piet perform his first great oratorio, Juditha Triumphans devicta Holofernis barbaric.<space/><template><target>sic</target></template><space/>This work was an allegorical description of the victory of the Venetians over the Turks in August 1716.</italics></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In early 18th-century Venice, opera was the most popular musical entertainment. It proved most profitable for Vivaldi. There were several theaters competing for the public's attention. Vivaldi started his career as an opera composer as a sideline: his first opera,<space/><italics><link><target>Ottone in villa</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 729) was performed not in Venice, but at the Garzerie Theater in<space/><link><target>Vicenza</target></link><space/>in 1713.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 98</extension><space/>The following year, Vivaldi became the<space/><link><target>impresario</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Teatro San Angelo</target></link><space/>in Venice, where his opera<space/><italics><link><target>Orlando finto pazzo</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 727) was performed. The work was not to the public's taste, and it closed after a couple of weeks, being replaced with a repeat of a different work already given the previous year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1715, he presented<space/><italics><link><target>Nerone fatto Cesare</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 724, now lost), with music by seven different composers, of which he was the leader. The opera contained eleven<space/><link><target>aria</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and was a success. In the late season, Vivaldi planned to put on an opera composed entirely by him,<space/><italics><link><target>Arsilda, regina di Ponto</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 700), but the state censor blocked the performance. The main character, Arsilda, falls in love with another woman, Lisea, who is pretending to be a man.<extension extension_name='ref' name="autogenerated1"></extension><space/>Vivaldi got the censor to accept the opera the following year, and it was a resounding success.</paragraph><paragraph>At this period, the<space/><italics>Piet</italics><space/>commissioned several liturgical works. The most important were two<space/><link><target>oratorio</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/><italics>Moyses Deus Pharaonis</italics>, (RV 643) is lost. The second,<space/><italics><link><target>Juditha triumphans</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 644), celebrates the victory of the Republic of Venice against the Turks and the recapture of the island of<space/><link><target>Corfu</target></link>. Composed in 1716, it is one of his sacred masterpieces. All eleven singing parts were performed by girls of the Piet, both the female and male roles. Many of the<space/><link><target>aria</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>include parts for solo instrumentsrecorders, oboes, violas d'amore, and mandolinsthat showcased the range of talents of the girls.<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon, p. 52</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Also in 1716, Vivaldi wrote and produced two more operas,<space/><italics><link><target>L'incoronazione di Dario</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 719) and<space/><italics>La costanza trionfante degli amori e degli odi</italics><space/>(RV 706). The latter was so popular that it performed two years later, re-edited and retitled<space/><italics>Artabano re dei Parti</italics><space/>(RV 701, now lost). It was also performed in Prague in 1732. In the following years, Vivaldi wrote several operas that were performed all over Italy.</paragraph><paragraph>His progressive operatic style caused him some trouble with more conservative musicians, like<space/><link><target>Benedetto Marcello</target></link>, a magistrate and amateur musician who wrote a<space/><link><target>pamphlet</target></link><space/>denouncing him and his operas. The pamphlet,<space/><italics><link><target>Il teatro alla moda</target></link></italics>, attacks Vivaldi without mentioning him directly. The cover drawing shows a boat (the Sant'Angelo), on the left end of which stands a little angel wearing a priest's hat and playing the violin. The Marcello family claimed ownership of the Teatro Sant'Angelo, and a long legal battle had been fought with the management for its restitution, without success. The obscure writing under the picture mentions non-existent places and names:<space/><italics>ALDIVIVA</italics><space/>is an anagram of<space/><italics>A. Vivaldi</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In a letter written by Vivaldi to his patron Marchese Bentivoglio in 1737, he makes reference to his &quot;94 operas&quot;. Only around 50 operas by Vivaldi have been discovered, and no other documentation of the remaining operas exists. Although Vivaldi may have exaggerated, in his dual role of composer and<space/><italics>impresario</italics><space/>it is plausible that he may either have written or been responsible for the production of as many as 94 operas during a career which by then had spanned almost 25 years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heller, p. 97</extension><space/>While Vivaldi certainly composed many operas in his time, he never reached the prominence of other great composers like<space/><link><target>Alessandro Scarlatti</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Johann Adolph Hasse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Leonardo Leo</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Baldassare Galuppi</target></link>, as evidenced by his inability to keep a production running for any extended period of time in any major opera house.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heller114">Heller, p. 114</extension></paragraph><paragraph>His most successful operas were<space/><italics>La costanza trionfante</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Farnace</italics><space/>which garnered six revivals each.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heller114"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Mantua and the<italics><space/>Four Seasons</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Vivaldi caricature.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Caricature</target></link><space/>by P. L. Ghezzi, Rome (1723)<extension extension_name='ref'>There are only three known surviving depictions of Vivaldi made in his lifetime: this caricature, the woodcut at the beginning of this article, and an oil portrait of the composer and his violin.<space/><italics>Groves Dictionary of Music and Musicians</italics><space/>has disputed the authenticity of the last portrait.</extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1717 or 1718, Vivaldi was offered a new prestigious position as<space/><italics>Maestro di Cappella</italics><space/>of the court of prince<space/><link><target>Philip of Hesse-Darmstadt</target></link>, governor of<space/><link><target>Mantua</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 64.</extension><space/>He moved there for three years and produced several operas, among which was<space/><italics><link><target>Tito Manlio</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 738). In 1721, he was in Milan, where he presented the pastoral drama<space/><italics><link><target>La Silvia</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 734, 9 arias survive). He visited Milan again the following year with the oratorio<space/><italics>L'adorazione delli tre re magi al bambino Ges</italics><space/>(RV 645, also lost). In 1722 he moved to Rome, where he introduced his operas' new style. The new<space/><link><target>pope Benedict XIII</target></link><space/>invited Vivaldi to play for him. In 1725, Vivaldi returned to Venice, where he produced four operas in the same year.</paragraph><paragraph>During this period Vivaldi wrote the<space/><italics><link><target>The Four Seasons (Vivaldi)</target><part>Four Seasons</part></link></italics>, four violin concertos depicting scenes appropriate for each season. Three of the concerti are of original conception, while the first, &quot;Spring&quot;, borrows motifs from a Sinfonia in the first act of his contemporaneous opera &quot;<italics>Il Giustino</italics>&quot;. The inspiration for the concertos was probably the countryside around Mantua. They were a revolution in musical conception: in them Vivaldi represented flowing creeks, singing birds (of different species, each specifically characterized), barking dogs, buzzing mosquitoes, crying shepherds, storms, drunken dancers, silent nights, hunting parties from both the hunters' and the prey's point of view, frozen landscapes, ice-skating children, and warming winter fires. Each concerto is associated with a<space/><link><target>sonnet</target></link>, possibly by Vivaldi, describing the scenes depicted in the music. They were published as the first four concertos in a collection of twelve,<space/><italics><link><target>Il cimento dell'armonia e dell'inventione</target></link></italics>, Opus 8, published in Amsterdam by<space/><link><target>Michel-Charles Le Cne</target></link><space/>in 1725.</paragraph><paragraph>During his time in Mantua, Vivaldi became acquainted with an aspiring young singer<space/><link><target>Anna Gir</target><part>Anna Tessieri Gir</part></link><space/>who was to become his student, protge, and favorite prima donna.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J. M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 66.</extension><space/>Anna, along with her older half-sister Paolina, became part of Vivaldi's entourage and regularly accompanied him on his many travels. There was speculation about the nature of Vivaldi's and Giro's relationship, but no evidence to indicate anything beyond friendship and professional collaboration. Although Vivaldi's relationship with Anna Gir was questioned, he adamantly denied any romantic relationship in a letter to his patron Bentivoglio dated 16 November 1737.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 67.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Later life and death</heading><paragraph>At the height of his career, Vivaldi received commissions from European nobility and royalty. The<space/><italics>serenata</italics><space/>(cantata)<space/><italics>Gloria e Imeneo</italics><space/>(RV 687) was commissioned in 1725 by the French<space/><link><target>ambassador</target></link><space/>to Venice in celebration of the marriage of<space/><link><target>Louis XV of France</target><part>Louis XV</part></link>. The following year, another<space/><italics>serenata</italics>,<space/><italics>La Sena festeggiante</italics><space/>(RV 694), was written for and premiered at the French embassy as well, celebrating the birth of the French royal princesses,<space/><link><target>Princess Henriette of France</target><part>Henriette</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Louise lisabeth of France</target><part>Louise lisabeth</part></link>. Vivaldi's Opus 9,<space/><italics><link><target>La Cetra (Vivaldi)</target><part>La Cetra</part></link></italics>, was dedicated to<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Emperor</part></link><space/><link><target>Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Charles VI</part></link>. In 1728, Vivaldi met the emperor while the emperor was visiting<space/><link><target>Trieste</target></link><space/>to oversee the construction of a new port. Charles admired the music of the Red Priest so much that he is said to have spoken more with the composer during their one meeting than he spoke to his ministers in over two years. He gave Vivaldi the title of<space/><link><target>knight</target></link>, a gold medal and an invitation to Vienna. Vivaldi gave Charles a manuscript copy of<space/><italics>La Cetra</italics>, a set of concerti almost completely different from the set of the same title published as Opus 9. The printing was probably delayed, forcing Vivaldi to gather an improvised collection for the emperor.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Teatro alla moda.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part></part><part>Frontispiece of ''Il teatro alla moda''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Accompanied by his father, Vivaldi traveled to Vienna and Prague in 1730, where his opera<space/><italics><link><target>Farnace</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 711) was presented.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vivaldi's connections with musical life in Prague and his association with<space/><link><target>Antonio Denzio</target></link>, the impresario of the<space/><link><target>Franz Anton von Sporck</target><part>Sporck theater in Prague</part></link><space/>are detailed in Daniel E. Freeman,<space/><italics>The Opera Theater of Count Franz Anton von Sporck in Prague</italics><space/>(Stuyvesant, N.Y.: Pendragon Press, 1992).</extension><space/>Some of his later operas were created in collaboration with two of Italy's major writers of the time.<space/><italics><link><target>L'Olimpiade</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Catone in Utica</target></link></italics><space/>were written by<space/><link><target>Pietro Metastasio</target></link>, the major representative of the<space/><link><target>Academy of Arcadia</target><part>Arcadian</part></link><space/>movement and court poet in Vienna.<space/><italics><link><target>Griselda (Vivaldi)</target><part>La Griselda</part></link></italics><space/>was rewritten by the young<space/><link><target>Carlo Goldoni</target></link><space/>from an earlier libretto by<space/><link><target>Apostolo Zeno</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Like many composers of the time, the final years of Vivaldi's life found him in financial difficulties. His compositions were no longer held in such high esteem as they once were in Venice; changing musical tastes quickly made them outmoded. In response, Vivaldi chose to sell off sizeable numbers of his manuscripts at paltry prices to finance his migration to<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walter Kolneder,<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: Documents of his life and works</italics><space/>(Amsterdam: Heinrichshofen's Verlag, Wilhelmshaven, Locarno, 1982), 179.</extension><space/>The reasons for Vivaldi's departure from Venice are unclear, but it seems likely that, after the success of his meeting with Emperor Charles VI, he wished to take up the position of a composer in the imperial court. On his way to Vienna, Vivaldi may have stopped in Graz to see Anna Gir.<extension extension_name='ref'>Walter Kolneder,<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: Documents of his life and works</italics><space/>(Amsterdam: Heinrichshofen's Verlag, Wilhelmshaven, Locarno, 1982), 180.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is also likely that Vivaldi went to Vienna to stage operas, especially as he took up residence near the<space/><link><target>Krntnertortheater</target></link>. Shortly after his arrival in Vienna, Charles VI died, which left the composer without any royal protection or a steady source of income. Soon afterwards, Vivaldi became impoverished<extension extension_name='ref'>Landon supplies this assertion and furthermore quotes the report of Vivaldi's death which reached Venice in the<space/><italics>Commemorali Gradenigo</italics>: &quot;Abbe Lord Antonio Vivaldi, incomparable virtuoso of the violin, known as the Red Priest, much esteemed for his compositions and concertos, who earned more than 50,000 ducats in his life, but his disorderly prodigality caused him to die a pauper in Vienna.&quot; Landon, p. 166</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Pincherle,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics><space/>(Paris: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, Inc., 1957), 53.</extension><space/>and died during the night of 27/28 July 1741, aged 63,<extension extension_name='ref'>Talbot (p. 69) gives the 27th as the day of death. Formichetti (p. 194) reports that he died during the night and his death was the first registered on the next day. Heller (p. 263) states: &quot;The composer's death is noted in the official coroner's report and in the burial account book of St. Stephen's Cathedral Parish as having occurred on 28 July 1741&quot;. But the so-called<space/><italics>Totenbeschauprotokoll</italics><space/>is not a reliable source, since the date can refer to when the entry was made, not to the actual time of death.</extension><space/>of &quot;internal infection&quot;, in a house owned by the widow of a Viennese saddlemaker. On 28 July he was buried in a simple grave in a burial ground that was owned by the public hospital fund. Vivaldi's funeral took place at<space/><link><target>St. Stephen's Cathedral, Vienna</target><part>St. Stephen's Cathedral</part></link>, but the young<space/><link><target>Joseph Haydn</target></link><space/>had nothing to do with this burial, since no music was performed on that occasion.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Michael Lorenz (musicologist)</target><part>Michael Lorenz</part></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://michaelorenz.blogspot.co.at/2014/06/haydn-singing-at-vivaldis-exequies.html'>&quot;Haydn Singing at Vivaldi's Exequies: An Ineradicable Myth&quot;</link><space/>(Vienna 2014)</extension><space/>The cost of his funeral with a 'Kleingelut' was 19 Gulden 45 Kreuzer which was rather expensive for the lowest class of peal of bells.</paragraph><paragraph>He was buried next to<space/><link><target>Karlskirche</target></link>, in an area which is now part of the site of the<space/><link><target>Vienna University of Technology</target><part>Technical Institute</part></link>. The house where he lived in Vienna has since been destroyed; the<space/><link><target>Hotel Sacher</target></link><space/>is built on part of the site. Memorial plaques have been placed at both locations, as well as a Vivaldi &quot;star&quot; in the Viennese Musikmeile and a monument at the Rooseveltplatz.</paragraph><paragraph>Only three portraits of Vivaldi are known to survive: an engraving, an ink sketch and an oil painting. The engraving, by Francois Morellon La Cave, was made in 1725 and shows Vivaldi holding a sheet of music. The ink sketch, a<space/><link><target>caricature</target></link>, was done by<space/><link><target>Pier Leone Ghezzi</target><part>Ghezzi</part></link><space/>in 1723 and shows Vivaldi's head and shoulders in profile. The oil painting, which can be seen in the Liceo Musicale of Bologna, gives what is possibly the most accurate picture and shows Vivaldi's red hair under his blonde wig.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot,<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics><space/>(London: J.M. Dent &amp; Sons, Ltd, 1978), 93.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Style and influence</heading><paragraph><template><target>listen</target><arg name="type">music
</arg><arg name="filename"><space/>01 - Vivaldi Spring mvt 1 Allegro - John Harrison violin.ogg
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>"La primavera" (Spring) – Movement 1: Allegro from ''The Four Seasons''
</arg><arg name="description"><space/>A 2000 live performance by [[Wichita State University]] Chamber Players.
</arg></template>Vivaldi's music was innovative. He brightened the formal and rhythmic structure of the concerto, in which he looked for harmonic contrasts and innovative melodies and themes; many of his compositions are flamboyantly, almost playfully, exuberant.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Johann Sebastian Bach</target></link><space/>was deeply influenced by Vivaldi's concertos and arias (recalled in his<space/><italics><link><target>St John Passion</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>St Matthew Passion</target></link></italics>, and<space/><link><target>Bach cantata</target><part>cantatas</part></link>). Bach transcribed six of Vivaldi's concerti for solo keyboard, three for organ, and one for four harpsichords, strings, and<space/><link><target>Figured bass</target><part>basso continuo</part></link><space/>(BWV 1065) based upon the concerto for four violins, two violas, cello, and basso continuo (<link><target>Ryom-Verzeichnis</target><part>RV</part></link><space/>580).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Posthumous reputation</heading><paragraph>During his lifetime, Vivaldi's popularity quickly made him famous in other countries, including France, but after his death the composer's popularity dwindled. After the Baroque period, Vivaldi's published concerti became relatively unknown and were largely ignored. Even Vivaldi's most famous work,<space/><italics>The Four Seasons</italics>, was unknown in its original edition during the<space/><link><target>Classical period (music)</target><part>Classical</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Romantic music</target><part>Romantic</part></link><space/>periods.</paragraph><paragraph>During the early 20th century,<space/><link><target>Fritz Kreisler</target></link>'s Concerto in C, in the Style of Vivaldi (which he passed off as an original Vivaldi work) helped revive Vivaldi's reputation. This spurred the French scholar<space/><link><target>Marc Pincherle</target></link><space/>to begin an academic study of Vivaldi's oeuvre. Many Vivaldi manuscripts were rediscovered, which were acquired by the<space/><link><target>Turin National University Library</target></link><space/>as a result of the generous sponsorship of<space/><link><target>Turin</target><trail>ese</trail></link><space/>businessmen Roberto Foa and Filippo Giordano, in memory of their sons. This led to a renewed interest in Vivaldi by, among others, Mario Rinaldi,<space/><link><target>Alfredo Casella</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ezra Pound</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Olga Rudge</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Desmond Chute</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arturo Toscanini</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arnold Schering</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Louis Kaufman</target></link>, all of whom were instrumental in the Vivaldi revival of the 20th century.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1926, in a monastery in<space/><link><target>Piedmont</target></link>, researchers discovered fourteen folios of Vivaldi's work that were previously thought to have been lost during the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>. Some missing volumes in the numbered set were discovered in the collections of the descendants of the Grand Duke Durazzo, who had acquired the monastery complex in the 18th century. The volumes contained 300 concertos, 19 operas and over 100 vocal-instrumental works.<extension extension_name='ref'>Antonio Vivaldi biography by Alexander Kuznetsov and Louise Thomas, a booklet attached to the CD &quot;The best of Vivaldi&quot;, published and recorded by Madacy Entertainment Group Inc, St. Laurent Quebec Canada</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The resurrection of Vivaldi's unpublished works in the 20th century is mostly due to the efforts of<space/><link><target>Alfredo Casella</target></link>, who in 1939 organized the historic Vivaldi Week, in which the rediscovered<space/><link><target>Gloria (Vivaldi)</target><part>Gloria</part></link><space/>(RV 589) and l'Olimpiade were revived. Since<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, Vivaldi's compositions have enjoyed wide success.<space/><link><target>Historically informed performance</target><trail>s</trail></link>, often on &quot;original instruments&quot;, have increased Vivaldi's fame still further.</paragraph><paragraph>Recent rediscoveries of works by Vivaldi include two<space/><link><target>psalm</target></link><space/>settings of<space/><italics>Nisi Dominus</italics><space/>(RV 803, in eight movements) and<space/><italics>Dixit Dominus</italics><space/>(RV 807, in eleven movements). These were identified in 2003 and 2005 respectively, by the Australian scholar Janice Stockigt. The Vivaldi scholar<space/><link><target>Michael Talbot (musicologist)</target><part>Michael Talbot</part></link><space/>described RV 807 as &quot;arguably the best nonoperatic work from Vivaldi's pen to come to light since... ...the 1920s&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Talbot, liner notes to the CD<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Dixit Dominus</italics>, Krnerscher Sing-Verein Dresden (Dresdner Instrumental-Concert), Peter Kopp,<space/><link><target>Deutsche Grammophon</target></link><space/>2006, catalogue number 4776145</extension><space/>Vivaldi's lost 1730 opera<space/><italics><link><target>Argippo</target></link></italics><space/>(RV 697) was rediscovered in 2006 by the<space/><link><target>harpsichordist</target></link><space/>and conductor Ondej Macek, whose Hofmusici orchestra performed the work at<space/><link><target>Prague Castle</target></link><space/>on 3 May 2008, its first performance since 1730.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of compositions by Antonio Vivaldi</arg><arg>List of operas by Vivaldi</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A composition by Vivaldi is identified by<space/><link><target>Ryom-Verzeichnis</target><part>RV number</part></link>, which refers to its place in the &quot;Ryom-Verzeichnis&quot; or &quot;Rpertoire des oeuvres d'Antonio Vivaldi&quot;, a catalog created in the 20th century by the musicologist<space/><link><target>Peter Ryom</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>The Four Seasons (Vivaldi)</target><part>''Le quattro stagioni'' (The Four Seasons)</part></link><space/>of 1723 is his most famous work. Part of<space/><italics><link><target>Il cimento dell'armonia e dell'inventione</target></link></italics><space/>(&quot;The Contest between Harmony and Invention&quot;), it depicts moods and scenes from each of the four seasons. This work has been described as an outstanding instance of pre-19th century<space/><link><target>program music</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gerard Schwarz,<space/><italics>Musically Speaking The Great Works Collection: Vivaldi</italics><space/>(CVP, Inc., 1995), 13.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Vivaldi wrote more than 500 other concertos. About 350 of these are for solo instrument and strings, of which 230 are for violin, the others being for<space/><link><target>bassoon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cello</target></link>,<space/><link><target>oboe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>flute</target></link>,<space/><link><target>viola d'amore</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Recorder (musical instrument)</target><part>recorder</part></link>,<space/><link><target>lute</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>mandolin</target></link>. About forty concertos are for two instruments and strings and about thirty are for three or more instruments and strings.</paragraph><paragraph>As well as about 46 operas, Vivaldi composed a large body of sacred choral music. Other works include<space/><link><target>sinfonia</target><trail>s</trail></link>, about 90<space/><link><target>sonata</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and chamber music.</paragraph><paragraph>Some sonatas for flute, published as<space/><italics>Il Pastor Fido</italics>, have been erroneously attributed to Vivaldi, but were composed by<space/><link><target>Nicolas Chdeville</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Catalogs of Vivaldi works</heading><paragraph>Vivaldi's works attracted cataloging efforts befitting a major composer. Scholarly work intended to increase the accuracy and variety of Vivaldi performances also supported new discoveries which made old catalogs incomplete. Works still in circulation today may be numbered under several different systems (some earlier catalogs are mentioned<space/><link><target>Ryom-Verzeichnis</target><part>here</part></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>Because the simply consecutive Complete Edition (CE) numbers did not reflect the individual works (Opus numbers) into which compositions were grouped, Fanna numbers were often used in conjunction with CE numbers. Combined Complete Edition (CE)/Fanna numbering was especially common in the work of Italian groups driving the mid-20th century revival of Vivaldi, such as Gli Accademici di Milano under Piero Santi. For example, the Bassoon Concerto in B<template><target>music</target><arg>flat</arg></template><space/>major, &quot;La Notte&quot; RV 501, became CE 12, F. VIII,1</paragraph><paragraph>Despite the awkwardness of having to overlay Fanna numbers onto the Complete Edition number for meaningful grouping of Vivaldi's oeuvre, these numbers displaced the older<space/><link><target>Marc Pincherle</target><part>Pincherle</part></link><space/>numbers as the (re-)discovery of more manuscripts had rendered older catalogs obsolete.</paragraph><paragraph>This cataloging work was led by the Istituto Italiano Antonio Vivaldi, where<space/><link><target>Gian Francesco Malipiero</target></link><space/>was both the Director and the editor of the published scores (Edizioni G. Ricordi). His work built on that of Antonio Fanna, a Venetian businessman and the Institute's founder, and thus formed a bridge to the scholarly catalog dominant today.</paragraph><paragraph>Compositions by Vivaldi are identified today by<space/><link><target>Ryom-Verzeichnis</target><part>RV number</part></link>, the number assigned by Danish musicologist<space/><link><target>Peter Ryom</target></link><space/>in works published mostly in the 1970s, such as the &quot;Ryom-Verzeichnis&quot; or &quot;Rpertoire des oeuvres d'Antonio Vivaldi&quot;. Like the Complete Edition before it, the RV does not typically assign its single, consecutive numbers to &quot;adjacent&quot; works that occupy one of the composer's single opus numbers. Its goal as a modern catalog is to index the manuscripts and sources that establish the existence and nature of all known works. These several numbering systems are cross-referenced at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.classical.net/music/composer/works/vivaldi/index.php'>classical.net</link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph>The movie<space/><italics><template><target>ill</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>Vivaldi, a Prince in Venice</arg><arg>Antonio Vivaldi, un prince à Venise</arg></template></italics><space/>was completed in 2005 as an Italian-French co-production under the direction of<space/><template><target>ill</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>Jean-Louis Guillermou</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>IMDb title</target><arg>tt0463283</arg><arg>Antonio Vivaldi, un prince à Venise</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2005,<space/><link><target>Australian Broadcasting Corporation</target><part>ABC</part></link><space/><link><target>Radio National</target></link><space/>commissioned a<space/><link><target>radio play</target></link><space/>about Vivaldi, which was written by<space/><link><target>Sean Riley (playwright)</target><part>Sean Riley</part></link>. Entitled<space/><italics>The Angel and the Red Priest</italics>, the play was later adapted for the stage and was performed at the<space/><link><target>Adelaide Festival of the Arts</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Angel and the Red Priest by Sean Riley</arg><arg name="url">http://www.abc.net.au/rn/airplay/stories/2011/3244574.htm</arg><arg name="work">Airplay</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Australian Broadcasting Corporation]] [[Radio National]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 July 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Janice Jordan Shefelman</target></link><space/>wrote a children's book detailing the life of Vivaldi entitled<space/><italics>I, Vivaldi</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bush</arg><arg name="first">Elizabeth</arg><arg name="title">I, Vivaldi (review)</arg><arg name="publisher">Bulletin of the Center for Children's Books</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><bold>Notes</bold><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Sources and further reading</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Brizi, Bruno, &quot;Maria Grazia Pensa&quot; in<space/><italics><link><target>Music &amp; Letters</target></link></italics>, Vol. 65, No. 1 (January 1984), pp.&amp;nbsp;6264</listitem><listitem><link><target>Manfred Bukofzer</target><part>Bukofzer, Manfred</part></link><space/>(1947).<space/><italics>Music in the Baroque Era</italics>. New York, W. W. Norton &amp; Co. ISBN 0-393-09745-5.</listitem><listitem>Cross, Eric (1984). Review of ''I libretti vivaldiani: recensione e collazione dei testimoni a stampa by Anna Laura Bellina;</listitem><listitem>Formichetti, Gianfranco<space/><italics>Venezia e il prete col violino. Vita di Antonio Vivaldi</italics>, Bompiani (2006), ISBN 88-452-5640-5.</listitem><listitem>Heller, Karl<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: The Red Priest of Venice</italics>, Amadeus Press (1997), ISBN 1-57467-015-8</listitem><listitem>Kolneder, Walter<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: Documents of His Life and Works</italics>, C F Peters Corp (1983), ISBN 3-7959-0338-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>H. C. Robbins Landon</target><part>Robbins Landon, H. C.</part></link>,<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Voice of the Baroque</italics>, University of Chicago Press, 1996 ISBN 0-226-46842-9</listitem><listitem>Romijn, Andr.<space/><italics>Hidden Harmonies: The Secret Life of Antonio Vivaldi</italics>, 2007 ISBN 978-0-9554100-1-7</listitem><listitem>Selfridge-Field, Eleanor (1994).<space/><italics>Venetian Instrumental Music, from Gabrieli to Vivaldi</italics>. New York, Dover Publications. ISBN 0-486-28151-5.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Michael Talbot (author)</target><part>Talbot, Michael</part></link>,<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi</italics>, Insel Verlag (1998), ISBN 3-458-33917-5<space/><template><target>de icon</target></template></listitem><listitem>Talbot, Michael: &quot;Antonio Vivaldi&quot;, Grove Music Online, ed. L. Macy (Accessed 26 August 2006), (subscription access)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Antonio Vivaldi</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.classical.net/music/composer/works/vivaldi/index.html'>Catalog of instrumental works</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.musiqueorguequebec.ca/catal/vivaldi/viva.html'>Complete works catalog</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>IMSLP</target><arg>Vivaldi, Antonio</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>ChoralWiki</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>BBC composer page</target><arg>vivaldi</arg><arg>Antonio Vivaldi</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>MutopiaComposer</target><arg>VivaldiA</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.anima-veneziana.narod.ru/index.html'>Project Anima Veneziana</link>, Free English eBooks: 1. Talbot, M.<space/><italics>Vivaldi</italics>. 1993; 2. Heller, K.<space/><italics>Antonio Vivaldi: The Red Priest of Venice</italics>. 1997; 3. Pincherle, Marc.<space/><italics>Vivaldi: Genius of the Baroque</italics>, 1957; 4. Ryom, Peter.<space/><italics>Vivaldi Werkverzeichnis</italics>. 1st edition, 2007</listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Antonio Vivaldi</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">981</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Antonio Vivaldi</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>Portal bar</target><arg>Classical music</arg><arg>Opera</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Vivaldi, Antonio</target></template><link><target>Category:1678 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1741 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Roman Catholic priests</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century Italian people</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century Roman Catholic priests</target></link><link><target>Category:Baroque composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Composers for cello</target></link><link><target>Category:Composers for violin</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian classical violinists</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian expatriates in Austria</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian male classical composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian opera composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian Roman Catholic priests</target></link><link><target>Category:Oratorio composers</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Venice</target></link></paragraph></article>