<article title='Dartmoor_Preservation_Association'><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox company</target><arg name="name"><space/>Friends of Dartmoor: DPA - Dartmoor Preservation Association
</arg><arg name="logo"><space/>DPA Infobox image.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>DPA logo embroidered on leisurewear
</arg><arg name="type"><space/>[[National parks of the United Kingdom|Conservation]] [[charitable organisation|charity]]
</arg><arg name="foundation"><space/>{{Start date|1883}}
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Old Duchy Hotel, Princetown, Yelverton, Devon, PL20 6QF
</arg><arg name="area_served"><space/>[[Dartmoor|Dartmoor National Park]]
</arg><arg name="key_people"><space/>{{Plainlist|
* Norman Cowling {{small|(Chairman)}}
* Colin Turner {{small|(President)}}
* Phil Hutt {{small|(Director)}}
}}
</arg><arg name="slogan"><space/>Campaign, Conserve, Connect
</arg><arg name="homepage"><space/>{{url|http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com}}
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>COI</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Dartmoor Preservation Association (DPA)</bold><space/>is one of the oldest environmental or amenity bodies in the UK, founded in 1883.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly">Kelly, M.<space/><italics>&quot;Quartz and Feldspar. Dartmoor: A British Landscape in Modern Times&quot;</italics>, Jonathan Cape, London, 2015, ISBN 9780224091138</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.3</arg></template><space/>It concerns itself with<space/><link><target>Dartmoor</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>National Parks of England and Wales</target><part>National Park</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Devon</target></link>, south-west England. Originally there were two main areas of concern. Firstly,<space/><link><target>Common land</target><part>commoners rights</part></link><space/>were being eroded through army use, including the firing of live artillery shells, and piecemeal enclosure of land around the margins.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Moore1890">Moore, Stuart A.<space/><italics>A short history of the rights of common upon the Forest of Dartmoor and the commons of Devon</italics>. Dartmoor Preservation Association, Plymouth, 1890. ISBN 0950138649.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.100</arg></template><space/>Secondly, there was increasing public interest in Dartmoors scenery, archaeology, history and wildlife<extension extension_name='ref' name="SomersCocks1983">Somers Cocks, J.<space/><italics>A Dartmoor Century 1883-1983: One hundred years of the Dartmoor Preservation Association</italics>. Dartmoor Preservation Association. Yelverton, Devon, 1983. ISBN 0950138649.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.7</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The DPA has opposed what it considered to be unsuitable developments on Dartmoor throughout its history. In its founding year, the secretary, Robert Burnard persuaded the War Department not to fire on the Okehampton Firing Range on Saturdays to allow access to the public. Many battles have been fought since, particularly against the military presence and the proposed building of reservoirs on the moor, notably under the Chairmanship of<space/><link><target>Sylvia Sayer</target><part>Lady Sayer</part></link>, granddaughter of Robert Burnard.</paragraph><paragraph>The DPA continues to follow the same objectives as when it was founded. For example, in June 2015, it supported the inhabitants of<space/><link><target>Widecombe-in-the-Moor</target></link><space/>against the erecting of a telecommunications mast in an area of pristine countryside against the wishes of the local population.</paragraph><paragraph>Dartmoor Preservation Association is a registered charity, Number 215665.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://apps.charitycommission.gov.uk/Showcharity/RegisterOfCharities/CharityFramework.aspx?RegisteredCharityNumber=215665&amp;amp;SubsidiaryNumber=0'></link><space/><italics>&quot;Charity Commission Register - Dartmoor Preservation Association&quot;</italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph>Dartmoor is said to be one of the last remaining areas of wilderness in Britain,<extension extension_name='ref'>Steen, Anthony. 2003,<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/westminster_hall/2003/oct/15/dartmoor-national-park-military-exercises'>&quot;Dartmoor National Park (Military Exercises)&quot;</link><space/>HC Deb 15 October 2003 vol 411 cc129-36WH</extension><space/>but it has been a managed landscape since the late<space/><link><target>Neolithic British Isles</target><part>Neolithic</part></link><space/>(3,000-2,500 BCE). The<space/><link><target>Bronze Age</target></link><space/>inhabitants (from 2,500 to 750 BCE) cleared ancient forest and developed farming. They made extensive use of surface<space/><link><target>wikt:moorstone</target><part>moorstone</part></link><space/>in the construction of<space/><link><target>Roundhouse (dwelling)</target><part>roundhouses</part></link><space/>(their remains now seen as &quot;hut circles&quot;), enclosures, land-dividing<space/><link><target>reave</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>stone row</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>stone circle</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>menhir</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>kistvaen</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Butler, Jeremy.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Atlas of Antiquities: Vol.1 The East</italics>. Devon Books, Kingkerswell, Devon. 1991. p.5. ISBN 0861148665.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Farming has continued through the Medieval period to the present day,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/lookingafter/laf-culturalheritage/laf-archaeology/laf-medievaldartmoor'>&quot;Medieval Dartmoor&quot; - Dartmoor National Park Authority website</link></extension><space/>but a more disruptive activity to the landscape was the appearance of<space/><link><target>Dartmoor tin-mining</target><part>tin-mining</part></link>, firstly by stream-working, then by lode-working and finally by underground mining.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Newman">Newman, Phil.<space/><italics>The Dartmoor Tin Industry: A Field Guide</italics>. Newton Abbot, Devon. 1968. ISBN 0953270807.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.11</arg></template><space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Newman"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.20</arg></template><space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Greeves, Tom.<space/><italics>Tin Mines and Miners of Dartmoor: A Photographic Record</italics>. Devon Books, Kingkerswell, Devon, 1986. p.21. ISBN 9780861147663.</extension><space/>Many valleys have been dug over and scarred, leaving a rich industrial archaeology.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Harris">Harris, Helen.<space/><italics>Industrial Archaeology of Dartmoor</italics>. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot, Devon. 1968. ISBN 0715343025.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.13</arg></template><space/>Other activities such as newtake wall building,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.legendarydartmoor.co.uk/bish-john.htm'>&quot;Dartmoor Newtakes&quot; - Legendary Dartmoor website</link></extension><space/><link><target>Peat</target><part>peat cutting</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Warren (domestic)</target><part>rabbit warrening</part></link>, quarrying, clay extraction and the building of a prominent<space/><link><target>HM Prison Dartmoor</target><part>prison</part></link><space/>have all left marks on the moor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Crossing, William.<space/><italics>Crossings Dartmoor Worker</italics>. 2nd Edn. Peninsula Press, Newton Abbot, Devon. 1992. p.48. ISBN 1872640206</extension><space/>Recent undertakings have left more obvious changes: the building of reservoirs and the planting of conifer forests.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SommersCocks1970">Somers Cocks, John. &quot;Exploitation&quot;. In<space/><italics>Dartmoor: A New Study</italics>. Editor Crispin Gill. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot Devon, 1970. ISBN 0715350412.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.267</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>History of the association</heading><paragraph>The use of moorstone continued up to recent times with the extensive building of dry stone walls around farm newtakes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanbrook, Elisabeth.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Forest Farms</italics>. Devon Books, Kinkerswell, 1994. pp.6-7. ISBN 0861148878.</extension><space/>Later, stone was cut and dressed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Worth, R. Hansford.<space/><italics>Worths Dartmoor</italics>. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot. 1967. pp.355-391. ISBN 0715351486.</extension><space/>The use of moorstone continued to such an extent that in 1847 boundary markers were cut around Pew Tor to protect it. Marker stones were erected around Roos Tor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brewer">Brewer, Dave.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Boundary Markers</italics>. Halsgrove. Tiverton, Devon, 2002. ISBN 1841141720</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.250–251</arg></template><space/>The taking of stone started to change the Dartmoor landscape: for example Eric Hemery (writing in 1983) stated that Swell Tor had been &quot;decapitated and disembowelled by the quarrymen&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hemery">Hemery, Eric.<space/><italics>High Dartmoor</italics>. Robert Hale Ltd, London. 1983. ISBN 0709188595</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.1029</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In August 1881, a public meeting was convened by the Portreeve of Tavistock in the Guildhall to discuss the continued taking of stone, particularly from landmark tors.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brewer"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.249</arg></template><space/>The DPA was founded two years later, in 1883. The protected area around Pew Tor was extended in December 1896. In 1901, the DPA commissioned a report into damage to ancient monuments, caused by the taking of stone for building and road-mending, and into unlawful enclosures of common land.<extension extension_name='ref'>Crossing, William.<space/><italics>Being Mr. Crossings report as to damage to ancient monuments and encroachments on Dartmoor, 1901</italics>. Reprinted 1997. Dartmoor Preservation Association Publication No. 9. pp.3-24. ISBN 0950138665.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Frontispiece of DPA 1890 book.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Frontispiece of DPA book about Commons and Commoners' Rights, published 1890</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Commoners rights</heading><paragraph>The first publication of the DPA, in 1890, was a short history of commoners rights on Dartmoor and the commons of Devon.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Moore1890"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.xi</arg></template><space/>This notes a decrease in the numbers of animals even in medieval times: in 1296 5,000 cattle, 487 horses, 131 folds of sheep; in 1316 3,292 cattle, 368 horses, 100 folds of sheep.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Moore1890"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.xix</arg></template><space/><italics>An important battle occurred in 1894 when the Corporation of London attempted to buy the whole of Dartmoor in order to pipe its water to Paddington alongside Brunels recently converted railway, when it went from broad gauge to standard gauge. The DPA led the revolt against this</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.212</arg></template><space/>In 1897, the DPA went to court to fight successfully the enclosure of a section of Peter Tavy Great Common, in support of a farmer.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SomersCocks1983"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.8</arg></template><space/>Commoners rights seem to have been a settled issue in recent years: except for where they are impinged upon by the military presence.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Military use</heading><paragraph><link><target>Dartmoor Training Area</target></link><space/>has been used regularly for military training since 1873, although it was used earlier during the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target><part>Napoleonic</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Crimean War</target><part>Crimean</part></link><space/>Wars.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SommersCocks1970"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.271</arg></template><space/>In 1906-07, seven miles of roads were built on the north moor to facilitate the movement of guns. There are three established firing ranges at<space/><link><target>Okehampton</target></link>, Willsworthy and Merrivale. The area taken up with live firing ranges is 9,187 hectares (22,664 acres) and they are used on average 120 days each year.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/33309/armed_forces_ondartmoor_brief_history.pdf'>''The Armed Forces on Dartmoor: A Brief History''</link></extension><space/>They are used for small arms, mortars and artillery smoke and illuminating shells.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.dartmoorsociety.com/files/debates/military.html'>&quot;The 6th Dartmoor Society Debate: The Military on Dartmoor&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The use of the moor by the military has been a major concern of the DPA since its founding. In its first year, Robert Burnard (DPA Secretary) persuaded the War Department not to fire on the Okehampton Firing Range on Saturdays so that there may be some public access to the area.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SomersCocks1983"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.8</arg></template><space/><link><target>Sylvia Sayer</target><part>Lady Sylvia Sayer</part></link><space/>was very outspoken about it being totally at odds with the area being designated as a National Park,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.devon.gov.uk/newsletter_may2000.pdf'>&quot;Lady Sayer and Dartmoor&quot; - Devon County Council Newsletter, May 2000</link></extension><space/>and in 1963 the DPA published a widely-circulated 24-page booklet entitled<space/><italics>Misuse of a National Park</italics><space/>which includes photographs of unexploded<space/><link><target>Shell (projectile)</target><part>shells</part></link><space/>lying on the open moor, corrugated iron buildings, large craters, a derelict<space/><link><target>tank</target></link><space/>used as a target, bullet marks on standing stones, etc. It also contains details of a 1958 incident in which a young boy was killed by a mortar shell near<space/><link><target>Cranmere Pool</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Misuse of a National Park
</arg><arg name="publisher">The Dartmoor Preservation Association</arg><arg name="location">Widecombe-in-the-Moor
</arg><arg name="year">1963</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Since the 1960s there has been much less military damage and litter as a result of the DPA persuading the Services to be more cautious.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hemery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.854</arg></template><space/>The military have changed since the Victorian era, they now have 120 conservation groups across the MOD, including Dartmoor Military Conservation Group.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.gov.uk/government/uploads/system/uploads/attachment_data/file/33352/issue_39_pt_2.pdf'>''&quot;Around the Regions - with the Conservation Groups&quot;'' - MOD web site upload</link></extension><space/>The current leases run for many years, with Cramber Tor most recently being granted a further 40-year license.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.westernmorningnews.co.uk/MoD-use-Dartmoor-military-training-2053/story-18031199-detail/story.html'>&quot;MOD can use Dartmoor for Military Training until 2053&quot; - ''Western Morning News'' website</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Afforestation</heading><paragraph>Early afforestation occurred when Brimpts was planted with trees in 1862.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.245</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>Forestry Commission</target></link><space/>was founded in 1919, following World War I and in that year the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Cornwall</target></link><space/>planted 800 acres of conifers at Fernworthy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SommersCocks1970"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.269</arg></template><space/>In 1921, Plymouth Corporation planted conifers around<space/><link><target>Burrator Reservoir</target></link>. The Forestry Commission planted Bellever and Laughter Tor farms in 1930-32 and in 1944-1945 Soussons Down was also planted. The DPA opposed these post-war plantings and R. Hansford Worth (1868-1950, a Plymouth engineer, scientist and antiquarian) delivered a lecture fiercely critical of the Duchy of Cornwall as the landowners at<space/><link><target>The Plymouth Athenaeum</target></link>, using the argument of encroachment on the rights of common and loss of ancient monuments.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.249</arg></template><space/>DPA opposition to forestry on Dartmoor arose again in 1953 when it wrote a policy on woodlands in the then-new national park.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.252</arg></template><space/>Opposition was exercised when Hawn, Dendles and High House Wastes, all near Cornwood, were designated for tree planting in 1959. Argument continued while Hawns and Dendles Wastes were ploughed in 1960. High House Waste was eventually purchased by the DPA in 1964 and<space/><link><target>The Nature Conservancy</target></link><space/>bought neighbouring Dendles in 1965.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.259</arg></template><space/>The situation in 2015 is that some of the Dartmoor plantations have been affected by the fungal disease<space/><link><target>Phytophthora ramorum</target></link><space/>which results in widespread clear felling to prevent further spread of the disease. The policy now is to replant with more native hardwood trees although more resistant conifers are also being used.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.forestry.gov.uk/pdf/FCReplantingrecommendations.pdf/$FILE/FCReplantingrecommendations.pdf'>&quot;Advice on replanting sites affected by Phytophthora ramorum&quot; - Forestry Commission website</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Reservoirs</heading><paragraph>There are eight<space/><link><target>Dartmoor reservoirs</target></link>, with the earliest being Tottiford Reservoir, 1861. Three were built in the mid-20th century: Fernworthy, 1942; Avon, 1957 and Meldon, 1972, and the DPA fought many battles over these. It opposed plans for reservoirs on Brent Moor (1899) and Holne Moor (1901) where, later, the Avon Reservoir and Venford Reservoirs were respectively built.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.278</arg></template><space/>The DPAs opposition was supported in the<space/><link><target>House of Commons of the United Kingdom</target><part>House of Commons</part></link><space/>with argument made regarding the effects on the local water table.<extension extension_name='ref'>Studholme, Sir Henry. 1959,<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1959/mar/17/torquay-corporation-water-bill-by-order#S5CV0602P0_19590317_HOC_414'>&quot;Torbay Corporation (Water) Bill (By Order)&quot;</link><space/>HC Deb 17 March 1959 vol 602 cc291-319</extension><space/>The DPA was one of many local and national amenity bodies that fought the building of the Meldon dam.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>289</arg></template><space/>The preservation battle for the Meldon valley was recorded in a DPA publication.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Meldon Story&quot; Dartmoor Preservation Association, 1972, pp.1-62.</extension><space/>The DPA offered a viable alternative site, Gorhuish Valley, for various reasons, including the fact that minerals such as arsenic would leach into the water supply if Meldon were selected.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, Carol, 1966.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1968/oct/24/north-devon-meldon-reservoir-water-order#S5CV0770P0_19681024_CWA_220'>&quot;North Devon (Meldon Reservoir) Water Order, 1966&quot;</link><space/>HC Deb 24 October 1968 vol 770 cc361-2W</extension><space/>The Meldon story was discussed many times in Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/search/Meldon+Reservoir'></link><space/>&quot;Hansard Search Results: Meldon Reservoir&quot;</extension><space/>Another battle was fought against the flooding of the Swincombe valley to form another reservoir. This was rejected in parliament in 1970, revived in 1974 and finally resolved by the building of the Roadford Reservoir to the west of the moor. In 1985 the DPA used funds from a bequest to purchase 50 acres of land where the dam of a reservoir at Swincombe would have to be.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brewer"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>pp.253–4</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>National Park designation</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act 1949</target></link><space/>led to Dartmoor being one of the first four parks to be designated, by an order made on 15 August 1951<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.legislation.gov.uk/ukpga/Geo6/12-13-14/97'>''National Parks and Access to the Countryside Act 1949''</link></extension><space/>and confirmed on 30 October 1951.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dartmoor.gov.uk"><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/learningabout/lab-printableresources/lab-factsheetshome/lab-historydartmoor'>&quot;The History of Dartmoor&quot; - Dartmoor National Park Authority website</link></extension><space/>Shortly after this, the DPA tried to ensure that the new National Park was run by an independent committee and not by the Dartmoor Standing Committee that was a subcommittee of Devon County Council Planning Committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.231</arg></template><space/>The committee was reformed as Dartmoor National Park Committee under the<space/><link><target>Local Government Act 1972</target></link><space/>but it was still a subcommittee of Devon County Council and as such it was not seen to be an independent guardian of the moor by the DPA. It was not until 1997 that an independent Dartmoor National Park Authority was enabled under the<space/><link><target>Environment Act 1995</target></link><space/>as a free-standing local authority, forty-four years after the park was created, although it is still dominated by local authorities and government appointees.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/aboutus/au-theauthority/au-members'>&quot;Dartmoor National Park Authority: Who Appoints Members?&quot;</link><space/>Dartmoor National Park Authority website. Retrieved 1 September 2015.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.231</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>North Hessary Tor TV mast</heading><paragraph>The DPA learned in October 1951 that the BBC planned to build a 750-foot television mast on<space/><link><target>North Hessary Tor</target></link>, near Princetown, that was eventually erected in 1955. This was to be a relay from a transmitting station at Wenvoe, South Wales. The DPA objected to this threat and sought expert opinion, offered alternative solutions, pressed for a public enquiry, engaged a lawyer, held public meetings, distributed pamphlets, wrote to the press and petitioned parliament.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.233</arg></template><space/>Eventually, a public enquiry was announced.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelly"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.238</arg></template><space/>When the decision was made to permit the mast, there were a number of conditions, included among them was that the development was built near the tor, leaving it still intact, and that its new approach road should not be fenced. During the process of obtaining land for the transmitter, one MP asked in the House of Commons: &quot;Will the Assistant Postmaster-General bear in mind that we have no desire to hinder the provision of this station but that it is felt that ancient common rights such as these, that have existed for a thousand years, should be adequately protected or properly extinguished by due process of law?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hayman, 1954.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1954/mar/10/station-site-north-hessary-tor'></link><space/>&quot;HC Deb 10 March 1954 vol 524 c2223&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:DPA boundary stone at Sharpitor.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPA boundary stone at Sharpitor</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sharpitor</heading><paragraph>During World War II, the RAF built a mast and buildings on Peek Hill, as RAF Sharpitor. In 1956, permission was granted to rebuild the station as part of the<space/><link><target>Gee (navigation)</target><part>&quot;Gee&quot; radio navigation system</part></link>, to be occupied for ten years. There followed delay in leaving and a proposal was made in 1970 by<space/><link><target>Devon and Cornwall Police</target><part>Devon &amp; Cornwall Police</part></link><space/>to use the mast, which was rejected. Then later the same year Plymouth Corporation wanted to use the exposed site for housing juvenile offenders. This was also rejected, but Plymouth appealed. At a public enquiry in June 1973<space/><link><target>Sylvia Sayer</target><part>Lady Sylvia Sayer</part></link><space/>represented the DPA and permission for development on the site was refused. A few years later, DPA fought successfully in support of South West Water (SWW) against renewed calls for a new reservoir at Swincombe. To mark the victory, Sylvia Sayer asked SWW if DPA could purchase the rocky outcrop of Sharpitor. The DPA purchased 32 acres in February 1984.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Brewer"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.253</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/about-the-dpa/land/285-the-sharpitor-story'></link><space/>&quot;The Sharpitor Story&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation Association website</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Okehampton bypass</heading><paragraph>Okehampton lies on the A30 main road, the shortest route from London to west Devon and Cornwall. The need for a bypass was mooted in 1963.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/learningabout/lab-printableresources/lab-factsheetshome/lab-okehamptonbypass'></link><space/>&quot;Okehampton Bypass Fact Sheet&quot; - Dartmoor National Park Authority website</extension><space/>In 1975, three routes were considered: a northern route through mainly farmland, a central route using a railway, and a southern route through Dartmoor National Park. In August 1976, the Department of the Environment announced the preferred route was through the National Park. A major event on the timeline of this project was a 96-day public enquiry from 1 May 1979 to 4 February 1980 held in Okehampton. In March 1984, the DPA with other organisations petitioned Parliament opposing compulsory purchase orders on public open spaces.<extension extension_name='ref'>Clark, David. 1984.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1984/nov/22/business-of-the-house#S6CV0068P0_19841122_HOC_186'></link><space/>&quot;Business of the House&quot; HC Deb 22 November 1984 vol 68 cc406-14</extension><space/>The Secretary of State announced in July 1985 that it was introducing a bill to reverse the decision of a Joint Parliamentary Committee and confirm a route through the National Park.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. Nicholas Ridley). 1985.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1985/jul/26/okehampton-bypass'></link><space/>&quot;Okehampton Bypass&quot; HC Deb 26 July 1985 vol 83 cc1435-41</extension><space/>This was followed by a confirmation bill in Nov 1985<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>The Secretary of State for Transport (Mr. Nicholas Ridley). 1985.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/commons/1985/nov/19/okehampton-bypass-confirmation-of-orders'></link><space/>&quot;Okehampton Bypass (Confirmation of Orders) Bill&quot; HC Deb 19 November 1985 vol 87 cc140-224</extension><space/>that received final approval in the<space/><link><target>House of Lords</target></link><space/>on 5 Dec. 1985.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Earl of Caithness. 1985.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/lords/1985/dec/05/okehampton-bypass-confirmation-of-orders'></link><space/>&quot;Okehampton Bypass (Confirmation of Orders) Bill&quot; HL Deb 05 December 1985 vol 468 cc1412-33</extension><space/>Construction started in Nov 1986 and the road was opened on 19 July 1988.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Since 2000</heading><paragraph>The DPA continues to follow the same objectives as when it was founded.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/about-the-dpa/constitution'>&quot;DPA Constitution&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation Association website</link></extension><space/>The activities have widened, involving local partners, it has a calendar of events, walks and work days with its Conservation Team undertaking a variety of moorland projects,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/events/forthcoming-events'>&quot;DPA Events&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation Association website</link></extension><space/>it funds the supply of walking boots to some children who need them for the<space/><link><target>Duke of Edinburgh Award Scheme</target></link><space/>through the Moor Boots Scheme,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://outsidetimes.com/inspired/boots-fund-makes-duke-of-edinburgh-possible-for-devon-students-5703/#RrvcotJyoPEBVPys.97'>&quot;DPA sets up Moor Boots fund&quot; - Outside Times website</link></extension><space/>it collaborates with the<space/><link><target>Campaign for National Parks</target></link>, it monitors the activities of<space/><link><target>Dartmoor National Park Authority</target></link><space/>who run the National Park. It objected to eight planning proposals (with success in seven cases), with many other achievements in the DPA Directors Annual Report.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dartmoorpreservation.com"><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/news-a-publications/archive-news/general-news-archive/280-director-s-report-for-the-2015-agm'>&quot;Director's Report for the DPA Annual General Meeting 2015&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation Association website</link></extension><space/>The DPA remains true to its original objectives and has also added other activities in support of Dartmoor and its inhabitants.</paragraph><heading level='3'>China clay expansion</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>china clay</target></link><space/>industry on Dartmoor was established long before the DPA was founded. The earliest record of a china clay pit refers to Hook Lake in 1502.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wade">Wade, E.A.<space/><italics>The Redlake Tramway &amp; China Clay Works</italics>. Twelveheads Press, Truro, 2004. ISBN 0906294096.</extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.7</arg></template><space/>The area was surveyed around 1827 by Cornishmen with thirty years experience in the clay industry. They obtained a twenty-one year lease in 1830, from the<space/><link><target>Earl of Morley</target></link><space/>who owned the land, to work the area between Lee Moor and Shaugh Moor. A rival pit was opened at Leftlake in about 1850 and at Hemerdon and Broomage in about 1855. Further pits were opened at Cholwichtown, Whitehill Yeo and Wigford Down/Brisworthy (circa 1860). Others followed at Smallhanger and Headon in the 1870s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wade"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.9</arg></template><space/>Redlake started working in 1910.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Harris"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>p.96</arg></template><space/>China clay pits are open cast mines that result in large holes in the ground accompanied by large waste tips. Over time, the pits become larger and more ground is needed for the waste, changing the landscape: the effect of this can be seen from space.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://www.google.com/maps/d/edit?mid=z0ikR9Wtiea0.kR5DL_24GeFw'></link><space/>Google Satellite map of china clay sites on Dartmoor</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The DPA argues that this is an activity that does not agree with the ethos of a National Park, whose purpose is to protect landscape from unsuitable development. In 1994, the National Park boundaries were changed to include common land at Shaugh Moor and exclude china clay worked land at Lee Moor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lord Brougham and Vaux. 1994.<space/><link><target>Hansard</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://hansard.millbanksystems.com/written_answers/1994/apr/14/dartmoor-national-park-boundary-variation'>&quot;Dartmoor National Park Boundary Variation&quot;</link><space/>HL Deb 14 April 1994 vol 553 c100WA</extension><space/>The DPA revived its campaign with the publication of a booklet in 1999 when the Blackabrook Valley, Crownhill Down and Shaugh Moor, near the popular tourist area of Cadover Bridge, all came under threat from exploitation or dumping of waste.<extension extension_name='ref'>Greeves, 1999, p.9</extension><space/>The china clay companies relinquished planning permissions in 2001.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dartmoor.gov.uk"></extension><space/>However, in November 2009, the clay companies,<space/><link><target>Sibelco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Imerys</target></link>, produced a report reviewing old mineral permissions under the<space/><link><target>Environment Act 1995</target></link><space/>with a view to joining up two pits.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.devon.gov.uk/plandoc_39_3652.pdf'>&quot;Lee Moor China Clay Quarry Complex&quot; - Devon County Council website</link></extension><space/>A presumed Bronze Age barrow, known as Emmets Post, was to be removed and three other monuments may be affected. The DPA were recorded twice, with other bodies, in a Devon County Council Development Management Committee Report for their representations in securing the future of the three areas where planning permissions were relinquished in 2001.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.devon.gov.uk/cma_report.htm?cmadoc=report_pte1327.html'>&quot;Devon County Council: Committee Report&quot; - Devon County Council website</link></extension><space/>Oxford Archaeology held an open day during their excavation of Emmets Post in 2014 prior to its removal.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://oxfordarchaeology.com/news/oasouth-news/343-open-day-at-emmets-post'>&quot;Open day at Emmets Post&quot; Oxford Archaeology website</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>House of Lords reception</heading><paragraph>The DPA and Exmoor Society held a joint reception at the House of Lords on 6 November 2008, hosted by Baroness Mallalieu, to lobby members of both Houses of Parliament and relevant Ministers about ensuring that environmental schemes for the uplands are &quot;fit for purpose&quot;. Both organisations funded an invited number of upland hill farmers to attend.<extension extension_name='ref'>Paxman, James. &quot;DPA News&quot;. Dartmoor Matters, No. 168, Winter 2008. p.3. UIN BLL01008562670</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="primocat.bl.uk"><link type='external' href='http://primocat.bl.uk/F?func=direct&amp;amp;local_base=ITEMV&amp;amp;doc_number=008562670&amp;amp;con_lng=eng'>&quot;Dartmoor Matters - British Library Item details&quot;, UIN BLL01008562670</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Whitehorse Hill excavation</heading><paragraph>The excavation in August 2011 on the north moor of a Bronze Age burial<space/><link><target>kistvaen</target></link>, or cist, that was originally uncovered in 2001 was part-funded by the DPA, along with other bodies.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/lookingafter/laf-culturalheritage/whitehorse-hill-burial'>&quot;Whitehorse Hill burial&quot; - Dartmoor National Park Authority website</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>South West Uplands Federation Conference</heading><paragraph>A conference for the upland farmers of Bodmin Moor, Exmoor and Dartmoor was held as a joint venture between the South West Uplands Federation and the DPA. It was run by the DPA at Exeter Racecourse in October 2012, with 150 delegates. Speakers came from the Foundation for Common Land, the Forest of Dartmoor Commoners, the University of Gloucestershire, the<space/><link><target>National Farmers Union of England and Wales</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Open Spaces Society</target></link>. The CEO raised sponsorship from Dartmoor National Park, Exmoor National Park, Natural England, Duchy of Cornwall amd the Exmoor Society - this reflecting the standing of the DPA with those bodies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="primocat.bl.uk"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Cowling, Norman. &quot;South West Uplands Federation Conference&quot;. Dartmoor Matters, No. 180, Winter 2012. p.4. UIN BLL01008562670.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Undergrounding power cables</heading><paragraph>Two major projects to underground overhead power cables in Dartmoor National Park have been completed in a joint project between Western Power Distribution, the South West Protected Landscapes Forum (SWPLF) and Dartmoor National Park Authority. The two schemes on Holne Moor and Walkhampton Common between them remove nearly 6&amp;nbsp;km of overhead line from open moorland. At nearly 5&amp;nbsp;km, the Walkhampton scheme is the largest to be undertaken in the South West region by Western Power Distribution. The old overhead line was readily visible from the B3212 Princetown to Yelverton Road, strung across Walkhampton Common from Devils Elbow to just above Horseyeatt at Peek Hill. The works to provide the new underground supply were mainly undertaken on the highway to minimise the impact on the sensitive moorland landscape, its archaeology, wildlife and livestock. The DPA has supported the undergrounding of these visually intrusive power lines for many years.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.westernmorningnews.co.uk/Eyesore-poles-power-cables-removed-Walkhampton/story-22714290-detail/story.html'></link><space/>&quot;'Eyesore' of poles and power cables removed from Walkhampton Common and Holne Moor on Dartmoor</extension></paragraph><table style="margin: 0 auto;"><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:DPA pylons BEFORE.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Walkhampton Common pylons and power cables before undergrounding</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:DPA pylons DURING.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Walkhampton Common pylons during undergrounding, posing with a cross-cut saw for the local press</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:DPA pylons AFTER.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Walkhampton Common after undergrounding of the power cables</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>The Dartmoor Conservation Garden</heading><paragraph>The Dartmoor Conservation Garden is a joint project between DPA and<space/><link><target>Dartmoor National Park Authority</target></link><space/>(DNPA) and is located in the Jack Wigmore Garden behind the High Moorland Centre in Princetown:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoor.gov.uk/visiting/vi-planningyourvisit/vi-infocentres/vi-highmoorlandcentre'>&quot;National Park Visitor Centre - Princetown&quot;</link></extension><space/>this is a memorial garden to a former Chair of the Authority. It is planted with a cross-section of typical native Dartmoor plants. It also houses some typical Dartmoor archaeological features, such as a 4,000-year-old<space/><link><target>Bronze Age</target></link><space/>burial<space/><link><target>kistvaen</target></link><space/>(or cist) and a Medieval granite cross from Ter Hill. This marked the Monk's Path but was constantly being pushed over by cattle. The purpose of the Garden is to illustrate the biodiversity on Dartmoor. The project came online in June 2015.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fleming, Pat. &quot;The Dartmoor Conservation Garden&quot;.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Magazine</italics>, Issue 119 Summer 2015. Moretonhampstead Devon. 2015. ISSN 02685027.</extension></paragraph><table style="margin: 0 auto;"><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Cutting bracken in Drake's Plymouth Leat.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPA Conservation Team volunteers cutting bracken in Drake's Plymouth Leat, June 2015</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:DPA stand at Chagford Fair, with 2nd place Rosette.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPA stand at Chagford Fair, with 2nd Place Rosette in the Trade Section for stand presentation, August 2014</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:January 2015 cutting scrub on Devonport Leat.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Conservation Team volunteers clearing scrub on Devonport Leat, January 2015</part></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Widecombe telecommunications mast</heading><paragraph>The DPA were involved in a campaign in June 2015 against four telecommunications masts planned for Dartmoor, with the first to be erected in the village of Widecombe. At short notice, the DPA banners were taken out, letters written, press interviews given and support given to the villagers when an inflatable mast was demonstrated with the effect that the planning application was withdrawn.<extension extension_name='ref' name="westernmorningnews.co.uk"><link type='external' href='http://www.westernmorningnews.co.uk/Dartmoor-mobile-phone-mast-plan-pulled-landscape/story-26647842-detail/story.html'>&quot;Dartmoor mobile phone mast plan pulled after landscape opposition&quot; - ''Western Morning News'' website</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Friends of Dartmoor Car Sticker.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Friends of Dartmoor Car Sticker</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Friends of Dartmoor</heading><paragraph>In common with other amenity bodies, such as those for the Lake District,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.friendsofthelakedistrict.org.uk/'>&quot;Friends of the Lake District&quot; website</link></extension><space/>Peak District,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.friendsofthepeak.org.uk'>&quot;Friends of the Peak District&quot; website</link></extension><space/>Pembrokeshire Coast,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fpcnp.org.uk/'>&quot;Friends of the Pembrokeshire Coast National Park&quot; website</link></extension><space/>Yorkshire Dales Three Peaks<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.yorkshiredales.org.uk/looking-after/howyoucanhelp/friends-of-the-three-peaks'>&quot;Friends of the Three Peaks&quot; website</link></extension><space/>and the New Forest Trust,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.newforesttrust.org.uk/friend'>&quot;Become a Friend of the New Forest Trust&quot; web page</link></extension><space/>the image of Dartmoor Preservation Association is evolving from its Victorian origins, although the original name is being retained. Friends of Dartmoor projects a more modern image of preservation where several years of diplomacy have achieved good relations with the partner agencies that operate in the Dartmoor arena. This is due mainly to the efforts of the previous CEO, James Paxman<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/news-a-publications/dpa-news-items1</extension><space/>and his successor, Phil Hutt.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dartmoorpreservation.com"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Constitution, objectives and policies</heading><paragraph>The DPA Constitution, objectives and policies are published on the DPA web site.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/about-the-dpa/policies'>&quot;DPA Policies&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation Association website</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Objectives enshrined in the Constitution are the protection, preservation and enhancement in the public interest of the landscape, antiquities, flora and fauna, natural beauty, cultural heritage and scientific interest of Dartmoor. Also the protection and preservation of public access to and on Dartmoor subject to the ancient rights of commoners. Co-operation with the commoners and any organisation in achieving DPA objectives, also the study of and the recording and publication of information upon the antiquities, history and natural history of Dartmoor. There is also an interest in the acquisition of land and rights to further DPA objectives, concomitant with being a charity.</paragraph><paragraph>The DPA has twenty-two policies listed on its web site: regarding access and rights of way, fencing, protecting monuments, diverse habitats, bracken, china clay quarrying, military training and live firing, hill farming and small scale traditional local industries, quarrying, television and telephone masts, wind farms, planning applications, housing developments, woodlands and forestry, ponies, swaling, and recreational activities.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com/about-the-dpa/policies'>&quot;Policies of the DPA&quot; - Dartmoor Preservation website</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Logo</heading><paragraph>The DPA logo incorporates a representation of a Dartmoor rock feature known as<space/><link><target>Bowerman's Nose</target></link>. The logo that includes a representation of Nuns Cross appeared on the DPA Dartmoor Newsletter No. 48, October 1966, with a comment that designs based on the initial letters DPA had been exhausted. The simpler logo appeared in November 1969, when Newsletter 52 carried the logo with &quot;DPA&quot; on it. This was replaced in 2004 with the multicoloured logo.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dartmoorpreservation.com/about-the-dpa/who-we-are/223-the-dpa-emblem'>&quot;The DPA Emblem&quot; - on the Dartmoor Preservation website</link></extension></paragraph><table style="margin: 0 auto;"><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:1966 logo with Nuns Cross.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPA logo from 1966, with Nun's Cross incorporated</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>File:1969 logo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPA logo from 1969</part></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Brewer, Dave.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Boundary Markers</italics>. Halsgrove. Tiverton, Devon, 2002. ISBN 1841141720</listitem><listitem>Crossing, William.<space/><italics>Crossings Dartmoor Worker</italics>. 2nd Edn. Peninsula Press, Newton Abbot, Devon, 1992. ISBN 1872640206</listitem><listitem>Dartmoor Preservation Association. &quot;The Meldon Story&quot;. DPA Publication No. 7. Crapstone, Plymouth, 1972. UIN BLL01004145656.</listitem><listitem>Greeves, Tom.<space/><italics>Tin Mines and Miners of Dartmoor: A Photographic Record</italics>. Devon Books, Kingkerswell, Devon, 1986. ISBN 9780861147663.</listitem><listitem>Greeves, Tom. &quot;Sacred Land Working Land: the case for the preservation of the Blackabrook Valley, Crownhill Down and Shaugh Moor from the expansion of the china clay industry.&quot; Dartmoor Preservation Association, Princetown, 1999. ISBN 095013869X.</listitem><listitem>Harris, Helen.<space/><italics>Industrial Archaeology of Dartmoor</italics>. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot, Devon, 1968. ISBN 0715343025.</listitem><listitem>Hemery, Eric.<space/><italics>High Dartmoor</italics>. Robert Hale Ltd, London, 1983. ISBN 0709188595</listitem><listitem>Kelly, Matthew.<space/><italics>Quartz and Feldspar: Dartmoor - A British Landscape in Modern Times</italics>, Jonathan Cape, London, 2015. ISBN 9780224091138</listitem><listitem>Moore, Stuart A. &quot;A short history of the rights of common upon the Forest of Dartmoor and the commons of Devon&quot;. Dartmoor Preservation Association, Plymouth, 1890. ISBN 0950138649</listitem><listitem>Newman, Phil.<space/><italics>The Dartmoor Tin Industry: A Field Guide</italics>. Newton Abbot, Devon, 1968. ISBN 0953270807.</listitem><listitem>Somers Cocks, John. &quot;Exploitation&quot;. In<space/><italics>Dartmoor: A New Study</italics>. Editor Crispin Gill. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot Devon, 1970. ISBN 0715350412.</listitem><listitem>Somers Cocks, J. &quot;A Dartmoor Century 1883-1983: One hundred years of the Dartmoor Preservation Association&quot;. Dartmoor Preservation Association. Yelverton, Devon, 1983. ISBN 0950138649.<space/></listitem><listitem>Stanbrook, Elisabeth.<space/><italics>Dartmoor Forest Farms</italics>. Devon Books, Kinkerswell, 1994. ISBN 0861148878</listitem><listitem>Wade, E.A.<space/><italics>The Redlake Tramway &amp; China Clay Works</italics>. Twelveheads Press, Truro, 2004. ISBN 0906294096.</listitem><listitem>Worth, R. Hansford.<space/><italics>Worths Dartmoor</italics>. David &amp; Charles, Newton Abbot, 1967. ISBN 0715351486.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cnp.org.uk/'>Campaign for National Parks website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://apps.charitycommission.gov.uk/Showcharity/RegisterOfCharities/CharityFramework.aspx?RegisteredCharityNumber=215665&amp;amp;SubsidiaryNumber=0'>Charity Commission Register: Dartmoor Preservation Association</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dartmoorpreservation.com'>Dartmoor Preservation Association website</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Dartmoor</target></link><link><target>Category:Conservation organisations based in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Organizations established in 1883</target></link><link><target>Category:1883 establishments in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Charities based in Devon</target></link></paragraph></article>