<article title='Empirical_research'><paragraph><bold>Empirical research</bold><space/>is<space/><link><target>research</target></link><space/>using<space/><link><target>empirical evidence</target></link>. It is a way of gaining<space/><link><target>knowledge</target></link><space/>by means of direct and indirect<space/><link><target>observation</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>experience</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Empiricism</target></link><space/>values such research more than other kinds. Empirical evidence (the record of one's direct observations or experiences) can be analyzed<space/><link><target>quantitative research</target><part>quantitatively</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>qualitative research</target><part>qualitatively</part></link>. Through quantifying the evidence or making sense of it in qualitative form, a researcher can answer empirical questions, which should be clearly defined and answerable with the evidence collected (usually called<space/><link><target>data</target></link>). Research design varies by field and by the question being investigated. Many researchers combine qualitative and quantitative forms of analysis to better answer questions which cannot be studied in laboratory settings, particularly in the social sciences and in education.</paragraph><paragraph>In some fields, quantitative research may begin with a research question (e.g., &quot;Does listening to vocal music during the learning of a word list have an effect on later memory for these words?&quot;) which is tested through experimentation. Usually, a researcher has a certain<space/><link><target>theory</target></link><space/>regarding the topic under investigation. Based on this theory some statements, or<space/><link><target>hypotheses</target></link>, will be proposed (e.g., &quot;Listening to vocal music has a negative effect on learning a word list.&quot;). From these hypotheses predictions about specific events are derived (e.g., &quot;People who study a word list while listening to vocal music will remember fewer words on a later memory test than people who study a word list in silence.&quot;). These predictions can then be tested with a suitable<space/><link><target>experiment</target></link>. Depending on the outcomes of the experiment, the theory on which the hypotheses and predictions were based will be supported or not,<extension extension_name='ref'>Goodwin, C. J. (2005).<space/><italics>Research in Psychology: Methods and Design.</italics><space/>USA: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Inc.</extension><space/>or may need to be modified and then subjected to further testing.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Terminology</heading><paragraph>The term<space/><link><target>empirical</target></link><space/>was originally used to refer to certain ancient Greek practitioners of medicine who rejected adherence to the dogmatic doctrines of the day, preferring instead to rely on the observation of phenomena as perceived in experience. Later empiricism referred to a theory of<space/><link><target>knowledge</target></link><space/>in philosophy which adheres to the principle that knowledge arises from experience and evidence gathered specifically using the senses. In scientific use the term empirical refers to the gathering of data using only evidence that is observable by the senses or in some cases using calibrated scientific instruments. What early philosophers described as empiricist and empirical research have in common is the dependence on observable data to formulate and test theories and come to conclusions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Usage</heading><paragraph>The researcher attempts to describe accurately the interaction between the instrument (or the human senses) and the entity being observed. If instrumentation is involved, the researcher is expected to<space/><link><target>calibrate</target></link><space/>his/her instrument by applying it to known standard objects and documenting the results before applying it to unknown objects. In other words, it describes the research that has not taken place before and their results.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In practice, the accumulation of evidence for or against any particular theory involves planned<space/><link><target>research design</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for the collection of empirical data, and academic rigor plays a large part of judging the merits of research design. Several<space/><link><target>typography</target><part>typographies</part></link><space/>for such designs have been suggested, one of the most popular of which comes from Campbell and Stanley (1963). They are responsible for popularizing the widely cited distinction among<space/><link><target>pre-experimental design</target><part>pre-experimental</part></link>,<space/><link><target>experimental design</target><part>experimental</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>quasi-experimental design</target><part>quasi-experimental</part></link><space/>designs and are staunch advocates of the central role of randomized experiments in<space/><link><target>educational research</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Scientific research</heading><paragraph>Accurate analysis of data using standardized statistical methods in<space/><link><target>Scientific method</target><part>scientific</part></link><space/>studies is critical to determining the validity of empirical research.<space/><link><target>statistics</target><part>Statistical</part></link><space/>formulas such as regression,<space/><link><target>uncertainty coefficient</target></link>, t-test,<space/><link><target>chi square</target></link>, and various types of ANOVA (analyses of variance) are fundamental to forming logical, valid conclusions. If empirical data reach significance under the appropriate statistical formula, the research hypothesis is supported. If not, the null hypothesis is supported (or, more accurately, not rejected), meaning no effect of the independent variable(s) was observed on the dependent variable(s).</paragraph><paragraph>It is important to understand that the outcome of empirical research using statistical hypothesis testing is never<space/><italics>proof</italics>. It can only<space/><italics>support</italics><space/>a hypothesis,<space/><italics>reject</italics><space/>it, or do neither. These methods yield only probabilities.</paragraph><paragraph>Among scientific researchers, empirical<space/><italics>evidence</italics><space/>(as distinct from empirical<space/><italics>research</italics>) refers to objective evidence that appears the same regardless of the observer. For example, a thermometer will not display different temperatures for each individual who observes it. Temperature, as measured by an accurate, well calibrated thermometer, is empirical evidence. By contrast, non-empirical evidence is subjective, depending on the observer. Following the previous example, observer A might truthfully report that a room is warm, while observer B might truthfully report that the same room is cool, though both observe the same reading on the thermometer. The use of empirical evidence negates this effect of personal (i.e., subjective) experience or time.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Empirical cycle</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Empirical Cycle.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Empirical cycle according to A.D. de Groot</part></link><link><target>Adriaan de Groot</target><part>A.D. de Groot</part></link>'s empirical cycle:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heitink-1999">Heitink, G. (1999).<space/><italics>Practical Theology: History, Theory, Action Domains: Manual for Practical Theology.</italics><space/>Grand Rapids, MI: Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing, p. 233. ISBN 9780802842947</extension></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Observation: The collecting and organisation of empirical facts; Forming hypothesis.</listitem><listitem>Induction: Formulating hypothesis.</listitem><listitem>Deduction: Deducting consequences of hypothesis as testable predictions.</listitem><listitem>Testing: Testing the hypothesis with new empirical material.</listitem><listitem>Evaluation: Evaluating the outcome of testing</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Case study research</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fact</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ericdigests.org/2003-4/empirical-research.html'>Some Key Concepts for the Design and Review of Empirical Research</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Empirical Research</target></template><link><target>Category:Research</target></link><link><target>Category:Empiricism</target><part>Research</part></link><link><target>Category:Concepts in epistemology</target></link><link><target>Category:Epistemology of science</target></link></paragraph></article>