<article title='Draugr'><paragraph><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="{{Expert-subject|Mythology/Norse_mythology_work_group|date">June 2011}}
{{Cleanup-rewrite|date</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>draugr</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>draug</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-non</target><arg>draugr</arg></template>, plural<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>non</arg><arg>'''draugar'''</arg></template>; modern<space/><template><target>lang-is</target><arg>draugur</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>lang-fo</target><arg>dreygur</arg></template><space/>and<space/><link><target>Norwegian language#Nouns</target><part>Norwegian</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Swedish language</target><part>Swedish</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Danish language</target><part>Danish</part></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>no</arg><arg>draugen</arg></template>), also called<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>non</arg><arg>'''aptrganga''' or '''aptrgangr'''</arg></template>, literally &quot;again-walker&quot; (<template><target>lang-is</target><arg>afturganga</arg></template>) is an<space/><link><target>undead</target></link><space/>creature from<space/><link><target>Norse mythology</target></link>, a subset of<space/><link><target>Germanic mythology</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The word<space/><italics>draugr</italics><space/>can be traced to a<space/><link><target>Proto-Indo European</target></link><space/>stem<space/><italics>*<template><target>PIE</target><arg>dʰrowgʰos</arg></template></italics><space/>&quot;phantom&quot;, from<space/><italics>*<template><target>PIE</target><arg>dʰrewgʰ-</arg></template></italics><space/>&quot;deceive&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eiec"><template><target>Cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="first1">Edgar C.<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Polomé<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Douglas Q.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Adams<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first1">J. P.<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last1">Mallory<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first2">Douglas Q.<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last2">Adams<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">[[Encyclopedia of Indo-European Culture]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">Spirit<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="page">538</arg></template></extension>The Old Norse meaning of the word is a<space/><link><target>revenant</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>The will appears to be strong, strong enough to draw the<space/><italics>hugr</italics><space/>[animate will] back to one's body. These reanimated individuals were known as<space/><italics>draugar</italics>. However, though the dead might live again, they could also die again.<space/><italics>Draugar</italics><space/>die a &quot;second death&quot; as Chester Gould calls it, when their bodies decay, are burned, dismembered or otherwise destroyed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Remley"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Remley</arg><arg name="first">Gregg A. Smith ; with a foreword by Paul G.</arg><arg name="title">The function of the living dead in medieval Norse and Celtic literature : death and desire</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Edwin Mellen Press</arg><arg name="location">Lewiston, New York</arg><arg name="isbn">9780773453531</arg></template></extension></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Draugar live in their graves, often guarding treasure buried with them in their burial mound. They are animated corpses unlike ghosts they have a corporeal body with similar physical abilities as in life. Older literature makes clear distinctions between sea-draugar and land-draugar.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Traits</heading><paragraph>Draugar possess superhuman strength, can increase their size at will, and carry the unmistakable stench of decay. &quot;The appearance of a<space/><italics>draugr</italics><space/>was that of a dead body: swollen, blackened and generally hideous to look at.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Remley"></extension><space/>They are undead figures from Norse and Icelandic mythology that appear to retain some semblance of intelligence. They exist either to guard their treasure, wreak havoc on living beings, or torment those who had wronged them in life. The draugr's ability to increase its size also increased its weight, and the body of the draugr was described as being extremely heavy. Thorolf of<space/><link><target>Eyrbyggja saga</target></link><space/>was &quot;uncorrupted, and with an ugly look about him... swollen to the size of an ox,&quot; and his body was so heavy that it could not be raised without levers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PE187">Palsson and Edwards,<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja Saga</italics>, p. 187.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="GS115"><italics>Grettirs Saga</italics>, p. 115.</extension><space/>They are also noted for the ability to rise from the grave as wisps of smoke and &quot;swim&quot; through solid rock,<extension extension_name='ref' name="MP103">Magnussen and Palsson,<space/><italics>Laxdaela Saga</italics>, p. 103</extension><space/>which would be useful as a means of exiting their graves.</paragraph><paragraph>In folklore, draugar slay their victims through various methods including crushing them with their enlarged forms, devouring their flesh, devouring them whole in their enlarged forms, indirectly killing them by driving them mad, and by drinking their blood. Animals feeding near the grave of a draugr may be driven mad by the creature's influence.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BC81-93"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Curran<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bob<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Vampires: A Field Guide to the Creatures that Stalk the Night<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Career Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages">81–93<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">1-56414-807-6</arg></template></extension><space/>They may also die from being driven mad. Thorolf, for example, caused birds that flew over his<space/><link><target>bowl barrow</target></link><space/>to drop dead.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PE115">Palsson and Edwards,<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja Saga</italics>, p. 115.</extension><space/>Draugar are also noted as being able to drive living people insane.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GV646">Gudbrandr Vigfusson and F. York Powell, &quot;Floamanna Saga&quot;, in<space/><italics>Origines Islandicae</italics>, Vol II, p. 646.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The draugr's victims were not limited to trespassers in its howe. The roaming undead decimated livestock by running the animals to death while either riding them or pursuing them in some hideous, half-flayed form. Shepherds, whose duties to their flocks left them out of doors at night time, were also particular targets for the hunger and hatred of the undead:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">[T]he oxen which had been used to haul Thorolf's body were ridden to death by demons, and every single beast that came near his grave went raving mad and howled itself to death. The shepherd at Hvamm often came racing home with Thorolf after him. One day that Fall neither sheep nor shepherd came back to the farm.<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Draugar are noted for having numerous magical abilities (referred to as<space/><italics>trollskap</italics>) resembling those of living witches and wizards such as shape-shifting, controlling the weather and seeing into the future.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HR163"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Davidson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Hilda Roderick Ellis<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Hilda Ellis Davidson<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Road to Hel: A Study of the Conception of the Dead in Old Norse Literature<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Michigan Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1943<space/></arg><arg name="page">163<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Among the creatures that a draugr may turn into are a seal,<extension extension_name='ref' name="PE165">Palsson and Edwards,<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja Saga</italics>, p. 165.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="LS80"><italics>Laxdaela Saga</italics>, p. 80.</extension><space/>a great flayed bull, a grey horse with a broken back but no ears or tail and a cat that would sit upon a sleeper's chest and grow steadily heavier until the victim suffocated.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JS166"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Simpson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jacqueline<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Icelandic Folktales and Legends<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1972<space/></arg><arg name="page">166<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">0-520-02116-9</arg></template></extension><space/>The draugr rinn (Thrain) shape-shifted into a &quot;cat-like creature&quot; (<italics>kattakyn</italics>) in<space/><italics><link><target>Hrmundar saga Gripssonar</target></link></italics>:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">Then Thrain turned himself into a [[troll]], and the barrow was filled with a horrible stench; and he stuck his claws into the back of Hromund's neck, tearing the flesh from his bones...<ref name</arg></template>Draugar have the ability to enter into the dreams of the living,<extension extension_name='ref' name="HR163"></extension><space/>&quot;but it generally happens even so that they leave beside the living person some gift, by which, on awakening, the living person may be assured of the tangible nature of the visit.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Chadwick</arg><arg>1946</arg><arg name="p">53</arg></template><space/>Draugar also have the ability to curse a victim, as shown in the<space/><link><target>Grettis saga</target></link>, where Grettir is cursed to be unable to become any stronger. Draugar also brought disease to a village and could create temporary darkness in daylight hours. While the draugr certainly preferred to be active during the night, it did not appear to be vulnerable to sunlight like some other<space/><link><target>revenant</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A draugr's presence may be shown by a great light that glowed from the mound like<space/><link><target>foxfire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP36">Fox and Palsson,<space/><italics>Grettirs Saga</italics>, p. 36.</extension><space/>This fire would form a barrier between the land of the living and the land of the dead.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HR161">Davidson,<space/><italics>The Road to Hel</italics>, p. 161.</extension><space/>The draugr could also move magically through the earth, swimming through solid stone as does Killer-Hrapp:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">Then Olaf tried to rush Hrapp, but Hrapp sank into the ground where he had been standing and that was the end of their encounter.<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some draugar are immune to<space/><link><target>weapon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and only a<space/><link><target>hero</target></link><space/>has the strength and courage needed to stand up to so formidable an opponent. In legends the hero would often have to wrestle the draugr back to his grave, thereby defeating him, since weapons would do no good. A good example of this kind of fight is found in<space/><italics><link><target>Hrmundar saga Gripssonar</target></link></italics>. Although iron could injure a draugr, as is the case with many supernatural creatures, it would not be sufficient to stop it.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JS107">Simpson,<space/><italics>Icelandic Folktales and Legends</italics>, p. 107.</extension><space/>Sometimes the hero is required to dispose of the body in unconventional ways. The preferred method is to cut off the draugr's head, burn the body, and dump the ashes in the sea; the emphasis being on making absolutely sure the draugr was dead and gone.<extension extension_name='ref' name="VA"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vikinganswerlady.com/ghosts.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Viking Answer Lady Webpage - The Walking Dead: Draugr and Aptrgangr in Old Norse Literature<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Vikinganswerlady.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005-12-14<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-07-01</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The draugar were said to be either<space/><italics>hel-blr</italics><space/>(&quot;blue-death&quot;) or, conversely,<space/><italics>nr-flr</italics><space/>(&quot;corpse-pale&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref' name="BC81-93"></extension><space/>The &quot;blue-death&quot; color was not actually<space/><link><target>grey</target></link><space/>but was a dark blue or maroon hue that covered the entire body. Glmr, the undead shepherd of<space/><italics>Grettis saga</italics>, was reported to be dark blue in color<extension extension_name='ref' name="FP72">Fox and Palsson,<space/><italics>Grettirs Saga</italics>, p. 72.</extension><space/>and in<space/><link><target>Laxdla saga</target></link>, the bones of a dead sorceress who had appeared in dreams were dug up and found to be &quot;blue and evil looking.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="MP235">Magnusson and Palsson,<space/><italics>Laxdaela Saga</italics>, p. 235.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The resting place of the draugr was a tomb that served much as a workable home for the creature. Draugar are able to leave this dwelling place and visit the living during the night. Such visits are supposed to be universally horrible events that often end in death for one or more of the living, which would then warrant the<space/><link><target>Burial#Exhumation</target><part>exhumation</part></link><space/>of the draugr by a hero.</paragraph><paragraph>The motivation of the actions of a draugr was primarily jealousy and greed. The greed of a draugr causes it to viciously attack any would-be grave robbers, but the draugr also expresses an innate jealousy of the living, stemming from a longing for the things of the life it once had. This idea is clearly expressed in<space/><italics><link><target>Frijfs saga hins frkna</target><part>Frijfs saga</part></link></italics>, where a dying king declared:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">My howe shall stand beside the firth. And there shall be but a short distance between mine and Thorsteinn's, for it is well that we should call to one another.<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This desire for the friendship experienced in life is one example of the manifestation of this aspect of the draugr. Draugar also exhibit an immense and nearly insatiable appetite, as shown in the encounter of Aran and Asmund, sword brothers who made an oath that if one should die, the other would sit vigil with him for three days inside the burial mound. When Aran died, Asmund brought his own possessions into the barrow: banners, armor, hawk, hound, and horse. Then Asmund set himself to wait the agreed upon three days:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">During the first night, Aran got up from his chair and killed the hawk and hound and ate them. On the second night he got up again from his chair, and killed the horse and tore it into pieces; then he took great bites at the horse-flesh with his teeth, the blood streaming down from his mouth all the while he was eating... The third night Asmund became very drowsy, and the first thing he knew, Aran had got him by the ears and torn them off.<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Creation of draugar</heading><paragraph>After a persons death, the main indication that the person will become a draugr is that the corpse is not in a horizontal position. In most cases, the corpse is found in an upright or sitting position, and this is an indication that the dead might return.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Jakobsson</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">296</arg></template><space/>Any mean, nasty, or greedy person can become a draugr. As noted by rmann, most medieval Icelandic ghosts are evil or marginal people. If not dissatisfied or evil, they are unpopular.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Jakobsson</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">295</arg></template><space/>This is the prime way that draugar share characteristics with ghosts, since any person can become a ghost.</paragraph><paragraph>In many Western mythologies, ghosts are generally people with unfinished business or those who are so evil their spirit makes an impact on the place they lived. Ghosts and draugar refuse to follow the prescribed path of death, selfishly staying on Earth when they are supposed to move on. This is easily understandable because, selfishness is an important attribute of every ghost, and therefore it is no wonder that ghosts tend to be people who were troublesome during their lifetime.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Jakobsson</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">288</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>However, unlike ghosts, draugar can also come about through infection by another draugr such as in the story of Glmr. When Glmr arrives in the haunted valley in<space/><italics>Grettis saga</italics>, &quot;the previous evil spirits are relegated to the sidelines and, when Glmr is found dead, they disappear, whereas he takes over their role as ghost of the valley.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Jakobsson</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">311</arg></template><space/>Although Glmr is an arguably marginal character to begin with, it is only after his fight with the first malignant spirit that the first spirit leaves the valley, and Glmr takes its place wreaking havoc. Similarly, in<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja saga</italics>, a shepherd is killed by a draugr and rises the next night as one himself.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Means of prevention</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Noerre Naeraa Kirke Runesten.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>175px</part><part>right</part><part>The Nrre Nr Runestone is interpreted as having a &quot;grave binding inscription&quot; used to keep the deceased in its grave.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mitchell<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stephen A.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Witchcraft and Magic in the Nordic Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Pennsylvania Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="pages">22–23<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8122-4290-4</arg></template></extension></part></link>Traditionally, a pair of open iron scissors were placed on the chest of the recently deceased, and straws or twigs might be hidden among their clothes. The big toes were tied together or needles were driven through the soles of the feet in order to keep the dead from being able to walk. Tradition also held that the coffin should be lifted and lowered in three different directions as it was carried from the house to confuse a possible draugr's sense of direction.</paragraph><paragraph>The most effective means of preventing the return of the dead was believed to be the corpse door. A special door was built, through which the corpse was carried feet-first with people surrounding it so the corpse couldn't see where it was going. The door was then bricked up to prevent a return. It is speculated that this belief began in<space/><link><target>Denmark</target></link><space/>and spread throughout the Norse culture. The belief was founded on the idea that the dead could only leave through the way they entered.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja saga</italics>, the draugar infesting the home of the Icelander Kiartan were driven off by holding a &quot;door-doom&quot;. One by one the draugar were summoned to the door-doom and given judgment and were forced out of the home by this legal method. The home was then purified with<space/><link><target>holy water</target></link><space/>to ensure they never came back.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Similar creatures</heading><paragraph>A variation of the draugr is the<space/><italics>haugbui</italics>. The haugbui (from Old Norse<space/><italics>haugr</italics>' &quot;howe, barrow, tumulus&quot;) was a mound-dweller, the dead body living on within its tomb. The notable difference between the two was that the haugbui is unable to leave its grave site and only attacks those that trespass upon their territory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BC81-93"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The haugbui was rarely found far from its burial place and is a type of undead commonly found in Norse saga material. The creature is said to either swim alongside boats or sail around them in a partially submerged vessel, always on their own. In some accounts, witnesses portray them as<space/><link><target>Shapeshifting</target><part>shapeshifters</part></link><space/>who take on the appearance of seaweed or<space/><link><target>moss</target></link>-covered stones on the shoreline.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://forums.skadi.net/archive/index.php/t-76010.html'>The Walking Dead: Draugr and Aptrgangr in Old Norse Literature</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The words<space/><italics><link><target>European dragon</target><part>dragon</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics>draugr</italics><space/>are not linguistically related. However, both the<space/><link><target>Serpent (symbolism)</target><part>serpent</part></link><space/>and the spirit serve as jealous guardians of the graves of kings or ancient civilizations. Dragons that act as draugar appear in<space/><italics><link><target>Beowulf</target></link></italics><space/>as well as in some of the heroic lays of the<space/><italics><link><target>Poetic Edda</target></link></italics><space/>(in the form of<space/><link><target>Fafnir</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Folklore</heading><heading level='3'>Icelandic Sagas</heading><paragraph>One of the best-known draugar is<space/><bold>Glmr</bold>, who is defeated by the hero in<space/><italics>Grettis saga</italics>. After Glmr dies on Christmas Eve, &quot;people became aware that Glmr was not resting in peace. He wrought such havoc that some people fainted at the sight of him, while others went out of their minds&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Scudder</arg><arg>2005</arg></template><space/>After a mundane battle, Grettir eventually gets Glmr on his back. Just before Grettir kills him, Glmr curses Grettir because &quot;Glmr was endowed with more evil force than most other ghosts&quot;,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Scudder</arg><arg>2005</arg></template><space/>and thus he was able to speak and leave Grettir with his curse after his death.</paragraph><paragraph>A somewhat ambivalent, alternative view of the draugr is presented by the example of<space/><link><target>Gunnar Hmundarson</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>Njl's saga</target></link></italics>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">It seemed as though the howe was agape, and that Gunnar had turned within the howe to look upwards at the moon. They thought that they saw four lights within the howe, but not a shadow to be seen. Then they saw that Gunnar was merry, with a joyful face.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>Eyrbyggja saga</italics>, a shepherd is assaulted by a blue-black draugr. The shepherd's neck is broken during the ensuing scuffle. The shepherd rises the next night as a draugr.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BC81-93"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Recent</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Draug.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>140px</part><part>A &quot;draug&quot; from modern Scandinavian folklore<extension extension_name='ref' name="JL2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/13508/13508-h/13508-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Weird Tales from the Northern Seas<space/></arg><arg name="author">Housman, Laurence (illustrations); R. Nisbet Bain (1893 translation); Jonas Lie (original Danish)<space/></arg><arg name="year">1893<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-03-17</arg></template></extension><space/>aboard a ship, in sub-human form, wearing oilskins</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In more recent<space/><link><target>Scandinavian folklore</target></link>, the draug (the modern spelling used in Denmark, Norway, and Sweden) is often identified with the spirits of<space/><link><target>Sailor</target><part>mariner</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/><link><target>Drowning</target><part>drowned</part></link><space/>at sea. The creature is said to possess a distinctly human form, with the exception that its head is composed entirely of<space/><link><target>seaweed</target></link>. In other tellings, the draug is described as being a headless fisherman, dressed in<space/><link><target>oilskin</target></link><space/>and sailing in half a boat (the Norwegian municipality of<space/><link><target>B, Nordland</target></link><space/>has the half-boat in its coat-of-arms). This trait is common in the northernmost part of Norway, where life and culture was based on fishing more than anywhere else. The reason for this may be that the fishermen often drowned in great numbers, and the stories of restless dead coming in from sea were more common up north than anywhere else in the country.</paragraph><paragraph>A recorded legend from<space/><link><target>Trndelag</target></link><space/>tells how a<space/><link><target>cadaver</target></link><space/>lying on a beach became the object of a quarrel between the two types of draug (headless and seaweed-headed). A similar source even tells of a third type, the<space/><italics>gleip</italics>, known to hitch themselves to sailors walking ashore and make them slip on the wet rocks.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>But, though the draug usually presages death, there is an amusing account in<space/><link><target>Northern Norway</target></link><space/>of a northerner who managed to outwit him:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">It was [[Christmas Eve]], and Ola went down to his boathouse to get the [[keg]] of [[brandy]] he had bought for the holidays. When he got in, he noticed a draugr sitting on the keg, staring out to sea. Ola, with great presence of mind and great bravery (it might not be amiss to state that he already had done some drinking), tiptoed up behind the draugr and struck him sharply in the small of the back, so that he went flying out through the window, with sparks hissing around him as he hit the water. Ola knew he had no time to lose, so he set off at a great rate, running through the churchyard which lay between his home and the boathouse. As he ran, he cried, "Up, all you [[Christian]] [[Spirit|souls]], and help me!" Then he heard the sound of fighting between the ghosts and the draugr, who were battling each other with [[Coffin|coffin boards]] and bunches of seaweed. The next morning, when people came to church, the whole yard was strewn with coffin covers, boat boards, and seaweed. After the fight, which the ghosts won, the draugr never came back to that district.</arg></template><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Literature</heading><paragraph>The modern and popular connection between the draug and the sea can be traced back to the author<space/><link><target>Jonas Lie (writer)</target><part>Jonas Lie</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>storytelling</target><part>story-teller</part></link><space/><link><target>Regine Nordmann</target></link>, as well as the drawings of<space/><link><target>Theodor Kittelsen</target></link>, who spent some years living in<space/><link><target>Svolvr</target></link>. Up north, the tradition of sea-draugs is especially vivid.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Arne Garborg</target></link><space/>describes land-draugs coming<space/><link><target>Haugtussa</target><part>fresh from the graveyards</part></link>, and the term<space/><italics>draug</italics><space/>is even used of<space/><link><target>vampires</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>The notion of draugs who live in the mountains is present in the poetic works of<space/><link><target>Henrik Ibsen</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Peer Gynt</target></link></italics>), and<space/><link><target>Aasmund Olavsson Vinje</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Nynorsk</target></link><space/>translation of<space/><italics><link><target>The Lord of the Rings</target></link></italics><space/>used the term for both<space/><link><target>Nazgl</target></link><space/>and the dead men of<space/><link><target>Dunharrow</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The term<space/><italics>draug</italics><space/>has come to be used to describe any type<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template><space/>of<space/><link><target>revenant</target></link><space/>in Nordic folklore.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Popular culture</heading><paragraph><template><target>Prose</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">September 2012</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>The Morganville Vampires</target></link></italics><space/>draugar are the ancient enemies of<space/><link><target>vampire</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These draugar are of the sea-draugar sort.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>barrow-wight</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of Middle-earth are based on the draugar, since they linger around their gold even after their death and can pass through walls like the normal draugar.</listitem><listitem>Draugar are featured heavily in<space/><italics><link><target>The Elder Scrolls III: Morrowind</target></link></italics><space/>expansion:<space/><italics><link><target>The Elder Scrolls III: Bloodmoon</target><part>Bloodmoon</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Elder Scrolls V: Skyrim</target></link></italics>, inhabiting the tombs of ancient Nords. In Bloodmoon, they are mindless undead; people who eat human flesh become draugar when they die. In Skyrim, they are shown as semi-intelligent (although they possess the same AI as other enemies) revenants clad in armor and speaking in the ancient dragon language. Many famous or infamous persons appear as named draugar when their tombs are entered.</listitem><listitem>The &quot;Draug&quot; are villains that walk ashore onto fictional Solomon Island, New England, in<space/><italics><link><target>The Secret World</target></link></italics>.</listitem><listitem>The villain Surt, in the Norse-inspired novel<space/><italics>The Sword and the Satchel</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Elizabeth H. Boyer</target></link>, is a draugr.</listitem><listitem>The video game<space/><italics><link><target>The Witcher 2: Assassins of Kings</target></link></italics><space/>features &quot;draugir&quot; as a type of enemy.</listitem><listitem>The Vrykul race of<space/><italics><link><target>World of Warcraft</target></link></italics><space/>is heavily inspired by the draugr, including variants that turn into seaweed upon death, undead &quot;vargul&quot; and blue-skinned warriors.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Norse funeral</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Spriggan</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Chadwick</arg><arg name="first">N. K.</arg><arg name="title">Norse ghosts: A study in the ''Draugr'' and the ''Haugbúi''</arg><arg name="journal">Folklore</arg><arg name="year">1946</arg><arg name="volume">57</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">50–65</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/0015587x.1946.9717812</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Chadwick</arg><arg name="first">N. K.</arg><arg name="title">Norse ghosts II</arg><arg name="journal">Folklore</arg><arg name="year">1946</arg><arg name="volume">57</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">106–127</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/0015587X.1946.9717823</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Jakobsson</arg><arg name="first">Ármann</arg><arg name="title">Vampires and watchmen: Categorizing the mediaeval Icelandic undead</arg><arg name="journal">JEGP, Journal of English and Germanic Philology</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="volume">110</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">281–300</arg><arg name="doi">10.1353/egp.2011.0056</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Jakobsson</arg><arg name="first">Ármann</arg><arg name="title">The fearless vampire killers: A note about the Icelandic ''draugr'' and demonic contamination in ''Grettis Saga''</arg><arg name="journal">Folklore</arg><arg name="volume">120</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="pages">307–316</arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/00155870903219771</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Scudder</arg><arg name="first">Bernard</arg><arg name="author-mask">Scudder, Bernard (trans.)</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="title">Egils Saga</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Group</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Scudder</arg><arg name="first">Bernard</arg><arg name="author-mask">Scudder, Bernard (trans.)</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="title">The Saga of Grettir the Strong</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Group</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.naha.stolaf.edu/pubs/nas/volume12/vol12_2.htm'>Norwegian Folk Narrative in America</link><space/><italics>Norwegian-American Studies</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.online-literature.com/jonas-lie/weird-tales-from-northern-seas/'>Weird Tales from Northern Seas</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vikinganswerlady.com/ghosts.shtml'>Draugr and Aptrgangr in Old Norse Literature</link></listitem><listitem></listitem><listitem><link><target>Media:TheFishermanAndTheDraug.pdf</target><part>''The Fisherman and the Draug'', by Jonas Lie</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Scandinavian folklore</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Creatures in Norse mythology</target></link><link><target>Category:Corporeal undead</target></link><link><target>Category:Circumpolar mythology</target></link><link><target>Category:Icelandic folklore</target></link><link><target>Category:Germanic legendary creatures</target></link><link><target>Category:Undead</target></link><link><target>Category:Zombies</target></link></paragraph></article>