<article title='Chemical_bond'><paragraph><template><target>pp-move-indef</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template>A<space/><bold>chemical bond</bold><space/>is an attraction between<space/><link><target>atom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that allows the formation of<space/><link><target>chemical substance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that contain two or more atoms. The bond is caused by the<space/><link><target>electrostatic force</target></link><space/>of attraction between opposite charges, either between<space/><link><target>electron</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Atomic nucleus</target><part>nuclei</part></link>, or as the result of a<space/><link><target>dipole</target></link><space/>attraction. The strength of chemical bonds varies considerably; there are &quot;strong bonds&quot; such as<space/><link><target>covalent bond</target><part>covalent</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>ionic bond</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and &quot;weak bonds&quot; such as<space/><link><target>Dipole-dipole interaction</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>London dispersion force</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>hydrogen bond</target><trail>ing</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Since opposite charges attract via a simple<space/><link><target>electromagnetic force</target></link>, the negatively charged<space/><link><target>electron</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that are orbiting the nucleus and the positively charged<space/><link><target>proton</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the nucleus attract each other. An electron positioned between two nuclei will be attracted to both of them, and the nuclei will be attracted toward electrons in this position. This attraction constitutes the chemical bond. Due to the<space/><link><target>matter wave</target></link><space/>nature of electrons and their smaller mass, they must occupy a much larger amount of volume compared with the nuclei, and this volume occupied by the electrons keeps the atomic nuclei relatively far apart, as compared with the size of the nuclei themselves. This phenomenon limits the distance between nuclei and atoms in a bond.</paragraph><paragraph>In general, strong chemical bonding is associated with the sharing or transfer of electrons between the participating atoms. The atoms in<space/><link><target>molecule</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>crystal</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>metal</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and diatomic gasesindeed most of the physical environment around usare held together by chemical bonds, which dictate the structure and the bulk properties of matter.<link><target>File:electron dot.svg</target><part>300px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Examples of<space/><link><target>Lewis dot</target></link>-style representations of chemical bonds between<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/>(C),<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>(H), and<space/><link><target>oxygen</target></link><space/>(O). Lewis dot diagrams were an early attempt to describe chemical bonding and are still widely used today.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>All bonds can be explained by quantum theory, but, in practice, simplification rules allow chemists to predict the strength, directionality, and polarity of bonds. The<space/><link><target>octet rule</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>VSEPR theory</target></link><space/>are two examples. More sophisticated theories are<space/><link><target>valence bond theory</target></link><space/>which includes<space/><link><target>orbital hybridization</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Resonance (chemistry)</target><part>resonance</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>linear combination of atomic orbitals molecular orbital method</target></link><space/>which includes<space/><link><target>ligand field theory</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Electrostatics</target></link><space/>are used to describe bond polarities and the effects they have on chemical substances.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview of main types of chemical bonds</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template>A chemical bond is an attraction between atoms. This attraction may be seen as the result of different behaviors of the outermost or<space/><link><target>valence electron</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of atoms. Although all of these behaviors merge into each other seamlessly in various bonding situations so that there is no clear line to be drawn between them, the behaviors of atoms become so<space/><bold>qualitatively</bold><space/>different as the character of the bond changes<space/><bold>quantitatively</bold>, that it remains useful and customary to differentiate between the bonds that cause these different properties of<space/><link><target>condensed matter</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the simplest view of a so-called<space/><link><target>covalent bond</target><part>'covalent' bond</part></link>, one or more electrons (often a pair of electrons) are drawn into the space between the two atomic nuclei. Here the negatively charged electrons are attracted to the positive charges of<space/><italics>both</italics><space/>nuclei, instead of just their own. This overcomes the repulsion between the two positively charged nuclei of the two atoms, and so this overwhelming attraction holds the two nuclei in a fixed configuration of equilibrium, even though they will still vibrate at equilibrium position. Thus, covalent bonding involves sharing of electrons in which the positively charged nuclei of two or more atoms simultaneously attract the negatively charged electrons that are being shared between them. These bonds exist between two particular identifiable atoms and have a direction in space, allowing them to be shown as single connecting lines between atoms in drawings, or modeled as sticks between spheres in models. In a<space/><link><target>polar covalent bond</target></link>, one or more electrons are unequally shared between two nuclei. Covalent bonds often result in the formation of small collections of better-connected atoms called<space/><link><target>molecule</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which in solids and liquids are bound to other molecules by forces that are often much weaker than the covalent bonds that hold the molecules internally together. Such weak intermolecular bonds give organic molecular substances, such as waxes and oils, their soft bulk character, and their low melting points (in liquids, molecules must cease most structured or oriented contact with each other). When covalent bonds link long chains of atoms in large molecules, however (as in polymers such as<space/><link><target>nylon</target></link>), or when covalent bonds extend in networks through solids that are not composed of discrete molecules (such as<space/><link><target>diamond</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>quartz</target></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>silicate minerals</target></link><space/>in many types of rock) then the structures that result may be both strong and tough, at least in the direction oriented correctly with networks of covalent bonds. Also, the melting points of such covalent polymers and networks increase greatly.</paragraph><paragraph>In a simplified view of an<space/><link><target>ionic bond</target><part>''ionic'' bond</part></link>, the bonding electron is not shared at all, but transferred. In this type of bond, the outer<space/><link><target>atomic orbital</target></link><space/>of one atom has a vacancy which allows the addition of one or more electrons. These newly added electrons potentially occupy a lower energy-state (effectively closer to more nuclear charge) than they experience in a different atom. Thus, one nucleus offers a more tightly bound position to an electron than does another nucleus, with the result that one atom may transfer an electron to the other. This transfer causes one atom to assume a net positive charge, and the other to assume a net negative charge. The<space/><italics>bond</italics><space/>then results from electrostatic attraction between atoms and the atoms become positive or negatively charged<space/><link><target>ion</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Ionic bonds may be seen as extreme examples of polarization in covalent bonds. Often, such bonds have no particular orientation in space, since they result from equal electrostatic attraction of each ion to all ions around them. Ionic bonds are strong (and thus ionic substances require high temperatures to melt) but also brittle, since the forces between ions are short-range and do not easily bridge cracks and fractures. This type of bond gives rise to the physical characteristics of crystals of classic mineral salts, such as table salt.</paragraph><paragraph>A less often mentioned type of bonding is<space/><link><target>metallic bond</target><part>''metallic'' bond</part><trail>ing</trail></link>. In this type of bonding, each atom in a metal donates one or more electrons to a &quot;sea&quot; of electrons that reside between many metal atoms. In this sea, each electron is free (by virtue of its wave nature) to be associated with great many atoms at once. The bond results because the metal atoms become somewhat positively charged due to loss of their electrons while the electrons remain attracted to many atoms, without being part of any given atom. Metallic bonding may be seen as an extreme example of delocalization of electrons over a large system of covalent bonds, in which every atom participates. This type of bonding is often very strong (resulting in the tensile strength of metals). However, metallic bonding is more collective in nature than other types, and so they allow metal crystals to more easily deform, because they are composed of atoms attracted to each other, but not in any particularly-oriented ways. This results in the malleability of metals. The sea of electrons in metallic bonding causes the characteristically good electrical and thermal conductivity of metals, and also their &quot;shiny&quot; reflection of most frequencies of white light.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove science</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of chemistry</arg><arg>History of the molecule</arg></template>Early speculations into the nature of the<space/><bold>chemical bond</bold>, from as early as the 12th century, supposed that certain types of<space/><link><target>chemical species</target></link><space/>were joined by a type of<space/><link><target>chemical affinity</target></link>. In 1704,<space/><link><target>Sir Isaac Newton</target></link><space/>famously outlined his atomic bonding theory, in &quot;Query 31&quot; of his<space/><link><target>Opticks</target></link>, whereby<space/><link><target>atom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>attach to each other by some &quot;<link><target>force</target></link>&quot;. Specifically, after acknowledging the various popular theories in vogue at the time, of how atoms were reasoned to attach to each other, i.e. &quot;hooked atoms&quot;, &quot;glued together by rest&quot;, or &quot;stuck together by conspiring motions&quot;, Newton states that he would rather infer from their cohesion, that &quot;particles attract one another by some<space/><link><target>force</target></link>, which in immediate contact is exceedingly strong, at small distances performs the chemical operations, and reaches not far from the particles with any sensible effect.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>In 1819, on the heels of the invention of the<space/><link><target>voltaic pile</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jns Jakob Berzelius</target></link><space/>developed a theory of chemical combination stressing the electronegative and electropositive character of the combining atoms. By the mid 19th century,<space/><link><target>Edward Frankland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>August Kekul</target><part>F.A. Kekul</part></link>, A.S. Couper,<space/><link><target>Alexander Butlerov</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Hermann Kolbe</target></link>, building on the<space/><link><target>Radical (chemistry)</target><part>theory of radicals</part></link>, developed the<space/><link><target>Valence (chemistry)</target><part>theory of valency</part></link>, originally called &quot;combining power&quot;, in which compounds were joined owing to an attraction of positive and negative poles. In 1916, chemist<space/><link><target>Gilbert N. Lewis</target></link><space/>developed the concept of the<space/><link><target>Covalent bond</target><part>electron-pair bond</part></link>, in which two atoms may share one to six electrons, thus forming the<space/><link><target>single electron bond</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>single bond</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>double bond</target></link>, or a<space/><link><target>triple bond</target></link>; in Lewis's own words, &quot;An electron may form a part of the shell of two different atoms and cannot be said to belong to either one exclusively.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Lewis</arg><arg name="first">Gilbert N.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Gilbert N. Lewis</arg><arg name="year">1916</arg><arg name="title">The Atom and the Molecule</arg><arg name="journal">[[Journal of the American Chemical Society]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">38</arg><arg name="page">772</arg><arg name="url">http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/specialcollections/coll/pauling/bond/papers/corr216.3-lewispub-19160400.html</arg><arg name="doi">10.1021/ja02261a002</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.itis.arezzo.it/index.php?option=com_content&amp;amp;view=article&amp;amp;id=221%3Athe-atom-and-the-molecule-&amp;amp;catid=106%3Apagine-html&amp;amp;Itemid=98'>a copy</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>That same year,<space/><link><target>Walther Kossel</target></link><space/>put forward a theory similar to Lewis' only his model assumed complete transfers of electrons between atoms, and was thus a model of<space/><link><target>ionic bond</target><trail>ing</trail></link>. Both Lewis and Kossel structured their bonding models on that of<space/><link><target>Abegg's rule</target></link><space/>(1904).</paragraph><paragraph>In 1927, the first mathematically complete quantum description of a simple chemical bond, i.e. that produced by one electron in the hydrogen molecular ion,<space/><link><target>Dihydrogen cation</target><part>H<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup></part></link>, was derived by the Danish physicist Oyvind Burrau.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Laidler, K. J.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="title">The World of Physical Chemistry</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="page">346</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-855919-4</arg></template></extension><space/>This work showed that the quantum approach to chemical bonds could be fundamentally and quantitatively correct, but the mathematical methods used could not be extended to molecules containing more than one electron. A more practical, albeit less quantitative, approach was put forward in the same year by<space/><link><target>Walter Heitler</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Fritz London</target></link>. The Heitler-London method forms the basis of what is now called<space/><link><target>valence bond theory</target></link>. In 1929, the<space/><link><target>linear combination of atomic orbitals molecular orbital method</target></link><space/>(LCAO) approximation was introduced by Sir<space/><link><target>John Lennard-Jones</target></link>, who also suggested methods to derive electronic structures of molecules of F<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><space/>(<link><target>fluorine</target></link>) and O<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><space/>(<link><target>oxygen</target></link>) molecules, from basic quantum principles. This<space/><link><target>molecular orbital</target></link><space/>theory represented a covalent bond as an orbital formed by combining the quantum mechanical<space/><link><target>Schrdinger equation</target><part>Schrdinger</part></link><space/>atomic orbitals which had been hypothesized for electrons in single atoms. The equations for bonding electrons in multi-electron atoms could not be solved to mathematical perfection (i.e.,<space/><italics>analytically</italics>), but approximations for them still gave many good qualitative predictions and results. Most quantitative calculations in modern<space/><link><target>quantum chemistry</target></link><space/>use either valence bond or molecular orbital theory as a starting point, although a third approach,<space/><link><target>density functional theory</target></link>, has become increasingly popular in recent years.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1933, H. H. James and A. S. Coolidge carried out a calculation on the dihydrogen molecule that, unlike all previous calculation which used functions only of the distance of the electron from the atomic nucleus, used functions which also explicitly added the distance between the two electrons.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>James
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>H. H.
</arg><arg name="author2">Coolidge, A. S.
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Ground State of the Hydrogen Molecule
</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Journal of Chemical Physics]]
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1
</arg><arg name="issue">12
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>825–835
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[American Institute of Physics]]
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1933
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1063/1.1749252<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>With up to 13 adjustable parameters they obtained a result very close to the experimental result for the dissociation energy. Later extensions have used up to 54 parameters and gave excellent agreement with experiments. This calculation convinced the scientific community that quantum theory could give agreement with experiment. However this approach has none of the physical pictures of the valence bond and molecular orbital theories and is difficult to extend to larger molecules.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Bonds in chemical formulas</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template>The fact that atoms and molecules are three-dimensional makes it difficult to use a single technique for indicating orbitals and bonds. In<space/><bold><link><target>molecular formula</target><trail>s</trail></link></bold><space/>the chemical bonds (binding orbitals) between atoms are indicated by various methods according to the type of discussion. Sometimes, they are completely neglected. For example, in<space/><link><target>organic chemistry</target></link><space/>chemists are sometimes concerned only with the<space/><link><target>functional group</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the molecule. Thus, the molecular formula of ethanol may be written in a paper in<space/><link><target>conformational isomerism</target><part>conformational</part></link><space/>form, three-dimensional form, full two-dimensional form (indicating every bond with no three-dimensional directions), compressed two-dimensional form (CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>OH), by separating the functional group from another part of the molecule (C<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>5</xhtml:sub>OH), or by its atomic constituents (C<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>O), according to what is discussed. Sometimes, even the non-bonding valence shell electrons (with the two-dimensional approximate directions) are marked, i.e. for elemental carbon<space/><xhtml:sub>.</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>'</xhtml:sup>C<xhtml:sup>'</xhtml:sup>. Some chemists may also mark the respective orbitals, i.e. the hypothetical ethene<xhtml:sup>4</xhtml:sup><space/>anion (<xhtml:sub>\</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>/</xhtml:sup>C=C<xhtml:sub>/</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>\</xhtml:sup><space/><xhtml:sup>4</xhtml:sup>) indicating the possibility of bond formation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Strong chemical bonds</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove science</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><table class="wikitable" style="float:right; clear:right; margin:0 0 1em 1em; text-align:center;"><tablerow><tablecell colspan="3"><bold>Typical<space/><link><target>bond length</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in pm<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>and bond<space/><link><target>energy</target><part>energies</part></link><space/>in kJ/mol.</bold><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>&lt;small&gt;Bond lengths can be converted to<space/><link><target>ngstrm</target><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>by division by 100 (1 = 100 pm).<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Data taken from University of Waterloo.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.science.uwaterloo.ca/~cchieh/cact/c120/bondel.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bond Lengths and Energies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Science.uwaterloo.ca<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-10-15</arg></template></extension><space/>&lt;small&gt;</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Bond</tablehead><tablehead>Length<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(pm)</tablehead><tablehead>Energy<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(kJ/mol)</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">H<space/><link><target>Hydrogen</target></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>HH</tablecell><tablecell>74</tablecell><tablecell>436</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>HO</tablecell><tablecell>96</tablecell><tablecell>366</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>HF</tablecell><tablecell>92</tablecell><tablecell>568</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>HCl</tablecell><tablecell>127</tablecell><tablecell>432</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">C<space/><link><target>Carbon</target></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CH</tablecell><tablecell>109</tablecell><tablecell>413</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CC</tablecell><tablecell>154</tablecell><tablecell>348</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CC=</tablecell><tablecell>151</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>=CC</tablecell><tablecell>147</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><heading level='1'>CC</heading></tablecell><tablecell>148</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>C=C</tablecell><tablecell>134</tablecell><tablecell>614</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CC</tablecell><tablecell>120</tablecell><tablecell>839</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CN</tablecell><tablecell>147</tablecell><tablecell>308</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CO</tablecell><tablecell>143</tablecell><tablecell>360</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CF</tablecell><tablecell>134</tablecell><tablecell>488</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>CCl</tablecell><tablecell>177</tablecell><tablecell>330</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">N<space/><link><target>Nitrogen</target></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>NH</tablecell><tablecell>101</tablecell><tablecell>391</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>NN</tablecell><tablecell>145</tablecell><tablecell>170</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>NN</tablecell><tablecell>110</tablecell><tablecell>945</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">O<space/><link><target>Oxygen</target></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>OO</tablecell><tablecell>148</tablecell><tablecell>145</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>O=O</tablecell><tablecell>121</tablecell><tablecell>498</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead colspan="3">F, Cl, Br, I<space/><link><target>Halogen</target><trail>s</trail></link></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>FF</tablecell><tablecell>142</tablecell><tablecell>158</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>ClCl</tablecell><tablecell>199</tablecell><tablecell>243</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>BrH</tablecell><tablecell>141</tablecell><tablecell>366</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>BrBr</tablecell><tablecell>228</tablecell><tablecell>193</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>IH</tablecell><tablecell>161</tablecell><tablecell>298</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>II</tablecell><tablecell>267</tablecell><tablecell>151</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Strong chemical bonds are the<space/><italics>intramolecular</italics><space/>forces which hold atoms together in<space/><link><target>molecule</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A strong chemical bond is formed from the transfer or sharing of<space/><link><target>electron</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>between atomic centers and relies on the<space/><link><target>electrostatic attraction</target></link><space/>between the protons in nuclei and the electrons in the orbitals.</paragraph><paragraph>The types of strong bond differ due to the difference in<space/><link><target>electronegativity</target></link><space/>of the constituent elements. A large difference in electronegativity leads to more polar (ionic) character in the bond.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ionic bond</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Ionic bonding</arg></template>Ionic bonding is a type of electrostatic interaction between atoms which have a large electronegativity difference. There is no precise value that distinguishes ionic from covalent bonding, but a difference of electronegativity of over 1.7 is likely to be ionic, and a difference of less than 1.7 is likely to be covalent.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Atkins
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Peter Atkins
<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Loretta Jones
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Chemistry: Molecules, Matter and Change
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>W. H. Freeman & Co.
<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997
<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York
<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>294–295
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7167-3107-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Ionic bonding leads to separate positive and negative<space/><link><target>ions</target></link>. Ionic charges are commonly between 3<link><target>elementary charge</target><part>e</part></link><space/>to +3<link><target>elementary charge</target><part>e</part></link>.Ionic bonding commonly occurs in<space/><link><target>Salt (chemistry)</target><part>metal salts</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>sodium chloride</target></link><space/>(table salt). A typical feature of ionic bonds is that the species form into ionic crystals, in which no ion is specifically paired with any single other ion, in a specific directional bond. Rather, each species of ion is surrounded by ions of the opposite charge, and the spacing between it and each of the oppositely charged ions near it, is the same for all surrounding atoms of the same type. It is thus no longer possible to associate an ion with any specific other single ionized atom near it. This is a situation unlike that in covalent crystals, where covalent bonds between specific atoms are still discernible from the shorter distances between them, as measured via such techniques as<space/><link><target>X-ray diffraction</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Ionic crystals may contain a mixture of covalent and ionic species, as for example salts of complex acids, such as sodium cyanide, NaCN. Many minerals are of this type. X-ray diffraction shows that in NaCN, for example, the bonds between sodium<space/><link><target>cation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(Na<xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup>) and the cyanide<space/><link><target>anion</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(CN<xhtml:sup></xhtml:sup>) are<space/><italics>ionic</italics>, with no sodium ion associated with any particular cyanide. However, the bonds between C and N atoms in cyanide are of the<space/><italics>covalent</italics><space/>type, making each of the carbon and nitrogen associated with<space/><italics>just one</italics><space/>of its opposite type, to which it is physically much closer than it is to other carbons or nitrogens in a sodium cyanide crystal.</paragraph><paragraph>When such crystals are melted into liquids, the ionic bonds are broken first because they are non-directional and allow the charged species to move freely. Similarly, when such salts dissolve into water, the ionic bonds are typically broken by the interaction with water, but the covalent bonds continue to hold. For example, in solution, the cyanide ions, still bound together as single CN<xhtml:sup></xhtml:sup><space/>ions, move independently through the solution, as do sodium ions, as Na<xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup>. In water, charged ions move apart because each of them are more strongly attracted to a number of water molecules, than to each other. The attraction between ions and water molecules in such solutions is due to a type of weak<space/><link><target>intermolecular force</target><part>dipole-dipole</part></link><space/>type chemical bond. In melted ionic compounds, the ions continue to be attracted to each other, but not in any ordered or crystalline way.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Covalent bond</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Covalent bond</arg></template>Covalent bonding is a common type of bonding, in which the electronegativity difference between the bonded atoms is small or nonexistent. Bonds within most<space/><link><target>organic compound</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are described as covalent. See<space/><link><target>sigma bond</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pi bond</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for LCAO-description of such bonding.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>polar covalent bond</target></link><space/>is a covalent bond with a significant ionic character. This means that the electrons are closer to one of the atoms than the other, creating an imbalance of charge. They occur as a bond between two atoms with moderately different electronegativities and give rise to<space/><link><target>dipole-dipole interactions</target></link>. The electronegativity of these bonds is 0.3 to 1.7.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>coordinate covalent bond</target></link><space/>is one where both bonding electrons are from one of the atoms involved in the bond. These bonds give rise to<space/><link><target>Lewis acids and bases</target></link>. The electrons are shared roughly equally between the atoms in contrast to ionic bonding. Such bonding occurs in molecules such as the<space/><link><target>ammonium ion</target></link><space/>(NH<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup>) and are shown by an arrow pointing to the Lewis acid. Also known as non-polar covalent bond, the electronegativity of these bonds range from 0 to 0.3.</paragraph><paragraph>Molecules which are formed primarily from non-polar covalent bonds are often<space/><link><target>Miscibility</target><part>immiscible</part></link><space/>in water or other<space/><link><target>polar solvent</target><trail>s</trail></link>, but much more soluble in<space/><link><target>non-polar solvent</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>hexane</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Single and multiple bonds</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>single bond</target></link><space/>between two atoms corresponds to the sharing of one pair of electrons. The electron density of these two bonding electrons is concentrated in the region between the two atoms, which is the defining quality of a<space/><link><target>sigma bond</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Pi-Bond.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Two p-orbitals forming a pi-bond.</part></link>A<space/><link><target>double bond</target></link><space/>between two atoms is formed by the sharing of two pairs of electrons, one in a sigma bond and one in a<space/><link><target>pi bond</target></link>, with electron density concentrated on two opposite sides of the internuclear axis. A<space/><link><target>triple bond</target></link><space/>consists of three shared electron pairs, forming one sigma and two pi bonds.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Quadruple bond</target><part>Quadruple</part></link><space/>and higher bonds are very rare and occur only between certain<space/><link><target>transition metal</target></link><space/>atoms.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Metallic bonding</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Metallic bonding</arg></template>In metallic bonding, bonding electrons are delocalized over a lattice of atoms. By contrast, in ionic compounds, the locations of the binding electrons and their charges are static. The freely-moving or delocalization of bonding electrons leads to classical metallic properties such as luster (surface light reflectivity),<space/><link><target>electrical conductivity</target><part>electrical</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>thermal conductivity</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ductility</target></link>, and high<space/><link><target>tensile strength</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Intermolecular bonding</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template><template><target>Main</target><arg>Intermolecular force</arg></template>There are four basic types of bonds that can be formed between two or more (otherwise non-associated) molecules, ions or atoms.<space/><link><target>Intermolecular force</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>cause molecules to be attracted or repulsed by each other. Often, these define some of the physical characteristics (such as the<space/><link><target>melting point</target></link>) of a substance.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>A large difference in<space/><link><target>electronegativity</target></link><space/>between two bonded atoms will cause a permanent charge separation, or dipole, in a molecule or ion. Two or more molecules or ions with permanent dipoles can interact within<space/><link><target>Intermolecular Force#Dipole-dipole interactions</target><part>dipole-dipole interactions</part></link>. The bonding electrons in a molecule or ion will, on average, be closer to the more electronegative atom more frequently than the less electronegative one, giving rise to<space/><link><target>partial charge</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on each atom, and causing<space/><link><target>electrostatic force</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>between molecules or ions.</listitem><listitem>A<space/><link><target>hydrogen bond</target></link><space/>is effectively a strong example of an interaction between two permanent dipoles. The large difference in electronegativities between<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>and any of<space/><link><target>fluorine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>nitrogen</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>oxygen</target></link>, coupled with their lone pairs of electrons cause strong electrostatic forces between molecules. Hydrogen bonds are responsible for the high boiling points of water and<space/><link><target>ammonia</target></link><space/>with respect to their heavier analogues.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>London dispersion force</target></link><space/>arises due to instantaneous dipoles in neighbouring atoms. As the negative charge of the<space/><link><target>electron</target></link><space/>is not uniform around the whole atom, there is always a charge imbalance. This small charge will induce a corresponding dipole in a nearby molecule; causing an attraction between the two. The electron then moves to another part of the<space/><link><target>electron cloud</target></link><space/>and the attraction is broken.</listitem><listitem>A<space/><link><target>cationpi interaction</target></link><space/>occurs between a<space/><link><target>pi bond</target></link><space/>and a cation.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Theories of chemical bonding</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">January 2014</arg></template>In the (unrealistic) limit of &quot;pure&quot;<space/><link><target>ionic bond</target><trail>ing</trail></link>, electrons are perfectly localized on one of the two atoms in the bond. Such bonds can be understood by<space/><link><target>classical physics</target></link>. The forces between the atoms are characterized by<space/><link><target>isotropic</target></link><space/>continuum electrostatic potentials. Their magnitude is in simple proportion to the charge difference.</paragraph><paragraph>Covalent bonds are better understood by<space/><link><target>valence bond theory</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>molecular orbital theory</target></link>. The properties of the atoms involved can be understood using concepts such as<space/><link><target>oxidation number</target></link>. The electron density within a bond is not assigned to individual atoms, but is instead delocalized between atoms. In valence bond theory, the two electrons on the two atoms are coupled together with the bond strength depending on the overlap between them. In molecular orbital theory, the<space/><link><target>Linear combination of atomic orbitals molecular orbital method</target><part>linear combination of atomic orbitals</part></link><space/>(LCAO) helps describe the delocalized molecular orbital structures and energies based on the atomic orbitals of the atoms they came from. Unlike pure ionic bonds, covalent bonds may have directed<space/><link><target>anisotropic</target></link><space/>properties. These may have their own names, such as<space/><link><target>sigma bond</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pi bond</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the general case, atoms form bonds that are intermediate between ionic and covalent, depending on the relative<space/><link><target>electronegativity</target></link><space/>of the atoms involved. This type of bond is sometimes called<space/><link><target>polar covalent bond</target><part>polar covalent</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>W. Locke (1997).<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ch.ic.ac.uk/vchemlib/course/mo_theory/main.html'>Introduction to Molecular Orbital Theory</link>. Retrieved May 18, 2005.</listitem><listitem>Carl R. Nave (2005).<space/><link type='external' href='http://hyperphysics.phy-astr.gsu.edu/hbase/chemical/bond.html'>HyperPhysics</link>. Retrieved May 18, 2005.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://osulibrary.oregonstate.edu/specialcollections/coll/pauling/bond/index.html'>Linus Pauling and the Nature of the Chemical Bond: A Documentary History</link>. Retrieved February 29, 2008.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Chemical bonds</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Chemical bonding</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Quantum chemistry</target></link></paragraph></article>