<article title='Alexei_Petrovich%2C_Tsarevich_of_Russia'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the son of Nicholas II</arg><arg>Alexei Nikolaevich, Tsarevich of Russia</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg>grand duke
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Alexei Petrovich
</arg><arg name="title">Tsarevich of Russia
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Alexeijpetrowitsch.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Portrait of Alexei by {{ill-WD|Johann Gottfried Tannauer|Q4451254}}, c. 1712-16, Russian Museum, Saint Petersburg
</arg><arg name="spouse">[[Charlotte Christine of Brunswick-Lüneburg]]
</arg><arg name="issue">[[Natalia Alexeievna (1714–1728)|Grand Duchess Natalia Alexeievna]]<br/>[[Peter II of Russia]]
</arg><arg name="house">[[House of Romanov]]
</arg><arg name="father">[[Peter I of Russia]]
</arg><arg name="mother">[[Eudoxia Lopukhina]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>({{OldStyleDate|28 February|1690|18 February}}
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Moscow]], [[Russia]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{OldStyleDate|7 July|1718|26 June}})<space/><br/>(aged 28)
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Petropavlovskaya fortress]], [[St. Petersburg]], [[Russia]]
</arg><arg name="place of burial">
</arg><arg></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Alexei Petrovich Romanov</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-ru</target><arg>Алексе́й Петро́вич</arg></template>) (<template><target>OldStyleDate</target><arg>28 February</arg><arg>1690</arg><arg>18 February</arg></template><space/>&amp;ndash;<space/><template><target>OldStyleDate</target><arg>7 July</arg><arg>1718</arg><arg>26 June</arg></template>), was a<space/><link><target>Russia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>Tsarevich</target></link>. He was born in<space/><link><target>Moscow</target></link>, the son of Tsar<space/><link><target>Peter I of Russia</target><part>Peter I</part></link><space/>and the Tsar's first wife<space/><link><target>Eudoxia Lopukhina</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Childhood</heading><paragraph>The young Alexei was brought up by his mother, who fostered an atmosphere of disdain towards<space/><link><target>Peter I of Russia</target><part>Peter the Great</part></link>, Alexei's father. Alexei's relations with his father suffered from the hatred between his father and his mother, as it was very difficult for him to feel affection for his mother's worst persecutor. From the ages of 6 to 9, Alexei was educated by his tutor Vyazemsky, but after the removal of his mother by Peter the Great to the<space/><link><target>Suzdal Kremlin#History</target><part>Suzdal Intercession Convent</part></link>, Alexei was confined to the care of educated foreigners, who taught him history, geography, mathematics and French.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Military career</heading><paragraph>In 1703, Alexei was ordered to follow the army to the field as a private in a<space/><link><target>artillery</target><part>bombardier</part></link><space/>regiment. In 1704, he was present at the capture of<space/><link><target>Narva</target></link>. At this period, the preceptors of the Tsarevich had the highest opinion of his ability. Alexei had strong leanings towards<space/><link><target>archaeology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>ecclesiology</target></link>. However, Peter had wished his son and heir to dedicate himself to the service of new<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>, and demanded from him unceasing labour in order to maintain Russia's new wealth and power. Painful relations between father and son, quite apart from the prior personal antipathies, were therefore inevitable. It was an additional misfortune for Alexei that his father should have been too busy to attend to him just as he was growing up from boyhood to manhood. He was left in the hands of<space/><link><target>reactionary</target></link><space/><link><target>boyars</target></link><space/>and priests, who encouraged him to hate his father and wish for the death of the Tsar.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image: , -.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>Grand Duchess Charlotte of Russia</part></link>In 1708 Peter sent Alexei to<space/><link><target>Smolensk</target></link><space/>to collect<space/><link><target>food</target><part>provender</part></link><space/>and recruits, and after that to<space/><link><target>Moscow</target></link><space/>to fortify it against<space/><link><target>Charles XII of Sweden</target></link>. At the end of 1709, Alexei went to<space/><link><target>Dresden</target></link><space/>for one year. There, he finished lessons in French, German, mathematics and fortification. After his education, Alexei married, albeit greatly against his will,<space/><link><target>Charlotte of Brunswick-Wolfenbttel</target><part>Princess Charlotte of Brunswick-Wolfenbttel</part></link>, whose family was connected by marriage to many of the great families of Europe (i.e., Charlotte's sister<space/><link><target>Elisabeth Christine of Brunswick-Wolfenbttel</target><part>Elizabeth</part></link><space/>was married to<space/><link><target>Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Holy Roman Emperor Charles VI</part></link>, ruler of the<space/><link><target>Habsburg Monarchy</target></link>). In theory, Alexei could have refused the marriage, and he had been encouraged by his father to at least meet his intended. &quot;Why haven't you written to tell me what you thought about her?&quot; wrote Peter (in a tone that can only be guessed) in a letter dated 13 August 1710.</paragraph><paragraph>The marriage contract was signed in September. The wedding was celebrated at<space/><link><target>Torgau</target></link>, the palace of the<space/><link><target>Christiane Eberhardine of Brandenburg-Bayreuth</target><part>Queen of Poland</part></link>, on 14 October 1711. One of the terms of the marriage contract agreed to by Alexei was that while any forthcoming children were to be raised in the Orthodox faith, Charlotte herself was allowed to retain her Protestant faith (an agreement that did not sit well at all with Alexei's followers).</paragraph><paragraph>As for the marriage itself, it was a failure from the very start. Alexei pronounced his bride &quot;pock-marked&quot; and &quot;too thin&quot;. He insisted on separate apartments and ignored her in public.</paragraph><paragraph>Three weeks later, the bridegroom was hurried away by his father to<space/><link><target>Toru</target></link><space/>to superintend the provisioning of the Russian troops in Poland. For the next twelve months Alexei was kept constantly on the move. His wife joined him at Toru in December, but in April 1712 a peremptory<space/><link><target>ukase</target></link><space/>ordered him off to the army in<space/><link><target>Pomerania</target></link>, and in the autumn of the same year he was forced to accompany his father on a tour of inspection through<space/><link><target>Finland</target></link>.<space/><link><target>File:Alexei Petrovich in youth (Guen, 1703).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Alexis in 1703</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>He had two children with Charlotte:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Grand Duchess Natalya Alexeyevna of Russia (17141728)</target><part>Natalia Alexeievna Romanova</part></link><space/>(3 March 1714 &amp;ndash; 3 November 1728)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter II of Russia</target><part>Peter Alexeyevich Romanov</part></link><space/>(23 October 1715 &amp;ndash; 30 January 1730)</listitem></list><paragraph>Peter Alexeyevich would succeed as<space/><link><target>Tsar</target></link><space/><link><target>Peter II of Russia</target><part>Peter II</part></link><space/>in 1727. With his death in 1730, the direct male-line of the House of Romanov became extinct.</paragraph><paragraph>After the birth of Natalia in 1714, Alexei brought his long-time Finnish serf<space/><link><target>Mistress (lover)</target><part>mistress</part></link><space/><link><target>Yefrosinya Fedorov</target><part>Afrosinia</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Farquhar, Michael (2001).<space/><italics>A Treasure of Royal Scandals</italics>, p.115. Penguin Books, New York. ISBN 0-7394-2025-9.</extension><space/>to live in the palace. Some historians speculate that it was his conservative powerbase's disapproval of his foreign, non-Orthodox bride, more so than her appearance, that caused Alexei to spurn Charlotte. Another influence was<space/><link><target>Alexander Kikin</target></link>, a high-placed official who had fallen out with the Tsar and had been deprived of his estates.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Self-exile</heading><paragraph>Immediately on his return from Finland, Alexei was dispatched by his father to<space/><link><target>Staraya Russa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lake Ladoga</target></link><space/>to see to the building of new ships. This was the last commission entrusted to him, since Peter had not been satisfied with his son's performance and his lack of enthusiasm. Nevertheless, Peter made one last effort to &quot;reclaim&quot; his son. On 11 October 1715, Charlotte died, after giving birth to a son, the grand-duke Peter, future tsar<space/><link><target>Peter II of Russia</target><part>Peter II</part></link>. On the day of the funeral, Peter sent Alexei a stern letter, urging him to take interest in the affairs of the state. Peter threatened to cut him off if he did not acquiesce in his father's plans. Alexei wrote a pitiful reply to his father, offering to renounce the succession in favour of his infant son Peter. Peter would agree but on the condition that Alexei remove himself as a dynastic threat and become a monk.</paragraph><paragraph>While Alexei was pondering his options, on 26 August 1716 Peter wrote to Alexei from abroad, urging him, if he desired to remain<space/><link><target>tsarevich</target></link>, to join him and the army without delay. Rather than face this ordeal, Alexei fled to<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link><space/>and placed himself under the protection of his brother-in-law, the emperor<space/><link><target>Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Charles VI</part></link>, who sent him for safety first to the<space/><link><target>Tirol Castle</target><part>Tirol</part><trail>ean</trail></link><space/>fortress of Ehrenberg (near<space/><link><target>Reutte</target></link>), and finally to the castle of<space/><link><target>Sant'Elmo</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Naples</target></link>. He was accompanied throughout his journey by Afrosinia. That the emperor sincerely sympathized with Alexei, and suspected Peter of harbouring murderous designs against his son, is plain from his confidential letter to<space/><link><target>George I of Great Britain</target></link>, whom he consulted on this delicate affair. Peter felt insulted: the flight of the tsarevich to a foreign potentate was a reproach and a scandal, and he had to be recovered and brought back to Russia at all costs. This difficult task was accomplished by Count<space/><link><target>Peter Tolstoi</target></link>, the most subtle and unscrupulous of Peter's servants.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Peter the Great Interrogating the Tsarevich Alexei Petrovich.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>350px</part><part>''Peter I interrogates Tsarevich Alexei Petrovich at Peterhof'', history painting by<space/><link><target>Nikolai Ge</target></link>, 1871,<space/><link><target>Tretyakov Gallery</target></link>, Moscow</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>The return</heading><paragraph>Alexei would only consent to return on his father solemnly swearing, that if he came back he should not be punished in the least, but cherished as a son and allowed to live quietly on his estates and marry Afrosinia.</paragraph><paragraph>On 31 January 1718, the tsarevich reached Moscow. Peter had already determined to institute a most searching<space/><link><target>inquisition</target></link><space/>in order to get at the bottom of the mystery of the flight. On 18 February a &quot;confession&quot; was extorted from Alexei which implicated most of his friends, and he then publicly renounced the succession to the throne in favour of the baby grand-duke Peter Petrovich. A brutal reign of terror ensued, in the course of which the ex-tsaritsa Eudoxia was dragged from her monastery and publicly tried for alleged<space/><link><target>adultery</target></link>, while all who had in any way befriended Alexei were<space/><link><target>impalement</target><part>impaled</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>breaking wheel</target><part>broken on the wheel</part></link><space/>while having their flesh torn with red-hot pincers or their bare backs or bare feet slowly roasted over burning coals, and were otherwise lingeringly done to death. All this was done to terrorize the reactionaries and isolate the tsarevich.</paragraph><paragraph>In April 1718 fresh confessions were extorted from, and in regard to, Alexei. This included the words of Afrosinia, who had turned state's evidence. &quot;I shall bring back the old people...&quot; Alexei is reported to have told her,<extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;...and choose myself new ones according to my will;when I become sovereign I shall live in Moscow and leave Saint Petersburg simply as any other town; I won't launch any ships; I shall maintain troops only for defense, and won't make war on anyone; I shall be content with the old domains. In winter I shall live in Moscow, and in summer in Iaroslav.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite this and other hearsay evidence, there were no facts to go upon. The worst that could be brought against him was that he had wished his father's death. In the eyes of Peter, his son was now a self-convicted and most dangerous traitor, whose life was forfeit. But there was no getting over the fact that his father had sworn to pardon him and let him live in peace if he returned to Russia. The whole matter was solemnly submitted to a grand council of<space/><link><target>prelate</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Governing Senate</target><part>senator</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Minister (government)</target><part>ministers</part></link><space/>and other<space/><link><target>Dignitary</target><part>dignitaries</part></link><space/>on 13 June 1718. The<space/><link><target>clergy</target></link>, for their part, declared the Tsarevich Alexei,</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;...had placed his Confidence in those who loved the ancient Customs, and that he had become acquainted with them by the Discourses they held, wherein they had constantly praised the ancient Manners, and spoke with Distaste of the Novelties his Father had introduced.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Declaring this to be a civil rather than an ecclesiastical matter, the clergy left the matter to the tsar's own decision.</paragraph><paragraph>At noon on 24 June, the temporal dignitariesthe 126 members of both the Senate and magistrates that comprised the courtdeclared Alexei guilty and sentenced him to death. But the examination by torture continued, so desperate was Peter to uncover any possible collusion.</paragraph><paragraph>On 19 June, the weak and ailing tsarevich received twenty-five strokes with the<space/><link><target>knout</target></link>, and then, on the 24th, he was subject to fifteen more. On 26 June, Alexei died in the<space/><link><target>Petropavlovskaya fortress</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Saint Petersburg</target></link>, two days after the senate had condemned him to death for conspiring rebellion against his father, and for hoping for the cooperation of the common people and the armed intervention of his brother-in-law, the emperor.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Attribution</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Alexius Petrovich</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Tsarevich Alexei Petrovich of Russia</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Matthew S. Anderson,<space/><italics>Peter the Great</italics><space/>(London: Thames and Hudson, 1978).</listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Nisbet Bain</target></link>,<space/><italics>The First Romanovs 16131725</italics><space/>(London, 1905).</listitem><listitem>Robert K. Massie,<space/><italics>Peter the Great, His Life and World</italics><space/>(New York: Ballantine, 1981).</listitem><listitem>B.H. Sumner,<space/><italics>Peter the Great and the Emergence of Russia</italics><space/>(London: 1950), pp 91100.</listitem><listitem>Fredrick Charles Weber,<space/><italics>The Present State of Russia</italics><space/>(2 vols.), (1723; reprint, London: Frank Cass and Co, 1968).</listitem><listitem>Lindsey Hughes,<space/><italics>Russia in the Age of Peter the Great</italics><space/>(New Haven and London: Yale University Press, 1998).</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-roy</target><arg>ru</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Peter I of Russia]]</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of heirs to the Russian throne|Heir to the Russian Throne]]</arg><arg name="years">1690&ndash;1718</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Peter II of Russia]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template><template><target>Russian tsareviches</target></template><template><target>Russian grand dukes</target></template><template><target>Tsarevich of Russia</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Alexei Petrovich Of Russia</target></template><link><target>Category:1690 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1718 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Moscow</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Romanov</target></link><link><target>Category:Heirs apparent who never acceded</target></link><link><target>Category:Recipients of the Order of St. Andrew</target></link><link><target>Category:Prisoners who died in Russian detention</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian people who died in prison custody</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Russian people</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century Russian people</target></link></paragraph></article>