<article title='Book_of_Judges'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the Biblical book</arg><arg></arg><arg>Judge (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Judges</target><arg name="width">22.0em</arg></template><template><target>Tanakh OT</target><arg>Nevi'im</arg><arg>historical</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Book of Judges</bold><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link>:<space/><italics>Sefer Shoftim</italics><space/>) is the seventh book of the<space/><link><target>Hebrew Bible</target></link><space/>and the Christian<space/><link><target>Bible</target></link>. Its title describes its contents: it contains the history of<space/><link><target>Biblical judges</target></link>, divinely inspired leaders whose direct knowledge of<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link><space/>allows them to act as champions for the<space/><link><target>Israelite</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>from oppression by foreign rulers, and models of wise and faithful behaviour required of them by their God Yahweh following the<space/><link><target>The Exodus</target><part>exodus from Egypt</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>conquest of Canaan</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Niditch</arg><arg name="p">2–3</arg></template><space/>The stories follow a consistent pattern: the people are unfaithful to Yahweh and he therefore delivers them into the hands of their enemies; the people repent and entreat Yahweh for mercy, which he sends in the form of a leader or champion (a &quot;judge&quot;); the judge delivers the Israelites from oppression and they prosper, but soon they fall again into unfaithfulness and the cycle is repeated.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template><space/>Scholars consider many of the stories in<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>to be the oldest in the<space/><link><target>Deuteronomistic history</target></link><space/>with their major redaction dated to the 8th century BCE and with materials (such as the<space/><link><target>Deborah#The Song of Deborah</target><part>Song of Deborah</part></link>) dating from much earlier, perhaps close to the period the book depicts.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">563-566</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Alter</arg><arg name="p">105</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contents</heading><paragraph><italics>Judges</italics><space/>can be divided into three major sections: a double prologue (chapters 1:13:6), a main body (3:716:31), and a double epilogue (1721).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">190</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Prologue</heading><paragraph>The book opens with the<space/><link><target>Israelite</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the land which God has promised to them but worshiping &quot;foreign gods&quot; instead of<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, the God of Israel, and with the<space/><link><target>Canaanites</target></link><space/>still present everywhere.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Spieckermann</arg><arg name="p">341</arg></template><space/>Chapters 1:12:5 are thus a confession of failure while chapters 2:63:6 are a major summary and reflection from the Deuteronomists.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>McKenzie</arg><arg name="p">14</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The opening thus sets out the pattern which the stories in the main text will follow:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">190</arg></template></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Israel &quot;does evil in the eyes of Yahweh&quot;,</listitem><listitem>the people are given into the hands of their enemies and cry out to Yahweh,</listitem><listitem>Yahweh raises up a leader,</listitem><listitem>the &quot;spirit of Yahweh&quot; comes upon the leader,</listitem><listitem>the leader manages to defeat the enemy, and</listitem><listitem>peace is regained.</listitem></list><paragraph>Once peace was regained, for a time Israel does right and receives Yahweh's blessings, only to later relapse into doing evil and repeating the pattern set forth above.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Main text</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:12 Tribes of Israel Map.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>235px</part><part>Map of the tribes of Israel.</part></link>Next comes the main text (<template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Judges</arg><arg>3:11–16:31</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>), six accounts each concerning a major judge and their struggles against the oppressive kings of surrounding nations, plus the story of Abimelech, an Israelite who oppresses his own people. The cyclic pattern set out in the prologue is readily apparent at the beginning, but as the stories progress it begins to disintegrate, mirroring the disintegration of the world of the Israelites.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">190</arg></template><space/>The stories are not presented in chronological order,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Amit</arg><arg name="p">508</arg></template><space/>but the judges<space/><link><target>syuzhet</target><part>as they appear in the text</part></link><space/>are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Othniel</target></link><space/>(3:9-11) vs.<space/><link><target>Cushan-Rishathaim</target></link>, King of<space/><link><target>Aram-Naharaim</target><part>Aram</part></link>; Israel has 40 years peace until the death of Othniel. (The statement that Israel has a certain period of peace after each judge is a recurrent theme)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ehud</target></link><space/>(3:1129) vs.<space/><link><target>Eglon (king)</target><part>Eglon</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Moab</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Deborah</target></link><space/>the prophetess and<space/><link><target>Barak</target></link><space/>the army leader (45) vs.<space/><link><target>Jabin</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Tel Hazor</target><part>Hazor</part></link><space/>(a city in<space/><link><target>Canaan</target></link>) and<space/><link><target>Sisera</target></link>, his captain</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gideon</target></link><space/>(68) vs.<space/><link><target>Midian</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Amalek</target></link>, and the &quot;children of the East&quot; (apparently desert tribes)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Abimelech (Judges)</target><part>Abimelech</part></link><space/>(9) (who is traditionally counted as a king not a judge, and is considered evil) vs. all the Israelites who oppose him</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jephthah</target></link><space/>(1112:7) vs. the<space/><link><target>Ammon</target><trail>ites</trail></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samson</target></link><space/>(1316) vs. the<space/><link><target>Philistines</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>There are also brief glosses on &quot;minor&quot; judges:<space/><link><target>Shamgar</target></link><space/>(3:31),<space/><link><target>Tola (Bible)</target><part>Tola</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jair</target></link><space/>(10:15),<space/><link><target>Ibzan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Elon</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Abdon (Judges)</target><part>Abdon</part></link><space/>(12:815).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">563-565</arg></template><space/>Some scholars have inferred that the minor judges were actual adjudicators, whereas the major judges were leaders and didn't actually make legal judgements.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">564</arg></template><space/>The only time a major judge is said to have made legal judgments was Deborah (4:4).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">561</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Epilogue</heading><paragraph>The book concludes with two appendices (<template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Judges</arg><arg>17:1–21:25</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>), stories which do not feature a specific judge:<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg name="p">5</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dan and the Idols of Micah</target></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Judges</arg><arg>17–18</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>), how the tribe of Dan conquers its territory in the north</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Gibeah</target><part>Gibeah and the Levite Concubine</part></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleverse-nb</target><arg></arg><arg>Judges</arg><arg>19–21</arg><arg>HE</arg></template>), a war between Benjamin and the other tribes.</listitem></list><paragraph>By the end of Judges the Israelites are in a worse condition than they were at the beginning, with Yahweh's treasures used to make idolatrous images, the Levites (priests) corrupted, the tribe of Dan conquering a remote village instead of the Canaanite cities, and the tribes of Israel making war on the Benjamites, their own brothers.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">202-204</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite their appearance at the end of the Book of Judges, certain characters (like<space/><link><target>Jonathan (Judges)</target><part>Jonathan</part></link>, the grandson of<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link>) and idioms present in the epilogue show that the events therein &quot;must have taken place ... early in the period of the judges.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davis</arg><arg name="p">328–361</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chronology</heading><paragraph>Judges contains a chronology of its events. It is overtly schematic, and shows signs of having been introduced at a later period.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hughes</arg><arg name="p">70-77</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Maarten van Heemskerck 024.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;Gideon thanks God for the miracle of the dew&quot;, painting by<space/><link><target>Maarten van Heemskerck</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Muse des Beaux-Arts de Strasbourg</target></link>)</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sources</heading><paragraph>The basic source for Judges was a collection of loosely connected stories about tribal heroes who saved the people in battle.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knight</arg><arg name="p">67</arg></template><space/>This original &quot;book of saviours,&quot; made up of the stories of<space/><link><target>Ehud</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jael</target></link><space/>and parts of<space/><link><target>Gideon</target></link>, had already been enlarged and transformed into &quot;wars of Yahweh&quot; before being given the final Deuteronomistic revision.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg name="p">5-6</arg></template><space/>In the 20th century the first part of the prologue (chapters 1:12:5) and the two parts of the epilogue (1721) were commonly seen as miscellaneous collections of fragments tacked onto the main text, and the second part of the prologue (2:63:6) as an introduction composed expressly for the book; this view has been challenged in the latter decades of the century, and there is an increasing willingness to see Judges as the work of a single individual, working by carefully selecting, reworking and positioning his source material to introduce and conclude his themes.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">201-202</arg></template><space/>A statement repeated throughout the book, &quot;In those days there was no king in Israel; every man did that which was right in his own eyes,&quot; implies a monarchist redaction.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Malamat</arg><arg name="p">132</arg></template><space/>The epilogue, in which Judah is assigned a leadership role twice, implies pro-Judah political leanings on the part of the author.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davis</arg><arg name="p">328</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Deuteronomistic history</heading><paragraph>Since the second half of the 20th century most scholars have agreed with<space/><link><target>Martin Noth</target></link>'s thesis that the books of<space/><link><target>Deuteronomy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Book of Joshua</target><part>Joshua</part></link>, Judges,<space/><link><target>Books of Samuel</target><part>Samuel</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Books of Kings</target><part>Kings</part></link><space/>form parts of a single work.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knoppers</arg><arg>2000a</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template><space/>Noth maintained that the history was written in the early Exilic period (6th century BCE) in order to demonstrate how Israel's history was worked out in accordance with the theology expressed in the book of Deuteronomy (which thus provides the name &quot;Deuteronomistic&quot;).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Walton</arg><arg name="p">169-170</arg></template><space/>Noth believed that this history was the work of a single author, living in the mid-6th century BCE, selecting, editing and composing from his sources to produce a coherent work.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knoppers</arg><arg>2000b</arg><arg name="p">119</arg></template><space/>Frank Moore Cross later proposed that an early version of the history was composed in Jerusalem in Josiah's time (late 7th century); this first version, Dtr1, was then revised and expanded to create a second edition, that identified by Noth, and which Cross labelled Dtr2.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Eynikel</arg><arg name="p">14</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Scholars agree that the Deuteronomists' hand can be seen in<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>through the book's cyclical nature: the Israelites fall into idolatry, God punishes them for their sins with oppression by foreign peoples, the Israelites cry out to God for help, and God sends a judge to deliver them from the foreign oppression. After a brief period of peace, the cycle repeats. Scholars also suggest that the Deuteronomists also included the humorous and sometimes disparaging commentary found in the book such as the story of the<space/><link><target>Ephraimites</target></link><space/>who could not pronounce the word &quot;<italics><link><target>shibboleth</target></link></italics>&quot; correctly (12:56).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">562</arg></template><space/>However, linguistic analysis, the negative portrayal of the northern tribes, and the lack of emphasis on prophecy, worship, or a centralized cult all suggest that the main redaction of<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>was done before the Deuteronomistic period (around the time of the destruction of the<space/><link><target>Northern Kingdom of Israel</target></link><space/>in 722).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Amit</arg><arg name="p">510</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes and genre</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Judges Bib Germ 1485 d.1 375.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>right</part><part>Illustrated page from the Book of Judges in a German bible dated 1485 (Bodleian Library)</part></link>The essence of Deuteronomistic theology is that Israel has entered into a<space/><link><target>biblical covenant</target><part>covenant</part></link><space/>(a treaty, a binding agreement) with the god<space/><link><target>Yahweh</target></link>, under which they agree to accept Yahweh as their god (hence the phrase &quot;God of Israel&quot;) and Yahweh promises them a land where they can live in peace and prosperity.<space/><link><target>Book of Deuteronomy</target><part>Deuteronomy</part></link><space/>contains the laws by which Israel is to live in the promised land,<space/><link><target>Book of Joshua</target><part>Joshua</part></link><space/>chronicles the conquest of<space/><link><target>Canaan</target></link>, the promised land, and its allotment among the tribes, Judges describes the settlement of the land,<space/><link><target>Books of Samuel</target><part>Samuel</part></link><space/>the consolidation of the land and people under<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Books of Kings</target><part>Kings</part></link><space/>the destruction of kingship and loss of the land.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Knight</arg><arg name="p">61</arg></template><space/>The final tragedy described in Kings is the result of Israel's failure to uphold its part of the covenant: faithfulness to Yahweh brings success, economic, military and political, but unfaithfulness brings defeat and oppression.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Niditch</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This is the theme played out in Judges: the people are unfaithful to Yahweh and he therefore delivers them into the hands of their enemies; the people then repent and entreat Yahweh for mercy, which he sends in the form of a judge; the judge delivers the Israelites from oppression, but after a while they fall into unfaithfulness again and the cycle is repeated.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Soggin</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Further themes are also present: the &quot;sovereign freedom of Yahweh&quot; (God does not always do what is expected of him); the &quot;satirisation of foreign kings&quot; (who consistently underestimate Israel and Yahweh); the concept of the &quot;flawed agent&quot; (judges who are not adequate to the task before them) and the disunity of the Israelite community (which gathers pace as the stories succeed one another).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Guest</arg><arg name="p">193-194</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The book is as intriguing for the themes it leaves out as for what it includes: the<space/><link><target>ark of the covenant</target></link>, which is given so much importance in the stories of<space/><link><target>Moses</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Joshua</target></link>, is almost entirely missing, cooperation between the various tribes is limited, and there is no mention of a central shrine for worship or of a high priest (the office to which<space/><link><target>Aaron</target></link><space/>was appointed at the end of<space/><link><target>the Exodus</target></link><space/>story).<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Matthews</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Although<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>probably had a monarchist redaction (see above), the book contains passages and themes that represent anti-monarchist views. One of the major themes of the book is Yahweh's sovereignty and the importance of being loyal to Him and His laws above all other gods and sovereigns. Indeed, the authority of the judges comes not through prominent dynasties nor through elections or appointments, but rather through the spirit of God.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Alter</arg><arg name="p">106</arg></template><space/>Anti-monarchist theology is most apparent toward the end of the Gideon cycle in which the Israelites beg Gideon to create a dynastic monarchy over them and Gideon refuses.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Davis</arg><arg name="p">326-327</arg></template><space/>The rest of Gideon's lifetime saw peace in the land, but after Gideon's death, his son Abimelech ruled Shechem as a Machiavellian tyrant guilty for much bloodshed (see chapters 8 and 9). However, the last few chapters of<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>(specifically, the stories of Samson, Micah, and Gibeah) highlight the violence and<space/><link><target>anarchy</target></link><space/>of decentralized rule.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Alter</arg><arg name="p">107-109</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Judges</italics><space/>is remarkable for the number of female characters who &quot;play significant roles, active and passive, in the narratives.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Bacon</arg><arg name="p">561</arg></template><space/>Rabbi<space/><link><target>Joseph Telushkin</target></link><space/>wrote, &quot;Most of the great women in the Bible either are married to a great man or related to one. ... A rare exception to this tradition is the prophetess and judge Deborah, perhaps the Bible's greatest woman figure. Deborah stands exclusively on her own merits. The only thing we know about her personal life is the name of her husband, Lapidot.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Telushkin</arg><arg name="p">58</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Tanakh</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Bible</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biblical canon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Biblical Judges</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Song of Deborah</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of ancient Israel and Judah</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Robert Alter</target><part>Alter, Robert</part></link>, trans. and commentary.<space/><italics>Ancient Israel: The Former Prophets: Joshua, Judges, Samuel, and Kings</italics>. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2013.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com.au/books?id=QuaFlf7_vbwC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=Ancient+Israel:+The+Former+Prophets:+Joshua,+Judges,+Samuel,+and+Kings&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=l8BJVdmIF6LHmAXNlIHAAw&amp;amp;ved=0CB0Q6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Judges&amp;amp;f=false'></link></listitem><listitem>Amit, Yairah. &quot;Judges&quot; Introduction and Annotations.<space/><italics>The Jewish Study Bible</italics>. Ed. Adele Berlin and Marc Zvi Brettler. New York: Oxford University Press, 2004. 508-557.</listitem><listitem>Bacon, Gershon and S. David Sperling. &quot;Judges (Heb.), Book of.&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopaedia Judaica</target></link></italics>. Second Edition, Volume 11. pp.&amp;nbsp;561566.</listitem><listitem>Davis, John J. and Herbert Wolf.<space/><italics>Judges</italics><space/>Introduction and Annotations.<space/><italics>Zondervan NIV Study Bible (Fully Revised)</italics>. Ed. Kenneth L. Barker. Grand Rapids, MI: Zondervan, 2002. 326363.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Eynikel</arg><arg name="first">Erik</arg><arg name="title">The reform of King Josiah and the composition of the Deuteronomistic history</arg><arg name="publisher">Brill</arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-90-04-10266-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Guest</arg><arg name="first">P. Deryn</arg><arg name="chapter">Judges</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James D. G. Dunn and John William Rogerson</arg><arg name="title">Eerdmans Commentary on the Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Eerdmans</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8028-3711-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Hughes
</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Jeremy
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Secrets of the Times: Myth and History in Biblical Chronology
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>A&C Black
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knight</arg><arg name="first">Douglas A</arg><arg name="chapter">Deuteronomy and the Deuteronomists</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen and Kent Harold Richards</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation</arg><arg name="publisher">T&T Clark</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-29289-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knoppers</arg><arg name="first">Gary</arg><arg name="chapter">Introduction</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Gary N. Knoppers, J. Gordon McConville</arg><arg name="title">Reconsidering Israel and Judah: recent studies on the Deuteronomistic history</arg><arg name="publisher">Eisenbrauns</arg><arg name="date">2000a</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-57506-037-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Knoppers</arg><arg name="first">Gary</arg><arg name="chapter">Is There a Future for the Deuteronomistic History?</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Thomas Romer</arg><arg name="title">The Future of the Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="publisher">Leuven University Press</arg><arg name="date">2000b</arg><arg name="isbn">978-90-429-0858-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Malamat A. &quot;Chapter VII: The Period of the Judges.&quot;<space/><italics>Judges</italics>. The World History of the Jewish People. 3. Givatayim, Israel: Rutgers UP, 1971. pp.&amp;nbsp;129163.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Matthews</arg><arg name="first">Victor Harold</arg><arg name="title">Judges and Ruth</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-00066-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Miller</arg><arg name="first">J Maxwell</arg><arg name="chapter">The Ancient Near East and Archaeology</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">James Luther Mays, David L. Petersen and Kent Harold Richards</arg><arg name="title">Old Testament Interpretation</arg><arg name="publisher">T&T Clark</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-567-29289-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Moore 
</arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Megan Bishop 
</arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Kelle 
</arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Brad E. 
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Biblical History and Israel's Past 
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011 
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans 
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com.au/books?id</arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv
</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Niditch</arg><arg name="first">Susan</arg><arg name="title">Judges: a commentary</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-664-22096-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Perdue</arg><arg name="first">Leo G</arg><arg name="chapter">Preface: The Hebrew Bible in Current Research</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Leo G. Perdue</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell companion to the Hebrew Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-21071-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1">De Pury</arg><arg name="first1">Albert</arg><arg name="last2">Romer</arg><arg name="first2">Thomas</arg><arg name="chapter">Deuteronomistic Historiography: History of Research and Related Issues</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Albert de Pury, Thomas Romer, Jean-Daniel Macchi</arg><arg name="title">Israël constructs its history: Deuteronomistic historiography in recent research</arg><arg name="publisher">Sheffield Academic Press</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84127-099-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Soggin</arg><arg name="first">Alberto</arg><arg name="title">Judges</arg><arg name="publisher">Westminster John Knox Press</arg><arg name="year">1981</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-664-22321-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Spieckerman</arg><arg name="first">Hermann</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Leo G. Perdue</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell companion to the Hebrew Bible</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-21071-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Joseph Telushkin</target><part>Telushkin, Joseph</part></link>.<space/><italics>Biblical Literacy: The Most Important People, Events, and Ideas of the Hebrew Bible</italics>. New York: William Morrow and Company, 1997.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Van Seters</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">In search of history: historiography in the ancient world and the origins of biblical history</arg><arg name="publisher">Eisenbrauns</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="isbn">9781575060132</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Walton</arg><arg name="first">John H</arg><arg name="chapter">The Deuteronomistic History</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="editor">Andrew E. Hill, John H. Walton</arg><arg name="title">A Survey of the Old Testament</arg><arg name="publisher">Zondervan</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-310-22903-2</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Judges (Bible)</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>Judges</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Original text</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/p/pt/pt0701.htm'><space/>''Shoftim'' Judges</link><space/>(<link><target>Hebrew language</target><part>Hebrew</part></link><space/>English at Mechon-Mamre.org)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Jewish translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.mechon-mamre.org/e/et/et0701.htm'>Judges at Mechon-Mamre</link><space/>(Jewish Publication Society translation)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/archive/LibraryArchive2.asp?AID=15750'>Shoftim Judges (Judaica Press)</link><space/>translation [with<space/><link><target>Rashi</target></link>'s commentary] at Chabad.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.g-dcast.com/judges/'>Book of Judges</link><space/>(G-dcast interpretations)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Christian translations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/cgi-bin/bible?language=english&amp;amp;version=NIV&amp;amp;passage=judges'>Judges at Bible Gateway</link><space/>(various versions)</listitem><listitem><link><target>s:Bible, King James, Judges</target><part>Judges at Wikisource</part></link><space/>(Authorised King James Version)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Articles</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jewishencyclopedia.com/view.jsp?artid=689&amp;amp;letter=J&amp;amp;search=Judges'>Book of Judges article</link><space/>(Jewish Encyclopedia)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>eastons</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg><space/>[[Nevi'im|History books]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before"><space/>[[Book of Joshua|Joshua]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>2<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Tanakh|Hebrew Bible]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Samuel|Samuel]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>1<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Christianity|Christian]]<br>[[Old Testament]]<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after"><space/>[[Book of Ruth|Ruth]]<space/></arg><arg name="rows"><space/>1<space/></arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Judges, Book Of</target></template><link><target>Category:Judges of ancient Israel</target><part>Book of Judges</part></link><link><target>Category:Nevi'im</target></link><link><target>Category:Year of work unknown</target></link><link><target>Category:Book of Judges</target></link></paragraph></article>