<article title='Chemical_formula'><paragraph><template><target>Distinguish2</target><arg>the 2-D graphical method of showing atomic spacial relationships called a [[structural formula]]</arg></template><template><target>Infobox</target><arg name="title"><space/>Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>
</arg><arg name="data1"><space/>[[File:Aluminium sulfate.jpg|160px|Aluminium sulfate (hexadecahydrate)]]
</arg><arg name="data2"><space/>[[Aluminium sulfate]] has the chemical formula Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>. It is pictured here in the form of aluminium sulfate hexadecahydrate (&nbsp;{{smaller|Al<sub>2</sub>(SO<sub>4</sub>)<sub>3</sub>•16[[Water|H<sub>2</sub>O]]}}&nbsp;).
</arg></template><link><target>File:Butan Lewis.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>235px</part><part><link><target>Structural formula</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>butane</target></link>. This is '''not''' a chemical formula. Examples of chemical formulas for butane are the ''empirical formula'' C<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>5</xhtml:sub>, the '''molecular formula''' C<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>10</xhtml:sub><space/>and the ''condensed'' (or ''semi-structural'') ''formula'' CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>chemical formula</bold><space/>is a way of expressing information about the proportions of<space/><link><target>atom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that constitute a particular<space/><link><target>chemical compound</target></link>, using a single line of<space/><link><target>chemical element</target></link><space/>symbols, numbers, and sometimes also other symbols, such as parentheses, dashes, brackets, commas and<space/><italics>plus</italics><space/>(+) and<space/><italics>minus</italics><space/>() signs. These are limited to a single typographic line of symbols, which may include subscripts and superscripts. A chemical formula is not a<space/><link><target>chemical nomenclature</target><part>chemical name</part></link>, and it contains no words. Although a chemical formula may imply certain simple chemical structures, it is not the same as a full chemical<space/><link><target>structural formula</target></link>. Chemical formulas can fully specify the structure of only the simplest of<space/><link><target>molecule</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>chemical substance</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and are generally more limited in power than are chemical names and structural formulas.</paragraph><paragraph>The simplest types of chemical formulas are called<space/><italics><link><target>empirical formula</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics>, which use letters and numbers indicating the numerical<space/><italics>proportions</italics><space/>of atoms of each type.<space/><italics>Molecular formulas</italics><space/>indicate the simple<space/><italics>numbers</italics><space/>of each type of atom in a molecule, with no information on structure. For example, the empirical formula for glucose is CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>O (twice as many hydrogen atoms as carbon and oxygen), while its molecular formula is C<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub><space/>(12 hydrogen atoms, six carbon and oxygen atoms).</paragraph><paragraph>Sometimes a chemical formula is complicated by being written as a<space/><link><target>condensed formula</target></link><space/>(or condensed molecular formula, occasionally called a &quot;semi-structural formula&quot;), which conveys additional information about the particular ways in which the atoms are<space/><link><target>chemical bond</target><part>chemically bonded</part></link><space/>together, either in<space/><link><target>covalent bond</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>ionic bond</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or various combinations of these types. This is possible if the relevant bonding is easy to show in one dimension. An example is the condensed molecular/chemical formula for ethanol, which is CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>-CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>-OH or CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>OH. However, even a condensed chemical formula is necessarily limited in its ability to show complex bonding relationships between atoms, especially atoms that have bonds to four or more different substituents.</paragraph><paragraph>Since a chemical formula must be expressed as a single line of chemical element symbols, it often cannot be as informative as a true structural formula, which is a graphical representation of the spacial relationship between atoms in chemical compounds (see for example the figure for butane structural and chemical formulas, at right). For reasons of structural complexity, there is no condensed chemical formula (or semi-structural formula) that specifies glucose (and there exist many different molecules, for example<space/><link><target>fructose</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mannose</target></link>, have the same molecular formula<space/><link><target>C6H12O6</target><part>C<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub></part></link><space/>as glucose). Linear equivalent chemical<space/><italics>names</italics><space/>exist that can and do specify any complex structural formula (see<space/><link><target>chemical nomenclature</target></link>), but such names must use many terms (words), rather than the simple element symbols, numbers, and simple typographical symbols that define a chemical formula.</paragraph><paragraph>Chemical formulas may be used in<space/><link><target>chemical equation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to describe<space/><link><target>chemical reaction</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other chemical transformations, such as the dissolving of ionic compounds into solution. While, as noted, chemical formulas do not have the full power of structural formulas to show chemical relationships between atoms, they are sufficient to keep track of numbers of atoms and numbers of electrical charges in chemical reactions, thus<space/><link><target>Chemical equation#Balancing chemical equations</target><part>balancing chemical equations</part></link><space/>so that these equations can be used in chemical problems involving conservation of atoms, and conservation of electric charge.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Overview</heading><paragraph>A chemical formula identifies each constituent<space/><link><target>chemical element</target><part>element</part></link><space/>by its<space/><link><target>chemical symbol</target></link><space/>and indicates the proportionate number of atoms of each element. In empirical formulas, these proportions begin with a key element and then assign numbers of atoms of the other elements in the compound, as ratios to the key element. For molecular compounds, these ratio numbers can all be expressed as whole numbers. For example, the empirical formula of<space/><link><target>ethanol</target></link><space/>may be written C<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>O because the molecules of ethanol all contain two carbon atoms, six hydrogen atoms, and one oxygen atom. Some types of ionic compounds, however, cannot be written with entirely whole-number empirical formulas. An example is<space/><link><target>boron carbide</target></link>, whose formula of CB<xhtml:sub>n</xhtml:sub><space/>is a variable non-whole number ratio with n ranging from over 4 to more than 6.5.</paragraph><paragraph>When the chemical compound of the formula consists of simple<space/><link><target>molecule</target><trail>s</trail></link>, chemical formulas often employ ways to suggest the structure of the molecule. These types of formulas are variously known as<space/><bold>molecular formulas</bold><space/>and<space/><bold><link><target>structural formula</target><part>condensed formulas</part></link></bold>. A molecular formula enumerates the number of atoms to reflect those in the molecule, so that the molecular formula for<space/><link><target>glucose</target></link><space/>is C<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub><space/>rather than the glucose empirical formula, which is CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>O. However, except for very simple substances, molecular chemical formulas lack needed structural information, and are ambiguous.</paragraph><paragraph>For simple molecules, a condensed (or semi-structural) formula is a type of chemical formula that may fully imply a correct structural formula. For example,<space/><link><target>ethanol</target></link><space/>may be represented by the condensed chemical formula CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>OH, and<space/><link><target>dimethyl ether</target></link><space/>by the condensed formula CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>OCH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>. These two molecules have the same empirical and molecular formulas (C<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>O), but may be differentiated by the condensed formulas shown, which are sufficient to represent the full structure of these simple<space/><link><target>organic compound</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Condensed chemical formulas may also be used to represent<space/><link><target>ionic compound</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that do not exist as discrete molecules, but nonetheless do contain covalently bound clusters within them. These<space/><link><target>polyatomic ion</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are groups of atoms that are covalently bound together and have an overall ionic charge, such as the sulfate<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>[S</arg><arg>O</arg><arg>4</arg><arg>]</arg><arg>2-</arg></template><space/>ion. Each polyatomic ion in a compound is written individually in order to illustrate the separate groupings. For example, the compound<space/><link><target>dichlorine hexoxide</target></link><space/>has an empirical formula<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>Cl</arg><arg>O</arg><arg>3</arg></template>, and molecular formula<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>Cl</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>O</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, but in liquid or solid forms, this compound is more correctly shown by an ionic condensed formula<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>[ClO</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>]</arg><arg>+</arg><arg>[ClO</arg><arg>4</arg><arg>]</arg><arg>-</arg></template>, which illustrates that this compound consists of<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>[ClO</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>]</arg><arg>+</arg></template><space/>ions and<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>[ClO</arg><arg>4</arg><arg>]</arg><arg>-</arg></template><space/>ions. In such cases, the condensed formula only need be complex enough to show at least one of each ionic species.</paragraph><paragraph>Chemical formulas as described here are distinct from the far more complex chemical systematic names that are used in various systems of<space/><link><target>chemical nomenclature</target></link>. For example, one systematic name for glucose is (2<italics>R</italics>,3<italics>S</italics>,4<italics>R</italics>,5<italics>R</italics>)-2,3,4,5,6-pentahydroxyhexanal. This name, interpreted by the rules behind it, fully specifies glucose's structural formula, but the name is not a chemical formula as usually understood, and uses terms and words not used in chemical formulas. Such names, unlike basic formulas, may be able to represent full structural formulas without graphs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Simple empirical formulas</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Empirical formula</arg></template>In<space/><link><target>chemistry</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>empirical formula</target></link><space/>of a chemical is a simple expression of the relative number of each type of atom or ratio of the elements in the compound. Empirical formulas are the standard for<space/><link><target>ionic compound</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>CaCl</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and for macromolecules, such as<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>SiO</arg><arg>2</arg></template>. An empirical formula makes no reference to<space/><link><target>isomer</target><trail>ism</trail></link>, structure, or absolute number of atoms. The term<space/><bold>empirical</bold><space/>refers to the process of<space/><link><target>elemental analysis</target></link>, a technique of<space/><link><target>analytical chemistry</target></link><space/>used to determine the relative percent composition of a pure chemical substance by element.</paragraph><paragraph>For example,<space/><link><target>hexane</target></link><space/>has a molecular formula of<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>C</arg><arg>6</arg><arg>H</arg><arg>14</arg></template>, or structurally<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>CH</arg><arg>3</arg><arg>CH</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>CH</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>CH</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>CH</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>CH</arg><arg>3</arg></template>, implying that it has a chain structure of 6<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/>atoms, and 14<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>atoms. However, the empirical formula for hexane is<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>C</arg><arg>3</arg><arg>H</arg><arg>7</arg></template>. Likewise the empirical formula for<space/><link><target>hydrogen peroxide</target></link>,<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>H</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>O</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, is simply HO expressing the 1:1 ratio of component elements.<space/><link><target>Formaldehyde</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>acetic acid</target></link><space/>have the same empirical formula,<space/><template><target>chem</target><arg>CH</arg><arg>2</arg><arg>O</arg></template>. This is the actual chemical formula for formaldehyde, but acetic acid has double the number of atoms.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Molecular formulas<template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Molecular formula</arg></template></heading><paragraph>Molecular formulas indicate the simple numbers of each type of atom in a molecule of a molecular substance. They are the same as empirical formulas for molecules that only have one atom of a particular type, but otherwise have larger numbers. An example of the difference is the empirical formula for glucose, which is CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>O (<italics>ratio</italics><space/>1:2:1), while its molecular formula is C<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub><space/>(<italics>number of atoms</italics><space/>6:12:6). For water, both formulas are H<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>O. A molecular formula provides more information about a molecule than its empirical formula, but is more difficult to establish.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Condensed formulas in organic chemistry implying molecular geometry and structural formulas</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Isobutane_numbered_2D.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part><link><target>Isobutane</target></link><space/>structural formula<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Molecular formula: C<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>10</xhtml:sub><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Condensed or semi-structural chemical formula: (CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Butan Lewis.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part><link><target>Butane</target></link><space/>structural formula<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Molecular formula: C<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>10</xhtml:sub><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Condensed or semi-structural formula: CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>connectivity (graph theory)</target><part>connectivity</part></link><space/>of a molecule often has a strong influence on its physical and chemical properties and behavior. Two molecules composed of the same numbers of the same types of atoms (i.e. a pair of<space/><link><target>isomer</target><trail>s</trail></link>) might have completely different chemical and/or physical properties if the atoms are connected differently or in different positions. In such cases, a<space/><link><target>structural formula</target></link><space/>is useful, as it illustrates which atoms are bonded to which other ones. From the connectivity, it is often possible to deduce the approximate<space/><link><target>molecular geometry</target><part>shape of the molecule</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A condensed chemical formula may represent the types and spatial arrangement of<space/><link><target>Chemical bond</target><part>bonds</part></link><space/>in a simple chemical substance, though it does not necessarily specify<space/><link><target>isomer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or complex structures. For example,<space/><link><target>ethane</target></link><space/>consists of two carbon atoms single-bonded to each other, with each carbon atom having three hydrogen atoms bonded to it. Its chemical formula can be rendered as CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>. In<space/><link><target>ethylene</target></link><space/>there is a double bond between the carbon atoms (and thus each carbon only has two hydrogens), therefore the chemical formula may be written: CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>, and the fact that there is a double bond between the carbons is implicit because carbon has a valence of four. However, a more explicit method is to write H<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>C=CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><space/>or less commonly H<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>C<bold>::</bold>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>. The two lines (or two pairs of dots) indicate that a<space/><link><target>double bond</target></link><space/>connects the atoms on either side of them.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>triple bond</target></link><space/>may be expressed with three lines or pairs of dots, and if there may be ambiguity, a single line or pair of dots may be used to indicate a single bond.</paragraph><paragraph>Molecules with multiple<space/><link><target>functional group</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that are the same may be expressed by enclosing the repeated group in<space/><link><target>parenthesis</target><part>round brackets</part></link>. For example,<space/><link><target>isobutane</target></link><space/>may be written (CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH. This condensed structural formula implies a different connectivity from other molecules that can be formed using the same atoms in the same proportions (isomers). The formula (CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH implies a central carbon atom attached to one hydrogen atom and three<space/><link><target>methyl group</target><part>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub><space/>groups</part></link>. The same number of atoms of each element (10 hydrogens and 4 carbons, or C<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>10</xhtml:sub>) may be used to make a straight chain molecule,<space/><link><target>butane</target></link>: CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Chemical names in answer to limitations of chemical formulas</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>chemical nomenclature</arg></template>The alkene called<space/><bold>but-2-ene</bold><space/>has two isomers, which the chemical formula CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>CH=CHCH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub><space/>does not identify. The relative position of the two methyl groups must be indicated by additional notation denoting whether the methyl groups are on the same side of the double bond (<italics>cis</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>Z</italics>) or on the opposite sides from each other (<italics>trans</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>E</italics>). Such extra symbols violate the rules for chemical formulas, and begin to enter the territory of more complex naming systems.</paragraph><paragraph>As noted above, in order to represent the full structural formulas of many complex organic and inorganic compounds,<space/><link><target>chemical nomenclature</target></link><space/>may be needed which goes well beyond the available resources used above in simple condensed formulas. See<space/><link><target>IUPAC nomenclature of organic chemistry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>IUPAC nomenclature of inorganic chemistry 2005</target></link><space/>for examples. In addition, linear naming systems such as<space/><link><target>International Chemical Identifier</target></link><space/>(InChI) allow a computer to construct a structural formula, and<space/><link><target>simplified molecular-input line-entry system</target></link><space/>(SMILES) allows a more human-readable ASCII input. However, all these nomenclature systems go beyond the standards of chemical formulas, and technically are chemical naming systems, not formula systems.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Polymers in condensed formulas</heading><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>polymer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in condensed chemical formulas, parentheses are placed around the repeating unit. For example, a<space/><link><target>hydrocarbon</target></link><space/>molecule that is described as CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>(CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>50</xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>, is a molecule with fifty repeating units. If the number of repeating units is unknown or variable, the letter<space/><italics>n</italics><space/>may be used to indicate this formula: CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>(CH<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub><italics>n</italics></xhtml:sub>CH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ions in condensed formulas</heading><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>ion</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the charge on a particular atom may be denoted with a right-hand superscript. For example, Na<xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup>, or Cu<xhtml:sup>2+</xhtml:sup>. The total charge on a charged molecule or a<space/><link><target>polyatomic ion</target></link><space/>may also be shown in this way. For example:<space/><link><target>Hydronium</target><part>H<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sup>+</xhtml:sup></part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Sulfate</target><part>SO<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup></part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>For more complex ions, brackets [ ] are often used to enclose the ionic formula, as in [B<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>]<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>, which is found in compounds such as<space/><link><target>Caesium dodecaborate</target><part>Cs<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub>[B<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub></part></link>]. Parentheses ( ) can be nested inside brackets to indicate a repeating unit, as in [Co(NH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub>]<xhtml:sup>3+</xhtml:sup>. Here (NH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub>)<xhtml:sub>6</xhtml:sub><space/>indicates that the ion contains six<space/><link><target>ammine</target><part>NH<xhtml:sub>3</xhtml:sub><space/>groups</part></link>, and [ ] encloses the entire formula of the ion with charge +3.<space/><template><target>Elucidate</target><arg name="date">November 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Isotopes</heading><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>isotope</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are more relevant to<space/><link><target>nuclear chemistry</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>stable isotope</target></link><space/>chemistry than to conventional chemistry, different isotopes may be indicated with a prefixed<space/><link><target>superscript</target></link><space/>in a chemical formula. For example, the phosphate ion containing radioactive phosphorus-32 is<space/><xhtml:sup>32</xhtml:sup>PO<xhtml:sub>4</xhtml:sub><xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup>. Also a study involving stable isotope ratios might include the molecule<space/><xhtml:sup>18</xhtml:sup>O<xhtml:sup>16</xhtml:sup>O.</paragraph><paragraph>A left-hand subscript is sometimes used redundantly to indicate the<space/><link><target>atomic number</target></link>. For example,<space/><xhtml:sub>8</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><space/>for dioxygen, and<space/><xhtml:sup>16</xhtml:sup><xhtml:sub>8</xhtml:sub>O<xhtml:sub>2</xhtml:sub><space/>for the most abundant isotopic species of dioxygen. This is convenient when writing equations for<space/><link><target>nuclear reaction</target><trail>s</trail></link>, in order to show the balance of charge more clearly.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Trapped atoms</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Endohedral fullerene.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>180px</part><part>Traditional formula: MC<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>The &quot;@&quot; notation: M@C<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub></part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Endohedral fullerene</arg></template>The @ symbol (<link><target>at sign</target></link>) indicates an atom or molecule trapped inside a cage but not chemically bound to it. For example, a<space/><link><target>buckminsterfullerene</target></link><space/>(C<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub>) with an atom (M) would simply be represented as MC<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub><space/>regardless of whether M was inside the fullerene without chemical bonding or outside, bound to one of the carbon atoms. Using the @ symbol, this would be denoted M@C<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub><space/>if M was inside the carbon network. A non-fullerene example is [As@Ni<xhtml:sub>12</xhtml:sub>As<xhtml:sub>20</xhtml:sub>]<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup>, an ion in which one As atom is trapped in a cage formed by the other 32 atoms.</paragraph><paragraph>This notation was proposed in 1991<extension extension_name='ref' name="YanChai"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Fullerenes wlth Metals Inside<space/></arg><arg name="author">Chai, Yan; Guo, Ting; Jin, Changming; Haufler, Robert E.; Chibante, L. P. Felipe; Fure, Jan; Wang, Lihong; Alford, J. Michael; Smalley, Richard E.<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Physical Chemistry<space/></arg><arg name="volume">95<space/></arg><arg name="issue">20<space/></arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="pages">7564–7568<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1021/j100173a002</arg></template></extension><space/>with the discovery of<space/><link><target>fullerene</target></link><space/>cages (<link><target>endohedral fullerene</target><trail>s</trail></link>), which can trap atoms such as<space/><link><target>Lanthanum</target><part>La</part></link><space/>to form, for example, La@C<xhtml:sub>60</xhtml:sub><space/>or La@C<xhtml:sub>82</xhtml:sub>. The choice of the symbol has been explained by the authors as being concise, readily printed and transmitted electronically (the at sign is included in<space/><link><target>ASCII</target></link>, which most modern character encoding schemes are based on), and the visual aspects suggesting the structure of an endohedral fullerene.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Non-stoichiometric chemical formulas</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Non-stoichiometric compound</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Chemical formulas most often use<space/><link><target>integer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for each element. However, there is a class of compounds, called<space/><link><target>non-stoichiometric compound</target><trail>s</trail></link>, that cannot be represented by small integers. Such a formula might be written using<space/><link><target>decimal fraction</target><trail>s</trail></link>, as in Fe<xhtml:sub>0.95</xhtml:sub>O, or it might include a variable part represented by a letter, as in Fe<xhtml:sub>1x</xhtml:sub>O, where x is normally much less than 1.</paragraph><heading level='2'>General forms for organic compounds</heading><paragraph>A chemical formula used for a series of compounds that differ from each other by a constant unit is called<space/><bold>general formula</bold>. Such a series is called the<space/><link><target>homologous series</target></link>, while its members are called homologs.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>For example,<space/><link><target>alcohols</target></link><space/>may be represented by: C<xhtml:sub><italics>n</italics></xhtml:sub>H<xhtml:sub>(2n + 1)</xhtml:sub>OH (<italics>n</italics><space/>1)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Hill System</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Hill system</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Hill system</bold><space/>is a system of writing chemical formulas such that the number of<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/><link><target>atom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in a<space/><link><target>molecule</target></link><space/>is indicated first, the number of<space/><link><target>hydrogen</target></link><space/>atoms next, and then the number of all other<space/><link><target>chemical element</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>subsequently, in<space/><link><target>alphabetical order</target></link>. When the formula contains no carbon, all the elements, including hydrogen, are listed alphabetically. This deterministic system enables straightforward sorting and searching of compounds.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dictionary of chemical formulas</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Element symbol</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Nuclear notation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Periodic table</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>IUPAC nomenclature of inorganic chemistry</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikidata property</target><arg name="1">P274<space/></arg><arg name="2">chemical formula<space/></arg></template><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>General Chemistry: Principles and Modern Applications<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>8th<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Prentice-Hall<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Ralph S. Petrucci, William S. Harwood, F. Geoffrey Herring<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-13-198825-5<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">46872308</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Molecules detected in outer space</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Chemical Formula</target></template><link><target>Category:Chemical formulas</target></link><link><target>Category:Chemical nomenclature</target></link><link><target>Category:Notation</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>fr:Formule brute</target></link></paragraph></article>