<article title='Agnosticism'><paragraph><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>Gnosticism</arg></template><template><target>good article</target></template><template><target>use mdy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2014</arg></template><template><target>God</target><arg>isms</arg></template><template><target>Irreligion sidebar</target><arg>agnosticism</arg></template><template><target>Certainty</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Agnosticism</bold><space/>is the view that the<space/><link><target>truth value</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of certain claims &amp;nbsp;especially<space/><link><target>Metaphysics</target><part>metaphysical</part></link><space/>and religious claims such as<space/><link><target>Existence of God</target><part>whether or not God</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Divinity</target><part>divine</part></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>supernatural</target></link><space/>exist&amp;nbsp; are unknown and perhaps unknowable.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hepburn"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="title">Agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ronald W.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Hepburn<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">MacMillan Reference USA (Gale)<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Donald M. Borchert<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1967<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">[[Encyclopedia of Philosophy|The Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">1<space/></arg><arg name="page">92<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-02-865780-2<space/></arg><arg name="quote">In the most general use of the term, agnosticism is the view that we do not know whether there is a God or not.</arg></template><space/>(page 56 in 1967 edition)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="RoweRoutledge"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">Agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="first">William L.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rowe<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">William L. Rowe<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">[[Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-07310-3<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Edward Craig<space/></arg><arg name="quote">In the popular sense, an agnostic is someone who neither believes nor disbelieves in God, whereas an atheist disbelieves in God. In the strict sense, however, agnosticism is the view that human reason is incapable of providing sufficient rational grounds to justify either the belief that God exists or the belief that God does not exist. In so far as one holds that our beliefs are rational only if they are sufficiently supported by human reason, the person who accepts the philosophical position of agnosticism will hold that neither the belief that God exists nor the belief that God does not exist is rational.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite dictionary</target><arg name="dictionary">OED Online, 3rd ed.<space/></arg><arg name="entry">agnostic, agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 2012<space/></arg><arg name="quote">'''agnostic'''.
: '''A'''. n[oun].
:# A person who believes that nothing is known or can be known of immaterial things, especially of the existence or nature of God.
:# In extended use: a person who is not persuaded by or committed to a particular point of view; a sceptic. Also: person of indeterminate ideology or conviction; an equivocator.
: '''B.''' adj[ective].
:# Of or relating to the belief that the existence of anything beyond and behind material phenomena is unknown and (as far as can be judged) unknowable. Also: holding this belief.
:# a. In extended use: not committed to or persuaded by a particular point of view; sceptical. Also: politically or ideologically unaligned; non-partisan, equivocal.
'''agnosticism''', n. The doctrine or tenets of agnostics with regard to the existence of anything beyond and behind material phenomena or to knowledge of a First Cause or God.</arg></template></extension><space/>According to the philosopher<space/><link><target>William L. Rowe</target></link>: &quot;In the popular sense of the term, an agnostic is someone who neither believes nor disbelieves in the existence of God, while a<space/><link><target>Theism</target><part>theist</part></link><space/>believes that God exists, an<space/><link><target>Atheism</target><part>atheist</part></link><space/>disbelieves in God&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RoweRoutledge"></extension><space/>Agnosticism is a<space/><link><target>doctrine</target></link><space/>or set of<space/><link><target>wikt:tenet</target><part>tenet</part><trail>s</trail></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>OED</target><arg>agnosticism</arg></template></extension><space/>rather than a religion as such.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Henry Huxley</target></link>, an English biologist, coined the word &quot;agnostic&quot; in 1869. Earlier thinkers, however, had written works that promoted agnostic points of view, such as<space/><link><target>Sanjaya Belatthaputta</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Ancient Indian philosophy</target><part>5th-century BCE Indian philosopher</part></link><space/>who expressed agnosticism about any<space/><link><target>afterlife</target></link>;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.accesstoinsight.org/tipitaka/dn/dn.02.0.than.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Samaññaphala Sutta: The Fruits of the Contemplative Life<space/></arg><arg name="others">a part of the Digha Nikaya translated in 1997 by Thanissaro Bhikkhu<space/></arg><arg name="quote">If you ask me if there exists another world (after death),&nbsp;... I don't think so. I don't think in that way. I don't think otherwise. I don't think not. I don't think not not.<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NFylf86U<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Bhaskar 1972">Bhaskar (1972).</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ridgeon2003"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Lloyd Ridgeon<space/></arg><arg name="title">Major World Religions: From Their Origins To The Present<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">March 13, 2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-203-42313-4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">63–</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Protagoras</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek philosophy</target><part>5th-century BCE Greek philosopher</part></link><space/>who expressed agnosticism about &quot;the gods&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Protagoras"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/protagor/<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy&nbsp;– Protagoras (c. 490&nbsp;– c. 420 BCE)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 22, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6N5BAlO9r<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 2, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="quote">While the pious might wish to look to the gods to provide absolute moral guidance in the relativistic universe of the Sophistic Enlightenment, that certainty also was cast into doubt by philosophic and sophistic thinkers, who pointed out the absurdity and immorality of the conventional epic accounts of the gods. Protagoras' prose treatise about the gods began "Concerning the gods, I have no means of knowing whether they exist or not or of what sort they may be. Many things prevent knowledge including the obscurity of the subject and the brevity of human life."</arg></template></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Nasadiya Sukta</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Rigveda</target></link><space/>is agnostic about the<space/><link><target>origin of the universe</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="patri"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.positiveatheism.org/india/s1990a22.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Progress of Atheism in India: A Historical Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Atheist Centre 1940–1990 Golden Jubilee<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 1990<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 29, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="author">Patri, Umesh and Prativa Devi<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9396tk<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Treharne2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Trevor Treharne<space/></arg><arg name="title">How to Prove God Does Not Exist: The Complete Guide to Validating Atheism<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Universal-Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-61233-118-8<space/></arg><arg name="pages">34 ff.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Schwab2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Helmut Schwab<space/></arg><arg name="title">Essential Writings: A Journey Through Time: A Modern "De Rerum Natura"<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">December 10, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">iUniverse<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4759-6026-6<space/></arg><arg name="pages">77 ff.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the time since Huxley coined the term, many other thinkers have written extensively about agnosticism.<template><target>TOC limit</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Defining agnosticism</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Agnosticism is of the essence of science, whether ancient or modern. It simply means that a man shall not say he knows or believes that which he has no scientific grounds for professing to know or believe.

Consequently Agnosticism puts aside not only the greater part of popular theology, but also the greater part of anti-theology. On the whole, the "bosh" of heterodoxy is more offensive to me than that of orthodoxy, because heterodoxy professes to be guided by reason and science, and orthodoxy does not.<ref>Thomas Huxley, [http://aleph0.clarku.edu/huxley/UnColl/Rdetc/AgnAnn.html "Agnosticism: A Symposium"], ''The Agnostic Annual'', 1884</ref></arg><arg>Thomas Henry Huxley</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>That which Agnostics deny and repudiate, as immoral, is the contrary doctrine, that there are propositions which men ought to believe, without logically satisfactory evidence; and that reprobation ought to attach to the profession of disbelief in such inadequately supported propositions.<ref>Thomas Huxley, [http://aleph0.clarku.edu/huxley/CE5/Agn-X.html "Agnosticism and Christianity"], ''Collected Essays V'', 1899</ref></arg><arg>Thomas Henry Huxley</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Agnosticism, in fact, is not a creed, but a method, the essence of which lies in the rigorous application of a single principle&nbsp;... Positively the principle may be expressed: In matters of the intellect, follow your reason as far as it will take you, without regard to any other consideration. And negatively: In matters of the intellect do not pretend that conclusions are certain which are not demonstrated or demonstrable.<ref>Thomas Huxley, [http://aleph0.clarku.edu/huxley/CE5/Agn.html "Agnosticism"], ''Collected Essays V'', 1889</ref><ref>{{cite journal|last">Huxley|first</arg><arg>Thomas Henry Huxley</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Being a scientist, above all else,<space/><link><target>Thomas Henry Huxley</target><part>Huxley</part></link><space/>presented agnosticism as a form of demarcation. A hypothesis with no supporting objective, testable, evidence is not an objective, scientific, claim. As such, there would be no way to test said hypotheses, leaving the results inconclusive. His agnosticism was not compatible with forming a belief as to the truth, or falsehood, of the claim at hand. Huxley came up with this term at a time when narrow definition atheism (the belief that no gods exist) was, by far, the most popular definition of the word.<space/><link><target>Karl Popper</target></link><space/>would also describe himself simply as an agnostic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Edward Zerin 1998">Edward Zerin: Karl Popper On God: The Lost Interview.<space/><italics>Skeptic</italics><space/><bold>6</bold>:2 (1998)</extension><space/>According to philosopher<space/><link><target>William L. Rowe</target></link>, in this strict sense, agnosticism is the view that human reason is incapable of providing sufficient rational grounds to justify either the belief that God exists or the belief that God does not exist.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RoweRoutledge"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Others have redefined this concept, making it compatible with forming a belief, and only incompatible with absolute certainty.<space/><link><target>George H. Smith</target></link>, while admitting that the narrow definition of atheist was the common usage definition of that word,<extension extension_name='ref'>George H. Smith, Atheism: The Case Against God, pg. 9</extension><space/>and admitting that the broad definition of agnostic was the common usage definition of that word,<extension extension_name='ref'>George H. Smith, Atheism: The Case Against God, pg. 12</extension><space/>promoted broadening the definition of atheist and narrowing the definition of agnostic. Terms such as<space/><link><target>agnostic atheism</target></link><space/>(the view of those who do not<space/><italics>believe</italics><space/>in the existence of any deity, but do not claim to<space/><italics>know</italics><space/>if a deity does or does not exist) and<space/><link><target>agnostic theism</target></link><space/>(the view of those who do not claim to<space/><italics>know</italics><space/>of the existence of any deity, but still<space/><italics>believe</italics><space/>in such an existence), are then used to distinguish between the two.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith1979"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">Atheism: The Case Against God<space/></arg><arg name="first">George H<space/></arg><arg name="last">Smith<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">George H. Smith<space/></arg><arg name="pages">10–11<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Properly considered, agnosticism is not a third alternative to theism and atheism because it is concerned with a different aspect of religious belief. Theism and atheism refer to the presence or absence of belief in a god; agnosticism refers to the impossibility of knowledge with regard to a god or supernatural being. The term ''agnostic'' does not, in itself, indicate whether or not one believes in a god. Agnosticism can be either theistic or atheistic.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87975-124-1<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Ascent of Faith: or, the Grounds of Certainty in Science and Religion</arg><arg name="year">1894</arg><arg name="first">Alexander James</arg><arg name="last">Harrison</arg><arg name="publisher">Hodder and Stroughton</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="page">21</arg><arg name="oclc">7234849</arg><arg name="ol">21834002M</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="quote">Let Agnostic Theism stand for that kind of Agnosticism which admits a Divine existence; Agnostic Atheism for that kind of Agnosticism which thinks it does not.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="barker-agnostic-atheism"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Barker</arg><arg name="first">Dan</arg><arg name="authorlink">Dan Barker</arg><arg name="title">Godless: How an Evangelical Preacher Became One of America's Leading Atheists</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Ulysses Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-56975-677-5</arg><arg name="ol">24313839M</arg><arg name="page">96</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="quote">People are invariably surprised to hear me say I am both an atheist and an agnostic, as if this somehow weakens my certainty. I usually reply with a question like, "Well, are you a Republican or an American?" The two words serve different concepts and are not mutually exclusive. Agnosticism addresses knowledge; atheism addresses belief. The agnostic says, "I don't have a knowledge that God exists." The atheist says, "I don't have a belief that God exists." You can say both things at the same time. Some agnostics are atheistic and some are theistic.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Smith's terminology hadn't caught on by the time<space/><link><target>Antony Flew</target></link><space/>came along, also promoting a broader definition of atheism, and also bringing into question the definition of agnosticism.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg><space/>In this interpretation an atheist becomes: not someone who positively asserts the non-existence of God; but someone who is simply not a theist. Let us, for future ready reference, introduce the labels 'positive atheist' for the former and 'negative atheist' for the latter.

The introduction of this new interpretation of the word 'atheism' may appear to be a piece of perverse Humpty-Dumptyism, going arbitrarily against established common usage. 'Whyever', it could be asked, 'don't you make it not the presumption of atheism but the presumption of agnosticism?'<ref>Antony Flew, God Freedom and Immorality: A Critical Analysis, 1984</ref></arg><arg>Antony Flew</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Most recently, the terms<space/><link><target>Apatheism</target><part>apathetic and pragmatic agnosticism</part></link><space/>have been coined with regard to the view that there is no proof of either the existence or non-existence of any deity, but since any deity that may exist appears unconcerned for the universe or the welfare of its inhabitants, the question is largely academic and that their existence therefore has little to no impact on personal human affairs and should be of little theological interest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rauch, Jonathan,<space/><italics>Let It Be: Three Cheers for Apatheism</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Atlantic Monthly</target></link></italics>, May 2003</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Etymology</heading><paragraph><italics>Agnostic</italics><space/>(<template><target>ety</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>ἀ- (a-)</arg><arg>without</arg><arg></arg><arg>[[wikt:γνῶσις|γνῶσις]] (gnōsis)</arg><arg>knowledge</arg></template>) was used by Thomas Henry Huxley in a speech at a meeting of the Metaphysical Society in 1869 to describe his philosophy, which rejects all claims of spiritual or mystical knowledge.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Dixon</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Thomas</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Science and Religion: A Very Short Introduction</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford</arg><arg name="page"><space/>63</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-929551-7</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="EB-Agnosticism"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">Antony</arg><arg name="first">Flew</arg><arg name="title">Agnosticism</arg><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/9356/agnosticism</arg><arg name="work">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 15, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Early<space/><link><target>Christian</target></link><space/>church leaders used the<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>word<space/><italics><link><target>gnosis</target></link></italics><space/>(knowledge) to describe &quot;spiritual knowledge&quot;. Agnosticism is not to be confused with religious views opposing the ancient religious movement of<space/><link><target>Gnosticism</target></link><space/>in particular; Huxley used the term in a broader, more abstract sense.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nknxjx"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">ag·nos·tic</arg><arg name="website">The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language</arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton Mifflin Harcourt</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="url">http://ahdictionary.com/word/search.html?q</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>November 15, 2013</arg></template></extension>Huxley identified agnosticism not as a creed but rather as a method of<space/><link><target>Skepticism</target><part>skeptical</part></link>, evidence-based inquiry.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Aphorisms and Reflections<space/></arg><arg name="first">Henrietta A.</arg><arg name="last">Huxley</arg><arg name="publisher">Kessinger Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="edition">reprint<space/></arg><arg name="pages">41–42</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4191-0730-6</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In recent years, scientific literature dealing with neuroscience and psychology has used the word to mean &quot;not knowable&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Oxford English Dictionary, Additions Series, 1993</extension>In technical and marketing literature, &quot;agnostic&quot; can also mean independence from some parametersfor example, &quot;platform agnostic&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="SparkSheet"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">What Does Platform Agnostic Mean?</arg><arg name="author">Sophie Woodrooffe and Dan Levy</arg><arg name="website">Sparksheet</arg><arg name="url">http://sparksheet.com/what-does-platform-agnostic-mean/</arg><arg name="date">September 9, 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 15, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9IyAfx<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>or &quot;hardware agnostic&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Datacenterdynamics"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Datacenter Dynamics</arg><arg name="title">EMC AND NETAPP&nbsp;– A SOFTWARE-DEFINED STORAGE BATTLE: Interoperability no longer matter of choice for big storage vendors</arg><arg name="url">http://www.datacenterdynamics.com/focus/archive/2013/07/emc-and-netapp-%E2%80%93-software-defined-storage-battle</arg><arg name="author">Yevgeniy Sverdlik</arg><arg name="date">July 31, 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>November 15, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9N1uV6<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Qualifying agnosticism</heading><paragraph><link><target>Scottish Enlightenment</target></link><space/>philosopher<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link><space/>contended that meaningful statements about the universe are always qualified by some degree of doubt. He asserted that the fallibility of human beings means that they cannot obtain absolute certainty except in trivial cases where a statement is true by definition (e.g.<space/><link><target>tautology (logic)</target><part>tautologies</part></link><space/>such as &quot;all bachelors are unmarried&quot; or &quot;all triangles have three corners&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'>Hume, David, &quot;An Enquiry Concerning Human Understanding&quot; (1748)</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Types</heading><paragraph>Agnosticism has sometimes been divided into two categories in academic and philosophical treatment:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Strong agnosticism (also called &quot;hard&quot;, &quot;closed&quot;, &quot;strict&quot;, or &quot;permanent agnosticism&quot;)</defkey><defval><space/>The view that the question of the existence or nonexistence of a deity or deities, and the nature of ultimate reality is unknowable by reason of our natural inability to verify any experience with anything but another subjective experience. A strong agnostic would say, &quot;I cannot know whether a deity exists or not, and neither can you.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oppy2006"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Graham Oppy</arg><arg name="title">Arguing about Gods</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">September 4, 2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-139-45889-4</arg><arg name="pages">15–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Barnes2003"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Michael H. Barnes</arg><arg name="title">In The Presence of Mystery: An Introduction To The Story Of Human Religiousness</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Twenty-Third Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-58595-259-5</arg><arg name="pages">3–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Poidevin2010"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Robin Le Poidevin</arg><arg name="title">Agnosticism: A Very Short Introduction</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">October 28, 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-161454-5</arg><arg name="pages">32–</arg></template></extension></defval></listitem><listitem><defkey>Weak agnosticism (also called &quot;soft&quot;, &quot;open&quot;, &quot;empirical&quot;, or &quot;temporal agnosticism&quot;)</defkey><defval><space/>The view that the existence or nonexistence of any deities is currently unknown but is not necessarily unknowable; therefore, one will withhold judgment until evidence, if any, becomes available. A weak agnostic would say, &quot;I don't know whether any deities exist or not, but maybe one day, if there is evidence, we can find something out.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oppy2006"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Barnes2003"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Poidevin2010"></extension></defval></listitem></list><paragraph>Agnosticism is sometimes used colloquially to refer to<space/><link><target>Epistemological pluralism</target><part>plurality</part></link><space/>of beliefs. An agnostic in this case might claim, &quot;The concepts of a universe with or without a God represent intellectual tools that aid our exploration of reality; neither of these ideas are inherently wrong and both bear a useful conceptual utility.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Greek philosophy</heading><paragraph>Agnostic thought, in the form of<space/><link><target>Philosophical skepticism</target><part>skepticism</part></link>, emerged as a formal philosophical position in<space/><link><target>ancient Greece</target></link>. Its proponents included<space/><link><target>Protagoras</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pyrrho</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carneades</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sextus Empiricus</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="Sextus"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.angelfire.com/md2/timewarp/skepticism.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sextus Empiricus's Outlines of Pyrrhonism<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NFddqTPD<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></extension>and, to some degree,<space/><link><target>Socrates</target></link>, who was a strong advocate for a skeptical approach to<space/><link><target>epistemology</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Gareth Southwell<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.philosophyonline.co.uk/tok/scepticism8.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Scepticism&nbsp;– History of Scepticism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Philosophyonline.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">August 14, 2010</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20100826031745/http://www.philosophyonline.co.uk/tok/scepticism8.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate">August 26, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pyrrho</target></link><space/>said that we should refrain from making judgment as we can never know the true reality. According to Pyrrho, having opinion was possible, but certainty and knowledge are impossible.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/pyrrho/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Pyrrho [Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy&#93;<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Iep.utm.edu</arg><arg name="date">June 20, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NFdZdhJE<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></extension><link><target>Carneades</target></link><space/>was also a skeptic in relation to all knowledge claims. He proposed a probability theory, however. According to him, certainty could never be attained.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://philosophos.com/philosophical_connections/profile_020.html</arg><arg name="title">Philosophical Connections: Carneades<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Philosophos.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NFdan6QI<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Protagoras</target></link><space/>rejected the conventional accounts of the gods. He said:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Protagoras"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Concerning the gods, I have no means of knowing whether they exist or not or of what sort they may be. Many things prevent knowledge including the obscurity of the subject and the brevity of human life.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hindu philosophy</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Sanjaya Belatthaputta</arg></template>Throughout the history of<space/><link><target>Hinduism</target></link><space/>there has been a strong tradition of philosophic speculation and skepticism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">World scriptures: an introduction to comparative religions</arg><arg name="first">Kramer</arg><arg name="last">Kenneth</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8091-2781-8</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="page">34</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Subodh Varma<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/life-style/spirituality/vintage-wisdom/The-gods-came-afterwards/articleshow/6014217.cms?referral</arg><arg name="title">The gods came afterwards<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>[[The Times of India]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>May 6, 2011</arg><arg name="accessdate">June 9, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9T0Dr8<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Rig Veda</target></link><space/>takes an agnostic view on the fundamental question of how the universe and the gods were created.<space/><link><target>Nasadiya Sukta</target></link><space/>(<italics>Creation Hymn</italics>) in the tenth chapter of the Rig Veda says:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kramer1986"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Kenneth Kramer</arg><arg name="title">World Scriptures: An Introduction to Comparative Religions</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">January 1986</arg><arg name="publisher">Paulist Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8091-2781-8</arg><arg name="pages">34–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Christian2011"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">David Christian</arg><arg name="title">Maps of Time: An Introduction to Big History</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">September 1, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-520-95067-2</arg><arg name="pages">18–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Singh2008"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Upinder Singh</arg><arg name="title">A History of Ancient and Early Medieval India: From the Stone Age to the 12th Century</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">Pearson Education India</arg><arg name="isbn">978-81-317-1120-0</arg><arg name="pages">206–</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg><poem>Who really knows?
Who will here proclaim it?
Whence was it produced? Whence is this creation?
The gods came afterwards, with the creation of this universe.
Who then knows whence it has arisen?</poem></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Hume, Kant, and Kierkegaard</heading><paragraph><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.logicmuseum.com/ontological/aristotleontological.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Aristotle on the existence of God<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Logicmuseum.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9X770Z<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><link><target>Anselm of Canterbury</target><part>Anselm</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/anselm.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Internet History Sourcebooks Project<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fordham.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9YKD9j<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="williams"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/spr2013/entries/anselm/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Saint Anselm<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 29, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="author">Williams, Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="year">2013<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Spring 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9ZKsTY<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><link><target>Aquinas</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/aquinas3.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Internet History Sourcebooks Project<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Fordham.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9sNfIP<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Owens1980"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Joseph Owens</arg><arg name="title">Saint Thomas Aquinas on the Existence of God: The Collected Papers of Joseph Owens</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1980</arg><arg name="publisher">SUNY Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-87395-401-3</arg></template></extension>and<space/><link><target>Descartes</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://oregonstate.edu/instruction/phl302/philosophers/descartes-god.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Descartes' Proof for the Existence of God<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oregonstate.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6Qh9vX8U9<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>presented arguments attempting to rationally prove the existence of God. The skeptical empiricism of<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>antinomy</target><part>antinomies</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, and the existential philosophy of<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>convinced many later philosophers to abandon these attempts, regarding it impossible to construct any unassailable proof for the existence or non-existence of God.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RoweRoutledge-online"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://www.texttribe.com/routledge/A/Agnosticism.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="first">William L.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rowe<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">William L. Rowe<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">[[Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-07310-3<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor & Francis<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Edward Craig<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20110722184326/http://www.texttribe.com/routledge/A/Agnosticism.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">July 22, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 17, 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In his 1844 book,<space/><italics><link><target>Philosophical Fragments</target></link></italics>, Kierkegaard writes:<extension extension_name='ref'>Kierkegaard, Sren.<space/><italics>Philosophical Fragments</italics>. Ch. 3</extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>Let us call this unknown something: God. It is nothing more than a name we assign to it. The idea of demonstrating that this unknown something (God) exists, could scarcely suggest itself to Reason. For if God does not exist it would of course be impossible to prove it; and if he does exist it would be folly to attempt it. For at the very outset, in beginning my proof, I would have presupposed it, not as doubtful but as certain (a presupposition is never doubtful, for the very reason that it is a presupposition), since otherwise I would not begin, readily understanding that the whole would be impossible if he did not exist. But if when I speak of proving God's existence I mean that I propose to prove that the Unknown, which exists, is God, then I express myself unfortunately. For in that case I do not prove anything, least of all an existence, but merely develop the content of a conception.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>David Hume</target><part>Hume</part></link><space/>was Huxley's favourite philosopher, calling him &quot;the Prince of Agnostics&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>A Hundred Years of British Philosophy, By Rudolf Metz, pg. 111</extension><space/><link><target>Denis Diderot</target><part>Diderot</part></link><space/>wrote to his mistress, telling of a visit by Hume to the<space/><link><target>Baron D'Holbach</target></link>, and describing how a word for the position that Huxley would later describe as agnosticism didn't seem to exist, or at least wasn't common knowledge, at the time.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The first time that M. Hume found himself at the table of the Baron, he was seated beside him. I don't know for what purpose the English philosopher took it into his head to remark to the Baron that he did not believe in atheists, that he had never seen any. The Baron said to him: "Count how many we are here." We are eighteen. The Baron added: "It isn't too bad a showing to be able to point out to you fifteen at once: the three others haven't made up their minds."<ref>Ernest Campbell Mossner, ''The Life of David Hume'', 2014, pg.483</ref></arg><arg>Denis Diderot</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Thomas Henry Huxley</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:ThomasHenryHuxley.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Thomas Henry Huxley</target></link></part></link>Agnostic views are as old as<space/><link><target>philosophical skepticism</target></link>, but the terms agnostic and agnosticism were created by<space/><link><target>Thomas Henry Huxley</target><part>Huxley</part></link><space/>to sum up his thoughts on contemporary developments of metaphysics about the &quot;unconditioned&quot; (<link><target>Sir William Hamilton, 9th Baronet</target><part>William Hamilton</part></link>) and the &quot;unknowable&quot; (<link><target>Herbert Spencer</target></link>). Though Huxley began to use the term &quot;agnostic&quot; in 1869, his opinions had taken shape some time before that date. In a letter of September 23, 1860, to<space/><link><target>Charles Kingsley</target></link>, Huxley discussed his views extensively:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Huxley1997"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Thomas Henry Huxley</arg><arg name="title">The Major Prose of Thomas Henry Huxley</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Georgia Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8203-1864-6</arg><arg name="pages">357–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Huxley2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Leonard Huxley</arg><arg name="title">Thomas Henry Huxley A Character Sketch</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">February 7, 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">tredition</arg><arg name="isbn">978-3-8472-0297-4</arg><arg name="pages">41–</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>I neither affirm nor deny the immortality of man. I see no reason for believing it, but, on the other hand, I have no means of disproving it. I have no ''a priori'' objections to the doctrine. No man who has to deal daily and hourly with nature can trouble himself about ''a priori'' difficulties. Give me such evidence as would justify me in believing in anything else, and I will believe that. Why should I not? It is not half so wonderful as the conservation of force or the indestructibility of matter&nbsp;...

It is no use to talk to me of analogies and probabilities. I know what I mean when I say I believe in the law of the inverse squares, and I will not rest my life and my hopes upon weaker convictions&nbsp;...

That my personality is the surest thing I know may be true. But the attempt to conceive what it is leads me into mere verbal subtleties. I have champed up all that chaff about the ego and the non-ego, noumena and phenomena, and all the rest of it, too often not to know that in attempting even to think of these questions, the human intellect flounders at once out of its depth.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>And again, to the same correspondent, May 6, 1863:<extension extension_name='ref' name="HuxleyHuxley2011"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">Leonard Huxley</arg><arg name="author2">Thomas Henry Huxley</arg><arg name="title">Life and Letters of Thomas Henry Huxley</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">December 22, 2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-108-04045-7</arg><arg name="pages">347–</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>I have never had the least sympathy with the ''a priori'' reasons against orthodoxy, and I have by nature and disposition the greatest possible antipathy to all the atheistic and infidel school. Nevertheless I know that I am, in spite of myself, exactly what the Christian would call, and, so far as I can see, is justified in calling, atheist and infidel. I cannot see one shadow or tittle of evidence that the great unknown underlying the phenomenon of the universe stands to us in the relation of a Father [who] loves us and cares for us as Christianity asserts. So with regard to the other great Christian dogmas, immortality of soul and future state of rewards and punishments, what possible objection can I—who am compelled perforce to believe in the immortality of what we call Matter and Force, and in a very unmistakable present state of rewards and punishments for our deeds—have to these doctrines? Give me a scintilla of evidence, and I am ready to jump at them.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Of the origin of the name agnostic to describe this attitude, Huxley gave the following account:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Collected Essays, Vol. V: Science and Christian Tradition</arg><arg name="first">Thomas</arg><arg name="last">Huxley</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-85506-922-9</arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan and Co 1893</arg><arg name="pages">237–239</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>When I reached intellectual maturity and began to ask myself whether I was an atheist, a theist, or a pantheist; a materialist or an idealist; Christian or a freethinker; I found that the more I learned and reflected, the less ready was the answer; until, at last, I came to the conclusion that I had neither art nor part with any of these denominations, except the last. The one thing in which most of these good people were agreed was the one thing in which I differed from them. They were quite sure they had attained a certain "gnosis"–had, more or less successfully, solved the problem of existence; while I was quite sure I had not, and had a pretty strong conviction that the problem was insoluble. And, with Hume and Kant on my side, I could not think myself presumptuous in holding fast by that opinion&nbsp;...

So I took thought, and invented what I conceived to be the appropriate title of "agnostic". It came into my head as suggestively antithetic to the "gnostic" of Church history, who professed to know so much about the very things of which I was ignorant.&nbsp;... To my great satisfaction the term took.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1889, Huxley wrote:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Therefore, although it be, as I believe, demonstrable that we have no real knowledge of the authorship, or of the date of composition of the Gospels, as they have come down to us, and that nothing better than more or less probable guesses can be arrived at on that subject.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Huxley</arg><arg name="first">Thomas Henry</arg><arg name="authorlink">Thomas Henry Huxley</arg><arg name="title">Essays Upon Some Controverted Questions</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1892</arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan</arg><arg name="page">364</arg><arg name="chapter">Agnosticism And Christianity</arg><arg name="quote">Agnosticism And Christianity: Therefore, although it be, as I believe, demonstrable that we have no real knowledge of the authorship, or of the date of composition of the Gospels, as they have come down to us, and that nothing better than more or less probable guesses can be arrived at on that subject. (Image of [https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>William Stewart Ross</heading><paragraph><link><target>William Stewart Ross</target></link><space/>wrote under the name of Saladin. He championed agnosticism in opposition to the<space/><link><target>atheism</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Charles Bradlaugh</target></link><space/>as an open-ended spiritual exploration.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alastair Bonnett 'The Agnostic Saladin'<space/><italics>History Today</italics>, 2013, 63,2, pp.&amp;nbsp;4752</extension>In<space/><italics>Why I am an Agnostic</italics><space/>(c. 1889) he claims that agnosticism is &quot;the very reverse of atheism&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RossTaylor1889"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author1">William Stewart Ross</arg><arg name="author2">Joseph Taylor</arg><arg name="title">Why I Am an Agnostic: Being a Manual of Agnosticism</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1889</arg><arg name="publisher">W. Stewart & Company</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Robert G. Ingersoll</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:RobertGIngersoll.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Robert G. Ingersoll</target></link></part></link><link><target>Robert G. Ingersoll</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>Illinois</target></link><space/>lawyer and politician who evolved into a well-known and sought-after orator in 19th-century America, has been referred to as the &quot;Great Agnostic&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brandt<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eric T., and Timothy Larsen<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Old Atheism Revisited: Robert G. Ingersoll and the Bible<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of the Historical Society<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>11<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>211–238<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1540-5923.2011.00330.x</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In an 1896 lecture titled<space/><italics>Why I Am An Agnostic</italics>, Ingersoll related why he was an agnostic:<extension extension_name='ref' name="infidels1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://infidels.org/library/historical/robert_ingersoll/why_i_am_agnostic.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Why I Am Agnostic</arg><arg name="publisher">Infidels.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 2, 2014</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>Is there a supernatural power—an arbitrary mind—an enthroned God—a supreme will that sways the tides and currents of the world—to which all causes bow? I do not deny. I do not know—but I do not believe. I believe that the natural is supreme—that from the infinite chain no link can be lost or broken—that there is no supernatural power that can answer prayer—no power that worship can persuade or change—no power that cares for man.

I believe that with infinite arms Nature embraces the all—that there is no interference—no chance—that behind every event are the necessary and countless causes, and that beyond every event will be and must be the necessary and countless effects.

Is there a God? I do not know. Is man immortal? I do not know. One thing I do know, and that is, that neither hope, nor fear, belief, nor denial, can change the fact. It is as it is, and it will be as it must be.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the conclusion of the speech he simply sums up the agnostic position as:<extension extension_name='ref' name="infidels1"></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>We can be as honest as we are ignorant. If we are, when asked what is beyond the horizon of the known, we must say that we do not know.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Physical determinism</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bertrand Russell</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Russell1907-2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link></part></link><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>pamphlet</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Why I Am Not a Christian</target></link></italics>, based on a speech delivered in 1927 and later included in a book of the same title, is considered a classic statement of agnosticism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Users.drew.edu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://users.drew.edu/~jlenz/whynot.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Why I Am Not A Christian, by Bertrand Russell<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Users.drew.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 6, 1927<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NFzw1Fbo<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Users.drew.edu"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Russell1992"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bertrand Russell</arg><arg name="title">Why I Am Not a Christian: And Other Essays on Religion and Related Subjects</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-07918-1</arg></template></extension>He calls upon his readers to &quot;stand on their own two feet and look fair and square at the world with a fearless attitude and a free intelligence&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Donald E. Smith</arg><arg name="title">The Hopeful Agnostic: What I Believe&nbsp;– I Guess</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">February 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">AuthorHouse</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4685-4459-6</arg><arg name="pages">15–</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1939, Russell gave a lecture on<space/><italics>The existence and nature of God</italics>, in which he characterized himself as an atheist. He said:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Russell</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bertrand</arg><arg name="title">Collected Papers, Vol 10</arg><arg name="page">255</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>The existence and nature of God is a subject of which I can discuss only half. If one arrives at a negative conclusion concerning the first part of the question, the second part of the question does not arise; and my position, as you may have gathered, is a negative one on this matter.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>However, later in the same lecture, discussing modern non-anthropomorphic concepts of God, Russell states:<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Collected Papers, Vol. 10</italics>, p.258</extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>That sort of God is, I think, not one that can actually be disproved, as I think the omnipotent and benevolent creator can.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In Russell's 1947 pamphlet,<space/><italics>Am I An Atheist or an Agnostic?</italics><space/>(subtitled<space/><italics>A Plea For Tolerance in the Face of New Dogmas</italics>), he ruminates on the problem of what to call himself:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ewell2006"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Ken Ewell</arg><arg name="title">Traveling with Philosophes</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">August 27, 2006</arg><arg name="publisher">iUniverse</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-595-85361-8</arg><arg name="pages">348–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Russell1997"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bertrand Russell</arg><arg name="title">Last Philosophical Testament: 1943–68</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Psychology Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-09409-2</arg><arg name="pages">91–</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>As a philosopher, if I were speaking to a purely philosophic audience I should say that I ought to describe myself as an Agnostic, because I do not think that there is a conclusive argument by which one can prove that there is not a God. On the other hand, if I am to convey the right impression to the ordinary man in the street I think I ought to say that I am an Atheist, because when I say that I cannot prove that there is not a God, I ought to add equally that I cannot prove that there are not the Homeric gods.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In his 1953 essay,<space/><italics>What Is An Agnostic?</italics><space/>Russell states:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Russell2009"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bertrand Russell</arg><arg name="title">The Basic Writings of Bertrand Russell</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">March 2, 2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-134-02867-2</arg><arg name="pages">557–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Farrell"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Victor Robert Farrell</arg><arg name="title">Wake Up!&nbsp;– Dynamite for the Daytime</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Lulu.com</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-9538864-2-5</arg><arg name="pages">367–</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>An agnostic thinks it impossible to know the truth in matters such as God and the future life with which Christianity and other religions are concerned. Or, if not impossible, at least impossible at the present time.

Are Agnostics Atheists?

No. An atheist, like a Christian, holds that we can know whether or not there is a God. The Christian holds that we can know there is a God; the atheist, that we can know there is not. The Agnostic suspends judgment, saying that there are not sufficient grounds either for affirmation or for denial.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Later in the essay, Russell adds:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://scepsis.net/eng/articles/id_5.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">'What Is an agnostic?' by Bertrand Russell<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Scepsis.net</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 2, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6N57z5djS<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">January 2, 2014</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>I think that if I heard a voice from the sky predicting all that was going to happen to me during the next twenty-four hours, including events that would have seemed highly improbable, and if all these events then produced to happen, I might perhaps be convinced at least of the existence of some superhuman intelligence.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Leslie Weatherhead</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target><arg>Leslie Weatherhead</arg></template>In 1965 Christian theologian<space/><link><target>Leslie Weatherhead</target></link><space/>published<space/><italics>The Christian Agnostic</italics>, in which he argues:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith2012"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Donald E. Smith</arg><arg name="title">The Hopeful Agnostic: What I Believe&nbsp;– I Guess</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">February 17, 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">AuthorHouse</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4685-4458-9</arg><arg name="pages">16–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Weatherhead1990"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Leslie D. Weatherhead</arg><arg name="title">The Christian Agnostic</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">September 1990</arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-687-06980-4</arg></template></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>...&nbsp;many professing agnostics are nearer belief in the true God than are many conventional church-goers who believe in a body that does not exist whom they miscall God.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Although radical and unpalatable to conventional theologians, Weatherhead's<space/><italics>agnosticism</italics><space/>falls far short of Huxley's, and short even of<space/><italics>weak agnosticism</italics>:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith2012"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Weatherhead1990"></extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>Of course, the human soul will always have the power to reject God, for choice is essential to its nature, but I cannot believe that anyone will finally do this.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Charles Darwin</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Charles Darwin seated crop.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Charles Darwin</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Raised in a religious environment,<space/><link><target>Charles Darwin</target></link><space/>studied to be an Anglican clergyman. While eventually doubting parts of his faith, Darwin continued to help in church affairs, even while avoiding church attendance. Darwin stated that it would be &quot;absurd to doubt that a man might be an ardent theist and an evolutionist&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fordyce"><link type='external' href='http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/entry-12041'>Letter 12041</link><space/>Darwin, C. R. to Fordyce, John, May 7, 1879.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/6QhA2bpBR'>Archived</link><space/>from the original on June 29, 2014.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="spencer"><link type='external' href='http://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/belief/2009/sep/17/darwin-evolution-religion'>Darwin's Complex loss of Faith</link><space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics><space/>September 17, 2009.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/6QhA8c6DM'>Archived</link><space/>from the original on June 29, 2014</extension><space/>Although reticent about his religious views, in 1879 he wrote that &quot;I have never been an atheist in the sense of denying the existence of a God. I think that generally ... an agnostic would be the most correct description of my state of mind.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fordyce"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Belief"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/content/view/130/125/</arg><arg name="title">Darwin Correspondence Project – Belief: historical essay</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 25, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20090225124103/http://www.darwinproject.ac.uk/content/view/130/125/<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 22, 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Demographics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Europe No Belief enhanced.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Percentage of people in various European countries who said: &quot;I don't believe there is any sort of spirit, God or life force.&quot; (2005)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/archives/ebs/ebs_225_report_en.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Social values, Science and Technology</arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 9, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20110430163128/http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/archives/ebs/ebs_225_report_en.pdf</arg><arg name="archivedate">April 30, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Demographic</target></link><space/>research services normally do not differentiate between various types of non-religious respondents, so agnostics are often classified in the same category as<space/><link><target>atheism</target><part>atheists</part></link><space/>or other<space/><link><target>irreligion</target><part>non-religious</part></link><space/>people.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://adherents.com/Religions_By_Adherents.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Major Religions Ranked by Size<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Adherents.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">August 14, 2010</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20100811013003/http://www.adherents.com/Religions_By_Adherents.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">August 11, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A 2010 survey published in<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link></italics><space/>found that the non-religious people or the agnostics made up about 9.6% of the world's population.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eb-2010"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="title">Religion: Year in Review 2010: Worldwide Adherents of All Religions</arg><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/1731588/Religion-Year-In-Review-2010/298437/Worldwide-Adherents-of-All-Religions</arg><arg name="work">Encyclopædia Britannica</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopædia Britannica Inc.</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 21, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhABEiLj<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>A NovemberDecember 2006 poll published in the<space/><italics><link><target>Financial Times</target></link></italics><space/>gives rates for the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and five European countries. The rates of agnosticism in the United States were at 14%, while the rates of agnosticism in the European countries surveyed were considerably higher:<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>(20%),<space/><link><target>Spain</target></link><space/>(30%),<space/><link><target>Great Britain</target></link><space/>(35%),<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>(25%), and<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>(32%).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Harris"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.harrisinteractive.com/news/allnewsbydate.asp?NewsID</arg><arg name="title">Religious Views and Beliefs Vary Greatly by Country, According to the Latest Financial Times/Harris Poll
</arg><arg name="publisher">Financial Times/Harris Interactive
</arg><arg name="date">December 20, 2006
</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 9, 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A study conducted by the<space/><link><target>Pew Research Center</target></link><space/>found that about 16% of the world's people, the third largest group after<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Islam</target></link>, have no religious affiliation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title">Study Finds One in 6 Follows No Religion</arg><arg name="last">Goodstein</arg><arg name="first">Laurie</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="date">December 18, 2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/18/world/pew-study-finds-one-in-6-follows-no-religion.html<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAEHdP9<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>According to a 2012 report by the Pew Research Center, agnostics made up 3.3% of the US adult population.<extension extension_name='ref' name="pew 2012"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Cary Funk</arg><arg name="first">Greg Smith</arg><arg name="title">"Nones" on the Rise: One-in-Five Adults Have No Religious Affiliation</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pewforum.org/files/2012/10/NonesOnTheRise-full.pdf</arg><arg name="publisher">Pew Research Center</arg><arg name="pages">9, 42</arg><arg name="accessdate">November 21, 2013<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAHAv1T<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>In the<space/><italics>U.S. Religious Landscape Survey</italics>, conducted by the Pew Research Center, 55% of agnostic respondents expressed &quot;a belief in God or a universal spirit&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Demographics1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/report2religious-landscape-study-key-findings.pdf</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Summary of Key Findings</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Pew Research Center]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 28, 2011</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>Nearly all adults (92%) say they believe in God or a universal spirit, including seven-in-ten of the unaffiliated. Indeed, one-in-five people who identify themselves as atheist (21%) and a majority of those who identify themselves as agnostic (55%) express a belief in God or a universal spirit.<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAIjCvN<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>whereas 41% stated that they thought that they felt a tension &quot;being non-religious in a society where most people are religious&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Demographics2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://religions.pewforum.org/pdf/report2religious-landscape-study-key-findings.pdf</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Summary of Key Findings</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Pew Research Center]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 28, 2011</arg><arg name="quote">Interestingly, a substantial number of adults who are not affiliated with a religion also sense that there is a conflict between religion and modern society&nbsp;– except for them the conflict involves being non-religious in a society where most people are religious. For instance, more than four-inten atheists and agnostics (44% and 41%, respectively) believe that such a tension exists.<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAK6gVb<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Atheists Agnostics Zuckerman en.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>400px</part><part>left</part><part>Proportion of atheists and agnostics around the world</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>According to the 2011<space/><link><target>Australian Bureau of Statistics</target></link>, 22% of<space/><link><target>Australians</target></link><space/>have &quot;no religion&quot;, a category that includes agnostics.<extension extension_name='ref' name="abs"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.abs.gov.au/ausstats/abs@.nsf/Lookup/2071.0main+features902012-2013</arg><arg name="title">Cultural Diversity in Australia</arg><arg name="publisher">Australian Bureau of Statistics</arg><arg name="year">2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">June 21, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAPzLvj<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>Between 64% and 65%<extension extension_name='ref' name="Martin2007"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Zuckerman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Phil</arg><arg name="editor">Martin, Michael T<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Cambridge Companion to Atheism<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, England<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-521-60367-6<space/></arg><arg name="ol"><space/>22379448M<space/></arg><arg name="page">56<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">April 9, 2011</arg></template></extension>of<space/><link><target>Japanese people</target><part>Japanese</part></link><space/>and up to 81%<extension extension_name='ref' name="Intelligence"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://davesource.com/Fringe/Fringe/Religion/Average-intelligence-predicts-atheism-rates-across-137-nations-Lynn-et-al.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Average intelligence predicts atheism rates across 137 nations</arg><arg name="date">January 3, 2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">October 21, 2012<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAWO570<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>of<space/><link><target>Vietnamese people</target><part>Vietnamese</part></link><space/>are atheists, agnostics, or do not believe in a god. An official<space/><link><target>European Union</target></link><space/>survey reported that 3% of the EU population is unsure about their belief in a god or spirit.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EU"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author"></arg><arg name="title">Social values, Science and Technology</arg><arg name="publisher">Directorate General Research, European Union</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="pages">7–11</arg><arg name="url">http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/archives/ebs/ebs_225_report_en.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 9, 2011</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20110430163128/http://ec.europa.eu/public_opinion/archives/ebs/ebs_225_report_en.pdf</arg><arg name="archivedate">April 30, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism</heading><paragraph>Agnosticism is criticized from a variety of standpoints. Some religious thinkers see agnosticism as limiting the mind's capacity to know reality to<space/><link><target>materialism</target></link>. Some atheists criticize the use of the term agnosticism as functionally indistinguishable from atheism; this results in frequent criticisms of those who adopt the term as avoiding the atheist label.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB-Agnosticism"></extension><space/>Some thinkers and philosophers deny the validity of agnosticism, seeing it as a limitation of humankind's capacity to know the reality, by asserting that human intelligence has a non-material,<space/><link><target>Spirituality</target><part>spiritual</part></link><space/>element. They affirm that &quot;not being able to see or hold some specific thing does not necessarily negate its existence,&quot; using<space/><link><target>gravity</target></link>,<space/><link><target>entropy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>reason</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>thought</target></link><space/>as examples.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Smith2012"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theistic</heading><paragraph>Theistic critics claim that agnosticism is impossible in practice, since a person can live only either as if God did not exist (<italics>etsi deus non-daretur</italics>), or as if God did exist (<italics>etsi deus daretur</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="SM"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://chiesa.espresso.repubblica.it/articolo/125081?eng</arg><arg name="title">Habermas writes to Ratzinger and Ruini responds</arg><arg name="author">Sandro Magister</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 25, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAiEVs0<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="FF"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.faithfacts.org/search-for-truth/questions-of-christians/why-cant-I-live-my-life-as-an-agnostic</arg><arg name="title">Why can't I live my life as an agnostic?</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 25, 2008</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20080516211947/http://www.faithfacts.org/search-for-truth/questions-of-christians/why-cant-I-live-my-life-as-an-agnostic</arg><arg name="archivedate">May 16, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="CCC"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Christianity and the Crisis of Cultures</arg><arg name="first">Joseph</arg><arg name="last">Ratzinger</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-58617-142-1</arg><arg name="publisher">Ignatius Press</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Religious scholars such as Laurence B. Brown criticize the misuse of the word agnosticism, claiming that it has become one of the most misapplied terms in metaphysics. Brown raises the question, &quot;You claim that nothing can be known with certainty ... how, then, can you be so sure?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Islamrel"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.islamreligion.com/articles/641/</arg><arg name="title">Religion of Islam: Agnosticism</arg><arg name="author">Laurence B. Brown</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 25, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAkdpU4<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Brown2008"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Laurence B. Brown</arg><arg name="title">MisGod'ed: A Roadmap of Guidance and Misguidance in the Abrahamic Religions</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">February 2008</arg><arg name="publisher">CreateSpace Independent Publishing Platform</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4196-8148-6</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Christian</heading><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XVI</target></link>, strong agnosticism in particular contradicts itself in affirming the power of reason to know scientific<space/><link><target>truth</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="YOJC"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="TT"></extension><space/>He blames the exclusion of reasoning from religion and ethics for dangerous pathologies such as crimes against humanity and ecological disasters.<extension extension_name='ref' name="YOJC"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Yes of Jesus Christ: Spiritual Exercises in Faith, Hope, and Love</arg><arg name="first">Joseph</arg><arg name="last">Ratzinger</arg><arg name="publisher">Cross Roads Publishing</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="TT"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Truth and Tolerance: Christian Belief And World Religions</arg><arg name="first">Joseph</arg><arg name="last">Ratzinger</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Ignatius Press]]</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.zenit.org/en/articles/papal-address-at-university-of-regensburg<space/></arg><arg name="title">Papal Address at University of Regensburg<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">zenit.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 12, 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 29, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="author">Benedict XVI<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAgp8TR<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension>&quot;Agnosticism&quot;, said Ratzinger, &quot;is always the fruit of a refusal of that knowledge which is in fact offered to man&amp;nbsp;... The knowledge of God has always existed&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TT"></extension><space/>He asserted that agnosticism is a choice of comfort, pride, dominion, and utility over truth, and is opposed by the following attitudes: the keenest self-criticism, humble listening to the whole of existence, the persistent patience and self-correction of the<space/><link><target>scientific method</target></link>, a readiness to be purified by the truth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="YOJC"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>sees merit in examining what it calls &quot;partial agnosticism&quot;, specifically those systems that &quot;do not aim at constructing a complete philosophy of the unknowable, but at excluding special kinds of truth, notably religious, from the domain of knowledge&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CEnc1"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="title">Agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01215c.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAofWNU<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">June 29, 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the Church is historically opposed to a full denial of the capacity of human reason to know God. The<space/><link><target>Council of the Vatican</target></link><space/>declares, &quot;God, the beginning and end of all, can, by the natural light of human reason, be known with certainty from the works of creation&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CEnc1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Blaise Pascal</target></link><space/>argued that even if there were truly no evidence for God, agnostics should consider what is now known as<space/><link><target>Pascal's Wager</target></link>: the<space/><link><target>Infinity</target><part>infinite</part></link><space/>expected value of acknowledging God is always greater than the finite expected value of not acknowledging his existence, and thus it is a safer &quot;bet&quot; to choose God.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PKPW"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.peterkreeft.com/topics/pascals-wager.htm</arg><arg name="title">Argument from Pascal's Wager</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 25, 2008</arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20080605044148/http://peterkreeft.com/topics/pascals-wager.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate">June 5, 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Peter Kreeft</target></link><space/>and Ronald Tacelli cited 20 arguments for God's existence,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.peterkreeft.com/topics-more/20_arguments-gods-existence.htm'>Twenty Arguments for the Existence of God</link>, from the<space/><italics>Handbook of Christian Apologetics</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Peter Kreeft</target></link><space/>and Fr. Ronald Tacelli, SJ,<space/><link><target>Intervarsity Press</target></link>, 1994.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/6QhAxhgdF'>Archived</link><space/>from the original on June 29, 2014.</extension><space/>asserting that any demand for evidence testable in a laboratory is in effect asking God, the supreme being, to become man's servant.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JON"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Jesus of Nazareth</arg><arg name="first">Joseph</arg><arg name="last">Ratzinger</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Atheistic</heading><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Richard Dawkins</target></link>, a distinction between agnosticism and atheism is unwieldy and depends on how close to zero a person is willing to rate the probability of existence for any given god-like entity. About himself, Dawkins continues, &quot;I am agnostic only to the extent that I am agnostic about fairies at the bottom of the garden.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>The God Delusion</target></link></italics><space/>p.&amp;nbsp;74</extension><space/>Dawkins also identifies two categories of agnostics; &quot;Temporary Agnostics in Practice&quot; (TAPs), and &quot;Permanent Agnostics in Principle&quot; (PAPs). Dawkins considers temporary agnosticism an entirely reasonable position, but views permanent agnosticism as &quot;fence-sitting, intellectual cowardice&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>The God Delusion</target></link></italics><space/>p.&amp;nbsp;70</extension><template><target>Failed verification</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Related concepts</heading><paragraph><link><target>Ignosticism</target></link><space/>is the view that a coherent definition of a deity must be put forward before the question of the existence of a deity can be meaningfully discussed. If the chosen definition is not coherent, the ignostic holds the<space/><link><target>theological noncognitivism</target><part>noncognitivist</part></link><space/>view that the existence of a deity is meaningless or empirically untestable.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.strongatheism.net/library/atheology/argument_from_noncognitivism/<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Argument From Non-Cognitivism<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">October 1, 2010<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6N59bmP1Y<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 2, 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Alfred Ayer</target><part>A.J. Ayer</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Theodore Drange</target></link>, and other philosophers see both atheism and agnosticism as incompatible with ignosticism on the grounds that atheism and agnosticism accept &quot;a deity exists&quot; as a meaningful proposition that can be argued for or against.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ayer,<space/><italics>Language</italics>, 115: &quot;There can be no way of proving that the existence of a God&amp;nbsp;... is even probable.&amp;nbsp;... For if the existence of such a god were probable, then the proposition that he existed would be an empirical hypothesis. And in that case it would be possible to deduce from it, and other empirical hypotheses, certain experimental propositions which were not deducible from those other hypotheses alone. But in fact this is not possible.&quot;</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Drange">Drange,<space/><italics>Atheism</italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>columns-list</target><arg>2</arg><arg>
* [[Apatheism]]
* [[Apophatic theology]]
* ''[[Asimov's Guide to the Bible]]''
* [[Avidyā (Buddhism)]]
* [[Existentialism]]
* [[Ietsism]]
* ''[[Ignoramus et ignorabimus]]''
* [[Instrumentalism]]
* [[Laïcité]]
* [[List of agnostics]]
* [[Nihilism]]
* [[Objectivism (Ayn Rand)]]
* [[Possibilianism]]
* [[Rationalism]]
* [[Relativism]]
* [[Religiosity]]
* [[Religious skepticism]]
* [[Russell's teapot]]
* [[Scientism]]
* [[Solipsism]]
* [[Subjectivism]]
* [[Unknown God]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><bold>Notes</bold><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bibliography</bold><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Agnosticism</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Forgotten Books</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4400-6878-2</arg><arg name="pages">164–</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Dawkins</target></link>, &quot;The poverty of agnosticism&quot;, in<space/><italics><link><target>The God Delusion</target></link></italics>, Black Swan, 2007 (ISBN 978-0-552-77429-1).</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Robin Le Poidevin</arg><arg name="title">Agnosticism: A Very Short Introduction</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">October 28, 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">OUP Oxford</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-19-957526-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Thomas H. Huxley</arg><arg name="title">Man's Place in Nature</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">February 4, 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Courier Dover Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-486-15134-2</arg><arg name="pages">1–</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">David Hume</arg><arg name="title">Dialogues Concerning Natural Religion</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1779</arg><arg name="pages">1–</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Immanuel Kant</arg><arg name="title">The Critique of Pure Reason</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">May 28, 2013</arg><arg name="publisher">Loki's Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-615-82576-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://www.religion-online.org/showbook.asp?title</arg><arg name="title">Philosophical Fragments<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Religion-online.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="author">Sören Kierkegaard<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-691-02036-5</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NG0lSGhb<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://www.andrew.cmu.edu/user/jksadegh/A%20Good%20Atheist%20Secularist%20Skeptical%20Book%20Collection/George%20H.%20Smith%20-%20Atheism-%20The%20Case%20Against%20God%20%28v1.1%29.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Atheism&nbsp;– The Case Against God<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">February 9, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="author">George H. Smith<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-87975-124-X<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/6NG0ojUBG<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">February 9, 2014</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>SEP</target><arg>atheism-agnosticism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>Agnosticism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>InPho</target><arg>idea</arg><arg>13</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shapell.org/manuscript.aspx?agnostic-einstein-religion-of-science-nature-but-still-jewish'>Albert Einstein on Religion</link><space/>Shapell Manuscript Foundation</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.agnosticuniverse.org/ingersoll-why_i_am_an_agnostic.html'>Why I Am An Agnostic</link><space/>by Robert G. Ingersoll, [1896].</listitem><listitem><italics><link type='external' href='http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/cgi-local/DHI/dhi.cgi?id=dv1-03'>Dictionary of the History of Ideas</link></italics>: Agnosticism</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://inters.org/agnosticism'>Agnosticism from INTERS&amp;nbsp; Interdisciplinary Encyclopedia of Religion and Science</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.religioustolerance.org/agnostic.htm'>Agnosticism</link>&amp;nbsp; from<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.religioustolerance.org/'>ReligiousTolerance.org</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chabad.org/library/article_cdo/aid/68831/jewish/What-do-Agnostics-Believe.htm'>What do Agnostics Believe?&amp;nbsp; A Jewish perspective</link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fides et Ratio</target></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.vatican.va/holy_father/john_paul_ii/encyclicals/documents/hf_jp-ii_enc_15101998_fides-et-ratio_en.html'>''&amp;nbsp; the relationship between faith and reason''</link><space/><link><target>Karol Wojtyla</target></link><space/>[1998]</listitem><listitem>For a utilitarian analysis of religion, see<space/><italics>The (F)Utility of Religion: Who Needs God(s)?A Prospective Bible for Non-Believers</italics><space/>at http://bradmusil.kramernet.org</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thenaturalreligion.org/'>The Natural Religion</link><space/>by Dr Brendan Connolly, 2008</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://xtf.lib.virginia.edu/xtf/view?docId</arg><arg name="first">Kai<space/></arg><arg name="last">Nielsen<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Agnosticism<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Dictionary of the History of Ideas<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Virginia Library<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1968</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Agnosticism</target></template><template><target>Philosophy of religion</target></template><template><target>Portal bar</target><arg>Religion</arg><arg>Philosophy</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Agnosticism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Epistemological theories</target></link><link><target>Category:Secularism</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophical movements</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of religion</target></link><link><target>Category:Skepticism</target></link></paragraph></article>