<article title='History_of_Cameroon'><paragraph><template><target>merge from</target><arg>Reunification of Cameroon</arg><arg name="discuss">Talk:History of Cameroon#Proposed merge with Reunification of Cameroon</arg><arg name="date">May 2013</arg></template><template><target>Update</target><arg name="inaccurate">yes</arg><arg>article</arg><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Culture of Cameroon</target></template><link><target>Image:German building at Ambam.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>German-built building at Ambam, today used as a school</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>This article documents the history of<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early history</heading><paragraph>The earliest inhabitants of<space/><link><target>Cameroon</target></link><space/>were probably the<space/><link><target>Baka (nomadic Central African people)</target><part>Baka</part></link><space/>(Pygmies). They still inhabit the forests of the south and east provinces.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">About.com</arg><arg name="url">http://africanhistory.about.com/od/cameroon/p/CameroonHist.htm></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Bantu languages</target><part>Bantu</part></link><space/>speakers originating in the Cameroonian highlands were among the first groups to move out before other invaders. The<space/><link><target>Mandara kingdom</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Mandara Mountains</target></link><space/>was founded around 1500 and erected<space/><link><target>Mandara Strongholds</target><part>fortified structures</part></link>, the purpose and exact history of which are still unresolved. The<space/><link><target>Aro Confederacy</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>had presence in western (later called British) Cameroon due to trade and migration in the 18th and 19th centuries.</paragraph><paragraph>During the late 1770s and the early 19th century, the<space/><link><target>Fula people</target><part>Fula</part><trail>ni</trail></link>, a<space/><link><target>pastoralism</target><part>pastoral</part></link><space/><link><target>Islam</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>people of the western<space/><link><target>Sahel</target></link>, conquered most of what is now northern Cameroon, subjugating or displacing its largely non-Muslim inhabitants.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the<space/><link><target>Portugal</target><part>Portuguese</part></link><space/>arrived on Cameroon's doorstep in the 16th century,<space/><link><target>malaria</target></link><space/>prevented significant European settlement and conquest of the interior until the late 1870s, when large supplies of the malaria suppressant,<space/><link><target>quinine</target></link>, became available. The early European presence in Cameroon was primarily devoted to coastal trade and the acquisition of<space/><link><target>slavery</target><part>slaves</part></link>. The northern part of Cameroon was an important part of the Muslim slave trade network. The slave trade was largely suppressed by the mid-19th century. Christian<space/><link><target>missionary</target><part>missions</part></link><space/>established a presence in the late 19th century and continue to play a role in Cameroonian life.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Colonization</heading><paragraph>[[Image:Cameroon boundary changes.PNG|thumb|right|<bold>Cameroon over time</bold><template><target>legend</target><arg>darkorange</arg><arg>German [[Kamerun]]</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>red</arg><arg>British [[Cameroons]]</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>blue</arg><arg>French [[Cameroun]]</arg></template><template><target>legend</target><arg>green</arg><arg>Republic of [[Cameroon]]</arg></template>]]<link><target>Image:Bundesarchiv Bild 163-051, Kamerun, Weihnachten am Mungo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>German Settlers celebrating Christmas in Kamerun</part></link></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>Further information:<space/><link><target>German Kamerun</target></link>,<space/><link><target>French Cameroun</target></link>,<space/><link><target>British Cameroons</target></link></italics></listitem></list><paragraph>Beginning on July 5, 1884, all of present-day Cameroon and parts of several of its neighbours became<space/><link><target>German colonial empire</target><part>a German colony</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kamerun</target></link>, with a capital first at<space/><link><target>Buea</target></link><space/>and later at<space/><link><target>Yaound</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Imperial German government made substantial investments in the infrastructure of Cameroon, including the extensive<space/><link><target>railway</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as the 160-metre<space/><link><target>Japoma Bridge</target><part>single-span railway bridge</part></link><space/>on the South<space/><link><target>Sanaga River</target></link><space/>branch. Hospitals were opened all over the colony, including two major hospitals at<space/><link><target>Douala</target></link>, one of which specialised in tropical diseases (the Germans had discovered the 1912, wrote in an official report in 1919 that the population of Kamerun had increased significantly. However, the indigenous peoples proved reluctant to work on these projects, so the Germans instigated a harsh and unpopular system of<space/><link><target>unfree labour</target><part>forced labour</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>DeLancey and DeLancey 125.</extension><space/>In fact,<space/><link><target>Jesko von Puttkamer</target></link><space/>was relieved of duty as governor of the colony due to his untoward actions toward the native Cameroonians.<extension extension_name='ref'>DeLancey and DeLancey 226.</extension><space/>In 1911 at the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Fez</target></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Agadir Crisis</target></link>, France ceded a nearly 300,000&amp;nbsp;km portion of the territory of<space/><link><target>French Equatorial Africa</target></link><space/>to Kamerun which became<space/><link><target>Neukamerun</target></link>, while Germany ceded a smaller area in the north in present day<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link><space/>to France.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>the British invaded Cameroon from<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>in 1914 in the<space/><link><target>Kamerun campaign</target></link>, with the last German fort in the country<space/><link><target>Siege of Mora</target><part>surrendering</part></link><space/>in February 1916. After the war this colony was partitioned between the United Kingdom and France under a June 28, 1919<space/><link><target>League of Nations mandate#Class B mandates</target><part>League of Nations mandates (Class B)</part></link>. France gained the larger geographical share, transferred Neukamerun back to neighboring French colonies, and ruled the rest from Yaound as<space/><link><target>French Cameroun</target><part>Cameroun</part></link><space/>(French Cameroons). Britain's territory, a strip bordering<space/><link><target>Nigeria</target></link><space/>from the sea to<space/><link><target>Lake Chad</target></link>, with an equal population was ruled from<space/><link><target>Lagos</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Cameroons</target></link><space/>(British Cameroons). German administrators were allowed to once again run the plantations of the southwestern coastal area. A British Parliamentary Publication,<space/><italics>Report on the British Sphere of the Cameroons</italics><space/>(May 1922, p.&amp;nbsp;62-8), reports that the German plantations there were &quot;as a whole . . . wonderful examples of industry, based on solid scientific knowledge. The natives have been taught discipline and have come to realise what can be achieved by industry. Large numbers who return to their villages take up cocoa or other cultivation on their own account, thus increasing the general prosperity of the country.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Towards Independence (1955-1960)</heading><paragraph>On 18 December 1956, the outlawed<space/><link><target>Union of the Peoples of Cameroon</target></link><space/>(UPC), based largely among the<space/><link><target>Bamileke</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bassa people (Cameroon)</target><part>Bassa</part></link><space/>ethnic groups, began an armed struggle for independence in French Cameroon. This rebellion continued, with diminishing intensity, even after independence until 1961.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://uca.edu/politicalscience/dadm-project/sub-saharan-africa-region/britishfrench-cameroon-1948-1961/</extension><space/>Some tens of thousands died during this conflict.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eckhardt, William, in World Military and Social Expenditures 1987-88 (12th ed., 1987) by<space/><link><target>Ruth Leger Sivard</target></link>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>The Cambridge History of Africa (1986), ed. J. D. Fage and R. Oliver</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Cameroonian parliamentary election, 1956</target><part>Legislative elections</part></link><space/>were held on 23 December 1956 and the resulting Assembly passed a decree on 16 April 1957 which made French Cameroon a State. It took back its former status of associated territory as a member of the French Union. Its inhabitants became Cameroonian citizens, Cameroonian institutions were created under the sign of parliamentary democracy. On 12 June 1958 the Legislative Assembly of French Cameroon asked the French government to: 'Accord independence to the State of Cameroon at the ends of their trusteeship. Transfer every competence related to the running of internal affairs of Cameroon to Cameroonians`. On 19 October 1958 France recognized the right of her United Nations trust territory of the Cameroons to choose independence.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res=F00817FC385B117A93C2AB178BD95F4C8585F9&amp;scp=1&amp;sq=Cameroon+independence&amp;st=p</extension><space/>On 24 October 1958 the Legislative Assembly of French Cameroon solemnly proclaimed the desire of Cameroonians to see their country accede full independence on 1 January 1960. It enjoined the government of French Cameroon to ask France to inform the General Assembly of the United Nations, to abrogate the trusteeship accord concomitant with the independence of French Cameroon. On 12 November 1958 having accorded French Cameroon total internal autonomy and thinking that this transfer no longer permitted it to assume its responsibilities over the trust territory for an unspecified period, the government of France asked the United Nations to grant the wish of French Cameroonians. On 15 December 1958 the United Nations General Assembly took note of the French governments declaration according to which French Cameroon, which was under French administration, would gain independence on 1 January 1960, thus marking an end to the trusteeship period (Resolution 1282. XIII).<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.cameroon50.cm/en/history-and-presentation/167-tutelle-a-independance.html</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/RESOLUTION/GEN/NR0/747/26/IMG/NR074726.pdf?OpenElement</extension><space/>On 13 March 1959 the United Nations General Assembly resolved that the UN Trusteeship Agreement with France for French Cameroon would end when French Cameroon became independent on 1 January 1960 (Resolution 1349. XIII).<extension extension_name='ref'>http://daccess-dds-ny.un.org/doc/RESOLUTION/GEN/NR0/335/84/IMG/NR033584.pdf?OpenElement</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Cameroon after independence</heading><paragraph>French Cameroon achieved independence on January 1, 1960 as<space/><bold>La Republique du Cameroun</bold>. After Guinea, it was the second of France's colonies in Sub-Saharan Africa to be granted independence. The following year, on October 1, 1961, the largely Muslim northern two-thirds of<space/><link><target>British Cameroons</target></link><space/>voted to join Nigeria; the largely Christian southern third,<space/><link><target>Southern Cameroons</target></link>, voted, in a referendum, to join with the Republic of Cameroon to form the<space/><bold>Federal Republic of Cameroon</bold>. The formerly French and British regions each maintained substantial<space/><link><target>Self-governance</target><part>autonomy</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Ahmadou Ahidjo</target></link>, a French-educated Fulani, was chosen president of the federation in 1961. Ahidjo, relying on a pervasive internal security apparatus, outlawed all political parties but his own in 1966. He successfully suppressed the continuing UPC rebellion, capturing the last important rebel leader in 1970. In 1972, a new constitution replaced the federation with a unitary state called the<space/><bold>United Republic of Cameroon</bold>. This is the major cause of tension between the French and English speaking areas of Cameroon. Southern Cameroonians feel the agreement at the Foumban constitution conference is not respected.</paragraph><paragraph>Although Ahidjo's rule was characterised as authoritarian, he was seen as noticeably lacking in charisma in comparison to many post-colonial African leaders. He didn't follow the anti-western policies pursued by many of these leaders, which helped Cameroon achieve a degree of comparative political stability and economic growth.</paragraph><paragraph>Ahidjo resigned as president in 1982 and was constitutionally succeeded by his<space/><link><target>Prime Minister</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paul Biya</target></link>, a career official from the<space/><link><target>Beti-Pahuin</target></link><space/>ethnic group. Ahidjo later regretted his choice of successors, but his supporters failed to overthrow Biya in a<space/><link><target>Cameroonian Palace Guard Revolt</target><part>1984 coup</part></link>. Biya won single-candidate elections in 1983 and 1984 when the country was again named the<space/><bold>Republic of Cameroon</bold>. Biya has remained in power, winning flawed multiparty elections in 1992, 1997, 2004 and 2011. His<space/><link><target>Cameroon People's Democratic Movement</target></link><space/>(CPDM) party holds a sizeable majority in the legislature.</paragraph><paragraph>By April 6th 1984, the country witnessed its first coup d'etat headed by col. Issa Adoum.At about 3 am rebel forces mostly of the Republican guard under the orders of colonel Ibrahim Saleh, attempted to<space/><bold>unseat Biya's government.</bold><space/>The rebels took charge of the Yaounde airport, national radio station and announced the takeover of government. They attacked the presidency. The civilian northerner who was manager of FONADER<space/><bold>Issa Adoum</bold><space/>was expected to become the new interim president. Unfortunately, many reasons led to its failure.The principal coup plotters had been arrested by April 10th 1984 and President Biya addressed the nation that calm had been restored.</paragraph><paragraph>On August 15, 1984,<space/><link><target>Lake Monoun</target></link><space/>exploded in a<space/><link><target>limnic eruption</target></link><space/>that released<space/><link><target>carbon dioxide</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Asphyxia</target><part>suffocating</part></link><space/>37 people to death. On August 21, 1986, another limnic eruption at<space/><link><target>Lake Nyos</target></link><space/>killed as many as 1,800 people and 3,500 livestock. The two disasters are the only recorded instances of limnic eruptions.</paragraph><paragraph>In May 2014, in the wake of the<space/><link><target>Chibok schoolgirl kidnapping</target></link>, Presidents Paul Biya of Cameroon and<space/><link><target>Idriss Dby</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link><space/>announced they were waging war on<space/><link><target>Boko Haram</target></link>, and deployed troops to the Nigerian border.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Cameroon, Chad Deploy Troops to Fight Boko Haram - Nigeria
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>ReliefWeb
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2014-06-10
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://reliefweb.int/report/nigeria/cameroon-chad-deploy-troops-fight-boko-haram
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kaze
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rennier
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dans le Nord du Cameroun, la "guerre" contre Boko Haram a commencé - Cameroon
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>ReliefWeb
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2014-06-10
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2014-06-06
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>French
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://reliefweb.int/report/cameroon/dans-le-nord-du-cameroun-la-guerre-contre-boko-haram-commenc
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Corruption in Cameroon</heading><paragraph>Despite democratic reform begun in 1990 with the legalization of political parties other than the CPDM, political power remains firmly in the hands of President Biya and a small circle of CPDM members from his own ethnic group. Biya was reelected on October 11, 1992 amid accusations of voting irregularities. Biya reportedly got 39 percent of the vote to 35 percent for<space/><link><target>John Fru Ndi</target></link>. (Ndi briefly proclaimed himself president before the government released the polling figures.) In contrast, the March 1, 1992 legislative election was considered free and fair by international observers, although many parties boycotted the elections and the CPDM won several constituencies by default. But even though opposition parties were well represented in the legislature (92 of 180 seats), there were, according to the<space/><link><target>Constitution of Cameroon</target><part>1992 constitution</part></link>, few legislative or judicial checks on the president.</paragraph><paragraph>Following the elections, civil unrest erupted as the population expressed the widespread belief that Ndi had won the presidential elections. By late 1992, Ndi and his supporters were under house arrest and the international community had made clear its displeasure at the antidemocratic and increasingly violent turn the Biya regime was taking.</paragraph><paragraph>Biya agreed in May 1993 to hold a so-called Great National Constitutional Debate and in June he began preparing a draft of a new constitution to be adopted either by referendum or by the National Assembly. In 1994, 16 opposition parties formed a loose alliance, dominated by Ndi's Social Democrats, to work for constitutional and electoral reform. In October 1995, the CPDM reelected Biya as its leader. In December of that year the National Assembly adopted a number of amendments to address the power of the president. These reforms included a strengthening of the judiciary, the creation of a partially elected 100-member senate, the creation of regional councils, and the fixing of the presidential term to 7 years, renewable once. Strikes and demonstrations became commonplace as Biya resisted implementation of reforms.</paragraph><paragraph>The May 1997 legislative elections were marred by mismanagement, vote-rigging, and fraud, resulting in the Supreme Court's cancellation of results in three constituencies (seven seats). Based on the misconduct of these elections, the opposition boycotted the October 1997 presidential elections, in which Biya claimed victory with 93 percent of the vote. To add further insult, Cameroon topped<space/><link><target>Transparency International</target></link>'s list of the most corrupt countries in the world in 1998, prompting the creation of an anticorruption body.</paragraph><paragraph>On June 30, 2002 the country held legislative and municipal elections that again were denounced by the opposition as fraudulent. The Supreme Court cancelled the results of nine constituencies, ordering new elections in these constituencies on September 15. In the end, the<space/><link><target>Cameroon People's Democratic Movement</target></link><space/>(CPDM)/Rassemblement Dmocratique du Peuple Camerounais (RDPC) won 149 of 180 seats.</paragraph><paragraph>The victory for the ruling party was cemented with the reelection of the 72-year-old president Paul Biya in October 2004, thus enhancing the chances of continued domination by the ruling party until the end of his term in 2011. By 2006, appeals were being heard in Biya's home province in favour of a constitutional amendment that would allow him to run for another term when his current term expires. However, against the backdrop of worsening social conditions and high poverty, students protested and conducted strikes for several weeks in April 2005, and clashes with police led to two student deaths. Opposition parties registered their intention to block any attempt to amend the constitution that would allow Biya to run for a third term.</paragraph><paragraph>In early 2006 a final resolution to the dispute between Cameroon and Nigeria over the oil-rich<space/><link><target>Bakassi peninsula</target></link><space/>was expected. In October 2002, the International Court of Justice had ruled in favour of Cameroon. Nonetheless, a lasting solution would require agreement by both countries presidents, parliaments, and by the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>. The peninsula was the site of fighting between the two countries in 1994 and again in June 2005, which led to the death of a Cameroonian soldier.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Football</heading><paragraph>Cameroon has received some international attention following the relative success of its<space/><link><target>Cameroon national football team</target><part>football team</part></link>. It has qualified for the FIFA World Cup on a number of occasions. Its most notable performance was at<space/><link><target>Italia 90</target></link>, when the team beat<space/><link><target>Argentina national football team</target><part>Argentina</part></link>, the then reigning Champions in the opening game; Cameroon eventually lost in extra time in the Quarter Finals to<space/><link><target>England national football team</target><part>England</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Prominent footballers from Cameroon include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Roger Milla</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samuel Eto'o</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rigobert Song</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Alexandre Song</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Thomas Nkono</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jean Makoun</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Geremi Njitap</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mboma Patrick</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Alioum Boukar</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Abega Teophile</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cyrille Makanaky</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ambazonia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of Africa</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Politics of Cameroon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of heads of government of Cameroon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of heads of state of Cameroon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of Douala</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>History of Cameroon</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/r/pa/ei/bgn/26431.htm'>Background Note: Cameroon</link><space/>from the U.S. Department of State.</listitem><listitem>Bullock, A. L. C. (1939).<space/><italics>Germany's Colonial Demands</italics>,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>DeLancey, Mark W., and DeLancey, Mark Dike (2000):<space/><italics>Historical Dictionary of the Republic of Cameroon</italics><space/>(3rd ed.). Lanham, Maryland: The Scarecrow Press.</listitem><listitem>Schnee, Heinrich (1926).<space/><italics>German Colonization, Past and Future: The Truth about the German Colonies.</italics><space/>London:<space/><link><target>George Allen &amp; Unwin</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://unimaps.com/cameroon1914/index.html'>Map of German Cameroon (Kamerun) in 1914</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Cameroon topics</target></template><template><target>History of Africa</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:History Of Cameroon</target></template><link><target>Category:History of Cameroon</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:History of Central Africa</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:History of Africa by country</target><part>Cameroon</part></link><link><target>Category:World Digital Library related</target></link></paragraph></article>