<article title='Abensberg'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox German location</target><arg name="type"><space/>Stadt
</arg><arg name="image_coa"><space/>Wappen von Abensberg.svg
</arg><arg name="lat_deg"><space/>48<space/></arg><arg name="lat_min"><space/>48</arg><arg name="lat_sec">
</arg><arg name="lon_deg"><space/>11<space/></arg><arg name="lon_min"><space/>51</arg><arg name="lon_sec">
</arg><arg name="image_plan"><space/>Abensberg in KEH.svg
</arg><arg name="state"><space/>Bayern
</arg><arg name="region"><space/>Niederbayern
</arg><arg name="district"><space/>Kelheim
</arg><arg name="elevation"><space/>370
</arg><arg name="area"><space/>60.28
</arg><arg name="postal_code"><space/>93326
</arg><arg name="area_code"><space/>09443
</arg><arg name="licence"><space/>KEH
</arg><arg name="Gemeindeschlüssel"><space/>09273111
</arg><arg name="NUTS"><space/>DE226
</arg><arg name="LOCODE"><space/>DE ABE
</arg><arg name="divisions"><space/>7 [[Ortsteil]]e
</arg><arg name="Adresse"><space/>Stadtplatz 1<br />93326 Abensberg
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>[http://www.abensberg.de/ www.abensberg.de]
</arg><arg name="mayor"><space/>Uwe Brandl
</arg><arg name="party"><space/>CSU
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Maderturm 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Maderturm</part></link><bold>Abensberg</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-de</target><arg>ˈaːbənsˌbɛʁk</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>Abensberg.ogg</arg></template>) is a town in the<space/><link><target>Lower Bavaria</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>Districts of Germany</target><part>district</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Kelheim (district)</target><part>Kelheim</part></link>, in<space/><link><target>Bavaria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>, lying around 30&amp;nbsp;km southwest of<space/><link><target>Regensburg</target></link>, 40&amp;nbsp;km east of<space/><link><target>Ingolstadt</target></link>, 50 northwest of<space/><link><target>Landshut</target></link><space/>and 100&amp;nbsp;km north of<space/><link><target>Munich</target></link>. It is situated on the<space/><link><target>Abens</target></link><space/>river, a tributary of the<space/><link><target>Danube</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Geography</heading><paragraph>The town lies on the<space/><link><target>Abens</target></link><space/>river, a tributary of the<space/><link><target>Danube</target></link>, around eight kilometres from the river's source. The area around Abensberg is characterized by the narrow valley of the Danube, where the<space/><link><target>Weltenburg Abbey</target></link><space/>stands, the valley of the<space/><link><target>Altmhl</target></link><space/>in the north, a left tributary of the Danube, and the famous<space/><link><target>Hallertau</target></link><space/><link><target>Humulus</target><part>hops-planting</part></link><space/>region in the south. The town is divided into the municipalities of Abensberg, Arnhofen, Holzharlanden, Hrlbach, Offenstetten, Pullach and Sandharland.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Divisions</heading><paragraph>Since the administrative reforms in Bavaria in the 1970s, the town also encompasses the following<space/><italics><link><target>Quarter (country subdivision)</target><part>Ortsteile</part></link></italics>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In the town: Abensberg (main settlement), Aunkofen (civil parish), Badhaus (village)</listitem><listitem>To the east: Gaden (village), See (village), Offenstetten (civil parish)</listitem><listitem>To the north east: Arnhofen (civil parish), Baiern (village), Pullach (civil parish), Kleedorf (village)</listitem><listitem>To the north: Sandharlanden (civil parish), Holzharlanden (civil parish), Buchhof (small<space/><link><target>Hamlet (place)</target><part>hamlet</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>To the west: Schwaighausen (village), Schillhof (hamlet), Gilla (small hamlet)</listitem><listitem>To the south: Aumhle (small hamlet), Allersdorf (hamlet)</listitem><listitem>To the south east: Lehen (small hamlet), Mitterhrlbach (hamlet), Upper Hrlbach (village), Lower Hrlbach (hamlet)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>There had been settlement on this part of the<space/><link><target>Abens</target></link><space/>river since long before the<space/><link><target>High Middle Ages</target></link>, dating back to<space/><link><target>Neolithic</target></link><space/>times. Of particular interest and national importance are the Neolithic flint mines at Arnhofen, where, around 7,000 years ago,<space/><link><target>Stone Age</target></link><space/>people made flint, which was fashioned into drills, blades and arrowheads, and was regarded as the steel of the Stone Age. Traces of over 20,000 individuals were found on this site. The modern history of Abensberg, which is often incorrectly compared with that of the 3rd century Roman<space/><link><target>castra</target></link><space/>(military outpost) of Abusina, begins with Gebhard, who was the first to mention Abensberg as a town, in the middle of the 12th century. The earliest written reference to the town, under the name of<space/><italics>Habensperch</italics>, came from this time, in around 1138. Gebhard was from the Babonen clan.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1256, the<space/><link><target>castrum</target></link><space/>of<space/><italics>Abensprech</italics><space/>was first mentioned, and on 12 June 1348, Ludwig, Margrave of Brandenburg, and his brother, Stephen, Duke of Bavaria, raised Abensberg to the status of a city, giving it the right to operate lower courts, enclose itself with a wall and hold markets. The wall was built by Ulrich III, Count of Abensberg. Some of the thirty-two round towers and eight turrets are still preserved to this day.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Middle Ages</target></link>, the people of Abensberg enjoyed a level of autonomy above their lord. They elected a city council, although only a small number of rich families were eligible for election.</paragraph><paragraph>In around 1390, the Carmelite Monastery of Our Lady of Abensberg was founded by Count John II and his wife, Agnes. Although Abensberg was an autonomous city, it remained dependent on the powerful<space/><link><target>List of rulers of Bavaria</target><part>Dukes of Bavaria</part></link>. The last Lord of Abensberg, Nicholas, supposedly named after his godfather,<space/><link><target>Nicholas of Kues</target></link>, a Catholic cardinal, was murdered in 1485 by Christopher, a<space/><link><target>Herzog</target><part>Duke</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Bavaria-Munich</target></link>. The year before, Nicholas had unchivalrously taken Christopher captive as he bathed before a tournament in Munich. Although Christopher renounced his claim for revenge, he lay in wait for Nicholas in Freising. When the latter arrived, he was killed by Seitz von Frauenberg. He is buried in the former convent of Abensberg. Abensberg then lost its independence and became a part of the Duchy of Bavaria, and from then on was administered by a ducal official, the so-called caretaker. The castle of Abensberg was destroyed during the<space/><link><target>Thirty Years' War</target></link>, although the city had bought a guarantee of protection from the Swedish general,<space/><link><target>Carl Gustaf Wrangel</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Johannes Aventinus</target></link><space/>(14771534) is the city's most famous son, the founder of the study of history in Bavaria. Aventinus, whose name was real name is Johann or Johannes Turmair (<italics>Aventinus</italics><space/>being the Latin name of his birthplace) wrote the<space/><italics>Annals of Bavaria</italics>, a valuable record of the early history of Germany and the first major written work on the subject. He is commemorated in the<space/><link><target>Walhalla temple</target></link>, a monument near<space/><link><target>Regensburg</target></link><space/>to the distinguished figures of German history. Until 1800, Abensberg was a municipality belonging to the<space/><link><target>Straubing</target></link><space/>district of the<space/><link><target>Prince-elector</target><part>Electorate</part></link><space/>of Bavaria. Abensberg also contained a magistrates' court. In the<space/><link><target>Battle of Abensberg</target></link><space/>on 1920 April 1809,<space/><link><target>Napoleon I of France</target><part>Napoleon</part></link><space/>gained a significant victory over the Austrians under<space/><link><target>Archduke Louis of Austria</target></link><space/>and General<space/><link><target>Johann von Hiller</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite EB1911</target><arg name="author">Anonymous</arg><arg name="wstitle">Abensberg</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Arms</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Wappen von Abensberg.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>100px</part><part>Arms of Abensberg</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The arms of the city are divided into two halves. On the left are the blue and white rhombuses of Bavaria, while the right half is split into two silver and black triangles. Two diagonally-crossed silver swords with golden handles rest on top.</paragraph><paragraph>The town has had a coat of arms since 1338, that of the Counts of Abensberg. With the death of the last Count, Nicholas of Abensberg, in 1485, the estates fell to the Duchy of Bavaria-Munich, meaning that henceforth only the Bavarian coat of arms was ever used.</paragraph><paragraph>On 31 December 1809, a decree of<space/><link><target>Maximilian I Joseph of Bavaria</target><part>King Maximilian of Bavaria</part></link><space/>granted the city a new coat of arms, as a recognition of their (mainly humanitarian and logistic) services in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Abensberg</target></link><space/>the same year. The diagonally divided field in silver and black came from the old crest of the Counts of Abensberg, while the white and blue diamonds came from that of the<space/><link><target>House of Wittelsbach</target></link>, the rulers of Bavaria. The swords recall the Battle of Abensberg.</paragraph><paragraph>The district of Offenstetten previously possessed its own coat of arms.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Twinning</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Parga</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Greece</target></link><space/>since 1986</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lonigo</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>since 1999</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Economy and Infrastructure</heading><paragraph>The area around Abensberg, the so-called sand belt between<space/><link><target>Siegburg</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Neustadt an der Donau</target></link>, Abensberg and<space/><link><target>Langquaid</target></link>, is used for the intensive farming of<space/><link><target>asparagus</target></link>, due to the optimal soil condition and climate. 212 hectares of land can produce ninety-four asparagus plants. Abensberg asparagus enjoys a reputation among connoisseurs as a particular delicacy. In addition to asparagus, the production of hops plays a major role locally, the region having its own label, and there are still three independent breweries in the area. The town of Abensberg marks the start of the<space/><italics>Deutsche Hopfenstrae</italics><space/>(<italics>German Hops Road</italics>), a nickname given to the<space/><link><target>Bundesstrae</target></link><space/>301, a German federal highway which runs through the heartland of Germany's hops-growing industry, ending in<space/><link><target>Freising</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Transport</heading><paragraph>The Abensberg railway station is located on the<space/><link><target>Danube Valley Railway (Bavaria)</target><part>Danube Valley Railway</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Regensburg Hauptbahnhof</target><part>Regensburg</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Ingolstadt Hauptbahnhof</target><part>Ingolstadt</part></link>. The city can be reached via the A-93 Holledau-Regensburg road (exit Abensberg). Three<space/><link><target>Bundesstrae</target></link><space/>(German federal highways) cross south of Abensberg:<space/><link><target>Bundesstrae 16</target><part>B 16</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bundesstrae 299</target><part>B 299</part></link><space/>and B 301.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Public facilities</heading><heading level='3'>Schools</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Education in Germany</arg></template>Abensberg has a Grundschule (primary school) and<space/><link><target>Hauptschule</target></link><space/>(open admission secondary school), and the Johann-Turmair-<link><target>Realschule</target></link>(secondary modern school). There is also a College of Agriculture and Home Economics. Since 2007, the Kelheim Berufsschule has had a campus in Abensberg, and outside the state sector is the St. Francis Vocational Training Centre, run by a Catholic youth organisation.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Culture and sightseeing</heading><heading level='3'>Theatre</heading><paragraph>In 2008, a former<space/><link><target>goods shed</target></link><space/>by the main railway station of Abensberg was converted into a theatre by local volunteers. The &quot;Theater am Bahnhof&quot; (<italics>Theatre at the Railway Station</italics>) is mostly used by the<space/><italics>Theatergruppe Lampenfieber</italics><space/>and was opened on 19 October 2008.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Museums</heading><paragraph>Abensberg has a long tradition of museums. In the nineteenth century, Nicholas Stark und Peter Paul Dollinger began a collection based on local history. This collection and the collection of the<space/><italics>Heimatverein</italics><space/>(local history society) were united in 1963 into the<space/><link><target>Johannes Aventinus</target><part>Aventinus</part></link><space/>Museum, in the cloister of the former Carmelite monastery. On 7 July 2006, the new Town Museum of Abensberg was opened in the former duke's castle in the town.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Kuchlbauer Brewery</heading><paragraph>Two blocks west of the Old Town is the Kuchlbauer Brewery and beer garden featuring the<space/><link><target>Kuchlbauer Tower</target></link>, a colorful and unconventional observation tower designed by Viennese architect<space/><link><target>Friedensreich Hundertwasser</target></link>. The brewery and tower are open to the public.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Image gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Abensberg Stadtansicht.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>View of the Old Town</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Abensberg Klosterkirche.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Carmelite Monastery</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Abensberg Stadtplatz.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Town Centre with Rathaus (town hall)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Abensberg RegensburgerTor.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Regensburg Gate</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Herzogskasten Abensberg.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Herzogskasten (Duke's castle)</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Abensberg Kuchlbauerturm von Hundertwasser.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Kuchlbauer Tower</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='3'>Missing memorial</heading><paragraph>Up until the 1950s, Abensberg and the surrounding villages contained a number of graves of victims of a<space/><link><target>Death marches (Holocaust)</target><part>Death March</part></link><space/>in the Spring of 1945 from the Hersbruck sub-camp of the<space/><link><target>Dachau concentration camp</target></link>, who were either murdered by the<space/><link><target>Schutzstaffel</target><part>SS</part></link><space/>or died of exhaustion. They were originally buried where they died, but were later moved on the orders of the US military government to the cemeteries of their previous homes. At the cemetery in what is now the district of<space/><link><target>Pullach</target></link><space/>stood a memorial stone which was mentioned as recently as 1967, but which is no longer at the site. The suffering of ten unknown victims of the camp was recorded on the stone.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Regular events</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>The Abensberger events calendar begins in February with the<space/><italics><link><target>Carnival</target><part>Faschingsgillamoos</part></link></italics><space/><link><target>funfair</target></link>, which reaches its high point on Mad Thursday.</listitem><listitem>There then follows the<space/><italics>Frhjahrsmarkt</italics><space/>(Spring market) two weeks before Easter, when all the shops in the town are permitted to open on Sunday (<link><target>Ladenschlussgesetz</target><part>which is normally prohibited in Bavaria</part></link>).</listitem><listitem></listitem><listitem>The<space/><italics>Brgerfest</italics><space/>is celebrated on the first weekend of July, when the palace gardens with their ancient walls are transformed into a medieval camp.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><italics>Schlossgartenfest</italics><space/>(Palace Garden Festival) takes place every year at the beginning of August. It is organised since 1977 by the<space/><link><target>Junge Union</target></link>, the youth branch of Germany's two main conservative political parties, the<space/><link><target>Christian Democratic Union (Germany)</target><part>CDU</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Christian Social Union of Bavaria</target><part>CSU</part></link>, and attracts all age groups from Abensberg and surrounding areas.</listitem><listitem>On the second Saturday in August, people can wander through the Night Market in the balmy Summer evening.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><italics>Gillamoos</italics>, the oldest and largest<space/><link><target>funfair</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Hallertau</target></link><space/>opens on the Thursday before the first Sunday in September and runs until the Monday thereafter. It is the highlight of the year in Abensberg and is a celebration of the people of Abensberg and the surrounding area.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><italics>Herbstmarkt</italics><space/>(autumn market), another Sunday shopping day, is on the first weekend in October.</listitem><listitem>Since 1997, a series of cultural, art, music and entertainment events have taken place in November at various locations in the town, under the title,<space/><italics>Novembernebel</italics><space/>(November fog)</listitem><listitem>On<space/><link><target>Saint Nicholas#Germany</target><part>Saint Nicholas Day</part></link><space/>(6 December), the<space/><italics>Niklasmarkt</italics><space/>(Nicholas Market) commemorates the<space/><italics>Niklasspende</italics>, a medieval foundation for the poor. This heralds the beginning of Advent and the Christmas period.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notable residents</heading><heading level='3'>Sons and daughters of the town</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Konrad von Abensberg (c.1075-1147):<space/><link><target>Archbishopric of Salzburg</target><part>Archbishop of Salzburg</part></link><space/>and monastic reformer</listitem><listitem>Erhart Falckener: crafter of<space/><link><target>Gothic architecture</target><part>Late Gothic</part></link><space/>church furnishings</listitem><listitem><link><target>Johannes Aventinus</target></link><space/>(14771534): Bavarian historian</listitem><listitem><link><target>Stephan Agricola</target></link><space/>(14911547): Lutheran reformer</listitem><listitem>Gilbert Michl (17501828): Composer and Abbot of<space/><link><target>Steingaden Abbey</target><part>Steingaden</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Joseph von Hazzi</target></link><space/>(17681845): Bavarian Privy Councillor</listitem><listitem>Sebastian Osterrieder (18641932): sculptor</listitem><listitem>Josef Stanglmeier (19181999): builder and politician</listitem><listitem>Alfred Edel (19321993): actor</listitem><listitem>Martin Neumeyer (born 1954): Member of the<space/><link><target>Landtag of Bavaria</target><part>Bavarian State Assembly</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Uwe Brandl</target></link><space/>(born 1959): Mayor of Abensberg</listitem><listitem><link><target>Stephan Ebn</target></link><space/>(born 1978): drummer and music producer</listitem></list><heading level='3'>People who have worked in the town</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Jakob Jonas (15001558): German philologist, jurist, politician and diplomat</listitem><listitem>Wigulus von Kreittmayr (17051790): by marriage Lord of Offenstetten and Hatzkofen</listitem><listitem>Daisy dOra (born 1913): actress and beauty queen</listitem><listitem><link><target>Friedensreich Hundertwasser</target></link><space/>(19282000): artist and architect</listitem><listitem>Andreas Fischer (born 1966): Member of the<space/><link><target>Landtag of Bavaria</target><part>Bavarian State Assembly</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ole Bischof</target></link><space/>(born 1979): Olympic Judo champion</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Battle of Abensberg</target></link><space/>occurred April 20, 1809.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Landshut (1809)</target><part>Battle of Landshut</part></link><space/>occurred April 21, 1809.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Eckmhl</target></link><space/>occurred 2122 April 1809.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Eckmhl</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Landshut</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.abensberg.de/'>Website of Abensberg</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.abensberger-impressionen.de/'>Abensberger Impressionen - Old Images of Abensberg</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Abensberg</arg></template><template><target>Cities and towns in Kelheim (district)</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Spa towns in Germany</target></link><link><target>Category:Kelheim (district)</target></link></paragraph></article>