<article title='Battle_of_Jutland'><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="conflict"><space/>Battle of Jutland
</arg><arg name="partof"><space/>[[World War I]]
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:Map of the Battle of Jutland, 1916.svg|300px]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>The Battle of Jutland, 1916
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>31 May – 1 June 1916
</arg><arg name="place"><space/>[[North Sea]], near [[Denmark]]
</arg><arg name="coordinates"><space/>{{Coord|56|42|N|5|52|E|type:event_region:DK|display</arg><arg name="result"><space/>Tactically inconclusive; Strategic British victory
</arg><arg name="combatant1">{{flagcountry|United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland}}<br>
* {{flagcountry|Australia}}<ref name</arg><arg name="combatant2"><space/>{{flagcountry|German Empire}}
</arg><arg name="commander1"><space/>{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe|Sir John Jellicoe]]<br/>{{flagicon|United Kingdom|naval}} [[David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty|Sir David Beatty]]
</arg><arg name="commander2"><space/>{{flagicon|German Empire|naval}} [[Reinhard Scheer]]<br/>{{flagicon|German Empire|naval}} [[Franz von Hipper|Franz Hipper]]
</arg><arg name="strength1"><space/>'''Total: 151 combat ships'''<br/>28 [[battleship]]s<br/>9 [[battlecruiser]]s<br/>8 [[Armored cruiser|armoured cruisers]]<br/>26 [[light cruiser]]s<br/>78 [[destroyer]]s<br/>1 [[minelayer]]<br/>1 [[seaplane carrier]]
</arg><arg name="strength2"><space/>'''Total: 99 combat ships'''<br/>16 [[battleship]]s<br/>5 [[battlecruiser]]s<br/>6 [[pre-dreadnought]]s<br/>11 [[light cruiser]]s<br/>61 [[torpedo boat|torpedo-boat]]s{{refn|group</arg><arg name="casualties1"><space/>6,094 killed<br/>674 wounded<br/>177 captured<br/>3 battlecruisers<space/><br/>3 armoured cruisers<space/><br/>8 destroyers<space/><br/>(113,300 [[long ton|ton]]s sunk)<ref name</arg><arg name="casualties2"><space/>2,551 killed<br/>507 wounded<br/>1 battlecruiser<space/><br/>1 pre-dreadnought<space/><br/>4 light cruisers<space/><br/>5 torpedo-boats<br/>(62,300 [[long ton|ton]]s sunk)<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Campaignbox North Sea 19141918</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Battle of Jutland</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-de</target><arg>[[Skagerrak]]<nowiki>schlacht</nowiki></arg></template>) was a<space/><link><target>naval battle</target></link><space/>fought by the British<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Grand Fleet</target></link><space/>under Admiral Sir John Jellicoe against the<space/><link><target>Imperial German Navy</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>High Seas Fleet</target></link><space/>under Vice-Admiral Reinhard Scheer during the<space/><link><target>First World War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Commonwealth"></extension><space/>The battle was fought from 31 May to 1 June 1916 in the<space/><link><target>North Sea</target></link>, near the coast of Denmark's<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link><space/>Peninsula. It was the largest naval battle and the only full-scale clash of<space/><link><target>battleship</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the war. It was only the third-ever<space/><link><target>fleet action</target></link><space/>between steel battleships, following the smaller but more decisive battles of the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Yellow Sea</target><part>Yellow Sea (1904)</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Tsushima</target><part>Tsushima (1905)</part></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Russo-Japanese War</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Grand Fleet was commanded by British Admiral<space/><link><target>John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe</target><part>Sir John Jellicoe</part></link>, and the High Seas Fleet by German Vice-Admiral<space/><link><target>Reinhard Scheer</target></link>. The High Seas Fleet's intention was to lure out, trap and destroy a portion of the Grand Fleet, as the German naval force was insufficient to openly engage the entire British fleet. This formed part of a larger strategy to break the British<space/><link><target>blockade of Germany</target></link><space/>and to allow German mercantile shipping to operate. Meanwhile, the Royal Navy pursued a strategy to engage and destroy the High Seas Fleet, or keep the German force contained and away from Britain's own<space/><link><target>Sea lines of communication</target><part>shipping lanes</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The German plan was to use Vice-Admiral<space/><link><target>Franz von Hipper</target><part>Franz Hipper's</part></link><space/>fast scouting group of five modern<space/><link><target>battlecruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to lure Vice-Admiral<space/><link><target>David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</target><part>Sir David Beatty's</part></link><space/>battlecruiser squadrons into the path of the main German fleet. Submarines were stationed in advance across the likely routes of the British ships. However, the British learned from signal intercepts that a major fleet operation was likely, so on 30 May Jellicoe sailed with the Grand Fleet to rendezvous with Beatty, passing over the locations of the German submarine picket lines while they were unprepared. The German plan had been delayed, causing further problems for their submarines which had reached the limit of their endurance at sea.</paragraph><paragraph>On the afternoon of 31 May, Beatty encountered Hipper's battlecruiser force long before the Germans had expected. In a running battle, Hipper successfully drew the British<space/><link><target>Vanguard (military formation)</target><part>vanguard</part></link><space/>into the path of the High Seas Fleet. By the time Beatty sighted the larger force and turned back towards the British main fleet, he had lost two battlecruisers from a force of six battlecruisers and four battleships, against the five ships commanded by Hipper. The battleships, commanded by Rear-Admiral<space/><link><target>Hugh Evan-Thomas</target><part>Sir Hugh Evan-Thomas</part></link>, were the last to turn and formed a<space/><link><target>rearguard</target></link><space/>as Beatty withdrew, now drawing the German fleet in pursuit towards the main British positions. Between 18:30, when the sun was lowering on the western horizon, backlighting the German forces, and nightfall at about 20:30, the two fleets totalling 250 ships between them directly engaged twice.</paragraph><paragraph>Fourteen British and eleven German ships were sunk, with great loss of life. After sunset, and throughout the night, Jellicoe manoeuvred to cut the Germans off from their base, hoping to continue the battle the next morning, but under the cover of darkness Scheer broke through the British light forces forming the rearguard of the Grand Fleet and returned to port.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell,<space/><italics>Analysis</italics><space/>pp. 274</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Both sides claimed victory. The British lost more ships and twice as many sailors, and the British press criticised the Grand Fleet's failure to force a decisive outcome, but Scheer's plan of destroying a substantial portion of the British fleet also failed. The Germans' &quot;<link><target>fleet in being</target></link>&quot; continued to pose a threat, requiring the British to keep their battleships concentrated in the North Sea, but the battle confirmed the German policy of avoiding all fleet-to-fleet contact. At the end of the year, after further unsuccessful attempts to reduce the Royal Navy's numerical advantage, the German Navy turned its efforts and resources to<space/><link><target>unrestricted submarine warfare</target></link><space/>and the destruction of Allied and neutral shipping which by April 1917 triggered the<space/><link><target>United States of America</target></link>'s declaration of war on Germany.<extension extension_name='ref'>Protasio, John. (2011).<space/><italics>The Day the World was Shocked: The Lusitania Disaster and Its Influence on the Course of World War I</italics><space/>pp.200-201, Casemate Publications (US) ISBN 978-1-935149-45-3</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Subsequent reviews commissioned by the Royal Navy generated strong disagreement between supporters of Jellicoe and Beatty concerning the two admirals' performance in the battle. Debate over their performance and the significance of the battle continues to this day.<template><target>TOC limit</target><arg name="limit">2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background and planning</heading><heading level='3'>German planning</heading><paragraph>With 16<space/><link><target>dreadnought</target></link>-class battleships, compared with the Royal Navy's 28, the<space/><link><target>German High Seas Fleet</target></link><space/>stood little chance of winning a head-to-head clash. The Germans therefore adopted a<space/><link><target>Defeat in detail</target><part>divide-and-conquer strategy</part></link>. They would stage raids into the North Sea and bombard the English coast, with the aim of luring out small British squadrons and pickets, which could then be destroyed by superior forces or submarines.</paragraph><paragraph>In January 1916, Admiral<space/><link><target>Hugo von Pohl</target><part>von Pohl</part></link>, commander of the German fleet, fell ill. He was replaced by Scheer, who believed that the fleet had been used too defensively, had better ships and men than the British, and ought to take the war to them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.49</extension><space/>According to Scheer, the German<space/><link><target>naval strategy</target></link><space/>should be:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>to damage the English fleet by offensive raids against the naval forces engaged in watching and blockading the [[Heligoland Bight|German Bight]], as well as by [[naval mine|mine]]-laying on the British coast and [[submarine]] attack, whenever possible. After an equality of strength had been realised as a result of these operations, and all our forces had been made ready and concentrated, an attempt was to be made with our fleet to seek battle under circumstances unfavourable to the enemy.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Scheer.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Reinhard Scheer</target></link>, German fleet commander</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On 25 April 1916, a decision was made by the German admiralty to halt indiscriminate attacks by submarine on merchant shipping. This followed protests from neutral countries, notably the United States, that their nationals had been the victims of attacks. Germany agreed that future attacks would only take place in accord with internationally agreed prize rules, which required an attacker to give a warning and allow the crews of vessels time to escape, and not to attack neutral vessels at all. Scheer believed that it would not be possible to continue attacks on these terms, which took away the advantage of secret approach by submarines and left them vulnerable to even relatively small guns on the target ships. Instead, he set about deploying the submarine fleet against military vessels.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.55</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It was hoped that, following a successful German submarine attack, fast British escorts, such as<space/><link><target>destroyers</target></link>, would be tied down by anti-submarine operations. If the Germans could catch the British in the expected locations, there were thought to be good prospects of at least partially redressing the balance of forces between the fleets. &quot;After the British sortied in response to the raiding attack force&quot;, the Royal Navy's centuries-old instincts for aggressive action could be exploited to draw its weakened units towards the main German fleet under Scheer. The hope was that Scheer would thus be able to ambush a section of the British fleet and destroy it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, p. 2</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Submarine deployments</heading><paragraph>A plan was devised to station submarines offshore from British naval bases, and then stage some action that would draw out the British ships to the waiting submarines. The battlecruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg></template><space/>had been damaged in a previous engagement, but was due to be repaired by mid May, so an operation was scheduled for 17 May 1916. At the start of May, difficulties with condensers were discovered on ships of the third battleship squadron, so the operation was put back to 23 May. Ten submarines<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-24</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-32</arg><arg>Germany</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-43</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-44</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>UC-47</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-51</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-52</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-63</arg><arg>Germany</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-66</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-70</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were given orders first to patrol in the central North Sea between 17 and 22 May, and then to take up waiting positions.<space/><italics>U-43</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>U-44</italics><space/>were stationed in the<space/><link><target>Pentland Firth</target></link>, which the Grand Fleet was likely to cross leaving<space/><link><target>Scapa Flow</target></link>, while the remainder proceeded to the<space/><link><target>Firth of Forth</target></link>, awaiting battlecruisers departing<space/><link><target>Rosyth Dockyard</target><part>Rosyth</part></link>. Each boat had an allocated area, within which it could move around as necessary to avoid detection, but was instructed to keep within it. During the initial North Sea patrol the boats were instructed to sail only north-south so that any enemy who chanced to encounter one would believe it was departing or returning from operations on the west coast (which required them to pass around the north of Britain). Once at their final positions, the boats were under strict orders to avoid premature detection that might give away the operation. It was arranged that a coded signal would be transmitted to alert the submarines exactly when the operation commenced: &quot;Take into account the enemy's forces may be putting to sea&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p. 56-57</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Additionally,<space/><italics>UB-27</italics><space/>was sent out on 20 May with instructions to work its way into the Firth of Forth past<space/><link><target>Isle of May</target><part>May Island</part></link>.<space/><italics>U-46</italics><space/>was ordered to patrol the coast of<space/><link><target>Sunderland, Tyne and Wear</target><part>Sunderland</part></link>, which had been chosen for the diversionary attack, but because of engine problems it was unable to leave port and<space/><italics>U-47</italics><space/>was diverted to this task. On 13 May,<space/><italics>U-72</italics><space/>was sent to lay mines in the Firth of Forth; on the 23rd,<space/><italics>U-74</italics><space/>departed to lay mines in the Moray Firth; and on the 24th,<space/><italics>U-75</italics><space/>was dispatched similarly west of the Orkney Islands.<space/><italics>UB-21</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>UB-22</italics><space/>were sent to patrol the Humber, where (incorrect) reports had suggested the presence of British warships.<space/><italics>U-22</italics>,<space/><italics>U-46</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>U-67</italics><space/>were positioned north of Terschelling to protect against intervention by British light forces stationed at Harwich.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.57-58</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 22 May 1916, it was discovered that<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>was still not watertight after repairs and would not now be ready until the 29th. The ambush submarines were now on station and experiencing difficulties of their own: visibility near the coast was frequently poor due to fog, and sea conditions were either so calm the slightest ripple, as from the periscope, could give away their position, or so rough as to make it very hard to keep the vessel at a steady depth. The British had become aware of unusual submarine activity, and had begun counter patrols that forced the submarines out of position.<space/><italics>UB-27</italics><space/>passed Bell Rock on the night of 23 May on its way into the Firth of Forth as planned, but was halted by engine trouble. After repairs it continued to approach, following behind merchant vessels, and reached Largo Bay on 25 May. There the boat became entangled in nets that fouled one of the propellers, forcing it to abandon the operation and return home.<space/><italics>U-74</italics><space/>was detected by four armed trawlers on 27 May and sunk<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>south-east of Peterhead.<space/><italics>U-75</italics><space/>laid its mines off the Orkney Islands, which, although they played no part in the battle, were responsible later for sinking the cruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Hampshire</arg><arg>1903</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>carrying<space/><link><target>Herbert Kitchener, 1st Earl Kitchener</target><part>Lord Kitchener</part></link><space/>(head of the army) on a mission to Russia on 5 June.<space/><italics>U-72</italics><space/>was forced to abandon its mission without laying any mines when an oil leak meant it was leaving a visible surface trail astern.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.58-60</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Carte Skagerrak-Kattegat2.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>The throat of the<space/><link><target>Skagerrak</target></link>, the strategic gateway to the Baltic and North Atlantic, waters off Jutland and Norway</part></link></paragraph><heading level='4'>Zeppelins</heading><paragraph>The Germans maintained a fleet of<space/><link><target>Zeppelin</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that they used for aerial reconnaissance and occasional bombing raids. The planned raid on Sunderland intended to use Zeppelins to watch out for the British fleet approaching from the north, which might otherwise surprise the raiders.</paragraph><paragraph>By 28 May, strong north-easterly winds meant that it would not be possible to send out the Zeppelins, so the raid again had to be postponed. The submarines could only stay on station until 1 June before their supplies would be exhausted and they had to return, so a decision had to be made quickly about the raid.</paragraph><paragraph>It was decided to use an alternative plan, abandoning the attack on Sunderland but instead sending a patrol of battlecruisers to the<space/><link><target>Skagerrak</target></link>, where it was likely they would encounter merchant ships carrying British cargo and British cruiser patrols. It was felt this could be done without air support, because the action would now be much closer to Germany, relying instead on cruiser and torpedo boat patrols for reconnaissance.</paragraph><paragraph>Orders for the alternative plan were issued on 28 May, although it was still hoped that last-minute improvements in the weather would allow the original plan to go ahead. The German fleet assembled in the<space/><link><target>Jade (river)</target><part>Jade River</part></link><space/>and at<space/><link><target>Wilhelmshaven</target></link><space/>and was instructed to raise steam and be ready for action from midnight on 28 May.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.61</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R10687, Vizeadmiral Hipper mit Stab cropped.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part><link><target>Franz von Hipper</target><part>Franz Hipper</part></link>, commander of the German battlecruiser squadron</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By 14:00 on 30 May, the wind was still too strong and the final decision was made to use the alternative plan. The coded signal &quot;31 May G.G.2490&quot; was transmitted to the ships of the fleet to inform them the Skagerrak attack would start on 31 May. The pre-arranged signal to the waiting submarines was transmitted throughout the day from the E-Dienst radio station at<space/><link><target>Brugge</target></link>, and the U-boat tender<space/><italics>Arcona</italics><space/>anchored at<space/><link><target>Emden</target></link>. Only two of the waiting submarines,<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-66</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMU</target><arg>U-32</arg><arg>Germany</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, received the order.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.62, 60,65</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British response</heading><paragraph>Unfortunately for the German plan, the British had obtained a copy of the main German codebook from the light cruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Magdeburg</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which had been boarded by the<space/><link><target>Imperial Russian Navy</target><part>Russian Navy</part></link><space/>after the ship ran aground in Russian<space/><link><target>territorial waters</target></link><space/>in 1914. German naval radio communications could therefore often be quickly deciphered, and the British<space/><link><target>Admiralty</target></link><space/>usually knew about German activities.</paragraph><paragraph>The British Admiralty's<space/><link><target>Room 40</target></link><space/>maintained<space/><link><target>direction finding</target></link><space/>and interception of German naval signals. It had intercepted and decrypted a German signal on 28 May that provided &quot;ample evidence that the German fleet was stirring in the North Sea.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Stille, Mark. British Dreadnought vs. German Dreadnought: Jutland 1916. 2010. Osprey Publishing.[Page 56]</extension><space/>Further signals were intercepted, and although they were not decrypted it was clear that a major operation was likely. At 11:00 on 30 May, Jellicoe was warned that the German fleet seemed prepared to sail the following morning. By 17:00, the Admiralty had intercepted the signal from Scheer, &quot;31 May G.G.2490&quot;, making it clear something significant was imminent.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.63-64</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Not knowing the Germans' objective, Jellicoe and his staff decided to position the fleet to head off any attempt by the Germans to enter the North Atlantic, or the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target><part>Baltic</part></link><space/>through the Skagerrak, by taking up a position off Norway where they could possibly cut off any German raid into the shipping lanes of the Atlantic, or prevent the Germans from heading into the Baltic. A position further west was unnecessary, as that area of the<space/><link><target>North Sea</target></link><space/>could be patrolled by air using blimps and scouting aircraft.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>May 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:John Jellicoe, Admiral of the Fleet.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>John Jellicoe, 1st Earl Jellicoe</target><part>John Jellicoe</part></link>, British fleet commander</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Consequently, Admiral Jellicoe led the sixteen dreadnought battleships of the 1st and 4th Battle Squadrons of the Grand Fleet and three battlecruisers of the 3rd Battlecruiser Squadron eastwards out of<space/><link><target>Scapa Flow</target></link><space/>at 22:30 on 30 May. He was to meet the 2nd Battle Squadron of eight dreadnought battleships commanded by Vice-Admiral<space/><link><target>Martyn Jerram</target></link><space/>coming from<space/><link><target>Cromarty</target></link>. Hipper's raiding force did not leave the<space/><link><target>Jade Estuary</target><part>Outer Jade Roads</part></link><space/>until 01:00 on 31 May, heading west of Heligoland Island following a cleared channel through the minefields, heading north at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>16</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg name="lk">in</arg></template>. The main German fleet of sixteen dreadnought battleships of 1st and 3rd Battle Squadrons left the Jade at 02:30, being joined off Heligoland at 04:00 by the six pre-dreadnoughts of the 2nd Battle Squadron coming from the Elbe River. Beatty's faster force of six ships of the 1st and 2nd Battlecruiser Squadrons plus the 5th Battle Squadron of four fast battleships left the Firth of Forth on the next day;<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2010</arg></template><space/>Jellicoe's intention was to rendezvous with him<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>90</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>west of the mouth of the Skagerrak off the coast of Jutland and wait for the Germans to appear or for their intentions to become clear. The planned position would give him the widest range of responses to likely German moves.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.64</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Naval tactics in 1916</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template>The principle of<space/><link><target>Force concentration</target><part>concentration of force</part></link><space/>was fundamental to the fleet tactics of this time (as in earlier periods). Tactical doctrine called for a fleet approaching battle to be in a compact formation of parallel columns, allowing relatively easy manoeuvring, and giving shortened sight lines within the formation, which simplified the passing of the signals necessary for command and control.</paragraph><paragraph>A fleet formed in several short columns could change its heading faster than one formed in a single long column. Since most command signals were made with<space/><link><target>flag</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Aldis lamp</target><part>signal lamps</part></link><space/>between ships, the flagship was usually placed at the head of the centre column so that its signals might be more easily seen by the many ships of the formation. Wireless telegraphy was in use, though security (radio direction finding), encryption, and the limitation of the radio sets made their extensive use more problematic. Command and control of such huge fleets remained difficult.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sutherland, Cramwell, p.13</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Thus, it might take a very long time for a signal from the flagship to be relayed to the entire formation. It was usually necessary for a signal to be confirmed by each ship before it could be relayed to other ships, and an order for a fleet movement would have to be received and acknowledged by every ship before it could be executed. In a large single-column formation, a signal could take 10 minutes or more to be passed from one end of the line to the other, whereas in a formation of parallel columns, visibility across the diagonals was often better (and always shorter) than in a single long column, and the diagonals gave signal &quot;redundancy&quot;, increasing the probability that a message would be quickly seen and correctly interpreted.</paragraph><paragraph>However, before battle was joined the heavy units of the fleet would, if possible, deploy into a single column. To form the battle line in the correct orientation relative to the enemy, the commanding admiral had to know the enemy fleet's distance, bearing, heading, and speed. It was the task of the scouting forces, consisting primarily of<space/><link><target>battlecruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>, to find the enemy and report this information in sufficient time, and, if possible, to deny the enemy's scouting forces the opportunity of obtaining the equivalent information.</paragraph><paragraph>Ideally, the battle line would cross the intended path of the enemy column so that the maximum number of guns could be brought to bear, while the enemy could fire only with the forward guns of the leading ships, a manoeuvre known as &quot;<link><target>crossing the T</target></link>&quot;. Admiral<space/><link><target>Tg Heihachir</target><part>Tg</part></link>, commander of the Japanese battleship fleet, had achieved this against Admiral<space/><link><target>Zinovy Rozhestvensky</target></link>'s Russian battleships in 1905 at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Tsushima</target></link>, with devastating results.<extension extension_name='ref'>Forczyk p. 58-62</extension><space/>Jellicoe was to achieve this twice in one hour against the High Seas Fleet at Jutland, but on both occasions Scheer managed to turn away and disengage, thereby avoiding a decisive action.<space/><template><target>clear left</target></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ship design</heading><paragraph>Within the existing technological limits, a trade-off had to be made between the weight and size of guns, the weight of armour protecting the ship, and the maximum speed. Battleships sacrificed speed for armour and heavy naval guns (<template><target>convert</target><arg>11</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>or larger). British battlecruisers sacrificed weight of armour for greater speed, while their German counterparts were armed with lighter guns and heavier armour. These weight savings allowed them to escape danger or catch other ships. Generally, the larger guns mounted on British ships allowed an engagement at greater range. In theory, a lightly armoured ship could stay out of range of a slower opponent while still scoring hits. The fast pace of development in the pre-war years meant that every few years, a new generation of ships rendered its predecessors obsolete. Thus, fairly young ships could still be obsolete compared to the newest ships, and fare badly in an engagement against them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Castles666">'Castles of Steel' p. 666</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher</target><part>Admiral John Fisher</part></link>, responsible for reconstruction of the British fleet in the pre-war period, favoured large guns and speed.<space/><link><target>Alfred von Tirpitz</target><part>Admiral Tirpitz</part></link>, responsible for the German fleet, favoured ship survivability and chose to sacrifice some gun size for improved armour. The German battlecruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Derfflinger</arg></template><space/>had<space/><link><target>belt armour</target></link><space/>equivalent in thickness though not in terms of comprehensiveness to the British battleship<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Iron Duke</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, significantly better than on the British battlecruisers such as<space/><italics>Tiger</italics>. German ships had better internal subdivision and had fewer doors and other weak points in their<space/><link><target>bulkhead (partition)</target><part>bulkheads</part></link>, but with the disadvantage that space for crew was greatly reduced.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Castles666"></extension><space/>As they were only designed for sorties in the North Sea, they did not need to be as habitable as the British vessels, and their crews could live in barracks ashore when in harbour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.168</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Order of battle</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Order of battle at Jutland</arg></template></paragraph><table class="wikitable" align="right" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="2" style="margin:10px; border:solid 1px #bbb;"><tablerow><tablehead></tablehead><tablehead>British</tablehead><tablehead>German</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Dreadnought<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Battleships</tablecell><tablecell>28</tablecell><tablecell>16</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Pre-Dreadnoughts</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Battlecruisers</tablecell><tablecell>9</tablecell><tablecell>5</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Armoured Cruisers</tablecell><tablecell>8</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Light Cruisers</tablecell><tablecell>26</tablecell><tablecell>11</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Destroyers</tablecell><tablecell>79</tablecell><tablecell>61</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Seaplane Carrier</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph>Warships of the period were armed with guns firing projectiles of varying weights, bearing<space/><link><target>high explosive</target></link><space/>warheads. The sum total of weight of all the projectiles fired by all the ship's guns is referred to as &quot;weight of broadside.&quot; At Jutland, the total of the British ships' weight of broadside was 332,360&amp;nbsp;lb (150,760&amp;nbsp;kg), while the German fleet's total was 134,216&amp;nbsp;lb (60,879&amp;nbsp;kg).<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.65</extension><space/>This does not take into consideration the ability of some ships and their crews to fire more or less rapidly than others, which would increase or decrease amount of fire that one combatant was able to bring to bear on their opponent for any length of time.</paragraph><paragraph>Jellicoe's Grand Fleet was split into two sections. The dreadnought Battle Fleet with which he sailed formed the main force and was composed of 24 battleships and three battlecruisers. The battleships were formed into three squadrons of eight ships, further subdivided into divisions of four, each led by a<space/><link><target>flag officer</target></link>. Accompanying them were eight<space/><link><target>armoured cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(classified by the Royal Navy since 1913 as &quot;cruisers&quot;), eight<space/><link><target>light cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>, four<space/><link><target>scout cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>, 51<space/><link><target>destroyer</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and one<space/><link><target>destroyer-minelayer</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jellicoe, Joe, The Grand Fleet, 19141916, London, Cassell, 1919</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Nw beatty 01.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>175px</part><part><link><target>David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</target><part>David Beatty</part></link>, commander of the British battlecruiser fleet</part></link>The Grand Fleet sailed without three of its battleships:<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Emperor of India</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in refit at Invergordon,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Queen Elizabeth</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>dry-docked at<space/><link><target>Rosyth Dockyard</target><part>Rosyth</part></link><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Dreadnought</arg><arg>1906</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in refit at Devonport. The brand new<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Royal Sovereign</arg><arg>05</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>was left behind, with only three weeks in service, her untrained crew judged unready for battle.</paragraph><paragraph>British<space/><link><target>reconnaissance</target></link><space/>was provided by the Battlecruiser Fleet under David Beatty: six battlecruisers, four fast<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Queen Elizabeth</arg><arg>battleship</arg></template>s, 14 light cruisers and 27 destroyers. Air scouting was provided for by the attachment of the<space/><link><target>seaplane tender</target></link><space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Engadine</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, one of the first<space/><link><target>aircraft carrier</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in history to participate in a naval engagement.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-26"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">26</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The German High Seas Fleet under Scheer was also split into a main force and a separate reconnaissance force. Scheer's main battle fleet was composed of 16 battleships and six<space/><link><target>Pre-dreadnought battleship</target><part>pre-dreadnought</part></link><space/>battleships arranged in an identical manner to the British. With them were six light cruisers and 31<space/><link><target>torpedo-boat</target><trail>s</trail></link>, (the latter being roughly equivalent to a British destroyer).<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The German scouting force, commanded by Franz Hipper, consisted of five battlecruisers, five light cruisers and 30 torpedo-boats. The Germans had no equivalent to<space/><italics>Engadine</italics>, and no<space/><link><target>aircraft</target><part>heavier-than-air aircraft</part></link><space/>to operate with the fleet, but had the Imperial German Naval Airship Service's force of<space/><link><target>rigid airship</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>available to patrol the North Sea.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>All of the battleships and battlecruisers on both sides carried<space/><link><target>torpedo</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>of various sizes, as did the lighter craft.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-26"></extension><space/>The British battleships carried three or four underwater torpedo tubes. The battlecruisers carried from two to five. All were either 18-inch or 21-inch diameter. The German battleships carried five or six underwater torpedo tubes in three sizes from 18 to 21 inch and the battlecruisers carried four or five tubes.</paragraph><paragraph>The German battle fleet was hampered by the slow speed and relatively poor armament of the six pre-dreadnoughts of II Squadron, which limited maximum fleet speed to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, compared to maximum British fleet speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>21</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-16"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">16–19</arg></template></extension><space/>On the British side, the eight armoured cruisers were deficient in both speed and armour protection.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">22</arg></template></extension><space/>Both of these obsolete squadrons were notably vulnerable to attacks by more modern enemy ships.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2009</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Battlecruiser action</heading><paragraph>The route of the British battlecruiser fleet took it through the patrol sector allocated to<space/><italics>U-32</italics>. After receiving the order to commence the operation, the U-boat moved to a position<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>80</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>east of May Island at dawn on 31 May. At 03:40, it sighted the cruisers<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Galatea</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Phaeton</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>leaving the Forth at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>. It launched one torpedo at the leading cruiser at a range of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1000</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, but its periscope jammed 'up', giving away the position of the submarine as it manoeuvred to fire a second. The lead cruiser turned away to dodge the torpedo, while the second turned towards the submarine, attempting to ram.<space/><italics>U-32</italics><space/><link><target>crash dive</target><trail>d</trail></link>, and on raising its periscope at 04:10 saw two battlecruisers (the 2nd Battlecruiser Squadron) heading south-east. They were too far away to attack, but<space/><italics><link><target>Captain lieutenant</target><part>Kapitnleutnant</part></link></italics><space/>von Spiegel reported the sighting of two battleships and two cruisers to Germany.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.65-66</extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>U-66</italics><space/>was also supposed to be patrolling off the Firth of Forth, but had been forced north to a position<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>off Peterhead by patrolling British vessels. This now brought it into contact with the 2nd Battle Squadron, coming from the Moray Firth. At 05:00, it had to crash dive when the cruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Duke of Edinburgh</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>appeared from the mist heading toward it. It was followed by another cruiser,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Boadicea</arg><arg>1908</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and eight battleships.<space/><italics>U-66</italics><space/>got within<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>350</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of the battleships preparing to fire, but was forced to dive by an approaching destroyer and missed the opportunity. At 06:35, it reported eight battleships and cruisers heading north.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p. 66-67</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The courses reported by both submarines were incorrect, because they reflected one leg of a zigzag being used by British ships to avoid submarines. Taken with a wireless intercept of more ships leaving Scapa Flow earlier in the night, they created the impression in the German High Command that the British fleet, whatever it was doing, was split into separate sections moving apart, which was precisely as the Germans wished to meet it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.67</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jellicoe's ships proceeded to their rendezvous undamaged and undiscovered. However, he was now misled by an Admiralty<space/><link><target>intelligence (information gathering)</target><part>intelligence</part></link><space/>report advising that the German main battle fleet was still in port.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">28–29</arg></template></extension><space/>The Director of Operations Division, Rear Admiral<space/><link><target>Thomas Jackson (Royal Navy officer)</target><part>Thomas Jackson</part></link>, had asked the intelligence division,<space/><link><target>Room 40</target></link>, for the current location of German call sign DK, used by Admiral Scheer. They had replied that it was currently transmitting from<space/><link><target>Wilhelmshaven</target></link>. It was known to the intelligence staff that Scheer deliberately used a different call sign when at sea, but no one asked for this information or explained the reason behind the query to locate the German fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.41-42</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The German battlecruisers cleared the minefields surrounding the<space/><link><target>Amrum</target></link><space/>swept channel by 09:00. They then proceeded north-west, passing<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>35</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>west of the<space/><link><target>Horns Rev</target><part>Horn's Reef</part></link><space/>lightship heading for the<space/><link><target>Little Fisher Bank</target></link><space/>at the mouth of the Skagerrak. The High Seas Fleet followed some<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>50</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>behind. The battlecruisers were in line ahead, with the four cruisers of the II scouting group plus supporting torpedo boats ranged in an arc<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>ahead and to either side. The IX torpedo boat flotilla formed close support immediately surrounding the battlecruisers. The High Seas Fleet similarly adopted a line-ahead formation, with close screening by torpedo boats to either side and a further screen of five cruisers surrounding the column<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5</arg><arg>-</arg><arg>8</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>away. The wind had finally moderated so that Zeppelins could be used, and by 11:30 five had been sent out:<space/><italics>L14</italics><space/>to the Skagerrak,<space/><italics>L23</italics><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>240</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>east of Noss Head in the Pentland Firth,<space/><italics>L21</italics><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>120</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>off Peterhead,<space/><italics>L9</italics><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>off Sunderland, and<space/><italics>L16</italics><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>80</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>east of Flamborough Head. Visibility, however, was still bad, with clouds down to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.69-70</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Contact</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:HMS Warspite and HMS Malaya during the battle of Jutland.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>HMS ''Warspite'' and ''Malaya'', seen from HMS ''Valiant'' at around 14:00&amp;nbsp;hrs</part></link>By around 14:00, Beatty's ships were proceeding eastward at roughly the same latitude as Hipper's squadron, which was heading north. Had the courses remained unchanged, Beatty would have passed between the two German fleets,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>south of the battlecruisers and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>north of the High Seas Fleet at around 16:30, possibly trapping his ships just as the German plan envisioned. However, his orders were to stop his scouting patrol when he reached a point<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>260</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>east of Britain and then turn north to meet Jellicoe, which he did at this time. Beatty's ships were divided into three columns, with the two battlecruiser squadrons leading in parallel lines<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>apart. The 5th Battle Squadron was stationed<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>to the north-west, on the side furthest away from any expected enemy contact, while a screen of cruisers and destroyers was spread south-east of the battlecruisers. After the turn, the 5th Battle Squadron was now leading the British ships in the westernmost column, and Beatty's squadron was centre and rearmost, with the 2nd BCS to the west.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.70-71</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Jutland battlecruiser action.png</target><part>400px</part><part>thumb</part><part>(1) 15:22&amp;nbsp;hrs, Hipper sights Beatty.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(2) 15:48&amp;nbsp;hrs, First shots fired by Hipper's squadron.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(3) 16:00&amp;nbsp;hrs-16:05&amp;nbsp;hrs, ''Indefatigable'' explodes, leaving two survivors.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(4) 16:25&amp;nbsp;hrs, ''Queen Mary'' explodes, nine survive.<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(5) 16:45&amp;nbsp;hrs, Beatty's battlecruisers move out of range of Hipper.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(6) 16:54&amp;nbsp;hrs, Evan-Thomas's battleships turn north behind Beatty.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>At 14:20 on 31 May, despite heavy haze and<space/><link><target>Scud (cloud)</target><part>scuds</part></link><space/>of fog giving poor visibility, scouts from Beatty's force reported enemy ships to the south-east; the British light units, investigating a neutral Danish<space/><link><target>Steamboat</target><part>steamer</part></link><space/>(<italics>N J Fjord</italics>), which was stopped between the two fleets, had found two German destroyers engaged on the same mission (<template><target>SMS</target><arg>B109</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>B110</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>). The first shots of the battle were fired at 14:28 when<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Galatea</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Phaeton</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>of the British 1st Light<space/><link><target>Cruiser Squadron</target></link><space/>opened on the German torpedo boats, which withdrew toward their own approaching light cruisers. At 14:36, the Germans scored the first hit of the battle when<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Elbing</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, of Rear-Admiral<space/><link><target>Friedrich Bdicker</target></link>'s Scouting Group II, hit her British counterpart<space/><italics>Galatea</italics><space/>at extreme range.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">31</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, Beatty began to move his battlecruisers and supporting forces south-eastwards and then east to cut the German ships off from their base, and ordered<space/><italics>Engadine</italics><space/>to launch a<space/><link><target>seaplane</target></link><space/>to try to get more information about the size and location of the German forces. This was the first time in history that a carrier-based aeroplane was used for reconnaissance in naval combat.<space/><italics>Engadine</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s plane did locate and report some German light cruisers just before 15:30, and came under anti-aircraft gunfire, but attempts to relay the plane's reports failed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-35"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">35</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unfortunately for Beatty, his initial course changes at 14:32 were not received by<space/><link><target>Hugh Evan-Thomas</target><part>Sir Hugh Evan-Thomas's</part></link><space/><link><target>5th Battle Squadron</target></link><space/>(the distance being too great to read his flags), because the battlecruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Tiger</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>the last ship in his column was no longer in a position where she could relay signals by searchlight to Evan-Thomas, as she had previously been ordered to do. Whereas before the north turn,<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>had been the closest ship to Evan-Thomas, she was now further away than Beatty in<space/><italics>Lion</italics>. Matters were aggravated because Evan-Thomas had not been briefed regarding standing orders within Beatty's squadron, as his squadron normally operated with the Grand Fleet. Fleet ships were expected to obey movement orders precisely and not deviate from them. Beatty's standing instructions expected his officers to use their initiative and keep station with the flagship.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Marder' III p.55</extension><space/>As a result, the four<space/><italics>Queen Elizabeth</italics>-class battleships which were the fastest and most heavily armed in the world at that time remained on the previous course for several minutes, ending up<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>10</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>behind rather than five.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">32</arg></template></extension><space/>Beatty also had the opportunity during the previous hours to concentrate his forces, and no reason not to do so, whereas he steamed ahead at full speed, faster than the battleships could manage. Dividing the force had serious consequences for the British, costing them what would have been an overwhelming advantage in ships and firepower during the first half-hour of the coming battle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-35"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>With visibility favouring the Germans, Hipper's battlecruisers at 15:22, steaming approximately north-west, sighted Beatty's squadron at a range of about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, while Beatty's forces did not identify Hipper's battlecruisers until 15:30.<space/><xhtml:span style="background: lightblue">(position 1 on map)</xhtml:span>. At 15:45, Hipper turned south-east to lead Beatty toward Scheer, who was<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>46</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>southeast with the main force of the High Seas Fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">34–35</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Run to the South</heading><paragraph>Beatty's conduct during the next 15 minutes has received a great deal of criticism, as his ships out-ranged and outnumbered the German squadron, yet he held his fire for over 10 minutes with the German ships in range. He also failed to use the time available to rearrange his battlecruisers into a fighting formation, with the result that they were still manoeuvring when the battle started.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooks p. 234-237</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At 15:48, with the opposing forces roughly parallel at<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15000</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, with the British to the south-west of the Germans (i.e., on the right side), Hipper opened fire, followed by the British ships as their guns came to bear upon targets<space/><xhtml:span style="background:lightblue">(position 2)</xhtml:span>. Thus began the opening phase of the battlecruiser action, known as the &quot;Run to the South&quot;, in which the British chased the Germans, and Hipper intentionally led Beatty toward Scheer. During the first minutes of the ensuing battle, all the British ships except<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics><space/>fired far over their German opponents, due to adverse visibility conditions, before finally getting the range. Only<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics><space/>had settled into formation, so the other four ships were hampered in aiming by their own turning. Beatty was to windward of Hipper, and therefore funnel and gun smoke from his own ships tended to obscure his targets, while Hipper's smoke blew clear. Also, the eastern sky was overcast and the grey German ships were indistinct and difficult to range.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">38–39</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:HMS Lion (1910).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>David Beatty, 1st Earl Beatty</target><part>Beatty's</part></link><space/>flagship ''Lion'' burning after being hit by a salvo from ''Ltzow''</part></link><link><target>File:HMS Indefatigable sinking.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>250px</part><part>HMS ''Indefatigable'' sinking after being struck by shells from the German battlecruiser ''Von der Tann''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Beatty had ordered his ships to engage in a line, one British ship engaging with one German and his<space/><link><target>flagship</target></link><space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Lion</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>doubling on the German flagship<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Lützow</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>. However, due to another mistake with signalling by flag, and possibly because<space/><italics>Queen Mary</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>were unable to see the German lead ship because of smoke,<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooks p. 239</extension><space/>the second German ship,<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics>, was left un-engaged and free to fire without disruption.<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Moltke</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>drew fire from two of Beatty's battlecruisers, but still fired with great accuracy during this time, hitting<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>9 times in the first 12 minutes. The Germans drew first blood. Aided by superior visibility, Hipper's five battlecruisers quickly registered hits on three of the six British battlecruisers. Seven minutes passed before the British managed to score their first hit.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">39–41</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first near-kill of the Run to the South occurred at 16:00, when a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>30.5</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>shell from<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>wrecked the &quot;Q&quot; turret amidships on Beatty's flagship<space/><italics>Lion</italics>. Dozens of crewmen were instantly killed, but far larger destruction was averted when the mortally wounded turret commander Major<space/><link><target>Francis John William Harvey</target><part>Francis Harvey</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Royal Marines</target></link><space/>promptly ordered the magazine doors shut and the magazine flooded. This prevented a magazine explosion at 16:28, when a flash fire ignited ready cordite charges beneath the turret and killed everyone in the chambers outside &quot;Q&quot; magazine.<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>was saved.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">64–66</arg></template></extension><space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>1909</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was not so lucky; at 16:02, just 14 minutes into the gunnery exchange, she was hit aft by three<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>shells from<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Von der Tann</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, causing damage sufficient to knock her out of line and detonating &quot;X&quot; magazine aft. Soon after, despite the near-maximum range,<space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics><space/>put another<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>shell on<space/><italics>Indefatigable</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s &quot;A&quot; turret forward. The plunging shells probably pierced the thin upper armour, and seconds later<space/><italics>Indefatigable</italics><space/>was ripped apart by another magazine explosion, sinking immediately with her crew of 1,019 officers and men, leaving only two survivors.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">60–61</arg></template></extension><space/><xhtml:span style="background:lightblue">(position 3)</xhtml:span>.</paragraph><paragraph>Hipper's position deteriorated somewhat by 16:15 as the 5th Battle Squadron finally came into range, so that he had to contend with gunfire from the four battleships astern as well as Beatty's five remaining battlecruisers to starboard. But he knew his baiting mission was close to completion, as his force was rapidly closing with Scheer's main body. At 16:08, the lead battleship of the 5th Battle Squadron,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Barham</arg><arg>04</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, caught up with Hipper and opened fire at extreme range, scoring a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>hit on<space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics><space/>within 60 seconds. Still, it was 16:15 before all the battleships of the 5th were able to fully engage at long range.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">49</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At 16:25, the battlecruiser action intensified again when<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Queen Mary</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was hit by what may have been a combined salvo from<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>; she disintegrated when both forward magazines exploded, sinking with all but nine of her 1,275 man crew lost.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">62–64</arg></template></extension><space/><xhtml:span style="background:lightblue">(position 4)</xhtml:span>. Commander von Hase, the first gunnery officer aboard<space/><italics>Derfflingler</italics>, noted:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>bquote</target><arg>The enemy was shooting superbly. Twice the ''Derfflinger'' came under their infernal hail and each time she was hit. But the ''Queen Mary'' was having a bad time; engaged by the ''Seydlitz'' as well as the ''Derfflinger'', she met her doom at 1626. A vivid red flame shot up from her forepart; then came an explosion forward, followed by a much heavier explosion amidships. Immediately afterwards, she blew up with a terrific explosion, the masts collapsing inwards and the smoke hiding everything.<ref>Bennett, p187</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Destruction of HMS Queen Mary.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>275px</part><part>HMS ''Queen Mary'' blowing up</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>During the Run to the South, from 15:48 to 16:54, the German battlecruisers made an estimated total of forty-two<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>28</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>30.5</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>hits on the British battlecruisers (nine on<space/><italics>Lion</italics>, six on<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics>, seven on<space/><italics>Queen Mary</italics>, 14 on<space/><italics>Tiger</italics>, one on<space/><italics>New Zealand</italics>, five on<space/><italics>Indefatigable</italics>), and two more on the battleship<space/><italics>Barham</italics>, compared with only eleven<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>13.5</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>hits by the British battlecruisers (four on<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics>, four on<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, two on<space/><italics>Moltke</italics>, one on<space/><italics>von der Tann</italics>), and six<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>hits by the battleships (one on<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, four on<space/><italics>Moltke</italics>, one on<space/><italics>von der Tann</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">78, 94</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Shortly after 16:26, a salvo struck on or around<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Princess Royal</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which was obscured by spray and smoke from shell bursts. A signalman promptly leapt on to the bridge of<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>and announced &quot;<italics>Princess Royal</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s blown up, Sir.&quot; Beatty famously turned to his<space/><link><target>flag captain</target></link>, saying &quot;<link><target>Ernle Chatfield, 1st Baron Chatfield</target><part>Chatfield</part></link>, there seems to be something wrong with our bloody ships today.&quot; (In popular legend, Beatty also immediately ordered his ships to &quot;turn two points to port&quot;, i.e., two<space/><link><target>Compass point</target><part>points</part></link><space/>nearer the enemy, but there is no official record of any such command or course change.)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">596</arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics>, as it turned out, was still afloat after the spray cleared.</paragraph><paragraph>At 16:30, Scheer's leading battleships sighted the distant battlecruiser action; soon after,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Southampton</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>of Beatty's 2nd<space/><link><target>Light Cruiser</target></link><space/>Squadron led by Commodore<space/><link><target>William Goodenough</target></link><space/>sighted the main body of Scheer's High Seas Fleet, dodging numerous heavy-calibre salvos to report in detail the German strength: 16 dreadnoughts with six older battleships. This was the first news that Beatty and Jellicoe had that Scheer and his battle fleet were even at sea. Simultaneously, an all-out destroyer action raged in the space between the opposing battlecruiser forces, as British and German destroyers fought with each other and attempted to torpedo the larger enemy ships. Each side fired many torpedoes, but both battlecruiser forces turned away from the attacks and all escaped harm except<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, which was hit forward at 16:57 by a torpedo fired by the British destroyer<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Petard</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>6</arg></template>. Though taking on water,<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>maintained speed. The destroyer<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nestor</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, under the command of<space/><link><target>Edward Bingham</target><part>Captain Barry Bingham</part></link>, led the British attacks. The British disabled the German torpedo boat<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V27</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, which the Germans soon abandoned and sank, and<space/><italics>Petard</italics><space/>then torpedoed and sank<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V29</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, her second score of the day.<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>S35</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V26</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>rescued the crews of their sunken sister ships. But<space/><italics>Nestor</italics><space/>and another British destroyer<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nomad</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>were immobilised by shell hits, and were later sunk by Scheer's passing dreadnoughts. Bingham was rescued, and won the Victoria Cross for his leadership in the destroyer action.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">50–56</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Run to the North</heading><paragraph>As soon as he himself sighted the vanguard of Scheer's distant battleship line<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>away, at 16:40, Beatty turned his battlecruiser force 180, heading north to draw the Germans toward Jellicoe.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">52</arg></template></extension><space/><xhtml:span style="background:lightblue">(position 5)</xhtml:span>. Beatty's withdrawal toward Jellicoe is called the &quot;Run to the North&quot;, in which the tables turned and the Germans chased the British. Because Beatty once again failed to signal his intentions adequately, the battleships of the 5th Battle Squadron which were too far behind to read his flags found themselves passing the battlecruisers on an opposing course and heading directly toward the approaching main body of the High Seas Fleet. At 16:48, at extreme range, Scheer's leading battleships opened fire.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-54"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">54</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, at 16:47, having received Goodenough's signal and knowing that Beatty was now leading the German battle fleet north to him, Jellicoe signalled to his own forces that the fleet action they had waited so long for was finally imminent; at 16:51, by radio, he informed the Admiralty so in London.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">58–59</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The difficulties of the 5th Battle Squadron were compounded when Beatty gave the order to Evan-Thomas to &quot;turn in succession&quot; (rather than &quot;turn together&quot;) at 16:48 as the battleships passed him. Evan-Thomas acknowledged the signal, but<space/><link><target>Lieutenant-Commander</target></link><space/><link><target>Ralph Seymour (naval officer)</target><part>Ralph Seymour</part></link>, Beatty's<space/><link><target>flag lieutenant</target></link>, aggravated the situation when he did not haul down the flags (to execute the signal) for some minutes. At 16:55, when the 5BS had moved within range of the enemy battleships, Evan-Thomas issued his own flag command warning his squadron to expect sudden manoeuvres and to follow his lead, before starting to turn on his own initiative. The order to turn in succession would have resulted in all four ships turning in the same patch of sea as they reached it one by one, giving the High Seas Fleet repeated opportunity with ample time to find the proper range. However, the captain of the trailing ship (<link><target>HMS Malaya</target><part>HMS ''Malaya''</part></link>) turned early, mitigating the adverse results.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-54"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Massie, pp. 600601</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For the next hour, the 5th Battle Squadron acted as Beatty's rearguard, drawing fire from all the German ships within range, while by 17:10 Beatty had deliberately eased his own squadron out of range of Hipper's now-superior battlecruiser force.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">96–97</arg></template></extension><space/>Since visibility and firepower now favoured the Germans, there was no incentive for Beatty to risk further battlecruiser losses when his own gunnery could not be effective. Illustrating the imbalance, Beatty's battlecruisers did not score any hits on the Germans in this phase until 17:45,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">135<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>but they had rapidly received five more before he opened the range (four on<space/><italics>Lion</italics>, of which three were by<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics>, and one on<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>by<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">124–125, p. 145</arg></template></extension><space/>Now the only targets the Germans could reach, the ships of the 5th Battle Squadron, received simultaneous fire from Hipper's battlecruisers to the east (which HMS<space/><italics>Barham</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Valiant</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>engaged) and Scheer's leading battleships to the south-east (which<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Warspite</arg><arg>03</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Malaya</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>engaged).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">100</arg></template></extension><space/>Three took hits:<space/><italics>Barham</italics><space/>(four by<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics>),<space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>(two by<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>), and<space/><italics>Malaya</italics><space/>(seven by the German battleships). Only<space/><italics>Valiant</italics><space/>was unscathed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">126–133</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The four battleships were far better suited to take this sort of pounding than the battlecruisers, and none were lost, though<space/><italics>Malaya</italics><space/>suffered heavy damage, an ammunition fire, and heavy crew casualties. At the same time, the<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>fire of the four British ships was accurate and effective. As the two British squadrons headed north at top speed, eagerly chased by the entire German fleet, the 5th Battle Squadron scored 13 hits on the enemy battlecruisers (four on<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics>, three on<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics>, six on<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>) and five on battleships (although only one, on<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Markgraf</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, did any serious damage).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">134–145</arg></template></extension><space/><xhtml:span style="background:lightblue">(position 6)</xhtml:span>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The fleets converge</heading><paragraph>Jellicoe was now aware that full fleet engagement was nearing, but had insufficient information on the position and course of the Germans. To assist Beatty, early in the battle at about 16:05, Jellicoe had ordered<space/><link><target>Rear-Admiral</target></link><space/><link><target>Horace Hood</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>3rd Battlecruiser Squadron (United Kingdom)</target><part>3rd Battlecruiser Squadron</part></link><space/>to speed ahead to find and support Beatty's force, and Hood was now racing SSE well in advance of Jellicoe's northern force.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">59</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Sir Robert Arbuthnot, 4th Baronet</target><part>Rear-Admiral Arbuthnot</part></link>'s 1st Cruiser Squadron patrolled the van of Jellicoe's main battleship force as it advanced steadily to the south-east.</paragraph><paragraph>At 17:33, the armoured cruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Black Prince</arg><arg>1904</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>of Arbuthnot's squadron, on the far southwest flank of Jellicoe's force, came within view of<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Falmouth</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which was about<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>ahead of Beatty with the 3rd Light Cruiser Squadron, establishing the first visual link between the converging bodies of the Grand Fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">118</arg></template></extension><space/>At 17:38, the scout cruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Chester</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, screening Hood's oncoming battlecruisers, was intercepted by the van of the German scouting forces under Rear-Admiral Bdicker.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">111</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Heavily outnumbered by Bdicker's four light cruisers,<space/><italics>Chester</italics><space/>was pounded before being relieved by Hood's heavy units, which swung westward for that purpose. Hood's flagship<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>disabled the light cruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Wiesbaden</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>shortly after 17:56.<space/><italics>Wiesbaden</italics><space/>became a sitting target for most of the British fleet during the next hour, but remained afloat and fired some torpedoes at the passing enemy battleships from long range. Meanwhile, Bdicker's other ships fled toward Hipper and Scheer in the mistaken belief that Hood was leading a larger force of British capital ships from the north and east. A chaotic destroyer action in mist and smoke ensued as German torpedo boats attempted to blunt the arrival of this new formation, but Hood's battlecruisers dodged all the torpedoes fired at them. In this action, after leading a torpedo counter-attack, the British destroyer<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shark</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was disabled, but continued to return fire at numerous passing enemy ships for the next hour.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">111–115</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>The fleet action</heading><heading level='3'>Deployment</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Jutland fleet action.png</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>(1) 18:00 Scouting forces rejoin their respective fleets.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(2) 18:15 British fleet deploys into battle line<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(3) 18:30 German fleet under fire turns away<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(4) 19:00 German fleet turns back<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(5) 19:15 German fleet turns away for second time<space/><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(6) 20:00<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(7) 21:00 Nightfall: Jellicoe assumes night cruising formation</part></link>In the meantime, Beatty and Evan-Thomas had resumed their engagement with Hipper's battlecruisers, this time with the visual conditions to their advantage. With several of his ships damaged, Hipper turned back toward Scheer at around 18:00, just as Beatty's flagship<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>was finally sighted from Jellicoe's flagship<space/><italics>Iron Duke</italics>. Jellicoe twice demanded the latest position of the German battlefleet from Beatty, who could not see the German battleships and failed to respond to the question until 18:14. Meanwhile, Jellicoe received confused sighting reports of varying accuracy and limited usefulness from light cruisers and battleships on the starboard (southern) flank of his force.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-120"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">120–121</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jellicoe was in a worrying position. He needed to know the location of the German fleet to judge when and how to deploy his battleships from their cruising formation (six columns of four ships each) into a single battle line. The deployment could be on either the westernmost or the easternmost column, and had to be carried out before the Germans arrived; but early deployment could mean losing any chance of a decisive encounter. Deploying to the west would bring his fleet closer to Scheer, gaining valuable time as dusk approached, but the Germans might arrive before the manoeuvre was complete. Deploying to the east would take the force away from Scheer, but Jellicoe's ships might be able to<space/><link><target>crossing the T</target><part>cross the &quot;T&quot;</part></link>, and visibility would strongly favour British gunnery Scheer's forces would be silhouetted against the setting sun to the west, while the Grand Fleet would be indistinct against the dark skies to the north and east, and would be hidden by reflection of the low sunlight off intervening haze and smoke. Deployment would take twenty irreplaceable minutes, and the fleets were closing at full speed. In one of the most critical and difficult tactical command decisions of the entire war, Jellicoe ordered deployment to the east at 18:15.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-120"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">612–613</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Windy Corner</heading><paragraph>Meanwhile, Hipper had rejoined Scheer, and the combined High Seas Fleet was heading north, directly toward Jellicoe. Scheer had no indication that Jellicoe was at sea, let alone that he was bearing down from the north-west, and was distracted by the intervention of Hood's ships to his north and east. Beatty's four surviving battlecruisers were now crossing the van of the British dreadnoughts to join Hood's three battlecruisers; at this time, Arbuthnot's flagship, the armoured cruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Defence</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, and her squadron-mate<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Warrior</arg><arg>1905</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>both charged across Beatty's bows, and<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>narrowly avoided a collision with<space/><italics>Warrior</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">115</arg></template></extension><space/>Nearby, numerous British light cruisers and destroyers on the south-western flank of the deploying battleships were also crossing each other's courses in attempts to reach their proper stations, often barely escaping collisions, and under fire from some of the approaching German ships. This period of peril and heavy traffic attending the merger and deployment of the British forces later became known as &quot;Windy Corner&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Massie, p. 614</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Arbuthnot was attracted by the drifting hull of the crippled<space/><italics>Wiesbaden</italics>. With<space/><italics>Warrior</italics>,<space/><italics>Defence</italics><space/>closed in for the kill, only to blunder right into the gun sights of Hipper's and Scheer's oncoming capital ships.<space/><italics>Defence</italics><space/>was deluged by heavy-calibre gunfire from many German battleships, which detonated her magazines in a spectacular explosion viewed by most of the deploying Grand Fleet; she sank with all hands (903 officers and men).<space/><italics>Warrior</italics><space/>was also hit badly, but she was spared destruction by a mishap to the nearby battleship<space/><italics>Warspite</italics>.<space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>had her steering gear overheat and jam under heavy load at high speed as the 5th Battle Squadron made a turn to the north at 18:19.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">153, p. 179</arg></template></extension><space/>Steaming at top speed in wide circles,<space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>appeared as a juicy target to the German dreadnoughts and took 13 hits, inadvertently drawing fire from the hapless<space/><italics>Warrior</italics>.<space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>was brought back under control and survived the onslaught, but was badly damaged, had to reduce speed, and withdrew northward; later (at 21:07), she was ordered back to port by Evan-Thomas.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">259</arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>went on to a long and illustrious career, serving also in<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>.<space/><italics>Warrior</italics>, on the other hand, was abandoned and sank the next day after her crew was taken off at 08:25 on 1 June by<space/><italics>Engadine</italics>, which towed the sinking armoured cruiser<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>during the night.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">319</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:InvincibleBlowingUpJutland1916.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Invincible'' blowing up after being struck by shells from ''Lutzow'' and ''Derfflinger''</part></link>As<space/><italics>Defence</italics><space/>sank and<space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>circled, at about 18:19, Hipper moved within range of Hood's 3rd Battlecruiser Squadron, but was still also within range of Beatty's ships. At first, visibility favoured the British:<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indomitable</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>hit<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>three times and<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>once,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">185–187</arg></template></extension><space/>while<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>quickly took 10 hits from<space/><italics>Lion</italics>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Inflexible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>, including two below-waterline hits forward by<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>that would ultimately doom Hipper's flagship.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">183</arg></template></extension><space/>But at 18:30,<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>abruptly appeared as a clear target before<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics>. The two German ships then fired three salvoes each at<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>, and sank her in 90 seconds. A<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>30.5</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>shell from the third salvo struck<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s Q-turret amidships, detonating the magazines below and causing her to blow up and sink. All but six of her crew of 1,032 officers and men, including Rear-Admiral Hood, were killed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">159</arg></template></extension><space/>Of the remaining British battlecruisers, only<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics><space/>received heavy-calibre hits at this time (two<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>30.5</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>by the battleship<space/><italics>Markgraf</italics>).<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics>, flooding forward and unable to communicate by radio, was now out of action and began to attempt to withdraw; therefore Hipper left his flagship and transferred to the torpedo boat<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>G39</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, hoping to board one of the other battlecruisers later.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Crossing the T</heading><paragraph>By 18:30, the main battle fleet action was joined for the first time, with Jellicoe effectively &quot;crossing Scheer's T&quot;. The officers on the lead German battleships, and Scheer himself, were taken completely by surprise when they emerged from drifting clouds of smoky mist to suddenly find themselves facing the massed firepower of the entire Grand Fleet main battle line, which they did not know was even at sea.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-621"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">621</arg></template></extension><space/>Jellicoe's flagship<space/><italics>Iron Duke</italics><space/>quickly scored seven hits on the lead German dreadnought,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>König</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">187–188</arg></template></extension><space/>but in this brief exchange, which lasted only minutes, as few as 10 of the Grand Fleet's 24 dreadnoughts actually opened fire. The Germans were hampered by poor visibility, in addition to being in an unfavourable tactical position, just as Jellicoe had intended. Realising he was heading into a death trap, Scheer ordered his fleet to turn and flee at 18:33. Under a pall of smoke and mist, Scheer's forces succeeded in disengaging by an expertly executed 180 turn in unison (&quot;battle about turn to starboard&quot;, German<space/><italics>Gefechtskehrtwendung nach Steuerbord</italics>), which was a well-practised emergency manoeuvre of the High Seas Fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">622</arg></template></extension><space/>Scheer declared:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>bquote</target><arg name="It was now obvious that we were confronted by a large portion of the English fleet. The entire arc stretching from north to east was a sea of fire. The flash from the muzzles of the guns was seen distinctly through the mist and smoke on the horizon, although the ships themselves were not distinguishable.<ref name">Massie-621/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Conscious of the risks to his capital ships posed by torpedoes, Jellicoe did not chase directly but headed south, determined to keep the High Seas Fleet west of him. Starting at 18:40, battleships at the rear of Jellicoe's line were in fact sighting and avoiding torpedoes, and at 18:54<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Marlborough</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was hit by a torpedo (probably from the disabled<space/><italics>Wiesbaden</italics>), which reduced her speed to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>16</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">167</arg></template></extension><space/>Meanwhile, Scheer, knowing that it was not yet dark enough to escape and that his fleet would suffer terribly in a stern chase, doubled back to the east at 18:55. In his memoirs he wrote, &quot;the manoeuvre would be bound to surprise the enemy, to upset his plans for the rest of the day, and if the blow fell heavily it would facilitate the breaking loose at night.&quot; But the turn to the east took his ships, again, directly towards Jellicoe's fully deployed battle line.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">624–625</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Simultaneously, the disabled British destroyer<space/><italics>HMS Shark</italics><space/>fought desperately against a group of four German torpedo boats and disabled<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V48</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>with gunfire, but was eventually torpedoed and sunk at 19:02 by the German destroyer<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>S54</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>.<space/><italics>Shark</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s<space/><link><target>Loftus William Jones</target><part>Captain Loftus Jones</part></link><space/>won the Victoria Cross for his heroism in continuing to fight against all odds.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">162</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Gefechtskehrtwendung</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>File:HMS Birmingham (1913) Jutland.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>HMS Birmingham (1913)</target><part>HMS ''Birmingham''</part></link><space/>under fire.</part></link>Commodore Goodenough's 2nd Light Cruiser Squadron dodged the fire of German battleships for a second time to re-establish contact with the High Seas Fleet shortly after 19:00. By 19:15, Jellicoe had crossed Scheer's &quot;T&quot; again. This time his arc of fire was tighter and deadlier, causing severe damage to the German battleships, particularly Rear-Admiral Behncke's leading 3rd Squadron (SMS<space/><italics>Knig</italics>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Grosser Kurfürst</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><italics>Markgraf</italics>, and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Kaiser</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>all being hit, along with<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Helgoland</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>of the 1st Squadron),<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-246"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">246</arg></template></extension><space/>while on the British side, only the battleship<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Colossus</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was hit (twice, by<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, but with little damage done).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">218</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At 19:17, for the second time in less than an hour, Scheer turned his outnumbered and out-gunned fleet to the west using the &quot;battle about turn&quot; (German:<space/><italics>Gefechtskehrtwendung</italics>), but this time it was executed only with difficulty, as the High Seas Fleet's lead squadrons began to lose formation under concentrated gunfire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">200–201</arg></template></extension><space/>To deter a British chase, Scheer ordered a major torpedo attack by his destroyers and a potentially sacrificial charge by Scouting Group I's four remaining battlecruisers. Hipper was still aboard the torpedo boat<space/><italics>G39</italics><space/>and was unable to command his squadron for this attack.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">197<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Therefore,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Derfflinger</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, under Captain Hartog, led the already badly damaged German battlecruisers directly into &quot;the greatest concentration of naval gunfire any fleet commander had ever faced&quot;, at ranges down to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>4</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-627-8"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">627–628</arg></template></extension><space/>In what became known as the &quot;death ride&quot;, all the battlecruisers except<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Moltke</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>were hit and further damaged, as 18 of the British battleships fired at them simultaneously.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-246"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">205</arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>had two main gun turrets destroyed. The crews of Scouting Group I suffered heavy casualties, but survived the pounding and veered away with the other battlecruisers once Scheer was out of trouble and the German destroyers were moving in to attack.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-627-8"></extension><space/>In this brief but intense portion of the engagement, from about 19:05 to about 19:30, the Germans sustained a total of 37 heavy hits while inflicting only two;<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>alone received 14.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Camp-246"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">220</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While his battlecruisers drew the fire of the British fleet, Scheer slipped away, laying smoke screens. Meanwhile, from about 19:16 to about 19:40, the British battleships were also engaging Scheer's torpedo boats, which executed several waves of torpedo attacks to cover his withdrawal. Jellicoe's ships turned away from the attacks and successfully evaded all 31 of the torpedoes launched at them though, in several cases, only just barely and sank the German destroyer<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>S35</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>. British light forces also sank<space/><italics>V48</italics>, which had previously been disabled by HMS<space/><italics>Shark</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">211–216</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">629–630</arg></template></extension><space/>This action, and the turn away, cost the British critical time and range in the last hour of daylight as Scheer intended, allowing him to get his heavy ships out of immediate danger.</paragraph><paragraph>The last major exchanges between capital ships in this battle took place just after sunset, from about 20:19 to about 20:35, as the surviving British battlecruisers caught up with their German counterparts, which were briefly relieved by Rear-Admiral Mauve's obsolete pre-dreadnoughts (the German 2nd Squadron).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">252–254</arg></template></extension><space/>The British received one heavy hit on<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics><space/>but scored five more on<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>and three on other German ships.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">272</arg></template></extension><space/>As twilight faded to night and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>King George V</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>exchanged a few final shots with<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Westfalen</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>neither side could have imagined that the only encounter between British and German dreadnoughts in the entire war was already concluded.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Night action and German withdrawal</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Night action at the Battle of Jutland</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At 21:00, Jellicoe, conscious of the Grand Fleet's deficiencies in night fighting, decided to try to avoid a major engagement until early dawn.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">635–636</arg></template></extension><space/>He placed a screen of cruisers and destroyers<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>behind his battle fleet to patrol the rear as he headed south to guard Scheer's expected escape route.<extension extension_name='ref'>Massie, p.637</extension><space/>In reality, Scheer opted to cross Jellicoe's wake and escape via<space/><link><target>Horns Reef</target></link>. Luckily for Scheer, most of the light forces in Jellicoe's rearguard failed to report the seven separate encounters with the German fleet during the night;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-645">Massie, p.645</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p.140-145</extension><space/>the very few radio reports that were sent to the British flagship were never received, possibly because the Germans were jamming British frequencies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">647</arg></template></extension><space/>Many of the destroyers failed to make the most of their opportunities to attack discovered ships, despite Jellicoe's expectations that the destroyer forces would, if necessary, be able to block the path of the German fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p.146</extension><space/>Jellicoe and his commanders did not understand that the furious gunfire and explosions to the north (seen and heard for hours by all the British battleships) indicated that the German heavy ships were breaking through the screen astern of the British fleet.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-645"></extension><space/>Instead, it was believed that the fighting was the result of night attacks by German destroyers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p. 159</extension><space/>The most powerful British ships of all (the 15-inch-gunned<space/><link><target>British 5th Battle Squadron</target><part>5th Battle Squadron</part></link>) directly observed German battleships crossing astern of them in action with British light forces, at ranges of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>or less, and gunners on HMS<space/><italics>Malaya</italics><space/>made ready to fire, but her captain declined,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">645–646</arg></template></extension><space/>deferring to the authority of Rear-Admiral Evan-Thomas and neither commander reported the sightings to Jellicoe, assuming that he could see for himself and that revealing the fleet's position by radio signals or gunfire was unwise.</paragraph><paragraph>While the nature of Scheer's escape, and Jellicoe's inaction, indicate the overall German superiority in night fighting, the results of the night action were no more clear-cut than were those of the battle as a whole. In the first of many surprise encounters by darkened ships at point-blank range,<space/><italics>Southampton</italics>, Commodore Goodenough's flagship, which had scouted so proficiently, was heavily damaged in action with a German Scouting Group composed of light cruisers, but managed to torpedo<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Frauenlob</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which went down at 22:23 with all hands (320 officers and men).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">639–640</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>From 23:20 to approximately 02:15, several British destroyer<space/><link><target>flotilla</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>launched torpedo attacks on the German battle fleet in a series of violent and chaotic engagements at extremely short range (often under<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>0.5</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-642-647"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">642–645, pp. 647–648</arg></template></extension><space/>At the cost of five destroyers sunk and some others damaged, they managed to torpedo the light cruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Rostock</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which sank several hours later, and the pre-dreadnought<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Pommern</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which blew up and sank with all hands (839 officers and men) at 03:10 during the last wave of attacks before dawn.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-642-647"></extension><space/>Three of the British destroyers collided in the chaos, and the German battleship<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Nassau</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>rammed the British destroyer<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Spitfire</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, blowing away most of the British ship's superstructure merely with the muzzle blast of its big guns, which could not be aimed low enough to hit the ship.<space/><italics>Nassau</italics><space/>was left with a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>11</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>hole in her side, reducing her maximum speed to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>kn</arg></template>, while the removed plating was left lying on<space/><italics>Spitfire</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s deck.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p. 142</extension><space/><italics>Spitfire</italics><space/>survived and made it back to port.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">643</arg></template></extension><space/>Another German cruiser,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Elbing</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>, was accidentally rammed by the dreadnought<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Posen</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and abandoned, sinking early the next day. Of the British destroyers,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Tipperary</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Ardent</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Fortune</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Sparrowhawk</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Turbulent</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>were lost during the night fighting.</paragraph><paragraph>Just after midnight on 1 June,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Thüringen</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and other German battleships sank<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Black Prince</arg><arg>1904</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>of the ill-fated 1st Cruiser Squadron, which had blundered into the German battle line. Deployed as part of a screening force several miles ahead of the main force of the Grand Fleet,<space/><italics>Black Prince</italics><space/>had lost contact in the darkness and took a position near what she thought was the British line. The Germans soon identified the new addition to its line and opened fire. Overwhelmed by point-blank gunfire,<space/><italics>Black Prince</italics><space/>blew up, (857 officers and men - all hands - were lost), as her squadron leader<space/><italics>Defence</italics><space/>had done hours earlier.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Analysis<space/></arg><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="pages">290</arg></template></extension><space/>Lost in the darkness, the battlecruisers<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Moltke</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>had similar point-blank encounters with the British battle line and were recognised, but were spared the fate of<space/><italics>Black Prince</italics><space/>when the captains of the British ships, again, declined to open fire, reluctant to reveal their fleet's position.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-651"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">651–652</arg></template></extension><space/>At 01:45, the sinking battlecruiser<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>fatally damaged by<space/><italics>Invincible</italics><space/>during the main action was torpedoed by the destroyer<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>G38</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>on orders of<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s Captain Viktor von Harder after the surviving crew of 1,150 transferred to destroyers that came alongside.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">650–651</arg></template></extension><space/>At 02:15, the German torpedo boat<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V4</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>suddenly had its bow blown off;<space/><italics>V2</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>V6</italics><space/>came alongside and took off the remaining crew, and the<space/><italics>V2</italics><space/>then sank the hulk. Since there was no enemy nearby, it was assumed that she had hit a mine or had been torpedoed by a submarine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tarrant_p222">Tarrant,<space/><italics>German Perspective</italics><space/>p245 (claimed), p222 (Arms and Armour paperback edition, 1997)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At 02:15, five British ships of the 13th Destroyer Flotilla under Captain James Uchtred Farie regrouped and headed south. At 02:25, they sighted the rear of the German line.<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Marksman</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>inquired of the leader<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Champion</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>as to whether he thought they were British or German ships. Answering that he thought they were German, Farie then veered off to the east and away from the German line. All but<space/><italics>Moresby</italics><space/>in the rear followed, as through the gloom she sighted what she thought were four pre-dreadnought battleships<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>nmi km</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>away. She hoisted a flag signal indicating that the enemy was to the west and then closed to firing range, letting off a torpedo set for high running at 02:37, then veering off to rejoin her flotilla. The four pre-dreadnought battleships were in fact two pre-dreadnoughts,<space/><italics>Schleswig-Holstein</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Schlesien</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, and the battlecruisers<space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics>.<space/><italics>Von der Tann</italics><space/>sighted the torpedo and was forced to steer sharply to starboard to avoid it as it passed close to her bows.<space/><italics>Moresby</italics><space/>rejoined<space/><italics>Champion</italics><space/>convinced she had scored a hit.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tarrant_p222"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, at 05:20, as Scheer's fleet was safely on its way home, the battleship<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Ostfriesland</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>struck a British mine on her starboard side, killing one man and wounding ten, but was able to make port.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">German Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="last">Tarrant<space/></arg><arg name="pages">259<space/></arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, critically damaged and very nearly sinking, barely survived the return voyage: after grounding and taking on even more water on the evening of 1 June, she had to be assisted stern first into port, where she dropped anchor at 07:30 on the morning of 2 June.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">German Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="pages">260–261</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Germans were helped in their escape by the failure of the British Admiralty in London to pass on seven critical radio intercepts obtained by naval intelligence indicating the true position, course and intentions of the High Seas Fleet during the night.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">6342</arg></template></extension><space/>One message was transmitted to Jellicoe at 23:15 that accurately reported the German fleet's course and speed as of 21:14. However, the erroneous signal from earlier in the day that reported the German fleet still in port, and an intelligence signal received at 22:45 giving another unlikely position for the German fleet, had reduced his confidence in intelligence reports. Had the other messages been forwarded, which confirmed the information received at 23:15, or had British ships reported accurately sightings and engagements with German destroyers, cruisers and battleships, then Jellicoe could have altered course to intercept Scheer at the Horns Reef. The unsent intercepted messages had been duly filed by the junior officer left on duty that night, who failed to appreciate their significance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p.148-151</extension><space/>By the time Jellicoe finally learned of Scheer's whereabouts at 04:15, the German was too far away to catch and it was clear that the battle could no longer be resumed.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Outcome</heading><heading level='3'>Reporting</heading><paragraph>At midday on 2 June, German authorities released a press statement claiming a victory, including the destruction of a battleship, two battlecruisers, two armoured cruisers, a light cruiser, a submarine and several destroyers, for the loss of<space/><italics>Pommern</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Wiesbaden</italics>. News that<space/><italics>Lutzow</italics>,<space/><italics>Elbing</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Rostock</italics><space/>had been scuttled was withheld, on the grounds this information would not be known to the enemy. The victory of the Skagerrak was celebrated in the press, children were given a holiday and the nation celebrated. The Kaiser announced a new chapter in world history. Post-war, the official German history hailed the battle as a victory and it continued to be celebrated until after World War II.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tarrant p.274-276</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Britain, the first official news came from German wireless broadcasts. Ships began to arrive in port, their crews sending messages to friends and relatives both of their survival and the loss of some 6,000 others. Authorities considered suppressing the news, but it had already spread widely. Some crews coming ashore found rumours had already reported them dead to relatives, while others were jeered for the defeat they had suffered. At 19:00 on 2 June, the Admiralty released a statement based on information from Jellicoe containing the bare news of losses on each side. The following day British newspapers reported a German victory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Steel &amp; Hart p.418-420</extension><space/>The<space/><italics><link><target>Daily Mirror</target></link></italics><space/>described the German Director of the Naval Department telling the<space/><italics>Reichstag</italics>: &quot;The result of the fighting is a significant success for our forces against a much stronger adversary&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBCMirror"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/worldwars/wwone/mirror03_06.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Daily Mirror Headlines: The Battle of Jutland, Published 3&nbsp;June&nbsp;1916<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC – History</arg></template></extension><space/>The British population was shocked that the long anticipated battle had been a victory for Germany. On 3 June, the Admiralty issued a further statement expanding on German losses, and another the following day with exaggerated claims. However, on 7 June the German admission of the losses of<space/><italics>Lutzow</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Rostock</italics><space/>started to redress the sense of the battle as a loss. International perception of the battle began to change towards a qualified British victory, the German attempt to change the balance of power in the North Sea having been repulsed. In July, bad news from the Somme campaign swept concern over Jutland from the British consciousness.<extension extension_name='ref'>Steele &amp; Hart p, 421422</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Assessments</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:SMS Seydlitz damage.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>275px</part><part>SMS ''Seydlitz'' was heavily damaged in the battle, hit by twenty-one main calibre shells, several secondary calibre and one torpedo. 98 men were killed and 55 injured.</part></link>At Jutland, the Germans, with a 99-strong fleet, sank<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>115000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of British ships, while a 151-strong British fleet sank<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>62000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of German ships. The British lost 6,094 seamen; the Germans 2,551. Several other ships were badly damaged, such as<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Lion</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Seydlitz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>As of the summer of 1916, the High Seas Fleet's strategy was to whittle away the numerical advantage of the Royal Navy by bringing its full strength to bear against isolated squadrons of enemy capital ships whilst declining to be drawn into a general fleet battle until it had achieved something resembling parity in heavy ships. In tactical terms, the High Seas Fleet had clearly inflicted significantly greater losses on the Grand Fleet than it had suffered itself at Jutland and the Germans never had any intention of attempting to hold the site of the battle,<extension extension_name='ref' name="suth"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Sutherland & Canwell<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Battle of Jutland<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pen & Sword<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84415-529-3</arg></template></extension><space/>so some historians support the German claim of victory at Jutland.</paragraph><paragraph>However, Scheer seems to have quickly realised that further battles with a similar rate of attrition would exhaust the High Seas Fleet long before it reduced the Grand Fleet. Further, after the 19 August advance was nearly intercepted by the Grand Fleet, he no longer believed that it would be possible to trap a single squadron of Royal Navy warships without having the Grand Fleet intervene before he could return to port. Therefore, the High Seas Fleet abandoned its forays into the North Sea and turned its attention to the Baltic for most of 1917 whilst Scheer switched tactics against Britain to unrestricted submarine warfare in the Atlantic.</paragraph><paragraph>At a strategic level, the outcome has been the subject of a huge amount of literature with no clear consensus. The battle was widely viewed as indecisive in the immediate aftermath and this view remains influential.</paragraph><paragraph>Despite numerical superiority, the British had been disappointed in their hopes for a decisive victory comparable to<space/><link><target>Battle of Trafalgar</target><part>Trafalgar</part></link><space/>and the objective of the influential strategic doctrines of<space/><link><target>Alfred Mahan</target></link>. The High Seas Fleet survived as a<space/><link><target>fleet in being</target></link>. Most of its losses were made good within a month even<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>, the most badly damaged ship to survive the battle, was repaired by October and officially back in service by November. However, the Germans had failed in their objective of destroying a substantial portion of the British Fleet, and no progress had been made towards the goal of allowing the High Seas Fleet to operate in the Atlantic Ocean.</paragraph><paragraph>Subsequently, there has been considerable support for the view of Jutland as a strategic victory for the British. While the British had not destroyed the German fleet and had lost more ships than their enemy, the Germans had retreated to harbour; at the end of the battle the British were in command of the area. The German fleet would only sortie into the North Sea thrice more, with a<space/><link><target>Action of 19 August 1916</target><part>raid on 19 August</part></link>, one in October 1916 and another in April 1918. Apart from these three abortive operations the High Seas Fleet unwilling to risk another encounter with the British fleet confined its activities to the Baltic Sea for the remainder of the war. The British, for their part, also abandoned seeking a decisive action following the 19 August operation; Jellicoe issued an order prohibiting the Grand Fleet from steaming south of the line of Horns Reef owing to the threat of mines and U-boats.<extension extension_name='ref'>Massie,<space/><italics>Castles</italics>, p. 684</extension><space/>A German naval expert, writing publicly about Jutland in November 1918, commented, &quot;Our Fleet losses were severe. On 1 June 1916, it was clear to every thinking person that this battle must, and would be, the last one&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.206 citing Captain Persius,<space/><link><target>Berliner Tageblatt</target></link>, 18 November 1918</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Marynarz Wilhelmshaven SMS Westfalen.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>162px</part><part>A crew member of SMS ''Westfalen''</part></link>At the end of the battle, the British had maintained their numerical superiority and had 23 dreadnoughts ready and four battlecruisers still able to fight, while the Germans had only 10 dreadnoughts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-665"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">665</arg></template></extension><space/>One month after the battle, the Grand Fleet was stronger than it had been before sailing to Jutland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-665"></extension><space/><italics>Warspite</italics><space/>was dry docked at Rosyth, returning to the fleet on 22 July, while<space/><italics>Malaya</italics><space/>was repaired in the floating dock at Invergordon, returning to duty on 11 July.<space/><italics>Barham</italics><space/>was docked for a month at Devenport before undergoing speed trials and returning to Scapa on 8 July.<space/><italics>Princess Royal</italics><space/>stayed initially at Rosyth but transferred to dry dock at Portsmouth before returning to duty at Rosyth 21 July.<space/><italics>Tiger</italics><space/>was dry docked at Rosyth and ready for service 2 July.<space/><italics>Queen Elizabeth</italics>,<space/><italics>Emperor of India</italics><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMAS</target><arg>Australia</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, which had been undergoing maintenance at the time of the battle, returned to the fleet immediately, followed shortly after by<space/><italics>Resolution</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Ramillies</italics>.<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>initially remained ready for sea duty despite the damaged turret, then underwent a month's repairs in July when Q turret was removed temporarily and replaced in September.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell p.335</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A third view, presented in a number of recent evaluations, is that Jutland, the last major fleet action between battleships, illustrated the irrelevance of battleship fleets following the development of the submarine, mine and torpedo.<extension extension_name='ref' name="isbn0-14-101155-6"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kennedy<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Rise and Fall<space/></arg><arg name="pages">257</arg></template></extension><space/>In this view, the most important consequence of Jutland was the decision of the Germans to engage in unrestricted submarine warfare. Although large numbers of battleships were constructed in the decades between the wars, it has been argued that this outcome reflected the social dominance among naval decision-makers of battleship advocates who constrained technological choices to fit traditional paradigms of fleet action.<extension extension_name='ref' name="isbn0-8018-6486-0"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">McBride, William Leon<space/></arg><arg name="title">Technological change and the United States Navy, 1865–1945<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Johns Hopkins University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Baltimore<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-8018-6486-0<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Battleships played a relatively minor role in World War II, in which the aircraft carrier emerged as the dominant offensive weapon of naval warfare.<extension extension_name='ref' name="isbn1-57488-663-0"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Polmar, Norman<space/></arg><arg name="title">Aircraft Carriers: A History of Carrier Aviation and Its Influence on World Events, Volume 1: 1909–1945<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Potomac Books<space/></arg><arg name="location">Washington<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-57488-663-0<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>British self-critique</heading><paragraph>The official British Admiralty examination of the Grand Fleet's performance recognised two main problems:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>British armour-piercing shells exploded outside the German armour rather than penetrating and exploding within. As a result, some German ships with only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>-thick armour survived hits from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>projectiles. Had these shells penetrated the armour and then exploded, German losses would probably have been far greater.</listitem><listitem>Communication between ships and the British commander-in-chief were comparatively poor. For most of the battle, Jellicoe had no idea where the German ships were, even though British ships were in contact. They failed to report enemy positions, contrary to the Grand Fleet's Battle Plan. Some of the most important signalling was carried out solely by flag instead of wireless or using redundant methods to ensure communicationsa questionable procedure, given the mixture of haze and smoke that obscured the battlefield, and a foreshadowing of similar failures by habit-bound and conservatively minded professional officers of rank to take advantage of new technology in World War II.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Shell performance</heading><paragraph>German<space/><link><target>Armour-piercing shot and shell</target><part>armour-piercing shells</part></link><space/>were far more effective than the British ones, which often failed to penetrate heavy armour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pp. 386387</extension><space/>The issue particularly concerned shells striking at oblique angles, which became increasingly the case at long range.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.170</extension><space/>Germany had adopted<space/><link><target>trinitrotoluene</target></link><space/>(TNT) as the explosive filler for artillery shells in 1902, while the United Kingdom was still using a<space/><link><target>picric acid</target></link><space/>mixture (Lyddite). The shock of impact of a shell against armour often prematurely detonated Lyddite in advance of<space/><link><target>fuze</target></link><space/>function while TNT detonation could be delayed until after the shell had penetrated and the fuze had functioned in the vulnerable area behind the armour plate.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brown, pp.151152</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The issue of poorly performing shells had been known to Jellicoe, who as Third Sea Lord from 1908 to 1910 had ordered new shells to be designed. However, the matter had not been followed through after his posting to sea and new shells had never been thoroughly tested.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Castles' p.61.</extension><space/>Beatty discovered the problem at a party aboard<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>a short time after the battle, when a Swedish Naval officer was present. He had recently visited Berlin, where the German navy had scoffed at how British shells had broken up on their ships' armour.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Castles668">'Castles' p. 668</extension><space/>The question of shell effectiveness had also been raised after the<space/><link><target>Battle of Dogger Bank (1915)</target><part>Battle of Dogger Bank</part></link>, but no action had been taken.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Marder">Marder III p.171</extension><space/>Hipper later commented, &quot;It was nothing but the poor quality of their bursting charges which saved us from disaster&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>'Castles' p. 671 citing Marder Vol. III p.81</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Admiral Dreyer, writing later about the battle, during which he had been captain of the British flagship<space/><italics>Iron Duke</italics>, estimated that effective shells as later introduced would have led to the sinking of six more German capital ships, based upon the actual number of hits achieved in the battle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p. 169</extension><space/>The system of testing shells, which remained in use up to 1944, meant that, statistically, a batch of shells of which 70% were faulty stood an even chance of being accepted. Indeed, even shells that failed this relatively mild test had still been issued to ships. Analysis of the test results afterwards by the Ordnance Board suggested the likelihood that 3070% of shells would not have passed the standard penetration test specified by the Admiralty.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Marder"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Efforts to replace the shells were initially resisted by the Admiralty, and action was not taken until Jellicoe became First Sea Lord in December 1916. As an initial response, the worst of the existing shells were withdrawn from ships in early 1917 and replaced from reserve supplies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III, p.215</extension><space/>New shells were designed, but did not arrive until April 1918, and were never used in action.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Castles668"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Battlecruiser losses</heading><paragraph>The British battlecruisers were designed to chase and destroy enemy cruisers from a range at which these ships could not reply. They were not designed to be<space/><link><target>ship of the line</target><part>ships of the line</part></link><space/>and exchange<space/><link><target>broadside</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with the enemy. Although one German and three British battlecruisers were sunk, none of them were destroyed by enemy shells penetrating the belt armour and detonating the magazines; each of the British battlecruisers was penetrated through a turret roof and her magazines ignited by flash fires passing through the turret and shell-handling rooms.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">666–667</arg></template></extension><space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>sustained 24 hits and her flooding could not be contained. She was eventually sunk by her escorts' torpedoes after her crew had been safely removed.<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics><space/>sustained 22 hits each but reached port (although in<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics>'s case only just).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">666</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The disturbing feature of the battlecruiser action is the fact that five German battlecruisers engaging six British vessels of this class, supported after the first twenty minutes, although at great range, by the fire of four battleships of the "Queen Elizabeth" class, were yet able to sink 'Queen Mary' and 'Indefatigable'....The facts which contributed to the British losses, first, were the indifferent armour protection of our battlecruisers, particularly as regards turret armour, and, second, deck plating and the disadvantage under which our vessels laboured in regard to the light.</arg><arg>Sir John Jellicoe</arg><arg>''Jellicoe's official despatch''</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Jellicoe and Beatty, as well as other senior officers, gave an impression that the loss of the battlecruisers was caused by weak armour, despite reports by two committees and earlier statements by Jellicoe and other senior officers that Cordite and its management were to blame. This led to calls for armour to be increased, and an additional<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>was placed over the relatively thin decks above magazines. To compensate for the increase in weight, ships had to carry correspondingly less fuel, water and other supplies. Whether or not thin deck armour was a potential weakness of British ships, the battle provided no evidence that it was the case. At least amongst the surviving ships, no enemy shell was found to have penetrated deck armour anywhere.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.218</extension><space/>The design of the new battlecruiser<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Hood</arg><arg>51</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>(which had started building at the time of the battle) was altered to give her<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>5000</arg><arg>LT</arg><arg>t</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of additional armour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p. 219</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Ammunition handling</heading><paragraph>British and German<space/><link><target>propellant</target></link><space/>charges differed in packaging, handling, and chemistry. The British propellant was of two types, MK1 and MD. The Mark 1 cordite had a formula of 37% nitrocellulose, 58% nitroglycerine, and 5% petroleum jelly. It was a good propellant but burned hot and caused an erosion problem in gun barrels. The petroleum jelly served as both a lubricant and a stabiliser. Cordite MD was developed to reduce barrel wear, its formula being 65% nitrocellulose, 30% nitroglycerine, and 5% petroleum jelly. While cordite MD solved the gun-barrel erosion issue, it did nothing to improve its storage properties, which were poor. Cordite was very sensitive to variations of temperature, and acid propagation/cordite deterioration would take place at a very rapid rate. Cordite MD also shed micro-dust particles of nitrocellulose and iron pyrite.<extension extension_name='ref' name="navweaps.com"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.navweaps.com/index_tech/tech-100.htm</arg><arg name="title">Naval Propellants - A Brief Overview</arg><arg name="author">Tony DiGiulian</arg><arg name="publisher">navweaps.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>While cordite propellant was manageable, it required a vigilant gunnery officer, strict cordite lot control, and frequent testing of the cordite lots in the ships' magazines.<extension extension_name='ref' name="worldwar1.co.uk"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.worldwar1.co.uk/grant.htm</arg><arg name="title">Battle of Jutland, Memoir - World War 1 Naval Combat</arg><arg name="publisher">worldwar1.co.uk</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 May 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>British<space/><link><target>cordite</target></link><space/>propellant (when uncased and exposed in the silk bag) tended to burn violently, causing uncontrollable &quot;flash fires&quot; when ignited by nearby shell hits. In 1945, a test was conducted by the U.S.N. Bureau of Ordnance (Bulletin of Ordnance Information, No.245, pp.&amp;nbsp;5460)<extension extension_name='ref' name="warship"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.warship.org/loss_of_hms_hood__part_3.htm#68</arg><arg name="title">Loss of HMS Hood&nbsp; Part 3</arg><arg name="publisher">warship.org</arg><arg name="accessdate">27 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>testing the sensitivity of Cordite to then-current U.S. Naval propellant powders against a measurable and repeatable flash source. It found that cordite would ignite at 530&amp;nbsp;mm/22&quot; from the flash and the current U.S. powder at 120&amp;nbsp;mm, /5&quot; the U.S. flashless powder at 25&amp;nbsp;mm./1&quot; This meant that about 75 times the propellant would immediately ignite when exposed to flash, as compared to the U.S. powder. British ships had inadequate protection against these flash fires. German propellant (<italics>RP C/12</italics>, handled in brass cartridge cases) was less vulnerable and less volatile in composition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pp. 377378</extension><space/>German propellants show that they were not that different in composition from corditewith one major exception:<space/><link><target>centralite</target></link>. This was symmetrical Diethyl Diphenyl Urea, which served as a stabiliser that was superior to the petroleum jelly used in British practice. It stored better and burned but did not explode. Stored and used in brass cases, it proved much less sensitive to flash. RP C/12 64.13% nitrocellulose, 29.77% nitroglycerine, 5.75% centralite, 0.25% magnesium oxide and 0.10% graphite.<extension extension_name='ref' name="navweaps.com"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Royal Navy Battle Cruiser Fleet had also emphasised speed in ammunition handling over established safety protocol. In practice drills, cordite could not be supplied to the guns rapidly enough through the hoists and hatches. To bring up the propellant in good time to load for the next broadside, many safety doors were kept open that should have been shut to safeguard against flash fires. Bags of cordite were also stocked and kept locally, creating a total breakdown of safety design features. By staging charges in the chambers between the gun turret and magazine, the Royal Navy enhanced their rate of fire but left their ships vulnerable to chain reaction ammunition fires and magazine explosions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="worldwar1.co.uk"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Campbell, pp. 371372</extension><space/>This 'bad safety habit' carried over into real battle practices.<extension extension_name='ref' name="worldwar1.co.uk"></extension><space/>Furthermore, the doctrine of a high rate of fire also led to the decision in 1913 to increase the supply of shells and cordite held on the British ships by 50%, for fear of running out of ammunition. When this exceeded the capacity of the ships' magazines, cordite was stored in insecure places.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Lambert<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bloody Ships<space/></arg><arg name="pages">36</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The British cordite charges were stored two silk bags to a metal cylindrical container, with a 16-oz gunpowder igniter charge, which was covered with a thick paper wad, four charges being used on each projectile. The gun crews were removing the charges from their containers and removing the paper covering over the gunpowder igniter charges. The effect of having eight loads at the ready was to have<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>4</arg><arg>ST</arg><arg>kg</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>of exposed explosive, with each charge leaking small amounts of gunpowder from the igniter bags. In effect, the gun crews had laid an explosive train from the turret to the magazines, and one shell hit to a battlecruiser turret was enough to end a ship.<extension extension_name='ref'>British Battlecruisers 191418, Lawrence Burr, Tony Bryan p.41-42</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A diving expedition during the summer of 2003 provided corroboration of this practice. It examined the wrecks of<space/><italics>Invincible</italics>,<space/><italics>Queen Mary</italics>,<space/><italics>Defence</italics>, and<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>to investigate the cause of the British ships' tendency to suffer from internal explosions. From this evidence, a major part of the blame may be laid on lax handling of the cordite propellant for the shells of the main guns. The wreck of the<space/><italics>Queen Mary</italics><space/>revealed cordite containers stacked in the working chamber of the X turret instead of the magazine.<extension extension_name='ref'>British Battlecruisers 191418, Lawrence Burr, Tony Bryan p.43</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There was a further difference in the propellant itself. While the German<space/><italics>RP C/12</italics><space/>burned when exposed to fire, it did not explode, as opposed to cordite.<space/><italics>RP C/12</italics><space/>was extensively studied by the British and, after World War I, would form the basis of the later Cordite SC.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNGER_projectiles.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">German Ammunition, Guns and Mountings Definitions<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20080517110752/http://www.navweaps.com/Weapons/WNGER_projectiles.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>17 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The memoirs of Alexander Grant, Gunner on<space/><italics>Lion</italics>, suggest that some British officers were aware of the dangers of careless handling of cordite:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>With the introduction of cordite to replace powder for firing guns, regulations regarding the necessary precautions for handling explosives became unconsciously considerably relaxed, even I regret to say, to a dangerous degree throughout the Service. The gradual lapse in the regulations on board ship seemed to be due to two factors. First, cordite is a much safer explosive to handle than gun-powder. Second, but more important, the altered construction of the magazines on board led to a feeling of false security....The iron or steel deck, the disappearance of the wood lining, the electric lights fitted inside, the steel doors, open because there was now no chute for passing cartridges out; all this gave officers and men a comparative easiness of mind regarding the precautions necessary with explosive material.<ref>[http://www.worldwar1.co.uk/grant.htm Memoir of Gunnery Officer Alexander Grant]</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Grant had already introduced measures onboard<space/><italics>Lion</italics><space/>to limit the number of cartridges kept outside the magazine and to ensure doors were kept closed, probably contributing to her survival.<extension extension_name='ref'>marder III p.174</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 5 June 1916, the First Lord of the Admiralty advised Cabinet Members that the three battlecruisers had been lost due to unsafe cordite management.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lawrence Burr p.40">British Battlecruisers 191418, Lawrence Burr, Tony Bryan p.40</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On 22 November 1916, following detailed interviews of the survivors of the destroyed battlecruisers, the Third Sea Lord, Rear Admiral Tudor, issued a report detailing the stacking of charges by the gun crews in the handling rooms to speed up loading of the guns.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lawrence Burr p.40"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After the battle, the B.C.F. Gunnery Committee issued a report (at the command of Admiral David Beatty) advocating immediate changes in flash protection and charge handling. It reported, among other things, that:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Some vent plates in magazines allowed flash into the magazines and should be retro-fitted to a new standard.</listitem><listitem>Bulkheads in HMS<space/><italics>Lion</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s magazine showed buckling from fire under pressure (overpressure) despite being flooded and therefore supported by water pressure and must be made stronger.</listitem><listitem>Doors opening inward to magazines were an extreme danger.</listitem><listitem>Current designs of turrets could not eliminate flash from shell bursts in the turret from reaching the handling rooms.</listitem><listitem>Ignition pads must not be attached to charges but instead be placed just before ramming.</listitem><listitem>Better methods must be found for safe storage of ready charges than the current method.</listitem><listitem>Some method for rapidly drowning charges already in the handling path must be devised.</listitem><listitem>Handling scuttles (special flash-proof fittings for moving propellant charges through ship's bulkheads), designed to handle overpressure, must be fitted.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.dreadnoughtproject.org/tfs/index.php/Advance_Report_of_B.C.F._Gunnery_Committee Advance Report of B.C.F. Gunnery Committee</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The United States Navy in 1939 had quantities of Cordite N, a Canadian propellant that was much improved, yet its<space/><link><target>Bureau of Ordnance</target></link><space/>objected strongly to its use onboard U.S. warships, considering it unsuitable as a naval propellant due to its inclusion of nitroglycerin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="navweaps.com"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Gunnery</heading><paragraph>British gunnery control systems, based on<space/><link><target>Frederic Charles Dreyer#Dreyer Fire Control Table</target><part>Dreyer tables</part></link>, were well in advance of the German ones, as demonstrated by the proportion of main calibre hits made on the German fleet. Because of its demonstrated advantages, it was installed on ships progressively as the war went on, had been fitted to a majority of British capital ships by May, 1916, and had been installed on the main guns of all but two of the Grand Fleet's capital ships.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooks p.224</extension><space/>The Royal Navy used centralised<space/><link><target>fire control system</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on their capital ships, directed from a point high up on the ship where the fall of shells could best be seen, utilising a director sight for both training and elevating the guns. In contrast, the German battlecruisers controlled the fire of turrets using a training-only director, which also did not fire the guns at once. The rest of the German capital ships were without even this innovation. German range-finding equipment was generally superior to the British<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>9</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>FT24, as its operators were trained to a higher standard due to the complexity of the Zeiss<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>range finders. Their<space/><link><target>Stereoscopic rangefinder</target><part>stereoscopic</part></link><space/>design meant that in certain conditions they could range on a target enshrouded by smoke.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooks, pp. 221222</extension><space/>The German equipment was not superior in range to the British<space/><link><target>Barr &amp; Stroud</target></link><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>rangefinder found in the newest British capital ships, and, unlike the British range finders, the German range takers had to be replaced as often as every thirty minutes, as their eyesight became impaired, affecting the ranges provided to their gunnery equipment.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brooks, p. 223</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The results of the battle confirmed the value of firing guns by centralised director. The battle prompted the Royal Navy to install director firing systems in cruisers and destroyers, where it had not thus far been used, and for secondary armament on battleships.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.213-214</extension></paragraph><paragraph>German ships were considered to have been quicker in determining the correct range to targets, thus obtaining an early advantage. The British used a 'bracket system', whereby a salvo was fired at the best-guess range and, depending where it landed, the range was progressively corrected up or down until successive shots were landing in front of and behind the enemy. The Germans used a 'ladder system', whereby an initial volley of three shots at different ranges was used, with the centre shot at the best-guess range. The ladder system allowed the gunners to get ranging information from the three shots more quickly than the bracket system, which required waiting between shots to see how the last had landed. British ships adopted the German system.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.166, 214</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It was determined that<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>9</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>range finders of the sort issued to most British ships were not adequate at long range and did not perform as well as the<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>15</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>range finders on some of the most modern ships. In 1917, range finders of base lengths of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>30</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>were introduced on the battleships to improve accuracy.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder p. 215</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Signalling</heading><paragraph>Throughout the battle, British ships experienced difficulties with communications, whereas the Germans did not suffer such problems. The British preferred signalling using ship-to-ship flag and lamp signals, avoiding wireless, whereas the Germans used wireless successfully. One conclusion drawn was that flag signals were not a satisfactory way to control the fleet. Experience using lamps, particularly at night when issuing challenges to other ships, demonstrated this was an excellent way to advertise your precise location to an enemy, inviting a reply by gunfire. Recognition signals by lamp, once seen, could also easily be copied in future engagements.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.175-176</extension></paragraph><paragraph>British ships both failed to report engagements with the enemy but also, in the case of cruisers and destroyers, failed to actively seek out the enemy. A culture had arisen within the fleet of not acting without orders, which could prove fatal when any circumstances prevented orders being sent or received. Commanders failed to engage the enemy because they believed other, more senior officers must also be aware of the enemy nearby, and would have given orders to act if this was expected. Wireless, the most direct way to pass messages across the fleet (although it was being jammed by German ships), was avoided either for perceived reasons of not giving away the presence of ships or for fear of cluttering up the airwaves with unnecessary reports.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.176-178</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Fleet Standing Orders</heading><paragraph>Naval operations were governed by standing orders issued to all the ships. These attempted to set out what ships should do in all circumstances, particularly in situations where ships would have to react without referring to higher authority, or when communications failed. A number of changes were introduced as a result of experience gained in the battle.</paragraph><paragraph>A new signal was introduced instructing squadron commanders to act independently as they thought best while still supporting the main fleet, particularly for use when circumstances would make it difficult to send detailed orders. The description stressed that this was not intended to be the only time commanders might take independent action, but was intended to make plain times when they definitely should. Similarly, instructions on what to do if the fleet was instructed to take evasive action against torpedoes were amended. Commanders were given discretion that if their part of the fleet was not under immediate attack, they should continue engaging the enemy rather than turning away with the rest of the fleet. In this battle, when the fleet turned away from Scheer's destroyer attack covering his retreat, not all the British ships had been affected, and could have continued to engage the enemy.<extension extension_name='ref'>MarderIII p.222</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A number of opportunities to attack enemy ships by torpedo had presented themselves but had been missed. All ships, not just the destroyers armed principally with torpedoes but also battleships, were reminded that they carried torpedoes intended to be used whenever an opportunity arose. Destroyers were instructed to close the enemy fleet to fire torpedoes as soon as engagements between the main ships on either side would keep enemy guns busy directed at larger targets. Destroyers should also be ready to immediately engage enemy destroyers if they should launch an attack, endeavouring to disrupt their chances of launching torpedoes and keep them away from the main fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.224-225</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To add some flexibility when deploying for attack, a new signal was provided for deploying the fleet to the centre, rather than as previously only either to left or right of the standard closed-up formation for travelling. The fast and powerful 5th Battle Squadron was moved to the front of the cruising formation so it would have the option of deploying left or right depending upon the enemy position. In the event of engagements at night, although the fleet still preferred to avoid night fighting, a destroyer and cruiser squadron would be specifically detailed to seek out the enemy and launch destroyer attacks.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marder III p.226</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Controversy</heading><paragraph>At the time, Jellicoe was criticised for his caution and for allowing Scheer to escape.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-631">Massie, p. 631</extension><space/>Beatty, in particular, was convinced that Jellicoe had missed a tremendous opportunity to annihilate the High Seas Fleet<extension extension_name='ref'>Massie, p. 670</extension><space/>and win what would amount to another<space/><link><target>battle of Trafalgar</target><part>Trafalgar</part></link>. Jellicoe was promoted away from active command to become First Sea Lord, the professional head of the Royal Navy, while Beatty replaced him as commander of the Grand Fleet.</paragraph><paragraph>The controversy raged within the navy and in public for about a decade after the war. Criticism focused on Jellicoe's decision at 19:15. Scheer had ordered his cruisers and destroyers forward in a torpedo attack to cover the turning away of his battleships. Jellicoe chose to turn to the south-east, and so keep out of range of the torpedoes. If, instead, he had turned to the west, could his ships have dodged the torpedoes and destroyed the German fleet?<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-631"></extension><space/>Supporters of Jellicoe, including the historian<space/><link><target>Cyril Falls</target></link>, pointed to the folly of risking defeat in battle when you already have<space/><link><target>command of the sea</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-675"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">675</arg></template></extension><space/>Jellicoe himself, in a letter to the Admiralty months before the battle, had stated that he intended to turn his fleet away from any mass torpedo attack (that being the universally accepted proper tactical response to such attacks, practised by all the major navies of the world<extension extension_name='ref' name="Massie-675"></extension>), and that in the event of a fleet engagement in which the enemy turned away he would assume that the intention was to draw him over mines or submarines and that he would decline to be so drawn. The Admiralty approved this plan and expressed full confidence in Jellicoe at the time (October 1914).<extension extension_name='ref'>Massie, p. 632</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The stakes were high, the pressure on Jellicoe immense, and his caution certainly understandable. His judgement might have been that even 90% odds in favour were not good enough to bet the British Empire. The former<space/><link><target>First Lord of the Admiralty</target></link><space/><link><target>Winston Churchill</target></link><space/>said of the battle that Jellicoe &quot;was the only man on either side who could have lost the war in an afternoon.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="page">681</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The criticism of Jellicoe also fails to sufficiently credit Scheer, who was determined to preserve his fleet by avoiding the full British battle line, and who showed great skill in effecting his escape.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="page">672</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Beatty's actions</heading><paragraph>On the other hand, some of Jellicoe's supporters condemned the actions of Beatty for the British failure to achieve a complete victory.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">670, 679</arg></template></extension><space/>Although Beatty was undeniably brave, his mismanagement of the initial encounter with Hipper's squadron and the High Seas Fleet cost considerable advantage in the first hours of the battle.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">673–674</arg></template></extension><space/>His most glaring failure was in not providing Jellicoe with periodic information on the position, course, and speed of the High Seas Fleet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">674</arg></template></extension><space/>Beatty, aboard the battlecruiser<space/><italics>Lion</italics>, left behind the four fast battleships of the 5th Battle Squadron the most powerful warships in the world at the time engaging with six ships when better control would have given him 10 against Hipper's five. Though Beatty's larger<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>13.5</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>guns out-ranged Hipper's<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>11</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>12</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>guns by thousands of yards, Beatty held his fire for 10 minutes and closed the German squadron until within range of the Germans' superior gunnery, under lighting conditions that favoured the Germans.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Castles<space/></arg><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="pages">589–590</arg></template></extension><space/>Most of the British losses in tonnage occurred in Beatty's force.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Losses</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Seeschlacht Vergleich.jpg</target><part>upright</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>1916 German propaganda postcard, comparing nearly accurate data of the adversaries' losses.</part></link><template><target>See also</target><arg>Damage to major ships at the Battle of Jutland</arg></template>The total loss of life was 9,823 men, of which the British losses were 6,784 and German losses were 3,039.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brewers Dictionary of 20th Century Phrase and Fable</extension><space/>No dreadnoughts were destroyed on either side during the battle.</paragraph><heading level='3'>British</heading><paragraph>113,300<space/><link><target>long ton</target><part>ton</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>sunk:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nasmith, pg261"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Battlecruisers<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>1909</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Queen Mary</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Armoured cruisers<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Black Prince</arg><arg>1904</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Warrior</arg><arg>1905</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Defence</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Flotilla leaders<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Tipperary</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Destroyers<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shark</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Sparrowhawk</arg><arg>1912</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Turbulent</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Ardent</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Fortune</arg><arg>1913</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nomad</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nestor</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>German</heading><paragraph>62,300<space/><link><target>long ton</target><part>ton</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>sunk:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nasmith, pg261"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Battlecruiser<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Lützow</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Pre-Dreadnought<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Pommern</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Light cruisers<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Frauenlob</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Elbing</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Rostock</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>Wiesbaden</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Destroyers (Heavy torpedo-boats)<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V48</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>S35</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V27</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V4</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>SMS</target><arg>V29</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Selected honours</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Victoria Cross</target></link><space/>is the highest military decoration awarded for valour &quot;in the face of the enemy&quot; to members of the<space/><link><target>British Empire</target></link><space/>armed forces. The<space/><link><target>Pour le Mrite</target><part>Ordre pour le Mrite</part></link><space/>was the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Prussia</target></link><space/>and consequently the<space/><link><target>German Empire</target></link>'s highest military order until the end of the<space/><link><target>First World War</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pour le Mrite</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Franz von Hipper</target><part>Franz Hipper</part></link><space/>(<template><target>SMS</target><arg>Lützow</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Reinhard Scheer</target></link><space/>(<template><target>SMS</target><arg>Friedrich der Grosse</arg><arg>1911</arg><arg>6</arg></template>)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Victoria Cross</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Edward Bingham</target><part>The Hon. Edward Barry Stewart Bingham</part></link><space/>(<template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nestor</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Jack Cornwell</target><part>John Travers Cornwell</part></link><space/>(<template><target>HMS</target><arg>Chester</arg><arg>1915</arg><arg>6</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Francis Harvey</target><part>Francis John William Harvey</part></link><space/>(<template><target>HMS</target><arg>Lion</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg>6</arg></template>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Loftus William Jones</target></link><space/>(<template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shark</arg><arg></arg><arg>6</arg></template>)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Status of the survivors and wrecks</heading><paragraph>In the years following the battle the wrecks were slowly discovered.<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>was found by the Royal Navy minesweeper<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Oakley</arg><arg>L72</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>in 1919.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Rules<space/></arg><arg name="last">Gordon<space/></arg><arg name="pages">539</arg></template></extension><space/>After the Second World War some of the wrecks seem to have been commercially salvaged. For instance, the Hydrographic Office record for SMS<space/><italics>Ltzow</italics><space/>(No.32344) shows that salvage operations were taking place on the wreck in 1960. In 20002001 a series of diving expeditions involving veteran shipwreck historian and archaeologist<space/><link><target>Innes McCartney</target></link><space/>located the wrecks of<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Defence</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>1909</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Nomad</arg><arg>1916</arg><arg>2</arg></template>. It was discovered that<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Indefatigable</arg><arg>1909</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, too had been ripped apart by salvors at some currently unknown time.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.periscopepublishing.com/images/Jutland%20gallery%20pages/Jutland%20exhibition.htm</arg><arg name="title">Jutland Expedition gallery 2001</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.divernetxtra.com/news/items/ships290601.htm</arg><arg name="title">Divernet Jutland 2001 press release</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2003 McCartney led a detailed survey of the wrecks for the<space/><link><target>Channel 4</target></link><space/>documentary &quot;Clash of the Dreadnoughts&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://docuwiki.net/index.php?title</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Jutland – Clash of the Dreadnoughts<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The film examined the last minutes of the lost ships and revealed for the first time how both 'P' and 'Q' turrets of<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>1907</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>had been blasted out of the ship and tossed into the sea before she broke in half. On the 90th anniversary of the battle, in 2006, the UK Ministry of Defence belatedly announced that the 14 British vessels lost in the battle were being designated as<space/><italics>protected places</italics><space/>under the<space/><link><target>Protection of Military Remains Act</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The last surviving veteran of the battle,<space/><link><target>Henry Allingham</target></link>, a British<space/><link><target>Royal Air Force</target><part>RAF</part></link><space/>(originally<space/><link><target>Royal Naval Air Service</target><part>RNAS</part></link>) airman, died on 18 July 2009, aged 113, by which time he was the oldest documented man in the world and one of the last surviving veterans of the whole war.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/5098174.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Britain's oldest veteran recalls WWI<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 June 2006</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>https://web.archive.org/web/20080421192644/http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/5098174.stm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>21 April 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension><space/>Also among the combatants was the then 20-year-old<space/><link><target>George VI of the United Kingdom</target><part>Prince Albert</part></link>, second in the line to the British throne, who would serve as King George VI of the United Kingdom from 1936 until his death in 1952. He served as a junior officer in the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk/2703403.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News</arg><arg name="first">Andrew</arg><arg name="last">Walker</arg><arg name="title">Profile: King George VI</arg><arg name="date">29 January 2003</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2013, one ship from the battle survives and is still afloat, the<space/><link><target>light cruiser</target></link><space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Caroline</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>6</arg></template>. Decommissioned in 2011, she is docked at the<space/><link><target>Royal Naval Reserve</target></link><space/>depot in<space/><link><target>Belfast</target></link>, Northern Ireland.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Remembrance</heading><paragraph>The Battle of Jutland was annually celebrated as a great victory by the right wing in Weimar Germany. This &quot;victory&quot; was used to repress the memory of the German navy's initiation of the<space/><link><target>German Revolution of 19181919</target></link>, as well as the memory of the defeat in World War I in general. (The celebrations of the<space/><link><target>Battle of Tannenberg (1914)</target><part>Battle of Tannenberg</part></link><space/>played a similar role in the<space/><link><target>Weimar Republic</target></link>.) This is especially true for the city of<space/><link><target>Wilhelmshaven</target></link>, where wreath-laying ceremonies and torch-lit parades were performed until the end of the 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gtz: Remembering the Battle, p. 360</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>World War I</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of the largest artificial non-nuclear explosions</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Explanatory notes</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Citations</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>4</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Bibliography</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bennett</arg><arg name="first">Geoffrey<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Geoffrey Bennett</arg><arg name="title">Naval Battles of the First World War</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher">Pen & Sword Military Classics</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84415-300-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Dreadnought Gunnery at the Battle of Jutland: The Question of Fire Control<space/></arg><arg name="last">Brooks</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge, Frank Cass series</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7146-5702-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Big Bang: A History of Explosives<space/></arg><arg name="last">Brown</arg><arg name="first">G.I.</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="publisher">Sutton Publishing</arg><arg name="location">Gloucestershire</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7509-1878-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="first">John<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland: An Analysis of the Fighting<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Lyons Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-55821-759-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">English<space/></arg><arg name="first">Major J.A.</arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Trafalgar Syndrome: Jutland and the Indecisiveness of Naval Warfare<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Naval War College Review</arg><arg name="volume">XXXII</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Forczyk</arg><arg name="first">Robert<space/></arg><arg name="title">Russian Battleship vs Japanese Battleship (Yellow Sea 1904–05)</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="location">Great Britain</arg><arg name="publisher">Osprey</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84603-330-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Götz<space/></arg><arg name="first">Georg<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">William<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Niven<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Chloe<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Paver<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Difficult Pasts. Memorialisation In Germany since 1945<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="pages">360–368<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Remembering the Battle of Jutland in Post-War Wilhelmshaven<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-230-20703-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gordon<space/></arg><arg name="first">Andrew<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Andrew Gordon (naval historian)<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Rules of the Game: Jutland and British Naval Command<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">John Murray<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Halpern<space/></arg><arg name="first">Paul G.<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Naval History of World War I<space/></arg><arg name="year">1994<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Routledge]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-85728-498-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Keegan<space/></arg><arg name="first">John<space/></arg><arg name="title">The First World War &#124;United States</arg><arg name="publisher">Alfred A. Knopf, Inc</arg><arg name="isbn">0-375-40052-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Kennedy</arg><arg name="first">Paul M.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Paul Kennedy</arg><arg name="title">The Rise and Fall of British Naval Mastery</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="year">1983</arg><arg name="isbn">0-333-35094-4<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Lambert<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nicholas A<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 1998<space/></arg><arg name="title">"Our Bloody Ships" or "Our Bloody System"? Jutland and the Loss of the Battle Cruisers, 1916<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The Journal of Military History<space/></arg><arg name="volume">61<space/></arg><arg name="pages">29–55<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/120394<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">120394<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Journal of Military History, Vol. 62, No. 1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Marder<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arthur J.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Arthur Marder<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Volume III: Jutland and after, May 1916 – December 1916<space/></arg><arg name="series">From the Dreadnought to Scapa Flow<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1966</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Massie</arg><arg name="first">Robert K.</arg><arg name="authorlink">Robert K. Massie</arg><arg name="title">[[Castles of Steel: Britain, Germany, and the Winning of the Great War at Sea]]</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="isbn">0-345-40878-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Massie<space/></arg><arg name="first">Robert K.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Robert K. Massie</arg><arg name="title">[[Dreadnought (book)|Dreadnought: Britain, Germany and the coming of the great war]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Random House<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-394-52833-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">McCartney</arg><arg name="first">Innes<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Innes McCartney<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Armoured Cruiser HMS ''Defence'': A Case Study in Assessing the Royal Navy Shipwrecks of the Battle of Jutland 1916 as an Archaeological Resource</arg><arg name="journal">International Journal of Nautical Archaeology</arg><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">McCartney</arg><arg name="first">Innes<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Innes McCartney<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland 1916: The Archaeology of a Modern Naval Battle: The Wreck of HMS ''Invincible'', The World's First Battle Cruiser</arg><arg name="journal">SKYLLIS, The Journal of the German Society for the Promotion of Underwater Archaeology - forthcoming</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samuel Eliot Morison</target><part>Morison, Samuel E.</part></link><space/><italics>Leyte, June 1944</italics>;<space/><link><target>History of United States Naval Operations in World War II</target></link>. 1956. Little &amp; Brown.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Nasmith<space/></arg><arg name="first">Col. George</arg><arg name="editor"><space/></arg><arg name="others">Introduction by Gen. Sir Arthur W. Currie<space/></arg><arg name="title">Canada's Sons and Great Britain during the World War</arg><arg name="publisher">Thomas Allen Publishings, Toronto</arg><arg name="year">1919</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">O'Connell, Robert J.</arg><arg name="title">Sacred vessels: the cult of the battleship and the rise of the U.S. Navy</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="year">1993</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-508006-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Tarrant<space/></arg><arg name="first">V.E.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland: The German Perspective – A New View of the Great Battle<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Weidenfeld & Nicolson</arg></template>(note:Tarrant makes all time references in German time, one hour ahead of times used in article)</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Further reading</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bacon<space/></arg><arg name="first">Reginald<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Reginald Bacon<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Jutland Scandal<space/></arg><arg name="year">1925<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="oclc">1900062</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Butler<space/></arg><arg name="first">Daniel Allen<space/></arg><arg name="title">Distant Victory: The Battle of Jutland and the Allied Triumph in the First World War<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Praeger Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-275-99073-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Corbett<space/></arg><arg name="first">Julian<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Julian Corbett<space/></arg><arg name="title">Volume III: Naval Operations<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Longmans & Co.<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-84342-491-6<space/></arg><arg name="series">Official History of the War (Reprint)</arg></template></listitem><listitem>H.W. Fawcett &amp; G.W.W. Hooper, RN (editors),<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/fightingatjutlan00fawcuoft'>The fighting at Jutland (abridged edition); the personal experiences of forty-five officers and men of the British Fleet</link><space/>London: MacMillan &amp; Co, 1921</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Frost<space/></arg><arg name="first">H.H.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Battle of Jutland<space/></arg><arg name="year">1936<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">USNI<space/></arg><arg name="location">Annapolis</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">George<space/></arg><arg name="first">S.C.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland to Junkyard<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Paul Harris Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="location">Edinburgh<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-86228-029-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Groos<space/></arg><arg name="first">''Fregattenkäpitan'' Otto<space/></arg><arg name="title">Der Krieg in der Nordsee<space/></arg><arg name="series">Der Krieg zur See: 1914–1918<space/></arg><arg name="volume">Bänd V<space/></arg><arg name="year">1925<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Mittler & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">Berlin<space/></arg><arg name="language">German</arg><arg name="oclc">2960788<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hough<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Richard Hough<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dreadnought, A history of the Modern Battleship<space/></arg><arg name="year">1975<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Macmillan Publishers]]</arg><arg name="ISBN">0517293676</arg><arg name="oclc">5101910</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Legg<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stuart<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland, an Eye-Witness Account of a Great Battle<space/></arg><arg name="year">1966<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The John Day Company<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York City</arg><arg name="oclc">505431</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">London<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland 1916, Clash of the Dreadnoughts<space/></arg><arg name="series">Campaign No. 72<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Osprey Publishing]]</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Marder<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arthur J.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Arthur Marder<space/></arg><arg name="title">Volume II: The War Years to the eve of Jutland, 1914–1916<space/></arg><arg name="series">From the Dreadnought to Scapa Flow<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Battlecruisers<space/></arg><arg name="last">Roberts<space/></arg><arg name="first">John Arthur<space/></arg><arg name="series">ShipShape<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Caxton Editions<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-84067-530-6<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Steel<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nigel<space/></arg><arg name="author2">Hart, Peter<space/></arg><arg name="title">Jutland 1916: Death in the Grey Wastes<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Orion Publishing Group|Cassell]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-304-35892-4</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Battle of Jutland</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Beatty's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.gwpda.org/1916/jutlandb.html'>official report</link></listitem><listitem>Jellicoe's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.gwpda.org/naval/jut02.htm'>official despatch</link></listitem><listitem>Jellicoe,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.richthofen.com/jellicoe/'>extract from ''The Grand Fleet''</link>, published 1919</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.worldwar1.co.uk/despatches.html'>World War I Naval Combat - Despatches</link></listitem><listitem>Scheer,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.richthofen.com/scheer/'>''Germany's High Seas Fleet in the World War''</link>, published 1920</listitem><listitem>Henry Allingham<space/><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/southern_counties/5044206.stm'>Last known survivor of the Battle of Jutland</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.northeastmedals.co.uk/britishguide/jutland/jellicoe_dispatch_1916.htm'>Jutland Casualties Listed by Ship</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://germannavalwarfare.info/indexJUT.htm'>Some Original Documents from the British Admiralty, [[Room 40</link>], regarding the Battle of Jutland]: Photocopies from<space/><link><target>The National Archives (United Kingdom)</target><part>The National Archives</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kew</target></link>,<space/><link><target>London Borough of Richmond upon Thames</target><part>Richmond</part></link>, UK.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Notable accounts</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wwi.lib.byu.edu/index.php/Kiplings%27_Reporting_on_The_Battle_of_Jutland'>by Rudyard Kipling</link><space/>Retrieved 2009-10-31.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.worldwar1.co.uk/grant.htm'>by Alexander Grant</link>, a gunner aboard HMS<space/><italics>Lion</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/northseadiary00kingiala/northseadiary00kingiala_djvu.txt'>A North Sea diary, 19141918</link>, by<space/><link><target>Stephen King-Hall</target></link>, a junior officer on the<space/><link><target>light cruiser</target></link><space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Southampton</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gwpda.org/naval/jut01.htm'>by Moritz von Egidy</link>, captain of SMS<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gwpda.org/naval/foeseyd.htm'>by Richard Foerster</link>, gunnery officer on<space/><italics>Seydlitz</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.wtj.com/archives/hase_03.htm'>by Georg von Hase</link>, gunnery officer on<space/><italics>Derfflinger</italics></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>(<bold>Note:</bold><space/>Due to the<space/><link><target>time zone</target><part>time</part></link><space/>difference, entries in some of the German accounts are one hour ahead of the times in this article.)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>World War I</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Jutland, Battle of</target></template><link><target>Category:Conflicts in 1916</target></link><link><target>Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Australia</target></link><link><target>Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Canada</target></link><link><target>Category:Naval battles of World War I involving Germany</target></link><link><target>Category:Naval battles of World War I involving the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:North Sea operations of World War I</target></link><link><target>Category:Protected Wrecks of the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:Military history of the North Sea</target></link><link><target>Category:1916 in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Battle of Jutland</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>