<article title='%C3%86thelberht_of_Kent'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="type"><space/>monarch
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>[[Saint]] Æthelberht 
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[King of Kent]]
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>EthelbertofKent.jpg</arg><arg>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Statue of Æthelberht<br>Interior of [[Rochester Cathedral]]
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>c.590&nbsp;– 616 AD
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Eormenric of Kent|Eormenric]]
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Eadbald of Kent|Eadbald]]
</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[List of monarchs of Kent|House of Kent]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Bertha of Kent]]
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>[[Eadbald of Kent|Eadbald]]<br />[[Æthelburg of Kent|Æthelburg]]
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>Eormenric
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>24 February 616 AD
</arg><arg name="death_place">
</arg><arg name="burial_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Anglo-Saxon paganism]]<br>then [[Chalcedonian Christianity]]
</arg></template><bold>thelberht</bold><space/>(also<space/><bold>thelbert</bold>,<space/><bold>Aethelberht</bold>,<space/><bold>Aethelbert</bold>, or<space/><bold>Ethelbert</bold>) (<template><target>circa</target></template><space/>560 24 February 616 AD) was<space/><link><target>Kings of Kent</target><part>King</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Kent</target><part>Kent</part></link><space/>from about 558 or 560 (the earlier date according to<space/><link><target>Thomas Sprott (chronicler)</target><part>Sprott</part></link>, the latter according to<space/><link><target>William of Malmesbury</target></link><space/>Book 1.9 ) until his death. The eighth-century monk<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>, in his<space/><italics><link><target>Ecclesiastical History of the English People</target></link></italics>, lists thelberht as the third king to hold<space/><italics>imperium</italics><space/>over other<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxons</target><part>Anglo-Saxon</part></link><space/>kingdoms. In the late ninth century<space/><italics><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</target></link></italics><space/>thelberht is referred to as a<space/><link><target>bretwalda</target></link>, or &quot;Britain-ruler&quot;. He was the first English king to convert to<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>thelberht was the son of<space/><link><target>Eormenric of Kent</target><part>Eormenric</part></link>, succeeding him as king, according to the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>. He married<space/><link><target>Bertha of Kent</target><part>Bertha</part></link>, the Christian daughter of<space/><link><target>Charibert</target></link>, king of the<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link>, thus building an alliance with the most powerful state in contemporary<space/><link><target>Western Europe</target></link>; the marriage probably took place before thelberht came to the throne. The influence of Bertha may have led to the decision by<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory I</target></link><space/>to send<space/><link><target>Augustine of Canterbury</target><part>Augustine</part></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>missionaries</target><part>missionary</part></link><space/>from Rome. Augustine landed on the<space/><link><target>Isle of Thanet</target></link><space/>in east Kent in 597. Shortly thereafter, thelberht converted to Christianity, churches were established, and wider-scale conversion to Christianity began in the kingdom. thelberht provided the new mission with land in Canterbury not only for what came to be known as<space/><link><target>Canterbury Cathedral</target></link><space/>but also for the eventual<space/><link><target>St Augustine's Abbey</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>thelberhts law</target></link><space/>for Kent, the earliest written code in any<space/><link><target>Germanic language</target></link>, instituted a complex system of fines. These can be found in the<space/><link><target>Textus Roffensis</target></link><space/>(circa 1120). Kent was rich, with strong trade ties to the continent, and thelberht may have instituted royal control over trade. For the first time following the Anglo-Saxon invasion, coins began circulating in Kent during his reign.thelberht later was<space/><link><target>Canonization of Saints</target><part>canonised</part></link><space/>for his role in establishing<space/><link><target>Chalcedonian Christianity</target></link><space/>among the Anglo-Saxons, as were his wife and daughter. His<space/><link><target>feast day</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Eastern Orthodox Church</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target></link><space/>was originally 24 February, but was changed to 25 February.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical context</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:England green top.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>The state of<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxon</target></link><space/>England at the time thelberht came to the throne of Kent</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the fifth century, raids on Britain by continental peoples had developed into full-scale migrations. The newcomers are known to have included<space/><link><target>Angles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Frisii</target><part>Frisians</part></link>, and there is evidence of other groups as well. These groups captured territory in the east and south of England, but at about the end of the fifth century, a British victory at the battle of<space/><link><target>Battle of Badon</target><part>Mount Badon</part></link><space/>(Mons Badonicus) halted the Anglo-Saxon advance for fifty years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_13">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, pp. 1316.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_23">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 23.</extension><space/>Beginning about 550, however, the British began to lose ground once more, and within twenty-five years it appears that control of almost all of southern England was in the hands of the invaders.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_RBaEE_204">Peter Hunter Blair (<italics>Roman Britain</italics>, p. 204) gives the twenty-five years from 550 to 575 as the dates of the final conquest.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Anglo-Saxons probably conquered Kent before Mons Badonicus. Both documentary and archaeological evidence exists about colonization by Jutes, from the southern part of the<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link><space/>peninsula.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_26">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 26.</extension><space/>According to legend, the brothers<space/><link><target>Hengist</target></link><space/>and Horsa, landed in 449 as mercenaries for a British king,<space/><link><target>Vortigern</target></link>. After a rebellion over pay and Horsa's death in battle, Hengist established the kingdom of Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_12">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, pp. 1213.</extension><space/>Some historians now think the underlying story of a rebelling mercenary force may be accurate; most now date the founding of the kingdom of Kent in the middle of the fifth-century, consistent with the legend.<extension extension_name='ref'>There is disagreement about the extent to which the legend can be treated as fact. For example, Yorke says &quot;Recent detailed studies [. . .] have confirmed that these accounts are largely mythic and that any reliable oral tradition which they may have embodied has been lost in the conventions of the origin-legend format&quot; (<italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 26), but Fletcher says of Hengist that &quot;there is no good reason for doubting his existence&quot; (<italics>Who's Who</italics>, pp. 1517), and Campbell adds that &quot;although the origins of such annals are deeply mysterious, and suspect, they cannot be simply discarded&quot; (Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 38).</extension><space/>This early date, only a few decades after the departure of the Romans, also suggests that more of Roman civilization may have survived into Anglo-Saxon rule in Kent than in other areas.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_38">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 38.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Overlordship was a central feature of Anglo-Saxon politics which began before thelberht's time; kings were described as overlords as late as the ninth century. The Anglo-Saxon invasion may have involved military coordination of different groups within the invaders, with a leader who had authority over many different groups;<space/><link><target>lle of Sussex</target></link><space/>may have been such a leader.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fletcher,<space/><italics>Who's Who</italics>, pp. 1517.</extension><space/>Once the new states began to form, conflicts among them began. Tribute from dependents could lead to wealth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_44">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 44.</extension><space/>A weaker state also might ask or pay for the protection of a stronger neighbour against a warlike third state.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_201">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, pp. 201203</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sources for this period in Kentish history include<space/><italics><link><target>Ecclesiastical History of the English People</target><part>The Ecclesiastical History of the English People</part></link></italics>, written in 731 by<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>Northumbria</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>monk</target></link>. Bede was interested primarily in England's<space/><link><target>Christianization</target></link>. Since thelberht was the first Anglo-Saxon king to convert to<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link>, Bede provides more substantial information about him than about any earlier king. One of Bedes correspondents was Albinus, abbot of the monastery of St. Peter and St. Paul (subsequently renamed<space/><link><target>St Augustine's Abbey</target><part>St. Augustine's</part></link>) in<space/><link><target>Canterbury</target></link>. The<space/><italics><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</target></link></italics>, a collection of annals assembled circa 890 in the kingdom of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link>, mentions several events in Kent during thelberhts reign.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_25">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 25.</extension><space/>Further mention of events in Kent occurs in the late sixth century history of the<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Gregory of Tours</target></link>. This is the earliest surviving source to mention any Anglo-Saxon kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_30">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 30.</extension><space/>Some of Pope<space/><link><target>Gregory the Great</target></link>s letters concern the mission of<space/><link><target>Augustine of Canterbury</target><part>St. Augustine</part></link><space/>to Kent in 597; these letters also mention the state of Kent and its relationships with neighbours. Other sources include regnal lists of the kings of Kent and early charters (land grants by kings to their followers or to the church). Although no originals survive from thelberhts reign, later copies exist. A law code from thelberhts reign also survives.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_25"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ancestry, accession, and chronology</heading><paragraph>According to Bede, thelberht was descended directly from Hengist. Bede gives the line of descent as follows: &quot;Ethelbert was son of Irminric, son of Octa, and after his grandfather Oeric, surnamed Oisc, the kings of the Kentish folk are commonly known as Oiscings. The father of Oeric was Hengist.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_112">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Book II, Ch. 5, from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 112.</extension><space/>An alternative form of this genealogy, found in the<space/><link><target>Historia Brittonum</target></link><space/>among other places, reverses the position of Octa and Oisc in the lineage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_26"></extension><space/>The first of these names that can be placed historically with reasonable confidence is thelberhts father, whose name now usually is spelled Eormenric. The only direct written reference to Eormenric is in Kentish genealogies, but Gregory of Tours does mention that thelberhts father was the king of Kent, though Gregory gives no date. Eormenrics name provides a hint of connections to the kingdom of the Franks, across the English channel; the element &quot;Eormen&quot; was rare in names of the Anglo-Saxon aristocracy, but much more common among Frankish nobles.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_28">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 28.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One other member of thelberhts family is known: his sister, Ricole, who is recorded by both Bede and the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>as the mother of Sberht, king of the East Saxons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_12"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_108">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Book II, Ch. 3, from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 108.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The dates of thelberhts birth and accession to the throne of Kent are both matters of debate. Bede, the earliest source to give dates, is thought to have drawn his information from correspondence with Albinus. Bede states that when thelberht died in 616 he had reigned for fifty-six years, placing his accession in 560. Bede also says that thelberht died twenty-one years after his baptism. Augustines mission from Rome is known to have arrived in 597, and according to Bede, it was this mission that converted thelberht.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_74">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Book I, Ch. 25 &amp; 26, from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 7477.</extension><space/>Hence Bedes dates are inconsistent. The<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>, an important source for early dates, is inconsistent with Bede and also has inconsistencies among different manuscript versions. Putting together the different dates in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>for birth, death, and length of reign, it appears that thelberhts reign was thought to have been either 560616, or 565618, but that the surviving sources have confused the two traditions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31">Kirby (<italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 313) provides an extended discussion of the difficult chronology of thelberhts reign.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is possible that thelberht was converted to Christianity before Augustines arrival. thelberhts wife was a Christian and brought a Frankish bishop with her, to attend her at court, so thelberht would have had knowledge of Christianity before the mission reached Kent. It also is possible that Bede had the date of thelberhts death wrong; if, in fact, thelberht died in 618, this would be consistent with his baptism in 597, which is in accord with the tradition that Augustine converted the king within a year of his arrival.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregory of Tours, in his<space/><italics>Historia Francorum</italics>, writes that<space/><link><target>Bertha of Kent</target><part>Bertha</part></link>, daughter of<space/><link><target>Charibert</target></link>, king of the Franks, married the son of the king of Kent. Bede says that thelberht received Bertha &quot;from her parents&quot;. If Bede is interpreted literally, the marriage would have had to take place before 567, when Charibert died. The traditions for thelberhts reign, then, would imply that thelberht married Bertha before either 560 or 565.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_74"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The extreme length of thelberhts reign also has been regarded with skepticism by historians; it has been suggested that he died in the fifty-sixth year of his life, rather than the fifty-sixth year of his reign. This would place the year of his birth approximately at 560, and he would not then have been able to marry until the mid 570s. According to Gregory of Tours, Charibert was king when he married Ingoberg, Berthas mother, which places that marriage no earlier than 561. It therefore is unlikely that Bertha was married much before about 580. These later dates for Bertha and thelberht also solve another possible problem: thelberht's daughter,<space/><link><target>thelburh of Kent</target><part>thelburh</part></link>, seems likely to have been Bertha's child, but the earlier dates would have Bertha aged sixty or so at thelburh's likely birthdate using the early dates.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregory, however, also says that he thinks that Ingoberg was seventy years old in 589; and this would make her about forty when she married Charibert. This is possible, but seems unlikely, especially as Charibert seems to have had a preference for younger women, again according to Gregorys account. This would imply an earlier birth date for Bertha. On the other hand, Gregory refers to thelberht at the time of his marriage to Bertha simply as &quot;a man of Kent&quot;, and in the 589 passage concerning Ingobergs death, which was written in about 590 or 591, he refers to thelberht as &quot;the son of the king of Kent&quot;. If this does not simply reflect Gregorys ignorance of Kentish affairs, which seems unlikely given the close ties between Kent and the Franks, then some assert that thelberhts reign cannot have begun before 589.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="GTours">IV 25 and IX 25 in<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Gregory of Tours</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The History of the Franks</arg><arg name="pages">219, 513</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1974</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-044295-2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While all of the contradictions above cannot be reconciled, the most probable dates that may be drawn from available data place thelberhts birth at approximately 560 and, perhaps, his marriage to Bertha at 580. His reign is most likely to have begun in 589 or 590.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_31"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Kingship of Kent</heading><paragraph>The later history of Kent shows clear evidence of a system of joint kingship, with the kingdom being divided into east Kent and west Kent, although it appears that there generally was a dominant king. This evidence is less clear for the earlier period, but there are early charters, known to be forged, which nevertheless imply that thelberht ruled as joint king with his son,<space/><link><target>Eadbald of Kent</target><part>Eadbald</part></link>. It may be that thelberht was king of east Kent and Eadbald became king of west Kent; the east Kent king seems generally to have been the dominant ruler later in Kentish history. Whether or not Eadbald became a joint king with thelberht, there is no question that thelberht had authority throughout the kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_32">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, pp. 3234.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The division into two kingdoms is most likely to date back to the sixth century; east Kent may have conquered west Kent and preserved the institutions of kingship as a subkingdom. This was a common pattern in Anglo-Saxon England, as the more powerful kingdoms absorbed their weaker neighbours. An unusual feature of the Kentish system was that only sons of kings appeared to be legitimate claimants to the throne, although this did not eliminate all strife over the succession.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_32"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main towns of the two kingdoms were Rochester, for west Kent, and Canterbury, for east Kent. Bede does not state that thelberht had a palace in Canterbury, but he does refer to Canterbury as thelberht's &quot;metropolis&quot;, and it is clear that it is thelberht's seat.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_32"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_38_2">Campbell et al.,<space/><italics>The Anglo-Saxons</italics>, p. 3839.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Relations with the Franks</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Aethelberht of Kent sculpture on Canterbury Cathedral.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Sculpture of King thelberht of Kent, an Anglo-Saxon king and saint, on Canterbury Cathedral in England.</part><trail>There</trail></link><space/>are many indications of close relations between Kent and the Franks. thelberhts marriage to Bertha certainly connected the two courts, although not as equals: the Franks would have thought of thelberht as an under-king. There is no record that thelberht ever accepted a continental king as his overlord and, as a result, historians are divided on the true nature of the relationship. Evidence for an explicit Frankish overlordship of Kent comes from a letter written by Pope Gregory the Great to<space/><link><target>Theuderic II</target><part>Theuderic</part></link>, king of<space/><link><target>Orlans</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Theudebert II</target><part>Theudebert</part></link>, king of<space/><link><target>Metz</target></link>. The letter concerned Augustines mission to Kent in 597, and in it Gregory says that he believes &quot;that you wish your subjects in every respect to be converted to that faith in which you, their kings and lords, stand&quot;. It may be that this is a papal compliment, rather than a description of the relationship between the kingdoms. It also has been suggested that Liudhard, Berthas chaplain, was intended as a representative of the Frankish church in Kent, which also could be interpreted as evidence of overlordship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 5960.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_34">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 3435.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A possible reason for the willingness of the Franks to connect themselves with the Kentish court is the fact that a Frankish king,<space/><link><target>Chilperic I</target></link>, is recorded as having conquered a people known as the Euthiones during the mid-sixth century. If, as seems likely from the name, these people were the continental remnants of the Jutish invaders of Kent, then it may be that the marriage was intended as a unifying political move, reconnecting different branches of the same people.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59"></extension><space/>Another perspective on the marriage may be gained by considering that it is likely that thelberht was not yet king at the time he and Bertha were wed: it may be that Frankish support for him, acquired via the marriage, was instrumental in gaining the throne for him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_34"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Regardless of the political relationship between thelberht and the Franks, there is abundant evidence of strong connections across the English Channel. There was a luxury trade between Kent and the Franks, and burial artifacts found include clothing, drink, and weapons that reflect Frankish cultural influence. The Kentish burials have a greater range of imported goods than those of the neighbouring Anglo-Saxon regions. This is not surprising given the easier access to trade. In addition, the grave goods are both richer and more numerous in Kentish graves than in those of the Anglo-Saxon regions, implying that the material wealth exhibited in Kent was derived from that trade.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_26"></extension><space/>Frankish influences also may be detected in the social and agrarian organization of Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59"></extension><space/>Other cultural influences may be seen in the burials as well, so it is not necessary to presume that there was direct settlement by the Franks in Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_26"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Rise to dominance</heading><heading level='3'>Bretwalda</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Entry for 827 in the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle, which lists the eight bretwaldas.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The entry for 827 in the [C] ms. (one of the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle#Surviving manuscripts</target><part>Abingdon manuscripts</part></link>) of the ''Anglo-Saxon Chronicle'', listing the eight ''bretwaldas''; thelberht's name, spelled &quot;elbriht&quot;, is the second-to-last word on the fifth line</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In his<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Bede includes his list of seven kings who held &quot;imperium&quot; over the other kingdoms south of the Humber. The usual translation for &quot;imperium&quot; is &quot;overlordship&quot;. Bede names thelberht as the third on the list, after lle of Sussex and<space/><link><target>Ceawlin of Wessex</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_111">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Book I, Ch. 25 &amp; 26, from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 111.</extension><space/>The anonymous annalist who composed one of the versions of the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>repeated Bedes list of seven kings in a famous entry under the year 827, with one additional king, Egbert of Wessex. The<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>also states that these kings held the title &quot;<italics>bretwalda</italics>&quot;, or &quot;Britain-ruler&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_60">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>,pp. 6061.</extension><space/>The exact meaning of<space/><italics>bretwalda</italics><space/>has been the subject of much debate; it has been described as a term &quot;of encomiastic poetry&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_34">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 3435.</extension><space/>but there also is evidence that it implied a definite role of military leadership.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_17">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 17.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The prior<space/><italics>bretwalda</italics><space/>noted, Ceawlin, is recorded by the<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics><space/>as having fought thelberht in 568. The entry states that thelberht lost the battle and was driven back to Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_18">Swanton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</italics>,pp. 1819.</extension><space/>The dating of the entries concerning the West Saxons in this section of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>is thought to be unreliable and a recent analysis suggests that Ceawlins reign is more likely to have been approximately 581588, rather than the dates of 560592 that are given in the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_50">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, pp. 5051.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_133">D.N. Dumville, &quot;The West Saxon Genealogical Regnal List and the chronology of Wessex&quot;, 1985, cited in Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 133.</extension><space/>The battle was at &quot;Wibbandun&quot;, which may be translated as Wibbas Mount; it is not known where this was.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Swanton_18"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At some point Ceawlin ceased to hold the title of<space/><italics>bretwalda</italics>, perhaps after a battle at Stoke Lyne, in Oxfordshire, which the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics><space/>dates to 584, some eight years before he was deposed in 592 (again using the<space/><italics>Chronicles</italics><space/>unreliable dating).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59"></extension><space/>thelberht certainly was a dominant ruler by 601, when Gregory the Great wrote to him: Gregory urges thelberht to spread Christianity among those kings and peoples subject to him, implying some level of overlordship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_37">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 37.</extension><space/>If the battle of Wibbandun was fought circa 590, as has been suggested, then thelberht must have gained his position as overlord some time in the 590s. This dating for Wibbandun is slightly inconsistent with the proposed dates of 581588 for Ceawlins reign, but those dates are not thought to be precise, merely the most plausible given the available data.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_133"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Relationships with other kingdoms</heading><paragraph>In addition to the evidence of the<space/><italics>Chronicle</italics>, that thelberht was accorded the title of bretwalda, there is evidence of his domination in several of the southern kingdoms. In Essex, thelberht appears to have been in a position to exercise authority shortly after 604, when his intervention helped in the conversion of King<space/><link><target>Saebert of Essex</target></link>, his nephew, to Christianity. It was thelberht, and not Sberht, who built and endowed St. Pauls in London, where<space/><link><target>St. Pauls Cathedral</target></link><space/>now stands. Further evidence is provided by Bede, who explicitly describes thelberht as Sberhts overlord.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_108"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_37"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_109">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 109.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bede describes thelberhts relationship with<space/><link><target>Rdwald</target></link>, king of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of East Anglia</target><part>East Anglia</part></link>, in a passage that is ambiguous. It seems to imply that Rdwald retained ducatus, or military command of his people, even while thelberht held imperium, the rule.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_111"></extension><space/>This further implies that being a bretwalda usually included holding the military command of other kingdoms and also that it was more than that, since thelberht is bretwalda despite Rdwalds control of his own troops.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_17"></extension><space/>Rdwald was converted to Christianity while in Kent but did not abandon his pagan beliefs; this and the fact that he retained military independence imply that thelberhts overlordship of East Anglia was much weaker than his influence with the East Saxons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_37"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_62">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 62.</extension><space/>An alternative interpretation, however, is that the passage in Bede should be translated as &quot;Rdwald, king of the East Angles, who while thelberht lived, even conceded to him the military leadership of his people&quot;; if this is Bede's intent, then East Anglia firmly was under thelberht's overlordship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blackwell_13">&quot;Rdwald&quot;, N. J. Higham, in Lapidge,<space/><italics>Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England</italics>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There is no evidence that thelberhts influence in other kingdoms was enough for him to convert any other kings to Christianity, although this interpretation partly is due to the lack of sourcesnothing is known of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Sussex</target><part>Sussex</part></link>s history, for example, for almost all of the seventh and eighth centuries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_20">For example, Yorke comments that &quot;it is impossible to write at any length about the history of [Sussex] in the seventh and eighth centuries&quot; (<italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 20).</extension><space/>thelberht was able to arrange a meeting in 602 in the<space/><link><target>River Severn</target><part>Severn</part></link><space/>valley, on the northwestern borders of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link>, however, and this may be an indication of the extent of his influence in the west.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_37"></extension><space/>No evidence survives showing Kentish domination of<space/><link><target>Mercia</target></link>, but it is known that Mercia was independent of<space/><link><target>Northumbria</target></link>, so it is quite plausible that it was under Kentish overlordship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_39">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 39.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Augustines mission and early Christianization</heading><paragraph>The native Britons had converted to Christianity under Roman rule. The Anglo-Saxon invasions separated the British church from European Christianity for centuries, so the church in Rome had no presence or authority in Britain, and in fact, Rome knew so little about the British church that it was unaware of any schism in customs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_36">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 36.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_110">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 110.</extension><space/>thelberht, however, would have known something about the Roman church from his Frankish wife, Bertha, who had brought a bishop, Liudhard, with her across the Channel. thelberht had a Roman church renovated to build a royal chapel for her,<space/><link><target>St Martin's Church, Canterbury</target><part>St Martin's</part></link>, still serving as the oldest church in the English-speaking world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_35">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 35.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ethelbert, King of Kent from All Souls College Chapel.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Stained-glass window of thelberht from the chapel of<space/><link><target>All Souls College, Oxford</target></link></part><trail>In</trail></link><space/>596, Pope Gregory the Great sent Augustine, prior of the monastery of St. Andrew in Rome, to England as a missionary, and in 597, a group of nearly forty monks, led by Augustine, landed on the Isle of Thanet in Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_30"></extension><space/>According to Bede, thelberht was sufficiently distrustful of the newcomers to insist on meeting them under the open sky, to prevent them from performing sorcery. The monks impressed thelberht, but he was not converted immediately. He agreed to allow the mission to settle in Canterbury and permitted them to preach.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_74"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It is not known when thelberht became a Christian. It is possible, despite Bedes account, that he already was a Christian before Augustines mission arrived. It is likely that Liudhard and Bertha pressed thelberht to consider becoming a Christian before the arrival of the mission, and it is also likely that a condition of thelberhts marriage to Bertha might have been that thelberht would consider conversion. Conversion via the influence of the Frankish court would have been seen as an explicit recognition of Frankish overlordship, however, so it is possible that thelberhts delay of his conversion until it could be accomplished via Roman influence, might have been an assertion of independence from Frankish control.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_28">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, pp. 2829.</extension><space/>It also has been argued that Augustines hesitationhe turned back to Rome, asking to be released from the missionis an indication that thelberht was a pagan at the time Augustine was sent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_35"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the latest, thelberht must have converted before 601, since that year Gregory wrote to him as a Christian king.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_37"></extension><space/>An old tradition records that thelberht converted on 1 June, in the summer of the year that Augustine arrived.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair_IASE_117">Hunter Blair,<space/><italics>An Introduction</italics>, p. 117.</extension><space/>thelberht quickly rendered support both by giving Augustine a Roman church in Canterbury, rebuilt into what soon became the cathedral, and by founding the church of Saints<space/><link><target>Saint Peter</target><part>Peter</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target><part>Paul</part></link><space/>east of the city walls for burial of Kentish royalty, which later became<space/><link><target>St Augustine's Abbey</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Through thelberhts influence Sberht, king of Essex, also was converted,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_109"></extension><space/>but there were limits to the effectiveness of the mission. The entire Kentish court did not convert: Eadbald, thelberhts son and heir, was a pagan at his accession.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_36"></extension><space/>Rdwald, king of East Anglia, was only partly converted (apparently while at thelberhts court) and retained a pagan shrine next to the new Christian altar.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_112">Bede,<space/><italics>Ecclesiastical History</italics>, Book II, Ch. 15, from Sherley-Price's translation, p. 112.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_36"></extension><space/>Augustine also was unsuccessful in gaining the allegiance of the British clergy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_110"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Law code</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Textus Roffensis ms.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>The first page of the twelfth-century manuscript of thelberhts law code</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Law of Æthelberht</arg></template>Some time after the arrival of Augustines mission, perhaps in 602 or 603, thelberht issued a set of laws, in ninety sections.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blackwell_13">&quot;thelberht&quot;, S.E. Kelly, in Lapidge,<space/><italics>Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England</italics>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Geary_209">Geary,<space/><italics>Readings</italics>, pp. 209211.</extension><space/>These laws are considered the earliest surviving code composed in any of the Germanic countries,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59"></extension><space/>and they were almost certainly among the first documents written down in<space/><link><target>Old English language</target><part>Anglo-Saxon</part></link>, as literacy would have arrived in England with Augustines mission.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_1">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 1.</extension><space/>The only surviving early manuscript, the<space/><italics>Textus Roffensis</italics>, dates from the twelfth century, and it now resides in the Medway Studies Centre in Strood, Kent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ASE23"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Hough</arg><arg name="first">Carole A.</arg><arg name="title">The early Kentish 'divorce laws': a reconsideration of Æthelberht, chs. 79 and 80</arg><arg name="journal">Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="volume">23</arg><arg name="pages">19–34</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-521-47200-8</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/S0263675100004476</arg></template></extension><space/>thelberhts code makes reference to the church in the very first item, which enumerates the compensation required for the property of a bishop, a deacon, a priest, and so on;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Geary_209"></extension><space/>but overall, the laws seem remarkably uninfluenced by Christian principles. Bede asserted that they were composed &quot;after the Roman manner&quot;, but there is little discernible Roman influence either. In subject matter, the laws have been compared to the<space/><link><target>Lex Salica</target></link><space/>of the Franks, but it is not thought that thelberht based his new code on any specific previous model.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_59"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Blackwell_13"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The laws are concerned with setting and enforcing the penalties for transgressions at all levels of society; the severity of the fine depended on the social rank of the victim, with crimes against the Church penalized the most, more greatly even than those against the king.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Beginnings of English Law</italics>, Lisi Oliver</extension><space/>The king had a financial interest in enforcement, for part of the fines would come to him in many cases, but the king also was responsible for law and order, and avoiding<space/><link><target>blood feud</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>by enforcing the rules on compensation for injury was part of the way the king maintained control.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_18">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 18.</extension><space/>thelberhts laws are mentioned by<space/><link><target>Alfred the Great</target></link>, who compiled his own laws, making use of the prior codes created by thelberht, as well as those of<space/><link><target>Offa of Mercia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ine of Wessex</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_276">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 276.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One of thelberhts laws seems to preserve a trace of a very old custom: the third item in the code states that &quot;If the king is drinking at a mans home, and anyone commits any evil deed there, he is to pay twofold compensation.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Geary_209"></extension><space/>This probably refers to the ancient custom of a king traveling the country, being hosted, and being provided for by his subjects wherever he went. The kings servants retained these rights for centuries after thelberhts time.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_288">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, pp. 288289.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Items 7781 in the code have been interpreted as a description of a womans financial rights after a divorce or legal separation. These clauses define how much of the household goods a woman could keep in different circumstances, depending on whether she keeps custody of the children, for example. It has recently been suggested by one source, however, that it would be more correct to interpret these clauses as referring to women who are widowed, rather than divorced.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ASE23"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Trade and coinage</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Eadbaldobv.1.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>A thrymsa from the reign of Eadbald, thelberhts son, none of the coins are known to carry thelberhts name, although they may have been minted during his reign</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There is little documentary evidence about the nature of trade in thelberhts Kent. It is known that the kings of Kent had established royal control of trade in the late seventh century, but it is not known how early this control began. There is archaeological evidence suggesting that the royal influence predates any of the written sources. It has been suggested that one of thelberhts achievements was to take control of trade away from the aristocracy and to make it a royal monopoly. The continental trade provided Kent access to luxury goods which gave it an advantage in trading with the other Anglo-Saxon nations, and the revenue from trade was important in itself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_40">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 40.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Kentish manufacture before 600 included glass beakers and jewelry. Kentish jewellers were highly skilled, and before the end of the sixth century they gained access to gold. Goods from Kent are found in cemeteries across the channel and as far away as at the mouth of the<space/><link><target>Loire River</target><part>Loire</part></link>. It is not known what Kent traded for all of this wealth, although it seems likely that there was a flourishing slave trade. It may well be that this wealth was the foundation of thelberhts strength, although his overlordship and the associated right to demand tribute would have brought wealth in its turn.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell_TAS_44"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It may have been during thelberhts reign that coins first began to be minted in England: none bear his name, but it is thought likely that the first coins predate the end of the sixth century. These early coins were gold, and probably were the shillings (<italics>scillingas</italics><space/>in Old English) that are mentioned in thelberhts laws.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_40"></extension><space/>The coins are also known to<space/><link><target>numismatics</target><part>numismatists</part></link><space/>as &quot;thrymsas&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blackwell_113">&quot;Coinage&quot;, M.A.S. Blackburn, in Lapidge,<space/><italics>Encyclopaedia of Anglo-Saxon England</italics>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Death and succession</heading><paragraph>thelberht died on 24 February 616 and was buried in the church of St Peter and St Paul (later<space/><link><target>St Augustine's Abbey</target></link>) but was later exhumed so his shrine could be placed above the high altar of the Norman church to which Saint thelberht attracted pilgrimage. He was succeeded by his son,<space/><link><target>Eadbald of Kent</target><part>Eadbald</part></link>, who was not a ChristianBede says he had been converted but went back to his pagan faith,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blackwell_13"></extension><space/>although he ultimately did become a Christian king.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Stenton_61">Stenton,<space/><italics>Anglo-Saxon England</italics>, p. 61.</extension><space/>Eadbald outraged the church by marrying his stepmother, which was contrary to Church law, and by refusing to accept baptism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bede_112"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sberht of the East Saxons also died at approximately this time, and he was succeeded by his three sons, none of whom were Christian. A subsequent revolt against Christianity and the expulsion of Mellitus, their bishop, may have been a reaction to Kentish overlordship after thelberhts death as much as a pagan opposition to Christianity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_48">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 48.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In addition to Eadbald, it is possible that thelberht had another son, thelwald. The evidence for this is a papal letter to Justus, archbishop of Canterbury from 619 to 625, that refers to a king named Aduluald, who is apparently different from Audubald, which refers to Eadbald. There is no agreement among modern scholars on how to interpret this: &quot;Aduluald&quot; might be intended as a representation of &quot;thelwald&quot;, and hence an indication of another king, perhaps a sub-king of west Kent;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yorke_32">Yorke,<space/><italics>Kings and Kingdoms</italics>, p. 3233.</extension><space/>or it may be merely a scribal error which should be read as referring to Eadbald.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kirby_39">Kirby,<space/><italics>Earliest English Kings</italics>, p. 39.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Liturgical Celebration</heading><paragraph>thelberht later was<space/><link><target>Canonization of Saints</target><part>canonised</part></link><space/>for his role in establishing<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link><space/>among the Anglo-Saxons. His<space/><link><target>feast day</target></link><space/>was originally 24 February but was changed to 25 February.<extension extension_name='ref' name="rc.net"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.catholic-forum.com/saints/sainte3p.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Patron Saints Index: Saint Ethelbert<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 June 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 2004 edition of the<space/><link><target>Roman Martyrology</target></link>, he is listed under his date of death, 24 February, with the citation: 'King of Kent, converted by St Augustine, bishop, the first leader of the English people to do so'.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Martyrologium Romanum</italics>, 2004, Vatican Press (Typis Vaticanis), page 163.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic</target></link><space/><link><target>Archdiocese of Southwark</target></link>, which contains Kent, commemorates him on 25 February.<extension extension_name='ref' name="swk"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.rcsouthwark.co.uk/liturgy_rites_dioccal.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Interim Diocesan Calendar Proper to the Archdiocese of Southwark<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 February 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>thelberht is honored together with<space/><link><target>Bertha of Kent</target><part>Bertha</part></link><space/>with a<space/><link><target>feast day</target></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Calendar of saints (Episcopal Church in the United States of America)</target><part>liturgical calendar of the Episcopal Church (USA)</part></link><space/>on 27 May.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Saints</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Anglo-Saxon saints</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of monarchs of Kent</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kentish Royal Legend</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Primary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Bede</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum|Ecclesiastical History of the English People]]</arg><arg name="others"><space/>Translated by Leo Sherley-Price, revised R.E. Latham, ed. D.H. Farmer</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-14-044565-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Swanton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxon Chronicle</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-92129-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Law-code of thelberht, ed. and tr. F. Liebermann,<space/><italics>Die Gesetze der Angelsachsen</italics>. 3 vols. Halle, 18981916: 38 (vol 1); ed. and tr. L. Oliver,<space/><italics>The Beginnings of English Law</italics>. Toronto Medieval Texts and Translations. Toronto, 2002.</listitem><listitem>Letters of<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory I</target><part>Gregory the Great</part></link>, ed. D. Norberg,<space/><italics>S. Gregorii magni registrum epistularum</italics>. 2 vols. Turnhout, 1982; tr. J.R.C. Martyn,<space/><italics>The letters of Gregory the Great</italics>. 3 vols. Toronto, 2004.</listitem><listitem>Earliest<space/><italics>vita</italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory I</target><part>Gregory the Great</part></link>, ed. and tr. Bertram Colgrave,<space/><italics>The earliest life of Gregory the Great by an anonymous monk of Whitby</italics>. Lawrence, 1968.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gregory of Tours</target></link>,<space/><italics>Libri Historiarum</italics>.</listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Secondary sources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Campbell</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Anglo-Saxons</arg><arg name="author2">John, Eric<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Wormald, Patrick</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin Books</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-014395-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Fletcher</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Who's Who in Roman Britain and Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Shepheard-Walwyn</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85683-089-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Geary</arg><arg name="first">Patrick J.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Readings in Medieval History</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Peterborough</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Broadview<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-55111-158-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="authorlink">Peter Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="title"><space/>An Introduction to Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="pages">13–16</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1960</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cambridge University Press]]</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hunter Blair</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Peter</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Roman Britain and Early England: 55 B.C. – A.D. 871</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1966</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>W.W. Norton & Company</arg><arg name="isbn">0-393-00361-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kirby</arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.P.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Earliest English Kings</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-09086-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Lapidge</arg><arg name="first">Michael</arg><arg name="title">The Blackwell Encyclopedia of Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn">0-631-22492-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Stenton</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Frank M.</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Frank Stenton</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Clarendon Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-821716-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Yorke</arg><arg name="first">Barbara</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Kings and Kingdoms of Early Anglo-Saxon England</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Seaby</arg><arg name="isbn">1-85264-027-8</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource author</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/560-975dooms.html#The%20Laws%20of%20%C6thelberht'>The Laws of thelberht, at Mediaeval Sourcebook</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Featured article</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Kentish Monarchs</target></template><template><target>Bretwalda</target></template><template><target>Anglo-Saxon saints</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Æthelberht
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Æthelbert; Aethelberht; Aethelbert; Ethelbert
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>King of Kent
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>c. 560
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH">
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>24 February 616
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Aethelberht Of Kent</target></template><link><target>Category:560s births</target></link><link><target>Category:616 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Kentish saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Catholic royal saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Converts to Christianity from pagan religions</target></link><link><target>Category:Kentish monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:Eastern Orthodox saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Medieval legislators</target></link><link><target>Category:7th-century Christian saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Gregorian mission</target></link><link><target>Category:Jutish people</target></link><link><target>Category:7th-century English monarchs</target></link><link><target>Category:6th-century monarchs in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Anglican saints</target></link><link><target>Category:Characters in works by Geoffrey of Monmouth</target></link><link><target>Category:English saints</target></link><link><target>Category:House of Kent</target></link></paragraph></article>