<article title='Catharism'><paragraph><template><target>redirect2</target><arg>Cathar</arg><arg>The Good Men</arg><arg>the Dutch house music duo</arg><arg>Zki & Dobre</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Cathar (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2010</arg></template><template><target>use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2013</arg></template><link><target>File:Cathar cross.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Occitan cross</target></link><space/>was a &quot;Cathar rallying symbol&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>La vie quotidienne des cathares du Langudoc</italics>, Ren Nelli.</extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Catharism</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>θ</arg><arg>ər</arg><arg>ɪ</arg><arg>z</arg><arg>əm</arg></template>; from the<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link>:<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>καθαροί</arg></template>,<space/><italics>katharoi</italics>, &quot;the pure [ones]&quot;)<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>OED</arg><arg>1989</arg><arg name="loc"><space/>"Cathar"</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>LSJ</target><arg>kaqaro/s</arg><arg>καθαροί</arg><arg>ref</arg></template>.</extension><space/>was a<space/><link><target>Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/><link><target>Dualism</target><part>dualist</part></link><space/>movement that thrived in some areas of<space/><link><target>Southern Europe</target></link>, particularly<space/><link><target>northern Italy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>southern France</target></link>, between the 12th and 14th centuries. Cathar beliefs varied between communities because Catharism was initially taught by<space/><link><target>Asceticism</target><part>ascetic</part></link><space/><link><target>priest</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>who had set few guidelines. The<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>denounced its practices and dismissed it as &quot;the Church of<space/><link><target>Satan</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">21</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Catharism had its roots in the<space/><link><target>Paulicianism</target><part>Paulician</part></link><space/>movement in<space/><link><target>Armenia</target></link><space/>and eastern<space/><link><target>Byzantine</target></link><space/>Anatolia and the<space/><link><target>Bogomilism</target><part>Bogomils</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>First Bulgarian Empire</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Cathars</italics>,<space/><bold>Heresy and Authority in Medieval Europe</bold>, ed. Edward Peters, (University of Pennsylvania Press, 1980), 108.</extension><space/>who were influenced by the Paulicians resettled in<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Plovdiv</target><part>Philipopolis</part></link>) by the Byzantines. Though the term &quot;Cathar&quot; (<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>θ</arg><arg>ɑː</arg><arg>r</arg></template>) has been used for centuries to identify the movement, whether the movement identified itself with this name is debatable.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Pegg</arg><arg>2001a</arg><arg name="pp">181 ff</arg></template><space/>In Cathar texts, the terms &quot;Good Men&quot; (<italics>Bons Hommes</italics>) or &quot;Good Christians&quot; are the common terms of<space/><link><target>self-identification</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Théry</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">75–117</arg></template><space/>The idea of two Gods or principles, one being good and the other evil, was central to Cathar beliefs. The good<space/><link><target>God</target></link><space/>was the God of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link><space/>and the creator of the spiritual realm, contrasted with the evil<space/><link><target>Old Testament</target></link><space/>Godthe creator of the physical world whom many Cathars, and particularly their persecutors, identified as Satan. All visible matter, including the human body, was created by this evil god; it was therefore tainted with<space/><link><target>sin</target></link>. This was the antithesis to the monotheistic Catholic Church, whose fundamental principle was that there was only one God who created all things visible and invisible.<extension extension_name='ref'>See:<space/><link><target>Nicene Creed</target></link></extension><space/>Cathars thought human<space/><link><target>spirit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were the genderless spirits of<space/><link><target>angel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>trapped within the physical creation of the evil god, cursed to be<space/><link><target>reincarnation</target><part>reincarnated</part></link><space/>until the Cathar faithful achieved salvation through a ritual called the<space/><link><target>consolamentum</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaus</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">114</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From the beginning of his reign,<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link><space/>attempted to end Catharism by sending missionaries and by persuading the local authorities to act against them. However, in 1208 Innocent's papal legate<space/><link><target>Pierre de Castelnau</target></link><space/>was murdered while returning to<space/><link><target>Rome</target></link><space/>after excommunicating<space/><link><target>Raymond VI, Count of Toulouse</target><part>Count Raymond VI of Toulouse</part></link>, who, in his view, was too lenient with the Cathars.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">15–16</arg></template><space/>Pope Innocent III then abandoned the option of sending Catholic<space/><link><target>missionary</target><part>missionaries</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>jurist</target><trail>s</trail></link>, declared Pierre de Castelnau a<space/><link><target>Christian martyrs</target><part>martyr</part></link><space/>and launched the<space/><link><target>Albigensian Crusade</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">15–16</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Madaule</arg><arg>1967</arg><arg name="pp">56–63</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Routes des chteaux cathares.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>This is a map signifying the routes of the Cathar castles (blue squares and lines) in the south of France around the turn of the 13th century.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The origins of the Cathars' beliefs are unclear but most theories agree they came from the<space/><link><target>Byzantine Empire</target></link><space/>mostly by the<space/><link><target>trade route</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and spread from the<space/><link><target>First Bulgarian Empire</target></link><space/>to the Netherlands. The name of<space/><link><target>Bulgarians</target></link><space/>(<italics>Bougres</italics>) was also applied to the Albigenses, and they maintained an association with the similar Christian movement of the<space/><link><target>Bogomilism</target><part>Bogomils</part></link><space/>(&quot;Friends of God&quot;) of<space/><link><target>Thrace</target></link>. &quot;That there was a substantial transmission of ritual and ideas from Bogomilism to Catharism is beyond reasonable doubt.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">31</arg></template><space/>Their doctrines have numerous resemblances to those of the Bogomils and the<space/><link><target>Paulicianism</target><part>Paulicians</part></link>, who influenced them, as well as the earlier<space/><link><target>Marcionites</target></link>, who were found in the same areas as the Paulicians, the<space/><link><target>Manicheans</target></link><space/>and the Christian<space/><link><target>Gnostics</target></link><space/>of the first few centuries AD, although, as many scholars, most notably<space/><link><target>Mark Gregory Pegg</target><part>Mark Pegg</part></link>, have pointed out, it would be erroneous to extrapolate direct, historical connections based on theoretical similarities perceived by modern scholars.<space/><link><target>St John Damascene</target></link>, writing in the 8th century AD, also notes of an earlier sect called the &quot;Cathari&quot;, in his book<space/><italics>On Heresies</italics>, taken from the epitome provided by<space/><link><target>Epiphanius of Salamis</target></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Panarion</target></link></italics>. He says of them: &quot;They absolutely reject those who marry a second time, and reject the possibility of penance [that is, forgiveness of sins after baptism]&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>John of Damascus</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="p">125</arg></template><space/>These are probably the same Cathari who are mentioned in Canon 8 of the First Ecumenical Council of Nicaea in the year 325, which states &quot;...[I]f those called Cathari come over [to the faith], let them first make profession that they are willing to communicate [share<space/><link><target>full communion</target></link>] with the twice-married, and grant pardon to those who have lapsed...&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaff</arg><arg>Wace</arg><arg>1994</arg><arg name="p">20</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It is likely that we have only a partial view of their beliefs, because the writings of the Cathars were mostly destroyed because of the doctrinal threat perceived by the Papacy;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Murphy</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="pp">26–27</arg></template><space/>much of our existing knowledge of the Cathars is derived from their opponents. Conclusions about Cathar ideology continue to be fiercely debated with commentators regularly accusing their opponents of speculation, distortion and bias. There are a few texts from the Cathars themselves which were preserved by their opponents (the<space/><italics>Rituel Cathare de Lyon</italics>) which give a glimpse of the inner workings of their faith, but these still leave many questions unanswered. One large text which has survived,<space/><italics>The Book of Two Principles</italics><space/>(<italics>Liber de duobus principiis</italics>),<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Dondaine</arg><arg>1939</arg></template><space/>elaborates the principles of dualistic theology from the point of view of some of the<space/><link><target>Albanenses</target></link><space/>Cathars.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Wakefield</arg><arg>Evans</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="pp">511–515</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It is now generally agreed by most scholars that identifiable historical Catharism did not emerge until at least 1143, when the first confirmed report of a group espousing similar beliefs is reported being active at Cologne by the cleric Eberwin of Steinfeld.<extension extension_name='ref'>See especially<space/><link><target>R.I. Moore</target></link>'s<space/><italics>The Origins of European Dissent</italics>, and the collection of essays<space/><italics>Heresy and the Persecuting Society in the Middle Ages: Essays on the Work of R.I. Moore</italics><space/>for a consideration of the origins of the Cathars, and proof against identifying earlier heretics in the West, such as those identified in 1025 at Monforte, outside<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link>, as being Cathars. Also see<space/><italics>Heresies of the High Middle Ages</italics>, a collection of pertinent documents on Western heresies of the High Middle Ages, edited by Walter Wakefield and Austin P. Evans.</extension><space/>A landmark in the &quot;institutional history&quot; of the Cathars was the<space/><link><target>Council of Saint-Flix</target><part>Council</part></link>, held in 1167 at<space/><link><target>Saint-Flix-Lauragais</target></link>, attended by many local figures and also by the<space/><link><target>Bogomilism</target><part>Bogomil</part></link><space/><italics>papa</italics><space/><link><target>Nicetas, Bogomil bishop</target><part>Nicetas</part></link>, the Cathar bishop of<space/><link><target>France</target><part>(northern) France</part></link><space/>and a leader of the Cathars of<space/><link><target>Lombardy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Cathars were largely a homegrown, Western European/Latin Christian phenomenon, springing up in the Rhineland cities (particularly Cologne) in the mid-12th century, northern France around the same time, and particularly southern France the<space/><link><target>Languedoc</target></link><space/>and the northern Italian cities in the mid-late 12th century. In the Languedoc and northern Italy, the Cathars attained their greatest popularity, surviving in the Languedoc, in much reduced form, up to around 1325 and in the Italian cities until the<space/><link><target>Medieval Inquisition</target><part>Inquisitions</part></link><space/>of the 1260s1300s finally rooted them out.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ladurie">See Emmanuel LeRoy Ladurie's<space/><italics>Montaillou: the Promised Land of Error</italics><space/>for a respected analysis of the social context of these last French Cathars, and<space/><italics>Power and Purity</italics><space/>by Carol Lansing for a consideration of 13th-century Catharism in Orvieto.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>General beliefs</heading><paragraph>Cathars, in general, formed an anti-<link><target>sacerdotal</target></link><space/>party in opposition to the Catholic Church, protesting against what they perceived to be the moral, spiritual and political corruption of the Church.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>G. K. Chesterton</target></link>, the English Roman Catholic author, claimed: &quot;... the medieval system began to be broken to pieces intellectually, long before it showed the slightest hint of falling to pieces morally. The huge early heresies, like the Albigenses, had not the faintest excuse in moral superiority.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Chesterton</arg><arg>1910</arg><arg name="p">[http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Contemporary reports suggest otherwise, however. St Bernard of Clairvaux, for instance, although opposed to the Cathars, said of them in Sermon 65 on the Song of Songs:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg name="If you question the heretic about his faith, nothing is more Christian; if about his daily converse, nothing more blameless; and what he says he proves by his actions ... As regards his life and conduct, he cheats no one, pushes ahead of no one, does violence to no one. Moreover, his cheeks are pale with fasting; he does not eat the bread of idleness; he labours with his hands and thus makes his living. Women are leaving their husbands, men are putting aside their wives, and they all flock to those heretics! Clerics and priests, the youthful and the adult among them, are leaving their congregations and churches and are often found in the company of weavers of both sexes.{{sfnp|Wakefield|Evans|1991|p"><space/>136}}<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When Bishop Fulk, a key leader of the anti-Cathar persecutions, excoriated the Languedoc Knights for not pursuing the heretics more diligently, he received the reply:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="We cannot. We have been reared in their midst. We have relatives among them and we see them living lives of perfection.{{sfnp|O'Shea|2000|p">42}}<space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sacraments</heading><paragraph>In contrast to the Catholic Church, the Cathars had but one sacrament, the<space/><link><target>Consolamentum</target></link>, or Consolation. This involved a brief spiritual ceremony to remove all sin from the believer and to induct him or her into the next higher level as a perfect.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><space/>Unlike the Roman Catholic<space/><link><target>sacrament of Penance</target></link>, the Consolamentum could be taken only once.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus it has been alleged that many believers would eventually receive the Consolamentum as death drew near, performing the ritual of liberation at a moment when the heavy obligations of purity required of Perfecti would be temporally short. Some of those who received the sacrament of the consolamentum upon their death-beds may thereafter have shunned further food or drink in order to speed death. This has been termed the<space/><italics>endura</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Murray<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Suicide in the Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.ca/books?id</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-19-820539-2</arg></template></extension><space/>It was claimed by some of the Catholic writers that when a Cathar, after receiving the Consolamentum, began to show signs of recovery he or she would be smothered in order to ensure his or her entry into paradise. Other than at such moments of<space/><italics>extremis</italics>, little evidence exists to suggest this was a common Cathar practice.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Barber</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">103–104</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Cathars also refused the Catholic Sacrament of the<space/><link><target>eucharist</target></link><space/>saying that it could not possibly be the body of Christ. They also refused to partake in the practice of<space/><link><target>Baptism</target></link><space/>by water. The following two quotes are taken from the Catholic Inquisitor<space/><link><target>Bernard Gui</target></link>s experiences with the Cathar practices and beliefs:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg>Then they attack and vituperate, in turn, all the [[sacraments]] of the Church, especially the sacrament of the [[eucharist]], saying that it cannot contain the body of Christ, for had this been as great as the largest mountain Christians would have entirely consumed it before this. They assert that the host comes from straw, that it passes through the tails of horses, to wit, when the flour is cleaned by a sieve (of horse hair); that, moreover, it passes through the body and comes to a vile end, which, they say, could not happen if God were in it.{{sfnp|Burr|1996}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg>Of baptism, they assert that the water is material and corruptible and is therefore the creation of the evil power, and cannot sanctify the spirit, but that the churchmen sell this water out of avarice, just as they sell earth for the burial of the dead, and oil to the sick when they anoint them, and as they sell the confession of sins as made to the priests.{{sfnp|Burr|1996}}</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theology</heading><paragraph>Some believe that the Catharist conception of Jesus resembled<space/><link><target>nontrinitarian</target></link><space/><link><target>modalistic monarchianism</target></link><space/>(Sabellianism) in the West and<space/><link><target>adoptionism</target></link><space/>in the East.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Columbia Encyclopedia<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Columbia University Press<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Cathari</arg></template>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://encyclopedia2.thefreedictionary.com/Albigensians<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Encyclopaedia 2<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Free dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Albigensians</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Bernard of Clairvaux</target></link>'s biographer and other sources accuse some Cathars of<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link>,<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">41</arg><arg name="ps">: "Bernard's biographer identifies another group in Toulouse which he calls Arians, who have sometimes been identified as Cathars but the evidence is scant. It is most likely that the first Cathars to penetrate Languedoc appealed..."</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Luscombe</arg><arg>Riley-Smith</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">522</arg><arg name="ps">: "Even though his biographer does not describe their beliefs, Arians would have been an appropriate label for moderate dualists with an unorthodox Christology, and the term was certainly later used in Languedoc to describe Cathars."</arg></template><space/>and some scholars see Cathar Christology as having traces of earlier Arian roots.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">115</arg><arg name="ps">: "However, they became converts to Arian Christianity, which later developed into Catharism. Arian and Cathar doctrines were sufficiently different from Catholic doctrine that the two branches were incompatible."</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Kienzle</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">92</arg><arg name="ps">: "The term ‘Arian' is often joined with ’Manichean' to designate Cathars. Geoffrey's comment implies that he and others called those heretics ’weavers', whereas they called themselves ’Arians'. Moreover, the Arians, who could have been...."</arg></template><space/>According to some of their contemporary enemies Cathars did not accept the Trinitarian understanding of Jesus, but considered him the human form of an angel similar to<space/><link><target>Docetic</target></link><space/>Christology.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Townsend</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">9</arg><arg name="ps">: "The Cathars did not accept the Church doctrine of Jesus being the 'Son of God'. They believed that Jesus was not embodied in the human form but an angel (Docetic Christology), which echoed back to the Arian controversy."</arg></template><space/><link><target>Zo Oldenbourg</target></link><space/>(2000) compared the Cathars to &quot;Western Buddhists&quot; because she considered that their view of the doctrine of &quot;resurrection&quot; taught by Jesus was, in fact, similar to the Buddhist doctrine of<space/><link><target>reincarnation</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Maseko</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">482</arg><arg name="ps">: "In the book 'Massacre at Montsegur' (a book widely regarded by medievalists as having a pronounced, pro-Cathar bias) the Cathars are referred to as 'Western Buddhists' because of their belief that the Doctrine of 'resurrection' taught."</arg></template><space/>The Cathars taught that to regain angelic status one had to renounce the material self completely. Until one was prepared to do so, he/she would be stuck in a cycle of reincarnation, condemned to live on the corrupt Earth.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">11</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The alleged sacred texts of the Cathars besides the New Testament, include The Gospel of the Secret Supper, or John's Interrogation and The Book of the Two Principles.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Gnostic Bible, Google Books.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Social relationships</heading><paragraph>Killing was abhorrent to the Cathars. Consequently, abstention from all animal food (<link><target>Pescetarianism</target><part>sometimes exempting fish</part></link>) was enjoined of the Perfecti. The Perfecti avoided eating anything considered to be a by-product of sexual reproduction.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><space/>War and<space/><link><target>capital punishment</target></link><space/>were also condemnedan abnormality in Medieval Europe. In a world where few could read, their rejection of oath-taking marked them as social outcasts.</paragraph><paragraph>Cathars also rejected marriage. Their theology was based principally on the belief that the physical world, including the flesh, was irredeemably evilas it stemmed from the evil principle or &quot;<link><target>demiurge</target></link>&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Weber</arg><arg>1908b</arg></template><space/>Therefore, reproduction was viewed by them as a moral evil to be avoidedas it continued the chain of reincarnation and suffering in the material world. It was claimed by their opponents that, given this loathing for procreation, they generally resorted to sodomy. Such was the situation that a charge of heresy leveled against a suspected Cathar was usually dismissed if the accused could show he was legally married.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Berruguete ordeal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>This portrays the story of a disputation between<space/><link><target>Saint Dominic</target></link><space/>and the Cathars (Albigensians), in which the books of both were thrown on a fire and St Dominic's books were miraculously preserved from the flames. Painting by<space/><link><target>Pedro Berruguete</target></link></part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Organization</heading><paragraph>It has been alleged that the Cathar Church of the Languedoc had a relatively<space/><link><target>Flat organization</target><part>flat structure</part></link>, distinguishing between<space/><italics>perfecti</italics><space/>(a term they did not use, instead<space/><italics>bonhommes</italics>) and<space/><italics>credentes</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><space/>By about 1140, liturgy and a system of doctrine had been established.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">49–50</arg></template><space/>It created a number of<space/><link><target>Episcopal see</target><part>bishoprics</part></link>, first at Albi around 1165<space/><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">2–4</arg></template><space/>and after the 1167 Council at Saint-Flix-Lauragais sites at Toulouse, Carcassonne, and Agen, so that four bishoprics were in existence by 1200.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">49–50</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">70</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">140</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In about 1225, during a lull in the<space/><link><target>Albigensian Crusade</target></link>, the bishopric of Razes was added. Bishops were supported by their two assistants: a<space/><italics>filius maior</italics><space/>(typically the successor) and a<space/><italics>filius minor</italics>, who were further assisted by deacons.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Moore</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">137</arg></template><space/>The<space/><italics>perfecti</italics><space/>were the spiritual elite, highly respected by many of the local people, leading a life of austerity and charity.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><space/>In the apostolic fashion they ministered to the people and travelled in pairs.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Role of women and gender</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cathars expelled.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Cathars being expelled from Carcassonne in 1209. In this group, women appear to be nearly as numerous as men and the Crusaders seem to give women equally harsh treatment for their beliefs.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Catharism has been seen as giving women the greatest opportunities for independent action since women were found as being believers as well as Perfecti, who were able to administer the sacrament of the<space/><italics>consolamentum</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Ward</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">241–42</arg></template><space/>The Cathars believed that one would be repeatedly<space/><link><target>reincarnation</target><part>reincarnated</part></link><space/>until one commits to the self-denial of the material world, which meant that a man could be reincarnated as a woman and<space/><link><target>Vice-versa</target><part>vice versa</part></link>, thereby rendering gender completely meaningless.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">10–12</arg></template><space/>The spirit was of utmost importance to the Cathars and was described as being<space/><link><target>wikt:Special:Search/immaterial</target><part>immaterial</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sexless</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">10–12</arg></template><space/>Because of this belief, the Cathars saw women equally capable of being spiritual leaders, which undermined the very concept of gender held by the<space/><link><target>Catholic Church</target></link><space/>and did not go unnoticed.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">25–26</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The women that were accused of being<space/><link><target>Heresy</target><part>heretics</part></link><space/>in early<space/><link><target>medieval Christianity</target></link><space/>included those labeled<space/><link><target>Gnostics</target></link>, Cathars, and<space/><link><target>Beguines</target></link>, as well as several other groups that were sometimes &quot;tortured and executed&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Clark</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">412</arg></template><space/>The Cathars, like the Gnostics who preceded them, assigned more importance to the role of<space/><link><target>Mary Magdalene</target></link><space/>in the spread of early<space/><link><target>Christianity</target></link><space/>than the Church previously did. Her vital role as a teacher contributed to the Cathar belief that women could serve as spiritual leaders. Women were found to be included in the Perfecti in significant numbers, with numerous receiving the<space/><italics>consolamentum</italics><space/>after being widowed.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Ward</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">241–42</arg></template><space/>Having reverence for the<space/><link><target>Gospel of John</target></link>, the Cathars saw Mary Magdalene as perhaps even more important than<space/><link><target>Saint Peter</target></link>, the founder of the Church.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">80–81</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Cathar movement proved to be extremely successful in gaining female followers because of its<space/><link><target>proto-feminist</target></link><space/>teachings along with the general feeling of exclusion from the Catholic church. Catharism attracted numerous women with the promise of a<space/><link><target>sacerdotal</target></link><space/>role that the Catholic Church did not allow.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaus</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">114</arg></template><space/>Catharism let women become a<space/><link><target>Cathar Perfect</target><part>perfect</part></link><space/>of the faith, a position of far more prestige than anything the Church offered.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">40–43</arg></template><space/>These female perfects were required to adhere to a strict and ascetic lifestyle, but were still able to have their own houses.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Kaelber</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">120</arg></template><space/>Although many women found something attractive in Catharism, not all found its teachings convincing. A notable example is<space/><link><target>Hildegard of Bingen</target></link>, who in 1163 gave a widely renowned<space/><link><target>sermon</target></link><space/>against the Cathars in<space/><link><target>Cologne</target></link>. During this speech, Hildegard announced a state of eternal punishment and<space/><link><target>damnation</target></link><space/>to all those who accepted Cathar beliefs.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Newman</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">753–755</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>While women perfects rarely traveled to preach the faith, they still played a vital role in the spreading of the Catharism by establishing group homes for women.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">41</arg></template><space/>Though it was extremely uncommon, there were isolated cases of female Cathars departing from their homes to spread the faith.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Weis</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="p">122</arg></template><space/>In the Cathar group homes, women were educated in the faith and these women would go on to bear children who would then also become believers. Through this pattern the faith grew<space/><link><target>exponential function</target><part>exponentially</part></link><space/>through the efforts of women as each generation passed.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">41</arg></template><space/>Among some groups of Cathars there were even more women than there were men.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Walther</arg><arg>1965</arg><arg name="p">167</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despite women having an instrumental role in the growing of the faith,<space/><link><target>misogyny</target></link><space/>was not completely absent from the Cathar movement. Some seemingly misogynistic Cathar beliefs include that one's last<space/><link><target>incarnation</target></link><space/>had to be experienced as a man to break the cycle.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">42</arg></template><space/>This belief was inspired by later French Cathars, which taught that women must be reborn as men in order to achieve<space/><link><target>salvation</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaus</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">114</arg></template><space/>Another one is that the sexual allure of women impedes man's ability to reject the material world.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">42</arg></template><space/>Toward the end of the Cathar movement, French Catharism became more misogynistic and started the practice of excluding women perfects.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaus</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">114</arg></template><space/>However, the influence of these type of misogynistic beliefs and practices remained rather limited on the whole of Catharism as later Italian perfects still included women.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schaus</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">114</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Suppression</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Garotte - Excerpt from Pedro Berruguete - Saint Dominic Presiding over an Auto-da-fe.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>Cathars being burnt at the stake in an ''<link><target>auto-de-f</target></link>'' presided over by Saint Dominic, as depicted by<space/><link><target>Pedro Berruguete</target></link>.</part></link>In 1147,<space/><link><target>Pope Eugene III</target></link><space/>sent a<space/><link><target>Papal legate</target><part>legate</part></link><space/>to the Cathar district in order to arrest the progress of the Cathars. The few isolated successes of<space/><link><target>Bernard of Clairvaux</target></link><space/>could not obscure the poor results of this mission, which clearly showed the power of the sect in the Languedoc at that period. The missions of<space/><link><target>Cardinal Peter of St. Chrysogonus</target></link><space/>to Toulouse and the Toulousain in 1178, and of<space/><link><target>Henry of Marcy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cardinal-bishop of Albano</target></link>, in 118081, obtained merely momentary successes. Henry's armed expedition, which took the stronghold at<space/><link><target>Lavaur, Tarn</target><part>Lavaur</part></link>, did not extinguish the movement.</paragraph><paragraph>Decisions of Catholic Church councilsin particular, those of the Council of<space/><link><target>Tours</target></link><space/>(1163) and of the<space/><link><target>Third Council of the Lateran</target></link><space/>(1179)had scarcely more effect upon the Cathars. When<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link><space/>came to power in 1198, he was resolved to deal with them.</paragraph><paragraph>At first Innocent tried pacific conversion, and sent a number of legates into the Cathar regions. They had to contend not only with the Cathars, the nobles who protected them, and the people who respected them, but also with many of the<space/><link><target>bishop</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the region, who resented the considerable authority the<space/><link><target>Pope</target></link><space/>had conferred upon his legates. In 1204, Innocent III suspended a number of bishops in<space/><link><target>Occitania</target></link>; in 1205 he appointed a new and vigorous<space/><link><target>bishop of Toulouse</target></link>, the former<space/><link><target>troubadour</target></link><space/><link><target>Folquet de Marselha</target><part>Foulques</part></link>. In 1206<space/><link><target>Diego of Osma</target></link><space/>and his canon, the future<space/><link><target>Saint Dominic</target></link>, began a programme of conversion in Languedoc; as part of this, Catholic-Cathar public debates were held at<space/><link><target>Verfeil, Haute-Garonne</target><part>Verfeil</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Servian (commune)</target><part>Servian</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Pamiers</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Montral, Aude</target><part>Montral</part></link><space/>and elsewhere.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Saint Dominic</target></link><space/>met and debated with the Cathars in 1203 during his mission to the Languedoc. He concluded that only preachers who displayed real sanctity, humility and asceticism could win over convinced Cathar believers. The institutional Church as a general rule did not possess these spiritual warrants.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Johnson<space/></arg><arg><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>251</arg></template><space/>His conviction led eventually to the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Dominican Order</target></link><space/>in 1216. The order was to live up to the terms of his famous rebuke, &quot;Zeal must be met by zeal, humility by humility, false sanctity by real sanctity, preaching falsehood by preaching truth.&quot; However, even St. Dominic managed only a few converts among the Cathari.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Albigensian Crusade</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Albigensian Crusade</arg></template><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date"><space/>July 2014</arg></template><link><target>File:Albigensian Crusade 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>270px</part><part><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link><space/>excommunicating the Albigensians (left), Massacre against the Albigensians by the crusaders (right)</part></link>In January 1208 the papal legate,<space/><link><target>Pierre de Castelnau</target></link>a Cistercian monk, theologian and canon lawyerwas sent to meet the ruler of the area,<space/><link><target>Raymond VI, Count of Toulouse</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">68–69</arg></template><space/>Known for excommunicating noblemen who protected the Cathars, Castelnau<space/><link><target>excommunicate</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>Raymond for<space/><link><target>abettor</target><part>abetting</part></link><space/>heresy following an allegedly fierce argument during which Raymond supposedly threatened Castelnau with violence.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg>72–73</arg></template><space/>Shortly thereafter, Castelnau was murdered as he returned to Rome, allegedly by a knight in the service of Count Raymond. His body was returned and laid to rest in the Abbey at Saint Gilles. As soon as he heard of the murder, the Pope ordered the legates to preach a<space/><link><target>Albigensian Crusade</target><part>crusade</part></link><space/>against the Cathars and wrote a letter to<space/><link><target>Philip II of France</target><part>Philip Augustus, King of France</part></link>, appealing for his interventionor an intervention led by his son,<space/><link><target>Louis VIII of France</target><part>Louis</part></link>. This was not the first appeal but some see the murder of the legate as a turning point in papal policy. Others claim it as a fortuitous event in allowing the Pope to excite popular opinion and to renew his pleas for intervention in the south. The chronicler of the crusade which followed,<space/><link><target>Peter of Vaux de Cernay</target></link>, portrays the sequence of events in such a way that, having failed in his effort to peaceably demonstrate the errors of Catharism, the Pope then called a formal crusade, appointing a series of leaders to head the assault. The French King refused to lead the crusade himself, and could not spare his son to do so eitherdespite his victory against<space/><link><target>John, King of England</target></link>, there were still pressing issues with Flanders and the empire and the threat of an<space/><link><target>House of Chteaudun</target><part>Angevin</part></link><space/>revival. Philip did however sanction the participation of some of his more bellicose and ambitioussome might say dangerousbarons, notably<space/><link><target>Simon de Montfort, 5th Earl of Leicester</target><part>Simon de Montfort</part></link><space/>and Bouchard de Marly. There followed twenty years of war against the Cathars and their allies in the Languedoc: the Albigensian Crusade.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Carcasonneouterwall.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>260px</part><part><link><target>Cit de Carcassonne</target></link><space/>today</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>This war pitted the nobles of the north of France against those of the south. The widespread northern enthusiasm for the Crusade was partially inspired by a papal decree permitting the confiscation of lands owned by Cathars and their supporters. This not only angered the lords of the south but also the French King, who was at least nominally the<space/><link><target>Suzerainty</target><part>suzerain</part></link><space/>of the lords whose lands were now open to<space/><link><target>Plunder</target><part>despoliation</part></link><space/>and seizure. Philip Augustus wrote to Pope Innocent in strong terms to point this outbut the Pope did not change his policy. As the Languedoc was supposedly teeming with Cathars and Cathar sympathisers, this made the region a target for northern French noblemen looking to acquire new fiefs. The barons of the north headed south to do battle.</paragraph><paragraph>Their first target was the lands of the Trencavel, powerful lords of Albi, Carcassonne and the Razesbut a family with few allies in the Midi. Little was thus done to form a regional coalition and the crusading army was able to take Carcassonne, the Trencavel capital, incarcerating Raymond Roger in his own citadel where he died, allegedly of natural causes; champions of the<space/><link><target>Occitania</target><part>Occitan</part></link><space/>cause from that day to this believe he was murdered. Simon de Montfort was granted the Trencavel lands by the Pope and did homage for them to the King of France, thus incurring the enmity of<space/><link><target>Peter II of Aragon</target></link><space/>who had held aloof from the conflict, even acting as a mediator at the time of the siege of Carcassonne. The remainder of the first of the two Cathar wars now essentially focused on Simon's attempt to hold on to his fabulous gains through winters where he was faced, with only a small force of confederates operating from the main winter camp at Fanjeau, with the desertion of local lords who had sworn fealty to him out of necessityand attempts to enlarge his newfound domains in the summer when his forces were greatly augmented by reinforcements from northern France, Germany and elsewhere. Summer campaigns saw him not only retake, sometimes with brutal reprisals, what he had lost in the 'close' season, but also seek to widen his sphere of operationand we see him in action in the Aveyron at St. Antonin and on the banks of the Rhone at Beaucaire. Simon's greatest triumph was the victory against superior numbers at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Muret</target></link>a battle which saw not only the defeat of Raymond of Toulouse and his Occitan alliesbut also the death of Peter of Aragonand the effective end of the ambitions of the house of Aragon/Barcelona in the Languedoc. This was in the medium and longer term of much greater significance to the royal house of France than it was to de Montfortand with the battle of Bouvines was to secure the position of Philip Augustus vis a vis England and the Empire. The<space/><link><target>Battle of Muret</target></link><space/>was a massive step in the creation of the unified French kingdom and the country we know todayalthough Edward III, the Black Prince and Henry V would threaten later to shake these foundations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Massacre</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dame guiraude supplice.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>210px</part><part>Massacre against the Albigensians by the crusaders</part></link>The crusader army came under the command, both spiritually and militarily, of the papal legate<space/><link><target>Arnaud-Amaury</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Abbot</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Cteaux</target></link>. In the first significant engagement of the war, the town of<space/><link><target>Bziers</target></link><space/>was<space/><link><target>siege</target><part>besieged</part></link><space/>on 22 July 1209. The Catholic inhabitants of the city were granted the freedom to leave unharmed, but many refused and opted to stay and fight alongside the Cathars.</paragraph><paragraph>The Cathars spent much of 1209 fending off the crusaders. The Bziers army attempted a<space/><link><target>sortie</target></link><space/>but was quickly defeated, then pursued by the crusaders back through the gates and into the city. Arnaud-Amaury, the Cistercian abbot-commander, is supposed to have been asked how to tell Cathars from<space/><link><target>Catholics</target></link>. His reply, recalled by<space/><link><target>Caesar of Heisterbach</target></link>, a fellow<space/><link><target>Cistercian</target></link>, thirty years later was<space/><italics>&quot;<link><target>Caedite eos. Novit enim Dominus qui sunt eius</target></link>&quot;</italics>&quot;Kill them all, the Lord will recognise His own&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="quote"><space/>Caedite eos. Novit enim Dominus qui sunt eis<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Caesarius<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>of Heisterbach<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Caesarius Heiserbacencis monachi ordinis Cisterciensis, Dialogus miraculorum<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>J<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Strange<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Cologne<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1851<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>JM Heberle<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>296–8</arg></template>. Caesarius (c) was a Cistercian Master of Novices.</extension><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Moore</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">180</arg><arg name="ps">. Note: Another Cistercian writing a few years after the events makes no mention of this remark while Caesar of Heisterbach wrote forty years later, however both are consistent with Arnaud's report to Pope Innocent III about the massacre.</arg></template><space/>The doors of the church of St Mary Magdalene were broken down and the refugees dragged out and slaughtered. Reportedly, 7,000 people died there. Elsewhere in the town many more thousands were mutilated and killed. Prisoners were blinded, dragged behind horses, and used for target practice.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Johnson</arg><arg>1976</arg><arg name="p">252</arg></template><space/>What remained of the city was razed by fire. Arnaud-Amaury wrote to<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link>, &quot;Today your Holiness, twenty thousand heretics were put to the sword, regardless of rank, age, or sex.&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Innocent III</arg><arg>1855</arg><arg name="loc">Vol. 216</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sibly</arg><arg>Sibly</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">128</arg></template><space/>The permanent population of Bziers at that time was then probably no more than 5,000, but local refugees seeking shelter within the city walls could conceivably have increased the number to 20,000.</paragraph><paragraph>After the success of his siege of<space/><link><target>Carcassonne</target></link>, which followed the<space/><link><target>Massacre at Bziers</target></link><space/>in 1209, Simon de Montfort was designated as leader of the Crusader army. Prominent opponents of the Crusaders were<space/><link><target>Raymond Roger Trencavel</target></link>, viscount of Carcassonne, and his feudal overlord<space/><link><target>Peter II of Aragon</target><part>Peter II</part></link>, the king of<space/><link><target>Crown of Aragon</target><part>Aragon</part></link>, who held fiefdoms and had a number of vassals in the region. Peter died fighting against the crusade on 12 September 1213 at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Muret</target></link>. Simon de Montfort was killed on 25 June 1218 after maintaining<space/><link><target>Siege of Toulouse (12171218)</target><part>a siege of Toulouse</part></link><space/>for nine months.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Chanson de la Croisade Albigeoise</target></link></italics><space/>laisse 205.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Treaty and persecution</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Filip2 albigensti.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>210px</part><part>The burning of the Cathar heretics</part></link>The official war ended in the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Paris (1229)</target></link>, by which the king of France dispossessed the<space/><link><target>house of Toulouse</target></link><space/>of the greater part of its<space/><link><target>fiefdom</target><part>fiefs</part></link>, and that of the Trencavels (<link><target>Viscount</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of Bziers and Carcassonne) of the whole of their fiefs. The independence of the princes of the Languedoc was at an end. But in spite of the wholesale massacre of Cathars during the war, Catharism was not yet extinguished and Catholic forces would continue to pursue Cathars.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1215, the bishops of the Catholic Church met at the<space/><link><target>Fourth Council of the Lateran</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Pope Innocent III</target></link>; part of the agenda was combating the Cathar heresy.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">179–81</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Medieval Inquisition</target><part>Inquisition</part></link><space/>was established in 1234 to uproot the remaining Cathars.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">230–232</arg></template><space/>Operating in the south at Toulouse, Albi,<space/><link><target>Carcassonne</target></link><space/>and other towns during the whole of the 13th century, and a great part of the 14th, it succeeded in crushing Catharism as a popular movement and driving its remaining adherents underground.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">230–232</arg></template><space/>Cathars who refused to recant were hanged, or burnt at the stake.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Martin</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="pp">105–121</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From May 1243 to March 1244, the Cathar fortress of<space/><link><target>Montsgur</target></link><space/>was besieged by the troops of the<space/><link><target>seneschal</target></link><space/>of Carcassonne and the<space/><link><target>archbishop of Narbonne</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">238–40</arg></template><space/>On 16 March 1244, a large and symbolically important massacre took place, where over 200<space/><link><target>Cathar Perfect</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were burnt in an enormous pyre at the<space/><italics>prat dels cremats</italics><space/>(&quot;field of the burned&quot;) near the foot of the castle.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">238–40</arg></template><space/>Moreover, the Church decreed lesser chastisements against laymen suspected of sympathy with Cathars, at the 1235 Council of<space/><link><target>Narbonne</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="type"><space/>[[Papal Bull|Bull]]<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Pope Innocent IV</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Innocent IV<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Ad extirpanda]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1252</arg></template>.</extension><link><target>Image:CatharCross.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Inquisitors required heretical sympathisers repentant first offenders to sew a yellow cross onto their clothes.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Weis</arg><arg>2001</arg><arg name="pp">11–12</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A popular though as yet unsubstantiated theory holds that a small party of Cathar Perfects escaped from the fortress before the massacre at<space/><italics>prat dels cremats</italics>. It is widely held in the Cathar region to this day that the escapees took with them<space/><italics>le trsor cathar</italics>. What this treasure consisted of has been a matter of considerable speculation: claims range from sacred Gnostic texts to the Cathars' accumulated wealth, which might have included the Holy Grail (see the Section on Historical Scholarship, below).</paragraph><paragraph>Hunted by the Inquisition and deserted by the nobles of their districts, the Cathars became more and more scattered fugitives: meeting surreptitiously in forests and mountain wilds. Later insurrections broke out under the leadership of<space/><link><target>Roger-Bernard II, Count of Foix</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Aimery III of Narbonne</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bernard Dlicieux</target></link>, a Franciscan friar later prosecuted for his adherence to another heretical movement, that of the<space/><link><target>Fraticelli</target><part>Spiritual Franciscans</part></link><space/>at the beginning of the 14th century. But by this time the Inquisition had grown very powerful. Consequently, many presumed to be Cathars were summoned to appear before it. Precise indications of this are found in the registers of the Inquisitors,<space/><link><target>Bernard of Caux</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean de St Pierre</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Geoffroy d'Ablis</target></link>, and others. The parfaits it was said only rarely recanted, and hundreds were burnt. Repentant lay believers were punished, but their lives were spared as long as they did not relapse. Having recanted, they were obliged to sew yellow crosses onto their outdoor clothing and to live apart from other Catholics, at least for a while.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Annihilation</heading><paragraph>After several decades of harassment and re-proselytising, and perhaps even more importantly, the systematic destruction of their religious texts, the sect was exhausted and could find no more adepts. The leader of a Cathar revival in the Pyrenean foothills,<space/><link><target>Peire Autier</target></link><space/>was captured and executed in April 1310 in Toulouse.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">237–38</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">242–43</arg></template><space/>After 1330, the records of the Inquisition contain very few proceedings against Cathars. The last known Cathar perfectus in the Languedoc,<space/><link><target>Guillaume Blibaste</target></link>, was executed in the autumn of 1321.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">239–46</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Sumption</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">242–43</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From the mid-12th century onwards, Italian Catharism came under increasing pressure from the Pope and the Inquisition, &quot;spelling the beginning of the end&quot;.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>O'Shea</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">230</arg></template><space/>Other movements, such as the<space/><link><target>Waldensians</target></link><space/>and the pantheistic<space/><link><target>Brethren of the Free Spirit</target></link>, which suffered persecution in the same area, survived in remote areas and in small numbers into the 14th and 15th centuries. Some Waldensian ideas were absorbed into early<space/><link><target>Protestant</target></link><space/>sects, such as the<space/><link><target>Hussites</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lollards</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Moravian Church</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Herrnhut</target><part>Herrnhuters of Germany</part></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later history</heading><paragraph>After the suppression of Catharism, the descendants of Cathars were at times required to live outside towns and their defences. They thus retained a certain Cathar identity, despite having returned to the Catholic religion.</paragraph><paragraph>Any use of the term &quot;Cathar&quot; to refer to people after the suppression of Catharism in the 14th century is a cultural or ancestral reference, and has no religious implication. Nevertheless, interest in the Cathars, their history, legacy and beliefs continues.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Pays Cathare</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Montsegur-w02.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The castle of<space/><link><target>Chteau de Montsgur</target><part>Montsgur</part></link><space/>was razed after 1244. The current fortress follows French<space/><link><target>Military engineering</target><part>military architecture</part></link><space/>of the 17th century.</part></link>The term<space/><italics>Pays Cathare</italics>, French meaning &quot;Cathar Country&quot; is used to highlight the Cathar heritage and history of the region where Catharism was traditionally strongest. This area is centred around fortresses such as<space/><link><target>Chteau de Montsgur</target><part>Montsgur</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carcassonne</target></link>; also the French<space/><link><target>departments of France</target><part>dpartement</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Aude</target></link><space/>uses the title<space/><italics>Pays Cathare</italics><space/>in tourist brochures.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.payscathare.com/www/contenu/d_payscathare.asp'>Pays Cathare</link></extension><space/>These areas have ruins from the wars against the Cathars which are still visible today.</paragraph><paragraph>Some criticise the promotion of the identity of<space/><italics>Pays Cathare</italics><space/>as an exaggeration for<space/><link><target>tourism</target><part>tourist</part></link><space/>purposes. Actually, most of the promoted<space/><link><target>Cathar castles</target></link><space/>were not built by Cathars but by local lords and later many of them were rebuilt and extended for strategic purposes. Good examples of these are the magnificent castles of<space/><link><target>Queribus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Peyrepertuse</target></link><space/>which are both perched on the side of precipitous drops on the last folds of the Corbieres mountains. They were for several hundred years frontier fortresses belonging to the French crown and most of what is still there dates from a post-Cathar era. The Cathars sought refuge at these sites. Many consider the<space/><link><target>County of Foix</target></link><space/>to be the actual historical centre of Catharism.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Oldest account of ordinary people told in their own words</heading><paragraph>In an effort to find the few remaining heretics in and around the village of<space/><link><target>Montaillou</target></link>, Jacques Fournier,<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Diocese of Pamiers</target><part>Bishop of Pamiers</part></link>, future<space/><link><target>Pope Benedict XII</target></link>, had those suspected of heresy interrogated in the presence of scribes who recorded their conversations. The late 13th- to early 14th-century document, discovered in the Vatican archives in the 1960s, and edited by<space/><link><target>Jean Duvernoy</target></link><space/>is the oldest<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><space/>known account of the daily lives of ordinary people told in their own words. It was translated by<space/><link><target>Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie</target></link><space/>as<space/><italics>Montaillou: The Promised Land of Error</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ladurie"></extension><space/>In the original, the book was entitled<space/><italics>Montaillou, Occitan Village</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical scholarship</heading><paragraph>The publication of the early scholarly book<space/><italics>Crusade against the Grail</italics><space/>by the young German<space/><link><target>Otto Rahn</target></link><space/>in the 1930s rekindled interest in the connection between the Cathars and the<space/><link><target>Holy Grail</target></link>, especially in Germany. Rahn was convinced that the 13th-century work<space/><italics><link><target>Parzival</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Wolfram von Eschenbach</target></link><space/>was a veiled account of the Cathars. The philosopher and Nazi government official<space/><link><target>Alfred Rosenberg</target></link><space/>speaks favourably of the Cathars in<space/><italics><link><target>The Myth of the Twentieth Century</target></link></italics>.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Academic books in English first appeared at the beginning of the millennium:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>for example, Malcolm Lambert's<space/><italics>The Cathars</italics><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Lambert</arg><arg>1998</arg></template><space/>and Malcolm Barber's<space/><italics>The Cathars</italics>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Barber</arg><arg>2000</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Starting in the 1990s and continuing to the present day, historians like R.I Moore have radically challenged the extent to which Catharism, as an institutionalized religion, actually existed. Building off the work of French historians such as Monique Zerner and Uwe Brunn, Moores<space/><italics>The War on Heresy</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>R.I Moore,<space/><italics>The War on Heresy</italics>. New York: Belknap Press, 2012.</extension><space/>argues that Catharism was contrived from the resources of [the] well-stocked imaginations of churchmen, with occasional reinforcement from miscellaneous and independent manifestations of local anticlericalism or apostolic enthusiasm.<extension extension_name='ref'>Moores summary in a review, H-France Review, 12, 44 (2012),</extension><space/>In short, Moore claims that the men and women persecuted as Cathars were not the followers of a secret religion imported from the East, instead they were part of a broader spiritual revival taking place in the later twelfth and early thirteenth century. Moores work is indicative of a larger historiographical trend towards examination of how heresy was constructed by the Church.<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Professor Peter Biller, review of The War on Heresy: Faith and Power in Medieval Europe, (review no. 1546), with Professor Robert I. Moore's responsehttp://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/1546Date accessed: 9 October, 2015</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In art and music</heading><paragraph>The principal legacy of the Cathar movement is in the poems and songs of the Cathar<space/><link><target>troubadors</target></link>, though this artistic legacy is only a smaller part of the wider<space/><link><target>Occitan</target></link><space/>linguistic and artistic heritage. Recent artistic projects concentrating on the Cathar element in Provenal and troubador art include commercial recording projects by Thomas Binkley, electric hurdy-gurdy artist Valentin Clastrier and his CD Heresie dedicated to the church at Cathars,<extension extension_name='ref'>L'Agonie du Languedoc: Claude Marti / Studio der frhen Musik Thomas Binkley, dir. EMI &quot;Reflexe&quot; 1C 063-30 132 [LP-Stereo]1975</extension><space/>La Nef,<extension extension_name='ref'>La Nef. Montsgur: La tragdie cathare. Dorian Recordings.DOR-90243</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jordi Savall</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Savall The Forgotten Kingdom: The Cathar Tragedy The Albigensian Crusade AVSA9873 A+C Alia Vox 2009</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph>The Cathars have been depicted or re-interpreted in popular books, video games, and films such as<space/><italics><link><target>The Holy Blood and the Holy Grail</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Bone Clocks</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Labyrinth (novel)</target><part>Labyrinth</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Broken Sword 5: The Serpent's Curse</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Paulo Coelho</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Brida_(novel)</target><part>Brida</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Bernard Cornwell</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>The Grail Quest</target></link></italics><space/>series and<space/><link><target>Theodore Roszak (scholar)</target><part>Theodore Roszak</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Flicker_(novel)</target><part>Flicker</part></link>. A number of semi-fictional conspiracy theories have been published that integrate the Cathars into their ideas, especially in France and Germany.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Catharism, along with other Christian heresies including<space/><link><target>Fraticelli</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Waldensianism</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lollardy</target></link>, is featured in the<space/><link><target>grand strategy game</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Crusader Kings II</target></link></italics>, It is notable as being the only Catholic heresy in-game that allows female priests; it also grants the option of absolute cognatic succession laws (such as<space/><link><target>Absolute primogeniture</target></link>) and the appointment of female generals and councilors.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Crusader Kings II</target></link>, developer:<link><target>Paradox Development Studio</target></link>, publisher:<link><target>Paradox Interactive</target></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Antonin Gadal</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Crusades</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Manisola</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><bold>Notes</bold><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bibliography</bold><template><target>Refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Inquisition & Power<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John H<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Arnold<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Philadelphia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Pennsylvania Press<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-8122-3618-1</arg></template>. An excellent and meticulously researched work dealing with Catharism in the context of the Inquisition's evolution; analyses Inquisitorial practice as the construction of the &quot;confessing subject&quot;.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Barber<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Malcolm<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cathars: Dualist heretics in Languedoc in the High Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Longman<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Harlow<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0582256620<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Berlioz<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Tuez-les tous Dieu reconnaîtra les siens. Le massacre de Béziers et la croisade des Albigeois vus par Césaire de Heisterbach<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Loubatières<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>French</arg></template>. A discussion of the command &quot;Kill them all, God will know his own.&quot; recorded by a contemporary Cistercian Chronicler.</listitem><listitem>Brunn, Uwe (2006),<space/><italics>Des contestataires aux cathares : Discours de rforme et propagande antihrtique dans les pays du Rhin et de la Meuse avant l'Inquisition</italics>, Paris, Institut d'tudes augustiniennes</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Burr<space/></arg><arg name="first1">David<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bernard Gui: Inquisitor's Manual<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Internet History Sourcebooks Project</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/bernardgui-inq.asp</arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Fordham University]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[New York City]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>25 May 2013<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Caernaii<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Petrus Vallis<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>[[PDF]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.documentacatholicaomnia.eu/04z/z_1209-1218__Petrus_Vallis_Caernaii__Historia_Albigensium_Et_Sacri_Belli_In_Eos_AD_1209__MLT.pdf.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Historia Albigensium et Sacri Belli in Eos<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Latin<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Migne Patrologia Latina<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>213<space/></arg><arg name="at"><space/>0543-0711</arg></template>. An history of the Albigensian war told by a contemporary.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Chesterton<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>G. K.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>G. K. Chesterton<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>What's Wrong with the World<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1910<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Clark<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Elizabeth A.<space/></arg><arg name="article"><space/>Women, Gender, and the Study of Christian History<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Church History<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>70<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="pages">395–426<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">3654496</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jean.duvernoy.free.fr/'>Jean Duvernoy, Jean: transcriptions of inquisitorial manuscripts</link>, many hitherto unpublished</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Dondaine<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Antoine OP<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Un traité neo-manichéen du XIIIe siècle: Le Liber de duobus principiis, suivi d'un fragment de rituel Cathare<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>French</arg><arg name="place"><space/>Rome<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Institutum Historicum Fratrum Praedicatorum<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1939<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Frassatto<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Michael<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heresy and the Persecuting Society in the Middle Ages: Essays on the Work of R.I. Moore<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Medieval Academy of America<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1975<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-9004150980<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Given<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Inquisition and Medieval Society: Power, Discipline, and Resistance in Languedoc<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Cornell University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0801487590<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Godlike Productions<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.godlikeproductions.com/forum1/message1085242/pg1<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Web Forum: Before the Catholics, The Cathars taught of Jesus, Power of Love<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Godlike Productions, Zero Point Ltd.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Gui<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Bernard<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink1"><space/>Bernard Gui<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Shirley<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Janet<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Inquisitor's Guide: A Medieval Manual on Heretics<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Ravenhall Books<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Welwyn Garden City]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1905043095<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Henry<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>William<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bibliotecapleyades.net/esp_autor_whenry04.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Secrets of The Cathars: Why the Dark Age Church Was Out to Destroy Them<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Biblioteca Pleyades and Atlantis Rising<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="author"><space/>Innocent III<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Pope Innocent III<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Volume 216, Patrologia Cursus Completus<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://archive.org/details/patrologiaecurs00berngoog<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Jacques Paul Migne]]<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Paris<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1855<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="author"><space/>John of Damascus</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>John of Damascus<space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/>Translator: Frederic H Chase<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Writings: The Fount of Knowledge: The Philosophical Chapters, On Heresies, The Orthodox Faith<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>The Fathers of the Church<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>CreateSpace<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1958<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Reprint<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1470149246<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Johnson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Paul Johnson (writer)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A History of Christianity<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Atheneum<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-689-70591-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Johnston<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ruth A<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>All Things Medieval: An Encyclopedia of the Medieval World<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>115<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Greenwood Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0313364624<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Johnston<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>William M<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Encyclopedia of Monasticism<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Fitzroy Dearborn Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-57958-090-4<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Kaelber<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Lutz<space/></arg><arg name="title">Weavers into Heretics? The Social Organization of Early-Thirteenth-Century Catharism in Comparative Perspective<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Social Science History, vol. 21, no. 1</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="pages">111–137<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Kienzle<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Beverly Mayne<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cistercians, heresy, and Crusade in Occitania, 1145–1229<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>York Medieval Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1903153000<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Lambert<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Malcolm<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Cathars<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0631143437<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Lambert<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Malcolm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Medieval Heresy: Popular Movements from the Gregorian Reform to the Reformation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0631222767<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Lansing<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Carol<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Power and Purity: Cathar Heresy in Medieval Italy<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Oxford University Press]] (USA)<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0195149807<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Le Roy Ladurie<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Emmanuel<space/></arg><arg name="title">Montaillou: The Promised Land of Error, Barbara Bray translator</arg><arg name="authorlink">Emmanuel Le Roy Ladurie<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Vintage Books</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1979</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0807615980</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>The new Cambridge medieval history: c. 1024 – c. 1198<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>522<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>David<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Luscombe<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Riley-Smith<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Madaule<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Jacques<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Albigensian Crusade: An Historical Essay</arg><arg name="publisher">Fordham UP</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">1967</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.askwhy.co.uk/christianity/0811Inquisition.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heresy and the Inquisition II Persecution of Heretics<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dr M D<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Magee<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>12 December 2002</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://gnosistraditions.faithweb.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Trail of Gnosis<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Judith<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Mann<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Gnosis Traditions Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Montségur and the Mystery of the Cathars<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Jean Markale<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jean<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Markale<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Inner Traditions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0892810901<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.innertraditions.com/titles/momyca.html<space/></arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Martin<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Sean<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Sean Martin (writer and director)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cathars: The Most Successful Heresy of the Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.pocketessentials.com/history/1904048331cathars<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Pocket Essentials]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-904048-33-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Maris<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Yves<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cathars – Memories of an initiate<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>AdA<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Maseko<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Achim N.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Church Schism & Corruption<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>482<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Lulu.com<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>South Africa<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781409221869<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John Clare<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pope Innocent III (1160/61–1216): To Root Up and to Plant<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>180<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Brill<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>90-04-12925-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>R I<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>R. I. Moore<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Origins of European Dissent<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wiley-Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0631144045<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>R I<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>R. I. Moore<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Birth of Heresy<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="publisher">Medieval Academy of America<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8020-7659-9<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>R I<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>R. I. Moore<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Formation of a Persecuting Society<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1405129640<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>R I<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>R. I. Moore<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The War on Heresy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Profile Books<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9781846682001<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moreland<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Miles<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Miles Away: A Walk Across France<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Random House<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-679-42527-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Murphy<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cullen<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>God's Jury: The Inquisition and the Making of the Modern World<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-618-09156-0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Houhton Mifflin Harcourt<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2012<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Possessed by the Spirit: Devout Women, Demoniacs, and the Apostolic Life in the Thirteenth Century<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Newman<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Barbara<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Speculum<space/></arg><arg name="volume">73<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="pages">733–770<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/2887496</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>O'Shea<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Stephen<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Perfect Heresy: The Revolutionary Life and Death of the Medieval Cathars</arg><arg name="publisher">Walker & Company</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1861972705<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pegg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>On Cathars, Albigenses, and good men of Languedoc<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Medieval History<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>27<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>181–190<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/s0304-4181(01)00008-2<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pegg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Corruption of Angels: The Great Inquisition of 1245–1245<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001b<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Princeton University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0691006567<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pegg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Heresy, good men, and nomenclature<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heresy and the Persecuting Society in the Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Michael<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Frassetto<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Studies in the History of Christian Traditions<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>129<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Leiden<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Brill<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>227–39</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pegg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Most Holy War: The Albigensian Crusade and the Battle for Christendom<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9780195171310<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pegg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mark<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.academia.edu/11602867/Mark_G._Pegg_Innocent_III_les_Pestilentiels_Proven%C3%A7aux_et_le_paradigme_%C3%A9puis%C3%A9_du_catharisme_dans_Innocent_III_et_le_Midi_._Cahiers_de_Fanjeaux_50_2015_p._277-307_trad._de_langlais_ (english and french abstracts)<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Innocent III, les 'pestilentiels Provençaux' et le paradigme épuisé du catharisme/Innocent III, 'Pestilential Provençals' and the Obsolete Paradigm of Catharism<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Innocent III et le Midi<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Cahiers de Fanjeaux, 50<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>9782708934542</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Presses Universitaires de Rennes<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Toulouse<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Privat<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2015<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>277-207<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Heresy and Authority in Medieval Europe<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Edward<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Peters<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of Pennsylvania Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1980</arg></template>. A collection of primary sources, some on Catharism.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Il volto del Cristo dualista. Da Marcione ai catari<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Enrico<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Riparelli<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Peter Lang<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Bern<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-303911490-0<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>Italian</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Roach<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Andrew P<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Devil's World: Heresy and Society 1100–1320<space/></arg><arg name="location">Harlow</arg><arg name="publisher">Pearson Longman</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Schaff<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Philip<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Wace<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Henry<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nicene and Post-Nicene Fathers<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Second Series<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>Volume 14: I Nice AD 325 (Canons of the Council of Nicaea)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Hendrickson<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Reprint<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1900<space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/>Trans. Henry R. Percival<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1565631168<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Schaus<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Margaret<space/></arg><arg name="title">Women And Gender in Medieval Europe: An Encyclopedia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Taylor and Francis Group</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0415969444<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Sibly<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>W A<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Sibly<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>M D<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Chronicle of William of Puylaurens: The Albigensian Crusade and Its Aftermath<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>128<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Boydell Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0851159256<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Oxford English Dictionary]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Oxford University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Second<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Simpson<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Oxford]]<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>{{harvid|OED|1989}}<space/></arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Stork<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Nancy P.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Inquisition Record of Jacques Fournier, Bishop of Pamiers 1318-1325<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.sjsu.edu/people/nancy.stork/courses/c4/s1/jacques_fournier<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[San Jose State University]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>California<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Sumption<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Jonathan Sumption<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Albigensian Crusade<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Faber and Faber<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>New<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1978<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1999<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0571200023<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template><space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Théry<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Julien<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>L'Hérésie des bons hommes (XIIe-début du XIVe s.). Comment nommer la dissidence religieuse non vaudoise ni béguine en Languedoc?<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>French<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://www.academia.edu/924035/_Lh%C3%A9r%C3%A9sie_des_bons_hommes._Comment_nommer_la_dissidence_religieuse_non_vaudoise_ni_b%C3%A9guine_en_Languedoc_XIIe-XIVe_s._Heresis_36-37_2002_p._75-117<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Heresis<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>36-37<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>75–117<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Théry<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Julien<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Cléricalisme et Hérésie des bons hommes : l'exemple d'Albi et de l'Albigeois (1276–1329)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>L'anticléricalisme en France méridionale (milieu XIIe-début XIVe&nbsp;s.)<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Cahiers de Fanjeaux<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>38<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>471–508<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Privat<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Paris<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-2708934412<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Théry<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Julien<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Les Hérésies, du XIIe au début du XIVe&nbsp;s.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Structures et dynamiques de la vie religieuse en Occident (1179–1449)<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>de Cevins<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Marie-Madeleine<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Matz<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Jean-Michel<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>French<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://www.academia.edu/499340/_Les_h%C3%A9r%C3%A9sies_du_XIIe_au_d%C3%A9but_du_XIVe_si%C3%A8cle_dans_Structures_et_dynamiques_de_la_vie_religieuse_en_Occident_1179-1449_ed._Marie-Madeleine_de_Cevins_Jean-Michel_Matz_Rennes_PUR_2010_p._373-386<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Presses Universitaires de Rennes<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Rennes]]<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>373–386<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Townsend<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Anne Bradford<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Cathars of Languedoc as heretics: From the perspectives of Five Contemporary Scholars<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>9<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>Dissertation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Union Institute and University<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1243491602<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Wakefield<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Walter Leggett<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Evans<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Austin P<space/></arg><arg name="title">Heresies of the High Middle Ages<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Columbia University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0231096324<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Walther<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Daniel</arg><arg name="article">A Survey of Recent Research on the Albigensian Cathari<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Church History<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>34<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="year">1965<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="pages">146–177<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">3162901</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Ward<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Jennifer<space/></arg><arg name="title">Women in Medieval Europe, 1200–1500</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Longman]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0582288270<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Weber<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="contribution-url"><space/>http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/01267e.htm<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Albigenses<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[New Advent]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1908a<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1">Weber<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Nicholas<space/></arg><arg name="contribution-url"><space/>http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/03435a.htm<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Cathari<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[New Advent]]<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Catholic Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1908b<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Weis<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>René<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Yellow Cross: The Story of the Last Cathars 1290–1329<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Random House]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Zerner, Monique (1998),<space/><italics>Inventer l'hrsie ? Discours polmiques et pouvoirs avant l'Inquisition</italics>, Nice : Centre d'tudes mdivales</listitem><listitem>Zerner, Monique (2001),<space/><italics>L'histoire du catharisme en discussion : le concile de Saint-Flix (1167)</italics>, Nice : Centre d'tudes mdivales</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Cathars</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gnosis.org/library/cathtx.htm<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Gnostic Society Library<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cathar texts</arg></template>, including the<space/><italics>Lyon Ritual</italics>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.theogamy.com/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Modern Day Cathars</arg></template>: Official website of the 21st century Cathar movement.</listitem><listitem><template><target>In Our Time</target><arg>Catharism</arg><arg>p005488v</arg><arg>Catharism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.castlesandmanorhouses.com/cathars<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Catharism and the Cathars of the Languedoc<space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/>Castles & Manor Houses</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20110607030845/http://www.castlesandmanorhouses.com/cathars/</arg><arg name="archivedate">7 June 2011</arg></template>: History, origins, theology and extirpation.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.catharcastles.info/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cathar castles</arg></template>: details, histories, photographs, plans and maps of 30 Cathar castles.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.aude-aude.com/content/view/81/40<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cathar castles<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Aude‐Aude<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>interactive map</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://travel.nytimes.com/2010/05/09/travel/09Languedoc.html<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>9 May 2010<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Besieged and the Beautiful in Languedoc<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tony<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Perrottet</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://paratge.wordpress.com/2013/05/05/heretiquespyrenees/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Heretics in the Catalan Pyrenees at the end of the 11th century?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Paratge<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>article<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2013</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Albigen</arg></template></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Gnosticism topics</target></template><template><target>History of Christianity</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Angels in Christianity</target></link><link><target>Category:Archangels</target></link><link><target>Category:Ascetics</target></link><link><target>Category:Catharism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Christian mysticism</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian vegetarianism</target></link><link><target>Category:Esoteric schools of thought</target></link><link><target>Category:Gnosticism</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Catholicism in France</target></link><link><target>Category:Individual angels</target></link><link><target>Category:Nontrinitarianism</target></link><link><target>Category:Persecution by Christians</target></link><link><target>Category:Persecution of Christians</target></link></paragraph></article>