<article title='Digital_television'><paragraph><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Digital terrestrial television</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">May 2010</arg></template><template><target>Table Digital video broadcast standards</target></template><bold>Digital television</bold><space/>(<bold>DTV</bold>) is the transmission of audio and video by digitally processed and multiplexed signal, in contrast to the totally analog and channel separated signals used by<space/><link><target>analog television</target></link>. Digital TV can support more than one program in the same channel<space/><link><target>Bandwidth (signal processing)</target><part>bandwidth</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.disabled-world.com/artman/publish/digital-hdtv.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">HDTV Set Top Boxes and Digital TV Broadcast Information<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 June 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>It is an innovative service that represents the first significant evolution in television technology since color television in the 1950s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kruger, L. G. (2001). Digital Television: An Overview. Hauppauge, New York: Nova Publishers.</extension><space/>Several regions of the world are in different stages of adaptation and are implementing different broadcasting standards. Below are the different widely used digital television broadcasting standards (DTB):</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Digital Video Broadcasting (<link><target>Digital Video Broadcasting</target><part>DVB</part></link>) uses coded orthogonal frequency-division multiplexing (<link><target>OFDM</target></link>) modulation and supports hierarchical transmission. This standard has been adopted in Europe, Australia and New Zealand.</listitem><listitem>Advanced Television System Committee (<link><target>ATSC</target></link>) uses eight-level vestigial sideband (<link><target>8VSB</target></link>) for terrestrial broadcasting. This standard has been adopted by six countries, United States, Canada, Mexico, South Korea, Dominican Republic and Honduras.</listitem><listitem>Integrated Services Digital Broadcasting (<link><target>ISDB</target></link>) is a system designed to provide good reception to fix receivers and also portable or mobile receivers. It utilizes<space/><link><target>OFDM</target></link><space/>and two-dimensional interleaving. It supports hierarchical transmission of up to three layers and uses<space/><link><target>MPEG-2 video</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Advanced Audio Coding</target></link>. This standard has been adopted in Japan and the Philippines.<space/><link><target>ISDB-T International</target></link><space/>is an adaptation of this standard using<space/><link><target>H.264/MPEG-4 AVC</target></link><space/>that been adopted in most of South America and is also being embraced by Portuguese-speaking African countries.</listitem><listitem>Digital Terrestrial Multimedia Broadcasting (<link><target>DTMB</target></link>) adopts time-domain synchronous (TDS) OFDM technology with a pseudo-random signal frame to serve as the guard interval (GI) of the OFDM block and the training symbol. The DTMB standard has been adopted in the People's Republic of China, including Hong Kong and Macau.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ong, C. Y., Song, J., Pan, C., &amp; Li, Y.(2010, May). Technology and Standards of Digital Television Terrestrial Multimedia Broadcasting [Topics in Wireless Communications], Communications Magazine, IEEE , 48(5),119-127</extension></listitem><listitem>Digital Multimedia Broadcasting (<link><target>Digital Multimedia Broadcasting</target><part>DMB</part></link>) is a digital<space/><link><target>radio transmission</target></link><space/><link><target>technology</target></link><space/>developed in<space/><link><target>South Korea</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.zdnet.co.kr/ArticleView.asp?artice_id</arg><arg name="title">Korea's Terrestrial DMB: Germany to begin broadcast this May<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">ZDNet Korea<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-06-17</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.textually.org/picturephoning/archives/cat_dmb.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">picturephoning.com: DMB<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Textually.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-06-17</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.reportworld.co.kr/cbqna/cb_answer_view.html?no</arg><arg name="title">South Korea : Social Media 답변 내용 : 악어새 - 리포트월드<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Reportworld.co.kr<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-06-17</arg></template></extension><space/>as part of the national<space/><link><target>information technology</target><part>IT</part></link><space/>project for sending multimedia such as<space/><link><target>TV</target></link>,<space/><link><target>radio</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>datacasting</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>mobile device</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as mobile phones, laptops and GPS navigation systems.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>Digital TV's roots have been tied very closely to the availability of inexpensive, high performance computers. It wasn't until the 1990s that digital TV became a real possibility.<extension extension_name='ref' name="benton"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.benton.org/initiatives/obligations/charting_the_digital_broadcasting_future/sec1<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Origins and Future Prospects of Digital Television<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Benton Foundation]]<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the mid-1980s as Japanese consumer electronics firms forged ahead with the development of HDTV technology, and as the MUSE analog format proposed by NHK, a Japanese company, was seen as a pacesetter that threatened to eclipse U.S. electronics companies. Until June 1990, the Japanese MUSE standardbased on an analog systemwas the front-runner among the more than 23 different technical concepts under consideration. Then, an American company, General Instrument, demonstrated the feasibility of a digital television signal. This breakthrough was of such significance that the FCC was persuaded to delay its decision on an ATV standard until a digitally based standard could be developed.</paragraph><paragraph>In March 1990, when it became clear that a digital standard was feasible, the FCC made a number of critical decisions. First, the Commission declared that the new ATV standard must be more than an enhanced<space/><link><target>analog signal</target></link>, but be able to provide a genuine HDTV signal with at least twice the resolution of existing television images. Then, to ensure that viewers who did not wish to buy a new digital television set could continue to receive conventional television broadcasts, it dictated that the new ATV standard must be capable of being &quot;simulcast&quot; on different channels. The new ATV standard also allowed the new DTV signal to be based on entirely new design principles. Although incompatible with the existing NTSC standard, the new DTV standard would be able to incorporate many improvements.<extension extension_name='ref' name="benton"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The final standard adopted by the FCC did not require a single standard for scanning formats, aspect ratios, or lines of resolution. This outcome resulted from a dispute between the consumer electronics industry (joined by some broadcasters) and the computer industry (joined by the film industry and some public interest groups) over which of the two scanning processesinterlaced or progressiveis superior. Interlaced scanning, which is used in televisions worldwide, scans even-numbered lines first, then odd-numbered ones. Progressive scanning, which is the format used in computers, scans lines in sequences, from top to bottom. The computer industry argued that progressive scanning is superior because it does not &quot;flicker&quot; in the manner of interlaced scanning. It also argued that progressive scanning enables easier connections with the Internet, and is more cheaply converted to interlaced formats than vice versa. The film industry also supported progressive scanning because it offers a more efficient means of converting filmed programming into digital formats. For their part, the consumer electronics industry and broadcasters argued that interlaced scanning was the only technology that could transmit the highest quality pictures then (and currently) feasible, i.e., 1,080 lines per picture and 1,920 pixels per line. Broadcasters also favored interlaced scanning because their vast archive of interlaced programming is not readily compatible with a progressive format.<extension extension_name='ref' name="benton"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Digital television transition</target></link><space/>started in the late 2000s. All the governments across the world set the deadline for analog shutdown by the 2010s. Initially the adoption rate was low. But soon, more and more households were converting to digital televisions. The transition is expected to be completed worldwide by mid to late 2010s.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Technical information</heading><heading level='3'>Formats and bandwidth</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Digital &amp; Analog TV screen quality comparison-1.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>right</part><part>Comparison of image quality between<space/><link><target>ISDB-T</target></link><space/>(top) and<space/><link><target>NTSC</target></link><space/>(bottom)</part></link>Digital television supports many different picture formats defined by the<space/><link><target>broadcast television system</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which are a combination of size,<space/><link><target>aspect ratio</target></link><space/>(width to height ratio).</paragraph><paragraph>With<space/><link><target>digital terrestrial television</target></link><space/>(DTT) broadcasting, the range of formats can be broadly divided into two categories:<space/><link><target>high definition television</target></link><space/>(HDTV) for the transmission of<space/><link><target>high-definition video</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>standard-definition television</target></link><space/>(SDTV). These terms by themselves are not very precise, and many subtle intermediate cases exist.</paragraph><paragraph>One of several different HDTV formats that can be transmitted over DTV is: 1280&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;720<space/><link><target>pixel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>progressive scan</target></link><space/>mode (abbreviated<space/><italics><link><target>720p</target></link></italics>) or 1920&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1080 pixels in<space/><link><target>interlaced video</target></link><space/>mode (<italics><link><target>1080i</target></link></italics>). Each of these uses a<space/><link><target>16:9</target></link><space/><link><target>aspect ratio</target></link>. (Some televisions are capable of receiving an HD resolution of 1920&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;1080 at a 60&amp;nbsp;Hz progressive scan frame rate&amp;nbsp; known as<space/><link><target>1080p</target></link>.) HDTV cannot be transmitted over analog<space/><link><target>television channel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>because of<space/><link><target>channel capacity</target></link><space/>issues.</paragraph><paragraph>Standard definition TV (SDTV), by comparison, may use one of several different formats taking the form of various aspect ratios depending on the technology used in the country of broadcast. For<space/><link><target>4:3</target></link><space/>aspect-ratio broadcasts, the 640&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;480 format is used in<space/><link><target>NTSC</target></link><space/>countries, while 720&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;576 is used in<space/><link><target>PAL</target></link><space/>countries. For<space/><link><target>16:9</target></link><space/>broadcasts, the 720&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;480 format is used in NTSC countries, while 720&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;576 is used in PAL countries. However, broadcasters may choose to reduce these resolutions to reduce<space/><link><target>bit rate</target></link><space/>(e.g., many DVB-T channels in the United Kingdom use a horizontal resolution of 544 or 704 pixels per line).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dtt.me.uk'>Latest snapshots - Freeview/DTT bitrates</link><space/>(Mendip transmitter, UK)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Each<space/><link><target>commercial broadcasting</target></link><space/><link><target>terrestrial television</target></link><space/>DTV channel in North America is permitted to be broadcast at a<space/><link><target>bit rate</target></link><space/>up to 19<space/><link><target>megabit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per second. However, the broadcaster does not need to use this entire bandwidth for just one broadcast channel. Instead the broadcast can use the channel to include<space/><link><target>PSIP</target></link><space/>and can also subdivide across several video<space/><link><target>subchannel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(a.k.a. feeds) of varying quality and compression rates, including non-video<space/><link><target>datacasting</target></link><space/>services that allow one-way high-bit-rate streaming of data to computers like<space/><link><target>National Datacast</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A broadcaster may opt to use a standard-definition (<link><target>SDTV</target></link>) digital signal instead of an<space/><link><target>HDTV</target></link><space/>signal, because current convention allows the bandwidth of a DTV channel (or &quot;<link><target>multiplex (TV)</target><part>multiplex</part></link>&quot;) to be subdivided into multiple<space/><link><target>digital subchannel</target><trail>s</trail></link>, (similar to what most FM<space/><link><target>radio station</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>offer with<space/><link><target>HD Radio</target></link>), providing multiple feeds of entirely different<space/><link><target>television program</target><trail>ming</trail></link><space/>on the same channel. This ability to provide either a single HDTV feed or multiple lower-resolution feeds is often referred to as distributing one's &quot;<link><target>bit budget</target></link>&quot; or<space/><link><target>multicasting</target></link>. This can sometimes be arranged automatically, using a<space/><link><target>statistical multiplexer</target></link><space/>(or &quot;stat-mux&quot;). With some implementations, image resolution may be less directly limited by bandwidth; for example in<space/><link><target>DVB-T</target></link>, broadcasters can choose from several different modulation schemes, giving them the option to reduce the transmission<space/><link><target>bit rate</target></link><space/>and make reception easier for more distant or mobile viewers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Receiving digital signal</heading><paragraph>There are several different ways to receive digital television. One of the oldest means of receiving DTV (and TV in general) is using an<space/><link><target>Television antenna</target><part>antenna</part></link><space/>(known as an<space/><italics>aerial</italics><space/>in some countries). This way is known as<space/><link><target>Digital terrestrial television</target></link><space/>(DTT or DVB-Terrestrial, DVB-T), which can be in two types: DVB-T and DVB-T2. With DTT, viewers are limited to whatever channels the antenna picks up. Signal quality will also vary. Regardless of what sale ads try to lead the public to believe, there is no such thing as a specialized DTV antenna. ANY Over the Air antenna that worked for analog TV should work for Digital TV (But DTV signal levels are lower thus requiring actually a bigger antenna with more gain unless you are visually close to the transmitting towers).</paragraph><paragraph>Other ways have been devised to receive digital television. Among the most familiar to people are<space/><link><target>digital cable</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>digital satellite</target></link>. In some countries where transmissions of TV signals are normally achieved by<space/><link><target>microwaves</target></link>, digital<space/><link><target>MMDS</target></link><space/>is used. Other standards, such as<space/><link><target>Digital multimedia broadcasting</target></link><space/>(DMB) and<space/><link><target>DVB-H</target></link>, have been devised to allow handheld devices such as<space/><link><target>mobile phones</target></link><space/>to receive TV signals. Another way is<space/><link><target>IPTV</target></link>, that is receiving TV via Internet Protocol, relying on<space/><link><target>digital subscriber line</target></link><space/>(DSL) or optical cable line. Finally, an alternative way is to receive digital TV signals via the open Internet (<link><target>Internet television</target></link>), whether from a central streaming service or a P2P (peer-to-peer) system.</paragraph><paragraph>Some signals carry<space/><link><target>encryption</target></link><space/>and specify use conditions (such as &quot;may not be recorded&quot; or &quot;may not be viewed on displays larger than 1 m in diagonal measure&quot;) backed up with the force of law under the World Intellectual Property Organization Copyright Treaty (<link><target>WIPO Copyright Treaty</target></link>) and national<space/><link><target>legislation</target></link><space/>implementing it, such as the U.S.<space/><link><target>Digital Millennium Copyright Act</target></link>. Access to encrypted channels can be controlled by a removable<space/><link><target>smart card</target></link>, for example via the Common Interface (<link><target>DVB-CI</target></link>) standard for Europe and via<space/><link><target>Point Of Deployment</target></link><space/>(POD) for IS or named differently<space/><link><target>CableCard</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Disadvantages</heading><paragraph>While poor signal analog TV quality could be evaluated by the user by the amount of noise on the screen, digital TV has no grey areas, it either works or does not when the signal is not strong enough.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Protection parameters for terrestrial DTV broadcasting</heading><paragraph><template><target>Clarify</target><arg name="date">March 2008</arg></template>Digital television signals must not interfere with each other, and they must also coexist with analog television until it is phased out.The following table gives allowable signal-to-noise and signal-to-interference ratios for various interference scenarios. This table is a crucial regulatory tool for controlling the placement and power levels of stations. Digital TV is more tolerant of interference than analog TV, and this is the reason a smaller range of channels can carry an all-digital set of television stations.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">As far as I know, it's the data compression possible with digital that makes higher channel density possible.</arg><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template></paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>System Parameters<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:small>(protection ratios)</xhtml:small></tablehead><tablehead>Canada [13]</tablehead><tablehead>USA [5]</tablehead><tablehead>EBU [9, 12]<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><xhtml:small>ITU-mode M3</xhtml:small></tablehead><tablehead>Japan &amp; Brazil [36, 37]<extension extension_name='ref'>ISDB-T (6&amp;nbsp;MHz, 64QAM, R=2/3), Analog TV (M/NTSC).<xhtml:br></xhtml:br></extension></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>C/N for AWGN Channel</tablehead><tablecell>+19.5&amp;nbsp;dB<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(16.5&amp;nbsp;dB<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_a">The Canadian parameter, C/(N+I) of noise plus co-channel DTV interface should be 16.5 dB.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br></extension>)</tablecell><tablecell>+15.19&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+19.3&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+19.2&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Co-Channel DTV into Analog TV</tablehead><tablecell>+33.8&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+34.44&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+34 ~ 37&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+38&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Co-Channel Analog TV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>+7.2&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+1.81&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+4&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+4&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Co-Channel DTV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>+19.5&amp;nbsp;dB<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>(16.5&amp;nbsp;dB<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_a"></extension>)</tablecell><tablecell>+15.27&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+19&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>+19&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Lower Adjacent Channel DTV into Analog TV</tablehead><tablecell>16&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>17.43&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>5 ~ 11&amp;nbsp;dB<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_c">Depending on analog TV systems used.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>6&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Upper Adjacent Channel DTV into Analog TV</tablehead><tablecell>12&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>11.95&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>1 ~ 10<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_c"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>5&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Lower Adjacent Channel Analog TV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>48&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>47.33&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>34 ~ 37&amp;nbsp;dB<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_c"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>35&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Upper Adjacent Channel Analog TV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>49&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>48.71&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>38 ~ 36&amp;nbsp;dB<extension extension_name='ref' name="protection_parameters_table_note_c"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>37&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Lower Adjacent Channel DTV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>27&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>28&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>30&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>28&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Upper Adjacent Channel DTV into DTV</tablehead><tablecell>27&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>26&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>30&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell><tablecell>29&amp;nbsp;dB</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Interaction</heading><paragraph>People can interact with a DTV system in various ways. One can, for example, browse the<space/><link><target>Electronic program guide</target></link>. Modern DTV systems sometimes use a return path providing feedback from the end user to the broadcaster. This is possible with a coaxial or fiber optic cable, a dialup modem, or Internet connection but is not possible with a standard antenna.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of these systems support<space/><link><target>video on demand</target></link><space/>using a<space/><link><target>communication channel</target></link><space/>localized to a neighborhood rather than a city (terrestrial) or an even larger area (satellite).</paragraph><heading level='3'>1-segment broadcasting</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>1seg</arg></template><link><target>1seg</target></link><space/>(1-segment) is a special form of<space/><link><target>ISDB</target></link>. Each channel is further divided into 13 segments. The 12 segments of them are allocated for<space/><link><target>HDTV</target></link><space/>and remaining segment, the 13th, is used for narrow-band receivers such as mobile television or<space/><link><target>cell phone</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Timeline of transition</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Digital television transition</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Comparison of analog vs digital</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Analog television</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>DTV has several advantages over analog TV, the most significant being that digital channels take up less bandwidth, and the bandwidth needs are continuously variable, at a corresponding reduction in image quality depending on the level of compression as well as the resolution of the transmitted image. This means that digital broadcasters can provide more digital channels in the same space, provide<space/><link><target>high-definition television</target></link><space/>service, or provide other non-television services such as multimedia or interactivity. DTV also permits special services such as multiplexing (more than one program on the same channel), electronic program guides and additional languages (spoken or subtitled). The sale of non-television services may provide an additional revenue source.</paragraph><paragraph>Digital and analog signals react to interference differently. For example, common problems with analog television include<space/><link><target>Ghosting (television)</target><part>ghosting</part></link><space/>of images, noise from weak signals, and many other potential problems which degrade the quality of the image and sound, although the program material may still be watchable. With digital television, the audio and video must be synchronized digitally, so reception of the digital signal must be very nearly complete; otherwise, neither audio nor video will be usable. Short of this complete failure, &quot;blocky&quot; video is seen when the digital signal experiences interference.</paragraph><paragraph>Analog TV started off with monophonic sound, and later evolved to stereophonic sound with two independent audio signal channels. DTV will allow up to 5 audio signal channels plus a<space/><link><target>sub-woofer</target></link><space/>bass channel, with broadcasts similar in quality to movie theaters and DVDs.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.pbs.org/opb/crashcourse/digital_v_analog/sound.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Digital TV: A Cringley Crash Course&nbsp;— Digital Vs. Analog<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pbs.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-01-13</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Compression artifacts and allocated bandwidth</heading><paragraph>DTV images have some picture defects that are not present on analog television or motion picture cinema, because of present-day limitations of bit rate and compression algorithms such as<space/><link><target>MPEG-2</target></link>. This defect is sometimes referred to as &quot;<link><target>mosquito noise</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Le Dinh, Phuc-Tue; Patry, Jacques
<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.videsignline.com/howto/180207350
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Video compression artifacts and MPEG noise reduction
<space/></arg><arg name="work">ideo Imaging DesignLine<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 24, 2006
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 30, 2010<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Because of the way the human visual system works, defects in an image that are localized to particular features of the image or that come and go are more perceptible than defects that are uniform and constant. However, the DTV system is designed to take advantage of other limitations of the human visual system to help mask these flaws, e.g. by allowing more<space/><link><target>compression artifacts</target></link><space/>during fast motion where the eye cannot track and resolve them as easily and, conversely, minimizing artifacts in still backgrounds that may be closely examined in a scene (since time allows).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Effects of poor reception</heading><paragraph>Changes in signal reception from factors such as degrading antenna connections or changing weather conditions may gradually reduce the quality of analog TV. The nature of digital TV results in a perfectly decodable video initially, until the receiving equipment starts picking up interference that overpowers the desired signal or if the signal is too weak to decode. Some equipment will show a garbled picture with significant damage, while other devices may go directly from perfectly decodable video to no video at all or lock up. This phenomenon is known as the digital<space/><link><target>cliff effect</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>For remote locations, distant channels that, as analog signals, were previously usable in a snowy and degraded state may, as digital signals, be perfectly decodable or may become completely unavailable. The use of higher frequencies will add to these problems, especially in cases where a clear line-of-sight from the receiving antenna to the transmitter is not available.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Effect on old analog technology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Update</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template>Television sets with only analog tuners cannot decode digital transmissions. When analog broadcasting over the air ceases, users of sets with analog-only tuners may use other sources of programming (e.g. cable, recorded media) or may purchase set-top converter boxes to tune in the digital signals. In the United States, a<space/><link><target>Coupon-eligible converter box</target><part>government-sponsored coupon</part></link><space/>was available to offset the cost of an external converter box. Analog switch-off (of full-power stations) took place on December 11, 2006 in The Netherlands,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ivir.nl/publications/sloot/switch-off.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">How Television went Digital in The Netherlands<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-02-04<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="work">Open Society Foundations September 2011<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>June 12, 2009 in the United States for full-power stations,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dtv.gov/affected.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Digital TV Transition: Will You Be Affected?<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-11-02<space/></arg><arg name="work">FCC<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>July 24, 2011 in Japan,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.broadcastingcable.com/blog/BC_DC_Eggerton_on_Washington/15430-New_DTV_Hard_Date_July_24_2011_.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">New DTV Hard Date: July 24, 2011?<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-11-02<space/></arg><arg name="work">B&C<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>August 31, 2011 in Canada,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ic.gc.ca/eic/site/smt-gst.nsf/vwapj/DTV_PLAN_Dec08-e.pdf/$file/DTV_PLAN_Dec08-e.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">DTV Post-Transition Allotment Plan<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-11-02<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="work">Spectrum Management and Telecommunications<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>February 13, 2012 in Arab states, May 1, 2012 in Germany, October 24, 2012 in the United Kingdom<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.digitaluk.co.uk/__data/assets/pdf_file/0004/82057/24-10-12_DSO_completion.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">End of analogue TV era as switchover completes in the UK<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-12-21<space/></arg><arg name="work">Digital UK<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and Ireland,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.saorview.ie/news/analogue-switch-off-has-finally-happened/</arg><arg name="title">Analogue switch off has finally happened</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-12-21<space/></arg><arg name="work">SAORVIEW</arg></template></extension><space/>October 31, 2012 in selected Indian cities,<extension extension_name='ref' name="india-switchover"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.digitalindiamib.com/digital_switch_over.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Find out when digital switch over is coming to you<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-12-21<space/></arg><arg name="work">Government of India Ministry of Information & Broadcasting<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and December 10, 2013 in Australia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.digitalready.gov.au/</arg><arg name="title">Australia's ready for digital TV<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-25<space/></arg><arg name="work">Digital Ready AU<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Completion of analog switch-off is scheduled for December 31, 2014 in the whole of India,<extension extension_name='ref' name="india-switchover"></extension><space/>by 2015 in the Philippines and Uruguay, by September 1, 2015 for low-power stations in the United States, and by 2017 in Costa Rica.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Disappearance of TV-audio receivers</heading><paragraph>Prior to the conversion to digital TV, analog television broadcast audio for TV channels on a separate FM carrier frequency from the video signal. This FM audio signal could be heard using standard radios equipped with the appropriate tuning circuits.</paragraph><paragraph>However, after the<space/><link><target>digital television transition</target><part>transition of many countries to digital TV</part></link>, no portable radio manufacturer has yet developed an alternative method for portable radios to play just the audio signal of digital TV channels. (<link><target>DTV radio</target></link><space/>is not the same thing.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Environmental issues</heading><paragraph>The adoption of a broadcast standard incompatible with existing analog receivers has created the problem of large numbers of analog receivers being discarded during<space/><link><target>digital television transition</target></link>. One superintendent of Public Works was quoted in 2009 as saying, &quot;Some of the studies Ive read in the trade magazines say up to a quarter of American households could be throwing a TV out in the next two years following the regulation change&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tonawanda-news.com/local/local_story_027233552.html'>North Tonawanda: council discusses future TV disposal</link>, Neale Gulley, Tonawanda News, January 27, 2009</extension><space/>In 2009, an estimated 99 million analog TV receivers were sitting unused in homes in the US alone and, while some obsolete receivers are being retrofitted with converters, many more are simply dumped in<space/><link><target>landfill</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>where they represent a source of toxic metals such as<space/><link><target>lead</target></link><space/>as well as lesser amounts of materials such as<space/><link><target>barium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cadmium</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>chromium</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wltx.com/news/story.aspx?storyid=69896&amp;amp;catid=306'>Old Toxic TVs Cause Problems</link>, USA TODAY, January 27, 2009</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.jsonline.com/news/wisconsin/38198929.html'>Unloading that old TV not quite so simple</link>, Lee Bergquist,<space/><link><target>Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel</target></link>, January 23, 2009</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to one campaign group, a<space/><link><target>cathode ray tube</target><part>CRT</part></link><space/><link><target>computer monitor</target></link><space/>or TV contains an average of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8</arg><arg>lb</arg><arg>kg</arg></template><space/>of lead.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/technology/7820229.stm'>Campaigners highlight 'toxic TVs'</link>, Maggie Shiels,<space/><link><target>BBC News</target></link>, 9 January 2009</extension><space/>According to another source, the lead in glass of a CRT varies from 1.08&amp;nbsp;lb to 11.28&amp;nbsp;lb, depending on screen size and type, but the lead is in the form of &quot;stable and immobile&quot; lead oxide mixed into the glass.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Lead in Cathode Ray Tubes (CRTs) Information Sheet**<space/></arg><arg name="date">2001-11-30<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.premierinc.com/quality-safety/tools-services/safety/topics/computers/downloads/k_3_lead_in_crts.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="page">1<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Electronic Industries Alliance]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-09-29</arg></template></extension><space/>It is claimed that the lead can have long-term negative effects on the environment if dumped as landfill.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">C.S.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Poon<space/></arg><arg name="title">Management of CRT glass from discarded computer monitors and TV sets<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Waste Management<space/></arg><arg name="volume">28<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1499–1499<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ewasteguide.info/biblio/management-cr<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.wasman.2008.06.001<space/></arg><arg name="quote">number of studies have demonstrated that the neck and funnel glasses of CRT are hazardous wastes, while the panel glass exhibits little toxicity.<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-09-29<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">18571917<space/></arg><arg name="issue">9</arg></template></extension><space/>However, the glass envelope can be recycled at suitably equipped facilities.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wcsh6.com/news/local/story.aspx?storyid=99680&amp;amp;catid=2'>What To Do With Your Old TV's</link>, Mike Webster,<space/><link><target>WCSH-TV</target></link>, January 28, 2009</extension><space/>Other portions of the receiver may be subject to disposal as<space/><link><target>hazardous material</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Local restrictions on disposal of these materials vary widely; in some cases<space/><link><target>second-hand store</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>have refused to accept working color television receivers for resale due to the increasing costs of disposing of unsold TVs. Those<space/><link><target>thrift store</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which are still accepting donated TVs have reported significant increases in good-condition working used television receivers abandoned by viewers who often expect them not to work after digital transition.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sun-sentinel.com/business/custom/consumer/sfl-flhlpvasquez0119sbjan19,0,4669489.column'>Many people throwing out perfectly good TVs over digital confusion</link>, Daniel Vasquez, Sun-Sentinel, Florida, January 19, 2009</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Michigan in 2009, one recycler estimated that as many as one household in four would dispose of or recycle a TV set in the following year.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://detnews.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20090123/METRO/901230383'>Trashing the tube: Digital conversion may spark glut of toxic waste</link>, Jennifer Chambers,<space/><link><target>Detroit News</target></link>, January 23, 2009</extension><space/>The digital television transition, migration to<space/><link><target>high-definition television</target></link><space/>receivers and the replacement of CRTs with flatscreens are all factors in the increasing number of discarded analog CRT-based television receivers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Broadcast television systems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Text to Speech in Digital Television</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Jeffrey A. Hart</target><part>Hart, Jeffrey A.</part></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://inethub.olvi.net.ua/ftp/Library/SomeLibrary/Techno/Hart%20J.A.%20-%20Technology,%20Television%20and%20Competition%5Bc%5D%20The%20Politics%20of%20Digital%20TV%20%282004%29%28en%29.pdf'>''Television, technology, and competition : HDTV and digital TV in the United States, Western Europe, and Japan''</link>, New York : Cambridge University Press, 2004. ISBN 0-521-82624-1</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Digital television</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://engineering.utsa.edu/~dakopian/teaching_files/WirelessComm/CommunicationForTV/OverviewDTV.pdf'>Overview of Digital Television Development Worldwide</link><space/><link><target>Proceedings of the IEEE</target></link>, VOL. 94, NO. 1, JANUARY 2006 (<link><target>University of Texas at San Antonio</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dtv.gov/'>The FCC's U.S. consumer-oriented DTV website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ricability-digitaltv.org.uk/'>Digital TV Consumer test reports - UK Government-funded website to support Digital Switchover</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikiHow</target><arg>Set-up-a-DTV-Digital-Converter-Box-and-Antenna</arg><arg>Set up a DTV Digital Converter Box and Antenna</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikiHow</target><arg>Scan-for-DTV-Channels-Using-a-Digital-TV-Converter-Box</arg><arg>Scan for DTV Channels Using a Digital TV Converter Box (and why this must be done 11 June 2009 in US)</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>wikiHow</target><arg>Use-Your-Older-VCR%2C-TiVo%2C-or-DVR-With-a-DTV-Converter-Box</arg><arg>Use Your Older VCR, TiVo, or DVR With a DTV Converter Box</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Digital television deployments</target></template><template><target>Telecommunications</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Digital Television</target></template><link><target>Category:Digital television</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:History of television</target></link><link><target>Category:Film and video technology</target></link><link><target>Category:Television terminology</target></link></paragraph></article>