<article title='Batavi_%28Germanic_tribe%29'><paragraph><link><target>Image:Funerary Stela Corporis Custodes.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Funerary stela of one of<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link>'s ''Corporis Custodes'', the imperial<space/><link><target>Germanic bodyguard</target></link>. The bodyguard, Indus, was of the Batavian tribe.</part></link>The<space/><bold>Batavi</bold><space/>were an ancient<space/><link><target>Germanic tribes</target><part>Germanic</part></link><space/>tribe that lived around the modern<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target><part>Dutch</part></link><space/><link><target>Rhine</target></link><space/>delta in the area that the Romans called<space/><link><target>Batavia (region)</target><part>Batavia</part></link>, from the second half of the first century BC to the third century AD. The name is also applied to several military units employed by the Romans that were originally raised among the Batavi. The tribal name, probably a derivation from<space/><italics>batawj</italics><space/>(&quot;good island&quot;, from<space/><link><target>Germanic Languages</target><part>Germanic</part></link><space/><italics>bat-</italics><space/>&quot;good, excellent,&quot; which is also in the English &quot;better,&quot; and<space/><italics>awj</italics><space/>&quot;island, land near water&quot;),<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2013</arg></template><space/>refers to the region's fertility, today known as the<space/><italics>fruitbasket of the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link></italics><space/>(the<space/><link><target>Betuwe</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>Finds of<space/><link><target>Wax tablet</target><part>wooden tablets</part></link><space/>show that at least some were literate.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Location</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Continental.coast.150AD.Germanic.peoples.jpg</target><part>frameless</part><part>240px</part><part>left</part></link>The Batavi, or at least the Batavian island in the<space/><link><target>Rhine river</target></link>, were mentioned by<space/><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link><space/>in his commentary<space/><italics><link><target>Commentarii de Bello Gallico</target></link></italics>. The island's easternmost point is at a split in the Rhine, one arm being the<space/><link><target>Waal (river)</target><part>Waal</part></link><space/>the other the<space/><link><target>Nederrijn</target><part>Lower Rhine</part></link>/<link><target>Oude Rijn (Utrecht and South Holland)</target><part>Old Rhine</part></link><space/>(hence the Latin name<space/><italics>Insula Batavorum</italics>, &quot;Island of the Batavi&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc</arg><arg name="title">C. Julius Caesar, 
Gallic War,
Book 4, chapter 10</arg><arg name="work">tufts.edu</arg></template></extension><space/>Much later<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link><space/>wrote that they had originally been a tribe of the<space/><link><target>Chatti</target></link>, a tribe in Germany never mentioned by Caesar, who were forced by internal dissension to move to their new home.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cornelius Tacitus,<space/><italics>Germany and its Tribes</italics><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/hopper/text?doc=Perseus%3Atext%3A1999.02.0083%3Achapter%3D29'>1.29</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Tacitus also reports that before their arrival the area had been &quot;an uninhabited district on the extremity of the coast of Gaul, and also of a neighbouring island, surrounded by the ocean in front, and by the river Rhine in the rear and on either side&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tacitus,<space/><italics>Historiae</italics><space/>iv.12</extension><space/>This view, however, is contradicted by the archeological evidence, which shows continuous habitation from at least the third century BC onward.<extension extension_name='ref'>N. Roymans, &quot;The Lower Rhine<space/><italics>Triquetrum</italics><space/>Coinages and the Ethnogenesis of the Batavians&quot;, in: T. Grnewald &amp; H.-J. Schalles (eds.),<space/><italics>Germania Inferior: Besiedlung, Gesellschaft und Wirtschaft an der Grenze der rmisch-germanischen Welt</italics><space/>(2000), 93-145, esp. 94.</extension><space/></paragraph><preblock><preline><space/></preline></preblock><paragraph>The strategic position, to wit the high bank of the Waalwhich offered an unimpeded view far into Germania Transrhenana (Germania Beyond the Rhine)was recognized first by<space/><link><target>Nero Claudius Drusus</target><part>Drusus</part></link>, who built a massive fortress (<italics>castra</italics>) and a headquarters (<italics>praetorium</italics>) in imperial style. The latter was in use until the Batavian revolt.</paragraph><paragraph>Archeological evidence suggests they lived in small villages, composed of six to 12 houses in the very fertile lands between the rivers, and lived by agriculture and cattle-raising. Finds of horse skeletons in graves suggest a strong equestrian preoccupation. On the south bank of the Waal (in what is now Nijmegen) a Roman administrative center was built, called<space/><italics>Oppidum Batavorum</italics>. An<space/><link><target>Oppidum</target></link><space/>was a fortified warehouse, where a tribe's treasures were stored and guarded. This centre was razed during the Batavian Revolt.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Military units</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Bataafseeed.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''The Conspiracy of the Batavians under Claudius Civilis'' by<space/><link><target>Rembrandt van Rijn</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The first Batavi commander we know of is named<space/><link><target>Chariovalda</target></link>, who led a charge across the Vsurgis (<link><target>Weser</target></link>) river against the<space/><link><target>Cherusci</target></link><space/>led by Arminius during the campaigns of Germanicus in<space/><italics>Germania Transrhenana</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tacitus, The Annals<space/><link><target>s:The Annals (Tacitus)/Book 2#11</target><part>2.11</part></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Tacitus (<italics><link><target>De origine et situ Germanorum</target></link></italics><space/>XXIX) described the Batavi as the bravest of the tribes of the area, hardened in the Germanic wars, with cohorts under their own commanders transferred to<space/><link><target>Britannia</target></link>. They retained the honour of the ancient association with the Romans, not required to pay tribute or taxes and used by the Romans only for war: &quot;They furnished to the Empire nothing but men and arms&quot;, Tacitus remarked. Well regarded for their skills in horsemanship and swimming&amp;mdash;for men and horses could cross the Rhine without losing formation, according to Tacitus.<space/><link><target>Dio Cassius</target></link><space/>describes this surprise tactic employed by<space/><link><target>Aulus Plautius</target></link><space/>against the &quot;barbarians&quot;&amp;mdash;the British Celts&amp;mdash; at the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Medway</target><part>battle of the River Medway</part></link>, 43:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>The barbarians thought that Romans would not be able to cross it without a bridge, and consequently bivouacked in rather careless fashion on the opposite bank; but he sent across a detachment of Germanic tribesmen, who were accustomed to swim easily in full armour across the most turbulent streams. [...] Thence the Britons retired to the river Thames at a point near where it empties into the ocean and at flood-tide forms a lake. This they easily crossed because they knew where the firm ground and the easy passages in this region were to be found; but the Romans in attempting to follow them were not so successful. However, the Germans swam across again and some others got over by a bridge a little way up-stream, after which they assailed the barbarians from several sides at once and cut down many of them.</italics><space/>(Cassius Dio, Roman History, Book 60:20)</listitem></list><paragraph>It is uncertain how they were able to accomplish this feat. The late 4th century writer on Roman military affairs Vegetius mentions soldiers using reed rafts, drawn by leather leads, to transport equipment across rivers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vegetius<space/><italics>De re militari</italics><space/>III.7</extension><space/>But the sources suggest the Batavi were able to swim across rivers actually wearing full armour and weapons. This would only have been possible by the use of some kind of buoyancy device:<space/><link><target>Ammianus Marcellinus</target></link><space/>mentions that the<space/><italics><link><target>Cornuti</target></link></italics><space/>regiment swam across a river floating on their shields &quot;as on a canoe&quot; (357).<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Ammianus Marcellinus</target></link><space/>XVI.11</extension><space/>Since the shields were wooden, they may have provided sufficient buoyancy</paragraph><paragraph>The Batavi were used to form the bulk of the Emperor's personal<space/><link><target>Germanic bodyguard</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Augustus</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Galba</target></link>. They also provided a contingent for their indirect successors, the Emperor's horse guards, the<space/><italics><link><target>Equites singulares Augusti</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>A Batavian contingent was used in an amphibious assault on<space/><link><target>Anglesey</target><part>Ynys Mon (Anglesey)</part></link>, taking the assembled<space/><link><target>Druids</target></link><space/>by surprise, as they were only expecting Roman ships.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tacitus Agricola 18.3-5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Numerous altars and tombstones of the cohorts of Batavi, dating to the 2nd century and 3rd century, have been found along<space/><link><target>Hadrian's Wall</target></link>, notably at<space/><link><target>Castlecary</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carrawburgh</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Yugoslavia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hungary</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Romania</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Austria</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Revolt of the Batavi</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Revolt of the Batavi</arg></template>Despite the alliance, one of the high-ranking Batavi, Julius Paullus, to give him his Roman name, was executed by Fonteius Capito on a false charge of rebellion. His kinsman<space/><link><target>Gaius Julius Civilis</target></link><space/>was paraded in chains in Rome before<space/><link><target>Nero</target></link>; though he was acquitted by<space/><link><target>Galba</target></link>, he was retained at Rome, and when he returned to his kin in the year of upheaval in the Roman Empire, 69, he headed a Batavian rebellion. He managed to capture<space/><link><target>Castra Vetera</target></link>, the Romans lost two legions while two others (I Germanica and XVI Gallica) were controlled by the rebels. The rebellion became a real threat to the Empire when the conflict escalated to northern Gaul and Germania. The Roman army retaliated and invaded the<space/><italics>insula Batavorum</italics>. A bridge was built over the river<space/><link><target>Nabalia</target></link>, where the warring parties approached each other on both sides to negotiate peace. The narrative was told in great detail in Tacitus' History, book iv, although, unfortunately, the narrative breaks off abruptly at the climax. Following the uprising,<space/><link><target>Legio X Gemina</target><part>Legio X ''Gemina''</part></link><space/>was housed in a stone<space/><italics>castra</italics><space/>to keep an eye on the Batavians.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Fate of the Batavi</heading><paragraph>The Batavi were still mentioned in 355 during the reign of<space/><link><target>Constantius II</target></link><space/>(317 - 361), when their island was already dominated by the<space/><link><target>Salian Franks</target><part>Salii</part></link>, a Frankish tribe that had sought Roman protection there in 297 after having been expelled from their own country by the Saxons.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Constantius Gallus</target></link><space/>added inhabitants of Batavia to his legions, &quot;of whose discipline we still make use.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tertullian.org/fathers/zosimus03_book3.htm</arg><arg name="title">Zosimus, New History. London: Green and Chaplin (1814). Book 3.</arg><arg name="work">tertullian.org</arg></template></extension><space/>It has been assumed they merged with the Salii shortly before or after and, after having been expelled by another tribe (it has been proposed this was the<space/><link><target>Chamavi</target></link>), shared their subsequent migration to<space/><link><target>Toxandria</target></link>. In the<space/><link><target>Late Roman army</target></link><space/>there was a unit called<space/><italics><link><target>Batavi (military unit)</target><part>Batavi</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The name of the Bavarian town of<space/><link><target>Passau</target></link><space/>descends from the Roman<space/><italics>Batavis</italics>, which was named after the Batavi. The town's name is old as it shows the typical effects of the<space/><link><target>High German consonant shift</target></link><space/>(b &gt; p, t &gt; ss).</paragraph><heading level='2'>The Batavian revival</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>History of the Netherlands#Batavians</arg></template>In the 16th-century emergence of a popular foundation story and origin myth for the<space/><link><target>Dutch people</target></link>, the Batavians came to be regarded as their ancestors during their national struggle for independence during the<space/><link><target>Eighty Years War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>This section follows<space/><link><target>Simon Schama</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Embarrassment of Riches: An Interpretation of Dutch Culture in the Golden Age</target></link></italics>, (New York) 1987, ch. II &quot;Patriotic Scripture&quot;, especially pp. 72 ff.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://humbox.ac.uk/2443/1/index.html'>The Batavian Myth</link>: A Study Pack from the Department of Dutch, University College London</extension><space/>The mix of fancy and fact in the<space/><italics>Cronyke van Hollandt, Zeelandt ende Vriesland</italics><space/>(called the<space/><italics>Divisiekroniek</italics>) by the Augustinian friar and humanist Cornelius Gerardi Aurelius, first published in 1517, brought the spare remarks in Tacitus' newly rediscovered<space/><italics>Germania</italics><space/>to a popular public; it was being reprinted as late as 1802.<extension extension_name='ref'>I. Schffer, &quot;The Batavian myth during the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries,&quot; in P. A. M. Geurts and A. E. M. Janssen,<space/><italics>Geschiedschrijving in Nederland</italics><space/>('Gravenhage) 1981:84-109, noted by Schama 1987.</extension><space/>Contemporary Dutch virtues of independence, fortitude and industry were fully recognizable among the Batavians in more scholarly history represented in<space/><link><target>Hugo Grotius</target></link>'<space/><italics>Liber de Antiquitate Republicae Batavicorum</italics><space/>(1610). The origin was perpetuated by Romeyn de Hooghe's<space/><italics>Spiegel van Staat der Vereenigden Nederlanden</italics><space/>(&quot;Mirror of the State of the United Netherlands,&quot; 1706), which also ran to many editions, and it was revived in the atmosphere of<space/><link><target>Romantic nationalism</target></link><space/>in the late eighteenth-century reforms that saw a short-lived<space/><link><target>Batavian Republic</target></link><space/>and, in the colony of the<space/><link><target>Dutch East Indies</target></link>, a capital (now<space/><link><target>Jakarta</target></link>) that was named Batavia. The success of this tale of origins was mostly due to resemblance in anthropology, which was based on<space/><link><target>tribal knowledge</target></link>. Being politically and geographically inclusive, this historical vision filled the needs of Dutch nation-building and integration in the 1890-1914 era.</paragraph><paragraph>However, a disadvantage of this historical nationalism soon became apparent. It suggested there were no strong external borders, while allowing for the fairly clear-cut internal borders that were emerging as the society pillarized into three parts. After 1945 the tribal knowledge lost its grip on anthropology and mostly vanished.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Marnix<space/></arg><arg name="last">Beyen<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Marnix Beyen<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Tribal Trinity: the Rise and Fall of the Franks, the Frisians and the Saxons in the Historical Consciousness of the Netherlands since 1850<space/></arg><arg name="journal">European History Quarterly<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000 30(4): 493-532<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0265-6914<space/></arg></template><space/>Fulltext:<space/><link><target>EBSCO</target></link></extension><space/>Modern variants of the Batavian<space/><link><target>founding myth</target></link><space/>are made more accurate by pointing out that the Batavians were one part of the ancestry of the Dutch people - together with the<space/><link><target>Frisians</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Saxons</target></link><space/>- by tracing patterns of<space/><link><target>DNA</target></link>. Echoes of this cultural continuity can still be found among various areas of Dutch modern culture, such as the very popular replica of the<space/><link><target>Batavia (ship)</target><part>ship ''Batavia''</part></link><space/>that can today be found in<space/><link><target>Lelystad</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Ancient Germanic culture</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Laeti</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Germanic peoples</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Nico Roymans, &quot;Hercules and the construction of a Batavian identity in the context of the Roman empire&quot;, in Ton Derks, Nico Roymans (ed.),<space/><italics>Ethnic Constructs in Antiquity: The Role of Power and Tradition</italics><space/>(Amsterdam, Amsterdam University Press, 2009) (Amsterdam Archaeological Studies, 13), 219-238.</listitem><listitem>Ton Derks, &quot;Ethnic identity in the Roman frontier. The epigraphy of Batavi and other Lower Rhine tribes&quot;, in Ton Derks, Nico Roymans (ed.),<space/><italics>Ethnic Constructs in Antiquity: The Role of Power and Tradition</italics><space/>(Amsterdam, Amsterdam University Press, 2009) (Amsterdam Archaeological Studies, 13), 239-282.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://humbox.ac.uk/2443/1/index.html'>The Batavian Myth</link>: A Study Pack from the Department of Dutch, University College London</listitem><listitem>Prof. M. Speidel: &quot;Riding for Caesar: the Roman Emperors' Horse-Guard&quot;, (Boston, Routledge, 1994)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://classics.mit.edu/Tacitus/histories.4.iv.html'>Tacitus, ''Histories'', Book iv</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/a/1/germania/germinf_map.gif'>A map</link><space/>of the Roman province<space/><link><target>Germania Inferior</target></link><space/>and neighbouring tribes.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.roman-britain.org/military/coh1bat.htm'>Cohors Primae Batavorum</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Germanic peoples</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Batavi (Germanic Tribe)</target></template><link><target>Category:Ancient Germanic peoples</target></link><link><target>Category:Batavi</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Prehistoric Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman Netherlands</target></link><link><target>Category:Chatti</target></link></paragraph></article>