<article title='Transport_in_Colombia'><paragraph><link><target>Image:Tunel de Occidente.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Tnel de Occidente in<space/><link><target>Antioquia</target></link>. The tunnel is the longest in Latin America.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold><link><target>Transport</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Colombia</target></link></bold><space/>is regulated by the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Transport (Colombia)</target><part>Ministry of Transport</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Road travel is the main means of transport; 69 percent of cargo is transported by road, as compared with 27 percent by railroad, 3 percent by internal waterways, and 1 percent by air.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"><link type='external' href='http://lcweb2.loc.gov/frd/cs/profiles/Colombia.pdf'>Colombia country profile</link>.<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link><space/><link><target>Federal Research Division</target></link><space/>(February 2007).<space/><italics>This article incorporates text from this source, which is in the<space/><link><target>public domain</target></link>.</italics></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Indigenous peoples influence</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Muisca raft Legend of El Dorado Offerings of gold.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Muisca</target></link><space/>culture golden raft.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>indigenous peoples in Colombia</target></link><space/>used and some continue to use the water ways as the way of transportation using<space/><link><target>raft</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and canoes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spanish influence</heading><paragraph>With the arrival of the Europeans the<space/><link><target>Spanish people</target><part>Spaniards brought</part></link><space/>the<space/><link><target>horse</target><trail>s</trail></link>, mules and donkey (which developed into the<space/><italics><link><target>Paso Fino</target></link></italics>) used by them in<space/><link><target>ranching</target></link><space/>duties later in the<space/><link><target>Spanish colonization of the Americas</target></link>. Horses contributed greatly to the transport of the Spanish conquerors and colonizers. They also introduced the wheel, and brought wooden carts and carriages to facilitate their transport. The Spaniards also developed the first roads, rudimentary and most of these in the<space/><link><target>Caribbean Region of Colombia</target><part>Caribbean region</part></link>. Due to the rough<space/><link><target>Geography of Colombia</target><part>terrain of Colombia</part></link><space/>communications between regions was difficult and affected the effectiveness of the central government creating isolation in some regions. Maritime navigation developed locally after Spain lifted its restrictions on ports within the<space/><link><target>Spanish Empire</target></link><space/>inducing mercantilism. Spanish also transported African slaves and forcedly migrated many indigenous tribes throughout Colombia.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Post-independence</heading><paragraph>With the independence and the influences of the European<space/><link><target>Industrial Revolution</target></link><space/>the main way of transport in Colombia became the navigation mainly through the<space/><link><target>Magdalena River</target></link><space/>which connected Honda in inland Colombia, with<space/><link><target>Barranquilla</target></link><space/>by the<space/><link><target>Caribbean sea</target></link><space/>to the trade with the United States and Europe. This also brought a large wave of immigrants from European and Middle Eastern countries. The industrialization process and transportation in Colombia were affected by the internal civil wars that surged after the independence from Spain and that continued throughout the 19th and 20th centuries.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Standardization</heading><paragraph>During the late 19th century European and American companies introduced railways to carry to the ports the local production of raw materials intended for exports and also imports from Europe.<space/><link><target>Steam ships</target></link><space/>began carrying Colombians, immigrants and goods from Europe and the United States over the<space/><link><target>Magdalena River</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:IMG 0639.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Pumarejo bridge</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Barranquilla</target></link>. The bridge serves to cross the<space/><link><target>Magdalena River</target></link><space/>between the<space/><link><target>Departments of Colombia</target><part>Departments</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Atlntico Department</target><part>Atlntico</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Magdalena Department</target><part>Magdalena</part></link>. It is also one of the oldest standing bridges in Colombia.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Ministry of Transport was created in 1905 during the Presidency of<space/><link><target>Rafael Reyes</target></link><space/>under the name of<space/><italics><space/>Ministerio de Obras Pblicas y Transporte</italics><space/>or Ministry of Public Works and Transport with the main function of taking care of national assets issues, including mines, oil (fuel), patents and trade marks, railways, roads, bridges, national buildings and land without landowners.</paragraph><paragraph>In the early 20th century roads and highways maintenance and construction regulations were established. Rivers were cleaned, dragged and channeled and the navigational industry was organized. The Public works districts were created, as well as the<space/><link><target>Ferrocarriles Nacionales de Colombia</target></link><space/>(National Railways of Colombia). Among other major projects developed were the aqueduct of<space/><link><target>Bogot</target></link>, La Regadera Dam and the Vitelma Water Treatment Plant. The Ministry also created the<space/><link><target>National Institute of Transit</target></link><space/>(from the Spanish<space/><italics>Instituto Nacional de Trnsito</italics>), (INTRA) under the Transport and tariffs Directorate and was in charge of designing the first National roads plan with the support of many foreign multinational construction companies.</paragraph><paragraph>Aviation was born in<space/><link><target>Barranquilla</target></link><space/>with the creation of<space/><link><target>SCADTA</target></link><space/>in 1919 a joint venture between Colombians and Germans that delivered mail to the main cities of Colombia which later merged with<space/><link><target>SACO (Colombia)</target><part>SACO</part></link><space/>to form<space/><link><target>Avianca</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Infrastructure</heading><heading level='3'>Railways</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Rail transport in Colombia</arg></template><link><target>File:Mapa de Colombia (ferrocarriles).svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Railroads of Colombia</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Colombia has<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3,034</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>of rail lines,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>150</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>of which are<space/><template><target>RailGauge</target><arg>1435mm</arg></template><space/>gauge and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>3,154</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>of which are<space/><template><target>RailGauge</target><arg>914mm</arg></template><space/>gauge. However, only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2,611</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>of lines are still in use. Rail transport in Colombia remains underdeveloped. The national railroad system, once the country's main mode of transport for freight, has been neglected in favor of road development and now accounts for only about a quarter of freight transport. Passenger-rail use was suspended in 1992 and resumed at the end of the 1990s. However, fewer than 165,000 passenger journeys were made in 1999, as compared with more than 5 million in 1972, and the figure was only 160,130 in 2005. Short sections of railroad, mainly the Bogot-Atlantic rim, are used to haul goods, mostly coal, to the Caribbean and Pacific ports. In 2005 a total of 27.5 million metric tons of cargo were transported by rail. Although the nation's rail network links seven of the country's 10 major cities, very little of it has been used regularly because of security concerns, lack of maintenance, and the power of the road transport union. During 20046, approximately 2,000 kilometers of the country's rail lines underwent refurbishment. This upgrade involved two main projects: the 1,484-kilometer line linking Bogot to the Caribbean Coast and the 499-kilometer Pacific coastal network that links the industrial city of<space/><link><target>Cali</target></link><space/>and the surrounding<space/><link><target>Colombian Coffee-Growers Axis</target><part>coffee-growing region</part></link><space/>to the port of<space/><link><target>Buenaventura, Valle del Cauca</target><part>Buenaventura</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Roads</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Highways in Colombia</arg></template><link><target>File:Mapa de Colombia (red vial).svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Main roads in Colombia</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The three main north-south highways are the Caribbean, Eastern, and Central Trunk Highways (troncales). Estimates of the length of Colombia's road system in 2004 ranged from 115,000 kilometers to 145,000 kilometers, of which fewer than 15 percent were paved. However, according to 2005 data reported by the Colombian government, the road network totaled 163,000 kilometers, 68 percent of which were paved and in good condition. The increase may reflect some newly built roads. President Uribe has vowed to pave more than 2,500 kilometers of roads during his administration, and about 5,000 kilometers of new secondary roads were being built in the 20036 period. Despite serious terrain obstacles, almost three-quarters of all cross-border dry cargo is now transported by road, 105,251 metric tons in 2005.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Highways are managed by the<space/><link><target>Ministry of Transport (Colombia)</target><part>Colombian Ministry of Transport</part></link><space/>through the<space/><link><target>National Roads Institute</target></link>. The security of the highways in Colombia is managed by the<space/><link><target>Highway Police (Colombia)</target><part>Highway Police</part></link><space/>unit of the<space/><link><target>Colombian National Police</target></link>. Colombia is crossed by the<space/><link><target>Panamerican Highway</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ports, waterways, and merchant marine</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Mapa_de_Colombia_(ros).svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Rivers of Colombia</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Seaports handle around 80 percent of international cargo. In 2005 a total of 105,251 metric tons of cargo were transported by water. Colombia's most important ocean terminals are Barranquilla, Cartagena, and Santa Marta on the Caribbean Coast and Buenaventura and Tumaco on the Pacific Coast. Exports mostly pass through the Caribbean ports of Cartagena and Santa Marta, while 65 percent of imports arrive at the port of Buenaventura. Other important ports and harbors are Baha de Portete, Leticia, Puerto Bolvar, San Andrs, Santa Marta, and Turbo. Since privatization was implemented in 1993, the efficiency of port handling has increased greatly. There are plans to construct a deep-water port at Baha Solano.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main inland waterways total about 18,200 kilometers, 11,000 kilometers of which are navigable by riverboats. A well-developed and important form of transport for both cargo and passengers, inland waterways transport approximately 3.8 million metric tons of freight and more than 5.5 million passengers annually. Main inland waterways are the MagdalenaCauca River system, which is navigable for 1,500 kilometers; the Atrato, which is navigable for 687 kilometers; the Orinoco system of more than five navigable rivers, which total more than 4,000 kilometers of potential navigation (mainly through Venezuela); and the Amazonas system, which has four main rivers totaling 3,000 navigable kilometers (mainly through Brazil). The government is planning an ambitious program to more fully utilize the main rivers for transport. In addition, the navy's riverine brigade has been patrolling waterways more aggressively in order to establish safer river transport in the more remote areas in the south and east of the country.<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The merchant marine totals 17 ships (1,000 gross registered tons or more), including four bulk, 13 cargo, one container, one liquefied gas, and three petroleum tanker ships. Colombia also has seven ships registered in other countries (Antigua and Barbuda, two; Panama, five).<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Aviation</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of airports in Colombia</arg></template><link><target>Image:Avianca 767-200 at El Dorado.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Avianca</target></link><space/><link><target>Boeing 767-200ER</target></link><space/>parked at the El Dorado Terminal</part></link><link><target>File:Aeropuerto el dorado 50.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>El Dorado International Airport</target></link><space/>of Bogot</part></link>All public airports in Colombia are managed and controlled by the<space/><link><target>Special Administrative Unit of Civil Aeronautics</target></link>. The customs/immigration issues are controlled by the<space/><link><target>Departamento Administrativo de Seguridad</target></link><space/>(DAS).</paragraph><paragraph>Colombia has well-developed air routes and an estimated total of 984 airports, 100 of which have paved runways, plus two heliports. Of the 74 main airports, 20 can accommodate jet aircraft. Two airports are more than 3,047 meters in length, nine are 2,4383,047 meters, 39 are 1,5242,437 meters, 38 are 9141,523 meters, 12 are shorter than 914 meters, and 880 have unpaved runways. The government has been selling its stake in local airports in order to allow their privatization. The country has 40 regional airports, and the cities of Bogot, Medelln, Cali, Barranquilla, Bucaramanga, Cartagena, Ccuta, Leticia, Pereira, San Andrs, and Santa Marta have international airports. Bogot's El Dorado International Airport handles 550 million metric tons of cargo and 22 million passengers a year, making it the largest airport in Latin America in terms of cargo and the third largest in passenger numbers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Urban transport</heading><paragraph>Urban transport systems have been developed in Bogot, Medelln, Cali and Barranquilla. Traffic congestion in Bogot has been greatly exacerbated by the lack of rail transport. However, this problem has been alleviated somewhat by the development of one of the world's largest and highest capacity<space/><link><target>Bus Rapid Transit</target><part>Bus Rapid Transit (BRT)</part></link><space/>Systems, known as the<space/><link><target>TransMilenio</target></link><space/>(opened 2000), and the restriction of vehicles through a daily,<space/><link><target>Pico y placa</target><part>rotating ban</part></link><space/>on private cars depending on plate numbers. Bogot's system consists of bus and minibus services managed by both private- and public-sector enterprises. Since 1995 Medelln has had a modern urban railway referred to as the<space/><link><target>Metro de Medelln</target></link>, which also connects with the cities of Itag, Envigado, and Bello. An elevated cable car system,<space/><link><target>Metrocable (Medellin)</target><part>Metrocable</part></link>, was added in 2004 to link some of Medelln's poorer mountainous neighborhoods with the Metro de Medelln. A<space/><link><target>Bus Rapid Transit</target><part>BRT</part></link><space/>line called Transmetro began operating in 2011, with a second line added in 2013. Other cities have also installed BRT systems such as<space/><link><target>Masivo Integrado de Occidente</target><part>Cali</part></link><space/>with a six line system (opened 2008),<space/><link><target>Transmetro</target><part>Barranquilla</part></link><space/>with two lines (opened 2010),<space/><link><target>Metrolinea</target><part>Bucaramanga</part></link><space/>with one line (opened 2010) and<space/><link><target>Megabs</target><part>Pereira</part></link><space/>with three lines (opened 2006).<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.brtdata.org/#/location/latin_america/colombia/</arg><arg name="title">Global BRT Data</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 August 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pipelines</heading><paragraph>Colombia has 4,350 kilometers of gas pipelines, 6,134 kilometers of oil pipelines, and 3,140 kilometers of refined-products pipelines. The country has five major oil pipelines, four of which connect with the Caribbean export terminal at Puerto Coveas. Until at least September 2005, the United States funded efforts to help protect a major pipeline, the 769-kilometer-long Cao LimnPuerto Coveas pipeline, which carries about 20 percent of Colombia's oil production to Puerto Coveas from the guerrilla-infested Arauca region in the eastern Andean foothills and Amazonian jungle. The number of attacks against pipelines began declining substantially in 2002. In 2004 there were only 17 attacks against the Cao LimnPuerto Coveas pipeline, down from 170 in 2001. However, a bombing in February 2005 shut the pipeline for several weeks, and attacks against the electrical gird system that provides energy to the Cao Limn oilfield have continued. New oil pipeline projects with Brazil and Venezuela are underway. In addition, the already strong cross-border trade links between Colombia and Venezuela were solidified in July 2004 with an agreement to build a US$320 million natural gas pipeline between the two countries, to be completed in 2008.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cp"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Megabs</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Railway stations in Colombia</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>es icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.mintransporte.gov.co/'>Colombia Ministry of Transport</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>es icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.invias.gov.co/'>Invias - Colombian National Institute of Highways</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>es icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dimar.mil.co/'>Colombian Maritime and Fluvial Port Authority</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>es icon</target></template><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.aerocivil.gov.co/'>COlombian Civil Aerospace Authority</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Colombia topics</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Americas topic</target><arg>Transport in</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Transport In Colombia</target></template><link><target>Category:Transport in Colombia</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>