<article title='Bragi'><paragraph><template><target>more footnotes</target><arg name="date">March 2013</arg></template><link><target>Image:Idunn and Bragi by Blommer.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Bragi is shown with a harp and accompanied by his wife<space/><link><target>Iunn</target></link><space/>in this 19th-century painting by<space/><link><target>Nils Blommr</target></link>.</part></link><bold>Bragi</bold><space/>is the<space/><link><target>skald</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>god of<space/><link><target>poetry</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Norse mythology</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph><italics>Bragi</italics><space/>is generally associated with<space/><italics>bragr</italics>, the Norse word for<space/><link><target>poetry</target></link>. The name of the god may have been derived from<space/><italics>bragr</italics>, or the term<space/><italics>bragr</italics><space/>may have been formed to describe 'what Bragi does'. A connection between the name Bragi and Old English<space/><italics>brego</italics><space/>'chieftain' has been suggested but is generally now discounted. A connection between Bragi and the<space/><italics>bragarfull</italics><space/>'promise cup' is sometimes suggested, as<space/><italics>bragafull</italics>, an alternate form of the word, might be translated as 'Bragi's cup'. See<space/><bold><link><target>Bragarfull</target></link></bold>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Attestations</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Bragi and Iunn by Frlich.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bragi, holding a harp, sings before his wife Iunn (1895) by<space/><link><target>Lorenz Frlich</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>Image:Bragi by Wahlbom.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;Bragi&quot; by<space/><link><target>Carl Wahlbom</target></link><space/>(1810-1858).</part></link><link><target>Image:Loki taunts Bragi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;Loki Taunts Bragi&quot; (1908) by<space/><link><target>W. G. Collingwood</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>Snorri Sturluson</target></link><space/>writes in the<space/><italics><link><target>Gylfaginning</target></link></italics><space/>after describing<space/><link><target>Odin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thor</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Baldr</target></link>:<template><target>quote</target><arg>One is called Bragi: he is renowned for wisdom, and most of all for fluency of speech and skill with words. He knows most of skaldship, and after him skaldship is called ''bragr'', and from his name that one is called ''bragr''-man or -woman, who possesses eloquence surpassing others, of women or of men. His wife is [[Iðunn]].</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Skldskaparml</target></link></italics><space/>Snorri writes:<template><target>quote</target><arg>How should one periphrase Bragi? By calling him ''husband of Iðunn'', ''first maker of poetry'', and ''the long-bearded god'' (after his name, a man who has a great beard is called Beard-Bragi), and ''son of Odin''.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>That Bragi is Odin's son is clearly mentioned only here and in some versions of a list of the sons of Odin (see<space/><bold><link><target>Sons of Odin</target></link></bold>). But &quot;wish-son&quot; in stanza 16 of the<space/><italics><link><target>Lokasenna</target></link></italics><space/>could mean &quot;Odin's son&quot; and is translated by Hollander as<space/><italics>Odin's kin</italics>. Bragi's mother is never named. If Bragi's mother is<space/><link><target>Frigg</target></link>, then Frigg is somewhat dismissive of Bragi in the<space/><italics>Lokasenna</italics><space/>in stanza 27 when Frigg complains that if she had a son in<space/><link><target>gir</target></link>'s hall as brave as<space/><link><target>Baldr</target></link><space/>then<space/><link><target>Loki</target></link><space/>would have to fight for his life.</paragraph><paragraph>In that poem Bragi at first forbids Loki to enter the hall but is overruled by Odin. Loki then gives a greeting to all gods and goddesses who are in the hall save to Bragi. Bragi generously offers his sword, horse, and an arm ring as peace gift but Loki only responds by accusing Bragi of cowardice, of being the most afraid to fight of any of the<space/><link><target>sir</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elves</target></link><space/>within the hall. Bragi responds that if they were outside the hall, he would have Loki's head, but Loki only repeats the accusation. When Bragi's wife Iunn attempts to calm Bragi, Loki accuses her of embracing her brother's slayer, a reference to matters that have not survived. It may be that Bragi had slain Iunn's brother.</paragraph><paragraph>A passage in the<space/><italics>Poetic Edda</italics><space/>poem<space/><italics><link><target>Sigrdrfuml</target></link></italics><space/>describes runes being graven on the sun, on the ear of one of the sun-horses and on the hoofs of the other, on<space/><link><target>Sleipnir</target></link>'s teeth, on bear's paw, on eagle's beak, on wolf's claw, and on several other things including on Bragi's tongue. Then the runes are shaved off and the shavings are mixed with mead and sent abroad so that sir have some, Elves have some,<space/><link><target>Vanir</target></link><space/>have some, and Men have some, these being beech runes and birth runes, ale runes, and magic runes. The meaning of this is obscure.</paragraph><paragraph>The first part of Snorri Sturluson's<space/><italics><link><target>Skldskaparml</target></link></italics><space/>is a dialogue between<space/><link><target>gir</target></link><space/>and Bragi about the nature of poetry, particularly skaldic poetry. Bragi tells the origin of the mead of poetry from the blood of<space/><link><target>Kvasir</target></link><space/>and how Odin obtained this mead. He then goes on to discuss various poetic metaphors known as<space/><italics><link><target>kenning</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Snorri Sturluson clearly distinguishes the god Bragi from the mortal skald Bragi Boddason, whom he often mentions separately. The appearance of Bragi in the<space/><italics>Lokasenna</italics><space/>indicates that if these two Bragis were originally the same, they have become separated for that author also, or that chronology has become very muddled and Bragi Boddason has been relocated to mythological time. Compare the appearance of the<space/><link><target>Wales</target><part>Welsh</part></link><space/><link><target>Taliesin</target></link><space/>in the second branch of the<space/><link><target>Mabinogion</target><part>Mabinogi</part></link>. Legendary chronology sometimes does become muddled. Whether Bragi the god originally arose as a deified version of Bragi Boddason was much debated in the 19th century, especially by the scholars<space/><link><target>Eugen Mogk</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sophus Bugge</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>John Lindow</target></link>, &quot;Narrative worlds, human environments, and poets: The case of Bragi&quot;, in<space/><italics>Old Norse Religion in Long-Term Perspectives: Origins, Changes, and Interactions</italics>, ed. Anders Andrn, Kristina Jennbert and Catharina Raudvere, Vgar till Midgrd 8, Lund: Nordic Academic Press, 2012, ISBN 9789187121159, pp.&amp;nbsp;21&amp;ndash;25,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=gjq6rvoIRpAC&amp;amp;pg=PA21&amp;amp;dq=Eugen+Mogk&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=sWzeVJb5KMmzoQT_ooCgDQ&amp;amp;ved=0CBwQ6AEwADgo#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Eugen%20Mogk&amp;amp;f=false'>p.&amp;nbsp;21</link>.</extension><space/>The debate remains undecided.</paragraph><paragraph>In the poem<space/><italics><link><target>Eirksml</target></link></italics><space/>Odin, in<space/><link><target>Valhalla</target></link>, hears the coming of the dead<space/><link><target>Norway</target><part>Norwegian</part></link><space/>king<space/><link><target>Eric Bloodaxe</target></link><space/>and his host, and bids the heroes<space/><link><target>Sigmund</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sinfjtli</target></link><space/>rise to greet him. Bragi is then mentioned, questioning how Odin knows that it is Eric and why Odin has let such a king die. In the poem<space/><italics><link><target>Hkonarml</target></link></italics>, Hkon the Good is taken to Valhalla by the<space/><link><target>valkyrie</target></link><space/><link><target>Gndul</target></link><space/>and Odin sends<space/><link><target>Hermr</target></link><space/>and Bragi to greet him. In these poems Bragi could be either a god or a dead hero in Valhalla. Attempting to decide is further confused because<space/><italics>Hermr</italics><space/>also seems to be sometimes the name of a god and sometimes the name of a hero. That Bragi was also the first to speak to Loki in the<space/><italics>Lokasenna</italics><space/>as Loki attempted to enter the hall might be a parallel. It might have been useful and customary that a man of great eloquence and versed in poetry should greet those entering a hall.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Skalds named Bragi</heading><heading level='3'>Bragi Boddason</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Bragi Boddason</arg></template>In the<space/><italics>Prose Edda</italics><space/>Snorri Sturluson quotes many stanzas attributed to<space/><bold>Bragi Boddason</bold><space/>the old (<italics>Bragi Boddason inn gamli</italics>), a Norwegian court poet who served several Swedish kings,<space/><link><target>Ragnar Lodbrok</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sten Beli</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bjrn at Hauge</target></link><space/>who reigned in the first half of the 9th century. This Bragi was reckoned as the first skaldic poet, and was certainly the earliest skaldic poet then remembered by name whose verse survived in memory.</paragraph><paragraph>Snorri especially quotes passages from Bragi's<space/><italics><link><target>Ragnarsdrpa</target></link></italics>, a poem supposedly composed in honor of the famous legendary Viking<space/><link><target>Ragnar Lodbrok</target><part>Ragnar Lodbrk</part></link><space/>('Hairy-breeches') describing the images on a decorated shield which Ragnar had given to Bragi. The images included Thor's fishing for<space/><link><target>Jrmungandr</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gefjun</target></link>'s ploughing of<space/><link><target>Zealand (Denmark)</target><part>Zealand</part></link><space/>from the soil of Sweden, the attack of<space/><link><target>Hamdir and Sorli</target></link><space/>against King<space/><link><target>Ermanaric</target><part>Jrmunrekk</part></link>, and the never-ending battle between<space/><link><target>Hedin and Hgni</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bragi son of Hlfdan the Old</heading><paragraph><bold>Bragi son of Hlfdan the Old</bold><space/>is mentioned only in the<space/><italics>Skjldskaparml</italics>. This Bragi is the sixth of the second of two groups of nine sons fathered by King Hlfdan the Old on Alvig the Wise, daughter of King Eymund of<space/><link><target>Novgorod</target><part>Hlmgard</part></link>. This second group of sons are all eponymous ancestors of legendary families of the north. Snorri says:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Bragi, from whom the Bragnings are sprung (that is the race of Hlfdan the Generous).</extension>Of the Bragnings as a race and of Hlfdan the Generous nothing else is known. However,<space/><italics>Bragning</italics><space/>is often, like some others of these dynastic names, used in poetry as a general word for 'king' or 'ruler'.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Bragi Hgnason</heading><paragraph>In the eddic poem<space/><italics><link><target>Helgakvia Hundingsbana II</target></link></italics>,<space/><bold>Bragi Hgnason</bold>, his brother Dag, and his sister Sigrn were children of<space/><link><target>Hgne</target></link>, the king of<space/><link><target>East Gtaland</target></link>. The poem relates how<space/><link><target>Sigmund</target></link>'s son<space/><link><target>Helgi Hundingsbane</target></link><space/>agreed to take Sigrn daughter of Hgni as his wife against her unwilling betrothal to Hodbrodd son of<space/><link><target>Granmar</target></link><space/>the king of<space/><link><target>Sdermanland</target></link>. In the subsequent battle of Frekastein (probably one of the 300<space/><link><target>hill fort</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of Sdermanland, as<space/><italics>stein</italics><space/>meant &quot;hill fort&quot;) against Hgni and Grammar, all the chieftains on Granmar's side are slain, including Bragi, except for Bragi's brother Dag.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>DuBois, Thomas A.<space/><italics>Nordic Religions in the Viking Age</italics>. Philadelphia: University of Pennsylvania Press, 1999. ISBN 0-8122-1714-4</listitem><listitem>Dumzil, Georges.<space/><italics>Gods of the Ancient Northmen</italics>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 1973. ISBN 0-520-02044-8</listitem><listitem>Lindow, John.<space/><italics>Handbook of Norse mythology</italics>. Santa Barbara, CA: ABC-CLIO, 2001. ISBN 1-57607-217-7</listitem><listitem>Munch, P. A.<space/><italics>Norse Mythology: Legends of Gods and Heroes</italics>. London: H. Milford, Oxford University Press, 1926.</listitem><listitem>Orchard, Andy.<space/><italics>Cassell's Dictionary of Norse Myth and Legend</italics>. London: Cassell, 2002. ISBN 0-304-36385-5</listitem><listitem>Turville-Petre, Gabriel.<space/><italics>Myth and Religion of the North: The Religion of Ancient Scandinavia</italics>. New York: Holt, Rinehart and Winston, 1964.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Bragi</arg></template><template><target>Norse mythology</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:sir</target></link><link><target>Category:Knowledge gods</target></link></paragraph></article>