<article title='Bolsheviks'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the Bolshevik faction in the RSDLP 1903–1912</arg><arg></arg><arg>Bolshevik (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><link><target>File:Presidium of the 9th Congress of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bolshevik Party meeting. Sitting (from left):<space/><link><target>Avel Enukidze</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mikhail Kalinin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nikolai Bukharin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mikhail Tomsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mikhail Lashevich</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lev Kamenev</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Yevgeni Preobrazhensky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Leonid Serebryakov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexei Rykov</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Kustodiev The Bolshevik.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Boris Kustodiev</target></link>s 1920 painting &quot;''Bolshevik''&quot;</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Bolsheviks</bold>, originally also<space/><bold>Bolshevists</bold><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Ushakov's Explanatory Dictionary of Russian Language]]<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Большевистский</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Efn</target><arg name="Both a synonym to "Bolshevik" and an adherent of Bolshevik policies.<ref>{{Citation | contribution-url"><space/>http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/bolshevist | title<space/></arg></template><space/>or<space/><bold>Bolsheviki</bold><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Bolsheviki Seize State Buildings, Defying Kerensky</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nytimes.com/learning/general/onthisday/big/1107.html#article</arg><arg name="accessdate">22 December 2013<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>The [[New York Times]]</arg><arg name="date">7 November 1917</arg></template></extension><space/>(<template><target>lang-rus</target><arg>большевики, большевик (singular)</arg><arg name="p">bəlʲʂɨˈvʲik</arg></template>; derived from<space/><italics>bol'shinstvo</italics>, &quot;majority&quot;, literally meaning &quot;one of the majority&quot;) were a<space/><link><target>faction (political)</target><part>faction</part></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Marxism</target><part>Marxist</part></link><space/><link><target>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party</target></link><space/>(RSDLP) which split apart from the<space/><link><target>Menshevik</target></link><space/>faction<template><target>Efn</target><arg><space/>Derived from меньшинство ''men'shinstvo'', "minority", which comes from меньше ''men'she'', "less". The split occurred at the Second [[Congress of the CPSU|Party Congress]] in 1903.</arg></template><space/>at the<space/><link><target>2nd Congress of the RSDLP</target><part>Second Party Congress</part></link><space/>in 1903.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Suny<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ronald Grigor<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Soviet Experiment<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-19-508105-3<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>57</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the Second Party Congress vote, the Bolsheviks won on the majority of important issues, hence their name.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Shub<space/></arg><arg><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>81</arg></template><space/>They ultimately became the<space/><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></link>.<template><target>Efn</target><arg><space/>After the split, the Bolshevik party was designated as RSDLP(b) (Russian: РСДРП(б)), where "b" stands for "Bolsheviks". Shortly after coming to power in November 1917 the party changed its name to the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks) (РКП(б)) and was generally known as the Communist Party after that point, however, it was not until 1952 that the party formally dropped the word "Bolshevik" from its name. See [[Congress of the CPSU]] article for the timeline of name changes.</arg></template><space/>The Bolsheviks came to power in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>October Revolution</target></link><space/>phase of the<space/><link><target>Russian Revolution of 1917</target></link>, and founded the<space/><link><target>Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic</target></link><space/>which would become the chief constituent of the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>in 1922.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bolsheviks, founded by<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexander Bogdanov</target></link>, were by 1905 a major organization consisting primarily of workers under a democratic internal<space/><link><target>hierarchy</target></link><space/>governed by the principle of<space/><link><target>democratic centralism</target></link>, who considered themselves the leaders of the revolutionary<space/><link><target>proletariat</target><part>working class</part></link><space/>of Russia. Their beliefs and practices were often referred to as<space/><bold>Bolshevism</bold>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History of the split</heading><paragraph><template><target>MarxismLeninism sidebar</target><arg>Related</arg></template>In the<space/><link><target>2nd Congress of the Russian Social Democratic Labour Party</target></link>, held in Brussels and London during August 1903, Lenin and<space/><link><target>Julius Martov</target></link><space/>disagreed over the membership rules. Lenin wanted members &quot;who recognise the Party Programme and support it by material means<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Service</arg><arg name="first">Robert</arg><arg name="title">Lenin : a biography<space/></arg><arg name="date">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Pan</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-33051838-3<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>154</arg><arg name="format"><space/>paperback</arg></template></extension><space/>and by personal participation in one of the party's organisations.&quot;<space/><link><target>Julius Martov</target></link><space/>suggested &quot;by regular personal assistance under the direction of one of the party's organisations.&quot; Lenin advocated limiting party membership to a smaller core of active members, as opposed to &quot;<link><target>Card-carrying Communists</target><part>card carriers</part></link>&quot; who might only be active in party branches from time to time or not at all. This active base would develop the cadre, a core of &quot;<link><target>professional revolutionaries</target></link>&quot;, consisting of loyal communists who would spend most of their time organising the party toward a mass revolutionary party capable of leading a<space/><link><target>Proletarian revolution</target><part>workers' revolution</part></link><space/>against the<space/><link><target>Tsardom of Russia</target><part>Tsarist</part></link><space/>autocracy.</paragraph><paragraph>A main source of the factions could be directly attributed to Lenins steadfast opinion and unwillingness to &quot;bear opinions which were contrary to his own&quot;.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Shub<space/></arg><arg><space/>1976<space/></arg><arg name="p">76</arg></template><space/>It was obvious at early stages in Lenins revolutionary practices that he would not be willing to concede on any party policy that conflicted with his own predetermined ideas. It was the loyalty that he had to his own self-envisioned utopia that caused the party split. He was seen even by fellow party members as being so narrow minded that he believed that there were types of people Friend and enemy-those who followed him, and all the rest.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>104</arg></template><space/><link><target>Leon Trotsky</target></link>, one of Lenins fellow revolutionaries (though they had differing views as to how the revolution and party should be handled), compared Lenin in 1904 to the French revolutionary<space/><link><target>Maximilien de Robespierre</target><part>Robespierre</part></link>.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>104</arg></template><space/>Lenins view of politics as verbal and ideological warfare and his inability to accept criticism even if it came from his own dedicated followers was the reason behind this accusation.</paragraph><paragraph>The root of the split was centered on a book that Lenin wrote while serving a sentence of exile titled<space/><italics><link><target>What is to be Done?</target></link></italics><space/>The book was published in 1902 in Germany; strict censorship in Russia prevented its legal publication and distribution.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>106</arg></template><space/>One of the main points of Lenins writing was the view that a revolution can only truly be achieved by the strong leadership of one person or a very select few over the masses. After the proposed revolution resulted in a successful overthrow of the government, this individual leader must release power to allow socialism to fully encompass the nation. Lenin also believed that revolutionary leaders must fully dedicate their entire lives to the cause in order to be successful. Lenin felt that if professional revolutionaries did not maintain control over the workers they would lose sight of the partys objective and sell out to oppositionists beliefs or abandon the revolution entirely.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>106</arg></template><space/>Lenins view of a socialist intelligentsia showed that he was not a complete supporter of the Marxist theory which also created some party unrest. For example, Lenin agreed with the Marxist belief of eliminating social classes, but in his utopian society there would still be visible distinctions between those in politics and the common worker. Through moral disagreement to unfair worker treatment and loyalty to a completely classless society Lenins variations were met with internal party discontent.<template><target>clarify</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><space/>Although the party split of Bolsheviks and Mensheviks would not become official until 1903, the differences originally began to surface with the publication of<space/><italics>What is to be Done?</italics>. Through the influence of the book, Lenin also undermined another group of reformers known as &quot;Economists&quot;, who were pushing for economic reform while leaving the government somewhat intact and failed to recognize the importance of uniting the working population with their cause.<extension extension_name='ref' name="party"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Formation of the Russian social-democratic labor party. Appearance of the bolshevik & the menshevik groups within the party<space/></arg><arg name="date">1939<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>International Publishers</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg></template></extension><template><target>Primary source-inline</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Other than the debate between Lenin and Julius Martov; Lenin felt membership should require support of the Party program, financial contributions, and finally involvement in a Party organization whereas Martov didnt see the need for joining Party organizations, internal unrest also rose over the structure that was best suited for Soviet power.<extension extension_name='ref' name="party"></extension><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><space/>As discussed in<space/><italics><link><target>What is to be Done?</target></link></italics>, Lenin firmly believed that a rigid political structure was needed to effectively initiate a formal revolution. This idea was met with opposition from his once close followers including Julius Martov, Georgy Plekhanov, Leon Trotsky, and Pavel Axelrod.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Tucker<space/></arg><arg><space/>1975</arg></template>&gt;<template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><space/>Georgy Plekhanov and Lenins major dispute arose addressing the topic of nationalizing land or leaving it for private use. Lenin wanted to nationalize to aid in collectivization. Plekhanov thought worker motivation would remain higher if individuals were able to maintain their own property. Those who opposed Lenin and wanted to continue on the Marxist path towards complete socialism and disagreed with his strict party membership guidelines became known as softs while Lenin supporters became known as hards.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Tucker<space/></arg><arg><space/>1975<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>xxxviii</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The base of active and experienced members would be the recruiting ground for this professional core. Sympathizers would be left outside and the party would be organised based on the concept of<space/><link><target>democratic centralism</target></link>. Martov, until then a close friend of Lenin, agreed with him that the core of the party should consist of professional revolutionaries, but argued that party membership should be open to sympathizers, revolutionary workers and other<space/><link><target>fellow traveler</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The two had disagreed on the issue as early as MarchMay 1903, but it was not until the Congress that their differences became irreconcilable and split the party.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Getzler<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Israel<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Israel Getzler<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Martov: A Political Biography of a Russian Social Democrat<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2003<space/></arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1967<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-521-52602-7<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>78</arg></template>.</extension><space/>At first the disagreement appeared to be minor and inspired by personal conflicts. For example, Lenin's insistence on dropping less active editorial board members from<space/><italics><link><target>Iskra</target></link></italics><space/>or Martovs support for the Organizing Committee of the Congress which Lenin opposed, The differences quickly grew and the split became irreparable.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Origins of the name</heading><paragraph>The two factions were originally known as &quot;hard&quot; (Lenins supporters) and &quot;soft&quot; (Martov's supporters). Soon, however, the terminology changed to &quot;Bolsheviks&quot; and &quot;Mensheviks&quot;, from the Russian &quot;bolshinstvo&quot; (majority) and &quot;menshinstvo&quot; (minority).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Wilson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Edmund</arg><arg name="title">To the Finland Station</arg><arg name="date">1977</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Fontana<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">0-00-632420-7</arg><arg name="page"><space/>402</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Edmund Wilson</arg></template></extension><space/>On the other hand, Martovs supporters won the vote concerning the question of party membership. Neither Lenin nor Martov had a firm majority throughout the Congress as delegates left or switched sides. At the end, the Congress was evenly split between the two factions.</paragraph><paragraph>From 1907 on, English language articles sometimes used the term &quot;Maximalist&quot; for &quot;Bolshevik&quot; and &quot;Minimalist&quot; for &quot;Menshevik&quot;, which proved confusing since there was also a &quot;Maximalist&quot; faction within the Russian<space/><link><target>Socialist-Revolutionary Party</target></link><space/>in 19041906 (which after 1906 formed a separate<space/><link><target>Union of Socialists-Revolutionaries Maximalists</target></link>) and then again after 1917.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Étienne<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Antonelli<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bolshevik Russia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>AA Knopf<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1920<space/></arg><arg name="others"><space/>Charles A. Carroll trans<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/>the term ‘Maximalist’ rather widely used as a translation for ‘Bolshevik’ is historically false.<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>59</arg></template><space/>307 pp.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Composition of the party</heading><paragraph>The average party member was very young. In 1907, 22% of Bolsheviks were under 20, 37% were 2024 and 16% were 2529. By 1905, 62% of the members were industrial workers (3% of the population in 1897<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Abraham<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Ascher<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Revolution of 1905<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>4</arg></template>.</extension>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Tony<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Cliff<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Lenin and the Revolutionary Party<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>37</arg></template>.</extension><space/>22% of Bolsheviks were gentry (1.7% of the total population), 38% were uprooted peasants, compared with 19% and 26% for the<space/><link><target>Mensheviks</target></link>. In 1907 78.3% of the Bolsheviks were Russian and 10% were Jewish (34% and 20% for the Mensheviks). Total membership was 8,400 in 1905, 13,000 in 1906 and 46,100 by 1907 (8,400, 18,000, 38,200 respectively for the Mensheviks). By 1910 both factions together had fewer than 10,000 members.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Richard<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Russian Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>364–5</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Beginning of the 1905 Revolution (19031905)</heading><paragraph>The two factions were in a state of flux in 190304 with many members changing sides. The founder of Russian Marxism,<space/><link><target>Georgy Plekhanov</target></link>, who was at first allied with<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link><space/>and the Bolsheviks, parted ways with them by 1904.<space/><link><target>Leon Trotsky</target></link><space/>at first supported the Mensheviks, but left them in September 1904 over their insistence on an alliance with Russian liberals and their opposition to a reconciliation with Lenin and the Bolsheviks. He remained a self-described &quot;non-factional social democrat&quot; until August 1917 when he joined Lenin and the Bolsheviks as their positions assembled and he came to believe that Lenin was right on the issue of the party.</paragraph><paragraph>All but one member of the Central Committee were arrested in<space/><link><target>Moscow</target></link><space/>in early 1905. The remaining member, with the power of appointing a new one, was won over by the Bolsheviks.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Tim<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>McDaniel<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Autocracy, capitalism, and revolution in Russia<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>246</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The lines between the Bolsheviks and the Mensheviks hardened in April 1905 when the Bolsheviks held a Bolsheviks-only meeting in London, which they called the Third Party Congress. The Mensheviks organised a rival conference and the split was thus formalised.</paragraph><paragraph>The Bolsheviks played a relatively minor role in the<space/><link><target>1905 Russian Revolution</target><part>1905 Revolution</part></link>, and were a minority in the<space/><link><target>St. Petersburg Soviet</target></link><space/>of Workers' Deputies led by Trotsky. The less significant Moscow<space/><link><target>Soviet (council)</target><part>Soviet</part></link>, however, was dominated by the Bolsheviks. These soviets became the model for those formed in 1917.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The Mensheviks (&quot;The minority&quot;) (19061907)</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">February 2012</arg></template>As the<space/><link><target>Russian Revolution of 1905</target></link><space/>progressed, Bolsheviks, Mensheviks and smaller non-Russian social democratic parties operating within the Russian Empire attempted to reunify at the<space/><link><target>4th Congress of the RSDLP</target><part>Fourth (Unification) Congress of the RSDLP</part></link><space/>held at<space/><link><target>Folkets hus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Norra Bantorget</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link>, April 1906. When the Mensheviks struck an alliance with the<space/><link><target>General Jewish Labour Bund in Lithuania, Poland and Russia</target><part>Jewish Bund</part></link>, the Bolsheviks found themselves in a minority.</paragraph><paragraph>However, all factions retained their respective factional structure and the Bolsheviks formed the<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Centre</target></link>, the de facto governing body of the Bolshevik faction within the RSDLP. At the Fifth Congress held in London in May 1907, the Bolsheviks were in the majority, but the two factions continued functioning mostly independently of each other.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Split between Lenin and Bogdanov (19081910)</heading><paragraph>Tensions had existed between Lenin and Bogdanov as early as 1904: Lenin had fallen out with<space/><link><target>Nikolai Valentinov</target></link>, after the latter had introduced him to<space/><link><target>Ernst Mach</target></link>'s Empiriocriticism, a viewpoint that Bogdanov had been exploring and developing as Empiriomonism. Having worked as co-editor with Plekhanov on<space/><italics>Zayra</italics><space/>he had come to agree with the latter's rejection of Bogdanov's Empiriomonism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Left-Bol"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Biggart</arg><arg name="first"><space/>John</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alexander Bogdanov, left-Bolshevism and the Proletkult 1904–1932</arg><arg name="date">1989<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of East Angla</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Norwich</arg><arg name="asin"><space/>B001ON1IY4<space/></arg><arg name="asin-tld">co.uk</arg></template></extension><space/>With the defeat of the revolution in mid-1907 and the adoption of a new, highly restrictive election law, the Bolsheviks began debating whether to boycott the new parliament known as the<space/><link><target>Third Duma</target></link>. Lenin,<space/><link><target>Grigory Zinoviev</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lev Kamenev</target></link><space/>and others argued for participating in the Duma while<space/><link><target>Alexander Bogdanov</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Anatoly Lunacharsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Mikhail Pokrovsky</target></link><space/>and others argued that the social democratic faction in the Duma should be recalled.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Wolfe</arg><arg name="first">Bertram D.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Three Who Made a Revolution</arg><arg name="date">1966</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin</arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-14-020783-X</arg><arg name="page">410</arg><arg name="authorlink">Bertram Wolfe</arg></template></extension><space/>The latter became known as<space/><link><target>recallists</target></link><space/>(&quot;otzovists&quot; in Russian). A smaller group within the Bolshevik faction demanded that the RSDLP central committee should give its sometimes unruly Duma faction an ultimatum, demanding complete subordination to all party decisions. This group became known as &quot;<link><target>ultimatists</target></link>&quot; and was generally allied with the recallists.</paragraph><paragraph>With most Bolshevik leaders either supporting Bogdanov or undecided by mid-1908 when the differences became irreconcilable, Lenin concentrated on undermining Bogdanov's reputation as a philosopher. In 1909 he published a scathing book of criticism entitled<space/><italics>Materialism and Empiriocriticism</italics><space/>(1909),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="place"><space/>Moscow<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>May 1909<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Zveno Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.marxists.org/archive/lenin/works/1908/mec/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Materialism & Empiriocriticism</arg></template>.</extension><space/>assaulting Bogdanovs position and accusing him of philosophical idealism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Alan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Woods<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bolshevism: The Road to Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wellred<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1999<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>1-900007-05-3<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.marxist.com/bolshevism/part3-5.html<space/></arg><arg name="chapter"><space/>Part Three: The Period of Reaction</arg></template>.</extension><space/>In June 1909, Bogdanov proposed the formation of Party Schools as &quot;Proletarian Universities&quot; at a Bolshevik mini-conference in<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link><space/>organised by the editorial board of the Bolshevik magazine<space/><italics><link><target>Proletary</target></link></italics><space/>in June 1909. However this was not accepted and Lenin tried to expel him from the Bolshevik faction.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>A Documentary History of Communism in Russia<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>Robert V<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Daniels<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>UPNE<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1993<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-87451-616-1<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>33</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Bogdanov was then involved with setting up<space/><link><target>Vpered</target></link>, which ran the Capri Party School from August to December 1909.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Marot<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John Eric<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alexander Bogdanov, Vpered, and the Role of the Intellectual in the Workers’ Movement<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Russian Review<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>49<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3 (Special Issue on Alexander Bogdanov)<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>241–64<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>July 1990<space/></arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>130152</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Final attempt at party unity (1910)</heading><paragraph>With both Bolsheviks and Mensheviks weakened by splits within their ranks and by<space/><link><target>Tsar</target><trail>ist</trail></link><space/>repression, they were tempted to try to re-unite the party. In January 1910, Leninists, recallists and various Menshevik factions held a meeting of the party's Central Committee in Paris. Kamenev and Zinoviev were dubious about the idea, but were willing to give it a try under pressure from &quot;conciliator&quot; Bolsheviks like<space/><link><target>Victor Nogin</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the more underlying reasons that aided in preventing any reunification of the party was the Russian police. The police were able to infiltrate both parties inner circles by sending in spies who then reported on the opposing partys intentions and hostilities.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p">109</arg></template><space/>This allowed the tensions to remain high between the Bolsheviks and Mensheviks. In turn it prevented them from uniting under common ground which could have possibly sped up the entire revolution.</paragraph><paragraph>Lenin was firmly opposed to any re-unification, but was outvoted within the Bolshevik leadership. The meeting reached a tentative agreement and one of its provisions made Trotsky's<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>-based<space/><italics><link><target>Pravda</target></link></italics><space/>a party-financed 'central organ'. Kamenev, Trotsky's brother-in-law, was added to the editorial board from the Bolsheviks, but the unification attempts failed in August 1910 when Kamenev resigned from the board amid mutual recriminations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Forming a separate party (1912)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:1919-Trotsky Lenin Kamenev-Party-Congress.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Left to right:<space/><link><target>Leon Trotsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lev Kamenev</target></link></part></link>The factions permanently broke off relations in January 1912 after the Bolsheviks organised a Bolsheviks-only<space/><link><target>Prague Party Conference</target></link><space/>and formally expelled Mensheviks and recallists from the party. As a result, they ceased to be a faction in the RSDLP and instead declared themselves an independent party, called<space/><bold>Russian Social Democratic Labour Party (bolsheviks)</bold><space/>or RSDLP(b). Unofficially the Party has been referred to as the &quot;Bolshevik Party&quot;. Throughout the century, the Party adopted a number of different names. In 1918, RSDLP(b) became<space/><bold>(All-)Russian Communist Party (bolsheviks)</bold><space/>and remained so until 1925. From 192552 the name was<space/><bold>All-Union Communist Party (bolsheviks)</bold>, and from 19521991<space/><bold><link><target>Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></link></bold>.</paragraph><paragraph>As the party split became permanent and politically recognized in 1912 due to an all Bolshevik meeting of Congress further divisions became evident. One of the most notable differences was how each faction decided to fund its revolution. The Mensheviks decided to fund their revolution through membership dues while Lenin often resorted to much more drastic measures since he required a higher budget.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>108</arg></template><space/>One of the common methods the Bolsheviks used was committing bank robberies, one of which in 1907 resulted in the party gaining over 250,000 rubbles which is the equivalent of about $125,000.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p">108</arg></template><space/>Bolsheviks were in constant need of money because Lenin practiced his beliefs exercised in his writings that revolutions must be led by individuals who devote their entire life to the cause. To compensate he awarded them with salaries for their sacrifice and dedication. This measure was taken to help ensure that the revolutionists stayed focused on their duties and motivated them to perform their jobs. Lenin also used the party money to print and copy pamphlets which were distributed in cities and at political rallies in attempts to expand their operations. This was an obvious difference between the Bolsheviks and Mensheviks party beliefs. Both factions also managed to gain funds simply by receiving donations from wealthy supporters.</paragraph><paragraph>Further differences in party agendas became evident as the beginning of World War I loomed near. Stalin was especially eager for the start of the war, hoping that it would turn into a war between classes or essentially a Russian Civil War.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>111</arg></template><space/>This desire for war was fueled by Lenins vision that the workers and peasants would resist joining the war effort, and therefore be more compelled to join the socialist movement. Through the increase in support Russia would then be forced to withdraw from the Allied Powers in order to resolve her internal conflict. Unfortunately for the Bolsheviks, Lenins assumptions were incorrect and despite his and the partys attempts to push for a civil war through involvement in two conferences in 1915 and 1916 in Switzerland the party remained in the minority in calling for the ceasefire by the Russian Army in World War I.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>111</arg></template>	Although the Bolshevik leadership decided to form a separate party, convincing pro-Bolshevik workers within Russia to follow suit proved difficult. When the first meeting of the Fourth Duma was convened in late 1912, only one out of six Bolshevik deputies,<space/><link><target>Matvei Muranov</target></link>, (another one, Roman Malinovsky, was later exposed as an<space/><link><target>Okhrana</target></link><space/>[Tsarist secret police] agent) voted to break away from the<space/><link><target>Menshevik</target></link><space/>faction within the Duma on 15 December 1912.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Robert B<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>McKean<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>St. Petersburg Between the Revolutions: workers and revolutionaries, June 1907 – February 1917<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>New Haven<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Yale University Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1990<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>140–1</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The Bolshevik leadership eventually prevailed and the Bolsheviks formed their own Duma faction in September 1913.</paragraph><paragraph>One final difference between the Bolsheviks and Mensheviks was simply how ferocious and tenacious the party was willing to be in order to achieve its goals. Lenin was open minded to retreating on political ideas if he saw the guarantee of long term gains benefiting the party. This practice was commonly seen trying to recruit peasants and uneducated workers by promising them how glorious life would be after the revolution. His approach was land seizure for the peasants and national self-determination for the minorities as nothing more than temporary concessions.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="p"><space/>108</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1952, at the<space/><link><target>19th Congress of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target><part>19th Party Congress</part></link>, according to<space/><link><target>Stalin</target></link>s suggestion, the Bolshevik party was renamed the Communist Party of Soviet Union.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Derogatory usage of &quot;Bolshevik&quot;</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Nieder mit dem Bolschewismus. Bolschewismus bringt Krieg und Verderben, Hunger und Tod LCCN2004665807.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''&quot;Down with Bolshevism. Bolshevism brings war and destruction, hunger and death&quot;'', anti-Bolshevik propaganda, Germany, 1919.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Bolo&quot; was used as derogatory expression for Bolsheviks used by<space/><link><target>British Empire</target><part>British</part></link><space/>service personnel in the<space/><link><target>North Russian Expeditionary Force</target></link><space/>which intervened against the<space/><link><target>Red Army</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="contribution-url"><space/>http://www.naval-history.net/WW1z05NorthRussia.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Naval History<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>North Russian Expeditionary Force 1919, Scrapbook Diary, Photographs, Mementoes<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>14 June 2012</arg></template>.</extension><space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target></link>, Joseph Goebbels, and other Nazi leaders used it in reference to the worldwide political movement coordinated by the<space/><link><target>Comintern</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Collins Mini Dictionary</italics>, 1998.</extension><space/>During the days of the<space/><link><target>Cold War</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>, labour union leaders and other leftists were sometimes derisively described as &quot;Bolshies&quot;. The usage is roughly equivalent to the term &quot;<link><target>Commie</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>Communist</target><part>Red</part></link>&quot;, or &quot;<link><target>pinko</target></link>&quot; in the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>during the same period. The term &quot;Bolshie&quot; later became a slang term for anyone who was rebellious, aggressive, or truculent.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.thefreedictionary.com/bolshie<space/></arg><arg name="title">bolshie<space/></arg><arg name="work">The free dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2014-03-08</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Democratic centralism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Left-wing uprisings against the Bolsheviks</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Leninism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>October Revolution</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Old Bolshevik</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Soviet Revolutionary Communists (Bolsheviks)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Related terms</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>MarxismLeninism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Trotskyism</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Non-Russian/Soviet groups having used the name &quot;Bolshevik&quot;</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bangladesh</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Maoist Bolshevik Reorganisation Movement of the Purba Banglar Sarbahara Party</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>India</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Party of India</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>India</target></link>/<link><target>Sri Lanka</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Bolshevik-Leninist Party of India, Ceylon and Burma</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>India</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Revolutionary Socialist Party (Bolshevik)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mexico</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Communist Party</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Senegal</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Nuclei</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sri Lanka</target></link>:<space/><link><target>Bolshevik Samasamaja Party</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Notelist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>32em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Pipes<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A concise History of the Russian Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1995</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-679-42277-8</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shub<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Lenin : a biography<space/></arg><arg name="date">1976</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Harmondsworth<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-14020809-2<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>rev.</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Tucker</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Robert</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Lenin Anthology<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1975<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>WW Norton & Co<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-393-09236-3</arg></template>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target></template><template><target>EB1922 Poster</target><arg>Bolshevism</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.marxist.com/bolshevism/<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Marxist<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bolshevism, the Road to Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Alan Woods (political theorist)</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alan<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Woods</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="contribution-url"><space/>http://www.datesofhistory.com/Bolshevik-Party-Russia.general.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dates of History<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Chronology of the Bolshevik Party World History Database</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Brinton<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Maurice<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Libcom<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://libcom.org/library/the-bolsheviks-and-workers-control-solidarity-group<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Bolsheviks and Workers Control<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Maurice Brinton</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg</target><arg name="no">17350<space/></arg><arg name="name">The Practice and Theory of Bolshevism</arg></template><space/>by<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link>, November 1920</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Bobrovskaya<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Cecilia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Marxists<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.marxists.org/history/archive/bobrovskaya/twenty-years/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Twenty Years in Underground Russia: Memoirs of a Rank-and-File Bolshevik<space/></arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Cecilia Bobrovskaya</arg></template>.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Russian Revolution 1917</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template><link><target>Category:Bolsheviks</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Communist parties in Russia</target></link><link><target>Category:Factions in the Communist Party of the Soviet Union</target></link><link><target>Category:Political parties established in 1903</target></link><link><target>Category:Political parties of the Russian Revolution</target></link><link><target>Category:Political party factions in Russia</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>cs:Komunistick strana Sovtskho svazu#Vznik strany bolevik</target></link></paragraph></article>