<article title='Bioterrorism'><paragraph><link><target>File:NBC-Mask M-17.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>United States</target></link><space/><link><target>Airman</target></link><space/>wearing an<space/><link><target>M17 gas mask</target><part>M-17</part></link><space/>nuclear, biological, and chemical warfare mask and hood</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>terrorism</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Bioterrorism</bold><space/>is<space/><link><target>terrorism</target></link><space/>involving the intentional release or dissemination of<space/><link><target>biological agent</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These agents are<space/><link><target>bacteria</target></link>,<space/><link><target>virus</target><trail>es</trail></link>, or<space/><link><target>toxin</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and may be in a naturally occurring or a human-modified form. For the use of this method in<space/><link><target>war</target><trail>fare</trail></link>, see<space/><link><target>biological warfare</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Definition</heading><paragraph><template><target>Globalize/US</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template>According to the U.S.<space/><link><target>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</target></link><space/>a<space/><italics>bioterrorism</italics><space/>attack is the deliberate release of viruses, bacteria, toxins or other harmful agents used to cause illness or death in people, animals, or plants. These agents are typically found in nature, but it is possible that they could be mutated or altered to increase their ability to cause disease, make them resistant to current medicines, or to increase their ability to be spread into the environment. Biological agents can be spread through the air, water, or in food. Terrorists tend to use biological agents because they are extremely difficult to detect and do not cause illness for several hours to several days. Some bioterrorism agents, like the smallpox virus, can be spread from person to person and some, like anthrax, cannot.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CDCBioterrorismOverview"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Bioterrorism Overview</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bt.cdc.gov/bioterrorism/overview.asp</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">2008-02-12</arg><arg name="publisher">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Bioterrorism is an attractive weapon because biological agents are relatively easy and inexpensive to obtain, can be easily disseminated, and can cause widespread fear and panic beyond the actual physical damage.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.medmicro.wisc.edu/undergraduate/courses/554/ppt/BT-PHproblem081030.ppt#332,5,Advantages'>of Biologics as Weapons Bioterrorism: A Threat to National Security or Public Health Defining Issue? MM&amp;I 554 University of WisconsinMadison and Wisconsin State Laboratory of Hygiene, September 30, 2008</link></extension><space/>Military leaders, however, have learned that, as a military asset, bioterrorism has some important limitations; it is difficult to employ a bioweapon in a way that only the enemy is affected and not friendly forces. A biological weapon is useful to<space/><link><target>terrorists</target></link><space/>mainly as a method of creating mass panic and disruption to a state or a country. However, technologists such as<space/><link><target>Bill Joy</target></link><space/>have warned of the potential power which genetic engineering might place in the hands of future bio-terrorists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Joy</arg><arg name="first">Bill</arg><arg name="title">[[Why the Future Doesn't Need Us]]: How 21st Century Technologies Threaten to Make Humans an Endangered Species</arg><arg name="date">2007-03-31</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-553-52835-0</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The use of agents that do not cause harm to humans but disrupt the<space/><link><target>economy</target></link><space/>have been discussed.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2007</arg></template><space/>A highly relevant pathogen in this context is the<space/><link><target>foot-and-mouth disease</target></link><space/>(FMD) virus, which is capable of causing widespread economic damage and public concern (as witnessed in the<space/><link><target>2001 United Kingdom foot-and-mouth outbreak</target><part>2001</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>2007 United Kingdom foot-and-mouth outbreak</target><part>2007</part></link><space/>FMD outbreaks in the UK), whilst having almost no capacity to infect humans.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>20th century</heading><paragraph>By the time<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>began, attempts to use<space/><link><target>anthrax</target></link><space/>were directed at animal populations. This generally proved to be ineffective. Shortly after the start of World War I, Germany launched a biological sabotage campaign in the United States, Russia, Romania, and France.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GregoryBWaggDMilitaryMedicine"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Gregory</arg><arg name="first">B</arg><arg name="coauthors">Waag, D.</arg><arg name="title">Military Medicine: Medical aspects of biological warfare</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bordeninstitute.army.mil/published_volumes/biological_warfare/BW-ch06.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Office of the Surgeon General, Department of the Army</arg><arg name="id">Library of Congress 97-22242</arg></template></extension><space/>At that time,<space/><link><target>Anton Dilger</target></link><space/>lived in Germany, but in 1915 he was sent to the United States carrying cultures of<space/><link><target>glanders</target></link>, a virulent disease of horses and mules. Dilger set up a laboratory in his home in<space/><link><target>Chevy Chase, Maryland</target></link>. He used<space/><link><target>stevedore</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>working the docks in Baltimore to infect horses with<space/><link><target>glanders</target></link><space/>while they were waiting to be shipped to Britain. Dilger was under suspicion as being a German agent, but was never arrested. Dilger eventually fled to Madrid, Spain, where he died during the Influenza Pandemic of 1918.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Experts Q & A</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/weapon/sfeature/qa.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">2006-12-15</arg><arg name="publisher">Public Broadcasting Service</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1916, the Russians arrested a German agent with similar intentions. Germany and its allies infected French cavalry horses and many of Russias mules and horses on the Eastern Front. These actions hindered artillery and troop movements, as well as supply convoys.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GregoryBWaggDMilitaryMedicine"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1972 police in<space/><link><target>Chicago</target></link><space/>arrested two college students, Allen Schwander and Stephen Pera, who had planned to poison the city's water supply with<space/><link><target>typhoid</target></link><space/>and other bacteria. Schwander had founded a terrorist group, &quot;R.I.S.E.&quot;, while Pera collected and grew cultures from the hospital where he worked. The two men fled to<space/><link><target>Cuba</target></link><space/>after being released on bail. Schwander died of natural causes in 1974, while Pera returned to the U.S. in 1975 and was put on probation.<extension extension_name='ref'>W. Seth Carus, &quot;R.I.S.E.&quot;, in<space/><italics>Toxic Terror: Assessing Terrorist Use of Chemical and Biological Weapons</italics><space/>(MIT Press, 2000), p55, p69</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>1984 Rajneeshee bioterror attack</target></link>: In<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link><space/>in 1984, followers of the<space/><link><target>Rajneesh</target><part>Bhagwan Shree Rajneesh</part></link><space/>attempted to control a local<space/><link><target>election</target></link><space/>by incapacitating the local population. This was done by infecting<space/><link><target>salad</target></link><space/>bars in 11 restaurants, produce in grocery stores, doorknobs, and other public domains with<space/><italics><link><target>Salmonella typhimurium</target></link></italics><space/>bacteria in the city of<space/><link><target>The Dalles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Oregon</target></link>. The attack infected 751 people with severe<space/><link><target>food poisoning</target></link>. There were no fatalities. This incident was the first known bioterrorist attack in the United States in the 20th century.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.medmicro.wisc.edu/undergraduate/courses/554/ppt/BT-PHproblem081030.ppt#363,15'>, Past U.S. Incidents of Food Bioterrorism Bioterrorism: A Threat to National Security or Public Health Defining Issue, University of WisconsinMadison and the Wisconsin State Laboratory of Hygiene, MM&amp;I 554, September 30, 2008</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Aum Shinrikyo</target></link><space/>anthrax release in Kameido : In June 1993 the religious group<space/><link><target>Aum Shinrikyo</target></link><space/>released anthrax in Tokyo. Eyewitnesses reported a foul odor. The attack was a total failure, infecting not a single person. The reason for this, ironically, is that the group used the vaccine strain of the bacterium. The spores recovered from the attack showed that they were identical to an anthrax vaccine strain given to animals at the time. These vaccine strains are missing the genes that cause a symptomatic response.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cdc.gov"><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.com/ncidod/EID/vol10no1/03-0238.htm'>, CDC-'''Bacillus anthracis''' Incident, Kameido, Tokyo, 1993</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>21st century</heading><paragraph><link><target>2001 anthrax attacks</target><part>2001 - USA and Chile - Anthrax Attacks</part></link>: In September and October 2001, several cases of anthrax broke out in the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>in the 2001 anthrax attacks, apparently caused deliberately. Letters laced with infectious anthrax were concurrently delivered to news media offices and the U.S Congress, alongside an<space/><link><target>2001 anthrax attacks#Anthrax letter to Chile</target><part>ambiguously related case</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Chile</target></link>. The letters killed 5.<xhtml:sup><link type='external' href='http://www.cnn.com/2008/CRIME/08/06/anthrax.case/index.html'>CNN</link></xhtml:sup></paragraph><heading level='2'>Types of agents</heading><paragraph><template><target>Globalize/US</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template>Under current<space/><link><target>United States law</target></link>,<space/><link><target>bio-agents</target></link><space/>which have been declared by the<space/><link><target>U.S. Department of Health and Human Services</target></link><space/>or the<space/><link><target>U.S. Department of Agriculture</target></link><space/>to have the &quot;potential to pose a severe threat to public health and safety&quot; are officially defined as &quot;<link><target>select agents</target></link>&quot;. The CDC categorizes these agents (A, B or C) and administers the<space/><link><target>Select Agent Program</target></link>, which regulates the laboratories which may possess, use, or transfer select agents within the United States. As with US attempts to categorize harmful recreational drugs, designer viruses are not yet categorized and avian H5N1 has been shown to achieve high mortality and human-communication in a laboratory setting.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Category A</heading><paragraph>These high-priority agents pose a risk to national security, can be easily transmitted and disseminated, result in high mortality, have potential major public health impact, may cause public panic, or require special action for public health preparedness.</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey><link><target>Tularemia</target></link><space/>or &quot;rabbit fever&quot;</defkey><defval><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/tularemia/'>CDC Tularemia</link></extension><space/>has a very low fatality rate if treated, but can severely incapacitate. The disease is caused by the<space/><italics><link><target>Francisella tularensis</target></link></italics><space/>bacterium, and can be contracted through contact with the<space/><link><target>fur</target></link>, inhalation, ingestion of contaminated water or insect bites.<space/><italics>Francisella tularensis</italics><space/>is very infectious. A small number (1050 or so organisms) can cause disease. If<space/><italics>F. tularensis</italics><space/>were used as a weapon, the bacteria would likely be made airborne for exposure by inhalation. People who inhale an infectious aerosol would generally experience severe respiratory illness, including life-threatening pneumonia and systemic infection, if they are not treated. The bacteria that cause tularemia occur widely in nature and could be isolated and grown in quantity in a laboratory, although manufacturing an effective aerosol weapon would require considerable sophistication.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.bt.cdc.gov/agent/tularemia/facts.asp</extension></defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Anthrax disease</target><part>Anthrax</part></link></defkey><defval><space/>Anthrax is a non-contagious disease caused by the spore-forming bacterium<space/><italics>Bacillus anthracis</italics>. An<space/><link><target>anthrax vaccines</target><part>anthrax vaccine</part></link><space/>does exist but requires many injections for stable use. When discovered early, anthrax can be cured by administering<space/><link><target>antibiotic</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>ciprofloxacin</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/doi/abs/10.1086/596063?url_ver=Z39.88-2003&amp;amp;rfr_id=ori:rid:crossref.org&amp;amp;rfr_dat=cr_pub%3dncbi.nlm.nih.gov'>Vietri N. J. et al., A Short Course of Antibiotic Treatment Is Effective in Preventing Death from Experimental Inhalational Anthrax after Discontinuing Antibiotics, The Journal of Infectious Diseases 2009</link></extension><space/>Its first modern incidence in biological warfare were when Scandinavian &quot;freedom fighters&quot; supplied by the German General Staff used anthrax with unknown results against the Imperial Russian Army in Finland in 1916.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bisher, Jamie, &quot;During World War I, Terrorists Schemed to Use Anthrax in the Cause of Finnish Independence,&quot; Military History, August 2003, pp. 1722.<link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20091027151654/http://geocities.com/jamie_bisher/anthrax.htm'>Anthrax Sabotage in Finland</link></extension><space/>In 1993, the<space/><link><target>Aum Shinrikyo</target></link><space/>used anthrax in an unsuccessful attempt in Tokyo with zero fatalities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cdc.gov"></extension><space/>Anthrax was used in a<space/><link><target>2001 anthrax attack</target><part>series of attacks</part></link><space/>on the offices of several United States Senators in late 2001. The anthrax was in a powder form and it was delivered by the mail.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/eid/vol8no10/02-0330.htm'>Puneet K. Dewan, Alicia M. Fry, Kayla Laserson, et al. Inhalational Anthrax Outbreak among Postal Workers, Washington, D.C., 2001 Emerging Infectious Diseases, Vol 8, No 10, October 2002</link></extension><space/>Anthrax is one of the few biological agents that federal employees have been vaccinated for. The strain used in the 2001 anthrax attack was identical to the strain used by the<space/><link><target>USAMRIID</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MacKenzie"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Debora MacKenzie<space/></arg><arg name="title">Anthrax attack bug 'identical' to army strain<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New Scientist<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">16 February 2013<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn2265
<space/></arg></template></extension></defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Smallpox</target></link></defkey><defval><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/smallpox/'>CDC Smallpox</link></extension><space/>Smallpox is a highly contagious<space/><link><target>virus</target></link>. It is transmitted easily through the atmosphere and has a high<space/><link><target>mortality rate</target></link><space/>(2040%). Smallpox was<space/><link><target>smallpox#Eradication</target><part>eradicated</part></link><space/>in the world in the 1970s, thanks to a worldwide vaccination program.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/smallpox/prep/cdc-prep.asp'>What CDC Is Doing to Protect the Public From Smallpox</link></extension><space/>However, some virus samples are still available in<space/><link><target>Russia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>America</part><trail>n</trail></link><space/>laboratories. Some believe that after the collapse of the Soviet Union, cultures of smallpox have become available in other countries. Although people born pre-1970 will have been vaccinated for smallpox under the WHO program, the effectiveness of vaccination is limited since the vaccine provides high level of immunity for only 3 to 5 years. Revaccination's protection lasts longer.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.smallpox.mil/messageMap/messageMapAll.asp?cID=57'>Military Vaccination Program website</link></extension><space/>As a biological weapon smallpox is dangerous because of the highly contagious nature of both the infected and their pox. Also, the infrequency with which vaccines are administered among the general population since the eradication of the disease would leave most people unprotected in the event of an outbreak. Smallpox occurs only in humans, and has no external hosts or vectors.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Botulinum toxin</target></link></defkey><defval><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/botulism/'>CDC Botulism</link></extension><space/>The neurotoxin<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2856357/'></link></extension><space/>Botulinum is one of the deadliest toxins known, and is produced by the bacterium<space/><italics><link><target>Clostridium botulinum</target></link></italics>. Botulism causes death by<space/><link><target>respiratory failure</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>paralysis</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/botulism/factsheet.asp'>CDC Botulism Factsheet</link></extension><space/>Furthermore, the toxin is readily available worldwide due to its cosmetic applications in injections.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Bubonic plague</target></link></defkey><defval><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/plague/'>CDC Plague</link></extension><space/>Plague is a disease caused by the<space/><italics><link><target>Yersinia pestis</target></link></italics><space/>bacterium. Rodents are the normal host of plague, and the disease is transmitted to humans by<space/><link><target>flea</target></link><space/>bites and occasionally by<space/><link><target>Bioaerosol</target><part>aerosol</part></link><space/>in the form of<space/><link><target>pneumonic plague</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/ncidod/dvbid/plague/index.htm'>CDC Plague Home Page</link></extension><space/>The disease has a history of use in biological warfare dating back many centuries, and is considered a threat due to its ease of culture and ability to remain in circulation among local rodents for a long period of time. The weaponized threat comes mainly in the form of pneumonic plague (infection by inhalation)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bt.cdc.gov/agent/plague/faq.asp'>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQ) About Plague</link></extension><space/>It was the disease that caused the<space/><link><target>Black Death</target></link><space/>in Medieval Europe.</defval></listitem><listitem><defkey><link><target>Viral hemorrhagic fever</target><trail>s</trail></link></defkey><defval><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/vhf/'>CDC VuralHemirrhagic Fevers</link></extension><space/>This includes hemorrhagic fevers caused by members of the family<space/><italics><link><target>Filoviridae</target></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>Marburg virus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ebola virus</target></link>), and by the family<space/><italics><link><target>Arenaviridae</target></link></italics><space/>(for example<space/><link><target>Lassa virus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Machupo virus</target></link>).<space/><link><target>Ebola virus disease</target></link><space/>,in particular, has caused high<space/><link><target>fatality rate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>ranging from 2590% with a 50% average. No cure currently exists, although vaccines are in development. The Soviet Union investigated the use of filoviruses for biological warfare, and the<space/><link><target>Aum Shinrikyo</target></link><space/>group unsuccessfully attempted to obtain cultures of Ebola virus.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template><space/>Death from Ebola virus disease is commonly due to<space/><link><target>multiple organ failure</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>hypovolemic shock</target></link>. Marburg virus was first discovered in<space/><link><target>Marburg</target></link>, Germany. No treatments currently exist aside from supportive care. The arenaviruses have a somewhat reduced case-fatality rate compared to disease caused by filoviruses, but are more widely distributed, chiefly in central<space/><link><target>Africa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>South America</target></link>.</defval></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Category B</heading><paragraph>Category B agents are moderately easy to disseminate and have low mortality rates.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Brucellosis</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Brucella</target><part>''Brucella'' species</part></link>)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/brucellosis/'>CDC Brucellosis</link></extension></listitem><listitem>Epsilon toxin of<space/><italics><link><target>Clostridium perfringens</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem>Food safety threats (for example,<space/><italics><link><target>Salmonella</target></link><space/>species</italics>,<space/><link><target>Escherichia coli O157:H7</target><part>''E coli'' O157:H7</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Shigella</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Staphylococcus aureus</target></link>'')</listitem><listitem><link><target>Glanders</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/nczved/dfbmd/disease_listing/glanders_gi.html'>CDC Glanders</link></extension><space/>(<italics><link><target>Burkholderia mallei</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Melioidosis</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Burkholderia pseudomallei</target></link></italics>)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/nczved/dfbmd/disease_listing/melioidosis_gi.html'>CDC Melioidosis</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/nczved/dfbmd/disease_listing/melioidosis_gi.html#2'>CDC Why has melioidosis become a current issue?</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Psittacosis</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Chlamydia psittaci</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Q fever</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Coxiella burnetii</target></link></italics>)<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/qfever/'>CDC Q Fever</link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ricin</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emergency.cdc.gov/agent/ricin/'>CDC Ricin</link></extension><space/>toxin from<space/><italics><link><target>Castor oil plant</target><part>Ricinus communis</part></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>castor bean</target><trail>s</trail></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Abrin</target></link><space/>toxin from<space/><italics><link><target>Rosary pea</target><part>Abrus precatorius</part></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>Rosary pea</target><trail>s</trail></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Staphylococcus</target><part>Staphylococcal</part></link><space/>enterotoxin B</listitem><listitem><link><target>Typhus</target></link><space/>(<italics><link><target>Rickettsia prowazekii</target></link></italics>)</listitem><listitem>Viral<space/><link><target>encephalitis</target></link><space/>(<link><target>alphavirus</target><trail>es</trail></link>, for example,:<space/><link><target>Venezuelan equine encephalitis virus</target><part>Venezuelan equine encephalitis</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Eastern equine encephalitis virus</target><part>eastern equine encephalitis</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Western equine encephalitis virus</target><part>western equine encephalitis</part></link>)</listitem><listitem>Water supply threats (for example,<space/><italics><link><target>Vibrio cholerae</target></link></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.webmd.com/a-to-z-guides/cholera-11156'>WebMD.com Cholera</link></extension><space/><italics><link><target>Cryptosporidium parvum</target></link></italics>)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Category C</heading><paragraph>Category C agents are emerging<space/><link><target>pathogen</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that might be<space/><link><target>genetic engineering</target><part>engineered</part></link><space/>for mass dissemination because of their availability, ease of production and dissemination, high mortality rate, or ability to cause a major health impact.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nipah virus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hantavirus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Severe acute respiratory syndrome</target><part>SARS</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>H1N1</target></link><space/>a strain of<space/><link><target>influenza</target></link><space/>(flu)</listitem><listitem><link><target>HIV</target></link>/<link><target>AIDS</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Planning and response</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Biodefense</arg></template><space/><template><target>Globalize/US</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template><space/>Planning may involve the development of biological identification systems. Until recently in the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>, most biological defense strategies have been geared to protecting soldiers on the battlefield rather than ordinary people in cities. Financial cutbacks have limited the tracking of disease outbreaks. Some outbreaks, such as food poisoning due to<space/><italics><link><target>Escherichia coli</target><part>E. coli</part></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>Salmonella</target></link></italics>, could be of either natural or deliberate origin.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Preparedness</heading><paragraph>Biological agents are relatively easy to obtain by terrorists and are becoming more threatening in the U.S., and laboratories are working on advanced detection systems to provide early warning, identify<space/><link><target>contamination</target><part>contaminated areas</part></link><space/>and populations at risk, and to facilitate prompt treatment. Methods for predicting the use of biological agents in urban areas as well as assessing the area for the hazards associated with a biological attack are being established in major cities. In addition,<space/><link><target>forensic</target></link><space/>technologies are working on identifying biological agents, their geographical origins and/or their initial source. Efforts include decontamination technologies to restore facilities without causing additional environmental concerns.</paragraph><paragraph>Early detection and rapid response to bioterrorism depend on close cooperation between<space/><link><target>public health</target></link><space/>authorities and law enforcement; however, such cooperation is currently lacking. National detection assets and vaccine stockpiles are not useful if local and state officials do not have access to them.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Bernett</arg><arg name="first">Brian C.</arg><arg name="title">US Biodefense and Homeland Security: Toward Detection and Attribution</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccc.nps.navy.mil/research/theses/bernett06.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-24</arg><arg name="date">December 2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Naval Postgraduate School</arg><arg name="location">Monterey, California, United States</arg><arg name="page">21</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Aspects of protection against bioterrorism in the United States include,</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Detection and resilience strategies in combating bioterrorism.</bold><space/>This occurs primarily through the efforts of the<space/><link><target>DHS Office of Health Affairs</target><part>Office of Health Affairs</part></link><space/>(OHA), a part of the<space/><link><target>Department of Homeland Security</target></link><space/>(DHS), whose role is to prepare for an emergency situation that impacts the health of the American populace. Detection has two primary technological factors. First there is OHA's BioWatch program in which collection devices are disseminated to thirty high risk areas throughout the country to detect the presence of aerosolized biological agents before symptoms present in patients.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepX">United States. Cong. House. Committee on Homeland Security. Ensuring Effective Preparedness Responses and Recovery for Events Impacting Health Security Hearing before the Subcommittee on Emergency Preparedness, Response and Communications of the Committee on Homeland Security, House of Representatives, One Hundred Twelfth Congress, First Session, March 17, 2011. 112th Cong., 1st sess. HR 397. Washington: U.S. G.P.O., 2012. Print.</extension><space/>This is significant primarily because it allows a more proactive response to a disease outbreak rather than the more passive treatment of the past.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Implementation of the Generation-3 automated detection system.</bold><space/>This advancement is significant simply because it enables action to be taken in four to six hours due to its automatic response system, whereas the previous system required aerosol detectors to be manually transported to laboratories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepX"></extension><space/>Resilience is a multifaceted issue as well, as addressed by OHA. One way in which this is ensured is through exercises that establish preparedness; programs like the Anthrax Response Exercise Series exist to ensure that, regardless of the incident, all emergency personnel will be aware of the role they must fill.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepX"></extension><space/>Moreover, by providing information and education to public leaders, emergency medical services and all employees of the DHS, OHS suggests it can significantly decrease the impact of bioterrorism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepX"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Enhancing the technological capabilities of first responders.</bold><space/>This is accomplished through numerous strategies. The first of these strategies was developed by the Science and Technology Directorate (S&amp;T) of DHS to ensure that the danger of suspicious powders could be effectively assessed, (as many dangerous biological agents such as anthrax exist as a white powder). By testing the accuracy and specificity of commercially available systems used by first responders, the hope is that all biologically harmful powders can be rendered ineffective.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepY">United States. Cong. House. Committee on Homeland Security. First Responder Technologies: Ensuring a Prioritized Approach for Homeland Security Research and Development : Joint Hearing before the Subcommittee on Emergency Preparedness, Response and Communications and the Subcommittee on Cybersecurity, Infrastructure Protection, and Security Technologies of the Committee on Homeland Security, House of Representatives, One Hundred Twelfth Congress, Second Session, May 9, 2012. 112th Cong., 2nd sess. HR 397. N.p.: n.p., n.d. Print.</extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Enhanced equipment for first responders.</bold><space/>One recent advancement is the commercialization of a new form of Tyvex armor which protects first responders and patients from chemical and biological contaminants. There has also been a new generation of Self-Contained Breathing Apparatuses (SCBA) which has been recently made more robust against bioterrorism agents. All of these technologies combine to form what seems like a relatively strong deterrent to bioterrorism. However, New York City as an entity has numerous organizations and strategies that effectively serve to deter and respond to bioterrorism as it comes. From here the logical progression is into the realm of New York Citys specific strategies to prevent bioterrorism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepY"></extension></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Project BioShield</bold><space/>The accrual of vaccines and treatments for potential biological threats, also known as medical countermeasures has been an important aspect in preparing for a potential bioterrorist attack; this took the form of a program beginning in 2004, referred to as<space/><link><target>Project Bioshield Act</target><part>Project BioShield</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hylton">Hylton, Wil S. &quot;How Ready Are We for Bioterrorism?&quot; The New York Times. The New York Times Company, 26 Oct. 2011. Web.</extension><space/>The significance of this program should not be overlooked as there is currently enough smallpox vaccine to inoculate every United States citizen and a variety of therapeutic drugs to treat the infected.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hylton"></extension><space/>The Department of Defense also has a variety of laboratories currently working to increase the quantity and efficacy of countermeasures that comprise the national stockpile.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepXYZ"></extension><space/>Efforts have also been taken to ensure that these medical countermeasures are able to be disseminated effectively in the event of a bioterrorist attack. The National Association of Chain Drug Stores championed this cause by encouraging the participation of the private sector in improving distribution of such countermeasures if required.<extension extension_name='ref' name="PrepXYZ">United States. Cong. House. Committee on Homeland Security. Taking Measure of Countermeasures. Hearing before the Subcommittee on Emergency Preparedness, Response and Communications of the Committee on Homeland Security, House of Representatives, One Hundred Twelfth Congress, First Session, April 13, 2011 and May 12, 2011. 112 Cong., 1st sess. HR 397. Washington: U.S. G.P.O., 2012. Print.</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>On a CNN news broadcast in 2011, the CNN chief medical correspondent, Dr. Sanjay Gupta, weighed in on the American governments recent approach to bioterrorist threats. He explains how, even though the United States would be better fending off bioterrorist attacks now than they would be a decade ago, the amount of money available to fight bioterrorism over the last three years has begun to decrease. Looking at a detailed report that examined the funding decrease for bioterrorism in fifty-one American cities, Dr. Gupta stated that the cities wouldnt be able to distribute vaccines as well and wouldnt be able to track viruses. He went on to say that movie portrayals of global pandemics, such as Contagion, were actually quite possible and may occur in the United States under the right conditions.<extension extension_name='ref'>John King, USA. CNNW. San Francisco. 20 Dec. 2011. Television.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A news broadcast by MSNBC in 2010 also stressed the low levels of bioterrorism preparedness in the United States. The broadcast stated that a bipartisan report gave the Obama administration a failing grade for its efforts to respond to a bioterrorist attack. The news broadcast invited the former New York City police commissioner, Howard Safir, to explain how the government would fare in combating such an attack. He said how biological and chemical weapons are probable and relatively easy to disperse. Furthermore, Safir thought that efficiency in bioterrorism preparedness is not necessarily a question of money, but is instead dependent on putting resources in the right places. The broadcast suggested that the nation was not ready for something more serious.<extension extension_name='ref'>MSNBC News Live. MSNBC. New York City. 26 Jan. 2010. Television</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Biosurveillance</heading><paragraph>In 1999, the<space/><link><target>University of Pittsburgh</target></link>'s Center for<space/><link><target>Biomedical</target></link><space/>Informatics deployed the first automated bioterrorism detection system, called<space/><link><target>Real-Time Outbreak Disease Surveillance</target><part>RODS (Real-Time Outbreak Disease Surveillance)</part></link>. RODS is designed to draw collect data from many data sources and use them to perform signal detection, that is, to detect a possible bioterrorism event at the earliest possible moment. RODS, and other systems like it, collect data from sources including clinic data, laboratory data, and data from over-the-counter drug sales.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WangerMRoleOfClinicalInformationSystems"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Wagner</arg><arg name="first">Michael M.</arg><arg name="coauthors">Espino, Jeremy;''et al.''</arg><arg name="title">Healthcare Information Management Systems</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="edition">3</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer-Verlag</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="pages">513–539</arg><arg name="chapter">The role of clinical information systems in public health surveillance</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="WangerMAvailabilityAndComparativeValueOfData"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Wagner</arg><arg name="first">Michael M.</arg><arg name="coauthors">Aryel, Ron;''et al.''</arg><arg name="title">Availability and Comparative Value of Data Elements Required for an Effective Bioterrorism Detection System</arg><arg name="url">http://rods.health.pitt.edu/LIBRARY/dato2AHRQInterimRpt112801.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">2001-11-28</arg><arg name="publisher">Real-time Outbreak and Disease Surveillance Laboratory</arg><arg name="page"></arg><arg name="pages"></arg></template></extension><space/>In 2000, Michael Wagner, the codirector of the RODS laboratory, and<space/><link><target>Ron Aryel</target></link>, a subcontractor, conceived the idea of obtaining live data feeds from &quot;non-traditional&quot; (non-health-care) data sources. The RODS laboratory's first efforts eventually led to the establishment of the National Retail Data Monitor, a system which collects data from 20,000 retail locations nationwide.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WangerMRoleOfClinicalInformationSystems"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>On February 5, 2002,<space/><link><target>George W. Bush</target></link><space/>visited the RODS laboratory and used it as a model for a<space/><link><target>USD</target><part>$</part></link>300 million spending proposal to equip all 50 states with biosurveillance systems. In a speech delivered at the nearby<space/><link><target>Masonic temple</target></link>, Bush compared the RODS system to a modern &quot;<link><target>DEW</target></link>&quot; line (referring to the Cold War ballistic missile early warning system).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Togyer</arg><arg name="first">Jason</arg><arg name="title">Pitt Magazine: Airborne Defense</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pittmag.pitt.edu/june2002/feature1.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">June 2002</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Pittsburgh</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The principles and practices of biosurveillance, a new interdisciplinary science, were defined and described in the<space/><italics>Handbook of Biosurveillance</italics>, edited by Michael Wagner, Andrew Moore and Ron Aryel, and published in 2006. Biosurveillance is the science of real-time disease outbreak detection. Its principles apply to both natural and man-made epidemics (bioterrorism).</paragraph><paragraph>Data which potentially could assist in early detection of a bioterrorism event include many categories of information. Health-related data such as that from hospital computer systems, clinical laboratories, electronic<space/><link><target>health record systems</target></link>, medical examiner record-keeping systems, 911 call center computers, and veterinary medical record systems could be of help; researchers are also considering the utility of data generated by<space/><link><target>ranching</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>feedlot</target></link><space/>operations, food processors,<space/><link><target>drinking water</target></link><space/>systems, school attendance recording, and physiologic monitors, among others.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WangerMAvailabilityAndComparativeValueOfData"></extension><space/>Intuitively, one would expect systems which collect more than one type of data to be more useful than systems which collect only one type of information (such as single-purpose laboratory or 911 call-center based systems), and be less prone to<space/><link><target>false alarms</target></link>, and this appears to be the case.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link>, disease surveillance is beginning to be organized on the continent-wide scale needed to track a biological emergency. The system not only monitors infected persons, but attempts to discern the origin of the outbreak.</paragraph><paragraph>Researchers are experimenting with devices to detect the existence of a threat:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Tiny<space/><link><target>integrated circuit</target><part>electronic chips</part></link><space/>that would contain living<space/><link><target>neuron</target><part>nerve cells</part></link><space/>to warn of the presence of bacterial toxins (identification of broad range toxins)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Fiber-optic</target></link><space/>tubes lined with<space/><link><target>antibody</target><part>antibodies</part></link><space/>coupled to light-emitting molecules (identification of specific pathogens, such as anthrax, botulinum, ricin)</listitem></list><paragraph>New research shows that ultraviolet<space/><link><target>avalanche photodiodes</target></link><space/>offer the high gain, reliability and robustness needed to detect anthrax and other bioterrorism agents in the air. The fabrication methods and device characteristics were described at the 50th Electronic Materials Conference in Santa Barbara on June 25, 2008. Details of the photodiodes were also published in the February 14, 2008 issue of the journal Electronics Letters and the November 2007 issue of the journal IEEE Photonics Technology Letters.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://newswise.com/articles/view/541788/'>Avalanche Photodiodes Target Bioterrorism Agents</link><space/>Newswise, Retrieved on June 25, 2008.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The United States Department of Defense conducts global biosurveillance through several programs, including the Global Emerging Infections Surveillance and Response System.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pellerin, Cheryl.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.defense.gov/news/newsarticle.aspx?id=65852'>&quot;Global Nature of Terrorism Drives Biosurveillance.&quot;</link><space/><italics>American Forces Press Service</italics>, 27 October 2011.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another powerful tool developed within New York City for use in countering bioterrorism is the development of the New York City<space/><link><target>Syndromic Surveillance</target></link><space/>System. This system is essentially a way of tracking disease progression throughout New York City, and was developed by the<space/><link><target>New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene</target></link><space/>(NYC DOHMH) in the wake of the 9/11 attacks. The system works by tracking the symptoms of those taken into the emergency departmentbased on the location of the hospital to which they are taken and their home addressand assessing any patterns in symptoms. These established trends can then be observed by medical epidemiologists to determine if there are any disease outbreaks in any particular locales; maps of disease prevalence can then be created rather easily.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chen, H, D Zeng, and Y Pan. &quot;Infectious Disease Informatics: Syndromic Surveillance for Public Health and Bio-Defense.&quot; 20120, XXII, 209p. 68 illus.., Hardcover.</extension><space/>This is an obviously beneficial tool in fighting bioterrorism as it provides a means through which such attacks could be discovered in their nascence; assuming bioterrorist attacks result in similar symptoms across the board, this strategy allows New York City to respond immediately to any bioterrorist threats that they may face with some level of alacrity.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Response to bioterrorism incident or threat</heading><paragraph><template><target>Globalize/US</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template>Government agencies which would be called on to respond to a bioterrorism incident would include law enforcement, hazardous materials/decontamination units and emergency medical units, if they exist.</paragraph><paragraph>The US military has specialized units, which can respond to a bioterrorism event; among them are the<space/><link><target>United States Marine Corps</target></link>'<space/><link><target>Chemical Biological Incident Response Force</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United States Army</target><part>U.S. Army</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>20th Support Command (CBRNE)</target></link>, which can detect, identify, and neutralize threats, and<space/><link><target>decontamination</target><part>decontaminate</part></link><space/>victims exposed to bioterror agents. US response would include the<space/><link><target>Center for Disease Control</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Historically, governments and authorities have relied on quarantines to protect their populations. International bodies such as the<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target></link><space/>already devote some of their resources to monitoring epidemics and have served clearing-house roles in historical epidemics.</paragraph><paragraph>Media attention toward the seriousness of biological attacks increased in 2013-2014. In July 2013,<space/><italics>Forbes</italics><space/>published an article with the title &quot;Bioterrorism: A Dirty Little Threat With Huge Potential Consequences.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Bell, Larry.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.forbes.com/sites/larrybell/2013/07/21/bioterrorism-a-dirty-little-threat-with-huge-potential-consequences/'>&quot;Bioterrorism: A Dirty Little Threat With Huge Potential Consequences&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Forbes</italics>. 2013-07-21 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension><space/>In November 2013, Fox News reported on a new strain of botulism, saying that the Centers for Disease and Control lists botulism as one of two agents that have the highest risks of mortality and morbidity, noting that there is no antidote for botulism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Heitz, David.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.foxnews.com/health/2013/11/02/deadly-bioterror-threats-6-real-risks/'>&quot;Deadly bioterror threats: 6 real risks&quot;</link>. Fox News. 2013-11-02 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension><space/>USA Today reported that the U.S. military in November was trying to develop a vaccine for troops from the bacteria that cause the disease Q fever, an agent the military once used as a biological weapon.<extension extension_name='ref'>Locker, Ray.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.usatoday.com/story/nation/2013/11/15/q-fever-vaccine-search-continues/3527345/'>&quot;Pentagon seeking vaccine for bioterror disease threat&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>USA Today</italics>. 2013-11-18 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension><space/>In February 2014, the former special assistant and senior director for biodefense policy to President George W. Bush called the bioterrorism risk imminent and uncertain<extension extension_name='ref'>Cohen, Bryan.<space/><link type='external' href='http://bioprepwatch.com/biological-threats/kadlec-says-biological-attack-is-uncertain-imminent-reality/335981/'>&quot;Kadlec says biological attack is uncertain, imminent reality&quot;</link>. Bio Prep Watch. 2014-02-17 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension><space/>and Congressman<space/><link><target>Bill Pascrell</target></link><space/>called for increasing federal measures against bioterrorism as a matter of life or death.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cohen, Bryan.<space/><link type='external' href='http://bioprepwatch.com/bioterrorism/pascrell-says-bioterror-threat-a-life-or-death-matter/335939/'>&quot;Pascrell: Bioterror threat a life or death matter&quot;</link>. Bio Prep Watch. 2014-02-12 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension><space/>The<space/><italics>New York Times</italics><space/>wrote a story saying the United States would spend $40 million to help certain low and middle-income countries deal with the threats of bioterrorism and infectious diseases.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tavernise, Sabrina.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/14/health/us-backs-new-global-initiative-against-infectious-diseases.html?hpw&amp;amp;rref=health&amp;amp;_r=0'>&quot;U.S. Backs New Global Initiative Against Infectious Diseases&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>New York Times</italics>. 2014-02-13 (Retrieved 2014-02-17)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Biological warfare in popular culture</arg><arg>Includes works about bioterrorism</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Block</arg><arg name="first">Steven M.</arg><arg name="title">The growing threat of biological weapons</arg><arg name="url">http://www.americanscientist.org/issues/feature/the-growing-threat-of-biological-weapons</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="volume">89:1</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">American Scientist</arg><arg name="doi">10.1511/2001.1.28</arg><arg name="journal">American Scientist</arg><arg name="page">28</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Christopher</arg><arg name="first">G. W.</arg><arg name="title">Adapted from Biological Warfare: A Historical Perspective</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="year">1998</arg><arg name="publisher">Operational Medicine Division</arg><arg name="location">Fort Detrick, Maryland</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last1">Eitzen</arg><arg name="first1">E.</arg><arg name="last2">Takafuji</arg><arg name="first2">E.</arg><arg name="title">Military Medicine: Medical Aspects of Chemical and Biological Warfare</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Office of the Surgeon General, Department of the Army</arg><arg name="chapter">Historical Overview of Biological Warfare</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Iraq's Biological Weapon Program</arg><arg name="url">http://www.iraqwatch.org/profiles/biological.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">August 2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Iraq's Biological Weapon Program</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Milanovich</arg><arg name="first">F.</arg><arg name="title">Reducing the threat of biological weapons</arg><arg name="url">http://www.llnl.gov/str/Milan.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="date">June 1998</arg><arg name="publisher">Science and Technology Review</arg><arg name="pages">4–9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Paquette</arg><arg name="first">Laure</arg><arg name="title">Bioterrorism in Medical and Healthcare Administration</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="edition">1</arg><arg name="date">2006-06-29</arg><arg name="publisher">CRC</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8247-5651-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Rózsa</arg><arg name="first">L.</arg><arg name="title">The motivation for biological aggression is an inherent and common aspect of the human behavioural repertoire</arg><arg name="url">http://www.zoologia.hu/list/motivation.pdf</arg><arg name="format">PDF</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-05-22</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Medical Hypotheses</arg><arg name="pages">72, 217–219</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Wagner</arg><arg name="first">M.</arg><arg name="coauthors">Moore, A.; Aryel, R.</arg><arg name="title">Handbook of Biosurveillance</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="publisher">Academic Press</arg><arg name="location">San Diego, California, United States</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>The Town That Was Poisoned</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://student.cs.ucc.ie/cs1064/jabowen/IPSC/articles/carusBiocrimes.pdf'>Bioterrorism and Biocrimes.The Illicit Use of Biological Agents Since 1900, by W. Seth Carus</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;q=cache:4klaEuJMfO8J:www.adl.org/learn/anthrax/beyond_anthrax.pdf+Stephen+Pera+%22Allen+Schwander+%22&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;pid=bl&amp;amp;srcid=ADGEESj7z1og116Xu462BdEPflh91VyPKxWR5pM56grte13Y7Rb1FsT13GstGge3I_6P7MmFQSW1HvyutwVtf1yTIKUEcN06_WI-0v_aSGzD7W8-y9N0ZjkUNZW1sy3fZfppzSZyt9QV&amp;amp;sig=AHIEtbQQNYSJL_dcDHdQvR_emtek0drKAg'>Beyond Anthrax.Extremism and the Bioterrorism Threat</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eht-forum.org/'>Emerging Health Threats Forum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://health.europa.eu/my_environment/bio_terrorism/index_en.htm'>EU Health Portal</link><space/>Information on EU activities related to bioterrorism</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bt.cdc.gov/bioterrorism/'>United States Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/bioterror/'>NOVA: Bioterror</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/professional/short-programs/courses/combating_bioterrorism.html'>Pandemics and Bioterrorism: From Realistic Threats to Effective Policies</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newslobby.net/2014/10/14/bioterrorism-could-ebola-be-a-possible-new-biological-weapon/'>Bioterrorism: Could Ebola be a Possible New Biological Weapon?</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Bioterrorism</target></template><template><target>U.S. biological defense</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Systems thinking</target></link><link><target>Category:Biological warfare</target></link><link><target>Category:Bioterrorism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Futurology</target></link><link><target>Category:Terrorism by method</target></link></paragraph></article>