<article title='Emma_Goldman'><paragraph><template><target>Use American English</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox philosopher</target><arg name="name"><space/>Emma Goldman
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Emma Goldman seated.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Goldman, [[circa]] 1911
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1869|6|27}}
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Kovno]], [[Russian Empire]]
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1940|5|14|1869|6|7}}
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Toronto]], Ontario, Canada
</arg><arg name="school_tradition"><space/>{{hlist |[[Anarchism]] |[[Anarcha-feminism]] |[[Anarcho-communism]]}}
</arg><arg name="influences"><space/>{{hlist |[[Friedrich Nietzsche]] |[[Johann Most]] |[[Henry David Thoreau]] |[[Ralph Waldo Emerson]] |[[Peter Kropotkin]] |[[Mikhail Bakunin]] |[[Mary Wollstonecraft]]|[[Nikolay Chernyshevsky]] |[[Oscar Wilde]] |[[Max Stirner]]}}
</arg><arg name="influenced"><space/>{{hlist |[[Roger Nash Baldwin]] |[[Ba Jin]] |[[Noe Ito]]<ref>{{cite book|last</arg></template><template><target>Anarchism sidebar</target><arg>People</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Emma Goldman</bold><space/>(<template><target>OldStyleDateNY</target><arg>June 27</arg><arg>June 15</arg></template>, 1869<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>May 14, 1940) was an<space/><link><target>anarchism</target><part>anarchist</part></link><space/>known for her political activism, writing, and speeches. She played a pivotal role in the development of<space/><link><target>anarchist political philosophy</target></link><space/>in North America and Europe in the first half of the 20th century.</paragraph><paragraph>Born in<space/><link><target>Kovno</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target></link><space/>(present-day<space/><link><target>Kaunas, Lithuania</target></link>), Goldman emigrated to the United States in 1885.<extension extension_name='ref' name="UIC">University of Illinois at Chicago<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.uic.edu/depts/lib/specialcoll/services/rjd/findingaids/EGoldmanb.html'>Biography of Emma Goldman</link>. UIC Library Emma Goldman Collection. Retrieved on December 13, 2008.</extension><space/>Attracted to anarchism after the<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link>, Goldman became a writer and a renowned lecturer on anarchist philosophy, women's rights, and social issues, attracting crowds of thousands.<extension extension_name='ref' name="UIC"></extension><space/>She and anarchist writer<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>, her lover and lifelong friend, planned to assassinate industrialist and financier<space/><link><target>Henry Clay Frick</target></link><space/>as an act of<space/><link><target>propaganda of the deed</target></link>. Although Frick survived the attempt on his life, Berkman was sentenced to 22 years in prison. Goldman was imprisoned several times in the years that followed, for &quot;inciting to riot&quot; and illegally distributing information about<space/><link><target>birth control</target></link>. In 1906, Goldman founded the anarchist journal<space/><italics><link><target>Mother Earth (magazine)</target><part>Mother Earth</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1917, Goldman and Berkman were sentenced to two years in jail for conspiring to &quot;induce persons not to register&quot; for the<space/><link><target>Conscription in the United States</target><part>newly instated draft</part></link>. After their release from prison, they were arrestedalong with hundreds of othersand deported to her native<space/><link><target>Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic</target><part>Russia</part></link>. Initially supportive of that country's<space/><link><target>Bolshevik</target></link><space/>revolution, Goldman reversed her opinion in the wake of the<space/><link><target>Kronstadt rebellion</target></link><space/>and denounced the<space/><link><target>Soviet Union</target></link><space/>for its violent repression of independent voices. In 1923, she published a book about her experiences,<space/><italics><link><target>My Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics>. While living in England, Canada, and France, she wrote an autobiography called<space/><italics><link><target>Living My Life</target></link></italics>. After the outbreak of the<space/><link><target>Spanish Civil War</target></link>, she traveled to Spain to support the<space/><link><target>Spanish Revolution</target><part>anarchist revolution</part></link><space/>there. She died in<space/><link><target>Toronto</target></link><space/>on May 14, 1940, aged 70.</paragraph><paragraph>During her life, Goldman was lionized as a<space/><link><target>free-thinking</target></link><space/>&quot;rebel woman&quot; by admirers, and denounced by critics as an advocate of politically motivated murder and violent revolution.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Voices"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Streitmatter</arg><arg name="first">Rodger</arg><arg name="title">Voices of Revolution: The Dissident Press in America</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Columbia University Press]]</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="pages">122–134</arg><arg name="isbn">0-231-12249-7</arg></template></extension><space/>Her writing and lectures spanned a wide variety of issues, including prisons,<space/><link><target>atheism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>freedom of speech</target></link>,<space/><link><target>militarism</target></link>,<space/><link><target>capitalism</target></link>, marriage,<space/><link><target>free love</target></link>, and homosexuality. Although she distanced herself from<space/><link><target>first-wave feminism</target></link><space/>and its efforts toward<space/><link><target>women's suffrage</target></link>, she developed new ways of incorporating gender politics into anarchism. After decades of obscurity, Goldman's iconic status was revived in the 1970s, when feminist and anarchist scholars rekindled popular interest in her life.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Family</heading><paragraph>Emma Goldman's<space/><link><target>Orthodox Judaism</target><part>Orthodox Jewish</part></link><space/>family lived in the Lithuanian city of<space/><link><target>Kaunas</target></link><space/>(called Kovno at the time, part of the<space/><link><target>Russian Empire</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 24.</extension><space/>Goldman's mother Taube Bienowitch had been married before, to a man with whom she had two daughtersHelena in 1860 and Lena in 1862. When her first husband died of<space/><link><target>tuberculosis</target></link>, Taube was devastated. Goldman later wrote: &quot;Whatever love she had had died with the young man to whom she had been married at the age of fifteen.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv447">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 447.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Taube's second<space/><link><target>arranged marriage</target><part>marriage was arranged</part></link><space/>by her family and, as Goldman puts it, &quot;mismated from the first&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv447"></extension><space/>Her second husband, Abraham Goldman, invested Taube's inheritance in a business that quickly failed. The ensuing hardship combined with the emotional distance of husband and wife to make the household a tense place for the children. When Taube became pregnant, Abraham hoped desperately for a son; a daughter, he believed, would serve as one more sign of failure.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 5.</extension><space/>They eventually had three sons, but their first child was Emma.<extension extension_name='ref'>The order of birth is unclear; Wexler (in<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 13) notes that although Goldman writes of herself as her mother's fourth child, her brother Louis (who died at the age of six) was probably born after her.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Emma Goldman was born on June 27, 1869. Her father used violence to punish his children, beating them when they disobeyed him. He used a whip only on Emma, the most rebellious of them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 13.</extension><space/>Her mother provided scarce comfort, calling only rarely on Abraham to tone down his beatings.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 12.</extension><space/>Goldman later speculated that her father's furious temper was at least partly a result of sexual frustration.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv447"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman's relationships with her elder half-sisters, Helena and Lena, were a study in contrasts. Helena, the oldest, provided the comfort they lacked from their mother; she filled Goldman's childhood with &quot;whatever joy it had&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 11.</extension><space/>Lena, however, was distant and uncharitable.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 12.</extension><space/>The three sisters were joined by brothers Louis (who died at the age of six), Herman (born in 1872), and Moishe (born in 1879).<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 1314.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Adolescence</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman's family.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Emma Goldman's family in St. Petersberg, Russia in 1882. From left to right: Emma, standing; Helena, seated, with Morris on her lap; Taube; Herman; Abraham.</part></link>When Emma was a young girl, the Goldman family moved to the village of<space/><link><target>Papil</target></link>, where her father ran an inn. While her sisters worked, she became friends with a servant named Petrushka, who excited her &quot;first erotic sensations&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 20.</extension><space/>Later in Papil she witnessed a peasant being whipped with a<space/><link><target>knout</target></link><space/>in the street. This event traumatized her and contributed to her lifelong distaste for violent authority.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 28.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the age of seven, Goldman moved with her family to the Prussian city of<space/><link><target>Knigsberg</target></link><space/>(then part of the German Empire), and she enrolled in a<space/><link><target>Realschule</target></link>. One teacher punished disobedient studentstargeting Goldman in particularby beating their hands with a ruler. Another teacher tried to molest his female students and was fired when Goldman fought back. She found a sympathetic mentor in her German teacher, who loaned her books and even took her to an opera. A passionate student, Goldman passed the exam for admission into a<space/><link><target>Gymnasium (school)</target><part>gymnasium</part></link>, but her religion teacher refused to provide a certificate of good behavior and she was unable to attend.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 67.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The family moved to the Russian city of<space/><link><target>Saint Petersburg</target></link>, where her father opened one unsuccessful store after another. Their poverty forced the children to work, and Goldman took an assortment of jobs including one in a<space/><link><target>corset</target></link><space/>shop.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 15.</extension><space/>As a teenager Goldman begged her father to allow her to return to school, but instead he threw her French book into the fire and shouted: &quot;Girls do not have to learn much! All a Jewish daughter needs to know is how to prepare<space/><link><target>gefilte fish</target></link>, cut noodles fine, and give the man plenty of children.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv12">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman pursued an independent education<space/><link><target>autodidact</target><part>on her own</part></link>, however, and soon began to study the political turmoil around her, particularly the<space/><link><target>Nihilist movement</target><part>Nihilists</part></link><space/>responsible for assassinating<space/><link><target>Alexander II of Russia</target></link>. The ensuing turmoil intrigued Goldman, even though she did not fully understand it at the time. When she read<space/><link><target>Nikolai Chernyshevsky</target><part>Chernyshevsky</part></link>'s novel,<space/><italics><link><target>What Is to Be Done? (novel)</target><part>What Is to Be Done?</part></link></italics><space/>(1863), she found a role model in the protagonist Vera, who adopts a Nihilist philosophy and escapes her repressive family to live freely and organize a sewing<space/><link><target>cooperative</target></link>. The book enthralled Goldman and remained a source of inspiration throughout her life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 2326.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Her father, meanwhile, continued to insist on a domestic future for her, and he tried to arrange for her to be married at the age of fifteen. They fought about the issue constantly; he complained that she was becoming a &quot;loose&quot; woman, and she insisted that she would marry for love alone.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JC16">Chalberg, p. 16.</extension><space/>At the corset shop, she was forced to fend off unwelcome advances from Russian officers and other men. One persistent suitor took her into a hotel room and committed what Goldman called &quot;violent contact&quot;;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 22.</extension><space/>two biographers call it rape.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JC16"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Falk,<space/><italics>Love</italics>, p. 14.</extension><space/>She was stunned by the experience, overcome by &quot;shock at the discovery that the contact between man and woman could be so brutal and painful.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv23">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 23.</extension><space/>Goldman felt that the encounter forever soured her interactions with men.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv23"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Rochester, New York</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma goldman 1886.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Emma Goldman in 1886</part></link>In 1885, Helena made plans to move to New York to join her sister Lena and her husband. Goldman wanted to join her sister, but their father refused to allow it. Despite Helena's offer to pay for the trip, Abraham turned a deaf ear to their pleas. Desperate, Goldman threatened to throw herself into the<space/><link><target>Neva River</target></link><space/>if she could not go. He finally agreed, and on December 29, 1885, Helena and Emma arrived at New York's<space/><link><target>Castle Garden</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 27.</extension><space/>They moved into the<space/><link><target>Rochester, New York</target><part>Rochester</part></link><space/>home Lena had made with her husband Samuel. Fleeing the rising<space/><link><target>antisemitism</target></link><space/>of Saint Petersburg, their parents and brothers joined them a year later. Goldman began working as a<space/><link><target>seamstress</target></link>, sewing overcoats for more than ten hours a day, earning two and a half dollars a week. She asked for a raise and was denied; she quit and took work at a smaller shop nearby.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 3031.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At her new job, Goldman met a fellow worker named Jacob Kershner, who shared her love for books, dancing, and traveling, as well as her frustration with the monotony of factory work. After four months, they married in February 1887.<extension extension_name='ref'>Falk,<space/><italics>Love</italics>, pp. 1516.</extension><space/>Once he moved in with Goldman's family, however, their relationship faltered. On their wedding night she discovered that he was impotent; they became emotionally and physically distant. Before long he became jealous and suspicious. She, meanwhile, was becoming more engaged with the political turmoil around herparticularly the fallout of the 1886<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link><space/>in Chicago and the<space/><link><target>anti-authoritarian</target></link><space/>political philosophy of<space/><link><target>anarchism</target></link>. Less than a year after the wedding, they were divorced; he begged her to return and threatened to poison himself if she did not. They reunited, but after three months she left once again. Her parents considered her behavior &quot;loose&quot; and refused to allow Goldman into their home.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 1517.</extension><space/>Carrying her sewing machine in one hand and a bag with five dollars in the other, she left Rochester and headed southeast to New York City.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 27.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Most and Berkman</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Goldman enjoyed a decades-long relationship with her lover<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>. Photo circa 19171919.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>On her first day in the city, Goldman met two men who would forever change her life. At Sachs's Caf, a gathering place for radicals, she was introduced to<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>, an anarchist who invited her to a public speech that evening. They went to hear<space/><link><target>Johann Most</target></link>, editor of a radical publication called<space/><italics><link><target>Freiheit (1879)</target><part>Freiheit</part></link></italics><space/>and an advocate of &quot;<link><target>propaganda of the deed</target></link>&quot;the use of violence to instigate change.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 2728.</extension><space/>She was impressed by his fiery oration, and he took her under his wing, training her in methods of public speaking. He encouraged her vigorously, telling her that she was &quot;to take my place when I am gone.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 40.</extension><space/>One of her first public talks in support of &quot;the Cause&quot; was in Rochester. After convincing Helena not to tell their parents of her speech, Goldman found her mind a blank once on stage. Suddenly,<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 51.</extension><template><target>quote</target><arg>something strange happened. In a flash I saw it—every incident of my three years in Rochester: the Garson factory, its drudgery and humiliation, the failure of my marriage, the Chicago crime...I began to speak. Words I had never heard myself utter before came pouring forth, faster and faster. They came with passionate intensity...The audience had vanished, the hall itself had disappeared; I was conscious only of my own words, of my ecstatic song.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Enchanted by the experience, she refined her public persona during subsequent engagements. Quickly, however, she found herself arguing with Most over her independence. After a momentous speech in Cleveland, she felt as though she had become &quot;a parrot repeating Most's views&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Goldman-Living-52">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 52.</extension><space/>and resolved to express herself on the stage. Upon her return in New York, Most became furious and told her: &quot;Who is not with me is against me!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 54.</extension><space/>She left<space/><italics>Freiheit</italics><space/>and joined with another publication,<space/><italics><link><target>Die Autonomie</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 53.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, she had begun a friendship with Berkman, whom she affectionately called Sasha. Before long they became lovers and moved into a communal apartment with his cousin Modest &quot;Fedya&quot; Stein and Goldman's friend, Helen Minkin, in rural<space/><link><target>Woodstock, Illinois</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 57.</extension><space/>Although their relationship had numerous difficulties, Goldman and Berkman would share a close bond for decades, united by their anarchist principles and commitment to personal equality.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 5758.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1892, Goldman joined with Berkman and Berkman's cousin, Modest Stein, in opening an ice cream shop in<space/><link><target>Worcester, Massachusetts</target></link>. After only a few months of operating the shop, however, Goldman and Berkman were deflected from the venture by their involvement in the<space/><link><target>Homestead Strike</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>People & Events: Henry Clay Frick (1849-1919)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[PBS]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>March 11, 2004<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/amex/goldman/peopleevents/p_frick.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-07-10<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Southwick<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Albert B.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Emma Goldman pays a visit<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>[[Telegram & Gazette]]<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Worcester, Massachusetts]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 26, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.telegram.com/article/20140626/COLUMN21/306269974/0<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-07-10</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Homestead plot</heading><paragraph><template><target>further2</target><arg>[[Homestead Strike]]</arg></template>One of the first political moments that brought Berkman and Goldman together was the<space/><link><target>Homestead Strike</target></link>. In June 1892, a steel plant in<space/><link><target>Homestead, Pennsylvania</target></link><space/>owned by<space/><link><target>Andrew Carnegie</target></link><space/>became the focus of national attention when talks between the<space/><link><target>Carnegie Steel Company</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Amalgamated Association of Iron and Steel Workers</target></link><space/>(AA) broke down. The factory's manager was<space/><link><target>Henry Clay Frick</target></link>, a fierce opponent of the union. When a final round of talks failed at the end of June, management closed the plant and locked out the workers, who immediately went on strike.<space/><link><target>Strikebreaker</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were brought in and the company hired<space/><link><target>Pinkerton National Detective Agency</target><part>Pinkerton guards</part></link><space/>to protect them. On July 6, a fight broke out between three hundred Pinkerton guards and a crowd of armed union workers. During the twelve-hour gunfight, seven guards and nine strikers were killed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 6162.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Henry Clay Frick.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman and Berkman believed that a retaliatory assassination of<space/><link><target>Carnegie Steel Company</target></link><space/>manager<space/><link><target>Henry Clay Frick</target></link><space/>(''pictured'') would &quot;strike terror into the soul of his class&quot; and &quot;bring the teachings of Anarchism before the world&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 63.</extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>When a majority of the nation's newspapers came out in support of the strikers, Goldman and Berkman resolved to assassinate Frick, an action they expected would inspire the workers to revolt against the capitalist system. Berkman chose to carry out the assassination, and ordered Goldman to stay behind in order to explain his motives after he went to jail. He would be in charge of the deed; she of the word.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 6365.</extension><space/>Berkman tried and failed to make a bomb, then set off for<space/><link><target>Pittsburgh</target></link><space/>to buy a gun and a suit of decent clothes. Goldman, meanwhile, decided to help fund the scheme through prostitution. Remembering the character of Sonya in<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoevsky</target></link>'s novel<space/><italics><link><target>Crime and Punishment</target></link></italics><space/>(1866), she mused: &quot;She had become a prostitute in order to support her little brothers and sisters...Sensitive Sonya could sell her body; why not I?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv91">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 91.</extension><space/>Once on the street, she caught the eye of a man who took her into a saloon, bought her a beer, gave her ten dollars, informed her she did not have &quot;the knack&quot;, and told her to quit the business. She was &quot;too astounded for speech&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv91"></extension><space/>She wrote to Helena, claiming illness, and asked her for fifteen dollars.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 45.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On July 23, Berkman gained access to Frick's office with a concealed handgun and shot Frick three times, then stabbed him in the leg. A group of workersfar from joining in his<space/><italics>attentat</italics>beat Berkman unconscious, and he was carried away by the police.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 4243; Falk,<space/><italics>Love</italics>, p. 25; Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 65.</extension><space/>Berkman was convicted of attempted murder<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Alexander Berkman, the Anarchist, to Be Deported; Case of Emma Goldman Now Up for Decision</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="date">November 26, 1919</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg></template></extension><space/>and sentenced to 22 years in prison;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 106.</extension><space/>his absence from her life was very difficult for Goldman.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 65.</extension><space/>Convinced Goldman was involved in the plot, police raided her apartment andfinding no evidencepressured her landlord into evicting her. Worse, the<space/><italics>attentat</italics><space/>had failed to rouse the masses: workers and anarchists alike condemned Berkman's action. Johann Most, their former mentor, lashed out at Berkman and the assassination attempt. Furious at these attacks, Goldman brought a toy horsewhip to a public lecture and demanded, onstage, that Most explain his betrayal. He dismissed her, whereupon she struck him with the whip, broke it on her knee, and hurled the pieces at him.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 6566.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 105.</extension><space/>She later regretted her assault, confiding to a friend: &quot;At the age of twenty-three, one does not reason.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 66.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>&quot;Inciting to riot&quot;</heading><paragraph>When the<space/><link><target>Panic of 1893</target></link><space/>struck in the following year, the United States suffered one of its worst economic crises ever. By year's end, the unemployment rate was higher than 20%,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/entry.php?rec=538'>&quot;Panic of 1893&quot;</link>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ohiohistorycentral.org/index.php'>Ohio History Central</link>. Ohio Historical Society, 2007. Retrieved on December 18, 2007.</extension><space/>and &quot;hunger demonstrations&quot; sometimes gave way to riots. Goldman began speaking to crowds of frustrated men and women in New York. On August 21, she spoke to a crowd of nearly 3,000 people in<space/><link><target>Union Square (New York City)</target><part>Union Square</part></link>, where she encouraged unemployed workers to take immediate action. Her exact words are unclear: undercover agents insist she ordered the crowd to &quot;take everything&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;by force&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 46.</extension><space/>while Goldman later recounted this message: &quot;Well then, demonstrate before the palaces of the rich; demand work. If they do not give you work, demand bread. If they deny you both, take bread.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv123">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 123.</extension><space/>Later in court, Detective-Sergeant Charles Jacobs offered yet another version of her speech.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 5859.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman surrounded by crowd.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Goldman (shown here in<space/><link><target>Union Square (New York City)</target><part>Union Square</part></link>, New York in 1916) urged unemployed workers to take<space/><link><target>direct action</target></link><space/>rather than depend on charity or government aid.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A week later she was arrested in<space/><link><target>Philadelphia</target></link><space/>and returned to New York City for trial, charged with &quot;inciting to riot&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 76.</extension><space/>During the train ride, Jacobs offered to drop the charges against her if she would inform on other radicals in the area. She responded by throwing a glass of ice water in his face.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 57.</extension><space/>As she awaited trial, Goldman was visited by<space/><link><target>Nellie Bly</target></link>, a reporter for the<space/><italics><link><target>New York World</target></link></italics>. She spent two hours talking to Goldman, and wrote a positive article about the woman she described as a &quot;modern<space/><link><target>Joan of Arc</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Nellie Bly</target></link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://sunsite3.berkeley.edu/Goldman/Samples/bly.html'>&quot;Nelly Bly Again: She Interviews Emma Goldman and Other Anarchists&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>New York World</target></link></italics>, September 17, 1893.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite this positive publicity, the jury was persuaded by Jacobs' testimony and scared by Goldman's politics. The assistant District Attorney questioned Goldman about her anarchism, as well as her atheism; the judge spoke of her as &quot;a dangerous woman&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 60.</extension><space/>She was sentenced to one year in the<space/><link><target>Roosevelt Island</target><part>Blackwell's Island</part></link><space/>Penitentiary. Once inside she suffered an attack of<space/><link><target>rheumatism</target></link><space/>and was sent to the infirmary; there she befriended a visiting doctor and began studying medicine. She also read dozens of books, including works by the American activist-writers<space/><link><target>Ralph Waldo Emerson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Henry David Thoreau</target></link>; novelist<space/><link><target>Nathaniel Hawthorne</target></link>; poet<space/><link><target>Walt Whitman</target></link>, and philosopher<space/><link><target>John Stuart Mill</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 78.</extension><space/>When she was released after ten months, a raucous crowd of nearly three thousand people greeted her at the<space/><link><target>Bowery Theatre</target><part>Thalia Theater</part></link><space/>in New York City. She soon became swamped with requests for interviews and lectures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 7879.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To make money, Goldman decided to pursue the medical work she had studied in prison. However, her preferred fields of specialization<link><target>midwifery</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>massage</target></link>were not available to nursing students in the US. Thus, she sailed to Europe, lecturing in London, Glasgow, and Edinburgh. She met with renowned anarchists like<space/><link><target>Errico Malatesta</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Louise Michel</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target></link>. In<space/><link><target>Vienna</target></link>, she received two diplomas and put them immediately to use back in the US. Alternating between lectures and midwifery, she conducted the first cross-country tour by an anarchist speaker. In November 1899 she returned to Europe, where she met the anarchist<space/><link><target>Hippolyte Havel</target></link>, with whom she went to France and helped organize the International Anarchist Congress on the outskirts of Paris.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 8489.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>McKinley assassination</heading><paragraph><template><target>further2</target><arg>[[Assassination of William McKinley]]</arg></template><link><target>File:First photograph of Leon F. Czolgosz, the assassin of President William McKinley, in jail.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Leon Czolgosz</target></link><space/>insisted that Goldman had not guided his plan to assassinate US President<space/><link><target>William McKinley</target></link>, but she was arrested and held for two weeks.</part></link>On September 6, 1901,<space/><link><target>Leon Czolgosz</target></link>, an unemployed factory worker and registered Republican with a history of mental illness, shot US President<space/><link><target>William McKinley</target></link><space/>twice during a public speaking event in Buffalo, New York. McKinley was hit in the breastbone and stomach, and died eight days later.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 6566.</extension><space/>Czolgosz was arrested, and interrogated around the clock. During interrogation he claimed to be an Anarchist and said he had been inspired to act after attending a speech held by Goldman. The authorities used this as a pretext to charge Goldman with planning McKinley's assassination. They tracked her to a residence in Chicago she shared with Havel, as well as Mary and<space/><link><target>Abe Isaak</target></link>, an anarchist couple.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 68.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 73.</extension><space/>Goldman was arrested, along with Abe Isaak, Havel, and ten other anarchists.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 104.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Newspaper article blaming Emma Goldman for inspiring Czolgosz to assassinate McKinley.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Propaganda published in the ''Chicago Daily Tribune'', September 8, 1901, blaming Emma Goldman for inspiring Leon Czolgosz to assassinate President William McKinley.</part></link>Earlier, Czolgosz had tried but failed to become friends with Goldman and her companions. During a talk in<space/><link><target>Cleveland</target></link>, Czolgosz had approached Goldman and asked her advice on which books he should read. In July 1901, he had appeared at the Isaak house, asking a series of unusual questions. They assumed he was an infiltrator, like a number of police agents sent to spy on radical groups. They had remained distant from him, and Abe Isaak sent a notice to associates warning of &quot;another spy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 103104.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Czolgosz repeatedly denied Goldman's involvement, the police held her in close custody, subjecting her to what she called the &quot;<link><target>Third degree (interrogation)</target><part>third degree</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 300.</extension><space/>She explained their distrust of him, and it was clear she had not had any significant contact with Czolgosz. No evidence was found linking Goldman to the attack, and she was eventually released after two weeks of detention. Before McKinley died, Goldman offered to provide nursing care, referring to him as &quot;merely a human being&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 76.</extension><space/>Czolgosz, despite considerable evidence of mental illness, was convicted of murder and executed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 74.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Throughout her detention and after her release, Goldman steadfastly refused to condemn Czolgosz's actions, standing virtually alone in doing so. Friends and supportersincluding Berkmanurged her to quit his cause. But Goldman defended Czolgosz as a &quot;supersensitive being&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cha78">Chalberg, p. 78.</extension><space/>and chastised other anarchists for abandoning him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cha78"></extension><space/>She was vilified in the press as the &quot;high priestess of anarchy&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Falk,<space/><italics>The American Years</italics>, p. 461.</extension><space/>while many newspapers declared the anarchist movement responsible for the murder.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 106112.</extension><space/>In the wake of these events, socialism gained support over anarchism among US radicals. McKinley's successor,<space/><link><target>Theodore Roosevelt</target></link>, declared his intent to crack down &quot;not only against anarchists, but against all active and passive sympathizers with anarchists&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 81.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>and Berkman's release</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman 1901 mugshot (single portrait).png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Mug shot taken in 1901 when Goldman was implicated in the assassination of President McKinley.</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Mother Earth (magazine)</arg></template>After Czolgosz's execution, Goldman withdrew from the world. Scorned by her fellow anarchists, vilified by the press, and separated from her love, she retreated into anonymity and nursing. &quot;It was bitter and hard to face life anew,&quot; she wrote later.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 318.</extension><space/>Using the name E. G. Smith, she vanished from public life and took on a series of private nursing jobs.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 115.</extension><space/>When the US Congress passed the<space/><link><target>Anarchist Exclusion Act</target></link>, however, a new wave of activism rose to oppose it, carrying Goldman back into the movement. A coalition of people and organizations across the<space/><link><target>left-wing politics</target><part>left</part></link><space/>end of the political spectrum opposed the law on grounds that it violated<space/><link><target>freedom of speech</target></link>, and she had the nation's ear once again.</paragraph><paragraph>When an English anarchist named<space/><link><target>John Turner (anarchist)</target><part>John Turner</part></link><space/>was arrested under the Anarchist Exclusion Act and threatened with deportation, Goldman joined forces with the<space/><link><target>Free Speech League</target></link><space/>to champion his cause.<extension extension_name='ref'>Falk,<space/><italics>Making Speech Free</italics>, p. 557.</extension><space/>The league enlisted the aid of<space/><link><target>Clarence Darrow</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Edgar Lee Masters</target></link>, who took Turner's case to the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of the United States</target><part>US Supreme Court</part></link>. Although Turner and the League lost, Goldman considered it a victory of propaganda.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 8487.</extension><space/>She had returned to anarchist activism, but it was taking its toll on her. &quot;I never felt so weighed down,&quot; she wrote to Berkman. &quot;I fear I am forever doomed to remain public property and to have my life worn out through the care for the lives of others.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 87.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Mother Earth 1912.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman's ''<link><target>Mother Earth (magazine)</target><part>Mother Earth</part></link>'' magazine became a home to radical activists and literary free thinkers around the US.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1906, Goldman decided to start a publication of her own, &quot;a place of expression for the young idealists in arts and letters&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 377.</extension><space/><italics><link><target>Mother Earth (magazine)</target><part>Mother Earth</part></link></italics><space/>was staffed by a cadre of radical activists, including Hippolyte Havel,<space/><link><target>Max Baginski</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Leonard Abbott</target></link>. In addition to publishing original works by its editors and anarchists around the world,<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>reprinted selections from a variety of writers. These included the French philosopher<space/><link><target>Pierre-Joseph Proudhon</target></link>, Russian anarchist<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target></link>, German philosopher<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link>, and British writer<space/><link><target>Mary Wollstonecraft</target></link>. Goldman wrote frequently about anarchism, politics, labor issues, atheism, sexuality, and feminism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 8891.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 121130.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On May 18 of the same year, Alexander Berkman was released from prison. Carrying a bouquet of roses, she met him on the platform and found herself &quot;seized by terror and pity&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 384.</extension><space/>as she beheld his gaunt, pale form. Neither was able to speak; they returned to her home in silence. For weeks, he struggled to readjust to life on the outside; an abortive speaking tour ended in failure, and in Cleveland he purchased a revolver with the intent of killing himself.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 94.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 9798.</extension><space/>He returned to New York, however, and learned that Goldman had been arrested with a group of activists meeting to reflect on Czolgosz. Invigorated anew by this violation of<space/><link><target>freedom of assembly</target></link>, he declared &quot;My resurrection has come!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 391.</extension><space/>and set about securing their release.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 98.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Berkman took the helm of<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>in 1907, while Goldman toured the country to raise funds to keep it functional. Editing the magazine was a revitalizing experience for Berkman; his relationship with Goldman faltered, however, and he had an affair with a 15-year-old anarchist named<space/><link><target>Becky Edelsohn</target></link>. Goldman was pained by his rejection of her, but considered it a consequence of his prison experience.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 97.</extension><space/>Later that year she served as a delegate from the US to the<space/><link><target>International Anarchist Congress of Amsterdam</target></link>. Anarchists and<space/><link><target>syndicalism</target><part>syndicalists</part></link><space/>from around the world gathered to sort out the tension between the two ideologies, but no decisive agreement was reached. Goldman returned to the US and continued speaking to large audiences.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 135137.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Reitman, essays, and birth control</heading><paragraph>For the next ten years, Goldman traveled around the country nonstop, delivering lectures and agitating for anarchism. The coalitions formed in opposition to the Anarchist Exclusion Act had given her an appreciation for reaching out to those of other political persuasions. When the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Justice</target><part>US Justice Department</part></link><space/>sent spies to observe, they reported the meetings as &quot;packed&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 166.</extension><space/>Writers, journalists, artists, judges, and workers from across the spectrum spoke of her &quot;magnetic power&quot;, her &quot;convincing presence&quot;, her &quot;force, eloquence, and fire&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 168.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:MargaretSanger-Underwood.LOC.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman joined<space/><link><target>Margaret Sanger</target></link><space/>in crusading for women's access to<space/><link><target>birth control</target></link>; both women were arrested for violating the<space/><link><target>Comstock Law</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the spring of 1908, Goldman met and fell in love with<space/><link><target>Ben Reitman</target></link>, the so-called &quot;Hobo doctor&quot;. Having grown up in Chicago's tenderloin district, Reitman spent several years as a drifter before attaining a medical degree from the<space/><link><target>University of Illinois College of Medicine</target><part>College of Physicians and Surgeons of Chicago</part></link>. As a doctor, he attended to people suffering from poverty and illness, particularly<space/><link><target>venereal disease</target><trail>s</trail></link>. He and Goldman began an affair; they shared a commitment to<space/><link><target>free love</target></link>, but whereas Reitman took a variety of lovers, Goldman did not. She tried to reconcile her feelings of jealousy with a belief in freedom of the heart, but found it difficult.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 140147.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Two years later, Goldman began feeling frustrated with lecture audiences. She yearned to &quot;reach the few who really want to learn, rather than the many who come to be amused&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGAn49">Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 49.</extension><space/>Thus she collected a series of speeches and items she had written for<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>and published a book called<space/><italics><link><target>Anarchism and Other Essays</target></link></italics>. Covering a wide variety of topics, Goldman tries to represent &quot;the mental and soul struggles of twenty-one years&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGAn49"></extension><space/>In addition to a comprehensive look at anarchism and its criticisms, the book includes essays on patriotism,<space/><link><target>women's suffrage</target></link>, marriage, and prisons.</paragraph><paragraph>When<space/><link><target>Margaret Sanger</target></link>, an advocate of access to<space/><link><target>contraception</target></link>, coined the term &quot;birth control&quot; and disseminated information about various methods in the June 1914 issue of her magazine<space/><italics>The Woman Rebel</italics>, she received aggressive support from Goldman, who had already been an active in efforts to increase birth control access for several years. In 1916, Goldman was arrested for giving lessons in public on how to use contraceptives.<extension extension_name='ref'>Alice S. Rossi. The Feminist Papers: From Adams to de Beauvoir. Lebanon, New Hampshire: Northeastern University Press, 1988, p. 507</extension><space/>Sanger, too, was arrested under the<space/><link><target>Comstock Law</target></link>, which prohibited the dissemination of &quot;obscene, lewd, or lascivious articles&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 210.</extension>including information relating to birth control. Although they later split from Sanger over charges of insufficient support, Goldman and Reitman distributed copies of Sanger's pamphlet<space/><italics>Family Limitation</italics><space/>(along with a similar essay of Reitman's). In 1915 Goldman conducted a nationwide speaking tour in part to raise awareness about contraception options. Although the nation's attitude toward the topic seemed to be liberalizing, Goldman was arrested on February 11, 1916, as she was about to give another public lecture.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/today/feb11.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Today in History: February 11<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Library of Congress<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">January 28, 2014<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Goldman was charged with violating the Comstock Law. Refusing to pay a $100 fine, Goldman spent two weeks in a prison workhouse, which she saw as an &quot;opportunity&quot; to reconnect with those rejected by society.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, pp. 211215.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>World War I</heading><paragraph>Although US President<space/><link><target>Woodrow Wilson</target></link><space/>was re-elected in 1916 under the slogan &quot;He kept us out of the war&quot;, at the start of his second term he decided that<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link>'s continued deployment of<space/><link><target>unrestricted submarine warfare</target></link><space/>was sufficient cause for the US to enter<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. Shortly afterward, Congress passed the<space/><link><target>Selective Service Act of 1917</target></link>, which required all males aged 2130 to register for military<space/><link><target>conscription</target></link>. Goldman saw the decision as an exercise in<space/><link><target>militarism</target><part>militarist</part></link><space/>aggression, driven by capitalism. She declared in<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>her intent to resist conscription, and to oppose US involvement in the war.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 186187; Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 230.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Goldman.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman was imprisoned for two years after opposing<space/><link><target>conscription</target></link><space/>in the US during<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>To this end, she and Berkman organized the<space/><link><target>No conscription league</target><part>No Conscription League</part></link><space/>of New York, which proclaimed: &quot;We oppose conscription because we are internationalists, antimilitarists, and opposed to all wars waged by capitalistic governments.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Berkman, p. 155.</extension><space/>The group became a vanguard for anti-draft activism, and chapters began to appear in other cities. When police began raiding the group's public events to find young men who had not registered for the draft, however, Goldman and others focused their efforts on spreading pamphlets and other written work.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 186187.</extension><space/>In the midst of the nation's patriotic fervor, many elements of the political left refused to support the League's efforts. The Women's Peace Party, for example, ceased its opposition to the war once the US entered it. The<space/><link><target>Socialist Party of America</target></link><space/>took an official stance against US involvement, but supported Wilson in most of his activities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, p. 129.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>On June 15, 1917, Goldman and Berkman were arrested during a raid of their offices which yielded &quot;a wagon load of anarchist records and propaganda&quot; for the authorities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nyt1"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Emma Goldman and A. Berkman Behind the Bars</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="date">June 16, 1917</arg><arg name="accessdate">December 17, 2007</arg></template></extension><space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>reported that Goldman asked to change into a more appropriate outfit, and emerged in a gown of &quot;royal purple&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nyt1"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 232.</extension><space/>The pair were charged with conspiracy to &quot;induce persons not to register&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 134.</extension><space/>under the newly enacted<space/><link><target>Espionage Act of 1917</target><part>Espionage Act</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Trials of Emma Goldman, Anarchist</arg><arg name="first">Francis H.</arg><arg name="last">Shaw</arg><arg name="journal">The Review of Politics</arg><arg name="volume">26</arg><arg name="issue">3</arg><arg name="pages">444–445</arg><arg name="date">July 1964</arg><arg name="quote">Prosecuted under the Espionage Act of 1917 for obstructing the draft, Emma Goldman...<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/S0034670500005210</arg></template></extension><space/>and were held on US$25,000 bail each. Defending herself and Berkman during their trial, Goldman invoked the<space/><link><target>First Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>First Amendment</part></link>, asking how the government could claim to fight for democracy abroad while suppressing free speech at home:<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Trial and Speeches of Alexander Berkman and Emma Goldman in the United States District Court, in the City of New York, July, 1917</italics><space/>(New York: Mother Earth Publishing Association, 1917)</extension></paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>We say that if America has entered the war to make the world safe for democracy, she must first make democracy safe in America. How else is the world to take America seriously, when democracy at home is daily being outraged, free speech suppressed, peaceable assemblies broken up by overbearing and brutal gangsters in uniform; when free press is curtailed and every independent opinion gagged? Verily, poor as we are in democracy, how can we give of it to the world?</extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, the jury found Goldman and Berkman guilty. Judge<space/><link><target>Julius Marshuetz Mayer</target></link><space/>imposed the maximum sentence: two years' imprisonment, a $10,000 fine each, and the possibility of<space/><link><target>deportation</target></link><space/>after their release from prison. As she was transported to Missouri State Penitentiary (now<space/><link><target>Jefferson City Correctional Center</target></link>), Goldman wrote to a friend: &quot;Two years imprisonment for having made an uncompromising stand for one's ideal. Why that is a small price.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 235244.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In prison, she was again assigned to work as a seamstress, under the eye of a &quot;miserable gutter-snipe of a 21-year-old boy paid to get results&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 141.</extension><space/>She met the socialist<space/><link><target>Kate Richards O'Hare</target></link>, who had also been imprisoned under the Espionage Act. Although they differed on political strategyKate O'Hare believed in voting to achieve state powerthe two women came together to agitate for better conditions among prisoners.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 141142.</extension><space/>Goldman also met and became friends with<space/><link><target>Gabriella Segata Antolini</target></link>, an anarchist and follower of<space/><link><target>Luigi Galleani</target></link>. Antolini had been arrested transporting a satchel filled with dynamite on a Chicago-bound train. She had refused to cooperate with authorities, and was sent to prison for 14 months. Working together to make life better for the other inmates, the three women became known as &quot;The Trinity&quot;. Goldman was released on September 27, 1919.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 253263.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Deportation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman's deportation photo, 1919.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Emma Goldman's deportation photo, 1919</part><part>upright</part></link>Goldman and Berkman were released from prison during America's<space/><link><target>First Red Scare</target><part>Red Scare of 191920</part></link>, when public anxiety about wartime pro-German activities had morphed into a pervasive fear of Bolshevism and the prospect of an imminent radical revolution.<space/><link><target>Attorney General</target></link><space/><link><target>Alexander Mitchell Palmer</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>J. Edgar Hoover</target></link>, head of the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Justice</target><part>US Department of Justice's</part></link><space/>General Intelligence Division, were intent on using the<space/><link><target>Anarchist Exclusion Act</target></link><space/>and its<space/><link><target>Immigration Act of 1918#Definition of anarchist</target><part>1918 expansion</part></link><space/>to deport any non-citizens they could identify as advocates of anarchy or revolution. &quot;Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman,&quot; Hoover wrote while they were in prison, &quot;are, beyond doubt, two of the most dangerous anarchists in this country and return to the community will result in undue harm.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 215.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At her deportation hearing on October 27, she refused to answer questions about her beliefs on the grounds that her American citizenship invalidated any attempt to deport her under the Anarchist Exclusion Act, which could be enforced only against non-citizens of the US. She presented a written statement instead: &quot;Today so-called aliens are deported. Tomorrow native Americans will be banished. Already some patrioteers are suggesting that native American sons to whom democracy is a sacred ideal should be exiled.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Deportation Defied by Emma Goldman</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="date">October 28, 1919</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 4, 2010</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Louis Freeland Post</target><part>Louis Post</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Labor</target><part>Department of Labor</part></link>, which had ultimate authority over deportation decisions, determined that the revocation of her husband's American citizenship in 1908 had revoked hers as well. After initially promising a court fight,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Will Fight Deportation</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="date">December 1, 1919</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 4, 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>she decided not to appeal his ruling.<extension extension_name='ref'>Post, pp. 1314.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Labor Department included Goldman and Berkman among 249 aliens it deported<space/><italics>en masse</italics>, mostly people with only vague associations with radical groups who had been swept up in<space/><link><target>Palmer Raids</target><part>government raids</part></link><space/>in November.<extension extension_name='ref'>McCormick, pp. 158163.</extension><space/><italics><link><target>USAT Buford</target><part>Buford</part></link></italics>, a ship the press nicknamed the &quot;Soviet Ark,&quot; sailed from the Army's<space/><link><target>New York Port of Embarkation</target></link><space/>on December 21.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ark"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">'Ark' with 300 Reds Sails Early Today for Unnamed Port</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="date">December 21, 1919</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 1, 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Clay<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Steven E.<space/></arg><arg name="title">U. S. Army Order Of Battle 1919-1941<space/></arg><arg name="series">Volume 4. The Services: Quartermaster, Medical, Military Police, Signal Corps, Chemical Warfare, And Miscellaneous Organizations, 1919-41<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4<space/></arg><arg name="year">2011<space/></arg><arg name="location">Fort Leavenworth, KS 66027<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Combat Studies Institute Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780984190140<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">2010022326<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://usacac.army.mil/cac2/cgsc/carl/download/csipubs/OrderOfBattle/OrderofBattle4.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 October 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Some 58 enlisted men and four officers provided security on the journey and pistols were distributed to the crew.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ark"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Post, p. 4.</extension><space/>Most of the press approved enthusiastically. The Cleveland<space/><italics>Plain Dealer</italics><space/>wrote: &quot;It is hoped and expected that other vessels, larger, more commodious, carrying similar cargoes, will follow in her wake.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Murray, 208-9</extension><space/>The ship landed her charges in<space/><link><target>Hanko</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Finland</target></link><space/>on Saturday, January 17, 1920.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Soviet Ark Lands its Reds in Finland</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times</arg><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="date">January 18, 1920</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 1, 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Upon arrival in Finland, authorities there conducted the deportees to the Russian frontier under a flag of truce.<extension extension_name='ref'>Murray, pp. 207208.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Post, pp. 111.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Russia</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman gives eulogy at Peter Kropotkin's funeral.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Here, Emma Goldman delivers a eulogy at<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target></link>'s funeral procession. Immediately in front of Goldman stands her lifelong comrade<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>. Kropotkin's funeral was the occasion of the last great demonstration of anarchists in Moscowtens of thousands of people poured into the streets to pay their respects.</part></link>Goldman initially viewed the Bolshevik revolution in a positive light. She wrote in<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>that despite its dependence on Communist government, it represented &quot;the most fundamental, far-reaching and all-embracing principles of human freedom and of economic well-being&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 243.</extension><space/>By the time she neared Europe, however, she expressed fears about what was to come. She was worried about the ongoing<space/><link><target>Russian Civil War</target></link><space/>and the possibility of being seized by anti-Bolshevik forces. The state, anti-capitalist though it was, also posed a threat. &quot;I could never in my life work within the confines of the State,&quot; she wrote to her niece, &quot;Bolshevist or otherwise.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 17.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Dissillusioncover.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman's experiences in<space/><link><target>Russian Soviet Federative Socialist Republic</target><part>Soviet Russia</part></link><space/>led to her 1923 book, ''<link><target>My Disillusionment in Russia</target></link>''.</part></link>She quickly discovered that her fears were justified. Days after returning to<space/><link><target>Petrograd</target></link><space/>(Saint Petersburg), she was shocked to hear a party official refer to free speech as a &quot;bourgeois superstition&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 150.</extension><space/>As she and Berkman traveled around the country, they found repression, mismanagement, and corruption<extension extension_name='ref' name="livingmylife">Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>Living My Life</italics>. 1931. New York:<space/><link><target>Dover Publications</target></link><space/>Inc., 1970. ISBN 0-486-22543-7.</extension><space/>instead of the equality and worker empowerment they had dreamed of. Those who questioned the government were demonized as<space/><link><target>counter-revolutionary</target><part>counter-revolutionaries</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="livingmylife"></extension><space/>and workers labored under severe conditions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="livingmylife"></extension><space/>They met with<space/><link><target>Vladimir Lenin</target></link>, who assured them that government suppression of press liberties was justified. He told them: &quot;There can be no free speech in a revolutionary period.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 235.</extension><space/>Berkman was more willing to forgive the government's actions in the name of &quot;historical necessity&quot;, but he eventually joined Goldman in opposing the Soviet state's authority.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 236237.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In March 1921, strikes erupted in Petrograd when workers took to the streets demanding better food rations and more<space/><link><target>Trade union</target><part>union</part></link><space/>autonomy. Goldman and Berkman felt a responsibility to support the strikers, stating: &quot;To remain silent now is impossible, even criminal.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 237.</extension><space/>The unrest spread to the port town of<space/><link><target>Kronstadt</target></link>, where a military response was ordered. In the<space/><link><target>Kronstadt rebellion</target><part>fighting that ensued</part></link>, approximately 1,000 rebelling sailors and soldiers were killed and two thousand more were arrested. In the wake of these events, Goldman and Berkman decided there was no future in the country for them. &quot;More and more&quot;, she wrote, &quot;we have come to the conclusion that we can do nothing here. And as we can not keep up a life of inactivity much longer we have decided to leave.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, pp. 4749.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In December 1921, they left the country and went to the Latvian capital city of<space/><link><target>Riga</target></link>. The US commissioner in that city wired officials in Washington DC, who began requesting information from other governments about the couple's activities. After a short trip to<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link>, they moved to<space/><link><target>Berlin</target></link><space/>for several years; during this time she agreed to write a series of articles about her time in Russia for<space/><link><target>Joseph Pulitzer</target></link>'s newspaper, the<space/><italics><link><target>New York World</target></link></italics>. These were later collected and published in book form as<space/><italics><link><target>My Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics><space/>(1923) and<space/><italics><link><target>My Further Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics><space/>(1924). The titles of these books were added by the publishers to be scintillating and Goldman protested, albeit in vain.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, pp. 5658.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>England, Canada, and France</heading><paragraph>Goldman found it difficult to acclimate to the German leftist community. Communists despised her outspokenness about Soviet repression; liberals derided her radicalism. While Berkman remained in Berlin helping Russian exiles, she moved to London in September 1924. Upon her arrival, the novelist<space/><link><target>Rebecca West</target></link><space/>arranged a reception dinner for her, attended by philosopher<space/><link><target>Bertrand Russell</target></link>, novelist<space/><link><target>H. G. Wells</target></link>, and more than two hundred others. When she spoke of her dissatisfaction with the Soviet government, the audience was shocked. Some left the gathering; others berated her for prematurely criticizing the Communist experiment.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 161162.</extension><space/>Later, in a letter, Russell declined to support her efforts at systemic change in the Soviet Union and ridiculed her anarchist idealism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 96.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Sacvan.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The 1927 executions of Italian anarchists<space/><link><target>Nicola Sacco</target></link><space/>(right) and<space/><link><target>Bartolomeo Vanzetti</target></link><space/>were troubling for Goldman, living alone in Canada at the time.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1925, the spectre of deportation loomed again, but a Scottish anarchist named<space/><link><target>James Colton</target></link><space/>offered to marry her and provide British citizenship. Although they were only distant acquaintances, she accepted and they were married on June 27, 1925. Her new status gave her peace of mind, and allowed her to travel to France and Canada.<extension extension_name='ref'>Falk,<space/><italics>Love</italics>, pp. 209210.</extension><space/>Life in London was stressful for Goldman; she wrote to Berkman: &quot;I am awfully tired and so lonely and heartsick. It is a dreadful feeling to come back here from lectures and find not a kindred soul, no one who cares whether one is dead or alive.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 111.</extension><space/>She worked on analytical studies of drama, expanding on the work she had published in 1914. But the audiences were &quot;awful&quot; and she never finished her second book on the subject.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 115.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman traveled to Canada in 1927, just in time to receive news of the impending executions of Italian anarchists<space/><link><target>Nicola Sacco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bartolomeo Vanzetti</target></link><space/>in Boston. Angered by the many irregularities of the case, she saw it as another travesty of justice in the US. She longed to join the mass demonstrations in<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link>; memories of the<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link><space/>overwhelmed her, compounded by her isolation. &quot;Then,&quot; she wrote, &quot;I had my life before me to take up the cause for those killed. Now I have nothing.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Chalberg, p. 164.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 122.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1928, she began writing her autobiography, with the support of a group of admirers, including journalist<space/><link><target>H. L. Mencken</target></link>, poet<space/><link><target>Edna St. Vincent Millay</target></link>, novelist<space/><link><target>Theodore Dreiser</target></link><space/>and art collector<space/><link><target>Peggy Guggenheim</target></link>, who raised $4,000 for her.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mary V. Dearborn,<space/><italics>Mistress of Modernism: The Life of Peggy Guggenheim</italics>, Houghton Mifflin, 2004, pp.6162</extension><space/>She secured a cottage in the French coastal city of<space/><link><target>Saint-Tropez</target></link><space/>and spent two years recounting her life. Berkman offered sharply critical feedback, which she eventually incorporated at the price of a strain on their relationship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 135.</extension><space/>Goldman intended the book,<space/><italics><link><target>Living My Life</target></link></italics>, as a single volume for a price the working class could afford (she urged no more than $5.00); her publisher<space/><link><target>Alfred A. Knopf</target></link>, however, released it as two volumes sold together for $7.50. Goldman was furious, but unable to force a change. Due in large part to the<space/><link><target>Great Depression</target></link>, sales were sluggish despite keen interest from libraries around the US.<extension extension_name='ref'>Chalberg, pp. 165166.</extension><space/>Critical reviews were generally enthusiastic;<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The New Yorker</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Saturday Review (US magazine)</target><part>Saturday Review of Literature</part></link></italics><space/>all listed it as one of the year's top non-fiction books.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 154.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1933, Goldman received permission to lecture in the United States under the condition that she speak only about drama and her autobiographybut not current political events. She returned to New York on February 2, 1934 to generally positive press coverageexcept from Communist publications. Soon she was surrounded by admirers and friends, besieged with invitations to talks and interviews. Her visa expired in May, and she went to<space/><link><target>Toronto</target></link><space/>in order to file another request to visit the US. However, this second attempt was denied. She stayed in Canada, writing articles for US publications.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, pp. 158164.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In February and March 1936, Berkman underwent a pair of<space/><link><target>prostate gland</target></link><space/>operations. Recuperating in<space/><link><target>Nice</target></link><space/>and cared for by his companion, Emmy Eckstein, he missed Goldman's sixty-seventh birthday in<space/><link><target>Saint-Tropez</target></link><space/>in June. She wrote in sadness, but he never read the letter; she received a call in the middle of the night that Berkman was in great distress. She left for Nice immediately but when she arrived that morning, Goldman found that he had shot himself and was in a nearly comatose<space/><link><target>paralysis</target></link>. He died the next day.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 298300.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Spanish Civil War</heading><paragraph>In July 1936, the<space/><link><target>Spanish Civil War</target></link><space/>started after an attempted<space/><italics>coup d'tat</italics><space/>by parts of the<space/><link><target>Spanish Army</target></link><space/>against the government of the<space/><link><target>Second Spanish Republic</target></link>. At the same time, the<space/><link><target>Anarchism in Spain</target><part>Spanish anarchists</part></link>, fighting against the<space/><link><target>National faction (Spanish Civil War)</target><part>Nationalist forces</part></link>, started<space/><link><target>Spanish Revolution</target><part>an anarchist revolution</part></link>. Goldman was invited to<space/><link><target>Barcelona</target></link><space/>and in an instant, as she wrote to her niece, &quot;the crushing weight that was pressing down on my heart since Sasha's death left me as by magic&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 301302.</extension><space/>She was welcomed by the<space/><link><target>Confederacin Nacional del Trabajo</target></link><space/>(CNT) and<space/><link><target>Federacin Anarquista Ibrica</target></link><space/>(FAI) organizations, and for the first time in her life lived in a<space/><link><target>Revolutionary Catalonia</target><part>community run by and for anarchists</part></link>, according to true anarchist principles. &quot;In all my life&quot;, she wrote later, &quot;I have not met with such warm hospitality, comradeship and solidarity.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler, p. 232.</extension><space/>After touring a series of<space/><link><target>collectives</target></link><space/>in the province of<space/><link><target>Huesca (province)</target><part>Huesca</part></link>, she told a group of workers: &quot;Your revolution will destroy forever [the notion] that anarchism stands for chaos.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, p. 303.</extension><space/>She began editing the weekly<space/><italics>CNT-FAI Information Bulletin</italics><space/>and responded to English-language mail.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 205.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:CNT FAI flag.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Goldman edited the English-language ''Bulletin'' of the<space/><link><target>Anarcho-syndicalist</target></link><space/>organizations<space/><link><target>Confederacin Nacional del Trabajo</target></link><space/>(CNT) and<space/><link><target>Federacin Anarquista Ibrica</target></link><space/>(FAI) during the<space/><link><target>Spanish Civil War</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman began to worry about the future of Spain's anarchism when the CNT-FAI joined a coalition government in 1937against the core anarchist principle of abstaining from state structuresand, more distressingly, made repeated concessions to Communist forces in the name of uniting against fascism. She wrote that cooperating with Communists in Spain was &quot;a denial of our comrades in Stalin's concentration camps&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 209.</extension><space/>Russia, meanwhile, refused to send weapons to anarchist forces, and disinformation campaigns were being waged against the anarchists across Europe and the US. Her faith in the movement unshaken, Goldman returned to London as an official representative of the CNT-FAI.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, pp. 209210.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Delivering lectures and giving interviews, Goldman enthusiastically supported the Spanish anarcho-syndicalists. She wrote regularly for<space/><italics><link><target>Freedom (newspaper)</target><part>Spain and the World</part></link></italics>, a biweekly newspaper focusing on the civil war. In May 1937, however, Communist-led forces<space/><link><target>Barcelona May Days</target><part>attacked anarchist strongholds</part></link><space/>and broke up agrarian collectives. Newspapers in England and elsewhere accepted the timeline of events offered by the<space/><link><target>Second Spanish Republic</target></link><space/>at face value. British journalist<space/><link><target>George Orwell</target></link>, present for the crackdown, wrote: &quot;[T]he accounts of the Barcelona riots in May&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;beat everything I have ever seen for lying.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 216.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman returned to Spain in September, but the CNT-FAI appeared to her like people &quot;in a burning house&quot;. Worse, anarchists and other radicals around the world refused to support their cause.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 222.</extension><space/>The Nationalist forces declared victory in Spain just before she returned to London. Frustrated by England's repressive atmospherewhich she called &quot;more fascist than the fascists&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler, p. 226.</extension>she returned to Canada in 1939. Her service to the anarchist cause in Spain was not forgotten, however. On her seventieth birthday, the former Secretary-General of the CNT-FAI, Mariano Vzquez, sent a message to her from Paris, praising her for her contributions and naming her as &quot;our spiritual mother&quot;. She called it &quot;the most beautiful tribute I have ever received&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Both quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 232.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Final years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman Grave.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman's grave in Illinois'<space/><link><target>German Waldheim Cemetery</target><part>Forest Home Cemetery</part></link>, near those of the anarchists executed for the<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link>. The dates on the stone are incorrect.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>As the events preceding<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>began to unfold in Europe, Goldman reiterated her opposition to wars waged by governments. &quot;[M]uch as I loathe<space/><link><target>Adolf Hitler</target><part>Hitler</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Benito Mussolini</target><part>Mussolini</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Joseph Stalin</target><part>Stalin</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Francisco Franco</target><part>Franco</part></link>&quot;, she wrote to a friend, &quot;I would not support a war against them and for the democracies which, in the last analysis, are only Fascist in disguise.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="WexEx236">Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 236.</extension><space/>She felt that England and France had missed their opportunity to oppose fascism, and that the coming war would only result in &quot;a new form of madness in the world&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WexEx236"></extension><space/>This position was vastly unpopular, as Hitler's attacks on Jewish communities reverberated throughout the Jewish diaspora.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Death</heading><paragraph>On Saturday, February 17, 1940, Goldman suffered a debilitating stroke. She became paralyzed on her right side, and although her hearing was unaffected, she could not speak. As one friend described it: &quot;Just to think that here was Emma, the greatest orator in America, unable to utter one word.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 240.</extension><space/>For three months she improved slightly, receiving visitors and on one occasion gesturing to her address book to signal that a friend might find friendly contacts during a trip to Mexico. She suffered another stroke on May 8, however, and on May 14 she died in<space/><link><target>Toronto</target></link>, aged 70.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler, pp. 240241.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Emma Goldman, Anarchist, Dead. Internationally Known Figure, Deported From The U.S., Is Stricken In Toronto. Disillusioned By Soviets Opposed Lenin And Trotsky As Betrayers Of Socialism Through Despotism.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://select.nytimes.com/gst/abstract.html?res</arg><arg name="quote">Emma Goldman, internationally known anarchist, died early today at her home here after an illness of several months. She was 70 years old.<space/></arg><arg name="work">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 14, 1940<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">April 20, 2008<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The US<space/><link><target>Immigration and Naturalization Service</target></link><space/>allowed her body to be brought back to the United States. She was buried in<space/><link><target>German Waldheim Cemetery</target></link><space/>(now named Forest Home Cemetery) in<space/><link><target>Forest Park, Illinois</target><part>Forest Park</part></link>, Illinois, a western suburb of Chicago, among the graves of other labor and social activists including Ben Reitman and those executed after the<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinnon,<space/><italics>Rebel</italics>, pp. 312313.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>bas relief</target></link><space/>on her grave marker was created by sculptor<space/><link><target>Jo Davidson</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Philosophy</heading><paragraph>Goldman spoke and wrote extensively on a wide variety of issues. While she rejected<space/><link><target>orthodoxy</target></link><space/>and fundamentalist thinking, she was an important contributor to several fields of modern political philosophy. She was influenced by many diverse thinkers and writers, including<space/><link><target>Mikhail Bakunin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Henry David Thoreau</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ralph Waldo Emerson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nikolai Chernyshevsky</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Mary Wollstonecraft</target></link>. Another philosopher who influenced Goldman was<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link>. In her autobiography, she wrote: &quot;Nietzsche was not a social theorist, but a poet, a rebel, and innovator. His aristocracy was neither of birth nor of purse; it was the spirit. In that respect Nietzsche was an anarchist, and all true anarchists were<space/><link><target>Aristocracy (government)</target><part>aristocrats</part></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, 194.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Anarchism</heading><paragraph>Anarchism was central to Goldman's view of the world and she is today considered one of the most important figures in the history of anarchism. First drawn to it during the persecution of anarchists after the 1886<space/><link><target>Haymarket affair</target></link>, she wrote and spoke regularly on behalf of anarchism. In the title essay of her book<space/><italics><link><target>Anarchism and Other Essays</target></link></italics>, she wrote:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Anarchism, then, really stands for the liberation of the human mind from the dominion of religion; the liberation of the human body from the dominion of property; liberation from the shackles and restraint of government. Anarchism stands for a social order based on the free grouping of individuals for the purpose of producing real social wealth; an order that will guarantee to every human being free access to the earth and full enjoyment of the necessities of life, according to individual desires, tastes, and inclinations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 62.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman's anarchism was intensely personal. She believed it was necessary for anarchist thinkers to live their beliefs, demonstrating their convictions with every action and word. &quot;I don't care if a man's theory for tomorrow is correct,&quot; she once wrote. &quot;I care if his spirit of today is correct.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="WexInt92">Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 92.</extension><space/>Anarchism and free association were to her logical responses to the confines of government control and capitalism. &quot;It seems to me that<space/><italics>these</italics><space/>are the new forms of life,&quot; she wrote, &quot;and that they will take the place of the old, not by preaching or voting, but by living them.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="WexInt92"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the same time, she believed that the movement on behalf of human liberty must be staffed by liberated humans. While dancing among fellow anarchists one evening, she was chided by an associate for her carefree demeanor. In her autobiography, Goldman wrote:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>I told him to mind his own business, I was tired of having the Cause constantly thrown in my face. I did not believe that a Cause which stood for a beautiful ideal, for anarchism, for release and freedom from conventions and prejudice, should demand denial of life and joy. I insisted that our Cause could not expect me to behave as a nun and that the movement should not be turned into a cloister. If it meant that, I did not want it. &quot;I want freedom, the right to self-expression, everybody's right to beautiful, radiant things.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 56.</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Tactical uses of violence</heading><paragraph>Goldman, in her political youth, held targeted violence to be a legitimate means of revolutionary struggle. Goldman at the time believed that the use of violence, while distasteful, could be justified in relation to the social benefits it might accrue. She advocated<space/><link><target>propaganda of the deed</target></link><italics>attentat</italics>, or violence carried out to encourage the masses to revolt. She supported her partner<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>'s attempt to kill industrialist<space/><link><target>Henry Clay Frick</target></link>, and even begged him to allow her to participate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv88">Goldman,<space/><italics>Living</italics>, p. 88.</extension><space/>She believed that Frick's actions during the<space/><link><target>Homestead strike</target></link><space/>were reprehensible and that his murder would produce a positive result for working people. &quot;Yes,&quot; she wrote later in her autobiography, &quot;the end in this case justified the means.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGLiv88"></extension><space/>While she never gave explicit approval of<space/><link><target>Leon Czolgosz</target></link>'s assassination of US President<space/><link><target>William McKinley</target></link>, she defended his ideals and believed actions like his were a natural consequence of repressive institutions. As she wrote in &quot;The Psychology of Political Violence&quot;: &quot;the accumulated forces in our social and economic life, culminating in an act of violence, are similar to the terrors of the atmosphere, manifested in storm and lightning.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 79.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Her experiences in Russia led her to qualify her earlier belief that revolutionary ends might justify violent means. In the afterword to<space/><italics><link><target>My Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics>, she wrote: &quot;There is no greater fallacy than the belief that aims and purposes are one thing, while methods and tactics are another.... The means employed become, through individual habit and social practice, part and parcel of the final purpose....&quot; In the same chapter, however, Goldman affirmed that &quot;Revolution is indeed a violent process,&quot; and noted that violence was the &quot;tragic inevitability of revolutionary upheavals...&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Disillusionment</italics>, pp. 260264.</extension><space/>Some misinterpreted her comments on the Bolshevik terror as a rejection of all militant force, but Goldman corrected this in the preface to the first US edition of<space/><italics>My Disillusionment in Russia</italics>:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>The argument that destruction and terror are part of revolution I do not dispute. I know that in the past every great political and social change necessitated violence...Black slavery might still be a legalized institution in the United States but for the militant spirit of the John Browns. I have never denied that violence is inevitable, nor do I gainsay it now. Yet it is one thing to employ violence in combat, as a means of defense. It is quite another thing to make a principle of terrorism, to institutionalize it, to assign it the most vital place in the social struggle. Such terrorism begets counter-revolution and in turn itself becomes counter-revolutionary.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman saw the militarization of Soviet society not as a result of armed resistance per se, but of the statist vision of the Bolsheviks, writing that &quot;an insignificant minority bent on creating an absolute State is necessarily driven to oppression and terrorism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ucblibrary3.berkeley.edu/Goldman/Writings/Russia/preface1.html'>&quot;Preface to First Volume of American Edition&quot; for ''My Disillusionment in Russia''</link><space/>(Emma Goldman Papers Project, University of California-Berkeley).</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Capitalism and labor</heading><paragraph>Goldman believed that the economic system of capitalism was incompatible with human liberty. &quot;The only demand that property recognizes,&quot; she wrote in<space/><italics>Anarchism and Other Essays</italics>, &quot;is its own gluttonous appetite for greater wealth, because wealth means power; the power to subdue, to crush, to exploit, the power to enslave, to outrage, to degrade.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGAnar54">Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 54.</extension><space/>She also argued that capitalism dehumanized workers, &quot;turning the producer into a mere particle of a machine, with less will and decision than his master of steel and iron.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGAnar54"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Originally opposed to anything less than complete revolution, Goldman was challenged during one talk by an elderly worker in the front row. In her autobiography, she wrote:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>He said that he understood my impatience with such small demands as a few hours less a day, or a few dollars more a week.... But what were men of his age to do? They were not likely to live to see the ultimate overthrow of the capitalist system. Were they also to forgo the release of perhaps two hours a day from the hated work? That was all they could hope to see realized in their lifetime.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Goldman-Living-52"></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman realized that smaller efforts for improvement such as higher wages and shorter hours could be part of a social revolution.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The state militarism, prison, voting, speech</heading><paragraph>Goldman viewed the state as essentially and inevitably a tool of control and domination. As a result, Goldman believed that voting was useless at best and dangerous at worst. Voting, she wrote, provided an illusion of participation while masking the true structures of decision-making. Instead, Goldman advocated targeted resistance in the form of strikes, protests, and &quot;direct action against the invasive, meddlesome authority of our moral code&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WexInt91">Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 91.</extension><space/>She maintained an anti-voting position even when many anarcho-syndicalists in 1930s Spain voted for the formation of a liberal republic. Goldman wrote that any power anarchists wielded as a voting bloc should instead be used to strike across the country.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 167.</extension><space/>She disagreed with the movement for<space/><link><target>women's suffrage</target></link>, which demanded the right of women to vote. In her essay &quot;Woman Suffrage&quot;, she ridicules the idea that women's involvement would infuse the democratic state with a more just orientation: &quot;As if women have not sold their votes, as if women politicians cannot be bought!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 205.</extension><space/>She agreed with the suffragists' assertion that women are equal to men, but disagreed that their participation alone would make the state more just. &quot;To assume, therefore, that she would succeed in purifying something which is not susceptible of purification, is to credit her with supernatural powers.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 198.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman was also a passionate critic of the prison system, critiquing both the treatment of prisoners and the social causes of crime. Goldman viewed crime as a natural outgrowth of an unjust economic system, and in her essay &quot;Prisons: A Social Crime and Failure&quot;, she quoted liberally from the 19th-century authors<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoevsky</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oscar Wilde</target></link><space/>on prisons, and wrote:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Year after year the gates of prison hells return to the world an emaciated, deformed, will-less, shipwrecked crew of humanity, with the Cain mark on their foreheads, their hopes crushed, all their natural inclinations thwarted. With nothing but hunger and inhumanity to greet them, these victims soon sink back into crime as the only possibility of existence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 120.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman was a committed<space/><link><target>war resister</target></link>, believing that wars were fought by the state on behalf of capitalists. She was particularly opposed to the<space/><link><target>conscription</target><part>draft</part></link>, viewing it as one of the worst of the state's forms of coercion, and was one of the founders of the<space/><link><target>No-Conscription League</target></link>for which she was ultimately arrested (1917), imprisoned and deported (1919).</paragraph><paragraph>Goldman was routinely surveilled, arrested, and imprisoned for her speech and organizing activities in support of<space/><link><target>workers</target></link><space/>and various strikes, access to<space/><link><target>birth control</target></link>, and in<space/><link><target>opposition to World War I</target></link>. As a result, she became active in the early 20th century free speech movement, seeing freedom of expression as a fundamental necessity for achieving social change.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Goldman-Living">See generally<space/><italics>Living My Life</italics>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stone-2004">See Geoffrey R. Stone,<space/><italics>Perilous Times: Free Speech in Wartime, From the Sedition Act of 1798 to the War on Terrorism</italics><space/>(2004), pp. 139152 (discussing persecution of Goldman and other anti-war activists, and the passage of the<space/><link><target>Espionage Act of 1917</target></link>).</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Falk-Volume2">Falk,<space/><italics>Making Speech Free</italics>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Rabban-1997">David M. Rabban,<space/><italics>Free Speech In Its Forgotten Years</italics><space/>(1997).</extension><space/>Her outspoken championship of her ideals, in the face of persistent arrests, inspired<space/><link><target>Roger Nash Baldwin</target><part>Roger Baldwin</part></link>, one of the founders of the<space/><link><target>American Civil Liberties Union</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Finan-2007">Christopher M. Finan,<space/><italics>From the Palmer Raids to the Patriot Act: A History of the Fight for Free Speech in America</italics>, p. 18.</extension><space/>Goldman's and Reitman's experiences in the<space/><link><target>San Diego free speech fight</target></link><space/>(1912) were notorious examples of state and capitalist repression of the<space/><link><target>Industrial Workers of the World</target></link>'s campaign of<space/><link><target>free speech fights</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Feminism and sexuality</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:EmmaGoldmanQuote2000.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Anarcha-feminist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>at an anti-globalization protest quote Emma Goldman.</part></link>Although she was hostile to the suffragist goals of<space/><link><target>first-wave feminism</target></link>, Goldman advocated passionately for the rights of women, and is today heralded as a founder of<space/><link><target>anarcha-feminism</target></link>, which challenges<space/><link><target>patriarchy</target></link><space/>as a hierarchy to be resisted alongside state power and class divisions.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marshall, p. 409.</extension><space/>In 1897, she wrote: &quot;I demand the independence of woman, her right to support herself; to live for herself; to love whomever she pleases, or as many as she pleases. I demand freedom for both sexes, freedom of action, freedom in love and freedom in motherhood.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Wexler,<space/><italics>Intimate</italics>, p. 94.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A nurse by training, Goldman was an early advocate for educating women concerning<space/><link><target>Birth control</target><part>contraception</part></link>. Like many feminists of her time, she saw abortion as a tragic consequence of social conditions, and birth control as a positive alternative. Goldman was also an advocate of<space/><link><target>free love</target></link>, and a strong critic of marriage. She saw early feminists as confined in their scope and bounded by social forces of<space/><link><target>Religious fanaticism</target><part>Puritanism</part></link><space/>and capitalism. She wrote: &quot;We are in need of unhampered growth out of old traditions and habits. The movement for women's emancipation has so far made but the first step in that direction.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><italics>Anarchism</italics>, p. 224.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>See generally Haaland; Goldman, &quot;The Traffic in Women&quot;; Goldman, &quot;On Love&quot;.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman was also an outspoken critic of<space/><link><target>homophobia</target><part>prejudice against homosexuals</part></link>. Her belief that social liberation should extend to gay men and lesbians was virtually unheard of at the time, even among anarchists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Katz</arg><arg name="first">Jonathan Ned</arg><arg name="title">Gay American History: Lesbians and Gay Men in the U.S.A.</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="location">New York City</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books</arg><arg name="pages">376–380</arg></template></extension><space/>As German sexologist<space/><link><target>Magnus Hirschfeld</target></link><space/>wrote, &quot;she was the first and only woman, indeed the first and only American, to take up the defense of homosexual love before the general public.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="hirschfeld">Goldman, Emma (1923). &quot;Offener Brief an den Herausgeber der Jahrbcher ber Louise Michel&quot; with a preface by Magnus Hirschfeld.<space/><italics>Jahrbuch fr sexuelle Zwischenstufen</italics><space/>23: 70. Translated from German by James Steakley. Goldman's original letter in English is not known to be extant.</extension><space/>In numerous speeches and letters, she defended the right of gay men and lesbians to love as they pleased and condemned the fear and stigma associated with homosexuality. As Goldman wrote in a letter to Hirschfeld, &quot;It is a tragedy, I feel, that people of a different sexual type are caught in a world which shows so little understanding for homosexuals and is so crassly indifferent to the various gradations and variations of gender and their great significance in life.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="hirschfeld"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Atheism</heading><paragraph>A committed<space/><link><target>atheist</target></link>, Goldman viewed religion as another instrument of control and domination. Her essay &quot;The Philosophy of Atheism&quot; quoted Bakunin at length on the subject and added:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Consciously or unconsciously, most theists see in gods and devils, heaven and hell, reward and punishment, a whip to lash the people into obedience, meekness and contentment.... The philosophy of Atheism expresses the expansion and growth of the human mind. The philosophy of<space/><link><target>theism</target></link>, if we can call it a philosophy, is static and fixed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Goldman</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Emma</arg><arg name="date">February 1916</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Philosophy of Atheism</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Mother Earth</arg><arg name="volume"><space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/The_Philosophy_of_Atheism</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>December 7, 2007</arg><arg name="quote"></arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In essays like &quot;The Hypocrisy of Puritanism&quot; and a speech entitled &quot;The Failure of Christianity&quot;, Goldman made more than a few enemies among religious communities by attacking their moralistic attitudes and efforts to control human behavior. She blamed Christianity for &quot;the perpetuation of a slave society&quot;, arguing that it dictated individuals' actions on Earth and offered poor people a false promise of a plentiful future in heaven.<extension extension_name='ref'>Goldman,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.positiveatheism.org/hist/goldman413.htm'>&quot;The Failure of Christianity&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics>, April 1913.</extension><space/>She was also critical of<space/><link><target>Zionism</target></link>, which she saw as another failed experiment in state control.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 41.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph>Goldman was well known during her life, described asamong other things&quot;the most dangerous woman in America&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Avrich
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Paul Avrich
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Anarchist Voices: An Oral History of Anarchism in America
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[AK Press]]
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>45
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-904859-27-5</arg></template></extension><space/>After her death and through the middle part of the 20th century, her fame faded. Scholars and historians of anarchism viewed her as a great speaker and activist, but did not regard her as a philosophical or theoretical thinker on par with, for instance,<space/><link><target>Peter Kropotkin</target><part>Kropotkin</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marshall, pp. 396401.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Emma Goldman.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Goldman's image, often accompanying a popular paraphrase of her ideas&quot;If I can't dance, I don't want to be in your revolution&quot;has been reproduced on countless walls, garments, stickers, and posters as an icon of freedom.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1970,<space/><link><target>Dover Press</target></link><space/>reissued Goldman's biography,<space/><italics>Living My Life</italics>, and in 1972, feminist writer<space/><link><target>Alix Kates Shulman</target></link><space/>issued a collection of Goldman's writing and speeches,<space/><italics>Red Emma Speaks</italics>. These works brought Goldman's life and writings to a larger audience, and she was in particular lionized by the<space/><link><target>Second-wave feminism</target><part>women's movement</part></link><space/>of the late 20th century. In 1973, Shulman was asked by a printer friend for a quotation by Goldman for use on a T-shirt. She sent him the selection from<space/><italics>Living My Life</italics><space/>about &quot;the right to self-expression, everybody's right to beautiful, radiant things&quot;, recounting that she had been admonished &quot;that it did not behoove an agitator to dance&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wexler1"></extension><space/>The printer created a statement based on these sentiments that has become one of Goldman's most famous quotations, even though she probably never said or wrote it as such: &quot;If I can't dance I don't want to be in your revolution.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Alix Kates Shulman</target><part>Shulman, Alix Kates</part></link>. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://sunsite3.berkeley.edu/Goldman/Features/dances_shulman.html'>Dances with Feminists</link>&quot;.<space/><italics>Women's Review of Books</italics>, Vol. IX, #3. December 1991. Available at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/Goldman/'>Emma Goldman Papers</link>. Retrieved on December 13, 2007.</extension><space/>Variations of this saying have appeared on thousands of T-shirts, buttons, posters, bumper stickers, coffee mugs, hats, and other items.<extension extension_name='ref' name="wexler1">Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 1.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The women's movement of the 1970s that &quot;rediscovered&quot; Goldman was accompanied by a resurgent anarchist movement, beginning in the late 1960s, which also reinvigorated scholarly attention to earlier anarchists. The growth of<space/><link><target>feminism</target></link><space/>also initiated some reevaluation of Goldman's philosophical work, with scholars pointing out the significance of Goldman's contributions to anarchist thought in her time. Goldman's belief in the value of<space/><link><target>aesthetics</target></link>, for example, can be seen in the later influences of<space/><link><target>anarchism and the arts</target></link>. Similarly, Goldman is now given credit for significantly influencing and broadening the scope of activism on issues of sexual liberty, reproductive rights, and freedom of expression.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marshall, pp. 408409.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman has been depicted in numerous works of fiction over the years, including<space/><link><target>Warren Beatty</target></link>'s 1981 film<space/><italics><link><target>Reds (film)</target><part>Reds</part></link></italics>, in which she was portrayed by<space/><link><target>Maureen Stapleton</target></link>, who won an<space/><link><target>Academy Awards</target><part>Academy Award</part></link><space/>for her performance. Goldman has also been a character in two Broadway musicals,<space/><italics><link><target>Ragtime (musical)</target><part>Ragtime</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Assassins (musical)</target><part>Assassins</part></link></italics>. Plays depicting Goldman's life include<space/><link><target>Howard Zinn</target></link>'s play,<space/><italics><link><target>Emma (play)</target><part>Emma</part></link></italics>;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Zinn
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Howard
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Howard Zinn
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Emma: A Play in Two Acts about Emma Goldman, American Anarchist
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[South End Press]]
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-89608-664-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Martin Duberman</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Mother Earth</italics><space/>(1991);<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Duberman
</arg><arg name="first">Martin
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Martin Duberman
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Mother Earth: An Epic Drama of Emma Goldman's Life
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[St. Martin's Press]]
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-312-05954-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Jessica Litwak</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: Love, Anarchy, and Other Affairs</italics><space/>(Goldman's relationship with Berkman and her arrest in connection with McKinley's assassination);<space/><link><target>Lynn Rogoff</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Love Ben, Love Emma</italics><space/>(Goldman's relationship with Reitman);<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.doollee.com/PlaywrightsR/rogoff-lynn.html'>Lynn Rogoff</link><space/>at doollee.com: The Playwrights Database</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Carol Bolt</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Red Emma</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wexler,<space/><italics>Exile</italics>, p. 249.</extension><space/><link><target>Ethel Mannin</target></link>'s 1941 novel<space/><italics>Red Rose</italics><space/>is also based on Goldman's Life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Mannin<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ethel<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Ethel Mannin<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Red Rose: A Novel Based on the Life of Emma Goldman ("Red Emma")<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Jarrolds<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1941<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Goldman has been honored by a number of organizations named in her memory. The Emma Goldman Clinic, a women's health center located in<space/><link><target>Iowa City, Iowa</target></link>, selected Goldman as a namesake &quot;in recognition of her challenging spirit.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.emmagoldman.com/about/about.htm'>About Us</link>&quot;. The Emma Goldman Clinic. 2007. Retrieved on December 15, 2007.</extension><space/><link><target>Red Emma's Bookstore Coffeehouse</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>infoshop</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Baltimore, Maryland</target></link><space/>adopted her name out of their belief &quot;in the ideas and ideals that she fought for her entire life: free speech, sexual and racial equality and independence, the right to organize in our jobs and in our own lives, ideas and ideals that we continue to fight for, even today&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.redemmas.org/section/About/emma/
</arg><arg name="title">Red Emma's Bookstore Coffeehouse: Who is Red Emma?
</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Red Emma's Bookstore Coffeehouse]]
</arg><arg name="accessdate">February 24, 2008</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Paul Gailiunas and his late wife<space/><link><target>Helen Hill</target></link><space/>co-wrote the anarchist song &quot;Emma Goldman&quot;, which was performed and released by the band Piggy: The Calypso Orchestra of the Maritimes in 1999.<extension extension_name='ref' name="divergences"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://divergences.be/spip.php?article425&lang</arg><arg name="title">Remembering Helen Hill: A New Orleans community comes together after the murder of a friend and activist</arg><arg name="author">John Clark</arg><arg name="date">14 May 2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Divergences</arg></template></extension><space/>The song was later performed by Gailiunas' new band The Troublemakers and released on their 2004 album<space/><italics>Here Come The Troublemakers</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="divergences"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Emma Goldman's speech to the jury at her and<space/><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target></link>'s trial in 1917 was listed as #65 in American Rhetoric's Top 100 Speeches of the 20th Century (listed by rank).<extension extension_name='ref' name="americanrhetoric1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Michael E. Eidenmuller<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.americanrhetoric.com/top100speechesall.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Top 100 Speeches of the 20th Century by Rank<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">American Rhetoric<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-02-13<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-10-27</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Michael E. Eidenmuller<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.americanrhetoric.com/speeches/emmagoldmanjuryaddress.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Emma Goldman - "Address to the Jury"<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">American Rhetoric<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-10-27</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Trial and Speeches of Alexander Berkman and Emma Goldman in the United States District Court, in the City of New York, July, 1917</italics><space/>(New York: Mother Earth Publishing Association, 1917)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><paragraph>Goldman was a prolific writer, penning countless pamphlets and articles on a diverse range of subjects. She authored six books, including an autobiography,<space/><italics><link><target>Living My Life</target></link></italics>, and a biography of fellow anarchist<space/><link><target>Voltairine de Cleyre</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/Goldman/Writings/Essays/voltairine.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Voltairine de Cleyre<space/></arg><arg name="first">Emma<space/></arg><arg name="last">Goldman<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oriole Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Berkeley Heights, New Jersey<space/></arg><arg name="year">1932<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">12414567<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-02-11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Books written by Emma Goldman</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Anarchism and Other Essays</target></link></italics>. New York: Mother Earth Publishing Association, 1910.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Social Significance of the Modern Drama</target></link></italics>. Boston: Gorham Press, 1914.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>My Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics>. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, Page and Co., 1923.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>My Further Disillusionment in Russia</target></link></italics>. Garden City, New York: Doubleday, Page and Co., 1924.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Living My Life</target></link></italics>. New York: Knopf, 1931.</listitem><listitem><italics>Voltairine de Cleyre</italics>. Berkeley Heights, New Jersey: Oriole Press, 1932.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Edited collections</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Red Emma Speaks: Selected Writings and Speeches</italics>. New York: Random House, 1972. ISBN 0-394-47095-8.</listitem><listitem><italics>Emma Goldman: A Documentary History Of The American Years, Volume 1&amp;nbsp; Made for America, 18901901</italics>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2003. ISBN 0-520-08670-8.</listitem><listitem><italics>Emma Goldman: A Documentary History Of The American Years, Volume 2&amp;nbsp; Making Speech Free, 19021909</italics>. Berkeley: University of California Press, 2004. ISBN 0-520-22569-4.</listitem><listitem><italics>Emma Goldman: A Documentary History of the American Years, Volume 3&amp;nbsp; Light and Shadows, 19101916</italics>. Stanford: Stanford University Press, 2012. ISBN 0-8047-7854-X.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Emma Goldman: The Anarchist Guest</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of the birth control movement in the United States</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of peace activists</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of women's rights activists</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Portal bar</target><arg>Anarchism</arg><arg>Atheism</arg><arg>Biography</arg><arg>Feminism</arg><arg>LGBT</arg><arg>Social movements</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paul Avrich</target><part>Avrich, Paul</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Haymarket Tragedy</italics>. Princeton:<space/><link><target>Princeton University Press</target></link>, 1984. ISBN 0-691-04711-1.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Alexander Berkman</target><part>Berkman, Alexander</part></link>.<space/><italics>Life of an Anarchist: The Alexander Berkman Reader</italics>. New York: Four Walls Eight Windows Press, 1992. ISBN 1-888363-17-7.</listitem><listitem>Chalberg, John.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: American Individualist</italics>. New York:<space/><link><target>HarperCollins Publishers Inc.</target></link>, 1991. ISBN 0-673-52102-8.</listitem><listitem>Drinnon, Richard.<space/><italics>Rebel in Paradise: A Biography of Emma Goldman</italics>. Chicago:<space/><link><target>University of Chicago Press</target></link>, 1961.<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>266217</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Drinnon, Richard and Anna Maria, eds.<space/><italics>Nowhere At Home: Letters from Exile of Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman</italics>. New York:<space/><link><target>Schocken Books</target></link>, 1975.<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>1055309</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Falk, Candace, et al.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: A Documentary History Of The American Years, Volume 1&amp;nbsp; Made for America, 18901901</italics>. Berkeley:<space/><link><target>University of California Press</target></link>, 2003. ISBN 0-520-08670-8.</listitem><listitem>Falk, Candace, et al.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: A Documentary History Of The American Years, Volume 2&amp;nbsp; Making Speech Free, 19021909</italics>. Berkeley:<space/><link><target>University of California Press</target></link>, 2004. ISBN 0-520-22569-4.</listitem><listitem>Falk, Candace Serena.<space/><italics>Love, Anarchy, and Emma Goldman</italics>. New Brunswick:<space/><link><target>Rutgers University Press</target></link>, 1990. ISBN 0-8135-1512-2.</listitem><listitem>Glassgold, Peter, ed.<space/><italics>Anarchy! An Anthology of Emma Goldman's Mother Earth</italics>. Washington, D.C.: Counterpoint, 2001. ISBN 1-58243-040-3.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>Anarchism and Other Essays</italics>. 3rd ed. 1917. New York:<space/><link><target>Dover Publications</target></link><space/>Inc., 1969. ISBN 0-486-22484-8.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>Living My Life</italics>. 1931. New York:<space/><link><target>Dover Publications</target></link><space/>Inc., 1970. ISBN 0-486-22543-7.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>My Disillusionment in Russia</italics>. 1923. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell Company, 1970.<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>76645</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>Red Emma Speaks</italics>. ed.<space/><link><target>Alix Kates Shulman</target></link>. New York:<space/><link><target>Random House</target></link>, 1972. ISBN 0-394-47095-8.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>The Social Significance of Modern Drama</italics>. 1914. New York: Applause Theatre Book Publishers, 1987. ISBN 0-936839-61-9.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>The Traffic in Women, and Other Essays on Feminism</italics>. Albion, CA: Times Change Press, 1970. ISBN 0-87810-001-6.</listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>The Tragedy of Woman's Emancipation</italics>. New York: Mother Earth Publishing Association, 1906.<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>15865931</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Goldman, Emma.<space/><italics>Vision on Fire: Emma Goldman on the Spanish Revolution</italics>. ed. David Porter. New Paltz, NY: Commonground Press, 1983. ISBN 0-9610348-2-3.</listitem><listitem>Haaland, Bonnie.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: Sexuality and the Impurity of the State</italics>. Montral, New York, London: Black Rose Books, 1993. ISBN 1-895431-64-6.</listitem><listitem>Marsh, Margaret S.<space/><italics>Anarchist Women 18701920</italics>. Philadelphia:<space/><link><target>Temple University Press</target></link>, 1981. ISBN 0-87722-202-9.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter Marshall (author)</target><part>Marshall, Peter</part></link>.<space/><italics>Demanding the Impossible: A History of Anarchism</italics>. London:<space/><link><target>HarperCollins</target></link>, 1992. ISBN 0-00-217855-9.</listitem><listitem>McCormick, Charles H.<space/><italics>Seeing Reds: Federal Surveillance of Radicals in the Pittsburgh Mill District, 19171921</italics>. Pittsburgh: University of Pittsburgh Press, 1997.</listitem><listitem>Moritz, Theresa.<space/><italics>The World's Most Dangerous Woman: A New Biography of Emma Goldman</italics>. Vancouver: Subway Books, 2001. ISBN 0-9681660-7-5.</listitem><listitem>Murray, Robert K.<space/><italics>Red Scare: A Study in National Hysteria, 19191920</italics>. Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1955. ISBN 0-313-22673-3</listitem><listitem>Post, Louis F.<space/><italics>The Deportations Delirium of Nineteen-twenty: A Personal Narrative of an Historic Official Experience</italics>. NY, 1923.</listitem><listitem>Solomon, Martha.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman</italics>. Boston: Twayne Publishers, 1987. ISBN 0-8057-7494-7.</listitem><listitem>Weiss, Penny A. and Loretta Kensinger, eds.<space/><italics>Feminist Interpretations of Emma Goldman</italics>. University Park:<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania State University Press</target></link>, 2007. ISBN 0-271-02976-5.</listitem><listitem>Wexler, Alice.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman: An Intimate Life</italics>. New York:<space/><link><target>Pantheon Books</target></link>, 1984. ISBN 0-394-52975-8. Republished as<space/><italics>Emma Goldman in America</italics>. Boston:<space/><link><target>Beacon Press</target></link>, 1984. ISBN 0-8070-7003-3.</listitem><listitem>Wexler, Alice.<space/><italics>Emma Goldman in Exile: From the Russian Revolution to the Spanish Civil War</italics>. Boston:<space/><link><target>Beacon Press</target></link>, 1989. ISBN 0-8070-7004-1.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Avrich<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Paul<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Avrich<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Karen<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sasha and Emma: The Anarchist Odyssey of Alexander Berkman and Emma Goldman<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, Mass.<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-674-06598-7<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>sisterlinks</target><arg name="wikt">no</arg><arg name="b">no</arg><arg name="q">Emma Goldman</arg><arg name="s">Author:Emma Goldman</arg><arg name="commons">Category:Emma Goldman</arg><arg name="n">no</arg><arg name="v">no</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Goldman,+Emma<space/></arg><arg name="name">Emma Goldman</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Emma Goldman</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">3133</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://sunsite.berkeley.edu/Goldman/'>Emma Goldman Papers Project</link><space/>at<space/><link><target>UC Berkeley</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>anarchives</target><arg>goldman/Goldmanarchive.html</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://theanarchistlibrary.org/authors/emma-goldman'>Works by Emma Goldman</link><space/>at the Anarchist Library</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://xroads.virginia.edu/~HYPER/Goldman/front.html'>''Anarchism and Other Essays''</link><space/>from American Studies at the University of Virginia</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://ditext.com/goldman/russia/russia.html'>''My Disillusionment in Russia''</link><space/>by Emma Goldman</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://nrs.harvard.edu/urn-3:RAD.SCHL:sch00027'>Emma Goldman Papers</link>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.radcliffe.edu/schles'>Schlesinger Library</link>, Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jwa.org/exhibits/wov/goldman/'>Emma Goldman &quot;Women of Valor&quot; exhibit</link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Jewish Women's Archive</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://jwa.org/encyclopedia/article/goldman-emma'>&quot;Emma Goldman&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>Jewish Women: A Comprehensive Historical Encyclopedia</italics>. Jewish Women's Archive.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Emma Goldman</target></template><template><target>American socialism navbox</target></template><template><target>Anarcho-communism</target></template><template><target>featured article</target></template><template><target>Libertarian socialism navbox</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Goldman, Emma
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Red Emma
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Lithuanian-born American anarchist
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>June 27, 1869
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Kovno]], [[Tsarist Russia]] (present-day [[Kaunas, Lithuania]])
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>May 14, 1940
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Toronto]], Ontario, Canada
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Goldman, Emma</target></template><link><target>Category:Emma Goldman</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1869 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1940 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American anarchists</target></link><link><target>Category:American anti-war activists</target></link><link><target>Category:American atheists</target></link><link><target>Category:American essayists</target></link><link><target>Category:American expatriates in Canada</target></link><link><target>Category:American expatriates in France</target></link><link><target>Category:American expatriates in the United Kingdom</target></link><link><target>Category:American feminist writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Lithuanian-Jewish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of Russian-Jewish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:American people of the Spanish Civil War</target></link><link><target>Category:American political writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American women philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:American women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:American women's rights activists</target></link><link><target>Category:Anarcha-feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:Anarchist communists</target></link><link><target>Category:Anarchist theorists</target></link><link><target>Category:American antiWorld War I activists</target></link><link><target>Category:Atheist feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:Atheist philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Forest Home Cemetery, Chicago</target></link><link><target>Category:Critics of religions</target></link><link><target>Category:Communist women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths in Canada</target></link><link><target>Category:English-language writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Free love advocates</target></link><link><target>Category:Free speech activists</target></link><link><target>Category:Imperial Russian emigrants to the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Imperial Russian Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish activists</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish American writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish anarchists</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish atheists</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish philosophers</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:LGBT rights activists from the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Libertarian socialists</target></link><link><target>Category:Lithuanian atheists</target></link><link><target>Category:Lithuanian emigrants to the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:Lithuanian Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Lithuanian women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:People associated with the Dil Pickle Club</target></link><link><target>Category:People deported from the United States</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Kaunas</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Kovno Governorate</target></link><link><target>Category:Persons convicted under the Espionage Act of 1917</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian people of the Spanish Civil War</target></link><link><target>Category:Russian revolutionaries</target></link><link><target>Category:Socialist feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:Women essayists</target></link><link><target>Category:Women in war 19001945</target></link><link><target>Category:Women in war in Spain</target></link><link><target>Category:Writers from New York City</target></link></paragraph></article>