<article title='Croquet'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the game</arg><arg>the food item</arg><arg>Croquette</arg><arg>the Smalltalk-based 3D software platform</arg><arg>Croquet project</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Modern croquet equipment.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Modern croquet equipment</part></link><link><target>File:Wyczkowski Game of croquet.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Leon Wyczkowski</target></link>, ''A Game of Croquet'' (1892-1895),<space/><link><target>National Museum, Warsaw</target><part>National Museum</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Warsaw</target></link></part></link><bold>Croquet</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>sport</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.croquet.org.uk/'>The Croquet Association (CA)</link>, the national governing body for the sport of Croquet in England, Wales, Northern Ireland, the Channel Islands and the Isle of Man</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.oxfordcroquet.com/'>Oxford Croquet.com</link>, &quot;Croquet is a satisfying sport utilising tactics and touch in equal measure&quot;</extension><space/>that involves hitting plastic or wooden<space/><link><target>ball</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>with a mallet through<space/><link><target>wikt:Special:Search/hoop</target><part>hoops</part></link><space/>(often called &quot;wickets&quot; in the United States) embedded in a grass playing court.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pall Mall - Project Gutenberg eText 14315.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Paille-maille</target></link><space/>(pall mall) illustrated in ''Old English Sports, Pastimes and Customs'', published 1891. Original image by Lauthier 1717</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The oldest document to bear the word<space/><italics>croquet</italics><space/>with a description of the modern game is the set of rules registered by<space/><link><target>Isaac Spratt</target></link><space/>in November 1856 with the Stationers' Company in<space/><link><target>London</target></link>. This record is now in the<space/><link><target>Public Record Office</target></link>. In 1868 the first croquet all-comers' meeting was held at<space/><link><target>Moreton-in-Marsh</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gloucestershire</target></link><space/>and in the same year the All England Croquet Club was formed at<space/><link><target>Wimbledon, London</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the book<space/><italics>Queen of Games: The History of Croquet</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Smith<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nicky<space/></arg><arg name="title">Queen of Games: The History of Croquet<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">George Weidenfeld & Nicolson<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1991<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-297-81176-2</arg></template></extension><space/>Nicky Smith presents two theories of the origin of the modern game that took<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>by storm in the 1860s and then spread overseas.</paragraph><paragraph>The first explanation is that the ancestral game was introduced to<space/><link><target>Great Britain</target><part>Britain</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>during the reign of<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target></link>, and was played under the name of<space/><link><target>paille-maille</target></link><space/>or pall mall, derived ultimately from Latin words for &quot;ball and<space/><link><target>mallet</target></link>&quot;. This was the explanation given in the ninth edition of<space/><italics><link><target>Encyclopaedia Britannica</target></link></italics>, dated 1877. In his 1810 book<space/><italics>The Sports and Pastimes of the People of England</italics>, Joseph Strutt describes the way pall mall was played in England in the early 17th century: &quot;Pale-maille is a game wherein a round box ball is struck with a mallet through a high arch of iron, which he that can do at the fewest blows, or at the number agreed upon, wins. It is to be observed, that there are two of these arches, that is one at either end of the alley. The game of mall was a fashionable amusement in the reign of Charles the Second, and the walk in Saint James's Park, now called the Mall, received its name from having been appropriated to the purpose of playing at mall, where Charles himself and his courtiers frequently exercised themselves in the practice of this pastime.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title">Sports and pastimes of the people of England<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joseph<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Strutt<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>94–5<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Google Books</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="year">1810</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Cotgrave, 1611</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Whilst the name pall mall and various games bearing this name may have been played elsewhere (France and Italy) the description above suggests that the croquet-like games were certainly popular in England as early as 1611.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><space/>Some early sources refer to pall mall being played over a large distance (as in golf), however an image in Strutt's 1801 book shows a croquet-like ground billiards game (balls on ground, hoop, bats and peg) being played over a<space/><italics>short</italics>, garden-sized distance. The image's caption describes the game as &quot;a curious ancient pastime&quot;, confirming that croquet games were not new in early nineteenth century England.<link><target>File:EarlyCroquetSportsofPeopleofEnglandStrutt.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Early croquet-like game from ''The Sports and Pastimes of the people of England'', first published 1801. Hoop, peg and two players with balls clearly shown.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Samuel Johnson</target></link>'s 1755 dictionary, his definition of &quot;pall mall&quot; clearly describes a game with similarities to modern croquet: &quot;A play in which the ball is struck with a mallet through an iron ring&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="title"><space/>A dictionary of the English language<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Samuel<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Walker<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Robert S.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Jameson<space/></arg><arg name="page">519<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1828</arg><arg name="author1"><space/>Johnson<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>However, there is no evidence that pall mall involved the croquet stroke which is the distinguishing characteristic of the modern game.</paragraph><paragraph>The second theory is that the rules of the modern game of croquet arrived from<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link><space/>during the 1850s, perhaps after being brought there from<space/><link><target>Brittany</target></link><space/>where a similar game was played on the beaches. Records show the similar game of &quot;crookey&quot; being played at<space/><link><target>Castlebellingham</target></link><space/>in 1834, which was introduced to<space/><link><target>Galway</target></link><space/>in 1835 and played on the bishop's palace garden, and in the same year to the genteel Dublin suburb of Kingstown (today<space/><link><target>Dn Laoghaire</target></link>) where it was first spelt as &quot;croquet&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Irish Daily Mail</target></link></italics>, 8 August 2009, p. 50.</extension><space/>There is, however, no pre-1858 Irish document that describes the way game was played, in particular there is no reference to the distinctive croquet stroke.<extension extension_name='ref' name="prichard"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Prichard<space/></arg><arg name="first">DMC<space/></arg><arg name="title">The History Of Croquet<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cassell<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-304-30759-9</arg></template></extension><space/>The noted croquet historian Dr Prior, in his book of 1872, makes the categoric statement &quot;One thing only is certain: it is from Ireland that croquet came to England and it was on the lawn of the late Lord Lonsdale that it was first played in this country.&quot; This was about 1851.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">A Brief History of Croquet in Ireland<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Clive<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Martin<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Simon<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eglington1.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A game of Croquet being played at<space/><link><target>Eglinton Country Park</target><part>Eglinton Castle</part></link>, North Ayrshire, in the early 1860s</part></link>John Jaques apparently claimed in a letter to<space/><link><target>Arthur Lillie</target></link><space/>in 1873 that he had himself seen the game played in Ireland and, &quot;I made the implements and published directions (such as they were) before Mr Spratt [mentioned above] introduced the subject to me.&quot;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><space/>Whatever the truth of the matter, Jaques certainly played an important role in popularising the game, producing editions of the rules in 1857, 1860, and 1864.</paragraph><paragraph>Regardless when and by what route it reached<space/><link><target>England</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>British Empire</target><part>British colonies</part></link><space/>in its recognizable form, croquet is, like pall mall,<space/><link><target>trucco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>jeu de mail</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kolven#History</target><part>kolven</part></link>, clearly a derivative of<space/><link><target>ground billiards</target></link>, which was popular in Western Europe back to at least the 14th century, with roots in<space/><link><target>classical antiquity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Shamos 1999"><template><target>Shamos 1999</target><arg>p. 117</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Clare"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Billiards and Snooker Bygones
</arg><arg name="last">Clare
</arg><arg name="first">Norman
</arg><arg name="publisher">Shire Publications
</arg><arg name="location">Princes Risborough, England
</arg><arg name="year">1996
</arg><arg name="origyear"><space/>1985
</arg><arg name="page">5
</arg><arg name="edition">amended
</arg><arg name="isbn">0-85263-730-6
</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Stein &amp; Rubino 2008"><template><target>Stein &amp; Rubino 2008</target><arg><space/>2, 4, 5, 27</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Croquet became highly popular as a social pastime in England during the 1860s. It was enthusiastically adopted and promoted by the<space/><link><target>Arthur Algernon Capell, 6th Earl of Essex</target><part>Earl of Essex</part></link><space/>who held lavish croquet parties at<space/><link><target>Cassiobury House</target></link>, his stately home in<space/><link><target>Watford</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hertfordshire</target></link>, and the Earl even launched his own<space/><italics>Cassiobury</italics><space/>brand croquet set.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">History</arg><arg name="url">http://www.watfordcroquet.org.uk/history.php</arg><arg name="website">Watford Cassiobury Croquet Club</arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Reid</arg><arg name="first1">Mayne</arg><arg name="title">Croquet, etc</arg><arg name="date">1869</arg><arg name="page">46</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>By 1867, Jaques had printed 65,000 copies of his<space/><italics>Laws and Regulations</italics><space/>of the game. It quickly spread to other<space/><link><target>English language</target><part>Anglophone</part></link><space/>countries, including<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link>,<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>. No doubt one of the attractions was that the game could be played by both sexes; this also ensured a certain amount of adverse comment.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Mn och kvinnor spelar krocket framfr hus p Liding - Nordiska Museet - NMA.0040765.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Croquet players in Sweden, early 20th century.</part></link>By the late 1870s, however, croquet had been eclipsed by another fashionable game,<space/><link><target>tennis</target></link>, and many of the newly created croquet clubs, including the All England club at Wimbledon, converted some or all of their lawns into<space/><link><target>tennis court</target><trail>s</trail></link>. There was a revival in the 1890s, but from then onwards, croquet was always a minority sport, with national individual participation amounting to a few thousand players. The<space/><link><target>All England Lawn Tennis and Croquet Club</target></link><space/>still has a croquet lawn, but has not hosted any significant tournaments. The English headquarters for the game is now in<space/><link><target>Cheltenham</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Captain Moreton's Eglinton Castle</heading><paragraph>The earliest known reference to croquet in Scotland is the booklet<space/><italics>The Game of Croquet, its Laws and Regulations</italics><space/>which was published in the mid-1860s for the proprietor of Eglinton Castle, the<space/><link><target>Earl of Eglinton</target></link>. On the page facing the title page is a picture of Eglinton Castle with a game of &quot;croquet&quot; in full swing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="C"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="chapter"><space/>Introduction<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.edinburghcroquetclub.com/intro.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Edinburgh Croquet Club</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>4 April 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The croquet lawn existed on the northern terrace, between<space/><link><target>Eglinton Castle</target></link><space/>and the Lugton Water. The 13th Earl developed a variation on croquet named Captain Moreton's Eglinton Castle croquet, which had small bells on the eight hoops &quot;to ring the changes&quot;, two pegs, a double hoop with a bell and two tunnels for the ball to pass through. In 1865 the 'Rules of the Eglinton Castle and Cassiobury Croquet' was published by Edmund Routledge. Several incomplete sets of this form of croquet are known to exist, and one complete set is still used for demonstration games in the West of Scotland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="C"></extension><space/>It is not known why the earl named the game thus.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eglinton Archive, Eglinton Country Park falconer</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Competitive variations</heading><paragraph>There are several variations of croquet currently played, differing in the scoring systems, order of shots, and layout (particularly in social games where play must be adapted to smaller-than-standard playing courts). Two forms of the game, association croquet and golf croquet, have rules that are agreed internationally and are played in many countries around the world. The United States has its own set of rules for domestic games.<space/><link><target>Gateball</target></link>, a sport originated in Japan under the influence of croquet, is played mainly in<space/><link><target>East Asia</target><part>East</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Western Hemisphere</target><part>the Americas</part></link><space/>and can also be regarded as a croquet variant.</paragraph><paragraph>As well as club-level games, there are regular world championships and international matches between croquet-playing countries. The sport has particularly strong followings in the UK, US, New Zealand and Australia; every four years, these countries play the<space/><link><target>MacRobertson International Croquet Shield</target><part>MacRobertson Shield</part></link><space/>tournament. Many other countries also play. The current world rankings<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wcfcroquet.org/Rankings/teamranking.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">WCF World Team Rankings<space/></arg><arg name="date">8 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">World Croquet Federation<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>show England in top place for association croquet, followed by Australia and New Zealand sharing second place, with the United States in fourth position; the same four countries appear in the top six of the golf croquet league table, below Egypt in top position, and with South Africa at number five.</paragraph><paragraph>Croquet is popularly believed to be viciously competitive.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;So they left the subject and played croquet, which is a very good game for people who are annoyed at each other, giving many opportunities for venting rancour.&quot;<space/><link><target>Rose Macaulay</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Towers of Trebizond</italics></extension><space/>This may derive from the fact that (unlike in golf) players will often attempt to move their opponents' balls to unfavourable positions. However, purely negative play is rarely a winning strategy: successful players (in all versions other than golf croquet) will use all four balls to set up a break for themselves, rather than simply making the game as difficult as possible for their opponents. At championship-standard association croquet, players can often make all 26 points (13 for each ball) in two turns.</paragraph><paragraph>Croquet<space/><link><target>Croquet at the 1900 Summer Olympics</target><part>was an event</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>1900 Summer Olympics</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Roque</target></link>, an American variation on croquet,<space/><link><target>Roque at the 1904 Summer Olympics</target><part>was an event</part></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>1904 Summer Olympics</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Pronunciation</heading><paragraph>Like similar words with a French derivation, the final 't' is silent. British pronunciation puts the accent on the first syllable, American on the second: krke versus kroke.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Variations</heading><heading level='3'>Association</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Croquetplayers.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Croquet being played at a club in the UK. (Four balls are visible on the lawn, showing that two games are in progress (&quot;double-banking&quot;): red and black belong to one game, green and brown to the other)</part></link>Association croquet is the name of an advanced game of croquet, played at international level. It involves four balls teamed in pairs, with both balls going through every hoop for one pair to win. The game's distinguishing feature is the &quot;croquet&quot; shot: when certain balls hit other balls, extra shots are allowed. The six hoops are arranged three at each end of the court, with a centre peg.</paragraph><paragraph>In association croquet one side takes the black and blue balls, the other takes red and yellow.At each turn, players can choose to play with either of their balls for that turn.At the start of a turn, the player plays a stroke. If the player either hits the ball through the correct hoop (&quot;runs&quot; the hoop), or hits another ball (a &quot;roquet&quot;), the turn continues.Following a roquet, the player picks up his or her own ball and puts it down next to the ball that it hit. The next shot is played with the two balls touching: this is the &quot;croquet stroke&quot; from which the game takes its name.</paragraph><paragraph>After the croquet stroke, the player plays a &quot;continuation&quot; stroke, during which the player may again attempt to make a roquet or run a hoop. Each of the other three balls may be roqueted once in a turn before a hoop is run, after which they become available to be roqueted again.The winner of the game is the team who completes the set circuit of six hoops (and then back again the other way), with both balls, and then strikes the centre peg (making a total of 13 points per ball = 26).</paragraph><paragraph>Good players may make &quot;breaks&quot; of several hoops in a single turn. The best players may take a ball round a full circuit in one turn. &quot;Advanced play&quot; (a variant of association play for expert players) gives penalties to a player who runs certain hoops in a turn, to allow the opponent a chance of getting back into the game; feats of skill such as triple peels or better, in which the partner ball (or occasionally an opponent ball) is caused to run a number of hoops in a turn by the striker's ball help avoid these penalties.</paragraph><paragraph>A handicap system ('bisques') provides less experienced players a chance of winning against more formidable opponents. Players of all ages and both sexes compete on level terms.</paragraph><paragraph>The World Championships are organised by the<space/><link><target>World Croquet Federation</target></link><space/>(WCF)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wcfcroquet.org/<space/></arg><arg name="title">WFC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">9 September 2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>World Croquet Federation<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>and usually take place every 2 or 3 years. The New Zealand team won the last<space/><link><target>MacRobertson International Croquet Shield</target></link><space/>tournament, which is the major international test tour trophy in association croquet. It is contested every three to four years between Australia, Great Britain, the United States and New Zealand. Historically the British have been the dominant force, winning 14 times out of the 20 times the event has been held. In individual competition, the UK is often divided by subnational country (England, Scotland and<space/><link><target>Wales</target></link>), while Northern Ireland joins with the republic in an All Ireland association (as it does in other sports). As of 2015, the Association Croquet World Champion is Robert Fletcher of Australia and the Women's Association Croquet World Champion is Miranda Chapman of England.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.croquetrecords.com/records/womensworlds/worlds2015.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Women's World Championship</arg><arg name="date">1 August 2015<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Croquet Records Website</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 August 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The world's top 10 association croquet players as of February 2014 are Robert Fletcher (Australia),<space/><link><target>Chris Clarke (croquet player)</target><part>Chris Clarke</part></link><space/>(New Zealand),<space/><link><target>Reg Bamford (croquet player)</target><part>Reg Bamford</part></link><space/>(South Africa), Paddy Chapman (New Zealand), Aaron Westerby (New Zealand), Greg Bryant (New Zealand), Toby Garrison (New Zealand),<space/><link><target>Robert Fulford (croquet player)</target><part>Robert Fulford</part></link><space/>(England), David Maugham (England), and Jamie Burch (England).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chris Williams"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://butedock.demon.co.uk/cgs/rank.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">Croquet Grading System<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Chris<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 May 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unlike most sports, men and women compete and are ranked together. Three women have won the British Open Championship:<space/><link><target>Lily Gower</target></link><space/>in 1905, Dorothy Steel in 1925, 1933, 1935 and 1936, and Hope Rotherham in 1960. While male players are in the majority at club level in the UK, the opposite is the case in Australia and New Zealand.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chris Williams"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The governing body in England is The<space/><link><target>Croquet Association</target></link>, which has been the driving force of the development of the game. The rules and tournament regulations are now maintained by the International Laws Committee, established by the croquet associations of England and Wales (CA), Australia (ACA), New Zealand (CNZ) and the United States (USCA).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Golf</heading><paragraph>In golf croquet, a hoop is won by the first ball to go through each hoop. Unlike association croquet, there are no additional turns for hitting other balls.</paragraph><paragraph>Each player takes a stroke in turn, each trying to hit a ball through the same hoop. The sequence of play is blue, red, black, yellow. Blue and black balls play against red and yellow. When a hoop is won, the sequence of play continues as before. The winner of the game is the player/team who wins the most hoops.</paragraph><paragraph>Golf croquet is the fastest-growing version of the game,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.croquet.org.uk/ca/survey/2007/survey.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20101121030026/http://croquet.org.uk/ca/survey/2007/survey.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>21 November 2010<space/></arg><arg name="title">Older, Wealthier and with a bit to Think about<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kevin<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Carter<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Croquet Association</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 November 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>owing largely to its simplicity and competitiveness. There is an especially large interest with competitive success by players in<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Egypt v Rest of World GC Event<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.croquet.org.uk/news/newsdb.asp?NewsID</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Williams<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Roehampton Club<space/></arg><arg name="date">21 July 2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Croquet Association<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>Golf croquet is easier to learn and play, but requires strategic skills and accurate play. In comparison with association croquet, play is faster and balls are more likely to be lifted off the ground.</paragraph><paragraph>In April 2013,<space/><link><target>Reg Bamford</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link><space/>beat Ahmed Nasr of Egypt in the final of the Golf Croquet World Championship in Cairo, becoming the first person to simultaneously hold the title in both association croquet and golf croquet.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Reg Bamford won the WCF GC Championship to become the first AC & GC World Champion<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tim<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>King<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Cairo<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>28 April 2013<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://www.croquet.org.uk/?p</arg><arg name="publisher">The Croquet Association<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>30 September 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>As of 2011, the Women's Golf Croquet World Champion was Rachel Rowe (England).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.croquet.org.uk/?p</arg><arg name="date">26 November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rachel Rowe won the 4th WCF Women's World Golf Croquet Championship<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="last1"><space/>Larsson<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Tim<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>King<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Bay of Plenty, New Zealand<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The Croquet Association<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">4 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Garden</heading><paragraph>Garden croquet is widely played in the UK. The rules are easy to learn and the game can be played on lawns of almost any size but usually around<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>32</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="disp">x</arg><arg><space/>wide (</arg><arg>)</arg></template><space/>by<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>40</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg name="disp">x</arg><arg><space/>long (</arg><arg>)</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>. The rules are similar to those described above for Association Croquet with three major differences:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The starting point for all balls is a spot three feet in from the boundary directly in front of hoop1.<space/></listitem><listitem>If a strikers ball goes off, there is no penalty, it comes back on three feet and the turn continues.</listitem><listitem>In a croquet stroke the croqueted ball does not have to move when the strikers ball is struck.</listitem></list><paragraph>This version of the game is easy for beginners to learn. The main Garden Croquet Club in the UK is the Bygrave Croquet Club which is a private club with five lawns. Other clubs also use garden croquet as an introduction to the game, notably the Hampstead Heath Croquet Club and the Watford Croquet Club.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:TwilightCroquet4034.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>An American game of croquet at twilight</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>American six-wicket</heading><paragraph>The American rules version of croquet, another six-hoop game, is the dominant version of the game in the United States and is also widely played in<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>. It is<space/><link><target>Sports governing body</target><part>governed</part></link><space/>by the<space/><link><target>United States Croquet Association</target></link>. Its genesis is mostly in association croquet, but it differs in a number of important ways that reflect the home-grown traditions of American &quot;backyard&quot; croquet.</paragraph><paragraph>Two of the most notable differences are that the balls are always played in the same sequence (blue, red, black, yellow) throughout the game, and that a ball's &quot;deadness&quot; on other balls is carried over from turn to turn until the ball has been &quot;cleared&quot; by scoring its next hoop. Tactics are simplified on the one hand by the strict sequence of play, and complicated on the other hand by the continuation of deadness. A further difference is the more restrictive boundary-line rules of American croquet.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ian Plummer"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.oxfordcroquet.com/laws/usca/index.asp<space/></arg><arg name="title">Association vs US (6-wicket) Rules Croquet<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ian<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Plummer<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 January 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford Croquet<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 February 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the American game, roqueting a ball out of bounds or running a hoop out of bounds causes the turn to end, and balls that go out of bounds are replaced only<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>9</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="spell">in</arg></template><space/>from the boundary rather than a yard (<template><target>Convert</target><arg>1</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg>cm</arg><arg name="disp"><space/>out</arg></template>) as in association croquet.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ian Plummer"></extension><space/>&quot;Attacking&quot; balls on the boundary line to bring them into play is thus far more challenging.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Nine-wicket</heading><paragraph>Nine-wicket croquet, sometimes called &quot;backyard croquet&quot;, is played mainly in Canada and the United States, and is the game most recreational players in those countries call simply &quot;croquet&quot;. This version of croquet varies from six-wicket croquet in that there are nine wickets, two stakes, and players can compete individually with a single ball, or as teams of two or three, with up to six players competing. The course is arranged in a double-diamond pattern, with one stake at each end of the course. Players start at one stake, navigate one side of the double diamond, hit the turning stake, then navigate the opposite side of the double diamond and hit the starting stake to win the game.</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike six-wicket croquet, where each time a ball is roqueted a croquet shot must be taken, players have three options after roqueting another ball. These reflect the more individual aspect of nine-wicket croquet. The options are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Nothing:</bold><space/>The player may leave the ball where it came to rest and take two shots.</listitem><listitem><bold>Mallet-head Length:</bold><space/>Players may place their ball a mallet-head's length or less from the ball he hit, and take 2 shots.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.9wicketcroquet.com/rules/26/backyard-croquet-basic-rules</extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Croquet:</bold><space/>As in six-wicket croquet, players may place their ball in contact with the ball they hit and strike their ball in such a way that both balls move. When making this shot, player may place their ball next to the ball they hit, place their hand or foot on top of their ball, then strike their own ball such that their opponent's ball moves while their own ball remains in place. A foot shot is sometimes called a &quot;buggy ride&quot;. They may then take their second shot as a &quot;continuation shot&quot;</listitem></list><paragraph>Ordinarily, the first person to finish the course wins the game. However, some players prefer to use an endgame procedure called &quot;poison&quot;. In poison, once a player has scored the last hoop but has not hit the starting stake, their ball becomes &quot;poison&quot;, which allows them to eliminate other balls from the game by roqueting them. If a non-poison ball roquets a poison ball, the standard roqueting options apply, but if a poison ball travels through a wicket or hits a stake for any reason, it forfeits and is eliminated from the game. The last person remaining is the winner.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.9wicketcroquet.com/rules/28/backyard-croquet-challenging-options#option6</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ricochet</heading><paragraph>This version of the game was invented by John Riches of Adelaide, Australia with help from Tom Armstrong in the 1980s. The game can be played by up to 6 people and is very easy to learn. For this reason it is often used as a stepping stone to association croquet. Ricochet has similar rules to association and garden croquet, except that when a ball is roqueted, the striker's ball remains live and two free shots are earned. This enables strikers to play their ball near to another opponent ball and ricochet that too thus earning two more free shots. Running a hoop earns one free shot.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Glossary of terms</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:CroquetConverse4037.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Backyard croquet being played in rough grass with inexpensive equipment, United States, 2009</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Backward ball</bold>: The ball of a side that has scored fewer hoops (compare with 'forward ball').<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Complete Croquet: A Guide to Skills, Tactics, and Strategy</arg><arg name="first"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Hawkins</arg><arg name="publisher">Crowood Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-84797-168-5</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Ball-in-hand</bold>: A ball that the striker can pick up to change its position, for example:</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='numbered'><listitem>any ball when it leaves the court has to be replaced on the yard-line</listitem><listitem>the strikers ball after making a roquet must be placed in contact with the roqueted ball</listitem><listitem>the strikers ball when the striker is entitled to a lift.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.croquet.org.uk/association/laws/6th/laws_6th.htm'>Laws of Association Croquet</link></italics>, 6th Edition, amended 2008, Croquet Association.</extension></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Ball in play</bold>: A ball after it has been played into the game, which is not a ball in hand or pegged out.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Baulk</bold>: An imaginary line on which a ball is placed for its first shot in the game, or when taking a lift. The A-baulk coincides with the western half of the yard line along the south boundary; the B-baulk occupies the eastern half of the north boundary yard line.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Bisque, half-bisque</bold><space/>A bisque is a free turn in a handicap match. A half-bisque is a restricted handicap turn in which no point may be scored.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Break down:</bold><space/>To end a turn by making a mistake.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Continuation stroke</bold>: Either the bonus stroke played after running a hoop in order or the second bonus stroke played after making a roquet.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Croquet stroke</bold>: A stroke taken after making a roquet, in which the striker's ball and the roqueted ball are placed together in contact.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Double tap</bold>: A fault in which the mallet makes more than one audible sound when it strikes the ball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Forward ball</bold>: The ball of a side that has scored more hoops (compare with 'backward ball').<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Hoop</bold>: Metal U-shaped gate pushed into ground.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension><space/>(Also called a<space/><bold>wicket</bold><space/>in the US).<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2009</arg></template></listitem><listitem><bold>Leave</bold>: The position of the balls after a successful break, in which the striker is able to leave the balls placed so as to make life as difficult as possible for the opponent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Lift</bold>: A turn in which the player is entitled to remove the ball from its current position and play instead from either baulk line. A lift is permitted when a ball has been placed by the opponent in a position where it is wired from all other balls, and also in advanced play when the opponent has completed a break that includes hoops 1-back or 4-back.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Object ball</bold>: A ball which is going to be rushed.</listitem><listitem><bold>Peg out</bold>: To cause a rover ball to strike the peg and conclude its active involvement in the game.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Peel</bold>: To send a ball other than the striker's ball through its target hoop.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Pioneer</bold>: A ball placed in a strategic position near the striker's next-but-one or next-but-two hoop, to assist in running that hoop later in the break.</listitem><listitem><bold>Primary colours</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>first colours</bold>: The main croquet ball colours used which are blue, red, black and yellow (in order of play). Blue and black, and red and yellow, are played by the same player or pair.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Push</bold>: A fault when the mallet pushes the striker's ball, rather than making a clean strike.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Roquet</bold>: (Second syllable rhymes with &quot;play&quot;.) When the strikers ball hits a ball that he is entitled to then take a croquet shot with. At the start of a turn, the striker is entitled to roquet all the other three balls once. Once the striker's ball goes through its target hoop, it is again entitled to roquet the other balls once.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Rover ball</bold>: A ball that has run all 12 hoops and can be pegged out.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Rover hoop</bold>: The last hoop, indicated by a red top bar. The first hoop has a blue top.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Run a hoop</bold>: To send the strikers ball through a hoop. If the hoop is the hoop in order for the strikers ball, the striker earns a bonus stroke.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Rush</bold>: A roquet when the roqueted ball is sent to a specific position on the court, such as the next hoop for the strikers ball or close to a ball that the striker wishes to roquet next.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Scatter shot</bold>: A continuation stroke used to hit a ball which may not be roqueted in order to send it to a less dangerous position.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Secondary colours</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>second colours</bold>; also known as<space/><bold>alternate colours</bold>:<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension><space/>The colours of the balls used in the second game played on the same court in double-banking: green, pink, brown and white (in order of play). Green and brown versus pink and white, are played by the same player or pair.<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Sextuple peel</bold><space/>(<bold>SXP</bold>): To peel the partner ball through its last six hoops in the course of a single turn. Very few players have achieved this feat, but it is being seen increasingly at championship level.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Tice</bold>: A ball sent to a location that will entice an opponent to shoot at it but miss.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Triple peel</bold><space/>(<bold>TP</bold>): To send a ball other than the strikers ball through its last three hoops, and then peg it out. See also<space/><link><target>Triple Peel</target></link>, A variant is the<space/><bold>Triple Peel on Opponent</bold><space/>(TPO), where the peelee is the opponent's ball rather than the partner ball. The significance of this manoevre is that in advanced play, making a break that includes the tenth hoop (called 4-back) is penalized by granting the opponent a lift (entitling him to take the next shot from either baulk line). Therefore, many breaks stop voluntarily with three hoops and the peg still to run.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Wired</bold>: When a hoop or the peg impedes the path of a striker's ball, or the swing of the mallet. A player will often endeavour to finish a turn with the opponent's balls wired from each other.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hawkins"></extension></listitem><listitem><bold>Yard line</bold>: An imaginary line one yard from the boundary. Balls that go off the boundary are generally replaced on the yard line (but if this happens on a croquet stroke, the turn ends).<extension extension_name='ref' name="laws"></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>In art and literature</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Edouard Manet 012.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''The Croquet Game'',<space/><link><target>douard Manet</target></link>, 1873</part></link><link><target>File:Louise Abbma - A Game of Croquet.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Louise Abbma</target></link>, ''A Game of Croquet'' (<link><target>Trouville-sur-Mer</target><part>Trouville</part></link>, 1872), private collection</part></link>The way croquet is depicted in paintings and books says much about popular perceptions of the game, though little about the reality of modern play.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1868 a song titled<space/><italics>Croquet</italics><space/>(essentially anonymous: by M.B.C.S and W.O.F.) was included in a popular song book by W. O. Perkins,<space/><italics>The Golden Robin</italics><space/>(Pub.<space/><link><target>Oliver Ditson &amp; Company</target></link>, New York). (&quot;Upon the smoothly shaven lawn, Beneath the skies of May, Oh, boys and girls, this merry morn, Come out and play Croquet ...&quot;); there are four full verses.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Winslow Homer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>douard Manet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Louise Abbma</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Pierre Bonnard</target></link><space/>all have paintings titled<space/><italics>The Croquet Game.</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Norman Rockwell</target></link><space/>often depicted the game, including in his painting<space/><italics>Croquet.</italics></listitem><listitem>A favorite subject of<space/><link><target>Edward Gorey</target></link>, a croquet reference often appeared in the first illustration of his books.<space/><italics><link><target>Edward Gorey#Books</target><part>The Epiplectic Bicycle</part></link></italics><space/>opens with two illustrations of the main characters playing with croquet mallets.</listitem><listitem><link><target>H. G. Wells</target></link><space/>wrote<space/><italics>The Croquet Player,</italics><space/>which uses croquet as a metaphor for the way in which people confront the very problem of their own existence.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lewis Carroll</target></link><space/>featured a<space/><link><target>Literary nonsense</target><part>nonsense</part></link><space/>version of the game in the popular children's novel<space/><italics><link><target>Alice's Adventures in Wonderland</target></link></italics>: a hedgehog was used as the ball, a flamingo as the mallet, and playing cards as the hoops.</listitem><listitem>In the<space/><italics><link><target>Thursday Next</target></link></italics><space/>series of novels, notably<space/><italics><link><target>Something Rotten</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Jasper Fforde</target></link><space/>depicts an<space/><link><target>Parallel universe (fiction)</target><part>alternative world</part></link><space/>in which croquet is a brutal mass spectator sport.</listitem><listitem>In the 1988 film<space/><italics><link><target>Heathers</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Winona Ryder</target></link><space/>and her friends, the Heathers, are depicted as playing croquet, though at the beginning, the Heathers are playing croquet to hit someone on the head.</listitem><listitem>The cover of the 1971 Genesis album &quot;Nursery Cryme&quot; shows Cynthia, a character in the song 'Musical Box' holding a croquet mallet with a few heads on the playing field including another character of the song Henry's head that she removed with said mallet.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>In politics</heading><paragraph>On 25 May 2006, the then<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>British</part></link><space/><link><target>Deputy Prime Minister</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Prescott</target></link>, was photographed by<space/><italics><link><target>The Mail on Sunday</target></link></italics><space/>playing croquet at his official residence,<space/><link><target>Dorneywood</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://property.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,14049-2206420,00.html</arg><arg name="title">Prescott Quits Country House to Save Skin</arg><arg name="last">Webster</arg><arg name="first">Philip</arg><arg name="date">1 June 2006</arg><arg name="work">The Times</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>Following shortly after a sex scandal<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/uk_politics/4945170.stm</arg><arg name="title">Prescott Admits Affair with Aide</arg><arg name="date">28 April 2006</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2009<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News</arg></template></extension><space/>that had forced Prescott to resign his ministerial responsibilities while retaining his salary and privileges,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.timesonline.co.uk/article/0,,17129-2167472,00.html</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Prescott loses his dream home: the mega-department</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Knight</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Sam</arg><arg name="date"><space/>5 May 2006</arg><arg name="work">The Times</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2009<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>the incident was portrayed as evidence that Prescott had little real responsibility for running the country during the absence of the Prime Minister. Shortly afterwards, Prescott announced that he would no longer make use of the Dorneywood residence.</paragraph><paragraph>It was also reported that the incident led to a 300% increase in sales of croquet equipment at<space/><link><target>Asda</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-388666/Prescott-helps-croquet-sets-sales-soar.html</arg><arg name="title">Prescott helps croquet sets sales soar</arg><arg name="date">1 June 2006</arg><arg name="work"><space/>Daily Mail</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>while the TV channel<space/><link><target>Channel 5 (UK)</target><part>Five</part></link><space/>announced that they would be running a series featuring croquet matches played at country houses pitting &quot;rich&quot; against &quot;poor&quot; players.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://politics.guardian.co.uk/media/story/0,,1789053,00.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Five pitches rich v poor in pro-celebrity croquet</arg><arg name="last">Busfield</arg><arg name="first">Steve</arg><arg name="date">2 June 2006</arg><arg name="work">The Guardian</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 May 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Clubs</heading><paragraph>About 200 croquet clubs across the United States are members of the United States Croquet Association.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.croquetamerica.com/usca/directory/clubs/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Clubs Directory<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">United Statese Croquet Association<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>USCA-affiliated clubs in major US cities include the New York, Chicago, Beverly Hills, Denver, Phoenix, San Francisco, Oakland, Houston, Boston, Detroit, Kansas City, Louisville, Seattle, and Portland Croquet Clubs.</paragraph><paragraph>Many colleges have croquet clubs as well, such as<space/><link><target>The University of Virginia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>The University of Chicago</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pennsylvania State University</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.athletics.psu.edu/recreation/clubs.asp?Club_ID</arg><arg name="title">Penn State Club Sports</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Bates College</target></link>,<space/><link><target>State_University_of_New_York_at_New_Paltz</target><part>SUNY New Paltz</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Harvard University</target></link>. Notably,<space/><link><target>St. John's College (Annapolis/Santa Fe)</target><part>St. John's College</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>US Naval Academy</target></link><space/>engage in a yearly match in<space/><link><target>Annapolis, Maryland</target></link>. Both schools also compete at the collegiate level and the rivalry continues to be an Annapolis tradition, attracting thousands of spectators each April.</paragraph><paragraph>In England and Wales, there are around 170 clubs affiliated with the Croquet Association.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.croquet.org.uk/clubs/index.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Clubs and Federations<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The Croquet Association<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>The larger clubs include Bowdon,<space/><link type='external' href='http://Cheltenhamcroquet.org'>Cheltenham</link>, Edgbaston, Surbiton, Guildford and Godalming, Nailsea, Nottingham, Roehampton, Sidmouth, and Woking. The<space/><link><target>All England Lawn Tennis and Croquet Club</target></link><space/>at Wimbledon is famous for its<space/><link><target>lawn tennis</target></link><space/>tournament, but retains an active croquet section. At the other end of the scale and also affiliated to the Croquet Association is<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bygravecroquetclub.org.uk'>Bygrave Croquet Club</link><space/>which specialises in playing and promoting Garden Croquet. There are also clubs in many Universities and Colleges, with an annual Varsity match being played between Oxford and Cambridge.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://users.ox.ac.uk/~croquet/varsity/archive.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Varsity Archive<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Croquet Club<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>With over 1800 participants, the 2011 Oxford University &quot;Cuppers&quot; (inter-college) tournament claimed to be not only the largest croquet tournament ever, but the largest sporting event in the University.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Oxford University Croquet Club - Welcome!<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://users.ox.ac.uk/~croquet/college/cuppersintro.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Users.ox.ac.uk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>3 November 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Scotland, the Edinburgh Croquet Club exists.<extension extension_name='ref' name="C"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Croquet Hall of Fame</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Extreme croquet</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Jaques of London</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Intercollegiate sports team champions#Croquet</target><part>US intercollegiate croquet champions</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Croquet</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.oakleywoods.com/'>Links</link><space/>to all national associations, where to play, rules, history, court layouts</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.oxfordcroquet.com/coach/synopsis/index.asp'>A Synopsis of the Laws of Association Croquet</link>, from Oxford Croquet</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.croquetamerica.com/croquet/rules/american/synopsis/'>Synopsis of American Croquet</link>, from the<space/><link><target>United States Croquet Association</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.9wicketcroquet.com/rules/'>The official rules of Backyard Croquet</link><space/>(nine-wicket layout), from the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.croquetamerica.com/'>United States Croquet Association</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://www.croquet.org.uk/garden/'>Official Rules of Garden Croquet</link><space/>(British six-hoop garden croquet)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.croquet.com/croquet/croquetrulesarticle.cfm'>Croquet Rules and Regulations</link>, from<space/><italics>Croquet.com</italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.croquet.org.uk/index.asp?section=tech&amp;amp;page=other%2fjargon.html'>The Croquet Association Jargon List</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://digitalcollections.library.ubc.ca/cdm/landingpage/collection/arkley'>Arkley Croquet Collection</link><space/>An exceptional selection of paintings, cartoons and photographs depicting the game of croquet, from UBC Library Digital Collections</listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Croquet</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Former Summer Olympic sports</target></link><link><target>Category:Lawn games</target></link><link><target>Category:Sports originating in England</target></link></paragraph></article>