<article title='Contra_dance'><paragraph><template><target>contra dance</target></template><link><target>Image:Peterborough contra dance November 2007 90739.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Contra dancers in<space/><link><target>Peterborough, New Hampshire</target><part>Peterborough</part></link>,<space/><link><target>New Hampshire</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Contra dance</bold><space/>(also<space/><bold>contradance</bold>,<space/><bold>contra-dance</bold><space/>and other variant spellings) refers to a folk dance, similar to a<space/><link><target>square dance</target></link>, except instead of the square formation, it is danced in lines of couples, with every other couple facing up or down the hall. It has mixed origins from<space/><link><target>English country dance</target></link>, Scottish, French dance styles in the 17th century, with strong African influence from Appalachia. Sometimes described as<space/><link><target>New England</target></link><space/>folk dance or<space/><link><target>Appalachia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>folk dance, contra dances can be found around the world and have much popularity in<space/><link><target>North America</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>where weekly or monthly dances and annual dance weekends are common. According to the Contra Dance Links website, contra dancing can be found in all 50 US states.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.contradancelinks.com/</arg><arg name="title">Contra Dance Links for the United States, Canada, and the World</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 May 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Considered a social dance that one can attend without a partner, but is danced in pairs, contra dancing is danced in long lines of couples/pairs formed starting from the stage and down the dance hall. Throughout the course of a dance, couples progress up and down these lines, dancing with each other couple in the line. The dance is led by a<space/><link><target>caller (dance)</target><part>caller</part></link><space/>who teaches the sequence of figures in the dance before the music starts. Callers describe the series of steps called &quot;figures&quot;, and in a single dance, a caller may include anywhere from 612 figures which are repeated as couples progress up and down the lines. Each figure takes 64 beats, after which the pattern is repeated. For more details, see<space/><link><target>Contra dance form</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The music played for contra dances includes, but is not limited to<space/><link><target>Folk music of Ireland</target><part>Irish</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Scottish music</target><part>Scottish</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Old-time music</target><part>old-time</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>French-Canadian music</target><part>French-Canadian</part></link><space/>folk tunes. The<space/><link><target>fiddle</target></link><space/>is considered the core instrument, though other stringed instruments such as the<space/><link><target>guitar</target></link>, banjo, bass and<space/><link><target>mandolin</target></link><space/>are played as well. Music in a dance can consist of a single tune or a medley of tunes, and<space/><link><target>key change</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>during the course of a dance are common.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>At the end of the 17th century, English<space/><link><target>country dance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were taken up by French dance masters. The French called these dances<space/><italics>contra-dances</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>contredanses</italics><space/>(which roughly translated &quot;opposites dance&quot;), as indicated in a 1710 dance book called<space/><italics>Recuil de Contredance</italics>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Holenko</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">4</arg></template><space/>As time progressed, these dances returned to England and were spread and reinterpreted in the United States, and eventually the French form of the name came to be associated with the American folk dances, where they were alternatively called &quot;country dances&quot; or in some parts of<space/><link><target>New England</target></link><space/>such as New Hampshire, &quot;contradances&quot;.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Laufman</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="p">158</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="OED"><paragraph><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://dictionary.oed.com/cgi/entry/50048899?single</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Contre-dance, -danse, contra-dance</arg><arg name="encyclopedia"><space/>Oxford English Dictionary, 2nd ed</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1989</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2006-11-01</arg></template></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>(as access to the</italics><space/>OED<space/><italics>online is not free, the relevant excerpt is provided)</italics><space/>&quot;Littr's theory, that there was already in 17th c. a French<space/><italics>contre-danse</italics><space/>with which the English word was confused and ran together, is not tenable; no trace of the name has been found in French before its appearance as an adaptation of the English. But new dances of this type were subsequently brought out in France, and introduced into England with the Frenchified form of the name, which led some Englishmen to the erroneous notion that the French was the original and correct form, and the English a corruption of it.&quot;</listitem></list></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Contra dances were fashionable in the United States and were considered one of the most popular social dances across class lines in the late 18th century, though these events were usually referred to as &quot;country dances&quot; until the 1780s, when the term contra dance became more common to describe these events.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Peterson</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">199–200</arg></template><space/>In the mid-19th century, group dances started to decline in popularity in favor of<space/><link><target>quadrilles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Les Lanciers</target><part>lancers</part></link>, and couple dances such as the<space/><link><target>waltz</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>polka</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Peterson</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">199–200</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Henry Ford</target></link>, founder of the<space/><link><target>Ford Motor Company</target></link>, had a role in preserving contra and American folk dancing generally, in part as a response in opposition to modern jazz influences in the United States.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlin</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">192</arg></template><space/>In the 1920s, he asked friend and dance coordinator in Massachusetts,<space/><link><target>Henry Lovett</target></link>, to come to Michigan to begin a dance program. Initially, Lovett could not as he was under contract at a local inn; consequently, Ford bought the property rights to the inn.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lowry"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Lowry</arg><arg name="first1">Klint</arg><arg name="title">Longtime contra dancing program comes to an end</arg><arg name="url">http://www.thenewsherald.com/stories/020205/lif_20050202001.shtml</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 January 2015</arg><arg name="work">The News-Herald</arg><arg name="publisher">Heritage Newspapers</arg><arg name="date">2 February 2005</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20080706015642/http://www.thenewsherald.com/stories/020205/lif_20050202001.shtml</arg><arg name="archivedate">6 July 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>Lovett and Ford initiated a dance program in<space/><link><target>Dearborn, Michigan</target></link><space/>that included several folk dances, including contras.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Spalding</arg><arg>2014</arg><arg name="p">147</arg></template><space/>Ford also published a book titled<space/><italics>Good Morning: After a Sleep of Twenty-Five Years, Old-Fashioned Dancing Is Being Revived</italics><space/>in 1926 detailing steps for some contra dances.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>La Chapelle</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="p">36</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1930s and 1940s, contra dances appear to have been done only in small towns in widely scattered parts of northeastern North America, such as<space/><link><target>Ohio</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Maritime provinces</target></link><space/>of Canada,<extension extension_name='ref'>Lois S. Fahs,<space/><italics>Swing Your Partner: Old Time Dances of New Brunswick and Nova Scotia</italics><space/>(Sackville, N.B.: The author, 1939).</extension><space/>and particularly northern New England.<space/><link><target>Ralph Page</target></link><space/>almost single-handedly maintained the New England tradition until it was revitalized in the 1950s and 1960s, particularly by<space/><link><target>Ted Sannella</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dudley Laufman</target></link>. The New England contra dance tradition was also maintained by the Ed Larkin Old Time Contra Dancers, formed by Edwin Loyal Larkin in 1934.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Palmer"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Palmer</arg><arg name="first1">Robin</arg><arg name="title">Ed Larkin dancers head for Tunbridge again</arg><arg name="url">http://timesargus.nybor.com/Story/71366.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 January 2015</arg><arg name="work">Barre-Times (Argus, Vermont)</arg><arg name="date">10 September 2003</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.contradancelinks.com/articles/vttunbridge20030910.html</arg><arg name="archivedate">31 October 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>The group he founded is still performing, teaching the dances, and holds monthly open house dances in Tunbridge.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Palmer"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="YTV"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Contra Dance Tunbridge Town Hall</arg><arg name="url">http://youngtraditionvermont.org/events/contra-dance-tunbridge-town-hall/</arg><arg name="website">Young Tradition Vermont</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 January 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>By then, early dance camps, retreats, and weekends had emerged, such as<space/><link><target>Pinewoods Dance Camp</target><part>Pinewoods Camp</part></link>, in<space/><link><target>Plymouth, Massachusetts</target></link>, which became primarily a music and dance camp in 1933,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pinewoods.org/pciHistory.shtml'>Pinewoods Camp History</link></extension><space/>and NEFFA, the<space/><link><target>New England Folk Festival</target></link>, also in Massachusetts, which began in 1944.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.neffa.org/history.html'>NEFFA History</link></extension><space/>These and others continue to be popular and some offer other dances and activities besides contra dancing.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1970s, Sannella and other callers introduced movements from<space/><link><target>English Country Dance</target></link>, such as<space/><link><target>contra dance choreography</target><part>heys and gypsies</part></link>, to the contra dances.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www-ssrl.slac.stanford.edu/~winston/ecd/gmurrow.htmlx'>how figures like heys and gypsies got into modern contradancing</link></extension><space/>New dances, such as<space/><italics>Shadrack's Delight</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Tony Parkes (caller)</target><part>Tony Parkes</part></link>, featured symmetrical dancing by all couples. (Previously, the actives and inactives see<space/><italics>Progression</italics><space/>below had significantly different roles). Double progression dances, popularized by Herbie Gaudreau,<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaudreau, Herbie,<space/><italics>Modern Contra Dancing</italics><space/>(Sandusky, OH: Square Dance Magazine, 1971).</extension><space/>added to the aerobic nature of the dances, and one caller,<space/><link><target>Gene Hubert</target></link>, wrote a quadruple progression dance,<space/><italics>Contra Madness</italics>. Becket formation was introduced, with partners next to each other in the line instead of opposite. The<space/><link><target>Brattleboro, Vermont</target><part>Brattleboro</part></link><space/>Dawn Dance started in 1976, and continues to run semiannually.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.dawndance.org/history.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A look at late-night dancing in the Brattleboro, VT area from the 1920s to the 1960s<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2007-01-15<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Michael McKernan<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Brattleboro Dawn Dances History<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.dawndance.org/'>Brattleboro Dawn Dances</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the early 1980s, Tod Whittemore started the first Saturday dance in the<space/><link><target>Peterborough, New Hampshire</target><part>Peterborough</part></link><space/>Town House, which remains one of the more popular regional dances.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.monadnockfolk.org/?page_id=30'>Peterborough Contra Dance</link></extension><space/>The Peterborough dance influenced<space/><link><target>Bob McQuillen</target></link><space/>who became a notable musician in New England. As musicians and callers moved to other locations, they founded contra dances in Michigan, Washington, Oregon, California, Texas, and elsewhere.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1970s, the Boston-area Lesbian and Gay Folk Dance was the first group regularly contra dancing without gender roles;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Nielsen</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">126</arg></template><space/>its dances were referred to as &quot;gender-free&quot; or &quot;gender-neutral&quot; dances. In 1981, a group in Minneapolis/St. Paul, MN, called &quot;Les be Gay and Dance&quot; was started, in which callers deliberately eliminated references to gender by avoiding the terms &quot;ladies&quot; or &quot;gents.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://epagepub.com/display_article.php?id</arg><arg name="title">Lavender Magazine – Issue 427 : Glimpses<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Epagepub.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-04</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1987, Chris Ricciotti started a gay dance group in Providence, RI, using the terms &quot;ladies&quot; and &quot;gents,&quot; although dancers were not lining up according to gender.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Nielsen</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">126</arg></template><space/>Other gender-free dance groups started in the area after that, and in 1989, at the gender-free dance group in Jamaica Plain, MA, a group of dancers led by Janet Dillon protested the use of these terms, and the armband system was devised: the traditionally male-role dancers would wear armbands and be called &quot;armbands&quot; or just &quot;bands,&quot; and the traditionally female-role dancers would be called &quot;bare arms&quot; or just &quot;bares.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.prescottvalleytribune.com/m/Articles.aspx?ArticleID</arg><arg name="title">Prescott Valley Tribune Mobile<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Prescottvalleytribune.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2013-10-30<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-04</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Events</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:ContraDanceCambridgeVFW.agr.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>A Thursday night contra dance at the Fresh Pond Veterans of Foreign Wars hall in<space/><link><target>Cambridge, Massachusetts</target></link>.</part></link>Unless explicitly labeled otherwise, contra dance events are open to all, regardless of experience. They are<space/><link><target>family-friendly</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>alcohol</target></link><space/>consumption is not part of the culture.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Sannella</arg><arg>1982</arg><arg name="p">12</arg><arg name="ps">: Although the author speaks of "public square dances," he is referring to the type of event that has come to be known as "contra dances." See also Steve Zakon, quoted in Dart 1995, chapter on "The Contra Dance Event."</arg></template><space/>Many events offer beginner-level instructions prior to the dance. A typical evening of contra dance is three hours long, including an intermission. The event consists of a number of individual<space/><italics>contra dances</italics>, divided by a scattering of other partner dances, perhaps one or more<space/><link><target>waltz</target><trail>es</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>schottische</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>polka</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or Swedish<space/><link><target>hambo</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In some places,<space/><link><target>square dance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are thrown into the mix. Music for the evening is typically performed by a live band, playing<space/><link><target>jig</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>reel (dance)</target><part>reels</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Ireland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>, or the<space/><link><target>United States</target><part>USA</part></link>. The tunes are<space/><link><target>traditional music</target><part>traditional</part></link><space/>and more than a century old, or modern compositions which follow the same form as the traditional pieces. Rarely, a rock tune will be woven in, to the delight of the dancers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Perpetual eMotion sing 'Eleanor Rigby'<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="title">5/6/11, 2 of 9: Perpetual e-Motion at the Concord Scout House</arg><arg name="accessdate">24 Oct 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Generally, a leader, known as a<space/><link><target>caller (dance)</target><part>caller</part></link>, will teach each individual dance just before the music for that dance begins. During this introductory walkthrough, participants learn the dance by walking through the steps and formations, following the caller's instructions. The caller gives the instructions orally, and sometimes augments them with demonstrations of steps by experienced dancers in the group. The walkthrough usually proceeds in the order of the moves as they will be done with the music; in some dances, the caller may vary the order of moves during the dance, a fact that is usually explained as part of the caller's instructions.</paragraph><paragraph>After the walkthrough, the music begins and the dancers repeat that sequence some number of times before that dance ends, often 10 to 15 minutes, depending on the length of the contra lines. Calls are normally given at least the first few times through, and often for the last. At the end of each dance, the dancers thank their partners. The contra dance tradition in North America is to change partners for every dance, while in the United Kingdom typically people dance with the same partner the entire evening. One who attends an evening of contra dances in North America does not need to bring his or her own partner. In the short break between individual dances, women and men invite each other to dance. Booking ahead by asking partner or partners ahead of time for each individual dance is common at some venues, but has been discouraged by some.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bobarcher.org/dance/uk_us_comparison.html'>English / American dancing - a comparison</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.musaique.com/contradance/articles/kevra-letter.html'>Susan Kevra's Letter to the Greenfield Contra Dancers</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gainesnet.com/booking.htm'>Dance Community Hospitality</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://ravitz.us/dance/call.php'>Notes on Calling Contra Dances</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most contra dances do not have a strict dress code.<extension extension_name='ref' name="contradance1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.contradance.org/html/new_dancer_info.php<space/></arg><arg name="title">CCD - What is Contra Dancing?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Contradance.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-05</arg></template></extension><space/>No special outfits are worn, but comfortable and loose-fitting clothing that does not restrict movement is usually recommended.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sactocds.org/NewWebsite/index.php/contra-dance-what-to-wear/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Contra Dance – What to Wear? &#124; Sacramento Country Dance Society<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sactocds.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-05</arg></template></extension><space/>Lightweight skirts are often worn,<extension extension_name='ref' name="contradance1"></extension><space/>at some dances by men as well as women, as these have a very pretty effect when swinging or twirling.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hatds.org/contra-faq.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Contra Dance in Houston, TX - Contra Dance Frequently Asked Questions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HATDS<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-12-05</arg></template></extension><space/>However, low, broken-in, soft-soled, non-marking shoes, such as dance shoes, sneakers, or sandals, are recommended and, in some places, required.<extension extension_name='ref' name="contradance1"></extension><space/>As dancing can be aerobic, dancers are sometimes encouraged to bring a change of clothes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CBDC"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Your first contra dance</arg><arg name="url">http://www.chicagobarndance.org/your-first-contra-dance/</arg><arg name="work">Chicago Barn Dance Company</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 December 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As in any social dance, cooperation is vital to contra dancing. Since over the course of any single dance, individuals interact with not just their partners but everyone else in the set, contra dancing might be considered a group activity. As will necessarily be the case when beginners are welcomed in by more practiced dancers, mistakes are made; most dancers are willing to help beginners in learning the steps. However, because the friendly, social nature of the dances can be misinterpreted or even abused, some groups have created anti-harassment policies.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CDSS-Social"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Social and Community Dynamics</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cdss.org/recruit-young-people.html#social</arg><arg name="work">Country Dance and Song Society</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 December 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="OFB"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Dance Guidelines</arg><arg name="url">http://www.oldfarmersball.com/newsletters/articles/guidelines.pdf</arg><arg name="work">Old Farmer’s Ball</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 December 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Form</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Contra dance form</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Formations</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Contra dance sets.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Contra dance sets, seen from the balcony of the town house of<space/><link><target>Peterborough, New Hampshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Although most people think a municipal hall is always called &quot;town hall,&quot; there is a long tradition of calling the building with town offices the &quot;town house&quot; as Peterborough calls their municipal building.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.townofpeterborough.com/index.asp?Type=B_BASIC&amp;amp;SEC=%7B492C637A-0E03-496F-A4D5-FF976BE0148B%7D'>Peterborough NH: Town House Rentals, Park Rentals &amp; Tent Rentals</link></extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Contra dances are arranged in long lines of couples. A pair of lines is called a<space/><italics>set</italics>. Sets are generally arranged so they run the length of the hall, with the<space/><italics>top</italics><space/>of the set being the end closest to the band and caller. Correspondingly, the<space/><italics>bottom</italics><space/>of the set is the end farthest from the caller.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pittman"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Pittman</arg><arg name="first1">Anne M.</arg><arg name="last2">Waller</arg><arg name="first2">Marlys S.</arg><arg name="last3">Dark</arg><arg name="first3">Cathy L.</arg><arg name="title">Dance a While: A Handbook for Folk, Square, Contra, and Social Dance, Tenth Edition</arg><arg name="date">2015</arg><arg name="publisher">Waveland Press</arg><arg name="isbn">1478629517</arg><arg name="page">197</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Couples consist of two people, traditionally but not necessarily one male and one female, typically referred to as the gent, gentleman or man, and lady or woman. Couples interact primarily with an adjacent couple for each round of the dance. Each sub-group of two interacting couples is known to choreographers as a<space/><italics>minor set</italics><space/>and to dancers as a<space/><italics>foursome</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>hands four</italics>. Couples in the same minor set are<space/><italics>neighbors</italics>. Minor sets originate at the head of the set, starting with the topmost dancers as the 1s (the<space/><italics>active couple</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>actives</italics>); the other couple are<space/><italics>2s</italics><space/>(or<space/><italics>inactives</italics>). The 1s are said to be<space/><italics>above</italics><space/>their neighboring 2s; 2s are<space/><italics>below</italics>. If there is an uneven number of couples dancing, the bottom-most couple will<space/><italics>wait out</italics><space/>the first time through the dance.</paragraph><paragraph>There are four common ways of arranging couples in the minor sets:<space/><italics>proper</italics>,<space/><italics>improper</italics>,<space/><italics>Becket</italics>, and<space/><italics>triple</italics><space/>formations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pittman"></extension><space/>There are many additional forms a contra dance may take. Five of them are:<space/><italics>triplet</italics>,<space/><italics>indecent</italics>,<space/><italics>four-face-four</italics>, and<space/><italics>whole-set</italics>. (For diagrams and full descriptions, see<space/><link><target>Contra dance form</target><part>Contra Dance Form</part></link><space/>main article.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Progression</heading><paragraph>A fundamental aspect of contra dancing is that the same dance, one time through which lasts roughly 30<space/><link><target>second</target><trail>s</trail></link>, is repeated over and over - but each time you dance with new neighbors. This change is effected by<space/><italics>progressing</italics><space/>the 1s<space/><italics>down</italics><space/>the set and progressing the 2s<space/><italics>up</italics><space/>(also<space/><italics>up the hall</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>down the hall</italics>; see the article on<space/><link><target>contra dance form</target></link><space/>for full characterizations of the progression in the eight dance forms mentioned above).</paragraph><paragraph>A single dance runs around ten minutes, long enough to progress 15-20 times. If the sets are short to medium length the caller will often try to run the dance until each couple has danced with every other couple both as a 1 and a 2 and returned to where they started. With longer sets (more than ~40 people) this would require long enough sets that the caller will usually only run the dance all the way around on (rare) non equal-turn dances.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Choreography</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Contra dance choreography</arg></template>Contra dance<space/><link><target>choreography</target></link><space/>specifies the dance formation, the<space/><italics>figures</italics>, and the sequence of those figures in a dance. Notably, contra dance figures (with a few exceptions) do not have defined footwork; within the limits of the music and the comfort of their fellow dancers, individuals move according to their own taste.</paragraph><paragraph>Most contra dances consist of a sequence of about 6 to 12 individual figures, prompted by the<space/><link><target>Caller (dance)</target><part>caller</part></link><space/>in time to the<space/><link><target>music</target></link><space/>as the figures are danced. As the sequence repeats, the caller may cut down his or her prompting, and eventually drop out, leaving the dancers to each other and the music.</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>figure</bold><space/>is a pattern of movement that typically takes eight<space/><italics>counts</italics>, although figures with four or 16 counts are also common. Each dance is a collection of figures assembled to allow the dancers to progress along the set (see &quot;Progression,&quot; above).</paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>count</bold><space/>(as used above) is one half of a<space/><link><target>bar (music)</target><part>musical measure</part></link>, such as one quarter note in 2/4 time or three eighth notes in 6/8 time. A count may also be called a<space/><italics>step</italics>, as contra dance is a walking form, and each count of a dance typically matches a single physical step in a figure.</paragraph><paragraph>Typical contra dance choreography comprises four<space/><bold>parts</bold>, each 16 counts (8 measures) long. The parts are called A1, A2, B1 and B2. This nomenclature stems from the music: Most contra dance tunes (as written) have two parts (A and B), each 8 measures long, and each fitting one part of the dance. The A and B parts are each played twice in a row, hence, A1, A2, B1, B2. While the same music is generally played in, for example, parts A1 and A2, distinct choreography is followed in those parts. Thus, a contra dance is typically 64<space/><italics>counts</italics>, and goes with a 32<space/><italics>measure</italics><space/>tune. Tunes of this form are called &quot;square&quot;; tunes that deviate from this form are called &quot;<link><target>crooked tune</target><part>crooked</part></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Sample contra dances:<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ibiblio.org/contradance/index/by_title.html'>Michael Dyck's Country Dance Index</link></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Traditional - the actives do most of the movement</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>Chorus Jig</italics><space/>(Proper duple minor)<list type='ident'><listitem>A1 (16) Actives down the outside and back. [The inactives stand still or substitute a swing]</listitem><listitem>A2 (16) Actives down the center, turn individually, come back, and cast off. [The inactives stand still for the first 3/4, take a step up the hall, and then participate in the cast]</listitem><listitem>B1 (16) Actives turn contra corners. [The inactives participate in half the turns]</listitem><listitem>B2 (16) Actives meet in the middle for a balance and swing, end swing facing up. [The inactives stand still]</listitem><listitem><bold>Note:</bold><space/>inactives will often clog in place or otherwise participate in the dance, even though the figures do not call for them to move.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Modern - the dance is symmetrical for actives and inactives</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><italics>Hay in the Barn</italics><space/>by Chart Guthrie (Improper duple minor)<list type='ident'><listitem>A1 (16) Neighbors balance and swing.</listitem><listitem>A2 (8) Ladies chain across, (8) Half hey, ladies pass right shoulders to start.</listitem><listitem>B1 (16) Partners balance and swing.</listitem><listitem>B2 (8) Ladies chain across, (8) Half hey, ladies pass right shoulders to start.</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Many modern contra dances have these characteristics:<extension extension_name='ref'>CONTRA DANCE CHOREOGRAPHY A Reflection of Social Change MARY McNAB DART 1995.</extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>longways for as many as will</listitem><listitem>first couples improper, or Becket formation</listitem><listitem>flowing choreography</listitem><listitem>no-one stationary for more than 16 beats (e.g. First Couple Balance &amp; Swing, finish facing down to make Lines of Four)</listitem><listitem>containing at least one swing and normally both a partner swing and a neighbour swing</listitem><listitem>the vast majority of the moves from a set of well-known moves that the dancers know already</listitem><listitem>composed mostly of moves that keep you connected to the other dancers</listitem><listitem>generally danced to 32 bar jigs or reels played at between 110 and 130 bpm</listitem><listitem>danced with a smooth walk with lots of spins and twirls</listitem></list><paragraph>An event which consists primarily (or solely) of dances in this style is sometimes referred to as a Modern Urban Contra Dance.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Music</heading><paragraph>The most common contra dance repertoire is rooted in the Anglo-Celtic tradition as it developed in North America.<space/><link><target>Folk music of Ireland</target><part>Irish</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Scottish music</target><part>Scottish</part></link>,<space/><link><target>French-Canadian music</target><part>French Canadian</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Old-time music</target><part>Old-time</part></link><space/>tunes are common, and<space/><link><target>Klezmer</target></link><space/>tunes have also been used. The old-time repertoire includes very few of the jigs common in the others.</paragraph><paragraph>Tunes used for a contra dance are nearly always &quot;square&quot; 64-beat tunes, in which one time through the tune is each of two 16-beat parts played twice (this is notated AABB). However, any 64-beat tune will do; for instance, three 8-beat parts could be played AABB AACC, or two 8-beat parts and one 16-beat part could be played AABB CC. Tunes not 64 beats long are called &quot;crooked&quot; and are almost never used for contra dancing, although a few crooked dances have been written as novelties.</paragraph><paragraph>In terms of instrumentation, fiddles are considered to be the primary instrument in contra dancing,<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Ledgin</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template><space/>though other stringed instruments can also be used, such as the<space/><link><target>mandolin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>banjo</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>guitar</target></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Holenko</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template><space/>Occasionally, percussion instruments are also used in contra dancing, such as the Irish<space/><link><target>bodhran</target></link><space/>or less frequently, the<space/><link><target>dumbek</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>washboard (musical instrument)</target><part>washboard</part></link>.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Holenko</arg><arg>2010</arg><arg name="p">5</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Until the 1970s it was traditional to play a single tune for the duration of a contra dance (about 5 to 10 minutes). Since then, contra dance musicians have typically played tunes in sets of two or three related (and sometimes contrasting) tunes, though single-tune dances are again becoming popular with some northeastern bands. In the Celtic repertoires it is common to change keys with each tune. A set might start with a tune in G, switch to a tune in D, and end with a tune in Bm. Here, D is related to G as its dominant (5th), while D and Bm share a key signature of two sharps. In the old-time tradition the musicians will either play the same tune for the whole dance, or switch to tunes in the same key. This is because the tunings of the banjo are key-specific. An old-time band might play a set of tunes in D, then use the time between dances to retune for a set of tunes in A. (Fiddlers also may take this opportunity to retune; tune- or key-specific fiddle tunings are uncommon in American Anglo-Celtic traditions other than old-time.)</paragraph><paragraph>In the Celtic repertoires it is most common for bands to play sets of reels and sets of jigs. However, since the underlying beat structure of jigs and reels is the same (two &quot;counts&quot; per bar) bands will occasionally mix jigs and reels in a set.</paragraph><paragraph>In recent years, younger contra dancers have begun establishing &quot;crossover contra&quot; or &quot;techno contra&quot; - contra dancing to techno, hip-hop, and other modern forms of music.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Forbes"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Forbes</arg><arg name="first1">Jeff</arg><arg name="title">Asheville and WNC folks helping grow ‘Techno contra’ dancing phenomenon</arg><arg name="url">https://mountainx.com/arts/art-news/asheville_and_wnc_folks_helping_grow_techno_contra_dancing_phenomenon/</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 June 2014</arg><arg name="work">Mountain Xpress</arg><arg name="date">17 September 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Neff"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Neff</arg><arg name="first1">Erin</arg><arg name="title">Contra Dance, Then and Now</arg><arg name="url">http://portlandcountrydance.org/download/footnotes_2010/Footnotes-July-Aug-10.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 June 2014</arg><arg name="work">Footnotes</arg><arg name="issue">July–August 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Portland Country Dance Community</arg></template></extension><space/>While challenging for DJs and callers, the fusion of contra patterns with moves from hip-hop, tango, and other forms of dance has made this form of contra dance a rising trend since 2008; it has become especially prevalent in Asheville, NC, but regular techno contra dance series are spreading up the East Coast to locales such as Charlottesville, VA, Washington, DC, Amherst, MA, and Greenfield, MA, with one-time or annual events cropping up in locations further West, including California and Washington state.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bob Dalsemer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quadrille</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ceili dance</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Carlin</arg><arg name="first1">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Folk.</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Infobase Pub.</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0816069786</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Daniels<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bruce Colin<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Puritans at Play: Leisure and Recreation in Colonial New England<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Palgrave Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-4039-7212-5<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template><space/>See chapter VI, &quot;Frolics for Fun: Dances, Weddings and Dinner Parties, pages 109 - 124.</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Dart<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mary McNab<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Contra Dance Choreography: A Reflection of Social Change<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Garland Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York & London<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cdss.org/elibrary/dart/index.htm<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2008-06-12<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8153-1984-3<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Holden<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rickey<space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>Frank Kaltman and Olga Kulbitsky</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Contra Dance Book
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[http://www.aads.be Anglo-American Dance Service]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1997<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Lovendegem, Belgium<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>90-802087-3-6<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template><space/>(Reprint: first published in 1956 by American Squares as a part of the<space/><italics>American Squares Dance Series</italics>)</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Holenko</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Contra Dance Encyclopedia</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Mel Bay Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">1609743776</arg><arg name="page">6</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jennings<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Larry<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Zesty Contras: A Selection of 500 New England Style Dances with a Provocative Explanatory Text<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[New England Folk Festival Association]]<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1983, revised with corrections 1988<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Cambridge Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jennings<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Larry<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Give-and-Take: A sequel to Zesty Contras, featuring 628 dances in the New England style, provocative remarks, exhortative essays and arcane analysis</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New England Folk Festival Association<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Cambridge, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Jennings<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Larry<space/></arg><arg name="coauthors"><space/>Dan Pearl and Ted Sannella<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Contra Connection & Basically for Callers: Reprints from the Country Dance and Song Society NEWS (2nd Edition)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Country Dance and Song Society<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Northampton, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-917024-14-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Keller</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Kate Van Winkle</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dance and Its Music in America, 1528-1789</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pendragon Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Hillsdale, NY<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-57647-127-2</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">La Chapelle</arg><arg name="first1">Peter</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Zuckerman</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Bruce</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Kun</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Josh</arg><arg name="editor3-last">Ansell</arg><arg name="editor3-first">Lisa</arg><arg name="title">The song is not the same : Jews and American popular music</arg><arg name="date">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Purdue University Press for the USC Casden Institute for the Study of the Jewish Role in American Life</arg><arg name="location">West Lafayette, Ind.</arg><arg name="isbn">1557535868</arg><arg name="pages">29–70</arg><arg name="chapter">"Dances Partake of the Racial Characteristics of the People Who Dance Them": Nordicism, Antisemitism, and Henry Ford's Old-Time Music and Dance Revivial</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Laufman</arg><arg name="first">Dudley Laufman, Jacqueline</arg><arg name="title">Traditional barn dances with calls & fiddling</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Human Kinetics</arg><arg name="location">Champaign, IL</arg><arg name="isbn">0736076123</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ledgin</arg><arg name="first">Stephanie P.</arg><arg name="title">Discovering Folk Music</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="isbn">0275993876</arg><arg name="page">17</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Linscott<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eloise Hubbard<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Folk Songs of Old New England
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Dover Publications<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>1993, a reprint of the 1963 2nd edition<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-486-27827-1<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template><space/>See chapter entitled &quot;Country Dancing,&quot; Pages 57 120. (The first edition was published in 1939.)</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Nielsen</arg><arg name="first">Erica M.</arg><arg name="title">Folk Dancing</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="location">Santa Barbara</arg><arg name="isbn">0313376891</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Nevell<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Richard<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A Time To Dance: American Country Dancing from Hornpipes to Hot Hash<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>St. Martin's Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1977<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-312-80522-7<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Parkes<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Tony<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Contra Dance Calling, A Basic Text<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Hands Four Productions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Bedford, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-9632880-1-1</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Peterson</arg><arg name="first">Davis R.</arg><arg name="title">Defining concise guide to United States popular culture</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">Bowling Green State University Popular Press</arg><arg name="location">Bowling Green, OH</arg><arg name="isbn">0879728213</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="editor">Ray Broadus Browne & Pat Browne</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sannella<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ted<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Ted Sannella<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Balance and Swing: A collection of fifty-five squares, contras and triplets in the New England tradition with music for each dance<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Country Dance and Song Society<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Northampton, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-917024-05-2<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sannella<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ted<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Swing the Next: A second collection of squares, contras, triplets and circles in the New England tradition, with music for each dance.<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Country Dance and Song Society<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Northampton, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-917024-05-2<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sannella<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Ted<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Calling Traditional New England Squares<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Country Dance and Song Society<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Northampton, Massachusetts<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-917024-16-8<space/></arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Spalding</arg><arg name="first1">Susan Eike</arg><arg name="title">Appalachian Dance: Creativity and Continuity in Six Communities</arg><arg name="date">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Illinois Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0252096452</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Contra dance associations</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cdss.org/'>Country Dance and Song Society (CDSS)</link><space/>preserves a variety of Anglo-American folk traditions in North America, including folk music, folk song, English country dance, contra dance and morris dance.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aads.be/'>Anglo-American Dance Service</link><space/>Based in Belgium, promoting contra dance and English dance in Western Europe.</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Descriptions &amp; definitions</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem>Gary Shapiro's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sbcds.org/contradance/whatis/'>What Is Contra Dance?</link></listitem><listitem>Hamilton Contra Dances<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.hamiltoncontra.ca/primer.html'>A Contra Dance Primer</link></listitem><listitem>Sharon Barrett Kennedy's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.art-rageous.net/Contradancing.html'>&quot;Now, What in the World is Contra Dancing?&quot;</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Different traditions and cultures in contra dance</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem>Colin Hume's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.colinhume.com/american.htm'>Advice to Americans in England</link></listitem><listitem>Mary Dart's book<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.westendweb.com/marydart/index.htm'>Contra Dance Choreography, A Reflection of Social Change</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Research resources</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem>University of New Hampshire Special Collections:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.izaak.unh.edu/nhltmd/'>New Hampshire Library of Traditional Music and Dance</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Finding contra dances</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://map.cdss.org/#types=contra'>CDSS Dance Map</link><space/>- interactive, crowd sourced map of contra and folk dances around the world</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.contradancelinks.com/'>Contra Dance Links</link><space/>- calendars and further links for the world</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thedancegypsy.com/'>The Dance Gypsy</link><space/>- locations of contra dances, and many other folk dances, around the world</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.neffa.org/Top/'>NEFFA LinkFest</link><space/>- indices of contra dances around the world, as well as callers and musicians</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='def'><listitem>In North America</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://simplifyconnections.appspot.com/?place=contraUSA'>Contra USA</link><space/>- participative map of US dances</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.contracorners.net/contra/links/dancemap.html'>Contra Corners</link><space/>- map of US dances</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tedcrane.com/DanceDB/'>Ted Crane's Dance Database</link></listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='def'><listitem>In France</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.infolk60.fr/def-contra-dance.php'>Contra dance in Paris</link><space/>- Contra dance in Paris and North France</listitem></list></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Photography and Video</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><list type='bullet'><listitem>A<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9veEzgGoO8Q'>video</link><space/>from the Concord Scout House in Massachusetts.</listitem><listitem>Doug Plummer's<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dougplummer.com/archives/contra/contra.html'>Northwest contra dance photos</link><space/>and<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.dougplummer.com/archives/newengland/contras.html'>New England contra dance photos</link></listitem><listitem>A<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=j9L0dz3qmsc'>video</link><space/>of the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.contracopia.net/sites/montpelier/'>Montpelier Vermont Contradance</link>, Will Mentor calling for Beeswax Sheepskin</listitem><listitem>Two American country dance<space/><link type='external' href='http://countrycorners.blogspot.com/'>films on DVD</link>: &quot;Country Corners&quot; (1976), and &quot;Full of Life A-Dancin'&quot; (1978).</listitem><listitem>A 2009 video of<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=-1cPyJWm-g4'>Crowfoot</link><space/>playing a contra dance, Tacoma, WA</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Contra Dance</target></template><link><target>Category:Contra dance</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Social dance</target></link></paragraph></article>