<article title='Divine_right_of_kings'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the Western tradition</arg><arg>the Eastern tradition</arg><arg>Mandate of Heaven</arg><arg>various rulers who claim a divine relationship</arg><arg>God emperor (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Monarchism</target><arg>Concepts</arg></template><template><target>Rights</target><arg>By claimant</arg></template><link><target>File:Louis XIV habill en soleil.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>190px</part><part><link><target>Louis XIV of France</target></link><space/>depicted as the Sun King.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>divine right of kings</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>divine right</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>politics</target><part>political</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>religion</target><part>religious</part></link><space/>doctrine of royal and<space/><link><target>political legitimacy</target></link>. It asserts that a<space/><link><target>monarch</target></link><space/>is subject to no earthly authority, deriving the right to rule directly from the will of<space/><link><target>God</target></link>. The king is thus not subject to the will of his people, the<space/><link><target>aristocracy</target></link>, or any other<space/><link><target>estate of the realm</target></link>, including (in the view of some, especially in Protestant countries or during the reign of Henry VIII of England) the Catholic Church. It is especially favored and promoted by unjust kings, because according to this doctrine, only God can judge an unjust king. The doctrine implies that any attempt to depose the king or to restrict his powers runs contrary to the will of God and may constitute a<space/><link><target>sacrilege</target><part>sacrilegious act</part></link>. It is often expressed in the phrase &quot;<link><target>by the Grace of God</target></link>,&quot; attached to the titles of a reigning monarch.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph>The remote origins of the theory are rooted in the medieval idea that God had bestowed earthly power on the king, just as God had given spiritual power and authority to the church, centering on the pope. The immediate author of the theory was<space/><link><target>Jean Bodin</target></link>,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="reason">are there no earlier writers?</arg><arg name="date">June 2012</arg></template><space/>who based it on the interpretation of<space/><link><target>Roman law</target></link>. With the rise of nation-states and the<space/><link><target>Protestant Reformation</target></link>, the theory of divine right justified the king's absolute authority in both political and spiritual matters. The theory came to the fore in England under the reign of<space/><link><target>James I of England</target></link><space/>(16031625, also known as James VI of Scotland 15671625).<space/><link><target>Louis XIV of France</target></link><space/>(16431715) strongly promoted the theory as well.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Scots texts of James VI of Scotland</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Scots language</target><part>Scots</part></link><space/>textbooks of the divine right of kings were written in 159798 by James VI of Scotland before his accession to the English throne. His<space/><italics><link><target>Basilikon Doron</target></link>,</italics><space/>a manual on the powers of a king, was written to edify his four-year-old son<space/><link><target>Henry Frederick, Prince of Wales</target><part>Henry Frederick</part></link><space/>that a king &quot;acknowledgeth himself ordained for his people, having received from the God a burden of government, whereof he must be countable.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>James I based his theories in part on his understanding of the Bible.</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>The state of monarchy is the supremest thing upon earth, for kings are not only God's lieutenants upon earth and sit upon God's throne, but even by God himself they are called gods. There be three principal [comparisons] that illustrate the state of monarchy: one taken out of the word of God, and the two other out of the grounds of policy and philosophy. In the Scriptures kings are called gods, and so their power after a certain relation compared to the Divine power. Kings are also compared to fathers of families; for a king is truly parens patriae [parent of the country], the politic father of his people. And lastly, kings are compared to the head of this microcosm of the body of man.<extension extension_name='ref' name="A speech to parliament"><link type='external' href='http://www.thenagain.info/Classes/Sources/JamesI.html'>A speech to parliament (1610)</link>.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>James' reference to &quot;God's Lieutenants&quot; is apparently a reference to the controversial text in Romans 13, where Paul refers to &quot;God's ministers.&quot;<extension extension_name='blockquote'>(1) Let every soul be subject unto the higher powers. For there is no power but of God: the powers that be are ordained of God. (2) Whosoever therefore resisteth the power, resisteth the ordinance of God: and they that resist shall receive to themselves damnation. (3) For rulers are not a terror to good works, but to the evil. Wilt thou then not be afraid of the power? do that which is good, and thou shalt have praise of the same: (4) For he is the minister of God to thee for good. But if thou do that which is evil, be afraid; for he beareth not the sword in vain: for he is the minister of God, a revenger to execute wrath upon him that doeth evil. (5) Wherefore ye must needs be subject, not only for wrath, but also for conscience sake. (6) For this cause pay ye tribute also: for they are God's ministers, attending continually upon this very thing. (7) Render therefore to all their dues: tribute to whom tribute is due; custom to whom custom; fear to whom fear; honour to whom honour.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Romans 13">https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=romans+13&amp;version=KJV Romans 13:1-7</extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Western conceptions</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Sacred king</arg><arg>Theocracy</arg></template>The conception of<space/><link><target>ordination</target></link><space/>brought with it largely unspoken parallels with the<space/><link><target>Anglican</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Priesthood (Catholic Church)</target><part>Catholic priesthood</part></link>, but the overriding metaphor in James's handbook was that of a father's relation to his children. &quot;Just as no misconduct on the part of a father can free his children from obedience to the<space/><link><target>Ten Commandments</target><part>fifth commandment</part></link>&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>that is, the commandment: &quot;Honor your father ...&quot; etc., which is the fifth in the reckoning usual among Jewish, Orthodox, and Protestant denominations, but to be according to the law, yet is he not bound thereto but of his good will ...&quot;</extension><space/>James also had printed his<space/><italics>Defense of the Right of Kings</italics><space/>in the face of English theories of inalienable popular and clerical rights. The divine right of kings, or divine-right theory of kingship, is a political and religious doctrine of royal and political legitimacy. It asserts that a monarch is subject to no earthly authority, deriving his right to rule directly from the will of God. The king is thus not subject to the will of his people, the aristocracy, or any other estate of the realm, including (in the view of some, especially in Protestant countries) the church. A weaker or more moderate form of this political theory does hold, however, that the king is subject to the church and the pope, although completely irreproachable in other ways; but according to this doctrine in its strong form, only God can judge an unjust king. The doctrine implies that any attempt to depose the king or to restrict his powers runs contrary to the will of God and may constitute a sacrilegious act.</paragraph><paragraph>One passage in scripture supporting the idea of divine right of kings was<space/><link><target>s:Bible (King James)/Romans#Chapter 13</target><part>Romans 13</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Martin Luther</target></link>, when urging the secular authorities to crush the<space/><link><target>German Peasants' War</target><part>Peasant Rebellion of 1525</part></link><space/>in Germany in his<space/><italics><link><target>Against the Murderous, Thieving Hordes of Peasants</target></link></italics>, based his argument on St. Paul's Epistle to the<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Romans</arg><arg>13:1–7</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>It is related to the ancient Catholic philosophies regarding monarchy, in which the monarch is God's<space/><link><target>vicegerent</target></link><space/>upon the earth and therefore subject to no inferior power. However, in Roman Catholic jurisprudence, the monarch is always subject to<space/><link><target>Natural law</target><part>natural</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>divine law</target></link>, which are regarded as superior to the monarch. The possibility of monarchy declining morally, overturning natural law, and degenerating into a tyranny oppressive of the general welfare was answered theologically with the Catholic concept of extra-legal<space/><link><target>tyrannicide</target></link>, ideally ratified by the pope. Until the<space/><link><target>Papal states</target><part>unification of Italy</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Bishop of Rome</target><part>Holy See</part></link><space/>did, from the time Christianity became the Roman<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target><part>state religion</part></link>, assert on that ground its primacy over secular princes; however this exercise of power never, even at its zenith, amounted to<space/><link><target>theocracy</target></link>, even in jurisdictions where the Bishop of Rome was the temporal authority.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:PapalPolitics2.JPG</target><part>270px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>''Antichristus'', a woodcut by<space/><link><target>Lucas Cranach the Elder</target></link>, of the pope using the temporal power to grant authority to a ruler contributing generously to the Catholic Church</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Catholic justified submission</heading><paragraph>Catholic thought justified submission to the monarchy by reference to the following:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The Old Testament, in which God chose kings to rule over Israel, beginning with<space/><link><target>Saul</target></link><space/>who was then rejected by God in favor of<space/><link><target>David</target></link>, whose dynasty continued (at least in the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Judah</target><part>southern kingdom</part></link>) until the<space/><link><target>Babylonian captivity</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>The New Testament, in which the first pope, St. Peter, commands that all Christians shall honour the Roman Emperor (<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>1</arg><arg>Peter</arg><arg>2:13–20</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template>), even though, at that time, he was still a pagan emperor. St. Paul agreed with St. Peter that subjects should be obedient to the powers that be because they are appointed by God, as he wrote in his Epistle to the<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Romans</arg><arg>13:1-7</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template>. Likewise, Jesus Christ proclaims in the Gospel of Matthew that one should &quot;Render unto Caesar the things which are Caesar's&quot;; that is at first, literally, the payment of taxes as binding those who use the imperial<space/><link><target>currency</target></link><space/>(See<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>Matthew</arg><arg>22:15–22</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template>). Jesus told<space/><link><target>Pontius Pilate</target></link><space/>that his authority as Roman governor of<space/><link><target>Judaea</target></link><space/>came from heaven according to<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg></arg><arg>John</arg><arg>19:10–11</arg><arg>NKJV</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>The endorsement by the popes and the church of the line of emperors beginning with the Emperors<space/><link><target>Constantine I</target><part>Constantine</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Theodosius I</target><part>Theodosius</part></link>, later the Eastern Roman emperors, and finally the Western Roman emperor,<space/><link><target>Charlemagne</target></link><space/>and his successors, the Catholic<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target><part>Holy Roman Emperors</part></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>The French Huguenot nobles and clergy, having rejected the pope and the Catholic Church, were left only with the supreme power of the king who, they taught, could not be gainsaid or judged by anyone. Since there was no longer the countervailing power of the papacy and since the Church of England was a creature of the state and had become subservient to it, this meant that there was nothing to regulate the powers of the king, and he became an absolute power. In theory,<space/><link><target>Divine law</target><part>divine</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Natural law</target><part>natural</part></link>, customary, and<space/><link><target>constitutional law</target></link><space/>still held sway over the king, but, absent a superior spiritual power, it was difficult to see how they could be enforced, since the king could not be tried by any of his own courts.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of the symbolism within the<space/><link><target>Coronation of the British monarch</target><part>coronation</part></link><space/>ceremony for British monarchs, in which they are<space/><link><target>anointed</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Holy Oil (Christianity)</target><part>holy oils</part></link><space/>by the<space/><link><target>Archbishop of Canterbury</target></link>, thereby<space/><italics><link><target>Holy Orders</target><part>ordaining</part></link></italics><space/>them to monarchy, perpetuates the ancient Roman Catholic monarchical ideas and ceremonial (although few Protestants realize this, the ceremony is nearly entirely based upon that of the Coronation of the Holy Roman Emperor).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2011</arg></template><space/>However, in the UK, the symbolism ends there, since the real governing authority of the monarch was all but extinguished by the Whig revolution of 168889 (see<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link>). The king or queen of the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>is one of the last monarchs still to be crowned in the traditional Christian ceremonial, which in most other countries has been replaced by an<space/><link><target>inauguration</target></link><space/>or other declaration.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:King Charles I from NPG.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>Charles I, being crowned by a hand from a cloud, possibly by God</part></link>The concept of divine right incorporates, but exaggerates, the ancient Christian concept of &quot;royal God-given rights&quot;, which teach that &quot;the right to rule is anointed by God&quot;, although this idea is found in many other cultures, including<space/><link><target>Aryan</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ancient Egypt</target><part>Egyptian</part></link><space/>traditions. In pagan religions, the king was often seen as a kind of god and so was an unchallengeable despot. The ancient Roman Catholic tradition overcame this idea with the doctrine of the &quot;Two Swords&quot; and so achieved, for the very first time, a balanced constitution for states. The advent of Protestantism saw something of a return to the idea of a mere unchallengeable despot.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Aquinas</target></link><space/>condoned extra-legal<space/><link><target>tyrannicide</target></link><space/>in the worst of circumstances:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>When there is no recourse to a superior by whom judgment can be made about an invader, then he who slays a tyrant to liberate his fatherland is [to be] praised and receives a reward.</arg><arg>''Commentary on the Magister Sententiarum''<ref>http://www.vaxxine.com/hyoomik/aquinas/regicide.html</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On the other hand, Aquinas forbade the overthrow of any morally, Christianly and spiritually legitimate king by his subjects. The only human power capable of deposing the king was the pope. The reasoning was that if a subject may overthrow his superior for some bad law, who was to be the judge of whether the law was bad? If the subject could so judge his own superior, then all lawful superior authority could lawfully be overthrown by the arbitrary judgement of an inferior, and thus all law was under constant threat. Towards the end of the Middle Ages, many philosophers, such as<space/><link><target>Nicholas of Cusa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Francisco Surez</target><part>Francisco Suarez</part></link>, propounded similar theories. The Church was the final guarantor that Christian kings would follow the laws and constitutional traditions of their ancestors and the laws of the presumptive god and of justice. Similarly, the Chinese concept of<space/><link><target>Mandate of Heaven</target></link><space/>required that the emperor properly carry out the proper<space/><link><target>ritual</target><trail>s</trail></link>, consult his ministers, and made it extremely difficult to undo any acts carried out by an ancestor.</paragraph><paragraph>The French prelate<space/><link><target>Jacques-Bnigne Bossuet</target></link><space/>made a classic statement of the doctrine of divine right in a sermon preached before King Louis XIV:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Sermons choisis de Bossuet</arg><arg name="author">[[Jacques-Bénigne Bossuet]]</arg><arg name="work">Sur le devoir des rois</arg></template><space/>p. 219,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=OWf5USWTfWQC&amp;amp;pg=PA219&amp;amp;img=1&amp;amp;zoom=3&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sig=ACfU3U0FBRrjh8fZ8ViFiVucnPKYolU_ew&amp;amp;ci=55%2C632%2C772%2C172&amp;amp;edge=0'>Image</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Les rois règnent par moi, dit la Sagesse éternelle: 'Per me reges regnant'; et de là nous devons conclure non seulement que les droits de la royauté sont établis par ses lois, mais que le choix des personnes est un effet de sa providence.</arg></template><template><target>quote</target><arg>Kings reign by Me, says Eternal Wisdom: 'Per me reges regnant' [in Latin]; and from that we must conclude not only that the rights of royalty are established by its laws, but also that the choice of persons [to occupy the throne] is an effect of its providence.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Divine right in Asia</heading><paragraph>In early Mesopotamian culture, kings were often regarded as deities after their death.<space/><link><target>Shulgi</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ur</target></link><space/>was among the first Mesopotamian rulers to declare himself to be divine. This was the direct precursor to the concept of &quot;Divine Right of kings&quot;, as well as in the Egyptian and Roman religions.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Mandate of Heaven</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Mandate of Heaven</arg><arg>Son of Heaven</arg></template><link><target>File:Amaterasu cave edit2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Emperor of Japan</target></link><space/>rules as a divine descendant of the sun goddess<space/><link><target>Amaterasu</target></link></part></link>In<space/><link><target>China</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>East Asia</target></link>, rulers justified their rule with the philosophy of the<space/><link><target>Mandate of Heaven</target></link>, which, although similar to the European concept, bore several key differences. While the divine right of kings granted unconditional legitimacy, the Mandate of Heaven was dependent on the behaviour of the ruler, the<space/><link><target>Son of Heaven</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Heaven</target></link><space/>would bless the authority of a just ruler, but it could be displeased with a despotic ruler and thus withdraw its mandate, transferring it to a more suitable and righteous person. This withdrawal of mandate also afforded the possibility of revolution as a means to remove the errant ruler; revolt was never legitimate under the European framework of divine right.</paragraph><paragraph>In China, the<space/><link><target>right of rebellion</target></link><space/>against an unjust ruler had been a part of the political philosophy ever since the<space/><link><target>Zhou dynasty</target></link>, whose rulers had used this philosophy to justify their overthrow of the previous<space/><link><target>Shang dynasty</target></link>. Chinese historians interpreted a successful revolt as evidence that the Mandate of Heaven had passed on to the usurper.</paragraph><paragraph>In Japan, the Son of Heaven title was less conditional than its Chinese equivalent. There was no divine mandate that punished the emperor for failing to rule justly. The right to rule of the Japanese emperor, descended from the sun goddess<space/><link><target>Amaterasu</target></link>, was absolute.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="last">Beasley</arg><arg name="chapter">The Making of a Monarchy</arg><arg name="title">The Japanese Experience: A Short History of Japan</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="publisher">University of California Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-520-22560-2</arg><arg name="page">29</arg><arg name="ref">harv</arg></template></extension><space/>The Japanese emperors traditionally wielded little secular power; generally, it was the duty of the sitting emperor to perform rituals and make public appearances, while true power was held by regents, high-ranking ministers or even retired emperors depending on the time period.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sultans in Southeast Asia</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Malay Annals</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>raja</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sultan</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the Malay States (today<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Brunei</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Philippines</target></link>) as well as their predecessors, such as the<space/><link><target>Indonesia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>kingdom of<space/><link><target>Majapahit</target></link>, also claimed divine right to rule. The sultan is mandated by God, and thus is expected to lead his country and people in religious matters, ceremonies as well as prayers. This divine right is called<space/><italics>Daulat</italics>, and although the notion of divine right is somewhat obsolete, it is still found in the phrase<space/><italics>Daulat Tuanku</italics><space/>that is used to publicly acclaim the reigning<space/><link><target>Yang di-Pertuan Agong</target></link><space/>and the other sultans of Malaysia. The exclamation is similar to the European &quot;<link><target>The king is dead, long live the king!</target><part>Long live the King</part></link>&quot;, and often accompanies pictures of the reigning monarch and<space/><link><target>Raja Permaisuri Agong</target><part>his consort</part></link><space/>on banners during royal occasions. In<space/><link><target>Indonesia</target></link>, especially on the island of<space/><link><target>Java</target></link>, the sultan's divine right is more commonly known as the<space/><italics>wahyu</italics>, or 'revelation', but it is not hereditary, and can be passed on to distant relatives.</paragraph><heading level='3'>South Asian kings</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Tamil culture</target></link>, before<space/><link><target>Brahmanism</target></link><space/>and especially during the<space/><link><target>Sangam period</target></link>, emperors were known as (<italics>Iraiyer</italics>), or &quot;those who spill&quot;, and kings were called (<italics>Ko</italics>) or (<italics>Kon</italics>). During this time, the distinction between kingship and godhood had not yet occurred, as the<space/><link><target>caste</target></link><space/>system had not yet been introduced. Even in Modern<space/><link><target>Tamil language</target><part>Tamil</part></link>, the word for temple is '', meaning &quot;king's house&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ramanujan</arg><arg name="first">A.K.</arg><arg name="title">Poems of Love and War: From the Eight Anthologies and the Ten Long Poems of Classical Tamil</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-231-15735-3</arg></template></extension><space/>Kings were understood to be the &quot;agents of God&quot;, as they protected the world like God did.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">N. Subramanian</arg><arg name="title">Śaṅgam polity: the administration and social life of the Śaṅgam Tamils</arg><arg name="year">1966</arg><arg name="publisher">Asia Pub. House</arg></template></extension><space/>This may well have been continued post-Brahminism in<space/><link><target>Tamilakam</target></link>, as the famous Thiruvalangadu inscription states:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Having noticed by the marks (on his body) that Arulmozhi was the very Vishnu&quot; in reference to the Emperor<space/><link><target>Raja Raja Chola I</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Rights</heading><paragraph>Historically, many notions of rights were<space/><link><target>authoritarianism</target><part>authoritarian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>hierarchy</target><part>hierarchical</part></link>, with different people granted different rights, and some having more rights than others. For instance, the right of a father to respect from his son did not indicate a right from the son to receive a return from that respect; and the divine right of kings, which permitted absolute power over subjects, did not leave a lot of room for many rights for the subjects themselves.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tws21decfrre"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Divine Right of Kings
</arg><arg name="quote"><space/>[...] the idea that a king was sacred, appointed by God and above the judgment of earthly powers [...] was called the Divine Right of Kings and it entered so powerfully into British culture during the 17th century that it shaped the pomp and circumstance of the Stuart monarchs, imbued the writing of Shakespeare and provoked the political thinking of Milton and Locke.
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>''BBC''
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>2007-10-11
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20071011.shtml
</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-12-21
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast, modern conceptions of rights often emphasize<space/><link><target>liberty</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>egalitarianism</target><part>equality</part></link><space/>as among the most important aspects of rights, for example in the<space/><link><target>American Revolution</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Opposition</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>All men are created equal</arg></template>In the sixteenth century, both Catholic and Protestant political thinkers began to question theidea of a monarch's &quot;divine right&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The Spanish Catholic historian<space/><link><target>Juan de Mariana</target></link><space/>put forward the argument in his book<italics><link><target>De rege et regis institutione</target></link></italics><space/>(1598) that since society was formed by a &quot;pact&quot; among all its members,&quot;there can be no doubt that they are able to call a king to account&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Baer, Robert V.<italics>Power &amp; Freedom: Political Thought and Constitutional Politics in the United States and Argentina</italics><space/>ProQuest, 2008ISBN 0549745106 (pp. 7071)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="p&amp;l">Blumenau, Ralph.<space/><italics>Philosophy and Living</italics><space/>Imprint Academic, 2002ISBN 0907845339 (pp. 198199)</extension><space/>Mariana thus challenged divine right theories by stating in certain circumstances,<space/><link><target>tyrannicide</target></link><space/>could be justified.<space/><link><target>Robert Bellarmine</target><part>Cardinal Robert Bellarmine</part></link><space/>also &quot;did not believe thatthe institute of monarchy had any divine sanction&quot; and shared Mariana's belief that there were times where Catholicscould lawfully remove a monarch.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p&amp;l"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Among groups of English<space/><link><target>Protestant</target></link><space/>exiles fleeing from<space/><link><target>Mary I of England</target><part>Queen Mary I</part></link>, some of the earliest anti-monarchist publications emerged. &quot;Weaned off uncritical royalism by the actions of Queen Mary The political thinking of men like<space/><link><target>John Ponet</target><part>Ponet</part></link>,<space/><link><target>John Knox</target><part>Knox</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Christopher Goodman</target><part>Goodman</part></link><space/>and Hales.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The English Reformation</arg><arg name="last">Dickens</arg><arg name="first">A.G.</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="publisher">Fontana/Collins</arg><arg name="location">London & Glasgow</arg><arg name="page">399</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1553, Mary I, a Roman Catholic, succeeded her Protestant half-brother,<space/><link><target>Edward VI of England</target><part>Edward VI</part></link>, to the English throne. Mary set about trying to restore Roman Catholicism by making sure that: Edward's religious laws were abolished in the Statute of Repeal Act (1553); the Protestant religious laws passed in the time of<space/><link><target>Henry VIII of England</target><part>Henry VIII</part></link><space/>were repealed; and the<space/><link><target>Revival of the Heresy Acts</target></link><space/>were passed in 1554. The<space/><link><target>Marian Persecutions</target></link><space/>began soon afterwards. In January 1555, the first of nearly 300 Protestants were burnt at the stake under &quot;Bloody Mary&quot;. When<space/><link><target>Thomas Wyatt the younger</target></link><space/>instigated what became known as<space/><link><target>Wyatt's rebellion</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Ponet</target></link>, the highest-ranking ecclesiastic among the exiles,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dickens391"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The English Reformation</arg><arg name="last">Dickens</arg><arg name="first">A.G.</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="publisher">Fontana/Collins</arg><arg name="location">London & Glasgow</arg><arg name="page">391</arg></template></extension><space/>allegedly participated in the uprising.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The English Reformation</arg><arg name="last">Dickens</arg><arg name="first">A.G.</arg><arg name="year">1978</arg><arg name="publisher">Fontana/Collins</arg><arg name="location">London & Glasgow</arg><arg name="page">358</arg></template></extension><space/>He escaped to<space/><link><target>Strasbourg</target></link><space/>after the Rebellion's defeat and, the following year, he published<space/><italics>A Shorte Treatise of Politike Power</italics>, in which he put forward a theory of justified opposition to secular rulers.</paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Ponet's treatise comes first in a new wave of anti-monarchical writings It has never been assessed at its true importance, for it antedates by several years those more brilliantly expressed but less radical<space/><link><target>Huguenot</target></link><space/>writings which have usually been taken to represent the<space/><link><target>Tyrannicide</target></link>-theories of the<space/><link><target>Protestant Reformation</target><part>Reformation</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dickens391"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Ponet's pamphlet was republished on the eve of<space/><link><target>King Charles I of England</target><part>King Charles I</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Execution of Charles I</target><part>execution</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>According to U.S. President<space/><link><target>John Adams</target></link>, Ponet's work contained &quot;all the essential principles of liberty, which were afterward dilated on by<space/><link><target>Algernon Sidney</target><part>Sidney</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Locke</target><part>Locke</part></link>&quot;, including the idea of a three-branched government.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Works of John Adams, with Life</arg><arg name="last">Adams</arg><arg name="first">C.F.</arg><arg name="year">1850–56</arg><arg name="location">Boston</arg><arg name="volume">6</arg><arg name="page">4</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In due course, opposition to the divine right of kings came from a number of sources, including poet<space/><link><target>John Milton</target></link><space/>in his pamphlet<space/><italics><link><target>The Tenure of Kings and Magistrates</target></link></italics>, and<space/><link><target>Thomas Paine</target></link><space/>in his pamphlet<space/><italics><link><target>Common Sense (pamphlet)</target><part>Common Sense</part></link></italics>. Probably the two most famous declarations of a right to revolution against tyranny in the English language are<space/><link><target>John Locke</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Essay concerning The True Original, Extent, and End of Civil-Government</italics><space/>and Thomas Jefferson's formulation in the<space/><link><target>United States Declaration of Independence</target></link><space/>that &quot;<link><target>all men are created equal</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><table><tablerow><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Absolutism (European history)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ancient Regime</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Caliph</target></link></listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Church and state in medieval Europe</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Concordat of Worms</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuius regio, eius religio</target></link></listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>First Council of the Lateran</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Legitimacy (political)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Bellarmine</target></link></listitem></list></tablecell><tablecell><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Robert Filmer</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sovereignty</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The True Law of Free Monarchies</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vindiciae contra tyrannos</target></link></listitem></list></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Burgess</arg><arg name="first">Glenn</arg><arg name="title">The Divine Right of Kings Reconsidered</arg><arg name="journal">The English Historical Review</arg><arg name="date">October 1992</arg><arg name="volume">107</arg><arg name="issue">425</arg><arg name="pages">837–861</arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/ehr/cvii.ccccxxv.837</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>In Our Time</target><arg>The Divine Right of Kings</arg><arg>b0080xph</arg><arg>The_Divine_Right_of_Kings</arg></template><template><target>Relpolnav</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Monarchy</target></link><link><target>Category:Political philosophy</target></link><link><target>Category:Political history of the Ancien Rgime</target></link><link><target>Category:Early Modern period</target></link><link><target>Category:Deified people</target></link><link><target>Category:Sovereignty</target></link></paragraph></article>