<article title='Angles'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template><template><target>Cleanup-rewrite</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><link><target>Image:Roman Empire 125.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>320px</part><part>Map of the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link><space/>under<space/><link><target>Hadrian</target></link><space/>(ruled 117138), showing the then homeland of the Angles (''Anglii'') on the<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link><space/>peninsula in today's Germany and Denmark</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Angles</bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-la</target><arg>Anglii</arg></template>) were one of the main<space/><link><target>Germanic peoples</target></link><space/>who settled in<space/><link><target>Great Britain</target><part>Britain</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Fall of the Western Roman Empire</target><part>post-Roman</part></link><space/>period. They founded several of the<space/><link><target>monarchy</target><part>kingdoms</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Anglo-Saxon England</target></link>, and their name is the root of the name<space/><italics>England</italics>. The name comes from the district of<space/><link><target>Angeln</target></link>, an area located on the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target><part>Baltic</part></link><space/>shore of what is now<space/><link><target>Schleswig-Holstein</target></link>, the most northern<space/><link><target>States of Germany</target><part>state of Germany</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Name</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Angeln#Name</arg></template>The name of the Angles was first recorded in Latinised form, as<space/><italics>Anglii</italics>, in the<space/><italics><link><target>Germania (book)</target><part>Germania</part></link></italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link>. It is thought to derive from the name of the area they originally inhabited:<space/><italics>Angeln</italics><space/>in modern German,<space/><italics>Angel</italics><space/>in<space/><link><target>Danish language</target><part>Danish</part></link>. This name has been hypothesised to originate from the<space/><link><target>Germanic languages</target><part>Germanic</part></link><space/>root for &quot;narrow&quot; (compare German<space/><italics>eng</italics><space/>= &quot;narrow&quot;), meaning &quot;the Narrow [Water]&quot;, i.e. the<space/><link><target>Schlei</target></link><space/><link><target>estuary</target></link>; the root would be angh, &quot;tight&quot;. Another theory is that the name meant &quot;hook&quot;, as in<space/><link><target>angling</target></link><space/>for fish;<space/><link><target>Julius Pokorny</target></link>, a major Indo-European linguist, derives it from *ang-, &quot;bend&quot; (see ankle).</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gregory the Great</target></link><space/>in an epistle simplified the Latinised name<space/><italics>Anglii</italics><space/>to<space/><italics>Angli</italics>, the latter form developing into the preferred form of the word. The country remained<space/><italics>Anglia</italics><space/>in Latin.<space/><link><target>Alfred the Great</target></link>'s translation of<space/><link><target>Paulus Orosius</target><part>Orosius</part></link>' history of the world uses<space/><italics>Angelcynn</italics><space/>(-kin) to describe England and the English people;<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link><space/>used<space/><italics>Angelfolc</italics><space/>(-folk); there are also such forms as<space/><italics>Engel</italics>,<space/><italics>Englan</italics><space/>(the people),<space/><italics>Englaland</italics>, and<space/><italics>Englisc</italics>, all showing<space/><link><target>i-mutation</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Greco-Roman historiography</heading><heading level='3'>Tacitus</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Angeln.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>The map shows both the Angeln and the Schwansen peninsulas</part></link><link><target>File:Angles saxons jutes.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Possible locations of the Angles, Saxons and Jutes before their migration to Britain.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest recorded mention of the Angles may be in chapter 40 of<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Germania (book)</target><part>Germania</part></link></italics>. Tacitus describes the &quot;Anglii&quot; as one of the more remote<space/><link><target>Suebi</target><trail>c</trail></link><space/>tribes compared to the<space/><link><target>Semnones</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Langobardi</target></link>, who lived on the<space/><link><target>Elbe</target></link><space/>and were better known to the Romans. He grouped the Angles with several other tribes in that region, the<space/><link><target>Reudigni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Aviones</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Varini</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Eudoses</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Suarini</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nuitones</target></link>.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Tacitus</arg><arg>98</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:la:De origine et situ Germanorum (Germania)#XL|Cap. XL]]</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Church</arg><arg>1868</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:Germany and Its Tribes#40|Ch.&nbsp;XL]]</arg></template><space/>These were all living behind ramparts of rivers and woods and therefore inaccessible to attack.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Tacitus</arg><arg>98</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:la:De origine et situ Germanorum (Germania)#XL|Cap. XL]]</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Church</arg><arg>1868</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:Germany and Its Tribes#40|Ch.&nbsp;XL]]</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He gives no precise indication of their geographical situation but states that, together with six other tribes, they worshiped<space/><link><target>Nerthus</target></link>, or Mother Earth, whose sanctuary was located on &quot;an island in the Ocean&quot;. As the Eudoses are the<space/><link><target>Jutes</target></link>, these names probably refer to localities in<space/><link><target>Jutland</target></link><space/>or on the Baltic coast, in which case their inhabitants would be Cimbri or Teutones for<space/><link><target>Pliny the Elder</target><part>Pliny</part></link>. The coast contains sufficient estuaries, inlets, rivers, islands, swamps and marshes to have been then inaccessible to those not familiar with the terrain, such as the Romans, who considered it unknown, inaccessible, with a small population and of little economic interest.</paragraph><paragraph>The majority of scholars believe that the Anglii lived on the coasts of the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target></link>, probably in the southern part of the Jutish peninsula. This view is based partly on Old English and Danish traditions regarding persons and events of the 4th century, and partly on the fact that striking affinities to the cult of Nerthus as described by Tacitus are to be found in pre-Christian<space/><link><target>Scandinavia</target><trail>n</trail></link>, especially Swedish and Danish, religion.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ptolemy</heading><paragraph><link><target>Ptolemy</target></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Geography (Ptolemy)</target><part>Geography</part></link></italics><space/>(2.10), half a century later, describes the<space/><italics>Sueboi Angeilloi</italics>, Latinised to<space/><italics>Suevi Angili</italics>, further south, living in a stretch of land between the northern Rhine and central Elbe, but apparently not touching either river, with the Suebic<space/><link><target>Langobardi</target></link><space/>on the Rhine to their west, and the Suebic<space/><link><target>Semnones</target></link><space/>on the Elbe stretching to their east.</paragraph><paragraph>These Suevi Angili would have been in<space/><link><target>Lower Saxony</target></link><space/>or near it, but they are not coastal. The three Suebic peoples are separated from the coastal<space/><link><target>Chauci</target></link>, (between<space/><link><target>Ems (river)</target><part>Ems</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elbe</target></link>), and<space/><link><target>Saxones</target></link>, (east of the Elbe mouth), by a series of tribes including, between<space/><link><target>Weser</target></link><space/>and Elbe, the<space/><link><target>Angrivarii</target></link>, &quot;Laccobardi&quot; (probably another reference to Langobardi, but taken by Ptolemy from another source), and<space/><link><target>Dulgubnii</target></link>. South of the Saxons, and east of the Elbe, Ptolemy lists &quot;Ouirounoi&quot; (Latinised as Viruni, and probably the Varini) and Teutonoari, which either denotes &quot;the Teuton men&quot;, or else it denotes people living in the area where the Teutons had previously lived (who Ptolemy places still living to the east of the Teutonoari). Ptolemy describes the coast to the east of the Saxons as inhabited by the<space/><link><target>Farodini</target></link>, a name not known from any other sources.</paragraph><paragraph>Owing to the uncertainty of this passage, there has been much speculation regarding the original home of the Anglii. One theory is that they or part of them dwelt or moved among other coastal people perhaps confederated up to the basin of the<space/><link><target>Saale</target></link><space/>(in the neighbourhood of the ancient canton of<space/><link><target>Unstruttal (Verwaltungsgemeinschaft)</target><part>Engilin</part></link>) on the<space/><link><target>Unstrut</target></link><space/>valleys below the<space/><link><target>Kyffhuserkreis</target></link>, from which region the<space/><italics>Lex Angliorum et Werinorum hoc est Thuringorum</italics><space/>is believed by many to have come. The ethnic names of<space/><link><target>Frisii</target><part>Frisians</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Warini</target><part>Warines</part></link><space/>are attested in the neighbourhood names of this<space/><link><target>Saxon</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Swabia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>lands.</paragraph><paragraph>A second possible solution is that these Angles of Ptolemy are not those of Schleswig at all. According to<space/><link><target>Julius Pokorny</target></link><space/>the Angri- in<space/><link><target>Angrivarii</target></link>, the -angr in<space/><link><target>Hardanger</target></link><space/>and the Angl- in Anglii all come from the same root meaning &quot;bend&quot;, but in different senses. In other words, the similarity of the names is strictly coincidental and does not reflect any ethnic unity beyond Germanic.</paragraph><paragraph>On the other hand, Gudmund Schtte, in his analysis of Ptolemy, believes that the Angles have simply been moved by an error coming from Ptolemy's use of imperfect sources. He points out that Angles are placed correctly just to the northeast of the<space/><link><target>Langobardi</target></link>, but that these have been duplicated, so that they appear once, correctly, on the lower Elbe, and a second time, incorrectly, at the northern Rhine.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Schütte</arg><arg>1917</arg><arg name="p">[http://archive.org/stream/ptolemysmapsofno00schrich#page/34/mode/2up/search/angles 34] & [http://archive.org/stream/ptolemysmapsofno00schrich#page/118/mode/2up/search/angles 118]</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Medieval historiography</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Kings of the Angles</arg></template><link><target>Image:Beda Petersburgiensis f3v.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Manuscript of Bede</part></link><link><target>Bede</target></link><space/>states that the Anglii, before coming to Great Britain, dwelt in a land called Angulus, &quot;which lies between the province of the Jutes and the Saxons, and remains unpopulated to this day.&quot; Similar evidence is given by the<space/><italics><link><target>Historia Brittonum</target></link></italics>. King<space/><link><target>Alfred the Great</target></link><space/>and the chronicler<space/><link><target>thelweard (historian)</target><part>thelweard</part></link><space/>identified this place with the district that is now called<space/><link><target>Angeln</target></link>, in the province of<space/><link><target>Schleswig</target></link><space/>(Slesvig) (though it may then have been of greater extent), and this identification agrees with the indications given by Bede.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Norwegian seafarer<space/><link><target>Ohthere of Hlogaland</target></link>'s account of a two-day voyage from the Oslo fjord to Schleswig, he reported the lands on his starboard bow, and Alfred appended the note &quot;on these islands dwelt the<space/><italics>Engle</italics><space/>before they came hither&quot;.<template><target>refn</target><arg name="group">n</arg><arg name="See the translation by Sweet,{{sfnp|Sweet|1883|p">19}} noted by Loyn.{{sfnp|Loyn|1991|p</arg></template><space/>Confirmation is afforded by English and Danish traditions relating to two kings named<space/><link><target>Wermund</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Offa of Angel</target></link>, from whom the<space/><link><target>Mercia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>royal family claimed descent and whose exploits are connected with Angeln, Schleswig, and<space/><link><target>Rendsburg</target></link>. Danish tradition has preserved record of two governors of Schleswig, father and son, in their service,<space/><link><target>Frowinus</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Freawine</target></link>) and<space/><link><target>Ket and Wig</target><part>Wigo</part></link><space/>(Wig), from whom the royal family of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link><space/>claimed descent. During the 5th century, the Anglii invaded Great Britain, after which time their name does not recur on the continent except in the title of<space/><italics>Suevi Angili</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Angles are the subject of a legend about<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory I</target></link>, who happened to see a group of Angle children from<space/><link><target>Deira (kingdom)</target><part>Deira</part></link><space/>for sale as slaves in the Roman market. As the story would later be told by the Anglo-Saxon monk and historian<space/><link><target>Bede</target></link>, Gregory was struck by the unusual appearance of the slaves and asked about their background. When told they were called &quot;<italics>Anglii</italics>&quot; (Angles), he replied with a Latin pun that translates well into English:<space/><italics>Bene, nam et angelicam habent faciem, et tales angelorum in caelis decet esse coheredes</italics><space/>(&quot;It is well, for they have an angelic face, and such people ought to be co-heirs of the<space/><link><target>angel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in heaven&quot;). Supposedly, this encounter inspired the Pope to launch a mission to bring Christianity to their countrymen.<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Bede</arg><arg>731</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:Historia Ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum - Liber Secundus|Lib.&nbsp;II]]</arg></template><template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Jane</arg><arg>1903</arg><arg name="loc">[[s:Ecclesiastical History of the English People/Book 2|Vol.&nbsp;II]]</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Archaeology</heading><paragraph>The province of Schleswig has proved rich in prehistoric antiquities that date apparently from the 4th and 5th centuries. A large cremation cemetery has been found at<space/><link><target>Borgstedt</target></link>, between Rendsburg and<space/><link><target>Eckernfrde</target></link>, and it has yielded many urns and brooches closely resembling those found in pagan graves in England. Of still greater importance are the great deposits at<space/><link><target>Thorsberg moor</target></link><space/>(in Angeln) and<space/><link><target>Nydam Mose</target><part>Nydam</part></link>, which contained large quantities of arms, ornaments, articles of clothing, agricultural implements, etc., and in Nydam even ships. By the help of these discoveries, Angle culture in the age preceding the invasion of Britannia can be pieced together.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Anglian kingdoms in England</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Anglo-Saxon settlement of Britain</arg><arg>Anglo-Saxons</arg><arg>History of Anglo-Saxon England</arg></template><link><target>Image:Britain peoples circa 600.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Angles, Saxons and Jutes throughout England</part></link>According to sources such as the History of Bede, after the invasion of Britannia, the Angles split up and founded the kingdoms of the Northumbria, East Anglia and Mercia. H.R. Loyn has observed in this context that &quot;a sea voyage is perilous to tribal institutions,&quot;<template><target>sfnp</target><arg>Loyn</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">25</arg></template><space/>and the apparently tribally-based kingdoms were produced in England. In early times there were two northern kingdoms (Bernicia and Deira) and two midland ones (Middle Anglia and Mercia), which had by the 7th century resolved themselves into two Angle kingdoms, viz.,<space/><link><target>Northumbria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mercia</target></link>. Northumbria held suzerainty amidst the<space/><link><target>Germanic peoples</target><part>Teutonic</part></link><space/>presence in the British Isles in the 7th century, but was eclipsed by the rise in power of the Mercian Kingdom in the 8th century. Both Kingdoms fell in the great assaults of the Danish<space/><link><target>Viking</target></link><space/>armies in the 9th century, their royal houses being effectively destroyed in the fighting, the Angle populations of the two fallen Kingdoms becoming governmentally captive under the<space/><link><target>Danelaw</target></link>'s dominion. Having withstood the Danish assaults further south, the Saxon kings of<space/><link><target>Wessex</target></link><space/>marched north in the late 9th and early 10th centuries and liberated the Angles from the Danelaw in a succession of victorious military campaigns, and were accepted by the Angles as their kings after having united their house in marriage with the surviving residue of the Angle royal lines. This marking the passing of the old '<link><target>Anglo-Saxon</target></link>' world and the dawn of the &quot;<link><target>English people</target><part>English</part></link>&quot; as a new people. The regions of East Anglia and Northumbria are still known by their original titles. Northumbria once stretched as far north as what is now southeast<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link>, including<space/><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link>, and as far south as the<space/><link><target>Humber Estuary</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The rest of that people stayed at the centre of the Angle homeland in the northeastern portion of the modern German<space/><italics>Bundesland</italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Schleswig-Holstein</target></link>, on the<space/><link><target>Jutland Peninsula</target></link>. There, a small peninsular area is still called &quot;<link><target>Angeln</target></link>&quot; today and is formed as a triangle drawn roughly from modern<space/><link><target>Flensburg</target></link><space/>on the Flensburger Fjord to the<space/><link><target>City of Schleswig</target></link><space/>and then to Maasholm, on the<space/><link><target>Schlei</target></link><space/>inlet.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Ancient Germanic culture</arg><arg>Anglo-Saxon England</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Angeln</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Anglo-Saxons</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>East Anglia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Kingdom of East Anglia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of ancient Germanic peoples</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mercia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Northumbria</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">n</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Citations</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">[[Bede|Beda]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[s:la:Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum|Historia ecclesiastica gentis Anglorum]] ''[''The Ecclesiastical History of the English People'']''<space/></arg><arg name="date">731<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Bede|731}}<space/></arg></template>.<space/><template><target>la icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">[[Bede]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:Bede's Ecclesiastical History of England|Bede's Ecclesiastical History of England: A Revised Translation]]''<space/></arg><arg name="date">1907<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">George Bell & Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="orig-year">Reprinting [[Lionel Cecil Jane|Jane]]'s 1903 translation for J.M. Dent & Co.'s 1903 ''[[s:The Ecclesiastical History of the English Nation|The Ecclesiastical History of the English Nation]]''<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Jane|1903}}<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Cornelius Tacitus<space/></arg><arg name="first">Publius<space/></arg><arg name="author-link">Tacitus<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[s:la:De origine et situ Germanorum|De origine et situ Germanorum]] ''[''On the Origin & Situation of the Germans'']''<space/></arg><arg name="year">98<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Tacitus|98}}<space/></arg></template>.<space/><template><target>la icon</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Cornelius Tacitus<space/></arg><arg name="first">Publius<space/></arg><arg name="author-link">Tacitus<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">[[s:Germany and Its Tribes|Germany and Its Tribes]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Complete Works of Tacitus<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Hadas<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Moses<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Cerrato<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Lisa<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Random House<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="date">1942<space/></arg><arg name="orig-year">First published in 1928, reprinting [[Alfred John Church|Church]] and [[William Jackson Brodribb|Brodribb]]'s translations for Macmillan & Co.'s 1868 ''[http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id</arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|Church|1868}}<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="contribution">[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Angles|Angles]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 9th ed.]], [[s:Encyclopædia Britannica, Ninth Edition/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Baynes<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Thomas Spencer<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Charles Scribner's Sons<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="date">1878<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1878}}<space/></arg><arg name="p">30<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Chadwick<space/></arg><arg name="first">Hector Munro<space/></arg><arg name="author-link">Hector Munro Chadwick<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Angli|Angli]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">''[[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica|''Encyclopædia Britannica'', 11th ed.]], [[s:1911 Encyclopædia Britannica/Volume II|Vol.&nbsp;II]]''<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Chisholm<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Hugh<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Phillips<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Walter Alison<space/></arg><arg name="display-editors">0<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">[[Cambridge, England|Cambridge]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">1911<space/></arg><arg name="ref">{{harvid|EB|1911}}<space/></arg><arg name="pp">18–19<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Schütte<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gudmund<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://archive.org/stream/ptolemysmapsofno00schrich<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ptolemy's Maps of Northern Europe: A Reconstruction of the Prototypes<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Græbe for H. Hagerup for the Royal Danish Geographical Society<space/></arg><arg name="location">Copenhagen<space/></arg><arg name="date">1917<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Sweet<space/></arg><arg name="first">Henry<space/></arg><arg name="title">King Alfred's Orosius<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/details/kingalfredsorosi79oros<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">E. Pickard Hall & J.H. Stacy for N. Trübner & Co. for the Early English Text Society<space/></arg><arg name="location">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="date">1883<space/></arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="last">Loyn<space/></arg><arg name="first">Henry Royston<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Social and Economic History of England: Anglo-Saxon England and the Norman Conquest, ''2nd ed.''<space/></arg><arg name="date">1991<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Longman Group<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0582072978<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg></template>.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Germanic peoples</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Angles (people)</target><part>Angles</part></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Germanic peoples</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Northumberland</target></link><link><target>Category:Migration Period</target></link><link><target>Category:Peoples of Anglo-Saxon England</target></link><link><target>Category:Post-medieval constructs about the Middle Ages</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles with images not understandable by color blind users</target></link></paragraph></article>