<article title='Don_Quixote'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg name="name"><space/>Don Quixote
</arg><arg name="title_orig"><space/>{{lang|es|El Ingenioso Hidalgo Don Quixote De la Mancha}}
</arg><arg name="translator">
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>El ingenioso hidalgo don Quijote de la Mancha.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Title page of first edition (1605)
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Miguel de Cervantes]]
</arg><arg name="illustrator">
</arg><arg name="cover_artist">
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>Spain
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>Spanish
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Burlesque]]
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Francisco de Robles]]
</arg><arg name="pub_date"><space/>1605 (Part One)<br>1615 (Part Two)
</arg><arg name="english_pub_date"><space/>1612 (Part One)<br>1620 (Part Two)
</arg><arg name="media_type"><space/>Print
</arg><arg name="pages">
</arg><arg name="isbn">
</arg><arg name="oclc">
</arg><arg name="dewey"><space/>863
</arg><arg name="congress"><space/>PQ6323
</arg></template><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>'''''Don Quixote'''''</arg></template><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>_</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>w</arg><arg>ɪ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>ə</arg><arg>t</arg><arg></arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Oxford English Dictionary, s.v. Don Quixote</extension><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˌ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>ɒ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>_</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>h</arg><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>iː</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>IPA-es</target><arg>ˈdoŋ kiˈxote</arg><arg>lang</arg><arg>Don Quijote-pronunciation-es 2.ogg</arg></template>), fully titled<space/><bold><italics>The Ingenious Gentleman Don Quixote of La Mancha</italics></bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-es</target><arg name="link">no</arg><arg>El ingenioso hidalgo don Quijote de la Mancha</arg></template>), is a Spanish novel by<space/><link><target>Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra</target></link>. Published in two volumes, in 1605 and 1615,<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>is considered one of the most influential works of literature from the<space/><link><target>Spanish Golden Age</target></link><space/>and the entire Spanish literary canon. As a founding work of modern Western literature and one of the earliest<space/><link><target>Western canon</target><part>canonical</part></link><space/>novels, it regularly appears high on lists of the greatest works of fiction ever published, such as the<space/><link><target>Bokklubben World Library</target></link><space/>collection that cites<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>as authors' choice for the &quot;best literary work ever written&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Angelique</arg><arg name="first">Chrisafis</arg><arg name="title">Don Quixote is the world's best book say the world's top authors</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2002/may/08/humanities.books</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 October 2012</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="work">The Guardian</arg><arg name="date">21 July 2003</arg></template></extension>It follows the adventures of a nameless<space/><link><target>Hidalgo (nobility)</target><part>hidalgo</part></link><space/>who reads so many<space/><link><target>chivalric romance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that he loses his sanity and decides to set out to revive<space/><link><target>chivalry</target></link>, undo wrongs, and bring justice to the world, under the name<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>He recruits a simple farmer,<space/><link><target>Sancho Panza</target></link>, as his squire, who often employs a unique, earthy wit in dealing with Don Quixote's rhetorical orations on antiquated<space/><link><target>knighthood</target></link>. Don Quixote, in the first part of the book, does not see the world for what it is and prefers to imagine that he is living out a knightly story. Throughout the novel, Cervantes uses such literary techniques as<space/><link><target>Realism (arts)</target><part>realism</part></link>,<space/><link><target>metatheatre</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>intertextuality</target></link>. It had a major influence on the literary community, as evidenced by direct references in<space/><link><target>Alexandre Dumas</target></link>'<space/><italics><link><target>The Three Musketeers</target></link></italics><space/>(1844),<space/><link><target>Mark Twain</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Adventures of Huckleberry Finn</target></link></italics><space/>(1884) and<space/><link><target>Edmond Rostand</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Cyrano de Bergerac (play)</target><part>Cyrano de Bergerac</part></link></italics><space/>(1897), as well as the word &quot;<link><target>quixotic (disambiguation)</target><part>quixotic</part></link>&quot;.<space/><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target></link><space/>cited<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>as one of the four greatest novels ever written, along with<space/><italics><link><target>The Life and Opinions of Tristram Shandy, Gentleman</target><part>Tristram Shandy</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Julie, or the New Heloise</target><part>La Nouvelle Hlose</part></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Wilhelm Meister's Apprenticeship</target><part>Wilhelm Meister</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="schopenhauer_art"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last"><space/>Schopenhauer</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Arthur</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Art of Literature</arg><arg name="work"><space/>The Essays of Arthur Schopenahuer<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/10714/pg10714.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>March 22, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Summary</heading><paragraph>Miguel de Cervantes said that the first chapters are taken from &quot;The Archive of La Mancha&quot; and the rest translated from the Arabic from the Moorish author Cide Hamete Benengeli. This metafictional trick appears to be designed to give a greater credibility to the text, by implying that Don Quixote is a real character and that the story truly occurred several decades back.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Part 1</heading><heading level='4'>The First Sally (Chapters 15)</heading><paragraph>Alonso Quixano, the protagonist of the novel (though he is not given this name until much later in the book), is a Hidalgo (member of the lesser Spanish nobility), nearing fifty years of age, living in an unnamed section of<space/><link><target>La Mancha</target></link><space/>with his niece and housekeeper, as well as a boy who is never heard of again after the first chapter. Although Quixano is usually a rational man, his reading in excess of books of<space/><link><target>chivalry</target></link><space/>has produced the distortion of his perception and the wavering of his mental faculties. In keeping with the<space/><link><target>humorism</target><part>humoral</part></link><space/>theory of the time, not sleeping adequately because he was reading has caused his brain to dry; Quixano's temperament is thus<space/><link><target>choleric</target></link>, the hot and dry humor. As a result, he is easily given to anger<extension extension_name='ref'>Otis H. Green. &quot;El Ingenioso Hidalgo&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Hispanic Review</target></link></italics><space/>25 (1957), 175193.</extension><space/>and believes every word of these fictional books of chivalry to be true.</paragraph><paragraph>Imitating the protagonists of these books, he decides to become a<space/><link><target>knight-errant</target></link><space/>in search of adventure. To these ends, he dons an old suit of<space/><link><target>armour</target></link>, renames himself &quot;Don Quixote&quot;, names his exhausted horse &quot;<link><target>Rocinante</target></link>&quot;, and designates Aldonza Lorenzo, a neighboring farm girl, as his<space/><link><target>Courtly love</target><part>lady love</part></link>, renaming her<space/><link><target>Dulcinea</target><part>Dulcinea del Toboso</part></link>, while she knows nothing of this. Expecting to become famous quickly, he arrives at an<space/><link><target>inn</target></link>, which he believes to be a<space/><link><target>castle</target></link>; calls the prostitutes he meets &quot;ladies&quot; (<italics>doncellas</italics>); and asks the innkeeper, whom he takes as the lord of the castle, to dub him a knight. He spends the night holding<space/><link><target>vigil</target></link><space/>over his armor, and becomes involved in a fight with<space/><link><target>Arriero</target><part>muleteers</part></link><space/>who try to remove his armor from the horse trough so that they can water their mules. In a pretended ceremony, the innkeeper dubs him a knight to be rid of him, and sends him on his way.</paragraph><paragraph>Don Quixote next &quot;frees&quot; a young boy tied to a tree and beaten by his master, and makes his master swear to treat the boy fairly; but the boy's beating is continued as soon as Quixote leaves. Don Quixote then encounters traders from<space/><link><target>Toledo, Spain</target><part>Toledo</part></link>, who &quot;insult&quot; the imaginary Dulcinea. He attacks them, only to be severely beaten and left on the side of the road, and returned to his home by a neighboring peasant.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Destruction of Don Quixote's library (Chapters 6 and 7)</heading><paragraph>While Don Quixote is unconscious in his bed, his niece, the housekeeper, the parish<space/><link><target>curate</target></link><space/>and the local barber burn most of his chivalric and other books. A large part of this section consists of the priest deciding which books deserve to be burned and which to be saved. This gives occasion for many comments on books Cervantes liked and disliked. For example, Cervantes' own pastoral novel<space/><italics><link><target>La Galatea</target></link></italics><space/>is saved, while the rather unbelievable romance<space/><italics>Felixmarte de Hyrcania</italics><space/>is burned. After the books are dealt with, they seal up the room which contained the library, later telling Don Quixote that it was the action of a wizard (<italics>encantador</italics>).</paragraph><heading level='4'>The Second Sally</heading><paragraph>After a short period of feigning health, Don Quixote requests his neighbor, Sancho Panza, to be his squire, promising him governorship of an island, or insula. Sancho, who is both greedy and unintelligent, agrees to the offer and sneaks away with Don Quixote in the early dawn. It is here that their famous adventures begin, starting with Don Quixote's attack on<space/><link><target>Tilting at windmills</target><part>windmills that he believes to be ferocious giants</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The two next encounter a group of friars accompanying a lady in a carriage. Don Quixote takes the friars to be enchanters who hold the lady captive, knocks a friar from his horse, and is immediately challenged by an armed<space/><link><target>Basque people</target><part>Basque</part></link><space/>traveling with the company. As he has no shield, the Basque uses a pillow to protect himself, which saves him when Don Quixote strikes him. Cervantes chooses this point, in the middle of the battle, to say that his source ends here. Soon, however, he resumes Don Quixote's adventures after a story about finding Arabic notebooks containing the rest of the story by Cid Hamet Ben Engeli. The combat ends with the lady leaving her carriage and commanding those traveling with her to &quot;surrender&quot; to Don Quixote.</paragraph><heading level='5'>The Pastoral Wanderings</heading><paragraph>Sancho and Don Quixote fall in with a group of goatherders. Don Quixote tells Sancho and the goatherders about the &quot;Golden Age&quot; of man, in which property does not exist and men live in peace. The goatherders invite the Knight and Sancho to the funeral of Grisstomo, once a student who left his studies to become a shepherd after reading pastoral novels (paralleling Don Quixote's decision to become a knight), seeking the shepherdess Marcela. At the funeral Marcela appears, vindicating herself from the bitter verses written about her by Grisstomo, and claiming her own autonomy and freedom from expectations put on her by pastoral clichs. She disappears into the woods, and Don Quixote and Sancho follow. Ultimately giving up, the two dismount by a pond to rest. Some<space/><link><target>Galician people</target><part>Galicians</part></link><space/>arrive to water their ponies, and Rocinante (Don Quixote's horse) attempts to mate with the ponies. The Galicians hit Rocinante with clubs to dissuade him, whereupon Don Quixote tries to defend Rocinante. The Galicians beat Don Quixote and Sancho, leaving them in great pain.</paragraph><heading level='5'>The Inn</heading><paragraph>After escaping the muleteers, Don Quixote and Sancho ride to a nearby inn. Once again, Don Quixote imagines the inn is a castle, although Sancho is not quite convinced. Don Quixote is given a bed in a former hayloft, and Sancho sleeps on the rug next to the bed; they share the loft with a muleteer. When night comes, Don Quixote imagines the servant girl at the inn, Maritornes, to be a beautiful princess, and makes her sit on his bed with him, scaring her. Seeing what is happening, the muleteer attacks Don Quixote, breaking the fragile bed and leading to a large and chaotic fight in which Don Quixote and Sancho are once again badly hurt. Don Quixote's explanation for everything is that they fought with an enchanted Moor. He also believes that he can cure their wounds with a mixture he calls &quot;the balm of Fierarbras&quot;, which only makes them sick. Don Quixote and Sancho decide to leave the inn, but Quixote, following the example of the fictional knights, leaves without paying. Sancho, however, remains and ends up wrapped in a blanket and tossed up in the air (blanketed) by several mischievous guests at the inn, something that is often mentioned over the rest of the novel. After his release, he and Don Quixote continue their travels.</paragraph><heading level='5'>The adventures with Cardenio and Dorotea</heading><paragraph>After Don Quixote frees a group of<space/><link><target>galley slave</target><trail>s</trail></link>, he and Sancho wander into the<space/><link><target>Sierra Morena</target></link>, and there encounter the dejected<space/><link><target>The History of Cardenio</target><part>Cardenio</part></link>. Cardenio relates the first part of his<space/><link><target>The History of Cardenio#Synopsis of &quot;Cardenio&quot;, the episode in the novel Don Quixote</target><part>story</part></link>, in which he falls deeply in love with his childhood friend Luscinda, and is hired as the companion to the Duke's son, leading to his friendship with the Duke's younger son, Don Fernando. Cardenio confides in Don Fernando his love for Luscinda and the delays in their engagement, caused by Cardenio's desire to keep with tradition. After reading Cardenio's poems praising Luscinda, Don Fernando falls in love with her. Don Quixote interrupts when Cardenio suggests that his beloved may have become unfaithful after the formulaic stories of spurned lovers in chivalric novels.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Don Quijote and Sancho Panza.jpg</target><part>250px</part><part>thumb</part><part>''Don Quixote de la Mancha and Sancho Panza'', 1863, by<space/><link><target>Gustave Dor</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the course of their travels, the protagonists meet innkeepers, prostitutes, goatherders, soldiers, priests, escaped convicts and scorned lovers. The aforementioned characters sometimes tell tales that incorporate events from the real world, like the conquest of the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Maynila</target></link><space/>or battles in the<space/><link><target>Eighty Years' War</target></link>. Their encounters are magnified by Don Quixote's imagination into chivalrous quests. Don Quixote's tendency to intervene violently in matters irrelevant to himself, and his habit of not paying debts, result in privations, injuries and humiliations (with Sancho often the victim). Finally, Don Quixote is persuaded to return to his home village. The narrator hints that there was a third quest, but says that records of it have been lost.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Part 2</heading><heading level='4'>The Third Sally</heading><paragraph>Although the two parts are now published as a single work,<space/><italics>Don Quixote, Part Two</italics><space/>was a sequel published ten years after the original novel. While<space/><italics>Part One</italics><space/>was mostly farcical, the second half is more serious and philosophical about the theme of deception.</paragraph><paragraph>As<space/><italics>Part Two</italics><space/>begins, it is assumed that the literate classes of Spain have all read the first part of the story. Cervantes's<space/><link><target>meta-fiction</target><trail>al</trail></link><space/>device was to make even the characters in the story familiar with the publication of<space/><italics>Part One</italics>, as well as with an actually published, fraudulent Part Two. When strangers encounter the duo in person, they already know their famous history. A Duke and Duchess, and others, deceive Don Quixote for entertainment, setting forth a string of imagined adventures resulting in a series of practical jokes. Some of them put Don Quixote's sense of chivalry and his devotion to Dulcinea through many tests. Pressed into finding Dulcinea, Sancho brings back three ragged peasant girls, and tells Don Quixote that they are Dulcinea and her ladies-in-waiting. When Don Quixote only sees the peasant girls, Sancho pretends (reversing some incidents of<space/><italics>Part One</italics>) that their derelict appearance results from an enchantment.</paragraph><paragraph>Sancho later gets his comeuppance for this when, as part of one of the Duke and Duchess's pranks, the two are led to believe that the only method to release Dulcinea from her spell is for Sancho to give himself three thousand lashes. Sancho naturally resists this course of action, leading to friction with his master. Under the Duke's patronage, Sancho eventually gets a governorship, though it is false; and he proves to be a wise and practical ruler; though this ends in humiliation as well. Near the end, Don Quixote reluctantly sways towards sanity.</paragraph><paragraph>The lengthy untold &quot;history&quot; of Don Quixote's adventures in knight-errantry comes to a close after his battle with the Knight of the White Moon (a young man from Don Quixote's hometown who had previously posed as the Knight of Mirrors) on the beach in<space/><link><target>Barcelona</target></link>, in which the reader finds him conquered. Bound by the rules of chivalry, Don Quixote submits to prearranged terms that the vanquished is to obey the will of the conqueror: here, it is that Don Quixote is to lay down his arms and cease his acts of chivalry for the period of one year (in which he may be cured of his madness).</paragraph><paragraph>Upon returning to his village, Don Quixote announces his plan to retire to the countryside as a shepherd, but his housekeeper urges him to stay home. Soon after, he retires to his bed with a deathly illness, and later awakes from a dream, having fully recovered his sanity. Sancho tries to restore his faith, but Quixano (his proper name) only renounces his previous ambition and apologizes for the harm he has caused. He dictates his will, which includes a provision that his niece will be disinherited if she marries a man who reads books of chivalry. After Alonso Quixano dies, the author emphasizes that there are no more adventures to relate, and that any further books about Don Quixote would be spurious.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Part Two</italics><space/>of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>explores the concept of a character understanding that he is written about: an idea much explored in the 20th century.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Meaning</heading><paragraph><link><target>Harold Bloom</target></link><space/>says that<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>is the writing of radical<space/><link><target>nihilism</target></link><space/>and anarchy, preferring the glory of fantasy over the real world which includes imminent death, being &quot;...the first modern novel&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/books/2003/dec/13/classics.miguelcervantes'>The Knight in the Mirror</link><space/>a 2003 book report in<space/><link><target>The Guardian</target></link><space/>about<space/><link><target>Harold Bloom</target></link>'s book.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Edith Grossman</target></link>, who wrote and published a highly acclaimed English translation of the novel in 2003, says that the book is mostly meant to move people into emotion using a systematic change of course, on the verge of both tragedy and comedy at the same time. Grossman has stated: &quot;The question is that Quixote has multiple interpretations... and how do I deal with that in my translation. I'm going to answer your question by avoiding it... so when I first started reading the Quixote I thought it was the most tragic book in the world, and I would read it and weep... As I grew older...my skin grew thicker... and so when I was working on the translation I was actually sitting at my computer and laughing out loud. This is done... as Cervantes did it... by never letting the reader rest. You are never certain that you truly got it. Because as soon as you think you understand something, Cervantes introduces something that contradicts your premise.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=muOZ6WdAg3o'>Edith Grossman about Don Quixote as tragedy and comedy</link><space/>a discussion held in New York City on 5 February 2009 by<space/><link><target>Words Without Borders</target></link><space/>(YouTube)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>List of works influenced by Don Quixote</arg></template><link><target>File:Honor Daumier 017 (Don Quixote).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Don Quixote by<space/><link><target>Honor Daumier</target></link><space/>(1868)</part></link>The novel's structure is in<space/><link><target>episode</target><part>episodic</part></link><space/>form. It is written in the<space/><italics><link><target>Picaresque novel</target><part>picaresco</part></link></italics><space/>style of the late 16th century, and features reference other picaresque novels including<space/><italics><link><target>Lazarillo de Tormes</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Ass</target></link></italics>. The full title is indicative of the tale's object, as<space/><italics>ingenioso</italics><space/>(Spanish) means &quot;quick with inventiveness&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>ingenio<space/><sup>'''1'''</sup></arg></template>,<space/><italics>Real Academia Espaola</italics></extension><space/>marking the transition of modern literature from<space/><link><target>Classical unities</target><part>dramatic</part></link><space/>to thematic unity. The novel takes place over a long period of time, including many adventures united by common themes of the nature of reality, reading, and dialogue in general.</paragraph><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>burlesque</target></link><space/>on the surface, the novel, especially in its second half, has served as an important thematic source not only in literature but also in much of art and music, inspiring works by<space/><link><target>Pablo Picasso</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Richard Strauss</target></link>. The contrasts between the tall, thin, fancy-struck and idealistic Quixote and the fat, squat, world-weary Panza is a motif echoed ever since the book's publication, and Don Quixote's imaginings are the butt of outrageous and cruel practical jokes in the novel.</paragraph><paragraph>Even faithful and simple Sancho is forced to deceive him at certain points. The novel is considered a satire of<space/><link><target>orthodoxy</target></link>, veracity and even nationalism. In exploring the individualism of his characters, Cervantes helped move beyond the narrow literary conventions of the<space/><link><target>chivalric romance</target></link><space/>literature that he<space/><link><target>Parody</target><part>spoofed</part></link>, which consists of straightforward retelling of a series of acts that redound to the<space/><link><target>Chivalry</target><part>knightly virtues</part></link><space/>of the hero. The character of Don Quixote became so well known in its time that the word<space/><italics><link><target>Quixotism</target><part>quixotic</part></link></italics><space/>was quickly adopted by many languages. Characters such as Sancho Panza and Don Quixote's steed,<space/><link><target>Rocinante</target></link>, are emblems of Western literary culture. The phrase &quot;<link><target>tilting at windmills</target></link>&quot; to describe an act of attacking imaginary enemies, derives from an iconic scene in the book.</paragraph><paragraph>It stands in a unique position between medieval<space/><link><target>Romance (heroic literature)</target><part>chivalric romance</part></link><space/>and the modern novel. The former consist of disconnected stories featuring the same characters and settings with little exploration of the inner life of even the main character. The latter are usually focused on the psychological evolution of their characters. In Part I, Quixote imposes himself on his environment. By Part II, people know about him through &quot;having read his adventures&quot;, and so, he needs to do less to maintain his image. By his deathbed, he has regained his sanity, and is once more &quot;Alonso Quixano the Good&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>When first published,<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>was usually interpreted as a<space/><link><target>comic novel</target></link>. After the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>it was popular for its central ethic that individuals can be right while society is quite wrong and seen as disenchanting. In the 19th century it was seen as a social commentary, but no one could easily tell &quot;whose side Cervantes was on&quot;. Many critics came to view the work as a tragedy in which Don Quixote's idealism and<space/><link><target>nobility</target></link><space/>are viewed by the post-chivalric world as insane, and are defeated and rendered useless by common reality. By the 20th century the novel had come to occupy a canonical space as one of the foundations of modern literature.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><heading level='3'>Sources</heading><paragraph>Sources for<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>include the Castillian novel<space/><italics><link><target>Amadis de Gaula</target></link></italics>, which had enjoyed great popularity throughout the 16th century. Another prominent source, which Cervantes evidently admires more, is<space/><italics><link><target>Tirant lo Blanch</target></link></italics>, which the priest describes in Chapter VI of<space/><italics>Quixote</italics><space/>as &quot;the best book in the world.&quot; (However, the sense in which it was &quot;best&quot; is much debated among scholars. The passage is called since the 19th century &quot;the most difficult passage of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>&quot;.)The scene of the book burning gives us an excellent list of Cervantes's likes and dislikes about literature.</paragraph><paragraph>Cervantes makes a number of references to the Italian poem<space/><italics><link><target>Orlando furioso</target></link></italics>. In chapter 10 of the first part of the novel, Don Quixote says he must take the magical helmet of Mambrino, an episode from Canto I of<space/><italics>Orlando</italics>, and itself a reference to<space/><link><target>Matteo Maria Boiardo</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Orlando innamorato</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Don Quijote de la Mancha</italics>, Miguel de Cervantes, Edicin de Florencio Sevilla Arroyo, rea 2002 p.161</extension><space/>The interpolated story in chapter 33 of Part four of the First Part is a retelling of a tale from Canto 43 of<space/><italics>Orlando</italics>, regarding a man who tests the fidelity of his wife.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Don Quixote&quot; by Miguel de Cervantes, translated and annotated by Edith Grossman, p.272</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another important source appears to have been Apuleius's<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Ass</target></link></italics>, one of the earliest known novels, a picaresque from late classical antiquity. The wineskins episode near the end of the interpolated tale &quot;The Curious Impertinent&quot; in chapter 35 of the first part of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>is a clear reference to Apuleius, and recent scholarship suggests that the moral philosophy and the basic trajectory of Apuleius's novel are fundamental to Cervantes's program.<extension extension_name='ref'>See chapter 2 of E. C. Graf's<space/><italics>Cervantes and Modernity</italics>.</extension><space/>Similarly, many of both Sancho's adventures in Part II and proverbs throughout are taken from popular Spanish and Italian folklore.</paragraph><paragraph>Cervantes's experiences as a<space/><link><target>galley slave</target></link><space/>in Algiers also influenced<space/><italics>Quixote</italics>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spurious<space/><italics>Second Part</italics><space/>by Avellaneda</heading><paragraph>It is not certain when Cervantes began writing<space/><italics>Part Two</italics><space/>of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, but he had probably not gotten much further than Chapter LIX by late July 1614. About September, however, a spurious Part Two, entitled<space/><italics>Second Volume of the Ingenious Gentleman Don Quixote of La Mancha: by the Licenciado (doctorate)<space/><link><target>Alonso Fernndez de Avellaneda</target></link>, of<space/><link><target>Tordesillas</target></link></italics>, was published in<space/><link><target>Tarragona</target></link><space/>by an unidentified<space/><link><target>Aragon</target><trail>ese</trail></link><space/>who was an admirer of<space/><link><target>Lope de Vega</target></link>, rival of Cervantes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ei">D. Eisenberg, &quot;Cervantes, Lope and Avellaneda&quot;,<space/><italics>Estudios cervantinos</italics><space/>(Barcelona: Sirmio, 1991), pp. 11941, http://www.cervantesvirtual.com/servlet/SirveObras/hisp/56826142007993728511191/p0000002.htm#I_7_.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some modern scholars suggest that Don Quixote's fictional encounter with Avellaneda in Chapter 59 of Part II should not be taken as the date that<space/><italics>Cervantes</italics><space/>encountered it, which may have been much earlier.</paragraph><paragraph>Avellaneda's identity has been the subject of many theories, but there is no consensus as to who he was. In its prologue, the author gratuitously insulted Cervantes, who not surprisingly took offense and responded; the last half of Chapter LIX and most of the following chapters of Cervantes'<space/><italics>Segunda Parte</italics><space/>lend some insight into the effects upon him; Cervantes manages to work in some subtle digs at Avellaneda's own work, and in his preface to Part II, comes very near to criticizing Avellaneda directly.</paragraph><paragraph>In his introduction to<space/><italics>The Portable Cervantes</italics>,<space/><link><target>Samuel Putnam</target></link>, a noted translator of Cervantes' novel, calls Avellaneda's version &quot;one of the most disgraceful performances in history&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cervantes, Miguel,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=9eAOicE_b4AC&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;dq=putnam+portable+cervantes&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=0A3QTfiaBIHz0gGF4aSfDg&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=1&amp;amp;ved=0CCoQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>''The Portable Cervantes''</link>, ed. Samuel Putnam (New York: Penguin, [1951] 1978), p. viii</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second part of Cervantes'<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, finished as a direct result of the Avellaneda book, has come to be regarded by some literary critics<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Putnam</arg><arg name="first">Samuel</arg><arg name="title">Introduction to The Portable Cervantes</arg><arg name="year">1976</arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin</arg><arg name="location">Harmondsworth</arg><arg name="isbn">0-14-015057-9</arg><arg name="page">14</arg></template></extension><space/>as superior to the first part, because of its greater depth of characterization, its discussions, mostly between Quixote and Sancho, on diverse subjects, and its philosophical insights.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Other stories</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Quixo-panza.jpg</target><part>Don Quixote and Sancho Panza</part><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Don Quixote, his horse Rocinante and his squire Sancho Panza after an unsuccessful attack on a windmill. By<space/><link><target>Gustave Dor</target></link>.</part></link><italics>Don Quixote, Part One</italics><space/>contains a number of stories which do not directly involve the two main characters, but which are narrated by some of the<space/><link><target>picaresque</target></link><space/>figures encountered by the Don and Sancho during their travels. The longest and best known of these is &quot;El Curioso Impertinente&quot; (the impertinently curious man), found in Part One, Book Four. This story, read to a group of travelers at an inn, tells of a<space/><link><target>Florence</target><part>Florentine</part></link><space/>nobleman, Anselmo, who becomes obsessed with testing his wife's fidelity, and talks his close friend<space/><link><target>Lothario</target></link><space/>into attempting to seduce her, with disastrous results for all.</paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Part Two</italics>, the author acknowledges the criticism of his digressions in<space/><italics>Part One</italics><space/>and promises to concentrate the narrative on the central characters (although at one point he laments that his narrative muse has been constrained in this manner). Nevertheless, &quot;Part Two&quot; contains several back narratives related by peripheral characters.</paragraph><paragraph>Several abridged editions have been published which delete some or all of the extra tales in order to concentrate on the central narrative.<extension extension_name='ref'>An example is<space/><italics>The Portable Cervantes</italics><space/>(New York: Viking Penguin, 1949), which contains an abridged version of the Samuel Putnam translation.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Style</heading><heading level='3'>Spelling and pronunciation</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template>Cervantes wrote his work in an early modern form of Spanish, heavily borrowing from<space/><link><target>Old Spanish language</target><part>Old Castilian</part></link>, the medieval form of the Spanish language. The language of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, although still containing<space/><link><target>archaisms</target></link>, is far more understandable to modern Spanish readers than is, for instance, the completely medieval Spanish of the<space/><italics><link><target>Poema de mio Cid</target></link></italics>, a kind of Spanish that is as different from Cervantes's language as<space/><link><target>Middle English</target></link><space/>is from<space/><link><target>Modern English</target></link>. The Old Castilian language was also used to show the higher class that came with being a knight errant.</paragraph><paragraph>In Don Quixote there are basically two different types of Castilian: Old Castilian is spoken only by Don Quixote, while the rest of the roles speak a modern version of Spanish. The Old Castilian of Don Quixote is a humoristic resource he copies the language spoken in the chivalric books that made him mad; and many times, when he talks nobody is able to understand him because his language is too old. This humorous effect is more difficult to see nowadays because the reader must be able to distinguish the two old versions of the language, but when the book was published it was much celebrated. (English translations can get some sense of the effect by having Don Quixote use King James Bible or Shakespearian English phrases.)</paragraph><paragraph>In Old Castilian the letter<space/><italics>x</italics><space/>represented the sound written<space/><italics>sh</italics><space/>in modern English, so the name was originally pronounced &quot;<template><target>Respell</target><arg>ki</arg><arg>SHOT</arg><arg>eh</arg></template><space/>&quot;<template><target>IPA</target><arg>[kiˈʃote]</arg></template>. However, as Old Castilian evolved towards modern Spanish, a<space/><link><target>sound change</target></link><space/>caused it to be pronounced with a<space/><link><target>voiceless velar fricative</target></link><space/>sound (like the<space/><link><target>Scots language</target><part>Scottish</part></link><space/>or German<space/><italics>ch</italics>), and today the Spanish pronunciation of &quot;Quixote&quot; is<space/><template><target>respell</target><arg>ki</arg><arg>HO</arg><arg>teh</arg></template><space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>[kiˈxote]</arg></template>. The original pronunciation is reflected in languages such as<space/><link><target>Astur-Leonese</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Galician language</target><part>Galician</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Catalan language</target><part>Catalan</part></link>, Italian,<space/><link><target>Portuguese language</target><part>Portuguese</part></link>, and French, where it is pronounced with a &quot;sh&quot; or &quot;ch&quot; sound; the French opera<space/><italics><link><target>Don Quichotte</target></link></italics><space/>is one of the best-known modern examples of this pronunciation.</paragraph><paragraph>Today, English speakers generally attempt something close to the modern Spanish pronunciation of<space/><italics>Quixote</italics><space/>(<italics>Quijote</italics>), as<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>[dɒŋ kiːˈhoʊteɪ]</arg></template><space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template>, although the traditional English<space/><link><target>spelling pronunciation</target><part>spelling-based pronunciation</part></link><space/>with the value of the letter x in modern English is still sometimes used, resulting in<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>/ˈkwɪksət/</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>/ˈkwɪksoʊt/</arg></template>. In<space/><link><target>Australian English</target></link>, the preferred pronunciation amongst members of the educated classes was<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>/ˈkwɪksət/</arg></template><space/>until well into the 1970s, as part of a tendency for the upper class to &quot;anglicise its borrowing ruthlessly&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="editor1-first">P. H.</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Peters</arg><arg name="title">Style in Australia: current practices in spelling, punctuation, hyphenation, capitalisation, etc.</arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="publisher">Dictionary Research Centre, [[Macquarie University]]</arg><arg name="location">[[Macquarie Park, New South Wales]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0858375885</arg><arg name="pages">48–49</arg></template></extension><space/>The traditional English rendering is preserved in the pronunciation of the adjectival form<space/><italics><link><target>quixotism</target><part>quixotic</part></link></italics>, i.e.,<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>/kwɪkˈsoʊtɨk/</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPA</target><arg>/kwɪkˈsɒtɪk/</arg></template>, defined by<space/><link><target>Merriam-Webster</target></link><space/>as the foolishly impractical pursuit of ideals, typically marked by rash and lofty romanticism.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/quixotic<space/></arg><arg name="title">Quixotic<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">17 May 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Setting</heading><paragraph>Cervantes' story takes place on the plains of<space/><link><target>La Mancha</target></link>, specifically the<space/><italics><link><target>comarca</target></link></italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Campo de Montiel (Ciudad Real)</target><part>Campo de Montiel</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">''En un lugar de La Mancha, de cuyo nombre no quiero acordarme, no ha mucho tiempo que vivía un hidalgo de los de lanza en astillero, adarga antigua, rocín flaco y galgo corredor.''<br/>(Somewhere in La Mancha, in a place whose name I do not care to remember, a gentleman lived not long ago, one of those who has a lance and ancient shield on a shelf and keeps a skinny nag and a greyhound for racing.)</arg><arg name="sign">Miguel de Cervantes</arg><arg name="source">''Don Quixote'', Volume I, Chapter I (translated by [[Edith Grossman]])</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The story also takes place in El Toboso where Don Quixote goes to seek Dulcinea's blessings.The location of the village to which Cervantes alludes in the opening sentence of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>has been the subject of debate since its publication over four centuries ago. Indeed, Cervantes deliberately omits the name of the village, giving an explanation in the final chapter:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">Such was the end of the Ingenious Gentleman of La Mancha, whose village Cide Hamete would not indicate precisely, in order to leave all the towns and villages of La Mancha to contend among themselves for the right to adopt him and claim him as a son, as the seven cities of Greece contended for Homer.</arg><arg name="sign">Miguel de Cervantes</arg><arg name="source">''Don Quixote'', Volume II, Chapter 74</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 2004, a multidisciplinary team of academics from<space/><link><target>Complutense University</target></link>, led by Francisco Parra Luna, Manuel Fernndez Nieto and Santiago Petschen Verdaguer, deduced that the village was that of<space/><link><target>Villanueva de los Infantes, Ciudad Real</target><part>Villanueva de los Infantes</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.timesonline.co.uk/tol/news/world/article404423.ece</arg><arg name="title">To Quixote's village at the speed of a nag</arg><arg name="publisher">Times Online<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>Their findings were published in a paper titled<space/><italics>&quot;'El Quijote' como un sistema de distancias/tiempos: hacia la localizacin del lugar de la Mancha&quot;</italics>, which was later published as a book:<space/><italics>El enigma resuelto del Quijote</italics>. The result was replicated in two subsequent investigations:<space/><italics>&quot;La determinacin del lugar de la Mancha como problema estadstico&quot;</italics><space/>and &quot;The Kinematics of the Quixote and the Identity of the 'Place in La Mancha'&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">La determinación del lugar de la Mancha como problema estadístico</arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/></arg><arg name="location">Valencia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Department of Statistics, [[University of Malaga]]<space/></arg><arg name="language">Spanish<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://dmle.cindoc.csic.es/pdf/BEIO_2006_22_01_04.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Kinematics of the Quixote and the Identity of the "Place in La Mancha"<space/></arg><arg name="page">7<space/></arg><arg name="location">Valencia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Department of Applied Mathematics, [[University of Valencia]]<space/></arg><arg name="format">PDF<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.uv.es/pla/Quixote/Kinematics2.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Researchers Isabel Sanchez Duque and Francisco Javier Escudero have found relevant information regarding the possible sources of inspiration of Cervantes for writing Don Quixote. Cervantes was friend of the family Villaseor, which was involved in a combat with Francisco de Acua. Both sides combated disguised as medieval knights in the road from<space/><link><target>El Toboso</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Miguel Esteban</target></link><space/>in 1581. They also found a person called Rodrigo Quijada, who bought the title of nobility of &quot;hidalgo&quot;, and created diverse conflicts with the help of a squire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.elmundo.es/cronica/2014/12/07/54830651268e3e242b8b4576.html</arg><arg name="title">Don Quijote era Acuña el Procurador</arg><arg name="publisher">El Mundo<space/></arg><arg name="location">Madrid</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://cultura.elpais.com/cultura/2014/12/07/actualidad/1417983722_234613.html</arg><arg name="title">Don Quijote de La Mancha: ¿realidad o ficción?</arg><arg name="publisher">El País<space/></arg><arg name="location">Madrid</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Language</heading><paragraph>Because of its widespread influence,<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>also helped cement the modern Spanish language. The opening sentence of the book created a classic Spanish clich with the phrase<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg><space/>"de cuyo nombre no quiero acordarme"<space/></arg></template><space/>(&quot;whose name I do not wish to recall&quot;):<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg><space/>"En un lugar de la Mancha, de cuyo nombre no quiero acordarme, no hace mucho tiempo que vivía un hidalgo de los de lanza en astillero, adarga antigua, rocín flaco y galgo corredor."</arg></template><space/>(&quot;In a village of La Mancha, whose name I do not wish to recall, there lived, not very long ago, one of those gentlemen with a lance in the lance-rack, an ancient shield, a skinny old horse, and a fast greyhound.&quot;)</paragraph><paragraph>The novel's farcical elements make use of punning and similar verbal playfulness. Character-naming in<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>makes ample figural use of contradiction, inversion, and irony, such as the names<space/><italics><link><target>Rocinante</target></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>rocinante: deriv. of ''rocín'', work horse; colloq., brusque labourer; rough, unkempt man. ''Real Academia Española.''</arg></template></extension><space/>(a reversal) and<space/><italics><link><target>Dulcinea</target></link></italics><space/>(an allusion to illusion), and the word<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>''quixote''</arg></template><space/>itself, possibly a pun on<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>''quijada''</arg></template><space/>(jaw) but certainly<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>''cuixot''</arg></template><space/>(Catalan: thighs), a reference to a horse's<space/><link><target>rump (animal)</target><part>rump</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>quijote<xhtml:sup><bold>1.2</bold></xhtml:sup>: rump or haunch.<space/><italics>Real Academia Espaola.</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As a military term, the word<space/><italics>quijote</italics><space/>refers to<space/><italics><link><target>cuisses</target></link></italics>, part of a full suit of<space/><link><target>plate armour</target></link><space/>protecting the thighs. The Spanish suffix<space/><italics>-ote</italics><space/>denotes the augmentativefor example,<space/><italics>grande</italics><space/>means large, but<space/><italics>grandote</italics><space/>means extra large. Following this example,<space/><italics>Quixote</italics><space/>would suggest 'The Great Quijano', a play on words that makes much sense in light of the character's delusions of grandeur.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>La Mancha</italics><space/>is a region of Spain, but<space/><italics>mancha</italics><space/>(Spanish word) means spot, mark, stain. Translators such as<space/><link><target>John Ormsby (translator)</target><part>John Ormsby</part></link><space/>have declared La Mancha to be one of the most desertlike, unremarkable regions of Spain, the least romantic and fanciful place that one would imagine as the home of a courageous knight.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Publication</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Monumento a Cervantes (Madrid) 10.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Bronze statues of Don Quixote and Sancho Panza, at the<space/><link><target>Plaza de Espaa (Madrid)</target><part>Plaza de Espaa</part></link><space/>in Madrid.</part></link>In July 1604, Cervantes sold the rights of<space/><italics>El ingenioso hidalgo don Quixote de la Mancha</italics><space/>(known as<space/><italics>Don Quixote, Part I</italics>) to the publisher-bookseller Francisco de Robles for an unknown sum<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>July 2015</arg></template>. License to publish was granted in September, the printing was finished in December, and the book came out on 16 January 1605.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.kcl.ac.uk/depsta/iss/library/speccoll/bomarch/bomnov05.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Don Quixote<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[King's College London]]<space/></arg><arg name="first">Hugh<space/></arg><arg name="last">Cahill<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2011-01-14</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BrO"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="title">Cervantes, Miguel de</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Encyclopaedia Britannica</arg><arg name="year">2002</arg></template><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>J. Ormsby,<space/><link type='external' href='http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/c/cervantes/c41d/preface1.html'>&quot;About Cervantes and Don Quixote&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The novel was an immediate success. The majority of the 400 copies of the first<space/><link><target>Edition (book)</target><part>edition</part></link><space/>were sent to the<space/><link><target>New World</target></link>, with the publisher hoping to get a better price in the Americas.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Histoire"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Don Quichotte', best-seller mondial<space/></arg><arg name="author">Serge Gruzinski, teacher at the [[EHESS]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">July–August 2007<space/></arg><arg name="work">n°322<space/></arg><arg name="page">30<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[L'Histoire]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Although most of them disappeared in a shipwreck near<space/><link><target>La Havana</target></link>, approximately 70 copies reached<space/><link><target>Lima</target></link>, from where they were sent to<space/><link><target>Cuzco</target></link><space/>in the heart of the defunct<space/><link><target>Inca Empire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Histoire"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Don Quixote - Engravings by Gustave Dor.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Collage of the engravings of The Adventures of don Quixote by Gustave Dor</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>No sooner was it in the hands of the public than preparations were made to issue derivative (pirated) editions. &quot;Don Quixote&quot; had been growing in favour, and its author's name was now known beyond the<space/><link><target>Pyrenees</target></link>. By August 1605 there were two Madrid editions, two published in Lisbon, and one in<space/><link><target>Valencia</target></link>. Publisher Francisco de Robles secured additional copyrights for<space/><link><target>Crown of Aragon</target><part>Aragon</part></link><space/>and Portugal for a second edition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Orm">J. Ormsby,<space/><link type='external' href='http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/c/cervantes/c41d/preface1.html'>&quot;About Cervantes and Don Quixote&quot;</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sale of these publishing rights deprived Cervantes of further financial profit on<space/><italics>Part One.</italics><space/>In 1607, an edition was printed in<space/><link><target>Brussels</target></link>. Robles, the Madrid publisher, found it necessary to meet demand with a third edition, a seventh publication in all, in 1608. Popularity of the book in Italy was such that a Milan bookseller issued an Italian edition in 1610. Yet another Brussels edition was called for in 1611.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BrO"></extension><space/>Since then, numerous editions have been released and in total, the novel is believed to have sold more than 10 million copies worldwide.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.vanderbilt.edu/magazines/vanderbilt-magazine/archives/images/inclass_f05.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="author">Paul Kingsbury<space/></arg><arg name="title">Lost in La Mancha<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Vanderbilt.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-05</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1613, Cervantes published the<space/><italics>Novelas Ejemplares</italics>, dedicated to the<space/><link><target>Maecenas</target></link><space/>of the day, the<space/><link><target>Conde de Lemos</target></link>. Eight and a half years after<space/><italics>Part One</italics><space/>had appeared, we get the first hint of a forthcoming<space/><italics>Segunda Parte</italics><space/>(Part Two). &quot;You shall see shortly,&quot; Cervantes says, &quot;the further exploits of Don Quixote and humours of Sancho Panza.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>See also the introduction to Cervantes, Miguel de (1984)<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, Penguin p.18, for a discussion of Cervantes's statement in response to Avellaneda's attempt to write a sequel.</extension><space/><italics>Don Quixote, Part Two</italics>, published by the same press as its predecessor, appeared late in 1615, and quickly reprinted in Brussels and Valencia (1616) and Lisbon (1617). Part two capitalizes on the potential of the first while developing and diversifying the material without sacrificing familiarity. Many people agree that it is richer and more profound.<template><target>Who</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/>Parts One and Two were published as one edition in Barcelona in 1617. Historically, Cervantes's work has been said to have &quot;smiled<space/><link><target>Spanish chivalry</target><part>Spain's chivalry</part></link><space/>away&quot;, suggesting that Don Quixote as a chivalric satire contributed to the demise of Spanish Chivalry.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Prestage</arg><arg name="first">Edgar</arg><arg name="title">Chivalry</arg><arg name="year">1928</arg><arg name="page">110</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>English editions in translation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Gustave Dor - Miguel de Cervantes - Don Quixote - Part 1 - Chapter 1 - Plate 1 &quot;A world of disorderly notions, picked out of his books, crowded into his imagination&quot;.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Don Quixote goes mad from his reading of books of chivalry. Engraving by<space/><link><target>Gustave Dor</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>There are many translations of the book, and it has been adapted many times in shortened versions. Many derivative editions were also written at the time, as was the custom of envious or unscrupulous writers. Seven years after the<space/><italics>Parte Primera</italics><space/>appeared,<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics><space/>had been translated into French, German, Italian, and English, with the first French translation of 'Part II' appearing in 1618, and the first English translation in 1620. One abridged adaptation, authored by Agustn Snchez, runs slightly over 150 pages, cutting away about 750 pages.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://belgrado.cervantes.es/Biblioteca/Fichas/Cervantes.%20Saavedra,%20Miguel%20de%20(1547-1616)_114_58_1.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">Library catalogue of the Cervantes Institute of Belgrade<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-12-26</arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://web.archive.org/web/20070814074311/http://belgrado.cervantes.es/Biblioteca/Fichas/Cervantes.%20Saavedra,%20Miguel%20de%20%281547-1616%29_114_58_1.shtml</arg><arg name="archivedate">14 August 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Shelton (translator)</target><part>Thomas Shelton</part></link>'s English translation of the<space/><italics>First Part</italics><space/>appeared in 1612 while Cervantes was still alive, although there is no evidence that Shelton had met the author. Although Shelton's version is cherished by some, according to<space/><link><target>John Ormsby (translator)</target><part>John Ormsby</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Samuel Putnam</target></link>, it was far from satisfactory as a carrying over of Cervantes's text.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Orm"></extension><space/>Shelton's translation of the novel's<space/><italics>Second Part</italics><space/>appeared in 1620.</paragraph><paragraph>Near the end of the 17th century,<space/><link><target>John Phillips (author)</target><part>John Phillips</part></link>, a nephew of poet<space/><link><target>John Milton</target></link>, published what Putnam considered the worst English translation. The translation, as literary critics claim, was not based on Cervantes' text but mostly upon a French work by Filleau de Saint-Martin and upon notes which Thomas Shelton had written.</paragraph><paragraph>Around 1700, a version by<space/><link><target>Pierre Antoine Motteux</target></link><space/>appeared. Motteux's translation enjoyed lasting popularity; it was reprinted as the<space/><link><target>Modern Library</target></link><space/>Series edition of the novel until recent times.<extension extension_name='ref' name="peabody">Sieber, Harry.<space/><link type='external' href='http://quixote.mse.jhu.edu/Translation.html'>&quot;''Don Quixote'' in Translation&quot;.</link><space/><italics>The Don Quixote Exhibit</italics>, Tour 2, Chapter 5. George Peabody Library. 1996. Retrieved 26 December 2012.</extension><space/>Nonetheless, future translators would find much to fault in Motteux's version: Samuel Putnam criticized &quot;the prevailing slapstick quality of this work, especially where<space/><link><target>Sancho Panza</target></link><space/>is involved, the obtrusion of the obscene where it is found in the original, and the slurring of difficulties through omissions or expanding upon the text&quot;. John Ormsby considered Motteux's version &quot;worse than worthless&quot;, and denounced its &quot;infusion of Cockney flippancy and facetiousness&quot; into the original.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">http://cervantes.tamu.edu/english/ctxt/DonQ-JohnOrmsby/DonQ-JohnOrmsby.html</arg><arg name="title">Don Quixote by Miguel de Cervantes, Translated by John Ormsby</arg><arg name="chapter">Translator's Preface: About this translation</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The proverb 'The proof of the pudding is in the eating' is widely attributed to Cervantes. The Spanish word for pudding, 'budn', however doesn't appear in the original text butpremieres in the Motteux translation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Proverb "Proof of the Pudding is in the Eating"<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://phrases.org.uk/meanings/proof-of-the-pudding.html</arg></template></extension><space/>In Smolletts translation of 1755 he notes that the original text reads literally &quot;you will see when the eggs are fried&quot; meaning 'time will tell'.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Don Quixote&quot; by Miguel de Cervantes, translated by Tobias Smollett, Introduction and Notes by Carole Slade; Barnes and Noble Classics, New York p.318</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A translation by Captain<space/><link><target>John Stevens (translator)</target><part>John Stevens</part></link>, which revised Thomas Shelton's version, also appeared in 1700, but its publication was overshadowed by the simultaneous release of Motteux's translation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="peabody"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1742, the<space/><link><target>Charles Jervas</target></link><space/>translation appeared, posthumously. Through a printer's error, it came to be known, and is still known, as &quot;the Jarvis translation&quot;. It was the most scholarly and accurate English translation of the novel up to that time, but future translator John Ormsby points out in his own introduction to the novel that the Jarvis translation has been criticized as being too stiff. Nevertheless, it became the most frequently reprinted translation of the novel until about 1885. Another 18th century translation into English was that of<space/><link><target>Tobias Smollett</target></link>, himself a novelist, first published in 1755. Like the Jarvis translation, it continues to be reprinted today.</paragraph><paragraph>Most modern translators take as their model the 1885 translation by John Ormsby. It is said<template><target>by whom</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template><space/>that his translation was the most honest of all translations, without expansions upon the text or changing of the proverbs.</paragraph><paragraph>An expurgated children's version, under the title<space/><italics>The Story of Don Quixote</italics>, was published in 1922 (available on<space/><link><target>Project Gutenberg</target></link>). It leaves out the risqu sections as well as chapters that young readers might consider dull, and embellishes a great deal on Cervantes's original text. The title page actually gives credit to the two editors as if they were the authors, and omits any mention of Cervantes.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/29468/29468-h/29468-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Project Gutenberg eBook of The Story of Don Quixote, by Arvid Paulson, Clayton Edwards, and Miguel de Cervantes Saavedra<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Gutenberg.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 July 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-05</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The most widely read English-language translations of the mid-20th century are by<space/><link><target>Samuel Putnam</target></link><space/>(1949),<space/><link><target>J. M. Cohen</target></link><space/>(1950;<space/><link><target>Penguin Classics</target></link>), and<space/><link><target>Walter Starkie</target></link><space/>(1957). The last English translation of the novel in the 20th century was by<space/><link><target>Burton Raffel</target></link>, published in 1996. The 21st century has already seen four new translations of the novel into English. The first is by<space/><link><target>John D. Rutherford</target></link><space/>and the second by<space/><link><target>Edith Grossman</target></link>. Reviewing the novel in the<space/><italics>New York Times</italics>,<space/><link><target>Carlos Fuentes</target></link><space/>called Grossman's translation a &quot;major literary achievement&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res</arg><arg name="first">Carlos</arg><arg name="last">Fuentes<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tilt<space/></arg><arg name="work">New York Times</arg><arg name="date">2 November 2003</arg></template></extension><space/>and another called it the &quot;most transparent and least impeded among more than a dozen English translations going back to the 17th century.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res</arg><arg name="title">Beholding Windmills and Wisdom From a New Vantage<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[New York Times]]</arg><arg name="date">14 November 2003</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="last">Eder</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2005, the year of the novel's 400th anniversary,<space/><link><target>Tom Lathrop</target></link><space/>published a new English translation of the novel, based on a lifetime of specialized study of the novel and its history.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.h-net.org/~cervant/csa/artics08/McGraths08.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Reviews: ''Don Quixote'' trans. Tom Lathrop</arg><arg name="publisher">[[H-Net]]</arg><arg name="first">Michael J</arg><arg name="last">McGrath</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg></template></extension>The fourth translation of the 21st century was released in 2006 by former university librarian James Montgomery, 26 years after he had begun it, in an attempt to &quot;recreate the sense of the original as closely as possible, though not at the expense of Cervantes' literary style.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.h-net.org/~cervant/csa/artics10/McGrathS10.pdf</arg><arg name="title">Reviews: ''Don Quixote'' trans. James Montgomery</arg><arg name="publisher">[[H-Net]]</arg><arg name="first">Michael J</arg><arg name="last">McGrath</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Don Quijote on the Internet</heading><paragraph>In April 2015<space/><link><target>Universidad Francisco Marroqun</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link><space/>launched the first massive, open, online course (<link><target>MOOC</target></link>) on Don Quijote de la Mancha. The course, available in both Spanish and English, is free and open to the general public all over the world. Is hosted by the prestigious US Cervantist Eric Clifford Graf. The course consists of 52 chapters uploaded in their entirety to the video server<space/><link><target>YouTube</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://donquijote.ufm.edu/en/</arg><arg name="title">Reviews: ''Discover Don Quijote de la Mancha''</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Novels</arg><arg>Spain</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Alonso Fernndez de Avellaneda</target></link></italics>&amp;nbsp; author of a spurious sequel to<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>, which in turn is referenced in the actual sequel</listitem><listitem><link><target>List of Don Quixote characters</target><part>List of ''Don Quixote'' characters</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of works influenced by Don Quixote</target><part>List of works influenced by ''Don Quixote''</part></link>&amp;nbsp; including a gallery of paintings and illustrations</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Tirant lo Blanc</target></link></italics>&amp;nbsp; one of the chivalric novels frequently referenced by Don Quixote</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Amadis de Gaula</target></link></italics>&amp;nbsp; one of the chivalric novels found in the library of Don Quixote</listitem><listitem><link><target>Antnio Jos da Silva</target></link>&amp;nbsp; writer of<space/><italics>Vida do Grande Dom Quixote de la Mancha e do Gordo Sancho Pana</italics><space/>(1733)</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Belianis</target></link></italics>&amp;nbsp; one of the chivalric novels found in the library of Don Quixote</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuco</target><part>coco</part></link>&amp;nbsp; In the last chapter, the epitaph of Don Quijote identifies him as &quot;el coco&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.gutenberg.org/files/2000/2000-h/2000-h.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">El Ingenioso Hidalgo Don Quijote de la Mancha<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Gutenberg.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-05</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Man of la Mancha</target></link></italics>, a musical play based on the life of Cervantes, author of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://users.ipfw.edu/jehle/cervante/csa/artics99/wasserma.htm'>Interview with Wasserman</link></extension></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>General:</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Books</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of best-selling books</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lists of 100 best books</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bloom, Harold (Ed.) (2000)<space/><italics>Cervantes's Don Quixote (Modern Critical Interpretations)</italics>. Chelsea House Publishers ISBN 0-7910-5922-7</listitem><listitem>D' Haen, Theo (Ed.) (2009)<space/><italics>International Don Quixote</italics>. Editions Rodopi B.V. ISBN 90-420-2583-2</listitem><listitem>Echevarra, Roberto Gonzlez (Ed.) (2005)<space/><italics>Cervantes' Don Quixote: a casebook</italics><space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link><space/>USA ISBN 0-19-516938-7</listitem><listitem>Duran, Manuel and Rogg, Fay R. (2006)<space/><italics>Fighting Windmills: Encounters with Don Quixote</italics>. Yale University Press ISBN 978-0-300-11022-7</listitem><listitem>Graf, Eric C. (2007)<space/><italics>Cervantes and Modernity: Four Essays on Don Quijote</italics>. Bucknell University Press ISBN 978-1-61148-261-4</listitem><listitem>Johnson, Carroll B (Ed.) (2006)<space/><italics>Don Quijote Across Four Centuries: 16052005</italics>. Juan de la Cuesta-Hispanic Monographs ISBN 1-58871-088-2</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Sister project links</target><arg name="v">no</arg><arg name="n">no</arg><arg name="b">no</arg></template><template><target>wikisourcelang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>El ingenioso hidalgo Don Quijote de la Mancha</arg></template><template><target>wikisourcelang</target><arg>es</arg><arg>El ingenioso caballero Don Quijote de la Mancha</arg></template><template><target>In Our Time</target><arg>''Don Quixote''</arg><arg>p003hydl</arg><arg>Don_Quixote</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/details/don_quixote_vol1_librivox'>''Don Quixote'', Volume 1</link><space/>(volunteer-read audiobook) from<space/><link><target>LibriVox</target></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Internet Archive</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.neh.gov/news/humanities/2008-09/OneMaster.html'>&quot;One Master, Many Cervantes&quot;</link>, by<space/><link><target>Ilan Stavans</target></link>. A history of English translations.<space/><italics>Humanities</italics>, September/October 2008. Volume 29, Number 5. Accessed 2010-08-04</listitem><listitem><template><target>gutenberg author</target><arg name="id">Cervantes<space/></arg><arg name="name">Cervantes</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.polyglotproject.com/books/Spanish/don_quijote'>The full text of ''Don Quijote'' in the original Spanish</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.donquichote.org'>Background information about ''Don Quijote'' and Cervantes</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bnc.cat/esl/Fons-i-col-leccions/Cerca-Fons-i-col-leccions/Col-leccio-Cervantina'>Cervantine Collection of the Biblioteca de Catalunya</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.museocasanataldecervantes.org/information'>Cervantes' Birthplace Museum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/rr/rarebook/coll/cervantes.html'>Miguel de Cervantes Collection</link><space/>has rare first volumes in multiple languages of<space/><italics>Don Quixote</italics>. From the Rare Book and Special Collections Division at the<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://donquijote.ufm.edu/en/'>Mooc UFM Discover ''Don Quijote de la Mancha''</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Don Quixote</target></template><template><target>Miguel de Cervantes</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Don Quixote</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1605</target></link><link><target>Category:1605 novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional knights</target></link><link><target>Category:Metafictional works</target></link><link><target>Category:Literary archetypes by name</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels by Miguel de Cervantes</target></link><link><target>Category:Prison writings</target></link><link><target>Category:Satirical novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Self-reflexive novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Spanish novels</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional Spanish people</target></link><link><target>Category:Don Quixote characters</target></link><link><target>Category:1600s fantasy novels</target></link><link><target>Category:1615 works</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels adapted into plays</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels adapted into films</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels set in Barcelona</target></link><link><target>Category:Chivalry</target></link></paragraph></article>