<article title='Cross_ownership'><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><bold>Cross ownership</bold><space/>is a method of reinforcing business relationships by owning stock in the companies with which a given company does business. Heavy cross ownership is referred to as circular ownership.</preline></preblock><paragraph>In the US, &quot;cross ownership&quot; also refers to a type of investment in different mass-media properties in one market.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cross ownership of stock</heading><paragraph>Some countries where cross ownership of shares is a major part of the business culture are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Japan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Germany</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Positives of cross ownership:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Closely ties each business to the economic destiny of its business partners</listitem><listitem>Promotes a slow rate of economic change</listitem></list><paragraph>Cross ownership of shares is criticized for:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Stagnating the economy</listitem><listitem>Wasting capital that could be used to improve productivity</listitem><listitem>Expanding economic downturns by preventing reallocation of capital</listitem></list><paragraph>A major factor in perpetuating cross ownership of shares is a high<space/><link><target>capital gains tax</target></link><space/>rate. A company has less incentive to sell cross owned shares if taxes are high because of the immediate reduction in the value of the assets.</paragraph><paragraph>For example, a company owns $1000 of stock in another company that was originally purchased for $200. If the capital gains tax rate is 50% (like Germany) and the company sells the stock,the company has $600 which is 40 percent less than before it sold the stock.</paragraph><paragraph>Long term cross ownership of shares combined with a high capital tax rate greatly increases periods of asset deflation both in time and in severity.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Media cross ownership</heading><paragraph>Cross ownership also refers to a type of media ownership in which one type of communications (say a newspaper) owns or is the sister company of another type of medium (such as a radio or TV station). One example is<space/><italics><link><target>The New York Times</target></link></italics><space/>'s former ownership of<space/><link><target>WQXR-FM</target><part>WQXR</part></link><space/>Radio and the<space/><italics><link><target>Chicago Tribune</target></link></italics>'s similar relationship with WGN Radio (<link><target>WGN-AM</target></link>) and Television (<link><target>WGN-TV</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Federal Communications Commission</target></link><space/>generally does not allow cross ownership, to keep from one license holder having too much local media ownership, unless the license holder obtains a waiver, such as<space/><link><target>News Corporation</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Tribune Company</target></link><space/>have in New York.</paragraph><paragraph>The mid-1970s cross-ownership guidelines grandfathered already-existing crossownerships, such as<space/><italics>Tribune</italics>-WGN,<space/><italics>New York Times</italics>-WQXR and the<space/><italics><link><target>New York Daily News</target></link></italics><space/>ownership of<space/><link><target>WPIX</target></link><space/>Television and Radio.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cross Ownership</target></template><link><target>Category:Management</target></link><link><target>Category:Strategic management</target></link></paragraph></article>