<article title='English_Civil_War'><paragraph><template><target>pp-pc1</target><arg name="expiry">December 25, 2015</arg></template><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>use British English</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="conflict"><space/>English Civil War
</arg><arg name="partof"><space/>the [[Wars of the Three Kingdoms]]
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>[[File:Battle of Naseby.jpg|300px|"Battle of Naseby" by an unknown artist]]
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>The victory of the [[Roundhead|Parliamentarian]] [[New Model Army]] over the [[Cavalier|Royalist]] Army at the [[Battle of Naseby]] on 14 June 1645 marked the decisive turning point in the English Civil War.
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>22 August 1642 – 3 September 1651
</arg><arg name="place"><space/>[[Kingdom of England]]
</arg><arg name="result">
Parliamentarian victory
*Execution of King [[Charles I of England|Charles I]]
*Exile of [[Charles II of England|Charles II]]
*Establishment of the republican [[Commonwealth of England|Commonwealth]] under [[Oliver Cromwell]]
</arg><arg name="combatant1"><space/>[[Cavalier|Royalist]]s
</arg><arg name="combatant2"><space/>[[Roundhead|Parliamentarian]]s
</arg><arg name="commander1"><space/>{{unbulleted list |[[Charles I of England|Charles I]] {{executed}} |[[Prince Rupert of the Rhine]]|[[Charles II of England|Charles II]]}}
</arg><arg name="commander2"><space/>{{unbulleted list |{{nowrap|[[Robert Devereux, 3rd Earl of Essex|Earl of Essex]]}} |[[Thomas Fairfax]] |[[Oliver Cromwell]]}}
</arg><arg name="casualties1"><space/>50,000<ref name</arg><arg name="casualties2"><space/>34,000<ref name</arg><arg name="casualties3"><space/>127,000 noncombat deaths (including some 40,000 civilians)<ref>[http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/187936/English-Civil-Wars/261392/Second-and-third-English-Civil-Wars-1648-51 Second and third English Civil Wars], "''While it is notoriously difficult to determine the number of casualties in any war, it has been estimated that the conflict in England and Wales claimed about 85,000 lives in combat, with a further 127,000 noncombat deaths (including some 40,000 civilians).''"</ref>
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>English Civil War</bold><space/>(16421651) was a series of armed conflicts and political machinations between Parliamentarians (&quot;<link><target>Roundhead</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;) and Royalists (&quot;<link><target>Cavalier</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;) in the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of England</target></link><space/>over, principally, the manner of its government. The<space/><link><target>First English Civil War</target><part>first</part></link><space/>(164246) and<space/><link><target>Second English Civil War</target><part>second</part></link><space/>(164849) wars pitted the supporters of<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>King Charles I</part></link><space/>against the supporters of the<space/><link><target>Long Parliament</target></link>, while the<space/><link><target>Third English Civil War</target><part>third</part></link><space/>(164951) saw fighting between supporters of<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target><part>King Charles II</part></link><space/>and supporters of the<space/><link><target>Rump Parliament</target></link>. The war ended with the Parliamentarian victory at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Worcester</target></link><space/>on 3 September 1651.</paragraph><paragraph>The overall outcome of the war was threefold: the trial and<space/><link><target>execution of Charles I</target></link>; the exile of his son, Charles II; and the replacement of<space/><link><target>English monarchy</target></link><space/>with, at first, the<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of England</target></link><space/>(164953) and then<space/><link><target>the Protectorate</target></link><space/>(165359) under<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link>'s personal rule. The monopoly of the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link><space/>on Christian worship in England ended with the victors consolidating the established<space/><link><target>Protestant Ascendancy</target></link><space/>in Ireland. Constitutionally, the wars established the precedent that an English monarch cannot govern without Parliament's consent, although the idea of parliament as the ruling power of England was legally established as part of the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link><space/>in 1688.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">The Editors Of The Encyclopedia Britannica</arg><arg name="title">Glorious Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.britannica.com/event/Glorious-Revolution</arg><arg name="website">Encyclopedia Britannica.com</arg><arg name="publisher">Encyclopedia Britannica</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 September 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Terminology</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;English Civil War&quot; appears most often in the singular form, although historians often divide the conflict into two or three separate wars. Nor were these wars restricted to England. Wales was then a part of the Kingdom of England, and was affected accordingly; from the outset, moreover, the conflicts involved wars with and civil wars within both Scotland and Ireland (see<space/><link><target>Wars of the Three Kingdoms</target></link><space/>for an overview).</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike other<space/><link><target>List of English civil wars</target><part>civil wars in England</part></link>, which focused on who should rule, this war was more concerned with the manner in which the kingdoms of<space/><link><target>Kingdom of England</target><part>England</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Scotland</target><part>Scotland</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Ireland</target><part>Ireland</part></link><space/>were governed. The<space/><link><target>1911 Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link><space/>called the series of conflicts the &quot;Great Rebellion&quot;, while some historians<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>especially<space/><link><target>Marxist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Christopher Hill (historian)</target><part>Christopher Hill</part></link><space/>(19122003)<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>have long favoured the term &quot;<link><target>English Revolution</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Hill</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="loc">for example</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Strategy and tactics</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template>Many of the officers and veteran soldiers of the English Civil war studied and implemented war strategies that had been learned and perfected in other wars across Europe, namely by the Spanish and the Dutch during the Dutch war for independence which began in 1568.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Anthony Baker</arg><arg name="title">A Battlefield Atlas of the English Civil War</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg><arg name="date">1986</arg><arg name="location">Shepperton, UK</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="pages">{{page needed|date</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main battle tactic came to be known as<space/><link><target>pike and shot</target></link><space/>infantry, in which both sides would line up facing each other with infantry brigades of musketeers in the centre, carrying matchlock muskets;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>these muskets were inaccurate,<template><target>according to whom</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>but could be lethal from up to 300 yards.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>The brigades would arrange themselves in lines of musketeers, three deep, where the first row would kneel, the second would crouch, and the third would stand, allowing all three to fire a volley simultaneously.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>At times there would be two groups of three lines allowing one group to reload while the other group arranged themselves and fired.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Alfred H. Burne & Peter Young</arg><arg name="title">The Great Civil War: A Military History of the First Civil War 1642–1646</arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="accessdate"></arg><arg name="date">1998</arg><arg name="location">London, UK</arg><arg name="publisher">Windrush Press</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="pages">{{page needed|date</arg></template></extension><space/>Mixed in among the musketeers were pikemen carrying pikes that were between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>long, whose primary purpose was to protect the musketeers from cavalry charges.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>Positioned each side of the infantry were the cavalry, with a right-wing led by the lieutenant-general, and a left-wing by the commissary general;<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>the main goal of the cavalry was to rout the opponents cavalry and then turn and overpower their infantry.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Royalist cavaliers' skill and speed on horseback led to many early victories. Prince Rupert, the leader of the kings cavalry, learned a tactic while fighting in the Dutch army where the cavalry would charge at full speed into the opponents infantry firing their pistols just before impact.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>However, with Oliver Cromwell and the introduction of the more disciplined new model army, a group of disciplined pikemen who would stand their ground in the face of charging cavalry and could have a devastating effect.<template><target>according to whom</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>While the Parliamentarian cavalry were slower than the cavaliers, they were also better disciplined.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template><space/>The Royalists had a tendency to chase down individual targets after the initial charge leaving their forces scattered and tired; Cromwells cavalry, on the other hand, trained to operate as a single unit, which led to many decisive victories.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Simkin, 2014, &quot;British History, The English Civil War, Civil War: Tactics,&quot; at<space/><italics>Spartacus Educational</italics><space/>(online), see<space/><link type='external' href='http://spartacus-educational.com/STUcivilwarMT.htm'></link>, accessed 20 April 2015.<template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">April 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><heading level='3'>The King's rule</heading><paragraph><template><target>History of England</target></template>The English Civil War broke out less than forty years after the death of Queen<space/><link><target>Elizabeth I of England</target><part>Elizabeth I</part></link><space/>in 1603. Elizabeth's death had resulted in the accession of her<space/><link><target>Cousin chart</target><part>first cousin twice-removed</part></link>,<space/><link><target>James VI and I</target><part>King James VI of Scotland</part></link>, to the English throne as James I of England, creating the first<space/><link><target>Union of the Crowns</target><part>personal union of the Scottish and English kingdoms</part></link>.<template><target>efn</target><arg>Although the early 17th century Stuart monarchs styled themselves King of Great Britain, France and Ireland, with the exception of the constitutional arrangements during the [[Interregnum (England)|Interregnum]] (see the [[Tender of Union]]), full union of the Scottish and English realms into a new realm of Great Britain did not occur until the passing of the [[Act of Union 1707]].</arg></template><space/>As King of Scots, James had become accustomed to Scotland's weak parliamentary tradition since assuming control of the Scottish government in 1583, so that upon assuming power south of the border, the new King of England was genuinely affronted by the constraints the English Parliament attempted to place on him in exchange for money. In spite of this, James' personal extravagance meant he was perennially short of money and had to resort to extra-Parliamentary sources of income.</paragraph><paragraph>James' personal extravagance was tempered by his peaceful disposition, so that by the succession of his son<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>Charles I</part></link><space/>to the English and Scottish thrones in 1625 the two kingdoms had both experienced relative peace, both internally and in their relations with each other, for as long as anyone could remember. Charles hoped to unite the kingdoms of England, Scotland and Ireland into a new single kingdom, fulfilling the dream of his father.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Croft</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">63</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Many English Parliamentarians had suspicions regarding such a move because they feared that setting up a new kingdom might destroy the old English traditions which had bound the English monarchy. As Charles shared his father's position on the power of the crown (James had described kings as &quot;little gods on Earth&quot;, chosen by God to rule in accordance with the doctrine of the &quot;<link><target>Divine Right of Kings</target></link>&quot;), the suspicions of the Parliamentarians had some justification.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>McClelland</arg><arg>1996</arg><arg name="p">224</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:King Charles I after original by van Dyck.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Charles I, painted by Van Dyck</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Parliament in the English constitutional framework</heading><paragraph>At the time, the<space/><link><target>Parliament of England</target></link><space/>did not have a large permanent role in the English system of government. Instead, Parliament functioned as a temporary advisory committee and was only summoned if, and when, the monarch saw fit to summon it. Once summoned, a parliament's continued existence was at the king's pleasure, since it was subject to dissolution by him at any time.</paragraph><paragraph>Yet in spite of this limited role, Parliament had, over the preceding centuries, acquired<space/><italics>de facto</italics><space/>powers of enough significance that monarchs could not simply ignore them indefinitely. Without question, for a monarch, Parliament's most indispensable power was its ability to raise tax revenues far in excess of all other sources of revenue at the Crown's disposal. By the seventeenth century, Parliament's tax-raising powers had come to be derived from the fact that the<space/><link><target>gentry</target></link><space/>was the only stratum of society with the ability and authority to actually collect and remit the most meaningful forms of taxation then available at the local level. This meant that if the king wanted to ensure a smooth collection of revenue, he needed the co-operation of the gentry. For all of the Crown's legal authority, by any modern standard, its resources were limited to the extent that, if and when the gentry refused to collect the king's taxes on a national scale, the Crown lacked any practical means with which to compel them.</paragraph><paragraph>Therefore, in order to secure their co-operation, monarchs permitted the gentry (and only the gentry) to elect representatives to sit in the House of Commons. When assembled along with the House of Lords, these elected representatives formed a Parliament. Parliaments therefore, allowed representatives of the gentry to meet, primarily (at least in the opinion of the monarch) so that they could give their sanction to whatever taxes the monarch expected their electorate to collect. In the process, the representatives could also confer and send policy proposals to the king in the form of bills. However, Parliament lacked any legal means of forcing its will upon the monarch; its only leverage with the king was the threat of its withholding the financial means required to execute his plans.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Johnston</arg><arg>1901</arg><arg name="pp">83–86</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Parliamentary concerns and the Petition of Right</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Sir Peter Lely 001.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Henrietta Maria of France</target><part>Henrietta Maria</part></link>, painted by<space/><link><target>Peter Lely</target></link>, 1660</part></link>Many concerns were raised over Charles's marriage to a Roman Catholic, French princess<space/><link><target>Henrietta Maria of France</target><part>Henrietta Maria</part></link>, in 1625. The Parliament refused to assign him the traditional right to collect customs duties for his entire reign, deciding instead to grant it only on a provisional basis and negotiate with him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gregg</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="pp">129–30</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Charles, meanwhile, decided to send an expeditionary force to relieve the French<space/><link><target>Huguenots</target></link><space/>whom French royal troops held<space/><link><target>Siege of La Rochelle</target><part>besieged in La Rochelle</part></link>. Military support for Protestants on the Continent was, in itself, popular both in Parliament and with the Protestant majority in general,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><space/>and it had the potential to alleviate concerns brought about by the King's marriage to a Catholic. However, Charles's insistence on having his unpopular royal favourite<space/><link><target>George Villiers, 1st Duke of Buckingham</target><part>George Villiers, the Duke of Buckingham</part></link>, assume command of the English force undermined that support. Unfortunately for Charles and Buckingham, the relief expedition proved a fiasco (1627),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gregg</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">166</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and Parliament, already hostile to Buckingham for his monopoly on<space/><link><target>Patronage</target><part>royal patronage</part></link>, opened<space/><link><target>impeachment</target></link><space/>proceedings against him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gregg-175"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gregg</arg><arg>1984</arg><arg name="p">175</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles responded by dissolving Parliament. This move, while saving Buckingham, reinforced the impression that Charles wanted to avoid Parliamentary scrutiny of his ministers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gregg-175"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Having dissolved Parliament and unable to raise money without it, the king assembled a new one in 1628. (The elected members included<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Edward Coke</target></link>.) The new Parliament drew up the<space/><link><target>Petition of Right</target></link>, and Charles accepted it as a concession in order to obtain his subsidy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss 2007 93"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">93</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Amongst other things, the Petition referred to the<space/><link><target>Magna Carta</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Petition of Right</target></link><space/>at III, VII.</extension><space/>However, it did not grant him the right of<space/><link><target>tonnage and poundage</target></link>, which Charles had been collecting without Parliamentary authorisation since 1625.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sommerville"></extension><space/>Several of the more active members of the opposition were imprisoned, which caused some outrage;<extension extension_name='ref' name="sommerville">Sommerville, Johann P. 1992. Parliament, Privilege, and the Liberties of the Subject. In: Jack H. Hexter (ed.) Parliament and Liberty from the Reign of Elizabeth to the English Civil War. P. 65, 71, 80</extension><space/>one,<space/><link><target>John Eliot (statesman)</target><part>John Eliot</part></link>, subsequently died in prison, becoming regarded as a martyr for the rights of Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'>Russell, Geoffrey. (ed.) 1998. Who's who in British History: A-H. V. 1. P.417</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Personal rule</heading><paragraph>Charles I avoided calling a Parliament for the next decade, a period known as the &quot;<link><target>personal rule of Charles I</target></link>&quot;, or the &quot;Eleven Years' Tyranny&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Rosner</arg><arg>Theibault</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">103</arg></template>.</extension><space/>During this period, Charles's lack of money determined policies. First and foremost, to avoid Parliament, the King needed to avoid war. Charles made peace with France and Spain, effectively ending England's involvement in the<space/><link><target>Thirty Years' War</target></link>. However, that in itself was far from enough to balance the Crown's finances.</paragraph><paragraph>Unable to raise revenue without Parliament, and unwilling to convene it, Charles resorted to other means. One method was reviving certain conventions, often long-outdated. For example, a failure to attend and to receive<space/><link><target>knighthood</target></link><space/>at Charles's coronation was a finable offence with the fine paid to the Crown. The King also tried to raise revenue through the<space/><link><target>ship money</target></link><space/>tax, by exploiting a naval war-scare in 1635, demanding that the inland English counties pay the tax for the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>. Established law supported this policy, but authorities had ignored it for centuries, and many regarded it as yet another extra-Parliamentary (and therefore illegal) tax.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pipes-143"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Pipes</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">143</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Some prominent men refused to pay ship money, arguing that the tax was illegal, but they lost in court, and the fines imposed on them for refusing to pay ship money (and for standing against the tax's legality) aroused widespread indignation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pipes-143"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the &quot;Personal Rule,&quot; Charles aroused most antagonism through his religious measures: he believed in<space/><link><target>Anglican</target><part>High Anglicanism</part></link>, a sacramental version of the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link>, theologically based upon<space/><link><target>Arminianism</target></link>, a creed shared with his main political advisor, Archbishop<space/><link><target>William Laud</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">48</arg></template>.</extension><space/>In 1633, Charles appointed Laud as<space/><link><target>Archbishop of Canterbury</target></link><space/>and started making the Church more ceremonial, replacing the wooden<space/><link><target>Mass (liturgy)#Communion rite</target><part>communion</part></link><space/>tables with stone altars.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">96</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Puritans accused Laud of reintroducing Catholicism; when they complained, he had them arrested. In 1637<space/><link><target>John Bastwick</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Henry Burton (Puritan)</target><part>Henry Burton</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>William Prynne</target></link><space/>had their ears cut off for writing pamphlets attacking Laud's viewsa rare penalty for<space/><link><target>Gentleman</target><part>gentlemen</part></link>, and one that aroused anger.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">201</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Moreover, the Church authorities revived the statutes passed in the time of<space/><link><target>Elizabeth I</target></link><space/>about church attendance, and fined Puritans for not attending Anglican church services.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1987</arg><arg name="p">173</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Rebellion in Scotland</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Bishops' War</arg></template>The end of Charles's independent governance came when he attempted to apply the same religious policies in Scotland. The<space/><link><target>Church of Scotland</target></link>, reluctantly<space/><link><target>Episcopal polity</target><part>episcopal</part></link><space/>in structure, had independent traditions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">74</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles, however, wanted one uniform Church throughout Britain<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">83</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and introduced a new, High Anglican version of the English<space/><link><target>Book of Common Prayer</target></link><space/>to Scotland in the middle of 1637. This was violently resisted; a riot broke out in Edinburgh,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">75</arg></template>.</extension><space/>which may have been started in<space/><link><target>St Giles' Cathedral</target></link>, according to legend, by<space/><link><target>Jenny Geddes</target></link>. In February 1638, the Scots formulated their objections to royal policy in the<space/><link><target>National Covenant</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">77</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This document took the form of a &quot;loyal protest,&quot; rejecting all innovations not first having been tested by free parliaments and General Assemblies of the Church.</paragraph><paragraph>In the spring of 1639, King Charles I accompanied his forces to the Scottish border to end the rebellion known as the<space/><link><target>Bishops' War</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss-96"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">96</arg></template>.</extension><space/>But, after an inconclusive military campaign, he accepted the offered Scottish truce: the<space/><link><target>Pacification of Berwick</target></link>. The truce proved temporary, and a second war followed in the middle of 1640. This time, a Scots army defeated Charles's forces in the north, then captured<space/><link><target>Newcastle upon Tyne</target><part>Newcastle</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">97</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles eventually agreed not to interfere with Scotland's religion and paid the Scots' war-expenses.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Recall of the English Parliament</heading><paragraph>Charles needed to suppress the rebellion in Scotland. He had insufficient funds, however, and needed to seek money from a newly elected<space/><link><target>Short Parliament</target><part>English Parliament</part></link><space/>in 1640.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Coward-180"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Coward</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">180</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The majority faction in the new Parliament, led by<space/><link><target>John Pym</target></link>, took this appeal for money as an opportunity to discuss grievances against the Crown and opposed the idea of an English invasion of Scotland. Charles took exception to this<space/><italics><link><target>lese majesty</target><part>lse-majest</part></link></italics><space/>(offence against the ruler) and dissolved the Parliament after only a few weeks; hence the name &quot;the<space/><link><target>Short Parliament</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Coward-180"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Without Parliament's support, Charles attacked Scotland again, breaking the truce at Berwick, and suffered a comprehensive defeat. The Scots went on to invade England, occupying<space/><link><target>Northumberland</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Durham, England</target><part>Durham</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Coward-180"></extension><space/>Meanwhile, another of Charles' chief advisors,<space/><link><target>Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford</target><part>Thomas Wentworth, 1st Viscount Wentworth</part></link>, had risen to the role of Lord Deputy of Ireland in 1632<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss-89"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">89</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and brought in much-needed revenue for Charles by persuading the Irish Catholic gentry to pay new taxes in return for promised religious concessions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Coward</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">172</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1639, Charles had recalled Wentworth to England and in 1640 made him Earl of Strafford, attempting to have him achieve similar results in Scotland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss-89"></extension><space/>This time he proved less successful and the English forces fled the field in their second encounter with the Scots in 1640.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss-89"></extension><space/>Almost the entirety of Northern England was occupied and Charles was forced to pay 850 per day to keep the Scots from advancing. If he did not, they would &quot;take&quot; the money by pillaging and burning the cities and towns of Northern England.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Sharp</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">13</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>All this put Charles in a desperate financial position. As King of Scots, he had to find money to pay the Scottish army in England; as King of England, he had to find money to pay and equip an English army to defend England. His means of raising English revenue without an English Parliament fell critically short of achieving this.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss 2007 93"></extension><space/>Against this backdrop, and according to advice from the<space/><link><target>Magnum Concilium</target></link><space/>(the<space/><link><target>House of Lords</target></link>, but without the<space/><link><target>House of Commons of England</target><part>Commons</part></link>, so not a Parliament), Charles finally bowed to pressure and summoned another English Parliament in November 1640.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Purkiss-96"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Long Parliament</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Long Parliament</arg></template><link><target>File:LongParliament.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Session of the Long Parliament</part></link>The new Parliament proved even more hostile to Charles than its predecessor. It immediately began to discuss grievances against Charles and his government and with Pym and<space/><link><target>John Hampden</target><part>Hampden</part></link><space/>(of<space/><link><target>ship money</target></link><space/>fame) in the lead, took the opportunity presented by the King's troubles to force various reforming measuresincluding many with strong 'anti-Papist' themesupon him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="pp">104,5</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The legislators passed a law which stated that a new Parliament should convene at least once every three yearswithout the King's summons, if necessary. Other laws passed by the Parliament made it illegal for the king to impose taxes without Parliamentary consent and later gave Parliament control over the king's ministers. Finally, the Parliament passed a law forbidding the King to dissolve it without its consent, even if the three years were up. Ever since, this Parliament has been known as the &quot;Long Parliament&quot;. However, Parliament did attempt to avert conflict by requiring all adults to sign<space/><link><target>Protestation of 1641</target><part>The Protestation</part></link>, an oath of allegiance to Charles.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Walter</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">294</arg></template>, for some of the complexities of how the Protestation was interpreted by different political actors.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Early in the Long Parliament's proceedings the house overwhelmingly accused<space/><link><target>Thomas Wentworth, 1st Earl of Strafford</target><part>Thomas Wentworth, Earl of Strafford</part></link><space/>of high treason and other crimes and misdemeanours.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Henry Vane the Younger</target></link><space/>supplied evidence in relation to Strafford's claimed improper use of the army in Ireland, alleging that Strafford was encouraging the King to use his army raised in Ireland to threaten England into compliance. This evidence was obtained from Vane's father,<space/><link><target>Henry Vane the Elder</target></link>, a member of the King's Privy council, who refused to confirm it in Parliament out of loyalty to Charles. On 10 April, Pym's case collapsed, but Pym made a direct appeal to<space/><link><target>Henry Vane the Younger</target></link><space/>to produce a copy of the notes from the King's Privy council, discovered by the younger Vane and secretly turned over to Pym, to the great anguish of the Elder Vane.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Upham187"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Upham</arg><arg>1842</arg><arg name="p">187</arg></template></extension><space/>These notes from the King's Privy Council contained evidence Strafford had told the King, &quot;Sir, you have done your duty, and your subjects have failed in theirs; and therefore you are absolved from the rules of government, and may supply yourself by extraordinary ways; you have an army in Ireland, with which you may reduce the kingdom.&quot;<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Upham</arg><arg>1842</arg><arg name="p">187</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Hibbert</arg><arg>1968</arg><arg name="p">154</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">224</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Pym immediately launched a Bill of Attainder, stating Strafford's guilt and demanding that the Earl be put to death.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">224</arg></template><space/>Unlike a guilty finding in a court case, attainder did not require a<space/><link><target>legal burden of proof</target></link>, but it did require<space/><link><target>Royal Assent</target><part>the king's approval</part></link>. Charles, however, guaranteed Strafford that he would not sign the attainder, without which the bill could not be passed.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">225</arg></template><space/>Furthermore, the Lords were opposed to the severity of the sentence of death imposed upon Strafford. Yet, increased tensions and<space/><link><target>First Army Plot</target><part>a plot</part></link><space/>in the army to support Strafford began to sway the issue.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">225</arg></template><space/>On 21 April, the Commons passed the Bill (204 in favour, 59 opposed, and 250 abstained),<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">123</arg></template><space/>and the Lords acquiesced. Charles, still incensed over the Commons' handling of Buckingham, refused. Strafford himself, hoping to head off the war he saw looming, wrote to the king and asked him to reconsider.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Abbott"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Jacob<space/></arg><arg name="last">Abbott<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author</arg><arg name="title">Charles I<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Chapter: Downfall of Strafford and Laud<space/></arg><arg name="chapterurl">http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author</arg></template></extension><space/>Charles, fearing for the safety of his family, signed on 10 May.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Smith</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">123</arg></template><space/>Strafford was beheaded two days later.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Coward</arg><arg>1994</arg><arg name="p">191</arg></template><space/>In the meantime both Parliament and the King agreed to an independent investigation into the king's involvement in Strafford's plot.</paragraph><paragraph>The Long Parliament then passed the<space/><link><target>Triennial Act</target></link>, also known as the<space/><link><target>Dissolution Act</target></link><space/>in May 1641, to which the Royal Assent was readily granted.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995</arg><arg name="p">222</arg></template><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kenyon</arg><arg>1978</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template><space/>The Triennial Act required that Parliament be summoned at least once every three years, and that when the King failed to issue proper summons, the members could assemble on their own. This act also forbade ship money without Parliament's consent, fines in destraint of knighthood and forced loans. Monopolies were cut back severely, and the Courts of<space/><link><target>Star Chamber</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Court of High Commission</target><part>High Commission</part></link><space/>were abolished by the<space/><link><target>Habeas Corpus Act 1640</target></link><space/>and the Triennial Act respectively.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Gregg</arg><arg>1981</arg><arg name="p"><space/>335</arg></template><space/>All remaining forms of taxation were legalised and regulated by the Tonnage and Poundage Act.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kenyon</arg><arg>1978</arg><arg name="p">129</arg></template><space/>On 3 May, Parliament decreed<space/><link><target>Protestation of 1641</target><part>The Protestation</part></link>, attacking the 'wicked counsels' of Charles's government, whereby those who signed the petition undertook to defend 'the true reformed religion', parliament, and the king's person, honour and estate. Throughout May, the House of Commons launched several bills attacking bishops and episcopalianism in general, each time defeated in the Lords.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Kenyon</arg><arg>1978</arg><arg name="p">130</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'>Jacob Abbott<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author=abbott&amp;amp;book=charles1&amp;amp;story=_contents'>Charles I</link></italics><space/>Chapter<space/><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.mainlesson.com/display.php?author=abbott&amp;amp;book=charles1&amp;amp;story=downfall'>Downfall of Strafford and Laud</link></italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It was hoped by both Charles and Parliament that the execution of Strafford and the Protestation would end the drift towards war; in fact, they encouraged it. Charles and his supporters continued to resent Parliament's demands, while Parliamentarians continued to suspect Charles of wanting to impose episcopalianism and unfettered royal rule by military force. Within months, the Irish Catholics, fearing a resurgence of Protestant power,<space/><link><target>Irish Rebellion of 1641</target><part>struck first</part></link>, and all Ireland soon descended into chaos.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="pp">109–113</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Rumours circulated that the King supported the Irish, and Puritan members of the Commons soon started murmuring that this exemplified the fate that Charles had in store for them all.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">113</arg></template><space/>for the concerns of a similar English Catholic rising.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In early January 1642, accompanied by 400 soldiers, Charles attempted to arrest five members of the House of Commons on a charge of treason.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sherwood-1997-41"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Sherwood</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">41</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This attempt failed. When the troops marched into Parliament, Charles enquired of<space/><link><target>William Lenthall</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>List of Speakers of the House of Commons of England</target><part>Speaker</part></link>, as to the whereabouts of the five. Lenthall replied, &quot;May it please your Majesty, I have neither eyes to see nor tongue to speak in this place but as the House is pleased to direct me, whose servant I am here.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sherwood-1997-41"></extension><space/>In other words, the Speaker proclaimed himself a servant of Parliament, rather than of the King.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sherwood-1997-41"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Local grievances</heading><paragraph>In the summer of 1642 these national troubles helped to polarise opinion, ending indecision about which side to support or what action to take. Opposition to Charles also arose owing to many local grievances. For example, the imposition of drainage-schemes in<space/><link><target>The Fens</target></link><space/>negatively affected the livelihood of thousands of people after the King awarded a number of drainage-contracts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Hughes</arg><arg>1991</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Many regarded the King as indifferent to the welfare of the people, and this played a role in bringing a large part of eastern England into Parliaments camp. This sentiment brought with it people such as the<space/><link><target>Edward Montagu, 2nd Earl of Manchester</target><part>Earl of Manchester</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link>, each a notable wartime adversary of the King. Conversely, one of the leading drainage contractors, the<space/><link><target>Robert Bertie, 1st Earl of Lindsey</target><part>Earl of Lindsey</part></link>, was to die fighting for the King at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Edgehill</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Purkiss</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">180</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>First English Civil War (16421646)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:English civil war map 1642 to 1645.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Maps of territory held by Royalists (red) and Parliamentarians (yellow), 16421645</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>First English Civil War</arg></template>In early January 1642, a few days after his failure to capture five members of the House of Commons, fearing for the safety of his family and retinue, Charles left the London area for the north of the country.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">57</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Further negotiations by frequent correspondence between the King and the<space/><link><target>Long Parliament</target></link><space/>through to early summer proved fruitless. As the summer progressed, cities and towns declared their sympathies for one faction or the other: for example, the garrison of Portsmouth under the command of Sir<space/><link><target>George Goring, Lord Goring</target><part>George Goring</part></link><space/>declared for the King,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">107</arg></template>.</extension><space/>but when Charles tried to acquire arms for his cause from<space/><link><target>Kingston upon Hull</target></link>, the depository for the weapons used in the previous Scottish campaigns, Sir<space/><link><target>Sir John Hotham, 1st Baronet</target><part>John Hotham</part></link>, the military governor appointed by Parliament in January, refused to let Charles enter Hull,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and when Charles returned with more men later,<space/><link><target>Siege of Hull (1642)</target><part>Hotham drove them off</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wedgwood 1970 100"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">100</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles issued a warrant for Hotham to be arrested as a traitor but was powerless to enforce it. Throughout the summer months, tensions rose and there was brawling in a number of places, with the first death from the conflict taking place in Manchester.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wedgwood 1970 100"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Royle</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">158–166</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the outset of the conflict, much of the country remained neutral, though the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/>and most English cities favoured Parliament, while the King found considerable support in rural communities. Historians estimate that between them, both sides had only about 15,000 men.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2007</arg></template><space/>However, the war quickly spread and eventually involved every level of society. Many areas attempted to remain neutral. Some formed bands of<space/><link><target>Clubmen</target></link><space/>to protect their localities against the worst excesses of the armies of both sides,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">403,4</arg></template>.</extension><space/>but most found it impossible to withstand both the King and Parliament. On one side, the King and his supporters fought for traditional government in Church and state. On the other, most supporters of the Parliamentary cause initially took up arms to defend what they thought of as the traditional balance of government in Church and state, which the bad advice the King had received from his advisers had undermined before and during the &quot;Eleven Years' Tyranny.&quot; The views of the Members of Parliament ranged from unquestioning support of the King at one point during the First Civil War, more members of the Commons and Lords gathered in the King's<space/><link><target>Oxford Parliament (1644)</target><part>Oxford Parliament</part></link><space/>than at<space/><link><target>Palace of Westminster</target><part>Westminster</part></link><space/>through to radicals, who wanted major reforms in favour of<space/><link><target>Nonconformism</target><part>religious independence</part></link><space/>and the redistribution of power at the national level.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template><space/>However, even the most radical supporters of the Parliamentarian cause still favoured the retention of Charles on the throne.</paragraph><paragraph>After the<space/><link><target>debacle at Hull</target></link>, Charles moved on to<space/><link><target>Nottingham</target></link>, where on 22 August 1642, he raised the<space/><link><target>Royal Standard of England</target><part>royal standard</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">111</arg></template>.</extension><space/>When he raised his standard, Charles had with him about 2,000 cavalry and a small number of Yorkshire infantry-men, and using the archaic system of a<space/><link><target>Commission of Array</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">96</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles's supporters started to build a larger army around the standard. Charles moved in a south-westerly direction, first to<space/><link><target>Stafford</target></link>, and then on to<space/><link><target>Shrewsbury</target></link>, because the support for his cause seemed particularly strong in the<space/><link><target>River Severn</target><part>Severn</part></link><space/>valley area and in<space/><link><target>North Wales</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Royle</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">170,183</arg></template>.</extension><space/>While passing through<space/><link><target>Wellington, Shropshire</target><part>Wellington</part></link>, in what became known as the &quot;<link><target>Wellington Declaration</target></link>,&quot; he declared that he would uphold the &quot;Protestant religion, the laws of England, and the liberty of Parliament.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Sherwood</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template>.</extension><link><target>File:Battle of Marston Moor, 1644.png</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Battle of Marston Moor</target></link>, 1644</part></link>The Parliamentarians who opposed the King had not remained passive during this pre-war period. As in the case of Kingston upon Hull, they had taken measures to secure strategic towns and cities by appointing to office men sympathetic to their cause, and on 9 June they had voted to raise an army of 10,000 volunteers and appointed<space/><link><target>Robert Devereux, 3rd Earl of Essex</target></link><space/>commander three days later.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">108,9</arg></template>.</extension><space/>He received orders &quot;to rescue His Majesty's person, and the persons of the<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target><part>Prince [of Wales</part></link>] and the<space/><link><target>James II of England</target><part>Duke of York</part></link><space/>out of the hands of those desperate persons who were about them.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Hibbert</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="p">65</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Lord Lieutenant</target><part>Lords Lieutenant</part></link>, whom Parliament appointed, used the<space/><link><target>Militia Ordinance</target></link><space/>to order the militia to join Essex's army.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Royle</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">165,161</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Two weeks after the King had raised his standard at Nottingham, Essex led his army north towards<space/><link><target>Northampton</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">113</arg></template>.</extension><space/>picking up support along the way (including a detachment of<space/><link><target>Cambridgeshire</target></link><space/>cavalry raised and commanded by<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Cromwell had already secured Cambridge and the supplies of college silver see<space/><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">106</arg></template>.</extension><space/>By the middle of September Essex's forces had grown to 21,000 infantry and 4,200 cavalry and<space/><link><target>dragoon</target><trail>s</trail></link>. On 14 September he moved his army to<space/><link><target>Coventry</target></link><space/>and then to the north of the<space/><link><target>Cotswolds</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Wegwood, p.115.</extension><space/>a strategy which placed his army between the Royalists and London. With the size of both armies now in the tens of thousands, and only Worcestershire between them, it was inevitable that cavalry reconnaissance units would sooner or later meet. This happened in the first major skirmish of the Civil War, when a cavalry troop of about 1,000 Royalists commanded by<space/><link><target>Prince Rupert</target></link>, a German nephew of the King and one of the outstanding cavalry commanders of the war,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">148</arg></template>.</extension><space/>defeated a Parliamentary cavalry detachment under the command of Colonel<space/><link><target>John Brown (soldier)</target><part>John Brown</part></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Battle of Powick Bridge</target></link>, at a bridge across the<space/><link><target>River Teme</target></link><space/>close to<space/><link><target>Worcester</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Royle</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="pp">171–188</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Rupert of the Rhine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Prince Rupert of the Rhine</target></link></part></link>Rupert withdrew to Shrewsbury, where a council-of-war discussed two courses of action: whether to advance towards Essex's new position near<space/><link><target>Worcester</target></link>, or to march along the now opened road towards London. The Council decided to take the London route, but not to avoid a battle, for the Royalist generals wanted to fight Essex before he grew too strong, and the temper of both sides made it impossible to postpone the decision. In the<space/><link><target>Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon</target><part>Earl of Clarendon's</part></link><space/>words: &quot;it was considered more counsellable to march towards London, it being morally sure that Essex would put himself in their way&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB11-GR"><link><target>Encyclopaedia Britannica Eleventh Edition</target></link><space/>Great Rebellion</extension><space/>Accordingly, the army left Shrewsbury on 12 October, gaining two days' start on the enemy, and moved south-east. This had the desired effect, as it forced Essex to move to intercept them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EB11-GR"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first<space/><link><target>pitched battle</target></link><space/>of the war, fought at<space/><link><target>Battle of Edgehill</target><part>Edgehill</part></link><space/>on 23 October 1642, proved inconclusive, and both the Royalists and Parliamentarians claimed it as a victory.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">130,1</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The second field action of the war, the stand-off at<space/><link><target>Turnham Green (Battle)</target><part>Turnham Green</part></link>, saw Charles forced to withdraw to<space/><link><target>Oxford</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">135</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This city would serve as his base for the remainder of the war.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">167–8;506–7</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1643 the Royalist forces won at<space/><link><target>Battle of Adwalton Moor</target><part>Adwalton Moor</part></link>, and gained control of most of<space/><link><target>Yorkshire</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">209</arg></template>.</extension><space/>In the Midlands, a Parliamentary force under<space/><link><target>Sir John Gell, 1st Baronet</target><part>Sir John Gell</part></link><space/>besieged and captured the cathedral city of<space/><link><target>Lichfield</target></link>, after the death of the original commander, Lord Brooke.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wanklyn-74"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wanklyn</arg><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">74</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This group subsequently joined forces with Sir John Brereton to fight the inconclusive<space/><link><target>Battle of Hopton Heath</target></link><space/>(19 March 1643), where the Royalist commander, the<space/><link><target>Earl of Northampton</target></link>, was killed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wanklyn-74"></extension><space/>Subsequent battles in the west of England at<space/><link><target>Battle of Lansdowne</target><part>Lansdowne</part></link><space/>and at<space/><link><target>Battle of Roundway Down</target><part>Roundway Down</part></link><space/>also went to the Royalists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wanklyn</arg><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">103</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Prince Rupert could then take<space/><link><target>Bristol</target></link>. In the same year, Oliver Cromwell formed his troop of &quot;<link><target>Ironside (cavalry)</target><part>Ironsides</part></link>&quot;, a disciplined unit that demonstrated his military leadership ability. With their assistance, he won a victory at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Gainsborough</target></link><space/>in July.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Young</arg><arg>Holmes</arg><arg>1974</arg><arg name="p">151</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At this stage, from 7th to 9 August 1643, there were some popular demonstrations in Londonboth pro and against war. They were protesting at Westminster. A peace demonstration by London women, which turned violent, was suppressed by<space/><link><target>William Waller</target></link>'s regiment of horse. Some women were beaten and even killed, and many arrested.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://bcw-project.org/timelines/1643'>1643 timeline.</link><space/>British Civil Wars, Commonwealth &amp; Protectorate website</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Following these events of August, the representative of Venice in England reported to the doge that the London government took considerable measures to stifle dissent.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mary Beth Norton,<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=RyQMJi5dMCAC&amp;amp;pg=PT93&amp;amp;lpg=PT93&amp;amp;dq=%22Venice+in+England+reported%22'>''Separated by Their Sex: Women in Public and Private in the Colonial Atlantic World.''</link><space/>Cornell University Press, 2011 ISBN 0801461375</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In general, the early part of the war went well for the Royalists. The turning point came in the late summer and early autumn of 1643, when the Earl of Essex's army forced the king to raise the<space/><link><target>siege of Gloucester</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">232</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and then brushed the Royalist army aside at the<space/><link><target>First Battle of Newbury</target></link><space/>(20 September 1643),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">238</arg></template>.</extension><space/>in order to return triumphantly to London. Other Parliamentarian forces won the<space/><link><target>Battle of Winceby</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">248</arg></template>.</extension><space/>giving them control of<space/><link><target>Lincoln, England</target><part>Lincoln</part></link>. Political manoeuvring to gain an advantage in numbers led Charles to negotiate a ceasefire in Ireland, freeing up English troops to fight on the Royalist side in England,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">298,9</arg></template>.</extension><space/>while Parliament offered concessions to the Scots in return for aid and assistance.</paragraph><paragraph>With the help of the Scots, Parliament won at<space/><link><target>Battle of Marston Moor</target><part>Marston Moor</part></link><space/>(2 July 1644),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wanklyn</arg><arg>Jones</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">189</arg></template>.</extension><space/>gaining<space/><link><target>York</target></link><space/>and the north of England.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">322</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Cromwell's conduct in this battle proved decisive,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">319</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and demonstrated his potential as both a political and an important military leader. The defeat at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lostwithiel</target></link><space/>in Cornwall, however, marked a serious reverse for Parliament in the south-west of England.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ashley, p.188.</extension><space/>Subsequent fighting around<space/><link><target>Second Battle of Newbury</target><part>Newbury</part></link><space/>(27 October 1644), though tactically indecisive, strategically gave another check to Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">359</arg></template>.</extension><link><target>File:Oliver Cromwell by Samuel Cooper.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link></part></link>In 1645 Parliament reaffirmed its determination to fight the war to a finish. It passed the<space/><link><target>Self-denying Ordinance</target></link>, by which all members of either House of Parliament laid down their commands, and re-organized its main forces into the<space/><link><target>New Model Army</target></link><space/>(&quot;Army&quot;), under the command of Sir<space/><link><target>Thomas Fairfax, 3rd Baron Fairfax of Cameron</target><part>Thomas Fairfax</part></link>, with Cromwell as his second-in-command and<space/><link><target>Lieutenant General</target><part>Lieutenant-General</part></link><space/>of Horse.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">373</arg></template>.</extension><space/>In two decisive engagementsthe<space/><link><target>Battle of Naseby</target></link><space/>on 14 June and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Langport</target></link><space/>on 10 Julythe Parliamentarians effectively destroyed Charles' armies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">428</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the remains of his English realm Charles attempted to recover a stable base of support by consolidating the<space/><link><target>English Midlands</target><part>Midlands</part></link>. He began to form an axis between Oxford and<space/><link><target>Newark on Trent</target></link><space/>in Nottinghamshire. Those towns had become fortresses and showed more reliable loyalty to him than to others. He took<space/><link><target>Leicester</target></link>, which lies between them, but found his resources exhausted. Having little opportunity to replenish them, in May 1646 he sought shelter with a Presbyterian Scottish army at<space/><link><target>Southwell, Nottinghamshire</target><part>Southwell</part></link><space/>in Nottinghamshire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="pp">519–520</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Charles was eventually handed over to the English Parliament by the Scots and was imprisoned.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Wedgwood</arg><arg>1970</arg><arg name="p">570</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This marked the end of the First English Civil War.<template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Second English Civil War (16481649)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Second English Civil War</arg></template><link><target>File:Lastseefather.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>&quot;And when did you last see your father?&quot; by<space/><link><target>William Frederick Yeames</target></link>.</part></link>Charles I took advantage of the deflection of attention away from himself to negotiate a secret treaty with the Scots, again promising church reform, on 28 December 1647.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Seel-64"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Seel</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">64</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Under the agreement, called the &quot;<link><target>Engagers</target><part>Engagement</part></link>&quot;, the Scots undertook to invade England on Charles' behalf and restore him to the throne on condition of the establishment of Presbyterianism for three years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Luminarium"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.luminarium.org/encyclopedia/kingcharles.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">King Charles I<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Luminarium Encyclopedia]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 April 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A series of Royalist uprisings throughout England and a Scottish invasion occurred in the summer of 1648. Forces loyal to Parliament<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Fairfax</arg><arg>1648</arg><arg name="loc">Letter</arg></template>.</extension><space/>put down most of the uprisings in England after little more than skirmishes, but uprisings in Kent, Essex and Cumberland, the rebellion in Wales, and the Scottish invasion involved the fighting of pitched battles and prolonged sieges.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Seel-64"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the spring of 1648 unpaid Parliamentarian troops in Wales changed sides. Colonel<space/><link><target>Thomas Horton (soldier)</target><part>Thomas Horton</part></link><space/>defeated the Royalist rebels at the<space/><link><target>Battle of St Fagans</target></link><space/>(8 May)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>John</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and the rebel leaders surrendered to Cromwell on 11 July after the protracted two-month<space/><link><target>siege of Pembroke</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Trevelyan</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">274</arg></template>.</extension><space/><link><target>Sir Thomas Fairfax</target></link><space/>defeated a Royalist uprising in Kent at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Maidstone</target></link><space/>on 1 June. Fairfax, after his success at<space/><link><target>Maidstone</target></link><space/>and the pacification of<space/><link><target>Kent</target></link>, turned northward to reduce<space/><link><target>Essex</target></link>, where, under their ardent, experienced and popular leader Sir<space/><link><target>Charles Lucas</target></link>, the Royalists had taken up arms in great numbers. Fairfax soon drove the enemy into<space/><link><target>Colchester</target></link>, but his first attack on the town met with a repulse and he had to settle down to<space/><link><target>siege of Colchester</target><part>a long siege</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Trevelyan</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="pp">274,5</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the North of England, Major-General<space/><link><target>John Lambert (General)</target><part>John Lambert</part></link><space/>fought a very successful campaign against a number of Royalist uprisingsthe largest that of Sir<space/><link><target>Marmaduke Langdale</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cumberland</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Newman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">87</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Thanks to Lambert's successes, the Scottish commander, the<space/><link><target>James Hamilton, 3rd Marquess and 1st Duke of Hamilton</target><part>Duke of Hamilton</part></link>, had perforce to take the western route through<space/><link><target>Carlisle, Cumbria</target><part>Carlisle</part></link><space/>in his pro-Royalist Scottish invasion of England.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Newman-89"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Newman</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">89</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The Parliamentarians under Cromwell engaged the Scots at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Preston (1648)</target><part>Battle of Preston</part></link><space/>(1719 August). The battle took place largely at<space/><link><target>Walton-le-Dale</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Preston, Lancashire</target><part>Preston</part></link><space/>in Lancashire, and resulted in a victory by the troops of Cromwell over the Royalists and Scots commanded by Hamilton.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Newman-89"></extension><space/>This Parliamentarian victory marked the end of the Second English Civil War.</paragraph><paragraph>Nearly all the Royalists who had fought in the First Civil War had given their parole not to bear arms against the Parliament, and many of these, like<space/><link><target>Jacob Astley, 1st Baron Astley of Reading</target><part>Lord Astley</part></link>, refused to break their word by taking any part in the second war. So the victors in the Second Civil War showed little mercy to those who had brought war into the land again. On the evening of the surrender of Colchester, Parliamentarians had Sir<space/><link><target>Charles Lucas</target></link><space/>and Sir<space/><link><target>George Lisle</target></link><space/>shot.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Trevelyan</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">275</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Parliamentary authorities sentenced the leaders of the Welsh rebels, Major-General<space/><link><target>Rowland Laugharne</target></link>, Colonel<space/><link><target>John Poyer</target></link><space/>and Colonel<space/><link><target>Rice Powel</target></link><space/>to death, but executed Poyer alone (25 April 1649), having selected him by lot.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gardiner</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">46</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Of five prominent Royalist peers who had fallen into the hands of Parliament, three, the Duke of Hamilton, the<space/><link><target>Henry Rich, 1st Earl of Holland</target><part>Earl of Holland</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Arthur Capell, 1st Baron Capell of Hadham</target><part>Lord Capel</part></link>, one of the Colchester prisoners and a man of high character, were beheaded at Westminster on 9 March.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gardiner</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">12</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Trial of Charles I for treason</heading><paragraph>Charles' secret pacts and encouragement of his supporters to break their parole caused Parliament to debate whether to return the King to power at all. Those who still supported Charles' place on the throne, such as the army leader and moderate Fairfax, tried once more to negotiate with him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Aylmer</arg><arg>1980</arg><arg name="p">23</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Furious that Parliament continued to countenance Charles as a ruler, the Army marched on Parliament and conducted &quot;<link><target>Pride's Purge</target></link>&quot; (named after the commanding officer of the operation,<space/><link><target>Thomas Pride</target></link>) in December 1648.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Aylmer</arg><arg>1980</arg><arg name="p">22</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Troops arrested 45 Members of Parliament and kept 146 out of the chamber. They allowed only 75 Members in, and then only at the Army's bidding. This<space/><link><target>Rump Parliament</target></link><space/>received orders to set up, in the name of the people of England, a<space/><link><target>High Court of Justice for the trial of Charles I</target></link><space/>for treason.<space/><template><target>sfn</target><arg>Aylmer</arg><arg>1980</arg><arg name="p">25</arg></template><space/>Fairfax, a constitutional monarchist and moderate, refused to participate whatsoever in the trial and resigned as head of the army, allowing Oliver Cromwell to ascend in power.</paragraph><paragraph>At the end of the trial the<space/><link><target>List of regicides of Charles I</target><part>59 Commissioners</part></link><space/>(judges) found Charles I guilty of<space/><link><target>high treason</target></link>, as a &quot;tyrant, traitor, murderer and public enemy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Kelsey</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">583–616</arg></template>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Kirby</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">12</arg></template><space/>cites (1649) 4 State Trials 995. Nalson, 2932.</extension><space/>His<space/><link><target>Decapitation</target><part>beheading</part></link><space/>took place on a scaffold in front of the<space/><link><target>Banqueting House</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Palace of Whitehall</target></link><space/>on 30 January 1649.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Stoyle</arg><arg>2011</arg><arg name="loc">"Overview: Civil War and Revolution, 1603 – 1714"</arg></template><space/>After the<space/><link><target>English Restoration</target><part>Restoration</part></link><space/>in 1660, of the surviving<space/><link><target>List of regicides of Charles I</target><part>regicide</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>not living in exile, nine were executed and most of the rest sentenced to life imprisonment.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Kirby</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">25</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Third English Civil War (16491651)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Third English Civil War</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ireland</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Cromwellian conquest of Ireland</arg></template><link><target>File:Massacre at Drogheda.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>160px</part><part>A 19th century representation of the Massacre at<space/><link><target>Drogheda</target></link>, 1649</part></link>Ireland had known continuous war since the<space/><link><target>Irish Rebellion of 1641</target><part>rebellion of 1641</part></link>, with most of the island controlled by the<space/><link><target>Confederate Ireland</target><part>Irish Confederates</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">121</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Increasingly threatened by the armies of the English Parliament after Charles I's arrest in 1648, the Confederates signed a treaty of alliance with the English Royalists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">122</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The joint Royalist and Confederate forces under<space/><link><target>James Butler, 1st Duke of Ormonde</target><part>the Duke of Ormonde</part></link><space/>attempted to eliminate the Parliamentary army holding<space/><link><target>Dublin</target></link>, but their opponents routed them at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Rathmines</target></link><space/>(2 August 1649).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">127</arg></template>.</extension><space/>As the former Member of Parliament<space/><link><target>Admiral Robert Blake</target></link><space/>blockaded Prince Rupert's fleet in<space/><link><target>Kinsale</target></link>, Oliver Cromwell could land at<space/><link><target>Dublin</target></link><space/>on 15 August 1649 with an army to quell the Royalist alliance in Ireland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Leniham-128"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">128</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Cromwell's suppression of the Royalists in Ireland during 1649 still has a strong resonance for many Irish people. After the<space/><link><target>siege of Drogheda</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Leniham-128"></extension><space/>the massacre of nearly 3,500 people comprising around 2,700 Royalist soldiers and 700 others, including civilians, prisoners, and Catholic priests (Cromwell claimed all the men were carrying arms) became one of the historical memories that has driven Irish-English and Catholic-Protestant strife during the last three centuries. The<space/><link><target>Parliament of England</target><part>Parliamentarian</part></link><space/>conquest of Ireland ground on for another four years until 1653, when the last<space/><link><target>Confederate Ireland</target><part>Irish Confederate</part></link><space/>and Royalist troops surrendered.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">132</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The victors confiscated almost all Irish Catholic-owned land in the wake of the conquest and distributed it to the Parliament's creditors, to the Parliamentary soldiers who served in Ireland, and to English people who had settled there before the war.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Leniham</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="pp">135–6</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Scotland</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms</arg></template>The execution of<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>Charles I</part></link><space/>altered the dynamics of<space/><link><target>Scotland in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms</target><part>the Civil War in Scotland</part></link>, which had raged between Royalists and<space/><link><target>Covenanter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>since 1644. By 1649, the struggle had left the Royalists there in disarray and their erstwhile leader, the<space/><link><target>James Graham, 1st Marquess of Montrose</target><part>Marquess of Montrose</part></link>, had gone into exile. At first,<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target><part>Charles II</part></link><space/>encouraged Montrose to raise a Highland army to fight on the Royalist side.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carpenter-145"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carpenter</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">145</arg></template>.</extension><space/>However, when the Scottish Covenanters (who did not agree with the execution of Charles I and who feared for the future of<space/><link><target>Presbyterianism</target></link><space/>under the new<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of England</target><part>Commonwealth</part></link>) offered him the crown of Scotland, Charles abandoned Montrose to his enemies. However, Montrose, who had raised a<space/><link><target>mercenary</target></link><space/>force in Norway,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carpenter-145"></extension><space/>had already landed and could not abandon the fight. He did not succeed in raising many Highland clans and the Covenanters defeated his army at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Carbisdale 1650</target><part>Battle of Carbisdale</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Ross-shire</target></link><space/>on 27 April 1650. The victors captured Montrose shortly afterwards and took him to<space/><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link>. On 20 May the Scottish Parliament sentenced him to death and had him hanged the next day.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carpenter-146"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carpenter</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">146</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Cromwell at Dunbar Andrew Carrick Gow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>&quot;Cromwell at Dunbar&quot;, by<space/><link><target>Andrew Carrick Gow</target></link></part></link>Charles II landed in Scotland at<space/><link><target>Garmouth</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Morayshire</target></link><space/>on 23 June 1650<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Brett</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">39</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and signed the 1638<space/><link><target>National Covenant</target></link><space/>and the 1643<space/><link><target>Solemn League and Covenant</target></link><space/>shortly after coming ashore.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Brett</arg><arg>2008</arg><arg name="p">41</arg></template>.</extension><space/>With his original Scottish Royalist followers and his new Covenanter allies, King Charles II became the greatest threat facing the new English republic. In response to the threat, Cromwell left some of his lieutenants in Ireland to continue the suppression of the Irish Royalists and returned to England.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carpenter-146"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He arrived in Scotland on 22 July 1650<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Reid</arg><arg>Turner</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="p">18</arg></template>.</extension><space/>and proceeded to lay siege to Edinburgh. By the end of August disease and a shortage of supplies had reduced his army, and he had to order a retreat towards his base at<space/><link><target>Dunbar</target></link>. A Scottish army, assembled under the command of<space/><link><target>David Leslie (Scottish general)</target><part>David Leslie</part></link>, tried to block the retreat, but Cromwell defeated them at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Dunbar (1650)</target><part>Battle of Dunbar</part></link><space/>on 3 September.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Reid</arg><arg>Turner</arg><arg>2004</arg><arg name="loc">p.</arg></template><template><target>Page needed</target><arg name="date">May 2010</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Cromwell's army then took Edinburgh, and by the end of the year his army had occupied much of southern Scotland.</paragraph><paragraph>In July 1651, Cromwell's forces crossed the<space/><link><target>Firth of Forth</target></link><space/>into<space/><link><target>Fife</target></link><space/>and defeated the Scots at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Inverkeithing</target></link><space/>(20 July 1651).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carpenter</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">158</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The New Model Army advanced towards<space/><link><target>Perth, Scotland</target><part>Perth</part></link>, which allowed Charles, at the head of the Scottish army, to move south into England. Cromwell followed Charles into England, leaving<space/><link><target>George Monck</target></link><space/>to finish the campaign in Scotland. Monck took<space/><link><target>Stirling</target></link><space/>on 14 August and<space/><link><target>Dundee</target></link><space/>on 1 September.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carpenter</arg><arg>2005</arg><arg name="p">185</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The next year, 1652, saw the mopping up of the remnants of Royalist resistance, and under the terms of the &quot;<link><target>Tender of Union</target></link>&quot;, the Scots received 30 seats in a united Parliament in London, with General Monck appointed as the military governor of Scotland.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Dand</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">20</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>England</heading><paragraph>Although Cromwell's New Model Army had defeated a Scottish army at Dunbar, Cromwell could not prevent Charles II from marching from Scotland deep into England at the head of another Royalist army.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weiser-01"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Weiser</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">1</arg></template>.</extension><space/>The Royalists marched to the west of England because English Royalist sympathies were strongest in that area, but although some English Royalists joined the army, they came in far fewer numbers than Charles and his Scottish supporters had hoped. Cromwell finally engaged and defeated the new king at<space/><link><target>Battle of Worcester</target><part>Worcester</part></link><space/>on 3 September 1651.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carpenter-145"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Worcester 1651</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Atkin</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Malcolm</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pen and Sword</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-84415-080-9</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Barnsley</arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Escape of Charles II</target><part>Charles II escaped</part></link>, via safe houses and a famous<space/><link><target>Royal Oak (tree)</target><part>oak tree</part></link>, to France, ending the civil wars.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weiser-01"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political control</heading><paragraph>During the Wars, the Parliamentarians established a number of successive committees to oversee the war-effort. The first of these, the<space/><link><target>English Committee of Safety</target><part>Committee of Safety</part></link>, set up in July 1642, comprised 15 Members of Parliament.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Plant</arg><arg>2009</arg><arg name="loc"></arg></template>.<space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>Following the<space/><link><target>England</target><part>Anglo</part></link>-Scottish alliance against the Royalists, the<space/><link><target>Committee of Both Kingdoms</target></link><space/>replaced the Committee of Safety between 1644 and 1648.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kennedy-96"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Kennedy</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">96</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Parliament dissolved the Committee of Both Kingdoms when the alliance ended, but its English members continued to meet and became known as the<space/><link><target>Derby House Committee</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kennedy-96"></extension><space/>A second Committee of Safety then replaced that committee.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Episcopacy</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><link><target>File:William Laud.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>William Laud</target></link>, Charles I's Archbishop of Canterbury.</part></link>During the period of the English Civil War, the role of bishops as wielders of political power and as upholders of the<space/><link><target>established church</target></link><space/>became a matter of heated political controversy.<space/><link><target>John Calvin</target></link><space/>formulated a doctrine of<space/><link><target>Presbyterianism</target></link>, which held that in the New Testament the offices of<space/><italics>presbyter</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>episkopos</italics><space/>were identical; he rejected the doctrine of<space/><link><target>apostolic succession</target></link>. Calvin's follower<space/><link><target>John Knox</target></link><space/>brought Presbyterianism to<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link><space/>when the Scottish church was reformed in 1560. In practice, Presbyterianism meant that committees of lay elders had a substantial voice in church government, as opposed to merely being subjects to a ruling<space/><link><target>hierarchy</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>This vision of at least partial<space/><link><target>democracy</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>ecclesiology</target></link><space/>paralleled the struggles between<space/><link><target>Parliament of England</target><part>Parliament</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>List of English monarchs</target><part>the King</part></link>. A body within the<space/><link><target>Puritan</target></link><space/>movement in the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link><space/>sought to abolish the office of bishop and remake the Church of England along Presbyterian lines. The<space/><link><target>Martin Marprelate</target></link><space/>tracts (158889), applying the<space/><link><target>pejorative</target></link><space/>name of<space/><italics><link><target>prelate</target><part>prelacy</part></link></italics><space/>to the church hierarchy, attacked the office of bishop with satire that deeply offended<space/><link><target>Elizabeth I of England</target><part>Elizabeth I</part></link><space/>and her<space/><link><target>Archbishop of Canterbury</target></link><space/><link><target>John Whitgift</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>vestments controversy</target></link><space/>also related to this movement, seeking further reductions in church ceremony, and labelling the use of elaborate vestments as &quot;unedifying&quot; and even<space/><link><target>idolatry and Christianity</target><part>idolatrous</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>James I of England</target><part>King James I</part></link>, reacting against the perceived contumacy of his Presbyterian Scottish subjects, adopted &quot;No Bishop, no King&quot; as a slogan; he tied the hierarchical authority of the bishop to the absolute authority he sought as king, and viewed attacks on the authority of the bishops as attacks on his own authority. Matters came to a head when King<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>Charles I</part></link><space/>appointed<space/><link><target>William Laud</target></link><space/>as the<space/><link><target>Archbishop of Canterbury</target></link>; Laud aggressively attacked the Presbyterian movement and sought to impose the full<space/><link><target>Book of Common Prayer</target><part>Anglican liturgy</part></link>. The controversy eventually led to Laud's<space/><link><target>impeachment</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>treason</target></link><space/>by a<space/><link><target>bill of attainder</target></link><space/>in 1645, and subsequent execution. Charles also attempted to impose episcopacy on Scotland; the Scots' violent rejection of bishops and liturgical worship sparked the<space/><link><target>Bishops' Wars</target></link><space/>in 16391640.</paragraph><paragraph>During the height of Puritan power in<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of England</target><part>the Commonwealth</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>the Protectorate</target></link>, episcopacy was formally abolished in the Church of England on 9 October 1646.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>King</arg><arg>1968</arg><arg name="p">523–537</arg></template><space/>The Church of England remained Presbyterian until the<space/><link><target>English Restoration</target><part>Restoration</part></link><space/>of the monarchy with<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target><part>Charles II</part></link><space/>in 1660.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Plant</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="loc"></arg></template>.<space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>English overseas possessions</heading><paragraph><template><target>details</target><arg>English overseas possessions in the Wars of the Three Kingdoms</arg></template><template><target>expand section</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template>During the period of the English Civil War, the English overseas possessions were highly involved.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Casualties</heading><paragraph>As usual in wars of this era, disease caused more deaths than combat. There are no accurate figures for these periods, and it is not possible to give a precise overall figure for those killed in battle, as opposed to those who died from disease, or even from a natural decline in population.</paragraph><paragraph>Figures for casualties during this period are unreliable, but some attempt has been made to provide rough estimates.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>White</arg><arg>2012</arg><arg name="loc"></arg></template>.<space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Carlton-211-214"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template>.</extension>In England, a conservative estimate is that roughly 100,000 people died from war-related disease during the three civil wars. Historical records count 84,830 dead from the wars themselves. Counting in accidents and the two Bishops' wars, an estimate of 190,000 dead is achieved,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carlton-211"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>out of a total population of about five million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="James-187"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>James</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="p">187</arg></template><space/>cites:<space/><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1995a</arg><arg name="p">212</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Figures for Scotland are more unreliable and should be treated with greater caution. Casualties include the deaths of prisoners-of-war in conditions that accelerated their deaths, with estimates of 10,000 prisoners not surviving or not returning home (8,000 captured during and immediately after the<space/><link><target>Battle of Worcester</target></link><space/>were deported to<space/><link><target>New England</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bermuda</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>West Indies</target></link><space/>to work for landowners as<space/><link><target>indentured labour</target><trail>ers</trail></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Royle</arg><arg>2006</arg><arg name="p">602</arg></template>.</extension>). There are no figures to calculate how many died from war-related diseases, but if the same ratio of disease to battle deaths from English figures is applied to the Scottish figures, a not unreasonable estimate of 60,000 people is achieved,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carlton-212"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>from a population of about one million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="James-187"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Figures for Ireland are described as &quot;miracles of conjecture&quot;. Certainly the devastation inflicted on Ireland was massive, with the best estimate provided by Sir<space/><link><target>William Petty</target></link>, the father of English demography. Petty estimates that 112,000 Protestants and 504,000 Catholics were killed through<space/><link><target>Black Death</target><part>plague</part></link>, war and<space/><link><target>famine</target></link>, giving an estimated total of 616,000 dead,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carlton-213"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template>.</extension><space/>from a pre-war population of about one and a half million.<extension extension_name='ref' name="James-187"></extension><space/>Although Petty's figures are the best available, they are still acknowledged as being tentative; they do not include the estimate of 40,000 driven into exile, some of whom served as soldiers in European continental armies, while others were sold as indentured servants to New England and the West Indies. Many of those sold to landowners in New England eventually prospered, but many of those sold to landowners in the West Indies were worked to death.</paragraph><paragraph>These estimates indicate that England suffered a 3.7% loss of population, Scotland a loss of 6%, while Ireland suffered a loss of 41% of its population. Putting these numbers into the context of other catastrophes helps to understand the devastation to Ireland in particular. The<space/><link><target>Great Hunger</target></link><space/>of 18451852 resulted in a loss of 16% of the population, while during the Second World War the population of the Soviet Union fell by 16%.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carlton-214"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Carlton</arg><arg>1992</arg><arg name="loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Popular gains</heading><paragraph>Ordinary people took advantage of the dislocation of civil society during the 1640s to derive advantages for themselves. The contemporary guild democracy movement won its greatest successes among London's transport workers, notably the Thames<space/><link><target>watermen</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">O'Riordan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="url">http://geocities.com/englishrevolution/workers.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20091026215834/http://geocities.com/englishrevolution/workers.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">26 October 2009<space/></arg><arg name="title">Self-determination and the London Transport Workers in the Century of Revolution</arg></template>.<space/><template><target>Self-published inline</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>Rural communities seized timber and other resources on the sequestrated estates of royalists and Catholics, and on the estates of the royal family and the church hierarchy. Some communities improved their conditions of tenure on such estates.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>O'Riordan</arg><arg>1993</arg><arg name="pp">184–200</arg></template><space/>The old<space/><italics>status quo</italics><space/>began a retrenchment after the end of the First Civil War in 1646, and more especially after the restoration of monarchy in 1660. But some gains were long-term. The democratic element introduced in the watermen's company in 1642, for example, survived, with vicissitudes, until 1827.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Lindley</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="p">160</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph>The wars left England, Scotland, and Ireland among the few countries in Europe without a monarch. In the wake of victory, many of the ideals (and many of the idealists) became sidelined. The republican government of the<space/><link><target>Commonwealth of England</target></link><space/>ruled England (and later all of Scotland and Ireland) from 1649 to 1653 and from 1659 to 1660. Between the two periods, and due to in-fighting amongst various factions in Parliament,<space/><link><target>Oliver Cromwell</target></link><space/>ruled over<space/><link><target>the Protectorate</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>Lord Protector</target></link><space/>(effectively a military dictator) until his death in 1658.<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Sherwood</arg><arg>1997</arg><arg name="pp">7–11</arg></template><space/>for a longer analysis of the relationship between Cromwell's position, the former monarchy and the military.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Upon his death, Oliver Cromwell's son<space/><link><target>Richard Cromwell</target><part>Richard</part></link><space/>became Lord Protector, but the Army had little confidence in him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template>.</extension><space/>After seven months the Army removed Richard, and in May 1659 it re-installed the Rump.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">9</arg></template>.</extension><space/>However, since the Rump Parliament acted as though nothing had changed since 1653 and as though it could treat the Army as it liked, military force shortly afterwards dissolved this, as well.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">12</arg></template>.</extension><space/>After the second dissolution of the Rump, in October 1659, the prospect of a total descent into anarchy loomed as the Army's pretence of unity finally dissolved into factions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">34</arg></template>.</extension><link><target>File:Musket volley by Sealed Knot.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A historical civil war re-enactment</part></link>Into this atmosphere General<space/><link><target>George Monck, 1st Duke of Albemarle</target><part>George Monck</part></link>, Governor of Scotland under the Cromwells, marched south with his army from Scotland. On 4 April 1660, in the<space/><link><target>Declaration of Breda</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles II of England</target><part>Charles II</part></link><space/>made known the conditions of his acceptance of the Crown of England.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">31</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Monck organised the<space/><link><target>Convention Parliament (1660)</target><part>Convention Parliament</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Keeble</arg><arg>2002</arg><arg name="p">48</arg></template>.</extension><space/>which met for the first time on 25 April 1660. On 8 May 1660, it declared that King Charles II had reigned as the lawful monarch since the execution of Charles I in January 1649. Charles returned from exile on 23 May 1660. On 29 May 1660, the populace in London acclaimed him as king.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Lodge</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="pp">5,6</arg></template>.</extension><space/>His coronation took place at<space/><link><target>Westminster Abbey</target></link><space/>on 23 April 1661. These events became known as the<space/><italics><link><target>Restoration (England)</target><part>Restoration</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Lodge</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">6</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although the monarchy was restored, it was still only with the consent of Parliament; therefore, the civil wars effectively set England and Scotland on course to adopt a<space/><link><target>parliamentary monarchy</target></link><space/>form of government.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Lodge</arg><arg>2007</arg><arg name="p">8</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This system would result in the outcome that the future<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Great Britain</target></link>, formed in 1707 under the<space/><link><target>Act of Union 1707</target><part>Acts of Union</part></link>, would manage to forestall the kind of often-bloody revolution, typical of European republican movements that followed the<space/><link><target>Jacobin (politics)</target><part>Jacobin</part></link><space/>revolution in 18th century France and the later success of<space/><link><target>Napoleon</target></link>, which generally resulted in the total abolition of monarchy. It was no coincidence that the United Kingdom was spared the wave of revolutions that occurred in Europe in the 1840s. Specifically, future monarchs became wary of pushing Parliament too hard, and Parliament effectively chose the line of royal succession in 1688 with the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link><space/>and in the 1701<space/><link><target>Act of Settlement 1701</target><part>Act of Settlement</part></link>. After the<space/><link><target>English Restoration</target><part>Restoration</part></link>, Parliament's factions became political parties (later becoming the<space/><link><target>Tory</target><part>Tories</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Whig (UK)</target><part>Whigs</part></link>) with competing views and varying abilities to influence the decisions of their monarchs.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historiography and explanations</heading><paragraph>In the early decades of the 20th century the<space/><link><target>Whig history</target><part>Whig school</part></link><space/>was the dominant theoretical view. They explained the Civil War as resulting from a centuries-long struggle between Parliament (especially the House of Commons) and the Monarchy, with Parliament defending the traditional rights of Englishmen, while the Stuart monarchy continually attempted to expand its right to arbitrarily dictate law. The most important Whig historian,<space/><link><target>Samuel Rawson Gardiner</target><part>S.R. Gardiner</part></link>, popularised the English Civil War as a 'Puritan Revolution': challenging the repressive Stuart Church, and preparing the way for<space/><link><target>religious toleration</target></link><space/>in the Restoration. Thus, Puritanism was the natural ally of a people preserving their traditional rights against arbitrary monarchical power.</paragraph><paragraph>The Whig view was challenged and largely superseded by the<space/><link><target>Marxism</target><part>Marxist</part></link><space/>school, which became popular in the 1940s, and which interpreted the English Civil War as a<space/><link><target>bourgeois</target></link><space/>revolution. According to Marxist historian<space/><link><target>Christopher Hill (historian)</target><part>Christopher Hill</part></link>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The Civil War was a class war, in which the despotism of Charles I was defended by the reactionary forces of the established Church and conservative landlords, Parliament beat the King because it could appeal to the enthusiastic support of the trading and industrial classes in town and countryside, to the yeomen and progressive gentry, and to wider masses of the population whenever they were able by free discussion to understand what the struggle was really about.</arg><arg name="Christopher Hill<ref>{{Harvnb|Kaye|1995|loc">[https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1970s,<space/><link><target>historical revisionism</target><part>revisionist historians</part></link><space/>challenged both the Whig and the Marxist theories,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Burgess"><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Burgess</arg><arg>1990</arg><arg name="pp">609–627</arg></template>.</extension><space/>notably in the 1973 anthology<space/><italics>The Origins of the English Civil War</italics><space/>(<link><target>Conrad Russell</target></link><space/>ed.). These historians produced work focused on the minutiae of the years immediately preceding the civil war, thereby returning to the contingency-based historiography of<space/><link><target>Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon</target><part>Clarendon's</part></link><space/>famous contemporary history<space/><italics>History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England</italics>. This, it was claimed, demonstrated that factional war-allegiance patterns did not fit either Whig or Marxist history.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gaunt</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="p">60</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Parliament was not inherently progressive, with the events of 1640 a precursor for the<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Gaunt</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg name="pp">60, 61</arg></template>.</extension><space/>nor did Puritans necessarily ally themselves with Parliamentarians.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2008</arg></template><space/>Many members of the bourgeoisie fought for the King, while many landed aristocrats supported Parliament. Thus, revisionist historians claim to have discredited some Whig and Marxist interpretations of the English Civil War.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Burgess"></extension><template><target>Failed verification</target><arg name="date">June 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From the 1990s, a number of historians discarded and replaced the historical title &quot;English Civil War&quot; with the titles the<space/><link><target>Wars of the Three Kingdoms</target></link><space/>and the &quot;British Civil Wars&quot;, positing that the civil war in England cannot be understood isolated from events in other parts of Great Britain and Ireland; King Charles I remains crucial, not just as King of England, but also because of his relationship with the peoples of his other realms. For example, the wars began when King Charles I tried imposing an Anglican Prayer Book upon Scotland, and when this was met with resistance from the<space/><link><target>Covenanter</target><trail>s</trail></link>, he needed an army to impose his will. However, this forced him to call an English Parliament to raise new taxes to pay for the army. The English Parliaments were not willing to grant Charles the revenue he needed to pay for the Scottish expeditionary army unless he addressed their grievances. By the early 1640s, Charles was left in a state of near permanent crisis management; often he was not willing to concede enough ground to any one faction to neutralise the threat, and in some circumstances to do so would only antagonise another faction. For example, Charles finally agreed upon terms with the Covenanters in August 1641, but although this might have weakened the position of the English Parliament, the<space/><link><target>Irish Rebellion of 1641</target></link><space/>broke out in October 1641, largely negating the political advantage he had obtained by relieving himself of the cost of the Scottish invasion.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ohlmeyer, Jane.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historybookshop.com/articles/commentary/civil-wars-of-three-kingdoms-ht.asp'>Civil Wars of the Three Kingdoms</link>-<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historytoday.com/frontpage.aspx'>History Today</link>. Retrieved 31 May 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Thomas Hobbes</target></link><space/>gives a much earlier historical account of the English Civil War in his essay<space/><link><target>Behemoth (Hobbes book)</target><part>Behemoth</part></link>, written in 1668 and published in 1681. He reports that the causes of the war were the doctrines of politics and conflicts that arose from science that disputed those political doctrines.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Hobbes</arg><arg name="first1">Thomas</arg><arg name="title">The English Works of Thomas Hobbes of Malmesbury</arg><arg name="date">1839</arg><arg name="publisher">J. Bohn</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="page">220</arg></template></extension><space/>Behemoth offered a uniquely historical and philosophical approach to naming the catalysts for the war. It also served as a political statement to explain why King Charles I was incapable of holding his place of power and maintaining peace in his kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cornell UP"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Kraynak</arg><arg name="first1">Robert P.</arg><arg name="title">History and Modernity in the Thought of Thomas Hobbes</arg><arg name="date">1990</arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell UP</arg><arg name="location">Ithaca, NY</arg><arg name="page">33</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Specifically, Hobbes analyses the following aspects of English thought during the war (listed in order of his discussions in Behemoth): the opinions of divinity and politics that spurred rebellion; rhetoric and doctrine used by the rebels against the king; and how opinions about taxation, the conscription of soldiers, and military strategy affected the outcomes of battles and shifts of sovereignty.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cornell UP"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Hobbes offered a unique contribution to historical interpretation of the civil war through his Behemoth by connecting the civil war to the motivations of intellectuals who Hobbes reports caused it by trying to spread certain ideas throughout the nation, largely for the sake of displaying their own wisdom and learning.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Goldsmith</arg><arg name="first1">M. M.</arg><arg name="title">Hobbes's Science of Politics</arg><arg name="date">1966</arg><arg name="publisher">Columbia UP</arg><arg name="location">Ithaca, NY</arg><arg name="pages">x–xiii</arg></template></extension><space/>Hobbes held the belief that clerical pretensions had contributed significantly to the trouble during the civil warwhether those of puritan fundamentalists, papal supremacists or divine right Episcopalians (Sommerville).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Sommerville</arg><arg name="first1">J.P.</arg><arg name="title">Thomas Hobbes</arg><arg name="url">http://faculty.history.wisc.edu/sommerville/367/367-091.htm</arg><arg name="website">University of Wisconsin-Madison</arg></template></extension><space/>Hobbes wanted to revoke all of independent power of the clergy and to change the civil system such that they were controlled by the state.</paragraph><paragraph>Some scholars suggest that Behemoth has not received its due respect as an academic work, being comparatively overlooked and underrated in the shadow of<space/><link><target>Leviathan (book)</target><part>Leviathan</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Kraynak</arg><arg name="first1">Robert P.</arg><arg name="title">History and Modernity in the Thought of Thomas Hobbes</arg><arg name="date">1990</arg><arg name="publisher">Cornell UP</arg><arg name="location">Ithaca, NY</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Macgillivray</arg><arg name="first1">Royce</arg><arg name="title">Thomas Hobbes's History of the English Civil War A Study of Behemoth</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the History of Ideas</arg><arg name="date">1970</arg><arg name="volume">31</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="page">179</arg><arg name="accessdate">23 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>One factor that may have contributed to its lack of reception as a historical work is that it takes the form of a dialogue. While philosophical dialogues are common, historical ones are not. Other factors that hindered its success include King Charles II's refusing its publication and Hobbes chiefly interpretive approach to the historical narrative.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Much can be gleaned about Hobbes as a person from looking at the difficulties he faced while seeking an audience for Behemoth. The essay illuminates a flaw shared by most of Hobbes's political philosophy as well, which is his lack of ability or willingness to empathize with perspectives that largely differed from his own. As his perspective was so much at odds with other views, Hobbes struggled to understand the thinking of most of his potential audience and people in general.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>For instance, he accredits the Presbyterians and Parliamentarians with improbably long-planned and wicked ambitions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>Whats more, he hardly understands the orthodox Royalists (he was himself a highly unorthodox Royalist) any better, and he makes only limited concessions of sincerity to the religious feelings of the various parties.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Re-enactments</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Civil war reeanactment.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A historical civil war re-enactment</part></link>Two large historical societies exist,<space/><link><target>The Sealed Knot (reenactment)</target><part>The Sealed Knot</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>The English Civil War Society</target></link>, which regularly<space/><link><target>English Civil War reenactment</target><part>re-enact</part></link><space/>events and battles of the Civil War in full period costume.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Timeline of the English Civil War</target></link>, showing events leading up to, culminating in, and resulting from the English Civil Wars.</listitem><listitem><link><target>First English Civil War, 1642</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>First English Civil War, 1643</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>First English Civil War, 1644</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>First English Civil War, 1645</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>First English Civil War, 1646</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cromwell's Soldiers' Pocket Bible</target></link>, booklet Cromwell issued to his army in 1643.</listitem><listitem><link><target>English Dissenters</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>William Hiseland</target></link>, the last Royalist veteran of the Civil War</listitem><listitem><link><target>Thirty Years' War</target></link>, a defining event in European history during the reign of Charles I.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Levellers</target></link>, a movement for power reform.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Diggers</target></link></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>notelist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Aylmer<space/></arg><arg name="first">G. E.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">The Historical Background<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">[[Constantinos Patrides|Patrides]]<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">C.A.<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Waddington<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Raymond B.<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Age of Milton: Backgrounds to Seventeenth-Century Literature</arg><arg name="publisher">Manchester: Manchester University Press<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1–33<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Brett<space/></arg><arg name="first">A. C. A.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="title">Charles II and His Court<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Read Books<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-140-20445-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Burgess<space/></arg><arg name="first">Glenn<space/></arg><arg name="year">1990<space/></arg><arg name="title">Historiographical reviews on revisionism: an analysis of early Stuart historiography in the 1970s and 1980s<space/></arg><arg name="journal">The Historical Journal</arg><arg name="volume">33<space/></arg><arg name="number">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">609–627<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://journals.cambridge.org/production/action/cjoGetFulltext?fulltextid</arg><arg name="doi">10.1017/s0018246x90000013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carlton<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles<space/></arg><arg name="year">1987<space/></arg><arg name="title">Archbishop William Laud<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Routledge and Keagan Paul<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carlton<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles<space/></arg><arg name="year">1992<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Experience of the British Civil Wars<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-10391-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carlton<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles<space/></arg><arg name="title">Charles I: The Personal Monarch<space/></arg><arg name="location">Great Britain<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-12141-8<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carlton<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995a<space/></arg><arg name="title">Going to the wars: The experience of the British civil wars, 1638–1651<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-415-10391-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Carpenter<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stanley D. M.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">Military leadership in the British civil wars, 1642–1651: The Genius Of This Age<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Abingdon: Frank Cass<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Croft<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pauline<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="title">King James<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Basingstoke and New York: Palgrave Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-333-61395-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Coward<space/></arg><arg name="first">Barry<space/></arg><arg name="year">1994<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Stuart Age<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Longman<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-582-48279-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Coward<space/></arg><arg name="first">Barry<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Stuart age: England, 1603–1714<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harlow: Pearson Education<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Dand<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles Hendry<space/></arg><arg name="year">1972<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Mighty Affair: how Scotland lost her parliament<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oliver and Boyd<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Fairfax<space/></arg><arg name="first">Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 May 1648<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.british-history.ac.uk/report.asp?compid</arg><arg name="chapter">House of Lords Journal Volume 10: 19 May 1648: Letter from L. Fairfax, about the Disposal of the Forces, to suppress the Insurrections in Suffolk, Lancashire, and S. Wales; and for Belvoir Castle to be secured<space/></arg><arg name="title">Journal of the House of Lords: volume 10: 1648–1649<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Institute of Historical Research<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Gardiner<space/></arg><arg name="first">Samuel R.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Samuel Rawson Gardiner</arg><arg name="title">History of the Commonwealth and Protectorate 1649–1660</arg><arg name="publisher">Elibron Classics<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Gaunt<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">The English Civil War: the essential readings<space/></arg><arg name="series">Blackwell essential readings in history<space/></arg><arg name="edition">illustrated<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley-Blackwell<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-631-20809-9<space/></arg><arg name="page">[http://books.google.co.nz/books?id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Gregg<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pauline<space/></arg><arg name="year">1981<space/></arg><arg name="title">King Charles I<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Dent<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Gregg<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pauline<space/></arg><arg name="year">1984<space/></arg><arg name="title">King Charles I</arg><arg name="publisher">Berkeley: University of California Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Hibbert<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Weidenfeld and Nicolson<space/></arg><arg name="year">1968</arg><arg name="title">Charles I</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Johnston<space/></arg><arg name="first">William Dawson</arg><arg name="year">1901<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The history of England from the accession of James the Second<space/></arg><arg name="volume">I<space/></arg><arg name="location">Boston and New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Houghton, Mifflin and company<space/></arg><arg name="pages">[https://archive.org/stream/historyenglandf01johngoog#page/n151/mode/1up 83]–86</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Hibbert<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cavaliers & Roundheads: the English Civil War, 1642–1649<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Scribner</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Hill<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="year">1972<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Christopher Hill (historian)<space/></arg><arg name="title">The World Turned Upside Down: Radical ideas during the English Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Viking</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Hughes<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ann</arg><arg name="year">1991<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Causes of the English Civil War<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Macmillan</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">King<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="date">July 1968<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Episcopate during the Civil Wars, 1642–1649<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[The English Historical Review]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>83<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>328<space/></arg><arg name="pages">523–537<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">564164<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/ehr/lxxxiii.cccxxviii.523</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">James<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lawarance<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">Warrior Race: A History of the British at War</arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">St. Martin's Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0-312-30737-3</arg><arg name="page">187</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">John<space/></arg><arg name="first">Terry<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Civil War in Pembrokeshire<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Logaston Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kaye<space/></arg><arg name="first">Harvey J.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="title">The British Marxist historians: an introductory analysis<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Palgrave Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-312-12733-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Keeble<space/></arg><arg name="first">N. H.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Restoration: England in the 1660s<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford: Blackwell</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kelsey<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sean<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ehr.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/content/abstract/118/477/583<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Trial of Charles I<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[English Historical Review]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">118<space/></arg><arg name="number">477<space/></arg><arg name="pages">583–616<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1093/ehr/118.477.583</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kennedy<space/></arg><arg name="first">D. E.</arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">The English Revolution, 1642–1649<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Macmillan</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kenyon<space/></arg><arg name="first">J.P.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1978<space/></arg><arg name="title">Stuart England<space/></arg><arg name="location">Harmondsworth<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Books<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Kirby<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Michael Kirby (judge)<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>22 January 1999<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.hcourt.gov.au/assets/publications/speeches/former-justices/kirbyj/kirbyj_charle88.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">The trial of King Charles I – defining moment for our constitutional liberties<space/></arg><arg name="series">speech to the Anglo-Australasian Lawyers association</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Leniham<space/></arg><arg name="first">Pádraig<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="title">Consolidating Conquest: Ireland 1603–1727<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harlow: Pearson Education</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Lindley<space/></arg><arg name="first">Keith<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="title">Popular politics and religion in Civil War London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Scolar Press</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Lodge<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="title">The History of England – From the Restoration to the Death of William III (1660–1702)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Read Books</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">McClelland<space/></arg><arg name="first">J. S.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="title">A History of Western Political Thought<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Newman<space/></arg><arg name="first">P. R.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="title">Atlas of the English Civil War<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">O'Riordan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Christopher<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://geocities.com/englishrevolution/popular.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20091026215835/http://geocities.com/englishrevolution/popular.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">26 October 2009<space/></arg><arg name="title">Popular Exploitation of Enemy Estates in the English Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[History (The Journal of the Historical Association)|History]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume">78<space/></arg><arg name="year">1993<space/></arg><arg name="pages">184–200<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1468-229x.1993.tb01577.x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Pipes<space/></arg><arg name="first">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">Property and Freedom<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alfred A. Knopf</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Plant<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 June 2002<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.british-civil-wars.co.uk/glossary/episcopacy.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">British Civil Wars, Commonwealth and Protectorate 1638–60:Episcopy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[http://www.british-civil-wars.co.uk/index.htm British Civil Wars website]</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 August 2011</arg></template><space/><template><target>Self-published inline</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Plant<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="date">3 August 2009<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.british-civil-wars.co.uk/glossary/committee-safety.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Committee of Safety<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[http://www.british-civil-wars.co.uk/index.htm British Civil Wars website]</arg><arg name="accessdate">25 November 2009</arg></template><space/><template><target>Self-published inline</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Purkiss<space/></arg><arg name="first">Diane<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="title">The English Civil War: A People's History<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Harper Perennial<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Reid<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stuart<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Turner<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Graham<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dunbar 1650: Cromwell's most famous victory<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Botley: Osprey<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Rosner<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lisa<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Theibault<space/></arg><arg name="first2">John<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Short History of Europe, 1600–1815: Search For A Reasonable World<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York: M. E. Sharpe<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Royle<space/></arg><arg name="first">Trevor</arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">Civil War: The Wars of the Three Kingdoms 1638–1660<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London:Abacus<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-349-11564-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Seel<space/></arg><arg name="first">Graham E.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">The English Wars and Republic, 1637–1660<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Sharp<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">England in crisis 1640–60<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford: Heinneman<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Sherwood<space/></arg><arg name="first">Roy Edward<space/></arg><arg name="year">1992<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Civil War in the Midlands, 1642–1651<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alan Sutton<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Sherwood<space/></arg><arg name="first">Roy Edward<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="title">Oliver Cromwell: King In All But Name, 1653–1658<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York: St Martin's Press</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Smith<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>David L.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Stuart Parliaments 1603–1689<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Arnold<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Stoyle<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mark<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 February 2011<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/civil_war_revolution/overview_civil_war_revolution_01.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="title">History – British History in depth: Overview: Civil War and Revolution, 1603 – 1714<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">December 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Trevelyan<space/></arg><arg name="first">George Macaulay</arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="title">England Under the Stuarts<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Routledge</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Upham<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles Wentworth<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Charles Wentworth Upham<space/></arg><arg name="year">1842<space/></arg><arg name="editor">[[Jared Sparks]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">Life of Sir Henry Vane, Fourth Governor of Massachusetts in The Library of American Biography<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harper & Brothers<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1115288024</arg></template><template><target>full</target><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Walter<space/></arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title">Understanding Popular Violence in the English Revolution: The Colchester Plunderers<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Wanklyn<space/></arg><arg name="first">Malcolm<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Jones<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Frank<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Military History of the English Civil War, 1642–1646: Strategy and Tactics<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harlow: Pearson Education<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Wedgwood<space/></arg><arg name="first">C. V.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1970<space/></arg><arg name="title">The King's War: 1641–1647<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London: Fontana<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Weiser<space/></arg><arg name="first">Brian<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="title">Charles II and the Politics of Access<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Woodbridge: Boydell.<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">White<space/></arg><arg name="first">Matthew<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://necrometrics.com/pre1700a.htm#EnglCW<space/></arg><arg name="title">Selected Death Tolls for Wars, Massacres and Atrocities Before the 20th century: British Isles, 1641–52<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">July 2012</arg></template><space/><template><target>Self-published inline</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><space/><template><target>better source</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Young<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Holmes<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Richard<space/></arg><arg name="year">1974<space/></arg><arg name="title">The English Civil War: a military history of the three civil wars 1642–1651<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Eyre Methuen<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ashley, Maurice.<space/><italics>The English Civil War.</italics><space/>Sutton. (1990)</listitem><listitem>Clarendon.<space/><italics>History of the Rebellion and Civil Wars in England: Begun in the Year 1641</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon</target></link><space/>(1717):<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio05clargoog'>Volume I, Part 1</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio09clargoog'>Volume I, Part 2</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio02clargoog'>Volume II, Part 1</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio07clargoog'>Volume II, Part 2</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio00clargoog'>Volume III, Part 1</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historyrebellio03clargoog'>Volume III, Part 2</link><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Life of Edward, Earl of Clarendon, in which is included a Continuation of his History of the Grand Rebellion</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Edward Hyde, 1st Earl of Clarendon</target></link><space/>(Clarendon Press, 1827):<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/lifeofedwardearl01clariala'>Volume I</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/lifeofedwardearl02clariala'>Volume II</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/lifeofedwardearl03clariala'>Volume III</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Gardiner, Samuel Rawson.<space/><italics>History of the Great Civil War, 16421649</italics><space/>(18861901):<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historygreatciv07gardgoog'>Volume I (16421644)</link>;<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historygreatciv04gardgoog'>Volume II (16441647)</link>;<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historygreatciv00gardgoog'>Volume III (16451647)</link>;<space/><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/stream/historygreatciv06gardgoog'>Volume IV (16471649)</link>, The basic narrative history used by all other scholars.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="ref">none</arg><arg name="last">Ludlow<space/></arg><arg name="first">Edmund<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Edmond Ludlow<space/></arg><arg name="year">1894<space/></arg><arg name="editor">[[C.H. Firth]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Memoirs of Edmund Ludlow Lieutenant-General of the Horse in the Army of the Commonwealth of England 1625–1672<space/></arg><arg name="location">Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Clarendon Press</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>citation</target><arg name="ref">none<space/></arg><arg name="last">Scott<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jonathan<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="title">England's Troubles: Seventeenth-century English political instability in European context<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0521423342</arg></template><space/>&quot;Jonathan Scott's major reinterpretation of the seventeenth century ... England's crisis is viewed in European perspective&quot; (<template><target>citation</target><arg name="ref">none<space/></arg><arg name="last">Morgan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Hiram<space/></arg><arg name="date">March 2001<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.history.ac.uk/reviews/review/187<space/></arg><arg name="title">review<space/></arg><arg name="journal">journal of Historical Research<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.14296/RiH/issn.1749.8155</arg></template>).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Sister project links</target><arg>English Civil War</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.englishcivilwar.org'>Englishcivilwar.org</link><space/>News, comment and discussion about the English Civil War</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://english-civil-war-society.org.uk/www/cms/'>Official website of the English Civil War Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nybooks.com/articles/2894'>The Revolution Over the Revolution</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>PDFlink</target><arg>[http://gainesjunction.tamu.edu/issues/vol2num1/bduke.pdf Jack Goldstone’s Model and the English Civil War]</arg><arg>103&nbsp;[[Kibibyte|KiB]]</arg></template><space/>by Brandon W Duke</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://boar.org.uk/ariwxe1CivilWar(home.htm'>This page has links to some transcriptions of contemporary documents concerning eastern England</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.archive.org/web/20070714115529/http://www.theteacher99.btinternet.co.uk/ecivil/index.htm'>A national Civil War chronology</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://boar.org.uk/oriwxs5CivilWarLincs(chron.htm'>Civil War chronology for Lincolnshire and its environs</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.connectedhistories.org/Search_results.aspx?dtf=1500-01-01&amp;amp;dtt=1899-12-31&amp;amp;kw=%22civil+war%22'>Connected Histories</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Kingdom of England</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:English Civil War</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Wars of the Three Kingdoms</target></link><link><target>Category:Civil wars in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Charles I of England</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century military history of the Kingdom of England</target></link><link><target>Category:Monarchism</target></link><link><target>Category:Republicanism in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Wars involving England</target></link><link><target>Category:Wars involving Scotland</target></link><link><target>Category:Wars involving Ireland</target></link><link><target>Category:17th century in England</target></link></paragraph></article>