<article title='Customer_relationship_management'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Business administration</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Customer relationship management</bold><space/>(<bold>CRM</bold>) is an approach to managing a companys interaction with current and future<space/><link><target>customers</target></link>. It often involves using technology to organize, automate, and synchronize<space/><link><target>sales</target></link>,<space/><link><target>marketing</target></link>,<space/><link><target>customer service</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>technical support</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Robert Shaw (Marketing)</target><part>Shaw, Robert</part></link>, Computer Aided Marketing &amp; Selling (1991) Butterworth Heinemann ISBN 978-0-7506-1707-9</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Characteristics</heading><paragraph>CRM is a<space/><link><target>customer orientation</target><part>customer-oriented</part></link><space/>feature with service response based on customer input, one-to-one solutions to customers' requirements, direct online communications with customer and customer service centers that are intended to help customers solve their issues. It includes the following functions:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Sales force automation</target></link>, which implements<space/><link><target>sales promotion</target></link><space/>analysis, automates the tracking of a client's account history for repeated sales or future sales, and oordinates sales, marketing, call centers, and retail outlets.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Data warehouse</target></link><space/>technology, used to<space/><link><target>Aggregate data</target><part>aggregate transaction information</part></link>, to merge the information with CRM products, and to provide<space/><link><target>key performance indicator</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Opportunity management</target></link><space/>which helps the company to manage unpredictable growth and demand, and implement a good<space/><link><target>forecasting</target></link><space/>model to integrate sales history with<space/><link><target>sales forecasting</target><part>sales projection</part><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zeng"></extension></listitem><listitem>CRM systems that track and measure marketing campaigns over multiple networks, tracking customer analysis by customer clicks and sales.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Impact on customer satisfaction</heading><paragraph>According to Bolton,<space/><link><target>customer satisfaction</target></link><space/>has significant implications for the economic performance of firms,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bolton, Ruth N. 1998">Bolton, Ruth N. (1998), A Dynamic Model of the Duration of the Customers Relationship with a Continuous Service Provider: The Role of Satisfaction, Marketing Science, 17 (1), 4565.</extension><space/>because it has been found to increase customer loyalty and usage behavior and reduce customer complaints, and the likelihood of<space/><link><target>churn rate</target><part>customer defection</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Fornell, Claes (1992), &quot;A National Customer Satisfaction Barometer: The Swedish Experience&quot;, Journal of Marketing, 56 (January), 6-22</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The implementation of CRM is likely to have an effect on customer satisfaction for at least three reasons:</paragraph><paragraph>Firstly, firms are able to customize their offerings for each customer. By accumulating information across customer interactions and processing this information to discover hidden patterns, CRM applications help firms customize their offerings to suit the individual tastes of their customers.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template><space/>This customization enhances the perceived quality of products and services from a customer's viewpoint, and because perceived quality is a determinant of customer satisfaction, it follows that CRM applications indirectly affect customer satisfaction.</paragraph><paragraph>Secondly, CRM applications enable firms to provide timely, accurate processing of customer orders and requests and the ongoing management of customer accounts. For example, Piccoli and Applegate (2003) discuss how Wyndham uses IT tools to deliver a consistent service experience across its various properties to a customer. Both an improved ability to customize and a reduced variability of the consumption experience enhance perceived quality, which in turn positively affects customer satisfaction.<extension extension_name='ref'>Piccoli, Gabriele and L. Applegate (2003), &quot;Wyndham International: Fostering High-Touch with High-Tech&quot;, Case Study No. 9-803-092, Harvard Business School</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Thirdly, CRM applications also help firms manage customer relationships more effectively across the stages of relationship initiation, maintenance, and termination.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reinartz, Werner, Manfred Krafft, and Wayne D. Hoyer (2004), &quot;The Customer Relationship Management Process: Its Measurement and Impact on Performance&quot;, Journal of Marketing Research, 41 (August), 293305</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Types</heading><heading level='3'>Call centers</heading><paragraph>As well as tracking, recording and storing customer information, CRM systems in<space/><link><target>call center</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>codify the interactions between company and customers by using analytics and<space/><link><target>key performance indicator</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to give the users information on where to focus their marketing and customer service. The intention is to maximize<space/><link><target>average revenue per user</target></link>, decrease<space/><link><target>churn rate</target></link><space/>and decrease idle and unproductive contact with the customers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sap1">SAP Insider (15 November 2007)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sdn.sap.com/irj/scn/go/portal/prtroot/docs/library/uuid/e044e180-8375-2a10-a2b2-b5709ea68ccb'>Still Struggling to Reduce Call Center Costs Without Losing Customers?</link></extension><space/>CRM software can also be used to identify and reward loyal customers over a period of time.</paragraph><paragraph>Growing in popularity is the idea of gamifying customer service environments. The repetitive and tedious act of answering support calls all day can be draining, even for the most enthusiastic customer service representative. When agents are bored with their work, they become less engaged and less motivated to do their jobs well. They are also prone to making mistakes.<space/><link><target>Gamification</target></link><space/>tools can motivate agents by tapping into their visceral need for reward, status, achievement, and competition.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Myron<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.destinationcrm.com/Articles/ReadArticle.aspx?ArticleID</arg><arg name="title">CRM in Customer Service<space/></arg><arg name="website">DestinationCRM.com<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Information Today, Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 October 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Business-to-business</heading><paragraph>According to a<space/><link><target>Sweeney Group</target></link><space/>definition, CRM is &quot;all the tools, technologies and procedures to manage, improve, or facilitate sales, support and related interactions with customers, prospects, and business partners throughout the enterprise&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="davenport">Davenport, T.H., Harris, J.G., Kohli, A.K. (2001), &quot;How do they know their customers so well?&quot;, MIT Sloan Management Review, Vol. 42 No.2, pp.63-73.</extension><space/>It assumes that CRM is involved in every<space/><link><target>Business-to-business</target><part>B2B</part></link><space/>transaction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="zeng">Yun E. Zeng, H. Joseph Wen, David C. Yen, &quot;Customer relationship management (CRM) in business-to-business (B2B) e-commerce&quot;, Emerald 11, (2003).</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the general notion that CRM systems were created for the customer-centric businesses, they can also be applied to B2B environments to streamline and improve customer management conditions. For the best level of CRM operation in a B2B environment, the software must be personalized and delivered at individual levels.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Henderson">Rebekah Henderson,<space/><italics>B2B Insights</italics><space/>(2013)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.b2binsights.com/how-to-build-a-b2b-friendly-crm/'>How to build a B2B-friendly CRM</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main differences between<space/><link><target>B2C</target></link><space/>and B2B CRM systems are as follows:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>B2B companies have smaller contact databases than B2C.</listitem><listitem>The volume of sales in B2B is relatively small.</listitem><listitem>In B2B there are less figure propositions, but in some cases they cost a lot more than B2C items.</listitem><listitem>Relationships in B2B environment are built over a longer period of time.</listitem><listitem>B2B CRM must be easily integrated with products from other companies. Such integration enables the creation of forecasts about customer behavior based on their buying history, bills, business success, etc.</listitem><listitem>An application for a B2B company must have a function to connect all the contacts, processes and deals among the customers segment and then prepare a paper.</listitem><listitem>Automation of sales process is an important requirement for B2B products. It should effectively manage the deal and progress it through all the phases towards signing.</listitem><listitem>A crucial point is personalization. It helps the B2B company to create and maintain strong and long-lasting relationship with the customer.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Social media</heading><paragraph>Balaram (2010)<extension extension_name='ref'>Balaram, A., Adhikari, B. (2010), Managing Customer Relationships in Service Organizations. Administration and Management Review, 21(2), 65-78.</extension><space/>presented evidence of a significant increase in the use of<space/><link><target>social network</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>sites, especially among young people. This has caused companies to use these sites to draw attention to their products, services and brands, with the aim of building up customer relationships to increase demand.</paragraph><paragraph>Some CRM systems integrate<space/><link><target>social media</target></link><space/>sites like<space/><link><target>Twitter</target></link>,<space/><link><target>LinkedIn</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Facebook</target></link><space/>to track and communicate with customers sharing their opinions and experiences with a company, products and services.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dest2">DestinationCRM.com (2009)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.destinationcrm.com/Articles/Editorial/Magazine-Features/Who-Owns-the-Social-Customer-54028.aspx'>Who Owns the Social Customer?</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Enterprise Feedback Management</target></link><space/>software platforms such as<space/><link><target>Confirmit</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Medallia</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Net Promoter</target><part>Satmetrix</part></link><space/>combine internal survey data with trends identified through social media to allow businesses to make more accurate decisions on which products to supply.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://searchbusinessanalytics.techtarget.com/feature/Seeking-treasure-from-social-media-tracking-Follow-the-customer<space/></arg><arg name="title">Seeking treasure from social media tracking? Follow the customer<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SearchBusinessAnalytics<space/></arg><arg name="date">2013-04-23<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-10-01<space/></arg><arg name="first">Aaron<space/></arg><arg name="last">Lester</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Other types</heading><paragraph>Some CRM software is available as a<space/><link><target>software as a service</target></link><space/>(SaaS), delivered via the internet and accessed via a<space/><link><target>web browser</target></link><space/>instead of being installed on a local computer. Businesses using the software do not purchase it, but typically pay a recurring subscription fee to the software vendor.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cloud Taxonomy CRM Software as a Service"><link type='external' href='http://cloudtaxonomy.opencrowd.com/taxonomy/software-as-a-service/customer-relationship-mgmt/'>''Cloud Taxonomy CRM Software as a Service''</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>small business</target><trail>es</trail></link><space/>a CRM system may consist of a contact manager system which integrates emails, documents, jobs, faxes, and scheduling for individual accounts.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">December 2014</arg></template><space/>CRM systems available for specific markets (legal, finance) frequently focus on event management and relationship tracking as opposed to financial return on investment (ROI).</paragraph><paragraph>Customer-centric relationship management (CCRM) is a nascent sub-discipline that focuses on customer preferences instead of customer leverage. CCRM aims to add value by engaging customers in individual, interactive relationships.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.gtnexus.com/blog/cloud-technology-platform/its-all-about-the-customer-stupid-the-importance-of-selecting-customer-centric-partners/'>Its all about the Customer, Stupid The Importance of Customer Centric Partners</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Systems for non-profit and membership-based organizations help track constituents, fund-raising, Sponsors demographics, membership levels, membership directories, volunteering and communication with individuals.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Adoption issues</heading><paragraph>In 2003, a<space/><link><target>Gartner</target></link><space/>report estimated that more than $2 billion had been spent on software that was not being used. According to<space/><italics>CSO Insights</italics>, less than 40 percent of 1,275 participating companies had end-user adoption rates above 90 percent.<extension extension_name='ref' name="dickie">Jim Dickie,<space/><italics>CSO Insights</italics><space/>(2006)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.destinationcrm.com/Articles/Columns-Departments/Reality-Check/Demystifying-CRM-Adoption-Rates-42496.aspx'>Demystifying CRM Adoption Rates</link></extension><space/>Many corporations only use CRM systems on a partial or fragmented basis.<extension extension_name='ref'>Joachim, David. &quot;CRM tools improve access, usability.&quot; (cover story).<space/><italics>B to B</italics><space/>87, no. 3 (11 March 2002): 1</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In a 2007 survey from the UK, four-fifths of senior executives reported that their biggest challenge is getting their staff to use the systems they had installed. 43 percent of respondents said they use less than half the functionality of their existing systems.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sims">David Sims, TMC.net (2007)<space/><link type='external' href='http://blog.tmcnet.com/telecom-crm/2007/11/30/crm-adoption-biggest-problem-in-83-percent-of-cases-wigan-gets-crm-tre.asp'>CRM Adoption Biggest Problem in 83 Percent of Cases</link></extension><space/>Recently, it was found in a study that market research regarding consumers' preferences may increase the adoption of CRM among the developing countries' consumers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Hasan">Hasan, M. R., Rahman, M., And Khan, M. M. (2013). Rural Consumers Adoption of CRM in a Developing Country Context. International Journal of Business and Management Invention (IJBMI), 2(9), 121-131.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ijbmi.org/papers/Vol(2)9/Version-1/P029101210131.pdf'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>CRM Paradox</heading><paragraph>The CRM Paradox, also referred to as the &quot;Dark side of CRM&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Nguyen">Nguyen, B. &amp; Mutum, D. S. (2012). A review of customer relationship management: successes, advances, pitfalls and futures, Business Process Management Journal, 18 (3). 400-419<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.emeraldinsight.com/journals.htm?issn=1463-7154&amp;amp;volume=18&amp;amp;issue=3&amp;amp;articleid=17036343&amp;amp;show=html'></link></extension>entails favoritism and differential treatment of some customers. This may cause perceptions of unfairness among other customers' buyers. They may opt out of relationships, spread negative information, or engage in misbehavior that may damage the firm.CRM fundamentally involves treating customers differently based on the assumption that customers are different and have different needs.Such perceived inequality may cause dissatisfaction, mistrust and result in unfair practices. A customer shows trust when he bonds in a relationship with a firm when he knows that the firm is acting fairly and adding value. However, customers may not trust that firms will be fair in splitting the<space/><template><target>cl-span</target><arg>[[value creation]] pie</arg><arg name="date">July 2014</arg></template><space/>in the first place. For example, Amazons test use of dynamic pricing (different prices for different customers) was a public relations nightmare for the company.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Martinez</arg><arg name="first1">Michael J.</arg><arg name="title">Amazon Error May End 'Dynamic Pricing'</arg><arg name="url">http://abcnews.go.com/Technology/story?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">7 September 2015</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC News</arg><arg name="date">29 September 2006</arg><arg name="ref">Dynamic</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Market leaders</heading><paragraph>The CRM market grew by 12.5 percent in 2012.<extension extension_name='ref'>Forbes.com (2013)<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.forbes.com/sites/louiscolumbus/2013/04/26/2013-crm-market-share-update-40-of-crm-systems-sold-are-saas-based/'>2013 CRM Market Share Update: 40% Of CRM Systems Sold Are SaaS-Based</link></extension><space/>The following table lists the top vendors in 20062008 and 2012-2014 (figures in millions of US dollars) published in<space/><link><target>Gartner</target></link><space/>studies.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite press release</target><arg name="url">http://www.gartner.com/it/page.jsp?id</arg><arg name="title">Gartner Says Worldwide Customer Relationship Management Market Grew 23 Percent in 2007</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-08-15</arg><arg name="date">12 September 2008<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Gartner, Inc<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite press release</target><arg name="url">http://www.gartner.com/it/page.jsp?id</arg><arg name="title">Gartner Says Worldwide CRM Market Grew 12.5 Percent in 2008</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-10-27</arg><arg name="date">15 June 2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Gartner, Inc<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite press release</target><arg name="url">http://www.forbes.com/sites/louiscolumbus/2015/05/22/gartner-crm-market-share-update-47-of-all-crm-systems-are-saas-based-salesforce-accelerates-lead/</arg><arg name="title">Gartner CRM Market Share Update: 47% Of All CRM Systems Are SaaS-Based, Salesforce Accelerates Lead</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-08-10</arg><arg name="date">22 May 2015<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Forbes<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable sortable"><tablerow><tablehead>Vendor</tablehead><tablehead>2014 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2014 Share(%)</tablehead><tablehead>2013 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2013 Share (%)</tablehead><tablehead>2012 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2012 Share (%)</tablehead><tablehead>2008 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2008 Share (%)</tablehead><tablehead>2007 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2007 Share (%)</tablehead><tablehead>2006 Revenue</tablehead><tablehead>2006 Share (%)</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Salesforce.com</target><part>Salesforce.com CRM</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>4,250.4</tablecell><tablecell>18.4</tablecell><tablecell>3,292</tablecell><tablecell>16.1</tablecell><tablecell>2,525.6</tablecell><tablecell>14.0</tablecell><tablecell>965</tablecell><tablecell>10.6</tablecell><tablecell>676.5</tablecell><tablecell>8.3</tablecell><tablecell>451.7</tablecell><tablecell>6.9</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>SAP AG</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>2,795.1</tablecell><tablecell>12.1</tablecell><tablecell>2,622</tablecell><tablecell>12.8</tablecell><tablecell>2,327.1</tablecell><tablecell>12.9</tablecell><tablecell>2,055</tablecell><tablecell>22.5</tablecell><tablecell>2,050.8</tablecell><tablecell>25.3</tablecell><tablecell>1,681.7</tablecell><tablecell>25.6</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>ZOHO</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>950.4</tablecell><tablecell>8.4</tablecell><tablecell>850</tablecell><tablecell>6.5</tablecell><tablecell>725.6</tablecell><tablecell>5.2</tablecell><tablecell>325</tablecell><tablecell>3.1</tablecell><tablecell>200.5</tablecell><tablecell>8.3</tablecell><tablecell>150.7</tablecell><tablecell>5.9</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Oracle Corporation</target><part>Oracle</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2,102.1</tablecell><tablecell>9.1</tablecell><tablecell>2,097</tablecell><tablecell>10.2</tablecell><tablecell>2,015.2</tablecell><tablecell>11.1</tablecell><tablecell>1,475</tablecell><tablecell>16.1</tablecell><tablecell>1,319.8</tablecell><tablecell>16.3</tablecell><tablecell>1,016.8</tablecell><tablecell>15.5</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Microsoft Dynamics CRM</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>1,432.2</tablecell><tablecell>6.2</tablecell><tablecell>1,392</tablecell><tablecell>6.8</tablecell><tablecell>1,135.3</tablecell><tablecell>6.3</tablecell><tablecell>581</tablecell><tablecell>6.4</tablecell><tablecell>332.1</tablecell><tablecell>4.1</tablecell><tablecell>176.1</tablecell><tablecell>2.7</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Others</tablecell><tablecell>12,520.2</tablecell><tablecell>54.2</tablecell><tablecell>11,076</tablecell><tablecell>54.1</tablecell><tablecell>10,086.8</tablecell><tablecell>55.7</tablecell><tablecell>3,620</tablecell><tablecell>39.6</tablecell><tablecell>3,289.1</tablecell><tablecell>40.6</tablecell><tablecell>2,881.6</tablecell><tablecell>43.8</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><bold>Total</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>23,100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>20,476</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>18,090</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>9,147</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>7,674</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>6,214</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>100</bold></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Trends</heading><paragraph>In the Gartner CRM Summit 2010 challenges like &quot;System tries to capture data from social networking traffic like Twitter, handles Facebook page addresses or other online social networking sites&quot; were discussed and solutions were provided that would help in bringing more clientele.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.hcltech.com/sites/default/files/CRM_Trends_Insurance.pdf'>CRM Trends in Insurance Industry</link><italics>CRM Trends in Insurance Industry</italics>: April, 2010</extension>Many CRM vendors offer subscription-based web tools (<link><target>cloud computing</target></link>) and SaaS. Some CRM systems are equipped with mobile capabilities, making information accessible to remote sales staff.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2013</arg></template><space/><link><target>Salesforce.com</target></link><space/>was the first company to provide enterprise applications through a web browser, and has maintained its leadership position.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pcworld.com/businesscenter/article/193463/put_cloud_crm_to_work.html'>Put Cloud CRM to Work</link><space/><italics>PC World</italics>: April, 2010</extension><space/>Salesforce continues to be a market leader as the CRM with the most customers<space/><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.capterra.com/customer-relationship-management-software/#infographic<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Top 20 Most Popular CRM<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Capterra<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and is rated-highly among their customers.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">https://www.salesforce.com/crm/top-rated/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Best CRM<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">salesforce.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Traditional providers have recently moved into the cloud-based market via acquisitions of smaller providers:<space/><link><target>Oracle Corporation</target><part>Oracle</part></link><space/>purchased<space/><link><target>RightNow</target></link><space/>in October 2011<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://techcrunch.com/2011/10/24/oracle-buys-cloud-based-customer-service-company-rightnow-for-1-5-billion/'>Oracle Buys Cloud-based Customer Service Company RightNow For $1.5 Billion</link><space/><italics>Techcrunch</italics>: 24 October 2011</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>SAP AG</target><part>SAP</part></link><space/>acquired<space/><link><target>SuccessFactors</target></link><space/>in December 2011.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.businessweek.com/news/2011-12-07/sap-challenges-oracle-with-3-4-billion-successfactors-purchase.html'>SAP Challenges Oracle With $3.4 Billion SuccessFactors Purchase</link><space/><italics>Bloomberg Businessweek</italics>: 7 December 2011</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The era of the &quot;social customer&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Greenberg<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>CRM at the Speed of Light<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGraw Hill<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>4th<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>7</arg></template></extension><space/>refers to the use of social media (<link><target>Twitter</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Facebook</target></link>,<space/><link><target>LinkedIn</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Google Plus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pinterest</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Instagram</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Yelp, Inc.</target><part>Yelp</part></link>, customer reviews in<space/><link><target>Amazon.com</target><part>Amazon</part></link>, etc.) by customers. CR philosophy and strategy has shifted to encompass social networks and user communities.</paragraph><paragraph>Sales forces also play an important role in CRM, as maximizing<space/><link><target>Sales Effectiveness</target><part>sales effectiveness</part></link><space/>and increasing sales<space/><link><target>productivity</target></link><space/>is a driving force behind the adoption of CRM. Empowering<space/><link><target>Sales management</target><part>sales managers</part></link><space/>was listed as one of the top 5 CRM trends in 2013.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Top 5 CRM Trends for 2013<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.enterpriseappstoday.com/crm/top-5-crm-trends-for-2013.html</arg><arg name="publisher">Enterprise Apps Today<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">7 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Another related development is<space/><link><target>vendor relationship management</target></link><space/>(VRM), which provide tools and services that allow customers to manage their individual relationship with vendors. VRM development has grown out of efforts by ProjectVRM at Harvard's<space/><link><target>Berkman Center for Internet &amp; Society</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Identity Commons</target></link>' Internet Identity Workshops, as well as by a growing number of startups and established companies. VRM was the subject of a cover story in the May 2010 issue of<space/><italics>CRM</italics><space/>Magazine.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.destinationcrm.com/Issue/1776-May-2010.htm'>Destinationcrm.com</link><space/><italics>CRM Magazine</italics>: May, 2010</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2001, Doug Laney from Gartner developed the concept and coined the term 'Extended Relationship Management' (XRM).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://blogs.gartner.com/doug-laney/files/2012/02/ad1074-The-Great-Enterprise-Balancing-Act-Extended-Relationship-Management-XRM.pdf'></link><space/><italics>The Great Enterprise Balancing Act: Extended Relationship Management (XRM)</italics>, Doug Laney, META Group publication, 10 December 2001</extension><space/>Laney defines XRM as extending CRM disciplines to secondary allies such as the government, press and industry consortia.</paragraph><paragraph>Dennison DeGregor (2011) describes a shift from 'push CRM' toward a 'customer transparency' (CT) model, due to the increased proliferation of channels, devices, and social media.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="year"><space/>2011<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Customer-Transparent Enterprise: Beyond 20th Century CRM<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Dennison<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>DeGregor<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Motivational Press<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-935723-23-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Automated online assistant</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Business intelligence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Business relationship management</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Comparison of CRM systems</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Consumer relationship system</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Customer knowledge</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Customer experience</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Customer experience transformation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Customer intelligence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Customer service</target></link><space/>contains<space/><link><target>International Organization for Standardization</target><part>ISO</part></link><space/>standards</listitem><listitem><link><target>Data management</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Data mining</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Database marketing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>E-crm</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Estate Resource Management</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Employee experience management</target></link><space/>(EEM)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Enterprise feedback management</target></link><space/>(EFM)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Event-driven marketing</target></link><space/>(EDM)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Farley file</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Help desk</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Individual resource management</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Partner relationship management (PRM)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Predictive analytics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Professional services automation software</target></link><space/>(PSA)</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Real-time marketing</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sales force management system</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sales intelligence</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sales process engineering</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Support automation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Supplier relationship management</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The International Customer Service Institute</target></link><space/>contains<space/><link><target>customer service</target></link><space/>standards</listitem><listitem><link><target>Vendor relationship management</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>33em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Timothy Bohling, Douglas Bowman, Steve LaValle, Vikas Mittal, Das Naryandas, Girish Ramani, &amp; Rajan Varadarajan. 2006. &quot;CRM Implementation: Effectiveness Issues and Insights&quot; Journal of Service Research, 9(2), November, 184-194.. Available at SSRN: http://ssrn.com/abstract=2343756</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Sub-disciplines of computing</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Customer Relationship Management</target></template><link><target>Category:Customer experience management</target></link><link><target>Category:Customer relationship management software</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:E-commerce</target></link><link><target>Category:Marketing</target></link><link><target>Category:Office and administrative support occupations</target></link></paragraph></article>