<article title='Alcoholics_Anonymous'><paragraph><template><target>pp-move-indef</target><arg name="small">yes</arg></template><link><target>File:Logo AA.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>Alcoholics Anonymous logo</part></link><link><target>Image:Figure alcoholicsanonymous ingolstadt.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part>AA meeting sign</part></link><link><target>File:AA - Medalj.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Sobriety token</target></link><space/>or &quot;chip&quot;, given for specified lengths of sobriety, on the back is<space/><link><target>Serenity Prayer</target></link>. Here green is for six months of sobriety; purple is for nine months.</part></link><bold>Alcoholics Anonymous</bold><space/>(<bold>AA</bold>) is an international<space/><link><target>Social work with groups#Mutual aid</target><part>mutual aid</part></link><space/>fellowship<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.aa.org/assets/en_US/smf-92_en.pdf</extension><space/>founded in 1935 (two years after the end of<space/><link><target>prohibition in the United States</target></link><space/>in December 1933) by<space/><link><target>Bill W.</target><part>Bill Wilson</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bob Smith (doctor)</target><part>Dr. Bob Smith</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Akron, Ohio</target></link>. AA states that its primary purpose is to help alcoholics &quot;to stay sober and help other alcoholics achieve<space/><link><target>sobriety</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">none</arg><arg name="author">Michael Gross,Ph.D</arg><arg name="journal">American Journal of Public Health</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="issue">December 1, 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aa.org/en_pdfs/smf-92_en.pdf'>AA.org</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Mkel 1996, p. 3</extension><space/>With other early members Bill Wilson and Bob Smith developed AA's<space/><link><target>the Twelve Steps</target><part>Twelve Step</part></link><space/>program of spiritual and character development. AA's initial<space/><link><target>Twelve Traditions</target></link><space/>were introduced in 1946 to help the fellowship be stable and unified while disengaged from &quot;outside issues&quot; and influences.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The Traditions recommend that members and groups remain anonymous in public media, altruistically helping other alcoholics and avoiding official affiliations with other organization. The Traditions also recommend that those representing AA avoid dogma and coercive hierarchies. Subsequent fellowships such as<space/><link><target>Narcotics Anonymous</target></link><space/>have adopted and adapted the Twelve Steps and the Twelve Traditions to their respective primary purposes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRADITIONS1949"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">The AA Grapevine<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="date">November 1949<space/></arg><arg name="volume">6<space/></arg><arg name="issue">6<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Twelve Traditions<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0362-2584<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">50379271</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Twelve-Step and Mutual-Help Programs for Addictive Disorders</arg><arg name="journal">Psychiatric Clinics of North America</arg><arg name="volume">22<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/S0193-953X(05)70085-X<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">10385942<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Chappel<space/></arg><arg name="first1">JN<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Dupont<space/></arg><arg name="first2">RL<space/></arg><arg name="pages">425–46</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to AA's 2014 membership survey, 27% of members have been sober less than one year, 24% have 15 years sober, 13% have 510 years, 14% have 1020 years, and 22% have more than 20 years sober.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MembershipSurvey"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous 2014 Membership Survey<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">A.A. World Services<space/></arg><arg name="date">2014<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/assets/en_US/p-48_membershipsurvey.pdf</arg></template></extension><space/>The 2006 Cochrane Review of eight studies measuring the effectiveness of AA found no significant difference between the results of AA and twelve-step participation compared to other treatments, stating that &quot;experimental studies have on the whole failed to demonstrate their effectiveness in reducing alcohol dependence or drinking problems when compared to other interventions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="FERRI2006"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first female member, Florence Rankin, joined AA in March 1937,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Anonymous</arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous</arg><arg name="year">1939</arg><arg name="publisher">Works Publishing Company</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="page">Original Manuscript p. 217</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bamuhigire</arg><arg name="first">Oscar Bamwebaze</arg><arg name="title">Healing power of self love : enhance your chances of recovery from addiction through the..</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="publisher">Iuniverse Inc</arg><arg name="location">[S.l.]</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-44010-137-3</arg><arg name="page">x</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/?id</arg></template></extension><space/>and the first non-Protestant member, a Roman Catholic, joined in 1939.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD52">Kurtz 1991. pp. 52&quot;</extension><space/>AA membership has since spread &quot;across diverse cultures holding different beliefs and values&quot;, including geopolitical areas resistant to<space/><link><target>grassroots</target></link><space/>movements.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TONIGAN2000"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Tonigan<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Scott J<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Connors<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Gerard J<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Miller<space/></arg><arg name="first3">William R</arg><arg name="title">Special Populations in Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="volume">22<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 2000</arg><arg name="pages">281–285<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Alcohol Health and Research World</arg><arg name="url">http://pubs.niaaa.nih.gov/publications/arh22-4/281.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">15706756</arg></template></extension><space/>In the fourth edition of Alcoholics Anonymous (November 2001), it states &quot;Since the third edition was published in 1976, worldwide membership of AA has just about doubled, to an estimated two million or more...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="edition">4th<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/bigbookonline/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">June 8, 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>AA's name is derived from its first book, informally called &quot;The Big Book&quot;, originally titled<space/><italics><link><target>The Big Book (Alcoholics Anonymous)</target><part>Alcoholics Anonymous: The Story of How More Than One Hundred Men Have Recovered From Alcoholism</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Oxford Group origins</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg><space/>History of Alcoholics Anonymous</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>AA sprang from<space/><link><target>The Oxford Group</target></link>, a non-denominational movement modeled after first-century Christianity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Cheever, Susan<space/></arg><arg name="title">My name is Bill: Bill Wilson: his life and the creation of Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Simon & Schuster<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="year">2004<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>129</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7432-0154-X<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Some members found the Group to help in maintaining sobriety. One such &quot;Grouper&quot;, as they were called, was<space/><link><target>Ebby Thacher</target></link>, Wilson's former drinking buddy and his acknowledged sponsor. Following the evangelical bent of the Group, Thacher told Wilson that he had &quot;got religion&quot; and was sober, and that Wilson could do the same if he set aside objections to religion and instead formed a personal idea of God, &quot;another power&quot; or &quot;higher power&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Pass It On, p 117"><italics>Pass It On</italics>, p 117.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOOD"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Kurtz, Ernest<space/></arg><arg name="title">Not-God: a history of Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hazelden Educational Services<space/></arg><arg name="location">Center City, Minn<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-89486-065-8<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Wilson felt with Thacher a &quot;kinship of common suffering&quot; andwhile drunkattended his first Group gathering. Within days, Wilson admitted himself to the<space/><link><target>Charles B. Towns</target><part>Charles B. Towns Hospital</part></link>, but not before drinking four beers on the waythe last time Wilson drank alcohol. Under the care of<space/><link><target>William Duncan Silkworth</target><part>Dr. William Duncan Silkworth</part></link><space/>(an early benefactor of AA), Wilson's detox included the<space/><link><target>deliriant</target></link><space/><link><target>Atropa belladonna</target><part>belladonna</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Pittman, Bill &quot;AA the Way it Began&quot; 1988, Glenn Abbey Books</extension><space/>At the hospital in a state of despair, Wilson experienced a bright flash of light, which he felt to be God revealing himself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD33">Kurtz 1991. pp. 1820</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Following his hospital discharge Wilson joined the Oxford Group and recruited other alcoholics to the Group. Wilson's early efforts to help others become sober were ineffective, prompting Dr. Silkworth to suggest that Wilson place less stress on religion and more on &quot;the science&quot; of treating alcoholism. Wilson's first success came during a business trip to Akron, Ohio, where he was introduced to Dr. Robert Smith, a surgeon and Oxford Group member who was unable to stay sober. After thirty days of working with Wilson, Smith drank his last drink on June 10, 1935, the date marked by AA for its anniversaries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD33"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD16-17">Kurtz 1991. pp. 1617</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While Wilson and Smith credited their sobriety to working with alcoholics under the auspices of the Oxford Group, a Group associate pastor sermonized against Wilson and his alcoholic Groupers for forming a &quot;secret, ashamed sub-group&quot; engaged in &quot;divergent works&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD16-17"></extension><space/>By 1937, Wilson separated from the Oxford Group. AA Historian Ernest Kurtz described the split:<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD45-46">Kurtz 1991. pp. 4546</extension><extension extension_name='blockquote'><italics>...more and more, Bill discovered that new adherents could get sober by believing in each other and in the strength of this group. Men [no women were members yet] who had proven over and over again, by extremely painful experience, that they could not get sober on their own had somehow become more powerful when two or three of them worked on their common problem. This, thenwhatever it was that occurred among themwas what they could accept as a power greater than themselves. They did not need the Oxford Group.</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1955, Wilson acknowledged AA's debt, saying &quot;The Oxford Groupers had clearly shown us what to do. And just as importantly, we learned from them<space/><italics>what not to do.</italics>&quot; Among the Oxford Group practices that AA retained were informal gatherings, a &quot;changed-life&quot; developed through &quot;stages&quot;, and working with others for no material gain, AA's analogs for these are meetings, &quot;the steps&quot;, and sponsorship. AA's tradition of anonymity was a reaction to the publicity-seeking practices of the Oxford Group, as well as AA's wish to not promote, Wilson said, &quot;erratic public characters who through broken anonymity might get drunk and destroy confidence in us.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOTGOD46-48">Kurtz 1991. pp. 468</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>The Big Book, the Twelve Steps and the Twelve Traditions</heading><paragraph>To share their method, Wilson and other members wrote the initially-titled book,<space/><italics>Alcoholics Anonymous: The Story of How More Than One Hundred Men Have Recovered from Alcoholism</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://gsowatch.aamo.info/1939/uslaw.htm'>GSOwatch.aamo.info</link></extension><space/>from which AA drew its name. Informally known as &quot;The Big Book&quot; (with its first 164 pages virtually unchanged since the 1939 edition), it suggests a twelve-step program in which members admit that they are powerless over alcohol and need help from a &quot;higher power&quot;. They seek guidance and strength through prayer and meditation from God or a<space/><link><target>Higher Power</target></link><space/>of their own understanding; take a moral inventory with care to include resentments; list and become ready to remove character defects; list and make amends to those harmed; continue to take a moral inventory, pray, meditate, and try to help other alcoholics recover. The second half of the book, &quot;Personal Stories&quot; (subject to additions, removal and retitling in subsequent editions), is made of AA members' redemptive autobiographical sketches.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1941, interviews on American radio and favorable articles in US magazines, including a piece by Jack Alexander in<space/><italics><link><target>The Saturday Evening Post</target></link></italics>, led to increased book sales and membership.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-12_theJackAlexArticle1.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 March 1941<space/></arg><arg name="author">Jack Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Saturday Eventing Post<space/></arg><arg name="edition">Reprinted in booklet form<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyRPXTQK<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-89638-199-4</arg></template></extension><space/>By 1946, as the growing fellowship quarreled over structure, purpose, and authority, as well as finances and publicity, Wilson began to form and promote what became known as AA's &quot;Twelve Traditions,&quot; which are guidelines for an altruistic, unaffiliated, non-coercive, and non-hierarchical structure that limited AA's purpose to only helping alcoholics on a non-professional level while shunning publicity. Eventually he gained formal adoption and inclusion of the Twelve Traditions in all future editions of the Big Book.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRADITIONS1949"></extension><space/>At the 1955 conference in St. Louis, Missouri, Wilson relinquished stewardship of AA to the General Service Conference,<extension extension_name='ref'>Pass It On 1984, p. 359</extension><space/>as AA grew to millions of members internationally.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAFACTFILE"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Organization and finances</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Twelve Traditions<space/></arg></template><link><target>File:Alcoholics Anonymous Regional Service Center by David Shankbone.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A regional service center for Alcoholics Anonymous</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>AA says it is &quot;not organized in the formal or political sense&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAFACTFILE"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">AA Fact File</arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/m-24_aafactfile.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">General Service Office of Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and Bill Wilson called it a &quot;benign anarchy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>AA Comes Of Age, p. 225</extension><space/>In Ireland, Shane Butler said that AA looks like it couldnt survive as theres no leadership or top-level telling local<space/><link><target>cumann</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>what to do, but it has worked and proved itself extremely robust. Butler explained that &quot;AAs 'inverted pyramid' style of governance has helped it to avoid many of the pitfalls that political and religious institutions have encountered since it was established here in 1946.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first">Steven<space/></arg><arg name="last">Carroll<space/></arg><arg name="title">Group avoids politics of alcohol – author<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2010-03-03</arg><arg name="publisher">http://www.irishtimes.com/<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/ireland/2010/0326/1224267100034.html<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2010-03-30<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2006, AA counted 1,867,212 members and 106,202 AA groups worldwide.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAFACTFILE"></extension><space/>The Twelve Traditions informally guide how individual AA groups function, and the Twelve Concepts for World Service guide how the organization is structured globally.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The A.A. Service Manual Combined with Twelve Concepts for World Services<space/></arg><arg name="last">Wilson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Bill<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Bill W.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/en_bm-31.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyPpMKt9</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A member who accepts a service position or an organizing role is a &quot;trusted servant&quot; with terms rotating and limited, typically lasting three months to two years and determined by group vote and the nature of the position. Each group is a self-governing entity with AA World Services acting only in an advisory capacity. AA is served entirely by alcoholics, except for seven &quot;nonalcoholic friends of the fellowship&quot; of the 21-member AA Board of Trustees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAFACTFILE"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>AA groups are self-supporting, relying on voluntary donations from members to cover expenses.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAFACTFILE"></extension><space/>The AA General Service Office (GSO) limits contributions to US$3,000 a year.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">A.A. GSO Guidelines: Finances<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/lang/en/en_pdfs/mg-15_finance.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyQ0kRis<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous General Service Office</arg></template></extension><space/>Above the group level, AA may hire outside professionals for services that require specialized expertise or full-time responsibilities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRADITIONS1949"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>AA receives proceeds from books and literature that constitute more than 50% of the income for its General Service Office.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GSO2005OPS"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pics_gen/en_gso07_operresults.jpg<space/></arg><arg name="title">GSO 2007 Operating Results<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Gross Profit from Literature ~8,6M (57%), Contributions ~$6.5M (43%)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous General Services Office<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyQeumnF</arg></template></extension><space/>Unlike individual groups, the GSO is not self-supporting and maintains a small salaried staff. It also maintains service centers, which coordinate activities such as printing literature, responding to public inquiries, and organizing conferences. They are funded by local members and are responsible to the AA groups they represent. Other International General Service Offices (Australia, Costa Rica, Russia, etc.) are independent of AA World Services in New York.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/lang/en/aa_international.cfm?origpage</arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous : International General Service Offices<space/></arg><arg name="work">Alcoholics Anonymous website<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-10-08<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyQO0oho</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Program</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Twelve-step program#Twelve Steps</arg><arg name="l1">Twelve-step program: The Twelve Steps</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The scope of AA's program is much broader than just abstinence from drinking alcohol.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HUMPHREYS1995"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Humphreys<space/></arg><arg name="first">Keith<space/></arg><arg name="title">World Views of Alcoholics Anonymous, Women for Sobriety, and Adult Children of Alcoholics/Al-Anon Mutual Help Groups<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Addiction Research & Theory<space/></arg><arg name="volume">3<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">231–243<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.3109/16066359509005240<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Kaskutas<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Lee Ann</arg></template></extension><space/>Its goal is to effect enough change in the alcoholic's thinking &quot;to bring about recovery from alcoholism&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Bill W. 2002, Appendix II</extension><space/>through a spiritual awakening. A spiritual awakening is meant to be achieved by taking the<space/><link><target>Twelve Steps</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="THISISAA"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">This is AA<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-1_thisisaa1.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous Work Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="year">1984<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyMzy9h6</arg></template></extension><space/>and sobriety is furthered by volunteering for AA<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-15_Q&amp;amp;AonSpon.pdf'>AA.org</link></extension><space/>and regular AA meeting attendance<extension extension_name='ref' name="NEWCOMER"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">A Newcomer Asks..<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="year">1980<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-24_anewcomerask.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyKg9w25<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12</arg></template></extension><space/>or contact with AA members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="THISISAA"></extension><space/>Members are encouraged to find an experienced fellow alcoholic, called a sponsor, to help them understand and follow the AA program. The sponsor should preferably have experience of all twelve of the steps, be the same sex as the sponsored person, and refrain from imposing personal views on the sponsored person.<extension extension_name='ref'>Questions and Answers on Sponsorship 2005 http://aa.org/pdf/products/p-15_Q&amp;AonSpon.pdf</extension><space/>Following the<space/><link><target>Helper theory</target><part>helper therapy principle</part></link>, sponsors in AA may benefit from their relationship with their charges, as &quot;helping behaviors&quot; correlate with increased abstinence and lower probabilities of binge drinking.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ZEMORE2004"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Zemore, S. E., Kaskutas, L. A., & Ammon, L. N.<space/></arg><arg name="date">August 2004<space/></arg><arg name="title">In 12-step groups, helping helps the helper<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Addiction<space/></arg><arg name="volume">99<space/></arg><arg name="issue">8<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1015–1023<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1360-0443.2004.00782.x<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">15265098</arg><arg name="last2">Kaskutas<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Ammon<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>AA's program is an inheritor of<space/><link><target>Counter-Enlightenment</target></link><space/>philosophy. AA shares the view that acceptance of one's inherent limitations is critical to finding one's proper place among other humans and God. Such ideas are described as &quot;Counter-Enlightenment&quot; because they are contrary to the<space/><link><target>Age of Enlightenment</target><part>Enlightenment</part></link>'s ideal that humans have the capacity to make their lives and societies a heaven on earth using their own power and reason.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HUMPHREYS1995"></extension><space/>After evaluating AA's literature and observing AA meetings for sixteen months, sociologists David R. Rudy and Arthur L. Greil found that for an AA member to remain sober a high level of commitment is necessary. This commitment is facilitated by a change in the member's<space/><link><target>world view</target><part>worldview</part></link>. To help members stay sober AA must, they argue, provide an all-encompassing worldview while creating and sustaining an atmosphere of transcendence in the organization. To be all-encompassing AA's ideology places an emphasis on tolerance rather than on a narrow religious worldview that could make the organization unpalatable to potential members and thereby limit its effectiveness. AA's emphasis on the spiritual nature of its program, however, is necessary to institutionalize a feeling of transcendence. A tension results from the risk that the necessity of transcendence, if taken too literally, would compromise AA's efforts to maintain a broad appeal. As this tension is an integral part of AA, Rudy and Greil argue that AA is best described as a<space/><italics>quasi-religious organization</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RUDY1989"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Rudy<space/></arg><arg name="first1">David R.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Greil<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Arthur L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Is Alcoholics Anonymous a Religious Organization?: Meditations on Marginality<space/></arg><arg name="volume">50<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="year">1989<space/></arg><arg name="pages">41–51<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3710917<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">3710917<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Sociological Analysis</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Meetings</heading><paragraph>AA meetings are &quot;quasi-ritualized therapeutic sessions run by and for, alcoholics&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Dimensions of Alcoholics Anonymous: 1935–1965</arg><arg name="journal">Substance Use & Misuse<space/></arg><arg name="volume">4<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="page">509<space/></arg><arg name="year">1969<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.3109/10826086909062033<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Leach<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Barry<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Norris<space/></arg><arg name="first2">John L.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Dancey<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Travis<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Bissell<space/></arg><arg name="first4">Leclair</arg></template></extension><space/>They are usually informal and often feature discussions. Local AA directories list a variety of weekly meetings. Those listed as &quot;closed&quot; are only for those with &quot;a desire to stop drinking&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRADITIONS1949"></extension><space/>while &quot;open&quot; meetings are available to anyone (nonalcoholics can attend as observers).<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAgroup"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The A.A. Group</arg><arg name="year">1990</arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc.</arg><arg name="page">13</arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-16_theaagroup.pdf</arg></template></extension><space/>At speaker meetings, one or two members tell their stories, while discussion meetings allocate the most time for general discussion. Some meetings are devoted to studying and discussing the AA literature.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Except for men's and women's meetings, and meetings targeting specific demographics (including newcomers,<space/><link><target>gay</target></link><space/>people, and young people), AA meetings do not exclude other alcoholics. While AA has pamphlets that suggest meeting formats,<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAGROUP"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The A.A. Group<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-16_theaagroup.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyO4jmjL</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BEGINNERS"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Suggestions For Leading Beginners Meetings<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/en_pdfs/mu-1_begmeetings.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyOIcOwB</arg></template></extension><space/>groups have the autonomy to hold and conduct meetings as they wish &quot;except in matters affecting other groups or AA as a whole&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TRADITIONS1949"></extension><space/>Different cultures affect ritual aspects of meetings, but around the world &quot;many particularities of the AA meeting format can be observed at almost any AA gathering&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mkel 1996, p. 149150</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Confidentiality</heading><preblock><preline>US courts have not extended the status of privileged communication, such as that enjoyed by clergy and lawyers, to AA related communications between members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="COLEMAN2005"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Coleman<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Phyllis<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Privilege and Confidentiality in 12-Step Self-Help Programs: Believing The Promises Could Be Hazardous to an Addict's Freedom<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>The Journal of Legal Medicine<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>26<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>435–474<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1080/01947640500364713<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0194-7648<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>4997813<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>16303734</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="HOFFMAN1994"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Hoffman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jan<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 June 1994<space/></arg><arg name="title">Faith in Confidentiality of Therapy Is Shaken<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1994/06/15/nyregion/faith-in-confidentiality-of-therapy-is-shaken.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-10-23</arg></template></extension></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Spirituality</heading><paragraph>A study found an association between an increase in attendance to AA meetings with increased spirituality and a decrease in the frequency and intensity of alcohol use. The research also found that AA was effective at helping agnostics and atheists become sober. The authors concluded that though spirituality was an important mechanism of behavioral change for some alcoholics, it was not the only effective mechanism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, John F. et al. Spirituality in Recovery: A Lagged Mediational Analysis of Alcoholics Anonymous Principal Theoretical Mechanism of Behavior Change Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research Vol. 35, No. 3 March 2011 pp.&amp;nbsp;110</extension><space/>Since the mid-1970s, a number of 'agnostic' or 'no-prayer' AA groups have begun across the U.S., Canada, and other parts of the world, which hold meetings that adhere to a tradition allowing alcoholics to freely express their doubts or disbelief that spirituality will help their recovery, and forgo use of opening or closing prayers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HNN2011"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">C.<space/></arg><arg name="first">Roger<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Humanist Network News<space/></arg><arg name="date">Nov 2011<space/></arg><arg name="title">A History of Agnsotic Groups in Alcoholics Anonymous: Part 1<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://americanhumanist.org/HNN/details/2011-11-a-history-of-agnostic-groups-in-alcoholics-anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-12</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="NYT2014"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Freedman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Samuel<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">Feb 21, 2014<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous, Without the Religion<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2014/02/22/us/alcoholics-anonymous-without-the-religion.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-26</arg></template></extension><space/>There are online resources listing AA meetings for atheists and agnostics.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.agnosticaanyc.org/worldwide.html for example is a directory of agnostic AA meetings</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Disease concept of alcoholism</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Disease theory of alcoholism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>More informally than not, AA's membership has helped popularize the disease concept of alcoholism, though AA officially has had no part in the development of such postulates which had appeared as early as the late eighteenth century.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Benjamin</arg><arg name="last">Rush</arg><arg name="title">Inquiry into the Effects of Ardent Spirits upon the Human Body and Mind</arg><arg name="publisher">Bartam</arg><arg name="location">Philadelphia</arg><arg name="year">1805</arg></template></extension><space/>Though AA initially avoided the term &quot;disease&quot;, in 1973 conference-approved literature categorically stated that &quot;we had the disease of alcoholism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-3_isaaforyou.pdf'>AA.org</link></extension><space/>Regardless of official positions, from AA's inception most members have believed alcoholism to be a disease.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bhrm.org"><link type='external' href='http://www.bhrm.org/papers/AAand%20DiseaseConcept.pdf'>BHRM.org</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Though cautious regarding the medical nature of alcoholism, AA has let others voice opinions. The Big Book states that alcoholism &quot;is an illness which only a spiritual experience will conquer.&quot; Ernest Kurtz says this is &quot;The closest the book Alcoholics Anonymous comes to a definition of alcoholism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="bhrm.org"></extension><space/>In his introduction to The Big Book, non-member<space/><link><target>William Duncan Silkworth</target><part>Dr. William Silkworth</part></link><space/>said those unable to moderate their drinking have an allergy. Addressing the allergy concept, AA said &quot;The doctors theory that we have an allergy to alcohol interests us. As laymen, our opinion as to its soundness may, of course, mean little.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Alcoholics Anonymous page xxx"><italics>Alcoholics Anonymous</italics><space/>page xxx</extension><space/>AA later acknowledged that &quot;alcoholism is not a true allergy, the experts now inform us.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Living Sober</italics><space/>p 68</extension><space/>Wilson explained in 1960 why AA had refrained from using the term &quot;disease&quot;:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>We AAs have never called alcoholism a disease because, technically speaking, it is not a disease entity. For example, there is no such thing as heart disease. Instead there are many separate heart ailments or combinations of them. It is something like that with alcoholism. Therefore, we did not wish to get in wrong with the medical profession by pronouncing alcoholism a disease entity. Hence, we have always called it an illness or a maladya far safer term for us to use.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gately<space/></arg><arg name="first">Iain<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008<space/></arg><arg name="title">Drink: A Cultural History of Alcohol<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penguin Group<space/></arg><arg name="page">417<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9781592403035</arg></template></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Canadian and United States demographics</heading><paragraph>AA's New York General Service Office regularly surveys AA members in North America. Its 2014 survey of over 6,000 members in Canada and the United States concluded that, in North America, AA members who responded to the survey were 62% male and 38% female. Average member sobriety is slightly under 10 years with 36% sober more than ten years, 13% sober from five to ten years, 24% sober from one to five years, and 27% sober less than one year.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MembershipSurvey"></extension><space/>Before coming to AA, 63% of members received some type of treatment or counseling, such as medical, psychological, or spiritual. After coming to AA, 59% received outside treatment or counseling. Of those members, 84% said that outside help played an important part in their recovery. The same survey showed that AA received 12% of its membership from courtordered attendance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MembershipSurvey"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Effectiveness</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Effectiveness of Alcoholics Anonymous</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Research limitations</heading><paragraph>AA tends to polarize observers into believers and non-believers,<extension extension_name='ref'>Vaillant, 1995, p 255.</extension><space/>and discussion of AA often creates controversy rather than objective reflection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Vaillant, 1995, p 265.</extension><space/>Moreover, a randomized study of AA is difficult: AA members are not randomly selected from the population of chronic alcoholics; they are instead self-selected or mandated by courts to attend AA meetings.<extension extension_name='ref'>Griffith 2002, p. 103117</extension><space/>There are two opposing types of self-selection bias: (1) drinkers may be motivated to stop drinking before they participate in AA; (2) AA may attract the more severe and difficult cases.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HUMPHREYS2002"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Humphreys<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Keith<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Recent Developments in Alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous and 12-Step Alcoholism Treatment Programs<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>16<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Springer US<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1007/b100495<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>149–164<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>12638636<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-306-47258-9<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Recent Developments in Alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Galanter<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Marc<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Begleiter<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Henri<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-last"><space/>Deitrich<space/></arg><arg name="editor3-first"><space/>Richard<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-last"><space/>Gallant<space/></arg><arg name="editor4-first"><space/>Donald</arg><arg name="displayeditors">4</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Scientific control</target><part>Controlled experiments</part></link><space/>with AA versus non-AA subjects are also difficult because AA is so easily accessible. Twelve-step groups like AA are not conducive to<space/><link><target>Sampling (statistics)#Probability and nonprobability sampling</target><part>probability sampling</part></link><space/>of members. Research on AA is therefore susceptible to<space/><link><target>sampling bias</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LEVY1979"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Self-Help Groups for Coping with Crisis<space/></arg><arg name="editors">Morton A. Lieberman; Leonard D. Borman<space/></arg><arg name="location">San Francisco<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Josey-Bass Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="year">1979<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Processes and Activities in Groups<space/></arg><arg name="pages">234–271<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Levy<space/></arg><arg name="first">Leon<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-87589-435-6<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">5491383</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Studies</heading><paragraph>Studies of AA's efficacy have produced inconsistent results. While some studies have suggested an association between AA attendance and increased abstinence or other positive outcomes,<extension extension_name='ref' name="PMC4285560"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Humphreys, Blodgett, Wagner<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Estimating the efficacy of Alcoholics Anonymous without self-selection bias: an instrumental variables re-analysis of randomized clinical trials<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/acer.12557<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>25421504</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="PMC2802221"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Walitzer, Dermen, Barrick<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Facilitating involvement in Alcoholics Anonymous during out-patient treatment: a randomized clinical trial.<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Addiction<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>19207347</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="PMC2661035"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Changing network support for drinking: network support project 2-year follow-up.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Litt, Kadden, Kabela-Cormier, Petry<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>J Consult Clin Psychol.<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1037/a0015252<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>19309183</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="MOOS2006A"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moos<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rudolf H.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Participation in Treatment and Alcoholics Anonymous: A 16-Year Follow-Up of Initially Untreated Individuals<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Clinical Psychology<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 2006<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>735–750<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1002/jclp.20259<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">16538654<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>62<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Moos<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>BS<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>6<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>2220012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="MOOS2006B"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Moos<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Rudolf H.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Rates and predictors of relapse after natural and treated remission from alcohol use disorders<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Addiction<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>101<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>212–222<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 2006<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1360-0443.2006.01310.x<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>16445550<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Moos<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>BS<space/></arg><arg name="pmc"><space/>1976118</arg></template></extension><space/>other studies have not.<extension extension_name='ref' name="STAHLBRANDT2007"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Two-Year Outcome of Alcohol Interventions in Swedish University Halls of Residence: A [[Cluster randomized trial|Cluster Randomized Trial]] of a Brief Skills Training Program, Twelve-Step Influenced Intervention, and Controls<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1530-0277.2006.00327.x<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Ståhlbrandt<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Henriettæ<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Johnsson<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Kent O.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Berglund<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Mats<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research<space/></arg><arg name="volume">31<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">17295731<space/></arg><arg name="issue">3<space/></arg><arg name="pages">458–66</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="TERRA2008"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Do Alcoholics Anonymous Groups Really Work? Factors of Adherence in a Brazilian Sample of Hospitalized Alcohol Dependents<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/10550490701756393<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Terra<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Mauro Barbosa<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Barros<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Helena Maria Tannhauser<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Stein<space/></arg><arg name="first3">Airton Tetelbom<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Figueira<space/></arg><arg name="first4">Ivan<space/></arg><arg name="last5">Palermo<space/></arg><arg name="first5">Luiz Henrique<space/></arg><arg name="last6">Athayde<space/></arg><arg name="first6">Luciana Dias<space/></arg><arg name="last7">Gonçalves<space/></arg><arg name="first7">Marcelo de Souza<space/></arg><arg name="last8">Da Silveira<space/></arg><arg name="first8">Dartiu Xavier<space/></arg><arg name="journal">American Journal on Addictions<space/></arg><arg name="volume">17<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">18214722<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">48–53</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 2006 Cochrane Review of eight studies (the studies reviewed were done between 1967 and 2005) measuring the effectiveness of AA found no significant difference between the results of AA and twelve-step participation compared to other treatments, stating that &quot;experimental studies have on the whole failed to demonstrate their effectiveness in reducing alcohol dependence or drinking problems when compared to other interventions.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="FERRI2006"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ferri<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>MMF<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous and other 12-step programmes for alcohol dependence<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Cochrane Database of Systematic Reviews<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.mrw.interscience.wiley.com/cochrane/clsysrev/articles/CD005032/frame.html<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1002/14651858.CD005032.pub2<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Amato<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Laura<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Davoli<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>Marina<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Ferri<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>Marica<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>16856072<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>CD005032<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Ferri<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Marica</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Retention</heading><paragraph>Every third year since 1968, AA has issued a pamphlet summarizing its latest<space/><link><target>wiktionary:triennial</target><part>triennial</part></link><space/>survey of meeting attendants. Additional published comments and analysis for academics and professionals have supplemented the survey results from 1970 through 1990.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MCINTIRE2000"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">McIntire<space/></arg><arg name="first">Don<space/></arg><arg name="title">How Well Does A.A. Work? An Analysis of Published AA Surveys (1968–1996) and Related Analyses/Comments<space/></arg><arg name="volume">18<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 2000<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1–18<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Alcoholism Treatment Quarterly]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1300/J020v18n04_01</arg></template></extension><space/>The 1990 commentary evaluated data of triennial surveys from 1977 through 1989 and found that after the first year, the rate of attrition slows. Only those in the first year were recorded by month. The survey states that the data &quot;strongly suggests that about half those who come to A.A. are gone within three months.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAInternalSurvey"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sobriety of members</heading><paragraph>Internal AA surveys suggest that about 40% of the members sober for less than a year will remain another year. About 80% of those sober more than one year, but less than five years will remain sober and active in the fellowship another year. About 90% of the members sober five years or more will remain sober and active in the fellowship another year. Those who remained sober outside the fellowship could not be calculated using the survey results.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AAInternalSurvey"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Comments On A.A. Triennial Surveys<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.scribd.com/doc/3264243/Comments-on-AAs-Triennial-Surveys<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 1990<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Health-care costs</heading><paragraph>As a volunteer-supported program, AA is free of charge. This contrasts with treatments for alcoholism such as inpatient treatment, drug therapy, psychotherapy, and cognitive-based therapy. One study found that the institutional use of twelve-step-facilitation therapy to encourage participation in AA reduced healthcare expenditures by 45% when compared to another group that was not encouraged to participate in AA.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HUMPHREYS2001"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Humphreys<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Keith<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2001<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Can encouraging substance abuse patients to participate in self-help groups reduce demand for health care? A quasi-experimental study<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Alcoholism: Clinical and Experimental Research<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>25<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>5<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>711–716<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1111/j.1530-0277.2001.tb02271.x<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>11371720<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>1530-0277<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Moos<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>R</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Relationship with institutions</heading><heading level='3'>Hospitals</heading><paragraph>Many AA meetings take place in treatment facilities. Carrying the message of AA into hospitals was how the co-founders of AA first remained sober. They discovered great value of working with alcoholics who are still suffering, and that even if the alcoholic they were working with did not stay sober, they did.<extension extension_name='ref' name="cheever"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Cheever</arg><arg name="first">Susan</arg><arg name="title">Bill W.: The Healer</arg><arg name="journal">Time Magazine</arg><arg name="date">June 14, 1999</arg><arg name="page">201</arg><arg name="url">http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,991266,00.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 June 2013</arg><arg name="quote">by helping another alcoholic, he could save himself</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="dickb"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">B.<space/></arg><arg name="first">Dick<space/></arg><arg name="title">Turning Point: A History of Early A.A.'s Spiritual Roots and Successes</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">Good Book Publishing Company</arg><arg name="isbn">9781885803078</arg><arg name="page">110</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="edition">Volume 10</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 June 2013</arg><arg name="chapter">Turning point</arg><arg name="quote">Bill went back to Towns constantly to work on alcoholics there, simply trying to help others had kept him from even thinking of drinking</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="lois"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Lois</arg><arg name="title">Lois remembers: memoirs of the co-founder of Al-Anon and wife of the co-founder of Alcoholics Anonymous</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg><arg name="publisher">Al-Anon Family Group Headquarters</arg><arg name="isbn">9780910034234</arg><arg name="page">95</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="edition">illustrated, reprint</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 June 2013</arg><arg name="quote">simply trying to help other had kept him from even thinking of drinking</arg></template></extension><space/>Bill Wilson wrote, &quot;Practical experience shows that nothing will so much insure immunity from drinking as intensive work with other alcoholics&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="year">1976<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="edition">3rd<space/></arg><arg name="page">89</arg></template></extension><space/>Bill Wilson visited Towns Hospital in New York City in an attempt to help the alcoholics who were patients there in 1934. At<space/><link><target>St. Thomas Hospital (Akron, Ohio)</target><part>St. Thomas Hospital</part></link><space/>in Akron, Ohio, Smith worked with still more alcoholics. In 1939, a New York mental institution, Rockland State Hospital, was one of the first institutions to allow AA hospital groups. Service to corrections and treatment facilities used to be combined until the General Service Conference, in 1977, voted to dissolve its Institutions Committee and form two separate committees, one for treatment facilities, and one for correctional facilities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://area62.org/committees/treatment.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Treatment Committee<space/></arg><arg name="author"></arg><arg name="work">http://area62.org/<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Area 62<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">9 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Prisons</heading><paragraph>In the United States and Canada, AA meetings are held in hundreds of correctional facilities. The AA General Service Office has published a workbook with detailed recommendations for methods of approaching correctional-facility officials with the intent of developing an in-prison AA program.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CORRECTIONS1"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Corrections Workbook<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous Word Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York, NY<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/m-45i_corrections.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyFWmoKq</arg></template></extension><space/>In addition, AA publishes a variety of pamphlets specifically for the incarcerated alcoholic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CORRECTIONS2"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Corrections Catalog<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/subpage.cfm?page</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyFe00Dd<space/></arg><arg name="quote">The titles include: ''Carrying the Message into Correctional Facilities, Where Do I Go From Here?, A.A. in Prison: Inmate to Inmate, A.A. in Correctional Facilities, It Sure Beats Sitting in a Cell, Memo to an Inmate Who May be an Alcoholic, A Message to Corrections Administrators''</arg></template></extension><space/>Additionally, the AA General Service Office provides a pamphlet with guidelines for members working with incarcerated alcoholics.<extension extension_name='ref' name="GUIDELINES"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">AA Guidelines from GSO: Cooperating with Court, DWI and Similar Programs<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/en_pdfs/mg-05_coopwithcourt.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyFnXpLK<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United States Court rulings</heading><paragraph>United States courts have ruled that inmates, parolees, and probationers cannot be ordered to attend AA. Though AA itself was not deemed a religion, it was ruled that it contained<space/><italics>enough</italics><space/>religious components (variously described in<space/><italics>Griffin v. Coughlin</italics><space/>below as, inter alia, &quot;religion&quot;, &quot;religious activity&quot;, &quot;religious exercise&quot;) to make coerced attendance at AA meetings a violation of the<space/><link><target>Establishment Clause</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>First Amendment to the United States Constitution</target><part>First Amendment</part></link><space/>of the constitution.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NYCTAP"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.law.cornell.edu/nyctap/I96_0137.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">IN THE MATTER OF DAVID GRIFFIN, APPELLANT, v. THOMAS A. COUGHLIN III, AS COMMISSIONER OF THE NEW YORK STATE DEPARTMENT OF CORRECTIONAL SERVICES, ET AL., RESPONDENTS.<space/></arg><arg name="author">LII Editorial Board<space/></arg><arg name="date">June 11, 1996<space/></arg><arg name="work">http://www.law.cornell.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 June 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="HONEYMAR1997"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="doi">10.2307/1123367<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous As a Condition of Drunk Driving Probation: When Does It Amount to Establishment of Religion<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Columbia Law Review<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="volume">97<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="author">Honeymar,<space/></arg><arg name="jstor">1123367<space/></arg><arg name="pages">437–472</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2007, the<space/><link><target>United States Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit</target><part>Ninth Circuit of the U.S. Court of Appeals</part></link><space/>stated that a parolee who was ordered to attend AA had standing to sue his parole office.<extension extension_name='ref' name="EGELKO2007"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last"><space/>Egelko<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bob<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Appeals court says requirement to attend AA unconstitutional<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>8 September 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2007-10-08<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyGIFiqE<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>San Francisco Chronicle<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Inouye-v-Kemna"><template><target>cite court</target><arg name="litigants">Inouye v. Kemna<space/></arg><arg name="vol">504<space/></arg><arg name="reporter">F.3d<space/></arg><arg name="opinion">705<space/></arg><arg name="pinpoint">714<space/><abbr title</arg><arg name="court">9th Cir.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ca9.uscourts.gov/datastore/opinions/2007/09/07/0615474.pdf#page</arg><arg name="quote">[T]he AA/[[Narcotics Anonymous|NA]] program involved here has such substantial religious components that governmentally compelled participation in it violated the [[Establishment Clause]].</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>American treatment industry</heading><paragraph>In 1949, the<space/><link><target>Hazelden</target></link><space/>treatment center was founded and staffed by AA members, and since then many alcoholic rehabilitation clinics have incorporated AA's precepts into their treatment programs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robertson1988"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Robertson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nan<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Nan C. Robertson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Getting Better: Inside Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Morrow<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-688-06869-1<space/></arg><arg name="page">220<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">17260252<space/></arg><arg name="ol">4127115W<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">87031153</arg></template></extension><space/>32% of AA's membership was introduced to it through a treatment facility.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MembershipSurvey"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom treatment industry</heading><paragraph>A cross-sectional survey of substance-misuse treatment providers in the West Midlands found fewer than 10% integrated twelve-step methods in their practice and only a third felt their consumers were suited for Alcoholics Anonymous or Narcotics Anonymous membership. Less than half were likely to recommend self-help groups to their clients. Providers with nursing qualifications were more likely to make such referrals than those without them. A statistically significant correlation was found between providers' self-reported level of spirituality and their likelihood of recommending AA or NA.<extension extension_name='ref' name="DAY2005"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="date">December 2005<space/></arg><arg name="title">United Kingdom substance misuse treatment workers' attitudes toward 12-step self-help groups<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Substance Abuse Treatment<space/></arg><arg name="volume">29<space/></arg><arg name="issue">4<space/></arg><arg name="pages">321–327<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.jsat.2005.08.009<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">16311185<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Day<space/></arg><arg name="first1">E<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Gaston<space/></arg><arg name="first2">RL<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Furlong<space/></arg><arg name="first3">E<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Murali<space/></arg><arg name="first4">V<space/></arg><arg name="last5">Copello<space/></arg><arg name="first5">A</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Twelve-step program#Criticism</arg><arg name="l1">Twelve-step program: Criticism</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Moderation or abstinence</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Alcoholism#Management</arg><arg name="l1">Alcoholism: Management</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Stanton Peele</target></link><space/>argued that some AA groups apply the<space/><link><target>Disease model of addiction</target><part>disease model</part></link><space/>to all problem drinkers, whether or not they are &quot;full-blown&quot; alcoholics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peele 1989</extension><space/>Along with Nancy Shute, Peele has advocated that besides AA, other options should be available to problem drinkers who can manage their drinking with the right treatment.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SHUTE1997"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shute<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Nancy<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The drinking dilemma: by calling abstinence the only cure, we ensure that the nation's $100 billion alcohol problem won't be solved<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[U.S. News & World Report]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>123<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>9<space/></arg><arg name="date">September 1997<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>54–64<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://silkworth.net/magazine_newspaper/us_news_world_report_sep_8_1997.html</arg></template></extension><space/>The Big Book, however, acknowledges &quot;moderate drinkers&quot; and &quot;a certain type of hard drinker&quot; are able to stop or moderate their drinking. The Big Book suggests no program for these drinkers, but instead seeks to help drinkers without &quot;power of choice in drink.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Alcoholics Anonymous</italics><space/>page 20-1,24</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Cultural identity</heading><paragraph>One review of AA warned of detrimental<space/><link><target>iatrogenesis</target><part>iatrogenic</part></link><space/>effects of twelve-step philosophy and concluded that AA uses many methods that are also used by cults.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ALEXANDER1984"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Alexander<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Francesa<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Michele<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Rollins<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous: the unseen cult<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>California Sociologist<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>17<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>33–48<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0162-8712<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>4025459<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Los Angeles<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[California State University]]<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.silkworth.net/sociology/Soc63OCR.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5lyBcw4EM<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-12<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-12</arg></template></extension><space/>A subsequent study concluded, however, that AA's program bore little resemblance to religious cults because the techniques used appeared beneficial.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WRIGHT1997"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Shared Ideology in Alcoholics Anonymous: A Grounded Theory Approach<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/108107397127806<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Right<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Kevin B. W<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of Health Communication<space/></arg><arg name="volume">2<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">10977242<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="pages">83–99</arg></template></extension><space/>Another study found that the AA program's focus on admission of having a problem increases deviant<space/><link><target>Stigma (sociological theory)</target><part>stigma</part></link><space/>and strips members of their previous<space/><link><target>cultural identity</target></link>, replacing it with the deviant identity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LEVINSON1983"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Levinson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Recent Developments in Alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Current status of the field: An anthropological perspective on the behavior modification treatment of alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>255–261<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Plenum Press<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="editor"><space/>Galanter, Marc<space/></arg><arg name="issn"><space/>0738-422X<space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/>6680227<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/978-1-4613-3617-4_14</arg></template></extension><space/>A survey of group members, however, found they had a<space/><link><target>Biculturalism</target><part>bicultural</part></link><space/>identity and saw AA's program as a complement to their other national, ethnic, and religious cultures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wilcox 1998, p. 109124</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Other criticisms</heading><preblock><preline>*&quot;Thirteenth-stepping&quot; is a pejorative term for AA members approaching new members for dates or sex. The<space/><italics>Journal of Addiction Nursing</italics><space/>reported that 50% of the women that participated in a survey (55 in all) experienced 13-stepping behavior from others.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">McGuiness</arg><arg name="first">Kristen</arg><arg name="title">The 13th Step: People Who Prey On Newcomers</arg><arg name="date">15 April 2011</arg><arg name="url">http://www.thefix.com/content/13th-step</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="BOGART2003"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">Journal of Addictions Nursing: A Journal for the Prevention and Management of Addictions<space/></arg><arg name="title">'13th-Stepping:' Why Alcoholics Anonymous Is Not Always a Safe Place for Women<space/></arg><arg name="last">Bogart<space/></arg><arg name="first">Cathy J.<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="volume">14<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">43–47<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1080/10884600305373<space/></arg><arg name="issn">1548-7148<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">34618968<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Bogart<space/></arg><arg name="first2">Cathy J.</arg></template></extension><space/>AA's pamphlet on sponsorship suggests that men be sponsored by men and women be sponsored by women.<extension extension_name='ref'>Questions and Answers on Sponsorship, page 10. 2005.</extension></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1964, Arthur H. Cain by his own count had attended over 500 AA meetings since 1947. Cain insisted that &quot;I do not suggest for a moment that a single A.A. quit the fellowship. On the contrary, I strongly urge sticking with it. To anyone who is having trouble with alcohol I say: try A.A. first; it's the answer for most people&quot;. Even so Cain thought that AA had become the domain of irreligious misfits &quot;Dogmatic and opinionated in their nonbeliefs&quot;, who scorned other societies such as<space/><link><target>Kiwanis</target><part>the Kiwanis Club</part></link>. Cain said AA had come to rely heavily on dogmatic slogans and the group. Without referencing or fashioning a definition of the term, Cain called AA a &quot;cult&quot; and &quot;a hindrance to research, psychiatry, and to many alcoholics who need a different kind of help&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CAIN1963"><link type='external' href='http://harpers.org/archive/1963/02/0014211'>Harpers.org</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://harpers.org/archive/1963/02/alcoholics-anonymous/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous &#124; Harper's Magazine<space/></arg><arg name="first">Arthur H.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Cainwork</arg><arg name="year">2014<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">May 4, 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Literature<space/><template><target>anchor</target><arg>AA Grapevine</arg></template></heading><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>Alcoholics Anonymous publishes several books, reports, pamphlets, and other media, including a periodical known as the<space/><italics>AA Grapevine</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="AASEARCHRESULTS">A<space/><link><target>Worldcat</target></link><space/>search for materials authored by<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3AAlcoholics+Anonymous.&amp;amp;qt=hot_author'>Alcoholics Anonymous</link><space/>and more specific divisions of the organization (<link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3AAlcoholics+Anonymous.&amp;amp;qt=hot_author'>AA Grapevine</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3AAlcoholics+Anonymous+World+Services%2C+inc.&amp;amp;qt=hot_author'>World Services</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3AAlcoholics+Anonymous.+General+Service+Conference.&amp;amp;qt=hot_author'>General Service Conference</link>,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcat.org/search?q=au%3AAlcoholics+Anonymous.+World+Service+Meeting&amp;amp;qt=hot_author'>World Service Meeting</link>) yields well over 500 results.</extension><space/>Two books are used primarily:<space/><italics>Alcoholics Anonymous</italics><space/>(the &quot;Big Book&quot;) and<space/><italics><link><target>Twelve Steps and Twelve Traditions</target></link></italics>, the latter explaining AA's fundamental principles in depth.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>June 1, 1976<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-916856-59-3<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>2353981<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://aa.org/bigbookonline/en_tableofcnt.cfm<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Twelve Steps and Twelve Traditions<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>February 10, 2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-916856-01-1<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>13572433<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="journal">The AA Grapevine<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="issn">0362-2584<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">50379271<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aagrapevine.org/index.php<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Index</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>November 2011<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-893007-16-2<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>49743393<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.aa.org/bigbookonline/</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>AA in music</heading><paragraph>Psychedelic folk musician Red Label Catharsis refers to AA in the song<space/><link type='external' href='https://redlabelcatharsis.bandcamp.com/track/we-agnostics'>We, Agnostics</link></paragraph><heading level='2'>AA in film</heading><heading level='3'>Films about Alcoholic Anonymous</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>My Name Is Bill W.</target></link></italics><space/>dramatized biography of co-founder Bill Wilson.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>When Love Is Not Enough: The Lois Wilson Story</target></link></italics><space/>a 2010 film about the wife of founder Bill Wilson, and the beginnings of Alcoholics Anonymous and<space/><link><target>Al-Anon</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Bill W. (film)</target><part>Bill W.</part></link></italics><space/>a 2011 biographical documentary film that tells the story of Bill Wilson using interviews, recreations, and rare archival material.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WKSU-BillW"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wksu.org/news/story/31179<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bill W. documentary at CIFF<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Urycki<space/></arg><arg name="first1">Mark<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 March 2012<space/></arg><arg name="location">Kent, Ohio<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[WKSU]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 May 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="LAT-BillW"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">'Bill W.' cuts through the anonymity</arg><arg name="first">Sheri<space/></arg><arg name="last">Linden</arg><arg name="url">http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-et-bill-w-capsule-20120518,0,3940309.story</arg><arg name="newspaper">Los Angeles Times<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Los Angeles Times]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Los Angeles</arg><arg name="date">18 May 2012<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="at"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">22 May 2012</arg><arg name="quote">Laudatory but never simplistic, "Bill W." is a thoroughly engrossing portrait of Wilson, his times and the visionary fellowship that is his legacy.</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Films where primary plot line includes AA</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Basketball Diaries - a 1995 film, starring Leonardo DiCaprio as a young high-school basketball star who gives into the pressures of life and finds an finds a new interest; heroin.<space/></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>When a Man Loves a Woman (film)</target><part>When a Man Loves a Woman</part></link></italics><space/>an airline pilot's wife attends AA meetings in a residential treatment facility</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Clean and Sober</target></link></italics><space/>a cocaine addict visits an AA meeting to get a sponsor</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Days of Wine and Roses (film)</target><part>Days of Wine and Roses</part></link></italics><space/>a 1962 film about a married couple struggling with alcoholism.<space/><link><target>Jack Lemmon</target></link>'s character attends an AA meeting in the film.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Drunks</target></link></italics><space/>a 1995 film starring Richard Lewis as an alcoholic who leaves an AA meeting and relapses. The film cuts back and forth between his eventual relapse and the other meeting attendants.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Come Back, Little Sheba (1952 film)</target><part>Come Back, Little Sheba</part></link></italics><space/>A 1952 film based on a play of the same title about a loveless marriage where the husband played by<space/><link><target>Burt Lancaster</target></link><space/>is an alcoholic who gets help from 2 members of the local AA chapter. A 1977 TV drama was also based on the play.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>I'll Cry Tomorrow</target></link></italics><space/>A 1955 film about singer<space/><link><target>Lillian Roth</target></link><space/>played by<space/><link><target>Susan Hayward</target></link><space/>who goes to AA to help her stop drinking. The film was based on Roth's<space/><link><target>I'll Cry Tomorrow (book)</target><part>autobiography of the same name</part></link><space/>detailing her alcoholism and sobriety through AA</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>You Kill Me</target></link></italics><space/>a 2007 crime-comedy film starring<space/><link><target>Ben Kingsley</target></link><space/>as a mob hit man with a drinking problem who is forced to accept a job at a mortuary and go to AA meetings, where he explains he wants to be free of his drinking problem because it is affecting his ability to kill effectively.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Smashed (film)</target><part>Smashed</part></link></italics><space/>a 2012 drama film starring<space/><link><target>Mary Elizabeth Winstead</target></link>. An elementary school teacher's drinking begins to interfere with her job, so she attempts to get sober. Despite stumbling, she manages to use the tools of sponsorship and AA meetings to stay sober one year.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Flight (2012 film)</target><part>Flight</part></link></italics><space/>a 2012 film starring<space/><link><target>Denzel Washington</target></link>. An alcoholic airplane pilot crash lands a flight and struggles with his addiction in the aftermath.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Shattered Spirits</target></link></italics><space/>- a 1986 movie starring<space/><link><target>Martin Sheen</target></link>. Sheen plays an alcoholic father whose drinking costs him his job and leads to an explosive confrontation with his eldest son.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0091938/</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Addiction recovery groups</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Al-Anon/Alateen</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Calix Society</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Community Reinforcement Approach and Family Training</target></link><space/>(CRAFT)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Drug rehabilitation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Effectiveness of Alcoholics Anonymous</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Group psychotherapy</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Intervention (counseling)</target><part>Intervention Counseling</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of twelve-step groups</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>My AA Grapevines</target></link><space/>- Many Images From AA Grapevine Covers, And Other AA Related Publications<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.myaagrapevines.com</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Recovery model</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Self-help groups for mental health</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stepping Stones (home)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Substance abuse</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Washingtonian movement</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="author">Bill W.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous: the story of how many thousands of men and women have recovered from alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="year">1955<space/></arg><arg name="edition">2nd<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York, New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">269381<space/></arg><arg name="postscript">{{inconsistent citations}}</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous: the story of how many thousands of men and women have recovered from alcoholism<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Alcoholics Anonymous World Services<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2002<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>4th<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York, New York<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-893007-16-2<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>408888189<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/bigbookonline/<space/></arg><arg name="author">Bill W.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Edwards<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Griffith<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Griffith Edwards<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcohol: The World's Favorite Drug<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Thomas Dunne Books<space/></arg><arg name="edition"><space/>1st<space/></arg><arg name="date">April 2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-312-28387-3<space/></arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>48176740</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Alcoholics Anonymous as a mutual-help movement: a study in eight societies<space/></arg><arg name="author">Klaus Mäkelä<space/></arg><arg name="author2">World Health Organization. Regional Office for Europe. et al.<space/></arg><arg name="author3">and others<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Wisconsin Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Madison, Wis<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">33242907<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-299-15000-3<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996</arg><arg name="displayauthors">2<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Silkworth: the little doctor who loved drunks<space/></arg><arg name="last">Mitchel<space/></arg><arg name="first">Dale<space/></arg><arg name="location">Center City, Minn<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hazelden<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-56838-794-6<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">51063745</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Pass It on: The Story of Bill Wilson and how the A.A. Message Reached the World<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc.<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York, NY<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 1984<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-916856-12-0<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">12308065</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Peele<space/></arg><arg name="first">Stanton<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Diseasing of America: how we allowed recovery zealots and the treatment industry to convince us we are out of control<space/></arg><arg name="location">San Francisco<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Jossey-Bass<space/></arg><arg name="year">1999<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">39605271<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-7879-4643-5</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Questions & Answers on Sponsorship<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Alcoholics Anonymous World Services, Inc<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.aa.org/pdf/products/p-15_Q&AonSpon.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-12-15<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-12-15<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/5m2vnLSW0</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Robertson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Nan<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Nan C. Robertson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Getting Better: Inside Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1988<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Morrow<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-688-06869-1<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">17260252<space/></arg><arg name="ol">4127115W<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">87031153</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Vaillant<space/></arg><arg name="first">George E.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">George Eman Vaillant<space/></arg><arg name="title">[[The Natural History of Alcoholism Revisited]]<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, Mass<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harvard University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">31605790<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-674-60377-X</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Wilcox<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>D.M.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Alcoholic thinking: Language, culture, and belief in Alcoholics Anonymous<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>[[Westport, CT]]<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Greenwood Publishing Group<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-275-96049-8</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Alcoholics Anonymous</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aa.org/'>AA official website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.alcoholics-anonymous.org.uk/'>AA Great Britain and English speaking continental Europe official website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aagsoindia.org/'>Alcoholics Anonymous General Service Office (India)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aa.org/en_pdfs/smf-121_en.pdf'>Alcoholics Anonymous Twelve Steps</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://aaagnostica.org/a-history-of-agnostic-groups-in-aa/'>A History of Agnostic Groups in AA</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Alcoholics Anonymous</target></template><template><target>Alcohealth</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Addiction and substance abuse organizations</target></link><link><target>Category:Alcohol abuse</target></link><link><target>Category:Alcoholics Anonymous</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:International non-profit organizations</target></link><link><target>Category:Non-profit organizations based in New York City</target></link><link><target>Category:Organizations established in 1935</target></link><link><target>Category:Therapeutic community</target></link><link><target>Category:Twelve-step programs</target></link></paragraph></article>