<article title='Casey_at_the_Bat'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the 1927 film</arg><arg>Casey at the Bat (film)</arg></template><link><target>Image:Casey at the bat.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.3</part><part>Tim Wiles, Director of Research at the<space/><link><target>Baseball Hall of Fame</target></link><space/>Library in<space/><link><target>Cooperstown</target></link>, frequently dresses up as Casey to recite the poem.</part></link>&quot;<bold>Casey at the Bat: A Ballad of the Republic Sung in the Year 1888</bold>&quot; is a<space/><link><target>baseball</target></link><space/>poem written in 1888 by<space/><link><target>Ernest Thayer</target></link>. First published in<space/><italics><link><target>The San Francisco Examiner</target></link></italics><space/>(then called the<space/><italics>The Daily Examiner</italics>) on June 3, 1888, it was later popularized by<space/><link><target>DeWolf Hopper</target></link><space/>in many<space/><link><target>vaudeville</target></link><space/>performances.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat</arg><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-almanac.com/poetry/po_case.shtml</arg><arg name="website">Baseball Almanac</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="catbird"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Armenti</arg><arg name="first1">Peter</arg><arg name="title">The First Publication of "Casey at the Bat"</arg><arg name="url">http://blogs.loc.gov/catbird/2013/06/the-first-publication-of-casey-at-the-bat/</arg><arg name="website">From the Catbird Seat</arg><arg name="publisher">Library of Congress</arg><arg name="date">4 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>It has become one of the best-known poems in<space/><link><target>American literature</target></link>. The poem was originally published anonymously (under the<space/><link><target>pen name</target></link><space/>&quot;Phin&quot;, based on Thayer's college nickname, &quot;Phinney&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gardner"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Synopsis</heading><paragraph>A baseball team from the fictional town of &quot;Mudville&quot; (implied to be the home team) is losing by two<space/><link><target>Run (baseball)</target><part>runs</part></link><space/>in its last inning. Both the team and its fans (a crowd of 5,000, according to the poem) believe they can win if Mighty Casey, Mudville's star player, gets up to bat. However, Casey is scheduled to be the fifth batter of the inning, and the first two batters (Cooney and Barrows) fail to get on base. The next two batters (Flynn and Jimmy Blake) are perceived to be weak hitters with little chance of reaching base to allow Casey a chance to bat.</paragraph><paragraph>Surprisingly, Flynn hits a single, and Blake follows with a double that allows Flynn to reach third base. Both runners are now in scoring position and Casey represents the potential winning run. Casey is so sure of his abilities that he does not swing at the first two pitches, both called strikes. On the last pitch, the overconfident Casey<space/><link><target>Strikeout</target><part>strikes out swinging</part></link>, ending the game and sending the crowd home unhappy.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Text</heading><paragraph><template><target>Listen</target><arg name="filename">CaseyAtTheBat.ogg
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat
<space/></arg><arg name="description">Recited by DeWolf Hopper, c. 1920.
<space/></arg><arg name="format">[[Ogg]]<space/></arg></template>The text is filled with references to baseball as it was in 1888, which in many ways is not far removed from today's version. As a work, the poem encapsulates much of the appeal of baseball, including the involvement of the crowd. It also has a fair amount of baseball jargon that can pose challenges for the uninitiated.</paragraph><paragraph>This is the complete poem as it originally appeared in<space/><italics><link><target>The San Francisco Examiner</target></link></italics>. After publication, various versions with minor changes were produced.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote_box</target><arg name="width">20%
</arg><arg name="align">right
</arg><arg name="quote">No one imagines that 'Casey' is great in the sense that the poetry of [[Shakespeare]] or [[Dante]] is great; a comic [[ballad]] obviously must be judged by different standards. One doesn’t criticize a slice of superb apple pie because it fails to taste like [[Crepe Suzette|crepes suzette]]. Thayer was only trying to write a comic ballad, with clanking rhymes and a vigorous beat, that could be read quickly, understood at once, and laughed at by any newspaper reader who knew baseball. Somehow, in harmony with the curious laws of humor and popular taste, he managed to produce the [[United States|nation]]’s best-known piece of [[comic verse]]—a ballad that began a native [[legend]] as colorful and permanent as that of [[Johnny Appleseed]] or [[Paul Bunyan]].</arg><arg name="author">Martin Gardner</arg><arg name="source">[[American Heritage (magazine)|''American Heritage'']]<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg><poem>The outlook wasn't brilliant for the Mudville Nine that day;
the score stood four to two, with but one inning more to play.
And then when Cooney died at first, and Barrows did the same,
a sickly silence fell upon the patrons of the game.

A straggling few got up to go in deep despair. The rest
clung to that hope which springs eternal in the human breast;
they thought, if only Casey could get but a whack at that –
they'd put up even money, now, with Casey at the bat.

But Flynn preceded Casey, as did also Jimmy Blake,
and the former was a lulu and the latter was a fake,
so upon that stricken multitude grim melancholy sat,
for there seemed but little chance of Casey's getting to the bat.

But Flynn let drive a single, to the wonderment of all,
and Blake, the much despised, tore the cover off the ball;
and when the dust had lifted, and the men saw what had occurred,
there was Jimmy safe at second and Flynn a-hugging third.

Then from five thousand throats and more there rose a lusty yell;
it rumbled through the valley, it rattled in the dell;
it knocked upon the mountain and recoiled upon the flat,
for Casey, mighty Casey, was advancing to the bat.

There was ease in Casey's manner as he stepped into his place;
there was pride in Casey's bearing and a smile on Casey's face.
And when, responding to the cheers, he lightly doffed his hat,
no stranger in the crowd could doubt 'twas Casey at the bat.

Ten thousand eyes were on him as he rubbed his hands with dirt;
five thousand tongues applauded when he wiped them on his shirt.
Then while the writhing pitcher ground the ball into his hip,
defiance gleamed in Casey's eye, a sneer curled Casey's lip.

And now the leather-covered sphere came hurtling through the air,
and Casey stood a-watching it in haughty grandeur there.
Close by the sturdy batsman the ball unheeded sped--
"That ain't my style," said Casey. "Strike one," the umpire said.

From the benches, black with people, there went up a muffled roar,
like the beating of the storm-waves on a stern and distant shore.
"Kill him! Kill the umpire!" shouted someone on the stand;
and it's likely they'd have killed him had not Casey raised his hand.

With a smile of Christian charity great Casey's visage shone;
he stilled the rising tumult; he bade the game go on;
he signaled to the pitcher, and once more the spheroid flew;
but Casey still ignored it, and the umpire said, "Strike two."

"Fraud!" cried the maddened thousands, and echo answered fraud;
but one scornful look from Casey and the audience was awed.
They saw his face grow stern and cold, they saw his muscles strain,
and they knew that Casey wouldn't let that ball go by again.

The sneer is gone from Casey's lip, his teeth are clenched in hate;
he pounds with cruel violence his bat upon the plate.
And now the pitcher holds the ball, and now he lets it go,
and now the air is shattered by the force of Casey's blow.

Oh, somewhere in this favored land the sun is shining bright;
the band is playing somewhere, and somewhere hearts are light,
and somewhere men are laughing, and somewhere children shout;
but there is no joy in Mudville — mighty Casey has struck out.</poem></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Inspiration</heading><paragraph>Thayer said he chose the name &quot;Casey&quot; after a non-player of Irish ancestry he once knew, and it is open to debate who, if anyone, he modeled the character after.</paragraph><paragraph>One candidate is National League star<space/><link><target>King Kelly</target><part>Mike &quot;King&quot; Kelly</part></link>, who became famous when Boston paid Chicago a record $10,000 for him. He had a personality that fans liked to cheer or jeer. After the 1887 season, Kelly went on a playing tour to San Francisco. Thayer, who wrote &quot;Casey&quot; in 1888, covered the San Francisco leg for the<space/><italics><link><target>San Francisco Examiner</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Thayer, in a letter he wrote in 1905, singles out Kelly as showing &quot;impudence&quot; in claiming to have written the poem. The author of the 2004 definitive bio of Kelly which included a close tracking of his vaudeville careerdid not find Kelly claiming to have been the author.<extension extension_name='ref' name="rosenberg"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Rosenberg</arg><arg name="first">Howard W.</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Cap Anson 2: The Theatrical and Kingly Mike Kelly: U.S. Team Sport's First Media Sensation and Baseball's Original Casey at the Bat</arg><arg name="publisher">Tile Books</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">0-9725574-1-5</arg></template></extension><template><target>r</target><arg>rosenberg</arg><arg name="page1">9</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Plagiarism</heading><paragraph>A month after the poem was published, it was reprinted as &quot;Kelly at the Bat&quot; in the<space/><italics><link><target>New York Sporting Times</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">
<space/></arg><arg name="first">
<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">
<space/></arg><arg name="coauthors">
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ernest Lawrence Thayer and "Casey at the Bat"
<space/></arg><arg name="work">
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Joslin Hall Rare Books News List
<space/></arg><arg name="date">
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.joslinhall.com/casey_at_the_bat.htm
<space/></arg><arg name="doi">
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>June 2, 2009</arg></template></extension>Aside from leaving off the first five verses, the only changes from the original are substitutions of Kelly for Casey, and<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link><space/>for Mudville.<extension extension_name='ref' name="moore"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Moore</arg><arg name="first1">Jim</arg><arg name="last2">Vermilyea</arg><arg name="first2">Natalie</arg><arg name="title">Ernest Thayer's "Casey at the bat" : background and characters of baseball's most famous poem</arg><arg name="date">1994</arg><arg name="publisher">McFarland & Co.</arg><arg name="location">Jefferson, N.C.</arg><arg name="isbn">9780899509976</arg><arg name="page">2</arg></template></extension><space/>King Kelly, then of the<space/><link><target>Atlanta Braves</target><part>Boston Beaneaters</part></link>, was one of baseball's two biggest stars at the time (along with<space/><link><target>Cap Anson</target></link>).<template><target>r</target><arg>rosenberg</arg><arg name="page1">9</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1897, &quot;Current Literature&quot; noted the two versions and said, &quot;The locality, as originally given, is Mudville, not Boston; the latter was substituted to give the poem local color.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat</arg><arg name="journal">Current Literature</arg><arg name="date">February 1897</arg><arg name="volume">21</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="page">129</arg><arg name="url">http://babel.hathitrust.org/cgi/pt?id</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Pre-publication version</heading><paragraph>Sportswriter<space/><link><target>Leonard Koppett</target></link><space/>claimed in a 1979 article that the published poem omits 18 lines penned by Thayer which change the entire point of the poem. Koppett said the full version of the poem takes the pitch count on Casey to full as his uncle Arnold stirs up wagering action in the stands before a wink passes between them and Casey throws the game.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Koppett</arg><arg name="first1">Leonard</arg><arg name="title">Casey at Bat? He Was Fraud!</arg><arg name="work">The Sporting News</arg><arg name="date">August 4, 1979</arg><arg name="page">16</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Live performances</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dewolfhopper1.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>upright=1.1</part><part>1909 theatrical poster with DeWolf Hopper in A Matinee Idol</part></link><link><target>DeWolf Hopper</target></link><space/>gave the poem's first stage<space/><link><target>recitation</target></link><space/>on August 14, 1888, at<space/><link><target>New York City</target><part>New York's</part></link><space/><link><target>Wallack Theatre</target></link><space/>as part of the<space/><link><target>comic opera</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Prinz Methusalem</target></link></italics><space/>in the presence of the Chicago and New York baseball teams, the<space/><link><target>Chicago Cubs</target><part>White Stockings</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>San Francisco Giants</target><part>Giants</part></link>; August 14, 1888 was also Thayer's 25th birthday. Hopper became known as an orator of the poem, and recited it more than 10,000 times (by his countsome tabulations are as much as four times higher) before his death.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gardner"></extension><template><target>Quote_box</target><arg name="width">20%
</arg><arg name="align">right
</arg><arg name="quote">"It is as perfect an [[epitome]] of our national game today as it was when every player drank his coffee from a [[mustache cup]]. There are one or more Caseys in every [[Baseball league|league]], [[Bush league|bush]] or big, and there is no day in the playing season that this same supreme [[tragedy]], as stark as [[Aristophanes]] for the moment, does not befall on some field."<ref name</arg></template>On stage in the early 1890s, baseball star Kelly recited the original &quot;Casey&quot; a few dozen times and not the parody. For example, in a review of a variety show he was in, in 1893, the Indianapolis News said, &quot;Many who attended the performance had heard of Kelly's singing and his reciting, and many had heard De Wolf Hopper recite 'Casey at the Bat' in his inimitable way. Kelly recited this in a sing-song, school-boy fashion.&quot; Upon Kelly's death, a writer would say he gained considerable notoriety by his ludicrous rendition of 'Casey at the Bat,' with which he concluded his `turn [act] at each performance.<template><target>r</target><arg>rosenberg</arg><arg name="page1">229</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the 1980s, the magic/comedy team<space/><link><target>Penn &amp; Teller</target></link><space/>performed a version of &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; with Teller (the &quot;silent&quot; partner) struggling to escape a<space/><link><target>straitjacket</target></link><space/>while suspended upside-down over a platform of sharp steel spikes. The set-up was that if<space/><link><target>Penn Jillette</target></link><space/>reached the end of the poem before<space/><link><target>Teller (entertainer)</target><part>Teller</part></link>'s escape, he would leap off his chair, releasing the rope which supported Teller, and send his partner to a gruesome death. The drama of the performance was taken up a notch after the third or fourth stanza, when Penn Jillette began to read out the rest of the poem much faster than the opening stanzas, greatly reducing the time that Teller had left to work free from his bonds.</paragraph><paragraph>On July 4, 2008, Jack Williams recited the poem accompanied by the<space/><link><target>Boston Pops</target></link><space/>during the annual Boston Pops Fireworks Spectacular at Boston's 4 July Celebration.</paragraph><paragraph>On July 14, 2013, the jam rock band<space/><link><target>Furthur (band)</target><part>Furthur</part></link><space/>performed the poem as part of a second-set medley in center field of Doubleday Field in Cooperstown, New York.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://archive.org/details/furthur2013-07-14.AKGc1000s</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Recordings</heading><paragraph><template><target>external media</target><arg name="width"><space/>210px<space/></arg><arg name="float"><space/>right<space/></arg><arg name="headerimage">[[File:2014DworskyKeillor.jpg|210px]]<space/></arg><arg name="video1"><space/>[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>October 15, 2015
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The first recorded version of &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; was made by<space/><link><target>Russell Hunting</target></link>, speaking in a broad Irish accent, in 1893; an<space/><link type='external' href='http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&amp;amp;num=1&amp;amp;start=1&amp;amp;query=cylinder5348'>1898 cylinder recording of the text made for the Columbia Graphophone label by Hunting</link><space/>can be accessed from the<space/><link><target>Cylinder Preservation and Digitization Project</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>University of California, Santa Barbara</target></link><space/>Library.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>DeWolf Hopper</target></link>'s more famous recorded recitation was released in October 1906.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1946,<space/><link><target>Walt Disney</target></link><space/>released a recording of the narration of the poem by<space/><link><target>Jerry Colonna (entertainer)</target><part>Jerry Colonna</part></link>, which accompanied the studio's<space/><link><target>animated cartoon</target></link><space/>adaptation of the poem (see below).</paragraph><paragraph>In 1973, the<space/><link><target>Cincinnati Symphony Orchestra</target></link><space/>commissioned its former Composer-in-Residence,<space/><link><target>Frank Proto</target></link>, to create a work to feature Baseball Hall-of-Famer<space/><link><target>Johnny Bench</target></link><space/>with the orchestra. The result &quot;Casey At The Bat - an American Folk Tale for Narrator and Orchestra&quot; was an immediate hit and recorded by Bench and the orchestra. It has since been performed over 800 times by nearly every Major and Metropolitan orchestra in the U.S. and Canada.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1980, baseball pitcher<space/><link><target>Tug McGraw</target></link><space/>recorded Casey at The Bat by<space/><link><target>Frank Proto</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Peter Nero</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Philly Pops</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1996, film star<space/><link><target>James Earl Jones</target></link><space/>recorded the poem with Arranger/Composer<space/><link><target>Steven Reineke</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Cincinnati Pops Orchestra</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Casey At The Bat</arg><arg name="url">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="work">Casey at the Bat – James Earl Jones</arg><arg name="publisher">YouTube</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 June 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>1998 CD: Play Ball! Erich Kunzel Cincinnati Pops Orchestra, Recorded 1996 with Arranger/Composer Steven Reineke and the Cincinnati Pops Orchestra (insert credits) http://www.amazon.com/dp/B0000064U5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2013,<space/><link><target>Dave Jageler</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Charlie Slowes</target></link>, both radio announcers for the<space/><link><target>Washington Nationals</target></link>, each made recordings of the poem for the<space/><link><target>Library of Congress</target></link><space/>to mark the 125th anniversary of its first publication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Osterberg</arg><arg name="first1">Gayle</arg><arg name="title">A Special Recording to Celebrate Casey’s 125th</arg><arg name="url">http://blogs.loc.gov/loc/2013/06/a-special-recording-to-celebrate-caseys-125th/</arg><arg name="website">Library of Congress Blog</arg><arg name="date">3 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Mudville</heading><paragraph>A rivalry of sorts has developed between two cities claiming to be the Mudville described in the poem.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Zezima</arg><arg name="first1">Katie</arg><arg name="title">Mudville Journal; In 'Casey' Rhubarb, 2 Cities Cry 'Foul!'</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2004/03/31/us/mudville-journal-in-casey-rhubarb-2-cities-cry-foul.html</arg><arg name="work">New York Times</arg><arg name="date">31 March 2004</arg></template></extension><link><target>Image:Holliston-mudville-casey-statue.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Holliston, Massachusetts Mudville Village, Statue and Plaque Dedicated to &quot;Casey&quot; of &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot;</part></link><link><target>Image:Holliston-mudville-welcome-sign.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>200px</part><part>Holliston, Massachusetts Mudville Village, Welcome Sign</part></link>Residents of<space/><link><target>Holliston, Massachusetts</target></link>, where there is a neighborhood called Mudville, claim it as the Mudville described in the poem. Thayer grew up in nearby<space/><link><target>Worcester, Massachusetts</target></link>, where he wrote the poem in 1888; his family owned a woolen mill less than a mile from Mudville's baseball field.</paragraph><paragraph>However, residents of<space/><link><target>Stockton, California</target></link><space/>which was known for a time as Mudville prior to incorporation in 1850also lay claim to being the inspiration for the poem. In 1887, Thayer covered baseball for<space/><italics><link><target>The San Francisco Examiner</target></link></italics>owned by his Harvard classmate<space/><link><target>William Randolph Hearst</target></link>and is said to have covered the local<space/><link><target>California League</target></link><space/>team, the<space/><link><target>Stockton Ports</target></link>. For the<space/><link><target>1902 in baseball</target><part>1902</part></link><space/>season, after the poem became popular, Stockton's team was renamed the Mudville Nine. The team reverted to the Mudville Nine moniker for the 2000 and 2001 seasons. The<space/><link><target>Visalia Rawhide</target></link>, another California League team, currently keep Mudville alive by playing in Mudville jerseys on June&amp;nbsp;3 each year.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Stockton Mudville Nine</arg><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-reference.com/bullpen/Stockton_Mudville_Nine</arg><arg name="website">Baseball Reference.com</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the towns' rival claims, Thayer himself told the<space/><italics><link><target>Syracuse Post-Standard</target></link></italics><space/>that &quot;the poem has no basis in fact.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gardner"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Residents of<space/><link><target>Marshalltown, Iowa</target></link><space/>(home of Hall of Famer<space/><link><target>Cap Anson</target></link>) often refer to their town as Mudville, though possibly for reasons of irreverence having little to do with Anson's former residency.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>June 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Adaptations</heading><paragraph>The poem has been<space/><link><target>Literary adaptation</target><part>adapted</part></link><space/>to diverse types of media:</paragraph><heading level='3'>Books</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Ralph Andreano's 1965 book,<space/><italics>No Joy in Mudville</italics>, laments the dearth of heroes in modern baseball.</listitem><listitem>In the book<space/><italics>Faithful</italics><space/>by Steward O'Nan and Stephen King, describing the 2004 season of the Boston Red Sox, a chapter contributed by King is named &quot;The Gloom is gone from Mudville&quot;.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wallace Tripp</target></link><space/>illustrated a popular 1978 book of the poem.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kurtis Scaletta</target></link>'s 2009 children's novel,<space/><italics>Mudville</italics>, is about a town where it has been raining for 22 years, delaying a baseball game between two rival towns.</listitem><listitem>Christopher Bing's 2000 children's book, an illustrated version of the original poem by Thayer, won a Caldecott Honor for its line drawing illustrations made to look like newspaper articles from 1888.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Comics</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Marvel Comics published a spoof in August 1969, in the 9th issue of &quot;Not Brand Echh&quot;, featuring parodies of their popular Heroes and Villains, and the Bulk (parody of the Hulk) as Casey.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Film</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1922,<space/><link><target>Lee De Forest</target></link><space/>recorded<space/><link><target>DeWolf Hopper</target></link><space/>reciting the poem in DeForest's<space/><link><target>Phonofilm</target></link><space/>sound-on-film process.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Progressive Silent Film List: Casey at the Bat</arg><arg name="url">http://www.silentera.com/PSFL/data/C/CaseyAtTheBat1922.html</arg><arg name="website">Silent Era</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In 1927, a feature-length<space/><link><target>silent film</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Casey at the Bat (1927 film)</target><part>Casey at the Bat</part></link></italics><space/>was released, starring<space/><link><target>Wallace Beery</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ford Sterling</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>ZaSu Pitts</target></link>the first film adaptation of the poem.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Walt Disney</target></link><space/>produced an<space/><link><target>animated short</target></link><space/>adaptation of the poem for the film<space/><italics><link><target>Make Mine Music</target></link></italics><space/>(1946) and uses the original text, but is set in 1902 according to the opening song's lyrics, instead of 1888. This version is recited by<space/><link><target>Jerry Colonna (entertainer)</target><part>Jerry Colonna</part></link>. It was later released as an individual short on July 16, 1954.</listitem><listitem>The poem is cited in Frederic Wiseman's documentary<space/><italics><link><target>High School</target></link></italics><space/>(1968) by a teacher in a classroom.</listitem><listitem>In 1986,<space/><link><target>Elliott Gould</target></link><space/>starred as &quot;Casey&quot; in the<space/><italics><link><target>Shelley Duvall</target></link>'s Tall Tales and Legends</italics><space/>adaptation of the story, which also starred<space/><link><target>Carol Kane</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Howard Cosell</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bob Uecker</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bill Macy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rae Dawn Chong</target></link>. The screenplay, adapted from the poem, was written by<space/><link><target>Andy Borowitz</target></link><space/>and the production was directed by<space/><link><target>David Steinberg</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>The Dream Team (film)</target><part>The Dream Team</part></link></italics><space/>(1989),<space/><link><target>Michael Keaton</target></link>'s character announces that &quot;there is no joy in Mudville&quot; after giving a fellow mental patient three &quot;strikes&quot; for psychotic behavior.</listitem><listitem>A reference to the poem occurs in<space/><italics><link><target>Short Cuts</target></link></italics><space/>(1993).</listitem><listitem>In the film<space/><italics><link><target>What Women Want</target></link></italics><space/>(2000), Mel Gibson's character tries to block out his daughter's thoughts by muttering the poem under his breath.<space/></listitem><listitem>The poem is shortly cited in the revised version of<space/><italics><link><target>Bad News Bears</target></link></italics>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Television</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Jackie Gleason</target></link><space/>in his &quot;Reginald Van Gleason III&quot; persona (in full Mudville baseball uniform) performed a recitation of the poem on his<space/><italics>And Awaaaay We Go!</italics><space/>album.</listitem><listitem>Season 1: Episode 35 of<space/><italics><link><target>The Twilight Zone</target></link></italics>, &quot;<link><target>The Mighty Casey</target></link>&quot;, concerns a baseball player who is actually a<space/><link><target>robot</target></link><space/>(June 17, 1960).</listitem><listitem>In the<space/><italics><link><target>Northern Exposure</target></link></italics><space/>episode &quot;The Graduate,&quot; Chris Stevens gains his<space/><link><target>Master's degree</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Comparative Literature</target></link><space/>by subjecting his assessors to a spirited re-enactment of the poem.</listitem><listitem>An episode of<space/><italics><link><target>The Simpsons</target></link></italics><space/>entitled &quot;<link><target>Homer at the Bat</target></link>&quot; takes its title from the poem.</listitem><listitem>An episode of<space/><italics><link><target>Tiny Toon Adventures</target></link></italics><space/>features a retelling of the poem with Buster Bunny in the title role. However, instead of striking out at the end, he hits a walk off home run.</listitem><listitem>An episode of<space/><italics><link><target>Animaniacs</target></link></italics><space/>entitled &quot;Jokahontas/Boids on the Hood/Mighty Wakko at the Bat&quot; includes a parody of the poem.</listitem><listitem>An episode of<space/><italics>The Cleveland Show</italics><space/>entitled &quot;How Cleveland Got His Groove Back&quot; features the main character, Cleveland Brown, striking out in a game. The following scene cuts to a storybook featuring the lines, &quot;But there is no joy in Stoolbend, mighty Cleveland has struck out,&quot; a play on the last line of the poem.</listitem><listitem>An episode of the television series<space/><italics><link><target>The Adventures of Jimmy Neutron: Boy Genius</target></link></italics><space/>entitled &quot;Return of the Nanobots&quot; has Cindy Vortex reciting a poem that ends with the lines &quot;But there is no joy in Retroville, 'cause Jimmy is an idiot.&quot;</listitem><listitem>In the fourth season of<space/><italics><link><target>Garfield and Friends</target></link></italics><space/>the episode entitled &quot;Mind Over Matter/Orson at the Bat/Multiple Choice Cartoon&quot; features Wade Duck narrating a parody of the poem as Orson Pig experiences it in a dream sequence.</listitem><listitem>A third-season episode of<space/><italics><link><target>Storm Chasers (TV series)</target><part>Storm Chasers</part></link></italics><space/>was titled &quot;Sean Casey At Bat&quot;. The episode featured Casey (a chaser) intercepting a tornado for the first time in TIV 2.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>How I Met Your Mother</target></link></italics>, the episode &quot;<link><target>Bedtime Stories (How I Met Your Mother)</target><part>Bedtime Stories</part></link>&quot; (which is done entirely in rhymes) features a subplot called<space/><link><target>Bedtime Stories (How I Met Your Mother)#&quot;Mosby At The Bat&quot;</target><part>&quot;Mosby At The Bat&quot;</part></link>. The subplot consists of<space/><link><target>Ted Mosby</target><part>Ted</part></link>, the main character, going on a date with a girl, who reveals that she once dated a<space/><link><target>New York Yankee</target></link>. However, when Ted asks, it turns out that the player was just his friend<space/><link><target>Barney Stinson</target><part>Barney</part></link>. The start of that section of the episode begins with &quot;The outlook wasn't brilliant for poor Ted's romantic life&quot;, a line based on the opening of the original poem.<extension extension_name='ref' name="HIMYM"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">How I Met Your Mother Episode Bedtime Stories Scripts</arg><arg name="url">http://www.springfieldspringfield.co.uk/view_episode_scripts.php?tv-show</arg><arg name="website">springfieldspringfield.co.uk</arg><arg name="accessdate">7 December 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>One Tree Hill (TV series)</target><part>One Tree Hill</part></link></italics>, the episode &quot;The Man Who Sailed Around His Soul&quot; was a flashback-heavy episode revolving around a baseball game with<space/><link><target>Jamie Scott (One Tree Hill)</target><part>Jamie Scott</part></link><space/>narrating the poem throughout.</listitem><listitem>On an episode of Penn and Teller<space/><link><target>Fool Us</target></link>, magician<space/><link><target>Rick Lax</target></link><space/>recites the entire poem while performing a card trick.</listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>Friends</target></link></italics><space/>Episode<space/><italics><link><target>The One With The Prom Video</target></link></italics><space/>Ross asks a Casey calling for Rachel &quot;And how do we spell Casey? It is like &quot;at the bat&quot; or &quot;and the Sunshine Band?&quot;</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Music</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Art-song composer<space/><link><target>Sidney Homer</target></link><space/>turned the poem into a song. Sheet music was published by G. Schirmer in 1920 as part of<space/><italics>Six Cheerful Songs to Poems of American Humor.</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>William Schuman</target></link><space/>composed an opera,<space/><italics>The Mighty Casey</italics><space/>(1953), based on the poem.</listitem><listitem>The song<space/><italics>No Joy in Mudville</italics><space/>from<space/><link><target>Death Cab for Cutie</target></link>'s album<space/><italics><link><target>We Have the Facts and We're Voting Yes</target></link></italics><space/>directly references the poem.</listitem><listitem>The song &quot;<link><target>Rocky Mountain Way</target></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>Joe Walsh</target></link><space/>includes the line, &quot;The bases are loaded and Casey's at bat, playing it play by play. Time to change the batter.&quot;</listitem><listitem>The song &quot;Felicia&quot; on the<space/><italics><link><target>Straight On till Morning (album)</target><part>Straight On till Morning</part></link></italics><space/>album by<space/><link><target>Blues Traveler</target></link><space/>includes the line &quot;I wouldn't feel so much like Casey who never got to bat.&quot;</listitem><listitem>The song &quot;<link><target>Centerfield (song)</target><part>Centerfield</part></link>&quot; by<space/><link><target>John Fogerty</target></link><space/>includes the line &quot;Well, I spent some time in the Mudville Nine, watchin' it from the bench. You know I took some lumps when the Mighty Case struck out.&quot;</listitem><listitem>The song &quot;To the Dogs or Whoever&quot; by<space/><link><target>Josh Ritter</target></link><space/>includes the stanza &quot;Was it<space/><link><target>Casey Jones</target></link><space/>or Casey at the Bat who died out of pride and got famous for that? Killed by a swerve, laid low by the curve, do you ever think they ever thought they got what they deserved?&quot;</listitem><listitem>The song &quot;No Joy In Pudville&quot; by<space/><link><target>Steroid Maximus</target></link><space/>is a reference to this poem.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Randol Alan Bass</target></link><space/>composed<space/><italics>Casey at the Bat</italics><space/>for the Dallas Symphony Orchestra. At the premier in April 2001,<space/><link><target>Pat Sajak</target></link><space/>was the narrator.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Randol Alan Bass – Casey at the Bat</arg><arg name="url">http://www.randolbassmusic.com/Works/General/CaseyAtTheBat/casey_at_the_bat.htm</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>Columbus, Ohio-based pop/rock band Casey At The Bat formed in 2012.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Theatre</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>&quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; was adapted into a 1953<space/><link><target>opera</target></link><space/>by American composer<space/><link><target>William Schuman</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Allen Feinstein</target></link><space/>composed an adaptation for orchestra with a narrator. An orchestral version was composed by Stephen Simon in 1976 for the bicentennial; Maestro Classics' has recorded it with the London Philharmonic Orchestra, Stephen Simon conducting with Yadu (Dr. Konrad Czynski) narrating. An orchestral adaptation by composer<space/><link><target>Frank Proto</target></link><space/>has been recorded by the<space/><link><target>Cincinnati Pops</target></link><space/>orchestra conducted by<space/><link><target>Erich Kunzel</target></link><space/>with baseball star<space/><link><target>Johnny Bench</target></link><space/>narrating. The Dallas Symphony commissioned an arrangement of &quot;Casey&quot; by Randol Alan Bass in 2001 which he later arranged for concert band. A version for wind band and narrator by Donald Shirer based on &quot;<link><target>Take Me Out to the Ball Game</target></link>&quot; had its world premiere in July 2008.</listitem><listitem>The last verse of the poem is quoted in the musical<space/><italics><link><target>Cabaret (musical)</target><part>Cabaret</part></link></italics><space/>Cliff recites it to Sally when they first meet.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Derivations</heading><paragraph>For a relatively short poem apparently dashed off quickly (and denied by its author for years), &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; had a profound effect on American popular culture. It has been<space/><link><target>Casey at the Bat#Live performances</target><part>recited</part></link>, re-enacted,<space/><link><target>Casey at the Bat#Other versions</target><part>adapted</part></link>, dissected, parodied and subjected to just about every other treatment one could imagine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gardner"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sequels</heading><paragraph>&quot;Casey's Revenge&quot;, by<space/><link><target>Grantland Rice</target></link><space/>(1907), gives Casey another chance against the pitcher who had struck him out in the original story. It was written in 1906, and its first known publication was in the quarterly magazine<space/><italics>The Speaker</italics><space/>in June 1907, under the pseudonym of James Wilson.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Gardner</arg><arg name="first">Martin</arg><arg name="title">The Annotated Casey at the Bat: A Collection of Ballads About the Mighty Casey</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">Dover Publications</arg><arg name="isbn">0-486-28598-7</arg><arg name="page">38</arg></template></extension><space/>In this version, Rice cites the nickname &quot;Strike-Out Casey&quot;, hence the influence on<space/><link><target>Casey Stengel</target></link>'s name. Casey's team is down<space/><italics>three</italics><space/>runs by the last of the ninth, and once again Casey is down to two strikeswith the bases full this time. However, he connects, hits the ball so far that it is never found.Here is the original version of the poem:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg><poem>There were saddened hearts in Mudville for a week or even more;
there were muttered oaths and curses- every fan in town was sore.
"Just think," said one, "how soft it looked with Casey at the bat,
and then to think he'd go and spring a bush league trick like that!"

All his past fame was forgotten- he was now a hopeless "shine."
They called him "Strike-Out Casey," from the mayor down the line;
and as he came to bat each day his bosom heaved a sigh,
while a look of hopeless fury shone in mighty Casey's eye.

He pondered in the days gone by that he had been their king,
that when he strolled up to the plate they made the welkin ring;
but now his nerve had vanished, for when he heard them hoot
he "fanned" or "popped out" daily, like some minor league recruit.

He soon began to sulk and loaf, his batting eye went lame;
no home runs on the score card now were chalked against his name;
the fans without exception gave the manager no peace,
for one and all kept clamoring for Casey's quick release.

The Mudville squad began to slump, the team was in the air;
their playing went from bad to worse – nobody seemed to care.
"Back to the woods with Casey!" was the cry from Rooters' Row.
"get some one who can hit the ball, and let that big dub go!"

The lane is long, some one has said, that never turns again,
and Fate, though fickle, often gives another chance to men;
and Casey smiled; his rugged face no longer wore a frown-
the pitcher who had started all the trouble came to town.

All Mudville had assembled – ten thousand fans had come
to see the twirler who had put big Casey on the bum;
and when he stepped into the box, the multitude went wild;
he doffed his cap in proud disdain, but Casey only smiled.

"Play ball!" the umpire's voice rang out, and then the game began.
But in that throng of thousands there was not a single fan
who thought that Mudville had a chance, and with the setting sun
their hopes sank low- the rival team was leading "four to one."

The last half of the ninth came round, with no change in the score;
but when the first man up hit safe, the crowd began to roar;
the din increased, the echo of ten thousand shouts was heard
when the pitcher hit the second and gave "four balls" to the third.

Three men on base – nobody out – three runs to tie the game!
A triple meant the highest niche in Mudville's hall of fame;
but here the rally ended and the gloom was deep as night,
when the fourth one "fouled to catcher" and the fifth "flew out to right."

A dismal groan in chorus came; a scowl was on each face
when Casey walked up, bat in hand, and slowly took his place;
his bloodshot eyes in fury gleamed, his teeth were clenched in hate;
he gave his cap a vicious hook and pounded on the plate.

But fame is fleeting as the wind and glory fades away;
there were no wild and woolly cheers, no glad acclaim this day;
they hissed and groaned and hooted as they clamored: "Strike him out!"
But Casey gave no outward sign that he had heard this shout.

The pitcher smiled and cut one loose – across the plate it sped;
another hiss, another groan. "Strike one!" the umpire said.
Zip! Like a shot the second curve broke just below the knee.
"Strike two!" the umpire roared aloud; but Casey made no plea.

No roasting for the umpire now – his was an easy lot;
but here the pitcher whirled again- was that a rifle shot?
A whack, a crack, and out through the space the leather pellet flew,
a blot against the distant sky, a speck against the blue.

Above the fence in center field in rapid whirling flight
the sphere sailed on – the blot grew dim and then was lost to sight.
Ten thousand hats were thrown in air, ten thousand threw a fit,
but no one ever found the ball that mighty Casey hit.

O, somewhere in this favored land dark clouds may hide the sun,
and somewhere bands no longer play and children have no fun!
And somewhere over blighted lives there hangs a heavy pall,
but Mudville hearts are happy now, for Casey hit the ball.</poem></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In response to the popularity of the 1946 Walt Disney animated adaptation, Disney made a sequel,<space/><italics>Casey Bats Again</italics><space/>(1954), in which Casey's nine daughters redeem his reputation.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1988, on the 100th anniversary of the poem,<space/><italics><link><target>Sports Illustrated</target></link></italics><space/>writer<space/><link><target>Frank Deford</target></link><space/>constructed a fanciful story (later expanded to book form) which posited Katie Casey, the subject of the song &quot;<link><target>Take Me Out to the Ball Game</target></link>&quot;, as being the daughter of the famous slugger from the poem.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2010, Ken Eagle wrote The Mudville Faithful, covering a century of the Mudville nine's ups and downs since Casey struck out. Faithful fans still root for the perpetually losing team, and are finally rewarded by a trip to the World Series, led by Casey's great-grandson who is also named Casey.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Parodies</heading><paragraph>Of the many<space/><link><target>parody</target><part>parodies</part></link><space/>made of the poem, some of the notable ones include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Mad (magazine)</target><part>Mad</part></link></italics><space/>republished the original version of the poem in the 1950s with artwork by<space/><link><target>Jack Davis (cartoonist)</target><part>Jack Davis</part></link><space/>and no alterations to the text. Later lampoons in<space/><italics>Mad</italics><space/>included &quot;'Cool' Casey at the Bat&quot; (1960), an interpretation of the poem in<space/><link><target>beatnik</target></link><space/>style, with artwork by<space/><link><target>Don Martin (cartoonist)</target><part>Don Martin</part></link>; &quot;Casey at the Dice&quot; in 1969, about a professional gambler; &quot;Casey at the Talks&quot; in 1977, a &quot;modern&quot; version of the famed poem in which Mudville tries unsuccessfully to sign free agent Casey[the last line of which is &quot;Mighty Casey has held out&quot;]; &quot;Baseball at the Bat&quot;, a satire on baseball itself, &quot;Howard at the Mike,&quot; about<space/><link><target>Howard Stern</target></link>; &quot;Casey at the Byte&quot; (1985), a tale of a cocky young computer expert who accidentally erases the White House Budget Plan; &quot;Clooney as the Bat&quot;, a mockery of<space/><link><target>George Clooney</target></link>'s role as<space/><link><target>Batman</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>Batman &amp; Robin (film)</target><part>Batman and Robin</part></link></italics>; and in 2006 as &quot;Barry at the Bat&quot;, poking fun at<space/><link><target>Barry Bonds</target></link>' alleged involvement in the<space/><link><target>BALCO</target></link><space/>scandal, and in 2001, &quot;Jordan at the Hoop&quot;, satirizing<space/><link><target>Michael Jordan</target></link>'s return to the NBA and his time with the<space/><link><target>Washington Wizards</target></link>. Another parody takes place in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>, which ends with &quot;Kasey&quot; in a<space/><link><target>gulag</target></link><space/>prison. A &quot;Poetry Round Robin&quot; where famous poems are rewritten in the style of the next poet in line, featured Casey at the Bat as written by<space/><link><target>Edgar Allan Poe</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Foster Brooks</target></link><space/>(&quot;the Lovable Lush&quot;) wrote &quot;Riley on the Mound&quot;, which recounts the story from the pitcher's perspective.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Radio performer<space/><link><target>Garrison Keillor</target></link>'s parodic version of the poem<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Keillor</arg><arg name="first1">Garrison</arg><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat (Road Game)</arg><arg name="url">http://www.baseball-almanac.com/poetry/po_case7.shtml</arg><arg name="website">Baseball Almanac</arg></template></extension><space/>reimagines the game as a road game, instead of a home game, for the Mudville team. The same events occur with Casey striking out in the ninth inning as in the original poem, but with everything told from the perspective of other team.</listitem><listitem>An episode of<space/><italics><link><target>Tiny Toon Adventures</target></link></italics><space/>featured a short titled &quot;Buster at the Bat&quot;, where<space/><link><target>Sylvester (Looney Tunes)</target><part>Sylvester</part></link><space/>provides narration as Buster goes up to bat. The poem was parodied again for an episode of<space/><italics><link><target>Animaniacs</target></link></italics>, this time with<space/><link><target>Yakko, Wakko, and Dot</target><part>Wakko</part></link><space/>as the title character and Yakko narrating.<space/></listitem><listitem>In<space/><italics><link><target>The Adventures of Jimmy Neutron: Boy Genius</target></link></italics><space/>episode &quot;Return of the Nanobots&quot;, Cindy's poem is identical to the ending of &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; but replaces Mudville with Retroville and the last famed line with &quot;cause Jimmy is an idiot!&quot;</listitem><listitem>An episode of the show<space/><italics><link><target>U.S. Acres</target></link></italics><space/>was titled &quot;Orson at the Bat&quot;.</listitem><listitem><link><target>The New York Times</target></link><space/>published a parody by Hart Seely and Frank Cammuso in which the poem was narrated by<space/><link><target>Phil Rizzuto</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>New York Yankees</target></link><space/>announcer who was known to veer off on tangents while calling the game. The poem was later published in Seely and Cammuso's book,<space/><italics>2007 Eleven And Other American Comedies</italics>.</listitem><listitem>Issue #92 of the comic Fables employs a paraphrased version of &quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; appropriating the character names to those of the Fable players. It is preceded by a mock apology to Ernest Thayer for the mangling of &quot;his beloved poem&quot;.</listitem><listitem><link><target>David Pogue</target></link><space/>penned a parody version titled 'A Desktop Critic: Steven Saves the Mac' for<space/><link><target>Macworld</target></link><space/>magazine that ran in their October 1999 issue.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">Pogue</arg><arg name="first1">David</arg><arg name="title">The Desktop Critic: Steven Saves the Mac</arg><arg name="url">http://www.macworld.com/article/15358/1999/10/desktopcritic.html</arg><arg name="work">Macworld</arg><arg name="date">October 1999</arg></template></extension><space/>It tells the story of<space/><link><target>Steve Jobs</target></link>' triumphant return to a struggling<space/><link><target>Apple Inc</target></link><space/>and his early efforts to reverse the company's fortunes.</listitem><listitem>Dick Flavin wrote a version titled Teddy at the Bat, after<space/><link><target>Boston Red Sox</target></link><space/>legend<space/><link><target>Ted Williams</target></link><space/>died in July, 2002. Flavin performed the poem at<space/><link><target>Fenway Park</target></link><space/>during the night-long tribute to Williams done at the park later that month. The poem replaced Flynn and Blake with<space/><link><target>Bobby Doerr</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Johnny Pesky</target></link>, the batters who preceded Williams in the 1946 Red Sox lineup.</listitem><listitem>In 2000, Michael J. Farrand adapted the<space/><link><target>rhyming scheme</target></link>, tone, and<space/><link><target>Literary theme</target><part>theme</part></link><space/>of the poemwhile reversing the outcometo create his poem &quot;The Man Who Gave All the Dreamers in Baseball Land Bigger Dreams to Dream&quot; about<space/><link><target>Kirk Gibson's 1988 World Series home run</target><part>Kirk Gibson's home run</part></link><space/>off<space/><link><target>Dennis Eckersley</target></link><space/>in Game 1 of the 1988<space/><link><target>World Series</target></link>. The poem appears at the<space/><link><target>Baseball Almanac</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Translations</heading><paragraph>There are three known translations of the poem into a foreign language, one in French, written in 2007 by French Canadian linguist Paul Laurendeau, with the title<space/><italics>Casey au bton</italics>, and two in Hebrew. One by the sports journalist Menachem Less titled &quot; &quot; [Hator Shel Casey Lachbot],<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.hoops.co.il/index.asp?page=ViewEL&amp;amp;id=98'>| !</link></extension><space/>and the other more recent and more true to the original cadence and style by Jason H. Elbaum called [Casey BaMachbayt].<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Elbaum</arg><arg name="first1">Jason H.</arg><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat in Hebrew</arg><arg name="url">http://caseyatthebatinhebrew.blogspot.com/</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Names</heading><paragraph><link><target>Casey Stengel</target></link><space/>describes in his autobiography how his nickname of &quot;K.C.&quot; (for his hometown,<space/><link><target>Kansas City, Missouri</target></link>) evolved into &quot;Casey&quot;. It was influenced not just by the name of the poem, which was widely popular in the 1910s, but also because he tended to strike out frequently in his early career so fans and writers started calling him &quot;strikeout Casey&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Stengel</arg><arg name="first1">Casey</arg><arg name="last2">Paxton</arg><arg name="first2">Harry T.</arg><arg name="title">Casey at the Bat: The Story of My Life in Baseball</arg><arg name="date">1962</arg><arg name="publisher">Random House</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="page">11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Contemporary culture</heading><heading level='3'>Games</heading><paragraph>The poem is referenced in the<space/><link><target>Super Nintendo Entertainment System</target></link><space/>game<space/><italics><link><target>EarthBound</target></link></italics>, where a weapon is named the Casey Bat, which is the strongest weapon in the game, but will only hit 25% of the time.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Television</heading><paragraph>A one-time character in the<space/><italics><link><target>Pokmon (anime)</target><part>Pokmon</part></link></italics><space/>anime, a girl who is a very enthusiastic fan of baseball, is named &quot;Casey&quot; in the English version in reference to the poem.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://bulbapedia.bulbagarden.net/wiki/Casey_(anime)</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theme parks</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Casey's Corner is a baseball-themed restaurant in<space/><link><target>Walt Disney World</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Magic Kingdom</target></link>, which serves primarily hotdogs. Pictures of Casey and the pitcher from the Disney animated adaptation are hanging on the walls, and a life-size statue of a baseball player identified as &quot;Casey&quot; stands just outside the restaurant. Additionally, the scoreboard in the restaurant shows that Mudville lost to the visitors by two runs.</listitem><listitem>A hot dog restaurant featuring the Disney character can be found at<space/><link><target>Disneyland Paris</target></link>'<space/><link><target>Disneyland Park (Paris)</target><part>Disneyland Park</part></link><space/>since its opening in 1992, under the name Casey's Corner.</listitem><listitem>A game called Casey at the Bat is in the Games of the Boardwalk at the<space/><link><target>Disneyland Resort</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Disney California Adventure Park</target><part>Disney California Adventure</part></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Postage stamp</heading><paragraph>On July 11, 1996, the<space/><link><target>United States Postal Service</target></link><space/>issued a<space/><link><target>commemorative stamp</target></link><space/>depicting &quot;Mighty Casey.&quot; The stamp was part of a set commemorating American<space/><link><target>folk hero</target><trail>es</trail></link>. Other stamps in the set depicted<space/><link><target>Paul Bunyan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Henry (folklore)</target><part>John Henry</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Pecos Bill</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Mighty Casey</arg><arg name="url">http://usstampgallery.com/view.php?id</arg><arg name="website">US Stamp Gallery</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mlb.mlb.com/mlb/events/casey_at_the_bat/mlb_anniversary_story.jsp?feature=clubhouse'>&quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; on MLB.com</link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>media:CaseyAtTheBat.ogg</target><part>Hear Hopper recite the poem</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.loc.gov/programs/static/national-recording-preservation-board/documents/CASEY%20AT%20THE%20BAT.pdf'>Library of Congress essay</link><space/>on its inclusion into the<space/><link><target>National Recording Registry</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cylinders.library.ucsb.edu/search.php?queryType=@attr+1=1020&amp;amp;num=1&amp;amp;start=1&amp;amp;query=cylinder5348'>''Casey at the Bat'' cylinder recording by Russell Hunting</link>, from the<space/><link><target>Cylinder Preservation and Digitization Project</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>University of California, Santa Barbara</target></link><space/>Library.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.joslinhall.com/casey_at_the_bat.htm'>&quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; Web site with biographical details on Thayer, Hopper, Mike &quot;King&quot; Kelly and chronology of the poem's publication.</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://baseballcardblog.blogspot.com/2008/12/casey-at-bat.html'>&quot;Casey at the Bat&quot; as told in baseball cards</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.baseball-almanac.com/poems.shtml'>Poems about Casey's later life</link>, including another by Grantland Rice, and one by<space/><link><target>Garrison Keillor</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>American tall tales</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Casey At The Bat</target></template><link><target>Category:American poems</target></link><link><target>Category:Baseball poems</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional baseball players</target></link><link><target>Category:American folklore</target></link><link><target>Category:1888 poems</target></link><link><target>Category:Works originally published in The San Francisco Examiner</target></link><link><target>Category:United States National Recording Registry recordings</target></link></paragraph></article>