<article title='Code_of_Hammurabi'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox document</target><arg name="document_name">Code of Hammurabi
</arg><arg name="image">Code-de-Hammurabi-1.jpg
</arg><arg name="image_width">250px
</arg><arg name="image_caption"><space/>Side view of the [[stele]] "fingertip".
</arg><arg name="date_created"><space/>c 1750 BC
</arg><arg name="date_ratified"></arg><arg name="writer">[[Hammurabi]]
</arg><arg name="signers">
</arg><arg name="purpose">[[Law code]]
</arg><arg name="wikisource">The Code of Hammurabi
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Code of Hammurabi</bold><space/>is a well-preserved<space/><link><target>Babylonian</target></link><space/><link><target>law code</target></link><space/>of ancient<space/><link><target>Mesopotamia</target></link>, dating back to about 1754 BC. It is one of the oldest deciphered writings of significant length in the world. The sixth Babylonian king,<space/><link><target>Hammurabi</target></link>, enacted the code, and partial copies exist on a man-sized stone<space/><italics><link><target>stele</target></link></italics><space/>and various clay tablets. The Code consists of 282 laws, with scaled punishments, adjusting &quot;an eye for an eye, a tooth for a tooth&quot; (<italics><link><target>lex talionis</target></link></italics>)<extension extension_name='ref'>Review: The Code of Hammurabi, J. Dyneley Prince, The American Journal of Theology Vol. 8, No. 3 (Jul., 1904), pp. 601609 Published by: The University of Chicago Press Stable URL: http://www.jstor.org/stable/3153895</extension><space/>as graded depending on social status, of slave versus free man.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bar"><link><target>Gabriele Bartz</target></link>, Eberhard Knig, (Arts and Architecture), Knemann, Kln, (2005), ISBN 3-8331-1943-8. The laws were based with scaled punishments, adjusting &quot;an eye for an eye&quot; depending on social status.</extension>Nearly one-half of the Code deals with matters of contract, establishing, for example, the wages to be paid to an ox driver or a surgeon. Other provisions set the terms of a transaction, establishing the liability of a builder for a house that collapses, for example, or property that is damaged while left in the care of another. A third of the code addresses issues concerning household and family relationships such as inheritance, divorce, paternity and<space/><link><target>sexual behavior</target></link>. Only one provision appears to impose obligations on an official; this provision establishes that a judge who reaches an incorrect decision is to be fined and removed from the bench permanently.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.commonlaw.com/Hammurabi.html'>Code of Hammurabi</link></extension><space/>A handful of provisions address issues related to military service.</paragraph><paragraph>The code was discovered by modern archaeologists in 1901, and its<space/><link><target>editio princeps</target></link><space/>translation published in 1902 by<space/><link><target>Jean-Vincent Scheil</target></link>. This nearly complete example of the Code is carved into a basalt<space/><link><target>stele</target></link><space/>in the shape of a huge<space/><link><target>index finger</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Iconographic Evidence for Some Mesopotamian Cult Statues, Dominique Collon, Die Welt der Gtterbilder, Edited by Groneberg, Brigitte; , Spieckermann, Hermann; , and Weiershuser, Frauke, Berlin, New York (Walter de Gruyter) 2007 Pages 5784</extension><space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2.25</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>foot</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>tall (<italics>see images at right</italics>). The Code is inscribed in the<space/><link><target>Akkadian language</target></link>, using<space/><link><target>cuneiform script</target></link><space/>carved into the stele. It is currently on display in the<space/><link><target>Louvre</target></link>, with exact replicas in the Oriental Institute at the University of Chicago, the library of the<space/><link><target>Theological University of the Reformed Churches</target></link><space/>(Dutch: Theologische Universiteit Kampen voor de Gereformeerde Kerken) in the Netherlands, the<space/><link><target>Pergamon Museum</target></link><space/>of Berlin and the<space/><link><target>National Museum of Iran</target></link><space/>in Tehran.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="align"><space/>Middle
</arg><arg name="image1"><space/>Prologue Hammurabi Code Louvre AO10237.jpg
</arg><arg name="width1"><space/>136
</arg><arg name="caption1"><space/>Code on clay tablets
</arg><arg name="image2"><space/>Code of Hammurabi.jpg
</arg><arg name="width2"><space/>136
</arg><arg name="caption2"><space/>Code on basalt stele
</arg><arg name="footer"><space/>Two versions of the Code at the [[Louvre]]
</arg></template><link><target>Hammurabi</target></link><space/>ruled for nearly 42 years, c. 1792 to 1750 BC according to the<space/><link><target>Middle chronology</target></link>. In the preface to the law, he states, &quot;Anu and Bel called by name me, Hammurabi, the exalted prince, who feared<space/><link><target>Marduk</target></link>, the patron god of Babylon (The Human Record, Andrea &amp; Overfield 2005), to bring about the rule in the land.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="wsu"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mesopotamia: The Code of Hammurabi<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Washington State University<space/></arg><arg name="year">1996<space/></arg><arg name="author">Edited by Richard Hooker; Translated by L.W King<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20070909114038/http://www.wsu.edu:80/~dee/MESO/CODE.HTM<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">9 September 2007<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>On the stone slab there are 44 columns and 28 paragraphs that contained 282 laws. The laws follow along the rules of 'an eye for an eye'.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Hammurabi's Code&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://library.thinkquest.org/20176/hammurabis_code.htm'></link>, Think Quest, retrieved on 2 Nov 2011.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>It had been taken as plunder by the Elamite king<space/><link><target>Shutruk-Nahhunte</target></link><space/>in the 12th century BC and was taken to<space/><link><target>Susa</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Elam</target></link><space/>(located in the present-day<space/><link><target>Khuzestan Province</target></link><space/>of Iran) where it was no longer available to the Babylonian people. However, when<space/><link><target>Cyrus the Great</target></link><space/>brought both Babylon and Susa under the rule of his<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target><part>Persian Empire</part></link>, and placed copies of the document in the<space/><link><target>Cyrus the Great#Library at Sippar</target><part>Library of Sippar</part></link>, the text became available for all the peoples of the vast Persian Empire to view.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marc Van De Mieroop: A History of the Ancient Near East, second edition p.296</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1901, Egyptologist<space/><link><target>Gustave Jquier</target></link>, a member of an expedition headed by<space/><link><target>Jacques de Morgan</target></link>, found the stele containing the Code of Hammurabi during archaeological excavations at the ancient site of Susa in Khuzestan.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Cultures in Contact: From Mesopotamia to the Mediterranean in the Second Millennium B.C</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Metropolitan Museum of Art]]</arg><arg name="date">2013</arg><arg name="access-date">November 1, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Law</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Babylonian law</arg></template>The Code of Hammurabi was one of several sets of laws in the<space/><link><target>ancient Near East</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="yale"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.yale.edu/lawweb/avalon/medieval/hamframe.htm</arg><arg name="title">The Code of Hammurabi: Translated by L. W. King</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 September 2007</arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="author"><space/>L. W. King</arg></template></extension>The code of laws was arranged in orderly groups, so that everyone who read the laws would know what was required of them.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Code of Hammurabi: Introduction,&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/ancient/hamcode.asp'></link>, Ancient History Sourcebook, March 1998, retrieved on 2 November 2011.</extension>Earlier collections of laws include the<space/><link><target>Code of Ur-Nammu</target></link>, king of<space/><link><target>Ur</target></link><space/>(c. 2050 BC), the<space/><link><target>Laws of Eshnunna</target></link><space/>(c. 1930 BC) and the codex of<space/><link><target>Lipit-Ishtar</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Isin</target></link><space/>(c. 1870 BC), while later ones include the<space/><link><target>Hittite laws</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Assyrian law</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>Mosaic Law</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barton, G.A:<space/><italics>Archaeology and the Bible</italics>. University of Michigan Library, 2009, (originally published in 1916 by American Sunday-School Union) p.406.</extension>These codes come from similar cultures in a relatively small geographical area, and they have passages which resemble each other.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barton 2009, p.406. Barton, a scientist of Semitic languages at the University of Pennsylvania from 1922 to 1931, stated that while there are similarities between the Mosaic Law and the Code of Hammurabi, a study of the entirety of both laws<space/><italics>&quot;convinces the student that the laws of the Old Testament are in no essential way dependent upon the Babylonian laws.&quot;</italics><space/>He states that<space/><italics>&quot;such resemblances&quot;</italics><space/>arose from<space/><italics>&quot;a similarity of antecedents and of general intellectual outlook&quot;</italics><space/>between the two cultures, but that<space/><italics>&quot;the striking differences show that there was no direct borrowing.&quot;</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Milkau Oberer Teil der Stele mit dem Text von Hammurapis Gesetzescode 369-2.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Figures at top of<space/><link><target>stele</target></link><space/>&quot;fingernail&quot; above Hammurabi's code of laws.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Code of Hammurabi is the longest surviving text from the Old Babylonian period.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;The Code of Hammurabi,&quot;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.historyguide.org/ancient/hammurabi.html'></link>, The History Guide, 3 August 2009, Retrieved on 2 November 2011.</extension>The code has been seen as an early example of a fundamental law, regulating a government i.e., a primitive<space/><link><target>constitution</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>What is a Constitution? William David Thomas, Gareth Stevens (2008) p. 8</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Flach, Jacques. Le Code de Hammourabi et la constitution originaire de la propriete dans l'ancienne Chaldee. (Revue historique. Paris, 1907. 8. v. 94, p. 272-289.</extension><space/>The code is also one of the earliest examples of the idea of<space/><link><target>presumption of innocence</target></link>, and it also suggests that both the accused and accuser have the opportunity to provide<space/><link><target>evidence</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Victimology: Theories and Applications, Ann Wolbert Burgess, Albert R. Roberts, Cheryl Regehr,Jones &amp; Bartlett Learning, 2009, p. 103</extension><space/>The occasional nature of many provisions suggests that the Code may be better understood as a codification of Hammurabi's supplementary judicial decisions, and that, by memorializing his wisdom and justice, its purpose may have been the self-glorification of Hammurabi rather than a modern legal code or constitution. However, its copying in subsequent generations indicates that it was used as a model of legal and judicial reasoning.<extension extension_name='ref'>For this alternative interpretation see Jean Bottro, &quot;The 'Code' of Hammurabi&quot; in<space/><italics>Mesopotamia: Writing, Reasoning and the Gods</italics><space/>(University of Chicago, 1992), pp. 156184.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other copies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hammurabi stele amnh ny.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Hammurabi stele at<space/><link><target>American Museum of Natural History</target></link>, New York, 2012.</part></link><link><target>File:Hammurabi code Istanbul.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A version of the Code at the<space/><link><target>Istanbul Archaeological Museums</target></link></part></link>Various copies of portions of the Code of Hammurabi have been found on baked clay tablets, some possibly older than the celebrated basalt stele now in the Louvre. The Prologue of the Code of Hammurabi (the first 305 inscribed squares on the stele) is on such a tablet, also at the Louvre (Inv #AO 10237). Some gaps in the list of benefits bestowed on cities recently annexed by Hammurabi may imply that it is older than the famous stele (it is currently dated to the early 18th century BC).<extension extension_name='ref'>Fant, Clyde E. and Mitchell G. Reddish (2008),<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=Dj6zVQJz7zYC&amp;amp;pg=PA62&amp;amp;lpg=PA62&amp;amp;dq=%22Code+of+Hammurabi%22+AND+2358&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=h-WEMEm_S7&amp;amp;sig=otruVc43aRR7ge-2v-78tcMQih8&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=tU1iSrvWNdmOtgfjr9EC&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=3'>''Lost Treasures of the Bible: Understanding the Bible Through Archaeological Artifacts in World Museums''</link>, Wm. B. Eerdmans Publishing Co., pg 62.</extension><space/>Likewise, the<space/><link><target>Museum of the Ancient Orient</target></link>, part of the<space/><link><target>Istanbul Archaeology Museums</target></link>, also has a &quot;Code of Hammurabi&quot; clay tablet, dated to 1750 BC, in (Room 5, Inv # Ni 2358).<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>John Freely</target><part>Freely, John</part></link>,<space/><italics>Blue Guide Istanbul</italics><space/>(5th ed., 2000),<space/><link><target>London</target></link>:<space/><link><target>A&amp;C Black</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New York</target></link>:<space/><link><target>WW Norton</target></link>, pg 121. (&quot;The most historic of the inscriptions here [i.e., Room 5, Museum of the Ancient Orient, Istanbul] is the famous Code of Hammurabi (#Ni 2358) dated 1750 BC, the world's oldest recorded set of laws.&quot;)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://english.istanbul.gov.tr/Default.aspx?pid=13150'>Museum of the Ancient Orient website</link><space/>(&quot;This museum contains a rich collection of ancient ... archaeological finds, including ... seals from Nippur and a copy of the Code of Hammurabi.&quot;)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July, 2010, archaeologists reported that a fragmentary Akkadian cuneiform tablet was discovered at<space/><link><target>Tel Hazor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>, containing a c. 1700 BC text that was said to be partly parallel to portions of the Hammurabi code. The Hazor law code fragments are currently being prepared for publication by a team from the<space/><link><target>Hebrew University of Jerusalem</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.israelnationalnews.com/News/News.aspx/138788'>Tablet Discovered by Hebrew U Matches Code of Hammurabi</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Laws covered</heading><paragraph><template><target>external media</target><arg name="width"><space/>210px<space/></arg><arg name="align"><space/>right<space/></arg><arg name="headerimage"><space/>[[File:P1050763 Louvre code Hammurabi face rwk.JPG|210px]]<space/></arg><arg name="video1"><space/>[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg></template>The laws covered such subjects as:</paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Slander</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #127: &quot;If any one &quot;point the finger&quot; at a sister of a god or the wife of any one, and can not prove it, this man shall be taken before the judges and his brow shall be marked. (by cutting the skin, or perhaps hair.)&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code">&quot;The Code of Hammurabi&quot;. Internet Sacred Text Archive. Evinity Publishing INC, 2011. Web. 17. Nov. 2013. &lt;http://www.sacred-texts.com/ane/ham/ham06.htm&gt;</extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Trade</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #265: &quot;If a herdsman, to whose care cattle or sheep have been entrusted, be guilty of fraud and make false returns of the natural increase, or sell them for money, then shall he be convicted and pay the owner ten times the loss.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Slavery</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #15: &quot;If any one take a male or female slave of the court, or a male or female slave of a freed man, outside the city gates, he shall be put to death.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>The duties of workers</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #42: &quot;If any one take over a field to till it, and obtain no harvest therefrom, it must be proved that he did no work on the field, and he must deliver grain, just as his neighbor raised, to the owner of the field.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Theft</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #22: &quot;If any one is committing a robbery and is caught, then he shall be put to death.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Food</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #104: &quot;If a merchant give an agent corn, wool, oil, or any other goods to transport, the agent shall give a receipt for the amount, and compensate the merchant therefor. Then he shall obtain a receipt from the merchant for the money that he gives the merchant.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Liability</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #53: &quot;If any one be too lazy to keep his dam in proper condition, and does not so keep it; if then the dam break and all the fields be flooded, then shall he in whose dam the break occurred be sold for money, and the money shall replace the corn which he has caused to be ruined.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Divorce</defkey></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #142: &quot;If a woman quarrel with her husband, and say: &quot;You are not congenial to me,&quot; the reasons for her prejudice must be presented. If she is guiltless, and there is no fault on her part, but he leaves and neglects her, then no guilt attaches to this woman, she shall take her dowry and go back to her father's house.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>One of the best known laws from Hammurabi's code was:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Ex. Law #196: &quot;If a man destroy the eye of another man, they shall destroy his eye. If one break a man's bone, they shall break his bone. If one destroy the eye of a freeman or break the bone of a freeman he shall pay one gold mina. If one destroy the eye of a man's slave or break a bone of a man's slave he shall pay one-half his price.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Code"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Hammurabi had many other punishments as well. If a son strikes his father, his hands shall be hewn off (translations vary).<extension extension_name='ref' name="king translation">Translated by L. W. King, Hammurabi's Code of Laws,<space/><link type='external' href='http://eawc.evansville.edu/anthology/hammurabi.htm'>''Hammurabi's Code of Laws''</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="harper translation">Translated by L. W. King, Hammurabi's Code of Laws,<space/><link><target>Media:The code of Hammurabi.pdf</target><part>The Code of Hammurabi King of Babylon</part></link><space/>by Robert Francis Harper (PDF)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Law</arg><arg>Ancient Near East</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Babylonian law</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Code of the Assura</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Code of Ur-Nammu</target></link><space/>the oldest known tablet containing a law code surviving today, it predates the Code of Hammurabi by some 300 years</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cuneiform Law</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hippocratic Oath</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of ancient legal codes</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quid pro quo</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Urukagina</target></link><space/>Sumerian king and creator of what is sometimes cited as the first example of a legal code in recorded history.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold><link><target>Editio princeps</target></link></bold>:<space/><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="chapter">Code des Lois de Hammurabi</arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/stream/mmoires04franuoft#page/11/mode/1up</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Jean-Vincent Scheil</arg><arg name="first">Jean-Vincent</arg><arg name="last">Scheil</arg><arg name="volume">4 (Textes Elamites-Semitiques)</arg><arg name="title">Memoires de la delegation en Perse</arg><arg name="date">1902</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Driver, G.R. & J.C. Miles<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Babylonian Laws<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wipf and Stock</arg><arg name="location">Eugene</arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-55635-229-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Roth</arg><arg name="first">Martha T.</arg><arg name="title">Law Collections from Mesopotamia and Asia Minor</arg><arg name="publisher">Scholars Press</arg><arg name="location"><space/>Atlanta<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7885-0378-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Bryant<space/></arg><arg name="first">Tamera</arg><arg name="title">The Life & Times of Hammurabi</arg><arg name="publisher">Mitchell Lane Publishers</arg><arg name="location">Bear</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-58415-338-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Mieroop</arg><arg name="first">Marc</arg><arg name="title">King Hammurabi of Babylon: a Biography<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Blackwell Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Cambridge</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4051-2660-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Hammurabi</arg><arg name="first">King</arg><arg name="author2">C. H. W. Johns (Translator)</arg><arg name="title">The Oldest Code of Laws in the World</arg><arg name="publisher">Lawbook Exchange Ltd</arg><arg name="location">City</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-58477-061-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Falkenstein, A. (195657).<space/><italics>Die neusumerischen Gerichtsurkunden IIII</italics>. Mnchen.</listitem><listitem>Elsen-Novk, G./Novk, M.:<space/><italics>Der 'Knig der Gerechtigkeit'. Zur Ikonologie und Teleologie des 'Codex' Hammurapi.</italics><space/>In: Baghdader Mitteilungen 37 (2006), pp.&amp;nbsp;131156.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Julius Oppert</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Joachim Menant</target></link><space/>(1877).<space/><italics>Documents juridiques de l'Assyrie et de la Chaldee</italics>. Pars.</listitem><listitem>Thomas, D. Winton, ed. (1958).<space/><italics>Documents from Old Testament Times</italics>. London and New York.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Beck</arg><arg name="first">Roger B.</arg><arg name="authorlink"></arg><arg name="author2"><space/>Linda Black, Larry S. Krieger, Phillip C. Naylor, Dahia Ibo Shabaka,</arg><arg name="title">World History: Patterns of Interaction</arg><arg name="publisher">McDougal Littell</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="location">Evanston, IL</arg><arg name="pages"></arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="doi"></arg><arg name="isbn">0-395-87274-X<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Codex Hammurabi</arg></template><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>Hammurabi</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.general-intelligence.com/library/hr.pdf'>The Code of Hammurabi Translated by L. W. King</link>.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.louvre.fr/en/oeuvre-notices/law-code-hammurabi-king-babylon'>Law Code of Hammurabi, king of Babylon | Muse du Louvre</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://fancyfrindle.com/the-code-of-hammurabi-a-king-with-rules/'>The Code of Hammurabi: A King with Rules</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://oll.libertyfund.org/index.php?option=com_staticxt&amp;amp;staticfile=show.php%3Ftitle=1276&amp;amp;Itemid=27'>Complete 1904 English translation of the Code of Hammurabi</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cliojournal.wikispaces.com/Hammurabi%27s+Code'>Hammurabi's Code</link>, Blaise Joseph,<space/><italics>Clio History Journal</italics>, 2009.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Code Of Hammurabi</target></template><link><target>Category:Legal codes</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Near East law</target></link><link><target>Category:Babylonia</target></link><link><target>Category:Manuscripts</target></link><link><target>Category:Codes of conduct</target></link><link><target>Category:Antiquities of the Louvre</target></link><link><target>Category:Bronze Age literature</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century BC works</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Near East steles</target></link><link><target>Category:2nd-millennium BC steles</target></link><link><target>Category:Akkadian inscriptions</target></link><link><target>Category:Slavery law</target></link></paragraph></article>