<article title='Elizabeth_Garrett_Anderson'><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Infobox medical person</target><arg name="name"><space/>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson (1900 portrait).jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>A portrait of Garrett Anderson circa 1900, by [[John Singer Sargent]]
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Elizabeth Garrett
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1836|6|9|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Whitechapel]], London, England
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1917|12|17|1836|6|9|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="profession"><space/>[[Physician]]
</arg><arg name="specialism">
</arg><arg name="research_field"><space/>
</arg><arg name="known_for"><space/>First woman to gain a medical qualification in Britain<br>Creating a medical school for women
</arg><arg name="years_active">
</arg><arg name="education"><space/>Studied privately with physicians in London hospitals<space/><br>[[Society of Apothecaries]]
</arg><arg name="work_institutions"><space/>[[New Hospital for Women]]<br>[[London School of Medicine for Women]]
</arg><arg name="prizes"><space/>
</arg><arg name="relations"><space/>James Anderson (husband)<space/><br><space/>[[Louisa Garrett Anderson]] (daughter)<space/><br><space/>[[Alan Garrett Anderson]] (son)<space/><br><space/>[[Millicent Fawcett|Millicent Garrett Fawcett]] (sister)<space/><br><space/>[[Newson Garrett]] (father)
</arg></template><bold>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson,</bold><space/><link><target>Worshipful Society of Apothecaries</target><part>LSA</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Doctor of Medicine</target><part>MD</part></link><space/>(9 June 1836&amp;nbsp; 17 December 1917), was an English<space/><link><target>physician</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>feminist</target></link>, the first Englishwoman to qualify as a physician and surgeon in<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target><part>Britain</part></link>, the co-founder of the first hospital staffed by women, the first<space/><link><target>Dean (education)</target><part>dean</part></link><space/>of a British medical school, the first female doctor of medicine in France, the first woman in Britain to be elected to a school board and, as Mayor of<space/><link><target>Aldeburgh</target></link>, the first female mayor and magistrate in Britain.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early life</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:My father and mother in their old age.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Her parents, Newson and Louisa Garrett in their old age; from ''What I Remember'' by<space/><link><target>Millicent Garrett Fawcett</target></link></part></link>Elizabeth Garrett was born on 9 June 1836 in<space/><link><target>Whitechapel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>London</target></link>, the second of twelve children of<space/><link><target>Newson Garrett</target></link><space/>(18121893), from<space/><link><target>Leiston</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Suffolk</target></link>, and his wife, Louisa<space/><template><target>ne</target></template><space/>Dunnell (18131903), from London.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 20</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Garrett ancestors had been ironworkers in<space/><link><target>East Suffolk</target></link><space/>since the early seventeenth century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 17</extension><space/>Newson was the youngest of three sons and not academically inclined, although he possessed the familys entrepreneurial spirit. When he finished school, the town of Leiston offered little to Newson, so he left for London to make his fortune. There, he fell in love with his brother's sister-in-law, Louisa Dunnell, the daughter of an innkeeper of Suffolk origin. After their wedding, the couple went to live in a<space/><link><target>pawnbroker</target></link>'s shop at 1<space/><link><target>Commercial Road</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Whitechapel</target></link>. The Garretts had their first three children in quick succession: Louie, Elizabeth and their brother (Newson Dunnell) who died at the age of six months. While Louisa grieved the loss of her third child, it was not easy to raise their two daughters in the London of that time.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 22</extension><space/>When Garrett was 3 years old, the family moved to 142<space/><link><target>Long Acre</target></link>, where they were to live for 2 years, whilst two more children were born and her father moved up in the world, becoming not only the manager of a larger pawnbroker's shop, but also a silversmith.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 23</extension><space/>Garrett's grandfather, owner of the family engineering works,<space/><link><target>Richard Garrett &amp; Sons</target></link>, had died in 1837, leaving the business to his eldest son, Garrett's uncle. Despite his lack of capital, Newson was determined to be successful and in 1841, at the age of 29, he moved his family to Suffolk, where he bought a barley and coal merchants business in<space/><link><target>Snape, Suffolk</target><part>Snape</part></link>, constructing<space/><link><target>Snape Maltings</target></link>, a fine range of buildings for malting barley.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 25</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Garretts lived in a square Georgian house opposite the church in<space/><link><target>Aldeburgh</target></link><space/>until 1852. Newson's malting business expanded and five more children were born, Alice (1842),<space/><link><target>Millicent Garrett Fawcett</target><part>Millicent</part></link><space/>(1847), who was to become a leader in the constitutional campaign for women's suffrage, Sam (1850), Josephine (1853) and George (1854). By 1850, Newson was a prosperous businessman and was able to build Alde House, a mansion on a hill behind Aldeburgh. A by-product of the industrial revolution,<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 28</extension><space/>Garrett grew up in an atmosphere of triumphant economic pioneering and the Garrett children were to grow up to become achievers in the professional classes of late-Victorian England. Garrett was encouraged to take an interest in local politics and, contrary to practices at the time, was allowed the freedom to explore the town with its nearby salt-marshes, beach and the small port of<space/><link><target>Slaughden</target></link><space/>with its boatbuilders' yards and sailmakers' lofts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 2832</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early education</heading><paragraph>There was no school in Aldeburgh so Garrett learned<space/><link><target>the three Rs</target></link><space/>from her mother. When she was 10 years old, a governess, Miss Edgeworth, a poor gentlewoman, was employed to educate Garrett and her sister. Mornings were spent in the schoolroom; there were regimental afternoon walks; educating the young ladies continued at mealtimes when Edgeworth ate with the family; at night, the governess slept in a curtained off area in the girls' bedroom. Garrett despised her governess and sought to outwit the teacher in the classroom.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 3233</extension><space/>When Garrett was 13 and her sister 15, they were sent to a private school, the Boarding School for Ladies in Blackheath, London, which was run by the step aunts of the poet<space/><link><target>Robert Browning</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 33</extension><space/>There, English literature, French, Italian and German as well as deportment, were taught.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Eganderson.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A portrait of Garrett in the 1860s</part></link>Later in life, Garrett recalled the stupidity of her teachers there, though her schooling there did help establish a love of reading.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 35-36</extension><space/>Her main complaint about the school was the lack of science and mathematics instruction.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><space/>Her reading matter included<space/><link><target>Alfred Tennyson, 1st Baron Tennyson</target><part>Tennyson</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Wordsworth</target></link>, Milton,<space/><link><target>Samuel Taylor Coleridge</target><part>Coleridge</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Trollope</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Thackeray</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>George Eliot</target></link>. Elizabeth and Louie were known as the bathing Garretts, as their father had insisted they be allowed a hot bath once a week.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 3536</extension><space/>However, they made what were to be lifelong friends there. When they finished in 1851, they were sent on a short tour abroad, ending with a memorable visit to the<space/><link><target>Great Exhibition</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Hyde Park, London</target><part>Hyde Park</part></link>, London.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After this formal education, Garrett spent the next nine years tending to domestic duties, but she continued to study Latin and arithmetic in the mornings and also read widely. Her sister Millicent recalled Garrett's weekly lectures, Talks on Things in General, when her younger siblings would gather her while she discussed politics and current affairs from<space/><link><target>Garibaldi</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>The History of England from the Accession of James the Second</target><part>Macaulay's ''History of England''</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 44</extension><space/>In 1854, when she was eighteen, Garrett and her sister went on a long visit to their school friends, Jane and Anne Crow, in<space/><link><target>Gateshead</target></link><space/>where she met<space/><link><target>Emily Davies</target></link>, the early feminist and future co-founder of<space/><link><target>Girton College</target></link>, Cambridge. Davies was to be a lifelong friend and confidante, always ready to give sound advice during the important decisions of Garretts career. It may have been in the<space/><italics><link><target>English Woman's Journal</target></link></italics>, first issued in 1858, that Garrett first read of<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Blackwell</target></link>, who had become the first female doctor in the United States in 1849.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><space/>When Blackwell visited London in 1859, Garrett travelled to the capital. By then, her sister Louie was married and living in London. Garrett joined the<space/><link><target>Society for Promoting the Employment of Women</target></link>, which organised Blackwell's lectures on &quot;Medicine as a Profession for Ladies&quot; and set up a private meeting between Garrett and the doctor.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 5052</extension><space/>It is said that during a visit to Alde House around 1860, one evening while sitting by the fireside, Garrett and Davies selected careers for advancing the frontiers of women's rights; Garrett was to open the medical profession to women, Davies the doors to a university education for women, while 13-year-old Millicent was allocated politics and votes for women.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 72</extension><space/>At first Newson was opposed to the radical idea of his daughter becoming a physician but came round and agreed to do all in his power, both financially and otherwise, to support Garrett.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 7376</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Medical education</heading><paragraph>After an initial unsuccessful visit to leading doctors in<space/><link><target>Harley Street</target></link>, Garrett decided to first spend six months as a surgery nurse at<space/><link><target>Middlesex Hospital</target></link>, London in August 1860.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 8293</extension><space/>On proving to be a good nurse, she was allowed to attend an outpatients' clinic, then her first operation. She unsuccessfully attempted to enroll in the hospital's Medical School but was allowed to attend private tuition in Latin, Greek and<space/><italics><link><target>materia medica</target></link></italics><space/>with the hospital's apothecary, while continuing her work as a nurse. She also employed a tutor to study anatomy and physiology three evenings a week. Eventually she was allowed into the dissecting room and the chemistry lectures. Gradually, Garrett became an unwelcome presence among the male students, who in 1861 presented a memorial to the school against her admittance as a fellow student, despite the support she enjoyed from the administration.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 104110</extension><space/>She was obliged to leave the Middlesex Hospital but she did so with an honours certificate in chemistry and<space/><italics>materia medica</italics>. Garrett then applied to several medical schools, including Oxford, Cambridge, Glasgow, Edinburgh,<space/><link><target>University of St Andrews</target><part>St Andrews</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Royal College of Surgeons</target></link>, all of which refused her admittance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 114115</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A companion to her in this struggle was the lesser known<space/><link><target>Sophia Jex-Blake</target><part>Dr Sophia Jex-Blake</part></link>. Whilst both are considered &quot;outstanding&quot; medical figures of the late 19th century, Anderson was able to obtain her credentials by way of a &quot;side door&quot; through a loophole in admissions at the Society of Apothecaries.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jstor.org"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Annie G.</arg><arg name="first1">Porritt</arg><arg name="title">Reviewed Work: The Life of Sophia Jex-Blake. by Margaret Todd</arg><arg name="journal">Political Science Quarterly</arg><arg name="date">1919</arg><arg name="volume">34</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="page">180</arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org/stable/2141537</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 March 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Having privately obtained a certificate in anatomy and physiology and in 1862, she was finally admitted by the<space/><link><target>Society of Apothecaries</target></link><space/>who, as a condition of their charter, could not legally exclude her on account of her sex.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jstor.org"></extension><space/>She continued her battle to qualify by studying privately with various professors, including some at the University of St Andrews, the Edinburgh Royal Maternity and the<space/><link><target>London Hospital Medical School</target></link>.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1865, she finally took her exam and obtained a licence (LSA) from the Society of Apothecaries to practise medicine, the first woman qualified in Britain to do so (previously there was Dr<space/><link><target>James Barry (surgeon)</target><part>James Barry</part></link><space/>who was assigned a female gender at birth but lived his adult life as a man). On the day, three out of seven candidates passed the exam, Garrett with the highest marks.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 162163</extension><space/>The Society of Apothecaries immediately amended its regulations to prevent other women obtaining a licence<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 176</extension><space/>meaning that Jex-Blake however could not follow this same path; the new rule disallowed privately educated women to be eligible for examination.<extension extension_name='ref' name="jstor.org"></extension><space/>It was not until 1876 that the new<space/><link><target>UK Medical Act of 1876</target><part>Medical Act</part></link><space/>(39 and 40 Vict, Ch. 41) passed which allowed British medical authorities to license all qualified applicants whatever their gender.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">British Medical Journal</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1908</arg><arg name="publisher">British Medical Association</arg><arg name="pages">1079–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Ph.D.2014"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">John A. Wagner Ph.D.</arg><arg name="title">Voices of Victorian England: Contemporary Accounts of Daily Life</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="date">25 February 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">ABC-CLIO</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-313-38689-3</arg><arg name="pages">211–</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Commons1892"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Great Britain. Parliament. House of Commons</arg><arg name="title">Parliamentary Papers, House of Commons and Command</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">1892</arg><arg name="publisher">H.M. Stationery Office</arg><arg name="pages">40–</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Career</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Elizabeth Garrett Anderson before the Faculty of Medicine, Paris.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Garrett before the<space/><link><target>University of Sorbonne</target><part>Faculty of Medicine, Paris</part></link></part></link>Though she was now a licentiate of the Society of Apothecaries, as a woman, Garrett could not take up a medical post in any hospital. So in late 1865, Garrett opened her own practice at 20 Upper Berkeley Street, London.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 167169</extension><space/>At first, patients were scarce but the practice gradually grew. After six months in practice, she wished to open an outpatients dispensary, to enable poor women to obtain medical help from a qualified practitioner of their own gender. In 1865, there was outbreak of cholera in Britain, affecting both rich and poor, and in their panic, some people forgot any prejudices they had in relation to a female physician. The first death due to cholera occurred in 1866, but by then Garrett had already opened St Mary's Dispensary for Women and Children, at 69 Seymour Place.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 173</extension><space/>In the first year, she tended to 3,000 new patients, who made 9,300 outpatient visits to the dispensary.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 175</extension><space/>On hearing that the Dean of the faculty of medicine at the<space/><link><target>University of Sorbonne</target></link>, Paris was in favour of admitting women as medical students, Garrett studied French so that she could apply for a medical degree, which she obtained in 1870 after some difficulty.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/wales/mid/sites/brecon_life/pages/franceshoggan.shtml'>Pioneering Physician</link>, BBC, Last updated: 2 January 2008</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Elizabeth Garrett Anderson, M.D.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Caricature of Garrett Anderson published in 1872</part></link>The same year she was elected to the first<space/><link><target>London School Board</target></link>, an office newly opened to women; Garrett's was the highest vote among all the candidates. Also in that year, she was made one of the visiting physicians of the East London Hospital for Children, becoming the first woman in Britain to be appointed to a medical post,<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 193195</extension><space/>but she found the duties of these two positions to be incompatible with her principal work in her private practice and the dispensary, as well as her role as a new mother, so she resigned from these posts by 1873.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 235</extension><space/>In 1872, the dispensary became the<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson and Obstetric Hospital</target><part>New Hospital for Women and Children</part></link>, treating women from all over London for gynaecological conditions; the hospital moved to new premises in Marylebone Street in 1874. Around this time, Garrett also entered into discussion with male medical views regarding women. In 1874,<space/><link><target>Henry Maudsley</target></link>s article on Sex and Mind in Education appeared, which argued that education for women caused over-exertion and thus reduced their reproductive capacity, sometimes causing nervous and even mental disorders.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 236</extension><space/>Garretts counter-argument was that the real danger for women was not education but boredom and that fresh air and exercise were preferable to sitting by the fire with a novel.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 237</extension><space/>In the same year, she co-founded London School of Medicine for Women with<space/><link><target>Sophia Jex-Blake</target></link><space/>and became a lecturer in what was the only teaching hospital in Britain to offer courses for women.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 241243</extension><space/>She continued to work there for the rest of her career and was dean of the school from 1883 to 1902. This school was later called the Royal Free Hospital of Medicine,<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 308</extension><space/>which later became part of what is now the medical school of<space/><link><target>University College London</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>BMA membership</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Elizabeth Garrett Anderson.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Garrett Anderson circa 1889</part></link><link><target>File:Lady mayoress.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>Garrett Anderson as mayor of<space/><link><target>Aldeburgh</target></link>, November 1908</part></link>In 1873 she gained membership of the<space/><link><target>British Medical Association</target></link><space/>and remained the only female member for 19 years, due to the Association's vote against the admission of further women&amp;nbsp; &quot;one of several instances where Garrett, uniquely, was able to enter a hitherto all male medical institution which subsequently moved formally to exclude any women who might seek to follow her.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="oxforddnb.com">M. A. Elston,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.oxforddnb.com/view/article/30406'>&quot;Anderson, Elizabeth Garrett (18361917)&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Oxford Dictionary of National Biography</target></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>, Sept 2004; online edn, Oct 2005.</extension><space/>In 1897, Garrett Anderson was elected president of the East Anglian branch of the British Medical Association.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 235236</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Garrett Anderson worked steadily at the development of the New Hospital for Women, and (from 1874) at the creation of the<space/><link><target>London School of Medicine for Women</target></link>, where she served as its dean.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Ogilvie</arg><arg name="first">Marilyn Bailey</arg><arg name="title">Women in science : antiquity through the nineteenth century : a biographical dictionary with annotated bibliography</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="publisher">MIT Press</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, Mass.</arg><arg name="isbn">0-262-15031-X</arg><arg name="edition">3. print.</arg></template></extension><space/>Both institutions have since been handsomely and suitably housed and equipped, the New Hospital for Women (in the<space/><link><target>Euston Road</target></link>) for many years being worked entirely by medical women, and the schools (in Hunter Street, WC1) having over 200 students, most of them preparing for the medical degree of London University (the present-day<space/><link><target>University College London</target></link>), which was opened to women in 1877.</paragraph><paragraph>On 9 November 1908, she was elected<space/><link><target>Mayors in England</target><part>mayor</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Aldeburgh</target></link>, the first female mayor in England. Her father was mayor in 1889.</paragraph><paragraph>She died in 1917 and is buried in the churchyard of<space/><link><target>St Peter and St Paul's Church, Aldeburgh</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="oxforddnb.com"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Womens Suffrage Movement</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Elizabeth Garrett Anderson; Emmeline Pankhurst.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Garrett Anderson with<space/><link><target>Emmeline Pankhurst</target></link><space/>on<space/><link><target>Black Friday (1910)</target><part>Black Friday</part></link>, 18 November 1910</part></link><link><target>File:Elizabeth Garrett Anderson NIH.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Garrett Anderson</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Garrett Anderson was also active in the women's suffrage movement. In 1866, Garrett Anderson and Davies presented petitions signed by more than 1,500 asking that female heads of household be given the vote.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 171</extension><space/>That year, Garrett Anderson joined the first<space/><link><target>British Women's Suffrage Committee</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><space/>She was not as active as her sister,<space/><link><target>Millicent Garrett Fawcett</target></link>, though Garrett Anderson became a member of the Central Committee of the National Society for Women's Suffrage in 1889. After her husband's death in 1907, she became more active. As mayor of Aldeburgh, she gave speeches for suffrage, before the increasing militant activity in the movement led to her withdrawal in 1911.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 338345</extension><space/>Her daughter<space/><link><target>Louisa Garrett Anderson</target><part>Louisa</part></link>, also a physician, was more active and more militant, spending time in prison in 1912 for her suffrage activities.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 345</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal life</heading><paragraph>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson once remarked that a doctor leads two lives, the professional and the private, and the boundaries between the two are never traversed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 261</extension><space/>In 1871, she married<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, pp. 217218</extension><space/>James George Skelton Anderson (d. 1907) of the<space/><link><target>Peninsular and Oriental Steam Navigation Company</target><part>Orient Steamship Company</part></link><space/>co-owned by his uncle<space/><link><target>Arthur Anderson (businessman)</target><part>Arthur Anderson</part></link>, but she did not give up her medical practice. She had three children,<space/><link><target>Louisa Garrett Anderson</target><part>Louisa</part></link><space/>(18731943), Margaret (18741875), who died of meningitis, and<space/><link><target>Alan Garrett Anderson</target><part>Alan</part></link><space/>(18771952). Louisa also became a pioneering doctor of medicine and feminist activist.</paragraph><paragraph>They retired to Aldeburgh in 1902,<extension extension_name='ref'>Manton, p. 331</extension><space/>moving to Alde House in 1903, after the death of Elizabeths mother. Skelton died of stroke in 1907.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ogilvie"></extension><space/>She enjoyed a happy marriage and in later life, devoted time to Alde House, gardening, and travelling with younger members of the extended family.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:The Garrett Anderson Centre, Ipswich Hospital - geograph.org.uk - 1238078.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Garrett Anderson Centre,<space/><link><target>Ipswich Hospital</target></link></part></link>The New Hospital for Women was renamed the<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Hospital</target></link><space/>in 1918 and amalgamated with the Obstetric Hospital in 2001 to form the Elizabeth Garrett Anderson and Obstetric Hospital<extension extension_name='ref' name="UCLH"><link type='external' href='http://www.uclh.nhs.uk/Our+hospitals/Elizabeth+Garrett+Anderson+and+Obstetric+Hospital.htm'>UCLH&amp;nbsp; Our hospitals&amp;nbsp; Elizabeth Garrett Anderson and Obstetric Hospital</link>. uclh.nhs.uk</extension><space/>before relocating to become the<space/><link><target>University College Hospital Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Wing</target></link><space/>at UCH.</paragraph><paragraph>The former Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Hospital buildings are incorporated into the new National Headquarters for the public service trade union<space/><link><target>UNISON</target></link>. The Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Gallery,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.egaforwomen.org.uk'>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Gallery</link></extension><space/>a permanent installation set within the restored hospital building, uses a variety of media to set the story of Garrett Anderson, her hospital, and women's struggle to achieve equality in the field of medicine within the wider framework of 19th and 20th century social history.</paragraph><paragraph>There is a secondary school for girls in Islington, London which is named after her;<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson School</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The archives of Elizabeth Garrett Anderson are held at<space/><link><target>The Women's Library</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.lse.ac.uk/library/Home.aspx'>Library of the London School of Economics</link>, ref<space/><link type='external' href='http://twl-calm.library.lse.ac.uk/CalmView/dserve.exe?dsqIni=Dserve.ini&amp;amp;dsqApp=Archive&amp;amp;dsqDb=Catalog&amp;amp;dsqCmd=Overview.tcl&amp;amp;dsqSearch=(RefNo=&#039;7EGA&#039;)'>7EGA</link>The archives of the Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Hospital (formerly the New Hospital for Women) are held at the<space/><link><target>London Metropolitan Archives</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cityoflondon.gov.uk/Corporation/LGNL_Services/Leisure_and_culture/Records_and_archives/records_held.htm'>Archives held at LMA</link>. ref H13/EGA. cityoflondon.gov.uk</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>more footnotes</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="ref">harv<space/></arg><arg name="last">Manton<space/></arg><arg name="first">Jo<space/></arg><arg name="year">1965<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Methuen</arg></template></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Attribution</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Anderson, Elizabeth Garrett</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Manton, Jo.<space/><italics>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson: England's First Woman Physician</italics>. Methuen, London 1965</listitem><listitem>Long, Tony, &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.wired.com/science/discoveries/news/2007/09/dayintech_0928'>28 Sep 1865: England Gets Its First Woman Physician, the Hard Way</link>,<space/><italics>Wired</italics>, 27 September 2007.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.francisboutle.co.uk/booklist/garrett/index.htm<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Crawford<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Elizabeth<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>20 September 2002<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Enterprising Women: The Garretts and their Circle<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Francis Boutle Publishers<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-903427-12-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.continuumbooks.com/Books/detail.aspx?ReturnURL</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Glynn<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jenifer<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Pioneering Garretts: Breaking the Barriers for Women<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-1-84725-207-4<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hambledon Continuum<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>15 January 2008</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Anonymous</arg><arg name="others">Illustrated by [[s:Author:Frederick Waddy|Frederick Waddy]]</arg><arg name="title">Cartoon portraits and biographical sketches of men of the day
</arg><arg name="url">http://en.wikisource.org/wiki/Cartoon_portraits_and_biographical_sketches_of_men_of_the_day/Dr._Garrett_Anderson
</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 January 2011</arg><arg name="year">1873</arg><arg name="publisher">Tinsley Brothers</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="pages">30–33</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson</arg></template><template><target>Americana Poster</target><arg>Garrett-Anderson, Elizabeth</arg><arg>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.spartacus-educational.com/WandersonE.htm'>Elizabeth Garrett Anderson</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/garrett_anderson_elizabeth.shtml'>BBC page on Elizabeth Garrett Anderson</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='https://secure.flickr.com/photos/richardjgibson/602289814/'>Picture of The United Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Hospital and Hospital for Women Soho, near Euston Station in London.</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Garrett Anderson, Elizabeth
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>English physician and feminist
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>9 June 1836
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Whitechapel]], London, England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>17 December 1917
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Garrett Anderson, Elizabeth</target></template><link><target>Category:19th-century English medical doctors</target></link><link><target>Category:English feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:British women medical doctors</target></link><link><target>Category:English suffragists</target></link><link><target>Category:Women of the Victorian era</target></link><link><target>Category:Mayors of places in Suffolk</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Aldeburgh</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Whitechapel</target></link><link><target>Category:1836 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Women mayors of places in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Members of the London School Board</target></link></paragraph></article>