<article title='Bookkeeping'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the computer programming concept</arg><arg>Bookkeeping code</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template><template><target>Bookkeeping</target></template><link><target>File:Pacioli.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>''Portrait of the Italian<space/><link><target>Luca Pacioli</target></link>'', painted by<space/><link><target>Jacopo de' Barbari</target></link>, 1495, (<link><target>Museo di Capodimonte</target></link>). Pacioli is regarded as the Father of Accounting and Bookkeeping.</part></link><bold>Bookkeeping</bold><space/>is the recording of financial transactions, and is part of the process of<space/><link><target>accounting</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>business</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Weygandt, Kieso, Kimmel (2003)"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Weygandt, Kieso, Kimmel</arg><arg name="title">Financial Accounting</arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Susan Elbe</arg><arg name="isbn">0-471-07241-9</arg><arg name="pages">6</arg></template></extension><space/>Transactions include purchases, sales, receipts, and payments by an individual person or an organization/corporation. There are several standard methods of bookkeeping, such as the<space/><link><target>single-entry bookkeeping system</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>double-entry bookkeeping system</target></link>, but, while they may be thought of as &quot;real&quot; bookkeeping, any process that involves the recording of financial transactions is a bookkeeping process.</paragraph><paragraph>Bookkeeping is usually performed by a<space/><bold>bookkeeper</bold>. A bookkeeper (or book-keeper) is a person who records the day-to-day financial transactions of a business. He or she is usually responsible for writing the<space/><italics>daybooks</italics>, which contain records of purchases, sales, receipts, and payments. The bookkeeper is responsible for ensuring that all transactions are recorded in the correct daybook, supplier's ledger, customer ledger, and<space/><link><target>general ledger</target></link>; an accountant can then create reports from the information concerning the financial transactions recorded by the bookkeeper.</paragraph><paragraph>The bookkeeper brings the books to the<space/><link><target>trial balance</target></link><space/>stage: an accountant may prepare the<space/><link><target>income statement</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>balance sheet</target></link><space/>using the trial balance and ledgers prepared by the bookkeeper.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;waste book&quot; was a term used in colonial America referring to bookkeeping. The purpose was to document daily transactions including receipts and expenditures. This was recorded in chronological order, and the purpose was for temporary use only. The daily transactions would then be recorded in a daybook or account ledger in order to balance an accounts. The name &quot;waste book&quot; comes from the fact that once the waste book's was transferred to the actual journal, the waste book could be discarded.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>Guides to Archives and Manuscript Collections at the University of Pittsburgh Library System<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Pittsburgh Waste Book and Fort Pitt Trading Post Papers<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://digital.library.pitt.edu/cgi-bin/f/findaid/findaid-idx?c</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-09-04<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Process</heading><paragraph>The bookkeeping process primarily records the<space/><italics>financial effects</italics><space/>of transactions. The difference between a manual and any electronic accounting system results from the former's<space/><link><target>latency (engineering)</target><part>latency</part></link><space/>between the recording of a financial transaction and its posting in the relevant account. This delayabsent in electronic accounting systems due to instantaneous posting into relevant accountsis a basic characteristic of manual systems, thus giving rise to primary books of accounts such as Cash Book, Bank Book, Purchase Book, and Sales Book for recording the immediate effect of a financial transaction.</paragraph><paragraph>In the normal course of business, a document is produced each time a transaction occurs. Sales and purchases usually have<space/><link><target>invoice</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>receipt</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Deposit slips are produced when lodgements (deposits) are made to a<space/><link><target>bank account</target></link>. Checks (spelled &quot;cheques&quot; in the UK and several other countries) are written to pay money out of the account. Bookkeeping first involves recording the details of all of these<space/><italics>source documents</italics><space/>into multi-column<space/><italics>journals</italics><space/>(also known as<space/><italics>books of first entry</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>daybooks</italics>). For example, all credit sales are recorded in the sales journal; all cash payments are recorded in the cash payments journal. Each column in a journal normally corresponds to an account. In the<space/><link><target>single-entry accounting system</target><part>single entry system</part></link>, each transaction is recorded only once. Most individuals who balance their check-book each month are using such a system, and most personal-finance software follows this approach.</paragraph><paragraph>After a certain period, typically a month, each column in each<space/><link><target>Journal entry</target><part>journal</part></link><space/>is totalled to give a summary for that period. Using the rules of double-entry, these journal summaries are then transferred to their respective accounts in the<space/><link><target>ledger</target></link>, or<space/><italics>account book</italics>. For example, the entries in the Sales Journal are taken and a debit entry is made in each customer's account (showing that the customer now owes us money), and a credit entry might be made in the account for &quot;Sale of class 2 widgets&quot; (showing that this activity has generated revenue for us). This process of transferring summaries or individual transactions to the ledger is called<space/><italics>posting</italics>. Once the posting process is complete, accounts kept using the &quot;T&quot; format undergo<space/><italics>balancing</italics>, which is simply a process to arrive at the balance of the account.</paragraph><paragraph>As a partial check that the posting process was done correctly, a working document called an<space/><italics>unadjusted trial balance</italics><space/>is created. In its simplest form, this is a three-column list. Column One contains the names of those accounts in the<space/><link><target>ledger</target></link><space/>which have a non-zero balance. If an account has a<space/><italics>debit</italics><space/>balance, the balance amount is copied into Column Two (the<space/><italics>debit column</italics>); if an account has a<space/><italics>credit</italics><space/>balance, the amount is copied into Column Three (the<space/><italics>credit column</italics>). The debit column is then totalled, and then the credit column is totalled. The two totals must agreewhich is not by chancebecause under the double-entry rules, whenever there is a posting, the debits of the posting equal the credits of the posting. If the two totals do not agree, an error has been made, either in the journals or during the posting process. The error must be located and rectified, and the totals of the debit column and the credit column recalculated to check for agreement before any further processing can take place.</paragraph><paragraph>Once the accounts balance, the accountant makes a number of adjustments and changes the balance amounts of some of the accounts. These adjustments must still obey the double-entry rule: for example, the<space/><italics><link><target>inventory</target></link></italics><space/>account and asset account might be changed to bring them into line with the actual numbers counted during a stocktake. At the same time, the<space/><italics>expense</italics><space/>account associated with usage of inventory is adjusted by an equal and opposite amount. Other adjustments such as posting<space/><link><target>depreciation</target></link><space/>and prepayments are also done at this time. This results in a listing called the<space/><italics>adjusted trial balance</italics>. It is the accounts in this list, and their corresponding debit or credit balances, that are used to prepare the financial statements.</paragraph><paragraph>Finally<space/><link><target>financial statement</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are drawn from the trial balance, which may include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>the<space/><link><target>income statement</target></link>, also known as the<space/><italics>statement of financial results</italics>,<space/><italics>profit and loss account</italics>, or<space/><italics>P&amp;L</italics></listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>balance sheet</target></link>, also known as the<space/><italics>statement of financial position</italics></listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>cash flow statement</target></link></listitem><listitem>the<space/><link><target>statement of retained earnings</target></link>, also known as the<space/><italics>statement of total recognised gains and losses</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>statement of changes in equity</italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Entry systems</heading><paragraph>Two common bookkeeping systems used by businesses and other organizations are the<space/><link><target>single-entry bookkeeping system</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>double-entry bookkeeping system</target></link>. Single-entry bookkeeping uses only income and expense<space/><link><target>Account (accountancy)</target><part>account</part><trail>s</trail></link>, recorded primarily in a revenue and expense journal. Single-entry bookkeeping is adequate for many small businesses. Double-entry bookkeeping requires posting (recording) each transaction twice, using<space/><link><target>debits and credits</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Single-entry system</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>single-entry bookkeeping system</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>The primary bookkeeping record in single-entry bookkeeping is the<space/><italics>cash book</italics>, which is similar to a checking account (UK: cheque account, current account) register, but allocates the income and expenses to various income and expense accounts. Separate account records are maintained for petty cash, accounts payable and receivable, and other relevant transactions such as<space/><link><target>inventory</target></link><space/>and travel expenses. These days, single-entry bookkeeping can be done with<space/><link><target>DIY</target></link><space/>bookkeeping software to speed up manual calculations.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Double-entry system</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>double-entry bookkeeping system</arg></template></paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>A<space/><italics>double-entry bookkeeping system</italics><space/>is a set of rules for recording financial information in a<space/><link><target>financial accounting</target></link><space/>system in which every transaction or event changes at least two different nominal<space/><link><target>ledger</target></link><space/>accounts.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Daybooks</heading><paragraph>A<space/><italics>daybook</italics><space/>is a descriptive and chronological (diary-like) record of day-to-day<space/><link><target>financial transactions</target></link><space/>also called a<space/><italics>book of original entry</italics>. The daybook's details must be entered formally into journals to enable posting to ledgers. Daybooks include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Sales daybook, for recording all the sales invoices.</listitem><listitem>Sales credits daybook, for recording all the sales credit notes.</listitem><listitem>Purchases daybook, for recording all the purchase invoices.</listitem><listitem>Purchases Debits daybook, for recording all the purchase Debit notes.</listitem><listitem>Cash daybook, usually known as the cash book, for recording all money received as well as money paid out. It may be split into two daybooks: receipts daybook for money received in, and payments daybook for money paid out.</listitem><listitem>General Journal daybook, for recording journals.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Petty cash book</heading><paragraph>A<space/><italics><link><target>petty cash</target></link></italics><space/>book is a record of small-value purchases before they are later transferred to the ledger and final accounts; it is maintained by a petty or junior cashier. This type of cash book usually uses the<space/><link><target>imprest system</target></link>: a certain amount of money is provided to the petty cashier by the senior cashier. This money is to cater for minor expenditures (hospitality, minor stationery, casual postage, and so on) and is reimbursed periodically on satisfactory explanation of how it was spent.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Journals</heading><paragraph><italics><link><target>Journal entry</target><part>Journals</part></link></italics><space/>are recorded in the general journal daybook. A journal is a formal and chronological record of<space/><link><target>financial transactions</target></link><space/>before their values are accounted for in the general ledger as<space/><link><target>debits and credits</target></link>. A company can maintain one journal for all transactions, or keep several journals based on similar activity (e.g., sales, cash receipts, revenue, etc.), making transactions easier to summarize and reference later. For every<space/><link><target>debits and credits</target><part>debit</part></link><space/>journal entry recorded, there must be an equivalent<space/><link><target>debits and credits</target><part>credit</part></link><space/>journal entry to maintain a balanced accounting equation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Haber<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jeffry<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Accounting Demystified<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>AMACOM<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2004<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8144-0790-0<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Ledgers</heading><paragraph>A<space/><italics><link><target>ledger</target></link></italics><space/>is a record of<space/><link><target>Account (accountancy)</target><part>accounts</part></link>. These accounts are recorded separately, showing their beginning/ending<space/><link><target>Balance (accounting)</target><part>balance</part></link>. A journal lists<space/><link><target>financial transactions</target></link><space/>in chronological order, without showing their balance but showing how much is going to be charged in each account. A ledger takes each financial transaction from the journal and records it into the corresponding account for every transaction listed. The ledger also sums up the total of every account, which is transferred into the<space/><link><target>balance sheet</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>income statement</target></link>. There are three different kinds of ledgers that deal with book-keeping:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Sales ledger, which deals mostly with the accounts receivable account. This ledger consists of the records of the financial transactions made by customers to the business.</listitem><listitem>Purchase ledger is the record of the purchasing transactions a company does; it goes hand in hand with the Accounts Payable account.</listitem><listitem>General ledger, representing the original five, main accounts:<space/><link><target>asset</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Liability (financial accounting)</target><part>liabilities</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Equity (finance)</target><part>equity</part></link>,<space/><link><target>income</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>expense</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Abbreviations used in bookkeeping</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>A/C Account</listitem><listitem>Acc Account</listitem><listitem>A/R Accounts receivable</listitem><listitem>A/P Accounts payable</listitem><listitem>B/S Balance sheet</listitem><listitem>c/d Carried down</listitem><listitem>b/d Brought down</listitem><listitem>c/f Carried forward</listitem><listitem>b/f Brought forward</listitem><listitem>Dr Debit</listitem><listitem>Cr Credit</listitem><listitem>G/L General ledger; (or N/L nominal ledger)</listitem><listitem>P&amp;L Profit and loss; (or I/S income statement)</listitem><listitem>P/R - Payroll</listitem><listitem>PP&amp;E Property, plant and equipment</listitem><listitem>TB Trial Balance</listitem><listitem>GST<space/><link><target>Goods and Services Tax (disambiguation)</target><part>Goods and services tax</part></link></listitem><listitem>VAT<space/><link><target>Value added tax</target></link></listitem><listitem>CST Central sale tax</listitem><listitem>TDS Tax deducted at source</listitem><listitem>AMT Alternate minimum tax</listitem><listitem>EBITDA Earnings before interest, taxes, depreciation and amortisation</listitem><listitem>EBDTA Earnings before depreciation, taxes and amortisation</listitem><listitem>EBT Earnings before tax</listitem><listitem>EAT Earnings after tax</listitem><listitem>PAT Profit after tax</listitem><listitem>PBT Profit before tax</listitem><listitem>Depr Depreciation</listitem><listitem>Dep Depreciation</listitem><listitem>CPO Cash paid out</listitem><listitem></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Chart of accounts</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>chart of accounts</target></link><space/>is a list of the<space/><link><target>Account (accountancy)</target><part>accounts</part></link><space/>codes that can be identified with numeric, alphabetical, or alphanumeric codes allowing the account to be located in the general ledger. The equity section of the chart of accounts is based on the fact that the legal structure of the entity is of a particular legal type. Possibilities include<space/><italics>sole trader</italics>,<space/><italics>partnership</italics>,<space/><italics>trust</italics>, and<space/><italics>company</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Marsden,Stephen (2008). Australian Master Bookkeepers Guide. Sydney: CCH ISBN = 978-1-921593-57-4</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Computerized bookkeeping</heading><paragraph>Computerized bookkeeping removes many of the paper &quot;books&quot; that are used to record the financial transactions of an entityinstead, relational databases take their place, but they still typically enforce the<space/><link><target>double-entry bookkeeping system</target></link><space/>and methodology.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Accountancy</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www..dx.am/'>Debt and credit in bookkeeping</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Accounting systems</target></link><link><target>Category:Accounting</target></link></paragraph></article>