<article title='Benny_Andersson'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox musical artist</target><arg name="name"><space/>Benny Andersson
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Benny Andersson 2012-09-24 001.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Andersson in September 2012
</arg><arg name="image_size"><space/>
</arg><arg name="background"><space/>solo_singer
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Göran Bror Andersson
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{Birth date and age|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Vällingby]], Stockholm, Sweden
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Composer, musician, producer, songwriter
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Folk rock]], [[Europop]], [[Swedish folk music|Swedish folk]], [[Euro disco]], [[schlager]]
</arg><arg name="years_active"><space/>1964–present
</arg><arg name="label"><space/>[[Polar Music]]
</arg><arg name="instrument"><space/>[[Accordion]], piano, keyboards, guitar, synthesiser, vocals, saxophone
</arg><arg name="associated_acts"><space/>[[ABBA]], [[Hep Stars]], [[Orsa Spelmän]], [[Björn Ulvaeus]]
</arg><arg name="website">
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Gran Bror &quot;Benny&quot; Andersson</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-sv</target><arg>ˈjœːɾan bɾuːɾ ˈbɛnʏ ˈandɛˌʂɔn</arg></template>) (born 16 December 1946), known professionally as<space/><bold>Benny Andersson</bold>, is a Swedish musician, composer, former member of the Swedish musical group<space/><link><target>ABBA</target></link><space/>(19721982), and co-composer of the musicals<space/><italics><link><target>Chess (musical)</target><part>Chess</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Kristina frn Duvemla</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Mamma Mia!</target></link></italics>. For the<space/><link><target>Mamma Mia! (film)</target><part>2008 film version of ''Mamma Mia!''</part></link><space/>he worked also as an executive producer. Since 2001 he is active with his own band the<space/><link><target>Benny Anderssons Orkester</target></link><space/>(BAO!).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early years</heading><paragraph>Goran Bror Andersson was born in<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>to 34-year-old civil engineer Gsta Andersson and his 26-year-old wife Laila. His sister Eva-Lis Andersson followed in 1948.</paragraph><paragraph>Andersson's musical background comes from his father and grandfather; they both enjoyed playing the<space/><link><target>accordion</target></link>, and at six, Benny got his own. Father Gsta and grandfather Efraim taught him Swedish<space/><link><target>folk music</target></link>,<space/><link><target>traditional music</target></link>, and the odd<space/><link><target>schlager</target></link>. Benny recalls the first records he bought were &quot;Du Bist Musik&quot; by Italian schlager singer<space/><link><target>Caterina Valente</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Elvis Presley</target></link>'s &quot;<link><target>Jailhouse Rock (song)</target><part>Jailhouse Rock</part></link>&quot;. He was especially impressed by the flip side &quot;Treat Me Nice&quot; as this featured a piano. This<space/><link><target>smrgsbord</target></link><space/>of different kinds of music was to influence and follow him through the years.</paragraph><paragraph>When Andersson was ten he got his own piano, and taught himself to play. He left school aged 15 and began to perform at youth clubs. This is when he met his first girlfriend Christina Grnvall, with whom he had two children: Peter (born 1963) and Helen (born 1965).</paragraph><paragraph>In early 1964, Benny and Christina joined &quot;Elverkets Spelmanslag&quot; (&quot;The Electricity Board Folk Music Group&quot;), the name was a punning reference to their electric instruments. The repertoire was mainly instrumentals, one of his numbers was &quot;<link><target>Baby Elephant Walk</target></link>&quot;, and he wrote his first songs.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The Hep Stars years (19641969)</heading><paragraph>In October 1964 he joined<space/><link><target>the Hep Stars</target></link><space/>as keyboardist and they made a breakthrough in March 1965 with their hit &quot;Cadillac&quot;, eventually becoming the most celebrated of the Swedish 1960s pop bands. Andersson consolidated his place as the band's keyboardist and musical driving force as well as a teen idol. The band performed mostly covers of international hits, but Andersson soon started writing his own material, and gave the band the classic hits &quot;No Response&quot;, &quot;Sunny Girl&quot;, &quot;Wedding&quot;, &quot;Consolation&quot;, &quot;It's Nice To Be Back&quot; and &quot;She Will Love You&quot; amongst others.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Before ABBA (19691972)</heading><paragraph>Andersson met<space/><link><target>Bjrn Ulvaeus</target></link><space/>in June 1966, and the two started writing songs together, their first being<space/><link type='external' href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mbEqcMOhU6k'>&quot;Isn't It Easy To Say&quot;</link>, eventually recorded by The Hep Stars. He also had a fruitful songwriting collaboration with<space/><link><target>Lasse Berghagen</target></link>, with whom he wrote several songs and submitted &quot;Hej, Clown&quot; for the 1969<space/><link><target>Melodifestivalen</target></link><space/>the Swedish<space/><link><target>Eurovision Song Festival</target></link><space/>finals. The song finished in second place. During this contest he met vocalist<space/><link><target>Anni-Frid Lyngstad</target></link>, and they soon became a couple. Around the same time his songwriting companion Ulvaeus met vocalist<space/><link><target>Agnetha Fltskog</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The personal relationships and Andersson and Ulvaeus' songwriting collaboration has led quite naturally to the very close co-operation which the four friends had during the following years. Benny and Bjrn scored their first hits as songwriters in the spring of 1969: &quot;<link><target>Ljuva sextital</target></link>&quot; (a hit with Brita Borg) and &quot;Speleman&quot; (a hit for The Hep Stars). As the two couples began supporting each other during recording sessions, the sound of the girls' voices convinced the songwriters to model their 'group' on various<space/><link><target>Middle of the road (music)</target><part>MOR</part></link><space/>acts such as<space/><link><target>Blue Mink</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Middle of the Road (band)</target><part>Middle of the Road</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>the Sweet</target></link>. Thus,<space/><link><target>ABBA</target></link><space/>came to life.</paragraph><heading level='2'>The ABBA years (19721982)</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>ABBA</arg></template>The foursome's breakthrough came with winning the<space/><link><target>Eurovision Song Contest</target></link><space/>for Sweden with &quot;<link><target>Waterloo (ABBA song)</target><part>Waterloo</part></link>&quot; on 6 April 1974. During the next eight years, Andersson (together with Ulvaeus) wrote music for and produced eight studio albums with ABBA. The group achieved great success globally and scored a chain of No. 1 hits.</paragraph><heading level='2'>After ABBA:<space/><italics>Chess</italics>,<space/><italics>Kristina</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Mamma Mia!</italics></heading><paragraph>After ABBA Andersson continued writing music with Ulvaeus. Their first project was the<space/><link><target>stage musical</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Chess (musical)</target><part>Chess</part></link></italics>, written with<space/><link><target>Tim Rice</target></link>. The<space/><italics>Chess</italics><space/>concept album with vocals by<space/><link><target>Elaine Paige</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Barbara Dickson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Murray Head</target></link><space/>and Swedes<space/><link><target>Tommy Krberg</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bjrn Skifs</target></link><space/>was released in October 1984, selling two million copies worldwide. The Paige/Dickson duet &quot;<link><target>I Know Him So Well</target></link>&quot; became a major UK No. 1 hit, and Murray Head's &quot;<link><target>One Night in Bangkok</target></link>&quot; gave Andersson/Ulvaeus a US No. 3 hit.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Chess</italics><space/>was staged in London's West End<space/><link><target>Prince Edward Theatre</target></link><space/>in May 1986 and received mixed to positive reviews, running for about three years. A revised staging on Broadway in April 1988 received poor reviews, running for two months.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1985, Andersson produced and released an album with brother and sister<space/><link><target>Anders Glenmark</target><part>Anders</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Karin Glenmark</target></link>, featuring new songs by Andersson/Ulvaeus. The duo named themselves<space/><link><target>Gemini (Swedish band)</target><part>Gemini</part></link>, and a second album with more music by Bjrn and Benny was released in April 1987, containing the big hit &quot;<link><target>Mio My Mio (song)</target><part>Mio My Mio</part></link>&quot;; also to be found on the soundtrack to the film<space/><italics><link><target>Mio in the Land of Faraway</target></link></italics>, for which Andersson co-produced the music.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1987, Andersson released his first solo album<space/><italics>Klinga Mina Klockor</italics><space/>(&quot;Chime, My Bells&quot;). All the music was written by and performed by himself on accordion, backed by the<space/><italics><link><target>Orsa Spelmn</target></link></italics><space/>(Orsa Folk Musicians) on fiddles. A second solo album followed:<space/><italics>November 1989</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1990, Andersson scored a Swedish #1 hit with &quot;Lassie&quot;, sung by female cabaret group<space/><link><target>Ainbusk</target></link>, for whom he also wrote the<space/><link><target>Svensktoppen</target></link><space/>hits &quot;lska Mig&quot; and &quot;Drmmarnas Golv&quot;. He decided to produce an album with<space/><link><target>Josefin Nilsson</target></link><space/>from this quartet, resulting in the 1993 English-language album<space/><italics>Shapes</italics>, featuring ten new Andersson/Ulvaeus compositions.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1992, he wrote the introduction melody for the European football championship, which was organised by Sweden that year.</paragraph><paragraph>From the late 1980s, Andersson had worked on an idea for an epic Swedish language musical based on his affection for traditional folk music, and in October 1995,<space/><italics><link><target>Kristina frn Duvemla</target></link></italics><space/>premiered in Sweden. The musical was based on<space/><italics><link><target>The Emigrants (novels)</target><part>The Emigrants</part></link></italics><space/>novels by Swedish writer<space/><link><target>Vilhelm Moberg</target></link>. The musical ran successfully for almost five years, before closing in June 1999. An English-language version, simply titled<space/><italics>Kristina</italics>, was staged in concert at<space/><link><target>Carnegie Hall</target></link><space/>in New York City for two nights in September 2009, yielding a live recording, and at the<space/><link><target>Royal Albert Hall</target></link><space/>for one night in April 2010.</paragraph><paragraph>Andersson's next project was<space/><italics><link><target>Mamma Mia!</target></link></italics>, a musical built around 24 of ABBA's songs, which has become a worldwide box-office blockbuster with versions in several languages currently being played in many countries, including the UK (West End premiere in April 1999), Canada (<link><target>Royal Alexandra Theatre</target><part>Toronto</part></link><space/>premiere in 2000), the USA (Broadway premiere in 2001), and Sweden (<link><target>Swedish language</target></link><space/>premiere in 2005).</paragraph><paragraph>For the 2004 semi-final of the<space/><link><target>Eurovision Song Contest</target></link>, staged in Istanbul thirty years after<space/><link><target>ABBA</target></link><space/>had won the contest in Brighton, Benny appeared briefly in a special comedy video made for the interval act, entitled &quot;Our Last Video&quot;. Each of the four members of the group appeared briefly in cameo roles, as did others such as<space/><link><target>Cher</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Rik Mayall</target></link>. The video was not included in the official DVD release of the Eurovision Contest, but was issued as a separate DVD release. It was billed as the first time the four had worked together since the group split; however, Frida's appearance was filmed separately.</paragraph><paragraph>A film version of<space/><italics><link><target>Mamma Mia!</target></link></italics><space/>premiered on 18 July 2008. In April/May 2007, Andersson worked on the film soundtrack, re-recording the old ABBA songs with musicians from the old ABBA recording sessions.<space/><italics><link><target>Mamma Mia! (film)</target><part>Mamma Mia! The Movie</part></link></italics><space/>has now become the most successful movie musical of all time and has been named the number one box office smash of 2008, and the biggest-selling DVD ever in the UK.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Benny Anderssons Orkester</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Benny Andersson Orkester.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part>Benny Andersson Orchestra at a concert in Minnesota in 2006.</part></link>Andersson currently performs with his own band of 16 musicians,<space/><link><target>Benny Anderssons Orkester</target><part>BAO</part></link>;<space/><italics>&quot;<bold>B</bold>enny<space/><bold>A</bold>nderssons<space/><bold>O</bold>rkester&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;Benny Andersson's orchestra&quot;), utilising the vocal talents of fellow Swedes<space/><link><target>Helen Sjholm</target></link><space/>(from<space/><italics>Kristina from Duvemla</italics>) and<space/><link><target>Tommy Krberg</target></link><space/>(of<space/><italics>Chess</italics><space/>fame), with lyrics to new material sometimes written by his song-writing partner and best friend of 40 years, Bjrn Ulvaeus. BAO has released five albums to huge success in Sweden, all containing hit singles.</paragraph><paragraph>BAO recently achieved a new record in Sweden on the<space/><link><target>Svensktoppen</target></link><space/>chart by staying there for 243 weeks with the song<space/><italics>Du r min man</italics><space/>(&quot;You Are My Man&quot;), sung by<space/><link><target>Helen Sjholm</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.sr.se/cgi-bin/p4/programsidor/artikel.asp?ProgramID=2023&amp;amp;Artikel=454899'>''Rekord p Svensktoppen''</link>,<space/><link><target>Sveriges Radio</target></link>. Retrieved 5 April 2009.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>New compositions</heading><paragraph>Andersson composes primarily for his 'band' BAO! with the vocalists Sjholm and Krberg, but keeps his older material alive through re-visiting it, like the staging of 'Mamma Mia!' and the Swedish version of 'Chess'.</paragraph><paragraph>For a compilation album of the Glenmark duo<space/><link><target>Gemini (Swedish band)</target><part>Gemini</part></link>, Andersson had Bjrn Ulvaeus write new Swedish lyrics for the re-recording of two songs from 1984 and 1987.Andersson and Ulvaeus have continuously been writing new material; most recently the two wrote seven songs for Andersson's 'BAO' 2011 album<space/><italics>O Klang Och Jubeltid</italics>, performed as usual by vocalists Sjholm, Krberg and Moreus. In July 2009, BAO, now named &quot;The Benny Andersson Band&quot;, released their first international record, the album<space/><italics>The Story of a Heart</italics>. It was a compilation of 14 tracks from Andersson's five Swedish-language releases between 1987 and 2007, including five songs now recorded with lyrics by Ulvaeus in English, and the new title song premiered on BBC2's<space/><italics>Ken Bruce Show</italics>. A Swedish-language version of the title track,<space/><italics>&quot;Sommaren Du Fick&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;The Summer You Got&quot;), was released as a single in Sweden prior to the English version, with vocals by Helen Sjholm.</paragraph><paragraph>In the spring of 2009, Andersson also released a single recorded by the staff at his privately owned<space/><link><target>Stockholm</target></link><space/>hotel<space/><italics>Hotel Rival</italics>, titled &quot;<link><target>2nd Best to None</target></link>&quot;, accompanied by a video showing the staff at work. In 2008, Andersson and Ulvaeus wrote a song for Swedish singer<space/><link><target>Sissela Kyle</target></link>, titled<space/><italics>&quot;Jag vill bli gammal&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;I Wanna Grow Old&quot;), for her Stockholm stage show<space/><italics>&quot;Your Days Are Numbered&quot;</italics>, which was never recorded and released, but did get a TV performance. Ulvaeus also contributed lyrics to ABBA's 1976 instrumental track &quot;Arrival&quot; for<space/><link><target>Sarah Brightman</target></link>'s cover version recorded for her 2008 album<space/><italics><link><target>Winter Symphony</target></link></italics>. New English lyrics have also been written for Andersson's 1999 song<space/><italics>&quot;Innan Gryningen&quot;</italics><space/>(then also named &quot;Millennium Hymn&quot;), with the new title &quot;The Silence of the Dawn&quot; for<space/><link><target>Barbara Dickson</target></link><space/>was performed live, but not yet recorded and released. In 2007, they wrote the new song<space/><italics>&quot;Han som har vunnit allt&quot;</italics><space/>(&quot;He Who's Won It All&quot;) for actor/singer<space/><link><target>Anders Ekborg</target></link>. Bjrn wrote English lyrics for two older songs from Benny's solo albums: &quot;I Walk with You Mama&quot; (&quot;Stockholm by Night&quot;, 1989) and &quot;After the Rain&quot; (&quot;Efter regnet&quot;, 1987) for opera singer<space/><link><target>Anne Sofie Von Otter</target></link>, for her Andersson tribute album<space/><italics>I Let the Music Speak</italics>.<space/><link><target>Barbra Dickson</target></link><space/>recorded (but not yet released) a Bjrn &amp; Benny song called 'The Day The Wall Came Tumbling Down'; the song eventually was released by Australian 'Mamma Mia!' musical star<space/><link><target>Anne Wood</target></link><space/>201 album of ABBA covers,<space/><link><target>Divine Discontent</target></link>. As of October 2012, Bjrn Ulvaeus has mentioned writing new material with Benny for a 'BAO' Christmas release (also mentioned as a BAO 'box'), and Benny is busy writing music for a Swedish language obscure musical, 'Hjlp Skes' ('Help is Wanted') together with Kristina Lugn and Lars Rudolfsson, premiering 8 February 2013.Andersson has also written music for a documentary film about<space/><link><target>Olof Palme</target></link>, re-recording the track 'Sorgmarch' from his last album as a theme throughout the film.The song &quot;Krlekens Tid&quot; -recorded 2004 by Helen Sjholm with BAO- -has also been performed in concert in English (lyrics by Ylva Eggehorn) by opera<space/><link><target>baritone</target></link><space/><link><target>Bryn Terfel</target></link>.On 15 April 2013, it was officially announced by the<space/><link><target>EBU</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Sveriges Television</target><part>SVT</part></link><space/>that Benny along with the ex-<link><target>ABBA</target></link><space/>member,<space/><link><target>Bjrn Ulvaeus</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Swedish people</target><part>Swedish</part></link><space/>DJ and record producer,<space/><link><target>Avicii</target></link>, have composed the anthem for the<space/><link><target>2013 Eurovision Song Contest</target></link>. The song was performed for the first time in the Final on 18 May.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.eurovision.tv/page/news?id</arg><arg name="title">ABBA's Benny, Björn and Avicii to write 'Eurovision anthem'</arg><arg name="work">[[EBU]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 April 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A new album of Benny Andersson compositions presented in a choral style was released on September 18th, 2015. &quot;Krlekens Tid&quot; was produced in Andersson's Mono Music studio, under the direction of choir master Gustaf Sjkvist who passed away before the album's release. Gustaf Sjkvists Choir, conducted by Cecilia Rydinger Alin, performed two concerts at Skeppsholmen on September 20th, featuring Benny Andersson on piano. The album includes songs in Swedish and English from a range of Andersson's projects, such as Chess, Kristina and BAO.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Film music</heading><paragraph>Benny Andersson has written music to several films for screen and television; the first attempt in the early 1970s for the obscure Swedish movie<space/><italics>The Seduction of Inga</italics>: the film flopped, but the 'Bjrn &amp; Benny' single &quot;She's My Kind of Girl&quot; surprised the composers by being released in Japan and becoming a Top 10 hit (the song renamed in Japan as &quot;The Little Girl of the Cold Wind&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>In 1987, Andersson wrote music and co-produced the soundtrack with Anders Eljas for the film<space/><italics><link><target>Mio in the Land of Faraway</target></link></italics>, based on Swedish author<space/><link><target>Astrid Lindgren</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/><italics><link><target>Mio, My Son</target></link></italics>. The title song became a huge hit in Sweden for<space/><link><target>Gemini (Swedish band)</target><part>Gemini</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2000, he wrote the music for fellow Swede (no relation)<space/><link><target>Roy Andersson</target></link>'s film<space/><italics><link><target>Songs from the Second Floor</target></link></italics><space/>(the music later re-recorded, featuring new lyrics, with BAO! with vocals by Helen Sjholm). He also wrote the theme for Roy Andersson's next film,<space/><italics><link><target>You, the Living</target></link></italics>, from 2007.</paragraph><paragraph>Andersson also worked on the film adaptation of<space/><italics>Mamma Mia!</italics>. He also wrote the film score for the 2012 documentary<space/><italics><link><target>Palme (film)</target><part>Palme</part></link></italics><space/>about Swedish prime minister<space/><link><target>Olof Palme</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.dn.se/kultur-noje/film-tv/filmare-spanar-in-personen-palme<space/></arg><arg name="title">Filmare spanar in personen Palme<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">DN.SE<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>He later won a<space/><link><target>Guldbagge Award</target></link><space/>for Best Original Score, for that film at the<space/><link><target>48th Guldbagge Awards</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sydsvenskan"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Nomineringarna till Guldbaggen</arg><arg name="url">http://www.sydsvenskan.se/kultur--nojen/nomineringarna-till-guldbaggen/</arg><arg name="publisher">Sydsvenskan.se</arg><arg name="language">Swedish</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 January 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Awards</heading><paragraph>Together with Ulvaeus, Andersson was nominated for a<space/><link><target>Drama Desk Award</target></link><space/>in a category &quot;Outstanding Music&quot; (for the musical<space/><italics>Chess</italics>), and for a<space/><link><target>Tony Award</target></link><space/>in a category &quot;Best Orchestrations&quot; (for musical<space/><italics>Mamma Mia!</italics>). Original cast recordings of both musicals were nominated for a<space/><link><target>Grammy Award</target></link>. Andersson/Ulvaeus also won a<space/><link><target>Touring Broadway Awards</target><part>Touring Broadway Award</part></link><space/>for the musical &quot;Mamma Mia&quot; (best score).</paragraph><paragraph>During his post-ABBA career Andersson won four Swedish<space/><link><target>Grammis</target></link><space/>awards, and together with Ulvaeus received the &quot;Special International&quot;<space/><link><target>Ivor Novello</target></link><space/>award from 'The British Academy of Composers and Songwriters', twice &quot;The Music Export Prize&quot; from the Swedish Ministry of Industry and Trade (2008),<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.sweden.gov.se/sb/d/11367/a/118215<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Government's Music Export Prize for 2008 goes to<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sweden.gov.se<space/></arg><arg name="date">7 January 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>as well as the &quot;Lifetime Achievement&quot; award from the Swedish Music Publishers Association (SMFF). In 2002, Andersson was given an honorary professorship by the Swedish Government for his &quot;ability to create high-class music reaching people around the world&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2007, he was elected a member of<space/><link><target>Royal Swedish Academy of Music</target></link>, and in 2008 received an Honorary Doctorate from the<space/><link><target>Stockholm University</target></link><space/>Faculty of Humanities for contributing importantly both to the preservation and the growth of the Swedish folk music tradition.</paragraph><paragraph>On 15 March 2010, Andersson appeared on stage in New York with former wife Anni-Frid Lyngstad to accept ABBA's award of induction into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame. During his acceptance speech he reflected on the important influence of traditional European music and the melancholy of the Swedish soul on ABBA's brand of pop music. &quot;If you live in a country like Sweden, with five, six months of snow, and the sun disappears totally for like two months, that would be reflected in the work of artists,&quot; he said. &quot;It's definitely in the Swedish folk music, you can hear it in the Russian folk songs, you can hear in the music from Jean Sibelius or Edvard Grieg from Norway, you can see it in the eyes of Greta Garbo and you can hear it in the voice of Jussi Bjrling. And you can hear in the sound of Frida and Agnetha on some of our songs too.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>In 2012, he received an Honorary Doctorate of Philosophy from the<space/><link><target>Lule Tekniska Universitet</target></link><space/>Faculty of Humanities and Social Sciences.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ltu.se/research/akh/Hedersdoktorer/Benny-Andersson-Filosofie-hedersdoktor-2012-1.96016?l</arg><arg name="title">Benny Andersson, Honorary Doctor of Philosophy 2012 – LTU – Luleå University of Technology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Ltu.se<space/></arg><arg name="date">31 August 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">27 June 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Andersson won the Swedish &quot;Guldbaggen&quot; award in 2012 as composer of the music for the film &quot;Palme&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/></arg><arg name="url">http://guldbaggen.se/nominering/benny-andersson<space/></arg><arg name="title">Bästa Musik 2012 Vinnare<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">guldbaggen.se<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 January 2012<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">3 August 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Personal life</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Frida Lyngstad and Benny Andersson 1976b.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>Andersson with Lyngstad in 1976</part></link>Andersson has been engaged to Christina Grnvall. In 1963, they had a son, Peter Grnvall and, in 1965, a daughter, Hlene. They split in 1966 and Christina never remarried. She kept custody of the children as Andersson was then at the peak of his Hep Stars' success. In the 1990s, Peter formed<space/><link><target>One More Time (band)</target><part>One More Time</part></link>, a group that enjoyed European success with the ABBA-like &quot;Highland&quot; and, later, as Sweden's entry to the<space/><link><target>Eurovision Song Contest 1996</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Andersson was engaged to<space/><link><target>Anni-Frid Lyngstad</target></link><space/>of ABBA for about nine years. They married in October 1978, but divorced in 1981.</paragraph><paragraph>He married Swedish TV presenter Mona Nrklit in November 1981 and had a son, Ludvig (born January 1982), who has since followed in his father's footsteps in forming his own band.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Discography</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Benny Andersson discography</arg></template><template><target>see also</target><arg>ABBA discography</arg><arg>Benny Anderssons Orkester</arg><arg>Hep Stars</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Also appears on</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Beginner's Guide to Scandinavia</italics><space/>(3CD, Nascente 2011)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Swedes in music</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Benny Andersson</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.icethesite.com'>icethesite (Benny Andersson and Bjrn Ulvaeus news site)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thehepstars.se/indexE.html'>The Hep Stars International Official website (Benny before ABBA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dummipedia.org/Chronology:Benny_Andersson'>Chronology: Benny Andersson</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.abbasite.com/'>Official ABBA site</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>worldcat id</target><arg>lccn-n82-243153</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-ach</target></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">{{flagicon|Luxembourg}} [[Anne-Marie David]]<br/>with ''"[[Tu te reconnaîtras]]"''</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of Eurovision Song Contest winners|Winner of the Eurovision Song Contest]]</arg><arg name="years">[[Eurovision Song Contest 1974|1974]]<br/><small>(as part of [[ABBA]])</small></arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">{{flagicon|Netherlands}} [[Teach-In]]<br/>with ''"[[Ding-A-Dong]]"''</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Nova (Swedish band)|Nova]]<br/>with ''"[[You're Summer]]"''</arg></template><space/><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[Sweden in the Eurovision Song Contest]]</arg><arg name="years">[[Eurovision Song Contest 1974|1974]]<br/><small>(as part of [[ABBA]])</small></arg></template><space/><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Lars Berghagen]]<space/><br/>with ''"[[Jennie, Jennie]]"''</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>ABBA</target></template><template><target>List of Eurovision Song Contest winners</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Andersson, Benny
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Swedish musician
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>16 December 1946
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Vällingby]], Stockholm, Sweden
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH">
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Andersson, Benny</target></template><link><target>Category:1946 births</target></link><link><target>Category:Living people</target></link><link><target>Category:Musicians from Stockholm</target></link><link><target>Category:ABBA members</target></link><link><target>Category:Members of the Royal Swedish Academy of Music</target></link><link><target>Category:Swedish songwriters</target></link><link><target>Category:Swedish musical theatre composers</target></link><link><target>Category:Swedish pop pianists</target></link><link><target>Category:Eurodisco musicians</target></link><link><target>Category:Ivor Novello Award winners</target></link><link><target>Category:Swedish feminists</target></link><link><target>Category:Eurovision Song Contest winners</target></link></paragraph></article>