<article title='Dactylic_hexameter'><paragraph><bold>Dactylic hexameter</bold><space/>(also known as &quot;heroic hexameter&quot;) is a form of<space/><link><target>meter (poetry)</target><part>meter</part></link><space/>or rhythmic scheme in poetry. It is traditionally associated with the quantitative meter of classical<space/><link><target>epic poetry</target></link><space/>in both<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Latin</target></link><space/>and was consequently considered to be<space/><italics>the</italics><space/>Grand Style of classical poetry. The premier examples of its use are<space/><link><target>Homer</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Iliad</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Odyssey</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><link><target>Virgil</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Aeneid</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph>The meter consists of lines made from six (in Greek ,<space/><italics>hex</italics>)<space/><link><target>Foot (prosody)</target><part>feet</part></link>, hence &quot;hexameter&quot;. In strict dactylic hexameter, each of these feet would be a<space/><link><target>dactyl (poetry)</target><part>dactyl</part></link><space/>(a long and two short syllables), but classical meter allows for the substitution of a<space/><link><target>spondee</target></link><space/>(two long syllables) in place of a dactyl in most positions. Specifically, the first four feet can either be dactyls or spondees more or less freely. The fifth foot is frequently a dactyl (around 95% of the time in Homer).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Because of the<space/><link><target>anceps</target></link><space/>(a short or long syllable), the sixth foot can be filled by either a<space/><link><target>trochee</target></link><space/>(a long then short syllable) or a spondee. However, because of the strong pause at the end of the line (which prevents elision and<space/><link><target>correption</target></link><space/>between lines in the dactylic hexameter), it is traditionally regarded as a spondee. Thus the dactylic line most normally looks as follows:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><space/>U | U | U | U | u u | X</listitem></list><paragraph>(Note that<space/><italics></italics><space/>is a<space/><link><target>long syllable</target></link>,<space/><italics>u</italics><space/>a short syllable and<space/><italics>U</italics><space/>either one long or two shorts and X anceps syllable.)</paragraph><paragraph>As in all classical verse forms, the phenomenon of<space/><italics><link><target>brevis in longo</target></link></italics><space/>is observed, so the last<space/><link><target>syllable</target></link><space/>can actually be short or long.</paragraph><paragraph>Hexameters also have a primary<space/><link><target>caesura</target></link><space/>&amp;mdash; a break in sense, much like the function of a<space/><link><target>comma</target></link><space/>in prose &amp;mdash; at one of several normal positions: After the first syllable in the third foot (the &quot;masculine&quot; caesura); after the second syllable in the third foot if the third foot is a dactyl (the &quot;feminine&quot; caesura); after the first syllable of the fourth foot; or after the first syllable of the second foot (the latter two often occur together in a line, breaking it into three separate units). The first possible caesura that one encounters in a line is considered the main caesura. A masculine caesura can offset a hiatus, causing lengthening of an otherwise light syllable.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In addition, hexameters have two<space/><link><target>Bridge (prosody)</target><part>bridges</part></link>, places where there very rarely is a break in a word-unit. The first, known as Meyer's Bridge, is in the second foot: if the second foot is a dactyl, the two short syllables generally will be part of the same word-unit. The second, known as Hermann's Bridge, is the same rule in the fourth foot: if the fourth foot is a dactyl, the two short syllables generally will be part of the same word-unit.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>It must be stressed that Meyer's and Hermann's Bridge concern only Homeric verse and are not observed in Latin dactylic hexameter. Even in Homer, these bridges are not prescriptive. The first line of the<space/><italics>Iliad</italics><space/>violates Meyer's Bridge ( ) since there is a word break between and .</paragraph><paragraph>Hexameters are frequently<space/><link><target>Enjambment</target><part>enjambed</part></link>, which helps to create the long, flowing narrative of epic. They are generally considered the most grandiose and formal meter.</paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><link><target>English language</target></link><space/>example of the dactylic hexameter, in quantitative meter:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>Down in a | deep dark | dell sat an | old cow | munching a | bean stalk</listitem></list><paragraph>As the absurd meaning of this example demonstrates, quantitative meter is extremely difficult to construct in English. Here is an example in normal stress meter (the first line of Longfellow's &quot;<link><target>Evangeline</target></link>&quot;):</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>This is the | forest pri | meval. The | murmuring | pines and the | hemlocks</listitem></list><paragraph>The &quot;foot&quot; is often compared to a musical measure and the long and short syllables to<space/><link><target>half note</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(minims) and quarter notes (crotchets), respectively.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Homers meter</heading><paragraph>The hexameter was first used by early Greek poets of the oral tradition, and the most complete extant examples of their works are the<space/><italics><link><target>Iliad</target></link></italics><space/>and the<space/><italics><link><target>Odyssey</target></link></italics>, which influenced the authors of all later classical epics that survive today. Early epic poetry was also accompanied by music, and<space/><link><target>Pitch accent</target><part>pitch changes</part></link><space/>associated with the accented Greek must have highlighted the melody, though the exact mechanism is still a topic of discussion.<extension extension_name='ref'>Cf. Alan Shaw's essay<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.altx.com/EBR/EBR5/GREEK.HTM'>Some Questions on Greek Poetry and Music</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Homeric poems arrange words in the line so that there is an interplay between the metrical ictusthe first long syllable of each footand the natural, spoken accent of words. If these two features of the language coincide too frequently, they overemphasize each other and the hexameter becomes sing-songy. Nevertheless, some reinforcement is desirable so that the poem has a natural rhythm. Balancing these two considerations is what eventually leads to rules regarding the correct placement of the caesura and breaks between words; in general, word breaks occur in the middle of metrical feet, while accent and ictus coincide only near the end of the line.</paragraph><paragraph>The first line of Homers<space/><italics>Iliad</italics>&quot;Sing, goddess, the anger of Peleus son Achilles&quot;provides an example:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>μῆνιν ἄειδε, θεά, Πηληϊάδεω Ἀχιλῆος</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>Dividing the line into metrical units:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>μῆνιν ἄ {{!}} ειδε, θε {{!}} ά, Πη {{!}} ληϊά {{!}} δεω Ἀχι {{!}} λῆος</arg></template><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>dactyl, dactyl, spondee, dactyl, dactyl, trochee.</listitem></list><paragraph>Note how the word endings do not coincide with the end of a metrical foot; for the early part of the line this forces the natural accent of each word to lie in the middle of a foot, playing against the natural rhythm of the ictus.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>This line also includes a masculine caesura after<space/><italics></italics>, a natural break that separates the line into two logical parts. Unlike later writers, Homeric lines more commonly employ the feminine caesura; an example occurs in<space/><italics>Iliad</italics><space/>I.5 ...and every bird; thus the plan of Zeus came to fulfillment:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>οἰωνοῖσί τε πᾶσι, Διὸς δ’ ἐτελείετο βουλή,</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>οἰω {{!}} νοῖσί τε {{!}} πᾶσι, Δι {{!}} ὸς δ’ ἐτε {{!}} λείετο {{!}} βουλή,</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>Homers hexameters contain a far higher proportion of dactyls than later hexameter poetry. They are also characterised by a laxer following of verse principles that the authors of later epics almost invariably adhered to. For example, Homer allows spondaic fifth feet (albeit not often), whereas many later authors virtually never did. There are also exceptions to Meyers Bridge and Hermanns Bridge in Homer (albeit rare), but such violations are exceedingly rare in a later author like<space/><link><target>Callimachus</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Homer also altered the forms of words to allow them to fit the hexameter, typically by using a<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek dialects</target><part>dialectal</part></link><space/>form:<space/><italics>ptolis</italics><space/>is an epic form used instead of the Attic<space/><italics>polis</italics><space/>wherever it is necessary for the meter. On occasion, the names of characters themselves actually seem to have been altered: the spelling of the name of Homers character Polydamas,<space/><italics>Pouludamas</italics>, appears to be an alternative rendering of the metrically unviable<space/><italics>Poludamas</italics><space/>(subduer of many).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, even after accepting the various alterations admitted by Homer, some lines remain impossible to scan as they stand now, e.g.<space/><italics>Iliad</italics><space/>I.108 not a good word spoken nor brought to pass:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>ἐσθλὸν δ’ οὐτέ τί πω εἶπας ἔπος οὔτ’ ἐτέλεσσας</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>The first three feet of this line scan spondee-dactyl-spondee, but the fourth foot of<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>-πας ἔπος</arg></template><space/>has three consecutive short syllables. These metrical inconsistencies (along with a knowledge of comparative linguistics) have led scholars to infer the presence of a lost<space/><link><target>digamma</target></link><space/>consonant in an old form of that line. In this example, the word<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>ἔπος</arg></template><space/>was originally<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>ϝέπος</arg></template><space/>in Ionian; this consonant lengthens the last syllable of the preceding<space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>εἶπας</arg></template><space/>and corrects the apparent defect in the meter. This example demonstrates the oral tradition of the Homeric epics that flourished long before they were written down sometime in the 7th century BC.</paragraph><paragraph>In spite of the occasional exceptions in early epic, most of the later rules of hexameter composition have their origins in the methods and practices of Homer.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Latin hexameter</heading><paragraph><template><target>Unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">March 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The hexameter came into Latin as an adaptation from Greek long after the practice of singing the epics had faded. Consequentially, the properties of the meter were learned as specific &quot;rules&quot; rather than as a natural result of musical expression. Also, because the Latin language generally has a higher percentage of long syllables than Greek, it is by nature more spondaic than Greek. These factors caused the Latin hexameter to take on distinct Latin characteristics.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest example of the use of hexameter in Latin poetry is that of the<space/><italics>Annales</italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ennius</target></link>, which established the dactylic hexameter as the standard for later Latin epic. Later Republican writers, such as<space/><link><target>Lucretius</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Catullus</target></link><space/>and even<space/><link><target>Cicero</target></link>, wrote their own compositions in the meter and it was at this time that many of the principles of Latin hexameter were firmly established, ones that would govern later writers such as<space/><link><target>Virgil</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ovid</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Marcus Annaeus Lucanus</target><part>Lucan</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Satires of Juvenal</target><part>Juvenal</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Virgil</target></link>'s opening line for the<space/><italics><link><target>Aeneid</target></link></italics><space/>is a classic example of Latin hexameter:<space/></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Arma virumque cano, Troiae qui primus ab oris</arg></template><space/>(dactyl, dactyl, spondee, spondee, dactyl, spondee)</listitem></list><paragraph>As in Greek, lines were arranged such that the metrically long syllablesthose occurring at the beginning of a footavoided the natural stress of a word. In the first few feet of the meter, meter and stress were expected to clash, while in the final few feet they were expected to resolve and coincidean effect that gives each line a natural &quot;dum-ditty-dum-dum&quot; (&quot;shave and a haircut&quot;) rhythm to close. Such an arrangement is a balance between an exaggerated emphasis on the metrewhich would cause the verse to be sing-songyand the need to provide some repeated rhythmic guide for skilled recitation.</paragraph><paragraph>In the following example of Ennius's early Latin hexameter composition, metrical weight (<italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>ictus</arg></template></italics>) falls on the first and last syllables of<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>certabant</arg></template></italics>; the ictus is therefore opposed to the natural stress on the second syllable when the word is pronounced. Similarly, the second syllable of the words<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>urbem</arg></template></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Romam</arg></template></italics><space/>carry the metrical ictus even though the first is naturally stressed in typical pronunciation. In the closing feet of the line, the natural stress that falls on the third syllable of<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Remoramne</arg></template></italics><space/>and the second syllable of<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>vocarent</arg></template></italics><space/>coincide with the metrical ictus and produce the characteristic &quot;shave and a haircut&quot; ending:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>certabant urbem Romam Remoramne vocarent.</arg></template></listitem><listitem>(<italics>Annales</italics><space/>1.86)</listitem></list><paragraph>Like their Greek predecessors, classical Latin poets avoided a large number of word breaks at the ends of foot divisions except between the fourth and fifth, where it was encouraged. In order to preserve the rhythmic close, Latin poets avoided the placement of a single syllable or four-syllable word at the end of a line. The caesura is also handled far more strictly, with Homer's feminine caesura becoming exceedingly rare, and the second-foot caesura always paired with one in the fourth.</paragraph><paragraph>One example of the evolution of the Latin verse form can be seen in a comparative analysis of the use of spondees in Ennius' time vs. the Augustan age. The repeated use of the heavily spondaic line came to be frowned upon, as well as the use of a high proportion of spondees in both of the first two feet. The following lines of Ennius would not have been felt admissible by later authors since they both contain repeated spondees at the beginning of consecutive lines:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>his verbis: "o gnata, tibi sunt ante ferendae</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Aerumnae, post ex fluvio fortuna resistet."</arg></template></listitem><listitem>(<italics>Annales</italics><space/>1.42f)</listitem></list><paragraph>However, it is from Vergil that the following famous, heavily spondaic line comes:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Monstr' horrend' inform' ingens, cui lumen ademptum.</arg></template></listitem><listitem>(<italics>Aeneid</italics><space/>III.658)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Virgil and the Augustan poets</heading><paragraph>By the age of Augustus, poets like Virgil closely followed the rules of the meter and approached it in a highly rhetorical way, looking for effects that can be exploited in skilled recitation. For example, the following line from the<space/><italics>Aeneid</italics><space/>(VIII.596) describes the movement of rushing horses and how &quot;a hoof shakes the crumbling field with a galloping sound&quot;:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>quadrupedante putrem sonitu quatit ungula campum</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>This line is made up of five dactyls and a closing spondee, an unusual rhythmic arrangement that imitates the described action. A similar effect is found in VIII.452, where Virgil describes how the blacksmith sons of Vulcan &quot;take up their arms with great strength one to another&quot; in forging Aeneas' shield:<space/></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>illi inter sese multa ui bracchia tollunt</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>The line consists of all spondees except for the usual dactyl in the fifth foot, and is meant to mimic the pounding sound of the work. A third example that mixes the two effects comes from I.42, where Juno pouts that Athena was allowed to use Jove's thunderbolts to destroy Ajax (&quot;she hurled Jove's quick fire from the clouds&quot;):<space/></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Ipsa Jovis rapidum jaculata e nubibus ignem</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>This line is nearly all dactyls except for the spondee at<space/><italics>-lata e</italics>. This change in rhythm paired with the harsh elision is intended to emphasize the crash of Athena's thunderbolt.</paragraph><paragraph>Virgil will occasionally deviate from the strict rules of the meter to produce a special effect. One example from I.105 describing a ship at sea during a storm has Virgil violating metrical standards to place a single-syllable word at the end of the line:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>...et undis</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>dat latus; insequitur cumulo praeruptus aquae mons.</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>The boat &quot;gives its side to the waves; there comes next in a heap a steep mountain of water.&quot; By placing the monosyllable<space/><italics>mons</italics><space/>at the end of the line, Virgil interrupts the usual &quot;shave and a haircut&quot; pattern to produce a jarring rhythm, an effect that echoes the crash of a large wave against the side of a ship.</paragraph><paragraph>One final, amusing example that comments on the importance Roman poets placed on their verse rules comes from the<space/><italics><link><target>Ars Poetica</target></link></italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Horace</target></link>, line 263:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Non quivis videt inmodulata poemata iudex,</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>The line, which lacks a proper caesura, is translated &quot;Not every critic sees an inharmonious verse.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='2'>Silver Age and later heroic verse</heading><paragraph>The verse innovations of the Augustan writers were carefully imitated by their successors in the Silver Age of<space/><link><target>Latin literature</target></link>. The verse form itself then was little changed, as the quality of a poet's hexameter was judged against the standard set by Virgil and the other Augustan poets, a respect for literary precedent encompassed by the Latin word<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>aemulatio</arg></template></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>E.g., the younger Pliny, in referring to an orator who prided himself on not attempting to rival Cicero, replied,<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Est enim ... mihi cum Cicerone aemulatio, nec sum contentus eloquentia saeculi nostri; nam stultissimum credo ad imitandum non optima quaeque proponere.</arg></template></italics><space/>(&quot;I do attempt to emulate Cicero, as I am not content with the eloquence of our age; I think it's idiotic not to imitate the best examples.&quot;)<space/><italics>Letters</italics><space/>I.5.123</extension><space/>Deviations were generally regarded as idiosyncrasies or hallmarks of personal style, and were not imitated by later poets.<space/><link><target>Juvenal</target></link>, for example, was fond of occasionally creating verses that placed a sense break between the fourth and fifth foot (instead of in the usual caesura positions), but this techniqueknown as the bucolic diaeresisdid not catch on with other poets.</paragraph><paragraph>In the late empire, writers experimented again by adding unusual restrictions to the standard hexameter. The rhopalic verse of<space/><link><target>Ausonius</target></link><space/>is a good example; besides following the standard hexameter pattern, each word in the line is one syllable longer than the previous, e.g.:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Spes, deus, aeternae stationis conciliator,</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>si castis precibus veniales invigilamus,</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>his, pater, oratis placabilis adstipulare.</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>Also notable is the tendency among late grammarians to thoroughly dissect the hexameters of Virgil and earlier poets. A treatise on poetry by<space/><link><target>Diomedes Grammaticus</target></link><space/>is a good example, as this work (among other things) categorizes dactylic hexameter verses in ways that were later interpreted under the<space/><link><target>golden line</target></link><space/>rubric. Independently, these two trends show the form becoming highly artificialmore like a puzzle to solve than a medium for personal poetic expression.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>By the Middle Ages, some writers adopted more relaxed versions of the meter.<space/><link><target>Bernard of Cluny</target></link>, for example, employs it in his<space/><italics>De Contemptu Mundi</italics>, but ignores classical conventions in favor of accentual effects and predictable rhyme both within and between verses, e.g.:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><template><target>lang</target><arg>la</arg><arg>Hora novissima, tempora pessima sunt &mdash; vigilemus.<br>Ecce minaciter imminet arbiter ille supremus.<br>Imminet imminet ut mala terminet, æqua coronet,<br>Recta remuneret, anxia liberet, æthera donet.</arg></template><list type='ident'><listitem>(I.1-4: These are the last days, the worst of times: let us keep watch.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Behold the menacing arrival of the supreme Judge.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>He is coming, he is coming to end evil, crown the just, reward the right, set the worried free, and give the skies.)</listitem></list></listitem></list><paragraph>Not all medieval writers are so at odds with the Virgilian standard, and with the rediscovery of classical literature, later Medieval and Renaissance writers are far more orthodox, but by then the form had become an academic exercise.<space/><link><target>Petrarch</target></link>, for example, devoted much time to his<space/><italics><link><target>Africa (Petrarch)</target><part>Africa</part></link></italics>, a dactylic hexameter epic on<space/><link><target>Scipio Africanus</target></link>, but this work was unappreciated in his time and remains little read today. In contrast,<space/><link><target>Dante</target></link><space/>decided to write his epic, the<space/><italics><link><target>Divine Comedy</target></link></italics><space/>in Italiana choice that defied the traditional epic choice of Latin dactylic hexametersand produced a masterpiece beloved both then and now.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>With the<space/><link><target>New Latin</target></link><space/>period, the language itself came to be regarded as a medium only for &quot;serious&quot; and learned expression, a view that left little room for Latin poetry. The emergence of<space/><link><target>Recent Latin</target></link><space/>in the 20th century restored classical orthodoxy among Latinists and sparked a general (if still academic) interest in the beauty of Latin poetry. Today, the modern Latin poets who use the dactylic hexameter are generally as faithful to Virgil as Rome's Silver Age poets.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.skidmore.edu/academics/classics/courses/metrica/'>Introduction to dactylic hexameter</link><space/>for Latin verse.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aoidoi.org/articles/meter/reading_dact_hex.php'>Reading dactylic hexameter</link>, specifically Homer.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://wiredforbooks.org/iliad/'>Recitation of Homer</link>, by Stanley Lombardo.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rhapsodes.fll.vt.edu/aeneid1.htm'>Oral reading of Virgil's ''Aeneid''</link>, by<space/><link><target>Robert Sonkowsky</target></link>, University of Minnesota.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thesaurus.flf.vu.lt/eiledara/index.php'>Greek hexameter analysis online tool</link>, University of Vilnius.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.classicsprofessor.com/VergilAP/scanning_hexameter.htm'>Audio/Visual Tutorials for Vergil's Hexameter</link>, by Dale Grote, UNC Charlotte.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hexameter.co'>Hexameter.co</link>, practice scanning lines of dactylic hexameter from a variety of Latin authors</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Odyssey navbox</target></template><template><target>Iliad navbox</target></template><template><target>Aeneid</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Poetic rhythm</target></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Greek epic poetry</target></link><link><target>Category:Latin poetry</target></link></paragraph></article>