<article title='Alloy'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template><link><target>File:Steel wire rope.png</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Wire rope</target></link><space/>made from<space/><link><target>steel</target></link>, which is a metal alloy whose major component is<space/><link><target>iron</target></link>, with<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/>content between 0.02% and 2.14% by mass.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>An<space/><bold>alloy</bold><space/>is a mixture of<space/><link><target>metal</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or a mixture of a metal and another<space/><link><target>Chemical element</target><part>element</part></link>. Alloys are defined by metallic bonding character.<extension extension_name='ref'>[Callister, W. D. &quot;Materials Science and Engineering: An Introduction&quot; 2007, 7th edition, John Wiley and Sons, Inc. New York, Section 4.3 and Chapter 9].</extension><space/>An alloy may be a<space/><link><target>solid solution</target></link><space/>of metal elements (a single phase) or a mixture of metallic phases (two or more solutions).<space/><link><target>Intermetallic</target></link><space/>compounds are alloys with a defined<space/><link><target>stoichiometry</target></link><space/>and crystal structure.<space/><link><target>Zintl phase</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are also sometimes considered alloys depending on bond types (see also:<space/><link><target>Van Arkel-Ketelaar triangle</target></link><space/>for information on classifying bonding in binary compounds).</paragraph><paragraph>Alloys are used in a wide variety of applications. In some cases, a combination of metals may reduce the overall cost of the material while preserving important properties. In other cases, the combination of metals imparts synergistic properties to the constituent metal elements such as corrosion resistance or mechanical strength. Examples of alloys are<space/><link><target>steel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>solder</target></link>,<space/><link><target>brass</target></link>,<space/><link><target>pewter</target></link>,<space/><link><target>duralumin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>phosphor bronze</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Amalgam (chemistry)</target><part>amalgam</part><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The alloy constituents are usually measured by mass. Alloys are usually classified as substitutional or<space/><link><target>interstitial alloy</target><trail>s</trail></link>, depending on the atomic arrangement that forms the alloy. They can be further classified as homogeneous (consisting of a single phase), or heterogeneous (consisting of two or more phases) or<space/><link><target>intermetallic</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Introduction</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Born bronze - Bronze casts.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Liquid<space/><link><target>bronze</target></link>, being poured into molds during casting.</part></link><link><target>File:A brass light.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>brass</target></link><space/>lamp.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>An alloy is a mixture of either pure or fairly pure<space/><link><target>chemical elements</target></link>, which forms an impure substance (admixture) that retains the characteristics of a<space/><link><target>metal</target></link>. An alloy is distinct from an impure metal, such as<space/><link><target>wrought iron</target></link>, in that, with an alloy, the added impurities are usually desirable and will typically have some useful benefit. Alloys are made by mixing two or more elements; at least one of which being a metal. This is usually called the primary metal or the base metal, and the name of this metal may also be the name of the alloy. The other constituents may or may not be metals but, when mixed with the molten base, they will be<space/><link><target>solubility</target><part>soluble</part></link>, dissolving into the mixture.</paragraph><paragraph>When the alloy cools and solidifies (<link><target>crystallize</target><trail>s</trail></link>), its mechanical properties will often be quite different from those of its individual constituents. A metal that is normally very soft and<space/><link><target>malleability</target><part>malleable</part></link>, such as<space/><link><target>aluminium</target></link>, can be altered by alloying it with another soft metal, like<space/><link><target>copper</target></link>. Although both metals are very soft and<space/><link><target>ductility</target><part>ductile</part></link>, the resulting<space/><link><target>aluminium alloy</target></link><space/>will be much<space/><link><target>hardness</target><part>harder</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>strength of materials</target><part>stronger</part></link>. Adding a small amount of non-metallic<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>iron</target></link><space/>produces an alloy called<space/><link><target>steel</target></link>. Due to its very-high strength and<space/><link><target>toughness</target></link><space/>(which is much higher than pure iron), and its ability to be greatly altered by<space/><link><target>heat treatment</target></link>, steel is one of the most common alloys in modern use. By adding<space/><link><target>chromium</target></link><space/>to steel, its resistance to<space/><link><target>corrosion</target></link><space/>can be enhanced, creating<space/><link><target>stainless steel</target></link>, while adding<space/><link><target>silicon</target></link><space/>will alter its electrical characteristics, producing<space/><link><target>silicon steel</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the elements usually must be soluble in the<space/><link><target>liquid</target></link><space/>state, they may not always be soluble in the<space/><link><target>solid</target></link><space/>state. If the metals remain soluble when solid, the alloy forms a<space/><link><target>solid solution</target></link>, becoming a homogeneous structure consisting of identical crystals, called a<space/><link><target>phase (matter)</target><part>phase</part></link>. If the mixture cools and the constituents become insoluble, they may separate to form two or more different types of crystals, creating a heterogeneous<space/><link><target>microstructure</target></link><space/>of different phases. However, in other alloys, the insoluble elements may not separate until after crystallization occurs. These alloys are called intermetallic alloys because, if cooled very quickly, they first crystallize as a homogeneous phase, but they are<space/><link><target>supersaturation</target><part>supersaturated</part></link><space/>with the secondary constituents. As time passes, the atoms of these supersaturated alloys separate within the crystals, forming intermetallic phases that serve to reinforce the crystals internally.</paragraph><paragraph>Some alloys occur naturally, such as<space/><link><target>electrum</target></link>, which is an alloy that is<space/><link><target>native metal</target><part>native</part></link><space/>to Earth, consisting of<space/><link><target>silver</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gold</target></link>. Meteorites are sometimes made of naturally occurring alloys of iron and<space/><link><target>nickel</target></link>, but are not native to the Earth. One of the first alloys made by humans was<space/><link><target>bronze</target></link>, which is made by mixing the metals<space/><link><target>tin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>copper</target></link>. Bronze was an extremely useful alloy to the ancients, because it is much stronger and harder than either of its components. Steel was another common alloy. However, in ancient times, it could only be created as an accidental byproduct from the heating of iron ore in fires (<link><target>smelting</target></link>) during the manufacture of iron. Other ancient alloys include<space/><link><target>pewter</target></link>,<space/><link><target>brass</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>pig iron</target></link>. In the modern age, steel can be created in many forms.<space/><link><target>Carbon steel</target></link><space/>can be made by varying only the carbon content, producing soft alloys like<space/><link><target>mild steel</target></link><space/>or hard alloys like<space/><link><target>spring steel</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Alloy steel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can be made by adding other elements, such as<space/><link><target>molybdenum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>vanadium</target></link><space/>or nickel, resulting in alloys such as<space/><link><target>high-speed steel</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>tool steel</target></link>. Small amounts of<space/><link><target>manganese</target></link><space/>are usually alloyed with most modern-steels because of its ability to remove unwanted impurities, like<space/><link><target>phosphorus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sulfur</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>oxygen</target></link>, which can have detrimental effects on the alloy. However, most alloys were not created until the 1900s, such as various aluminium,<space/><link><target>titanium alloy</target><part>titanium</part></link>,<space/><link><target>nickel alloys</target><part>nickel</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>magnesium alloy</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Some modern<space/><link><target>superalloy</target><trail>s</trail></link>, such as<space/><link><target>incoloy</target></link>,<space/><link><target>inconel</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>hastelloy</target></link>, may consist of a multitude of different components.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Terminology</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Inconel gate valve--The-Alloy-Valve-Stockist.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A gate valve, made from<space/><link><target>Inconel</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The term alloy is used to describe a mixture of atoms in which the primary constituent is a metal. The primary metal is called the<space/><italics>base</italics>, the<space/><italics>matrix</italics>, or the<space/><italics><link><target>solvent</target></link></italics>. The secondary constituents are often called<space/><italics>solutes</italics>. If there is a mixture of only two types of atoms, not counting impurities, such as a<space/><link><target>copper-nickel</target></link><space/>alloy, then it is called a<space/><italics>binary alloy.</italics><space/>If there are three types of atoms forming the mixture, such as iron, nickel and chromium, then it is called a<space/><italics>ternary alloy.</italics><space/>An alloy with four constituents is a<space/><italics>quaternary alloy,</italics><space/>while a five-part alloy is termed a<space/><italics>quinary alloy.</italics><space/>Because the percentage of each constituent can be varied, with any mixture the entire range of possible variations is called a<space/><italics>system</italics>. In this respect, all of the various forms of an alloy containing only two constituents, like iron and carbon, is called a<space/><italics>binary system,</italics><space/>while all of the alloy combinations possible with a ternary alloy, such as alloys of iron, carbon and chromium, is called a<space/><italics>ternary system</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bauccio, Michael (1003)<space/><italics>ASM metals reference book</italics>. ASM International. ISBN 0871704781.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although an alloy is technically an impure metal, when referring to alloys, the term &quot;impurities&quot; usually denotes those elements which are not desired. These impurities are often found in the base metals or the solutes, but they may also be introduced during the alloying process. For instance, sulfur is a common impurity in steel. Sulfur combines readily with iron to form<space/><link><target>iron sulfide</target></link>, which is very brittle, creating weak spots in the steel.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Verhoeven, John D.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Steel Metallurgy for the Non-metallurgist</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">ASM International</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-61503-056-9</arg><arg name="page">56</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Lithium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>sodium</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>calcium</target></link><space/>are common impurities in aluminium alloys, which can have adverse effects on the<space/><link><target>structural integrity</target></link><space/>of castings. Conversely, otherwise pure-metals that simply contain unwanted impurities are often called &quot;impure metals&quot; and are not usually referred to as alloys. Oxygen, present in the air, readily combines with most metals to form<space/><link><target>metal oxide</target><trail>s</trail></link>; especially at higher temperatures encountered during alloying. Great care is often taken during the alloying process to remove excess impurities, using<space/><link><target>flux (metallurgy)</target><part>fluxes</part></link>, chemical additives, or other methods of<space/><link><target>extractive metallurgy</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Davis, Joseph R. (1993)<space/><italics>ASM Specialty Handbook: Aluminum and Aluminum Alloys</italics>. ASM International. p. 211. ISBN 978-0-87170-496-2.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In practice, some alloys are used so predominantly with respect to their base metals that the name of the primary constituent is also used as the name of the alloy. For example, 14<space/><link><target>Karat (purity)</target><part>karat</part></link><space/><link><target>gold</target></link><space/>is an alloy of gold with other elements. Similarly, the<space/><link><target>silver</target></link><space/>used in<space/><link><target>jewelry</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>aluminium</target></link><space/>used as a structural building material are also alloys.</paragraph><paragraph>The term &quot;alloy&quot; is sometimes used in everyday speech as a synonym for a particular alloy. For example, automobile wheels made of an<space/><link><target>aluminium alloy</target></link><space/>are commonly referred to as simply &quot;<link><target>alloy wheel</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;, although in point of fact steels and most other metals in practical use are also alloys. Steel is such a common alloy that many items made from it, like<space/><link><target>wheel</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>barrel</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or<space/><link><target>girder</target><trail>s</trail></link>, are simply referred to by the name of the item, assuming it is made of steel. When made from other materials, they are typically specified as such, (i.e.: &quot;bronze wheel,&quot; &quot;plastic barrel,&quot; or &quot;wood girder&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Theory</heading><paragraph>Alloying a metal is done by combining it with one or more other metals or non-metals that often enhance its properties. For example,<space/><link><target>steel</target></link><space/>is stronger than<space/><link><target>iron</target></link>, its primary element. The<space/><link><target>electrical conductivity</target><part>electrical</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>thermal conductivity</target></link><space/>of alloys is usually lower than that of the pure metals. The physical properties, such as<space/><link><target>density</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Reactivity (chemistry)</target><part>reactivity</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Young's modulus</target></link><space/>of an alloy may not differ greatly from those of its elements, but engineering properties such as<space/><link><target>tensile strength</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Mills, Adelbert Phillo (1922)<space/><italics>Materials of Construction: Their Manufacture and Properties</italics>, John Wiley &amp; sons, inc, originally published by the University of Wisconsin, Madison</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>shear strength</target></link><space/>may be substantially different from those of the constituent materials. This is sometimes a result of the sizes of the<space/><link><target>atom</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the alloy, because larger atoms exert a compressive force on neighboring atoms, and smaller atoms exert a tensile force on their neighbors, helping the alloy resist deformation. Sometimes alloys may exhibit marked differences in behavior even when small amounts of one element are present. For example, impurities in semiconducting<space/><link><target>ferromagnetic</target></link><space/>alloys lead to different properties, as first predicted by White, Hogan, Suhl, Tian Abrie and Nakamura.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Hogan</arg><arg name="first1">C.</arg><arg name="title">Density of States of an Insulating Ferromagnetic Alloy</arg><arg name="journal">Physical Review</arg><arg name="volume">188</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">870</arg><arg name="year">1969</arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/PhysRev.188.870</arg><arg name="bibcode">1969PhRv..188..870H</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1">Zhang</arg><arg name="first1">X.</arg><arg name="last2">Suhl</arg><arg name="first2">H.</arg><arg name="title">Spin-wave-related period doublings and chaos under transverse pumping</arg><arg name="journal">Physical Review A</arg><arg name="volume">32</arg><arg name="pages">2530–2533</arg><arg name="year">1985</arg><arg name="doi">10.1103/PhysRevA.32.2530</arg><arg name="pmid">9896377</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="bibcode">1985PhRvA..32.2530Z</arg></template></extension>Some alloys are made by melting and mixing two or more metals.<space/><link><target>Bronze</target></link>, an alloy of<space/><link><target>copper</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>tin</target></link>, was the first alloy discovered, during the<space/><link><target>prehistory</target><part>prehistoric</part></link><space/>period now known as the<space/><link><target>bronze age</target></link>; it was harder than pure copper and originally used to make tools and weapons, but was later superseded by metals and alloys with better properties. In later times bronze has been used for<space/><link><target>ornament (architecture)</target><part>ornaments</part></link>,<space/><link><target>bell (instrument)</target><part>bell</part><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>statue</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>bearing (mechanical)</target><part>bearings</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Brass</target></link><space/>is an alloy made from<space/><link><target>copper</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>zinc</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike pure metals, most alloys do not have a single<space/><link><target>melting point</target></link>, but a melting range in which the material is a mixture of<space/><link><target>solid</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>liquid</target></link><space/>phases. The temperature at which melting begins is called the<space/><link><target>solidus (chemistry)</target><part>solidus</part></link>, and the temperature when melting is just complete is called the<space/><link><target>liquidus</target></link>. However, for many alloys there is a particular proportion of constituents (in some cases more than one)either a<space/><link><target>eutectic</target></link><space/>mixture or a<space/><link><target>Eutectic system#Peritectic</target><part>peritectic composition</part></link>which gives the alloy a unique melting point.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Heat-treatable alloys</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:IronAlfa&amp;IronGamma.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Allotropes of iron</target></link>, (<link><target>alpha iron</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>gamma iron</target></link>) showing the differences in atomic arrangement.</part></link><link><target>File:Photomicrograph of annealed and quenched steel, from 1911 Britannica plates 11 and 14.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Photomicrographs of<space/><link><target>steel</target></link>. Top photo:<space/><link><target>annealing (metallurgy)</target><part>Annealed</part></link><space/>(slowly cooled) steel forms a heterogeneous, lamellar microstructure called<space/><link><target>pearlite</target></link>, consisting of the phases<space/><link><target>cementite</target></link><space/>(light) and<space/><link><target>Ferrite (iron)</target><part>ferrite</part></link><space/>(dark). Bottom photo:<space/><link><target>Quenched</target></link><space/>(quickly cooled) steel forms a single phase called<space/><link><target>martensite</target></link>, in which the carbon remains trapped within the crystals, creating internal stresses.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Alloys are often made to alter the mechanical properties of the base metal, to induce<space/><link><target>hardness</target></link>,<space/><link><target>toughness</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ductility</target></link>, or other desired properties. Most metals and alloys can be<space/><link><target>work hardening</target><part>work hardened</part></link><space/>by creating defects in their crystal structure. These defects are created during<space/><link><target>plastic deformation</target></link>, such as hammering or bending, and are permanent unless the metal is<space/><link><target>recrystallization (metallurgy)</target><part>recrystallized</part></link>. However, some alloys can also have their properties altered by<space/><link><target>heat treatment</target></link>. Nearly all metals can be softened by<space/><link><target>annealing (metallurgy)</target><part>annealing</part></link>, which recrystallizes the alloy and repairs the defects, but not as many can be hardened by controlled heating and cooling. Many alloys of<space/><link><target>aluminium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>copper</target></link>,<space/><link><target>magnesium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>titanium</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>nickel</target></link><space/>can be strengthened to some degree by some method of heat treatment, but few respond to this to the same degree that<space/><link><target>steel</target></link><space/>does.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jon L. Dossett Page 1-14"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>At a certain temperature, (usually between<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1500</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1600</arg><arg>F</arg><arg>C</arg></template>, depending on carbon content), the base metal of steel undergoes a change in the arrangement of the atoms in its crystal matrix, called<space/><link><target>allotropy</target></link>. This allows the small carbon atoms to enter the interstices of the iron crystal,<space/><link><target>diffusion</target><part>diffusing</part></link><space/>into the iron matrix. When this happens, the carbon atoms are said to be in<space/><italics><link><target>solid solution</target><part>solution</part></link>,</italics><space/>or mixed with the iron, forming a single, homogeneous, crystalline phase called<space/><link><target>austenite</target></link>. If the steel is cooled slowly, the iron will gradually change into its low temperature allotrope. When this happens the carbon atoms will no longer be<space/><link><target>solubility</target><part>soluble</part></link><space/>with the iron, and will be forced to<space/><link><target>precipitation (chemistry)</target><part>precipitate</part></link><space/>out of solution,<space/><link><target>nucleating</target></link><space/>into the spaces between the crystals. The steel then becomes heterogeneous, being formed of two phases; the carbon (<link><target>carbide</target></link>) phase<space/><link><target>cementite</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>ferrite (iron)</target><part>ferrite</part></link>. This type of heat treatment produces steel that is rather soft and bendable. However, if the steel is cooled quickly the carbon atoms will not have time to precipitate. When rapidly cooled, a<space/><link><target>diffusionless transformation</target><part>diffusionless (martensite) transformation</part></link><space/>occurs, in which the carbon atoms become trapped in solution. This causes the iron crystals to deform intrinsically when the crystal structure tries to change to its low temperature state, making it very hard and brittle.</paragraph><paragraph>Conversely, most heat-treatable alloys are<space/><link><target>precipitation hardening</target></link><space/>alloys, which produce the opposite effects that steel does. When heated to form a solution and then cooled quickly, these alloys become much softer than normal, during the diffusionless transformation, and then harden as they age. The solutes in these alloys will precipitate over time, forming<space/><link><target>intermetallics</target><part>intermetallic</part></link><space/>phases, which are difficult to discern from the base metal. Unlike steel, in which the solid solution separates to form different crystal phases, precipitation hardening alloys separate to form different phases within the same crystal. These intermetallic alloys appear homogeneous in crystal structure, but tend to behave heterogeneous, becoming hard and somewhat brittle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jon L. Dossett Page 1-14"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Substitutional and interstitial alloys</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Alloy atomic arrangements showing the different types.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Different atomic mechanisms of alloy formation, showing pure metal, substitutional, interstitial, and a combination of the two.</part></link>When a molten metal is mixed with another substance, there are two mechanisms that can cause an alloy to form, called<space/><italics>atom exchange</italics><space/>and the<space/><italics>interstitial mechanism</italics>. The relative size of each element in the mix plays a primary role in determining which mechanism will occur. When the atoms are relatively similar in size, the atom exchange method usually happens, where some of the atoms composing the metallic crystals are substituted with atoms of the other constituent. This is called a<space/><italics>substitutional alloy</italics>. Examples of substitutional alloys include bronze and brass, in which some of the copper atoms are substituted with either tin or zinc atoms. With the interstitial mechanism, one atom is usually much smaller than the other, so cannot successfully replace an atom in the crystals of the base metal. The smaller atoms become trapped in the spaces between the atoms in the crystal matrix, called the<space/><italics>interstices</italics>. This is referred to as an<space/><italics>interstitial alloy</italics>. Steel is an example of an interstitial alloy, because the very small carbon atoms fit into interstices of the iron matrix.<space/><link><target>Stainless steel</target></link><space/>is an example of a combination of interstitial and substitutional alloys, because the carbon atoms fit into the interstices, but some of the iron atoms are replaced with nickel and chromium atoms.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jon L. Dossett Page 1-14">Dossett, Jon L. and Boyer, Howard E. (2006)<space/><italics>Practical heat treating</italics>. ASM International. pp. 114. ISBN 1615031103.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History and examples</heading><heading level='3'>Meteoric iron</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Meteorite and a meteoritic iron hatchet.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A<space/><link><target>meteorite</target></link><space/>and a hatchet that was forged from<space/><link><target>meteoric iron</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The use of alloys by humans started with the use of<space/><link><target>meteoric iron</target></link>, a naturally occurring alloy of<space/><link><target>nickel</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>iron</target></link>. It is the main constituent of<space/><link><target>iron meteorite</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which occasionally fall down on Earth from outer space. As no metallurgic processes were used to separate iron from nickel, the alloy was used as it was.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Rickard, T. A. 
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Use of Meteoric Iron
</arg><arg name="journal">Journal of the Royal Anthropological Institute
</arg><arg name="volume"><space/>71
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>1/2
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1941
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>55–66
</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.2307/2844401
</arg><arg name="jstor">2844401
</arg><arg name="publisher">Royal Anthropological Institute of Great Britain and Ireland</arg></template></extension><space/>Meteoric iron could be forged from a red heat to make objects such as tools, weapons, and nails. In many cultures it was shaped by cold hammering into knives and arrowheads. They were often used as anvils. Meteoric iron was very rare and valuable, and difficult for ancient people to work.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Buchwald</target><part>Buchwald</part></link>, pp. 1322</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bronze and brass</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bronzebeile.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bronze</target></link><space/>axe 1100&amp;nbsp;BC</part></link><link><target>File:Trzieher Bremen 1405.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bronze</target></link><space/>doorknocker</part></link>Iron is usually found as<space/><link><target>iron ore</target></link><space/>on Earth, except for one deposit of<space/><link><target>native iron</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Greenland</target></link>, which was used by the<space/><link><target>Inuit</target></link><space/>people.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Buchwald</target><part>Buchwald</part></link>, pp. 3537</extension><space/>Native<space/><link><target>copper</target></link>, however, was found worldwide, along with<space/><link><target>silver</target></link>,<space/><link><target>gold</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>platinum</target></link>, which were also used to make tools, jewelry, and other objects since Neolithic times. Copper was the hardest of these metals, and the most widely distributed. It became one of the most important metals to the ancients. Eventually, humans learned to<space/><link><target>smelting</target><part>smelt</part></link><space/>metals such as copper and<space/><link><target>tin</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>ore</target></link>, and, around 2500 BC, began alloying the two metals to form<space/><link><target>bronze</target></link>, which is much harder than its ingredients. Tin was rare, however, being found mostly in Great Britain. In the Middle East, people began alloying copper with<space/><link><target>zinc</target></link><space/>to form<space/><link><target>brass</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>#Buchwald</target><part>Buchwald</part></link>, pp. 3941</extension><space/>Ancient civilizations took into account the mixture and the various properties it produced, such as<space/><link><target>hardness</target></link>,<space/><link><target>toughness</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>melting point</target></link>, under various conditions of<space/><link><target>temperature</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>work hardening</target></link>, developing much of the information contained in modern<space/><link><target>Phase diagram</target><part>alloy phase diagram</part><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r1"></extension><space/>Arrowheads from the Chinese<space/><link><target>Qin dynasty</target></link><space/>(around 200 BC) were often constructed with a hard bronze-head, but a softer bronze-tang, combining the alloys to prevent both dulling and breaking during use.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wgbh/nova/ancient/emperors-ghost-army.html'>Emperor's Ghost Army</link>. pbs.org. November 2014</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Amalgams</heading><paragraph><link><target>Mercury (element)</target><part>Mercury</part></link><space/>has been smelted from<space/><link><target>cinnabar</target></link><space/>for thousands of years. Mercury dissolves many metals, such as gold, silver, and tin, to form<space/><link><target>amalgam (chemistry)</target><part>amalgam</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(an alloy in a soft paste, or liquid form at ambient temperature). Amalgams have been used since 200 BC in China for plating objects with precious metals, called<space/><link><target>gilding</target></link>, such as<space/><link><target>armor</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>mirror</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The ancient Romans often used mercury-tin amalgams for gilding their armor. The amalgam was applied as a paste and then heated until the mercury vaporized, leaving the gold, silver, or tin behind.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rapp, George (2009)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=ed0yC98aAKYC&amp;amp;pg=PA180'>''Archaeomineralogy''</link>. Springer. p. 180. ISBN 3-540-78593-0</extension><space/>Mercury was often used in mining, to extract precious metals like gold and silver from their ores.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miskimin, Harry A. (1977)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=QE04AAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA31'>''The economy of later Renaissance Europe, 14601600''</link>. Cambridge University Press. p. 31. ISBN 0-521-29208-5.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Precious-metal alloys</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:25 litrai en lectrum reprsentant un trpied delphien.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Electrum</target></link>, a natural alloy of silver and gold, was often used for making coins.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Many ancient civilizations alloyed metals for purely aesthetic purposes. In ancient<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mycenae</target></link>, gold was often alloyed with copper to produce red-gold, or iron to produce a bright burgundy-gold. Gold was often found alloyed with silver or other metals to produce various types of<space/><link><target>colored gold</target></link>. These metals were also used to strengthen each other, for more practical purposes. Copper was often added to silver to make<space/><link><target>sterling silver</target></link>, increasing its strength for use in dishes, silverware, and other practical items. Quite often, precious metals were alloyed with less valuable substances as a means to deceive buyers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Nicholson, Paul T. and Shaw, Ian (2000)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=Vj7A9jJrZP0C&amp;amp;pg=PA164'>''Ancient Egyptian materials and technology''</link>. Cambridge University Press. pp. 164167. ISBN 0-521-45257-0.</extension><space/>Around 250 BC,<space/><link><target>Archimedes</target></link><space/>was commissioned by the king to find a way to check the purity of the gold in a crown, leading to the famous bath-house shouting of &quot;Eureka!&quot; upon the discovery of<space/><link><target>Archimedes' principle</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kay, Melvyn (2008)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=xCtAV_MCD1EC&amp;amp;pg=PA45'>''Practical Hydraulics''</link>. Taylor and Francis. p. 45. ISBN 0-415-35115-4.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pewter</heading><paragraph>The term<space/><link><target>pewter</target></link><space/>covers a variety of alloys consisting primarily of tin. As a pure metal, tin was much too soft to be used for any practical purpose. However, in the<space/><link><target>Bronze age</target></link>, tin was a rare metal and, in many parts of Europe and the Mediterranean, was often valued higher than gold. To make jewelry, forks and spoons, or other objects from tin, it was usually alloyed with other metals to increase its strength and hardness. These metals were typically<space/><link><target>lead</target></link>,<space/><link><target>antimony</target></link>,<space/><link><target>bismuth</target></link><space/>or copper. These solutes sometimes were added individually in varying amounts, or added together, making a wide variety of things, ranging from practical items, like dishes, surgical tools, candlesticks or funnels, to decorative items such as ear rings and hair clips.</paragraph><paragraph>The earliest examples of pewter come from ancient Egypt, around 1450 BC. The use of pewter was widespread across Europe, from France to Norway and Britain (where most of the ancient tin was mined) to the Near East.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hull, Charles (1992)<space/><italics>Pewter</italics>. Shire Publications. pp. 34; ISBN 0747801525</extension><space/>The alloy was also used in China and the Far East, arriving in Japan around 800 AD, where it was used for making objects like ceremonial vessels, tea canisters, or chalices used in<space/><link><target>shinto</target></link><space/>shrines.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brinkley, Frank (1904)<space/><italics>Japan and China: Japan, its history, arts, and literature</italics>. Oxford University. p. 317</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Steel and pig iron</heading><paragraph>The first known smelting of iron began in<space/><link><target>Anatolia</target></link>, around 1800 BC. Called the<space/><link><target>bloomery</target><part>bloomery process</part></link>, it produced very soft but<space/><link><target>ductile</target></link><space/><link><target>wrought iron</target></link>. By 800 BC, iron-making technology had spread to Europe, arriving in Japan around 700 AD.<space/><link><target>Pig iron</target></link>, a very hard but brittle alloy of iron and<space/><link><target>carbon</target></link>, was being produced in<space/><link><target>History of China#Shang Dynasty (c. 17001046 BC)</target><part>China</part></link><space/>as early as 1200 BC, but did not arrive in Europe until the Middle Ages. Pig iron has a lower melting point than iron, and was used for making<space/><link><target>cast-iron</target></link>. However, these metals found little practical use until the introduction of<space/><link><target>crucible steel</target></link><space/>around 300 BC. These steels were of poor quality, and the introduction of<space/><link><target>pattern welding</target></link>, around the 1st century AD, sought to balance the extreme properties of the alloys by laminating them, to create a tougher metal. Around 700 AD, the Japanese began folding bloomery-steel and cast-iron in alternating layers to increase the strength of their swords, using clay fluxes to remove<space/><link><target>slag</target></link><space/>and impurities. This method of<space/><link><target>Japanese swordsmithing</target></link><space/>produced one of the purest steel-alloys of the early Middle Ages.<extension extension_name='ref' name="r1">Smith, Cyril (1960)<space/><italics>History of metallography</italics>. MIT Press. pp. 24. ISBN 0-262-69120-5.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>While the use of iron started to become more widespread around 1200 BC, mainly because of interruptions in the trade routes for tin, the metal is much softer than bronze. However, very small amounts of<space/><link><target>steel</target></link>, (an alloy of iron and around 1% carbon), was always a byproduct of the bloomery process. The ability to modify the hardness of steel by<space/><link><target>heat treatment</target></link><space/>had been known since 1100 BC, and the rare material was valued for the manufacture of tools and weapons. Because the ancients could not produce temperatures high enough to melt iron fully, the production of steel in decent quantities did not occur until the introduction of<space/><link><target>blister steel</target></link><space/>during the Middle Ages. This method introduced carbon by heating wrought iron in charcoal for long periods of time, but the penetration of carbon was not very deep, so the alloy was not homogeneous. In 1740,<space/><link><target>Benjamin Huntsman</target></link><space/>began melting blister steel in a crucible to even out the carbon content, creating the first process for the mass production of<space/><link><target>tool steel</target></link>. Huntsman's process was used for manufacturing tool steel until the early 1900s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="George Adam Roberts Page 2-3">Roberts, George Adam; Krauss, George; Kennedy, Richard and Kennedy, Richard L. (1998)<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=ScphevR_eP8C&amp;amp;pg=PA2'>''Tool steels''</link>. ASM International. pp. 23. ISBN 0-87170-599-0.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>With the introduction of the blast furnace to Europe in the Middle Ages,<space/><link><target>pig iron</target></link><space/>was able to be produced in much higher volumes than wrought iron. Because pig iron could be melted, people began to develop processes of reducing the carbon in the<space/><link><target>liquid</target></link><space/>pig iron to create steel.<space/><link><target>Puddling (metallurgy)</target><part>Puddling</part></link><space/>was introduced during the 1700s, where molten pig iron was stirred while exposed to the air, to remove the carbon by<space/><link><target>oxidation</target></link>. In 1858,<space/><link><target>Sir Henry Bessemer</target></link><space/>developed a process of steel-making by blowing hot air through liquid pig iron to reduce the carbon content. The<space/><link><target>Bessemer process</target></link><space/>was able to produce the first large scale manufacture of steel.<extension extension_name='ref' name="George Adam Roberts Page 2-3"></extension><space/>Once the Bessemer process began to gain widespread use, other alloys of steel began to follow.<space/><link><target>Mangalloy</target></link>, an alloy of steel and<space/><link><target>manganese</target></link><space/>exhibiting extreme hardness and toughness, was one of the first<space/><link><target>alloy steel</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and was created by<space/><link><target>Robert Hadfield</target></link><space/>in 1882.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Bramfitt, B. L.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Metallographer's Guide: Practice and Procedures for Irons and Steels</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">ASM International</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-61503-146-7</arg><arg name="pages">13–</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Precipitation-hardening alloys</heading><paragraph>In 1906,<space/><link><target>precipitation hardening</target></link><space/>alloys were discovered by<space/><link><target>Alfred Wilm</target></link>. Precipitation hardening alloys, such as certain alloys of<space/><link><target>aluminium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>titanium</target></link>, and copper, are heat-treatable alloys that soften when<space/><link><target>quenching</target><part>quenched</part></link><space/>(cooled quickly), and then harden over time. After quenching a ternary alloy of aluminium, copper, and<space/><link><target>magnesium</target></link>, Wilm discovered that the alloy increased in hardness when left to age at room temperature. Although an explanation for the phenomenon was not provided until 1919,<space/><link><target>duralumin</target></link><space/>was one of the first &quot;age hardening&quot; alloys to be used, and was soon followed by many others. Because they often exhibit a combination of high strength and low weight, these alloys became widely used in many forms of industry, including the construction of modern<space/><link><target>aircraft</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jacobs, M. H.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.slideshare.net/corematerials/talat-lecture-1204-precipitation-hardening-2318135'>Precipitation Hardnening</link>. University of Birmingham. TALAT Lecture 1204. slideshare.net</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>CALPHAD</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Ideal mixture</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of alloys</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>35em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="ref">Buchwald</arg><arg name="author">Buchwald, Vagn Fabritius<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="title">Iron and steel in ancient times</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Det Kongelige Danske Videnskabernes Selskab<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>8773043087</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>alloy</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Alloys</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite EB1911</target><arg name="wstitle">Alloys</arg><arg name="author">[[William Chandler Roberts-Austen]]; Francis Henry Neville<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.uni-ulm.de/~hhoster/personal/surface_alloys.html'>Surface Alloys</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite AmCyc</target><arg name="wstitle">Alloy<space/></arg><arg name="short">x</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Alloys</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Metallurgy</target></link><link><target>Category:Chemistry</target></link></paragraph></article>