<article title='Ada_Lovelace'><paragraph><template><target>Use British English</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template><template><target>Infobox person</target><arg name="name"><space/>Ada, Countess of Lovelace
<space/></arg><arg name="image"><space/>Ada Lovelace portrait.jpg
<space/></arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Ada, Countess of Lovelace, 1840
<space/></arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>The Hon. Augusta Ada Byron
</arg><arg name="birth_date">{{birth date|1815|12|10|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>London, England
<space/></arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|1852|11|27|1815|12|10|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Marylebone]], London, England
<space/></arg><arg name="resting_place"><space/>[[Church of St. Mary Magdalene, Hucknall]], Nottingham, England
<space/></arg><arg name="field"><space/>Mathematics, computing
<space/></arg><arg name="parents">
 {{plainlist |
* [[Lord Byron|George Gordon Byron, 6th Baron Byron]]
* [[Anne Isabella Byron, Baroness Byron|Anne Isabella Milbanke, 11th Baroness Wentworth]]
 }}
<space/></arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[William King-Noel, 1st Earl of Lovelace]]
<space/></arg><arg name="children">
 {{plainlist |
* [[Byron King-Noel, Viscount Ockham|Byron King-Noel, Viscount Ockham and 12th Baron Wentworth]]
* [[Anne Blunt, 15th Baroness Wentworth]]
* [[Ralph King-Milbanke, 2nd Earl of Lovelace]]}}
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Countess of Lovelace</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Augusta Ada King, Countess of Lovelace</bold><space/>(<italics>ne</italics><space/><bold>Byron</bold>; 10 December 1815&amp;nbsp; 27 November 1852) was a British mathematician and writer, chiefly known for her work on<space/><link><target>Charles Babbage</target></link>'s early mechanical general-purpose computer, the<space/><link><target>Analytical Engine</target></link>. Her notes on the engine include what is recognised as the first<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>intended to be carried out by a machine. Because of this, she is often regarded as the first computer<space/><link><target>programmer</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Annals of the History of Computing"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Fuegi</arg><arg>Francis</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">16–26</arg></template>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Phillips</arg><arg name="first">Ana Lena</arg><arg name="title">Crowdsourcing gender equity: Ada Lovelace Day, and its companion website, aims to raise the profile of women in science and technology</arg><arg name="journal">American Scientist</arg><arg name="date">November–December 2011</arg><arg name="volume">99</arg><arg name="issue">6</arg><arg name="page">463</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Lovelace Google"><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="date">10 December 2012</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/technology/2012/dec/10/ada-lovelace-honoured-google-doodle</arg><arg name="title">Ada Lovelace honoured by Google doodle</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Guardian</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 December 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lovelace was born 10 December 1815 as the only legitimate child of the poet<space/><link><target>Lord Byron</target><part>George Gordon, Lord Byron</part></link><space/>and his wife<space/><link><target>Anne Isabella Byron, Baroness Byron</target><part>Anne Isabella Milbanke</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.biography.com/people/ada-lovelace-20825323'>Ada Lovelace Biography</link>, biography.com</extension><space/>All<space/><link><target>Lord Byron#Children</target><part>Byron's other children</part></link><space/>were born out of wedlock to other women.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCL"></extension><space/>Byron separated from his wife a month after Ada was born and left England forever four months later, eventually dying of disease in the<space/><link><target>Greek War of Independence</target></link><space/>when Ada was eight years old. Ada's mother remained bitter towards Lord Byron and promoted Ada's interest in mathematics and logic in an effort to prevent her from developing what she saw as the<space/><link><target>insanity</target></link><space/>seen in her father, but Ada remained interested in him despite this (and was, upon her eventual death, buried next to him at her request).</paragraph><paragraph>Ada described her approach as &quot;poetical science&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">234–235</arg></template><space/>and herself as an &quot;Analyst (&amp; Metaphysician)&quot;.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">156–157</arg></template><space/>As a teen, her mathematical talents led her to an ongoing working relationship and friendship with fellow British mathematician Charles Babbage also known as father of computers, and in particular, Babbage's work on the Analytical Engine. Between 1842 and 1843, she translated an article by Italian military engineer<space/><link><target>Luigi Menabrea</target></link><space/>on the engine, which she supplemented with an elaborate set of notes of her own, simply called<space/><italics>Notes</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>These notes contain what many consider to be the first computer programthat is, an algorithm designed to be carried out by a machine. Lovelace's notes are important in the early<space/><link><target>history of computers</target></link>. She also developed a vision of the capability of computers to go beyond mere calculating or number-crunching, while others, including Babbage himself, focused only on those capabilities.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Fuegi</arg><arg>Francis</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">19, 25</arg></template><space/>Her mind-set of &quot;poetical science&quot; led her to ask questions about the Analytical Engine (as shown in her notes) examining how individuals and society relate to technology as a collaborative tool.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCL"><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Toole</arg><arg name="first">Betty Alexandra</arg><arg name="title">Poetical Science</arg><arg name="journal">The Byron Journal</arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="pages">55–65</arg><arg name="doi">10.3828/bj.1987.6</arg></template>.</extension><template><target>Listen</target><arg name="type">speech</arg><arg name="pos">right</arg><arg name="filename">Ada Lovelace (As Told By U.S. Chief Technology Officer Megan Smith).ogg</arg><arg name="title">Ada Lovelace (As Told By U.S. Chief Technology Officer Megan Smith)</arg><arg name="description"><space/></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Childhood</heading><paragraph>Byron expected his baby to be a &quot;glorious boy&quot; and was disappointed when his wife gave birth to a girl.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template><space/>Augusta was named after Byron's half-sister,<space/><link><target>Augusta Leigh</target></link>, and was called &quot;Ada&quot; by Byron himself.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Stein</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Miniature of Ada Byron.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Ada, aged four</part></link>On 16 January 1816 Annabella, at Byron's behest, left for her parents' home at<space/><link><target>Kirkby Mallory</target></link><space/>taking one-month-old Ada with her.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">35</arg></template><space/>Although English law at the time gave fathers full custody of their children in cases of separation, Byron made no attempt to claim his parental rights<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Stein</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">16</arg></template><space/>but did request that his sister keep him informed of Ada's welfare.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">80</arg></template><space/>On 21 April Byron signed the Deed of Separation, although very reluctantly, and left England for good a few days later.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="pp">36–38</arg></template><space/>Aside from an acrimonious separation, Annabella continually made allegations about Byron's immoral behaviour throughout her life.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">74–77</arg></template><space/>This set of events made Ada famous in Victorian society. Byron did not have a relationship with his daughter, and never saw her again. He died in 1824 when she was eight years old. Her mother was the only significant parental figure in her life.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Turney p. 138"><template><target>Harvnb</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">138</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Ada was not shown the family portrait of her father (covered in green shroud) until her twentieth birthday.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">10</arg></template><space/>Her mother became Baroness Wentworth in her own right in 1856.</paragraph><paragraph>Annabella did not have a close relationship with the young Ada, and often left her in the care of her own mother Judith, Hon. Lady Milbanke, who doted on her grandchild. However, because of societal attitudes of the timewhich favoured the husband in any separation, with the welfare of any child acting as mitigationAnnabella had to present herself as a loving mother to the rest of society. This included writing anxious letters to Lady Milbanke about Ada's welfare, with a cover note saying to retain the letters in case she had to use them to show maternal concern.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">85–87</arg></template><space/>In one letter to Lady Milbanke, she referred to Ada as &quot;it&quot;: &quot;I talk to it for your satisfaction, not my own, and shall be very glad when you have it under your own.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">86</arg></template><space/>In her teenage years, several of her mother's close friends watched Ada for any sign of moral deviation. Ada dubbed these observers the &quot;Furies&quot;, and later complained they exaggerated and invented stories about her.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">119</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ada Byron aged seventeen (1832).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>left</part><part>Ada, aged seventeen, 1832</part></link>Ada was often ill, beginning in early childhood. At the age of eight, she experienced headaches that obscured her vision.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg><space/>Stein</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">17</arg></template><space/>In June 1829, she was paralysed after a bout of<space/><link><target>measles</target></link>. She was subjected to continuous bed rest for nearly a year, which may have extended her period of disability. By 1831 she was able to walk with crutches. Despite being ill Ada developed her mathematical and technological skills. At age 12 this future &quot;Lady Fairy&quot;, as Charles Babbage affectionately called her, decided she wanted to fly. Ada went about the project methodically, thoughtfully, with imagination and passion. Her first step in February 1828, was to construct wings. She investigated different material and sizes. She considered various materials for the wings; paper, oilsilk, wires and feathers. She examined the anatomy of birds to determine the right proportion between the wings and the body. She decided to write a book<space/><italics>Flyology</italics><space/>illustrating, with plates, some of her findings. She decided what equipment she would need, for example, a compass, to &quot;cut across the country by the most direct road&quot;, so that she could surmount mountains, rivers and valleys. Her final step was to integrate steam with the &quot;art of flying&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCL"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In early 1833 Ada had an affair with a tutor and, after being caught, tried to elope with him. The tutor's relatives recognised her and contacted her mother. Annabella and her friends covered the incident up to prevent a public scandal.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">120–21</arg></template><space/>Ada never met her younger half-sister,<space/><link><target>Allegra Byron</target><part>Allegra</part></link>, the daughter of Lord Byron and<space/><link><target>Claire Clairmont</target></link>. Allegra died in 1822 at the age of five. Ada did have some contact with<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Medora Leigh</target></link>, the daughter of Byron's half-sister Augusta Leigh, who purposely avoided Ada as much as possible when introduced at Court.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">155</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Adult years</heading><paragraph>Lovelace developed a strong relationship with her tutor<space/><link><target>Mary Somerville</target></link>, who would introduce her to Charles Babbage in 1833. She had a strong respect and affection for Somerville.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">138–40</arg></template><space/>and the two of them corresponded for many years. Other acquaintances included<space/><link><target>Andrew Crosse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>David Brewster</target><part>Sir David Brewster</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles Wheatstone</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles Dickens</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Michael Faraday</target></link>. She was presented at Court at the age of seventeen &quot;and became a popular belle of the season&quot; in part because of her &quot;brilliant mind.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">138</arg></template><space/>By 1834 Ada was a regular at Court and started attending various events. She danced often and was able to charm many people, and was described by most people as being dainty, although<space/><link><target>John Hobhouse, 1st Baron Broughton</target><part>John Hobhouse</part></link>, Byron's friend, described her as &quot;a large, coarse-skinned young woman but with something of my friend's features, particularly the mouth&quot;.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="pp">138–39</arg></template><space/>This description followed their meeting on 24 February 1834 in which Ada made it clear to Hobhouse that she did not like him, probably because of the influence of her mother, which led her to dislike all of her father's friends. This first impression was not to last, and they later became friends.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">139</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On 8 July 1835 she married<space/><link><target>William King, 1st Earl of Lovelace</target><part>William, 8th Baron King</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="williamkings" group="lower-alpha"></extension><space/>becoming Lady King.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://www.thepeerage.com/p2744.htm#i27434</arg><arg name="contribution">Ada Augusta Byron</arg><arg name="title">The Peerage</arg></template>.</extension><space/>Their residence was<space/><link><target>Ockham Park</target></link>, a large estate in<space/><link><target>Surrey</target></link>, along with another estate on<space/><link><target>Torridon</target><part>Loch Torridon</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Ross-shire</target></link>, and a home in London. They spent their honeymoon at Worthy Manor in Ashley Combe near<space/><link><target>Porlock Weir</target></link>, Somerset. The Manor had been built as a hunting lodge in 1799 and was improved by King in preparation for their honeymoon. It later became their summer retreat and was further improved during this time.</paragraph><paragraph>They had three children:<space/><link><target>Byron King-Noel, Viscount Ockham</target><part>Byron</part></link><space/>(born 12 May 1836);<space/><link><target>Lady Anne Blunt</target><part>Anne Isabella</part></link><space/>(called Annabella; born 22 September 1837); and<space/><link><target>Ralph King-Milbanke, 2nd Earl of Lovelace</target><part>Ralph Gordon</part></link><space/>(born 2 July 1839). Immediately after the birth of Annabella, Lady King experienced &quot;a tedious and suffering illness, which took months to cure.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">139</arg></template><space/>In 1838, her husband was made<space/><link><target>Earl of Lovelace</target></link><space/>and Viscount Ockham,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Lovelace, Earl of</arg><arg name="url">http://www.cracroftspeerage.co.uk/online/content/lovelace1838.htm</arg><arg name="publisher">Cracroft's Peerage</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg></template></extension><space/>meaning Ada became the Countess of Lovelace. In 184344, Ada's mother assigned<space/><link><target>William Benjamin Carpenter</target></link><space/>to teach Ada's children, and to act as a 'moral' instructor for Ada.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">285–86</arg></template><space/>He quickly fell for her, and encouraged her to express any frustrated affections, claiming that his marriage meant he'd never act in an &quot;unbecoming&quot; manner. When it became clear that Carpenter was trying to start an affair, Ada cut it off.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">289–96</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In 1841 Lovelace and<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Medora Leigh</target><part>Medora Leigh</part></link><space/>(the daughter of Lord Byron's half-sister Augusta Leigh) were told by Ada's mother that her father was also Medora's father.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">159</arg></template><space/>On 27 February 1841 Ada wrote to her mother: &quot;I am not in the least astonished. In fact you merely confirm what I have for years and years felt scarcely a doubt about, but should have considered it most improper in me to hint to you that I in any way suspected.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">160</arg></template><space/>She did not blame the incestuous relationship on Byron, but instead blamed Augusta Leigh: &quot;I fear she is more inherently wicked than he ever was.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Moore</arg><arg>1961</arg><arg name="p">431</arg></template><space/>In the 1840s Ada flirted with scandals: firstly from a relaxed relationship with men who were not her husband, which led to rumours of affairs<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">302</arg></template>and secondly, her love of gambling. The gambling led to her forming a syndicate with male friends, and an ambitious attempt in 1851 to create a mathematical model for successful large bets. This went disastrously wrong, leaving her thousands of pounds in debt to the syndicate, forcing her to admit it all to her husband.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">340–42</arg></template><space/>She had a shadowy relationship with Andrew Crosse's son John from 1844 onwards. John Crosse destroyed most of their correspondence after her death as part of a legal agreement. She bequeathed him the only heirlooms her father had personally left to her.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">336–37</arg></template><space/>During her final illness, she would panic at the idea of the younger Crosse being kept from visiting her.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">361</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Education</heading><paragraph>Throughout her illnesses, she continued her education.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Stein</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="pp">28–30</arg></template><space/>Her mother's obsession with rooting out any of the insanity of which she accused Byron was one of the reasons that Ada was taught mathematics from an early age. She was privately schooled in mathematics and science by<space/><link><target>William Frend (social reformer)</target><part>William Frend</part></link>, William King,<extension extension_name='ref' name="williamkings" group="lower-alpha">Sources disagree on whether William King, her maths tutor, and William King, her later husband, were the same person.</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mary Somerville</target></link>, the noted researcher and scientific author of the 19th century. One of her later tutors was the mathematician and logician<space/><link><target>Augustus De Morgan</target></link>. From 1832, when she was seventeen, her remarkable mathematical abilities began to emerge,<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Turney</arg><arg>1972</arg><arg name="p">138</arg></template><space/>and her interest in mathematics dominated the majority of her adult life. In a letter to Lady Byron, De Morgan suggested that her daughter's skill in mathematics could lead her to become &quot;an original mathematical investigator, perhaps of first-rate eminence&quot;.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Stein</arg><arg>1985</arg><arg name="p">82</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lovelace often questioned basic assumptions by integrating poetry and science. While studying<space/><link><target>differential calculus</target></link>, she wrote to De Morgan:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>I may remark that the curious transformations many formulae can undergo, the unsuspected and to a beginner apparently impossible identity of forms exceedingly dissimilar at first sight, is I think one of the chief difficulties in the early part of mathematical studies. I am often reminded of certain sprites and fairies one reads of, who are at one's elbows in one shape now, and the next minute in a form most dissimilar...<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="p">99</arg></template></extension><space/>Lovelace believed that intuition and imagination were critical to effectively applying mathematical and scientific concepts. She valued<space/><link><target>metaphysics</target></link><space/>as much as mathematics, viewing both as tools for exploring &quot;the unseen worlds around us&quot;.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">91–100</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Death</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ada Lovelace in 1852.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Painting of Ada Lovelace at a piano in 1852 by Henry Phillips. While she was in great pain at the time, she sat for the painting as Phillips' father, Thomas Phillips, had painted Ada's father, Lord Byron.</part></link>Lovelace died at the age of 36&amp;nbsp; the same age that her father had died&amp;nbsp; on 27 November 1852,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="publisher">GRO</arg><arg name="title">Register of Deaths</arg><arg name="contribution">December 1852 1a * MARYLEBONE&nbsp;– Augusta Ada Lovelace</arg></template>.</extension><space/>from<space/><link><target>uterine cancer</target></link><space/>probably exacerbated by<space/><link><target>bloodletting</target></link><space/>by her physicians.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Baum</arg><arg>1986</arg><arg name="pp">99–100</arg></template><space/>The illness lasted several months, in which time Annabella took command over whom Ada saw, and excluded all of her friends and confidants. Under her mother's influence, she had a religious transformation and was coaxed into repenting of her previous conduct and making Annabella her executor.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">370</arg></template><space/>She lost contact with her husband after she confessed something to him on 30 August which caused him to abandon her bedside. What she told him is unknown.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">369</arg></template><space/>She was buried, at her request, next to her father at the<space/><link><target>Church of St. Mary Magdalene, Hucknall</target><part>Church of St. Mary Magdalene</part></link><space/>in Hucknall, Nottinghamshire.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Work</heading><paragraph>Throughout her life, Lovelace was strongly interested in scientific developments and fads of the day, including<space/><link><target>phrenology</target></link><template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">198</arg></template><space/>and<space/><link><target>mesmerism</target></link>.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">232–33</arg></template><space/>After her work with Babbage, Lovelace continued to work on other projects. In 1844 she commented to a friend Woronzow Greig about her desire to create a mathematical model for how the brain gives rise to thoughts and nerves to feelings (&quot;a calculus of the nervous system&quot;).<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">305</arg></template><space/>She never achieved this, however. In part, her interest in the brain came from a long-running pre-occupation, inherited from her mother, about her 'potential' madness. As part of her research into this project, she visited the electrical engineer Andrew Crosse in 1844 to learn how to carry out electrical experiments.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">310–14</arg></template><space/>In the same year, she wrote a review of a paper by Baron<space/><link><target>Karl von Reichenbach</target></link>,<space/><italics>Researches on Magnetism</italics>, but this was not published and does not appear to have progressed past the first draft.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">315–17</arg></template><space/>In 1851, the year before her cancer struck, she wrote to her mother mentioning &quot;certain productions&quot; she was working on regarding the relation of maths and music.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">335</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Ada Lovelace.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Portrait of Ada by British painter<space/><link><target>Margaret Sarah Carpenter</target></link><space/>(1836)</part></link>Lovelace first met Babbage in June 1833, through their mutual friend Mary Somerville. Later that month Babbage invited Lovelace to see the prototype for his<space/><link><target>Difference Engine</target></link>.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">36–38</arg></template><space/>She became fascinated with the machine and used her relationship with Somerville to visit Babbage as often as she could. Babbage was impressed by Lovelace's intellect and analytic skills. He called her<space/><italics>The Enchantress of Numbers</italics>. In 1843 he wrote of her:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quote</target><arg name="Forget this world and all its troubles and if possible its multitudinous Charlatans—every thing in short but the Enchantress of Numbers.{{Sfn|Toole|1998|p">xi}}</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>anchor</target><arg>Ada_Byron's_notes_on_the_analytical_engine</arg></template>During a nine-month period in 184243, Lovelace translated the Italian mathematician<space/><link><target>Luigi Menabrea</target></link>'s article on Babbage's newest proposed machine, the<space/><link><target>Analytical Engine</target></link>. With the article, she appended a set of notes.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Menabrea</arg><arg>1843</arg></template><space/>Explaining the Analytical Engine's function was a difficult task, as even other scientists did not really grasp the concept and the British establishment was uninterested in it.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">265</arg></template><space/>Lovelace's notes even had to explain how the Engine differed from the original Difference Engine.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">267</arg></template><space/>Her work was well received at the time; the scientist<space/><link><target>Michael Faraday</target></link><space/>described himself as a supporter of her writing.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p"><space/>307</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The notes are around three times longer than the article itself and include (in Section G<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html</arg><arg name="title">Sketch of ''The Analytical Engine'', with notes upon the Memoir by the Translator</arg><arg name="publisher">fourmilab.ch</arg><arg name="place">[[Switzerland]]</arg><arg name="date"></arg><arg name="accessdate">28 March 2014</arg></template></extension>), in complete detail, a method for calculating a sequence of<space/><link><target>Bernoulli numbers</target></link><space/>with the Engine, which would have run correctly had the Analytical Engine been built (only his Difference Engine has been built, completed in London in 2002).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.computerhistory.org/babbage</arg><arg name="title">The Babbage Engine</arg><arg name="publisher">Computer History Museum</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg></template></extension><space/>Based on this work Lovelace is now widely considered the first computer programmer<extension extension_name='ref' name="Annals of the History of Computing"></extension><space/>and her method is recognised as the world's first computer program.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gleick, J. (2011)<space/><italics><link><target>The Information: A History, a Theory, a Flood</target></link></italics>, London, Fourth Estate, pp. 116118.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Section G also contains Lovelace's dismissal of<space/><link><target>artificial intelligence</target></link>. She wrote that &quot;The Analytical Engine has no pretensions whatever to originate anything. It can do whatever we know how to order it to perform. It can follow analysis; but it has no power of anticipating any analytical relations or truths.&quot; This objection has been the subject of much debate and rebuttal, for example by<space/><link><target>Alan Turing</target></link><space/>in his paper &quot;<link><target>Computing Machinery and Intelligence</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Lovelace and Babbage had a minor falling out when the papers were published, when he tried to leave his own statement (a criticism of the government's treatment of his Engine) as an unsigned prefacewhich would imply that she had written that also. When<space/><link><target>Richard Taylor (editor)</target><part>Taylor</part></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Scientific Memoirs</target></link></italics><space/>ruled that the statement should be signed, Babbage wrote to Lovelace asking her to withdraw the paper. This was the first that she knew he was leaving it unsigned, and she wrote back refusing to withdraw the paper. The historian<space/><link><target>Benjamin Woolley</target></link><space/>theorised that, &quot;His actions suggested he had so enthusiastically sought Ada's involvement, and so happily indulged her&amp;nbsp;... because of her 'celebrated name'.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">277–80</arg></template><space/>Their friendship recovered, and they continued to correspond. On 12 August 1851, when she was dying of cancer, Lovelace wrote to him asking him to be her executor, though this letter did not give him the necessary legal authority. Part of the terrace at Worthy Manor was known as<space/><italics>Philosopher's Walk</italics>, as it was there that Lovelace and Babbage were reputed to have walked while discussing mathematical principles.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">307</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>First computer program</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Diagram for the computation of Bernoulli numbers.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Lovelace's diagram from Note G, the first published computer algorithm</part></link>In 1840, Babbage was invited to give a seminar at the<space/><link><target>University of Turin</target></link><space/>about his Analytical Engine.<space/><link><target>Luigi Menabrea</target></link>, a young Italian engineer, and the future<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of Italy</target></link>, wrote up Babbage's lecture in French, and this transcript was subsequently published in the<space/><link><target>Bibliothque universelle de Genve</target></link><space/>in October 1842.Babbage's friend<space/><link><target>Charles Wheatstone</target></link><space/>commissioned Lovelace to translate Menabrea's paper into English. She then augmented the paper with notes, which were added to the translation. Lovelace spent the better part of a year doing this, assisted with input from Babbage. These notes, which are more extensive than Menabrea's paper, were then published in<space/><italics>Taylor's<space/><link><target>Scientific Memoirs</target></link></italics><space/>under the<space/><link><target>initialism</target></link><space/><italics>AAL</italics>. In 1953, more than a century after her death, Lovelace's notes on Babbage's Analytical Engine were republished. The engine has now been recognised as an early model for a computer and her notes as a description of a computer and software.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Fuegi</arg><arg>Francis</arg><arg>2003</arg><arg name="pp">16–26</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Lovelace's notes were labelled alphabetically from A to G. In note G, she describes an<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>for the Analytical Engine to compute<space/><link><target>Bernoulli number</target><trail>s</trail></link>. It is considered the first algorithm ever specifically tailored for implementation on a computer, and Ada has often been cited as the first computer programmer for this reason.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Simonite</arg><arg name="first">Tom</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newscientist.com/blogs/shortsharpscience/2009/03/ada-lovelace-day.html</arg><arg name="title">Short Sharp Science: Celebrating Ada Lovelace: the 'world's first programmer'</arg><arg name="work">New Scientist</arg><arg name="date">24 March 2009</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 April 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Parker</arg><arg name="first1">Matt</arg><arg name="title">Things to Make and Do in the Fourth Dimension</arg><arg name="date">2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Farrar, Straus & Giroux</arg><arg name="isbn">0374275653</arg><arg name="page">261</arg></template></extension><space/>The engine was never completed so her code was never tested.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kim_toole"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Conceptual leap</heading><paragraph>In her notes, Lovelace emphasised the difference between the Analytical Engine and previous calculating machines, particularly its ability to be programmed to solve problems of any complexity.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">175–82</arg></template><space/>She realised the potential of the device extended far beyond mere number crunching. She wrote:<template><target>Quote</target><arg name="<p>[The Analytical Engine] might act upon other things besides number, were objects found whose mutual fundamental relations could be expressed by those of the abstract science of operations, and which should be also susceptible of adaptations to the action of the operating notation and mechanism of the engine...</p>

<p>Supposing, for instance, that the fundamental relations of pitched sounds in the science of harmony and of musical composition were susceptible of such expression and adaptations, the engine might compose elaborate and scientific pieces of music of any degree of complexity or extent.<ref>{{cite web|last">Hooper|first</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>This analysis was a conceptual leap from previous ideas about the capabilities of computing devices, and anticipated the capabilities and implications of modern computing one hundred years before they were realised.<space/><link><target>Walter Isaacson</target></link><space/>ascribes Lovelace's insight regarding the application of computing to<space/><italics>any</italics><space/>process based on logical symbols to an observation about textiles: &quot;When she saw some mechanical looms that used<space/><link><target>punched cards</target><part>punchcards</part></link><space/>to direct the weaving of beautiful<space/><link><target>Pattern</target><part>patterns</part></link>, it reminded her of how Babbages engine used punched cards to make calculations.&quot;<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="Isaacson">Isaacson, Walter. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://fortune.com/2014/09/18/walter-isaacson-the-women-of-eniac/'>Walter Isaacson on the women of ENIAC</link>.&quot; Fortune magazine. 18 September 2014.</extension><space/>This insight is seen as significant by writers such as Betty Toole and Benjamin Woolley, as well as the programmer<space/><link><target>John Graham-Cumming</target></link>, whose project Plan 28 has the aim of constructing the first complete Analytical Engine.<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Toole</arg><arg>1998</arg><arg name="pp">2–3, 14</arg></template><template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="pp">272–77</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Kent</arg><arg name="first">Leo</arg><arg name="url">http://www.humansinvent.com/#!/8947/the-10-year-plan-to-build-babbages-analytical-engine</arg><arg name="title">The 10-year-plan to build Babbage's Analytical Engine</arg><arg name="publisher">Humans Invent</arg><arg name="date">17 September 2012</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 October 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Controversy over extent of contributions</heading><heading level='3'>Criticism</heading><paragraph>Though Lovelace is sometimes referred to as the first computer programmer, at least two people have published claims to the contrary:</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Allan Bromley (historian)</target><part>Allan G. Bromley</part></link>, in the 1990 essay<space/><italics>Difference and Analytical Engines</italics>, wrote,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Bromley</arg><arg name="first">Allan G.</arg><arg name="contribution">"Difference and Analytical Engines</arg><arg name="title">Computing Before Computers</arg><arg name="editor-first">William</arg><arg name="editor-last">Aspray</arg><arg name="publisher">Iowa State Press</arg><arg name="year">1990</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>All but one of the programs cited in her notes had been prepared by Babbage from three to seven years earlier. The exception was prepared by Babbage for her, although she did detect a 'bug' in it. Not only is there no evidence that Ada ever prepared a program for the Analytical Engine, but her correspondence with Babbage shows that she did not have the knowledge to do so.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:AdaLovelaceplaque.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Blue plaque</target></link><space/>to Lovelace in<space/><link><target>St. James's Square</target></link>, London</part></link>In his PhD thesis, Bruce Collier, who went on to write a minor biography of Babbage aimed at school children, claimed:<template><target>quote</target><arg name="It would be only a slight exaggeration to say that Babbage wrote the 'Notes' to Menabrea's paper, but for reasons of his own encouraged the illusion in the minds of Ada and the public that they were authored by her. It is no exaggeration to say that she was a manic depressive with the most amazing delusions about her own talents, and a rather shallow understanding of both Charles Babbage and the Analytical Engine.<ref>{{Citation|last">Collier|first</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Defence</heading><paragraph>Lovelace did, however, work for nine months on her article while consulting with Babbage on difficult equations. By Babbage's own admission, she pointed out what otherwise might have been remembered as the first<space/><link><target>computer bug</target></link><space/>in his equations, which also makes her possibly the world's first<space/><link><target>debugger</target></link>. Of Lovelace's contribution, Babbage wrote, in his<space/><italics>Passages from the Life of a Philosopher</italics><space/>(1864):<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Passages from the life of a philosopher</arg><arg name="first">Charles</arg><arg name="last">Babbage</arg><arg name="year">1864</arg><arg name="page">136</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8135-2066-5</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>I then suggested that she add some notes to Menabrea's memoir, an idea which was immediately adopted. We discussed together the various illustrations that might be introduced; I suggested several but the selection was entirely her own. So also was the algebraic working out of the different problems, except, indeed, that relating to the numbers of Bernoulli, which I had offered to do to save Lady Lovelace the trouble. This she sent back to me for an amendment, having detected a grave mistake which I had made in the process.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Eugene Eric Kim and Betty Alexandar Toole elucidate Lovelace's role in writing the first computer program by describing her role as that of a programmer who derives an<space/><link><target>algorithm</target></link><space/>from a<space/><link><target>formula</target></link>:<extension extension_name='ref' name="kim_toole"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>From this letter, two things are clear. First, including a program that computed Bernoulli numbers was Ada's idea. Second, Babbage at the very least provided the formulas for calculating Bernoulli numbers... Letters between Babbage and Ada at the time seem to indicate that Babbage's contributions were limited to the mathematical formula and that Ada created the program herself.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Kim and Toole also write:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="[Lovelace] was certainly capable of writing the program herself given the proper formula; this is clear from her depth of understanding regarding the process of programming and from her improvements on Babbage's programming notation.<ref name">"kim_toole">{{cite journal|title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The curator and author<space/><link><target>Doron Swade</target></link>, in his 2001 book<space/><italics>The Difference Engine</italics>, writes:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="The first algorithms or stepwise operations leading to a solution—what we now recognize as a 'program', although the word was used neither by her nor by Babbage—were certainly published under her name. But the work had been completed by Babbage much earlier.<ref>{{Citation|last">Swade|first</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Kim and Toole dispute this claim:<extension extension_name='ref' name="kim_toole"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Babbage had written several small programs for the Analytical Engine in his notebook in 1836 and 1837, but none of them approached the complexity of the Bernoulli numbers program.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Far more clear is her important role and legacy as an author in<space/><link><target>prediction</target><part>predicting</part></link><space/>the potential of computers to perform tasks more complex than simple industrial<space/><link><target>arithmetic</target></link>, as well as her role as an inspiration to Babbage and generations of computer scientists to come afterwards.</paragraph><paragraph>The writer Benjamin Woolley writes that while Lovelace's mathematical abilities have been contested,<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">276</arg></template><space/>she can claim &quot;some contribution&quot;:<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">272</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>Note A, the first she wrote, and the one over which Babbage had the least influence, contains a sophisticated analysis of the idea and implications of mechanical computation...</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Woolley claims that this discussion of the implications of Babbage's invention was the most important aspect of her work. According to Woolley, her notes were &quot;detailed and thorough [a]nd still... metaphysical, meaningfully so.&quot; They explained how the machine worked and &quot;[rose] above the technical minutiae of Babbage's extraordinary invention to reveal its true grandeur.&quot;<template><target>Sfn</target><arg>Woolley</arg><arg>1999</arg><arg name="p">277</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Finally, according to ComputerHistory.org:<extension extension_name='ref' name="computerhistory"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Ada Lovelace - The Babbage Engine</arg><arg name="url">http://www.computerhistory.org/babbage/adalovelace/<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">13 November 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg><space/>She has been referred to as '[the] [[prophet]] of the computer age'. Certainly she was the first to express the potential for computers outside mathematics.</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ada Lovelace color.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>An illustration inspired by the<space/><link><target>A. E. Chalon</target></link><space/>portrait created for the<space/><link><target>Ada Initiative</target></link>, which supports open technology and women</part></link>Lovelace has been portrayed in<space/><link><target>Romulus Linney (playwright)</target><part>Romulus Linney</part></link>'s 1977 play<space/><italics><link><target>Childe Byron</target></link></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Theatre in review: A lusty Byron in Rockland</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[New York Times]]</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1984/05/13/nyregion/theater-in-review-a-lusty-byron-in-rockland.html</arg><arg name="first">Alvin</arg><arg name="last">Klein</arg><arg name="authorlink">Alvin Klein</arg><arg name="date">13 May 1984</arg></template></extension><space/>the 1990<space/><link><target>steampunk</target></link><space/>novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Difference Engine</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>William Gibson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Bruce Sterling</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="contribution">The Future Looms: Weaving Women and Cybernetics</arg><arg name="first">Sadie</arg><arg name="last">Plant</arg><arg name="pages">45–64</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="title">Cyberspace/Cyberbodies/Cyberpunk: Cultures of Technological Embodiment</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Mike</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Featherstone</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Roger</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Burrows</arg><arg name="publisher">SAGE Publications, in association with ''Theory, Culture & Society'', School of Human Studies, Univ. of Teesside</arg><arg name="year">1995</arg></template></extension><space/>the 1997 film<space/><italics><link><target>Conceiving Ada</target></link></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">'Conceiving Ada': Calling Byron's Daughter, Inventor of a Computer</arg><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/library/film/022699ada-film-review.html</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[New York Times]]</arg><arg name="first">Stephen</arg><arg name="last">Holden</arg><arg name="authorlink">Stephen Holden</arg><arg name="date">26 February 1999</arg></template></extension><space/>and in<space/><link><target>John Crowley</target></link>'s 2005 novel<space/><italics>Lord Byron's Novel: The Evening Land</italics>, where she is featured as an unseen character whose personality is forcefully depicted in her annotations and anti-heroic efforts to archive her father's lost novel.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Byron's heir</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Los Angeles Times]]</arg><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/2005/jun/05/books/bk-straub5</arg><arg name="first">Peter</arg><arg name="last">Straub</arg><arg name="authorlink">Peter Straub</arg><arg name="date">5 June 2005</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Tom Stoppard</target></link>'s 1993 play<space/><italics><link><target>Arcadia (play)</target><part>Arcadia</part></link></italics>, the precocious teenage genius Thomasina Coverly (a character &quot;apparently based&quot; on Ada Lovelacethe play also involves<space/><link><target>Lord Byron</target></link>) comes to understand<space/><link><target>chaos theory</target></link>, and theorises the<space/><link><target>second law of thermodynamics</target></link>, before either is officially recognised.<extension extension_name='ref' name="newyorker13">&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.newyorker.com/books/page-turner/tom-stoppards-arcadia-at-twenty'>Tom Stoppards 'Arcadia,' at Twenty&quot;</link>.<space/><italics>The New Yorker</italics>.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tomw.net.au/arcadia.txt'>Profile</link>, Gale Edwards, 1994, Director of &quot;Arcadia&quot; for the Sydney Theatre Company</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Lovelace and Babbage are the main characters in<space/><link><target>Sydney Padua</target></link>'s webcomic and graphic novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Thrilling Adventures of Lovelace and Babbage</target></link></italics>. The comic features extensive footnotes on the history of Ada Lovelace and many lines of dialogue are drawn from actual correspondence.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Doctorow</arg><arg name="first1">Cory</arg><arg name="title">Comic about Ada Lovelace and Charles Babbage</arg><arg name="url">http://boingboing.net/2009/10/05/comic-about-ada-love.html</arg><arg name="website">BoingBoing</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 October 2014</arg><arg name="date">5 October 2009</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Commemoration</heading><paragraph>The computer language<space/><link><target>Ada (programming language)</target><part>Ada</part></link>, created on behalf of the<space/><link><target>United States Department of Defense</target></link>, was named after Lovelace. The reference manual for the language was approved on 10 December 1980 and the<space/><link><target>United States Military Standard</target><part>Department of Defense Military Standard</part></link><space/>for the language,<space/><italics>MIL-STD-1815</italics>, was given the number of the year of her birth. Since 1998 the<space/><link><target>British Computer Society</target></link><space/>has awarded a<space/><link><target>Lovelace Medal</target><part>medal</part></link><space/>in her name<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://www.bcs.org/server.php?show</arg><arg name="title">Lovelace Lecture & Medal</arg><arg name="publisher">BCS</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 March 2008</arg></template></extension><space/>and in 2008 initiated an annual competition for women students of computer science.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="publisher">Leeds</arg><arg name="url">http://www.comp.leeds.ac.uk/bcswomen</arg><arg name="title">Undergraduate Lovelace Colloquium, BCSWomen</arg><arg name="accessdate">6 March 2008</arg></template></extension>In the UK the<space/><link><target>BCSWomen</target></link><space/>Lovelace Colloquium, the annual conference for women undergraduates is named after Lovelace.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.aber.ac.uk/en/cs/lovelace-colloquium/<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>UK<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>BCSWomen Lovelace Colloquium<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Ada Lovelace Day&quot; is an annual event celebrated in mid-October<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="work"><space/>About<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://findingada.com/about/faq/<space/></arg><arg name="title">FAQ<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Finding Ada<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>10 December 2012</arg></template></extension><space/>whose goal is to &quot;...&amp;nbsp;raise the profile of women in science, technology, engineering and maths,&quot; and to &quot;create new role models for girls and women&quot; in these fields.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Ada Initiative</target></link><space/>is a non-profit organisation dedicated to increasing the involvement of women in the free culture and open source movements.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url">https://lwn.net/Articles/471813/<space/></arg><arg name="title">An update on the Ada Initiative<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>LWN<space/></arg><arg name="last">Aurora<space/></arg><arg name="first">Valerie<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 December 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>5 October 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Engineering in Computer Science and Telecommunications College building in<space/><link><target>Zaragoza University</target></link><space/>is called the Ada Byron Building.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Ada Byron Building<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://wikimapia.org/1641862/Ada-Byron-Building</arg></template></extension><space/>The village computer centre in the village of<space/><link><target>Porlock</target></link>, near where Ada Lovelace lived, is named after her. There is a building in the small town of<space/><link><target>Kirkby-in-Ashfield</target></link>, Nottinghamshire named<space/><italics>Ada Lovelace House</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="publisher">Ashfield District Council</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ashfield-dc.gov.uk/ccm/navigation/business/business-support/conference-facilities/</arg><arg name="title">Conference Facilities</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 October 2012</arg></template></extension>One of the<space/><link><target>tunnel boring machine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>excavating the tunnels for London's<space/><link><target>Crossrail</target></link><space/>project is named<space/><italics>Ada</italics><space/>in commemoration of Ada Lovelace.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Kremer</arg><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="title">Crossrail: Where is it in the list of 'big digs'?</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/magazine-23518137</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News</arg><arg name="date">1 August 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Ada: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and Technology</italics><space/>is an &quot;open-access, multi-modal,<space/><link><target>open peer review</target><part>[open-]peer-reviewed</part></link><space/>feminist journal concerned with the intersections of gender, new media, and technology&quot; that began in 2012 and is run by the Fembot Collective.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://adanewmedia.org/faq/</arg><arg name="title">FAQ - Ada: A Journal of Gender, New Media, and Technology</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Oregon Libraries</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 April 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Adafruit Industries</target></link><space/>is an open-source hardware company named in honour of Lovelace.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">PCH</arg><arg name="title">PCH Talks with Limor Fried</arg><arg name="url">https://theblueprint.com/stories/limor-fried/</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 April 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Titles and styles by which she was known</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>10 December 1815&amp;nbsp; 8 July 1835: The Honourable Ada Byron</listitem><listitem>8 July 1835&amp;nbsp; 30 June 1838: The Right Honourable The Lady King</listitem><listitem>30 June 1838&amp;nbsp; 27 November 1852: The Right Honourable The Countess of Lovelace</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Ancestry</heading><paragraph><template><target>ahnentafel top</target><arg name="width">100%</arg></template><template><target>ahnentafel-compact5</target><arg name="style"><space/>1. '''Augusta Ada King, Countess of Lovelace'''
</arg><arg name="border"><space/>2. [[Lord Byron|George Gordon Byron, 6th Baron Byron]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle"><space/>3. [[Anne Isabella Byron, Baroness Byron|Anne Isabella Milbanke, 11th Baroness Wentworth]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_1"><space/>4. [[John "Mad Jack" Byron|Captain John Byron]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_2"><space/>5. Catherine Gordon
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_3"><space/>6. Admiral Sir Ralph Milbanke, [[Milbanke baronets|6th Baronet, of Halnaby]]
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_4"><space/>7. The Hon. Judith Noel
</arg><arg name="boxstyle_5"><space/>8. [[John Byron|Vice Admiral The Hon. John Byron]]
</arg><arg name="1"><space/>9. Sophia Trevanion
</arg><arg name="2"><space/>10. [[George Gordon of Gight]]
</arg><arg name="3"><space/>11. Catherine Innes
</arg><arg name="4"><space/>12. Sir Ralph Milbanke, [[Milbanke baronets|5th Baronet, of Halnaby]]
</arg><arg name="5"><space/>13. Elizabeth Hedworth
</arg><arg name="6"><space/>14. Edward Noel, [[Baron Wentworth|1st Viscount Wentworth]]
</arg><arg name="7"><space/>15. Judith Lamb
</arg><arg name="8"><space/>16. [[William Byron, 4th Baron Byron]]
</arg><arg name="9"><space/>17. The Hon. Frances [[William Berkeley, 4th Baron Berkeley of Stratton|Berkeley]]
</arg><arg name="10"><space/>18. John Trevanion
</arg><arg name="11"><space/>19. The Hon. Barbara [[William Berkeley, 4th Baron Berkeley of Stratton|Berkeley]]
</arg><arg name="12"><space/>20. Alexander Gordon of [[Gight]]
</arg><arg name="13"><space/>21. Margaret Duff
</arg><arg name="14"><space/>22. Alexander Innes
</arg><arg name="15"><space/>23. Katherine Abercromby
</arg><arg name="16"><space/>24. Sir Ralph Milbanke, [[Milbanke baronets|4th Baronet, of Halnaby]]
</arg><arg name="17"><space/>25. Anne Delaval
</arg><arg name="18"><space/>26. John Hedworth
</arg><arg name="19"><space/>27. Susanna Sophia Pelsant
</arg><arg name="20"><space/>28. [[Sir Clobery Noel, 5th Baronet|Sir Clobery Noel, 5th Baronet, of Kirkby Mallery]]
</arg><arg name="21"><space/>29. Elizabeth Rowney
</arg><arg name="22"><space/>30. William Lamb
</arg><arg name="23"><space/>31. Martha
</arg><arg name="24"><space/>24. Sir Ralph Milbanke, [[Milbanke baronets|4th Baronet, of Halnaby]]
</arg><arg name="25"><space/>25. Anne Delaval
</arg><arg name="26"><space/>26. John Hedworth
</arg><arg name="27"><space/>27. Susanna Sophia Pelsant
</arg><arg name="28"><space/>28. [[Sir Clobery Noel, 5th Baronet|Sir Clobery Noel, 5th Baronet, of Kirkby Mallery]]
</arg><arg name="29"><space/>29. Elizabeth Rowney
</arg><arg name="30"><space/>30. William Lamb
</arg><arg name="31"><space/>31. Martha
</arg></template><template><target>ahnentafel bottom</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Publications</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link type='external' href='http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html'>Sketch of the Analytical Engine Invented by Charles Babbage, Esq.</link></italics><space/>with notes by trans. Ada Lovelace, in<space/><italics><link><target>Scientific Memoirs</target></link>, Vol 3</italics><space/>(1842).</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Computer programming</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>Great Lives</target></link></italics><space/>(BBC Radio 4) aired on 17 September 2013 was dedicated to the story of Ada Lovelace.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b03b0ydy</arg><arg name="title">BBC Radio 4 - Great Lives, Series 31, Konnie Huq on Ada Lovelace</arg><arg name="work">[[BBC]]</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Women in computing</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Notelist</target></template>Sources make it clear that William King, her tutor, and William King, her future husband, were not related.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wade, Mary Dodson.<space/><italics>Ada Byron Lovelace: The Lady and the Computer.</italics><space/>New York: Dillon Press, 1994.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>18em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Baum<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Joan<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Calculating Passion of Ada Byron<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Archon<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1986<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-208-02119-1</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Elwin<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Malcolm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Lord Byron's Family<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Murray<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1975</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Essinger<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada's algorithm: How Lord Byron's daughter Ada Lovelace launched the digital age<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Melville House Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-1-61219-408-0</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Fuegi<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>J<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Francis<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>J<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Lovelace & Babbage and the creation of the 1843 'notes'<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>IEEE<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Annals of the History of Computing<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>25<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="date">October–December 2003<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1109/MAHC.2003.1253887</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Isaacson<space/></arg><arg name="first">Walter<space/></arg><arg name="date">2014<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Innovators: How a Group of Hackers, Geniuses, and Geeks Created the Digital Revolution<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Simon & Schuster</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Kim<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Eugene<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Toole<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Betty Alexandra<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada and the First Computer<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Scientific American<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 1999</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lewis<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Judith S.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Princess of Parallelograms and her daughter: Math and gender in the nineteenth century English aristocracy<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Women's Studies International Forum]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>18<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>4<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>387–394<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[ScienceDirect]]<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1016/0277-5395(95)80030-S<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>July–August 1995<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0277-5395(95)80030-S<space/></arg><arg name="ref"><space/>harv<space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/>.</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Marchand<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Leslie<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Byron A Portrait<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Murray<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1971</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Menabrea<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Luigi Federico<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Federico Luigi Menabrea<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1843<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Sketch of the Analytical Engine Invented by Charles Babbage<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[Scientific Memoirs]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>3<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>29 August 2008<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080915134651/http://www.fourmilab.ch/babbage/sketch.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>15 September 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template><space/>With notes upon the memoir by the translator.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Doris Langley<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada, Countess of Lovelace<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Murray<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1977</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Moore<space/></arg><arg name="first">Doris Langley<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Late Lord Byron<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1961<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Lippincott<space/></arg><arg name="location">Philadelphia<space/></arg><arg name="oclc">358063<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-06-013013-X</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Stein<space/></arg><arg name="first">Dorothy<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ada: A Life and a Legacy<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1985<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">The MIT Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, [[Massachusetts|MA]]<space/></arg><arg name="series">MIT Press Series in the History of Computing<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-262-19242-X</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Betty Alexandra<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Toole<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada, the Enchantress of Numbers: A Selection from the Letters of Ada Lovelace, and her Description of the First Computer<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1992<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Strawberry Press<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0912647094</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Betty Alexandra<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Toole<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada, the Enchantress of Numbers: Prophet of the Computer Age<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Strawberry Press<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0912647183</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first"><space/>Catherine<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Turney<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Byron's Daughter: A Biography of Elizabeth Medora Leigh<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1972<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Scribner<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0684127539</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Woolley<space/></arg><arg name="first">Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 1999<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Bride of Science: Romance, Reason, and Byron's Daughter<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Pan Macmillan<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>AU<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>7 April 2013<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-333-72436-4</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last">Woolley<space/></arg><arg name="first">Benjamin<space/></arg><arg name="date">February 2002<space/></arg><arg name="origyear">1999<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Bride of Science: Romance, Reason, and Byron's Daughter<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>McGraw-Hill Ryerson<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>7 April 2013<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-07138860-3</arg></template>.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource author</target><arg>Augusta Ada Byron</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.sdsc.edu/ScienceWomen/lovelace.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace: Founder of Scientific Computing<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>SDSC<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Women in Science</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.agnesscott.edu/lriddle/women/love.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Byron, Lady Lovelace<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Biographies of Women Mathematicians<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Agnes Scott College]]</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://archiveshub.ac.uk/data/gb161dep.lovelacebyron1-460<space/></arg><arg name="title">Papers of the Noel, Byron and Lovelace families<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Archives hub<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>UK</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.computerhistory.org/babbage/adalovelace/<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Babbage<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace & The Analytical Engine<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Computer History</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://net.educause.edu/apps/er/review/reviewArticles/31240.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Ada & the Analytical Engine<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Educause</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.g4tv.com/techtvvault/features/27659/Ada_Lovelace_Countess_of_Controversy.html<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Tech TV vault<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace, Countess of Controversy<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>G4 TV</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.bbc.co.uk/radio4/history/inourtime/inourtime_20080306.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>The BBC (Radio 4)<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>In Our Time<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>streaming<space/></arg><arg name="type"><space/>audio<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>UK<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>6 March 2008</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cs.yale.edu/homes/tap/Files/ada-lovelace-notes.html<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace's Notes and The Ladies Diary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Yale</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The fascinating story Ada Lovelace<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sabine Allaeys (Youtube)</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.brainpickings.org/index.php/2013/12/10/ada-lovelace-science-religion-letter/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Ada Lovelace, the World’s First Computer Programmer, on Science and Religion<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Maria Popova (Brain)<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.brainpickings.org/2014/12/10/ada-lovelace-walter-isaacson-innovators/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>How Ada Lovelace, Lord Byron’s Daughter, Became the World’s First Computer Programmer<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Maria Popova (Brain)<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>MacTutor Biography</target><arg name="id">Lovelace</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Byron</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Lovelace, Ada King, Countess Of</target></template><link><target>Category:1815 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1852 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century English mathematicians</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century women scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century women writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Ada (programming language)</target></link><link><target>Category:British computer scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:British countesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials in Nottinghamshire</target></link><link><target>Category:Byron family</target></link><link><target>Category:Cancer deaths in England</target></link><link><target>Category:Computer designers</target></link><link><target>Category:Daughters of barons</target></link><link><target>Category:Deaths from uterine cancer</target></link><link><target>Category:English computer programmers</target></link><link><target>Category:English computer scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:English people of Scottish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:English scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:English women poets</target></link><link><target>Category:Lord Byron</target></link><link><target>Category:Programming language designers</target></link><link><target>Category:Women computer scientists</target></link><link><target>Category:Women in engineering</target></link><link><target>Category:Women in technology</target></link><link><target>Category:Women mathematicians</target></link><link><target>Category:Women of the Victorian era</target></link></paragraph></article>