<article title='Beltane'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the Scottish rock band</arg><arg>The Beltanes</arg></template><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Beltaine</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox holiday</target><arg name="holiday_name"><space/>Beltane
</arg><arg name="type"><space/>default
</arg><arg name="longtype"><space/>Cultural,<br>Pagan ([[Celtic polytheism]], [[Celtic Neopaganism]], [[Wicca]])
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Beltane Bonfire on Calton Hill.JPG 
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>A Beltane [[bonfire]] on [[Calton Hill]] in Edinburgh
</arg><arg name="nickname"><space/>''Lá Bealtaine'' (Irish)<br>''Là Bealltainn'' (Scottish Gaelic)<br>''Laa Boaltinn/Boaldyn''<ref>Celtic myths and legends by Charles Squire ISBN 1-84204-015-4</ref><space/>(Manx)<br>Beltaine; Beltine<ref name</arg><arg name="observedby"><space/>Historically: [[Gaels]]<br>Today: [[Irish people]], [[Scottish people]], [[Manx people]], [[Celtic Neopaganism|Celtic neopagans]] and [[Wicca]]ns
</arg><arg name="significance"><space/>beginning of summer
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1 May<br><small>(or 1 November for Neopagans in the [[Southern Hemisphere|S. Hemisphere]])</small><space/>
</arg><arg name="celebrations"><space/>lighting bonfires, decorating homes with May flowers, making May bushes, visiting holy wells, feasting
</arg><arg name="relatedto"><space/>May Day, [[Calan Mai]], [[Walpurgis Night]]
</arg><arg name="frequency"><space/>annual
</arg><arg name="duration"><space/>1 day
</arg></template><bold>Beltane</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>ɛ</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>.</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>ei</arg><arg>n</arg></template>)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beltane</arg><arg name="url">http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/Beltane?s</arg><arg name="work">Dictionary.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Beltane</arg><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/beltane</arg><arg name="work">Merriam-Webster Dictionary</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>Anglicisation</target><part>anglicised</part></link><space/>name for the<space/><link><target>Gaels</target><part>Gaelic</part></link><space/>May Day festival. Most commonly it is held on 1 May, or about halfway between the<space/><link><target>March equinox</target><part>spring equinox</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>summer solstice</target></link>. Historically, it was widely observed throughout Ireland,<space/><link><target>Scotland</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Isle of Man</target></link>. In Irish the name for the festival day is<space/><italics>L Bealtaine</italics><space/>(<template><target>IPA-ga</target><arg>l̪ˠaː ˈbʲal̪ˠt̪ˠənʲə</arg><arg></arg></template>), in<space/><link><target>Scottish Gaelic</target></link><space/><italics>L Bealltainn</italics><space/>(<template><target>IPA-gd</target><arg>l̪ˠa: ˈpjaul̪ˠt̪ˠɪɲ</arg><arg></arg></template>) and in<space/><link><target>Manx language</target><part>Manx Gaelic</part></link><space/><italics>Laa Boaltinn/Boaldyn</italics>. It is one of the four Gaelic seasonal festivalsalong with<space/><link><target>Samhain</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Imbolc</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lughnasadh</target></link>and is similar to the Welsh<space/><link><target>Calan Mai</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Beltane is mentioned in some of the<space/><link><target>Early Irish literature</target><part>earliest Irish literature</part></link><space/>and it is associated with important events in<space/><link><target>Irish mythology</target></link>. It marked the beginning of summer and was when cattle were driven out to the summer pastures. Rituals were performed to protect the cattle, crops and people, and to encourage growth. Special<space/><link><target>bonfire</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were kindled, and their flames, smoke and ashes were deemed to have protective powers. The people and their cattle would walk around the bonfire or between two bonfires, and sometimes leap over the flames or embers. All household fires would be doused and then re-lit from the Beltane bonfire. These gatherings would be accompanied by a feast, and some of the food and drink would be offered to the<space/><italics><link><target>aos s</target></link></italics>. Doors, windows, byres and the cattle themselves would be decorated with yellow May flowers, perhaps because they evoked fire. In parts of Ireland, people would make a May Bush: a thorn bush decorated with flowers, ribbons and bright shells.<space/><link><target>Holy well</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were also visited, while Beltane<space/><link><target>dew</target></link><space/>was thought to bring beauty and maintain youthfulness. Many of these customs were part of May Day or Midsummer festivals in other parts of Great Britain and Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>Beltane celebrations had largely died out by the mid-20th century, although some of its customs continued and in some places it has been revived as a cultural event. Since the late 20th century,<space/><link><target>Celtic Neopaganism</target><part>Celtic neopagans</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wicca</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>have observed Beltane, or something based on it, as a religious holiday. Neopagans in the Southern Hemisphere often celebrate Beltane at the other end of the year (around 1 November).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historic Beltane customs</heading><paragraph>Beltane was one of four Gaelic seasonal festivals:<space/><link><target>Samhain</target></link><space/>(~1 November),<space/><link><target>Imbolc</target></link><space/>(~1 February), Beltane (~1 May) and<space/><link><target>Lughnasadh</target></link><space/>(~1 August). Beltane marked the beginning of the pastoral summer season, when livestock were driven out to the summer pastures.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton">Hutton, Ronald.<space/><italics>The Stations of the Sun: A History of the Ritual Year in Britain</italics>. Oxford University Press, 1996. pp.&amp;nbsp;218225</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="koch">Koch, John T.<space/><italics>Celtic Culture: A Historical Encyclopedia</italics>. 2006. p.&amp;nbsp;202</extension><space/>Rituals were held at that time to protect them from harm, both natural and supernatural, and this mainly involved the &quot;symbolic use of fire&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>There were also rituals to protect crops, dairy products and people, and to encourage growth. The<space/><italics><link><target>aos s</target></link></italics><space/>(often referred to as spirits or fairies) were thought to be especially active at Beltane (as at Samhain)<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>and the goal of many Beltane rituals was to appease them. Most scholars see the<space/><italics>aos s</italics><space/>as remnants of the pagan gods and nature spirits.<extension extension_name='ref'>Santino, Jack.<space/><italics>The Hallowed Eve: Dimensions of Culture in a Calendar Festival of Northern Ireland</italics>. University Press of Kentucky, 1998. p.&amp;nbsp;105</extension><space/>Beltaine was a &quot;spring time festival of optimism&quot; during which &quot;fertility ritual again was important, perhaps connecting with the waxing power of the sun&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chadwick"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Before the modern era</heading><paragraph>Beltane (the beginning of summer) and Samhain (the beginning of winter) are thought to have been the most important of the four Gaelic festivals. Sir<space/><link><target>James George Frazer</target></link><space/>wrote in<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics><space/>that the times of Beltane and Samhain are of little importance to European crop-growers, but of great importance to herdsmen. Thus, he suggests that halving the year at 1 May and 1 November dates from a time when the Celts were mainly a pastoral people, dependent on their herds.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>James George Frazer</target><part>Frazer, Sir James George</part></link>.<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics>. Forgotten Books, 2008. p.&amp;nbsp;644</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest mention of Beltane is in<space/><link><target>Old Irish literature</target></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Gaelic Ireland</target></link>. According to the early medieval texts<space/><italics><link><target>Sanas Cormaic</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Tochmarc Emire</target></link></italics>, Beltane was held on 1 May and marked the beginning of summer. The texts say that, to protect cattle from disease, the<space/><link><target>druid</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>would make two fires &quot;with great incantations&quot; and drive the cattle between them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stokes, Whitley (ed.) and John O'Donovan (tr.).<space/><italics>Sanas Cormaic: Cormac's Glossary</italics>. Irish Archaeological and Celtic Society. Calcutta: O.T. Cutter, 1868.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T301021/index.html'>''The Wooing of Emer by C Chulainn'' Translated by Kuno Meyer</link>. CELT: Corpus of Electronic Texts.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to 17th century historian<space/><link><target>Geoffrey Keating</target></link>, there was a great gathering at the hill of<space/><link><target>Uisneach</target></link><space/>each Beltane in medieval Ireland, where a sacrifice was made to a god named Beil. Keating wrote that two bonfires would be lit in every district of Ireland, and cattle would be driven between them to protect them from disease.<extension extension_name='ref'>Keating, Geoffrey.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucc.ie/celt/published/T100054/index.html'>''The History of Ireland'' Translated by David Comyn and Patrick S. Dinneen</link>. CELT: Corpus of Electronic Texts.</extension><space/>There is no reference to such a gathering in<space/><link><target>Irish annals</target><part>the annals</part></link>, but the medieval<space/><italics><link><target>Dindsenchas</target></link></italics><space/>includes a tale of a hero lighting a holy fire on Uisneach that blazed for seven years. Ronald Hutton writes that this may &quot;preserve a tradition of Beltane ceremonies there&quot;, but adds &quot;Keating or his source may simply have conflated this legend with the information in<space/><italics>Sanas Chormaic</italics><space/>to produce a piece of pseudo-history.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>Nevertheless, excavations at Uisneach in the 20th century found evidence of large fires and charred bones, showing it to have been ritually significant.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="patterson2">Patterson, Nerys.<space/><italics>Cattle Lords and Clansmen: The Social Structure of Early Ireland</italics>. University of Notre Dame Press, 1994. p.&amp;nbsp;139</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="mackillop">MacKillop, James.<space/><italics>A Dictionary of Celtic Mythology</italics>. Oxford University Press, 1998. pp.&amp;nbsp;39, 400402, 421</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern era</heading><paragraph>From the late 18th century to the mid 20th century, many accounts of Beltane customs were recorded by<space/><link><target>folkloristics</target><part>folklorists</part></link><space/>and other writers.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Bonfires</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Beltain Festival at Butser Ancient Farm - geograph.org.uk - 268.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A Beltane bonfire at<space/><link><target>Butser Ancient Farm</target></link></part></link>Bonfires continued to be a key part of the festival in the modern era. All hearth fires and candles would be doused before the bonfire was lit, generally on a mountain or hill.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chadwick"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher">Danaher, Kevin (1972)<space/><italics>The Year in Ireland: Irish Calendar Customs</italics><space/>Dublin, Mercier. ISBN 1-85635-093-2 pp. 86127</extension><space/><link><target>Ronald Hutton</target></link><space/>writes that &quot;To increase the potency of the holy flames, in Britain at least they were often kindled by the most primitive of all means, of friction between wood.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>In the 19th century, for example, John Ramsay described Scottish Highlanders kindling a<space/><link><target>need-fire</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>force-fire</target></link><space/>at Beltane. Such a fire was deemed sacred.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>In the 19th century, the ritual of driving cattle between two firesas described in<space/><italics>Sanas Cormaic</italics><space/>almost 1000 years beforewas still practised across most of Ireland and in parts of Scotland.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>Sometimes the cattle would be driven &quot;around&quot; a bonfire or be made to leap over flames or embers. The people themselves would do likewise.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>In the Isle of Man, people ensured that the smoke blew over them and their cattle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="koch"></extension><space/>When the bonfire had died down, people would daub themselves with its ashes and sprinkle it over their crops and livestock.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>Burning torches from the bonfire would be taken home, where they would be carried around the house or boundary of the farmstead<extension extension_name='ref'>Evans,<space/><italics>Irish Folk Ways</italics>, pp. 274275</extension><space/>and would be used to re-light the hearth.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>From these rituals, it is clear that the fire was seen as having protective powers.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>Similar rituals were part of May Day, Midsummer or Easter customs in other parts of the British Isles and mainland Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Frazer, James George (1922).<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/frazer/index.htm'>Chapter 62: The Fire-Festivals of Europe</link>.</extension><space/>According to Frazer, the fire rituals are a kind of<space/><link><target>sympathetic magic</target><part>imitative or sympathetic magic</part></link>. According to one theory, they were meant to mimic the Sun and to &quot;ensure a needful supply of sunshine for men, animals, and plants&quot;. According to another, they were meant to symbolically &quot;burn up and destroy all harmful influences&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Frazer, James George (1922).<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/frazer/gb06301.htm'>Chapter 63, Part 1: On the Fire-festivals in general</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Beltane_Fire_Dragon.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A Beltane bonfire at<space/><link><target>WEHEC</target></link><space/>2015</part></link>Food was also cooked at the bonfire and there were rituals involving it.<space/><link><target>Alexander Carmichael</target></link><space/>wrote that there was a feast featuring lamb, and that formerly this lamb was sacrificed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carmichael,<space/><italics><link><target>Carmina Gadelica</target></link><space/>Volume 1</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;191</extension><space/>In 1769,<space/><link><target>Thomas Pennant</target></link><space/>wrote that, in<space/><link><target>Perthshire</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>caudle</target></link><space/>made from eggs, butter, oatmeal and milk was cooked on the bonfire. Some of the mixture was poured on the ground as a<space/><link><target>libation</target></link>. Everyone present would then take an oatmeal cake, called the<space/><italics>bannoch Bealltainn</italics><space/>or &quot;Beltane<space/><link><target>Bannock (food)</target><part>bannock</part></link>&quot;. A bit of it was offered to the spirits to protect their livestock (one bit to protect the horses, one bit to protect the sheep, and so forth) and a bit was offered to each of the animals that might harm their livestock (one to the fox, one to the eagle, and so forth). Afterwards, they would drink the caudle.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to 18th century writers, in parts of Scotland there was another ritual involving the oatmeal cake. The cake would be cut and one of the slices marked with charcoal. The slices would then be put in a<space/><link><target>Bonnet (headgear)</target><part>bonnet</part></link><space/>and everyone would take one out while blindfolded. According to one writer, whomever got the marked piece would have to leap through the fire three times. According to another, those present would pretend to throw him into the fire and, for some time afterwards, they would speak of him as if he were dead. This &quot;may embody a memory of actual human sacrifice&quot;, or it may have always been symbolic.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>A similar ritual (i.e. of pretending to burn someone in the fire) was practised at spring and summer bonfire festivals in other parts of Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Frazer, James George (1922).<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/frazer/gb06402.htm'>Chapter 64, Part 2: The Burning of Men and Animals in the Fires</link>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Flowers and May Bushes</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hawthorn in flower on Smeardon Down.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A flowering hawthorn</part></link>Yellow flowers such as<space/><link><target>Primula vulgaris</target><part>primrose</part></link>,<space/><link><target>rowan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Crataegus monogyna</target><part>hawthorn</part></link>,<space/><link><target>gorse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>hazel</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Caltha palustris</target><part>marsh marigold</part></link><space/>were placed at doorways and windows in 19th century Ireland, Scotland and Mann. Sometimes loose flowers were strewn at the doors and windows and sometimes they were made into<space/><link><target>flower bouquet</target><part>bouquets</part></link>,<space/><link><target>garland</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or crosses and fastened to them. They would also be fastened to cows and equipment for milking and butter making. It is likely that such flowers were used because they evoked fire.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hutton"></extension><space/>Similar May Day customs are found across Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>The May Bush was popular in parts of Ireland until the late 19th century. This was a small tree or branchtypically hawthorn, rowan or sycamoredecorated with bright flowers, ribbons, painted shells, and so forth. There were household May Bushes (which would be placed outside each house) and communal May Bushes (which would be set in a public spot or paraded around the neighbourhood). In<space/><link><target>Dublin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Belfast</target></link>, May Bushes were brought into town from the countryside and decorated by the whole neighbourhood.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><space/>Each neighbourhood vied for the most handsome tree and, sometimes, residents of one would try to steal the May Bush of another. This led to the May Bush being outlawed in<space/><link><target>Victorian era</target><part>Victorian times</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><space/>In some places, it was customary to dance around the May Bush, and at the end of the festivities it may be burnt in the bonfire.<extension extension_name='ref' name="clark">Clark, Katharine.<space/><italics>An Irish Book of Shadows</italics>. Galde Press, 2001. p.&amp;nbsp;172</extension><space/>Some, however, were left in place for a month. Thorn trees were seen as special trees and were associated with the<space/><italics>aos s</italics>. The custom of decorating a May Bush or<space/><link><target>Maypole</target><part>May Tree</part></link><space/>was found in many parts of Europe. Frazer believes that such customs are a relic of<space/><link><target>tree worship</target></link><space/>and writes: &quot;The intention of these customs is to bring home to the village, and to each house, the blessings which the<space/><link><target>List of tree deities</target><part>tree-spirit</part></link><space/>has in its power to bestow.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Frazer, James George (1922).<space/><italics><link><target>The Golden Bough</target><part>The Golden Bough: A Study in Magic and Religion</part></link></italics>.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/pag/frazer/gb01000.htm'>Chapter 10: Relics of Tree Worship in Modern Europe</link>.</extension><space/><link><target>Emyr Estyn Evans</target></link><space/>suggests that the May Bush custom may have come to Ireland from England, because it seemed to be found in areas with strong English influence and because the Irish saw it as unlucky to damage certain thorn trees.<extension extension_name='ref' name="folkways"><link><target>Emyr Estyn Evans</target><part>Evans, Emyr Estyn</part></link>.<space/><italics>Irish Folk Ways</italics>. Routledge, 1957. pp.&amp;nbsp;272274</extension><space/>However, &quot;lucky&quot; and &quot;unlucky&quot; trees varied by region, and it has been suggested that Beltane was the only time when cutting thorn trees was allowed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="watts">Watts, D C.<space/><italics>Dictionary of Plant Lore</italics>. Academic Press, 2007. p.&amp;nbsp;246</extension><space/>The practice of bedecking a May Bush with flowers, ribbons, garlands and bright shells is found among the Gaelic diaspora, most notably in<space/><link><target>Newfoundland (island)</target><part>Newfoundland</part></link>, and in some Easter traditions on the<space/><link><target>East Coast of the United States</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Other customs</heading><paragraph><link><target>Holy well</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were often visited at Beltane, and at the other Gaelic festivals of Imbolc and Lughnasadh. Visitors to holy wells would pray for health while walking<space/><link><target>sunwise</target></link><space/>(moving from east to west) around the well. They would then leave offerings; typically coins or<space/><link><target>clootie</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>clootie well</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><space/>The first water drawn from a well on Beltane was seen as being especially potent, as was Beltane morning<space/><link><target>dew</target></link>. At dawn on Beltane, maidens would roll in the dew or wash their faces with it. It would also be collected in a jar, left in the sunlight, and then filtered. The dew was thought to increase sexual attractiveness, maintain youthfulness, and help with skin ailments.<extension extension_name='ref' name="koch"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="clark"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>People also took steps specifically to ward-off or appease the<space/><italics><link><target>aos s</target></link></italics>. Food was left or milk poured at the doorstep or places associated with the<space/><italics>aos s</italics>, such as 'fairy trees', as an offering.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Evans, p. 272">Evans,<space/><italics>Irish Folk Ways</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;272</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Danaher,<space/><italics>The Year in Ireland</italics>, p.&amp;nbsp;121</extension><space/>In Ireland, cattle would be brought to '<link><target>fairy fort</target><trail>s</trail></link>', where a small amount of their blood would be collected. The owners would then pour it into the earth with prayers for the herd's safety. Sometimes the blood would be left to dry and then be burnt.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Evans, p. 272"></extension><space/>It was thought that dairy products were especially at risk from harmful spirits.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McNeill2">McNeill (1959) Vol. 2. p.&amp;nbsp;63</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell"><link><target>John Gregorson Campbell</target><part>Campbell, John Gregorson</part></link><space/>(1900, 1902, 2005)<space/><italics>The Gaelic Otherworld</italics>. Edited by Ronald Black. Edinburgh, Birlinn Ltd. ISBN 1-84158-207-7 pp.&amp;nbsp;5524</extension><space/>To protect farm produce and encourage fertility, farmers would lead a procession around the boundaries of their farm. They would &quot;carry with them seeds of grain, implements of husbandry, the first well water, and the herb vervain (or rowan as a substitute). The procession generally stopped at the four cardinal points of the compass, beginning in the east, and rituals were performed in each of the four directions&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Danaher,<space/><italics>The Year in Ireland</italics>, pp. 116117</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The festival persisted widely up until the 1950s, and in some places the celebration of Beltane continues today.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mackillop"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McNeill2"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Campbell"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Revival</heading><paragraph>As a festival, Beltane had largely died out by the mid-20th century, although some of its customs continued and in some places it has been revived as a cultural event. In Ireland, Beltane fires were common until the mid 20th century,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><space/>but the custom seems to have lasted to the present day only in<space/><link><target>County Limerick</target></link><space/>(especially in<space/><link><target>Limerick</target></link><space/>itself) and in<space/><link><target>Arklow</target></link>,<space/><link><target>County Wicklow</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wicklowpeople.ie/news/council-faces-cleanup-bill-after-maybush-fires-1021379.html'>Council faces clean-up after maybush fires.</link><space/>Wicklow People, 5 May 2005.</extension><space/>However, the custom has been revived in some parts of the country. Some cultural groups have sought to revive the custom at<space/><link><target>Uisneach</target></link><space/>and perhaps at the<space/><link><target>Hill of Tara</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Aideen O'Leary reports (&quot;An Irish Apocryphal Apostle: Muirch's Portrayal of Saint Patrick&quot;<space/><italics>The Harvard Theological Review</italics><space/><bold>89</bold>.3 [July 1996:287301] p. 289) that, for didactic and dramatic purposes, the festival of Beltane, as presided over by Patrick's opponent King<space/><link><target>Legaire mac Nill</target></link>, was moved to the eve of Easter and from Uisneach to Tara by<space/><link><target>Muirchu moccu Machtheni</target><part>Muirch</part></link><space/>(late 7th century) in his<space/><italics>Vita sancti Patricii</italics>; he describes the festival as<space/><italics>in Temora, istorium Babylone</italics><space/>(&quot;at Tara, their Babylon&quot;). However there is no authentic connection of Tara with Babylon, nor any known connection of Tara with Beltane.</extension><space/>The lighting of a community Beltane fire from which each hearth fire is then relit is observed today in some parts of the<space/><link><target>Gaelic diaspora</target></link>, though in most of these cases it is a cultural revival rather than an unbroken survival of the ancient tradition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danaher"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Dames">Dames, Michael (1992)<space/><italics>Mythic Ireland</italics>. London, Thames &amp; Hudson ISBN 0-500-27872-5. pp. 20610</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McNeill">McNeill, F. Marian (1959)<space/><italics>The Silver Bough</italics>, Vol. 2. William MacLellan, Glasgow ISBN 0-85335-162-7 p. 56</extension><space/>In some areas of Newfoundland, the custom of decorating the May Bush is also still extant.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.heritage.nf.ca/society/custom_may_bush.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">The May Bush in Newfoundland: Newfoundland and Labrador Heritage<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Heritage.nf.ca<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The town of<space/><link><target>Peebles</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Scottish Borders</target></link><space/>holds a traditional week-long Beltane Fair every year in June, when a local girl is crowned Beltane Queen on the steps of the parish church. Like other Borders festivals, it incorporates a<space/><link><target>Common Riding</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.peeblesbeltanefestival.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="title">Home<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Peeblesbeltanefestival.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Edinburgh Beltane Fire Festival 2012 - Red Beastie Drummers.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Beltane Fire Festival</target></link><space/>dancers, 2012</part></link>Since 1988, a<space/><link><target>Beltane Fire Festival</target></link><space/>has been held every year during the night of 30 April on<space/><link><target>Calton Hill, Edinburgh</target><part>Calton Hill</part></link><space/>in Edinburgh, Scotland. While inspired by traditional Beltane, this festival is a modern arts and cultural event which incorporates myth and drama from a variety of world cultures and diverse literary sources.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.beltane.org'>Beltane Fire Society</link><space/>Official event website</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Neo-Paganism</heading><paragraph>Beltane and Beltane-based festivals are held by some<space/><link><target>Neopaganism</target><part>Neopagans</part></link>. As there are many kinds of Neopaganism, their Beltane celebrations can be very different despite the shared name. Some try to emulate the historic festival as much as possible.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallagher"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Gallagher<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Eugene V.<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Ashcraft<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>W. Michael<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Introduction to new and alternative religions in America<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Greenwood Press<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Westport, Conn.<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-275-98713-2<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>178<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Other Neopagans base their celebrations on many sources, the Gaelic festival being only one of them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Adler1">Adler, Margot (1979)<space/><italics>Drawing Down the Moon: Witches, Druids, Goddess-Worshippers, and Other Pagans in America Today</italics>. Boston, Beacon Press ISBN 0-8070-3237-9. p.&amp;nbsp;397 Excerpts from Manhattan Pagan Way Beltane ritual script, 1978</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McColman1">McColman, Carl (2003)<space/><italics>Complete Idiot's Guide to Celtic Wisdom</italics>. Alpha Press ISBN 0-02-864417-4. p. 51</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Neopagans usually celebrate Beltane on 30 April 1 May in the Northern Hemisphere and 31 October 1 November in the Southern Hemisphere, beginning and ending at sunset.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SpiralDance"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Nevill Drury</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Murphy</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Pizza</arg><arg name="editor2-first">James R</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Lewis</arg><arg name="title">Handbook of Contemporary Paganism<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="chapter">The Modern Magical Revival: Esbats and Sabbats</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.za/books?id</arg><arg name="pages">63–67<space/></arg><arg name="location">[[Leiden]], Netherlands</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Brill Publishers]]</arg><arg name="isbn">9789004163737</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Witchcraft and Paganism in Australia<space/></arg><arg name="last">Hume<space/></arg><arg name="first">Lynne<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Melbourne University Press<space/></arg><arg name="location">Melbourne<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780522847826</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Vos</arg><arg name="first">Donna</arg><arg name="title">Dancing Under an African Moon: Paganism and Wicca in South Africa<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002</arg><arg name="pages">79–86</arg><arg name="publisher">Zebra Press</arg><arg name="location">Cape Town</arg><arg name="isbn">9781868726530</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Bodsworth</arg><arg name="first">Roxanne T</arg><arg name="title">Sunwyse: Celebrating the Sacred Wheel of the Year in Australia<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003</arg><arg name="publisher">Hihorse Publishing</arg><arg name="location">Victoria, Australia</arg><arg name="isbn">9780909223038</arg></template></extension><space/>Some Neopagans celebrate it at the astronomical midpoint between the spring<space/><link><target>equinox</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>summer solstice</target></link><space/>(or the full moon nearest this point). In the Northern Hemisphere, this midpoint is when the ecliptic longitude of the Sun reaches 45 degrees.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archaeoastronomy.com/seasons.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Equinoxes, Solstice, Cross Quarters shown as seasonal cusps, worshipped by pagans and later religious holidays<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Archaeoastronomy.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 March 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2014, this is on 5 May.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.archaeoastronomy.com/2014.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chart of 2013 equinox, solstice and cross quarter dates and times, worldwide from<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">archaeoastronomy.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">5 March 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Celtic Reconstructionist</heading><paragraph><link><target>Celtic Reconstructionist Paganism</target><part>Celtic Reconstructionists</part></link><space/>strive to reconstruct the pre-Christian religions of the Celts. Their religious practices are based on research and historical accounts,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallagher"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McColman2">McColman (2003) pp.&amp;nbsp;12, 51</extension><space/>but may be modified slightly to suit modern life. They avoid modern<space/><link><target>syncretism</target></link><space/>and eclecticism (i.e. combining practises from unrelated cultures).<extension extension_name='ref' name="CRFAQ1">NicDhna, Kathryn et al. (2007)<space/><italics>The CR FAQ: An Introduction to Celtic Reconstructionist Paganism</italics>. River House Publishing. ISBN 978-0-615-15800-6 pp. 5356, 64, 130131</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Celtic Reconstructionists usually celebrate<space/><italics>L Bealtaine</italics><space/>when the local<space/><link><target>Common Hawthorn</target><part>hawthorn</part></link><space/>trees are in bloom. Many observe the traditional bonfire rites, to whatever extent this is feasible where they live. This may involve passing themselves and their pets or livestock between two bonfires, and bringing home a candle lit from the bonfire. If they are unable to make a bonfire or attend a bonfire ceremony, torches or candles may be used instead. They may decorate their homes with a May Bush, branches from blooming thorn trees, or equal-armed rowan crosses. Holy wells may be visited and offerings made to the spirits or deities of the wells. Traditional festival foods may also be prepared.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CRFAQ2">NicDhna (2007) pp. 100103</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Healy">Healy, Elizabeth (2001)<space/><italics>In Search of Ireland's Holy Wells</italics>. Dublin, Wolfhound Press ISBN 0-86327-865-5 p.&amp;nbsp;27</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Wicca</heading><paragraph><link><target>Wicca</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>use the name<space/><italics>Beltane</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>Beltain</italics><space/>for their May Day celebrations. It is one of the yearly Sabbats of the<space/><link><target>Wheel of the Year</target></link>, following<space/><link><target>Ostara</target></link><space/>and preceding<space/><link><target>Midsummer</target></link>. Unlike Celtic Reconstructionism, Wicca is syncretic and melds practises from many different cultures. In general, the Wiccan Beltane is more akin to the Germanic/English May Day festival, both in its significance (focusing on fertility) and its rituals (such as<space/><link><target>maypole</target></link><space/>dancing). Some Wiccans enact a ritual union of the<space/><link><target>Horned God</target><part>May Lord</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Triple Goddess (Neopaganism)</target><part>May Lady</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SpiralDance"><link><target>Starhawk</target></link><space/>(1979, 1989)<space/><italics><link><target>The Spiral Dance</target><part>The Spiral Dance: A Rebirth of the Ancient Religion of the Great Goddess</part></link></italics>. New York, Harper and Row ISBN 0-06-250814-8 pp. 181 196 (revised edition)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Name</heading><paragraph>In Irish, the festival is usually called<space/><italics>L Bealtaine</italics><space/>(&quot;day of Beltane&quot;) while the month of May is<space/><italics>M Bhealtaine</italics><space/>(&quot;month of Beltane&quot;). In<space/><link><target>Scottish Gaelic</target></link>, the month is called<space/><italics>(An) Citean</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>a' Mhigh</italics>, and the festival is<space/><italics>Latha Bealltainn</italics>. Sometimes the older Scottish Gaelic spelling<space/><italics>Bealltuinn</italics><space/>is used. The word<space/><italics>Citean</italics><space/>comes from<space/><italics>Cad<space/><link><target>Shamhain</target></link></italics>, an old alternative name for the festival.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In modern Scottish Gaelic,<space/><italics>Latha Buidhe Bealltainn</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>L Buidhe Bealltainn</italics><space/>(&quot;the yellow day of Beltane&quot;) is used to describe the first day of May. This term<space/><italics>L Buidhe Bealtaine</italics><space/>is also used in Irish and is translated as &quot;Bright May Day&quot;. In Ireland it is referred to in a common folk tale as<space/><italics>Luan Lae Bealtaine</italics>; the first day of the week (Monday/<italics>Luan</italics>) is added to emphasise the first day of summer.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>Since the early 20th century it has been commonly accepted that<space/><link><target>Old Irish</target></link><space/><italics>Beltaine</italics><space/>is derived from a<space/><link><target>Common Celtic</target></link><space/><italics>*belo-te(p)ni</italics>, meaning &quot;bright fire&quot;. The element<space/><italics>*belo-</italics><space/>might be cognate with the English word<space/><italics>bale</italics><space/>(as in bale-fire) meaning &quot;white&quot; or &quot;shining&quot;; compare<space/><link><target>Old English</target></link><space/><italics>bael</italics>, and<space/><link><target>Lithuanian language</target><part>Lithuanian</part></link>/<link><target>Latvian language</target><part>Latvian</part></link><space/><italics>baltas/balts</italics>, found in the name of the<space/><link><target>Baltic Sea</target><part>Baltic</part></link>; in<space/><link><target>Slavic languages</target></link><space/><italics>byelo</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>beloye</italics><space/>also means &quot;white&quot;, as in<space/><italics></italics><space/>(<link><target>White Russia</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Belarus</target></link>) or<space/><italics><space/></italics><space/>(<link><target>White Sea</target></link>). A more recent etymology by Xavier Delamarre would derive it from a Common Celtic<space/><italics>*Beltinij</italics>, cognate with the name of the Lithuanian goddess of death<space/><italics><link><target>Giltin</target></link></italics>, the root of both being<space/><link><target>Proto-Indo-European language</target><part>Proto-Indo-European</part></link><space/><italics>*gelH-</italics><space/>(&quot;suffering, death&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'>Delamarre, Xavier. Dictionnaire de la langue gauloise, Editions Errance, Paris, 2003, p. 70</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In Duinnn's Irish dictionary (1904), Beltane is referred to as<space/><italics>Cadamh(ain)</italics><space/>which it explains is short for<space/><italics>Cad-shamh(ain)</italics><space/>meaning &quot;first (of) summer&quot;. The dictionary also states that<space/><italics>Dia Cadamhan</italics><space/>is May Day and<space/><italics>M Cadamhan</italics><space/>is the month of May.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Beltany stone circle.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Beltany stone circle in Ireland</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Toponymy</heading><paragraph>There are a number of<space/><link><target>place names in Ireland</target></link><space/>containing the word<space/><italics>Bealtaine</italics>, indicating places where Bealtaine festivities were once held. It is often anglicised as<space/><italics>Beltany</italics>. There are three Beltanys in<space/><link><target>County Donegal</target></link>, including the<space/><link><target>Beltany stone circle</target></link>, and two in<space/><link><target>County Tyrone</target></link>. In<space/><link><target>County Armagh</target></link><space/>there is a place called<space/><link><target>Laurelvale</target><part>Tamnaghvelton</part></link>/<italics>Tamhnach Bhealtaine</italics><space/>(&quot;the Beltane field&quot;). Lisbalting/<italics>Lios Bealtaine</italics><space/>(&quot;the Beltane ringfort&quot;) is in<space/><link><target>County Tipperary</target></link>, while Glasheennabaultina/<italics>Glaisn na Bealtaine</italics><space/>(&quot;the Beltane stream&quot;) is the name of a stream joining the River Galey in<space/><link><target>County Limerick</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Holidays</arg></template><template><target>multicol</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Calendars</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Celtic calendar</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Coligny calendar</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Irish calendar</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Wheel of the year</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>multicol-break</target></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Holidays</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lughnasadh</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Samhain</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Imbolc</target></link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Other</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Beltane Fire Festival</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Walpurgis Night</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Welsh Holidays</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>multicol-end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Carmichael, Alexander (1992).<space/><italics><link><target>Carmina Gadelica</target></link></italics>. Lindisfarne Press. ISBN 0-940262-50-9</listitem><listitem>Chadwick, Nora (1970)<space/><italics>The Celts</italics>. London, Penguin ISBN 0-14-021211-6</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kevin Danaher</target><part>Danaher, Kevin</part></link><space/>(1972)<space/><italics>The Year in Ireland</italics>. Dublin, Mercier ISBN 1-85635-093-2</listitem><listitem><link><target>W. Y. Evans-Wentz</target><part>Evans-Wentz, W. Y.</part></link><space/>(1966, 1990)<space/><italics>The Fairy-Faith in Celtic Countries</italics>. New York, Citadel ISBN 0-8065-1160-5</listitem><listitem>MacKillop, James (1998).<space/><italics>Dictionary of Celtic Mythology</italics>. Oxford University Press ISBN 0-19-280120-1</listitem><listitem><link><target>F. Marian McNeill</target><part>McNeill, F. Marian</part></link><space/>(1959)<space/><italics>The Silver Bough</italics>, Vol. 14. William MacLellan, Glasgow</listitem><listitem><link><target>Eve Blantyre Simpson</target><part>Simpson, Eve Blantyre</part></link><space/>(1908),<space/><italics>Folk lore in lowland Scotland</italics>, London:<space/><link><target>J.M. Dent</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.beltane.org/'>Edinburgh's Beltane Fire Society</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/196/155.html'>Extract on The Beltane Fires from Sir James George Frazer's book The Golden Bough 1922</link>; from<space/><italics>bartleby.com</italics></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Celts</target><arg name="state">collapsed</arg></template><template><target>Celtic mythology topics</target></template><template><target>Wheel of the Year</target></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Holidays in Scotland</target></link><link><target>Category:Irish culture</target></link><link><target>Category:Irish folklore</target></link><link><target>Category:Manx culture</target></link><link><target>Category:April observances</target></link><link><target>Category:May observances</target></link><link><target>Category:November observances</target></link><link><target>Category:Neopagan holidays</target></link><link><target>Category:Scottish culture</target></link><link><target>Category:Scottish folklore</target></link><link><target>Category:Summer holidays</target></link><link><target>Category:Spring holidays</target></link><link><target>Category:Irish words and phrases</target></link><link><target>Category:Cross-quarter days</target></link><link><target>Category:Gaelic culture</target></link><link><target>Category:Irish mythology</target></link><link><target>Category:Scottish mythology</target></link></paragraph></article>