<article title='Car_Talk'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Third Half</arg><arg>the Macedonian film</arg><arg>The Third Half</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Infobox radio show</target><arg name="show_name"><space/>Car Talk
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Car Talk Logo.svg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>170px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="format"><space/>Automotive repair/advice,<br />Humor
</arg><arg name="audio_format"><space/>[[Stereophonic sound|Stereophonic]]
</arg><arg name="record_location"><space/>[[Boston, Massachusetts]]
</arg><arg name="runtime"><space/>approx. 50 min
</arg><arg name="creator"><space/>
</arg><arg name="developer">
</arg><arg name="executive_producer"><space/>Doug Berman
</arg><arg name="presenter"><space/>[[Tom and Ray Magliozzi|Tom Magliozzi]]<br />[[Tom and Ray Magliozzi|Ray Magliozzi]]
</arg><arg name="opentheme"><space/>"Dawggy&nbsp;Mountain&nbsp;Breakdown", [[David Grisman]], composer
</arg><arg name="othertheme"><space/>[[B. J. Leiderman]]<ref>{{cite web | url</arg><arg name="country"><space/>United States
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="home_station"><space/>[[WBUR-FM]]
</arg><arg name="syndicates"><space/>[[NPR|National Public Radio]]
</arg><arg name="first_aired"><space/>1977 (WBUR-FM); 1987 (nationally) 
</arg><arg name="last_aired"><space/>2012 (original episodes)
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>{{URL|cartalk.com}}
</arg><arg name="podcast"><space/>
</arg></template><bold><italics>Car Talk</italics></bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Peabody Award</target></link>winning<space/><link><target>Talk radio</target><part>radio talk show</part></link><space/>broadcast weekly on<space/><link><target>NPR</target></link><space/>stations and elsewhere. Its subjects were automobiles and automotive repair, discussed often in a humorous way. It was hosted by brothers<space/><link><target>Tom and Ray Magliozzi</target></link>, known also as &quot;Click and Clack, the<space/><link><target>Tappet#Internal combustion engines</target><part>Tappet</part></link><space/>Brothers&quot;. The show was produced from 1977 to October 2012, when the Magliozzi brothers retired. Edited reruns continue to be available for airing on NPR affiliates.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bauder"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.google.com/hostednews/ap/article/ALeqM5jOCGFHXdRDFYjEtqQss6Z1jiCmtg?docId</arg><arg name="title">NPR 'Car Talk' duo retiring; reruns to continue<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="last">Bauder<space/></arg><arg name="date">8 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="agency">[[Associated Press]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 June 2012<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">http://www.webcitation.org/68djZLtRU<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2012-06-23</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Premise</heading><paragraph><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/>was presented in the form of a call-in radio show: listeners called in with questions related to motor vehicle maintenance and repair. Most of the advice sought was diagnostic, with callers describing symptoms and demonstrating sounds of an ailing vehicle while the Magliozzis make an attempt at identifying the malfunction. While the hosts peppered their call-in sessions with jokes directed at both the caller and at themselves, the Magliozzis were usually able to arrive at a diagnosis and give helpful advice. However, when they were stumped, they attempted anyway with an answer they claimed was &quot;<bold>unencumbered by the thought process</bold>&quot;, the official motto of the show.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://shop.npr.org/wear/clothing/car-talk-unencumbered-latin-t-shirt<space/></arg><arg name="title">NPR Store Unencumbered by the thought process</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Edited reruns are carried on<space/><link><target>XM Satellite Radio</target></link><space/>via both the Public Radio and NPR Now channels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.siriusxm.com/siriusxmpublicradio/weeklyschedule<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sirius XM's Public Radio Schedule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sirius XM Radio</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.siriusxm.com/nprnow/weeklyschedule<space/></arg><arg name="title">Sirius XM's NPR Now Schedule<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Sirius XM Radio</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">NPR's Car Talk Listeners Pick Ugliest New Car</arg><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/about/press/050409.uglycar.html<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Car Talk is public radio's most popular entertainment program, airing on nearly 600 stations with more than 4.4 million listeners a week tuning in for an hour-long tune-up on car advice and humor.</arg><arg name="work">[[NPR|National Public Radio]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-12-07<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">NPR Programs Attract Record-Breaking Audiences Public Radio Listenership at All-Time High<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/about/press/020319.recordbreak.html</arg><arg name="quote">Growth in the NPR news/talk audience outpaced similar gains realized by commercial news/talk radio.<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[NPR|National Public Radio]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-17<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/><link><target>theme music</target></link><space/>was &quot;Dawggy Mountain Breakdown&quot; by<space/><link><target>bluegrass music</target><part>bluegrass</part></link><space/>artist<space/><link><target>David Grisman</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/music-show-4</arg><arg name="title">Music on the Show</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Call-in procedure</heading><paragraph>Throughout the program, listeners were encouraged to dial the<space/><link><target>toll-free telephone number</target></link>, 1-888-CAR-TALK (1-888-227-8255), which connected to a 24-hour answering service. Although the approximately 2,000 queries received each week were screened by the<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/>staff, the questions were unknown to the Magliozzis in advance as &quot;that would entail researching the right answer, which is what? ...&amp;nbsp;Work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="faq"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/faq/faq-straight.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Car Talk Official FAQs<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Car Talk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-15</arg></template></extension><space/>Producers selected and contacted the callers several days ahead of the show's Wednesday taping to arrange the segment. The caller spoke briefly to a producer before being connected live with the hosts, and was given little coaching other than being told to be prepared to talk, not to use any written preparation and to &quot;have fun&quot;. The show deliberately taped more callers than it has time to air each week in order to be able to choose the best ones for broadcast. Those segments that did make it to air were generally edited for time. For the last four years of the show, new shows included previously broadcast segments as much as 10 years old. The re-used segments, including re-used puzzlers, were not acknowledged as old material and sometimes new caller material was mixed in alongside the recycled calls.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Mayer<space/></arg><arg name="first">Doug<space/></arg><arg name="title">Car Talk Forums:Old Callers</arg><arg name="url">http://community.cartalk.com/discussion/2211396/old-callers</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>anchor</target><arg>ThirdHalf</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Features</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template>The show originally consisted of two segments with a break in between. Then the show was changed to three segments. The hosts used to refer to content coming up in the second half of the program. Ever since the shift to the three-segment format, it became a running joke to refer to the last segment as &quot;the third half&quot; of the program.</paragraph><paragraph>The show opened with a short comedy segment, typically jokes sent in by listeners, followed by eight call-in sessions. The hosts ran a contest called the &quot;Puzzler&quot;, in which a riddle, sometimes car-related, was presented. The answer to the previous week's &quot;Puzzler&quot; was given at the beginning of the &quot;second half&quot; of the show, and a new &quot;Puzzler&quot; was given at the start of the &quot;third half&quot;. The hosts gave instructions to listeners to write answers addressed to &quot;Puzzler Tower&quot; on some non-existent or expensive object, such as a &quot;$26 bill&quot; or an advanced digital<space/><link><target>Single-lens reflex camera</target><part>SLR</part></link><space/>camera. This gag initially started as suggestions that the answers be written &quot;on the back of a $20 bill&quot;. A<space/><link><target>running gag</target></link><space/>concerned Tom's inability to remember the previous week's &quot;Puzzler&quot; without heavy prompting from Ray. For each puzzler, one correct answer was chosen at random, with the winner receiving a $26 gift certificate to the<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/>store, referred to as the &quot;Shameless Commerce Division&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cartalk.com/content/puzzler/'>&quot;Puzzler&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/>website</extension><space/>It was originally $25, but was increased for inflation after a few years. Originally, the winner received a specific item from the store, but it soon changed to a gift certificate to allow the winner to choose the item they wanted (though Tom often made an item suggestion).</paragraph><paragraph>A recurring feature was &quot;Stump the Chumps,&quot; in which the hosts revisited a caller from a previous show to determine the accuracy and the effect, if any, of their advice. A similar feature began in May 2001, &quot;Where Are They Now, Tommy?&quot; It began with a comical musical theme with a sputtering, backfiring car engine and a horn as a backdrop. Tom then announced who the previous caller was, followed by a short replay of the essence of the previous call, preceded and followed by harp music often used in other audiovisual media to indicate recalling and returning from a dream. The hosts then greeted the previous caller, confirming that they have not spoken since their previous appearance and asking them if there have been any influences on the answer they're about to relate, such as arcane bribes by the NPR staff. The repair story was then discussed, followed by a fanfare and applause if the Tappet Brothers' diagnosis was correct, or a wah-wah-wah music piece mixed with a car starter operated by a weak battery (an engine which won't start) if the diagnosis was wrong. The hosts then thanked the caller for their return appearance.</paragraph><paragraph>The brothers also had an official Animal-Vehicle Biologist and Wildlife Guru named Kieran Lindsey.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://search.vt.edu/search/person.html?person</arg><arg name="title">Kieran Lindsey - People Search &#124; Virginia Tech<space/></arg><arg name="work">Search.vt.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-09</arg><arg name="quote">Kieran Jane Lindsey; Director, Natural Resources Distance Learning Corsortium, College of Natural Resources & Env.</arg></template></extension><space/>She answered questions like<space/><italics>How do I remove a snake from my car?</italics><space/>and offered advice on how those living in cities and suburbs can reconnect with wildlife.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://withgoodreasonradio.org/2011/10/girl-scouts-beyond-campfires-and-cookie/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Girl Scouts: Beyond Campfires and Cookies<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Virginia Foundation for the Humanities]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 29, 2011<space/></arg><arg name="quote">Answering questions like how to remove a snake from your car, urban wildlife biologist Kieran Lindsey (Virginia Tech) is the new official Animal-Vehicle Biologist and Wildlife Guru for Car Talk on NPR. Lindsey offers tips for how those of us living in cities and suburbs can reconnect with the wildlife around us—what she calls “next-door nature.”<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-08-09</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>famous_callers</arg></template><space/>Celebrities have been callers as well. Examples include<space/><link><target>Geena Davis</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Morley Safer</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ashley Judd</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gordon Elliott</target></link>, former Major League pitcher<space/><link><target>Bill Lee (left-handed pitcher)</target><part>Bill Lee</part></link>, and astronaut<space/><link><target>John M. Grunsfeld</target></link><space/>calling from the<space/><link><target>Space Shuttle</target></link>. There were numerous appearances from NPR personalities, including<space/><link><target>Bob Edwards</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Susan Stamberg</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Scott Simon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ray Suarez</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Will Shortz</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sylvia Poggioli</target></link>, and commentator and author<space/><link><target>Daniel Pinkwater</target></link>. On one occasion, the show featured<space/><link><target>Martha Stewart</target></link><space/>as an in-studio guest, whom the Magliozzis twice during the segment referred to as &quot;Margaret&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In addition to at least one on-orbit call, the Brothers once received a call asking advice on winterizing an electric car. When they asked what kind of car, the caller stated it was a &quot;kit car&quot;, a $400 million &quot;kit car&quot;. It was a joke call from the<space/><link><target>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</target></link><space/>concerning the preparation of the<space/><link><target>Mars rover</target></link><space/>for the oncoming Martian winter.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.cartalk.com/content/winter-driving-tips-mars</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.cartalk.com/content/9703-lost-space</extension><space/>Click and Clack have also been featured in editorial cartoons, including one where a befuddled NASA engineer calls them to ask how to fix the<space/><link><target>Space Shuttle</target></link>.<template><target>episode needed</target><arg name="date">March 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Humor</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove section</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template>Humor and wisecracking pervaded the program. Tom and Ray are known for their<space/><link><target>Self-deprecation</target><part>self-deprecating humor</part></link>, often joking about the supposedly poor quality of their advice and the show in general. They also commented at the end of each show: &quot;Well, it's happened againyou've wasted another perfectly good hour listening to<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics>.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>At some point in almost every show, usually when giving the address for the Puzzler answers, Ray mentioned<space/><link><target>Cambridge, Massachusetts</target></link><space/>(where the show originated), at which point Tom reverently interjected with a tone of civic pride, &quot;Our fair city&quot;. Ray invariably mocked &quot;'Cambridge, MA', the United States Postal Service's two-letter abbreviation for 'Massachusetts&quot;', by pronouncing it as a word.</paragraph><paragraph>Preceding each break in the show, one of the hosts led up to the network identification with a humorous take on a disgusted reaction of some usually famous person to hearing that identification. The full line went along the pattern of, for example, &quot;And even though<space/><link><target>Roger Clemens#SteroidUseControversy</target><part>Roger Clemens</part></link><space/>stabs his radio with a syringe whenever he hears<space/><italics>us</italics><space/>say it, this is NPR: National Public Radio&quot; (later just &quot;...&amp;nbsp;this is NPR&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>At one point in the show, often after the break, Ray usually stated that: &quot;Support for this show is provided by,&quot; followed by an absurd fundraiser.<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The ending credits of the show started with thanks to the colorfully nicknamed actual staffers: producer Doug &quot;the subway fugitive, not a slave to fashion, bongo boy frogman&quot; Berman;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://o.seattletimes.nwsource.com/html/editorials/2018445674_edit17talk.html</arg><arg name="title">Tom and Ray, the Tappet Brothers, are exhausted</arg><arg name="date">2012-06-16</arg><arg name="publisher">[[The Seattle Times]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-08-03</arg></template></extension><space/>&quot;John 'Bugsy' Lawlor, just back from the&amp;nbsp;...&quot; every week a different eating event with rhyming foodstuff names; David &quot;Calves of Belleville&quot; Greene;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/music-show-0</arg><arg name="title">Music on the Show<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">cartalk.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-24</arg></template></extension><space/>Catherine &quot;<link><target>Young Frankenstein</target><part>Frau Blcher</part></link>&quot; Fenollosa, whose name caused a horse to neigh and gallop (an allusion to a running gag in the movie<space/><italics><link><target>Young Frankenstein</target></link></italics>);<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/help-us-help-henry-2010-1<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Help Us Help Henry 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">cartalk.com</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-24</arg></template></extension><space/>and Carly &quot;High Voltage&quot; Nix,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/whos-real-high-voltage-car-talk-plaza<space/></arg><arg name="title">Who's the real "High Voltage" at Car Talk Plaza?</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Nix<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Carly</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>cartalk.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-03-31</arg></template></extension><space/>among others. Following the real staff was a lengthy list of pun-filled fictional staffers and sponsors such as statistician Marge Innovera (&quot;<link><target>margin of error</target></link>&quot;), customer care representative Haywood Jabuzoff (&quot;Hey, would ya buzz off&quot;), meteorologist Claudio Vernight (&quot;cloudy overnight&quot;), optometric firm C.&amp;nbsp;F. Eye Care (&quot;see if I care&quot;), Russian chauffeur Pikup Andropov (&quot;pick up and drop off&quot;),<space/><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link><space/>biographer Warren Peace (&quot;<link><target>War and Peace</target></link>&quot;), hygiene officer and chief of the Tokyo office Otaka Shawa (&quot;oh take a shower&quot;), Swedish snowboard instructor Soren Derkeister (&quot;sore in the keister&quot;), law firm<space/><link><target>Dewey, Cheatem &amp; Howe</target><part>Dewey, Cheetham &amp; Howe</part></link><space/>(&quot;Do we cheat 'em? And how!&quot;), and many, many others, usually concluding with Erasmus B. Dragon (&quot;Her ass must be draggin'&quot;), whose job title varied, but who was often said to be head of the show's working mothers' support group.<extension extension_name='ref' name="credits"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/about/credits/credits.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Car Talk Credits<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Car Talk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-15</arg></template></extension><space/>They sometimes advised that &quot;our chief counsel from the law firm of Dewey, Cheetham, &amp; Howe is Hugh Louis Dewey, known to [group of people] in Harvard Square as Huey Louie Dewey.&quot;<space/><link><target>Huey, Dewey, and Louie</target><part>Huey, Louie, and Dewey</part></link><space/>were the juvenile nephews being raised by<space/><link><target>Donald Duck</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Walt Disney's Comics and Stories</target></link>. Guest accommodations were provided by The Horseshoe Road Inn (&quot;the horse you rode in&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>At the end of the show, Ray warned the audience, &quot;Don't drive like my brother&quot;, to which Tom replied, &quot;And don't drive like<space/><italics>my</italics><space/>brother.&quot; The original tag line was &quot;Don't drive like a knucklehead.&quot; There have been variations such as, &quot;Don't drive like my brother&amp;nbsp;...&quot; &quot;And don't drive like his brother&quot;, and &quot;Don't drive like my sister&amp;nbsp;...&quot; &quot;And don't drive like<space/><italics>my</italics><space/>sister.&quot; The tagline was heard in a cameo for the<space/><link><target>Pixar</target></link><space/>film<space/><italics><link><target>Cars (film)</target><part>Cars</part></link></italics>, in which Tom and Ray voiced<space/><link><target>Anthropomorphism</target><part>anthropomorphized</part></link><space/>vehicles (<link><target>List of Cars characters#Rusty and Dusty Rust-eze</target><part>Rusty and Dusty Rust-Eze</part></link>, respectively a 1963<space/><link><target>Dodge Dart</target></link><space/>V1.0 and 1963<space/><link><target>Dodge A100</target></link><space/>van, as<space/><link><target>Lightning McQueen</target></link>'s racing<space/><link><target>Sponsor (commercial)</target><part>sponsors</part></link>) with personalities similar to their own on-air personae.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>IMDb title</target><arg>0317219</arg><arg>Cars</arg></template>. Retrieved on June 25, 2007</extension><space/>Tom notoriously once owned a &quot;convertible, green with large areas of rust&quot;<space/><link><target>Dodge Dart</target></link>, known jokingly on the program by the faux-elegant name &quot;Dartre&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cartalk.com/content/features/dart/<space/></arg><arg name="title">1963 Dodge Dart test notes<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Car Talk<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-15</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>expand section</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template>In 1977, radio station<space/><link><target>WBUR-FM</target></link><space/>in Boston was supposed to have mechanics talking about car repair on one of its programs, but only Tom was there. He did so well that both brothers were asked to host their own show, and they continued to do it every week. In 1986, the program was the third most popular on WBUR with 11,500 listeners, and NPR wanted to distribute it nationally.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Lumsden"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">'Click and Clack': frick and frack gearheads</arg><arg name="last">Lumsden</arg><arg name="first">Carolyn</arg><arg name="work">[[Daily Breeze]]</arg><arg name="date">July 11, 1986</arg><arg name="page">E19</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1992,<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics><space/>won a<space/><link><target>List of Peabody Award winners (199099)#1992</target><part>Peabody Award</part></link>, saying &quot;Each week, master mechanics Tom and Ray Magliozzi provide useful information about preserving and protecting our cars. But the real core of this program is what it tells us about human mechanics&amp;nbsp;... The insight and laughter provided by Messrs. Magliozzi, in conjunction with their producer Doug Berman, provide a weekly mental tune-up for a vast and ever-growing public radio audience.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://peabodyawards.com/past-winners/award/?pbaward</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Car Talk</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>George Foster Peabody Awards</arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-08-29</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In May 2007, the program, which previously had been available only digitally as a paid subscription from<space/><link><target>Audible.com</target></link>, became a free<space/><link><target>podcast</target></link><space/>distributed by NPR, after a two-month test period where only a &quot;call of the week&quot; was available via podcast.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date"><space/>April 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As of 2012, it had 3.3 million listeners each week, on about 660 stations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bauder"></extension><space/>On June 8, 2012, the brothers announced that they would no longer broadcast new episodes as of October. Executive producer Doug Berman said the best material from 25 years of past shows would be used to put together &quot;repurposed&quot; shows for NPR to broadcast. Berman estimated the archives contain enough for eight years' worth of material before anything would have to be repeated. The brothers will no longer continue to write their syndicated newspaper column.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bauder"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2012/06/08/154576808/car-talk-guys-are-retiring-but-their-best-stuff-will-be-rebroadcast</arg><arg name="title">Car Talk Guys Are Retiring, But Their Best Stuff Will Be Rebroadcast</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Hosts</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Tom and Ray Magliozzi</arg></template><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">April 2012</arg></template><link><target>Image:Car Talk Dewey, Cheetham &amp; Howe.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>280px</part><part>right</part><part>The name of the DC&amp;H corporate offices is visible on the third floor window above the corner of Brattle and JFK Streets, in<space/><link><target>Harvard Square</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cambridge, Massachusetts</target></link>.</part></link>The Magliozzis are long-time<space/><link><target>auto mechanic</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Ray Magliozzi has a bachelor of science degree in humanities and science from<space/><link><target>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</target><part>MIT</part></link>, while Tom had a bachelor of science degree in economics from MIT and an<space/><link><target>Master of Business Administration</target><part>MBA</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Doctor of Business Administration</target><part>DBA</part></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Boston University School of Management</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The duo, usually led by Ray, were known for rants on the evils of the<space/><link><target>internal combustion engine</target></link>, people who talk on<space/><link><target>mobile phone</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>while driving,<space/><link><target>Peugeot</target><trail>s</trail></link>, women named Donna who always seem to drive<space/><link><target>Chevrolet Camaro</target><trail>s</trail></link>, lawyers, the clever use of the<space/><link><target>English language</target></link>, people who choose to live in Alaska (or similar snowy, icy climates), and practically anything else, including themselves. They had a relaxed and humorous approach to cars, car repair,<space/><link><target>cup holder</target><trail>s</trail></link>, pets, lawyers, car repair mechanics,<space/><link><target>Sport utility vehicle</target><part>SUV</part><trail>s</trail></link>, and almost everything else. They often cast a critical, jaundiced insider's eye toward the auto industry. Tom and Ray were committed to the values of defensive driving and environmentalism.</paragraph><paragraph>The Magliozzis operated a garage together. The show's offices were located nearby at the corner of JFK Street and Brattle Street in<space/><link><target>Harvard Square</target></link>, marked as &quot;<link><target>Dewey, Cheatem &amp; Howe</target><part>Dewey, Cheetham &amp; Howe</part></link>&quot;, the imaginary law firm to which they refer on-air. DC&amp;H doubled as the business name of Tappet Brothers Associates, the corporation established to manage the business end of<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics>. Initially a joke, the company was incorporated after the show expanded from a single station to national syndication.</paragraph><paragraph>The two were<space/><link><target>Commencement speech</target><part>commencement speakers</part></link><space/>at MIT in 1999.</paragraph><paragraph>Executive producer Doug Berman said in 2012, &quot;The guys are culturally right up there with<space/><link><target>Mark Twain</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Marx Brothers</target></link>. They will stand the test of time. People will still be enjoying them years from now. They're that good.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bauder"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Tom Magliozzi died on November 3, 2014, at age 77, due to complications from Alzheimer's disease.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.npr.org/2014/11/03/357428287/tom-magliozzi-popular-co-host-of-nprs-car-talk-dies-at-77</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Adaptations</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Click and Clack's As the Wrench Turns</arg></template>The show was the inspiration for the short-lived<space/><italics><link><target>The George Wendt Show</target></link></italics>, which briefly aired on CBS in the<space/><link><target>199495 United States network television schedule</target><part>1994-1995 season</part></link>- as a<space/><link><target>mid-season replacement</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.tvguide.com/tvshows/george-wendt/201634<space/></arg><arg name="title">The George Wendt Show on CBS<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper">[[TV Guide]]</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In July 2007, PBS announced that it had<space/><link><target>Green-light</target><part>green-lit</part></link><space/>an animated adaptation of<space/><italics>Car Talk</italics>, to air on prime-time in 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.prnewswire.com/cgi-bin/stories.pl?ACCT</arg><arg name="title">PBS Greenlights 'Car Talk' Television Series<space/></arg><arg name="date">2007-07-11<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>The show, titled<space/><italics><link><target>Click and Clack's As the Wrench Turns</target></link></italics><space/>is based on the adventures of the fictional &quot;Click and Clack&quot; brothers' garage at &quot;Car Talk Plaza&quot;. The ten episodes aired in July and August 2008.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="work">Times Herald-Record<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.recordonline.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID</arg><arg name="title">TV Guy: Cartoon series stars Click and Click<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kevin<space/></arg><arg name="last">McDonough<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-07-09</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Car Talk: The Musical!!!</italics><space/>was written and directed by Wesley Savick, and composed by Michael Wartofsky. The adaptation was presented by<space/><link><target>Suffolk University</target></link>, and opened on March 31, 2011, at the Modern Theatre in Boston, Massachusetts.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="work">Boston Globe<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://articles.boston.com/2011-03-29/ae/29360749_1_wizard-bitterness-magliozzis<space/></arg><arg name="title">Suffolk players get a lot of mileage out of 'Car Talk'<space/></arg><arg name="first">Joel<space/></arg><arg name="last">Brown<space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-03-29</arg></template></extension><space/>The play was not officially endorsed by the Magliozzis, but they participated in the production, lending their voices to a central puppet character named &quot;The Wizard of Cahs&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="work">Broadway World<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://boston.broadwayworld.com/article/Suffolk_University_Theatre_Department_Presents_Car_Talk_The_Musical_20110402<space/></arg><arg name="title">Suffolk University presents Car Talk: The Musical!!! Closes 4/3<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/></arg><arg name="date">2011-04-03</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Official website</target></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pbs.org/wrenchturns/'>''Click and Clack's As the Wrench Turns'' official site</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://web.mit.edu/newsoffice/1999/clickclackspeech.html'>Transcript of the Magliozzis' commencement address at MIT, 1999</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>NPR</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:1977 radio programme debuts</target></link><link><target>Category:1970s American radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:1980s American radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:1990s American radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:2000s American radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:2010s American radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:American talk radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:Automobile maintenance</target></link><link><target>Category:Media in Boston, Massachusetts</target></link><link><target>Category:NPR programs</target></link><link><target>Category:Peabody Award winning radio programs</target></link><link><target>Category:National Radio Hall of Fame inductees</target></link><link><target>Category:Cambridge, Massachusetts</target></link></paragraph></article>