<article title='Double-barreled_shotgun'><paragraph><link><target>Image:ShotgunAction.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>A view of the break-action of a typical side-by-side double-barreled shotgun, with the<space/><link><target>Anson &amp; Deeley boxlock action</target></link><space/>open and the extractor visible. The opening lever and the<space/><link><target>Safety (firearms)</target><part>safety catch</part></link><space/>can also be clearly seen.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>double-barreled shotgun</bold><space/>(&quot;double&quot; in context) is a<space/><link><target>shotgun</target></link><space/>with two parallel<space/><link><target>Gun barrel</target><part>barrels</part></link>, allowing two shots to be fired in quick succession.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Construction</heading><paragraph>Modern double-barreled shotguns, often known as<space/><italics>doubles</italics>, are almost universally<space/><link><target>break open</target></link><space/>actions, with the barrels tilting up at the rear to expose the breech ends of the barrels for unloading and reloading. Since there is no reciprocating action needed to eject and reload the<space/><link><target>shotgun shell</target><part>shells</part></link>, doubles are more compact than repeating designs such as<space/><link><target>pump action shotgun</target><part>pump action</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>lever-action</target></link><space/>shotguns.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Barrel configuration</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>coach gun</arg><arg>sawed-off shotgun</arg></template>Double-barreled shotguns come in two basic configurations: the<space/><bold>side by side shotgun</bold><space/>(SxS) and the<space/><bold>over/under shotgun</bold><space/>(&quot;over and under&quot;, O/U, etc.), indicating the arrangement of barrels. The original double-barreled guns were nearly all SxS designs, which was a more practical design in the days of<space/><link><target>muzzle-loading</target></link><space/><link><target>firearm</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Early<space/><link><target>cartridge (firearms)</target><part>cartridge</part></link><space/>shotguns also used the SxS action, because they kept the exposed hammers of the earlier muzzle-loading shotguns they evolved from. When<space/><link><target>hammerless</target></link><space/>designs started to become common, the O/U design was introduced, and most modern sporting doubles are O/U designs.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tbm"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Twin barrel myths: side-by-side vs. over-under</arg><arg name="work">Guns Magazine</arg><arg name="date">July 2010</arg><arg name="author">John Barsness</arg><arg name="url">http://findarticles.com/p/articles/mi_m0BQY/is_7_56/ai_n56222158/</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>One significant advantage that doubles have over single barrel repeating shotguns is the ability to provide access to more than one choke at a time. Some shotgun sports, such as<space/><link><target>Skeet shooting</target><part>skeet</part></link>, use crossing targets presented in a narrow range of distance, and only require one level of choke. Others, like<space/><link><target>sporting clays</target></link>, give the shooter targets at differing ranges, and targets that might approach or recede from the shooter, and so must be engaged at differing ranges. Having two barrels lets the shooter use a more open choke for near targets, and a tighter choke for distant targets, providing the optimal shot pattern for each distance.</paragraph><paragraph>Their disadvantage lies in the fact that the barrels of a double-barreled shotgun, whether<space/><italics>O/U</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>SxS</italics>, are not parallel, but slightly angled, so that shots from the barrels converge, usually at &quot;40 yards out&quot;. For the<space/><italics>SxS</italics><space/>configuration, the shotstring continues on its path to the opposite side of the rib after the converging point; for example, the left barrel's discharge travels on the left of the rib till it hits dead center at 40 yards out, after that, the discharge continues on to the right. In the<space/><italics>O/U</italics><space/>configuration with a parallel rib, both barrels' discharges will keep to the dead center, but the discharge from the &quot;under&quot; barrel will shoot higher than the discharge from the &quot;over&quot; barrel after 40 yards. Thus, double-barreled shotguns are accurate only at practical shotgun ranges, though the range of their ammunition easily exceeds four to six times that range.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>SxS</italics><space/>shotguns are often more expensive, and may take more practice to aim effectively than a<space/><italics>O/U</italics>. The off-center nature of the recoil in a SxS gun may make shooting the body-side barrel slightly more painful by comparison to an OU, single-shot, or pump/lever action shotgun. Gas-operated, and to a lesser extent recoil-operated, designs will recoil less than either. More<space/><italics>SxS</italics><space/>than<space/><italics>O/U</italics><space/>guns have traditional 'cast-off' stocks, where the end of the buttstock veers to the right, allowing a right-handed user to point the gun more easily.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tbm"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Trigger mechanism</heading><paragraph>The early doubles used two triggers, one for each barrel. These were located front to back inside the trigger guard, the index finger being used to pull either trigger, as having two fingers inside the trigger guard can cause a recoil induced double-discharge. Double trigger designs are typically set up for right-handed users.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tbm"></extension><space/>In double trigger designs, it is often possible to pull both triggers at once, firing both barrels simultaneously, though this is generally not recommended as it doubles the recoil, battering both shooter and shotgun. Discharging both barrels at the same time has long been a hunting trick employed by hunters using 8 gauge &quot;elephant&quot; shotguns, firing the two two-ounce slugs for sheer stopping power at close range.</paragraph><paragraph>Later models use a single trigger that alternately fires both barrels, called a<space/><italics>single selective trigger</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>SST</italics>. The SST does not allow firing both barrels at once, since the single trigger must be pulled twice in order to fire both barrels. The change from one barrel to the other may be done by a<space/><link><target>clockwork</target></link><space/>type system, where a cam alternates between barrels, or by an<space/><link><target>inertia</target><trail>l</trail></link><space/>system where the recoil of firing the first barrel toggles the trigger to the next barrel. A double-barreled shotgun with an inertial trigger works best with full power shotshells; shooting low recoil shotshells often will not reliably toggle the inertial trigger, causing an apparent failure to fire occasionally when attempting to depress the trigger a second time to fire the second barrel. Generally there is a method of selecting the order in which the barrels of an SST shotgun fire; commonly this is done through manipulation of the<space/><link><target>Safety (firearms)</target><part>safety</part></link>, pushing to one side to select top barrel first and the other side to select bottom barrel first. In the event that an inertial trigger does not toggle to the second barrel when firing low recoil shotshells, manually selecting the order to the second barrel will enable the second barrel to fire when the trigger is depressed again.</paragraph><paragraph>One of the advantages of the double, with double triggers or SST, is that a second shot can be taken almost immediately after the first, utilizing different chokes for the two shots. (Assuming, of course, that full power shotshells are fired, at least for a double-barreled shotgun with an inertial type SST, as needed to toggle the inertial trigger.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Regulation</heading><paragraph><bold><italics>Regulation</italics></bold><space/>is a term used for multi-barreled firearms that indicates how close to the same point of aim the barrels will shoot. Regulation is very important, because a poorly regulated gun may hit consistently with one barrel, but miss consistently with the other, making the gun nearly useless for anything requiring two shots. Fortunately, the short ranges and spread of shot provide a significant overlap, so a small error in regulation in a double will often be too small to be noticed. Generally the shotguns are regulated to hit the point of aim at a given distance, usually the maximum expected range since that is the range at which a full choke would be used, and where precise regulation matters most.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Regional use</heading><paragraph>The double-barreled shotgun is seen as a weapon of prestige and authority in rural parts of<space/><link><target>India</target></link>,<template><target>cn</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><space/>where it is known as<space/><italics>dunali</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Popular Dictionary in English and Hindustani and Hindustani and English: With a Number of Useful Tables</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 September 2013</arg><arg name="year">1881</arg><arg name="publisher">Methodist Episcopal Church Press</arg><arg name="page">48</arg></template></extension><space/>(literally &quot;two pipes&quot;). It is especially common in<space/><link><target>Bihar</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Purvanchal</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Uttar Pradesh</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Haryana</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Punjab (India)</target><part>Punjab</part></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2009</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Boxlock action</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Coach gun</target></link><space/>- A style of double-barrel shotgun from the American Wild West</listitem><listitem><link><target>Combination gun</target><part>Combination guns and drillings</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Double-barrelled name</target><part>Double-barreled name</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Double-barreled cannon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Double rifle</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Lupara</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Multiple barrel firearm</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Multiple Barrel Firearms</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Double-barreled shotguns</target><part>Double-barreled shotgun</part></link><link><target>Category:Multiple barrel firearms</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>hr:Puka dvocijevka</target></link></paragraph></article>