<article title='Geography_of_El_Salvador'><paragraph><link><target>File:Un-el-salvador.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>550px</part><part>A map of El Salvador.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>El Salvador borders the<space/><link><target>Pacific Ocean</target><part>North Pacific Ocean</part></link><space/>to the south and southwest, with<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link><space/>to the north-northwest and<space/><link><target>Honduras</target></link><space/>to the north-northeast. In the southeast, the<space/><link><target>Golfo de Fonseca</target></link><space/>separates it from<space/><link><target>Nicaragua</target></link>.<space/><link><target>El Salvador</target></link><space/>is the smallest Central American country and is the only one without a<space/><link><target>coast</target><trail>line</trail></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Caribbean sea</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plate tectonics</heading><paragraph>El Salvador, along with the rest of Central America, is one of the most seismologically active regions on earth, situated atop three of the large<space/><link><target>tectonics</target><part>tectonic</part></link><space/>plates that constitute the Earth's surface. The motion of these plates causes the area's<space/><link><target>earthquake</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>volcano</target><part>volcanic</part></link><space/>activity.</paragraph><paragraph>Most of Central America and the<space/><link><target>Caribbean Basin</target></link><space/>rests on the relatively motionless<space/><link><target>Caribbean Plate</target></link>. The Pacific Ocean floor, however, is being carried northeast by the underlying motion of the<space/><link><target>Cocos Plate</target></link>. Ocean floor material is largely composed of<space/><link><target>basalt</target></link>, which is relatively dense; when it collides with the lighter<space/><link><target>granite</target></link><space/>rocks of Central America, the ocean floor is forced down under the land mass, creating the deep<space/><link><target>Middle America Trench</target></link><space/>that lies off the coast of El Salvador.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The subduction of the Cocos Plate accounts for the frequency of earthquakes near the coast. As the rocks constituting the ocean floor are forced down, they melt, and the molten material pours up through weaknesses in the surface rock, producing volcanoes and<space/><link><target>geyser</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>North of El Salvador, Mexico and most of Guatemala are riding on the westward-moving<space/><link><target>North American Plate</target></link><space/>that butts against the northern edge of the stationary<space/><link><target>Caribbean Plate</target></link><space/>in southern Guatemala. The grinding action of these two plates creates a fault (similar to the<space/><link><target>San Andreas Fault</target><part>San Andreas fault</part></link><space/>in California) that runs the length of the valley of the Rio Motagua in Guatemala. Motion along this fault is the source of earthquakes in northernmost El Salvador.</paragraph><paragraph>El Salvador has a long history of<space/><link><target>List of earthquakes in El Salvador</target><part>destructive earthquakes</part></link><space/>and volcanic eruptions.<space/><link><target>San Salvador</target></link><space/>was destroyed in 1756 and 1854, and suffered heavy damage in the 1919, 1982, and 1986 tremors. The country has over twenty volcanoes, although only two, San Miguel and<space/><link><target>Izalco (volcano)</target><part>Izalco</part></link>, have been active in recent years. From the early nineteenth century to the mid-1950s, Izalco erupted with a regularity that earned it the name &quot;Lighthouse of the Pacific.&quot; Its brilliant flares were clearly visible for great distances at sea, and at night its glowing lava turned it into a brilliant luminous cone.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Physical features</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:El Salvador Topography.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>450px</part><part>El Salvador's topography.</part></link><link><target>Image:El salvador econ 1980.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>450px</part><part>Economic activity of El Salvador, 1980.</part></link><link><target>Image:El salvador land 1980.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>450px</part><part>Vegetation and land use, 1980.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Two parallel mountain ranges cross El Salvador to the west with a central<space/><link><target>plateau</target></link><space/>between them and a narrow coastal plain hugging the Pacific. These physical features divide the country into two physiographic regions. The mountain ranges and central plateau, covering 85 percent of the land, comprise the interior highlands. The remaining coastal plains are referred to as the Pacific lowlands.</paragraph><paragraph>The northern range of mountains, the<space/><link><target>Sierra Madre de Chiapas</target><part>Sierra Madre</part></link>, form a continuous chain along the border with Honduras. Elevations in this region range from 1,600 to 2,700 meters. The area was once heavily forested, but<space/><link><target>overexploitation</target></link><space/>led to extensive erosion, and it has become semibarren. As a result, it is the country's most sparsely populated zone, with little farming or other development.</paragraph><paragraph>The southern range of mountains is actually a discontinuous chain of more than twenty volcanoes, clustered into five groups. The westernmost group, near the Guatemalan border, contains<space/><link><target>Izalco (volcano)</target><part>Izalco</part></link><space/>and Santa Ana, which at 2,365 meters is the highest volcano in El Salvador. Between the cones lie<space/><link><target>alluvial</target></link><space/>basins and rolling hills eroded from ash deposits. The volcanic soil is rich, and much of El Salvador's<space/><link><target>coffee</target></link><space/>is planted on these slopes.</paragraph><paragraph>The central plateau constitutes only 25 percent of the land area but contains the heaviest concentration of population and the country's largest cities. This plain is about 50 kilometers wide and has an average elevation of 600 meters. Terrain here is rolling, with occasional escarpments,<space/><link><target>lava</target></link><space/>fields, and<space/><link><target>geysers</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>A narrow plain extends from the coastal volcanic range to the Pacific Ocean. This region has a width ranging from one to thirty-two kilometers with the widest section in the east, adjacent to the<space/><link><target>Golfo de Fonseca</target></link>. Near<space/><link><target>La Libertad, La Libertad</target><part>La Libertad</part></link>, however, the mass of the mountains push the lowlands out; the slopes of adjacent volcanoes come down directly to the ocean. Surfaces in the Pacific lowlands are generally flat or gently rolling and result from the<space/><link><target>alluvial</target></link><space/>deposits of nearby slopes.</paragraph><paragraph>El Salvador has over 300 rivers, the most important of which is the<space/><link><target>Rio Lempa</target></link>. Originating in Guatemala, the Rio Lempa cuts across the northern range of mountains, flows along much of the central plateau, and finally cuts through the southern volcanic range to empty into the Pacific. It is El Salvador's only navigable river, it and its tributaries drain about half the country. Other rivers are generally short and drain the Pacific lowlands or flow from the central plateau through gaps in the southern mountain range to the Pacific.</paragraph><paragraph>Numerous lakes of volcanic origin are found in the interior highlands; many of these lakes are surrounded by mountains and have high, steep banks. The largest lake, the<space/><link><target>Lago de Ilopango</target></link>, lies just to the east of the capital. Other large lakes include the<space/><link><target>Coatepeque Caldera</target><part>Lago de Coatepeque</part></link><space/>in the west and the<space/><link><target>Lake Gija</target><part>Lago de Gija</part></link><space/>on the Guatemalan border. The<space/><link><target>Cerrn Grande Hydroelectric Dam</target><part>Cerron Grande Dam</part></link><space/>on the Rio Lempa has created a large reservoir, the Embalse Cerron Grande, in northern El Salvador.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Izalco (volcano)</target><part>Izalco</part></link><space/>has erupted at least 51 times since 1770. It earned the nickname &quot;Lighthouse of the Pacific&quot; because it was the most active volcano in Central America.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Climate</heading><paragraph>El Salvador has a<space/><link><target>tropical</target></link><space/>climate with pronounced wet and dry seasons. Temperatures vary primarily with elevation and show little seasonal change. The Pacific lowlands are uniformly hot and humid; the central plateau and mountain areas are more moderate.</paragraph><paragraph>The rainy season, known locally as<space/><italics>invierno</italics>, or winter, extends from May to October. Almost all the annual rainfall and the highest humidity occurs during this time, and yearly rain totals, particularly on southern-facing mountain slopes, can be as high as<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2000</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>. Protected areas and the central plateau receive lesser, although still significant, amounts. Rainfall during this season generally comes from low pressure over the Pacific and usually falls in heavy afternoon thunderstorms. Although<space/><link><target>hurricane</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>occasionally form in the Pacific, they seldom affect El Salvador, with the notable exception of<space/><link><target>Hurricane Mitch</target></link><space/>in 1998 (which actually formed over the Atlantic Basin) and<space/><link><target>1973 Pacific hurricane season#Hurricane Emily</target><part>Hurricane Emily</part></link><space/>in 1973.</paragraph><paragraph>From November through April, the northeast<space/><link><target>trade winds</target></link><space/>control weather patterns. During these months, air flowing from the Caribbean has lost most of its precipitation while passing over the mountains in Honduras. By the time this air reaches El Salvador, it is dry, hot, and hazy. This season is known locally as<space/><italics>verano</italics>, or summer.</paragraph><paragraph>Temperatures vary little with season; elevation is the primary determinant. The Pacific lowlands are the hottest region, with annual averages ranging from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25</arg><arg>to</arg><arg>29</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>°F</arg><arg>1</arg></template>. San Salvador is representative of the central plateau, with an annual average temperature of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>23</arg><arg>°C</arg></template><space/>and absolute high and low readings of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>38</arg><arg>and</arg><arg>6</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>°F</arg><arg>1</arg></template>, respectively. Mountain areas are the coolest, with annual averages from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>12</arg><arg>to</arg><arg>23</arg><arg>°C</arg><arg>°F</arg><arg>1</arg></template><space/>and minimum temperatures sometimes approaching freezing.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Other facts</heading><paragraph>El Salvador's physical shape form, evokes a similar resemblance to a rugged and miniature version of the U.S State of California. During the 1980s, the country's coastal roads were compared to California's coastal roads by American surfers and El Salvador became known as the wild west of Central America, characterized by roughness and lawlessness.</paragraph><paragraph>The total land area of El Salvador is 23,041&amp;nbsp;km, with 20,721&amp;nbsp;km of land and 320&amp;nbsp;km of water. This is slightly smaller than the<space/><link><target>U.S. state</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Massachusetts</target></link>. El Salvador has 590&amp;nbsp;km of borders, including 391&amp;nbsp;km of borders with<space/><link><target>Honduras</target></link><space/>and 199&amp;nbsp;km with<space/><link><target>Guatemala</target></link>. El Salvador has a coastline of 307&amp;nbsp;km.</paragraph><paragraph>El Salvador claims a<space/><link><target>territorial sea</target></link><space/>of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>200</arg><arg>nmi</arg><arg>km mi</arg><arg>1</arg><arg name="lk">in</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Climate:</bold>tropical; rainy season (May to October); dry season (November to April); tropical on coast; temperate in uplands</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Terrain:</bold>mostly mountains with narrow coastal belt and central plateau</paragraph><paragraph>The lowest point of elevation in El Salvador is the<space/><link><target>Pacific Ocean</target></link>, at<space/><link><target>sea level</target></link>. The highest point is<space/><link><target>Cerro El Pital</target></link>, at 2,730 m.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural resources:</bold><link><target>hydropower</target></link>,<space/><link><target>geothermal power</target></link>,<space/><link><target>petroleum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>arable land</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>Land use (2012 estimate) includes 34.03 percent<space/><link><target>arable land</target></link>, 10.86 percent permanent crops, 55.12 percent other.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Irrigated land:</bold>449.9&amp;nbsp;km (2003)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Total renewable water resources:</bold>25.23 km<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup><space/>(2011)</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Natural hazards:</bold>El Salvador is known as the &quot;Land of Volcanoes&quot;; there are frequent and sometimes very destructive earthquakes and volcanic activity; catastophic hurricanes are uncommon.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Environmental issues</heading><paragraph><link><target>Deforestation</target></link>; soil<space/><link><target>erosion</target></link>; water pollution; contamination of soils from disposal of<space/><link><target>toxic waste</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>El Salvador is party to the<space/><link><target>Convention on Biological Diversity</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kyoto Protocol to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Convention to Combat Desertification</target></link>,<space/><link><target>CITES</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Basel Convention</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Partial Test Ban Treaty</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Montreal Protocol</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ramsar Convention</target></link>. El Salvador has signed, but not ratified the<space/><link><target>United Nations Convention on the Law of the Sea</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>loc</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>CIA World Factbook</target></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>El Salvador topics</target></template><template><target>Geography of North America</target></template><template><target>North America topic</target><arg>Climate of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Geography of El Salvador</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>