<article title='Cable_car_%28railway%29'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>ground-based mass transit</arg><arg>other cable railway systems</arg><arg>Cable railway</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Cable car</arg></template><link><target>File:11 Cable Car on Powell St crop, SF, CA, jjron 25.03.2012.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A<space/><link><target>San Francisco cable car system</target><part>San Francisco cable car</part></link><space/>on the Powell &amp; Hyde line</part></link><link><target>File:Cable car.theora.ogv</target><part>thumb</part><part>View from Cable Car in San Francisco</part></link><link><target>Image:Cable Car.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Cable Car in San Francisco - double-ended car (California line)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>cable car</bold><space/>in the context of<space/><link><target>Public transport</target><part>mass transit</part></link><space/>is a system using rail cars that are hauled by a continuously moving<space/><link><target>Wire rope</target><part>cable</part></link><space/>running at a constant speed. Individual cars stop and start by releasing and gripping this cable as required. Cable cars are distinct from<space/><link><target>funicular</target><trail>s</trail></link>, where the cars are permanently attached to the cable, and<space/><link><target>cable railway</target><trail>s</trail></link>, which are similar to funiculars, but where the rail vehicles are attached and detached manually.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Minories stationLBR.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Winding drums on the<space/><link><target>London and Blackwall Railway</target><part>London and Blackwall</part></link><space/>cable-operated railway, 1840</part></link><link><target>File:Cable Driving Plant, Designed and Constructed by Poole and Hunt, Baltimore, MD.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Cable Driving Plant, Designed and Constructed by Poole &amp; Hunt, Baltimore, MD. Drawing by P.F. Goist, circa 1882. The powerhouse has two horizontal single-cylinder engines. The lithograph shows a hypothetical prototype of a cable powerhouse, rather than any actual built structure.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Hilton</arg><arg name="first">George W.</arg><arg name="title">The Cable Car in America</arg><arg name="year">1971</arg><arg name="publisher">Howell NorthBooks</arg><arg name="location">Berkeley, CA.</arg></template></extension><space/>Poole &amp; Hunt, machinists and engineers, was a major cable industry designer and contractor and manufacturer of gearing, sheaves, shafting and wire rope drums. They did work for cable railways in Baltimore, Chicago, Hoboken, Kansas City, New York, and Philadelphia.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">The Cable in Chicago: Speeding along the Streets Rapid Transit there for Miles</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 February 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Baltimore Sun, page 8</arg><arg name="date">Nov 9, 1889</arg></template></extension></part></link>The first cable-operated railway, employing a moving rope that could be picked up or released by a grip on the cars wasthe Fawdon railway (or wagonway) in 1826, a<space/><link><target>Colliery railway line</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Erskine Hazard, Observations upon Rail-roads,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=yrgFAAAAYAAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA275'>The Franklin Journal and American Mechanics' Magazine</link>, Vol. III, No. 4 (April 1827); page 275.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Fawdon Wagonway,<space/><link type='external' href='http://sine.ncl.ac.uk/view_structure_information.asp?struct_id=722'>Structural Images of the North East</link>, University of Newcastle upon Tyne, 26 Mar. 2004.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>London and Blackwall Railway</target></link>, which opened for passengers in east<space/><link><target>London</target></link>, England, in 1840 used such a system.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Robertson</arg><arg name="first">Andrew</arg><arg name="date">March 1848</arg><arg name="title">Blackwall Railway Machinery</arg><arg name="journal">The Civil engineer and architect's journal</arg><arg name="publisher">Wiley & Putnam</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="volume">11</arg></template></extension><space/>The rope available at the time proved too susceptible to wear and the system was abandoned in favour of<space/><link><target>steam locomotive</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>after eight years. In America, the first cable car installation in operation probably was the<space/><link><target>IRT Ninth Avenue Line</target><part>West Side and Yonkers Patent Railway</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link>, which ran from 1 July 1868 to 1870. The cable technology used in this elevated railway involved collar-equipped cables and claw-equipped cars, and proved cumbersome. The line was closed and rebuilt, and reopened with<space/><link><target>steam locomotive</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Other cable cars to use grips were those of the<space/><link><target>Clay Street Hill Railroad</target></link>, which later became part of the<space/><link><target>San Francisco cable car system</target></link>. The building of this line was promoted by<space/><link><target>Andrew Smith Hallidie</target></link><space/>with design work by<space/><link><target>William Eppelsheimer</target></link>, and it was first tested in 1873. The success of these grips ensured that this line became the model for other cable car transit systems, and this model is often known as the<space/><italics>Hallidie Cable Car</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1881 the<space/><link><target>Dunedin cable tramway system</target></link><space/>opened in<space/><link><target>Dunedin</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link><space/>and became the first such system outside San Francisco. For Dunedin,<space/><link><target>George Smith Duncan</target></link><space/>further developed the Hallidie model, introducing the pull curve and the slot brake; the former was a way to pull cars through a curve, since Dunedin's curves were too sharp to allow coasting, while the latter forced a wedge down into the cable slot to stop the car. Both of these innovations were generally adopted by other cities, including San Francisco.</paragraph><paragraph>In Australia the<space/><link><target>Melbourne cable tramway system</target></link><space/>operated from 1885 to 1940. It was one of the most extensive in the world with 1200 trams and trailers operating over 15 routes with 103&amp;nbsp;km (64 miles) of track. Sydney also had a few cable tram routes.</paragraph><paragraph>Cable cars rapidly spread to other cities, although the major attraction for most was the ability to displace<space/><link><target>horsecar</target></link><space/>(or<space/><link><target>mule</target></link>-drawn) systems rather than the ability to climb hills. Many people at the time viewed horse-drawn transit as unnecessarily cruel, and the fact that a typical horse could work only four or five hours per day necessitated the maintenance of large<space/><link><target>stables</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>draft animals</target></link><space/>that had to be fed, housed, groomed, medicated and rested. Thus, for a period, economics worked in favour of cable cars even in relatively flat cities.</paragraph><paragraph>For example, the<space/><link><target>Chicago City Railway</target></link>, also designed by Eppelsheimer, opened in<space/><link><target>Chicago</target></link><space/>in 1882 and went on to become the largest and most profitable cable car system. As with many cities, the problem in flat Chicago was not one of grades but of transportation capacity. This caused a different approach to the combination of grip car and trailer. Rather than using a grip car and single trailer, as many cities did, or combining the grip and trailer into a single car, like San Francisco's<space/><italics>California Cars</italics>, Chicago used grip cars to pull trains of up to three trailers.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1883 the<space/><link><target>New York and Brooklyn Bridge Railway</target></link><space/>was opened, which had a most curious feature: though it was a cable car system, it used<space/><link><target>steam locomotive</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to get the cars into and out of the terminals. After 1896 the system was changed to one on which a motor car was added to each train to maneuver at the terminals, while en route, the trains were still propelled by the cable.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Image:Cablecarpicjpg.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>upright</part><part>A San Francisco cable car travels along California Street in the city's Financial District</part></link>On 25 September 1883 a test of a cable car system was held by<space/><link><target>Liverpool United Tramways and Omnibus Company</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Kirkdale, Liverpool</target><part>Kirkdale</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Liverpool</target></link>. This would have been the first cable car system in Europe, but the company decided against implementing it. Instead the distinction went to the 1884 route from<space/><link><target>Archway, London</target><part>Archway</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Highgate</target></link>, north London, which used a continuous cable and grip system on the 1 in 11 (9%) climb of Highgate Hill. The installation was not reliable and was replaced by electric traction in 1909.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Taylor<space/></arg><arg name="first">Sheila<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Moving Metropolis<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Calmann and King<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="page">82<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-85669-241-8</arg></template></extension><space/>Other cable car systems were implemented in Europe, though, among which was the<space/><link><target>Glasgow Subway</target><part>Glasgow District Subway</part></link>, the first underground cable car system, in 1896. (<link><target>London</target></link>'s first deep-level tube railway, the<space/><link><target>City &amp; South London Railway</target></link>, had earlier also been built for cable haulage but had been converted to electric traction before opening in 1890.) A few more cable car systems were built in the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, but European cities, having many more curves in their streets, were less suitable for cable cars than American cities.</paragraph><paragraph>Though some new cable car systems were still being built, by 1890 the cheaper to construct and simpler to operate<space/><link><target>electricity</target><part>electrically</part></link>-powered<space/><link><target>tram</target><part>trolley</part></link><space/>or tram started to become the norm, and eventually started to replace existing cable car systems. For a while hybrid cable/electric systems operated, for example in Chicago where electric cars had to be pulled by grip cars through the loop area, due to the lack of trolley wires there. Eventually, San Francisco became the only street-running manually operated system to surviveDunedin, the second city with such cars, was also the second-last city to operate them, closing down in 1957.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Recent Revival</heading><paragraph>In the last decades of the 20th century cable traction in general has seen a limited revival as<space/><link><target>People mover</target><part>automatic people movers</part></link>, used in resort areas, airports (for example,<space/><link><target>LINK Train</target><part>Toronto Airport</part></link>), huge hospital centers and some urban settings. While many of these systems involve cars permanently attached to the cable, the<space/><link><target>Minimetro</target></link><space/>system from<space/><link><target>Poma</target></link>/<link><target>Leitner Group</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Cable Liner</target></link><space/>system from<space/><link><target>DCC Doppelmayr Cable Car</target></link><space/>both have variants that allow the cars to be automatically decoupled from the cable under computer control, and can thus be considered a modern interpretation of the cable car.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Operation</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:San Francisco Cable Car Power House.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Machinery driving the San Francisco cable car system</part></link><link><target>File:Cablecar tracks in San Francisco, 1970.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>The cable slot lies between the two tracks of the railway, providing an ingress for the grip, 1970</part></link>The cable is itself powered by a stationary motor or engine situated in a cable house or power house. The speed at which it moves is relatively constant depending on the number of units gripping the cable at any given time.</paragraph><paragraph>The cable car begins moving when a clamping device attached to the car, called a<space/><italics><link><target>Cable grip</target><part>grip</part></link></italics>, applies pressure to (&quot;grips&quot;) the moving cable. Conversely the car is stopped by releasing pressure on the cable (with or without completely detaching) and applying the brakes. This gripping and ungripping action may be manual, as was the case in all early cable car systems, or automatic, as is the case in some recent cable operated<space/><link><target>people mover</target></link><space/>type systems. Gripping must be an even and gradual process in order to avoid bringing the car to cable speed too quickly and unacceptably jarring the<space/><link><target>passenger</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the case of manual systems, the grip resembles a very large pair of<space/><link><target>pliers</target></link>, and considerable strength and skill are required to operate the car. As many early cable car operators discovered the hard way, if the grip is not applied properly, it can damage the cable, or even worse, become entangled in the cable. In the latter case, the cable car may not be able to stop and can wreak havoc along its route until the cable house realizes the mishap and halts the cable.</paragraph><paragraph>One apparent advantage of the cable car is its relative energy efficiency, because of the economy of centrally located power stations, and the ability of descending cars to transfer energy to ascending cars. However, this advantage is totally negated by the relatively large energy consumption required to simply move the cable over and under the numerous guide rollers and around the many<space/><link><target>sheave</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Approximately 95% of the tractive effort in the San Francisco system is expended in simply moving the four cables at 9.5 miles per hour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Source: San Francisco Municipal Railway</extension><space/>Electric cars with<space/><link><target>regenerative braking</target></link><space/>do offer the advantages, without the problem of moving a cable. In the case of steep grades, however, cable traction has the major advantage of not depending on<space/><link><target>rail adhesion</target><part>adhesion between wheels and rails</part></link>. There is also the obvious advantage that keeping the car gripped to the cable will also limit the downhill speed to that of the cable.</paragraph><paragraph>Because of the constant and relatively low speed, a cable car's potential to cause harm in an accident can be underestimated. Even with a cable car traveling at only 9 miles per hour, the mass of the cable car and the combined strength and speed of the cable can do quite a lot of damage in a collision.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Relation to Funiculars</heading><paragraph>A cable car is superficially similar to a<space/><link><target>funicular</target></link>, but differs from such a system in that its cars are not permanently attached to the cable and can stop independently, whereas a funicular has cars that are permanently attached to the propulsion cable, which is itself stopped and started. A cable car cannot climb as steep a grade as a funicular, but many more cars can be operated with a single cable, making it more flexible, and allowing a higher capacity. During the rush hour on San Francisco's Market Street Railway, a car would leave the terminal every 15 seconds.<template><target>when</target><arg name="date">December 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A few funicular railways operate in street traffic, and because of this operation are often incorrectly described as cable cars. Examples of such operation, and the consequent confusion, are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Great Orme Tramway</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Llandudno</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wales</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Several street funiculars in<space/><link><target>Lisbon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Even more confusingly, a hybrid cable car/funicular line once existed in the form of the original<space/><link><target>Wellington Cable Car</target></link>, in the<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link><space/>city of<space/><link><target>Wellington</target></link>. This line had both a continuous loop haulage cable that the cars gripped using a cable car gripper, and a balance cable permanently attached to both cars over an undriven pulley at the top of the line. The descending car gripped the haulage cable and was pulled downhill, in turn pulling the ascending car (which remained ungripped) uphill by the balance cable. This line was rebuilt in 1979 and is now a standard funicular, although it retains its old cable car name.</paragraph><heading level='2'>List of cable car systems</heading><heading level='3'>Cities currently operating cable cars</heading><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='4'>Traditional cable car systems</heading><paragraph>The best known existing cable car system is the<space/><link><target>San Francisco cable car system</target></link><space/>in the city of<space/><link><target>San Francisco, California</target></link>. San Francisco's cable cars constitute the oldest and largest such system in permanent operation, and it is the only one to still operate in the traditional manner with manually operated cars running in street traffic.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Modern cable car systems</heading><preblock><preline>Several cities operate a modern version of the cable car system. These systems are fully automated and run on their own reserved right of way. They are commonly referred to as<space/><link><target>people mover</target><trail>s</trail></link>, although that term is also applied to systems with other forms of propulsion, including funicular style cable propulsion.</preline></preblock><paragraph>These cities include:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Laon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Poma 2000</target></link>)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.tul-laon.net/poma.php<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>POMA<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Transports Urbain Laonnois<space/></arg><arg name="language"><space/>French<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-04-02<space/></arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Las Vegas Strip</target><part>Las Vegas</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>Two lines linking the<space/><link><target>Mandalay Bay Resort and Casino</target><part>Mandalay Bay</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Luxor (hotel)</target><part>Luxor</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Excalibur Hotel and Casino</target><part>Excalibur</part></link><space/>hotels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.dcc.at/doppelmayr/references/en/tmp_1_435423795/Las_Vegas_Mandalay_Bay_detail.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Doppelmayr Cable Car<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Doppelmayr<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2009-10-22</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Mandalay Bay Tram</target></link></extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Milan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>(connecting the<space/><link><target>San Raffaele Hospital</target></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Cascina Gobba (Milan Metro)</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mississauga</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ontario</target></link>, connecting terminals 1 and 3 and the Viscount parking lot at<space/><link><target>Toronto Pearson International Airport</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Oakland, California</target></link>, United States,<space/><link><target>BART to OAK</target></link><space/>mass transit to airport link</listitem><listitem><link><target>Venice</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Venice People Mover</target></link><space/>connects the Isola del Tronchetto with Piazzale Roma.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Perugia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>(<link><target>MiniMetro</target></link>)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Cities previously operating cable cars</heading><heading level='4'>Australia</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Melbourne cable tram 1905.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>Cable tram and trailer on the St Kilda Line in<space/><link><target>Melbourne</target></link><space/>in 1905.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Melbourne</target></link><space/>(18851940, the<space/><link><target>Melbourne cable tramway system</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Trams in Sydney</target><part>Sydney</part></link><space/>(18861905)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Colombia</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bogot</target></link>, destroyed during the<space/><link><target>Bogotazo</target></link><space/>(1948)<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">No evidence of a cable car system in Bogota can be found anywhere else</arg><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='4'>France</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paris</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Tramway funiculaire de Belleville</target></link><space/>18731935)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>New Zealand</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Dunedin</target></link><space/>(18811957, the<space/><link><target>Dunedin cable tramway system</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wellington</target></link><space/>(19021979, the original<space/><link><target>Wellington Cable Car</target></link><space/>hybrid system)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Philippines</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Manila</target></link><space/>(Early 1900s - 1930s, the Manila- Malabon railway.)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Portugal</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Lisbon</target></link><space/>(converted to regular<space/><link><target>Trams in Lisbon</target><part>tram</part></link><space/>lines in the early 20th century:<space/><italics>So Sebastio</italics>,<space/><italics>Estrela</italics>, and<space/><italics>Graa</italics>)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:GOT Tram 4 Descending 05-07-17 04.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>Great Orme Tramway Tram No.4 Descending Old Road,<space/><link><target>Llandudno</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Edinburgh</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Edinburgh Corporation Tramways</target></link>, 18991923 (replaced by electric trams))</listitem><listitem><link><target>Glasgow</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Glasgow Subway</target></link>, 18961935, converted to electric traction)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hastings</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Liverpool</target></link><space/>(trial in 1883)</listitem><listitem><link><target>London</target></link><space/>(18841909, connecting<space/><link><target>Archway, London</target><part>Archway</part></link><space/>with<space/><link><target>Highgate</target></link>, the first cable car in regular operation in Europe)</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link><target>Lynton and Lynmouth Cliff Railway</target></link><space/>(1890 onwards)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Matlock, Derbyshire</target><part>Matlock</part></link><space/>(18931927, the<space/><link><target>Matlock Cable Tramway</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Llandudno, Wales</target></link><space/>(The<space/><link><target>Great Orme Tramway</target></link>), although it operates as a funicular railway this is the only cable powered street tramway that is still carrying passengers in Great Britain.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Isle of Man</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Douglas, Isle of Man</target><part>Douglas</part></link><space/>(18961929)</listitem></list><heading level='4'>United States</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Cable car on Yesler Way at 3rd Avenue in 1940.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>A Seattle cable car in 1940, just before service ended. Seattle was the last city in the U.S. to abandon all its street cable railways, with the last three lines all closing in 1940, leaving San Francisco as the only U.S. city where cable cars continued to operate.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hilton-p167">Hilton (1982), p. 167.</extension></part></link></paragraph><preblock><preline>*<space/><link><target>Baltimore, Maryland</target></link><space/>(18901897)</preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Binghamton, New York</target></link><space/>(trial in 1885)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Brooklyn</target><part>Brooklyn, New York</part></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>New York and Brooklyn Bridge Railway</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brooklyn Cable Company</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Park Avenue Line (Brooklyn surface)</target><part>Park Avenue Line</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Brooklyn Heights Railroad</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Montague Street Line</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Butte, Montana</target></link><space/>(18891897)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Cable cars in Chicago</target><part>Chicago, Illinois</part></link><space/>(18821906)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Chicago City Railway</target></link></listitem><listitem>North Chicago Street Railroad</listitem><listitem>West Chicago Street Railroad</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cincinnati</target><part>Cincinnati, Ohio</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cleveland</target><part>Cleveland, Ohio</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Denver</target><part>Denver, Colorado</part></link><space/>(18861900, the<space/><link><target>Denver Tramway</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Grand Rapids, Michigan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Hoboken, New Jersey</target></link><space/>(18861892, the<space/><link><target>North Hudson County Railway</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Hoboken Elevated</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Kansas City, Missouri</target></link><space/>(1885-1913), including 9th St Incline (1888-1902)<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>8th St. Tunnel in use (1887-1956)</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Los Angeles</target><part>Los Angeles, California</part></link><space/>(18851889)<space/><link><target>Second Street Cable Railway</target></link>, (1886-1902)<space/><link><target>Temple Street Cable Railway</target></link>, (1889-1896)<space/><link><target>Los Angeles Cable Railway</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>New York City</target></link>,<space/><link><target>New York</target></link><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>West Side and Yonkers Patent Railway</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Ninth Avenue Line (Manhattan elevated)</target><part>Ninth Avenue Line</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>New York and Brooklyn Bridge Railway</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Third Avenue Railroad</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>125th Street Crosstown Line</target></link></listitem><listitem>Third Avenue Railroad's<space/><link><target>Third Avenue Line (Manhattan surface)</target><part>Third Avenue Line</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Metropolitan Street Railway</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Broadway Line (Lower Manhattan surface)</target><part>Broadway Line</part></link></listitem><listitem>Metropolitan Street Railway's<space/><link><target>Broadway and Columbus Avenue Line</target></link></listitem><listitem>Metropolitan Street Railway's<space/><link><target>Broadway and Lexington Avenue Line</target></link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Newark, New Jersey</target></link><space/>(18881889)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Oakland, California</target></link><space/>(18861899)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Omaha, Nebraska</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Philadelphia</target><part>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pittsburgh</target><part>Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Portland, Oregon</target></link><space/>(18901904)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Providence, Rhode Island</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>St. Louis, Missouri</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Saint Paul, Minnesota</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>San Diego</target></link>, California (18901892)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Seattle, Washington</target></link><space/>(18881940)<extension extension_name='ref' name="hilton-p389">Hilton (1982), pp. 389407.</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sioux City, Iowa</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Spokane, Washington</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tacoma, Washington</target></link><space/>(18911938)<extension extension_name='ref' name="hilton-p465">Hilton (1982), p. 465.</extension></listitem><listitem><link><target>Tulsa, Oklahoma</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Washington, D.C.</target></link><space/>(18901899, part of the<space/><link><target>Washington streetcars</target><part>Washington streetcar system</part></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wichita, Kansas</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>div col</target><arg>3</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Aerial tramway</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cable car</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cable railway</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cable ferry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cable Liner</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Elevator</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Funicular</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Grade (slope)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of funicular railways</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rack railway</target></link><space/>(Cog railway)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Reaction ferry</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>San Francisco cable car system</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>div col end</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>General</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>George Hilton (historian)</target><part>Hilton, George W.</part></link><space/>(1982).<space/><italics>The Cable Car in America (Revised Edition)</italics>. San Diego, California: HowellNorth Books. Reprinted 1997 by<space/><link><target>Stanford University Press</target></link>. ISBN 0-8047-3051-2.</listitem><listitem><italics>Of Cables and Grips: The Cable Cars of San Francisco</italics>, by Robert Callwell and Walter Rice, published by Friends of the Cable Car Museum, first edition, 2000.</listitem><listitem><italics>Chicago Cable Cars</italics>, by Greg Borzo, published by The History Press (2012), ISBN 978-1-60949-327-1</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Specific</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Cable car on rails</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Cable transport</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Information</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cablecarmuseum.com'>Cable Car Museum</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cable-car-guy.com'>Cable Car Guy</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ghidelli.net/scripophily/cal%20cable.html'>a scripophily based article re. the San Francisco Cal Cable and the Swiss Borel Bankers (in German)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lostnewyorkcity.com/buildingphotos/Plate-51-b.html'>The Cable Building</link><space/>(New York City) Broadway Cable car line.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cablecarmuseum.org/archive/Anat/Anat.html'>How Cable Cars Operate</link><space/>San Francisco Cable Car Museum</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch_popup?v=NINOxRxze9k'>San Francisco Cable Car Movie from 1905</link></listitem></list><paragraph><bold>Patents</bold></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>US patent</target><arg>19736</arg></template><italics>Railroad track</italics></listitem><listitem><template><target>US patent</target><arg>110971</arg></template><italics>Endless wire ropeway</italics></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cable Car (Railway)</target></template><link><target>Category:Cable railways</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Cable car railways</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Rail technologies</target></link><link><target>Category:Railways by type</target></link><link><target>Category:Articles containing video clips</target></link></paragraph></article>