<article title='Alemanni'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg>Alamanni (disambiguation)</arg></template><link><target>File:Alemanni expansion.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>320px</part><part>Area settled by the Alemanni, and sites of Roman-Alemannic battles, 3rd to 6th centuries</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Alemanni</bold><space/>(also<space/><italics>Alamanni</italics>;<extension extension_name='ref'>The spelling with &quot;e&quot; is used in Encyc. Brit. 9th. ed., (c. 1880), Everyman's Encyc. 1967, Everyman's Smaller Classical Dictionary, 1910. The current edition of Britannica spells with &quot;e&quot;, as does Columbia and Edward Gibbon, Vol. 3, Chapter XXXVIII. The Latinized spelling with<space/><italics>a</italics><space/>is current in older literature (so in the<space/><link><target>1911 Britannica</target></link>, but remains in use e.g. in Wood (2003), Drinkwater (2007).</extension><space/><italics>Suebi</italics><space/>&quot;Swabians&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>The Alemanni were alternatively known as<space/><italics>Suebi</italics><space/>from about the 5th century, and that name became prevalent in the high medieval period, eponymous of the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Swabia</target></link>. The name is taken from that of the<space/><italics><link><target>Suebi</target></link></italics><space/>mentioned by Julius Caesar, and although these older<space/><italics>Suebi</italics><space/>did likely contribute to the ethnogenesis of the Alemanni, there is no direct connection to the contemporary<space/><link><target>Kingdom of the Suebi</target></link><space/>in Galicia.</extension>) were a confederation of<space/><link><target>Germanic peoples</target><part>Germanic tribe</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on the<space/><link><target>upper Rhine</target></link><space/>river. First mentioned by<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>in the context of the campaign of<space/><link><target>Caracalla</target></link><space/>of 213, the Alemanni captured the<space/><link><target>Agri Decumates</target></link><space/>in 260, and later expanded into present-day<space/><link><target>Alsace</target></link>, and northern<space/><link><target>Switzerland</target></link>, leading to the establishment of the<space/><link><target>Old High German</target></link><space/>language in those regions.</paragraph><paragraph>In 496, the Alemanni were<space/><link><target>Battle of Tolbiac</target><part>conquered</part></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Franks</target><part>Frankish</part></link><space/>leader<space/><link><target>Clovis I</target><part>Clovis</part></link><space/>and incorporated into his<space/><link><target>Frankish Empire</target><part>dominions</part></link>. Mentioned as still<space/><link><target>Germanic paganism</target><part>pagan</part></link><space/>allies of the<space/><link><target>Germanic Christianity</target><part>Christian</part></link><space/>Franks, the Alemanni were gradually Christianized during the 7th century. The<space/><italics><link><target>Pactus Alamannorum</target></link></italics><space/>is a record of their customary law during this period. Until the 8th century, Frankish suzerainty over Alemannia was mostly nominal. But after an uprising by<space/><link><target>Theudebald, Duke of Alamannia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carloman I</target><part>Carloman</part></link><space/>executed the Alamannic nobility and installed Frankish dukes. During the later and weaker years of the<space/><link><target>Carolingian Empire</target></link><space/>the Alemannic counts became almost independent, and a struggle for supremacy took place between them and the<space/><link><target>Bishopric of Constance</target></link>. The chief family in Alamannia was that of the counts of<space/><link><target>Raetia Curiensis</target></link>, who were sometimes called margraves, and one of whom,<space/><link><target>Burchard II, Duke of Swabia</target><part>Burchard II</part></link>, established the<space/><link><target>Duchy of Swabia</target></link>, which was recognized by<space/><link><target>Henry the Fowler</target></link><space/>in 919 and became a<space/><link><target>stem duchy</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The area settled by the Alemanni corresponds roughly to the area where<space/><link><target>Alemannic German</target></link><space/>dialects remain spoken, including German<space/><link><target>Swabia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Baden</target></link>, French<space/><link><target>Alsace</target></link>,<space/><link><target>German-speaking Switzerland</target></link><space/>and Austrian<space/><link><target>Vorarlberg</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Name</heading><paragraph>According to<space/><link><target>Asinius Quadratus</target></link><space/>(quoted in the mid-6th century by Byzantine historian<space/><link><target>Agathias</target></link>) their name means &quot;all men&quot;. It indicates that they were a conglomeration drawn from various Germanic tribes. This was the derivation of<space/><italics>Alemanni</italics><space/>used by<space/><link><target>Edward Gibbon</target></link>, in his<space/><italics>Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire</italics><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Edward Gibbon.<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ccel.org/g/gibbon/decline/volume1/chap10.htm#MIX<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chapter 10<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Ccel.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-01-02</arg></template></extension><space/>and by the anonymous contributor of notes assembled from the papers of<space/><link><target>Nicolas Frret</target></link>, published in 1753, who noted that it was the name used by outsiders for those who called themselves the<space/><italics><link><target>Suebi</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Histoire de l'Acadmie Royale des Inscriptions et Belles-Lettres, avec les Mmoires de Littrature tirs des Registres de cette Acadmie, depuis l'anne MDCCXLIV jusques et compris l'anne MDCCXLVI</italics>, vol. XVIII, (Paris 1753) pp.4971. Excerpts are on-line at<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.eliohs.unifi.it/testi/700/freret/vues.html#notaed'>ELIOHS</link>.</extension><space/>This etymology has remained the standard derivation of the term.<extension extension_name='ref'>It is cited in most etymological dictionaries, such as the<space/><italics><link><target>American Heritage Dictionary</target></link></italics><space/>(large edition) under the root,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.bartleby.com/61/roots/IE295.html'>*man-</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Walafrid Strabo</target></link>, a monk of the<space/><link><target>Abbey of St. Gall</target></link><space/>writing in the 9th century, remarked, in discussing the people of Switzerland and the surrounding regions, that only foreigners called them the<space/><italics>Alemanni</italics>, but that they gave themselves the name of<space/><italics>Suebi</italics>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The name of Germany and the German language in several languages is derived from the name of this early Germanic tribal alliance. For details, see<space/><link><target>Names of Germany</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>First explicit mention</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Alamannischi Girtelbschleg.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Alemannic belt mountings, from a 7th-century grave in the<space/><link><target>Alemannic grave field</target><part>grave field</part></link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Weingarten (Wrttemberg)</target><part>Weingarten</part></link>.</part></link>The Alemanni were first mentioned by<space/><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>describing the campaign of<space/><link><target>Caracalla</target></link><space/>in 213. At that time they apparently dwelt in the basin of the<space/><link><target>Main River</target><part>Main</part></link>, to the south of the<space/><link><target>Chatti</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Cassius Dio</target></link><space/>(78.13.4) portrays the Alemanni as victims of this treacherous emperor.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Cassius_Dio/78*.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Chicago<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cassius Dio: Roman History</arg></template></extension><space/>They had asked for his help, says Dio, but instead he colonized their country, changed their place names and executed their warriors under a pretext of coming to their aid. When he became ill, the Alemanni claimed to have put a hex on him (78.15.2). Caracalla, it was claimed, tried to counter this influence by invoking his ancestral spirits.</paragraph><paragraph>In retribution Caracalla then led the<space/><link><target>Legio II Traiana Fortis</target><part>Legio II ''Traiana Fortis''</part></link><space/>against the Alemanni, who lost and were pacified for a time. The legion was as a result honored with the name<space/><italics>Germanica</italics>. The 4th-century fictional<space/><link><target>Historia Augusta</target></link>,<space/><italics>Life of Antoninus Caracalla</italics>, relates (10.5) that Caracalla then assumed the name<space/><italics>Alemannicus</italics>, at which Helvius Pertinax jested that he should really be called<space/><italics>Geticus Maximus</italics>, because in the year before he had murdered his brother,<space/><link><target>Publius Septimius Geta</target><part>Geta</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://penelope.uchicago.edu/Thayer/E/Roman/Texts/Historia_Augusta/Caracalla*.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">University of Chicago<space/></arg><arg name="title">Historia Augusta: The Life of Antoninus Caracalla</arg></template></extension><space/>Not on good terms with Caracalla, Geta had been invited to a family reconciliation, at which time he was ambushed by centurions in Caracalla's army and slain in his mother Julia's arms. True or not, Caracalla, pursued by devils of his own, left Rome never to return.</paragraph><paragraph>Caracalla left for the frontier, where for the rest of his short reign he was known for his unpredictable and arbitrary operations launched by surprise after a pretext of peace negotiations. If he had any reasons of state for such actions they remained unknown to his contemporaries. Whether or not the Alemanni had been previously neutral, they were certainly further influenced by Caracalla to become thereafter notoriously implacable enemies of Rome.</paragraph><paragraph>This mutually antagonistic relationship is perhaps the reason why the Roman writers persisted in calling the Alemanni<space/><italics>barbari</italics>, &quot;savages&quot;. The archaeology, however, shows that they were largely Romanized, lived in Roman-style houses and used Roman artifacts, the Alemannic women having adopted the Roman fashion of the<space/><italics><link><target>tunic</target></link></italics><space/>even earlier than the men.</paragraph><paragraph>Most of the Alemanni were probably at the time in fact resident in or close to the borders of<space/><link><target>Germania Superior</target></link>. Although Dio is the earliest writer to mention them,<space/><link><target>Ammianus Marcellinus</target></link><space/>used the name to refer to Germans on the<space/><link><target>Limes Germanicus</target></link><space/>in the time of<space/><link><target>Trajan</target></link>'s governorship of the province shortly after it was formed, c. 98/99. At that time the entire frontier was being fortified for the first time. Trees from the earliest fortifications found in<space/><link><target>Germania Inferior</target></link><space/>are dated by<space/><link><target>dendrochronology</target></link><space/>to 99/100 AD. Shortly afterwards Trajan was chosen by<space/><link><target>Nerva</target></link><space/>to be his successor, adopted with public fanfare in absentia by the old man shortly before his death. By 100 AD. Trajan was back in Rome as Emperor instead of merely being a Consul.</paragraph><paragraph>Ammianus relates (<link type='external' href='http://www.gmu.edu/departments/fld/CLASSICS/ammianus17.html'>xvii.1.11</link>) that much later the Emperor<space/><link><target>Julian the Apostate</target><part>Julian</part></link><space/>undertook a<space/><link><target>punitive expedition</target></link><space/>against the Alemanni, who by then were in Alsace, and crossed the Main (Latin<space/><italics>Menus</italics>), entering the forest, where the trails were blocked by felled trees. As winter was upon them, they reoccupied a&quot;fortification which was founded on the soil of the Alemanni that Trajan wished to be called with his own name&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>munimentum quod in Alamannorum solo conditum Traianus suo nomine voluit appellari.</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In this context the use of Alemanni is possibly an anachronism but it reveals that Ammianus believed they were the same people, which is consistent with the location of the Alemanni of Caracalla's campaigns.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Alemanni and Hermunduri</heading><paragraph>The early detailed source, the<space/><italics><link><target>Germania (book)</target><part>Germania</part></link></italics><space/>of<space/><link><target>Tacitus</target></link>, has sometimes been interpreted in such a way as to provide yet other historical problems. In<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/cla/tac/g01040.htm'>Chapter 42</link><space/>we read of the<space/><link><target>Hermunduri</target></link>, a tribe certainly located in the region that later became<space/><link><target>Thuringia</target></link>. Tacitus stated that they traded with<space/><link><target>Rhaetia</target></link>, which in Ptolemy is located across the Danube from<space/><link><target>Germania Superior</target></link>. A logical conclusion to draw is that the Hermunduri extended over later<space/><link><target>Swabia</target></link><space/>and therefore the Alemanni originally derived from the Hermunduri!</paragraph><paragraph>However, no Hermunduri appear in Ptolemy, though after the time of Ptolemy, the Hermunduri joined with the<space/><link><target>Marcomanni</target></link><space/>in the wars of 166180 against the empire. A careful reading of Tacitus provides one solution. He says that the source of the<space/><link><target>Elbe</target></link><space/>is among the Hermunduri, somewhat to the east of the upper<space/><link><target>Main (river)</target><part>Main</part></link>. He places them also between the<space/><link><target>Naristi</target></link><space/>(Varisti), whose location at the very edge of the ancient<space/><link><target>Black Forest</target></link><space/>is well known, and the<space/><link><target>Marcomanni</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Quadi</target></link>. Moreover, the Hermunduri were broken in the<space/><link><target>Marcomannic Wars</target></link><space/>and made a separate peace with Rome. The Alemanni thus were probably not primarily the Hermunduri, although some elements of them may have been present in the mix of peoples at that time that became Alemannian.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Ptolemy's<space/><italics>Geography</italics></heading><paragraph>Before the mention of<space/><italics>Alemanni</italics><space/>in the time of Caracalla, you would search in vain for Alemanni in the moderately detailed geography of southern Germany in Claudius<space/><link><target>Ptolemy</target></link>, written in Greek in the mid-2nd century; it is likely that at that time, the people who later used that name were known by other designations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ptolemy's description has some limitations. Upper Germany and Lower Germany are mentioned by name, but only as specific districts of Gallia Belgica (2.8), the border between them was an unidentified river, the Obruncus. The region is repeated again under Germany, but this time he does not list Roman boundaries. Germania Superior, the Agri Decumates and the limes are not to be found there, even though they certainly existed at the time. &quot;Germania Magna&quot; is found within the Rhine, Danube, Vistula and shores of the &quot;Oceanus Germanicus&quot;. Most of the tribes are missing or listed without name. The Main is not there, nor Lake Constance. The Danube runs from the Alps. The Rhine does not bend to the south next to Swabia. Ptolemy's Germania is like a surreal image of itself, accurate only if you follow certain known lines, but the overall shape is greatly distorted.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Nevertheless, some conclusions can be drawn from Ptolemy. Germania Superior is easily identified. Following up the Rhine one comes to a town, Mattiacum, which must be at the border of the Roman Germany (vicinity of<space/><link><target>Wiesbaden</target></link>). Upstream from it and between the Rhine and<space/><link><target>Abnoba</target></link><space/>(in the<space/><link><target>Black Forest</target></link>) are the<space/><link><target>Ingriones</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Intuergi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vangiones</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Caritni</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vispi</target></link>, some of whom were there since the days of the early empire or before. On the other side of the northern Black Forest were the<space/><link><target>Chatti</target></link><space/>about where<space/><link><target>Hesse</target></link><space/>is today, on the lower Main.</paragraph><paragraph>Historic Swabia was eventually replaced by today's<space/><link><target>Baden-Wrttemberg</target></link>, but it had been the most significant territory of mediaeval<space/><link><target>Alamannia</target></link>, comprising all Germania Superior and territory east to<space/><link><target>Bavaria</target></link>. It did not include the upper Main, but that is where Caracalla campaigned. Moreover, the territory of Germania Superior was not originally included among the Alemanni's possessions.</paragraph><paragraph>However, if we look for the peoples in the region from the upper Main in the north, south to the Danube and east to the<space/><link><target>Czech Republic</target></link><space/>where the<space/><link><target>Quadi</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Marcomanni</target></link><space/>were located, Ptolemy does not give any tribes. There are the<space/><link><target>Tubanti</target></link><space/>just south of the<space/><link><target>Chatti</target></link><space/>and at the other end of what was then the Black Forest, the<space/><link><target>Varisti</target></link>, whose location is known. One possible reason for this distribution is that the population preferred not to live in the forest except in troubled times. The region between the forest and the<space/><link><target>Danube</target></link><space/>on the other hand included about a dozen settlements, or &quot;cantons&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Ptolemy's view of Germans in the region indicates that the tribal structure had lost its grip in the Black Forest region and was replaced by a canton structure. The tribes stayed in the Roman province, perhaps because the Romans offered stability. Also, Caracalla perhaps<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template><space/>felt more comfortable about campaigning in the upper Main because he was not declaring war on any specific historic tribe, such as the Chatti or<space/><link><target>Cherusci</target></link>, against whom Rome had suffered grievous losses. By Caracalla's time the name<space/><italics>Alemanni</italics><space/>was being used by cantons themselves banding together for purposes of supporting a citizen army (the &quot;war bands&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Concentration of Germanic peoples under Ariovistus</heading><paragraph>The term Suebi has a double meaning in the sources. On the one hand Tacitus'<space/><italics>Germania</italics><space/>tells us (<link type='external' href='http://www.sacred-texts.com/cla/tac/g01030.htm'>Chapters 38, 39)</link><space/>that they occupy more than half of Germany, use a distinctive hair style, and are spiritually centered on the<space/><link><target>Semnones</target></link>. On the other hand, the Suebi of the upper Danube are described as though they were a tribe.</paragraph><paragraph>The solution to the puzzle as well as explaining the historical circumstances leading to the choice of the Agri Decumates as a defensive point and the concentration of Germans there are probably to be found in the German attack on the Gallic fortified town of<space/><link><target>Vesontio</target></link><space/>in 58 BC. The upper Rhine and Danube appear to form a funnel pointing straight at Vesontio.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Julius Caesar</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>Gallic Wars</target></link></italics><space/>tells us (<link type='external' href='http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-new2?id=CaeComm.sgm&amp;amp;images=images/modeng&amp;amp;data=/texts/english/modeng/parsed&amp;amp;tag=public&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;division=div2'>1.51</link>) that<space/><link><target>Ariovistus</target></link><space/>had gathered an army from a wide region of Germany, but especially the<space/><link><target>Harudes</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Marcomanni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Triboci</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vangiones</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Nemetes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sedusii</target></link>. The Suebi were being invited to join. They lived in 100 cantons (<link type='external' href='http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-new2?id=CaeComm.sgm&amp;amp;images=images/modeng&amp;amp;data=/texts/english/modeng/parsed&amp;amp;tag=public&amp;amp;part=4&amp;amp;division=div2'>4.1</link>) from which 1000 young men per year were chosen for military service, a citizen-army by our standards and by comparison with the Roman professional army.</paragraph><paragraph>Ariovistus had become involved in an invasion of<space/><link><target>Gaul</target></link>, which the German wished to settle. Intending to take the strategic town of Vesontio, he concentrated his forces on the Rhine near Lake Constance, and when the Suebi arrived, he crossed. The Gauls had called to Rome for military aid. Caesar occupied the town first and defeated the Germans before its walls, slaughtering most of the German army as it tried to flee across the river (1.36ff). He did not pursue the retreating remnants, leaving what was left of the German army and their dependents intact on the other side of the Rhine.</paragraph><paragraph>The Gauls were ambivalent in their policies toward the Romans. In 53 BC the<space/><link><target>Treveri</target></link><space/>broke their alliance and attempted to break free of Rome. Caesar foresaw that they would now attempt to ally themselves with the Germans. He crossed the Rhine to forestall that event, a successful strategy. Remembering their expensive defeat at the Battle of Vesontio, the Germans withdrew to the Black Forest, concentrating there a mixed population dominated by Suebi. As they had left their tribal homes behind, they probably took over all the former Celtic cantons along the Danube.</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='3'>Conflicts with the Roman Empire</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Karte limes.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Limes Germanicus</target></link><space/>83 to 260 CE.</part></link><template><target>Campaignbox Rome against the Alamanni</target></template>The Alemanni were continually engaged in conflicts with the<space/><link><target>Roman Empire</target></link><space/>in the 3rd and 4th centuries. They launched a major invasion of<space/><link><target>Gaul</target></link><space/>and northern<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link><space/>in 268, when the Romans were forced to denude much of their German frontier of troops in response to a massive invasion of the<space/><link><target>Goths</target></link><space/>from the east. Their raids throughout the three parts of Gaul were traumatic:<space/><link><target>Gregory of Tours</target></link><space/>(died ca 594) mentions their destructive force at the time of<space/><link><target>Valerian (emperor)</target><part>Valerian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Gallienus</target></link><space/>(253260), when the Alemanni assembled under their &quot;king&quot;, whom he calls<space/><link><target>Chrocus</target></link>, who &quot;by the advice, it is said, of his wicked mother, and overran the whole of the Gauls, and destroyed from their foundations all the temples which had been built in ancient times. And coming to<space/><link><target>Clermont-Ferrand</target><part>Clermont</part></link><space/>he set on fire, overthrew and destroyed that shrine which they call<space/><italics>Vasso Galatae</italics><space/>in the Gallic tongue,&quot; martyring many Christians (<link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/basis/gregory-hist.html#book3'>''Historia Francorum'' Book I.3234</link>). Thus 6th-century Gallo-Romans of Gregory's class, surrounded by the ruins of<space/><link><target>Roman temple</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and public buildings, attributed the destruction they saw to the plundering raids of the Alemanni.</paragraph><paragraph>In the early summer of 268, the<space/><link><target>Roman Emperors</target><part>Emperor</part></link><space/><link><target>Gallienus</target></link><space/>halted their advance into Italy, but then had to deal with the Goths. When the Gothic campaign ended in Roman victory at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Naissus</target></link><space/>in September, Gallienus' successor<space/><link><target>Claudius II</target><part>Claudius II Gothicus</part></link><space/>turned north to deal with the Alemanni, who were swarming over all Italy north of the<space/><link><target>Po River</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>After efforts to secure a peaceful withdrawal failed, Claudius forced the Alemanni to battle at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Lake Benacus</target></link><space/>in November. The Alemanni were routed, forced back into Germany, and did not threaten Roman territory for many years afterwards.</paragraph><paragraph>Their most famous battle against Rome took place in<space/><link><target>Argentoratum</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Strasbourg</target></link>), in 357, where they were defeated by<space/><link><target>Julian the Apostate</target><part>Julian</part></link>, later Emperor of Rome, and their king<space/><link><target>Chnodomarius</target></link><space/>was taken prisoner to Rome.</paragraph><paragraph>On January 2, 366, the Alemanni yet again crossed the frozen<space/><link><target>Rhine</target></link><space/>in large numbers, to invade the Gallic provinces, this time being defeated by Valentinian (see<space/><link><target>Battle of Solicinium</target></link>). In the great mixed invasion of 406, the Alemanni appear to have crossed the<space/><link><target>Rhine</target><part>Rhine river</part></link><space/>a final time, conquering and then settling what is today<space/><link><target>Alsace</target></link><space/>and a large part of the<space/><link><target>Swiss Plateau</target></link>. The crossing is described in<space/><link><target>Wallace Breem</target></link>'s historical novel &quot;Eagle in the Snow.&quot;<space/><link><target>Fredegar</target></link>'s Chronicle gives the account. At<space/><italics>Alba Augusta</italics><space/>(<link><target>Alba-la-Romaine</target></link>) the devastation was so complete, that the Christian bishop retired to<space/><link><target>Viviers, Ardche</target><part>Viviers</part></link>, but in Gregory's account at Mende in<space/><link><target>Lozre</target></link>, also deep in the heart of Gaul, bishop Privatus was forced to sacrifice to idols in the very cave where he was later venerated<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template>. It is thought<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template><space/>this detail may be a generic literary ploy to epitomize the horrors of barbarian violence.</paragraph><heading level='4'>List of battles between Romans and Alemanni</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>259,<space/><link><target>Battle of Mediolanum</target></link><link><target>Emperor Gallienus</target></link><space/>defeats the Alemanni to rescue Rome</listitem><listitem>268,<space/><link><target>Battle of Lake Benacus</target></link>Romans under Emperor<space/><link><target>Claudius II</target></link><space/>defeat the Alemanni.</listitem><listitem>271<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Battle of Placentia (271)</target><part>Battle of Placentia</part></link>Emperor<space/><link><target>Aurelian</target></link><space/>is defeated by the Alemanni forces invading Italy</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Fano</target></link>Aurelian defeats the Alemanni, who begin to retreat from Italy</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Pavia (271)</target><part>Battle of Pavia</part></link>Aurelian destroys the retreating Alemanni army.</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>298<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Battle of Lingones</target></link><link><target>Caesar (title)</target><part>Caesar</part></link><space/><link><target>Constantius Chlorus</target></link><space/>defeats the Alemanni</listitem><listitem><link><target>Battle of Vindonissa</target></link>Constantius again defeats the Alemanni</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>356,<space/><link><target>Battle of Reims (356)</target><part>Battle of Reims</part></link><link><target>Caesar (title)</target><part>Caesar</part></link><space/><link><target>Julian the Apostate</target><part>Julian</part></link><space/>is defeated by the Alemanni</listitem><listitem>357,<space/><link><target>Battle of Strasbourg</target></link>Julian expels the Alemanni from the<space/><link><target>Rhineland</target></link></listitem><listitem>367,<space/><link><target>Battle of Solicinium</target></link>Romans under Emperor<space/><link><target>Valentinian I</target></link><space/>defeat yet another Alemanni incursion.</listitem><listitem>378,<space/><link><target>Battle of Argentovaria</target></link>Western Emperor<space/><link><target>Gratianus</target></link><space/>is victorious over the Alemanni, yet again.</listitem><listitem>451,<space/><link><target>Battle of the Catalaunian Fields</target></link>-Roman General<space/><link><target>Flavius Aetius</target><part>Aetius</part></link><space/>and his army of Romans and barbarian allies defeat Attila's army of<space/><link><target>Huns</target></link><space/>and other Germanic allies, including the Alemanni.</listitem><listitem>554,<space/><link><target>Battle of the Volturnus (554)</target><part>Battle of the Volturnus</part></link>-Armenian-Roman General<space/><link><target>Narses</target></link><space/>defeats a combined force of<space/><link><target>Franks</target></link><space/>and Alemanni in northern<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Subjugation by the Franks</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Alamannia</arg></template><link><target>Image:Alamannien Hochburgund ca 1000.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>Alemannia (yellow) and Upper Burgundy (green) around 1000.</part></link>The kingdom of Alamannia between Strasbourg and Augsburg lasted until 496, when the Alemanni were conquered by<space/><link><target>Clovis I</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Tolbiac</target></link>. The war of Clovis with the Alemanni forms the setting for the conversion of Clovis, briefly treated by<space/><link><target>Gregory of Tours</target></link>. (<link type='external' href='http://www.fordham.edu/halsall/source/gregory-clovisconv.html#n30'>Book II.31</link>) Subsequently the Alemanni formed part of the<space/><link><target>Franks</target><part>Frankish</part></link><space/>dominions and were governed by a Frankish duke.</paragraph><paragraph>In 746,<space/><link><target>Carloman, son of Charles Martel</target><part>Carloman</part></link><space/>ended an uprising by summarily executing all Alemannic nobility at the<space/><link><target>blood court at Cannstatt</target></link>, and for the following century, Alemannia was ruled by Frankish dukes. Following the<space/><link><target>treaty of Verdun</target></link><space/>of 843, Alemannia became a province of the eastern kingdom of<space/><link><target>Louis the German</target></link>, the precursor of the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Empire</target></link>. The duchy persisted until 1268.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Culture</heading><heading level='3'>Language</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Alemannic-Dialects-Map-English.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>The traditional distribution area of Western Upper German (Alemannic) dialect features in the 19th and 20th centuries</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The German spoken today over the range of the former Alemanni is termed<space/><link><target>Alemannic German</target></link>, and is recognised among the subgroups of the<space/><link><target>High German languages</target></link>. Alemannic runic inscriptions such as those on the<space/><link><target>Pforzen buckle</target></link><space/>are among the earliest testimonies of<space/><link><target>Old High German</target></link>.The<space/><link><target>High German consonant shift</target></link><space/>is thought to have originated around the 5th century either in Alemannia or among the<space/><link><target>Lombards</target></link>; before that the dialect spoken by Alemannic tribes was little different from that of other West Germanic peoples.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><italics>Alemannia</italics><space/>lost its distinct jurisdictional identity when<space/><link><target>Charles Martel</target></link><space/>absorbed it into the Frankish empire, early in the 8th century. Today,<space/><italics>Alemannic</italics><space/>is a linguistic term, referring to<space/><link><target>Alemannic German</target></link>, encompassing the dialects of the southern two thirds of<space/><link><target>Baden-Wrttemberg</target></link><space/>(German State), in western<space/><link><target>Bavaria</target></link><space/>(German State), in<space/><link><target>Vorarlberg</target></link><space/>(Austrian State),<space/><link><target>Swiss German</target></link><space/>in Switzerland and the<space/><link><target>Alsatian language</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Alsace</target></link><space/>(France).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Political organization</heading><paragraph>The Alemanni established a series of territorially defined<space/><italics>pagi</italics><space/>(cantons) on the east bank of the Rhine. The exact number and extent of these<space/><italics>pagi</italics><space/>is unclear and probably changed over time.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Pagi</italics>, usually pairs of<space/><italics>pagi</italics><space/>combined, formed kingdoms (<italics>regna</italics>) which, it is generally believed, were permanent and hereditary. Ammianus describes Alemanni rulers with various terms:<space/><italics>reges excelsiores ante alios</italics><space/>(&quot;paramount kings&quot;),<space/><italics>reges proximi</italics><space/>(&quot;neighbouring kings&quot;),<space/><italics>reguli</italics><space/>(&quot;petty kings&quot;) and<space/><italics>regales</italics><space/>(&quot;princes&quot;). This may be a formal hierarchy, or they may be vague, overlapping terms, or a combination of both.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinkwater (2007) 118, 120</extension><space/>In 357, there appear to have been two paramount kings (Chnodomar and Westralp) who probably acted as presidents of the confederation and seven other kings (<italics>reges</italics>). Their territories were small and mostly strung along the Rhine (although a few were in the hinterland).<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinkwater (2007) 223 (map)</extension><space/>It is possible that the<space/><italics>reguli</italics><space/>were the rulers of the two<space/><italics>pagi</italics><space/>in each kingdom. Underneath the royal class were the nobles (called<space/><italics>optimates</italics><space/>by the Romans) and warriors (called<space/><italics>armati</italics><space/>by the Romans). The warriors consisted of professional warbands and levies of free men.<extension extension_name='ref'>Speidel (2004)</extension><space/>Each nobleman could raise an average of c. 50 warriors.<extension extension_name='ref'>Drinkwater (2007) 120</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Religion</heading><paragraph><template><target>further</target><arg>Germanic Christianity</arg><arg>Religion in Switzerland#History</arg><arg>Pre-Christian Alpine traditions</arg><arg>Continental Germanic mythology</arg></template><link><target>File:Reiterscheibe von Pliezhausen v2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The gold bracteate of<space/><link><target>Pliezhausen</target></link><space/>(6th or 7th century) shows typical iconography of the pagan period. The bracteate depicts the &quot;horse-stabber underhoof&quot; scene, a supine warrior stabbing a horse while it runs over him. The scene is adapted from<space/><link><target>Germania Superior</target><part>Roman era</part></link><space/>gravestones of the region.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Speidel,<space/><italics>Ancient Germanic warriors: warrior styles from Trajan's column to Icelandic sagas</italics>, Routledge, 2004, ISBN 978-0415311991, p. 162.Harald Kleinschmidt,<space/><italics>People on the move: attitudes toward and perceptions of migration in medieval and modern Europe</italics>, Greenwood Publishing Group, 2003,ISBN, 9780275974176,<space/><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=yOuIvdMqzzAC&amp;amp;pg=PA66&amp;amp;lpg=PA66&amp;amp;dq=Pliezhausen+bracteate&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=uj4u0BHepO&amp;amp;sig=jixswrN0rxGLOTfTZKPcb7wlV6I&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=6aVRTNGtH8vuOfSj5NUE&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=3&amp;amp;ved=0CBwQ6AEwAg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Pliezhausen%20bracteate&amp;amp;f=false'>p. 66.</link></extension></part></link><link><target>File:Gutenstein warrior.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The 7th-century<space/><link><target>:de:Schwertscheide von Gutenstein</target><part>Gutenstein scabbard</part></link>, found near<space/><link><target>Sigmaringen</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Baden-Wrttemberg</target></link>, is a late testimony of pagan ritual in Alemannia, showing a warrior in ritual wolf costume, holding a<space/><link><target>ring-spatha</target></link>.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>Christianization</target></link><space/>of the Alemanni took place during<space/><link><target>Merovingian</target></link><space/>times (6th to 8th centuries). We know that in the 6th century, the Alemanni were predominantly pagan, and in the 8th century, they were predominantly Christian. The intervening 7th century was a period of genuine<space/><link><target>syncretism</target></link><space/>during which Christian symbolism and doctrine gradually grew in influence.</paragraph><paragraph>Some scholars have speculated that members of the Alemannic elite such as king<space/><link><target>Gibuld</target></link><space/>due to<space/><link><target>Visigothic Kingdom</target><part>Visigothic</part></link><space/>influence may have been converted to<space/><link><target>Arianism</target></link><space/>even in the later 5th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Schubert, Hans (1909).<space/><italics>Das lteste germanische Christentum oder der Sogenannte &quot;Arianismus&quot; der Germanen</italics>. Tbingen: J.C.B. Mohr. pg.32. Cf. also Bossert, G. &quot;Alemanni&quot; in: Jackson, S.M. (Ed.).<space/><italics>New Schaff-Herzog Encyclopedia of Religious Knowledge</italics>, Vol. 1, pg. 114: &quot;[the Alamannic] prince, Gibuld, was an Arian, probably converted by Goths&quot;.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the mid-6th century, the Byzantine historian<space/><link><target>Agathias of Myrina</target></link><space/>records, in the context of the wars of the Goths and Franks against Byzantium, that the Alemanni fighting among the troops of Frankish king<space/><link><target>Theudebald</target></link><space/>were like the Franks in all respects except religion, since<template><target>quote</target><arg name="text">they worship certain trees, the waters of rivers, hills and mountain valleys, in whose honour they sacrifice horses, cattle and countless other animals by beheading them, and imagine that they are performing an act of piety thereby.<ref>{{cite book|url</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He also spoke of the particular ruthlessness of the Alemanni in destroying Christian sanctuaries and plundering churches while the genuine Franks were respectful towards those sanctuaries. Agathias expresses his hope that the Alemanni would assume better manners through prolonged contact with the Franks, which is by all appearances, in a manner of speaking, what eventually happened.<extension extension_name='ref'>R. Keydell,<space/><italics>Agathiae Myrinaei historiarum libri quinque</italics><space/>Corpus Fontium Historiae Byzantinae. Series Berolinensis 2. Berlin: De Gruyter, 1967, p. 18f.<template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>7. Νόμιμα δὲ αὐτοῖς [τῶν Ἀλαμανῶν ἔθνος] εἰσι μέν που καὶ πάτρια, τὸ δέ γε ἐν κοινῷ ἐπικρατοῦν τε καὶ ἄρχον τῇ Φραγγικῇ ἕπονται πολιτείᾳ, μόνα δέ γε τὰ ἐς (5) θεὸν αὐτοῖς οὐ ταὐτὰ ξυνδοκεῖ. δένδρα τε γάρ τινα ἱλάσκονται καὶ ῥεῖθρα ποταμῶν καὶ λόφους καὶ φάραγγας, καὶ τούτοις, ὥσπερ ὅσια δρῶντες, ἵππους τε καὶ βόας καὶ ἄλλα ἄττα μυρία καρατομοῦντες ἐπιθειάζουσιν. 2 ἀλλὰ γὰρ ἡ τῶν Φράγγων αὐτοὺς ἐπιμιξία, εnὖ ποιοῦσα, καὶ ἐς τόδε μετακοσμεῖ καὶ ἤδη ἐφέλκεται τοὺς εὐφρονεστέρους, οὐ πολλοῦ δὲ οἶμαι (10) χρόνου καὶ ἅπασιν ἐκνικήσει. 3 τὸ γὰρ τῆς δόξης παράλογόν τε καὶ ἔμπληκτον καὶ αὐτοῖς οἶμαι τοῖς χρωμένοις, εἰ μὴ πάμπαν εἶεν ἠλίθιοι, γνώριμόν τέ ἐστι καὶ εὐφώρατον καὶ οἶον ἀποσβῆναι ῥᾳδίως. ἐλεεῖσθαι μὲν οὖν μᾶλλον ἢ χαλεπαίνεσθαι δίκαιοι ἂν εἶεν καὶ πλείστης μεταλαγχάνειν συγγνώμης ἅπαντες, ὅσοι δὴ τοῦ ἀληθοῦς ἁμαρτάνουσιν. οὐ γὰρ (15) δήπου ἑκόντες εἶναι ἀλῶνται καὶ ὀλισθαίνουσιν, ἀλλὰ τοῦ ἀγαθοῦ ἐφιέμενοι, ἔπειτα σφαλέντες τῇ κρίσει τὸ λοιπὸν ἔχονται τῶν δοκηθέντων ἀπρίξ, ὁποῖα ἄττα καὶ τύχοιεν ὄντα. 4 τήν γε μὴν τῶν θυσιῶν ὠμότητα καὶ κακοδαιμονίαν οὐκ οἶδα εἰ οἷόν τε λόγῳ ἀκέσασθαι, εἴτε ἄλσεσιν ἐπιτελοῖντο ὥσπερ ἀμέλει παρὰ βαρβάροις, εἴτε τοῖς πάλαι νενομισμέ-(20)νοις θεοῖς, ὁποῖα αἱ τῶν Ἑλλήνων ἐθέλουσιν ἁγιστεῖαι.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Apostles of the Alemanni were<space/><link><target>Saint Columbanus</target></link><space/>and his disciple<space/><link><target>Saint Gall</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Jonas of Bobbio</target></link><space/>records that Columbanus was active in<space/><link><target>Bregenz</target></link>, where he disrupted a beer sacrifice to<space/><link><target>Wodan</target></link>. Despite these activities, for some time, the Alemanni seem to have continued their pagan cult activities, with only superficial or<space/><link><target>Syncretism</target><part>syncretistic</part></link><space/>Christian elements. In particular, there is no change in burial practice, and tumulus warrior graves continued to be erected throughout Merovingian times. Syncretism of traditional Germanic animal-style with Christian symbolism is also present in artwork, but Christian symbolism becomes more and more prevalent during the 7th century. Unlike the later Christianization of the Saxons and of the Slavs, the Alemanni seem to have adopted Christianity gradually, and voluntarily, spread in emulation of the Merovingian elite.</paragraph><paragraph>From c. the 520s to the 620s, there was a surge of<space/><link><target>Alemannic Elder Futhark inscriptions</target></link>. About 70 specimens have survived, roughly half of them on<space/><link><target>fibula (brooch)</target><part>fibulae</part></link>, others on belt buckles (see<space/><link><target>Pforzen buckle</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Blach fibula</target></link>) and other jewelry and weapon parts. Use of runes subsides with the advance of Christianity.The<space/><link><target>Nordendorf fibula</target></link><space/>(early 7th century) clearly records pagan theonyms,<space/><italics>logaorewodanwigionar<space/></italics><space/>read as &quot;Wodan and Donar are magicians/sorcerers&quot;, but this may be interpreted as either a pagan invocation of the powers of these deities, or a Christian protective charm against them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dwel"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Düwel<space/></arg><arg name="first">Klaus<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="editor-last">Kamp<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first">Norbert<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last">Wollasch<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first">Joachim<space/></arg><arg name="contribution">Runen und Interpretatio Christiana: Zur Religioneschichtlichen Stellung der Bügelfidel von Nordendorf I<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tradition als Historische Kraft<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Walter de Gruyter<space/></arg><arg name="year">1982<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/></arg><arg name="pages">78–86<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="isbn">311-008237-3</arg></template></extension>A runic inscription on a fibula found at<space/><link><target>Bad Ems</target></link><space/>reflects Christian pious sentiment (and is also explicitly marked with a Christian cross), reading<space/><italics>god fura dih deofile<space/></italics><space/>(&quot;God for/before you, Theophilus!&quot;, or alternatively &quot;God before you, Devil!&quot;). Dated to between AD 660 and 690, it marks the end of the native Alemannic tradition of runic literacy. Bad Ems is in<space/><link><target>Rhineland-Palatinate</target></link>, on the northwestern boundary of Alemannic settlement, where Frankish influence would have been strongest.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wolfgang Jungandreas, 'God fura dih, deofile ' in: Zeitschrift fr deutsches Altertum und deutsche Literatur, 101, 1972, pp. 8485.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The establishment of the bishopric of<space/><link><target>Konstanz</target></link><space/>cannot be dated exactly and was possibly undertaken by Columbanus himself (before 612). In any case, it existed by 635, when<space/><link><target>Gunzo</target></link><space/>appointed<space/><link><target>John of Grab</target></link><space/>bishop. Constance was a missionary bishopric in newly converted lands, and did not look back on late Roman church history (unlike the Raetian bishopric of<space/><link><target>Chur</target></link>, established 451) and<space/><link><target>Basel</target></link>, which was an episcopal seat from 740, and which continued the line of Bishops of<space/><link><target>Augusta Raurica</target></link><space/>(see<space/><link><target>Bishop of Basel</target></link>). The establishment of the church as an institution recognized by worldly rulers is also visible in legal history. In the early 7th century<space/><italics><link><target>Pactus Alamannorum</target></link></italics><space/>hardly ever mentions the special privileges of the church, while<space/><link><target>Lantfrid</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Lex Alamannorum</target></link></italics><space/>of 720 has an entire chapter reserved for ecclesial matters alone.</paragraph><heading level='2'>List of Alemannic rulers</heading><heading level='3'>Independent kings</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Chrocus</target></link><space/>306</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mederich</target></link><space/>(father of Agenarich, brother to Chnodomar)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chnodomar</target></link><space/>350, 357</listitem><listitem>Vestralp 357, 359</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ur (Alamannic ruler)</target><part>Ur</part></link><space/>357, 359</listitem><listitem><link><target>Agenarich</target></link><space/>(Serapio) 357</listitem><listitem><link><target>Suomar</target></link><space/>357, 358</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hortar</target></link><space/>357, 359</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gundomad</target></link><space/>354 (co-regent of Vadomar)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ursicin</target></link><space/>357, 359</listitem><listitem><link><target>Makrian</target></link><space/>368371</listitem><listitem>Rando 368</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hariobaud</target></link><space/>4th century</listitem><listitem><link><target>Vadomar</target></link><space/>vor 354360</listitem><listitem><link><target>Vithicab</target></link><space/>360368</listitem><listitem><link><target>Priarius</target></link><space/>?378</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gibuld</target></link><space/>(Gebavult) c. 470</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Dukes under Frankish suzerainty</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Butilin</target></link><space/>539554</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leuthari I</target></link><space/>before 552554</listitem><listitem><link><target>Haming</target></link><space/>539554</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lantachar</target></link><space/>until 548 (Avenches diocese)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Magnachar</target></link><space/>565 (Avenches diocese)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Vaefar</target></link><space/>573 (Avenches diocese)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Theodefrid</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Leutfred</target></link><space/>570587</listitem><listitem><link><target>Uncilin</target></link><space/>587607</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gunzo</target></link><space/>613</listitem><listitem><link><target>Chrodobert</target></link><space/>630</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leuthari II</target></link><space/>642</listitem><listitem><link><target>Gotfrid</target></link><space/>until 709</listitem><listitem><link><target>Willehari</target></link><space/>709712 (in<space/><link><target>Ortenau</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lantfrid</target></link><space/>709730</listitem><listitem><link><target>Theudebald, Duke of Alamannia</target><part>Theudebald</part></link><space/>709744</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Carolinger ruler</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Carloman (mayor of the palace)</target><part>Carloman</part></link><space/>744747</listitem><listitem><link><target>Drogo (mayor of the palace)</target><part>Drogo</part></link><space/>747748</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pepin the Short</target></link><space/>748768</listitem><listitem><link><target>Carloman I</target></link><space/>768771</listitem><listitem><link><target>Charles the Bald</target></link><space/>829840</listitem><listitem><link><target>Louis the German</target></link><space/>843864</listitem><listitem><link><target>Charles the Fat</target></link><space/>864880</listitem><listitem><link><target>Louis the Younger</target></link><space/>880882</listitem><listitem><link><target>Charles the Fat</target></link><space/>882888</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bernard (son of Charles the Fat)</target><part>Bernard</part></link><space/>888892</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Ancient Germanic culture</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Annales Alamannici</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of confederations of Germanic tribes</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Literature</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Drinkwater, J. F. (2007)<space/><italics>The Alamanni and Rome (213496)</italics></listitem><listitem>Ian Wood (ed.),<space/><italics>Franks and Alamanni in the Merovingian Period: An Ethnographic Perspective (Studies in Historical Archaeoethnology)</italics>, Boydell &amp; Brewer Ltd, 2003, ISBN 1-84383-035-3.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Melchior Goldast</target></link>,<space/><italics>Rerum Alamannicarum scriptores</italics><space/>(1606, 2nd ed. Senckenburg 1730)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Archaeology of Alemannia</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://members.tripod.com/~Linus_Gemvik/decumates.html'>The Agri Decumates</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.hp.uab.edu/image_archive/ujg/ujgd.html'>The Alemanni</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.anistor.co.hol.gr/english/enback/e022.htm'>The Military Orientation of the Roman Emperors Septimius Severus to Gallienus (146268 C.E.)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.badische-seiten.de/bilder/schwaebisch-alemannische-fasnet/'>Brauchtum und Masken Alemannic Fastnacht</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Germanic peoples</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Alamanni</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Ancient Germanic peoples</target></link><link><target>Category:Historical ethnic groups of Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Iron Age Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Early Middle Ages</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Swabia</target></link></paragraph></article>