<article title='Charles_Williams_%28British_writer%29'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the British writer born in 1886</arg><arg>other people called Charles or Charlie Williams</arg><arg>Charles Williams (disambiguation)</arg><arg>the British writer born in 1971</arg><arg>Charlie Williams (British writer)</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">August 2014</arg></template><template><target>More footnotes</target><arg name="date">March 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox writer</target><arg name="name"><space/>Charles Williams 
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Charles Walter Stansby Williams 
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Charles Williams.jpg
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>200px
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>London, England
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="occupation"><space/>Novelist
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>Florence Conway
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>English
</arg><arg name="citizenship"><space/>
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[Fantasy literature|Fantasy]]
</arg><arg name="movement">
</arg><arg name="notableworks"><space/>''[[War in Heaven (novel)|War in Heaven]]''<space/><br /><space/>''[[The Place of the Lion]]''<space/><br /><space/>''[[The Greater Trumps]]''<br /><space/>''[[Descent into Hell (novel)|Descent into Hell]]''
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>
</arg></template><bold>Charles Walter Stansby Williams</bold><space/>(20 September 1886 15 May 1945) was a British poet, novelist, playwright, theologian, literary critic, and member of the<space/><link><target>Inklings</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><paragraph>Williams was born in London in 1886, the only son of Richard and Mary Williams of Islington. He had one sister, Edith, born in 1889. Educated at<space/><link><target>St Albans School (Hertfordshire)</target><part>St Albans School</part></link>, Hertfordshire, Williams was awarded a scholarship to<space/><link><target>University College London</target></link>, but was forced to leave in 1904 without taking a degree because his family lacked the financial resources to support him. In the same year he began work in a<space/><link><target>Methodist</target></link><space/><link><target>bookroom</target></link>. Williams was hired by the<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link><space/>(OUP) as a proofreading assistant in 1908 and quickly climbed to the position of editor. He continued to work at the OUP in various positions of increasing responsibility until his death in 1945. One of his greatest editorial achievements was the publication of the first major English-language edition of the works of<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://dspace.lasrworks.org/bitstream/handle/10349/770/From%20a%20Publisher%27s%20Point%20of%20View.pdf?sequence</arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>From a Publisher's Point of View: Charles Williams’s Role in Publishing Kierkegaard in English<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Michael J<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Paulus, Jr<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Suzanne<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Bray<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Richard<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Sturch<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams and His Contemporaries<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Newcastle, UK<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Cambridge Scholars Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-1-4438-0565-0<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>[[PDF]]</arg></template>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although chiefly remembered as a novelist, Williams also published poetry, works of literary criticism, theology, drama, history, biography, and a voluminous number of book reviews. Some of his best known novels are<space/><italics>War in Heaven</italics><space/>(1930),<space/><italics><link><target>Descent into Hell (novel)</target><part>Descent into Hell</part></link></italics><space/>(1937), and<space/><italics>All Hallows' Eve</italics><space/>(1945).<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>David N. Samuelson, &quot;Charles Williams&quot; in<space/><link><target>E. F. Bleiler</target></link>,<space/><italics>Supernatural Fiction Writers : Fantasy and Horror</italics>.New York : Scribner's, 1985, ISBN 0684178087, (pp. 631638 ).</extension><space/><link><target>T. S. Eliot</target></link>, who wrote an introduction for the last of these, described Williams's novels as &quot;supernatural thrillers&quot; because they explore the sacramental intersection of the physical with the spiritual while also examining the ways in which power, even spiritual power, can corrupt as well as sanctify. All of Williams's fantasies, unlike those of<space/><link><target>J. R. R. Tolkien</target></link><space/>and most of those of<space/><link><target>C. S. Lewis</target></link>, are set in the contemporary world. Williamshas been described by<space/><link><target>Colin Manlove</target></link><space/>as one of the three main writers of &quot;Christianfantasy&quot; in the twentieth century (the other two being C. S. Lewis and<space/><link><target>T. F. Powys</target></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Margarita Carretero Gonzlez, Encarnacin Hidalgo Tenorio,<space/><italics>Behind the Veil of Familiarity: C.S. Lewis (18981998)</italics>. Peter Lang, 2001ISBN 0820450995 (p. 305).</extension><space/>More recent writers of fantasy novels with contemporary settings, notably<space/><link><target>Tim Powers</target></link>, cite Williams as a model and inspiration.<space/><link><target>W. H. Auden</target></link>, one of Williams's greatest admirers, reportedly re-read Williams's extraordinary and highly unconventional history of the church,<space/><italics>The Descent of the Dove</italics><space/>(1939), every year. Williams's study of Dante entitled<space/><italics>The Figure of Beatrice</italics><space/>(1944) was very highly regarded at its time of publication and continues to be consulted by<space/><link><target>Dante</target></link><space/>scholars today. His work inspired<space/><link><target>Dorothy L. Sayers</target></link><space/>to undertake her translation of<space/><italics>The Divine Comedy</italics>. Williams, however, regarded his most important work to be his extremely dense and complex<space/><link><target>King Arthur</target><part>Arthurian</part></link><space/>poetry, of which two books were published,<space/><italics>Taliessin through Logres</italics><space/>(1938) and<space/><italics>The Region of the Summer Stars</italics><space/>(1944), and more remained unfinished at his death. Some of Williams' best essays were collected and published in<space/><link><target>Anne Ridler</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Image of the City and Other Essays</italics><space/>(1958)<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template>.</paragraph><paragraph>Williams gathered many followers and disciples during his lifetime. He was, for a period, a member of the Salvator Mundi Temple of the<space/><link><target>Fellowship of the Rosy Cross</target></link>. He met fellow Anglican<space/><link><target>Evelyn Underhill</target></link><space/>(who was affiliated with a similar group, the<space/><link><target>Order of the Golden Dawn</target></link>) in 1937 and was later to write the introduction to her published<space/><italics>Letters</italics><space/>in 1943.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url">http://homepages.ihug.co.nz/~dcandmkw/spirit/eucw%20-%20int.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">IHUG<space/></arg><arg name="place">NZ<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20060421221635/http://homepages.ihug.co.nz:80/~dcandmkw/spirit/eucw%20-%20int.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">21 April 2006<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In 1917 Williams married his first sweetheart, Florence Conway, following a long courtship during which he presented her with a sonnet sequence that would later become his first published book of poetry.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Silver Stair</italics>. London: Herbert &amp; Daniel, 1912.</extension><space/>Their son Michael was born in 1924. Later, he would struggle to reconcile a long-lasting (but probably unconsummated: indeed only vaguely, at most, reciprocated) love affair with Phyllis Jones (who joined the<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link><space/>in 1924 as librarian) with his Christian faith (he was an unswerving and devoted member of the<space/><link><target>Church of England</target></link>, reputedly with a tolerance of the scepticism of others and a firm belief in the necessity of a &quot;<link><target>doubting Thomas</target></link>&quot; in any apostolic body).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.charleswilliamssociety.org.uk/<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Charles Williams Society<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>UK</arg></template></extension><space/>Williams also formed master-disciple relationships with young woman admirers. The best known (though probably not the most significant) of these occurred in the early 1940s with Lois Lang-Sims. Lang-Sims, whom Williams referred to as Lalage, published a series of letters that Williams wrote to her during this period in a volume entitled<space/><italics>Letters to Lalage</italics><space/>(1989).</paragraph><paragraph>Although Williams attracted the attention and admiration of some of the most notable writers of his day, including<space/><link><target>T. S. Eliot</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>W. H. Auden</target></link>, his greatest admirer was probably<space/><link><target>C. S. Lewis</target></link>, whose novel<space/><italics><link><target>That Hideous Strength</target></link></italics><space/>(1945) has been regarded as partially inspired by his acquaintance with both the man and his novels and poems. Williams came to know Lewis after reading Lewis's then-recently published study<space/><italics><link><target>The Allegory of Love</target></link></italics>; he was so impressed he jotted down a letter of congratulation and dropped it in the mail. Coincidentally, Lewis had just finished reading Williams's novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Place of the Lion</target></link></italics><space/>and had written a similar note of congratulation. The letters crossed in the mail and led to an enduring and fruitful friendship. When<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>broke out in 1939,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link><space/>moved its offices from London to<space/><link><target>Oxford</target></link>. Williams was reluctant to leave his beloved city, and Florence refused to go. From the nearly 700 letters he wrote his wife during the war years a generous selection has been published; &quot;primarily . . . love letters,&quot; the editor calls them.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roma A. King, Jr., ed.,<space/><italics>To Michal from Serge: Letters from Charles Williams to his wife, Florence, 19391945</italics>. Kent, O., and London: Kent State University Press, 2002. (p. 4)</extension><space/>But the move to Oxford did allow him to participate regularly in Lewiss literary society known as the<space/><link><target>Inklings</target></link>. In this setting Williams was able to read (and improve) his final published novel,<space/><italics>All Hallows' Eve</italics>, as well as to hear<space/><link><target>J. R. R. Tolkien</target></link><space/>read aloud to the group some of his early drafts of<space/><italics><link><target>The Lord of the Rings</target></link></italics>. In addition to meeting in Lewis's rooms at Oxford, they also regularly met at<space/><link><target>The Eagle and Child</target></link><space/>pub in Oxford (better known by its nickname &quot;The Bird and Baby&quot;). During this time Williams also gave lectures at Oxford on<space/><link><target>John Milton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Wordsworth</target></link>, and other authors, and received an honorary M.A. degree. Williams is buried in<space/><link><target>St Cross Churchyard</target></link><space/>Oxford: his headstone bears the word &quot;poet&quot;, followed by the words &quot;Under the Mercy&quot;, a blessing often used by Williams himself<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Williams's theology</heading><paragraph>Williams developed the concept of Co-inherence, described as a theology of romantic love. Co-inherence was a term used in Patristic theology to describe the relationship between the human and divine natures of Jesus Christ, and the relationship between the persons of the blessed Trinity. Williams extended the term to include the ideal relationship between the individual parts of God's creation, including human beings. It is our mutual indwelling: Christ in us and we in Christ, interdependent. It is also the web of interrelationships, social and economic and ecological, by which the social fabric and the natural world function. But especially for Williams, Co-inherence is a way of talking about the Body of Christ and the Communion of saints. For Williams, salvation was not a solitary affair. &quot;The thread of the love of God was strong enough to save you and all the others, but not strong enough to save you alone.&quot; He proposed an order, Companions of the Co-inherence, who would practice substitution and exchange, living in love-in-God, truly bearing one another's burdens, being willing to sacrifice and to forgive, living from and for one another in Christ.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Williams's fiction</heading><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>He is writing that sort of book in which we begin by saying, let us suppose that this everyday world were at some one point invaded by the marvelous.<space/></arg><arg name="C. S. Lewis on Charles Williams' novels<ref>{{Cite book | type"><space/>audio | first<space/></arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Shadows of Ecstasy<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1933</arg></template><space/>A humanistic adept has discovered that by focusing his energies inward he can extend his life almost indefinitely. He undertakes an experiment using African lore to die and resurrect his own body thereby assuring his immortality. His followers begin a revolutionary movement to supplant European civilisation.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>War in Heaven<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1930</arg></template><space/>The<space/><link><target>Holy Grail</target></link><space/>surfaces in an obscure country parish and becomes variously a sacramental object to protect or a vessel of power to exploit.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Many Dimensions<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1931</arg></template><space/>An evil antiquarian illegally purchases the fabled Stone of Suleiman (Williams uses this Muslim form rather than the more familiar<space/><link><target>King Solomon</target></link>) from its Islamic guardian in<space/><link><target>Baghdad</target></link><space/>and returns to England to discover not only that the Stone can multiply itself infinitely without diminishing the original, but that it also allows its possessor to transcend the barriers of space and time.</listitem><listitem>&quot;Et in Sempiternum Pereant,&quot; 1931? (first published in 1986) Lord Arglay (protagonist in<space/><italics>Many Dimensions</italics>) risks his life in a vain effort to rescue a ghost on the path to damnation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Glen Cavaliero, &quot;A Metaphysical Epiphany? Charles Williams and the Art of the Ghost Story,&quot; in<space/><italics>The Rhetoric of Vision</italics>, ed. Charles A. Huttar and Peter J. Schakel. Lewisburg: Bucknell UP, 1996 (pp. 9397).</extension></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[The Place of the Lion]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1931</arg></template><space/><link><target>Platonism</target><part>Platonic</part></link><space/><link><target>archetypes</target></link><space/>begin to appear around an English country town, wreaking havoc and drawing to the surface the spiritual strengths and flaws of individual characters.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Greater Trumps<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1932</arg></template><space/>The original<space/><link><target>Tarot</target></link><space/>deck is used to unlock enormous metaphysical powers by allowing the possessors to see across space and time, create matter, and raise powerful natural storms.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>[[Descent into Hell (novel)|Descent into Hell]]<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1937</arg></template><space/>Generally thought to be Williams's best novel,<space/><italics>Descent</italics><space/>deals with various forms of selfishness, and how the cycle of sin brings about the necessity for redemptive acts. In it, an academic becomes so far removed from the world that he fetishises a woman to the extent that his perversion takes the form of a<space/><link><target>succubus</target></link>. Other characters include a<space/><link><target>doppelgnger</target></link>, the ghost of a suicidal<space/><link><target>Victorian era</target><part>Victorian</part></link><space/>labourer, and a playwright modelled in some ways on the author. It is illustrative of Williams's belief in the replacement of sin and substitutional love.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>All Hallows' Eve<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1945</arg></template><space/>Opens with a discussion between the ghosts of two dead women wandering about London. Ultimately explores the meaning of human suffering and empathy by dissolving the barrier between the living and the dead through both black magic and divine love.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Works</heading><heading level='3'>Novels</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>War in Heaven</italics><space/>(London: Victor Gollancz)</listitem><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>Many Dimensions</italics><space/>(London: Victor Gollancz)</listitem><listitem>1931:<space/><italics>The Place of the Lion</italics><space/>(London: Mundanus)</listitem><listitem>1932:<space/><italics>The Greater Trumps</italics><space/>(London: Victor Gollancz)</listitem><listitem>1933:<space/><italics>Shadows of Ecstasy</italics><space/>(London: Victor Gollancz)</listitem><listitem>1937:<space/><italics><link><target>Descent into Hell (novel)</target><part>Descent into Hell</part></link></italics><space/>(London: Faber &amp; Faber)</listitem><listitem>1945:<space/><italics>All Hallows' Eve</italics><space/>(London: Faber &amp; Faber)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="date">1945</arg><arg name="author">Williams, Charles</arg><arg name="title">All Hallows' Eve</arg><arg name="publisher">Faber & Faber</arg><arg name="url">https://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/williams/charles/all-hallows-eve/</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>197072:<space/><italics>The Noises That Werent There</italics>. Unfinished. First three chapters published in<space/><italics>Mythlore</italics><space/>6 (Autumn 1970), 7 (Winter 1971) and 8 (Winter 1972).</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Plays</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>c. 1912:<space/><italics>The Chapel of the Thorn</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>David Llewellyn Dodds, &quot;<italics>The Chapel of the Thorn</italics>, an Unknown Dramatic Poem by C. Williams,&quot;<space/><italics>Inklings Jahrbuch</italics><space/>5 (1987): 134,</extension><space/>(edition by Srina Higgins in progress)<space/></listitem><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>A Myth of Shakespeare</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>A Myth of Francis Bacon</italics><space/>(Published in the Charles Williams Society Newsletter, 11, 12, and 14)</listitem><listitem>192931:<space/><italics>Three Plays</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)<list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Rite of the Passion</italics><space/>(1929)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Chaste Wanton</italics><space/>(1930)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Witch</italics><space/>(1931)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>1963:<space/><italics>Collected Plays by Charles Williams</italics><space/>(edited by John Heath-Stubbs; London: Oxford University Press)<list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Thomas Cranmer of Canterbury</italics><space/>(1936). Canterbury Festival play, following T. S. Eliot's<space/><italics>Murder in the Cathedral</italics><space/>in the preceding (inaugural) year.</listitem><listitem><italics>Seed of Adam</italics><space/>(1937)</listitem><listitem><italics>Judgement at Chelmsford</italics><space/>(1939)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Death of Good Fortune</italics><space/>(1939)</listitem><listitem><italics>The House by the Stable</italics><space/>(1939)</listitem><listitem><italics>Terror of Light</italics><space/>(1940)</listitem><listitem><italics>Grab and Grace</italics><space/>(1941)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Three Temptations</italics><space/>(1942)</listitem><listitem><italics>House of the Octopus</italics><space/>(1945)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>2000:<space/><italics>The Masques of Amen House</italics><space/>(edited by David Bratman. Mythopoeic Press).<space/><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Masque of the Manuscript</italics><space/>(1927)<space/></listitem><listitem><italics>The Masque of Perusal</italics><space/>(1929)</listitem><listitem><italics>The Masque of the Termination of Copyright</italics><space/>(1930)</listitem></list></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Poetry</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1912:<space/><italics>The Silver Stair</italics><space/>(London: Herbert and Daniel)</listitem><listitem>1917:<space/><italics>Poems of Conformity</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1920:<space/><italics>Divorce</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1924:<space/><italics>Windows of Night</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>Heroes and Kings</italics><space/>(London: Sylvan Press)</listitem><listitem>1954:<space/><italics>Taliessin through Logres</italics><space/>(1938) and<space/><italics>The Region of the Summer Stars</italics><space/>(1944) (London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1991:<space/><italics>Charles Williams</italics>, ed. David Llewellyn Dodds (Woodbridge and Cambridge, UK: Boydell &amp; Brewer: Arthurian Poets series). Part II, Uncollected and unpublished poems (pp.&amp;nbsp;149281).</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Theology</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1938:<space/><italics>He Came Down from Heaven</italics><space/>(London: Heinemann).</listitem><listitem>1939:<space/><italics>The Descent of the Dove: A Short History of the Holy Spirit in the Church</italics><space/>(London: Longmans, Green)</listitem><listitem>1941:<space/><italics>Witchcraft</italics><space/>(London: Faber &amp; Faber)</listitem><listitem>1942:<space/><italics>The Forgiveness of Sins</italics><space/>(London: G. Bles)</listitem><listitem>1958:<space/><italics>The Image of the City and Other Essays</italics><space/>(edited by Anne Ridler; London: Oxford University Press). Parts II through V</listitem><listitem>1990:<space/><italics>Outlines of Romantic Theology</italics><space/>(Grand Rapids, Mich.: Eerdmans)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Literary criticism</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1930:<space/><italics>Poetry at Present</italics><space/>(Oxford: Clarendon Press).</listitem><listitem>1932:<space/><italics>The English Poetic Mind</italics><space/>(Oxford: Clarendon Press).</listitem><listitem>1933:<space/><italics>Reason and Beauty in the Poetic Mind</italics><space/>(Oxford: Clarendon Press)</listitem><listitem>1943:<space/><italics>The Figure of Beatrice</italics><space/>(London: Faber &amp; Faber)</listitem><listitem>1948:<space/><italics>The Figure of Arthur</italics><space/>(unfinished), in<space/><italics>Arthurian Torso</italics>, ed. C. S. Lewis (London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>1958:<space/><italics>The Image of the City and Other Essays</italics><space/>(edited by Anne Ridler; London: Oxford University Press). Parts I and VI</listitem><listitem>1974:<space/><italics>Religion and Love in Dante: The Theology of Romantic Love</italics><space/>(Pennsylvania: Folcroft Library Editions).</listitem><listitem>2003:<space/><italics>The Detective Fiction Reviews of Charles Williams</italics><space/>(edited by Jared C. Lobdell; McFarland)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Biography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1933:<space/><italics>Bacon</italics><space/>(London: Arthur Barker)</listitem><listitem>1933:<space/><italics>A Short Life of Shakespeare</italics><space/>(Oxford: Clarendon Press). Abridgment of the 2-volume work by Sir Edmund Chambers</listitem><listitem>1934:<space/><italics>James I</italics><space/>(London: Arthur Barker)</listitem><listitem>1935:<space/><italics>Rochester</italics><space/>(London: Arthur Barker)</listitem><listitem>1936:<space/><italics>Queen Elizabeth</italics><space/>(London: Duckworth)</listitem><listitem>1937:<space/><italics>Henry VII</italics><space/>(London: Arthur Barker)</listitem><listitem>1937:<space/><italics>Stories of Great Names</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press). Alexander, Julius Caesar, Charlemagne, Joan of Arc, Shakespeare, Voltaire, John Wesley</listitem><listitem>1946:<space/><italics>Flecker of Dean Close</italics><space/>(London: Canterbury Press)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Other works</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>1989:<space/><italics>Letters to Lalage: The Letters of Charles Williams to Lois Lang-Sims</italics><space/>(Kent State University Press)</listitem><listitem>2002:<space/><italics>To Michal from Serge: Letters from Charles Williams to His Wife, Florence, 19391945</italics><space/>(edited by Roma King Jr.; Kent State University Press)</listitem><listitem>1986: &quot;Et in Sempiternum Pereant&quot; (a short story) in<space/><italics>The Oxford Book of English Ghost Stories</italics><space/>(London: Oxford University Press)</listitem><listitem>Introduction to Evelyn Underhills Letters</listitem><listitem>Introduction to the second edition of Gerard Manley Hopkins's Poems</listitem><listitem>Introduction to Kierkegaard's<space/><italics>The Present Age</italics><space/></listitem><listitem><italics>The Story of the Aeneid</italics><space/>as retold by Williams</listitem><listitem>selected daily readings in<space/><italics>A New Christian Year</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>The Passion of Christ</italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Secondary literature</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Ashenden<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Gavin<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: Alchemy and Integration<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Kent State University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Carpenter<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Humphrey<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Inklings<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Allen & Unwin<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1978</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Cavaliero<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Glen<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: Poet of Theology<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Grand Rapids<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Dunning<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Stephen M.<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Crisis and the Quest – A Kierkegaardian Reading of Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Paternoster Biblical and Theological Monographs<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Glyer<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Diana Pavlac<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Company They Keep: C. S. Lewis and J. R. R. Tolkien as Writers in Community<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Kent State University Press<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Kent, O.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2007<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>978-0-87338-890-0</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hadfield<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Alice Mary<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: An Exploration of His Life and Work<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Oxford<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford UP<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Heath-Stubbs<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>John<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="type"><space/>British council<space/></arg><arg name="format"><space/>pamphlets<space/></arg><arg name="series"><space/>Writers & their work<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Longmans<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1955</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Hefling<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Charles<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Charles Williams: Words, Images, and (the) Incarnation<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>David<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Hein<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Edward<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Henderson<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>C. S. Lewis and Friends: Faith and the Power of Imagination<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>73–90<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>SPCK<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2011</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Hillegas, Mark R., ed. (1969),<space/><italics>Shadows of Imagination: The Fantasies of C. S. Lewis, J. R. R. Tolkien, and Charles Williams</italics>, Carbondale and Edwardsville: Southern Illinois University Press.<space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Horne<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Brian<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: A Celebration<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Gracewing<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1995<space/></arg><arg name="ISBN"><space/>0-852-44331-5</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Howard<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Thomas<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Novels of Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>New York and London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1983</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="editor1-last"><space/>Huttar<space/></arg><arg name="editor1-first"><space/>Charles A<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-first"><space/>Peter J<space/></arg><arg name="editor2-last"><space/>Schakel<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Rhetoric of Vision: Essays on Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Lewisburg, London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Bucknell University Press, Associated University Presses<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="title"><space/>Thinking with the Inklings<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Karlson<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Henry<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>1-4505-4130-5</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>King, Roma A., Jr. (1990),<space/><italics>The Pattern in the Web: The Mythical Poetry of Charles Williams</italics>. Kent, O., and London: Kent State University Press.</listitem><listitem>Lewis, C. S. (1948), &quot;Williams and the Arthuriad,&quot; in<space/><italics>Arthurian Torso</italics>, ed. C. S. Lewis, London: Oxford University Press, pp.&amp;nbsp;93200.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Lindop<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Grevel<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: The Third Inkling<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Oxford University Press; announced for October 2015</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Moorman, Charles (1960),<space/><italics>Arthurian Triptych: Mythic Materials in Charles Williams, C. S. Lewis, and T. S. Eliot</italics>, Berkeley and Los Angeles: University of California Press.</listitem><listitem>Moorman, Charles (1966),<space/><italics>The Precincts of Felicity: The Augustinian City of the Oxford Christians</italics>. Gainesville: University of Florida Press.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Shideler<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Mary McDermott<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams: A Critical Essay<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Grand Rapids<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Eerdmans<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1966</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="author-link"><space/>James A. Owen</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Owen<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>James A<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[The Chronicles of the Imaginarium Geographica]]<space/></arg><arg name="type"><space/>series</arg></template><space/>features Charles Williams, C.S. Lewis, and J.R.R. Tolkien as the main characters.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sibley<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Agnes<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Boston<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Twayne<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1982</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="last"><space/>Walsh<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Chad<space/></arg><arg name="contribution"><space/>Charles Williams' Novels and the Contemporary Mutation of Consciousness<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Myth, Allegory and Gospel: An Interpretation of J.R.R. Tolkien, C.S. Lewis, G.K. Chesterton, Charles Williams<space/></arg><arg name="editor-first"><space/>John Warwick<space/></arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>Montgomery<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Minneapolis<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Bethany Fellowship<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1974<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>53–77</arg></template>.</listitem><listitem>Wendling, Susan (2006), &quot;Charles Williams: Priest of the Co-inherence&quot;, in<space/><italics>INKLINGS Forever</italics>, Vol. V, a collection of essays presented at the Fifth Frances White Ewbank Colloquium on C.S. Lewis and Friends, presented at Taylor University.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikisource</target><arg>Author:Charles Williams</arg><arg>Charles Williams</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>url</target><arg>charleswilliamssociety.org.uk/<space/></arg><arg>The Charles Williams Society</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>isfdb name</target><arg name="id">255</arg><arg name="name">Charles Williams</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>url</target><arg>www.wheaton.edu/wadecenter/<space/></arg><arg>The Marion E. Wade Center</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Charles Walter Stansby Williams<space/></arg><arg name="birth">1886<space/></arg><arg name="death">1945</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Librivox author</target><arg name="id">3169</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Williams, Charles
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>British writer
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>20 September 1886
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>London, England
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>15 May 1945
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH">
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Williams, Charles</target></template><link><target>Category:1886 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1945 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Alumni of University College London</target></link><link><target>Category:Writers of modern Arthurian fiction</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian mystics</target></link><link><target>Category:Christian writers</target></link><link><target>Category:English fantasy writers</target></link><link><target>Category:English theologians</target></link><link><target>Category:Inklings</target></link><link><target>Category:Mythopoeic writers</target></link><link><target>Category:Oxford University Press</target></link><link><target>Category:People from St Albans</target></link><link><target>Category:People educated at St Albans School, Hertfordshire</target></link><link><target>Category:Taliesin</target></link><link><target>Category:Male poets</target></link><link><target>Category:English male short story writers</target></link><link><target>Category:English male novelists</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century English poets</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century English novelists</target></link></paragraph></article>