<article title='Council_of_Constance'><paragraph><template><target>Ecumenical council</target><arg name="council_name">Council of Constance
</arg><arg name="council_date">1414–1418
</arg><arg name="accepted_by">[[Catholicism]]
</arg><arg name="previous">[[Council of Vienne|Vienne]]
</arg><arg name="next">[[Council of Siena|Siena]] (Counciliarism)<br>[[Council of Florence|Florence]] (Ecumenical)
</arg><arg name="convoked_by">[[Antipope John XXIII]], confirmed by [[Pope Gregory XII]]
</arg><arg name="attendance">600
</arg><arg name="presided_by">
</arg><arg name="topics">[[Western Schism]]
</arg><arg name="documents"><space/>Deposition of [[Antipope John XXIII|John XXIII]] and [[Antipope Benedict XIII|Benedict XIII]], condemnation of [[Jan Hus]], election of [[Pope Martin V|Martin V]]
</arg></template><template><target>Ecumenical councils of the Catholic Church</target></template>The<space/><bold>Council of<space/><link><target>Konstanz</target><part>Constance</part></link></bold><space/>is the 15th century<space/><link><target>ecumenical council</target></link><space/>recognized by the<space/><link><target>Roman Catholic Church</target></link>, held from 1414 to 1418. The council ended the<space/><link><target>Western Schism</target></link>, by deposing or accepting the resignation of the remaining papal claimants and electing<space/><link><target>Pope Martin V</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Council also condemned<space/><link><target>Jan Hus</target></link><space/>as a heretic and facilitated his execution by the civil authority. It also ruled on issues of national sovereignty, the rights of pagans, and just war in response to a conflict between the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Poland (13851569)</target><part>Kingdom of Poland</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Knights</target><part>Order of the Teutonic Knights</part></link>. The Council is important for its relationship to ecclesial<space/><link><target>Conciliarism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Papal supremacy</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origin and background</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Meister der Chronik des Konzils von Konstanz 001.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Emperor Sigismund, his second wife,<space/><link><target>Barbara of Celje</target></link>, and their daughter,<space/><link><target>Elizabeth of Luxembourg</target></link>, at the Council of Constance</part></link>The council's main purpose was to end the Papal schism which had resulted from the confusion following the<space/><link><target>Avignon Papacy</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory XI</target></link>'s return to Rome in 1377, followed by his death and the controversial election of his successor,<space/><link><target>Pope Urban VI</target></link>, resulted in the defection of a number of cardinals and the election of a rival pope based at Avignon in 1378. After thirty years of schism, the<space/><link><target>Council of Pisa</target></link><space/>had sought to resolve the situation by deposing the two claimant popes and elected a new pope,<space/><link><target>Pope Alexander V</target><part>Alexander V</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Vom Schisma zur 'verfluchten Dreiheit'<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">From the Schism to the 'Accursed Trinity'<space/></arg><arg name="first">Ansgar<space/></arg><arg name="last">Frenken<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Damals<space/></arg><arg name="pages">16–21</arg></template></extension><space/>The council claimed that in such a situation, a council of bishops had greater authority than just one bishop, even if he were the bishop of Rome. Though Alexander and his successor,<space/><link><target>Antipope John XXIII</target><part>John XXIII</part></link>, gained widespread support, especially at the cost of the Avignon pope, the schism remained, now involving not two but three claimants:<space/><link><target>Pope Gregory XII</target><part>Gregory XII</part></link><space/>at Rome,<space/><link><target>Antipope Benedict XIII</target><part>Benedict XIII</part></link><space/>at Avignon and John XXIII.</paragraph><paragraph>Therefore, many voices, including<space/><link><target>Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>Sigismund, King of Germany and Hungary</part></link><space/>(and later Holy Roman Emperor) pressed for another council to resolve the issue. That council was called by<space/><link><target>Antipope John XXIII</target><part>John XXIII</part></link><space/>and was held from 16 November 1414 to 22 April 1418 in<space/><link><target>Konstanz</target><part>Constance</part></link>, Germany. According to<space/><link><target>Joseph McCabe</target></link>, the council was attended by roughly 29<space/><link><target>Cardinal (Catholicism)</target><part>cardinal</part><trail>s</trail></link>, 100 &quot;learned doctors of law and divinity,&quot; 134<space/><link><target>abbot</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and 183<space/><link><target>Bishop (Catholic Church)</target><part>bishop</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>archbishop</target><trail>s</trail></link>. An innovation at the Council was that instead of voting as individuals, the bishops voted in national blocks, explicitly confirming the national pressures that had fueled the schism since 1378.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Decrees and doctrinal status</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Richental Konzilssitzung Muenster.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Bishops debating with the pope at the Council of Constance</part></link>The famous decree<space/><italics>Haec Sancta Synodus,</italics><space/>which gave primacy to the authority of the Council and thus became a source for ecclesial<space/><link><target>conciliarism</target></link>, was promulgated in the fifth session, 6 April 1415:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>"Legitimately assembled in the holy Spirit, constituting a general council and representing the Catholic church militant, it has power immediately from Christ; and that everyone of whatever state or dignity, even papal, is bound to obey it in those matters which pertain to the faith, the eradication of the said schism and the general reform of the said church of God in head and members."</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Marks the high-water mark of the Conciliar movement of reform.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Piar"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.piar.hu/councils/ecum16.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Councils<space/></arg><arg name="place"><space/>Hungary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Piar</arg></template>.</extension><space/>This decree, however, is not considered valid by the Magisterium of the Catholic Church, since it was never approved by Pope Gregory XII or his successors, and was passed by the Council in a session before his confirmation. The Church declared the first sessions of the Council of Constance an invalid and illicit assembly of Bishops, gathered under the authority of John XXIII.</paragraph><paragraph>The acts of the Council were not made public until 1442, at the behest of the<space/><link><target>Council of Basel</target></link>; they were printed in 1500. The creation of a book on how to die was ordered by the council, and thus written in 1415 called<space/><italics><link><target>Ars moriendi</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Ending the Western Schism</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template><link><target>Image:Imperia.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''<link><target>Imperia (statue)</target><part>Imperia</part></link>'', a 1993-erected statue commemorating the Council</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>With the support of<space/><link><target>Sigismund, Holy Roman Emperor</target><part>King Sigismund</part></link>, enthroned before the high altar of the cathedral of Constance, the Council of Constance recommended that all three papal claimants abdicate, and that another be chosen. In part because of the constant presence of the King, other rulers demanded that they have a say in who would be pope.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Sigismunds Meisterstück<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">Sigismund's Masterpiece<space/></arg><arg name="first">Karin<space/></arg><arg name="last">Stober<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Damals<space/></arg><arg name="pages">24–31</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gregory XII then sent representatives to Constance, whom he granted full powers to summon, open and preside over an Ecumenical Council; he also empowered them to present his resignation to the Papacy. This would pave the way for the end of the Western Schism.</paragraph><paragraph>The legates were received by King Sigismund and by the assembled Bishops, and the King yielded the presidency of the proceedings to the papal legates, Cardinal Dominici of Ragusa and Prince Charles of Malatesta. On 4 July 1415 the Bull of Gregory XII which appointed Malatesta and Cardinal Dominici of Ragusa as his proxies at the council was formally read before the assembled Bishops. The cardinal then read a decree of Gregory XII which convoked the council and authorized its succeeding acts. Thereupon, the Bishops voted to accept the summons. Prince Malatesta immediately informed the Council that he was empowered by a commission from Pope Gregory XII to resign the Papal Throne on the Pontiff's behalf. He asked the Council whether they would prefer to receive the abdication at that point or at a later date. The Bishops voted to receive the Papal abdication immediately. Thereupon the commission by Gregory XII authorizing his proxy to resign the Papacy on his behalf was read and Malatesta, acting in the name of Gregory XII, pronounced the resignation of the papacy by Gregory XII and handed a written copy of the resignation to the assembly.</paragraph><paragraph>Former Pope Gregory XII was then created titular<space/><link><target>Cardinal Bishop of Porto and Santa Ruffina</target></link><space/>by the Council, with rank immediately below the Pope (which made him the highest-ranking person in the Church, since, due to his abdication, the See of Peter was vacant). Gregory XII's cardinals were accepted as true cardinals by the Council, but the members of the council delayed electing a new pope for fear that a new pope would restrict further discussion of pressing issues in the Church.</paragraph><paragraph>By the time the anti-popes were all deposed and the new Pope,<space/><link><target>Pope Martin V</target><part>Martin V</part></link>, was elected, two years had passed since Gregory XII's abdication, and Gregory was already dead. The council took great care to protect the legitimacy of the succession, ratified all his acts and a new pontiff was chosen. The new pope,<space/><link><target>Pope Martin V</target><part>Martin V</part></link>, elected November 1417, soon asserted the absolute authority of the papal office.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Condemnation of Jan Hus</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Vaclav Brozik - Hus.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Painting of<space/><link><target>Jan Hus</target></link><space/>in Council of Constance by<space/><link><target>Vclav Brok</target></link></part></link>A second goal of the council was to continue the reforms begun at the Council of Pisa. These reforms were largely directed against<space/><link><target>John Wycliffe</target></link>, mentioned in the opening session, and condemned in the eighth, 4 May 1415 and<space/><link><target>Jan Hus</target></link>, and their followers.<space/><link><target>Jan Hus</target></link>, summoned to Constance under a letter of<space/><link><target>safe conduct</target></link>, was found guilty of heresy by the council and turned over to the secular court. &quot; This holy synod of Constance, seeing that God's church has nothing more that it can do, relinquishes Jan Hus to the judgment of the secular authority and decrees that he is to be relinquished to the secular court.&quot; (Council of Constance-Session 156 July 1415). The secular court sentenced him to the stake.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Jerome of Prague</target></link>, a supporter of Jan Hus, came to Constance, to offer assistance. But he was similarly arrested, judged, found guilty of heresy and turned over to the same secular court, with the same outcome as Hus.<space/><link><target>Gian Francesco Poggio Bracciolini</target><part>Poggio Bracciolini</part></link><space/>attended the Council and related the unfairness of the process against Jerome.<extension extension_name='ref'>William Shepherd,<space/><italics>The Life of Poggio Bracciolini</italics>, 1837, Ch. II, p. 68-81.<space/><link type='external' href='https://play.google.com/books/reader?id=F40NAAAAQAAJ&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;output=reader&amp;amp;authuser=0&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;pg=GBS.PA81'>Google Play Book</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>PolishLithuanianTeutonic conflict</heading><paragraph>In 1411, the<space/><link><target>Peace of Thorn (1411)</target><part>First Peace of Thorn</part></link><space/>ended the<space/><link><target>PolishLithuanianTeutonic War</target></link>, in which the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Knights</target></link><space/>fought the<space/><link><target>Poland during the Jagiellon dynasty</target><part>Kingdom of Poland</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Grand Duchy of Lithuania</target></link>. However, the peace was not stable and further conflicts arose regarding demarcation of the<space/><link><target>Samogitia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>borders. The tensions erupted into the brief<space/><link><target>Hunger War</target></link><space/>in summer 1414. It was concluded that the disputes would be mediated by the Council of Constance.</paragraph><paragraph>The Polish position was defended by<space/><link><target>Paulus Vladimiri</target></link>, rector of the<space/><link><target>Jagiellonian University</target></link>, who challenged legality of the Teutonic crusade. He argued that a forced conversion was incompatible with free will, which was an essential component of a genuine conversion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension><space/>Therefore the Knights could only wage a defensive war if pagans violated<space/><link><target>natural rights</target></link><space/>of the Christians. Vladimiri further stipulated that infidels had rights which had to be respected, and neither the Pope nor the<space/><link><target>Holy Roman Emperor</target></link><space/>had the authority to violate them. Poles and Lithuanians also brought a group of Samogitian representatives to testify of atrocities committed by the Knights.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Dominican theologian,<space/><link><target>John of Falkenberg</target></link>, proved to be the fiercest opponent of the Poles. In his<space/><italics>Liber de doctrina</italics>, Falkenberg argued that &quot;<italics>the Emperor has the right to slay even peaceful infidels simply because they are pagans...</italics>&quot;. The Poles deserve death for defending infidels, and should be exterminated even more than the infidels; they should be deprived of their sovereignty and reduced to slavery.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Cassar"></extension><space/>In<space/><italics>Satira</italics>, he attacked Polish King<space/><link><target>Jogaila</target></link>, calling him a &quot;mad dog&quot; unworthy to be king. Falkenberg was condemned and imprisoned for such libel, but was not officially accused of heresy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension><space/>Other opponents included<space/><link><target>Grand Master of the Teutonic Knights</target><part>Grand Master's</part></link><space/>proctor Peter Wormditt, Dominic of San Gimignano, John Urbach, Ardecino de Porta of Novara, and<space/><link><target>Bishop of Ciudad Rodrigo</target></link><space/>Andrew Escobar. They argued that the Knights were perfectly justified in their crusade as it was a sacred duty of Christians to spread the true faith.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension><space/>Cardinal<space/><link><target>Pierre d'Ailly</target></link><space/>published an independent opinion that attempted to somewhat balance both Polish and Teutonic positions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Council did not make any political decisions. It established the<space/><link><target>Diocese of Samogitia</target></link>, with its seat in<space/><link><target>Varniai</target><part>Medininkai</part></link><space/>and subordinated to Lithuanian dioceses, and appointed<space/><link><target>Matthias of Trakai</target></link><space/>as the first bishop. Pope Martin V appointed Polish King<space/><link><target>Jogaila</target></link><space/>and Lithuanian Grand Duke<space/><link><target>Vytautas</target></link><space/>as<space/><link><target>vicars general</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Pskov</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Veliky Novgorod</target></link><space/>in recognition of their Catholicism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chris"></extension><space/>After another round of futile negotiations, the<space/><link><target>Gollub War</target></link><space/>broke out in 1422. It ended with the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Melno</target></link>. Polish-Teutonic wars continued for another hundred years.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>In-line</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="refs">
<ref name</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>General</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>Cantor, Norman F. 1993.<space/><italics>Civilization of the Middle Ages</italics><space/>pp 498ff.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="language">German<space/></arg><arg name="journal">[[Damals]]</arg><arg name="title">Damals Magazine<space/></arg><arg name="year">2014<space/></arg><arg name="issue">2<space/></arg><arg name="volume">46</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Stump, Philip.<space/><italics>The Reforms of the Council of Constance (14141418)</italics>. Brill, 1994.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.piar.hu/councils/ecum16.htm'>Tanner, Norman P., editor, ''Decrees of the Ecumenical Councils''</link>:<space/><italics>Council of Constance 141418</italics>, excerpts of the sessions (in English)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vincenter.org/98/cassar.htm'>Dr. Joseph Cassar: The Rights of Nations</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Council of Constance</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/04288a.htm'>Catholic Encyclopedia: Council of Constance</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.legionofmarytidewater.com/faith/ECUM16.HTM'>Council of Constance</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.medievalarchives.com/Constance'>Council of Constance: Heretics, Schism and the Teutonic Knights</link><space/>on<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.medievalarchives.com/PodcastList'>Medieval Archives Podcast</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>WesternSchism</target></template><template><target>Papal elections and conclaves from 1061</target></template><template><target>Ecumenical councils</target></template><template><target>Samogitian dispute</target></template><template><target>Coord</target><arg>47</arg><arg>39</arg><arg>48</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>10</arg><arg>37</arg><arg>E</arg><arg>type:event_region:DE-BW</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Council Of Constance</target></template><link><target>Category:Ecumenical councils</target></link><link><target>Category:1414 establishments in the Holy Roman Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:1418 disestablishments in the Holy Roman Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:1417 elections</target></link><link><target>Category:Hussite Wars</target></link><link><target>Category:15th-century Roman Catholicism</target></link><link><target>Category:15th-century Roman Catholic Church Councils</target><part>Constance</part></link><link><target>Category:Roman Catholic Church Councils held in Germany</target><part>Constance</part></link><link><target>Category:Western Schism</target></link><link><target>Category:History of Baden-Wrttemberg</target></link><link><target>Category:Konstanz (district)</target></link><link><target>Category:1410s in Germany</target></link></paragraph></article>