<article title='Coma'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target><arg>Coma (disambiguation)</arg><arg>Comas (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>Comma</arg></template><template><target>Infobox symptom</target><arg name="Name"><space/>Coma
<space/></arg><arg name="Field"><space/>[[Neurology]]
</arg><arg name="DiseasesDB">16940
<space/></arg><arg name="ICD10"><space/>{{ICD10|R|40|2|r|40}}
<space/></arg><arg name="ICD9"><space/>{{ICD9|780.01}}
</arg><arg name="MeshID">D003128
</arg></template>In medicine,<space/><bold>coma</bold><space/>(from the<space/><link><target>Greek language</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/><template><target>lang</target><arg>grc</arg><arg>κῶμα</arg></template><space/><italics>koma</italics>, meaning &quot;deep sleep&quot;)<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term</arg><arg name="title">''Coma'' Origin</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Online Etymology Dictionary]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">14 August 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>is a state of<space/><link><target>unconsciousness</target></link><space/>in which a person: cannot be awakened; fails to respond normally to painful stimuli, light, or sound; lacks a normal wake-sleep cycle; and does not initiate voluntary actions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RR"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Weyhenmyeye, James A.; Eve A. Gallman<space/></arg><arg name="title">Rapid Review Neuroscience 1st Ed<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Mosby Elsevier<space/></arg><arg name="year">2007<space/></arg><arg name="pages">177–9<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-323-02261-8</arg></template></extension><space/>A person in a state of coma is described as being<space/><bold>comatose</bold>. Typically, a distinction is made in the medical community between a coma and a<space/><link><target>medically induced coma</target></link>, the former is generally understood to be a result of circumstances beyond the control of the medical community, while the latter is generally understood to be a means by which medical professionals may allow a patient's injuries to heal in a controlled environment.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>A comatose person exhibits a complete absence of wakefulness and is unable to consciously feel, speak, hear, or move.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bordini</arg><arg name="first">A.L.</arg><arg name="author2">Luiz, T.F.<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Fernandes, M.<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Arruda, W. O.<space/></arg><arg name="author5"><space/>Teive, H. A.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Coma scales: a historical review</arg><arg name="journal">Arquivos de neuro-psiquiatria</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="pages">930–937</arg><arg name="doi">10.1590/S0004-282X2010000600019</arg><arg name="volume">68</arg><arg name="issue">6</arg><arg name="pmid">21243255</arg></template></extension><space/>For a patient to maintain consciousness, two important neurological components must function. The first is the<space/><link><target>cerebral cortex</target></link>the gray matter that forms the outer layer of the brain. The other is a structure located in the brainstem, called<space/><link><target>reticular activating system</target></link><space/>(RAS).<extension extension_name='ref' name="med"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Hannaman, Robert A.</arg><arg name="title">MedStudy Internal Medicine Review Core Curriculum: Neurology 11th Ed</arg><arg name="publisher">MedStudy</arg><arg name="year">2005<space/></arg><arg name="pages">(11–1) to (11–2)<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">1-932703-01-2</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Persistent vegetative state: A medical minefield</arg><arg name="journal">[[New Scientist]]</arg><arg name="date">July 7, 2007</arg><arg name="pages">40–3</arg><arg name="url">http://www.newscientist.com/article/mg19526111.800-persistent-vegetative-state-a-medical-minefield.html?full</arg></template><space/>See<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.newscientist.com/data/images/archive/2611/26111801.jpg'>diagram</link>.</extension>Injury to either or both of these components is sufficient to cause a patient to experience a coma. The cerebral cortex is a group of tight, dense, &quot;gray matter&quot; composed of the nuclei of the neurons whose axons then form the &quot;white matter&quot;, and is responsible for perception, relay of the sensory input (sensation) via the thalamic pathway, and many other neurological functions, including complex thinking.</paragraph><paragraph>RAS, on the other hand, is a more primitive structure in the brainstem that is tightly in connection with reticular formation (RF). The RAS area of the brain has two tracts, the ascending and descending tract. Made up of a system of acetylcholine-producing neurons, the ascending track, or ascending reticular activating system (ARAS), works to arouse and wake up the brain, from the RF, through the thalamus, and then finally to the cerebral cortex.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Young 2009 3247"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Young</arg><arg name="first">G.B.</arg><arg name="title">Coma</arg><arg name="journal">Ann N Y Acad . BjjSci</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="issue">1157</arg><arg name="pages">32–47</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1749-6632.2009.04471.x</arg><arg name="volume">1157</arg><arg name="bibcode">2009NYASA1157...32Y</arg></template></extension><space/>A failure in ARAS functioning may then lead to a coma.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Signs and symptoms</heading><paragraph><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="direction">horizontal</arg><arg name="width">160</arg><arg name="image1">Aaron in Coma1.jpg</arg><arg name="caption1">Image of a man in a coma.<ref>{{cite web |url</arg><arg name="image2">comaventilator.jpg</arg><arg name="caption2">Image of the man still unresponsive to stimuli.<ref>{{cite web |url</arg></template>Generally, a person who is unable to voluntarily open the eyes, does not have a sleep-wake cycle, is unresponsive in spite of strong tactile (painful), or verbal stimuli and who generally scores between 3 to 8<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Glasgow Coma Scale</arg><arg name="author">Russ Rowlett</arg><arg name="publisher">University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</arg><arg name="url">http://www.unc.edu/~rowlett/units/scales/glasgow.htm</arg></template></extension><space/>on the<space/><link><target>Glasgow Coma Scale</target></link><space/>is considered in a coma.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RR"></extension><space/>Coma may have developed in humans as a response to injury to allow the body to pause bodily actions and heal the most immediate injuries - if at all - before waking. It therefore could be a compensatory state in which the body's expenditure of energy is not superfluous. The severity and mode of onset of coma depends on the underlying cause. For instance, severe<space/><link><target>hypoglycemia</target></link><space/>(low blood sugar) or<space/><link><target>hypercapnia</target></link><space/>(increased<space/><link><target>carbon dioxide</target></link><space/>levels in the blood) initially cause mild agitation and confusion, but progress to<space/><link><target>obtundation</target></link>, stupor and finally complete unconsciousness. In contrast, coma resulting from a severe<space/><link><target>traumatic brain injury</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>subarachnoid hemorrhage</target></link><space/>can be instantaneous. The mode of onset may therefore be indicative of the underlying cause.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Causes of coma</heading><paragraph>Coma may result from a variety of conditions, including<space/><link><target>Substance intoxication</target><part>intoxication</part></link><space/>(such as drug abuse, overdose or misuse of over the counter medications, prescribed medication, or controlled substances),<space/><link><target>metabolism</target><part>metabolic</part></link><space/>abnormalities, central nervous system diseases, acute neurologic injuries such as<space/><link><target>stroke</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>herniation</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Hypoxia (medical)</target><part>hypoxia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>hypothermia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>hypoglycemia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Eclampsia</target></link><space/>or traumatic injuries such as<space/><link><target>head trauma</target></link><space/>caused by falls or<space/><link><target>vehicle collision</target><trail>s</trail></link>. It may also be deliberately<space/><link><target>induced coma</target><part>induced</part></link><space/>by pharmaceutical agents during major<space/><link><target>neurosurgery</target></link>, to preserve higher brain functions following<space/><link><target>brain trauma</target></link>, or to save the patient from extreme pain during healing of injuries or diseases.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Induced Coma</arg><arg name="author">Benjamin Werdro</arg><arg name="url">http://www.medicinenet.com/coma/page8.htm#induced</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Forty percent of comatose states result from drug poisoning.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Liversedge 2010 337339"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Liversedge</arg><arg name="author2">Hirsch</arg><arg name="title">Coma</arg><arg name="journal">Anaesthesia &amp; Intensive Care Medicine</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="pages">337–339</arg><arg name="doi">10.1016/j.mpaic.2010.05.008</arg><arg name="first1">Timothy</arg><arg name="volume">11</arg><arg name="issue">9</arg></template></extension><space/>Drugs damage or weaken the synaptic functioning in the ARAS and keep the system from properly functioning to arouse the brain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Young 2009 3247"></extension><space/>Secondary effects of drugs, which include abnormal heart rate and blood pressure, as well as abnormal breathing and sweating, may also indirectly harm the functioning of the ARAS and lead to a coma. Seizures and hallucinations have shown to also play a major role in ARAS malfunction. Given that drug poisoning is the cause for a large portion of patients in a coma, hospitals first test all comatose patients by observing pupil size and eye movement, through the vestibular-ocular reflex.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Young 2009 3247"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The second most common cause of coma, which makes up about 25% of comatose patients, occurs from lack of oxygen, generally resulting from cardiac arrest.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Liversedge 2010 337339"></extension><space/>The Central Nervous System (CNS) requires a great deal of oxygen for its neurons. Oxygen deprivation in the brain, also known as hypoxia, causes neuronal extracellular sodium and calcium to decrease and intracellular calcium to increase, which harms neuron communication.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Busl</arg><arg name="first">K. M.</arg><arg name="author2">Greer, D. M.</arg><arg name="title">Hypoxic-ischemic brain injury: Pathophysiology, neuropathology and mechanisms</arg><arg name="journal">NeuroRehabilitation</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="pages">5–13</arg></template></extension><space/>Lack of oxygen in the brain also causes<space/><link><target>Adenosine triphosphate</target><part>ATP</part></link><space/>exhaustion and cellular breakdown from cytoskeleton damage and nitric oxide production.</paragraph><paragraph>Twenty percent of comatose states result from the side effects of a stroke.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Liversedge 2010 337339"></extension><space/>During a stroke, blood flow to part of the brain is restricted or blocked. An ischemic stroke, brain hemorrhage, or tumor may cause such cessation of blood flow. Lack of blood to cells in the brain prevents oxygen from getting to the neurons, and consequently causes cells to become disrupted and eventually die. As brain cells die, brain tissue continues to deteriorate, which may affect functioning of the ARAS.</paragraph><paragraph>The remaining 15% of comatose cases result from trauma, excessive blood loss, malnutrition, hypothermia, hyperthermia, abnormal glucose levels, and many other biological disorders.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Diagnosis</heading><paragraph>Diagnosis of coma is simple, but diagnosing the cause of the underlying disease process is often challenging. The first priority in treatment of a comatose patient is stabilization following the basic ABCs (standing for airway, breathing, and circulation). Once a person in a coma is stable, investigations are performed to assess the underlying cause. Investigative methods are divided into<space/><link><target>physical examination</target></link><space/>findings and imaging (such as<space/><link><target>Cat scan</target><part>CAT scan</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Mri</target><part>MRI</part></link>, etc.) and special studies (<link><target>EEG</target></link>, etc.)</paragraph><heading level='3'>Diagnostic steps</heading><paragraph>When an unconscious patient enters a hospital, the hospital utilizes a series of diagnostic steps to identify the cause of unconsciousness. According to Young,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Young 2009 3247"></extension><space/>the following steps should be taken when dealing with a patient possibly in a coma:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Perform a general examination and medical history check</listitem><listitem>Make sure the patient is in an actual comatose state and or is not in locked-in state (patient is either able to voluntarily move his eyes or blink) or psychogenic unresponsiveness (<link><target>Caloric_reflex_test</target><part>caloric stimulation of the vestibular apparatus</part></link><space/>results in slow deviation of eyes towards the stimulation followed by rapid correction to mid-line. This response cannot be voluntarily suppressed, so if the patient does not have this response, psychogenic coma can be ruled out.)</listitem><listitem>Find the site of the brain that may be causing coma (i.e., brain stem, back of brain) and assess the severity of the coma with the Glasgow coma scale</listitem><listitem>Take blood work to see if drugs were involved or if it was a result of hypoventilation/hyperventilation</listitem><listitem>Check for levels of serum glucose, calcium, sodium, potassium, magnesium, phosphate, urea, and creatinine</listitem><listitem>Perform brain scans to observe any abnormal brain functioning using either CT or MRI scans</listitem><listitem>Continue to monitor brain waves and identify seizures of patient using EEGs</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Initial assessment and evaluation</heading><paragraph>In the initial assessment of coma, it is common to gauge the<space/><link><target>level of consciousness</target></link><space/>by spontaneously exhibited actions, response to vocal stimuli (&quot;Can you hear me?&quot;), and painful stimuli; this is known as the<space/><link><target>AVPU</target></link><space/>(alert, vocal stimuli, painful stimuli, unresponsive) scale. More elaborate scales, such as the<space/><link><target>Glasgow Coma Scale</target></link>, quantify an individual's reactions such as eye opening, movement and verbal response on a scale; Glasgow Coma Scale (GCS) is an indication of the extent of brain injury varying from 3 (indicating severe brain injury and death) to a maximum of 15 (indicating mild or no brain injury).</paragraph><paragraph>In those with deep unconsciousness, there is a risk of<space/><link><target>asphyxiation</target></link><space/>as the control over the muscles in the face and throat is diminished. As a result, those presenting to a hospital with coma are typically assessed for this risk (&quot;<link><target>airway management</target></link>&quot;). If the risk of asphyxiation is deemed high, doctors may use various devices (such as an<space/><link><target>oropharyngeal airway</target></link>,<space/><link><target>nasopharyngeal airway</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>endotracheal tube</target></link>) to safeguard the airway.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Physical examination findings</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Decorticate.PNG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Decorticate posturing</target></link>, indicating a<space/><link><target>lesion</target></link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>red nucleus</target></link><space/>or above. This positioning is stereotypical for upper<space/><link><target>brain stem</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>Cortex (anatomy)</target><part>cortical</part></link><space/>damage. The other variant is<space/><link><target>decerebrate posturing</target></link>, not seen in this picture.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Physical examination is critical after stabilization. It should include<space/><link><target>vital signs</target></link>, a general portion dedicated to making observations about the patient's<space/><link><target>Respiration (physiology)</target><part>respiration</part></link><space/>(breathing pattern), body movements (if any), and of the patient's<space/><link><target>body habitus</target></link><space/>(physique); it should also include assessment of the brainstem and cortical function through special reflex tests such as the<space/><link><target>oculocephalic reflex</target></link><space/>test (doll's eyes test),<space/><link><target>caloric reflex test</target><part>oculovestibular reflex</part></link><space/>test (cold caloric test), nasal tickle,<space/><link><target>corneal reflex</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>gag reflex</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Vital signs in medicine are temperature (rectal is most accurate), blood pressure, heart rate (pulse), respiratory rate, and oxygen saturation. It should be easy to evaluate these vitals quickly to gain insight into a patient's metabolism, fluid status, heart function, vascular integrity, and tissue oxygenation.</paragraph><paragraph>Respiratory pattern (breathing rhythm) is significant and should be noted in a comatose patient. Certain stereotypical patterns of breathing have been identified including<space/><link><target>CheyneStokes respiration</target><part>CheyneStokes</part></link>, a form of breathing in which the patient's breathing pattern is described as alternating episodes of<space/><link><target>hyperventilation</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>apnea</target></link>. This is a dangerous pattern and is often seen in pending herniations, extensive cortical lesions, or brainstem damage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="med"></extension><space/>Another pattern of breathing is<space/><link><target>apneustic breathing</target></link>, which is characterized by sudden pauses of<space/><link><target>Inhalation</target><part>inspiration</part></link><space/>and is due to a lesion of the<space/><link><target>pons</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RR"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="med"></extension><space/><link><target>Ataxic respiration</target><part>Ataxic breathing</part></link><space/>is irregular and is due to a lesion (damage) of the<space/><link><target>Medulla oblongata</target><part>medulla</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Assessment of posture and body habitus is the next step. It involves general observation about the patient's positioning. There are often two stereotypical postures seen in comatose patients.<space/><link><target>Decorticate posturing</target></link><space/>is a stereotypical posturing in which the patient has arms<space/><link><target>Flexion</target><part>flexed</part></link><space/>at the elbow, and arms adducted toward the body, with both legs<space/><link><target>Extension (kinesiology)</target><part>extended</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Decerebrate posturing</target></link><space/>is a stereotypical posturing in which the legs are similarly extended (stretched), but the arms are also stretched (extended at the elbow). The posturing is critical since it indicates where the damage is in the central nervous system. A decorticate posturing indicates a lesion (a point of damage) at or above the<space/><link><target>red nucleus</target></link>, whereas a decerebrate posturing indicates a lesion at or below the red nucleus. In other words, a decorticate lesion is closer to the cortex, as opposed to a decerebrate cortex that is closer to the brainstem.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Oculocephalic reflex</target></link><space/>also known as the doll's eye is performed to assess the integrity of the brainstem. Patient's eyelids are gently elevated and the cornea is visualized. The patient's head is then moved to the patient's left, to observe if the eyes stay or deviate toward the patient's right; same maneuver is attempted on the opposite side. If the patient's eyes move in a direction opposite to the direction of the rotation of the head, then the patient is said to have an intact brainstem. However, failure of both eyes to move to one side, can indicate damage or destruction of the affected side. In special cases, where only one eye deviates and the other does not, this often indicates a lesion (or damage) of the<space/><link><target>medial longitudinal fasciculus</target></link><space/>(MLF), which is a brainstem nerve tract.<space/><link><target>Caloric reflex test</target></link><space/>also evaluates both cortical and brainstem function; cold water is injected into one ear and the patient is observed for eye movement; if the patient's eyes slowly deviate toward the ear where the water was injected, then the brainstem is intact, however failure to deviate toward the injected ear indicates damage of the brainstem on that side. Cortex is responsible for a rapid<space/><link><target>nystagmus</target></link><space/>away from this deviated position and is often seen in patients who are conscious or merely lethargic.</paragraph><paragraph>An important part of the physical exam is also assessment of the<space/><link><target>cranial nerves</target></link>. Due to the unconscious status of the patient, only a limited number of the nerves can be assessed. These include the cranial nerves number 2 (CN II), number 3 (CN III), number 5 (CN V), number 7 (CN VII), and cranial nerves 9 and 10 (CN IX, CN X).<space/><link><target>Gag reflex</target></link><space/>helps assess cranial nerves 9 and 10. Pupil reaction to light is important because it shows an intact retina, and cranial nerve number 2 (CN II); if pupils are reactive to light, then that also indicates that the cranial nerve number 3 (CN III) (or at least its<space/><link><target>parasympathetic</target></link><space/>fibers) are intact.<space/><link><target>Corneal reflex</target></link><space/>assess the integrity of cranial nerve number 7 (CN VII), and cranial nerve number 5 (CN V). Cranial nerve number 5 (CN V), and its ophthalmic branch (V<xhtml:sub>1</xhtml:sub>) are responsible for the afferent arm of the reflex, and the cranial nerve number 7 (CN VII) also known a facial nerve, is responsible for the efferent arm, causing contraction of the muscle<space/><link><target>orbicularis oculi</target></link><space/>resulting in closing of the eyes.</paragraph><paragraph>Pupil assessment is often a critical portion of a comatose examination, as it can give information as to the cause of the coma; the following table is a technical, medical guideline for common pupil findings and their possible interpretations:<extension extension_name='ref' name="med"></extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Pupil sizes (left eye vs. right eye)</tablehead><tablehead>Possible interpretation</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Darkblue.jpg</target><part>250px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Normal eye with two pupils equal in size and reactive to light. This means that the patient is probably not in a coma and is probably lethargic, under influence of a drug, or sleeping.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Myosis due to opiate use.jpg</target><part>250px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>&quot;Pinpoint&quot; pupils indicate<space/><link><target>heroin</target></link><space/>or opiate overdose, and can be responsible for a patient's coma. The pinpoint pupils are still reactive to light,<space/><link><target>wikt:bilateral</target><part>bilaterally</part></link><space/>(in both eyes, not just one). Another possibility is the damage of the pons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="med"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Anizokoria.JPG</target><part>250px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>One pupil is dilated and unreactive, while the other is normal (in this case, the right eye is dilated, while the left eye is normal in size). This could mean a damage to the<space/><link><target>oculomotor nerve</target></link><space/>(cranial nerve number 3, CN III) on the right side, or possibility of vascular involvement.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>File:Cyclopentolate 1 percent Pupils.jpg</target><part>250px</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Both pupils are dilated and unreactive to light. This could be due to overdose of certain medications,<space/><link><target>hypothermia</target></link><space/>or severe<space/><link><target>Hypoxia (medical)</target><part>anoxia</part></link><space/>(lack of oxygen).</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Imaging and special tests findings</heading><paragraph>Imaging basically encompasses<space/><link><target>computed tomography</target></link><space/>(CAT or CT) scan of the brain, or<space/><link><target>MRI</target></link><space/>for example, and is performed to identify specific causes of the coma, such as<space/><link><target>hemorrhage</target></link><space/>in the brain or<space/><link><target>herniation</target></link><space/>of the brain structures. Special tests such as an<space/><link><target>EEG</target></link><space/>can also show a lot about the activity level of the cortex such as semantic processing,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Daltrozzo01">Daltrozzo, J., Wioland, N., Mutschler, V., Lutun, P., Jaeger, A., Calon, B., Meyer, A., Pottecher, T., Lang, S., Kotchoubey, B. (2009c). Cortical Information Processing in Coma, Cognitive &amp; Behavioral Neurology, 22(1), 53-62.<link type='external' href='http://daltrozzo.net78.net/papers/Daltrozzo_et_al_%202009.pdf'></link></extension><space/>presence of<space/><link><target>seizures</target></link>, and are important available tools not only for the assessment of the cortical activity but also for predicting the likelihood of the patient's awakening.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Daltrozzo02">Daltrozzo, J., Wioland, N., Mutschler, V., Kotchoubey, B. (2007). Predicting Coma and other Low Responsive Patients Outcome using Event-Related Brain Potentials: A Meta-analysis. Clinical Neurophysiology, 118, 606-614.<link type='external' href='http://daltrozzo.net78.net/papers/daltrozzo_et_al_2007a.pdf'></link></extension><space/>The autonomous responses such as the<space/><link><target>skin conductance response</target></link><space/>may also provide further insight on the patient's emotional processing.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Daltrozzo03">Daltrozzo, J., Wioland, N., Mutschler, V., Lutun, P., Calon, B., Meyer, A., Jaeger, A., Pottecher, T., Kotchoubey, B. (2010a). Electrodermal Response in Coma and Other Low Responsive Patients. Neuroscience Letters, 475(1), 44-47.<link type='external' href='http://daltrozzo.net78.net/papers/Daltrozzo_et_al_2010b.pdf'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>History</heading><paragraph>When diagnosing any neurological condition, history and examination are fundamental. History is obtained by family, friends or EMS. The<space/><link><target>Glasgow Coma Scale</target></link><space/>is a helpful system used to examine and determine the depth of coma, track patients progress and predict outcome as best as possible. In general a correct diagnosis can be achieved by combining findings from physical exam, imaging, and history components and directs the appropriate therapy.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Severity and classification</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Coma scale</arg></template>A coma can be classified as (1)<space/><link><target>Tentorium cerebelli</target><part>supratentoral</part></link><space/>(above<space/><link><target>Tentorium cerebelli</target></link>), (2)<space/><link><target>Tentorium cerebelli</target><part>infratentoral</part></link><space/>(below Tentorium cerebelli), (3) metabolic or (4) diffused.<extension extension_name='ref' name="med"></extension><space/>This classification is merely dependent on the position of the original damage that caused the coma, and does not correlate with severity or the prognosis.The severity of coma impairment however is categorized into several levels. Patients may or may not progress through these levels. In the first level, the brain responsiveness lessens, normal reflexes are lost, the patient no longer responds to pain and cannot hear.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Rancho Los Amigos Scale</target></link><space/>is a complex scale that has eight separate levels, and is often used in the first few weeks or months of coma while the patient is under closer observation, and when shifts between levels are more frequent.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Treatment</heading><heading level='3'>Medical treatment</heading><paragraph>The treatment hospitals use on comatose patients depends on both the severity and cause of the comatose state. Although the best treatment for comatose patients remains unknown, hospitals usually place comatose patients in an Intensive Care Unit (ICU) immediately.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Young 2009 3247"></extension><space/>In the ICU, the hospital monitors a patients breathing and brain activity through CT scans. Attention must first be directed to maintaining the patient's respiration and circulation, using intubation and ventilation, administration of intravenous fluids or blood and other supportive care as needed. Once a patient is stable and no longer in immediate danger, the medical staff may concentrate on maintaining the health of patients physical state. The concentration is directed to preventing infections such as pneumonias, bedsores (<link><target>decubitus ulcers</target></link>), and providing balanced nutrition.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sr"></extension><space/>These infections may appear from the patient not being able to move around, and being confined to the bed. The nursing staff moves the patient every 23 hours from side to side and depending on the state of consciousness sometimes to a chair. The goal is to move the patient as much as possible to try to avoid bedsores,<space/><link><target>atelectasis</target></link><space/>and pneumonia. Pneumonia can occur from the persons inability to swallow leading to<space/><link><target>Pulmonary aspiration</target><part>aspiration</part></link>, lack of gag reflex or from feeding tube, (<link><target>aspiration pneumonia</target></link>). Physical therapy may also be used to prevent<space/><link><target>contractures</target></link><space/>and orthopedic deformities that would limit recovery for those patients who emerge from coma.</paragraph><paragraph>A person in a coma may become restless, or seize and need special care to prevent them from hurting themselves. Medicine may be given to calm such individuals. Patients who are restless may also try to pull on tubes or dressings so soft cloth wrist restraints may be put on. Side rails on the bed should be kept up to prevent the patient from falling.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sr"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Coma</arg><arg name="url">http://medicalcenter.osu.edu/PatientEd/Materials/PDFDocs/dis-cond/general/coma.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-12-08</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In attempt to wake comatose patients, some hospitals treat their patients by either reversing the cause of comatose (i.e., glucose shock if low sugar), giving medication to stop brain swelling, or inducing hypothermia. Inducing hypothermia on comatose patients provides one of the main treatments for patients after suffering from cardiac arrest. In this treatment, medical personnel expose patients to external or intravascular cooling at 32-34 C for 24 h.; this treatment cools patients down about 2-3 C less than normal body temperature.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baldursdottir 2010 821826"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Baldursdottir</arg><arg name="first">S.</arg><arg name="author2">Sigvaldason, K.<space/></arg><arg name="author3">Karason, S.<space/></arg><arg name="author4">Valsson, F.<space/></arg><arg name="author5"><space/>Sigurdsson, G. H.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Induced hypothermia in comatose survivors of asphyxia: a case series of 14 consecutive cases</arg><arg name="journal">Acta Anaesthesiol. Scand.</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="pages">821–826</arg><arg name="doi">10.1111/j.1399-6576.2010.02248.x</arg><arg name="volume">54</arg><arg name="issue">7</arg><arg name="pmid">20497127</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2002, Baldursdottir and her coworkers<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baldursdottir 2010 821826"></extension><space/>found that in the hospital, more comatose patients survived after induced hypothermia than patients that remained at normal body temperature. For this reason, the hospital chose to continue the induced hypothermia technique for all of its comatose patients that suffered from cardiac arrest.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baldursdottir 2010 821826"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Emotional challenges</heading><paragraph>Coma has a wide variety of emotional reactions from the family members of the affected patients, as well as the primary care givers taking care of the patients. Common reactions, such as desperation, anger, frustration, and denial are possible. The focus of the patient care should be on creating an amicable relationship with the family members or dependents of a comatose patient as well as creating a rapport with the medical staff.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Caring for Care Giver and Family</arg><arg name="author">Coma Care</arg><arg name="date">2010-03-30</arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-12-08</arg><arg name="url">http://www.comacare.com/cgi-bin/giga.cgi?</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Prognosis</heading><paragraph>Comas can last from several days to several weeks. In more severe cases a coma may last for over five weeks, while some have lasted as long as several years. After this time, some patients gradually come out of the coma, some progress to a<space/><link><target>Persistent vegetative state</target><part>vegetative state</part></link>, and others die. Some patients who have entered a vegetative state go on to regain a degree of awareness. Others remain in a vegetative state for years or even decades (the longest recorded period being 42 years).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.miamiherald.com/2012/11/22/3109800/edwarda-obara-who-spent-4-decades.html'>Edwarda OBara, who spent 4 decades in a coma, dies at 59</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-asia-india-32776897'>Aruna Shanba, who spent 42 years in coma.</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The outcome for coma and vegetative state depends on the cause, location, severity and extent of neurological damage. A deeper coma alone does not necessarily mean a slimmer chance of recovery, because some people in deep coma recover well while others in a so-called milder coma sometimes fail to improve.</paragraph><paragraph>People may emerge from a coma with a combination of physical, intellectual and psychological difficulties that need special attention. Recovery usually occurs graduallypatients acquire more and more ability to respond. Some patients never progress beyond very basic responses, but many recover full awareness.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Coma Information Page: National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke (NINDS)</arg><arg name="author">NINDS</arg><arg name="date"><space/>October 29, 2010</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2010-12-08</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ninds.nih.gov/disorders/coma/coma.htm#What_is_the_prognosis</arg></template></extension><space/>Regaining consciousness is not instant: in the first days, patients are only awake for a few minutes, and duration of time awake gradually increases. This is unlike the situation in many movies where people who awake from comas are instantly able to continue their normal lives. In reality, the coma patient awakes sometimes in a profound state of confusion, not knowing how they got there and sometimes suffering from<space/><link><target>dysarthria</target></link>, the inability to articulate any speech, and with many other disabilities.</paragraph><paragraph>Predicted chances of recovery are variable owing to different techniques used to measure the extent of neurological damage. All the predictions are based on<space/><link><target>statistical</target></link><space/>rates with some level of chance for recovery present: a person with a low chance of recovery may still awaken. Time is the best general predictor of a chance of recovery: after four months of coma caused by<space/><link><target>brain damage</target></link>, the chance of partial recovery is less than 15%, and the chance of full recovery is very low.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Formisano R<space/></arg><arg name="title">Clinical predictors and neuropleropsychological outcome in severe traumatic brain injury patients<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Acta Neurochir (Wien)</arg><arg name="volume">146<space/></arg><arg name="issue">5<space/></arg><arg name="pages">457–62<space/></arg><arg name="date">May 2004<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">15118882<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1007/s00701-004-0225-4<space/></arg><arg name="url"></arg><arg name="author2"><space/>Carlesimo GA<space/></arg><arg name="author3"><space/>Sabbadini M<space/></arg><arg name="author4">and others<space/></arg><arg name="displayauthors">3<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The most common cause of death for a person in a vegetative state is secondary<space/><link><target>infection</target></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>pneumonia</target></link>, which can occur in patients who lie still for extended periods.</paragraph><paragraph>There are reports of patients coming out of coma after long periods of time. After 19 years in a<space/><link><target>minimally conscious state</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Terry Wallis</target></link><space/>spontaneously began speaking and regained awareness of his surroundings.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.smh.com.au/articles/2003/07/11/1057783356390.html<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Sydney Morning Herald<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mother stunned by coma victim's unexpected words<space/></arg><arg name="date">2003-07-12</arg></template></extension><space/>Similarly,<space/><link><target>Poland</target><part>Polish</part></link><space/>railroad worker<space/><link><target>Jan Grzebski</target></link><space/>woke up from a 19-year coma in 2007.</paragraph><paragraph>A brain-damaged man, trapped in a coma-like state for six years, was brought back to consciousness in 2003 by doctors who planted electrodes deep inside his brain. The method, called<space/><link><target>deep brain stimulation</target></link><space/>(DBS) successfully roused communication, complex movement and eating ability in the 38-year-old American man who suffered a traumatic brain injury. His injuries left him in a<space/><link><target>minimally conscious state</target></link><space/>(MCS), a condition akin to a coma but characterized by occasional, but brief, evidence of environmental and self-awareness that coma patients lack.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Electrodes stir man from six-year coma-like state<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cosmosmagazine.com/node/1513<space/></arg><arg name="work">Cosmos Magazine<space/></arg><arg name="date">2 August 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Comas lasting seconds to minutes result in<space/><link><target>post-traumatic amnesia</target></link><space/>(PTA) that lasts hours to days; recovery plateau occurs over days to weeks.Comas that last hours to days result in PTA lasting days to weeks; recovery plateau occurs over months.Comas lasting weeks result in PTA that lasts months; recovery plateau occurs over months to years.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.memorylossonline.com/glossary/posttraumaticamnesia.html</arg><arg name="title">Post-traumatic amnesia</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Society and culture</heading><paragraph>Research by Dr. Eelco Wijdicks on the depiction of comas in movies was published in Neurology in May 2006. Dr. Wijdicks studied 30 films (made between 1970 and 2004) that portrayed actors in prolonged comas, and he concluded that only two films accurately depicted the state of a coma victim and the agony of waiting for a patient to awaken:<space/><italics><link><target>Reversal of Fortune</target></link></italics><space/>(1990) and<space/><italics><link><target>The Dreamlife of Angels</target></link></italics><space/>(1998). The remaining 28 were criticized for portraying miraculous awakenings with no lasting side effects, unrealistic depictions of treatments and equipment required, and comatose patients remaining muscular and tanned.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Eelco F.M. Wijdicks, MD and Coen A. Wijdicks, BS<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.neurology.org/cgi/content/abstract/66/9/1300<space/></arg><arg name="title">The portrayal of coma in contemporary motion pictures<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Neurology<space/></arg><arg name="volume">66<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1300–1303<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-11-25<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">16682658<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1212/01.wnl.0000210497.62202.e9<space/></arg><arg name="issue">9
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>Medicine</arg></template><template><target>wiktionary</target><arg>κῶμα</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Brain death</target></link>, lack of activity in both cortex, and lack of brainstem function</listitem><listitem><link><target>Coma scale</target></link>, a system to assess the severity of coma</listitem><listitem><link><target>Locked-in syndrome</target></link>, Paralysis of most muscles, except ocular muscles of the eyes, while patient is conscious</listitem><listitem><link><target>Persistent vegetative state</target></link><space/>(vegetative coma), deep coma without detectable awareness. Damage to the cortex, with an intact brainstem.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Process Oriented Coma Work</target></link>, for an approach to working with residual consciousness in comatose patients.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>disorders of consciousness</target></template><template><target>Cognition, perception, emotional state and behaviour symptoms and signs</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Intensive care medicine</target></link><link><target>Category:Emergency medicine</target></link><link><target>Category:Symptoms and signs: Cognition, perception, emotional state and behaviour</target></link><link><target>Category:Coma</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>