<article title='Existentialism'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Existential</arg><arg>the logical sense of the term</arg><arg>Existential quantification</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Existence (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>distinguish</target><arg>Essentialism</arg></template><link><target>File:Kierkegaard-Dostoyevsky-Nietzsche-Sartre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>From left to right, top to bottom:<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target><part>Kierkegaard</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoyevsky</target><part>Dostoyevsky</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target><part>Nietzsche</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target><part>Sartre</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Existentialism</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ɛ</arg><arg>g</arg><arg>z</arg><arg>ɪ</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>ɛ</arg><arg>n</arg><arg>ʃ</arg><arg>ə</arg><arg>l</arg><arg>ɪ</arg><arg>z</arg><arg>əm</arg></template>)<extension extension_name='ref'>Oxford University Press,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/existentialism'>&quot;Oxford Dictionary: 'existentialism'&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Oxford English Dictionary</italics>, Retrieved 22 August 2014.</extension><space/>is a term applied to the work of certain late 19th- and 20th-century<space/><link><target>Europe</target><trail>an</trail></link><space/>philosophers who, despite profound doctrinal differences,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crowell-SEoP"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existentialism<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="author">Crowell, Steven<space/></arg><arg name="date">October 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>John Macquarrie,<space/><italics>Existentialism</italics>, New York (1972), pp. 1821.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Philosophy 1995 p. 259"><italics>Oxford Companion to Philosophy</italics>, ed. Ted Honderich, New York (1995), p. 259.</extension><space/>shared the belief that philosophical thinking begins with the human subjectnot merely the thinking subject, but the acting, feeling, living human<space/><link><target>individual</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Macquarrie,<space/><italics>Existentialism</italics>, New York (1972), pp. 1415.</extension><space/>In existentialism, the individual's starting point is characterised by what has been called &quot;the existential attitude&quot;, or a sense of disorientation and confusion in the face of an apparently meaningless or<space/><link><target>Absurdism</target><part>absurd</part></link><space/>world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robert C. Solomon 1974, pp. 1">Robert C. Solomon,<space/><italics>Existentialism</italics><space/>(McGraw-Hill, 1974, pp. 12).</extension><space/>Many existentialists have also regarded traditional systematic or academic philosophies, in both style and content, as too abstract and remote from concrete human experience.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ernst Breisach,<space/><italics>Introduction to Modern Existentialism</italics>, New York (1962), p. 5.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Walter Kaufmann,<space/><italics>Existentialism: From Dostoyevesky to Sartre</italics>, New York (1956) p. 12.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>is generally considered to have been the first existentialist philosopher,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crowell-SEoP"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Marino, Gordon.<space/><italics>Basic Writings of Existentialism</italics><space/>(Modern Library, 2004, p. ix, 3).</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="McDonald2009Stanford"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">McDonald<space/></arg><arg name="first">William<space/></arg><arg name="title">Søren Kierkegaard<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">[[Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy]] (Summer 2009 Edition)<space/></arg><arg name="editor">Edward N. Zalta<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/archives/sum2009/entries/kierkegaard/</arg></template></extension><space/>though he did not use the term existentialism.<extension extension_name='ref'>However he did title his 1846 book<space/><italics>Concluding Unscientific Postscript to Philosophical Fragments</italics>, (Subtitle) A Mimical-Pathetic-Dialectical Compilation an Existential Contribution, and mentioned the term on pages 121-122, 191, 350-351, 387ff of that book. and he did, in fact, use it like this:<space/><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;All skepticism is a kind of idealism. Hence when the sceptic<space/><link><target>Zeno of Elea</target><part>Zeno</part></link><space/>pursued the study of skepticism by endeavoring existentially to keep himself unaffected by whatever happened, so that when once he had gone out of his way to avoid a mad dog, he shamefacedly admitted that even a skeptical philosopher is also sometimes a man, I find nothing ridiculous in this. There is no contradiction, and the comical always lies in a contradiction. On the other hand, when one thinks of all the miserable idealistic lecture-witticisms, the jesting and coquetry in connection with playing the idealist while in the professorial chair, so that the lecturer is not really an idealist, but only plays the fashionable game of being an idealist; when one remembers the lecture-phrase about doubting everything, while occupying the lecture platform, aye, then it is impossible not to write a satire merely by recounting the facts. Through an existential attempt to be an idealist, one would learn in the course of half a year something very different from this game of hide-and-seek on the lecture platform. There is no special difficulty connected with being an<space/><link><target>idealist</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>imagination</target></link>; but to exist as an idealist is an extremely strenuous task, because existence itself constitutes a hindrance and an objection. To express existentially what one has understood about oneself, and in this manner to understand oneself, is in no way comical. But to understand everything except ones own self is very comical.&quot; Soren Kierkegaard,<space/><italics>Concluding Unscientific Postscript to Philosophical Fragments</italics><space/>1846 p. 315-316 translated by David F. Swenson and Walter Lowrie 1941 Fifth Printing Princeton University Press</extension></extension><space/>He proposed that each individualnot society or religionis solely responsible for giving<space/><link><target>Meaning (existential)</target><part>meaning</part></link><space/>to life and living it<space/><link><target>Authenticity (philosophy)</target><part>passionately and sincerely (&quot;authentically&quot;)</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Watts, Michael.<space/><italics>Kierkegaard</italics><space/>(Oneworld, 2003, pp.4-6).</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lowrie, Walter.<space/><italics>Kierkegaard's attack upon &quot;Christendom&quot;</italics><space/>(Princeton, 1969, pp. 37-40).</extension><space/>Existentialism became popular in the years following<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, and strongly influenced many disciplines besides philosophy, including theology, drama, art, literature, and psychology.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/?id</arg><arg name="last">Guignon and Pereboom, Derk<space/></arg><arg name="first">Charles B.<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existentialism: basic writings<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hackett Publishing<space/></arg><arg name="year">2001<space/></arg><arg name="page">xiii<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9780872205956</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Definitional issues and background</heading><paragraph>There has never been general agreement on the definition of existentialism. The term is often seen as a historical convenience as it was first applied to many philosophers in hindsight, long after they had died. In fact, while existentialism is generally considered to have originated with Kierkegaard, the first prominent existentialist philosopher to adopt the term as a self-description was<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link>. Sartre posits the idea that &quot;what all existentialists have in common is the fundamental doctrine that existence precedes essence&quot;, as scholar<space/><link><target>Frederick Copleston</target></link><space/>explains.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title"><space/>Existentialism<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>F.C.<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Copleston<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>23<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>84<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>19–37<space/></arg><arg name="jstor"><space/>4544850<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1017/S0031819100065955<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009</arg></template></extension><space/>According to philosopher<space/><link><target>Steven Crowell</target></link>, defining existentialism has been relatively difficult, and he argues that it is better<space/><link><target>understanding</target><part>understood</part></link><space/>as a general approach used to reject certain systematic philosophies rather than as a systematic philosophy itself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crowell-SEoP"></extension><space/>Sartre himself, in a lecture delivered in 1945, described existentialism as &quot;the attempt to draw all the consequences from a position of consistent atheism.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>See<space/><link><target>James Wood (critic)</target><part>James Wood</part></link>'s introduction to<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>Sartre<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Jean-Paul<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nausea<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Penguin Classics]]<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-141-18549-1<space/></arg></template><space/>Quote on p.&amp;nbsp;<link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=CGbBbtDOZbwC&amp;amp;pg=PT5'>vii</link>.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although many outside Scandinavia consider the term existentialism to have originated from Kierkegaard himself, it is more likely that Kierkegaard adopted this term (or at least the term &quot;existential&quot; as a description of his philosophy) from the Norwegian poet and literary critic<space/><link><target>Johan Sebastian Cammermeyer Welhaven</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tidsskrift for Norsk Psykologforening, Vol 45, nummer 10, 2008, side 1298-1304,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.psykologtidsskriftet.no/index.php?seks_id=61613&amp;amp;a=2'>Welhaven og psykologien: Del 2. Welhaven peker fremover</link><space/>(in Norwegian)</extension><space/>This assertion comes from two sources. The Norwegian philosopher<space/><link><target>Erik Lundestad</target></link><space/>refers to the Danish philosopher<space/><link><target>Fredrik Christian Sibbern</target></link>. Sibbern is supposed to have had two conversations in 1841, the first with Welhaven and the second with Kierkegaard. It is in the first conversation that it is believed that Welhaven came up with &quot;a word that he said covered a certain thinking, which had a close and positive attitude to life, a relationship he described as existential&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lundestad, 1998, pp. 169</extension><space/>This was then brought to Kierkegaard by Sibbern.</paragraph><paragraph>The second claim comes from the Norwegian historian<space/><link><target>Rune Slagstad</target></link>, who claims to prove that Kierkegaard himself said the term &quot;existential&quot; was borrowed from the poet. He strongly believes that it was Kierkegaard himself who said that &quot;<link><target>Hegelianism</target><part>Hegelians</part></link><space/>do not study philosophy 'existentially'; to use a phrase by Welhaven from one time when I spoke with him about philosophy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Slagstad, 2001, p 89</extension><space/>On the other hand, the Norwegian historian<space/><link><target>Anne-Lise Seip</target></link><space/>is critical of Slagstad, and believes the statement in fact stems from the Norwegian literary historian<space/><link><target>Cathrinus Bang</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Seip, 2007, p 352</extension></paragraph><paragraph>There also exists the belief that meaninglessness and absurdity create a behavior pattern that is not consistent with that which is considered &quot;normal&quot;. In other words, existentialism &quot;jars you out of your habits.&quot; Like war, sexual disease, and the like, the individual consciousness is paramount to the societal impact one may have and it is your reality that dictates your actions, not anybody else's.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Concepts</heading><heading level='3'>Existence precedes essence</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Existence precedes essence</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A central proposition of Existentialism is that<space/><italics>existence precedes<space/><link><target>essence</target></link></italics>, which means that the most important consideration for individuals is that they are individualsindependently acting and responsible, conscious beings (&quot;existence&quot;)rather than what labels, roles, stereotypes, definitions, or other preconceived categories the individuals fit (&quot;essence&quot;). The actual life of the individuals is what constitutes what could be called their &quot;true essence&quot; instead of there being an arbitrarily attributed essence others use to define them. Thus, human beings, through their own<space/><link><target>consciousness</target></link>, create their own values and determine a meaning to their life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>fr icon</target></template><space/>(Dictionary) &quot;L'existencialisme&quot; - see &quot;l'identit de la personne&quot;</extension><space/>Although it was Sartre who explicitly coined the phrase, similar notions can be found in the thought of existentialist philosophers such as<space/><link><target>Heidegger</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Kierkegaard</target></link>:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Quotation</target><arg>"The subjective ''thinker’s form'', the form of his communication, is his ''style''. His form must be just as manifold as are the opposites that he holds together. The systematic ''eins, zwei, drei'' is an abstract form that also must inevitably run into trouble whenever it is to be applied to the concrete. To the same degree as the subjective thinker is concrete, to the same degree his form must also be concretely dialectical. But just as he himself is not a poet, not an ethicist, not a dialectician, so also his form is none of these directly. His form must first and last be related to existence, and in this regard he must have at his disposal the poetic, the ethical, the dialectical, the religious. Subordinate character, setting, etc., which belong to the well balanced character of the esthetic production, are in themselves breadth; the subjective thinker has only one setting—existence—and has nothing to do with localities and such things. The setting is not the fairyland of the imagination, where poetry produces consummation, nor is the setting laid in England, and historical accuracy is not a concern. The setting is inwardness in existing as a human being; the concretion is the relation of the existence-categories to one another. Historical accuracy and historical actuality are breadth." Søren Kierkegaard (Concluding Postscript, Hong p. 357–358)</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It is often claimed in this context that people define themselves, which is often perceived as stating that they can wish to be somethinganything, a bird, for instanceand then be it. According to most existentialist philosophers, however, this would constitute an inauthentic existence. Instead, the phrase should be taken to say that people are (1) defined only insofar as they act and (2) that they are responsible for their actions. For example, someone who acts cruelly towards other people is, by that act, defined as a cruel person. Furthermore, by this action of cruelty, such persons are themselves responsible for their new identity (cruel persons). This is as opposed to their genes, or<space/><italics>human nature</italics>, bearing the blame.</paragraph><paragraph>As Sartre writes in his work<space/><italics><link><target>Existentialism is a Humanism</target></link></italics>: &quot;... man first of all exists, encounters himself, surges up in the worldand defines himself afterwards.&quot; Of course, the more positive, therapeutic aspect of this is also implied: A person can choose to act in a different way, and to be a good person instead of a cruel person. Here it is also clear that since humans can choose to be either cruel or good, they are, in fact, neither of these things essentially.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Baird<space/></arg><arg name="first">Forrest E.<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/></arg><arg name="author2">Walter Kaufmann<space/></arg><arg name="title">From Plato to Derrida<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Pearson Prentice Hall<space/></arg><arg name="year">2008<space/></arg><arg name="location">Upper Saddle River, New Jersey<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-13-158591-6</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The Absurd</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Absurdism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The notion of the Absurd contains the idea that there is no meaning in the world beyond what meaning we give it. This meaninglessness also encompasses the amorality or &quot;unfairness&quot; of the world. This contrasts with the notion that &quot;bad things don't happen to good people&quot;; to the world, metaphorically speaking, there is no such thing as a good person or a bad person; what happens happens, and it may just as well happen to a &quot;good&quot; person as to a &quot;bad&quot; person.<extension extension_name='ref' name="plato.stanford.edu">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#AnxNotAbs'>3.1 Anxiety, Nothingness, the Absurd</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Because of the world's absurdity, at any point in time, anything can happen to anyone, and a tragic event could plummet someone into direct confrontation with the Absurd. The notion of the Absurd has been prominent in literature throughout history. Many of the literary works of<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Samuel Beckett</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franz Kafka</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoyevsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Eugne Ionesco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Luigi Pirandello</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="luigitheatre"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Bassnett</arg><arg name="first1">Susan</arg><arg name="last2">Lorch</arg><arg name="first2">Jennifer</arg><arg name="title">Luigi Pirandello in the Theatre</arg><arg name="date">March 18, 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="understandex"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Thompson</arg><arg name="first1">Mel</arg><arg name="last2">Rodgers</arg><arg name="first2">Nigel</arg><arg name="title">Understanding Existentialism: Teach Yourself</arg><arg name="date">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Hodder & Stoughton</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="crisisconsciousness"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Caputi</arg><arg name="first1">Anthony Francis</arg><arg name="title">Pirandello and the Crisis of Modern Consciousness</arg><arg name="date">1988</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Illinois Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="masks"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Mariani</arg><arg name="first1">Umberto</arg><arg name="title">Living Masks: The Achievement of Pirandello</arg><arg name="date">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Toronto Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Joseph Heller</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target></link><space/>contain descriptions of people who encounter the absurdity of the world.</paragraph><paragraph>It is in relation to the concept of the devastating awareness of meaninglessness that Albert Camus claimed that &quot;there is only one truly serious philosophical problem, and that is suicide&quot; in his<space/><italics><link><target>The Myth of Sisyphus</target></link></italics>. Although &quot;prescriptions&quot; against the possibly deleterious consequences of these kinds of encounters vary, from Kierkegaard's religious &quot;stage&quot; to Camus' insistence on persevering in spite of absurdity, the concern with helping people avoid living their lives in ways that put them in the perpetual danger of having everything meaningful break down is common to most existentialist philosophers. The possibility of having everything meaningful break down poses a threat of<space/><link><target>Quietism (philosophy)</target><part>quietism</part></link>, which is inherently against the existentialist philosophy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Jean-Paul Sartre<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/sartre/works/exist/sartre.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existentialism is a Humanism, Jean-Paul Sartre 1946<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Marxists.org<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-03-08</arg></template></extension><space/>It has been said that the possibility of suicide makes all humans existentialists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title">Suicide and Self-Deception</arg><arg name="author">E Keen</arg><arg name="publisher">Psychoanalytic Review</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="url">http://www.pep-web.org/document.php?id</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Facticity</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Facticity</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Facticity is a concept defined by Sartre in<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Nothingness</target></link></italics><space/>as the<space/><italics><link><target>being-in-itself</target><part>in-itself</part></link></italics>, of which humans are in the mode of not being. This can be more easily understood when considering it in relation to the temporal dimension of past: one's past is what one is, in the sense that it co-constitutes oneself. However, to say that one is only one's past would be to ignore a significant part of reality (the present and the future), while saying that one's past is only what one was, would entirely detach it from oneself now. A denial of one's own concrete past constitutes an inauthentic lifestyle, and the same goes for all other kinds of facticity (having a bodye.g. one that doesn't allow a person to run faster than the speed of soundidentity, values, etc.).<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#FacTra'>2.1 Facticity and Transcendence</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Facticity is both a limitation and a condition of freedom. It is a limitation in that a large part of one's facticity consists of things one couldn't have chosen (birthplace, etc.), but a condition in the sense that one's values most likely depend on it. However, even though one's facticity is &quot;set in stone&quot; (as being past, for instance), it cannot determine a person: The value ascribed to one's facticity is still ascribed to it freely by that person. As an example, consider two men, one of whom has no memory of his past and the other remembers everything. They have both committed many crimes, but the first man, knowing nothing about this, leads a rather normal life while the second man, feeling trapped by his own past, continues a life of crime, blaming his own past for &quot;trapping&quot; him in this life. There is nothing essential about his committing crimes, but he ascribes this meaning to his past.</paragraph><paragraph>However, to disregard one's facticity when, in the continual process of self-making, one projects oneself into the future, that would be to put oneself in denial of oneself, and would thus be inauthentic. In other words, the origin of one's projection must still be one's facticity, though in the mode of not being it (essentially). Another aspect of facticity is that it entails<space/><link><target>angst</target></link>, both in the sense that freedom &quot;produces&quot; angst when limited by facticity, and in the sense that the lack of the possibility of having facticity to &quot;step in&quot; for one to take responsibility for something one has done also produces angst.</paragraph><paragraph>Another aspect of existential freedom is that one can change one's values. Thus, one is responsible for one's values, regardless of society's values. The focus on freedom in existentialism is related to the limits of the responsibility one bears as a result of one's freedom: the relationship between freedom and responsibility is one of interdependency, and a clarification of freedom also clarifies that for which one is responsible.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#FreVal'>3. Freedom and Value</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#IdeVal'>3.2 The Ideality of Values</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authenticity</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Authenticity (philosophy)</arg><arg name="l1">Authenticity</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Many noted existentialist writers consider the theme of authentic existence important. Authentic existence involves the idea that one has to &quot;create oneself&quot; and then live in accordance with this self. What is meant by<space/><link><target>authenticity (philosophy)</target><part>authenticity</part></link><space/>is that in acting, one should act as oneself, not as &quot;one&quot; acts or as &quot;one's genes&quot; or any other essence requires. The authentic act is one that is in accordance with one's freedom. Of course, as a condition of freedom is facticity, this includes one's facticity, but not to the degree that this facticity can in any way determine one's choices (in the sense that one could then blame one's background for making the choice one made). The role of facticity in relation to authenticity involves letting one's actual values come into play when one makes a choice (instead of, like Kierkegaard's Aesthete, &quot;choosing&quot; randomly), so that one also takes responsibility for the act instead of choosing either-or without allowing the options to have different values.<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#Aut'>2.3 Authenticity</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast to this, the inauthentic is the denial to live in accordance with one's freedom. This can take many forms, from pretending choices are meaningless or random, through convincing oneself that some form of<space/><link><target>determinism</target></link><space/>is true, to a sort of &quot;mimicry&quot; where one acts as &quot;one should.&quot; How &quot;one&quot; should act is often determined by an image one has of how one such as oneself (say, a bank manager, lion tamer, prostitute, etc.) acts. This image usually corresponds to some sort of social norm, but this does not mean that all acting in accordance with social norms is inauthentic: The main point is the attitude one takes to one's own freedom and responsibility, and the extent to which one acts in accordance with this freedom.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The Other and the Look</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Other</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The Other (when written with a capital &quot;O&quot;) is a concept more properly belonging to<space/><link><target>phenomenology (philosophy)</target><part>phenomenology</part></link><space/>and its account of<space/><link><target>intersubjectivity</target></link>. However, the concept has seen widespread use in existentialist writings, and the conclusions drawn from it differ slightly from the phenomenological accounts. The experience of the Other is the experience of another free subject who inhabits the same world as a person does. In its most basic form, it is this experience of the Other that constitutes intersubjectivity and objectivity. To clarify, when one experiences someone else, and this Other person experiences the world (the same world that a person experiences)--only from &quot;over there&quot;the world itself is constituted as objective in that it is something that is &quot;there&quot; as identical for both of the subjects; a person experiences the other person as experiencing the same things. This experience of the Other's look is what is termed the Look (sometimes the<space/><link><target>The Gaze</target><part>Gaze</part></link>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy, Existentialism,<space/><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/existentialism/#Ali'>2.2 Alienation</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>While this experience, in its basic phenomenological sense, constitutes the world as objective, and oneself as objectively existing subjectivity (one experiences oneself as seen in the Other's Look in precisely the same way that one experiences the Other as seen by him, as subjectivity), in existentialism, it also acts as a kind of limitation of freedom. This is because the Look tends to objectify what it sees. As such, when one experiences oneself in the Look, one doesn't experience oneself as nothing (no thing), but as something. Sartre's own example of a man peeping at someone through a keyhole can help clarify this: at first, this man is entirely caught up in the situation he is in; he is in a pre-reflexive state where his entire consciousness is directed at what goes on in the room. Suddenly, he hears a creaking floorboard behind him, and he becomes aware of himself as seen by the Other. He is thus filled with shame for he perceives himself as he would perceive someone else doing what he was doing, as a Peeping Tom. The Look is then co-constitutive of one's facticity.</paragraph><paragraph>Another characteristic feature of the Look is that no Other really needs to have been there: It is quite possible that the creaking floorboard was nothing but the movement of an old house; the Look isn't some kind of mystical telepathic experience of the actual way the other sees one (there may also have been someone there, but he could have not noticed that the person was there). It is only one's perception of the way another might perceive him.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Angst and Dread</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Angst</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Living educational theory</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>&quot;Existential<space/><link><target>angst</target></link>&quot;, sometimes called dread, anxiety, or<space/><link><target>anguish</target></link>, is a term that is common to many existentialist thinkers. It is generally held to be a negative feeling arising from the experience of human freedom and responsibility. The archetypal example is the experience one has when standing on a cliff where one not only fears falling off it, but also dreads the possibility of throwing oneself off. In this experience that &quot;nothing is holding me back&quot;, one senses the lack of anything that predetermines one to either throw oneself off or to stand still, and one experiences one's own freedom.<extension extension_name='ref' name="plato.stanford.edu"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>It can also be seen in relation to the previous point how angst is before nothing, and this is what sets it apart from fear that has an object. While in the case of fear, one can take definitive measures to remove the object of fear, in the case of angst, no such &quot;constructive&quot; measures are possible. The use of the word &quot;nothing&quot; in this context relates both to the inherent insecurity about the consequences of one's actions, and to the fact that, in experiencing freedom as angst, one also realizes that one is fully responsible for these consequences. There is nothing in people (genetically, for instance) that acts in their steadthat they can blame if something goes wrong. Therefore, not every choice is perceived as having dreadful possible consequences (and, it can be claimed, human lives would be unbearable if every choice facilitated dread). However, this doesn't change the fact that freedom remains a condition of every action.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Despair</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Philosophy of Søren Kierkegaard#Despair</arg><arg name="l1">Despair</arg></template><template><target>See also</target><arg>Existential crisis</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Despair, in existentialism, is generally defined as a loss of hope.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.tfd.com/despair<space/></arg><arg name="title">despair - definition of despair by the Free Online Dictionary, Thesaurus and Encyclopedia<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Tfd.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-03-08</arg></template></extension><space/>More specifically, it is a loss of hope in reaction to a breakdown in one or more of the defining qualities of one's self or identity. If a person is invested in being a particular thing, such as a bus driver or an upstanding citizen, and then finds his being-thing compromised, he would normally be found in state of despair a hopeless state. For example, a singer who loses the ability to sing may despair if she has nothing else to fall back onnothing to rely on for her identity. She finds herself unable to be what defined her being.</paragraph><paragraph>What sets the existentialist notion of despair apart from the conventional definition is that existentialist despair is a state one is in even when he isn't overtly in despair. So long as a person's identity depends on qualities that can crumble, he is in perpetual despairand as there is, in Sartrean terms, no human essence found in conventional reality on which to constitute the individual's sense of identity, despair is a universal human condition. As Kierkegaard defines it in<space/><italics><link><target>Either/Or</target></link></italics>: &quot;Let each one learn what he can; both of us can learn that a persons unhappiness never lies in his lack of control over external conditions, since this would only make him completely unhappy.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Either/Or Part II p. 188 Hong</extension><space/>In<space/><italics><link><target>Works of Love</target></link></italics>, he said:<space/><template><target>Quotation</target><arg>When the God-forsaken worldliness of earthly life shuts itself in complacency, the confined air develops poison, the moment gets stuck and stands still, the prospect is lost, a need is felt for a refreshing, enlivening breeze to cleanse the air and dispel the poisonous vapors lest we suffocate in worldliness. ... Lovingly to hope all things is the opposite of despairingly to hope [[nothing]] at all. Love hopes all things – yet is never put to shame. To relate oneself expectantly to the possibility of the good is to hope. To relate oneself expectantly to the possibility of evil is to fear. By the decision to choose hope one decides infinitely more than it seems, because it is an eternal decision. p. 246-250</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Opposition to positivism and rationalism</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Positivism</arg><arg>Rationalism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Existentialists oppose definitions of human beings as primarily rational, and, therefore, oppose<space/><link><target>positivism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>rationalism</target></link>. Existentialism asserts that people actually make decisions based on subjective meaning rather than pure rationality. The rejection of reason as the source of meaning is a common theme of existentialist thought, as is the focus on the feelings of<space/><link><target>anxiety</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>angst</target><part>dread</part></link><space/>that we feel in the face of our own radical<space/><link><target>free will</target><part>freedom</part></link><space/>and our awareness of death. Kierkegaard advocated rationality as means to interact with the objective world (e.g. in the natural sciences), but when it comes to existential problems, reason is insufficient: &quot;Human reason has boundaries&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Sren Kierkegaard's Journals and Papers</italics><space/>Vol 5, p. 5</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Like Kierkegaard, Sartre saw problems with rationality, calling it a form of &quot;bad faith&quot;, an attempt by the self to impose structure on a world of phenomena&quot;the Other&quot;that is fundamentally irrational and random. According to Sartre, rationality and other forms of bad faith hinder people from finding meaning in freedom. To try to suppress their feelings of anxiety and dread, people confine themselves within everyday experience, Sartre asserts, thereby relinquishing their freedom and acquiescing to being possessed in one form or another by &quot;the Look&quot; of &quot;the Other&quot; (i.e. possessed by another personor at least one's idea of that other person).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Existentialism and religion</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Atheistic existentialism</arg><arg>Christian existentialism</arg><arg>Jewish existentialism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An existentialist reading of the Bible would demand that the reader recognize that he is an existing<space/><link><target>subject (philosophy)</target><part>subject</part></link><space/>studying the words more as a recollection of events. This is in contrast to looking at a collection of &quot;truths&quot; that are outside and unrelated to the reader, but may develop a sense of reality/God. Such a reader is not obligated to follow the commandments as if an external agent is forcing them upon him, but as though they are inside him and guiding him from inside. This is the task Kierkegaard takes up when he asks: &quot;Who has the more difficult task: the teacher who lectures on earnest things a meteor's distance from everyday life-or the learner who should put it to use?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kierkegaard, Soren.<space/><italics>Works of Love</italics>. Harper &amp; Row, Publishers. New York, N.Y. 1962. p. 62</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Existentialism and nihilism</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Existential nihilism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>nihilism</target></link><space/>and existentialism are distinct philosophies, they are often confused with one another. A primary cause of confusion is that<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link><space/>is an important philosopher in both fields, but also the existentialist insistence on the inherent meaninglessness of the world. Existentialist philosophers often stress the importance of<space/><link><target>Angst</target></link><space/>as signifying the absolute lack of any objective ground for action, a move that is often reduced to a<space/><link><target>Moral nihilism</target><part>moral</part></link><space/>or an<space/><link><target>existential nihilism</target></link>. A pervasive theme in the works of existentialist philosophy, however, is to persist through encounters with the absurd, as seen in<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target><part>Camus</part></link>'<space/><italics>The Myth of Sisyphus</italics><space/>(&quot;One must imagine Sisyphus happy&quot;),<extension extension_name='ref'>Camus, Albert. &quot;The Myth of Sisyphus&quot;.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nyu.edu/classes/keefer/hell/camus.html'>NYU.edu</link></extension><space/>and it is only very rarely that existentialist philosophers dismiss morality or one's self-created meaning: Kierkegaard regained a sort of morality in the religious (although he wouldn't himself agree that it was ethical; the religious suspends the ethical), and<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target><part>Sartre</part></link>'s final words in<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Nothingness</target></link></italics><space/>are &quot;All these questions, which refer us to a pure and not an accessory (or impure) reflection, can find their reply only on the ethical plane. We shall devote to them a future work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Jean-Paul Sartre,<space/><italics>Being and Nothingness</italics>, Routledge Classics (2003).</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;existentialism&quot; was coined by the French Catholic philosopher<space/><link><target>Gabriel Marcel</target></link><space/>in the mid-1940s.<extension extension_name='ref'>D.E. Cooper<space/><italics>Existentialism: A Reconstruction</italics><space/>(Basil Blackwell, 1990, page 1)</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Thomas R. Flynn 2006, page 89">Thomas R. Flynn,<space/><italics>Existentialism: A Very Short Introduction</italics><space/>(Oxford University Press), 2006, page 89</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Christine Daigle 2006, page 5">Christine Daigle,<space/><italics>Existentialist Thinkers and Ethics</italics><space/>(McGill-Queen's press, 2006, page 5)</extension><space/>At first, when Marcel applied the term to him at a colloquium in 1945,<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>rejected it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ann Fulton, Apostles of Sartre: Existentialism in America, 1945-1963 (Evanston, IL: Northwestern University Press, 1999) 18-19.</extension><space/>Sartre subsequently changed his mind and, on October 29, 1945, publicly adopted the existentialist label in a lecture to the<space/><italics>Club Maintenant</italics><space/>in Paris. The lecture was published as<space/><italics><link><target>L'existentialisme est un humanisme</target></link></italics><space/>(<link><target>Existentialism is a Humanism</target></link>), a short book that did much to popularize existentialist thought.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>L'Existentialisme est un Humanisme</italics><space/>(Editions Nagel, 1946);<space/><italics>English</italics><space/>Jean-Paul Sartre,<space/><italics>Existentialism and Humanism</italics><space/>(Eyre Methuen, 1948)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some scholars argue that the term should be used only to refer to the cultural movement in Europe in the 1940s and 1950s associated with the works of the philosophers<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Simone de Beauvoir</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Maurice Merleau-Ponty</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crowell-SEoP"></extension><space/>Other scholars extend the term to Kierkegaard, and yet others extend it as far back as<space/><link><target>Socrates</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Crowell, Steven.<space/><italics>The Cambridge Companion to Existentialism</italics>, Cambridge, 2011, p. 316.</extension><space/>However, the term is often identified with the philosophical views of Jean-Paul Sartre.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Crowell-SEoP"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>19th century</heading><heading level='4'>Kierkegaard and Nietzsche</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Søren Kierkegaard and Friedrich Nietzsche</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link><space/>were two of the first philosophers considered fundamental to the existentialist movement, though neither used the term &quot;existentialism&quot; and it is unclear whether they would have supported the existentialism of the 20th century. They focused on subjective human experience rather than the objective truths of mathematics and science, which they believed were too detached or observational to truly get at the human experience. Like<space/><link><target>Blaise Pascal</target><part>Pascal</part></link>, they were interested in people's quiet struggle with the apparent meaninglessness of life and the use of diversion to escape from boredom. Unlike Pascal, Kierkegaard and Nietzsche also considered the role of making free choices, particularly regarding fundamental values and beliefs, and how such choices change the nature and identity of the chooser.<extension extension_name='ref'>Luper, Steven. &quot;Existing&quot;. Mayfield Publishing, 2000, p.45 and 11</extension><space/>Kierkegaard's<space/><link><target>knight of faith</target></link><space/>and Nietzsche's<space/><link><target>bermensch</target></link><space/>are representative of people who exhibit<space/><link><target>Free will</target><part>Freedom</part></link>, in that they define the nature of their own existence. Nietzsche's idealized individual invents his own values and creates the very terms they excel under. By contrast, Kierkegaard, opposed to the level of abstraction in Hegel, and not nearly as hostile (actually welcoming) to Christianity as Nietzsche, argues through a pseudonym that the objective certainty of religious truths (specifically Christian) is not only impossible, but even founded on logical paradoxes. Yet he continues to imply that a<space/><link><target>leap of faith</target></link><space/>is a possible means for an individual to reach a higher stage of existence that transcends and contains both an aesthetic and ethical value of life. Kierkegaard and Nietzsche were also precursors to other intellectual movements, including<space/><link><target>postmodernism</target></link>, and various strands of<space/><link><target>psychology</target></link>. However, Kierkegaard believed that individuals should live in accordance with their thinking.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Dostoyevsky</heading><paragraph>The first important literary author also important to existentialism was the Russian<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoyevsky</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hubben, William.<space/><italics>Dostoyevsky, Kierkegaard, Nietzsche and Kafka, Jabber-wacky</italics>, Scribner, 1997.</extension><space/>Dostoyevsky's<space/><italics><link><target>Notes from Underground</target></link></italics><space/>portrays a man unable to fit into society and unhappy with the identities he creates for himself.<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link>, in his book on existentialism<space/><italics><link><target>Existentialism is a Humanism</target></link></italics>, quoted Dostoyevsky's<space/><italics><link><target>The Brothers Karamazov</target></link></italics><space/>as an example of<space/><link><target>existential crisis</target></link>. Sartre attributes Ivan Karamazov's claim, &quot;If God did not exist, everything would be permitted&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Sartre, Jean-Paul.<space/><italics>Existentialism is a Humanism</italics><space/>http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/sartre/works/exist/sartre.htm ; Retrieved 2012-04-01.</extension><space/>to Dostoyevsky himself, though this quote does not appear in the novel.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.egs.edu/faculty/slavoj-zizek/articles/if-there-is-a-god-then-anything-is-permitted/</arg><arg name="author">Zizek, Slavoj</arg><arg name="title">If there is a God, then everything is permitted</arg></template></extension><space/>However, a similar sentiment is explicitly stated when Alyosha visits Dimitri in prison. Dimitri mentions his conversations with Rakitin in which the idea that &quot;Then, if He doesn't exist, man is king of the earth, of the universe&quot; allowing the inference contained in Sartre's attribution to remain a valid idea contested within the novel.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dostoyevsky Fyodor. &quot;<link><target>The Brothers Karamazov</target></link>&quot;.</extension><space/>Other Dostoyevsky novels covered issues raised in existentialist philosophy while presenting story lines divergent from secular existentialism: for example, in<space/><italics><link><target>Crime and Punishment</target></link></italics>, the protagonist Raskolnikov experiences an existential crisis and then moves toward a Christian Orthodox worldview similar to that advocated by Dostoyevsky himself.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early 20th century</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Martin Heidegger</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the first decades of the 20th century, a number of philosophers and writers explored existentialist ideas. The Spanish philosopher<space/><link><target>Miguel de Unamuno y Jugo</target></link>, in his 1913 book<space/><italics>The Tragic Sense of Life in Men and Nations</italics>, emphasized the life of &quot;flesh and bone&quot; as opposed to that of abstract rationalism. Unamuno rejected systematic philosophy in favor of the individual's quest for faith. He retained a sense of the tragic, even absurd nature of the quest, symbolized by his enduring interest in<space/><link><target>Cervantes</target></link>' fictional character<space/><link><target>Don Quixote</target></link>. A novelist, poet and dramatist as well as philosophy professor at the University of Salamanca, Unamuno wrote a short story about a priest's crisis of faith,<space/><italics><link><target>San Manuel Bueno, Mrtir</target><part>Saint Manuel the Good, Martyr</part></link></italics>, which has been collected in anthologies of existentialist fiction. Another Spanish thinker,<space/><link><target>Ortega y Gasset</target></link>, writing in 1914, held that human existence must always be defined as the individual person combined with the concrete circumstances of his life: &quot;<italics>Yo soy yo y mi circunstancia</italics>&quot; (&quot;I am myself and my circumstances&quot;). Sartre likewise believed that human existence is not an abstract matter, but is always situated (&quot;<italics>en situation</italics>&quot;).</paragraph><paragraph>Although<space/><link><target>Martin Buber</target></link><space/>wrote his major philosophical works in German, and studied and taught at the Universities of Berlin and<space/><link><target>Frankfurt</target></link>, he stands apart from the mainstream of German philosophy. Born into a Jewish family in Vienna in 1878, he was also a scholar of Jewish culture and involved at various times in<space/><link><target>Zionism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hasidism</target></link>. In 1938, he moved permanently to<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link>. His best-known philosophical work was the short book<space/><italics><link><target>I and Thou</target></link></italics>, published in 1922. For Buber, the fundamental fact of human existence, too readily overlooked by scientific rationalism and abstract philosophical thought, is &quot;man with man&quot;, a dialogue that takes place in the so-called &quot;sphere of between&quot; (<italics>&quot;das Zwischenmenschliche&quot;</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Maurice S. Friedman,<space/><italics>Martin Buber. The Life of Dialogue</italics><space/>(University of Chicago press, 1955, page 85)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Two Ukrainian/Russian thinkers,<space/><link><target>Lev Shestov</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nikolai Berdyaev</target></link>, became well known as existentialist thinkers during their post-Revolutionary exiles in Paris. Shestov, born into a Ukrainian-Jewish family in Kiev, had launched an attack on rationalism and systematization in philosophy as early as 1905 in his book of aphorisms<space/><italics>All Things Are Possible</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Berdyaev, also from Kiev but with a background in the Eastern Orthodox Church, drew a radical distinction between the world of spirit and the everyday world of objects. Human freedom, for Berdyaev, is rooted in the realm of spirit, a realm independent of scientific notions of causation. To the extent the individual human being lives in the objective world, he is estranged from authentic spiritual freedom. &quot;Man&quot; is not to be interpreted naturalistically, but as a being created in God's image, an originator of free, creative acts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ernst Breisach,<space/><italics>Introduction to Modern Existentialism</italics>, New York (1962), pages 173176</extension><space/>He published a major work on these themes,<space/><italics>The Destiny of Man</italics>, in 1931.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gabriel Marcel</target></link>, long before coining the term &quot;existentialism&quot;, introduced important existentialist themes to a French audience in his early essay &quot;Existence and Objectivity&quot; (1925) and in his<space/><italics>Metaphysical Journal</italics><space/>(1927).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Samuel M. Keen 1967">Samuel M. Keen, &quot;Gabriel Marcel&quot; in Paul Edwards (ed.)<space/><italics>The Encyclopaedia of Philosophy</italics><space/>(Macmillan Publishing Co, 1967)</extension><space/>A dramatist as well as a philosopher, Marcel found his philosophical starting point in a condition of metaphysical alienation: the human individual searching for harmony in a transient life. Harmony, for Marcel, was to be sought through &quot;secondary reflection&quot;, a &quot;dialogical&quot; rather than &quot;dialectical&quot; approach to the world, characterized by &quot;wonder and astonishment&quot; and open to the &quot;presence&quot; of other people and of God rather than merely to &quot;information&quot; about them. For Marcel, such presence implied more than simply being there (as one thing might be in the presence of another thing); it connoted &quot;extravagant&quot; availability, and the willingness to put oneself at the disposal of the other.<extension extension_name='ref'>John Macquarrie,<space/><italics>Existentialism</italics><space/>(Pelican, 1973, page 110)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Marcel contrasted<space/><italics>secondary reflection</italics><space/>with abstract, scientific-technical<space/><italics>primary reflection</italics>, which he associated with the activity of the abstract<space/><link><target>Ren Descartes</target><part>Cartesian</part></link><space/>ego. For Marcel, philosophy was a concrete activity undertaken by a sensing, feeling human being incarnate embodied in a concrete world.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Samuel M. Keen 1967"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>John Macquarrie,<space/><italics>Existentialism</italics><space/>(Pelican, 1973, page 96)</extension><space/>Although<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>adopted the term &quot;existentialism&quot; for his own philosophy in the 1940s, Marcel's thought has been described as &quot;almost diametrically opposed&quot; to that of Sartre.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Samuel M. Keen 1967"></extension><space/>Unlike Sartre, Marcel was a Christian, and became a Catholic convert in 1929.</paragraph><paragraph>In Germany, the psychologist and philosopher<space/><link><target>Karl Jaspers</target></link><space/>who later described existentialism as a &quot;phantom&quot; created by the public<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Karl Jaspers, &quot;Philosophical Autobiography&quot; in Paul Arthur Schilpp (ed.) ''The Philosophy of Karl Jaspers (The Library of Living Philosophers IX (Tudor Publishing Company, 1957, page 75/11)</extension><space/>called his own thought, heavily influenced by Kierkegaard and Nietzsche,<space/><italics>Existenzphilosophie</italics>. For Jaspers, &quot;<italics>Existenz</italics>-philosophy is the way of thought by means of which man seeks to become himself...This way of thought does not cognize objects, but elucidates and makes actual the being of the thinker.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Karl Jaspers, &quot;Philosophical Autobiography&quot; in Paul Arthur Schilpp (ed.) ''The Philosophy of Karl Jaspers (The Library of Living Philosophers IX (Tudor Publishing Company, 1957, page 40)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Jaspers, a professor at the University of<space/><link><target>Heidelberg</target></link>, was acquainted with<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link>, who held a professorship at<space/><link><target>Marburg</target></link><space/>before acceding to Husserl's chair at<space/><link><target>Freiburg</target></link><space/>in 1928. They held many philosophical discussions, but later became estranged over Heidegger's support of<space/><link><target>Nazism</target><part>National Socialism</part></link>. They shared an admiration for Kierkegaard,<extension extension_name='ref'>Karl Jaspers, &quot;Philosophical Autobiography&quot; in Paul Arthur Schilpp (ed.) ''The Philosophy of Karl Jaspers (The Library of Living Philosophers IX (Tudor Publishing Company, 1957, page 75/2 and following)</extension><space/>and in the 1930s, Heidegger lectured extensively on Nietzsche. Nevertheless, the extent to which Heidegger should be considered an existentialist is debatable. In<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Time</target></link></italics><space/>he presented a method of rooting philosophical explanations in human existence (<italics>Dasein</italics>) to be analysed in terms of existential categories (<italics>existentiale</italics>); and this has led many commentators to treat him as an important figure in the existentialist movement.</paragraph><heading level='3'>After the Second World War</heading><paragraph>Following the<space/><link><target>Second World War</target></link>, existentialism became a well-known and significant philosophical and cultural movement, mainly through the public prominence of two French writers,<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target></link>, who wrote best-selling novels, plays and widely read journalism as well as theoretical texts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Patrick Baert,<space/><italics>The Existentialist Moment; The Rise of Sartre as a Public Intellectual</italics><space/>(Polity Press, 2015)</extension><space/>These years also saw the growing reputation of Heidegger's book<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Time</target></link></italics><space/>outside Germany.<link><target>File:Sartre and de Beauvoir at Balzac Memorial.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>French philosophers<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Simone de Beauvoir</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Sartre dealt with existentialist themes in his 1938 novel<space/><italics><link><target>Nausea (novel)</target><part>Nausea</part></link></italics><space/>and the short stories in his 1939 collection<space/><italics><link><target>The Wall (book)</target><part>The Wall</part></link></italics>, and had published his treatise on existentialism,<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Nothingness</target></link></italics>, in 1943, but it was in the two years following the liberation of Paris from the German occupying forces that he and his close associates Camus, Simone de Beauvoir, Maurice Merleau-Ponty, and others became internationally famous as the leading figures of a movement known as existentialism.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ronald Aronson 2004">Ronald Aronson,<space/><italics>Camus and Sartre</italics><space/>(University of Chicago Press, 2004, chapter 3<space/><italics>passim</italics>)</extension><space/>In a very short space of time, Camus and Sartre in particular became the leading public intellectuals of post-war France, achieving by the end of 1945 &quot;a fame that reached across all audiences.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ronald Aronson,<space/><italics>Camus and Sartre</italics><space/>(University of Chicago Press, 2004, page 44)</extension><space/>Camus was an editor of the most popular leftist (former<space/><link><target>French Resistance</target></link>) newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Combat (newspaper)</target><part>Combat</part></link></italics>; Sartre launched his journal of leftist thought,<space/><italics><link><target>Les Temps Modernes</target></link></italics>, and two weeks later gave the widely reported lecture on existentialism and<space/><link><target>secular humanism</target></link><space/>to a packed meeting of the Club Maintenant. Beauvoir wrote that &quot;not a week passed without the newspapers discussing us&quot;;<extension extension_name='ref'>Simone de Beauvoir,<space/><italics>Force of Circumstance</italics>, quoted in Ronald Aronson,<space/><italics>Camus and Sartre</italics><space/>(University of Chicago Press, 2004, page 48)</extension><space/>existentialism became &quot;the first media craze of the postwar era.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ronald Aronson,<space/><italics>Camus and Sartre</italics><space/>(University of Chicago Press, 2004, page 48)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the end of 1947, Camus' earlier fiction and plays had been reprinted, his new play<space/><italics><link><target>Caligula (play)</target><part>Caligula</part></link></italics><space/>had been performed and his novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Plague</target></link></italics><space/>published; the first two novels of Sartre's<space/><italics><link><target>The Roads to Freedom</target></link></italics><space/>trilogy had appeared, as had Beauvoir's novel<space/><italics><link><target>The Blood of Others</target></link></italics>. Works by Camus and Sartre were already appearing in foreign editions. The Paris-based existentialists had become famous.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ronald Aronson 2004"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sartre had traveled to Germany in 1930 to study the<space/><link><target>phenomenology (philosophy)</target><part>phenomenology</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Edmund Husserl</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Rdiger Safranski,<space/><italics>Martin Heidgger Between Good and Evil</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press, 1998, page 343</extension><space/>and he included critical comments on their work in his major treatise<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Nothingness</target></link></italics>. Heidegger's thought had also become known in French philosophical circles through its use by<space/><link><target>Alexandre Kojve</target></link><space/>in explicating Hegel in a series of lectures given in Paris in the 1930s.<extension extension_name='ref'>Entry on Kojve in Martin Cohen (editor),<space/><italics>The Essentials of Philosophy and Ethics</italics>(Hodder Arnold, 2006, page 158); see also Alexandre Kojve,<space/><italics>Introduction to the Reading of Hegel: Lectures on the Phenomenology of Spirit</italics><space/>(Cornell University Press, 1980)</extension><space/>The lectures were highly influential; members of the audience included not only Sartre and Merleau-Ponty, but<space/><link><target>Raymond Queneau</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Georges Bataille</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Louis Althusser</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andr Breton</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Jacques Lacan</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Entry on Kojve in Martin Cohen (editor),<space/><italics>The Essentials of Philosophy and Ethics</italics>(Hodder Arnold, 2006, page 158)</extension><space/>A selection from Heidegger's<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Time</target></link></italics><space/>was published in French in 1938, and his essays began to appear in French philosophy journals.<link><target>File:Albert Camus, gagnant de prix Nobel, portrait en buste, pos au bureau, faisant face gauche, cigarette de tabagisme.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>French-Algerian philosopher, novelist, and playwright<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Heidegger read Sartre's work and was initially impressed, commenting: &quot;Here for the first time I encountered an independent thinker who, from the foundations up, has experienced the area out of which I think. Your work shows such an immediate comprehension of my philosophy as I have never before encountered.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Martin Hediegger, letter, quoted in Rdiger Safranski,<space/><italics>Martin Heidgger Between Good and Evil</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press, 1998, page 349)</extension><space/>Later, however, in response to a question posed by his French follower<space/><link><target>Jean Beaufret</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Rdiger Safranski,<space/><italics>Martin Heidegger Between Good and Evil</italics><space/>(Harvard University Press, 1998, page 356)</extension><space/>Heidegger distanced himself from Sartre's position and existentialism in general in his<space/><italics>Letter on Humanism</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>William J. Richardson,<space/><italics>Martin Heidegger: From Phenomenology to Thought</italics><space/>(Martjinus Nijhoff,1967, page 351)</extension><space/>Heidegger's reputation continued to grow in France during the 1950s and 1960s. In the 1960s, Sartre attempted to reconcile existentialism and<space/><link><target>Marxism</target></link><space/>in his work<space/><italics><link><target>Critique of Dialectical Reason</target></link></italics>. A major theme throughout his writings was freedom and responsibility.</paragraph><paragraph>Camus was a friend of Sartre, until their falling-out, and wrote several works with existential themes including<space/><italics><link><target>The Rebel (book)</target><part>The Rebel</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics>Summer in Algiers</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Myth of Sisyphus</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>The Stranger (novel)</target><part>The Stranger</part></link></italics>, the latter being &quot;consideredto what would have been Camus's irritationthe exemplary existentialist novel.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Messud<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Claire<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Claire Messud<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>A New 'L'Étranger'<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nybooks.com/articles/archives/2014/jun/05/camus-new-letranger/<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>[[The New York Review of Books]]<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>61<space/></arg><arg name="number"><space/>10<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>1 June 2014<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Camus, like many others, rejected the existentialist label, and considered his works concerned with facing the absurd. In the titular book, Camus uses the analogy of the Greek myth of<space/><link><target>Sisyphus</target></link><space/>to demonstrate the futility of existence. In the myth, Sisyphus is condemned for eternity to roll a rock up a hill, but when he reaches the summit, the rock will roll to the bottom again. Camus believes that this existence is pointless but that Sisyphus ultimately finds meaning and purpose in his task, simply by continually applying himself to it. The first half of the book contains an extended rebuttal of what Camus took to be existentialist philosophy in the works of Kierkegaard, Shestov, Heidegger, and Jaspers.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Simone de Beauvoir</target></link>, an important existentialist who spent much of her life as Sartre's partner, wrote about feminist and existentialist ethics in her works, including<space/><italics><link><target>The Second Sex</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Ethics of Ambiguity</target></link></italics>. Although often overlooked due to her relationship with Sartre,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bergoffen-SEoP"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/beauvoir/</arg><arg name="title">Simone de Beauvoir</arg><arg name="encyclopedia">Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy<space/></arg><arg name="author">Bergoffen, Debra</arg><arg name="date">September 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>de Beauvoir integrated existentialism with other forms of thinking such as feminism, unheard of at the time, resulting in alienation from fellow writers such as Camus.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Paul Tillich</target></link>, an important existentialist theologian following Kierkegaard and<space/><link><target>Karl Barth</target></link>, applied existentialist concepts to<space/><link><target>Christian theology</target></link>, and helped introduce<space/><link><target>neo-orthodoxy</target><part>existential theology</part></link><space/>to the general public. His seminal work<space/><italics>The Courage to Be</italics><space/>follows Kierkegaard's analysis of anxiety and life's absurdity, but puts forward the thesis that modern humans must, via God, achieve selfhood in spite of life's absurdity.<space/><link><target>Rudolf Bultmann</target></link><space/>used Kierkegaard's and Heidegger's philosophy of existence to demythologize Christianity by interpreting Christian mythical concepts into existentialist concepts.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Maurice Merleau-Ponty</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>existential phenomenology</target><part>existential phenomenologist</part></link>, was for a time a companion of Sartre. His understanding of<space/><link><target>Husserl</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>phenomenology (philosophy)</target><part>phenomenology</part></link><space/>was far greater than that of Merleau-Ponty's fellow existentialists.<template><target>vague</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template><space/>It has been said that his work<space/><italics>Humanism and Terror</italics><space/>greatly influenced Sartre. However, in later years they were to disagree irreparably, dividing many existentialists such as de Beauvoir,<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2011</arg></template><space/>who sided with Sartre.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Colin Wilson</target></link>, an English writer, published his study<space/><italics><link><target>The Outsider (Colin Wilson)</target><part>The Outsider</part></link></italics><space/>in 1956, initially to critical acclaim. In this book and others (e.g.<space/><italics>Introduction to the New Existentialism</italics>), he attempted to reinvigorate what he perceived as a pessimistic philosophy and bring it to a wider audience. He was not, however, academically trained, and his work was attacked by professional philosophers for lack of rigor and critical standards.<extension extension_name='ref'>K. Gunnar Bergstrm,<space/><italics>An Odyssey to Freedom</italics><space/>University of Uppsala, 1983, page 92;Colin Stanley,<space/><italics>Colin Wilson, a Celebration: Essays and Recollections</italics><space/>Cecil Woolf, 1988, page 43)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Influence outside philosophy</heading><heading level='3'>Art</heading><heading level='4'>Film and television</heading><paragraph>The French director<space/><link><target>Jean Genet</target></link>'s 1950 fantasy-erotic film<space/><italics><link><target>Un chant d'amour</target></link></italics><space/>shows two inmates in solitary cells whose only contact is through a hole in their cell wall, who are spied on by the prison warden. Reviewer James Travers calls the film a, &quot;...visual poem evoking homosexual desire and existentialist suffering,&quot; which &quot;...&amp;nbsp;conveys the bleakness of an existence in a godless universe with painful believability&quot;; he calls it &quot;...&amp;nbsp;probably the most effective fusion of existentialist philosophy and cinema.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><space/>James Travers 2005<space/><link type='external' href='http://archive.is/20130122234248/http://filmsdefrance.com/FDF_Un_chant_d_amour_rev.html'>google search</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Stanley Kubrick</target></link>'s 1957 anti-war film<space/><italics><link><target>Paths of Glory</target></link></italics><space/>&quot;illustrates, and even illuminates...existentialism&quot; by examining the &quot;necessary absurdity of the human condition&quot; and the &quot;horror of war&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holt2007">Holt, Jason. &quot;Existential Ethics: Where do the Paths of Glory Lead?&quot;. In<space/><italics>The Philosophy of Stanley Kubr</italics>ick. By Jerold J. Abrams. Published 2007. University Press of Kentucky. ISBN 0-8131-2445-X</extension><space/>The film tells the story of a fictional World War I French army regiment ordered to attack an impregnable German stronghold; when the attack fails, three soldiers are chosen at random, court-martialed by a &quot;kangaroo court&quot;, and executed by firing squad. The film examines existentialist ethics, such as the issue of whether objectivity is possible and the &quot;problem of authenticity&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Holt2007"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Orson Welles</target></link>' 1962 film<space/><italics>-<space/><link><target>The_Trial_(1962_film)</target><part>The Trial</part></link></italics><space/>based upon Franz Kafka's book of the same name (Der Process) is characteristic of both existentialist and absurdist themes in its depiction of a man (Joseph K.) arrested for a crime for which the charges are neither revealed to him nor to the reader.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Neon Genesis Evangelion (anime)</target><part>Neon Genesis Evangelion</part></link>, commonly referred to as Evangelion or Eva, is a Japanese science-fiction animation series created by the anime studio Gainax and was both directed and written by<space/><link><target>Hideaki Anno</target></link>. Existential themes of individuality, consciousness, freedom, choice, and responsibility are heavily relied upon throughout the entire series, particularly through the philosophies of<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link>. Episode 16's title,<space/><template><target>Nihongo</target><arg>"The Sickness Unto Death, And…"</arg><arg>死に至る病、そして</arg><arg>Shi ni itaru yamai, soshite</arg></template><space/>is a reference to Kierkegaard's book,<space/><italics><link><target>The Sickness Unto Death</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>On the lighter side, the British comedy troupe<space/><link><target>Monty Python</target></link><space/>have explored existentialist themes throughout their works, from many of the sketches in their original television show,<space/><italics><link><target>Monty Python's Flying Circus</target></link></italics>, to their 1983 film<space/><italics><link><target>Monty Python's The Meaning of Life</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.amazon.com/Films-with-an-Existential-Theme/lm/2XUY93GON1RKW</arg><arg name="title">Amazon.com's Films with an Existential Theme</arg><arg name="accessdate">2009-02-02</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Some contemporary films dealing with existentialist issues include<space/><italics><link><target>Fight Club</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>I Heart Huckabees</target><part>I Huckabees</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Waking Life</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Matrix</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Ordinary People</target></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Life in a Day (2011 film)</target><part>Life in a Day</part></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.existential-therapy.com/Arts/Movies.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existential & Psychological Movie Recommendations<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Existential-therapy.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-03-08</arg></template></extension><space/>Likewise, films throughout the 20th century such as<space/><italics><link><target>The Seventh Seal</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Ikiru</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Taxi Driver</target></link></italics>,<italics><space/><link><target>Toy Story</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Ghost in the Shell (film)</target><part>Ghost in the Shell</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Harold and Maude</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>High Noon</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Easy Rider</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest (film)</target><part>One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>A Clockwork Orange (film)</target><part>A Clockwork Orange</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Groundhog Day (film)</target><part>Groundhog Day</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Apocalypse Now</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Badlands (film)</target><part>Badlands</part></link></italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Blade Runner</target></link></italics><space/>also have existentialist qualities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://uhaweb.hartford.edu/BEAUCHEMI/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existentialism in Film<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Uhaweb.hartford.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-03-08</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>The Matrix</italics><space/>has been compared with another movie,<space/><italics><link><target>Dark City (1998 film)</target><part>Dark City</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.weirdpro.com/?page_id=656</extension><space/>where the issues of identity and reality are raised. In<space/><italics>Dark City</italics>, the inhabitants of the city are situated in a world controlled by<space/><link><target>demiurge</target><trail>s</trail></link>, much like the prisoners in<space/><link><target>Allegory of the Cave</target><part>Plato's cave</part></link>, in which prisoners see a world of shadows reflected onto a cave wall, rather than the world as it actually is.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://jaysanalysis.com/tag/demiurge/</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Musician-Popular Film Artist<space/><link><target>John Lennon</target></link>'s<space/><italics>God</italics><space/>models existentialist ideals. Lennon says, &quot;God is a concept by which we measure our pain...I just believe in me.&quot;</paragraph><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph>Notable directors known for their existentialist films include<space/><link><target>Ingmar Bergman</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franois Truffaut</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean-Luc Godard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Michelangelo Antonioni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Akira Kurosawa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Terrence Malick</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Stanley Kubrick</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andrei Tarkovsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hideaki Anno</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Wes Anderson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Woody Allen</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Christopher Nolan</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://hcl.harvard.edu/hfa/films/2005winter/existential.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Existentialist Adaptations - Harvard Film Archive<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hcl.harvard.edu<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-03-08</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Charlie Kaufman</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Synecdoche, New York</target></link></italics><space/>focuses on the protagonist's desire to find existential meaning.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.latimes.com/entertainment/news/movies/la-et-synecdoche24-2008oct24,0,5252277.story</arg><arg name="title">Review: 'Synecdoche, New York'</arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-11-17<space/></arg><arg name="work">Los Angeles Times<space/></arg><arg name="first">Carina<space/></arg><arg name="last">Chocano<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-10-24</arg></template></extension><space/>Similarly, in Kurosawa's<space/><italics><link><target>Red Beard</target></link></italics>, the protagonist's experiences as an intern in a rural health clinic in Japan lead him to an<space/><link><target>existential crisis</target></link><space/>whereby he questions his reason for being. This, in turn, leads him to a better understanding of humanity.</paragraph><paragraph>Recently released French film,<space/><italics><link><target>Mood Indigo (film)</target><part>Mood Indigo</part></link></italics><space/>(directed by<space/><link><target>Michel Gondry</target></link>) embraced various elements of existentialism.</paragraph><paragraph>The film<space/><italics><link><target>The Shawshank Redemption</target></link></italics>, released in 1994, depicts life in a prison in<space/><link><target>Maine</target></link>,<space/><link><target>USA</target></link><space/>to explore several existentialist concepts.<extension extension_name='ref'>For an examination of the existentialist elements within the film, see<space/><link><target>Philosophy Now</target></link>, issue 102, accessible<space/><link type='external' href='http://philosophynow.org/issues/102/The_Shawshank_Redemption'>here (link)</link>, accessed 3rd June 2014.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Literature</heading><paragraph>Existential perspectives are also found in modern literature to varying degrees, especially since the 1920s.<space/><link><target>Louis-Ferdinand Cline</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Journey to the End of the Night</target></link></italics><space/>(Voyage au bout de la nuit, 1932) celebrated by both Sartre and Beauvoir, contained many of the themes that would be found in later existential literature, and is in some ways, the proto-existential novel. Jean-Paul Sartre's 1938 novel<space/><italics><link><target>Nausea (novel)</target><part>Nausea</part></link></italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="SartreNausea"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="first"><space/>Jean-Paul</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Sartre</arg><arg name="coauthor">(Translated by [[Robert Baldick]])</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nausea</arg><arg name="place"><space/>London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Penguin</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000. First published 1938</arg><arg name="page"><space/></arg><arg name="isbn"></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>was &quot;steeped in Existential ideas&quot;, and is considered an accessible way of grasping his philosophical stance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Earnshaw2006"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Steven</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Earnshaw</arg><arg name="author-link"></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Existentialism: A Guide for the Perplexed</arg><arg name="place"><space/>London</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Continuum</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006</arg><arg name="page"><space/>75</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-8264-8530-8</arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Between 1900 and 1960, other authors such as<space/><link><target>Albert Camus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franz Kafka</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Rainer Maria Rilke</target></link>,<space/><link><target>T.S. Eliot</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Herman Hesse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Luigi Pirandello</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="luigitheatre"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="understandex"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="masks"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="luigip"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Cincotta</arg><arg name="first1">Madeleine Strong</arg><arg name="title">Luigi Pirandello: The Humorous Existentialist</arg><arg name="date">1989</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Wollongong Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="luigi"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Bassanese</arg><arg name="first1">Fiora A.</arg><arg name="title">Understanding Luigi Pirandello</arg><arg name="date">Jan 1, 1997</arg><arg name="publisher">University of South Carolina Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="playwrights"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">DiGaetani</arg><arg name="first1">John Louis</arg><arg name="title">Stages of Struggle: Modern Playwrights and Their Psychological Inspirations</arg><arg name="date">Jan 25, 2008</arg><arg name="publisher">McFarland</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Ralph Ellison</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ellison"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Graham</arg><arg name="first1">Maryemma</arg><arg name="last2">Singh</arg><arg name="first2">Amritjit</arg><arg name="title">Conversations with Ralph Ellison</arg><arg name="date">1995</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Mississippi Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="existentialamerica"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Cotkin</arg><arg name="first1">George</arg><arg name="title">Existential American</arg><arg name="date">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">JHU Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="readinglearning"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Thomas</arg><arg name="first1">Paul Lee</arg><arg name="title">Reading, Learning, Teach Ralph Ellison</arg><arg name="date">2008</arg><arg name="publisher">Peter Lang</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="ellisongenius"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Jackson</arg><arg name="first1">Lawrence Patrick</arg><arg name="title">Ralph Ellison: Emergence of Genius</arg><arg name="date">2007</arg><arg name="publisher">University of Georgia Press</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jack Kerouac</target></link>, composed literature or poetry that contained, to varying degrees, elements of existential or proto-existential thought. The philosophy's influence even reached pulp literature shortly after the turn of the 20th century, as seen in the existential disparity witnessed in Man's lack of control of his fate in the works of<space/><link><target>H.P. Lovecraft</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">https://web.archive.org/web/20141006180224/http://www.horrorreview.com/essay/eglovecraft12008.html</arg><arg name="title">Zarathustra . . . Cthulhu . Meursault: Existential Futility in H.P. Lovecraft’s ‘The Call of Cthulhu’</arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-02-17<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Horror Review<space/></arg><arg name="first">Michael<space/></arg><arg name="last">Gurnow<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-10-15</arg></template></extension><space/>Since the late 1960s, a great deal of cultural activity in literature contains<space/><link><target>postmodernism</target><part>postmodernist</part></link><space/>as well as existential elements. Books such as<space/><italics><link><target>Do Androids Dream of Electric Sheep?</target></link></italics><space/>(1968) (now republished as<space/><italics><link><target>Blade Runner</target></link></italics>) by<space/><link><target>Philip K. Dick</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Slaughterhouse-Five</target></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Kurt Vonnegut</target></link>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Fight Club (novel)</target><part>Fight Club</part></link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Chuck Palahniuk</target></link><space/>all distort the line between reality and appearance while simultaneously espousing existential themes. Ideas from such writers as<space/><link><target>Fyodor Dostoyevsky</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franz Kafka</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Friedrich Nietzsche</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Herbert Marcuse</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gilles Deleuze</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Eduard von Hartmann</target></link><space/>permeate the works of modern novelists such as<space/><link><target>Chuck Palahniuk</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Crispin Glover</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Andrew Hussie</target></link>,<space/><link><target>David Foster Wallace</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Charles Bukowski</target></link>, and one often finds in their works a delicate balance between distastefulness and beauty.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Theatre</heading><paragraph><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>wrote<space/><italics><link><target>No Exit</target></link></italics><space/>in 1944, an existentialist<space/><link><target>play (theatre)</target><part>play</part></link><space/>originally published in French as<space/><italics>Huis Clos</italics><space/>(meaning<space/><italics><link><target>wikt:in camera</target><part>In Camera</part></link></italics><space/>or &quot;behind closed doors&quot;), which is the source of the popular quote, &quot;Hell is other people.&quot; (In French, &quot;L'enfer, c'est les autres&quot;). The play begins with a Valet leading a man into a room that the audience soon realizes is in hell. Eventually he is joined by two women. After their entry, the Valet leaves and the door is shut and locked. All three expect to be tortured, but no torturer arrives. Instead, they realize they are there to torture each other, which they do effectively by probing each other's sins, desires, and unpleasant memories.</paragraph><paragraph>Existentialist themes are displayed in the<space/><link><target>Theatre of the Absurd</target></link>, notably in<space/><link><target>Samuel Beckett</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Waiting for Godot</target></link></italics>, in which two men divert themselves while they wait expectantly for someone (or something) named Godot who never arrives. They claim Godot is an acquaintance, but in fact, hardly know him, admitting they would not recognize him if they saw him. Samuel Beckett, once asked who or what Godot is, replied, &quot;If I knew, I would have said so in the play.&quot; To occupy themselves, the men eat, sleep, talk, argue, sing, play games,<space/><link><target>Physical exercise</target><part>exercise</part></link>, swap hats, and contemplate<space/><link><target>suicide</target></link>anything &quot;to hold the terrible silence at bay&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Times</italics>, 31 December 1964. Quoted in Knowlson, J.,<space/><italics>Damned to Fame: The Life of Samuel Beckett</italics><space/>(London: Bloomsbury, 1996), p 57</extension><space/>The play &quot;exploits several archetypal forms and situations, all of which lend themselves to both comedy and<space/><link><target>pathos</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Cronin, A.,<space/><italics>Samuel Beckett The Last Modernist</italics><space/>(London: Flamingo, 1997), p 391</extension><space/>The play also illustrates an attitude toward human experience on earth: the poignancy, oppression, camaraderie, hope, corruption, and bewilderment of human experience that can be reconciled only in the mind and art of the absurdist. The play examines questions such as death, the<space/><link><target>Meaning of life (philosophy)#Existentialism</target><part>meaning of human existence</part></link><space/>and the place of God in human existence.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Tom Stoppard</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Rosencrantz &amp; Guildenstern Are Dead</target></link></italics><space/>is an<space/><link><target>Theatre of the Absurd</target><part>absurdist</part></link><space/><link><target>tragicomedy</target></link><space/>first staged at the<space/><link><target>Edinburgh Festival Fringe</target></link><space/>in 1966.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Chrono"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author"><space/>Michael H. Hutchins<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Tom Stoppard Bibliography: Chronology<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Stephen Sondheim Reference Guide<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.sondheimguide.com/Stoppard/chronology.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 August 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-06-23</arg></template></extension><space/>The play expands upon the exploits of two minor characters from<space/><link><target>William Shakespeare</target><part>Shakespeare's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>Hamlet</target></link></italics>. Comparisons have also been drawn to<space/><link><target>Samuel Beckett</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Waiting For Godot</target></link></italics>, for the presence of two central characters who appear almost as two halves of a single character. Many plot features are similar as well: the characters pass time by playing<space/><link><target>Questions (game)</target><part>Questions</part></link>, impersonating other characters, and interrupting each other or remaining silent for long periods of time. The two characters are portrayed as two clowns or fools in a world beyond their understanding. They stumble through philosophical arguments while not realizing the implications, and muse on the irrationality and randomness of the world.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Jean Anouilh</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Antigone (Anouilh play)</target><part>Antigone</part></link></italics><space/>also presents arguments founded on existentialist ideas.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Wren</arg><arg name="first">Celia<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>12 December 2007<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>From Forum, an Earnest and Painstaking 'Antigone'<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2007/12/11/AR2007121102254.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Washington Post<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-04-07</arg></template></extension><space/>It is a tragedy inspired by Greek mythology and the play of the same name (Antigone, by Sophocles) from the 5th century BC. In English, it is often distinguished from its antecedent by being pronounced in its original French form, approximately &quot;Ante-GN.&quot; The play was first performed in Paris on 6 February 1944, during the Nazi occupation of France. Produced under Nazi censorship, the play is purposefully ambiguous with regards to the rejection of authority (represented by Antigone) and the acceptance of it (represented by Creon). The parallels to the French Resistance and the Nazi occupation have been drawn. Antigone rejects life as desperately meaningless but without affirmatively choosing a noble death. The crux of the play is the lengthy dialogue concerning the nature of power, fate, and choice, during which Antigone says that she is, &quot;...&amp;nbsp;disgusted with [the]...promise of a humdrum happiness.&quot; She states that she would rather die than live a mediocre existence.</paragraph><paragraph>Critic<space/><link><target>Martin Esslin</target></link><space/>in his book<space/><italics>Theatre of the Absurd</italics><space/>pointed out how many contemporary playwrights such as<space/><link><target>Samuel Beckett</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Eugne Ionesco</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean Genet</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Arthur Adamov</target></link><space/>wove into their plays the existentialist belief that we are absurd beings loose in a universe empty of real meaning. Esslin noted that many of these playwrights demonstrated the philosophy better than did the plays by Sartre and Camus. Though most of such playwrights, subsequently labeled &quot;Absurdist&quot; (based on Esslin's book), denied affiliations with existentialism and were often staunchly anti-philosophical (for example Ionesco often claimed he identified more with<space/><link><target>'Pataphysics</target></link><space/>or with<space/><link><target>Surrealism</target></link><space/>than with existentialism), the playwrights are often linked to existentialism based on Esslin's observation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kernan, Alvin B.<space/><italics>The Modern American Theater: A Collection of Critical Essays</italics>. Englewood Cliffs, New Jersey:<space/><link><target>Prentice-Hall</target></link>, 1967.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Psychoanalysis and psychotherapy</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Existential therapy</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A major offshoot of existentialism as a philosophy is existentialist psychology and psychoanalysis, which first crystallized in the work of<space/><link><target>Otto Rank</target></link>, Freud's closest associate for 20 years. Without awareness of the writings of Rank,<space/><link><target>Ludwig Binswanger</target></link><space/>was influenced by<space/><link><target>Sigmund Freud</target><part>Freud</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Edmund Husserl</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Martin Heidegger</target><part>Heidegger</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target><part>Sartre</part></link>. A later figure was<space/><link><target>Viktor Frankl</target></link>, who briefly met<space/><link><target>Sigmund Freud</target><part>Freud</part></link><space/>and studied with<space/><link><target>Carl Jung</target><part>Jung</part></link><space/>as a young man.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.logotherapie-international.eu/Frankl-Jung.English%20summary.pdf?2f569316a8c0d70a23e25e57788725a0=877b85765d9546f605211252412792ec'>Logotherapie-international.eu</link></extension><space/>His<space/><link><target>logotherapy</target></link><space/>can be regarded as a form of existentialist therapy. The existentialists would also influence<space/><link><target>social psychology</target></link>, antipositivist micro-<link><target>sociology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>symbolic interactionism</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>post-structuralism</target></link>, with the work of thinkers such as<space/><link><target>Georg Simmel</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Stewart, Jon.<space/><italics>Kierkegaard and Existentialism</italics>. p.38</extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Michel Foucault</target></link>. Foucault was a great reader of Kierkegaard even though he almost never refers this author, who nonetheless had for him an importance as secret as it was decisive.<extension extension_name='ref'>Flynn, Thomas R.<space/><italics>Sartre, Foucault, and Historical Reason</italics>, p. 323.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>An early contributor to existentialist psychology in the United States was<space/><link><target>Rollo May</target></link>, who was strongly influenced by<space/><link><target>Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Otto Rank</target></link>. One of the most prolific writers on techniques and theory of existentialist psychology in the USA is<space/><link><target>Irvin D. Yalom</target></link>. Yalom states that<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Aside from their reaction against Freud's mechanistic, deterministic model of the mind and their assumption of a phenomenological approach in therapy, the existentialist analysts have little in common and have never been regarded as a cohesive ideological school. These thinkers - who include Ludwig Binswanger,<space/><link><target>Medard Boss</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Eugne Minkowski</target></link>, V.E. Gebsattel, Roland Kuhn, G. Caruso, F.T. Buytendijk, G. Bally and Victor Frankl - were almost entirely unknown to the American psychotherapeutic community until Rollo May's highly influential 1985 book<space/><italics>Existence</italics><space/>- and especially his introductory essay - introduced their work into this country.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Yalom1980"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="first"><space/>Irvin D.</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Yalom</arg><arg name="author-link"><space/>Irvin D. Yalom</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Existential Psychotherapy</arg><arg name="place"><space/>New York</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>BasicBooks (Subsidiary of Perseus Books, L.L.C.</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1980</arg><arg name="page"><space/>17</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-465-02147-6</arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template><space/>Note: The copyright year has not changed, but the book remains in print.</extension></extension>A more recent contributor to the development of a European version of existentialist psychotherapy is the British-based<space/><link><target>Emmy van Deurzen</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Anxiety's importance in existentialism makes it a popular topic in<space/><link><target>psychotherapy</target></link>. Therapists often offer existentialist<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>as an explanation for anxiety. The assertion is that anxiety is manifested of an individual's complete freedom to decide, and complete responsibility for the outcome of such decisions. Psychotherapists using an existentialist approach believe that a patient can harness his anxiety and use it constructively. Instead of suppressing anxiety, patients are advised to use it as grounds for change. By embracing anxiety as inevitable, a person can use it to achieve his full potential in life.<space/><link><target>Humanistic psychology</target></link><space/>also had major impetus from existentialist psychology and shares many of the fundamental tenets.<space/><link><target>Terror management theory</target></link>, based on the writings of<space/><link><target>Ernest Becker</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Otto Rank</target></link>, is a developing area of study within the academic study of psychology. It looks at what researchers claim are implicit emotional reactions of people confronted with the knowledge that they will eventually die.</paragraph><paragraph>Also,<space/><link><target>Gerd B. Achenbach</target></link><space/>has refreshed the socratic tradition with his own blend of<space/><link><target>philosophical counseling</target></link>. So did<space/><link><target>Michel Weber</target></link><space/>with his Chromatiques Center in Belgium.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticisms</heading><heading level='3'>General criticisms</heading><paragraph><link><target>Walter Kaufmann (philosopher)</target><part>Walter Kaufmann</part></link><space/>criticized 'the profoundly unsound methods and the dangerous contempt for reason that have been so prominent in existentialism.'<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Kaufmann, Walter Arnold, From Shakespeare To Existentialism (Princeton University Press 1979), p.xvi</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Logical positivists</target><part>Logical positivist</part></link><space/>philosophers, such as<space/><link><target>Rudolf Carnap</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>A. J. Ayer</target></link>, assert that existentialists are often confused about the verb &quot;to be&quot; in their analyses of &quot;being&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Carnap, Rudolf 1932 pp.219">Carnap, Rudolf,<space/><italics>Uberwindung der Metaphysik durch logische Analyse der Sprache</italics><space/>[<italics>Overcoming Metaphysics by the Logical Analysis of Speech</italics>], Erkenntnis (1932), pp.219241. Carnap's critique of Heidegger's &quot;What is Metaphysics&quot;.</extension><space/>Specifically, they argue that the verb is transitive and pre-fixed to a<space/><link><target>predicate (grammar)</target><part>predicate</part></link><space/>(e.g., an apple<space/><italics>is red</italics>) (without a predicate, the word is meaningless), and that existentialists frequently misuse the term in this manner.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Colin Wilson</target></link><space/>has stated in his book<space/><italics>The Angry Years</italics><space/>that existentialism has created many of its own difficulties: &quot;we can see how this question of freedom of the will has been vitiated by post-romantic philosophy, with its inbuilt tendency to laziness and boredom, we can also see how it came about that existentialism found itself in a hole of its own digging, and how the philosophical developments since then have amounted to walking in circles round that hole.<extension extension_name='ref'>Colin, Wilson,<space/><italics>The Angry Years</italics><space/>(2007), p.214</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sartre's philosophy</heading><paragraph>Many critics argue Sartre's philosophy is contradictory. Specifically, they argue that Sartre makes metaphysical arguments despite his claiming that his philosophical views ignore metaphysics.<space/><link><target>Herbert Marcuse</target></link><space/>criticized<space/><italics><link><target>Being and Nothingness</target></link></italics><space/>(1943) by<space/><link><target>Jean-Paul Sartre</target></link><space/>for projecting anxiety and meaninglessness onto the nature of existence itself: &quot;Insofar as Existentialism is a philosophical doctrine, it remains an idealistic doctrine: it<space/><link><target>hypostatic abstraction</target><part>hypostatizes</part></link><space/>specific historical conditions of human existence into ontological and metaphysical characteristics. Existentialism thus becomes part of the very ideology which it attacks, and its radicalism is illusory&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Marcuse1972">Marcuse, Herbert. &quot;Sartre's Existentialism&quot;. Printed in<space/><italics>Studies in Critical Philosophy</italics>. Translated by Joris De Bres. London: NLB, 1972. p. 161</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Letter on Humanism</italics>, Heidegger criticized Sartre's existentialism:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Existentialism says existence precedes essence. In this statement he is taking<space/><italics>existentia</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>essentia</italics><space/>according to their metaphysical meaning, which, from Plato's time on, has said that<space/><italics>essentia</italics><space/>precedes<space/><italics>existentia</italics>. Sartre reverses this statement. But the reversal of a metaphysical statement remains a metaphysical statement. With it, he stays with metaphysics, in oblivion of the truth of Being.<extension extension_name='ref'>Martin Heidegger, &quot;Letter on Humanism&quot;, in<space/><italics>Basic Writings: Nine Key Essays, plus the Introduction to<space/></italics>Being and Time<italics><space/></italics>, trans. David Farrell Krell (London, Routledge; 1978), 208.<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=kVc9AAAAIAAJ&amp;amp;lpg=PA208&amp;amp;ots=Wd-UQTTzCG&amp;amp;dq=But%20the%20reversal%20of%20a%20metaphysical%20statement%20remains%20a%20metaphysical%20statement.%20With%20it%2C%20he%20stays%20with%20metaphysics%2C%20in%20oblivion%20of%20the%20truth%20of%20Being.&amp;amp;pg=PA208#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=But%20the%20reversal%20of%20a%20metaphysical%20statement%20remains%20a%20metaphysical%20statement.%20With%20it,%20he%20stays%20with%20metaphysics,%20in%20oblivion%20of%20the%20truth%20of%20Being.&amp;amp;f=false'>Google Books</link></extension></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Columns-list</target><arg>3</arg><arg>
* [[Abandonment (existentialism)]]
* [[Absurdism]]
* [[Atheist existentialism]]
* [[Christian existentialism]]
* [[Disenchantment]]
* [[Existentiell]]
* [[List of existentialists]]
* [[Meaning (existential)]]
* [[phenomenology (philosophy)|Phenomenology]]
</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Suhrawardi and the School of Illumination</arg><arg name="first">Mehdi Amin</arg><arg name="last">Razavi</arg><arg name="year">1997</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Routledge]]</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7007-0412-4</arg><arg name="postscript"></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Albert Camus Lyrical and Critical essays. Edited by Philip Thody (interviev with Jeanie Delpech, in Les Nouvelles litteraires, November 15, 1945). pg 345</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Appignanesi</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="author2">[[Oscar Zarate]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">Introducing Existentialism</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="publisher">Icon</arg><arg name="location">Cambridge, UK</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84046-266-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Appignanesi</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Introducing Existentialism</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="edition">3rd</arg><arg name="publisher">Icon Books (UK), Totem Books (USA)</arg><arg name="location">Thriplow, Cambridge</arg><arg name="isbn">1-84046-717-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Cooper</arg><arg name="first">David E.</arg><arg name="title">Existentialism: A Reconstruction</arg><arg name="year">1999</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">Blackwell</arg><arg name="location">Oxford, UK</arg><arg name="isbn">0-631-21322-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Deurzen</arg><arg name="first">Emmy van</arg><arg name="title">Everyday Mysteries: a Handbook of Existential Psychotherapy</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge</arg><arg name="location">London</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-415-37643-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Fallico, Arthuro B. (1962).<space/><italics>Art &amp; Existentialism</italics>. Englewood Cliffs, N.J.: Prentice-Hall.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Attack Upon Christendom<space/></arg><arg name="year">1855</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Concept of Anxiety<space/></arg><arg name="year">1843</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Concluding Unscientific Postscript<space/></arg><arg name="year">1846</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Either/Or<space/></arg><arg name="year">1843</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Fear and Trembling<space/></arg><arg name="year">1843</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Sickness Unto Death<space/></arg><arg name="year">1849</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Works of Love<space/></arg><arg name="year">1847</arg><arg name="first">Søren<space/></arg><arg name="last">Kierkegaard</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Luper</arg><arg name="first">Steven (ed.)</arg><arg name="title">Existing: An Introduction to Existential Thought</arg><arg name="year">2000</arg><arg name="publisher">Mayfield</arg><arg name="location">Mountain View, California</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7674-0587-0</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Marino</arg><arg name="first">Gordon (ed.)</arg><arg name="title">Basic Writings of Existentialism</arg><arg name="year">2004</arg><arg name="publisher">Modern Library</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-375-75989-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Phenomenology of Perception<space/></arg><arg name="year">1962</arg><arg name="first">M.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Merleau-Ponty<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Routledge and Kegan Paul<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title"><space/>Colin Smith</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Nihilism: The Root of the Revolution of the Modern Age</arg><arg name="url">http://www.columbia.edu/cu/augustine/arch/nihilism.html</arg><arg name="last">Rose<space/></arg><arg name="first">Eugene (Fr. Seraphim)<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Seraphim Rose</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Saint Herman Press (1 September 1994)<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0-938635-15-8</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Being and Nothingness<space/></arg><arg name="year">1943</arg><arg name="first">Jean-Paul<space/></arg><arg name="last">Sartre<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Existentialism and Humanism<space/></arg><arg name="year">1945</arg><arg name="first">Jean-Paul<space/></arg><arg name="last">Sartre<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Stewart</arg><arg name="first">Jon (ed.)</arg><arg name="title">Kierkegaard and Existentialism</arg><arg name="year">2011</arg><arg name="publisher">Ashgate</arg><arg name="location">Farnham, England</arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4094-2641-7</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Solomon</arg><arg name="first">Robert C. (ed.)</arg><arg name="authorlink">Robert C. Solomon</arg><arg name="title">Existentialism</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="edition">2nd</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-517463-1</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Existentialism: A Beginner's Guide<space/></arg><arg name="first">Thomas E.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Wartenberg<space/></arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>sisterlinks</target><arg name="d">Q38066</arg><arg name="n">no</arg><arg name="mw">no</arg><arg name="m">no</arg><arg name="species">no</arg><arg name="c">Category:Existentialism</arg><arg name="b">Introduction to Philosophy/Existentialism</arg><arg name="s">no</arg><arg name="v">no</arg><arg name="voy">no</arg></template><template><target>toomanylinks</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>DMOZ</target><arg>Society/Philosophy/Continental_Philosophy/Existentialism/</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>existent</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>In Our Time</target><arg>Existentialism</arg><arg>p00547h8</arg><arg>Existentialism</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.friesian.com/existent.htm'>Friesian interpretation of Existentialism</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>SEP</target><arg>existentialism</arg><arg>Existentialism</arg><arg>Steven Crowell</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/sartre/works/exist/sartre.htm'>&quot;Existentialism is a Humanism&quot;, a lecture given by Jean-Paul Sartre</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tameri.com/csw/exist/'>''The Existential Primer''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://publish.uwo.ca/~dmann/waking_essay.htm'>Buddhists, Existentialists and Situationists: Waking up in Waking Life</link></listitem></list><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Journals and articles</defkey></listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.stirrings-still.org'>Stirrings Still</link>: The International Journal of Existential Literature</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.existentialanalysis.co.uk'>Existential Analysis</link><space/>published by The Society for Existential Analysis</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Navboxes</target><arg name="list">
{{Philosophy topics}}
{{continental philosophy}}
{{metaphysics}}
{{philosophy of religion}}
{{Ethics}}
{{Philosophy of education sidebar}}
</arg></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Existentialism</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:19th-century philosophy</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century philosophy</target></link><link><target>Category:Metaphysical theories</target></link><link><target>Category:Modernism</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophical movements</target></link><link><target>Category:Philosophy of life</target></link><link><target>Category:Postmodernism</target></link><link><target>Category:Social theories</target></link><link><target>Category:Individualism</target></link></paragraph></article>