<article title='Dragoon'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>mounted infantry, later cavalry, troops</arg><arg>other uses</arg><arg>Dragoon (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">February 2012</arg></template><link><target>File:Battle of Jena.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>French dragoons with captured Prussian flag at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jena</target></link>.</part></link><space/>The word<space/><bold><italics>dragoon</italics></bold><space/>originally meant<space/><link><target>mounted infantry</target></link>, who were trained in<space/><link><target>horse riding</target></link><space/>as well as infantry<space/><link><target>combat</target><part>fighting skills</part></link>. However, usage altered over time and during the 18th century, dragoons evolved into conventional cavalry units. In most armies, &quot;dragoons&quot; came to signify ordinary medium cavalry.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Dragoon regiments were established in most European armies during the late 17th and early 18th centuries.</paragraph><paragraph>The name is derived from a type of<space/><link><target>firearm</target></link><space/>(called a<space/><bold><link><target>Blunderbuss</target><part>dragon</part></link></bold>) carried by dragoons of the<space/><link><target>French Army</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.oed.com/view/Entry/57447?isAdvanced</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dragoon<space/></arg><arg name="website"><space/>Oxford English Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="quote"><space/>A kind of carbine or musket.</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>https://en.wikisource.org/wiki/1911_Encyclop%C3%A6dia_Britannica/Dragoon<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Dragoon<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Encyclopedia Britanica<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1911<space/></arg><arg name="quote">... took his name from his weapon, a species of carbine or short musket called the dragon.</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The title has been retained in modern times by a number of<space/><link><target>armoured warfare</target><part>armoured</part></link><space/>or ceremonial mounted<space/><link><target>regiment</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins and name</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dragonnades430.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Cartoon of a French dragoon intimidating a<space/><link><target>Huguenot</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>dragonnades</target></link>.</part></link><link><target>File:Leonard Wintorowski sterreichisch-ungarische Dragoner 1915.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Austro-Hungarian dragoons 1915, by Leonard Wintorowski</part></link>The establishment of dragoons evolved from the practice of sometimes transporting infantry by horse when speed of movement was needed. In 1552<space/><link><target>Alexander Farnese, Prince of Parma</target><part>Prince Alexander of Parma</part></link><space/>mounted several companies of infantry on<space/><link><target>pack horse</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to achieve surprise.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p.330, Bismark"></extension><space/>Another early instance was ordered by<space/><link><target>Louis of Nassau</target></link><space/>in 1572 during operations near<space/><link><target>Mons</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>County of Hainaut</target><part>Hainaut</part></link>, when 500 infantry were transported this way.<extension extension_name='ref' name="p.330, Bismark">p.330, Bismark</extension><space/>It is also suggested the first dragoons were raised by the Marshal<space/><link><target>Duke of Brissac</target><part>de Brissac</part></link><space/>in 1600.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.331, Bismark</extension><space/>According to old German literature, dragoons were invented by Count<space/><link><target>Ernst von Mansfeld</target></link>, one of the greatest German military commanders, in the early 1620s. There are other instances of mounted infantry predating this. However Mansfeld, who had learned his profession in Hungary and the Netherlands, often used horses to make his foot troops more mobile, creating what was called an &quot;arme volante&quot; (<link><target>French Language</target><part>French</part></link><space/>for<space/><italics>flying army</italics>).</paragraph><paragraph>The name possibly derives from an early weapon, a short<space/><link><target>wheellock</target></link><space/>called a<space/><italics>dragon</italics><space/>because the first dragoons raised in France had their carbine's muzzle decorated with a dragon's head. The practice comes from a time when all gunpowder weapons had distinctive names, including the<space/><link><target>culverin</target></link>, serpentine, falcon,<space/><link><target>falconet (cannon)</target><part>falconet</part></link>, etc.<extension extension_name='ref'>p.333, Bismark</extension><space/>It is also sometimes claimed a galloping infantryman with his loose coat and the burning match resembled a<space/><link><target>dragon</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>p. 48, A Dictionary of Military Uniform W. Y. Carman ISBN 0-684-15130-8</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Use as a verb</heading><paragraph>Dragoon is occasionally used to mean to subjugate or persecute by the imposition of troops; and by extension to compel by any violent measures or threats. The verb dates from 1689, at a time when dragoons were being used by the French monarchy to<space/><link><target>Edict of Fontainebleau</target><part>persecute Protestants</part></link>, particularly by forcing protestants to lodge a dragoon in their house to watch over them, at the householders expense.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/etymology/dragoon'>Online Etymology Dictionary | Etymology of Words &amp; Word Origins | Dictionary.com</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early history and role</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dragoon-illustration.jpeg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Dragoon illustration Light Dragoon. A trooper of William Washington cavalry, 2nd Continental Light Dragoons.</part></link>Early dragoons were not organized in<space/><link><target>squadron (cavalry)</target><part>squadrons</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>troop</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as were cavalry, but in<space/><link><target>company (military unit)</target><part>companies</part></link><space/>like the infantry: their<space/><link><target>commissioned officer</target><part>officers</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>non-commissioned officer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>bore infantry ranks. Dragoon regiments used drummers, not buglers, to communicate orders on the battlefield. The flexibility of mounted infantry made dragoons a useful arm, especially when employed for what would now be termed &quot;<link><target>internal security</target></link>&quot; against smugglers or civil unrest, and on<space/><link><target>line of communication</target></link><space/>security duties. During the<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link><space/>dragoons were used for a variety of tasks: providing outposts, holding defiles or bridges in the front or rear of the main army, lining hedges or holding enclosures, and providing dismounted musketeers to support regular cavalry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Young &amp; Richard Holmes, page 42 &quot;The English Civil War&quot;, ISBN 1-84022-222-0</extension><space/>Supplied with inferior horses and more basic equipment, the dragoon regiments were cheaper to recruit and maintain than the expensive regiments of cavalry. When in the 17th century<space/><link><target>Gustav II Adolf</target></link><space/>introduced dragoons into the Swedish Army, he provided them with a sabre, an axe and a<space/><link><target>matchlock</target></link><space/>musket, utilizing them as &quot;labourers on horseback&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Brzezinski, page 16 &quot;The Army of Gustavus Adolphus 2 - &quot;, ISBN 1-85532-350-8</extension><space/>Many of the European armies henceforth imitated this all-purpose set of weaponry.</paragraph><paragraph>A non-military use of dragoons was the 1681<space/><link><target>Dragonnades</target></link>, a policy instituted by<space/><link><target>Louis XIV of France</target><part>Louis XIV</part></link><space/>to intimidate<space/><link><target>Huguenot</target></link><space/>families into either leaving France or re-converting to<space/><link><target>Catholicism</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>billeting</target></link><space/>ill-disciplined dragoons in Protestant households. While other categories of infantry and cavalry were also used, the mobility, flexibility and available numbers of the dragoon regiments made them particularly suitable for repressive work of this nature over a wide area.</paragraph><paragraph>Dragoons were at a disadvantage when engaged against true cavalry, and constantly sought to improve their horsemanship, armament and social status. By the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link><space/>the primary role of dragoons in most European armies had progressed from that of mounted infantry to that of heavy cavalry.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dragoons are sometimes described as 'medium' cavalry, midway between heavy/armoured and light regiments, though this was a classification that was rarely given at the time. page 19 &quot;Napoleonic Cavalry&quot;, Philip Haythornthwaite, ISBN 0-304-35508-9</extension><space/>Earlier dragoon responsibilities for scouting and<space/><link><target>picket (military)</target><part>picket</part></link><space/>duty had passed to<space/><link><target>hussars</target></link><space/>and similar light cavalry corps in the French, Austrian, Prussian, and other armies. In the<space/><link><target>Imperial Russian Army</target></link>, due to the availability of the<space/><link><target>cossack</target></link><space/>troops, the dragoons were retained in their original role for much longer.</paragraph><paragraph>An exception to the rule was the British Army. To reduce military budgets, all horse (cavalry) regiments were gradually demoted to dragoons from 1746 onward which meant they were paid on a lower scale. When this was completed in 1788, the heavy cavalry regiments had become either<space/><link><target>Dragoon Guards</target></link><space/>or Heavy Dragoons (depending on their precedence). The designation of Dragoon Guards did not mean that these regiments (the former 2nd to 8th Horse) had become Household Troops, but simply that they had been given a more dignified designation to compensate for the loss of pay and prestige.<extension extension_name='ref'>Michael Barthorp, page 22 &quot;British Cavalry Uniforms Since 1660&quot;, ISBN 0-7137-1043-8</extension><space/>Starting in 1756, seven regiments of Light Dragoons were raised. These Light Dragoons were trained in<space/><link><target>reconnaissance</target></link>,<space/><link><target>skirmish</target><trail>ing</trail></link><space/>and other work requiring<space/><link><target>Endurance riding</target><part>endurance</part></link><space/>in accordance with contemporary standards of light cavalry performance. The success of this new class of cavalry was such that that eight regular Dragoon regiments were converted to Light Dragoons between 1768 and 1783.<extension extension_name='ref'>page 24 &quot;British Cavalry Uniforms Since 1660&quot;, Michael Barthorp, ISBN 0-7137-1043-8</extension><link><target>Image:Helm eines k.u.k. Dragoneroffiziers.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Austria-Hungarian dragoon officer's helmet</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>19th century</heading><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>, dragoons generally assumed a cavalry role, though remaining a lighter class of mounted troops than the armored<space/><link><target>cuirassier</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Dragoons rode larger horses than the light cavalry and wielded straight, rather than curved swords. Emperor<space/><link><target>Napoleon</target></link><space/>often formed complete divisions out of his 30 dragoon regiments<extension extension_name='ref'>In 1811 six regiments were converted to<space/><italics>Chevau-Legers Lanciers</italics></extension><space/>and used them as battle cavalry to break the enemy's main resistance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rothenberg, p 141</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>In northern and eastern Europe they were employed as heavy cavalry, while in the Iberian peninsula they fulfilled, in addition, the role of lighter cavalry, for example in anti-guerrilla operations. page 19 &quot;Napoleonic Cavalry&quot;, Philip Haythornthwaite, ISBN 0-304-35508-9</extension><space/>In 1809, French dragoons scored notable successes against Spanish armies at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Ocana</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Battle of Alba de Tormes</target></link>. British heavy dragoons made devastating charges against French infantry at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Salamanca</target></link><space/>in 1812 and at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Waterloo</target></link><space/>in 1815.</paragraph><paragraph>In the Spanish army, in 1635, Pedro de la Puente organized a body of dragoons in<space/><link><target>Innsbruck</target></link>, Austria, and in 1640 one was created in Spain as a<space/><italics><link><target>tercio</target></link></italics><space/>of a thousand dragoons armed with the<space/><link><target>arquebus</target></link>. In 1704, along with the rest of the tercios, the Spanish dragoons were reorganised into regiments by<space/><link><target>Philip V of Spain</target><part>Philip V</part></link>. During the 18th century several additional regiments of dragoons were created in the Spanish Americas, some of them to function as a police force. In 1803 the regiments of dragoons began to be called light cavalry and shortly after 1815 this class of cavalry disappeared from the Spanish Army. However three regiments of Spanish dragoons had been reestablished by the 1880s and these continued in existence until the overthrow of the monarchy in 1931.</paragraph><paragraph>In New Spain, soon to be<space/><link><target>Mxico</target></link>, Dragoons were important and elite units of the Royal Army. A number of dragoons became important military and political figures, among them<space/><link><target>Ignacio Allende</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Juan Aldama</target></link>, members of the Queen's Regiment of Dragoons who defected and then initiated the Independence movement in Mxico, beginning in 1810. Another important Dragoon was<space/><link><target>Agustin de Iturbide</target></link>, who would ultimately achieve Mexican Independence in 1821. He was known as the greatest horseman in Mxico and became so renowned in battle during his youth that he acquired the nickname<space/><italics>El Dragn de Hierro</italics><space/>or &quot;The Iron Dragon&quot; (in Spanish, &quot;dragon&quot; and &quot;dragoon&quot; both sound and are written exactly the same). He would go on to become Agustn I, after being elected Emperor of Mxico. The political importance of Dragoons during this time in the nascent country cannot be overstated.</paragraph><paragraph>In several stages between 1816 and 1861, the 21 existing Light Dragoon regiments in the British Army were disbanded or converted to<space/><link><target>lancer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>hussar</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>British Cavalry Uniforms Since 1660, Michael Barthorp ISBN 0-7137-1043-8</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Between 1881 and 1910 all Russian cavalry (other than<space/><link><target>Cossacks</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Imperial Guard (Russia)</target><part>Imperial Guard</part></link><space/>regiments) were designated as dragoons, reflecting an emphasis on dismounted action in their training and a growing acceptance of the impracticality of employing historical<space/><link><target>cavalry tactics</target></link><space/>against modern firepower.<link><target>Image:Karlsruhe Leibdragonerdenkmal.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part><link><target>Baden</target></link><space/>dragoon in a<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>monument at<space/><link><target>Karlsruhe</target></link>. While almost an<space/><link><target>anachronism</target></link><space/>after the early stages of that war, German dragoons did see continuing service on the Eastern Front until 1917. Note the functional<space/><link><target>Stahlhelm</target></link><space/>helmet</part></link>In<space/><link><target>Japan</target></link>, in the late 19th century/early 20th century, dragoons were deployed in the same way as in other armies, but were dressed as<space/><link><target>hussars</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>20th century</heading><paragraph>In 1914 there were still dragoon regiments in the British, French, German, Russian, Austro-Hungarian, Peruvian, Norwegian, Swedish, Danish and Spanish armies. Their uniforms varied greatly, lacking the characteristic features of hussar or lancer regiments. There were occasional reminders of the mounted infantry origins of this class of soldier. Thus the dragoon regiments of the<space/><link><target>German Army (German Empire)</target><part>Imperial German Army</part></link><space/>wore the<space/><link><target>pickelhaube</target></link><space/>(spiked helmet) of the same design as those of the infantry and the British dragoons wore scarlet tunics,<extension extension_name='ref'>hussars and all but one of the lancer regiments wore dark blue.</extension><space/>In other respects however dragoons had adopted the same tactics, roles and equipment as other branches of the cavalry and the distinction had become simply one of traditional titles. Weaponry had ceased to have a historic connection, with both the French and German dragoon regiments carrying lances during the early stages of World War I.</paragraph><paragraph>The historic Geman, Russian and Austro-Hungarian dragoon regiments ceased to exist as distinct branches following the overthrow of the respective Imperial regimes of these countries during 1917-18. The Spanish dragoons, which dated back to 1640, were reclassified as numbered cavalry regiments in 1931 as part of the army modernization policies of the new Republic.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Australian light horse</target><part>The Australian Light Horse</part></link><space/>were similar to 18th-century dragoon regiments in some respects, being mounted infantry which normally fought on foot, their horses' purpose being transportation. They served during the<space/><link><target>Second Boer War</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. The Australian 4th Light Horse Brigade became famous for the<space/><link><target>Battle of Beersheba (1917)</target><part>Battle of Beersheba</part></link><space/>in 1917 where they charged on horseback using rifle bayonets, since neither sabres or lances were part of their equipment.</paragraph><paragraph>Probably the last use of real dragoons (infantry on horseback) in combat was made by the<space/><link><target>Portuguese Army</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Portuguese Colonial War</target><part>war in Angola</part></link><space/>during the 1960s and early 1970s. In 1966, the Portuguese created an experimental horse platoon, to operate against the guerrillas in the high grass region of Eastern<space/><link><target>Angola</target></link>, in which each soldier was armed with a<space/><link><target>Heckler &amp; Koch G3</target><part>G3</part></link><space/><link><target>assault rifle</target></link><space/>for combat on foot and with an<space/><link><target>Semi-automatic pistol</target><part>automatic pistol</part></link><space/>to fire from horseback. The troops on horseback were able to operate in difficult terrain unsuited to motor vehicles and had the advantage of being able to control the area around them, with a clear view over the grass that foot troops did not have. Moreover, these unconventional troops created a psychological impact on an enemy that was not used to facing horse troops, and thus had no training or strategy to deal with them. The experimental horse platoon was so successful that its entire parent battalion was transformed from an armored reconnaissance unit to a three-squadron horse battalion known as the &quot;<link><target>Dragoons of Angola</target></link>&quot;. One of the typical operations carried out by the Dragoons of Angola, in cooperation with<space/><link><target>airmobile</target></link><space/>forces, consisted of the dragoons chasing the guerrillas and pushing them in one direction, with the airmobile troops being launched from<space/><link><target>helicopter</target></link><space/>in the enemy rear, trapping the enemy between the two forces.<extension extension_name='ref'>CANN, Jonh P., &quot;Counterinsurgency in Africa: The Portuguese Way of War, 1961-1974&quot;, Hailer Publishing, 2005</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern dragoons</heading><heading level='3'>Brazil</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:1352FP484.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part>Independence Day parade with the Brazilian dragoons.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>President of Brazil</target><part>Brazilian president</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>honor guard</target></link><space/>is provided (amongst other units) by a regiment of dragoons: the 1st Guards Cavalry Regiment of the<space/><link><target>Brazilian Army</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>This regiment is known as the &quot;Drages da Independncia&quot; (Independence Dragoons). The name was given in 1927 and refers to the fact that a detachment of dragoons escorted the<space/><link><target>Prince Royal of Portugal</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pedro I of Brazil</target><part>Pedro I</part></link>, at the time when he<space/><link><target>Brazilian Declaration of Independence</target><part>declared Brazilian independence</part></link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Portugal</target></link>, on September 7, 1822.</paragraph><paragraph>The Independence Dragoons wear 19th-century dress uniforms similar to those of the earlier Imperial Honor Guard, which are used as the regimental full dress uniform since 1927. The uniform was designed by<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste Debret</target><part>Debret</part></link>, in white and red, with plumed bronze helmets. The colors and pattern were influenced by the Austrian dragoons of the period, as the<space/><link><target>Maria Leopoldina of Austria</target><part>Brazilian Empress Consort</part></link><space/>was also an<space/><link><target>Austrian Empire</target><part>Austrian Archduchess</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Exército Brasileiro - Braço Forte, Mão Amiga<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.exercito.gov.br/VO/175/unifor.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20090312093820/http://www.exercito.gov.br/VO/175/unifor.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2009-03-12<space/></arg><arg name="language">Portuguese</arg></template></extension><space/>The color of the plumes varies according to rank. The Independence Dragoons are armed with<space/><link><target>lance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and sabres, the latter only for the officers and the colour guard.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-01</arg><arg name="url">http://www.presidencia.gov.br/estrutura_presidencia/gsi/cerimonial/principais_tropas/dragoes_independencia<space/></arg><arg name="title">Presidência da República - GSI<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">office of the president of Brazil<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20080621100028/http://www.presidencia.gov.br/estrutura_presidencia/gsi/cerimonial/principais_tropas/dragoes_independencia/<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2008-06-21<space/></arg><arg name="language">Portuguese</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The regiment was established in 1808 by the Prince Regent and future<space/><link><target>List of Portuguese monarchs</target><part>king of Portugal</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Joo VI of Portugal</target><part>John VI</part></link>, with the duty of protecting the Portuguese royal family, which had sought refuge in<space/><link><target>Brazil</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic wars</target></link>. However dragoons had existed in Portugal since at least the early 18th century and, in 1719, units of this type of cavalry were sent to Brazil, initially to escort shipments of gold and diamonds and to guard the<space/><link><target>Viceroy</target></link><space/>who resided in Rio de Janeiro (1st Cavalry Regiment Vice-Roy Guard<space/><link><target>Squadron (cavalry)</target><part>Squadron</part></link>). Later, they were also sent to the south to serve against the Spanish during frontier clashes. After the proclamation of Brazilian independence, the title of the regiment was changed to that of the Imperial Honor Guard, with the role of protecting the Imperial Family. The Guard was later disbanded by<space/><link><target>Pedro II of Brazil</target><part>Emperor Peter II</part></link><space/>and would be recreated only later in the republican era.<extension extension_name='ref'>CARVALHO, Jos Murilo de. D. Pedro II: Ser ou no ser. So Paulo: Companhia das Letras, 2007, p.98</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the time of the<space/><link><target>Empire of Brazil#The republican coup</target><part>Republic proclamation</part></link><space/>in 1889, horse #6 of the Imperial Honor Guard was ridden by the officer making the declaration of the end of Imperial rule, Second Lieutenant Eduardo Jos Barbosa. This is commemorated by the custom under which the horse having this number is used only by the commander of the modern regiment.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Canada</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Memorial Stained Glass window, 2770 LCol KL Jefferson, Royal Military College of Canada.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Memorial Stained Glass window at<space/><link><target>Royal Military College of Canada</target></link><space/>of 2770 LCol KL Jefferson, a member of the<space/><link><target>12th Manitoba Dragoons</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>armoured regiment</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Canadian Army</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Canadian Forces</target></link></part></link>There are three dragoon regiments in the<space/><link><target>Canadian Forces</target></link>: the<space/><link><target>Royal Canadian Dragoons</target></link><space/>and two<space/><link><target>military reserve</target><part>reserve</part></link><space/>regiments, the<space/><link><target>British Columbia Dragoons</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Saskatchewan Dragoons</target></link>.The Royal Canadian Dragoons is the senior<space/><link><target>Armoured warfare</target><part>Armoured</part></link><space/>regiment in the<space/><link><target>Canadian Forces</target></link>. The current role of The Royal Canadian Dragoons is to provide Armour Reconnaissance support to 2 Canadian Mechanized Brigade Group (2 CMBG) operations.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Royal Canadian Mounted Police</target></link><space/>were accorded the formal status of a regiment of dragoons in 1921.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-01<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.regiments.org/regiments/na-canada/cav/RCMP.htm#colours<space/></arg><arg name="title">Royal Canadian Mounted Police<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">2008-01-18<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/web/20080118041642/http://www.regiments.org/regiments/na-canada/cav/RCMP.htm#colours</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.webcitation.org/query?url=http://www.geocities.com/ottawa_heraldry/heraldist1.html&amp;amp;date=2009-10-26+00:05:28'>heraldist1</link></extension><space/>The modern RCMP does not retain any military status however.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Chile</heading><paragraph>Founded as the<space/><italics>Dragones de la Reina</italics><space/>(Queen's Dragoons) in 1758 and later renamed the Dragoons of Chile in 1812, and then becoming the<space/><link><target>Carabineros de Chile</target></link><space/>in 1903. The<space/><link><target>Carabinier</target><part>Carabineros</part></link><space/>are the national<space/><link><target>police</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Chile</target></link>. The military counterpart, that of the 15th Reinforced Regiment &quot;Dragoons&quot; is now as of 2010 the 4th Armored Brigade &quot;Chorrillos&quot; based in<space/><link><target>Punta Arenas</target></link><space/>as the 6th Armored Cavalry Squadron &quot;Dragoons&quot;, and form part of the 5th Army Division</paragraph><heading level='3'>Denmark</heading><paragraph>The Royal<space/><link><target>Danish Army</target></link><space/>includes amongst its historic regiments the<space/><link><target>Jydske Dragonregiment</target><part>Jutish Dragoon Regiment</part></link>, which was raised in 1670.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Finland</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rakuunakilta riders.JPG</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>Finnish Dragoon in 1922 uniform</part></link>The Finnish Dragoon squadron exists in conjunction with the Army Academy in<space/><link><target>Lappeenranta</target></link><space/>and continues the traditions of the former 1. Squadron of the<space/><link><target>Uusimaa</target></link><space/>Dragoon battalion.</paragraph><heading level='3'>France</heading><paragraph>The modern<space/><link><target>French Army</target></link><space/>retains three dragoon regiments from the 32 that it possessed at the beginning of World War I: the 2nd, which is a nuclear, bacteriologic and chemical protection regiment, the 4th, an armor regiment equipped with Leclerc tanks, and the<space/><link><target>13th Parachute Dragoon Regiment</target><part>13th</part></link><space/>(Special Reconnaissance).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Norway</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Norwegian Army</target></link><space/>during the early part of the 20th century, dragoons served in part as mounted troops, and in part on skis or bicycles (<italics>hjulryttere</italics>, meaning &quot;wheel-riders&quot;). Dragoons fought on horses, bicycles and skis against the German invasion in 1940. After World War II the dragoon regiments were reorganized as<space/><link><target>armour</target><trail>ed</trail></link><space/><link><target>reconnaissance</target></link><space/>units. &quot;Dragon&quot; is the rank of a compulsory service private cavalryman while enlisted (regular) cavalrymen have the same rank as infantrymen: &quot;Grenader&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Peru</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dragones del Per.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>220px</part><part></part><part><xhtml:center>Changing of the Dragoon guard by the &quot;Field Marshal Nieto&quot; Regiment of Cavalry, Life-Guard of the President of the Republic of Peru</xhtml:center></part></link>The<space/><link><target>Presidential Life Guard Dragoons Regiment</target><part>Presidential Escort Life Guard Dragoons Regiment &quot;Field Marshal Domingo Nieto&quot;</part></link>, named after Field Marshal<space/><link><target>Domingo Nieto</target></link>, of the<space/><link><target>List of Presidents of Peru</target><part>President of the Republic of Per</part></link><space/>were the traditional Guard of the<space/><link><target>Government Palace (Peru)</target><part>Government Palace of Per</part></link><space/>until March 5, 1987 and its disbandment in that year. However by Ministerial Resolution No 139-2012/DE/EP of February 2, 2012 the restoration of the Cavalry Regiment &quot;Marshal Domingo Nieto&quot; as the official escort of the President of the Republic of Peru was announced. The main mission of the reestablished regiment was to guarantee the security of the President of the Republic and of the Government Palace.</paragraph><paragraph>This regiment of dragoons was created in 1904 following the suggestion of a French military mission which undertook the reorganization of the<space/><link><target>Peruvian Army</target></link><space/>in 1896. The initial title of the unit was Cavalry Squadron &quot;President's Escort&quot;. It was modelled on the French dragoons of the period. The unit was later renamed as the Cavalry Regiment &quot;President's Escort&quot; before receiving its current title in 1949.</paragraph><paragraph>The Peruvian Dragoon Guard has throughout its existence worn French-style uniforms of black tunic and red breeches in winter and white coat and red breeches in summer, with red and white plumed bronze helmets with the<space/><link><target>coat of arms of Peru</target></link><space/>and golden or red<space/><link><target>epaulettes</target></link><space/>depending on rank. They retain their original armament of<space/><link><target>lance</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sabre</target><trail>s</trail></link>, until the 1980s<space/><link><target>rifle</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were used for dismounted drill.</paragraph><paragraph>At<space/><link><target>24-hour clock</target><part>13:00 hours</part></link><space/>every day, the main esplanade in front of the<space/><link><target>Government Palace (Peru)</target><part>Government Palace of Per</part></link><space/>fronting Lima's Main Square serves as the stage for the changing of the guard, undertaken by members of the Presidential Life Guard Escort Dragoons, mounted or dismounted. While the dismounted changing is held on Mondays and Fridays, the mounted ceremony is held twice a month on a Sunday.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Portugal</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Portuguese Army</target></link><space/>still maintains two units which are descended from former regiments of dragoons. These are the 3rd Regiment of Cavalry (the former &quot;<link><target>Olivenza</target><part>Olivena</part></link><space/>Dragoons&quot;) and the 6th Regiment of Cavalry (the former &quot;<link><target>Chaves (Portugal)</target><part>Chaves</part></link><space/>Dragoons&quot;). Both regiments are, presently, armoured units. The<space/><link><target>Portuguese Rapid Reaction Brigade</target></link>' Armoured Reconnaissance Squadron a unit from the 3rd Regiment of Cavalry is known as the &quot;Paratroopers Dragoons&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Portuguese Colonial War</target></link><space/>in the 1960s and the 1970s, the Portuguese Army created an experimental horse platoon, to combat the guerrillas in eastern<space/><link><target>Angola</target></link>. This unit was soon augmented, becoming a group of three squadrons, known as the &quot;<link><target>Angola Dragoons</target></link>&quot;. The Angola Dragoons operated as mounted infantry like the original dragoons each soldier being armed with a<space/><link><target>pistol</target></link><space/>to fire when on horseback and with an<space/><link><target>automatic rifle</target></link>, to use when dismounted. A unit of the same type was being created in<space/><link><target>Mozambique</target></link><space/>when the war ended in 1974.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Spain</heading><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Spanish army</target></link><space/>in 1635 Pedro de la Puente organized in<space/><link><target>Innsbruck</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Austria</target></link>) a body of dragoons, and in 1640 Spain, a<space/><link><target>tercio</target></link><space/>of thousand<space/><link><target>musket</target></link><space/>armed dragons was established. At the end of the 17th century the Spanish had three Tercios in Spain, three Tercios in the<space/><link><target>Netherlands</target></link><space/>and three more in the<space/><link><target>Milan</target></link>, Italy.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1704 the Spanish dragoon like the rest of Tercios, were dissolved and transformed into<space/><link><target>regiment</target></link><space/>s by<space/><link><target>Philip V of Spain</target><part>Felipe V</part></link>. In the 18th century several regiments of dragoons were created in the American viceroys, some of them for police duties.</paragraph><paragraph>Between 1803 and 1815 the Spanish dragoon regiments were renamed as light cavalry (<italics>cazadores</italics>). However this branch of mounted troops was recreated in the late nineteenth century. In 1930 three Spanish dragoon regiments were still in existence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Knotel, pages 408-409 &quot;Uniforms of the World&quot;, ISBN 0-684-16304-7</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sweden</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Norrlands dragonregemente</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Swedish Army</target></link>, dragoons comprise the<space/><link><target>Military Police</target></link><space/>and Military Police Rangers. They also form the Dragoons Battalion of the<space/><link><target>Life Guards (Swedish Army)</target><part>Life Guards</part></link>. The Dragoons Battalion have roots that go back as far as 1523, making it one of the world's oldest military units still in service and the only mounted unit still retained by the Swedish Army. Horses are used for ceremonial purposes only, most often when the dragoons take part in the changing of the guards at The Royal Palace in Stockholm. &quot;<italics>Livdragon</italics>&quot; is the rank of a private cavalryman.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Switzerland</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dragon IMG 3508.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Carbine of a Swiss dragoon, with the strap system allowing a quick draw while mounted. On display at Morges military museum.</part></link>In the Swiss Army, mounted dragoons existed until the early 1970s, when they were converted into Armoured Grenadiers units. The &quot;<italics>Dragoner</italics>&quot; had to prove he was able to keep a horse at home before entering the army. At the end of basic training they had to buy a horse at a reduced price from the army and to take it home together with equipment, uniform and weapon. In the &quot;yearly repetition course&quot; the dragoons served with their horses, often riding from home to the meeting point.</paragraph><paragraph>The abolition of the dragoon units, believed to be the last non-ceremonial horse cavalry in Europe, was a contentious issue in Switzerland. On 5 December 1972 the Swiss<space/><italics><link><target>National Council of Switzerland</target><part>National Council</part></link></italics><space/>approved the measure by 91 votes, against 71 for retention.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">11214 BRG<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-01<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.parlament.ch/afs/data/d/gesch/1972/d_gesch_19720214_620.htm<space/></arg><arg name="date">1972<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">National Council of SwitzerlandNational Council of Switzerland</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>United Kingdom</heading><paragraph>Thirty-one dragoon regiments were in existence at the height of the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic War</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(seven Dragoon Guard regiments - 1st to 7th; five Dragoon regiments - 1st to 6th (5th Dragoons disbanded for mutiny), nineteen Light Dragoon regiments - 7th to 25th).</paragraph><paragraph>In the present-day<space/><link><target>British Army</target></link><space/>regular army, four regiments are designated as dragoons:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>1st The Queen's Dragoon Guards</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Scots Dragoon Guards</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Dragoon Guards</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Light Dragoons</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>The three regiments named as<space/><link><target>Dragoon guards</target><part>Dragoon Guards</part></link><space/>were historically considered heavy cavalry, although by continental standards they were not the heaviest type of cavalry since they carried no armour (unlike<space/><link><target>cuirassier</target><trail>s</trail></link>). The designation &quot;Dragoon Guards&quot; does not indicate the status of<space/><link><target>Household Troops</target></link><space/>but was a distinction awarded to former &quot;Regiments of Horse&quot; when these were converted to Dragoons in 1746.</paragraph><paragraph>The Light Dragoons were formed as light cavalry during the<space/><link><target>Napoleonic Wars</target></link>, and were similar to<space/><link><target>hussar</target><trail>s</trail></link>. In the early 19th century several regiments were simultaneously designated as light dragoons and as<space/><link><target>hussars</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Territorial Army (United Kingdom)</target><part>Territorial Army</part></link>, one of the five squadrons of the<space/><link><target>Royal Yeomanry</target></link><space/>is designated as dragoons: The<space/><link><target>Westminster Dragoons</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>United States</heading><heading level='3'>History</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Battle of Resaca de la Palma.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>220px</part><part>alt=Sepia print of cavalrymen cutting with swords at foot soldiers. A cannon is visible at the left.</part><part>United States dragoons charged Mexican infantry at the<space/><link><target>Battle of Resaca de la Palma</target></link><space/>in May 1846.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Towards the end of 1776 George Washington realized the need for a mounted branch of the military. In January 1777 four regiments of light dragoons were raised. Short term enlistments were abandoned and the Dragoons joined for three years, or &quot;the war&quot;. They participated in most of the major engagements of the<space/><link><target>American Revolutionary War</target></link>, including the Battles of<space/><link><target>Battle of White Plains</target><part>White Plains</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Trenton</target><part>Trenton</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Princeton</target><part>Princeton</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Brandywine</target><part>Brandywine</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Germantown</target><part>Germantown</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Saratoga</target><part>Saratoga</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of Cowpens</target><part>Cowpens</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Battle of Monmouth</target><part>Monmouth</part></link>, as well as the Yorktown campaign.</paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the<space/><link><target>War of 1812</target></link><space/>the U.S. organized the<space/><link><target>Regiment of Light Dragoons (United States)</target><part>Regiment of Light Dragoons</part></link>. For the war<space/><link><target>2nd Regiment of Light Dragoons (United States)</target><part>a second regiment</part></link><space/>was activated; that regiment was consolidated with the original regiment in 1814. The original regiment was consolidated with the Corps of Artillery in June 1815.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Heitman">Heitman pp. 7980</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 1st United States Dragoons explored<space/><link><target>Iowa</target></link><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Black Hawk Purchase</target></link><space/>put the area under U.S. control. In the summer of 1835, the regiment blazed a trail along the<space/><link><target>Des Moines river</target></link><space/>and established outposts from present-day<space/><link><target>Des Moines, Iowa</target><part>Des Moines</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Fort Dodge, Iowa</target><part>Fort Dodge</part></link>. In 1933, the State of Iowa opened the<space/><link><target>Dragoon Trail</target></link>, a scenic and historic drive that follows the path of the 1st United States Dragoons on their historic march.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1861 the two existing U.S. Dragoon regiments were re-designated as the 1st and 2nd Cavalry. This reorganization did not affect their role or equipment, although the traditional orange uniform braiding of the dragoons was replaced by the standard yellow of the Cavalry branch. This marked the official end of dragoons in the U.S. Army, although certain modern units trace their origins back to the historic dragoon regiments.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Modern</heading><paragraph>The 1st and 2nd Battalion,<space/><link><target>48th Infantry Regiment (United States)</target><part>48th Infantry</part></link><space/>were mechanized infantry units assigned to the<space/><link><target>3rd Armored Division (United States)</target><part>3rd Armored Division</part></link><space/>(3AD) in West Germany during the Cold War. The unit crest of the 48th Infantry designated the unit as Dragoons.</paragraph><paragraph>The 1st Dragoons was reformed in the<space/><link><target>Vietnam War</target><part>Vietnam</part></link><space/>era as the<space/><link><target>1st Cavalry Regiment (United States)</target><part>1st Squadron, 1st U.S. Cavalry</part></link>. It has served in the Iraqi War and remains as the oldest cavalry unit, as well as the most decorated one, in the U.S. Army. Today's modern 11 Cavalry is a scout/attack unit, equipped with<space/><link><target>MRAP</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Bradley Fighting Vehicle</target><part>M3A3 Bradley CFVs</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Stryker</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2011</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another modern<space/><link><target>United States Army</target></link><space/>unit informally known as the 2nd Dragoons, is the<space/><link><target>2nd Cavalry Regiment (United States)</target><part>2nd Cavalry Regiment</part></link>. This unit was originally organized as the Second Regiment of Dragoons in 1836 and was renamed the Second Cavalry Regiment in 1861, being redesignated as the<space/><link><target>2nd Armored Cavalry Regiment</target></link><space/>in 1948. The regiment is currently equipped with the<space/><link><target>Stryker</target></link><space/>family of wheeled fighting vehicles and was redesignated 2d Stryker Cavalry Regiment in 2006. In 2011 the 2d Dragoon regiment was redesignated 2d Cavalry Regiment. The 2nd Cavalry Regiment has the distinction of being the longest continuously serving regiment in the United States Army.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://history.dragoons.org/2005/12/10/regimental-designations-and-deployments/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Regimental Designations and Deployments &#124; 2d Dragoons<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">History.dragoons.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-04-09</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 113th Army Band, at Ft. Knox, KY is also officially nicknamed as &quot;The Dragoons.&quot; This derives from its formation as the Band, First Regiment of Dragoons on July 8, 1840.</paragraph><paragraph>Company D, 3rd Light Armored Reconnaissance Battalion of the USMC, are named the &quot;Dragoons&quot;. Their combat history includes<space/><link><target>Iraq War</target><part>Operation Iraqi Freedom</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Operation Enduring Freedom</target></link><space/>from 2002 to 2013.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.1stmardiv.marines.mil/Units/3DLARBN.aspx<space/></arg><arg name="title">1st Marine Division ><space/>Units ><space/>3D LAR BN<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">1stmardiv.marines.mil<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2015-04-09</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Carabinier</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gendarmerie</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Dragonnades</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Citations and notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="authorlink">Gunther E. Rothenberg<space/></arg><arg name="last">Rothenberg<space/></arg><arg name="first">Gunther Erich
<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Art of Warfare in the Age of Napoleon<space/></arg><arg name="location">Bloomington
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Indiana University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">1978<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">77086495
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0253310768<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-01
<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">von Bismark<space/></arg><arg name="first">Graf Friedrich Wilhelm<space/></arg><arg name="others">[[North Ludlow Beamish]] (translator)
<space/></arg><arg name="title">On the Uses and Application of Cavalry in War from the Text of Bismark: With Practical Examples Selected from Ancient and Modern History
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">T. & W. Boone<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="year">1855<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-01
<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Heitman</arg><arg name="first1">Francis B.
<space/></arg><arg name="title">Historical register and dictionary of the United States Army
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">War Department</arg><arg name="accessdate">4 September 2014</arg><arg name="year">1903
<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/details/historicalregist01heitrich</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Cavalry Regiments in the U.S. Army<space/></arg><arg name="first">James A.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Sawicki<space/></arg><arg name="year">1985
<space/></arg><arg name="page">415<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Wyvern Publications<space/></arg><arg name="location">[[Dumfries, VA]]<space/></arg><arg name="lccn">85050072
<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">0960240462</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wiktionary</target></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Dragoons</arg></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target><arg>dragoon</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://napoleonistyka.atspace.com/French_Cavalry.html'>Napoleonic Cavalry: Dragoons, Cuirassiers</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.saskd.ca/opportunities.htm'>Saskatchewan Dragoons (Canada)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bcdragoon.ca/'>British Columbia Dragoons (Canada)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.history.army.mil/books/R&amp;amp;H/R&amp;amp;H-1CV.htm'>First Regiment of Cavalry (USA)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.militaryhorse.org/'>The Society of the Military Horse</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://repmariscalnieto.galeon.com/dragoons.html'>Field Marshal Nieto Regiment of Cavalry (Per)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=6SWcVaqH9rA'>Per 1970: Changing of the Dragoon Guard</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:Cavalry</target></link><link><target>Category:Infantry</target></link><link><target>Category:Dragoons</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:18th- and 19th-century warrior types</target></link><link><target>Category:Obsolete occupations</target></link></paragraph></article>