<article title='Vladimir_Harkonnen'><paragraph><template><target>Infobox character</target><arg name="colour"><space/>#DAA520
</arg><arg name="series"><space/>[[Dune (franchise)|Dune]]
</arg><arg name="creator"><space/>[[Frank Herbert]]
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Baron Vladimir Harkonnen
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Baron Harkonnen-John Schoenherr-Illustrated Dune (1978).jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Baron Vladimir Harkonnen by [[John Schoenherr]], from ''[[The Illustrated Dune]]'' (1978)
</arg><arg name="children"><space/>[[Lady Jessica]]
</arg><arg name="relatives"><space/>{{Plainlist|
* [[Dmitri Harkonnen]] (father)<space/><ref name</arg><arg name="family"><space/>[[House Harkonnen]]
</arg><arg name="portrayer"><space/>{{Plainlist|
* [[Kenneth McMillan (actor)|Kenneth McMillan]] ([[Dune (film)|1984 film]])
* [[Ian McNeice]] ([[Frank Herbert's Dune|2000 series]]/[[Frank Herbert's Children of Dune|2003 series]])
}}
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>''[[Dune (novel)|Dune]]'' (1965)
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>''[[Dune: House Corrino]]'' (2001)<space/><ref>A [[ghola]] of Baron Harkonnen is created in ''[[Hunters of Dune]]'' (2006) and also appears in ''[[Sandworms of Dune]]'' (2007); these may or may not be considered appearances of the original character.</ref>
</arg></template><link><target>File:McMillan as Harkonnen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Kenneth McMillan (actor)</target><part>Kenneth McMillan</part></link><space/>as Harkonnen in ''<link><target>Dune (film)</target><part>Dune</part></link>'' (1984)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Baron Vladimir Harkonnen</bold><space/>is a<space/><link><target>fictional character</target></link><space/>and antagonist from the<space/><link><target>Dune (franchise)</target><part>''Dune'' universe</part></link><space/>created by<space/><link><target>Frank Herbert</target></link>. He is primarily featured in the 1965 novel<space/><italics><link><target>Dune (novel)</target><part>Dune</part></link></italics><space/>and is also a prominent character in the<space/><italics><link><target>Prelude to Dune</target></link></italics><space/><link><target>prequel</target></link><space/><link><target>trilogy</target></link><space/>(1999-2001) by<space/><link><target>Brian Herbert</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kevin J. Anderson</target></link>. The character is brought back as a<space/><link><target>ghola</target></link><space/>in the Herbert/Anderson<space/><link><target>sequel</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which conclude the original series,<space/><italics><link><target>Hunters of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2006) and<space/><italics><link><target>Sandworms of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2007).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Characteristics</heading><paragraph>Herbert's &quot;Appendix IV: The Almanak en-Ashraf (Selected Excerpts of the Noble Houses)&quot; in<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>says of Harkonnen (in part):<template><target>quote</target><arg name="VLADIMIR HARKONNEN (10,110-10,193) Commonly referred to as Baron Harkonnen, his title is officially Siridar (planetary governor) Baron. Vladimir Harkonnen is the direct-line male descendant of the Bashar [[Abulurd Harkonnen]] who was banished for cowardice after the [[Battle of Corrin]]. The return of [[House Harkonnen]] to power generally is ascribed to adroit manipulation of the [[whale fur]] market and later consolidation with [[Melange (fictional drug)|melange]] wealth from [[Arrakis]].<ref name">"Appendix">{{cite book |last</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics>Dune</italics>, Herbert writes that the Baron possesses a &quot;<link><target>bass (vocal range)</target><part>basso</part></link><space/>voice&quot; and is so &quot;grossly and immensely fat&quot; that he requires<space/><link><target>anti-gravity</target></link><space/>devices known as<space/><link><target>suspensor (Dune)</target><part>suspensor</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to support his weight.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suspensors">From<space/><italics>Dune</italics>: &quot;As [Baron Vladimir Harkonnen] emerged from the shadows, his figure took on dimension &amp;mdash; grossly and immensely fat. And with subtle bulges beneath folds of his dark robes to reveal that all this fat was sustained partly by portable suspensors harnessed to his flesh. He might weigh two hundred Standard kilos in actuality, but his feet would carry no more than fifty of them.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As ruthless and cruel as he is intelligent and cunning, the Baron's greatest skill is his talent for the subtle and clever manipulation of others through their weaknesses or his understanding of human nature. His sexual preference for young men is implied in<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Children of Dune</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>From<space/><italics>Dune</italics>: &quot;I'll be in my sleeping chambers,&quot; the Baron said. &quot;Bring me that young fellow we bought on<space/><link><target>Gamont</target></link>, the one with the lovely eyes. Drug him well. I don't feel like wrestling.&quot;</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>From<space/><italics>Dune</italics>: &quot;Why haven't you ever bought a Bene Gesserit, Uncle?&quot; Feyd-Rautha asked. &quot;With a Truthsayer at your side &amp;mdash;&quot; &quot;You know my tastes!&quot; the Baron snapped.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>The Baron says to Feyd in<space/><italics>Dune</italics>: &quot;This old fool saw through the shielded needle you'd planted in that slave boy's thigh. Right where I'd put my hand on it, eh?&quot;</extension><space/>It is noted, however, that he &quot;once permitted himself to be seduced&quot; in the liaison which produced his secret daughter.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jessica's father">Paul says to Jessica in<space/><italics>Dune</italics>, &quot;And, mother mine, there's a thing you don't know and should &amp;mdash; we are Harkonnens ... take my word for it. I've walked the future, I've looked at a record, I've seen a place, I have all the data. We're Harkonnens ... You're the Baron's own daughter,&quot; he said, and watched the way she pressed her hands to her mouth. &quot;The Baron sampled many pleasures in his youth, and once permitted himself to be seduced. But it was for the genetic purposes of the Bene Gesserit, by one of you.&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Plotlines</heading><heading level='3'><italics>Dune</italics></heading><paragraph>As<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>begins, a longstanding feud exists between the Harkonnens of<space/><link><target>Giedi Prime</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>House Atreides</target><part>Atreides</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Caladan</target></link>. The Baron's intent to exterminate the Atreides line seems close to fruition as<space/><link><target>Leto I Atreides</target><part>Duke Leto Atreides</part></link><space/>is lured to the<space/><link><target>desert planet</target></link><space/>Arrakis on the pretense of taking over the valuable melange operation there. The Baron has an agent in the Atreides household: Leto's own physician, the trusted<space/><link><target>Suk School</target><part>Suk doctor</part></link><space/><link><target>Wellington Yueh</target></link>. Though Suk Imperial Conditioning supposedly makes the subject incapable of inflicting harm, the Baron's twisted<space/><link><target>Mentat</target></link><space/><link><target>Piter De Vries</target></link><space/>notes:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>It's assumed that ultimate conditioning cannot be removed without killing the subject. However, as<space/><link><target>Archimedes</target><part>someone</part></link><space/>once observed, given the right lever you can move a planet. We found the lever that moved the doctor.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Baron has taken Yueh's wife<space/><link><target>Wanna (Dune)</target><part>Wanna</part></link><space/>prisoner, threatening her with interminable torture unless Yueh complies with his demands. Harkonnen also distracts Leto's Mentat<space/><link><target>Thufir Hawat</target></link><space/>from discovering Yueh by guiding Hawat toward another suspect: Leto's<space/><link><target>Bene Gesserit</target></link><space/><link><target>concubinage</target><part>concubine</part></link><space/><link><target>Lady Jessica</target></link>. The Atreides are soon attacked by Harkonnen forces (secretly supplemented by the seemingly unstoppable Imperial<space/><link><target>Sardaukar</target></link>) as Yueh disables the protective shields around the Atreides palace on Arrakis. As instructed, Yueh takes Leto prisoner; however, desiring to slay the Baron, Yueh provides the captive Leto with a fake tooth filled with poisonous gas as a means of simultaneous<space/><link><target>assassination</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>suicide</target></link>. De Vries kills Yueh but he also dies with Leto in the assassination attempt; however Harkonnen survives. The Baron then manipulates Hawat into his service, by convincing Hawat that Lady Jessica was the traitor and using Hawat's desire for revenge on Lady Jessica and the Emperor as motivation to assist House Harkonnen.</paragraph><paragraph>Leto and Jessica's son<space/><link><target>Paul Atreides</target></link><space/>flee into the desert with Jessica, and both are presumed dead. Paul's<space/><link><target>prescience</target></link><space/>helps him determine the identity of Jessica's father, the &quot;maternal grandfather who cannot be named&quot; &amp;mdash; the Baron himself.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Jessica's father"></extension><space/>Over the next two years, Harkonnen learns that both of his nephews<space/><link><target>Glossu Rabban</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Feyd-Rautha</target></link><space/>are conspiring against him to obtain his throne; he lets them continue to do so, reasoning that they have to somehow learn to organize a<space/><link><target>conspiracy (political)</target><part>conspiracy</part></link>. As punishment for a failed assassination attempt against him, Harkonnen forces Feyd to single-handedly slaughter all the female slaves who serve as Feyd's lovers. He explains that Feyd has to learn the price of failure.</paragraph><paragraph>The Baron's plan to assure Feyd's power is to install him as ruler of Arrakis after a period of tyrannical misrule by Rabban, making Feyd appear to be the savior of the people. However, a crisis on Arrakis begins when the mysterious<space/><link><target>Muad'Dib</target></link><space/>emerges as a leader of the native<space/><link><target>Fremen</target></link><space/>tribes against the rule of the Harkonnens. Eventually, a series of Fremen victories against Beast Rabban threaten to disrupt the trade of the spice. The<space/><link><target>Padishah Emperor</target></link><space/><link><target>Shaddam IV</target></link><space/>decides to intervene himself and arrives on Arrakis along with legions of Sardaukar forces. Shaddam and the Baron are shocked to learn that Muad'Dib is, of course, a very-much-alive Paul Atreides. The Imperial forces fall prey to a surprise attack by the Fremen. Part of the Fremen/Atreides strategy is to wait until a<space/><link><target>sandworm (Dune)</target><part>sandworm</part></link><space/>shorts out the force field shields of the Harkonnen/Imperial transport ships, disable them with projectile weapons, and then attack with a vast assault force, using sandworms under cover of the severe weather to break the enemy lines. The Sardaukar and Harkonnen forces are trapped on the planet, astonished at the sandworm mounts and vast numbers of their attackers. Their past ruthlessness gives them little hope of quarter from the enraged Fremen.</paragraph><paragraph>Rabban dies in the initial part of the battle; the Harkonnen army is massacred to the last man and almost all the Imperial Sardaukar are killed. Baron Harkonnen himself is poisoned with a<space/><link><target>gom jabbar</target></link><space/>by Paul's young sister<space/><link><target>Alia Atreides</target></link>, his own granddaughter, and dies at the age of 83. Paul then kills Feyd in ritual combat. House Harkonnen's virtual extermination removes it as a galactic power, but Paul's ascension to the Imperial throne in Shaddam's place guarantees that Vladimir's descendants will long reign as the Imperial House Atreides.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Children of Dune</italics></heading><paragraph>Alia had been born with her ancestral memories in the womb, a circumstance the Bene Gesserit refer to as<space/><link><target>abomination (Dune)</target><part>Abomination</part></link>, because in their experience it is inevitable that the individual will become possessed by the personality of one of their ancestors. In<space/><italics><link><target>Children of Dune</target></link></italics>, Alia falls victim to this prediction when she shares control of her body with the ego-memory of the Baron Harkonnen, and eventually falls under his power. Alia eventually commits<space/><link><target>suicide</target></link>, realizing that Harkonnen's<space/><link><target>consciousness</target></link><space/>has surpassed her abilities to contain him.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Prelude to Dune</italics></heading><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>Prelude to Dune</italics><space/>prequel series by Brian Herbert and Anderson, it is established that Baron Vladimir Harkonnen is the son and heir of<space/><link><target>Dmitri Harkonnen</target></link><space/>and his wife Victoria. Harkonnen's father had been the head of House Harkonnen and ruled the planet Giedi Prime. Trained since youth as a possible successor, Vladimir had been eventually chosen over his half-brother<space/><link><target>Abulurd Harkonnen</target><part>Abulurd</part></link><space/>(namesake of the original). Unhappy with his brother's doings, Abulurd eventually marries Emmi Rabban and renounces the family name and his rights to the title. Under the name Abulurd Rabban, he reigns as governor of the secondary Harkonnen planet<space/><link><target>Lankiveil</target></link>. Abulurd and his wife have two sons: Glossu Rabban (later nicknamed &quot;Beast Rabban&quot; after he murders his own father) and Feyd-Rautha; Vladimir later adopts the boys back into House Harkonnen, and Feyd becomes his designated heir.</paragraph><paragraph>The Baron's most prominent political rival is Duke Leto Atreides; the Harkonnens and the Atreides have been bitter enemies for millennia, since the<space/><link><target>Battle of Corrin</target></link><space/>that ended the<space/><link><target>Butlerian Jihad</target></link>. When Emperor Shaddam IV orchestrates a plot to destroy the &quot;Red Duke&quot; Leto, the Baron eagerly lends his aid.</paragraph><paragraph>The young Baron Vladimir is described as an exceedingly handsome man, possessing red hair and a near-perfect physique. The Bene Gesserit<space/><link><target>Reverend Mother (Dune)</target><part>Reverend Mother</part></link><space/><link><target>Gaius Helen Mohiam</target></link><space/>is instructed by the Sisterhood to collect the genetic material of Baron Vladimir Harkonnen (through conception) for their breeding program. As the Baron's<space/><link><target>homosexuality</target></link><space/>is something of an open secret, Mohiam<space/><link><target>blackmail</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>him into having sexual relations with her and conceives his child. When that daughter proves genetically undesirable, Mohiam kills her and returns to Harkonnen for a second try; at this point he drugs and viciously rapes her. She exacts her retribution by infecting him with a rare, incurable disease that later causes his obesity. Mohiam's second child with the Baron is Jessica.<extension extension_name='ref'>According to the authors, the revelation that Mohiam is Jessica's mother was pulled directly from Frank Herbert's working notes for the original<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>series. See:<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.scifi.com/transcripts/2000/herbertandanderson.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Chat with Brian Herbert and Kevin J. Anderson: ''Dune: House Harkonnen''<space/></arg><arg name="year">2000<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">SciFi.com (Internet Archive)<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">November 5, 2007<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20071105073412/http://www.scifi.com/transcripts/2000/herbertandanderson.html<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>2007-11-05</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Dune: House Harkonnen</target></link></italics>, the deteriorating Baron at first walks with the assistance of a cane, then relies on belt-mounted suspensors to retain mobility. He consults numerous doctors in the expanse of time between the<space/><italics><link><target>Dune: House Atreides</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Dune: House Harkonnen</italics>, up to and including his future instrument Dr. Yueh, all of whom are ultimately no help. To conceal this debilitation, he pretends that his obesity is due to intentional overindulgence, lest the<space/><link><target>Landsraad</target></link><space/>remove him from power. When he determines that Mohiam inflicted him with the disease, he attempts to coerce her into revealing the cure, but soon discovers that there is none.</paragraph><paragraph>The Baron, Duke Leto, and Jessica herself are unaware that Jessica is secretly the Baron's daughter or that he has even fathered one; in the year 10,176, the Baron's grandson Paul is born to Leto and Jessica.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>Hunters of Dune</italics></heading><paragraph>In<space/><italics><link><target>Hunters of Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(2006), the continuation of the original series by Brian Herbert and Kevin J. Anderson, the Baron is resurrected as a ghola (5,029 years after the death of Alia) by the<space/><link><target>Lost Tleilaxu</target></link><space/><link><target>Uxtal</target></link>, acting on orders from the<space/><link><target>Face Dancer</target></link><space/><link><target>Khrone</target></link>. Khrone intends to use the Baron ghola to manipulate a ghola of Paul Atreides, named<space/><link><target>Paolo (Dune)</target><part>Paolo</part></link>. Khrone tries various torture techniques for three years to awaken the 12-year-old Baron's genetic memories; these methods fail due to the Baron's<space/><link><target>sadomasochism</target><part>sadomasochistic</part></link><space/>nature. Khrone is successful when he imprisons the Baron in a sensory deprivation tank for a prolonged period; the Baron's memories of his former life return. Ironically, the reincarnated Baron is soon haunted by the voice of Alia in his mind; the source of this inner Alia is never explained.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In adaptations</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:McNeice as Harkonnen (2000).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Ian McNeice</target></link><space/>as Harkonnen in the<space/><link><target>Frank Herbert's Dune</target><part>''Dune'' miniseries</part></link><space/>(2000)</part></link>In<space/><link><target>David Lynch</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Dune (film)</target><part>1984 film</part></link>, Baron Harkonnen was portrayed by<space/><link><target>Kenneth McMillan (actor)</target><part>Kenneth McMillan</part></link>. In this characterization, he is grotesquely overweight, dressed in filthy garments and covered in large, black<space/><link><target>pustule</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which require constant draining and treatment. This version of the character is more overtly unstable than in the novel, screaming and laughing incoherently at any given moment and even drinking the blood of a servant after removing a &quot;heart plug.&quot; Diverging from the novel, after Alia pricks Harkonnen with the gom jabbar, she pushes him and sends him flying through a hole in the palace wall, to be devoured by a giant sandworm.</paragraph><paragraph>British actor<space/><link><target>Ian McNeice</target></link>'s interpretation of the Baron in the 2000<space/><link><target>Syfy</target><part>Sci-Fi Channel</part></link><space/><link><target>miniseries</target></link><space/><italics><link><target>Frank Herbert's Dune</target></link></italics><space/>(and its<space/><link><target>sequel</target></link>, 2003's<space/><italics><link><target>Frank Herbert's Children of Dune</target><part>Children of Dune</part></link></italics>) is, though dramatic, somewhat lighter, more eloquent and sane in comparison to Lynch's version, and therefore more consistent with the novel. Though the Baron still takes<space/><link><target>Sadomasochism</target><part>sadistic</part></link><space/>enjoyment in the suffering of others, he is portrayed as somewhat flamboyant, pompous, calculating and self-indulgent, with a tendency to speak in<space/><link><target>iambic pentameter</target></link><space/>when the mood strikes him.</paragraph><paragraph>Though Herbert's novel<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>seems to describe Harkonnen's suspensor belt as simply enabling him to stand and walk upright rather than actually &quot;fly,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Suspensors"></extension><space/>both the 1984 film and the 2000 miniseries feature the Baron utilizing the suspensors to levitate off the ground and float through the air in a flying-like manner. The later<space/><italics>Prelude to Dune</italics><space/>prequels also employ this floating ability. Herbert does, however, note Harkonnen floating slightly off the floor after he is killed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Floating">From<space/><italics>Dune</italics>: &quot;He rolled sideways in his suspensors, a sagging mass of flesh supported inches off the floor with head lolling and mouth hanging open.&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other media</heading><paragraph>The video game<space/><italics><link><target>Emperor: Battle for Dune</target></link></italics>, whose in-game<space/><link><target>cut scene</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are visually inspired by David Lynch's film, features a character named Baron Rakan Harkonnen, portrayed by<space/><link><target>Mike McShane</target></link>. This Harkonnen is nearly identical to the film's version of Vladimir in both appearance (minus the belt-mounted suspensors) and personality, and also dies by poisoning.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>H. R. Giger</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>Harkonnen Capo Chair</target></link><space/>is a chair originally designed by the artist as set dressing for an unrealized 1970s adaptation of<space/><italics>Dune</italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Alejandro Jodorowsky</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">H. R.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Giger<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">H. R. Giger<space/></arg><arg name="title">H.R.Giger's Film Design<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Titan Books]]<space/></arg><arg name="date">1996<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">9781852867195</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hrgiger.com/chairs.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">H.R. Giger's Harkonnen Chairs<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">HRGiger.com<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 August 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>imdb character</target><arg>0008386</arg><arg>Baron Vladimir Harkonnen</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Dune franchise</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Harkonnen, Vladimir</target></template><link><target>Category:Dune characters</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional gay males</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional dictators</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional barons and baronesses</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional murderers</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional rapists</target></link><link><target>Category:Fictional characters introduced in 1965</target></link><link><target>Category:Literary villains</target></link></paragraph></article>