<article title='Carbine'><paragraph><template><target>other uses</target><arg>Carbine (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Distinguish</target><arg>carbyne</arg><arg>carbene</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg>article pertaining to a class of [[firearm]]s</arg><arg name="date">May 2009</arg></template><link><target>File:Muskets carbines musketoons blunderbuss.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Various muzzle-loading arms, to scale; numbers 1, 10, and 11 are identified as carbines. (Encyclopdia Britannica, 1910)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>carbine</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɑr</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>iː</arg><arg>n</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>ɑr</arg><arg>b</arg><arg>aɪ</arg><arg>n</arg></template>),<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/search?q=carbine'>&quot;Carbine&quot;</link>.<space/><link><target>Dictionary.com</target></link>. Retrieved October 8, 2014.</extension><space/>from French<space/><italics>carabine</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;carbine.&quot; Merriam-Webster Online Dictionary. 2010. http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/carbine</extension><space/>is a<space/><link><target>long gun</target><part>long arm</part></link><space/>firearm but with a shorter barrel than a<space/><link><target>rifle</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>musket</target></link>. Many carbines are shortened versions of full length rifles, shooting the same ammunition, while others fire lower-powered ammunition, including those designed for pistols.</paragraph><paragraph>The smaller size and lighter weight of carbines makes them easier to handle. They are typically issued to high-mobility troops such as special-operations soldiers and paratroopers, as well as to mounted, supply, or other non-infantry personnel whose roles do not require full-sized rifles.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><heading level='3'>Word origin</heading><paragraph>Some sources derive the name of the weapon from the name of its first users cavalry troopers called &quot;<link><target>carabinier</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;, from the French<space/><italics>carabine</italics>, from the Old French<space/><italics>carabin</italics><space/>(soldier armed with a musket), perhaps from<space/><italics>escarrabin</italics>, gravedigger, which derives from<space/><italics>scarabee</italics>,<space/><link><target>Scarabaeidae</target><part>scarab beetle</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.thefreedictionary.com/carbine'>The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, Fourth Edition</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Early history: before the 1900s</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Carbine mod 1793-IMG 4737-white.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Carbine model 1793, used by the French Army during the<space/><link><target>French Revolutionary Wars</target></link>.</part></link><template><target>multiple image</target><arg name="align"><space/>right<space/></arg><arg name="direction"><space/>horizontal<space/></arg><arg name="header_align"><space/>left/right/center<space/></arg><arg name="header"></arg><arg name="footer"><space/>'''Left image''': [[Jean Lepage]] [[flintlock]] carbine named "du [[French Consulate|Premier Consul]]" in honour of [[Napoleon]] , circa 1800.<br><space/>'''Right image''': Rifling of Lepage carbine.</arg><arg name="footer_align"><space/>left<space/></arg><arg name="image1">Lepage silex gun dite du Premier Consul circa 1800.jpg</arg><arg name="width1"><space/>350</arg><arg name="caption1"><space/></arg><arg name="image2">Rifling of Lepage carbine circa 1800.jpg</arg><arg name="width2"><space/>69<space/></arg><arg name="caption2"><space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The carbine was originally a lighter, shortened weapon developed for the cavalry. Carbines were short enough to be loaded and fired from horseback but this was rarely done<template><target>spaced ndash</target></template>a moving horse is a very unsteady platform, and once halted a soldier can load and fire more easily if dismounted, which also makes him a smaller target. The principal advantage of the carbine's length was portability. Troops could carry full length muskets comfortably enough on horseback if just riding from A to B (the practice of the original<space/><link><target>dragoon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and other<space/><link><target>mounted infantry</target></link>). Cavalry proper (a &quot;Regiment of Horse&quot;) had to ride with some agility and engage in sword-wielding melees with opposing cavalry so carrying anything long would be a dangerous encumbrance. A carbine was typically no longer than a sheathed sabre, both arranged to hang with their tops clear of the rider's elbows and bottoms clear of the horse's legs.</paragraph><paragraph>Carbines were usually less accurate and less powerful than the longer muskets (and later rifles) of the infantry, due to a shorter<space/><link><target>Sight (device)</target><part>sight</part></link><space/>plane and lower velocity of bullets fired from the shortened barrel. With the advent of fast-burning<space/><link><target>smokeless powder</target></link>, the velocity disadvantages of the shorter barrels became less of an issue (see<space/><link><target>internal ballistics</target></link>). Eventually, the use of horse-mounted cavalry would decline, but carbines continued to be issued and used by many who preferred a lighter, more compact weapon even at the cost of reduced long-range accuracy and power.</paragraph><paragraph>During the 19th century, carbines were often developed separately from the infantry rifles, and in many cases did not even use the same ammunition, which made for supply difficulties. A notable weapon developed towards the end of the<space/><link><target>American Civil War</target></link><space/>by the Union was the<space/><link><target>Spencer carbine</target></link>. It had a spring-powered<space/><link><target>Magazine (firearm)</target><part>magazine</part></link><space/>in the stock which held seven rounds. In the late 19th century it became common for a number of nations to make<space/><link><target>bolt-action</target></link><space/>rifles in both full-length and carbine versions. One of the most popular and recognizable carbines was the Winchester<space/><link><target>lever-action</target></link><space/>carbine, with several versions using<space/><link><target>revolver</target></link><space/>cartridges. This made it an ideal choice for<space/><link><target>cowboy</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and explorers, who could carry a revolver and a carbine, both using the same ammunition.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Shorter rifles, shorter carbines: World War I and World War II</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Garandcar.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>M1 Garand and M1 Carbine</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the decades following<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>, the standard battle rifle used by armies around the world had been growing shorter, either by redesign or by the general issue of carbine versions instead of full-length rifles. For example, the Russian Model 1891 rifle with an<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>800</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>barrel was shortened to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>730</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in 1930, and to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>510</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in 1938; the German<space/><link><target>Mauser</target></link><space/>98 rifles went from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>740</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in 1898 to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>600</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in 1935 as the<space/><italics>Karabiner Kurz</italics><space/>(K98k or<space/><link><target>Kar98k</target></link>), or &quot;short carbine&quot;. The barrel lengths in rifles used by the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>did not change between the<space/><link><target>bolt-action</target></link><space/><link><target>M1903 Springfield rifle</target><part>M1903</part></link><space/>rifle of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/><link><target>M1 Garand rifle</target></link>, but the<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>610</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>barrel on the M1903 was short for its day. The US<space/><link><target>M1 carbine</target><part>M1 Carbine</part></link><space/>was more of a traditional carbine in that it was significantly shorter and lighter, with a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>457.2</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>barrel, than the M1 Garand rifle. The M1 Carbine was not a shorter version of the<space/><link><target>M1 Garand rifle</target><part>M1 Garand</part></link>, as was typical for rifles vs. carbines in the 19th century, but a wholly different design firing a smaller, less-powerful cartridge.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>File:Jungle Carbine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>A LeeEnfield No. 5 Mk I &quot;<link><target>Jungle Carbine</target></link>&quot; rifle, which fired a full-size<space/><link><target>.303 British</target><part>.303 calibre</part></link><space/>rifle cartridge.</part></link>The<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link><space/>also developed a &quot;<link><target>Jungle Carbine</target></link>&quot; version of their<space/><link><target>LeeEnfield</target></link><space/>service rifle, featuring a shorter barrel, flash suppressor, and manufacturing modifications designed to decrease the rifle's weight. Officially titled<space/><italics>Rifle, No. 5 Mk I</italics>, it was introduced in the closing months of World War II, but did not see widespread service until the<space/><link><target>Korean War</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Mau Mau uprising</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Malayan Emergency</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>After World War II</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Karabiner 98k.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Mauser ''<link><target>Karabiner 98k</target><part>Karabiner 98 Kurz</part></link>''. Translate as '''Carbine 98 Short''' or a shortened carbine of the<space/><link><target>Gewehr 98</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:FAL IMG 1528.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>FN FAL</target></link><space/>rifle - (left) full size, (right) carbine/paratrooper variant with a folding stock and shortened barrel</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A shorter weapon was more convenient when riding in a truck,<space/><link><target>armored personnel carrier</target></link>,<space/><link><target>helicopter</target></link><space/>or aircraft, and also when engaged in close-range combat. Based on the combat experience of World War II, the criteria used for selecting infantry weapons began to change. Unlike previous wars, which were often fought mainly from fixed lines and trenches, World War II was a highly mobile war, often fought in cities, forests, or other areas where mobility and visibility were restricted. In addition, improvements in<space/><link><target>artillery</target></link><space/>made moving infantry in open areas even less practical than it had been.</paragraph><paragraph>The majority of enemy contacts were at ranges of less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>300</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>yd</arg><arg name="abbr">off</arg></template>, and the enemy was exposed to fire for only short periods of time as they moved from cover to cover. Most rounds fired were not aimed at an enemy combatant, but instead fired in the enemy's direction to keep them from moving and firing back (see<space/><link><target>suppressive fire</target></link>). These situations did not require a heavy rifle, firing full-power rifle bullets with long-range accuracy. A less-powerful weapon would still produce casualties at the shorter ranges encountered in actual combat, and the reduced recoil would allow more shots to be fired in the short amount of time an enemy was visible. The lower-powered round would also weigh less, allowing a soldier to carry more ammunition. With no need of a long barrel to fire full-power ammunition, a shorter barrel could be used. A shorter barrel made the weapon weigh less and was easier to handle in tight spaces, and was easier to shoulder quickly to fire a shot at an unexpected target.<space/><link><target>Automatic firearm</target><part>Full-automatic</part></link><space/>fire was also considered a desirable feature, allowing the soldier to fire short bursts of three to five rounds, increasing the probability of a hit on a moving target.</paragraph><paragraph>The Germans had experimented with<space/><link><target>selective-fire</target></link><space/>carbines firing rifle cartridges during the early years of World War II. These were determined to be less than ideal, as the recoil of full-power rifle cartridges caused the weapon to be uncontrollable in full-automatic fire. They then developed an intermediate-power cartridge round, which was accomplished by reducing the power and the length of the standard<space/><link><target>7.9257mm Mauser</target></link><space/>rifle cartridge to create the<space/><link><target>7.9233mm</target></link><space/><italics>Kurz</italics><space/>(Short) cartridge. A selective-fire weapon was developed to fire this shorter cartridge, eventually resulting in the<space/><link><target>Sturmgewehr 44</target></link>, later translated as &quot;<link><target>assault rifle</target></link>&quot;. After World War II, the USSR would adopt a similar weapon, the<space/><link><target>AK-47</target></link>, which became the standard Soviet infantry weapon. The United States during World War II also had the<space/><link><target>M1 carbine</target><part>M2 Carbine</part></link>, a selective-fire version of the<space/><link><target>M1 carbine</target><part>M1 Carbine</part></link><space/>firing the same .30 Carbine cartridge. However, the semi-automatic M1 carbine was produced in a 10-to-1 ratio to the M2.</paragraph><paragraph>Although the<space/><link><target>NATO</target></link><space/>countries did not adopt an intermediate-power round, they continued the trend toward shorter and lighter<space/><link><target>magazine (firearm)</target><part>magazine</part></link>-fed<space/><link><target>battle rifle</target><trail>s</trail></link>. NATO adopted the<space/><link><target>7.6251mm NATO</target></link><space/>round (which in reality is only slightly different ballistically to the<space/><link><target>.308 Winchester</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>.303 British</target></link><space/>cartridges), along with several rifles such as the<space/><link><target>FN FAL</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>M14 rifle</target><part>M14</part></link>.<link><target>File:M855 drop during 25-meter zeroing trajectory M16A2 M4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Bullet drop of the M16A2 rifle (yellow) vs M4 carbine (red)</part></link>By the 1960s NATO had adopted the<space/><link><target>5.56 NATO</target></link><space/>cartridge. This round was even lighter and smaller than the Soviet AK-47 cartridge, but possessed higher velocity. In U.S. service, the<space/><link><target>M16 rifle</target><part>M16</part></link><space/>assault rifle replaced the M14 as the standard<space/><link><target>infantry</target></link><space/>weapon, although the M14 continued to be used by<space/><link><target>designated marksmen</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Lighter carbines came to be adopted as the standard infantry long rifle. What changed was that only a certain number of soldiers now needed to retain longer range weapons, serving as designated marksmen. Development of lighter assault rifles continued, matched by developments in even lighter carbines. At the same time the infantry switched to 5.56&amp;nbsp;mm weapons, carbines like the<space/><link><target>AKS-74U</target></link><space/>(which fired a Warsaw pact<space/><link><target>5.4539mm</target></link><space/>round) and<space/><link><target>CAR-15</target></link><space/>were being developed.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Modern history</heading><heading level='3'>Contemporary military forces</heading><paragraph><template><target>Double image</target><arg>right</arg><arg>AUG A1 508mm 04.jpg</arg><arg>200</arg><arg>AUG A1 407mm 03.jpg</arg><arg>200</arg><arg name="Steyr AUG ''rifle'' ({{convert|508|mm|in|1|abbr">on}} barrel).</arg><arg name="Steyr AUG ''carbine'' ({{convert|407|mm|in|1|abbr">on}} barrel). Carbine conversion is achieved by changing to a shorter barrel.</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>By the 1990s, the US had adopted the<space/><link><target>M4 carbine</target></link>, a derivative of the M16 family which fired the same<space/><link><target>5.56</target><trail>mm</trail></link><space/>cartridge but was lighter and shorter (in overall length and barrel length), resulting in marginally reduced range and power.</paragraph><paragraph>Meanwhile, many armies are experiencing a backlash against carbines and lighter rifles in general, and are equipping selected soldiers, usually called<space/><link><target>Designated marksman</target><part>Designated Marksmen</part></link>, or DM, with higher power rifles. While firing a higher quantity of smaller bullets makes it easier to hit a target (and is therefore good for beginner marksmen), it offers very little to more advanced marksmen. Furthermore, the additional range of the heavier weapons has proven to be necessary in open environments such as deserts. As a result, the focus on more highly trained soldiers equipped with, for example, 7.62&amp;nbsp;mm NATO firing rifles, such as the<space/><link><target>U.S. Marine Corps Designated Marksman Rifle</target></link><space/>variant of the<space/><link><target>M14 rifle</target><part>M14</part></link>, has increased somewhat. A squad of soldiers armed with assault rifles would have a single soldier assigned as DM who would carry a battle rifle for selectively engaging long range targets. The DM differs from the sniper in that the DM moves with his unit, and engages targets at ranges beyond the 500 meter (about 550 yd) effective range of modern assault rifles, but less than the 600 meter (about 650 yd) range which is the optimal engagement range for snipers.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Special forces</heading><paragraph>Special forces need to perform fast, decisive operations. A pistol, though light and quick to operate, is viewed as not having enough power. Consequently, carbines have gained wide acceptance among<space/><link><target>United States Special Operations Command</target><part>SOCOM</part></link>,<space/><link><target>United Kingdom Special Forces</target><part>UKSF</part></link><space/>and other communities.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Usage</heading><paragraph>The smaller size and lighter weight of carbines makes them easier to handle in close-quarter situations such as<space/><link><target>urban warfare</target><part>urban</part></link><space/>engagements, when deploying from military vehicles, or in any situation where space is confined. The disadvantages of carbines relative to rifles include inferior long-range accuracy and a shorter effective range. Larger than a<space/><link><target>submachine gun</target></link>, they are harder to maneuver in tight encounters where superior range and<space/><link><target>stopping power</target></link><space/>at distance are not great considerations. Firing the same ammunition as rifles gives carbines the advantage of standardization over those<space/><link><target>personal defense weapon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(PDWs) that require proprietary<space/><link><target>Cartridge (firearms)</target><part>cartridges</part></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The modern usage of the term carbine covers much the same scope as it always had, namely lighter weapons (generally rifles) with barrels up to 20 inches in length. These weapons can be considered carbines, while rifles with barrels longer than 20 inches are generally not considered carbines unless specifically named so. Modern carbines use ammunition ranging from that used in light pistols up to powerful rifle cartridges, with the usual exception of high velocity magnum cartridges. In the more powerful cartridges, the short barrel of a carbine has significant disadvantages in velocity, and the high residual pressure when the bullet exits the barrel results in substantially greater<space/><link><target>Wiktionary:muzzle blast</target><part>muzzle blast</part></link>.<space/><link><target>Flash suppressor</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>muzzle brake</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are common solutions to this problem, which may ease their acceptance.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pistol-caliber carbines (PCC)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Marlin Model 1894C .357 Magnum.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Marlin Model 1894</target><trail>C</trail></link><space/>&amp;mdash; .357 Magnum carbine</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>One of the more unusual classes of carbine is the pistol caliber carbine or PCC. These first appeared soon after metallic cartridges became common. These were developed as &quot;companions&quot; to the popular<space/><link><target>revolver</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the day, firing the same cartridge but allowing more velocity and accuracy than the revolver. These were carried by<space/><link><target>cowboy</target><trail>s</trail></link>, lawmen, and others in the<space/><link><target>Old West</target></link>. The classic combination would be a<space/><link><target>Winchester rifle</target><part>Winchester</part></link><space/>lever action carbine and a<space/><link><target>Colt's Manufacturing Company</target><part>Colt</part></link><space/>revolver in<space/><link><target>.44-40 Winchester</target><part>.44-40</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>.38-40 Winchester</target><part>.38-40</part></link>. During the 20th century, this trend continued with more modern and powerful revolver cartridges, in the form of<space/><link><target>Winchester Model 1894</target><part>Winchester</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Marlin Model 1894</target><part>Marlin</part></link><space/>lever action carbines chambered in<space/><link><target>.38 Special</target></link>/<link><target>.357 Magnum</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>.44 Special</target></link>/<link><target>.44 Magnum</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern equivalents also exist, such as the discontinued<space/><link><target>Ruger Police Carbine</target></link>, which uses the same magazine as the Ruger<space/><link><target>pistol</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the same caliber, as well as the (also discontinued)<space/><link><target>Marlin Camp Carbine</target></link><space/>(which, in .45ACP, used M1911 magazines). The<space/><link><target>Beretta Cx4 Storm</target></link><space/>shares magazines with many<space/><link><target>Beretta</target></link><space/>pistols, and is designed to be complementary to the<space/><link><target>Beretta Px4 Storm</target></link><space/>pistol. The<space/><link><target>Hi-Point 995 Carbine</target></link><space/>is a cheaper, yet reliable alternative to other pistol caliber carbines in the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and its magazines can be used in the<space/><link><target>Hi-Point C-9 and C-9 Comp</target><part>Hi-Point C-9</part></link><space/>pistol. Another example is the<space/><link><target>Kel-Tec SUB-2000</target></link><space/>series chambered in either 9&amp;nbsp;mm Luger or .40S&amp;W which can be configured to accept Glock, Beretta, S&amp;W or SIG pistol magazines. The SUB-2000 also has the unique ability to fold in half.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Kel-Tec SUB-2000.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part><link><target>Kel-Tec SUB-2000</target></link><space/>carbine in<space/><link><target>919mm Parabellum</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The primary advantages of a carbine over a pistol using the same ammunition are increased accuracy due to the buttstock and longer barrel (and with it, sight radius), relatively low muzzle blast/flash/recoil, higher muzzle velocity and energy of a longer barrel for increased wounding potential and penetration (depending on the particular load used), and (sometimes, but not always) greater adaptability for easily accepting accessories such as optics, lights, and lasers. An example of increased power is the 9mm Luger cartridge reaching .357 magnum velocities out of a carbine. Furthermore, PCCs may not be as legally restricted as comparable handguns, depending on the jurisdiction.</paragraph><paragraph>One less-noted advantage of PCCs is their lower muzzle report compared to more powerful rifles; because they are less noisy when fired, they are less likely to cause permanent hearing damage when fired indoor without hearing protection - this can be an important consideration during home defense. Compared to &quot;regular&quot; carbines/rifles (such as those in .223 and 7.6239mm), pistol-caliber carbines may suffer from a shorter effective range, more pronounced trajectory, less power, and less effectiveness against body armor.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Pistol conversion carbine/ Carbine Conversion Unit (CCU)</heading><paragraph>Kits, called CCU - Carbine Conversion Unit, exist which will convert many pistols into carbines by the addition of a shoulder stock; notable examples are the long barreled<space/><link><target>Colt Buntline</target></link><space/><link><target>revolver</target></link><space/>stock, the<space/><link><target>Mauser C96</target></link><space/>&quot;Broomhandle&quot; holster/stock, and various others for models such as the<space/><link><target>Browning Hi-Power</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Luger pistol</target><part>Luger</part></link>, Colt<space/><link><target>M1911 Colt pistol</target><part>M1911</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Heckler &amp; Koch VP70</target></link>. Since these stock additions retain the short pistol barrel (as short as<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>) they are highly restricted in the United States under the NFA unless the shoulder stocks are of original manufacture for the gun and the gun has been &quot;delisted&quot;, as is the case with so-equipped &quot;Broomhandle&quot; Mausers and Lugers.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Legal issues</heading><heading level='3'>United States</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Browning HP (Finnish) with stock.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>A Browning Hi-Power, made for the Finnish military, with attached shoulder stock to turn it into a short carbine</part></link>Firearms with shoulder stocks and barrels less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>406</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>in length are classified as &quot;<link><target>short barreled rifle</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; (under the US<space/><link><target>National Firearms Act</target></link><space/>or<space/><bold>NFA</bold>), and are sometimes restricted in the same way that<space/><link><target>Sawn-off shotgun</target><part>short barrel shotguns</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>machine gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are. Because of this, rifles with barrels of less than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>406</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template>, or pistols with shoulder stocks, are rare. A list of firearms not covered by the NFA due to their antique status may be found here<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.atf.gov/firearms/curios/sec3a.htm</extension><space/>or due to their<space/><italics>Curio and Relic</italics><space/>status may be found here;<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.atf.gov/firearms/curios/sec3.htm</extension><space/>these lists includes a number of carbines with barrels less than the minimum legal length and firearms that are &quot;primarily collector's items and are not likely to be used as weapons and, therefore, are excluded from the provisions of the National Firearms Act. &quot; Firearms classified as<space/><link><target>machine gun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are also not subject to the barrel length restriction.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Another class of carbine is a semi-automatic version of a<space/><link><target>submachine gun</target></link>, with an extended barrel, usually just over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>406</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg>in</arg><arg name="abbr">on</arg></template><space/>long, which will escape ban by some<space/><link><target>assault weapons legislation</target></link>. While functionally identical to pistol-caliber carbines, these are banned in some places as<space/><link><target>assault weapon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>based on their cosmetic similarity to submachine guns. However, they may not accept certain parts (such as magazines or collapsing stocks) from the submachine guns that they resemble. These are a popular compromise for (American) shooters who would like to own a submachine gun but cannot due to local restrictions or the prohibitive cost of buying a civilian legal submachine gun (full automatics or semi-automatics with barrels shorter than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>16</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg></template><space/>are restricted under Title II of the<space/><link><target>National Firearms Act</target></link>). Many owners may choose to shorten the barrels down to NFA-lengths, and register them as &quot;short barrel rifles&quot;<space/><link><target>National Firearms Act#Categories of Weapons Regulated</target><part>SBRs</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Examples of PCCs that are derivatives of submachine guns but are rifles under Title I (<link><target>Gun Control Act of 1968</target><part>Gun Control Act</part></link>) include the<space/><link><target>HK USC</target></link><space/>(derived from the HK .45ACP UMP submachine gun), the HK94 (derived from the<space/><link><target>MP5</target></link>), pistol-caliber AR-15s (such as the<space/><link><target>Bushmaster Firearms International</target><part>Bushmaster</part></link><space/>Carbon 15 9&amp;nbsp;mm Carbine), semi-automatic only versions of the<space/><link><target>Thompson submachine gun</target><part>Thompson</part></link><space/>by Auto-Ordnance and the FN PS90 (derived from the<space/><link><target>FN P90</target></link><space/>SMG). Unlike the above-mentioned PCCs, these carbines use either magazines from their SMG derivatives, or proprietary magazines (as in the case of the USC).</paragraph><paragraph>In some historical cases the term<space/><italics>machine carbine</italics><space/>was the official title for sub-machine guns, such as the British<space/><link><target>Sten</target></link><space/>and Australian<space/><link><target>Owen gun</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The semi-automatic only version of the<space/><link><target>Sterling submachine gun</target></link><space/>was also officially called a &quot;carbine&quot;. The original Sterling semi-auto would be classed a &quot;short barrel rifle&quot; under the U.S.<space/><link><target>National Firearms Act</target></link>, but fully legal long-barrel versions of the Sterling have been made for the U.S. collector market.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of carbines</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Personal defense weapon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Short-barreled rifle</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Beard, Ross E.<space/><italics>Carbine : the story of David Marshall Williams</italics>. Williamstown, NJ: Phillips, 1997. ISBN 0-932-57226-X<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>757855022</arg></template></listitem><listitem><italics>Carbines : cal. .30 carbines M1, M1A1, M2 and M3</italics>. Washington, DC: Headquarters, Departments of the Army and the Air Force, 1953.</listitem><listitem>McAulay, John D.<space/><italics>Carbines of the Civil War, 1861-1865</italics>. Union City, TN: Pioneer Press, 1981. ISBN 978-0-913159-45-3<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>8111324</arg></template></listitem><listitem>McAulay, John D.<space/><italics>Carbines of the U.S. Cavalry, 1861-1905</italics>. Lincoln, RI: Andrew Mowbray Publishers, 1996. ISBN 0-917-21870-1<space/><template><target>OCLC</target><arg>36087526</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Carbines</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Rifles</target></link><link><target>Category:18th-century weapons</target></link></paragraph></article>