<article title='All_Quiet_on_the_Western_Front'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg>the 1929 novel</arg></template><template><target>Infobox book</target><arg name="name"><space/>All Quiet on the Western Front
</arg><arg name="title_orig"><space/>Im Westen nichts Neues
</arg><arg name="translator"><space/>[[Arthur Wesley Wheen|A. W. Wheen]]
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Remarque Im Westen nichts Neues 1929.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>1st edition cover
</arg><arg name="author"><space/>[[Erich Maria Remarque]]
</arg><arg name="illustrator">
</arg><arg name="cover_artist">
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>Germany
</arg><arg name="language"><space/>German
</arg><arg name="series">
</arg><arg name="genre"><space/>[[War novel]]
</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Ullstein Verlag|Propyläen Verlag]]
</arg><arg name="pub_date"><space/>29 January 1929
</arg><arg name="english_pub_date"><space/>[[Little, Brown and Company]], 1929
</arg><arg name="media_type"><space/>Print ([[Hardcover|Hardback]])
</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>295
</arg><arg name="oclc"><space/>295972
</arg></template><bold><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics></bold><space/>(<template><target>lang-de</target><arg>Im Westen nichts Neues</arg><arg name="lit">In the West Nothing New</arg></template>) is a novel by<space/><link><target>Erich Maria Remarque</target></link>, a German veteran of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. The book describes the German soldiers' extreme physical and mental stress during the war, and the detachment from civilian life felt by many of these soldiers upon returning home from the front.</paragraph><paragraph>The novel was first published in November and December 1928 in the German newspaper<space/><italics><link><target>Vossische Zeitung</target></link></italics><space/>and in book form in late January 1929. The book and its sequel,<space/><italics><link><target>The Road Back</target></link></italics><space/>(1930), were among the books banned and burned in<space/><link><target>Nazi Germany</target></link>.<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>sold 2.5 million copies in 22 languages in its first 18 months in print.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Eksteins
<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Modris
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>All Quiet on the Western Front and the Fate of a War
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Journal of Contemporary History
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>15
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>2
<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>353
<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[SAGE Publications]]
<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>April 1980
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1177/002200948001500207<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1930, the book was adapted as an Academy-Award winning<space/><link><target>All Quiet on the Western Front (1930 film)</target><part>film of the same name</part></link>, directed by<space/><link><target>Lewis Milestone</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Title and translation</heading><paragraph>The 1929 English translation by<space/><link><target>Arthur Wesley Wheen</target></link><space/>gives the title as<space/><italics><space/>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics>. The literal translation of &quot;Im Westen nichts Neues&quot; is &quot;In the West Nothing New,&quot; with &quot;West&quot; being the<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Front</part></link>; the phrase refers to the content of an official communiqu at the end of the novel.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Brian O Murdoch</target><part>Brian Murdoch's</part></link><space/>1993 translation would render the phrase as &quot;there was nothing new to report on the Western Front&quot; within the narrative. Explaining his retention of the original book-title, he says:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>Although it does not match the German exactly, Wheen's title has justly become part of the English language and is retained here with gratitude.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The phrase &quot;all quiet on the Western Front&quot; has become a colloquial expression meaning stagnation, or lack of visible change, in any context.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Plot summary</heading><paragraph>The book tells the story of Paul Bumer, a German soldier whourged on by his school teacherjoins the<space/><link><target>German Army (German Empire)</target><part>German army</part></link><space/>shortly after the start of<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link>. His class was &quot;scattered over the platoons amongst<space/><link><target>Frisians</target><part>Frisian</part></link><space/>fishermen, peasants, and labourers.&quot; Bumer arrives at the<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Front</part></link><space/>with his friends and schoolmates (Leer, Mller, Kropp and a number of other characters). There they meet Stanislaus Katczinsky, an older soldier, nicknamed Kat, who becomes Paul's mentor. While fighting at the front, Bumer and his comrades have to engage in frequent battles and endure the treacherous and filthy conditions of trench warfare.</paragraph><paragraph>At the very beginning of the book, Erich Maria Remarque says &quot;This book is to be neither an accusation nor a confession, and least of all an adventure, for death is not an adventure to those who stand face to face with it. It will try simply to tell of a generation of men who, even though they may have escaped (its) shells, were destroyed by the war.&quot; The book does not focus on heroic stories of bravery, but rather gives a view of the conditions in which the soldiers find themselves. The monotony between battles, the constant threat of<space/><link><target>artillery</target></link><space/>fire and bombardments, the struggle to find food, the lack of training of young recruits (meaning lower chances of survival), and the overarching role of random chance in the lives and deaths of the soldiers are described in detail.</paragraph><paragraph>The battles fought here have no names and seem to have little overall significance, except for the impending possibility of injury or death for Bumer and his comrades. Only pitifully small pieces of land are gained, about the size of a football field, which are often lost again later. Remarque often refers to the living soldiers as old and dead, emotionally drained and shaken. &quot;We are not youth any longer. We don't want to take the world by storm. We are fleeing from ourselves, from our life. We were eighteen and had begun to love life and the world; and we had to shoot it to pieces.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Paul's visit on leave to his home highlights the cost of the war on his psyche. The town has not changed since he went off to war; however, he finds that he does &quot;not belong here anymore, it is a foreign world.&quot; He feels disconnected from most of the townspeople. His father asks him &quot;stupid and distressing&quot; questions about his war experiences, not understanding &quot;that a man cannot talk of such things.&quot; An old schoolmaster lectures him about strategy and advancing to Paris, while insisting that Paul and his friends know only their &quot;own little sector&quot; of the war but nothing of the big picture.</paragraph><paragraph>Indeed, the only person he remains connected to is his dying mother, with whom he shares a tender, yet restrained relationship. The night before he is to return from leave, he stays up with her, exchanging small expressions of love and concern for each other. He thinks to himself, &quot;Ah! Mother, Mother! How can it be that I must part from you? Here I sit and there you are lying; we have so much to say, and we shall never say it.&quot; In the end, he concludes that he &quot;ought never to have come [home] on leave.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Paul feels glad to be reunited with his comrades. Soon after, he volunteers to go on a patrol and kills a man for the first time in hand-to-hand combat. He watches the man die, in pain for hours. He feels remorse and asks forgiveness from the man's corpse. He is devastated and later confesses to Kat and Albert, who try to comfort him and reassure him that it is only part of the war.They are then sent on what Paul calls a &quot;good job.&quot; They must guard a supply depot in a village that was evacuated due to being shelled too heavily. During this time, the men are able to adequately feed themselves; unlike the near-starvation conditions in the German trenches. In addition, the men enjoy themselves while living off the spoils from the village and officers' luxuries from the supply depot (such as fine cigars). While evacuating the villagers (enemy civilians), Paul and Albert are taken by surprise by artillery fired at the civilian convoy and wounded by a shell. On the train back home, Albert takes a turn for the worse and cannot complete the journey, instead being sent off the train to recuperate in a Catholic hospital.Paul uses a combination of bartering and manipulation to stay by Albert's side. Albert eventually has his leg amputated, while Paul is deemed fit for service and returned to the front.</paragraph><paragraph>By now, the war is nearing its end and the German Army is retreating. In despair, Paul watches as his friends fall one by one. It is the death of Kat that eventually makes Paul careless about living. In the final chapter, he comments that peace is coming soon, but he does not see the future as bright and shining with hope. Paul feels that he has no aims or goals left in life and that their generation will be different and misunderstood. When he dies at the end of the novel, the situation report from the frontline states, &quot;All is Quiet on the Western Front,&quot; symbolizing the insignificance of one individual's death during the war.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>One of the major themes of the novel is the difficulty of soldiers to revert to civilian life after having experienced extreme combat situations. Remarque comments in the preface that &quot;[All Quiet on the Western Front] will try simply to tell of a generation of men who, even though they may have escaped its shells, were destroyed by the war.&quot; This internal destruction can be found as early as the first chapter as Paul comments that, although all the boys are young, their youth has left them.</paragraph><paragraph>In addition, the massive loss of life and negligible gains from the fighting are constantly emphasized. Soldiers' lives are thrown away by their commanding officers who are stationed comfortable away from the front, ignorant of the daily terrors of the front line.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Main characters</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:AllQuietOnTheWesternFront.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Cover of first English language edition. The design is based upon a German<space/><link><target>war bonds</target></link><space/>poster by<space/><link><target>Fritz Erler (painter)</target><part>Fritz Erler</part></link>.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'>Paul Bumer</heading><paragraph>Paul Bumer is the main character and narrator. At 18 years of age, Paul enlists in the German Army and is deployed to the<space/><link><target>Western Front (World War I)</target><part>Western Front</part></link><space/>where he experiences the severe psychological and physical effects of the war. Before the war, Paul was a creative, sensitive and passionate person, writing poems and having a clear love for his family. But as the war changed his attitude and personality, poems and other aspects of his past life become something Paul was no longer linked to, since the horrors of war trained him to disconnect himself from his feelings. He feels he can't tell anyone about his experiences, and feels like an outsider where his family is concerned.</paragraph><paragraph>By the end of the book, Paul realises that he no longer knows what to do with himself and decides that he has nothing more to lose. The war appears to have snuffed out his hopes and dreams, which he feels he can never regain. After years of fighting, Paul is finally killed in October 1918, on an extraordinarily quiet, peaceful day. The army report that day contains only one phrase: All quiet on the Western Front. As Paul dies, his face is calm, as though almost glad the end had come.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>Albert Kropp</heading><paragraph>Kropp was in Paul's class at school and is described as the clearest thinker of the group as well as the smallest. Kropp is wounded towards the end of the novel and undergoes an<space/><link><target>amputation</target></link>. Both he and Bumer end up spending time in a<space/><link><target>Catholic</target></link><space/>hospital together, Bumer suffering from shrapnel wounds to the leg and arm. Though Kropp initially plans to commit<space/><link><target>suicide</target></link><space/>if he requires an amputation, the book suggests he postponed suicide because of the strength of military camaraderie. Kropp and Bumer part ways when Bumer is recalled to his regiment after recovering. Paul comments that saying farewell was &quot;very hard, but it is something a soldier learns to deal with.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Chapter Ten of All Quiet on the Western Front</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Haie Westhus</heading><paragraph>Haie is described as being tall and strong, and a<space/><link><target>peat</target></link>-digger by profession. Overall, his size and behavior make him seem older than Paul, yet he is the same age as Paul and his school-friends (roughly 19 at the start of the book). Haie in addition has a good sense of humor. During combat, he is injured in his back, fatally (Chapter 6) the resulting wound is large enough for Paul to see Haie's breathing lung when Himmelsto (Himmelstoss) carries him to safety.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Fredrich Mller</heading><paragraph>Mller is about 18 and a half years of age, one of Bumer's classmates, when he also joins the German army as a volunteer to go to the war. Carrying his old school books with him to the battlefield, he constantly reminds himself of the importance of learning and education. Even while under enemy fire, he &quot;mutters propositions in physics&quot;. He became interested in Kemmerich's boots and inherits them when Kemmerich dies early in the novel. He is killed later in the book after being shot point-blank in the stomach with a &quot;light pistol&quot; (flare gun). As he was dying &quot;quite conscious and in terrible pain&quot;, he gave his boots which he inherited from Kemmerich to Paul.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Stanislaus &quot;Kat&quot; Katczinsky</heading><paragraph>Kat has the most positive influence on Paul and his comrades on the battlefield. Katczinsky was a cobbler in civilian life; he is older than Paul Bumer and his comrades, about 40 years old, and serves as their leadership figure. He also represents a literary model highlighting the differences between the younger and older soldiers. While the older men have already had a life of professional and personal experience before the war, Bumer and the men of his age have had little life experience or time for personal growth.</paragraph><paragraph>Kat is also well known for his ability to scavenge nearly any item needed, especially food. At one point he secures four boxes of lobster. Bumer describes Kat as possessing a<space/><link><target>Extrasensory perception</target><part>sixth sense</part></link>. One night, Bumer along with a group of other soldiers are holed up in a factory with neither rations nor comfortable bedding. Katczinsky leaves for a short while, returning with straw to put over the bare wires of the beds. Later, to feed the hungry men, Kat brings bread, a bag of horse flesh, a lump of fat, a pinch of salt and a pan in which to cook the food.</paragraph><paragraph>Kat is hit by shrapnel at the end of the story, leaving him with a smashed shin. Paul carries him back to camp on his back, only to discover upon their arrival that a stray splinter had hit Kat in the back of the head and killed him on the way. He is thus the last of Paul's close friends to die in battle. It is Kat's death that eventually makes Bumer careless whether he survives the war or not, but that he can face the rest of his life without fear. &quot;Let the months and the years come, they can take nothing from me, they can take nothing more. I am so alone, and so without hope that I can confront them without fear.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='3'>Tjaden</heading><paragraph>One of Bumer's non-schoolmate friends. Before the war Tjaden was a locksmith. A big eater with a grudge against the former postman-turned corporal Himmelsto (thanks to his strict 'disciplinary actions'), he manages to forgive Himmelsto later in the book. Throughout the book, Paul frequently remarks on how much of an eater he is, yet somehow manages to stay as &quot;thin as a rake.&quot; Tjaden appears in the sequel,<space/><italics><link><target>The Road Back</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Minor characters</heading><heading level='3'>Kantorek</heading><paragraph>Kantorek was the<space/><link><target>schoolmaster</target></link><space/>of Paul and his friends, including Kropp, Leer, Mller, and Behm. Behaving &quot;in a way that cost [him] nothing,&quot; Kantorek is a strong supporter of the war and encourages Bumer and other students in his class to join the war effort. Among twenty enlistees was Joseph Behm, the first of the class to die in battle. In an example of tragic irony, Behm was the only one who did not want to enter the war.</paragraph><paragraph>Kantorek is a hypocrite, urging the young men he teaches to fight in the name of patriotism, while not voluntarily enlisting himself. In a twist of fate, Kantorek is later called up as a soldier as well. He very reluctantly joins the ranks of his former students, only to be drilled and taunted by Mittelstdt, one of the students he had earlier persuaded to enlist.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Peter Leer</heading><paragraph>Leer is an intelligent soldier in Bumer's company, and one of his classmates. He is very popular with women; when he and his comrades meet three French women, he is the first to seduce one of them. Bumer describes Leer's ability to attract women by saying &quot;Leer is an old hand at the game&quot;. In chapter 11, Leer is hit by a shell fragment, which also hits Bertinck. The shrapnel tears open Leer's hip, causing him to bleed to death quickly. His death causes Paul to ask himself, &quot;What use is it to him now that he was such a good mathematician in school?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>(London: Putnam &amp; Company Ltd, 1970 reprint), page 240.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Bertinck</heading><paragraph>Lieutenant Bertinck is the leader of Bumer's<space/><link><target>Company (military)</target><part>company</part></link>. His men have a great respect for him, and Bertinck has great respect for his men. He permits them to eat the rations of the men that had been killed in action, standing up to the chef Ginger who would only allow them their allotted share. Bertinck is genuinely despondent when he learns that few of his men had survived an engagement.</paragraph><paragraph>When he and the other characters are trapped in a trench under heavy attack, Bertinck, who has been injured in the firefight, spots a flamethrower team advancing on them. He gets out of cover and takes aim on the flamethrower but misses, and gets hit by enemy fire. With his next shot he kills the flamethrower, and immediately afterwards an enemy shell explodes on his position blowing off his chin. The same explosion also fatally wounds Leer.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Himmelsto</heading><paragraph>Corporal Himmelsto (spelled Himmelstoss in some editions) was a postman before enlisting in the war. He is a power-hungry corporal with special contempt for Paul and his friends, taking sadistic pleasure in punishing the minor infractions of his trainees during their basic training in preparation for their deployment. Paul later figures that the training taught by Himmelsto made them &quot;hard, suspicious, pitiless, and tough&quot; but most importantly it taught them comradeship. However, Bumer and his comrades have a chance to get back at Himmelsto because of his punishments, mercilessly whipping him on the night before they board trains to go to the front.</paragraph><paragraph>Himmelsto later joins them at the front, revealing himself as a coward who shirks his duties for fear of getting hurt or killed, and pretends to be wounded because of a scratch on his face. Paul Bumer beats him because of it and when a lieutenant comes along looking for men for a trench charge, Himmelsto joins and leads the charge. He carries Haie Westhus's body to Bumer after he is fatally wounded. Matured and repentant through his experiences Himmelsto later asks for forgiveness from his previous charges. As he becomes the new staff cook, to prove his friendship he secures two pounds of sugar for Bumer and half a pound of butter for Tjaden.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Detering</heading><paragraph>Detering is a farmer who constantly longs to return to his wife and farm. He is also fond of horses and is angered when he sees them used in combat. He says, &quot;It is of the vilest baseness to use horses in the war,&quot; when the group hears several wounded horses writhe and scream for a long time before dying during a bombardment. He tries to shoot them to put them out of misery, but is stopped by Kat to keep their current position hidden. He is driven to desert when he sees a cherry tree in blossom, which reminds him of home too much and inspires him to leave. He is found by military police and court-martialed, and is never heard from again.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Josef Hamacher</heading><paragraph>Hamacher is a patient at the Catholic hospital where Paul and Albert Kropp are temporarily stationed. He has an intimate knowledge of the workings of the hospital. He also has a &quot;Special Permit,&quot; certifying him as sporadically not responsible for his actions due to a head wound, though he is clearly quite sane and exploiting his permit so he can stay in the hospital and away from the war as long as possible.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Franz Kemmerich</heading><paragraph>A young boy of only 19 years. Franz Kemmerich had enlisted in the army for World War I along with his best friend and classmate, Bumer. Kemmerich is shot in the leg early in the story; his injured leg has to be amputated, and he dies shortly after. In anticipation of Kemmerich's imminent death, Mller was eager to get his boots. While in the hospital, someone steals Kemmerich's watch that he intended to give to his mother, causing him great distress and prompting him to ask about his watch every time his friends visit him in the hospital. Paul later finds the watch and hands it over to Kemmerich's mother, only to lie Franz died instantly and painlessly when questioned.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Joseph Behm</heading><paragraph>A student in Paul's class. Behm was the only student that was not quickly influenced by Kantorek's patriotism to join the war. Eventually, due to pressure from friends and Kantorek, he joins the war. He is the first of Paul's friends to die. He is blinded in<space/><link><target>no man's land</target></link><space/>and believed to be dead by his friends. The next day, when he is seen walking blindly around<space/><link><target>no-man's-land</target></link>, it is discovered that he was only unconscious. However, he is killed before he can be rescued.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Publication and Reception</heading><paragraph>From November 10 to December 9, 1928,<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>was published in serial form in<space/><link><target>Vossische Zeitung</target></link><space/>magazine. It was released in book form the following year to smashing success, selling one and a half million copies that same year. Although publishers had worried that interest in the<space/><link><target>Great War</target></link><space/>had waned more than 10 years after the<space/><link><target>Armistice with Germany</target><part>armistice</part></link>, Remarque's realistic depiction of trench warfare from the perspective of young soldiers struck a chord with the war's survivorssoldiers and civilians alikeand provoked strong reactions, both positive and negative, around the world.</paragraph><paragraph>With<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics>, Remarque emerged as an eloquent spokesperson for a generation that had been, in his own words, &quot;destroyed by war, even though it might have escaped its shells.&quot; Remarque's harshest critics, in turn, were his countrymen, many of whom felt the book denigrated the German war effort, and that Remarque had exaggerated the horrors of war to further his pacifist agenda. The strongest voices against Remarque came from the emerging<space/><link><target>Nazi Party</target><part>National Socialist Party</part></link><space/>and its ideological allies. In 1933, when the Nazis rose to power,<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>became one of the first<space/><link><target>degenerate art</target><part>degenerate books</part></link><space/>to be publicly burnt;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.history.com/this-day-in-history/remarque-publishes-all-quiet-on-the-western-front</arg><arg name="title">Nov 10, 1928: Remarque publishes All Quiet on the Western Front</arg><arg name="work">[[History.com]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>in 1930 screenings of the<space/><link><target>All Quiet on the Western Front (1930 film)</target><part>Academy Award-winning film based on the book</part></link><space/>were met with Nazi-organized protests and mob attacks on both movie theatres and audience members.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SI"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last1">Sauer</arg><arg name="first1">Patrick</arg><arg name="title">The Most Loved and Hated Novel About World War I</arg><arg name="url">http://www.smithsonianmag.com/history/most-loved-and-hated-novel-about-world-war-I-180955540/</arg><arg name="website">Smithsonian.com</arg><arg name="publisher">Smithsonian Institution</arg><arg name="accessdate">June 21, 2015</arg><arg name="date">June 16, 2015</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, objections to Remarques portrayal of the German army personnel during World War I were not limited to the Nazis. Dr. Karl Kroner (<link><target>:de:Karl Kroner</target><part>de</part></link>) objected to Remarques depiction of the medical personnel as being inattentive, uncaring, or absent from frontline action. Dr. Kroner was specifically worried that the book would perpetuate German stereotypes abroad that had subsided since the First World War. He offered the following clarification: People abroad will draw the following conclusions: if German doctors deal with their own fellow countrymen in this manner, what acts of inhumanity will they not perpetuate against helpless prisoners delivered up into their hands or against the populations of occupied territory?<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="clardy"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://modernism.research.yale.edu/wiki/index.php/All_Quiet_on_the_Western_Front#Reception</arg><arg name="title">All Quiet on the Western Front: Reception</arg><arg name="author">Patrick Clardy</arg><arg name="work">Yale Modernism Lab</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 June 2013</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="barker"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first1">Christine R.</arg><arg name="last1">Barker</arg><arg name="first2">Rex William</arg><arg name="last2">Last</arg><arg name="title">Erich Maria Remarque</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="publisher">Barnes & Noble Books</arg><arg name="year">1979</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A fellow patient of Remarques in the military hospital in<space/><link><target>Duisburg</target></link><space/>objected to the negative depictions of the nuns and patients, and of the general portrayal of soldiers: There were soldiers to whom the protection of homeland, protection of house and homestead, protection of family were the highest objective, and to whom this will to protect their homeland gave the strength to endure any extremities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="barker"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>These criticisms suggest that perhaps experiences of the war and the personal reactions of individual soldiers to their experiences may be more diverse than Remarque portrays them; however, it is beyond question that Remarque gives voice to a side of the war and its experience that was overlooked or suppressed at the time. This perspective is crucial to understanding the true effects of World War I. The evidence can be seen in the lingering depression that Remarque and many of his friends and acquaintances were suffering a decade later.<extension extension_name='ref' name="clardy"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In contrast,<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>was trumpeted by<space/><link><target>pacifists</target></link><space/>as an anti-war book.<extension extension_name='ref' name="barker"></extension><space/>Remarque makes a point in the opening statement that the novel does not advocate any political position, but is merely an attempt to describe the experiences of the soldier.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Hans</arg><arg name="last">Wagner</arg><arg name="title">Understanding Erich Maria Remarque</arg><arg name="location">Columbia, SC</arg><arg name="publisher">University of South Carolina Press</arg><arg name="year">1991</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The main artistic criticism was that it was a mediocre attempt to cash in on public sentiment. The enormous popularity the work received was a point of contention for some literary critics, who scoffed at the fact that such a simple work could be so earth-shattering. Much of this literary criticism came from<space/><link><target>Salomo Friedlaender</target></link>, who wrote a book<space/><italics>Hat Erich Maria Remarque wirklich gelebt?</italics><space/>&quot;Did Erich Maria Remarque really live?&quot;. Another author,<space/><link><target>Max Joseph Wolff</target></link>, wrote a parody titled<space/><italics>Vor Troja nichts Neues</italics><space/>&quot;Before Troja, nothing new&quot; under the pseudonym<space/><italics>Emil Marius Requark</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://d-nb.info/578423782'>Catalogue entry</link><space/>for<space/><italics>Vor Troja nichts Neues</italics><space/>in the German National Library, retrieved 29 January 2014</extension><space/>Friedlaenders criticism's were mainly personal in naturehe attacked Remarque as being ego-centric and greedy. Remarque publicly stated that he wrote<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>for personal reasons, not for profit, as Friedlaender had claimed.<extension extension_name='ref' name="clardy"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="barker"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Adaptations</heading><heading level='3'>Film</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:AllQuietWesternFrontPosterA.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Poster for the movie ''All Quiet on the Western Front'' (1930), featuring star<space/><link><target>Lew Ayres</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>All Quiet on the Western Front (1930 film)</arg></template>In 1930, an American film of the novel was made, directed by<space/><link><target>Lewis Milestone</target></link>; with a screenplay by<space/><link><target>Maxwell Anderson</target></link>,<space/><link><target>George Abbott</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Del Andrews</target></link>,<space/><link><target>C. Gardner Sullivan</target></link>; and with uncredited work by<space/><link><target>Walter Anthony</target></link><space/>and Milestone. It stars<space/><link><target>Louis Wolheim</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lew Ayres</target></link>,<space/><link><target>John Wray (actor)</target><part>John Wray</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Arnold Lucy</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Ben Alexander (actor)</target><part>Ben Alexander</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The film won the<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Best Picture</target></link><space/>in 1930 for its producer<space/><link><target>Carl Laemmle Jr.</target></link>, and an<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Directing</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>Lewis Milestone</target></link>. It was the first all-talking non-musical film to win the Best Picture Oscar. It also received two further nominations:<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Best Cinematography</target><part>Best Cinematography</part></link>, for<space/><link><target>Arthur Edeson</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Academy Award for Writing Adapted Screenplay</target><part>Best Writing Achievement</part></link><space/>for Abbott, Anderson and Andrews.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>In June 2009, an announcement was made that<space/><italics>All Quiet on the Western Front</italics><space/>would be remade.<extension extension_name='ref' name="imdb"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">IMDb</arg><arg name="url">http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1016150/<space/></arg><arg name="title">IMDB entry</arg></template></extension><space/>Director<space/><link><target>Mimi Leder</target></link><space/>was linked with the film in 2011,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.hollywoodreporter.com/risky-business/mimi-leder-direct-all-quiet-215569</arg><arg name="work">Hollywood Reporter</arg><arg name="title">Risky Business</arg></template></extension><space/>but as of 2013, the film was still listed as being in pre-production.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>TV film</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>All Quiet on the Western Front (1979 film)</arg></template>In 1979, the film was remade for CBS television by<space/><link><target>Delbert Mann</target></link>, starring<space/><link><target>Richard Thomas (actor)</target><part>Richard Thomas</part></link><space/>of<space/><italics><link><target>The Waltons</target></link></italics><space/>as Paul Bumer and<space/><link><target>Ernest Borgnine</target></link><space/>as Kat. The movie was filmed in<space/><link><target>Czechoslovakia</target></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Music</heading><paragraph><link><target>Elton John</target></link>'s album<space/><italics><link><target>Jump Up! (Elton John album)</target><part>Jump Up!</part></link></italics><space/>(1982) features the song, &quot;<link><target>All Quiet on the Western Front (song)</target><part>All Quiet on the Western Front</part></link>&quot; (written by Elton and<space/><link><target>Bernie Taupin</target></link>). The song is a sorrowful rendition of the novel's story (&quot;It's gone all quiet on the Western Front / Male Angels sigh / ghosts in a flooded trench / As Germany dies&quot;).</paragraph><heading level='3'>Radio</heading><paragraph>On November 9, 2008, a radio adaptation of the novel was broadcast on<space/><link><target>BBC Radio 3</target></link>, starring<space/><link><target>Robert Lonsdale</target></link><space/>as Paul Bumer and Shannon Graney as Katczinsky. Its screenplay was written by Dave Sheasby, and the show was directed by David Hunter.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b00fd2tv<space/></arg><arg name="title">BBC Radio 3 - Drama on 3, All Quiet on the Western Front<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bbc.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">2008-11-09<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2013-02-07</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Theatre</heading><paragraph>In 2009, prior to a UK Tour,<space/><link><target>Nottingham Playhouse</target></link><space/>commissioned a play of the book by Robin Kingsland.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>portal</target><arg>Novels</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bildungsroman</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of books with anti-war themes</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><extension extension_name='references'></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template><template><target>commons cat</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cliffsnotes.com/WileyCDA/LitNote/id-6.html'>CliffsNotes</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sparknotes.com/lit/allquiet/'>Spark Notes</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shmoop.com/all-quiet-on-western-front/'>''All Quiet on the Western Front''</link><space/>study guide, themes, quotes, literary devices, multimedia, teacher resources</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Remarque</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:All Quiet On The Western Front</target></template><link><target>Category:1929 novels</target></link><link><target>Category:20th-century German novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Anti-war novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Book censorship</target></link><link><target>Category:German novels</target></link><link><target>Category:German novels adapted into films</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels by Erich Maria Remarque</target></link><link><target>Category:Novels first published in serial form</target></link><link><target>Category:Roman clef novels</target></link><link><target>Category:Works originally published in Vossische Zeitung</target></link><link><target>Category:World War I novels</target></link></paragraph></article>