<article title='Costume_jewelry'><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Swatch Bijoux Jewelry.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Swatch</target></link><space/>Bijoux Jewelry</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Costume jewelry</bold>,<space/><bold>trinkets</bold>,<space/><bold>fashion jewelry</bold>,<space/><bold>junk jewelry</bold>,<space/><bold>fake jewelry</bold>, or<space/><bold>fallalery</bold><space/>is<space/><link><target>jewelry</target></link><space/>manufactured as ornamentation to complement a particular fashionable<space/><link><target>costume</target></link><space/>or garment<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker">Baker, Lillian. Fifty Years of Collectable Fashion Jewelry. Paducah: Collector Books, 1986.</extension><space/>as opposed to &quot;real&quot; (fine) jewelry which may be regarded primarily as collectibles, keepsakes, or investments.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The term costume jewelry dates back to the early 20th century. It reflects the use of the word &quot;costume&quot; to refer to what is now called an &quot;<link><target>Clothing</target><part>outfit</part></link>&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Components</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:A002.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>An example of gold plated jewelry</part></link>Originally, costume or fashion jewelry was made of inexpensive simulated gemstones, such as<space/><link><target>rhinestone</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>lucite</target></link>, set in<space/><link><target>pewter</target></link>,<space/><link><target>silver</target></link>,<space/><link><target>nickel</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>brass</target></link>. During the depression years, rhinestones were even down-graded by some manufacturers to meet the cost of production.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>During the World War II era,<space/><link><target>sterling silver</target></link><space/>was often incorporated into costume jewelry designs primarily because:</paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>The components used for base metal were needed for war time production (i.e., military applications) and a ban was placed on their use in the private sector.</listitem><listitem>Base metal was originally popular because it could approximate platinum's color,<space/><link><target>sterling silver</target></link><space/>fulfilled the same function.<space/></listitem></list><paragraph>This resulted in a number of years during which sterling silver costume jewelry was produced and some can still be found in today's vintage jewelry marketplace.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern costume jewelry incorporates a wide range of materials. High end<space/><link><target>crystals</target></link>,<space/><link><target>cubic zirconia</target></link><space/>simulated diamonds, and some semi-precious stones are used in place of precious stones. Metals include gold- or silver-plated brass, and sometimes<space/><link><target>vermeil</target></link><space/>or sterling silver. Lower-priced jewelry may still use gold plating over pewter, nickel or other metals; items made in countries outside the United States may contain<space/><link><target>lead</target></link>. Some pieces incorporate<space/><link><target>plastic</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Acrylic resin</target><part>acrylic</part></link>,<space/><link><target>leather</target></link><space/>or wood.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical expression</heading><paragraph>Costume jewelry can be characterized by the period in history in which it was made.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Art Deco period (19201930s)</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Art Deco</target></link><space/>movement was an attempt to combine the harshness of mass production with the sensitivity of art and design. It was during this period that Coco Chanel introduced costume jewelry to complete the costume. The Art Deco movement died with the onset of the<space/><link><target>Great Depression</target></link><space/>and the outbreak of<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://emptyeasel.com/2007/08/21/the-art-deco-movement-technology-and-geometry-combined-with-modern-art/'>&quot;The Art Deco Movement: Technology and Geometry Combined with Modern Art.&quot;</link><space/>2005. Empty Easel.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Schiffer, some of the characteristics of the costume jewelry in the Art Deco period were:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schiffer"></extension><space/></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Free-flowing curves were replaced with a harshly geometric and symmetrical theme</listitem><listitem>Long pendants, bangle bracelets, cocktail rings, and elaborate accessory items such as cigarette cases and holders</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Retro period (1935 to 1950)</heading><paragraph>In the Retro period, designers struggled with the art versus<space/><link><target>mass production</target></link><space/>dilemma. Natural materials merged with plastics. The retro period primarily included American-made jewelry, which has a distinct American look. With the war in Europe, many European jewelry firms were forced shut down. Many European designers immigrated to the U.S. since the economy was recovering.</paragraph><paragraph>According to Schiffer, some of the characteristics of the costume jewelry in the Retro period were:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schiffer"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Glamour, elegance, and sophistication</listitem><listitem>Flowers, bows, and sunburst designs with a Hollywood flair</listitem><listitem>Moonstones, horse motifs, military influence, and ballerinas</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bakelite</target></link><space/>and other plastic jewelry</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Art Modern period (1945 to 1960)</heading><paragraph>In the Art Modern period following World War II, jewelry designs became more traditional and understated. The big, bold styles of the Retro period went out of style and were replaced by the more tailored styles of the 1950s and 1960s.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Schiffer, some of the characteristics of the costume jewelry in the Art Modern period were:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schiffer"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Bold, lavish jewelry</listitem><listitem>Large, chunky bracelets, charm bracelets, Jade/opal, charm bracelets, citrine,<space/><link><target>topaz</target></link></listitem><listitem>Poodle pins, Christmas tree pins, and other Christmas jewelry</listitem><listitem>Rhinestones</listitem></list><paragraph>With the advent of the Mod period came &quot;<italics>Body Jewelry</italics>&quot;. Carl Schimel of Kim Craftsmen Jewelry was at the forefront of this style.<extension extension_name='ref'>See archived article from<space/><link type='external' href='http://news.google.com/newspapers?nid=1368&amp;amp;dat=19690731&amp;amp;id=K3RQAAAAIBAJ&amp;amp;sjid=NREEAAAAIBAJ&amp;amp;pg=7278,6232783'>The Milwaukee Sentinel Jul 31, 1969: Mod Bods And Chains</link></extension><space/>While Kim Craftsmen closed in the early 1990s, many collectors still forage for their items at antique shows and flea markets.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Milwaukee Sentinel Jul 31, 1969. p.4</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Feith, Molly. &quot;Kim Craftsmen A Tale of Two Brothers.&quot; Costume Jewelry Collectors International. Spring 2010 Vol. 1, Issue 1</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Boston Museum of Fine Art recently displayed Carl Schimel's &quot;<italics>Chastity Belt</italics>&quot; created in 1969 in their &quot;<italics>When High Fashion Inhaled The '60s'Hippie Chic</italics>'&quot; at MFA.<space/><link type='external' href='http://educators.mfa.org/node/398878'>This piece</link><space/>and exhibit was reviewed by Gregg Cook of Boston NPR &quot;Carl Schimels circa 1969 base metal Chastity Beltdisplayed here atop a black bodystockingimitates medieval designs in its erotic chains and medallion (<italics>a container meant to hold birth control pills,</italics><space/>according to the MFA). (Greg Cook) http://artery.wbur.org/2013/07/20/hippie-chic-mfa a photo of this piece can be seen at http://media.wbur.org/wordpress/18/files/2013/07/picHippieChicCook_0176.jpg</paragraph><heading level='2'>General history</heading><paragraph>Costume jewelry has been part of culture for almost 300 years. During the 18th century, jewelers began making pieces with inexpensive glass. In the 19th century, costume jewelry made of semi-precious material came into the market. Jewels made of semi-precious material were more affordable, and this affordability gave common people the chance to own costume jewelry.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schiffer">Schiffer, Nancy.<space/><italics>The Best of Costume Jewelry</italics>. Atglen: Schiffer Publishing, 1999.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>But the real golden era for the costume jewelry began in the middle of the 20th century. The new<space/><link><target>middle class</target></link><space/>wanted beautiful, but affordable, jewelry. The demand for jewelry of this type coincided with the machine-age and the<space/><link><target>industrial revolution</target></link>. The revolution made the production of carefully executed replicas of admired<space/><link><target>heirloom</target></link><space/>pieces possible.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>As the class structure in America changed, so did measures of real wealth. Women in all social stations, even the working-class woman, could own a small piece of costume jewelry. The average town and country woman could acquire and wear a considerable amount of this mass-produced jewelry that was both affordable and stylish.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Schiffer"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Costume jewelry was also made popular by various designers in the mid-20th century. Some of the most remembered names in costume jewelry include both the high and low priced brands: Crown Trifari,<space/><link><target>Dior</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chanel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Miriam Haskell</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Monet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Napier Company (jewellery)</target><part>Napier</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Corocraft</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Coventry</target></link>, and Kim Craftsmen.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Baker"></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Felth, Molly. &quot;Kim Craftsmen A Tale of Two Brothers.&quot; CJCI Magazine, Summer 2010 Vol. 1, Issue 2.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A significant factor in the popularization of costume jewelry was the Hollywood movie. The leading female stars of the 1940s and 1950s often wore and then endorsed the pieces produced by a range of designers. If you admired a necklace worn by<space/><link><target>Bette Davis</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>The Private Lives of Elizabeth and Essex</target></link></italics>, you could buy a copy from<space/><link><target>Joseff of Hollywood</target></link>, who made the original. Stars such as<space/><link><target>Vivien Leigh</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Taylor</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jane Russell</target></link><space/>appeared in adverts for the pieces and the availability of the collections in shops such as<space/><link><target>F.W. Woolworth Company</target><part>Woolworth</part></link><space/>made it possible for ordinary women to own and wear such jewelry.<extension extension_name='ref'>See Tanenbaum, C. (2006)<space/><italics>Fabulous Fakes: A Passion for Vintage Costume Jewelry</italics>, ISBN 978-1-57965-292-0</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Coco Chanel</target></link><space/>greatly popularized the use of<space/><link><target>faux</target></link><space/>jewelry in her years as a fashion designer, bringing costume jewelry to life with gold and faux pearls.<link><target>Kenneth Jay Lane</target></link><space/>has since the 1960s been known for creating unique pieces for<space/><link><target>Jackie Onassis</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Elizabeth Taylor</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Diana Vreeland</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Audrey Hepburn</target></link>. He is probably best known for his three-strand faux pearl necklace worn by<space/><link><target>Barbara Bush</target></link><space/>to her husband's<space/><link><target>inaugural</target></link><space/>ball.</paragraph><paragraph>In many instances, high-end fashion jewelry has achieved a &quot;collectible&quot; status, and increases in value over time. Today, there is a substantial secondary market for<space/><link><target>vintage</target></link><space/>fashion jewelry. The main collecting market is for 'signed pieces', that is pieces which have the maker's mark, usually stamped on the reverse. Amongst the most sought after are<space/><link><target>Miriam Haskell</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Corocraft</target><part>Coro</part></link>, Butler and Wilson, Crown Trifari and Sphinx. However, there is also demand for good quality 'unsigned' pieces, especially if they are of an unusual design.<extension extension_name='ref'>Miller, J. (2007)<space/><italics>Costume Jewellery</italics>, ISBN 1-4053-1812-0</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Business and industry</heading><paragraph>Costume jewelry is considered a discrete category of<space/><link><target>fashion accessory</target></link>, and displays many characteristics of a self-contained industry. Costume jewelry manufacturers are located throughout the world, with a particular concentration in parts of China and India, where entire city-wide and region-wide economies are dominated by the trade of these goods. There has been considerable controversy in the United States and elsewhere about the lack of regulations in the manufacture of such jewelrythese range from<space/><link><target>human rights</target></link><space/>issues surrounding the treatment of labor, to the use of manufacturing processes in which small, but potentially harmful, amounts of<space/><link><target>toxic metals</target></link><space/>are added during production. In 2010, the Associated Press released the story that toxic levels of the metal<space/><link><target>cadmium</target></link>. were found in children's jewelry. An<space/><link><target>Associated Press</target><part>AP</part></link><space/>investigation found some pieces contained more than 80 percent of cadmium.. The wider issues surrounding imports, exports, trade laws, and<space/><link><target>globalization</target></link><space/>also apply to the costume jewelry trade.</paragraph><paragraph>As part of the<space/><link><target>supply chain</target></link>, wholesalers in the United States and other nations purchase costume jewelry from manufacturers and typically import or export it to wholesale distributors and suppliers who deal directly with retailers. Wholesale costume jewelry merchants would traditionally seek out new suppliers at<space/><link><target>trade shows</target></link>. As the<space/><link><target>Internet</target></link><space/>has become increasingly important in global trade, the trade-show model has changed. Retailers can now select from a large number of wholesalers with sites on the World Wide Web. Some of these sites also market directly to consumers, who can purchase costume jewelry at greatly reduced prices. Some of these sites include<space/><link><target>fashion jewelry</target></link><space/>as a separate category, while some use this term in favor of costume jewelry. The trend of jewelry-making at home by hobbyists for personal enjoyment or for sale on sites like<space/><link><target>Etsy</target></link><space/>has resulted in the common practice of buying wholesale costume jewelry in bulk and using it for parts.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Marcasite jewellery</target><part>Marcasite jewelry</part></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Costume jewellery</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Costume Jewelry</target></template><link><target>Category:Fashion</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewellery components</target></link></paragraph></article>