<article title='Camille_Pissarro'><paragraph><template><target>Redirect</target><arg>Pissarro</arg><arg>the surname</arg><arg>Pissarro (surname)</arg></template><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox artist</target><arg name="bgcolour"><space/>#76A8FF
</arg><arg name="name"><space/>Camille Pissarro
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Pissarro-portrait.jpg
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Circa 1900
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>Jacob Abraham Camille Pissarro
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|1830|7|10|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Charlotte Amalie, United States Virgin Islands|Charlotte Amalie]], [[Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands|Saint Thomas]], [[Danish West Indies]] (now [[United States Virgin Islands|US Virgin Islands]])
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>Paris, France
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>Danish-French
</arg><arg name="field"><space/>Painting
</arg><arg name="movement"><space/>[[Impressionism]]<br>[[Post-Impressionism]]
</arg><arg name="influenced by"><space/>[[Eugène Delacroix]], [[Édouard Manet]], [[Camille Corot]], [[Charles-François Daubigny]]
</arg><arg name="influenced"><space/>[[Paul Cézanne]], [[Paul Gauguin]], [[Lucien Pissarro]]
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Camille Pissarro</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>kamij pisaʁo</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>; 10 July 1830&amp;nbsp; 13 November 1903) was a Danish-French<space/><link><target>Impressionist</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Neo-Impressionist</target></link><space/>painter born on the island of<space/><link><target>Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands</target><part>St Thomas</part></link><space/>(now in the<space/><link><target>US Virgin Islands</target></link>, but then in the<space/><link><target>Danish West Indies</target></link>). His importance resides in his contributions to both<space/><link><target>Impressionism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Post-Impressionism</target></link>. Pissarro studied from great forerunners, including<space/><link><target>Gustave Courbet</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste-Camille Corot</target></link>. He later studied and worked alongside<space/><link><target>Georges Seurat</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Signac</target></link><space/>when he took on the Neo-Impressionist style at the age of 54.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1873 he helped establish a collective society of fifteen aspiring artists, becoming the &quot;pivotal&quot; figure in holding the group together and encouraging the other members. Art historian<space/><link><target>John Rewald</target></link><space/>called Pissarro the &quot;dean of the Impressionist painters&quot;, not only because he was the oldest of the group, but also &quot;by virtue of his wisdom and his balanced, kind, and warmhearted personality&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald">Rewald, John.<space/><italics>Camille Pissarro</italics>, Harry N. Abrams (1989)</extension><space/><link><target>Paul Czanne</target><part>Czanne</part></link><space/>said &quot;he was a father for me. A man to consult and a little like the good Lord,&quot; and he was also one of<space/><link><target>Paul Gauguin</target><part>Gauguin</part></link>'s masters.<space/><link><target>Renoir</target></link><space/>referred to his work as &quot;revolutionary&quot;, through his artistic portrayals of the &quot;common man&quot;, as Pissarro insisted on painting individuals in natural settings without &quot;artifice or grandeur&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Pissarro is the only artist to have shown his work at all eight Paris Impressionist exhibitions, from 1874 to 1886. He &quot;acted as a father figure not only to the Impressionists&quot; but to all four of the major Post-Impressionists, including<space/><link><target>Georges Seurat</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paul Czanne</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Vincent van Gogh</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Gauguin</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bade">Bade, Patrick.<space/><italics>Monet and the Impressionists</italics>, Fog City Press (2003) p. 81</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Early years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro 2012 011.JPG</target><part></part><part>thumb</part><part>''Paisaje tropical con casas rurales y palmeras'', c. 1853.<space/><link><target>National Art Gallery (Caracas)</target><part>Galera de Arte Nacional, Caracas</part></link></part></link><link><target>File:Deux femmes causant au bord de la mer, Saint Thomas (Camille Pissarro) NGA 1985.64.30.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''Two Women Chatting by the Sea'',<space/><link><target>Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands</target><part>St. Thomas</part></link>, (1856), (private collection)</part></link><bold>Jacob Abraham Camille Pissarro</bold><space/>was born on 10 July 1830 on the island of<space/><link><target>St. Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands</target><part>St. Thomas</part></link><space/>to Frederick and Rachel Manzano de Pissarro.<extension extension_name='ref' name="collier"><template><target>cite encyclopedia</target><arg name="last">Hamilton<space/></arg><arg name="first">George Heard<space/></arg><arg name="editor">William D. Halsey<space/></arg><arg name="encyclopedia">''Collier's Encyclopedia''<space/></arg><arg name="title">Pissarro, Camille<space/></arg><arg name="year">1976<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Macmillan Educational Corporation<space/></arg><arg name="volume">19<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York<space/></arg><arg name="page">83</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Wold Eiermann, &quot;Camille Pissarro 18301903,&quot; in Christoph Becker,<space/><italics>Camille Pissarro</italics><space/>(Hatje Cantz: Ostfildern-Ruit, 1999), 1.</extension><space/>His father, who was of<space/><link><target>Jews of Portugal</target><part>Portuguese Jewish</part></link><space/>descent, held French nationality and his mother was native<space/><link><target>Creole peoples#Caribbean</target><part>Creole</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bade"></extension><space/>His father was a merchant who came to the island from France to deal with the business affairs of a deceased uncle, and married his widow. The marriage, however, caused a stir within St. Thomas' small Jewish community, either because Rachel was outside the faith or because she was previously married to Frederick's uncle, and in subsequent years his four children were forced to attend the all-black primary school.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mendez">Mendez, Serafin.<space/><italics>Notable Caribbeans and Caribbean Americans: a Biographical Dictionary</italics>, Greenwood Publishing (2003) pp. 349350</extension><space/>Upon his death, his will specified that his estate be split equally between the synagogue and St. Thomas' Protestant church.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Joachim">Pissarro, Joachim.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.artchive.com/artchive/ftptoc/pissarro_ext.html'>&quot;Camille Pissarro biography&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>Artchive</italics></extension></paragraph><paragraph>When Camille was twelve his father sent him to boarding school in France. He studied at the Savary Academy in<space/><link><target>Passy</target></link><space/>near Paris. While a young student, he developed an early appreciation of the French art masters. Monsieur Savary himself gave him a strong grounding in drawing and painting and suggested he draw from nature when he returned to St. Thomas, which he did when he was seventeen. However, his father preferred he work in his business, giving him a job working as a cargo clerk. He took every opportunity during those next five years at the job to practice drawing during breaks and after work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"><italics>The Great Masters</italics>, Quantum Books (2004) pp. 279319</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When he turned twenty-one, Danish artist<space/><link><target>Fritz Melbye</target></link>, then living on St. Thomas, inspired Pissarro to take on painting as a full-time profession, becoming his teacher and friend. Pissarro then chose to leave his family and job and live in<space/><link><target>Venezuela</target></link>, where he and Melbye spent the next two years working as artists in<space/><link><target>Caracas</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>La Guaira</target></link>. He drew everything he could, including landscapes, village scenes, and numerous sketches, enough to fill up multiple sketchbooks. In 1855 he moved back to Paris where he began working as assistant to<space/><link><target>Anton Melbye</target></link>, Fritz Melbye's brother.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"><italics>Camille Pissarro</italics>, Art Gallery of New South Wales, (2005)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.pissarro.vi/exhibition.htm</arg><arg name="title">Exhibition</arg><arg name="publisher">St. Thomas Synagogue</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 October 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Life in France</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro Jalais Hill, Pontoise The Metropolitan Museum of Art.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>''Jalais Hill, Pontoise'',<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link><space/>1867</part></link>In Paris he worked as assistant to Danish painter<space/><link><target>Anton Melbye</target></link>. He also studied paintings by other artists whose style impressed him:<space/><link><target>Courbet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles-Franois Daubigny</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean-Franois Millet</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Jean-Baptiste-Camille Corot</target><part>Corot</part></link>. He also enrolled in various classes taught by masters, at schools such as<space/><link><target>cole des Beaux-Arts</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Acadmie Suisse</target></link>. But Pissarro eventually found their teaching methods &quot;stifling,&quot; states art historian<space/><link><target>John Rewald</target></link>. This prompted him to search for alternative instruction, which he requested and received from Corot.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>11</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Paris Salon and Corot's influence</heading><paragraph>His initial paintings were in accord with the standards at the time to be displayed at the Paris<space/><link><target>Salon (Paris)</target><part>Salon</part></link>, the official body whose academic traditions dictated the kind of art that was acceptable. The Salon's annual exhibition was essentially the only marketplace for young artists to gain exposure. As a result, Pissarro worked in the traditional and prescribed manner to satisfy the tastes of its official committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1859 his first painting was accepted and exhibited. His other paintings during that period were influenced by<space/><link><target>Camille Corot</target></link>, who tutored him.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.artknowledgenews.com/Pissarro'>Pissarro Exhibition PowerPoint with sound</link></extension><space/>He and Corot both shared a love of rural scenes painted from nature. It was by Corot that Pissarro was inspired to paint outdoors, also called &quot;<link><target>plein air</target></link>&quot; painting. Pissarro found Corot, along with the work of<space/><link><target>Gustave Courbet</target></link>, to be &quot;statements of pictorial truth,&quot; writes Rewald. He discussed their work often.<space/><link><target>Jean-Franois Millet</target></link><space/>was another whose work he admired, especially his &quot;sentimental renditions of rural life&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>12</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Use of natural outdoor settings</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro 012.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Entre du village de<space/><link><target>:fr:Voisins (Louveciennes)</target><part>Voisins</part></link>'' (1872)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>During this period Pissarro began to understand and appreciate the importance of expressing on canvas the beauties of nature without adulteration.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>12</arg></template><space/>After a year in Paris, he therefore began to leave the city and paint scenes in the countryside to capture the daily reality of village life. He found the French countryside to be &quot;picturesque,&quot; and worthy of being painted. It was still mostly agricultural and sometimes called the &quot;golden age of the peasantry&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>17</arg></template><space/>Pissarro later explained the technique of painting outdoors to a student:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Work at the same time upon sky, water, branches, ground, keeping everything going on an equal basis and unceasingly rework until you have got it. Paint generously and unhesitatingly, for it is best not to lose the first impression.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Rewald, John.<space/><italics>The History of Impressionism</italics>, Harry Abrams, (1990) p. 458</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>Corot, however, would complete his own scenic paintings back in his studio where they would often be revised to his preconceptions. Pissarro, on the other hand, preferred to finish his paintings outdoors, often at one sitting, which gave his work a more realistic feel. As a result, his art was sometimes criticised as being &quot;vulgar,&quot; because he painted what he saw: &quot;rutted and edged hodgepodge of bushes, mounds of earth, and trees in various stages of development.&quot; According to one source, details such as those were equivalent to today's art showing garbage cans or beer bottles on the side of a street scene. This difference in style created disagreements between Pissarro and Corot.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>With Monet, Czanne, and Guillaumin</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Road to Versailles at Louveciennes 1869 Camille Pissarro.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>In 1869 Pissarro settled in<space/><link><target>Louveciennes</target></link><space/>and would often paint the road to Versailles in various seasons.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[The Walters Art Museum]]<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://art.thewalters.org/detail/20599<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Road to Versailles</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>The Walters Art Museum</target></link>.</part></link>In 1859, while attending the free school, the<space/><link><target>Acadmie Suisse</target></link>, Pissarro became friends with a number of younger artists who likewise chose to paint in the more realistic style. Among them were<space/><link><target>Claude Monet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Armand Guillaumin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Czanne</target></link>. What they shared in common was their dissatisfaction with the dictates of the Salon. Czanne's work had been mocked at the time by the others in the school, and, writes Rewald, in his later years Czanne &quot;never forgot the sympathy and understanding with which Pissarro encouraged him.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>16</arg></template><space/>As a part of the group, Pissarro was comforted from knowing he was not alone, and that others similarly struggled with their art.</paragraph><paragraph>Pissarro agreed with the group about the importance of portraying individuals in natural settings, and expressed his dislike of any artifice or grandeur in his works, despite what the Salon demanded for its exhibits. In 1863 almost all of the group's paintings were rejected by the Salon, and French Emperor<space/><link><target>Napoleon III</target></link><space/>instead decided to place their paintings in a separate exhibit hall, the<space/><link><target>Salon des Refuss</target></link>. However, only works of Pissarro and Czanne were included, and the separate exhibit brought a hostile response from both the officials of the Salon and the public.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In subsequent Salon exhibits of 1865 and 1866, Pissarro acknowledged his influences from Melbye and Corot, whom he listed as his masters in the catalogue. But in the exhibition of 1868 he no longer credited other artists as an influence, in effect declaring his independence as a painter. This was noted at the time by art critic and author<space/><link><target>mile Zola</target></link>, who offered his opinion:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Camille Pissarro is one of the three or four true painters of this day&amp;nbsp;... I have rarely encountered a technique that is so sure.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Image:Camille Pissaro et sa femme Julie Vellay en 1877 Pontoise.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>''Camille Pissarro and his wife, Julie Vellay'', 1877,<space/><link><target>Pontoise</target></link></part></link>Another writer tries to describe elements of Pissarro's style:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;The brightness of his palette envelops objects in atmosphere&amp;nbsp;... He paints the smell of the earth.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>35</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>And though, on orders from the hanging Committee and the<space/><link><target>Charles-Philippe de Chennevires-Pointel</target><part>Marquis de Chennevires</part></link>, Pissarro's paintings of<space/><link><target>Pontoise</target></link><space/>for example had been skyed, hung near the ceiling, this did not prevent<space/><link><target>Jules-Antoine Castagnary</target></link><space/>from noting that the qualities of his paintings had been observed by art lovers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ross King, The Judgement of Paris, p.230 Chatto &amp; Windus 206</extension><space/>At the age of thirty-eight, Pissarro had begun to win himself a reputation as a landscapist to rival Corot and Daubigny.</paragraph><paragraph>In the late 1860s or early 1870s, Pissarro became fascinated with<space/><link><target>Japanese prints</target></link>, which influenced his desire to experiment in new compositions. He described the art to his son<space/><link><target>Lucien Pissarro</target><part>Lucien</part></link>:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;It is marvelous. This is what I see in the art of this astonishing people&amp;nbsp;... nothing that leaps to the eye, a calm, a grandeur, an extraordinary unity, a rather subdued radiance&amp;nbsp;...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>19</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Marriage and children</heading><paragraph>In 1871 he married his mother's maid, Julie Vellay, a vineyard grower's daughter, with whom he would later have seven children. They lived outside of Paris in<space/><link><target>Pontoise</target></link><space/>and later in<space/><link><target>Louveciennes</target></link>, both of which places inspired many of his paintings including scenes of village life, along with rivers, woods, and people at work. He also kept in touch with the other artists of his earlier group, especially Monet, Renoir, Czanne, and<space/><link><target>Frdric Bazille</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>The London years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bath Road, London by Camille Pissarro.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Bath Road,<space/><link><target>Chiswick</target></link><space/>by Camille Pissarro, 1897. Oil on canvas.</part></link>After the outbreak of the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian War</target></link><space/>of 187071, having only Danish nationality and being unable to join the army, he moved his family to Norwood, then a village on the edge of London. However, his style of painting, which was a forerunner of what was later called &quot;Impressionism&quot;, did not do well. He wrote to his friend,<space/><link><target>Theodore Duret</target></link>, that &quot;my painting doesn't catch on, not at all&amp;nbsp;...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Pissarro met the Paris art dealer<space/><link><target>Paul Durand-Ruel</target></link>, in London, who became the dealer who helped sell his art for most of his life. Durand-Ruel put him in touch with<space/><link><target>Monet</target></link><space/>who was likewise in London during this period. They both viewed the work of British landscape artists<space/><link><target>John Constable</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>J. M. W. Turner</target></link>, which confirmed their belief that their style of open air painting gave the truest depiction of light and atmosphere, an effect that they felt could not be achieved in the studio alone. Pissarro's paintings also began to take on a more spontaneous look, with loosely blended brushstrokes and areas of<space/><link><target>impasto</target></link>, giving more depth to the work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey>Paintings</defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>Through the paintings Pissarro completed at this time, he records<space/><link><target>Sydenham</target></link><space/>and the Norwoods at a time when they were just recently connected by railways, but prior to the expansion of suburbia. One of the largest of these paintings is a view of<space/><italics>St. Bartholomew's Church</italics><space/>at Lawrie Park Avenue, commonly known as<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nationalgallery.org.uk/cgi-bin/WebObjects.dll/CollectionPublisher.woa/wa/work?workNumber=NG6493'>''The Avenue, Sydenham''</link>, in the collection of the<space/><link><target>London National Gallery</target></link>. Twelve oil paintings date from his stay in Upper Norwood and are listed and illustrated in the<space/><link><target>catalogue raisonn</target></link><space/>prepared jointly by his fifth child Ludovic-Rodolphe Pissarro and<space/><link><target>Lionello Venturi</target></link><space/>and published in 1939. These paintings include<space/><italics>Norwood Under the Snow</italics>, and<space/><italics><link><target>Lordship Lane (Dulwich)</target><part>Lordship Lane Station</part></link></italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.artchive.com/artchive/P/pissarro/pissarro_lordship.jpg.html'>artchive.com</link><space/>entry for Pissarro Lordship Lane</extension><space/>views of<space/><link><target>The Crystal Palace</target></link><space/>relocated from<space/><link><target>Hyde Park, London</target><part>Hyde Park</part></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Dulwich College</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Sydenham Hill</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics>All Saints Church<space/><link><target>Upper Norwood</target></link></italics>, and a lost painting of St. Stephen's Church.</paragraph><paragraph>Returning to France, in 1890 Pissarro again visited England and painted some ten scenes of central London. He came back again in 1892, painting in<space/><link><target>Kew Gardens</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kew Green</target></link>, and also in 1897, when he produced several oils described as being of<space/><link><target>Bedford Park, London</target><part>Bedford Park</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Chiswick</target></link>, but in fact all being of the nearby<space/><link><target>Stamford Brook</target></link><space/>area except for one of Bath Road, which runs from Stamford Brook along the south edge of Bedford Park.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url">http://brentfordandchiswicklhs.org.uk/publications/the-journal/journal-6-1997/camille-pissarro-paintings-of-stamford-brook-1897/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Camille Pissarro: Paintings of Stamford Brook, 1897<space/></arg><arg name="author">Seaton, Shirley<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Brentford & Chiswick Local History Journal<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="volume">6</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>For more details of his British visits, see Nicholas Reed,<space/><italics>Camille Pissarro at Crystal Palace</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Pissarro in West London</italics>, published by Lilburne Press.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>French Impressionism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro 023.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''Landscape at<space/><link><target>Pontoise</target></link>'', 1874</part></link>When Pissarro returned to his home in France after the war, he discovered that of the 1,500 paintings he had done over 20 years, which he was forced to leave behind when he moved to London, only 40 remained. The rest had been damaged or destroyed by the soldiers, who often used them as floor mats outside in the mud to keep their boots clean. It is assumed that many of those lost were done in the Impressionist style he was then developing, thereby &quot;documenting the birth of<space/><link><target>Impressionism</target></link>.&quot; Armand Silvestre, a critic, went so far as to call Pissarro &quot;basically the inventor of this [Impressionist] painting&quot;; however, Pissarro's role in the Impressionist movement was &quot;less that of the great man of ideas than that of the good counselor and appeaser&amp;nbsp;...&quot; &quot;Monet&amp;nbsp;... could be seen as the guiding force.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>280, 283</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>He soon reestablished his friendships with the other Impressionist artists of his earlier group, including Czanne, Monet, Manet, Renoir, and Degas. Pissarro now expressed his opinion to the group that he wanted an alternative to the<space/><link><target>Salon (Paris)</target><part>Salon</part></link><space/>so their group could display their own unique styles.</paragraph><paragraph>To assist in that endeavour, in 1873 he helped establish a separate collective, called the &quot;Socit Anonyme des Artistes, Peintres, Sculpteurs et Graveurs,&quot; which included fifteen artists. Pissarro created the group's first charter and became the &quot;pivotal&quot; figure in establishing and holding the group together. One writer noted that with his prematurely grey beard, the forty-three-year-old Pissarro was regarded as a &quot;wise elder and father figure&quot; by the group.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension><space/>Yet he was able to work alongside the other artists on equal terms due to his youthful temperament and creativity. Another writer said of him that &quot;he has unchanging spiritual youth and the look of an ancestor who remained a young man&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>36</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Impressionist exhibitions that shocked the critics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro (French, 1830-1903) Le grand noyer l'Hermitage.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>''Le grand noyer l'Hermitage'', 1875, - the new manner of painting was too sketchy and looked incomplete.</part></link>The following year, in 1874, the group held their first 'Impressionist' Exhibition, which shocked and &quot;horrified&quot; the critics, who primarily appreciated only scenes portraying religious, historical, or mythological settings. They found fault with the Impressionist paintings on many grounds:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The subject matter was considered &quot;vulgar&quot; and &quot;commonplace,&quot; with scenes of street people going about their everyday lives. Pissarro's paintings, for instance, showed scenes of muddy, dirty, and unkempt settings;</listitem></list><list type='bullet'><listitem>The manner of painting was too sketchy and looked incomplete, especially compared to the traditional styles of the period. The use of visible and expressive brushwork by all the artists was considered an insult to the craft of traditional artists, who often spent weeks on their work. Here, the paintings were often done in one sitting and the paints were applied wet-on-wet;</listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem>The use of color by the Impressionists relied on new theories they developed, such as having shadows painted with the reflected light of surrounding, and often unseen, objects.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>A &quot;revolutionary&quot; style</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro, Le verger (The Orchard), 1872.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>'' Orchard in Bloom, Louveciennes'' (1872)</part></link><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - The Hay Cart, Montfoucault - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumbnail</part><part>''The Hay Cart, Montfoucault'' (1879)</part></link>Pissarro showed five of his paintings, all landscapes, at the exhibit, and again<space/><link><target>mile Zola</target></link><space/>praised his art and that of the others. In the Impressionist exhibit of 1876; however,<space/><link><target>art critic</target></link><space/>Albert Wolff complained in his review, &quot;Try to make M. Pissarro understand that trees are not violet, that sky is not the color of fresh butter&amp;nbsp;...&quot; Journalist and art critic<space/><link><target>Octave Mirbeau</target></link><space/>on the other hand, writes, &quot;Camille Pissarro has been a revolutionary through the revitalized working methods with which he has endowed painting&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>36</arg></template>According to Rewald, Pissarro had taken on an attitude more simple and natural than the other artists. He writes:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Rather than glorifyingconsciously or notthe rugged existence of the peasants, he placed them without any 'pose' in their habitual surroundings, thus becoming an objective chronicler of one of the many facets of contemporary life.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>20</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>In later years, Czanne also recalled this period and referred to Pissarro as &quot;the first Impressionist&quot;. In 1906, a few years after Pissarro's death, Czanne, then 67 and a role model for the new generation of artists, paid Pissarro a debt of gratitude by having himself listed in an exhibition catalogue as &quot;Paul Czanne, pupil of Pissarro&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>45</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Pissarro,<space/><link><target>Degas</target></link>, and American impressionist<space/><link><target>Mary Cassatt</target></link><space/>planned a journal of their original prints in the late 1870s, a project that nevertheless came to nothing when Degas withdrew.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Mathews</arg><arg name="pp"><space/>139, 149</arg></template><extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension><space/>Art historian and the artist's great-grandson Joachim Pissarro notes that they &quot;professed a passionate disdain for the Salons and refused to exhibit at them.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Joachim"></extension><space/>Together they shared an &quot;almost militant resolution&quot; against the Salon, and through their later correspondences it is clear that their mutual admiration &quot;was based on a kinship of ethical as well as aesthetic concerns&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Joachim"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Cassatt had befriended Degas and Pissarro years earlier when she joined Pissarro's newly formed French Impressionist group and gave up opportunities to exhibit in the United States. She and Pissarro were often treated as &quot;two outsiders&quot; by the Salon since neither were French or had become French citizens. However, she was &quot;fired up with the cause&quot; of promoting Impressionism and looked forward to exhibiting &quot;out of solidarity with her new friends&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Roe, Sue.<space/><italics>The Private Lives of the Impressionists</italics>, HarperCollins (2006) p. 187</extension><space/>Towards the end of the 1890s she began to distance herself from the Impressionists, avoiding Degas at times she did not have the strength to defend herself against his &quot;wicked tongue&quot;. Instead, she came to prefer the company of &quot;the gentle Camille Pissarro&quot;, with whom she could speak frankly about the changing attitudes toward art.<template><target>sfn</target><arg>Mathews</arg><arg name="pp"><space/>190, 238-9</arg></template><space/>She once described him as a teacher &quot;that could have taught the stones to draw correctly.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Neo-Impressionist period</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Hay Harvest at ragny, 1901, Camille Pissarro.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>Hay Harvest at ragny, 1901,<space/><link><target>National Gallery of Canada</target></link>, Ottawa</part></link><link><target>File:Enfant ttant sa mre by Camille Pissarro 1882.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>''Enfant ttant sa mre'', drypoint and aquatint, 1882, 123 mm x 112 mm,<space/><link><target>British Museum, London</target><part>British Museum.</part></link></part></link>By the 1880s, Pissarro began to explore new themes and methods of painting to break out of what he felt was an artistic &quot;mire&quot;. As a result, Pissarro went back to his earlier themes by painting the life of country people, which he had done in Venezuela in his youth. Degas described Pissarro's subjects as &quot;peasants working to make a living&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>However, this period also marked the end of the Impressionist period due to Pissarro's leaving the movement. As Joachim Pissarro points out, &quot;Once such a die-hard Impressionist as Pissarro had turned his back on Impressionism, it was apparent that Impressionism had no chance of surviving&amp;nbsp;...&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>52</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>It was Pissarro's intention during this period to help &quot;educate the public&quot; by painting people at work or at home in realistic settings, without idealising their lives.<space/><link><target>Pierre-Auguste Renoir</target></link>, in 1882, referred to Pissarro's work during this period as &quot;revolutionary,&quot; in his attempt to portray the &quot;common man.&quot; Pissarro himself did not use his art to overtly preach any kind of political message, however, although his preference for painting humble subjects was intended to be seen and purchased by his upper class clientele. He also began painting with a more unified brushwork along with pure strokes of color.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Studying with Seurat and Signac</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - La Rcolte des Foins, ragny - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>''La Rcolte des Foins, Eragny'' (1887)</part></link>In 1885 he met<space/><link><target>Georges Seurat</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Paul Signac</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Cogniat, Raymond,<space/><italics>Pissarro</italics>, Crown (1975), p. 92. ISBN 0-517-52477-5</extension><space/>both of whom relied on a more &quot;scientific&quot; theory of painting by using very small patches of pure colours to create the illusion of blended colours and shading when viewed from a distance. Pissarro then spent the years from 1885 to 1888 practising this more time-consuming and laborious technique, referred to as<space/><link><target>pointillism</target></link>. The paintings that resulted were distinctly different from his Impressionist works, and were on display in the 1886 Impressionist Exhibition, but under a separate section, along with works by Seurat, Signac, and his son<space/><link><target>Lucien Pissarro</target><part>Lucien</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>All four works were considered an &quot;exception&quot; to the eighth exhibition. Joachim Pissarro notes that virtually every reviewer who commented on Pissarro's work noted &quot;his extraordinary capacity to change his art, revise his position and take on new challenges.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>52</arg></template><space/>One critic writes:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;It is difficult to speak of Camille Pissarro&amp;nbsp;... What we have here is a fighter from way back, a master who continually grows and courageously adapts to new theories.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>51</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>Pissarro explained the new art form as a &quot;phase in the logical march of Impressionism&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>49</arg></template><space/>but he was alone among the other Impressionists with this attitude, however. Joachim Pissarro states that Pissarro thereby became the &quot;only artist who went from Impressionism to<space/><link><target>Neo-Impressionism</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1884, art dealer<space/><link><target>Theo van Gogh (art dealer)</target><part>Theo van Gogh</part></link><space/>asked Pissarro if he would take in his older brother,<space/><link><target>Vincent van Gogh</target><part>Vincent</part></link>, as a boarder in his home. Lucien Pissarro wrote that his father was impressed by Van Gogh's work and had &quot;foreseen the power of this artist&quot;, who was 23 years younger. Although Van Gogh never boarded with him, Pissarro did explain to him the various ways of finding and expressing light and color, ideas which he later used in his paintings, notes Lucien.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>43</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Abandoning Neo-Impressionism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Pissarro - Pont Boieldieu in Rouen, Rainy Weather.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>Pont Boieldieu in Rouen, Rainy Weather</target></link>'', (1896),<space/><link><target>Art Gallery of Ontario</target></link></part></link>Pissarro eventually turned away from Neo-Impressionism, claiming its system was too artificial. He explains in a letter to a friend:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;Having tried this theory for four years and having then abandoned it&amp;nbsp;... I can no longer consider myself one of the neo-impressionists&amp;nbsp;... It was impossible to be true to my sensations and consequently to render life and movement, impossible to be faithful to the effects, so random and so admirable, of nature, impossible to give an individual character to my drawing, [that] I had to give up.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>41</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>However, after reverting to his earlier style, his work became, according to Rewald, &quot;more subtle, his color scheme more refined, his drawing firmer&amp;nbsp;... So it was that Pissarro approached old age with an increased mastery.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>41</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>But the change also added to Pissarro's continual financial hardship which he felt until his 60s. His &quot;headstrong courage and a tenacity to undertake and sustain the career of an artist&quot;, writes Joachim Pissarro, was due to his &quot;lack of fear of the immediate repercussions&quot; of his stylistic decisions. In addition, his work was strong enough to &quot;bolster his morale and keep him going&quot;, he writes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Joachim"></extension><space/>His Impressionist contemporaries, however, continued to view his independence as a &quot;mark of integrity&quot;, and they turned to him for advice, referring to him as &quot;Pre Pissarro&quot; (father Pissarro).<extension extension_name='ref' name="Joachim"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Later years</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro Two Young Peasant Women The Metropolitan Museum of Art.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>''Two Young Peasant Women'' (1891 and 1892),<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In his older age Pissarro suffered from a recurring eye infection that prevented him from working outdoors except in warm weather. As a result of this disability, he began painting outdoor scenes while sitting by the window of hotel rooms. He often chose hotel rooms on upper levels to get a broader view. He moved around northern France and painted from hotels in Rouen, Paris, Le Havre and Dieppe. On his visits to London, he would do the same.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Pissarro died in Paris on 13 November 1903 and was buried in<space/><link><target>Pre Lachaise Cemetery</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="collier"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy and influence</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>Camille Pissarro, c. 1900</part></link>During the period Pissarro exhibited his works, art critic<space/><link><target>Armand Silvestre</target></link><space/>had called Pissarro the &quot;most real and most naive member&quot; of the Impressionist group.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelder">Kelder, Diane.<space/><italics>The Great Book of French Impressionism</italics>, Abbeville Press (1980) pp. 127, 135</extension><space/>His work has also been described by art historian Diane Kelder as expressing &quot;the same quiet dignity, sincerity, and durability that distinguished his person.&quot; She adds that &quot;no member of the group did more to mediate the internecine disputes that threatened at times to break it apart, and no one was a more diligent proselytizer of the new painting.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelder"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>According to Pissarro's son, Lucien, his father painted regularly with<space/><link><target>Czanne</target></link><space/>beginning in 1872. He recalls that Czanne walked a few miles to join Pissarro at various settings in Pontoise. While they shared ideas during their work, the younger Czanne wanted to study the countryside through Pissarro's eyes, as he admired Pissarro's landscapes from the 1860s. Czanne, although only nine years younger than Pissarro, said that &quot;he was a father for me. A man to consult and a little like the good Lord.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Lucien Pissarro</target></link><space/>was taught painting by his father, and described him as a &quot;splendid teacher, never imposing his personality on his pupil.&quot;<space/><link><target>Gauguin</target></link>, who also studied under him, referred to Pissarro &quot;as a force with which future artists would have to reckon&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gallery"></extension><space/>Art historian Diane Kelder notes that it was Pissarro who introduced Gauguin, who was then a young stockbroker studying to become an artist, to Degas and Czanne.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Kelder"></extension><space/>Gauguin, near the end of his career, wrote a letter to a friend in 1902, shortly before Pissarro's death:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>&quot;If we observe the totality of Pissarro's work, we find there, despite fluctuations, not only an extreme artistic will, never belied, but also an essentially intuitive, purebred art&amp;nbsp;... He was one of my masters and I do not deny him.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Rewald"></extension><template><target>rp</target><arg>45</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph>The American impressionist<space/><link><target>Mary Cassatt</target></link>, who at one point lived in Paris to study art, and joined his Impressionist group, noted that he was &quot;such a teacher that he could have taught the stones to draw correctly.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Masters"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Caribbean author and scholar<space/><link><target>Derek Walcott</target></link><space/>based his book-length poem,<space/><italics>Tiepolo's Hound</italics><space/>(2000), on Pissarro's life.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>'Doubting Thomas' -- review of Derek Walcott's Tiepolo's Hound</arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.academia.edu/2184537/Doubting_Thomas_--_review_of_Derek_Walcotts_Tiepolos_Hound</arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>2015-04-27</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><heading level='3'>Lost and found paintings</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro - Self-portrait - Tate Britain.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>Self-portrait</target></link>,'' 1903,<space/><link><target>Tate Gallery</target></link>, London</part></link>During the early 1930s throughout Europe, Jewish owners of numerous fine art masterpieces found themselves forced to give up or sell off their collections for minimal prices due to anti-Jewish laws created by the new Nazi regime. Many Jews were forced to flee Germany. When those forced into exile owned valuables, including artwork, they were often seized by officials for personal gain. In the decades after World War II, many art masterpieces were found on display in various galleries and museums in Europe and the United States. Some, as a result of legal action, were later returned to the families of the original owners. Many of the recovered paintings were then donated to the same or other museums as a gift.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Muller">Muller, Melissa; Monika, Tatzkow.<space/><italics>Lost Lives, Lost Art</italics>, Vendome Press (2010)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>One such lost piece, Pissarro's 1897 oil painting,<space/><italics>Rue St. Honor, Apres Midi, Effet de Pluie</italics>, was discovered hanging at<space/><link><target>Madrid</target></link>'s government-owned museum, the<space/><link><target>Museo Thyssen-Bornemisza</target></link>. In January 2011 the Spanish government denied a request by the US ambassador to return the painting.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/07/us/07treasure.html?partner=rss&amp;amp;emc=rss'>&quot;WikiLeaks Cables Make Appearance in a Tale of Sunken Treasure and Nazi Theft&quot;</link>,<space/><italics>New York Times</italics>, 6 January 2011</extension><space/>At the subsequent trial in Los Angeles,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.fox5sandiego.com/news/kswb-masterpiece-lost-to-nazis,0,7588663.story'>&quot;Family fights to recover masterpiece lost to Nazis&quot;</link>, Fox News, 23 September 2010</extension><space/>the court ruled that the Thyssen-Bornemisza Collection Foundation was the rightful owner.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://artdaily.com/index.asp?int_sec=11&amp;amp;int_new=56309&amp;amp;int_modo=1'>&quot;U.S. District Court confirms Thyssen-Bornemisza Collection Foundation of Spain as owner of artwork&quot;</link></extension><space/>Pissarro's<space/><italics>Le Quai Malaquais, Printemps</italics><space/>is said to have been similarly stolen,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.lootedartcommission.com/MO89VR49433'>&quot;Nazi-Looted Pissarro in Zurich Bank Pits Heiress Against Dealer&quot;</link>, Commission for Looted Art in Europe, 6 June 2007</extension><space/>while in 1999, Pissarro's 1897<space/><italics><link><target>Le Boulevard de Montmartre, Matine de Printemps</target></link></italics><space/>appeared in the<space/><link><target>Israel Museum</target></link><space/>in Jerusalem, its donor having been unaware of its pre-war provenance.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mazyler, Michael J.<space/><italics>Holocaust Justice</italics>, N.Y. University Press (2003) p. 205</extension><space/>In January 2012,<space/><italics>Le March aux Poissons</italics><space/>(The Fish Market), a color<space/><link><target>monotype</target></link>, was returned after 30 years.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.cnn.com/2012/01/25/us/impressionist-art-returned/?hpt=hp_t3'>&quot;Stolen impressionist art returned after 3 decades</link>,<space/><italics>CNN</italics>, 25 January 2012</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During his lifetime, Camille Pissarro sold few of his paintings. By the 21st century, however, his paintings were selling for millions. An auction record for the artist was set on 6 November 2007 at<space/><link><target>Christie's</target></link><space/>in New York, where a group of four paintings,<space/><italics>Les Quatre Saisons</italics><space/>(the Four Seasons), sold for $14,601,000 (estimate $12,000,000 $18,000,000). In November 2009<space/><italics>Le Pont Boieldieu et la Gare d'Orlans, Rouen, Soleil</italics><space/>sold for $7,026,500 at<space/><link><target>Sotheby's</target></link><space/>in New York. In February 2014 the 1897<space/><italics>Le Boulevard de Montmartre, Matine de Printemps</italics>, originally owned by the German industrialist and<space/><link><target>Holocaust</target></link><space/>victim<space/><link><target>Max Silberberg</target></link><space/>(<link><target>:de:Max Silberberg</target><part>de</part></link>), sold at Sotheby's in London for 19.9M, nearly five times the previous record.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/entertainment-arts-26064373<space/></arg><arg name="title">BBC News - Pissarro painting sells for a record £19.9m<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Bbc.co.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-06</arg></template></extension><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Pissarro Camille - Boulevard Montmartre Paris.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>Boulevard Montmartre Paris</italics>, 1897,<space/><link><target>Hermitage Museum</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Boulevard Montmartre, morning, cloudy weather - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Boulevard Montmartre, morning, cloudy weather, 1897,<space/><link><target>National Gallery of Victoria</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:The Boulevard Montmartre on a Winter Morning.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Boulevard Montmartre on a Winter Morning</italics>, 1897,<space/><link><target>Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Boulevard Montmartre, Spring - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics><link><target>Le Boulevard de Montmartre, Matine de Printemps</target></link></italics>, street view from hotel window, 1897</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro 009.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Boulevard Montmartre la nuit</italics>, 1898</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>A family of painters</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - The Artist's Palette with a Landscape (c.1878).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''The Artist's Palette with a Landscape'' c. 1878,<space/><link><target>Clark Art Institute</target></link></part></link>Camille's son<space/><link><target>Lucien Pissarro</target><part>Lucien</part></link><space/>was an Impressionist and Neo-impressionist painter as were his second and third sons<space/><link><target>Georges Henri Manzana Pissarro</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Flix Pissarro</target></link>. Lucien's daughter<space/><link><target>Orovida Camille Pissarro</target><part>Orovida Pissarro</part></link><space/>was also a painter. Camille's great-grandson, Joachim Pissarro, became Head Curator of Drawing and Painting at the<space/><link><target>Museum of Modern Art</target></link><space/>in New York City and a professor in Hunter College's Art Department.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.hunter.cuny.edu/provost/repository/files/Hunter%202008-09%20PMP%206-18-09%20final.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">Hunter College Performance Goals and Targets 2008–2009 Academic Year<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Hunter College, CUNY<space/></arg><arg name="date">18 June 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">15 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>From the only daughter of Camille, Jeanne Pissarro, other painters include Henri Bonin-Pissarro (19182003) and<space/><link><target>Claude Bonin-Pissarro</target></link><space/>(born 1921), who is the father of the Abstract artist Frdric Bonin-Pissarro (born 1964).</paragraph><heading level='2'>List of paintings</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics><link><target>The Banks of the Oise near Pontoise</target></link></italics><space/>1873,<space/><link><target>Indianapolis Museum of Art</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Pont Boieldieu in Rouen, Rainy Weather</target></link></italics>, 1896,<space/><link><target>Art Gallery of Ontario</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Le Boulevard de Montmartre, Matine de Printemps</target></link></italics>, view from window, 1897 - Private Collection</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Hay Harvest at ragny</target></link></italics>, 1901<space/><link><target>National Gallery of Canada</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Self-portrait</target></link></italics>, 1903, Tate Gallery, London</listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Alle dans une fret (sur 1859).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>Alle dans une fort</italics><space/>(&quot;Road in a Forest&quot;), 1859</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro 010.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Le chemin</italics>, (&quot;The Way&quot;) c. 1864</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro 018.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Chtaignier Louveciennes</italics>, 1870,<space/><link><target>Muse d'Orsay</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Alle dans le parc de Marly.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Woods at Marly</italics>, 1871,<space/><link><target>Thyssen-Bornemisza Museum</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:La Route.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Road to Versailles, Louveciennes: Morning Frost</italics>, 1871,<space/><link><target>Dallas Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:PissarroOld Chelsea Bridge.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Old Chelsea Bridge, London</italics><space/>1871,<space/><link><target>Smith College</target></link><space/>Museum of Arts</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Pissaro, Camille, Still Life Apples and Pears.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Still Life: Apples and Pears in a Round Basket</italics>, 1872,<space/><link><target>Henry Pearlman</target><part>The Henry and Rose Pearlman Collection</part></link>, on long-term loan to the<space/><link><target>Princeton University Art Museum</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Paul Czanne.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Camille Pissarro, portrait of<space/><link><target>Paul Czanne</target></link>,<space/><link><target>National Gallery</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:MuMA - Pissarro - Un carrefour l'Hermitage, Pontoise.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Un Carrefour l'Hermitage, Pontoise</italics>, 1876,<space/><link><target>Muse Malraux</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro 011.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Toits rouges, coin d'un village, hiver</italics>, Cte de Saint-Denis, Pontoise, 1877,<space/><link><target>Muse d'Orsay</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro - The Cte des Bufs at L'Hermitage - National Gallery London.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Cte des Bufs at L'Hermitage</italics>, 1877,<space/><link><target>National Gallery</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro - Dans le jardin des Mathurins, Pontoise - 503.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The garden of Pontoise</italics>, 1877</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro Washerwoman, Study The Metropolitan Museum of Art.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Washerwoman, Study</italics>, 1880,<space/><link><target>The Metropolitan Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - Conversation - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Conversation</italics>, c. 1881,<space/><link><target>National Museum of Western Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - The Harvest - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Harvest</italics>, 1882,<space/><link><target>Bridgestone Museum of Art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Tokyo</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:CAMILLE PISSARRO (1830-1903) Le jardin de Maubuisson, Pontoise, la mre Bellette 21 7-16 x 25 7-8 in. (54.5 x 65.7cm).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Le jardin de Maubuisson, Pontoise, 1882</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:The Church at Eragny Pissarro.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>The Church at Eragny</italics>, 1884,<space/><link><target>Walters Art Museum</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Bergre rentrant des moutons.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>Bergre rentrant des moutons (Shepherdess Bringing in Sheep)</italics><space/>1886,<space/><link><target>University of Oklahoma</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro 019.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Children on a Farm,</italics><space/>1887, collection of G. Signac, Paris</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:14 oct 2014 theatre fr.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Place du Thtre Franais: Fog Effect</italics>, 1897,<space/><link><target>Dallas Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Camille Pissarro 016.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>''Haying at<space/><link><target>ragny-sur-Epte</target><part>Eragny</part></link>, 1889, private collection</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro 036.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Rouen, Rue de l'picerie</italics>, 1898, private collection</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro - La Place due Thtre Franais - Google Art Project.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/><italics>La Place due Thtre Franais</italics>, 1898,<space/><link><target>Los Angeles County Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro (1830-1903) - 'View of Rouen', 1898.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>View of Rouen</italics>, 1898,<space/><link><target>Honolulu Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Camille Pissarro (1830-1903) - 'Morning, Winter Sunshine, Frost, the Pont-Neuf, the Seine, the Louvre, Soleil D'hiver Gella Blanc', ca. 1901.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Morning, Winter Sunshine, Frost, the Pont-Neuf, the Seine, the Louvre, Soleil D'hiver Gella Blanc</italics>, c. 1901,<space/><link><target>Honolulu Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Pissarro, Jardin Mirbeau aux Damps.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Le Jardin de Mirbeau aux Damps</italics>,<space/><italics><link><target>Octave Mirbeau</target></link>'s garden in Damps</italics>, 1891</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Place du Havre, Paris.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Place du Havre</italics>, Paris, 1893,<space/><link><target>Art Institute of Chicago</target></link></tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Pissarro havre.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><italics>Ship entering the Harbor at Le Havre</italics>, 1903,<space/><link><target>Dallas Museum of Art</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><heading level='3'>Primary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Rewald, John, ed., with the assistance of Lucien Pissarro:<space/><italics>Camille Pissarro, Lettres son fils Lucien</italics>, Editions Albin Michel, Paris 1950; previously published, translated to English:<space/><italics>Camille Pissarro, Letters to his son Lucien</italics>, New York 1943 &amp; London 1944; 3rd revised edition, Paul P Appel Publishers, 1972 ISBN 0-911858-22-9</listitem><listitem>Bailly-Herzberg, Janine, ed.:<space/><italics><template><target>lang</target><arg>fr</arg><arg>Correspondance de Camille Pissarro</arg></template></italics>, 5 volumes, Presses Universitaires de France, Paris, 1980 &amp; Editions du Valhermeil, Paris, 19861991 ISBN 2-13-036694-5 ISBN 2-905684-05-4 ISBN 2-905684-09-7 ISBN 2-905684-17-8 ISBN 2-905684-35-6</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="ref">harv
</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Mathews 
</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Nancy Mowll 
</arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Nancy Mowll Mathews
</arg><arg name="editor-first">
</arg><arg name="editor-last"><space/>
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>Mary Cassatt: A Life 
</arg><arg name="url"><space/>{{Google books|EtXCGXMSE9oC|title</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[Villard (imprint)|Villard Books]] 
</arg><arg name="location"><space/>New York 
</arg><arg name="year"><space/>1994 
</arg><arg name="chapter">
</arg><arg name="chapterurl"><space/>
</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-0-394-58497-3
</arg><arg name="lccn"><space/>98-8028
</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Thorold, Anne, ed.:<space/><italics>The letters of Lucien to Camille Pissarro 18831903</italics>, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, New York &amp; Oakleigh, 1993 ISBN 0-521-39034-6</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Clement, Russell T. and Houze, Annick,<space/><italics><space/>Neo-Impressionist Painters: A Sourcebook on Georges Seurat, Camille Pissarro, Paul Signac, Tho van Rysselberghe, Henri-Edmond Cross, Charles Angrand, Maximilien Luce, and Albert Dubois-Pillet</italics><space/>(1999), Greenwood Press, ISBN 0-313-30382-7</listitem><listitem>Eitner, Lorenz,<space/><italics>An Outline of 19th Century European Painting: From David through Czanne</italics><space/>(1992), HarperCollins Publishers, ISBN 0-06-430223-7</listitem><listitem>Nochlin, Linda,<space/><italics>The Politics of Vision: Essays on Nineteenth-Century Art and Society</italics><space/>(1991) Westview Press, ISBN 0-06-430187-7</listitem><listitem>Rewald, John,<space/><italics><space/>The History of Impressionism</italics><space/>(1961), Museum of Modern Art, ISBN 0-8109-6035-4</listitem><listitem>Stone, Irving,<space/><italics>Depths of Glory</italics><space/>(1987), Signet, ISBN 0-451-14602-6</listitem></list><heading level='3'><italics>Critical Catalogue of Paintings</italics></heading><paragraph>In June 2006 publishers Skira/Wildenstein released<space/><italics>Pissarro: Critical Catalogue of Paintings</italics>, compiled by Joachim Pissarro (descendant of the painter) and Claire Durand-Ruel Snollaerts (descendant of the French art dealer<space/><link><target>Paul Durand-Ruel</target></link>). The 1,500-page, three-volume work is the most comprehensive collection of Pissarro paintings to date, and contains accompanying images of drawings and studies, as well as photographs of Pissarro and his family that had not previously been published. ISBN 88-7624-525-1</paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Camille Pissarro</arg></template><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikisource1911Enc</target><arg>Pissarro, Camille</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.shapell.org/manuscript.aspx?camille-pissarro-protests-dreyfus-affair-conviction'>Camille Pissarro Protests Alfred Dreyfus' Conviction: Original Letter</link><space/>Shapell Manuscript Foundation</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://img.groundspeak.com/waymarking/0bddb4a7-c023-40f9-8066-328e59cac492.jpg'>Photograph of Pissarro's mausoleum at Cimetire Pre Lachaise, Paris</link><space/>(<link><target>JPG</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.clarkart.edu/exhibitions/pissarro/content/exhibition.cfm'>''Pissarro's People'', exhibition held at the Sterling and Francine Clark Art Institute, Williamstown MA, June 12 October 2, 2011</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.getty.edu/vow/ULANFullDisplay?find=camille+pissarro&amp;amp;role=&amp;amp;nation=&amp;amp;prev_page=1&amp;amp;subjectid=500001924'>Union List of Artist Names, Getty Vocabularies.</link><space/>ULAN Full Record Display for Camille Pissarro. Getty Vocabulary Program, Getty Research Institute. Los Angeles, California.</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/arts/yourpaintings/artists/camille-pissarro-5403'>BBC Your Paintings: works by Camille Pissarro in public British collections</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.muma-lehavre.fr/en/exhibitions/pissarro-dans-les-ports'>Exhibition Pissarro dans les ports, 2013, Museum of modern art Andr Malraux - MuMa</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Impressionists</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Pissarro, Camille
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES">
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>Artist
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>10 July 1830
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>Charlotte Amalie, United States Virgin Islands (St. Thomas)
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>13 November 1903
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>Paris, France
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Pissarro, Camille</target></template><link><target>Category:Camille Pissarro</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Pissarro family</target></link><link><target>Category:1830 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1903 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:People from Saint Thomas, U.S. Virgin Islands</target></link><link><target>Category:19th-century French painters</target></link><link><target>Category:Danish Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Danish painters</target></link><link><target>Category:French expatriates in England</target></link><link><target>Category:French Impressionist painters</target></link><link><target>Category:French Jews</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish painters</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish artists</target></link><link><target>Category:Alumni of the cole des Beaux-Arts</target></link><link><target>Category:People of the Paris Commune</target></link><link><target>Category:School of Paris</target></link><link><target>Category:Jewish School of Paris</target></link><link><target>Category:Burials at Pre Lachaise Cemetery</target></link><link><target>Category:French people of Portuguese-Jewish descent</target></link><link><target>Category:French people of Creole descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Danish people of French descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Danish people of Portuguese descent</target></link><link><target>Category:Danish people of Jewish descent</target></link></paragraph></article>