<article title='Ahmed_II'><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><template><target>Infobox royalty</target><arg name="name"><space/>Ahmed II
</arg><arg name="title"><space/>[[Ottoman Caliphate|Caliph of Islam]]<br/>[[Amir al-Mu'minin]]<br/>[[Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]<br/>[[Custodian of the Two Holy Mosques]]
</arg><arg name="titletext"><space/>
</arg><arg name="more"><space/>
</arg><arg name="type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Ahmed II by John Young.jpg
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>
</arg><arg name="moretext"><space/>
</arg><arg name="reign"><space/>{{nowrap|22 June 1691 – 6 February 1695}}
</arg><arg name="reign-type"><space/>Reign
</arg><arg name="coronation"><space/>
</arg><arg name="cor-type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="predecessor"><space/>[[Suleiman II]]
</arg><arg name="pre-type"><space/>Predecessor
</arg><arg name="regent"><space/>
</arg><arg name="reg-type"><space/>
</arg><arg name="successor"><space/>[[Mustafa II]]
</arg><arg name="suc-type"><space/>Successor
</arg><arg name="succession"><space/>[[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]
</arg><arg name="spouse"><space/>[[Rabia Sultan]]
</arg><arg name="spouse-type"><space/>Consort
</arg><arg name="consort"><space/>yes
</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>
</arg><arg name="full name"><space/>
</arg><arg name="house"><space/>[[House of Osman]]
</arg><arg name="house-type"><space/>Royal house
</arg><arg name="father"><space/>[[Ibrahim of the Ottoman Empire|Ibrahim]]
</arg><arg name="mother"><space/>[[Hatice Muazzez Sultan]]
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="burial_date"><space/>
</arg><arg name="burial_place"><space/>
</arg><arg name="religion"><space/>[[Sunni Islam]]
</arg><arg name="signature_type"><space/>[[Tughra]]
</arg><arg name="signature"><space/>Tughra of Ahmed II.JPG
</arg></template><bold>Ahmed II</bold><space/>(<link><target>Ottoman Turkish language</target><part>Ottoman Turkish</part></link>:<space/><italics>Amed-i<space/><xhtml:u>s</xhtml:u>n</italics>)<space/><xhtml:span dir="ltr">(February 25, 1643 February 6, 1695)</xhtml:span><space/>was the<space/><link><target>Sultan</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Ottoman Empire</target></link><space/>from 1691 to 1695. Ahmed II was born at<space/><link><target>Topkap Palace</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Constantinople</target></link>, the son of Sultan<space/><link><target>Ibrahim of the Ottoman Empire</target><part>Ibrahim</part></link><space/>(1640&amp;ndash;48) by<space/><link><target>Valide Sultan</target></link><space/><link><target>Hatice Muazzez</target></link>, and succeeded his brother<space/><link><target>Suleiman II</target></link><space/>(1687&amp;ndash;91) in 1691.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Reign</heading><paragraph>During his short reign, Sultan Ahmed II devoted most of his attention to the wars against the Habsburgs and related foreign policy, governmental and economic issues. Of these, the most important were the tax reforms and the introduction of the lifelong tax farm system (malikane) (see tax farming). Ahmeds reign witnessed major military defeats against the Austrian Habsburgs in the long Hungarian war of 168399, several devastating fires in Istanbul, and the emergence of ayan, or local magnates, which further weakened the central governments hold over the provinces.</paragraph><paragraph>Among the most important features of Ahmeds reign was his reliance on Kprlzade Fazl Mustafa Pasha. Following his accession to the throne, Sultan Ahmed II confirmed Kprlzade Fazl Mustafa Pasha in his office as grand vizier. In office from 1689, Fazl Mustafa Pasha was from the famous Kprl family of grand viziers, and like most of his Kprl predecessors in the same office, was an able administrator and military commander. Like his father Kprl Mehmed Pasha (grand vizier 165661) before him, he ordered the removal and execution of dozens of corrupt state officials of the previous regime and replaced them with men loyal to himself. He overhauled the tax system by adjusting it to the capabilities of the taxpayers affected by the latest wars. He also reformed troop mobilization and increased the pool of conscripts available for the army by drafting tribesmen in the Balkans and Anatolia. In October 1690 he recaptured Belgrade (northern Serbia), a key fortress that commanded the confluence of the rivers Danube and Sava; in Ottoman hands since 1521, the fortress had been conquered by the Habsburgs in 1688.</paragraph><paragraph>Fazl Mustafa Pashas victory at Belgrade was a major military achievement that gave the Ottomans hope that the military debacles of the 1680swhich had led to the loss of Hungary and Transylvania, an Ottoman vassal principality ruled by pro-Istanbul Hungarian princes could be reversed. However, Ottoman success proved ephemeral. On August 19, 1691, Fazl Mustafa Pasha suffered a devastating defeat at Slankamen (northwest of Belgrade) at the hands of Ludwig Wilhelm von Baden, the Habsburg commander in chief in Hungary, fittingly nicknamed Trkenlouis (Louis the Turk) for his splendid victories against the Ottomans. In the confrontation, recognized by contemporaries as the bloodiest battle of the century, the Ottomans suffered heavy losses: 20,000 men, including the grand vizier. With him, the sultan lost his most capable military commander and the last member of the Kprl family, who for the previous half century had been instrumental in strengthening the Ottoman military.</paragraph><paragraph>Under Fazl Mustafa Pashas successors, the Ottomans suffered further defeats. In June 1692 the Habsburgs conquered Vrad (Oradea, Romania), the seat of an Ottoman governor (beylerbeyi) since 1660. Although the best Habsburg forces were elsewhere, fighting French invaders along the German Rhinepart of the Holy Roman Empire, ruled by the Austrian Habsburgsthe Ottomans were unable to regain their Hungarian possessions. In 1694 they tried to recapture Vrad, but to no avail. On January 12, 1695, they gave up the fortress of Gyula, the center of an Ottoman sancak or subprovince since 1566. With the fall of Gyula, the only territory still in Ottoman hands in Hungary was to the east of the River Tisza and to the south of the river Maros, with its center at Temesvr. Three weeks later, on February 6, 1695, Ahmed II died in<space/><link><target>Edirne Palace</target></link>, worn out by disease and sorrow.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Marriages and issue</heading><paragraph>He married<space/><link><target>Rabia Sultan</target></link><space/>and had two sons and two daughters:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>ehzade Ibrahim<space/></listitem><listitem>ehzade Selim<space/></listitem><listitem>Asiye Sultan</listitem><listitem>Atike Sultan</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Caroline Finkel, Osmans Dream: The Story of the Ottoman Empire, 13001923 (London: John Murray, 2005), 31215</listitem><listitem>Michael Hochendlinger, Austrias Wars of Emergence: War, State and Society in the Habsburg Monarchy, 16831797 (London: Longman, 2003), 15764.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commonscat-inline</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource author-inline</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>s-start</target></template><template><target>s-hou</target><arg>[[Ottoman Dynasty|House of Osman]]</arg><arg></arg><arg>February 25, 1643</arg><arg></arg><arg>February 6, 1695</arg></template><template><target>s-reg</target><arg></arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Suleiman II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of sultans of the Ottoman Empire|Sultan of the Ottoman Empire]]</arg><arg name="years">Jun 22, 1691 – Feb 6, 1695</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Mustafa II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-rel</target><arg>su</arg></template><template><target>s-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Suleiman II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-ttl</target><arg name="title">[[List of caliphs|Caliph of Islam]]</arg><arg name="years">Jun 22, 1691 – Feb 6, 1695</arg></template><template><target>s-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Mustafa II]]</arg></template><template><target>s-end</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Sultans of the Ottoman Empire</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:1643 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1695 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Ottoman people of the Great Turkish War</target></link><link><target>Category:17th-century Ottoman sultans</target></link><link><target>Category:Ottoman Turks</target></link></paragraph></article>