<article title='Cosmic_censorship_hypothesis'><paragraph>The weak and the strong<space/><bold>cosmic censorship hypotheses</bold><space/>are two mathematical conjectures about the structure of<space/><link><target>gravitational singularity</target><part>singularities</part></link><space/>arising in<space/><link><target>general relativity</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Singularities that arise in the<space/><link><target>Solutions of the Einstein field equations</target><part>solutions</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Einstein's field equation</target><part>Einstein's equations</part></link><space/>are typically hidden within<space/><link><target>event horizon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and therefore cannot be seen from the rest of<space/><link><target>spacetime</target></link>. Singularities that are not so hidden are called<space/><italics><link><target>naked singularity</target><part>naked</part></link></italics>. The<space/><bold>weak cosmic censorship hypothesis</bold><space/>was conceived by<space/><link><target>Roger Penrose</target></link><space/>in 1969 and posits that no naked singularities, other than the<space/><link><target>Big Bang</target></link><space/>singularity, exist in the<space/><link><target>universe</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Basics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Roger Penrose-6Nov2005.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Roger Penrose first formulated the cosmic censorship hypothesis in 1969.</part></link>Since the physical behavior of singularities is unknown, if singularities can be observed from the rest of spacetime,<space/><link><target>causality</target></link><space/>may break down, and<space/><link><target>physics</target></link><space/>may lose its predictive power. The issue cannot be avoided, since according to the<space/><link><target>Penrose-Hawking singularity theorems</target></link>, singularities are inevitable in physically reasonable situations. Still, in the absence of naked singularities, the universe is<space/><link><target>determinism</target><part>deterministic</part></link><space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2013</arg></template><space/>&amp;mdash;it is possible to predict the entire evolution of the universe (possibly excluding some finite regions of space hidden inside event horizons of singularities), knowing only its condition at a certain moment of time (more precisely, everywhere on a<space/><link><target>spacelike</target></link><space/>three-dimensional hypersurface, called the<space/><link><target>Cauchy surface</target></link>). Failure of the cosmic censorship hypothesis leads to the failure of determinism, because it is yet impossible to predict the behavior of spacetime in the causal future of a singularity. Cosmic censorship is not merely a problem of formal interest; some form of it is assumed whenever<space/><link><target>black hole</target></link><space/>event horizons are mentioned.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The hypothesis was first formulated by<space/><link><target>Roger Penrose</target></link><space/>in 1969, and it is not stated in a completely formal way. In a sense it is more of a research program proposal: part of the research is to find a proper formal statement that is physically reasonable and that can be proved to be true or false (and that is sufficiently general to be interesting).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.theory.caltech.edu/people/preskill/nyt_bet_story.html'>A Bet on a Cosmic Scale, And a Concession, Sort Of (New York Times, February 12, 1997)</link></extension><space/>Because the statement is not a strictly formal one, there is sufficient latitude for (at least) two independent formulations, a weak form, and a strong form.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Weak and strong cosmic censorship hypothesis</heading><paragraph>The weak and the strong cosmic censorship hypothesis are two conjectures concerned with the global geometry of spacetimes.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold>weak cosmic censorship hypothesis</bold><space/>asserts there can be no singularity visible from<space/><link><target>future null infinity</target></link>. In other words, singularities need to be hidden from an observer at infinity by the event horizon of a<space/><link><target>black hole</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>Mathematically, the conjecture states that, for generic initial data, the maximal Cauchy development possesses a complete future null infinity.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><bold>strong cosmic censorship hypothesis</bold><space/>asserts that, generically, general relativity is a deterministic theory, in the same sense that classical mechanics is a deterministic theory. In other words, the classical fate of all observers should be predictable from the initial data. Mathematically, the conjecture states that the maximal Cauchy development of generic compact or asymptotically flat initial data is locally inextendible as a regular<space/><link><target>Lorentzian manifold</target></link>.</listitem></list><paragraph>The two conjectures are mathematically independent, as there exist spacetimes for which the weak cosmic censorship is valid but the strong cosmic censorship is violated and, conversely, there exist spacetimes for which the weak cosmic censorship is violated but the strong cosmic censorship is valid.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Example</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Kerr Metric</target></link>, corresponding to a black hole of mass<space/><extension extension_name='math'>M</extension><space/>and angular momentum<space/><extension extension_name='math'>J</extension>, can be used to derive the<space/><link><target>effective potential</target></link><space/>for particle<space/><link><target>orbits</target></link><space/>restricted to the equator (as defined by rotation). This potential looks like:<extension extension_name='ref' name="hartle_gravity">James B Hartle,<space/><italics>Gravity</italics><space/>in chapter 15: Rotating Black Holes. (2003. ISBN 0-8053-8662-9)</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>V_{\rm{eff}}(r,e,l)=-\frac{M}{r}+\frac{l^2-a^2(e^2-1)}{2r^2}-\frac{M(l-a e)^2}{r^3},~~~
a\equiv \frac{J}{M}<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>r</extension><space/>is the coordinate radius,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>e</extension><space/>and<space/><extension extension_name='math'>l</extension><space/>are the test-particle's conserved energy and angular momentum respectively (constructed from the<space/><link><target>killing vectors</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>To preserve<space/><italics>cosmic censorship</italics>, the black hole is restricted to the case of &lt;math&gt;a &lt; 1&lt;/math&gt;. For there to exist an<space/><link><target>event horizon</target></link><space/>around the singularity, the requirement: &lt;math&gt;a &lt; 1&lt;/math&gt; must be satisfied:.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hartle_gravity"></extension><space/>This amounts to the<space/><link><target>angular momentum</target></link><space/>of the black hole being constrained to below a critical value, outside of which the horizon would disappear.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The following thought experiment is reproduced from Hartle's<space/><italics>Gravity</italics>:</paragraph><paragraph>Imagine specifically trying to violate the censorship conjecture. This could be done by somehow imparting an angular momentum upon the black hole, making it exceed the critical value (assume it starts infinitesimally below it). This could be done by sending a particle of angular momentum<space/><extension extension_name='math'>l = 2Me</extension>. Because this particle has angular momentum, it can only be captured by the black hole if the maximum potential of the black hole is less than<space/><extension extension_name='math'>(e^2-1)/2</extension>.</paragraph><paragraph>Solving the above effective potential equation for the maximum under the given conditions results in a maximum potential of exactly<space/><extension extension_name='math'>(e^2-1)/2</extension>! Testing other values shows that no particle with enough angular momentum to violate the censorship conjecture would be able to enter the black hole,<space/><bold>because</bold><space/>they have too much angular momentum to fall in.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Problems with the concept</heading><paragraph>There are a number of difficulties in formalizing the hypothesis:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>There are technical difficulties with properly formalizing the notion of a singularity.</listitem><listitem>It is not difficult to construct spacetimes which have naked singularities, but which are not &quot;physically reasonable;&quot; the canonical example of such a spacetime is perhaps the &quot;superextremal&quot; &lt;math&gt;M&lt;|Q|&lt;/math&gt;<space/><link><target>Reissner-Nordstrm</target></link><space/>solution, which contains a singularity at<space/><extension extension_name='math'>r=0</extension><space/>that is not surrounded by a horizon. A formal statement needs some set of hypotheses which exclude these situations.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Caustic (mathematics)</target><part>Caustic</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>may occur in simple models of<space/><link><target>gravitational collapse</target></link>, and can appear to lead to singularities. These have more to do with the simplified models of bulk matter used, and in any case have nothing to do with general relativity, and need to be excluded.</listitem><listitem>Computer models of gravitational collapse have shown that naked singularities can arise, but these models rely on very special circumstances (such as spherical symmetry). These special circumstances need to be excluded by some hypothesis.</listitem></list><paragraph>In 1991,<space/><link><target>John Preskill</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kip Thorne</target></link><space/><link><target>scientific wager</target><part>bet against</part></link><space/><link><target>Stephen Hawking</target></link><space/>that the hypothesis was false. Hawking conceded the bet in 1997, due to the discovery of the special situations just mentioned, which he characterized as &quot;technicalities&quot;. Hawking later reformulated the bet to exclude those technicalities. The revised bet is still open, the prize being &quot;clothing to cover the winner's nakedness&quot;.<link type='external' href='http://www.theory.caltech.edu/people/preskill/new_naked_bet.html'></link>(see also<space/><link><target>ThorneHawkingPreskill bet</target></link>.)</paragraph><heading level='2'>Counter-example</heading><paragraph>An exact solution to the scalar-Einstein equations<space/><extension extension_name='math'>R_{ab}=2\phi_a\phi_b</extension><space/>which forms a counter example to many formulations of the cosmic censorship hypothesis was found by Mark D. Roberts in 1985:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>ds^2=-(1+2\sigma)dv^2+2dv\,dr+r(r-2\sigma v)\left(d\theta^2 + \sin^2 \theta \,d\phi^2\right),\quad
\phi = \frac{1}{2} \ln\left(1 - \frac{2\sigma v}{r}\right),</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\sigma</extension><space/>is a constant.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Black hole information paradox</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Chronology protection conjecture</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Earman, John:<space/><italics>Bangs, Crunches, Whimpers, and Shrieks: Singularities and Acausalities in Relativistic Spacetimes</italics><space/>(1995), see especially chapter 2 (ISBN 0-19-509591-X)</listitem><listitem>Roberts, Mark D. : ''Scalar Field Counter-Examples to the Cosmic Censorship Hypothesis. Gen.Rel.Grav.21(1989)907-939.</listitem><listitem>Penrose, Roger: &quot;The Question of Cosmic Censorship&quot;, Chapter 5 in<space/><italics>Black Holes and Relativistic Stars</italics>, Robert Wald (editor), (1994) (ISBN 0-226-87034-0)</listitem><listitem>Penrose, Roger: &quot;Singularities and time-asymmetry&quot;, Chapter 12 in<space/><italics>General Relativity: An Einstein Centenary Survey</italics><space/>(Hawking and Israel, editors), (1979), see especially section 12.3.2, pp.&amp;nbsp;617629 (ISBN 0-521-22285-0)</listitem><listitem>Shapiro, S. L., and Teukolsky, S. A.: &quot;Formation of Naked Singularities: The Violation of Cosmic Censorship&quot;, Physical Review Letters<space/><bold>66</bold>, 994-997 (1991)</listitem><listitem>Wald, Robert,<space/><italics>General Relativity</italics>, 299-308 (1984) (ISBN 0-226-87033-2)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theory.caltech.edu/people/preskill/old_naked_bet.html'>The old bet</link><space/>(conceded in 1997)</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.theory.caltech.edu/people/preskill/new_naked_bet.html'>The new bet</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>black holes</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Cosmic Censorship Hypothesis</target></template><link><target>Category:Black holes</target></link><link><target>Category:General relativity</target></link></paragraph></article>