<article title='Ambush'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target><arg>Ambush (disambiguation)</arg></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">August 2007</arg></template><link><target>File:Polish ambush.PNG</target><part>thumb</part><part>Ambush of Polish partisans during<space/><link><target>January Uprising</target></link></part></link>An<space/><bold>ambush</bold><space/>is a long-established<space/><link><target>military tactics</target><part>military tactic</part></link>, in which<space/><link><target>combatants</target></link><space/>take advantage of concealment and the<space/><link><target>element of surprise</target></link><space/>to attack unsuspecting enemy combatants from concealed positions, such as among dense<space/><link><target>underbrush</target></link><space/>or behind<space/><link><target>hill</target><trail>tops</trail></link>. Ambushes have been used consistently throughout history, from<space/><link><target>ancient warfare</target><part>ancient</part></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>modern warfare</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The use by early humans of the ambush may date as far back as two million years when anthropologists have recently suggested that ambush techniques were used to hunt large game.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bunn</arg><arg name="first">Henry T.</arg><arg name="author2">Alia N. Gurtov</arg><arg name="title">Prey Mortality Profiles Indicate That Early Pleistocene Homo at Olduvai Was an Ambush Predator.</arg><arg name="journal">Quaternary International</arg><arg name="date">February 16, 2014</arg><arg name="volume">322–323</arg><arg name="pages">44–53</arg><arg name="accessdate">26 March 2014</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>More recently, an ambush often might involve thousands of soldiers on a large scale, such as over a<space/><link><target>mountain pass</target></link>. Ambushes appear many times in military history. One outstanding example from ancient times is the<space/><link><target>Battle of the Trebia</target></link><space/>river. Hannibal encamped within striking distance of the Romans with the Trebia River between them, and placed a strong force of cavalry and infantry in concealment, near the battle zone. He had noticed, says Polybius, a<space/><italics>&quot;place between the two camps, flat indeed and treeless, but well adapted for an ambuscade, as it was traversed by a water-course with steep banks, densely overgrown with brambles and other thorny plants, and here he proposed to lay a stratagem to surprise the enemy&quot;</italics>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>When the Roman infantry became entangled in combat with his army, the hidden ambush force attacked the legionnaires in the rear. The result was slaughter and defeat for the Romans. Nevertheless, the battle also displays the effects of good tactical discipline on the part of the ambushed force. Although most of the legions were lost, about 10,000 Romans cut their way through to safety, maintaining<space/><link><target>unit cohesion</target></link>. This ability to maintain discipline and break out or maneuver away from a<space/><link><target>kill zone</target></link><space/>is a hallmark of good troops and training in any ambush situation. See Ranger reference below.</paragraph><paragraph>Another famous ambush was that sprung by Germanic warchief<space/><link><target>Arminius</target></link><space/>against the Romans at<space/><link><target>Battle of the Teutoburg Forest</target></link>. This particular ambush was to have an impact on the course of Western history. The Germanic forces demonstrated several principles needed for a successful ambush. They took cover in difficult forested terrain, allowing the warriors time and space to mass without detection. They had the element of surprise, and this was also aided by the defection of Arminius from Roman ranks prior to the battle. They sprang the attack when the Romans were most vulnerable; when they had left their fortified camp, and were on the march in a pounding rainstorm.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The Germans did not dawdle at the hour of decision but attacked quickly, using a massive series of short, rapid, vicious charges against the length of the whole Roman line, with charging units sometimes withdrawing to the forest to regroup while others took their place. The Germans also made use of blocking obstacles, erecting a trench and earthen wall to hinder Roman movement along the route of the killing zone. The result was mass slaughter of the Romans, and the destruction of 3 legions. The Germanic victory caused a limit on Roman expansion in the West. Ultimately, it established the Rhine as the boundary of the Roman Empire for the next four hundred years, until the decline of the Roman influence in the West. The Roman Empire made no further concerted attempts to conquer Germania beyond the Rhine.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Arabia during Muhammad's era</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>List of battles of Muhammad</arg></template>According to Muslim tradition Islamic Prophet Muhammad made use of ambush tactics in his military campaigns. His first such use was during the<space/><link><target>Caravan raids</target></link>, in the Kharrar caravan raid Sa`d ibn Abi Waqqas was ordered to lead a raid against the<space/><link><target>Quraysh tribe</target><part>Quraysh</part></link>. His group consisted of about twenty Muhajirs. This raid was done about a month after the previous. Sa'd, with his soldiers, set up an ambush in the valley of<space/><link><target>Kharrar</target></link><space/>on the road to Mecca and waited to raid a returning Meccan caravan from Syria. But the caravan had already passed and the Muslims returned to Medina without any loot.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Mubarakpuri, The Sealed Nectar p. 127">Mubarakpuri, The Sealed Nectar (Free Version), p. 127.</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Haykal 1976"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">The Life of Muhammad<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="first">Husayn<space/></arg><arg name="last">Haykal</arg><arg name="year">1976</arg><arg name="publisher">Islamic Book Trust<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-983-9154-17-7</arg><arg name="pages">217–218</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Arab tribes during Muhammad's era also made use of ambush tactics.<template><target>fact</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template><space/>One example retold in Muslim tradtion is said to have taken place during the<space/><link><target>First Raid on Banu Thalabah</target></link>. The Banu Thalabah tribe were already aware of the impending attack; so they lay in wait for the Muslims, and when Muhammad ibn Maslama arrived at the site.The Banu Thalabah, with 100 men ambushed them, while the Muslims were making preparation to sleep; and after a brief resistance killed all of Muhammad ibn Maslamas men. Muhammad ibn Maslama pretended to be dead. A Muslim who happened to pass that way found him and assisted him to return to<space/><link><target>Medina</target></link>. The raid was unsuccessful.<extension extension_name='ref' name="mubarakpuri"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">The Sealed Nectar</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.co.uk/books?id</arg><arg name="first">Saifur Rahman Al</arg><arg name="last">Mubarakpuri</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Darussalam Publications</arg><arg name="page">205</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Procedure</heading><paragraph>In modern warfare, an ambush is most often employed by ground troops up to<space/><link><target>platoon</target></link><space/>size against enemy targets, which may be other ground troops, or possibly vehicles. However, in some situations, especially when deep behind enemy lines, the actual attack will be carried out by a platoon, a<space/><link><target>Company (military unit)</target><part>company</part></link>-sized unit will be deployed to support the attack group, setting up and maintaining a forward patrol harbour from which the attacking force will deploy, and to which they will retire after the attack.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Planning</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Ambush.gif</target><part>thumb</part><part>US Army idealised linear ambush plan</part></link><link><target>File:Ambush_L_shaped.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>US Army idealised L-shaped ambush plan</part></link>Ambushes are complex, multi-phase operations, and are, therefore, usually planned in some detail. First, a suitable killing zone is identified. This is the place where the ambush will be laid. It is generally a place where enemy units are expected to pass, and which gives reasonable cover for the deployment, execution, and extraction phases of the ambush patrol. A path along a wooded valley floor would be a typical example.</paragraph><paragraph>Ambush can be described geometrically as:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><bold>Linear</bold>, when a number of firing units are equally distant from the linear<space/><link><target>kill zone</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><bold>L-shaped</bold>, when a short leg of firing units are placed to<space/><link><target>enfilade</target></link><space/>(fire the length of) the sides of the linear kill zone.</listitem><listitem><bold>V-shaped</bold>, when the firing units are distant from the kill zone at the end where the enemy enters, so the firing units lay down bands of intersecting and interlocking fire. This ambush is normally triggered only when the enemy is well into the kill zone. The intersecting bands of fire prevent any attempt of moving out of the kill zone.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.globalsecurity.org/military/library/policy/army/fm/7-85/ch6.htm'>FM 7-85 Chapter 6 Special Light Infantry Operations</link></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Viet Cong ambush techniques</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:vchelicopterfight2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The VC/NVA prepared the battlefield carefully. Siting automatic weapons at treetop level for example helped shoot down several US helicopters during the Battle of Dak To, 1967<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>Terrence Maitland, A CONTAGION OF WAR: THE VIETNAM EXPERIENCE SERIES, (Boston Publishing Company), 1983, p. 180</extension></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Ambush criteria:</bold><space/>The terrain for the ambush had to meet strict criteria:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>provide concealment to prevent detection from the ground or air</listitem><listitem>enable ambush force to deploy, encircle and divide the enemy</listitem><listitem>allow for heavy weapons emplacements to provide sustained fire</listitem><listitem>enable the ambush force to set up observation posts for early detection of the enemy</listitem><listitem>permit the secret movement of troops to the ambush position and the dispersal of troops during withdrawal</listitem></list><paragraph>One important feature of the ambush was that the target units should 'pile up' after being attacked, thus preventing them any easy means of withdrawal from the<space/><link><target>kill zone</target></link><space/>and hindering their use of heavy weapons and supporting fires. Terrain was usually selected which would facilitate this and slow down the enemy. The terrain around the ambush site which was not favorable to the ambushing force, or which offered some protection to the target, was heavily mined and booby trapped or pre-registered for mortars.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Ambush units:</bold><space/>The NVA/VC ambush formations consisted of:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>lead-blocking element</listitem><listitem>main-assault element</listitem><listitem>rear-blocking element</listitem><listitem>observation posts</listitem><listitem>command post</listitem></list><paragraph>Other elements might also be included if the situation demanded, such as a sniper screen along a nearby avenue of approach to delay enemy reinforcement.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Command posts:</bold><space/>When deploying into an ambush site, the NVA first occupied several observation posts, placed to detect the enemy as early as possible and to report on the formation it was using, its strength and firepower, as well as to provide early warning to the unit commander. Usually one main OP and several secondary OP's were established. Runners and occasionally radios were used to communicate between the OP's and the main command post. The OP's were located so that they could observe enemy movement into the ambush and often they would remain in position throughout the ambush in order to report routes of reinforcement and withdrawal by the enemy as well as his maneuver options. Frequently the OP's were reinforced to squad size and served as flank security. The command post was situated in a central location, often on terrain which afforded it a vantage point overlooking the ambush site.</paragraph><paragraph><bold>Recon methods:</bold><space/>Recon elements observing a potential ambush target on the move generally stayed 300500 meters away. Sometimes a &quot;leapfrogging&quot; recon technique was used. Surveillance units were echeloned one behind the other. As the enemy drew close to the first, it fell back behind the last recon team, leaving an advance group in its place. This one in turn fell back as the enemy again closed the gap, and the cycle rotated. This method helped keep the enemy under continuous observation from a variety of vantage points, and allowed the recon groups to cover one another.<extension extension_name='ref' name="RAND Corp">RAND Corp, &quot;Insurgent Organization and Operations: A Case Study of the Viet Cong in the Delta, 19641966,&quot; (Santa Monica: August 1967)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ambush predator</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Viet Cong and PAVN battle tactics#Offensive tactics</target><part>Viet Cong and PAVN battle tactics</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Flanking maneuver</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Flypaper theory (strategy)</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of military tactics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Sniper</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.angelfire.com/art/enchanter/herbert.html'>Extract from Lt Col Anthony B. Herbert's Soldiers handbook</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.scribd.com/doc/100897/ebook-US-Army-Ranger-Handbook'>US Army Ranger Handbook</link><space/>section 5-14 for ambushes and 6-11 for reaction to ambushes</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Ambush</target></template><link><target>Category:Assault tactics</target></link><link><target>Category:Military tactics</target></link><link><target>Category:Guerrilla warfare tactics</target></link></paragraph></article>