<article title='Geography_of_Egypt'><paragraph><template><target>Location map+</target><arg>Egypt<space/></arg><arg name="width">300<space/></arg><arg name="float">right<space/></arg><arg name="caption">Map of Egypt<space/></arg><arg name="places">
{{Location map~ |Egypt |lat</arg></template><link><target>File:LocationEgypt.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Location of Egypt</part></link><template><target>MapLibrary</target><arg>Egypt_sat.png</arg><arg>Egypt</arg></template><template><target>Coord</target><arg>27</arg><arg>00</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>30</arg><arg>00</arg><arg>E</arg><arg>type:country</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template>The<space/><bold>geography of Egypt</bold><space/>relates to two regions: North Africa and Southwest Asia.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Egypt</target></link><space/>has coastlines on both the<space/><link><target>Mediterranean Sea</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Red Sea</target></link>. The country borders<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>to the west, the<space/><link><target>Gaza Strip</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link><space/>to the east, and<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>to the<space/><link><target>south</target></link>. Covering 1,001,449&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup><space/>(386,662&amp;nbsp;mi<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>), Egypt has a land area about the same as that of<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>New Mexico</target></link><space/>combined, four times bigger than that of the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>, twice as big as that of<space/><link><target>France</target></link>, and three times bigger than Germany.</paragraph><paragraph>The longest straight-line distance in Egypt from north to south is 1,024&amp;nbsp;km (636&amp;nbsp;mi), while that from east to west measures 1,240&amp;nbsp;km (771&amp;nbsp;mi). More than 2,900&amp;nbsp;km (1800&amp;nbsp;mi) of coastline on the Mediterranean Sea, the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Suez</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Aqaba</target></link>, and the Red Sea constitute Egypt's<space/><link><target>maritime boundaries</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Governorates</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Governorates of Egypt</arg></template>Egypt is divided into 27<space/><link><target>governorate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>, which include two city-governorates:<space/><link><target>Alexandria</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Alexandria Governorate</target></link>) and<space/><link><target>Cairo</target></link><space/>(<link><target>Cairo Governorate</target></link>). There are nine governorates of<space/><link><target>Lower Egypt</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Nile Delta</target></link><space/>region,tes of<space/><link><target>Upper Egypt</target></link><space/>along the<space/><link><target>Nile</target></link><space/>river south from Cairo to<space/><link><target>Aswan</target></link><space/>and five frontier governorates covering Sinai and the deserts that lie west and east of the Nile river.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Natural regions</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Egypt Topography.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>Topography of Egypt</part><trail>Egypt</trail></link><space/>is predominantly<space/><link><target>desert</target></link>. Only 35,000&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup><space/>- 3.5% - of the total land area is<space/><link><target>Agriculture</target><part>cultivate</part><trail>d</trail></link><space/>and permanently settled. Most of the country lies within the wide band of desert that stretches eastwards from Africa's<space/><link><target>Atlantic Ocean</target><part>Atlantic Coast</part></link><space/>across the<space/><link><target>continent</target></link><space/>and into southwest Asia.</paragraph><paragraph>Egypt's<space/><link><target>geological</target></link><space/>history has produced four major<space/><link><target>physical regions</target></link>:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Nile</target></link><space/>Valley and<space/><link><target>Nile Delta</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Western Desert (North Africa)</target><part>Western Desert</part></link><space/>(also known as the<space/><link><target>Libyan Desert</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Eastern Desert</target></link><space/>(extends from the Nile Valley all the way to the<space/><link><target>Red Sea</target></link><space/>coast)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sinai Peninsula</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Despite covering only about 5.5% of the total area of Egypt, the<space/><link><target>Nile Valley</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Nile Delta</target></link><space/>are the most important regions, being the country's only cultivable regions and supporting about 99% of the population. The Nile valley extends approximately 800&amp;nbsp;km from Aswan to the outskirts of Cairo. The Nile Valley is very cool and known as<space/><link><target>Upper Egypt</target></link>, while the Nile Delta region is known as<space/><link><target>Lower Egypt</target></link>. Steep rocky cliffs rise along the banks of the Nile in some stretches, while other areas along the Nile are flat, with space for agricultural production. In the past, flooding of the Nile during the summer provided silt and water to make agriculture possible on land that is otherwise very dry. Since construction of the<space/><link><target>Aswan Dam</target></link>, agriculture in the Nile valley depends on<space/><link><target>irrigation</target></link>. The Nile delta consists of flat, low-lying areas. Some parts of the delta are marshy and water-logged, and thus not suitable for agriculture. Other areas of the delta are used for agriculture.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Pyramid Builders of Ancient Egypt: A Modern Investigation of Pharaoh's Workforce<space/></arg><arg name="author">Rosalie, David<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Routledge<space/></arg><arg name="year">1997<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">The Geography and Historical Background<space/></arg><arg name="pages">14</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Nile Valley and Delta</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Nile composite NASA.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Nile delta, and the entire course of the Nile</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Nile</arg><arg>Nile Delta</arg></template>The Nile Valley and Delta, the most extensive<space/><link><target>oasis</target></link><space/>on earth, was created by the world's longest river and its seemingly inexhaustible sources. Without the<space/><link><target>topographic</target></link><space/><link><target>Stream channel</target><part>channel</part></link><space/>that permits the Nile to flow across the<space/><link><target>Sahara</target></link>, Egypt would be entirely desert. The length within Egypt of the River Nile in its northwards course from three central African sources the<space/><link><target>White Nile</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Blue Nile</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Atbara</target></link><space/>totals some 1,600&amp;nbsp;km.</paragraph><paragraph>The White Nile, which begins at<space/><link><target>Lake Victoria</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Uganda</target></link>, supplies about 28% of the Nile's Egyptian waters. In its course from Lake Victoria to<space/><link><target>Juba</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>South Sudan</target></link>, the White Nile's channel drops more than 600 m. In its 1,600-km course from Juba to<space/><link><target>Khartoum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link>'s capital, the river descends just 75 m. In South Sudan, the White Nile passes through the<space/><link><target>Sudd</target></link>, a wide, flat plain covered with<space/><link><target>swamp</target></link><space/><link><target>vegetation</target></link><space/>and slows almost to the point of<space/><link><target>Water stagnation</target><part>stagnation</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Blue Nile, which originates at<space/><link><target>Lake Tana</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Ethiopia</target></link>, provides on average some 58% of the Nile's Egyptian waters. This river has a steeper gradient and therefore flows more swiftly than the White Nile, which it joins at Khartoum. Unlike the White Nile, the Blue Nile carries a considerable amount of<space/><link><target>sediment</target></link>. For several kilometres north of Khartoum, water closer to the eastern bank of the river, coming from the Blue Nile, is visibly<space/><link><target>mud</target><trail>dy</trail></link>, while that closer to the western bank, and coming from the White Nile, is clearer.</paragraph><paragraph>The much shorter Atbara River, which also originates in Ethiopia, joins the main Nile north of Khartoum between the fifth and sixth<space/><link><target>Cataracts of the Nile</target><part>cataracts</part></link><space/>(areas of steep rapids) and provides about 14% of the Nile's waters in Egypt. During the low-water season, which runs from January to June, the Atbarah shrinks to a number of pools. But, in late-summer, when torrential rains fall on the<space/><link><target>Ethiopian Highlands</target></link>, the Atbarah provides 22% of the Nile's flow.</paragraph><paragraph>The Blue Nile has a similar pattern. It contributes 17% of the Nile's waters in the low-water season and 68% during the high-water season. In contrast, the White Nile provides only 10% of the Nile's waters during the high-water season but contributes more than 80% during the low-water period. Thus, before the<space/><link><target>Aswan High Dam</target></link><space/>was completed in 1971, the White Nile watered the Egyptian stretch of the river throughout the year, whereas the Blue Nile, carrying seasonal rain from Ethiopia, caused the Nile to overflow its banks and deposit a layer of fertile mud over adjacent fields. The great flood of the main Nile usually occurred in Egypt during August, September, and October, but it sometimes began as early as June at<space/><link><target>Aswan</target></link><space/>and often did not completely wane until January.</paragraph><paragraph>The Nile enters Egypt a few kilometres north of<space/><link><target>Wadi Halfa</target></link>, a Sudanese town that was completely rebuilt on high ground when its original site was submerged in the<space/><link><target>reservoir</target></link><space/>created by the Aswan High Dam. As a result of the dam's construction, the Nile actually begins its flow into Egypt as<space/><link><target>Lake Nasser</target></link>, which extends southwards from the dam for 320&amp;nbsp;km to the border and for an additional 158&amp;nbsp;km within Sudan. Lake Nasser's waters fill the area through<space/><link><target>Lower Nubia</target></link><space/>(Upper Egypt and northern Sudan) within the narrow<space/><link><target>canyon</target></link><space/>between the<space/><link><target>cliffs</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>sandstone</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>granite</target></link><space/>created by the flow of the river over many centuries. Below Aswan the cultivated<space/><link><target>floodplain</target></link><space/>strip widens to as much as twenty km. North of Isna (160&amp;nbsp;km north of Aswan), the plateau on both sides of the valley rises to as much as 550 m above sea level; at Qina (some 90&amp;nbsp;km north of Isna) the 300-m limestone cliffs force the Nile to change course towards the southwest for about 60&amp;nbsp;km before it turns northwest for about 160&amp;nbsp;km to Asyut. Northward from Asyut, the<space/><link><target>escarpment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>on both sides diminish, and the valley widens to a maximum of 22&amp;nbsp;km.</paragraph><paragraph>At Cairo, the Nile spreads out over what was once a broad<space/><link><target>estuary</target></link>, subsequently filled by silt deposits to form what is now a fertile, fan-shaped<space/><link><target>River delta</target><part>delta</part></link><space/>some 250&amp;nbsp;km wide at its seaward extremity and extending about 160&amp;nbsp;km from north to south. The Nile Delta covers approximately 22,000&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup><space/>(roughly equivalent in area to that of<space/><link><target>Massachusetts</target></link>). According to historical accounts from the first century AD, seven branches of the Nile once ran through the delta. According to later accounts, the Nile had, by around the twelfth century, just six branches. Since then, nature and man have closed all but two main outlets: the east branch,<space/><link><target>Damietta</target></link><space/>(also seen as Dumyat; 240&amp;nbsp;km long), and the west branch,<space/><link><target>Rosetta</target></link><space/>(235&amp;nbsp;km long). Both outlets are named after the<space/><link><target>port</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>located at their respective mouths. A network of<space/><link><target>drainage</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>irrigation</target></link><space/><link><target>canals</target></link><space/>supplements these remaining outlets. In the north, near the coast, the Nile delta embraces a series of<space/><link><target>salt marshes</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>lake</target><trail>s</trail></link>, the most notable among which are<space/><link><target>Idku</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Al Burullus</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Manzilah</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The fertility and productivity of the land adjacent to the Nile depends largely on the<space/><link><target>silt</target></link><space/>deposited by floodwaters.<space/><link><target>Archaeological</target></link><space/>research indicates that people once lived at a much higher elevation along the river than they do today, probably because the river was higher or the floods more severe. The timing and the amount of annual flow were always unpredictable. Measurements of annual flows as low as 1.2 billion m<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup><space/>and as high as 4.25 billion m<xhtml:sup>3</xhtml:sup><space/>have been recorded. For centuries Egyptians attempted to predict and take advantage of these flows and thereby moderate the severity of floods.</paragraph><paragraph>The construction of<space/><link><target>dams</target></link><space/>on the Nile, particularly the Aswan High Dam, transformed the mighty river into a large and predictable<space/><link><target>irrigation</target></link><space/><link><target>ditch</target></link>. Lake Nasser, the world's largest artificial lake, has enabled planned use of the Nile regardless of the amount of rainfall in<space/><link><target>Central Africa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>East Africa</target></link>. The dams have also affected the Nile Valley's<space/><link><target>fertility</target></link>, which was dependent for centuries not only on the water brought to the<space/><link><target>arable land</target></link><space/>but also on the materials left by the water. Researchers have estimated that beneficial silt deposits in the valley began about 10,000 years ago. The average annual deposit of arable soil through the course of the river valley amounted to some nine metres. Analysis of the flow revealed that 10.7 million tons of solid matter passed Cairo each year. Today the Aswan High Dam obstructs most of this sediment, now retained in Lake Nasser. The reduction in annual silt deposits has contributed to rising water tables and increasing soil salinity in the Delta, the erosion of the river's banks in<space/><link><target>Upper Egypt</target></link>, and the erosion of the<space/><link><target>alluvial fan</target></link><space/>along the shore of the Mediterranean Sea.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Western Desert</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Libyan Desert</arg></template>The Western Desert covers an area of some 700,000&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup>, thereby accounting for around two-thirds of Egypt's total land area. This immense desert to the west of the Nile spans the area from the Mediterranean Sea southwards to the Sudanese border. The desert's<space/><link><target>Jilf al Kabir Plateau</target></link>, at a mean altitude of some 1000 m, constitutes an exception to the uninterrupted territory of basement rocks covered by layers of horizontally bedded sediments forming a massive plain or low plateau. The<space/><link><target>Great Sand Sea</target></link><space/>lies within the desert's plain and extends from the<space/><link><target>Siwa Oasis</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Jilf al Kabir</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Escarpment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(ridges) and deep depressions (basins) exist in several parts of the Western Desert, and no rivers or streams drain into or out of the area.</paragraph><paragraph>The government has considered the Western Desert a frontier region and has divided it into two governorates at about the twenty-eighth parallel:<space/><link><target>Matruh Governorate</target><part>Matruh</part></link><space/>to the north and New Valley (Al Wadi al Jadid) to the south. There are seven important depressions in the Western Desert, and all are considered oases except the largest,<space/><link><target>Qattara</target></link>, the water of which is salty. The<space/><link><target>Qattara Depression</target></link>, which includes the country's lowest point, encompasses<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>19605</arg><arg>km2</arg><arg>mi2</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>, which is similar to the size of<space/><link><target>Lake Ontario</target></link>. It is largely below sea level and is<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>133</arg><arg>m</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>below sea level at the lowest.<space/><link><target>Badlands</target></link>, salt marshes, and salt lakes cover the sparsely inhabited Qattara Depression.</paragraph><paragraph>Limited<space/><link><target>agricultural</target></link><space/>production, the presence of some natural resources, and permanent<space/><link><target>Community</target><part>settlements</part></link><space/>are found in the other six depressions, all of which have fresh water provided by the Nile or by local<space/><link><target>groundwater</target></link>. The Siwah Oasis, close to the Libyan border and west of Qattara, is isolated from the rest of Egypt but has sustained life since ancient times. The Siwa's cliff-hung Temple of Amun was renowned for its oracles for more than 1,000 years.<space/><link><target>Herodotus</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alexander the Great</target></link><space/>were among the many illustrious people who visited the temple in the pre-Christian era.</paragraph><paragraph>The other major<space/><link><target>oases</target></link><space/>form a<space/><link><target>topographic</target></link><space/>chain of<space/><link><target>Depression (geology)</target><part>basin</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>extending from the<space/><link><target>Faiyum Oasis</target></link><space/>(sometimes called the Fayyum Depression) which lies<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>60</arg><arg>km</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template><space/>southwest of<space/><link><target>Cairo</target></link>, south to the<space/><link><target>Bahariya</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Farafra</target><part>Farafirah</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Dakhla Oasis</target><part>Dakhilah</part></link><space/>oases before reaching the country's largest oasis,<space/><link><target>Kharga</target><part>Kharijah</part></link>. A brackish lake,<space/><link><target>Birket Qarun</target></link>, at the northern reaches of Al Fayyum Oasis, drained into the Nile in ancient times. For centuries sweetwater<space/><link><target>artesian wells</target></link><space/>in the Fayyum Oasis have permitted extensive<space/><link><target>Tillage</target><part>cultivation</part></link><space/>in an irrigated area that extends over<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1800</arg><arg>km2</arg><arg>mi2</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="sp">us</arg></template>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Eastern Desert</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Dust storms off Egypt.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>300px</part><part>A large plume of Saharan Desert dust (light brownish pixels) blown across Libya and Egypt northward over the Mediterranean Sea toward the Middle East, on February 2, 2003.</part></link><template><target>Main</target><arg>Eastern Desert</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The topographic features of the desert region east of the Nile differ from those to the west of the Nile. The Eastern Desert is relatively mountainous. The elevation rises abruptly from the Nile, and an downward-sloping plateau of sand gives way within 100&amp;nbsp;km to arid, defoliated, rocky hills running north and south between the Sudan border and the Delta. The hills reach elevations of more than 1,900 m. The region's most prominent feature is the easterly chain of rugged mountains, the Red Sea Hills, which extend from the Nile Valley eastward to the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Suez</target></link><space/>and the Red Sea. This elevated region has a natural drainage pattern that rarely functions because of insufficient rainfall. It also has a complex of irregular, sharply cut<space/><link><target>wadis</target></link><space/>that extend westward toward the Nile. The desert environment extends all the way to the Red Sea coast.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Sinai Peninsula</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Katharinenkloster Sinai BW 2.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Mount Catherine</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Sinai</target></link>, the country's highest point</part></link>The<space/><link><target>Sinai Peninsula</target></link><space/>is a triangular-shaped<space/><link><target>peninsula</target></link>, about 61,100&amp;nbsp;km<xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup><space/>in area (slightly smaller than the<space/><link><target>U.S. state</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>West Virginia</target></link>). Similar to the desert, the peninsula contains mountains in its southern sector that are a geological extension of the Red Sea Hills, the low range along the Red Sea coast that includes<space/><link><target>Mount Catherine</target></link><space/>(Jabal Katrinah), the country's highest point, at 2,642 m above sea-level. The Red Sea may have been named after these mountains, which are red.</paragraph><paragraph>The southern side of the peninsula has a sharp escarpment that subsides after a narrow coastal shelf that slopes into the Red Sea and the<space/><link><target>Gulf of Aqaba</target></link>. The elevation of Sinai's southern rim is about 1,000 m. Moving northward, the elevation of this<space/><link><target>limestone</target></link><space/>plateau decreases. The northern third of Sinai is a flat, sandy coastal plain, which extends from the Suez Canal into the<space/><link><target>Gaza Strip</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Israel</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Before the Israeli military occupied Sinai during the June 1967 War (Arab-Israeli war, also known as the Six-Day War), a single Egyptian governorate administered the whole peninsula. By 1982 after all of Sinai was returned to Egypt, the central government divided the peninsula into two governorates. North Sinai has its capital at Al Arish and the South Sinai has its capital in Artt Turkishy.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Urban and rural areas</heading><paragraph>In the 1970 census, 57 percent of Egypt's population was counted as rural, including those residing in agricultural areas in the Nile Valley and Delta, as well as the much smaller number of persons living in desert areas. Rural areas differ from the urban in terms of poverty, fertility rates, and other social factors. Agriculture is a key component of the economy in rural areas, though some people are employed in the tourist industry or other non-farm occupations. In 1992, the percentage of Egypt's population employed in agriculture was 33 percent. The agricultural industry is dependent on<space/><link><target>irrigation</target></link><space/>from the Nile river.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">Directions of Change in Rural Egypt<space/></arg><arg name="author">Hopkins, Nicholas and Kirsten Westergaard<space/></arg><arg name="year">1998<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">American University in Cairo<space/></arg><arg name="pages">2–4</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Extreme points</heading><paragraph>This is a list of the extreme points of<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>, the points that are farther north, south, east or west than any other location.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Northernmost point unnamed headland immediately north-west of<space/><link><target>Sidi Barrani</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Matruh Governorate</target></link></listitem><listitem>Easternmost point<space/><link><target>Ras Hadarba</target></link><space/>(Cape Elba),<space/><link><target>Red Sea Governorate</target></link>*</listitem><listitem>Southernmost point -<space/><link><target>Jabal Bartazuga</target></link><space/>on the Sudanese border,<space/><link><target>Red Sea Governorate</target></link><space/>**</listitem><listitem>Westernmost point - unnamed point on the border with<space/><link><target>Libya</target></link><space/>immediately east of the ruin of<space/><link><target>Qasr al Qarn</target></link><space/>in Libya,<space/><link><target>Matruh Governorate</target></link></listitem><listitem><italics>* Ras Hadarba lies within the<space/><link><target>Hala'ib triangle</target></link><space/>which is claimed by<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link><space/>but occupied by Egypt. If it is excluded, then Egypt's easternmost point is the<space/><link><target>Ras Banas</target></link><space/><link><target>peninsula</target></link><space/>on the mainland or, including islands,<space/><link><target>Mukawwa Island</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><italics>** Egypt's southernmost point lies in the<space/><link><target>Bir Tawil</target></link><space/>region, an area that is commonly included as part of Egypt but is not claimed by it. If this area is excluded then Egypt has no southernmost point, its southern border being formed by the<space/><link><target>22nd parallel north</target></link>.</italics></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Climate of Egypt</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Northern coast of Egypt</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of cities in Egypt</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>loc</target></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>CIA World Factbook</target></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>commons category</target><arg>Geography of Egypt</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lib.utexas.edu/maps/africa/egypt_pol97.jpg'>Map</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.aldokkan.com/geography/geography.htm'>Ancient Egyptian Geography</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Egypt topics</target></template><template><target>Geography of Africa</target></template><template><target>Geography of Asia</target></template><template><target>Africa topic</target><arg>Climate of</arg></template><template><target>Asia topic</target><arg>Climate of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Geography Of Egypt</target></template><link><target>Category:Geography of Egypt</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Geography of North Africa</target><part>Egypt</part></link><link><target>Category:Geography of the Middle East</target><part>Egypt</part></link></paragraph></article>