<article title='Islamic_conquest_of_Afghanistan'><paragraph><template><target>History of Afghanistan</target></template>The<space/><bold>Islamic conquest of Afghanistan</bold><space/>(642870) began in the middle of the 7th century<extension extension_name='ref' name="Romano">A Historical Atlas of Afghanistan (2003), by Amy Romano, pg. 18.</extension><space/>after the<space/><link><target>Islamic conquest of Persia</target></link><space/>was completed, when<space/><link><target>Arab people</target><part>Arab</part></link><space/><link><target>Muslim</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>defeated the<space/><link><target>Sassanid Empire</target></link><space/>at the battles of<space/><link><target>Battle of Walaja</target><part>Walaja</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Battle of al-Qdisiyyah</target><part>al-Qdisiyyah</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Battle of Nihawnd</target><part>Nahavand</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LC"><link type='external' href='http://lcweb2.loc.gov/cgi-bin/query/r?frd/cstdy:@field(DOCID+af0006)'>''Islamic Conquest''</link>,<space/><link><target>Library of Congress Country Studies</target></link><space/>on Afghanistan</extension><space/>The Muslim Arabs then began to move towards the lands east of<space/><link><target>Persia</target></link><space/>and in 652 captured the city,<space/><link><target>Herat</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Britannica"><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/7798/Afghanistan'>Afghanistan, ''The 7th-18th centuries''</link>,<space/><link><target>Encyclopdia Britannica</target></link></extension><space/>By 667, the<space/><link><target>Afghan (name)</target><part>Afghan</part></link><space/>area was under invasion by the Arabs but in 683<space/><link><target>Kabul</target></link><space/>and other parts of Afghanistan fought with resistance and completely routed the invading army which was led by the Governor of Seistan. The near-complete conversion of<space/><link><target>Afghans</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Islam</target></link><space/>was during the period of the<space/><link><target>Ghaznavids</target></link><space/>in the 10th century, when Afghans converted voluntarily<template><target>Citation required</target><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template><space/>with<space/><link><target>Kafiristan</target></link><space/>holding out until<space/><link><target>Emir</target></link><space/><link><target>Abdur Rahman Khan</target></link><space/>conquered and forcibly converted them in the 1890s.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Caliphate</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Caliphate</arg></template><link><target>File:Ancient Khorasan highlighted.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Names of territories during the<space/><link><target>Caliphate</target></link></part></link>The invasion of Persia was completed five years after the death of the<space/><link><target>Islamic prophet</target></link><space/><link><target>Muhammad</target></link>, and all of the Persian territories came under Arab control, though pockets of tribal resistance continued for centuries in the<space/><link><target>Afghan (name)</target><part>Afghan</part></link><space/>territories.<extension extension_name='ref' name="LC"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Britannica"></extension><space/>During the 7th century,<space/><link><target>Umayyad</target><part>Arab armies</part></link><space/>made their way into the region of Afghanistan from<space/><link><target>Greater Khorasan</target><part>Khorasan</part></link><space/>with the new religion of<space/><link><target>Islam</target></link>. At this point in time, the area that is currently Afghanistan had a multi-religious population consisting of<space/><link><target>Hindu</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(mostly<space/><link><target>Surya</target></link><space/>worshippers),<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Zoroastrian</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Jews</target></link>, and others.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Kabul Shahis</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Kabul Shahi</arg></template>The area had been under the rule of the<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target></link><space/>and then<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>dynasty called the<space/><link><target>Kabul Shahi</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>since the 5th century. Muslims missionaries converted many people to Islam however the entire population did not convert with repetitive revolts from the mountain tribes in the Afghan area taking place. The<space/><link><target>Hindu Shahi</target></link><space/>were defeated in the early part of the 10th century by<space/><link><target>Mahmud of Ghazna</target></link><space/>who ruled between 998 and 1030. He expelled them from<space/><link><target>Gandhara</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Afghanistan Page 15">Afghanistan: a new history By Martin Ewans Edition: 2, illustrated Published by Routledge, 2002 Page 15 ISBN 0-415-29826-1, ISBN 978-0-415-29826-1</extension><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><space/>Earlier in 870,<space/><link><target>Ya'qub bin Laith as-Saffar</target><part>Yaqub bin Laith as-Saffar</part></link>, a local ruler from the<space/><link><target>Saffarids</target><part>Saffarid</part></link><space/>dynasty of<space/><link><target>Zaranj</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, conquered most of present-day Afghanistan in the name of Islam. In many cases, the people he conquered had rebelled against their Islamic overlords and reverted to prior forms of worship.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dupree, Nancy Hatch (1971) &quot;Sites in Perspective (Chapter 3)&quot;<space/><italics>An Historical Guide To Afghanistan</italics><space/>Afghan Tourist Organization, Kabul,<space/><link type='external' href='http://worldcat.org/oclc/241390'>OCLC 241390</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>From the 8th century to the 9th century, many inhabitants of what is present-day<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link>, were converted to<space/><link><target>Sunni Islam</target></link>. It is surmised from the writings of<space/><link><target>Al Biruni</target></link><space/>that some<space/><link><target>Pashtun people</target><part>Pashtuns</part></link><space/>living in<space/><link><target>Pakhtunkhwa</target></link><space/>(present-day western Pakistan) had not been completely converted. Al Biruni, writing in Tarikh al Hind, also alludes to the Pashtun tribes of Pakhtunkhwa as Hindus.<space/></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg name="Al Beruni mentions the Afghans once (''ed Sachau, I 208'') saying that in the western mountains of India live various tribes of Afghans who extend to the neighbourhood of the Sindh (ie Indus) valley. Thus in the eleventh century when the Afghans are first mentioned, they are found occupying the Sulaiman Mountains now occupied by their descendents, the very tribes which the advocates of the exclusive claims of the Durannis will not admit to be true Afghans. Al Beruni no doubt also alludes to them in the passage (''loc. Cit .p 199'') where he says that rebellious savage races, tribes of Hindus, or akin to them inhabit the mountains which form the frontier of India towards the west.<ref name">"North-West Frontier Province Vol Page 211">A Glossary Of The Tribes And Castes Of The Punjab And North-West Frontier Province Vol. 3 By H.A. Rose, Denzil Ibbetson Sir Published by Atlantic Publishers & Distributors, 1997 Page 211 ISBN 81-85297-70-3, ISBN 978-81-85297-70-5</ref></arg></template><space/></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>The most explicit mentioning of the Afghans appears in Al- Baruni’s Tarikh Al-Hind (eleventh century AD). Here it is said that various tribes of Afghans lived in the mountains in the west of India. Al Baruni adds that they were savage people and he describes them as Hindus.<ref>The Afghans By Willem Vogelsang Edition: illustrated Published by Wiley-Blackwell, 2002 Page 118 ISBN 0-631-19841-5, ISBN 978-0-631-19841-3</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Various historical sources such as Martin Ewans, E.J. Brill and Farishta have recorded the introduction of Islam to Kabul and other parts of Afghanistan to the invasions of<space/><link><target>Mahmud of Ghazna</target></link><space/></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg name="The Arabs advanced through Sistan and conquered Sindh early in the eighth century. Elsewhere however their incursions were no more than temporary, and it was not until the rise of the Saffarid dynasty in the ninth century that the frontiers of Islam effectively reached Ghazni and Kabul. Even then a Hindu dynasty the Hindu Shahis, held Gandhara and eastern borders. From the tenth century onwards as Persian language and culture continued to spread into Afghanistan, the focus of power shifted to Ghazni, where a Turkish dynasty, who started by ruling the town for the Samanid dynasty of Bokhara, proceeded to create an empire in their own right. The greatest of the Ghaznavids was Muhmad who ruled between 998 and 1030. He expelled the Hindus from Ghandhara, made no fewer than 17 raids into India.<ref name">"Afghanistan Page 15"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg name="He encouraged mass conversions to Islam, in India as well as in Afghanistan<ref name">"Afghanistan Page 15"/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Muhammad al-Idrisi</target><part>Al-Idirisi</part></link><space/>(1100-1165/1166) testifies that until as late as the 12th century, a contract of investiture for every Hindu Shahi king was performed at Kabul and that here he was obliged to agree to certain ancient conditions which completed the contract.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Al-Idrisi 1991, p 127">Al-Idrisi, p 67, Maqbul Ahmed; Al-Hind, the Making of the Indo-Islamic World, 1991, p 127, Andre Wink.</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>In 1192 AD, according to Farishta, the army assembled by Muizz al din Muhammed bin Sam consisted of Turks, Tajiks and Afghans, and his opponent Pithorai (Prithoi Rai) assembled a force of Rajput and Afghan horsemen. Thus, in this great war Mussulmans and Hindu Afghans are represented as fighting on both sides, which probably indicates that they were not yet completely converted to Islam.<ref>E.J. Brill's First Encyclopaedia of Islam, 1913-1936 By M Th Houtsma, T W Arnold, A J Wensinck Edition: reprint, illustrated Published by BRILL, Page 151 1993 ISBN 90-04-09796-1, ISBN 978-90-04-09796-4</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the end of the 9th century, the<space/><link><target>Samanid Dynasty</target><part>Samanids</part></link><space/>extended its rule from<space/><link><target>Bukhara</target></link><space/>to as far south as the<space/><link><target>Indus River</target></link><space/>and west into parts of Persia. Although Arab Muslim intellectual life was still centered in<space/><link><target>Baghdad</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sunni Islam</target></link>, predominated in the Samanid areas at this time. This period of time was considered an era of great cultural, intellectual, and artistic flourishing under the patronage of the<space/><link><target>Muslim</target></link><space/>Samanids. By the mid-10th century, the Samanid Dynasty had crumbled in the face of attacks from<space/><link><target>Turkish people</target><part>Turkish</part></link><space/>tribes to the north and from the<space/><link><target>Ghaznavids</target></link>, a rising<space/><link><target>Turkic peoples</target><part>Turkic</part></link><space/>dynasty in Afghanistan.</paragraph><paragraph>The region was ruled by<space/><link><target>Hindu</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Buddhist</target></link><space/>dynasty called the<space/><link><target>Kabul Shahi</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>since the 5th century. Mountain tribe revolts hindered the process of converting the tribes. In 870,<space/><link><target>Ya'qub-i Laith Saffari</target></link>, a local<space/><link><target>Tajik people</target><part>Persian</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Encyclopedia of world history</italics>, Editors Peter N. Stearns and William Leonard Langer, (Houghton Mifflin Company, 2001), 115</extension><space/>ruler from the<space/><link><target>Saffarids</target><part>Saffarid dynasty</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Zaranj</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, conquered most of the cities of present-day Afghanistan in the name of Islam.<space/><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Arab armies carrying the banner of Islam came out of the west to defeat the [[Sasanians]] in 642 and then they marched with confidence to the east. On the western periphery of the [[Afghan (name)|Afghan]] area the princes of [[Herat]] and [[Seistan]] gave way to rule by Arab governors but in the east, in the mountains, cities submitted only to rise in revolt and the hastily converted returned to their old beliefs once the armies passed. The harshness and avariciousness of Arab rule produced such unrest, however, that once the waning power of the [[Caliphate]] became apparent, native rulers once again established themselves independent. Among these the [[Saffarids]] of Seistan shone briefly in the Afghan area. The fanatic founder of this dynasty, the coppersmith’s apprentice Yaqub ibn Layth Saffari, came forth from his capital at Zaranj in 870 and marched through [[Lashkar Gah|Bost]], [[Kandahar]], [[Ghazni]], [[Kabul]], [[Bamyan, Afghanistan|Bamyan]], [[Balkh]] and [[Herat]], conquering in the name of Islam.<ref name">"Dupree">[[Nancy Hatch Dupree|Dupree, Nancy Hatch]] (1971) "Sites in Perspective (Chapter 3)" ''An Historical Guide To Afghanistan'' Afghan Tourist Organization, Kabul, [http://worldcat.org/oclc/241390 OCLC 241390]</ref></arg><arg>[[Nancy Hatch Dupree]]</arg><arg>1971</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>During the 8th through the 9th centuries, many inhabitants of what is present-day<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link><space/>and western<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link><space/>were converted to<space/><link><target>Sunni Islam</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="SNS">Ancient Indian History and Civilization, by Sailendra Nath Sen, p 347.</extension><space/>In some cases, however, people that were conquered by the Muslims would rebel and revert to prior forms of worship.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dupree"></extension><space/>The mountain areas were still not completely converted and remained largely by people of non-Muslim faiths. In a book called<space/><link><target>Hudud ul-'alam</target><part>Hudud-al-Alam</part></link>, written in 982, it mentions a village near<space/><link><target>Jalalabad</target></link>, Afghanistan, where the local king used to have many Hindu, Muslim and Afghan wives.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WV">Willem Vogelsang,<space/><italics>The Afghans</italics>, Edition: illustrated Published by Wiley-Blackwell, 2002, Page 18, ISBN 0-631-19841-5, ISBN 978-0-631-19841-3 (<link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=9kfJ6MlMsJQC&amp;amp;pg=RA1-PA18&amp;amp;lpg=RA1-PA18&amp;amp;dq=Hindu+Pashtuns&amp;amp;source=bl&amp;amp;ots=53eiiBfFg-&amp;amp;sig=Gg8zdnCCGM8oM5rBiRWbVmURUmo&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=0CXsSa3QHOOwtgf7y9iXBg&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=10#PRA1-PA18,M1'>LINK</link>)</extension><space/><template><target>quote</target><arg name="In the eighth and ninth centuries ancestors of many of today's Turkic-speaking Afghans settled in the Hindu Kush area (partly to obtain better grazing land) and began to assimilate much of the culture and language of the [[Pashtun tribes]] already present there...<ref name">"LC" /></arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ghaznavids and Ghurids</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Ghaznavids</arg><arg>Ghurid Dynasty</arg></template>Out of the<space/><link><target>Samanids</target><part>Samanid dynasty</part></link><space/>came the<space/><link><target>Ghaznavids</target></link>, whose warriors forged the first great Islamic empire from<space/><link><target>Ghazni</target></link><space/>(Afghanistan) that spanned much of the Iranian plateau,<space/><link><target>Central Asia</target></link><space/>and conducted many successful raids into<space/><link><target>Indian subcontinent</target><part>India</part></link>. During the end of the 9th century, the Samanids extended its rule from<space/><link><target>Bukhara</target></link><space/>to as far south as the<space/><link><target>Indus River</target></link><space/>and west into most of Persia. By the mid-10th century, the Samanid dynasty had crumble in the face of attacks from<space/><link><target>Turkic peoples</target><part>Turkish tribes</part></link><space/>to the north and from the Ghaznavids, a rising<space/><link><target>Turkic peoples</target><part>Turkic</part></link><space/>Muslim dynasty in Afghanistan. Besides Turkic people, large part of the Ghaznavid Empire was made up of local Muslim Afghans from what is now Afghanistan and western parts of Pakistan.</paragraph><paragraph>It is surmised from the writings of<space/><link><target>Al Biruni</target></link><space/>that some Afghans who lived in west of India (modern-day<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>) had not been completely converted to Islam.<template><target>quote</target><arg name="The most explicit mentioning of the Afghans appears in Al- Baruni’s Tarikh al hind (11th century). Here it is said that various tribes of Afghans lived in the mountains in the west of [[Hindustan|India]]. Al Baruni adds that they were savage people and he describes them as Hindus.<ref name">"WV" /></arg><arg>Willem Vogelsang</arg><arg>2002</arg></template><link><target>File:Ghaznavid Empire 975 - 1187 (AD).PNG</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Ghaznavids</target><part>Ghaznavid Empire</part></link>. Its main capital was<space/><link><target>Ghazni</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lahore</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link><space/>served as the second capital.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg name="Al Beruni mentions the Afghans once (''ed Sachau, I 208'') saying that in the western mountains of India live various tribes of Afghans who extend to the neighbourhood of the Sindh (i.e., Indus) valley. Thus in the eleventh century when the Afghans are first mentioned, they are found occupying the Sulaiman Mountains now occupied by their descendants, the very tribes which the advocates of the exclusive claims of the Durannis will not admit to be true Afghans. Al Beruni no doubt also alludes to them in the passage (''loc. Cit. p. 199'') where he says that rebellious savage races, tribes of Hindus, or akin to them inhabit the mountains which form the frontier of India towards the west.<ref name">"North-West Frontier Province Vol Page 211"/></arg><arg>H.A. Rose</arg><arg>1997</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Various historical sources such as Martin Ewans, E.J. Brill and<space/><link><target>Firishta</target><part>Farishta</part></link><space/>have recorded that the complete conversion of Afghanistan, Pakistan to Islam was during the rule of<space/><link><target>Sultan</target></link><space/><link><target>Mahmud of Ghazni</target></link>.<space/><link><target>File:Sultan-Mahmud-Ghaznawi.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part><link><target>Sultan</target></link><space/><link><target>Mahmud of Ghazni</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>quote</target><arg>The Arabs advanced through Sistan and conquered Sindh early in the eighth century. Elsewhere however their incursions were no more than temporary, and it was not until the rise of the [[Saffarids|Saffarid dynasty]] in the ninth century that the frontiers of Islam effectively reached Ghazni and Kabul. Even then a Hindu dynasty the Hindushahis, held Gandhara and eastern borders. From the tenth century onwards as Persian language and culture continued to spread into Afghanistan, the focus of power shifted to Ghazni, where a Turkish dynasty, who started by ruling the town for the Samanid dynasty of Bokhara, proceeded to create an empire in their own right. The greatest of the Ghaznavids was Mahmud who ruled between 998 and 1030. He expelled the Hindus from Ghandhara, made no fewer than 17 raids into India. He encouraged mass conversions to Islam, in India as well as in Afghanistan.<ref>Afghanistan: a new history By Martin Ewans Edition: 2, illustrated Published by Routledge, 2002 Page 15 ISBN 0-415-29826-1, ISBN 978-0-415-29826-1</ref></arg><arg>Martin Ewans</arg><arg>2002</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Muhammad al-Idrisi</target><part>Al-Idirisi</part></link><space/>testifies that until as late as the 12th century, a contract of investiture for every Shahi king was performed at Kabul and that here he was obliged to agree to certain ancient conditions which completed the contract.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Al-Idrisi 1991, p 127"></extension><space/>The Ghaznavid military incursions assured the domination of<space/><link><target>Sunni Islam</target></link><space/>in what is now Afghanistan and western Pakistan. The most renowned of the dynasty's rulers was Mahmud of Ghazni, who consolidated control over the areas south of the<space/><link><target>Amu Darya</target></link><space/>then carried out devastating raids into India. With his booty from India, Mahmud built a great capital at<space/><link><target>Ghazni</target></link>, founded universities, and patronized scholars. By the time of his death, Mahmud ruled a vast empire that stretched from<space/><link><target>Kurdistan</target></link><space/>to the entire<space/><link><target>Hindu Kush</target></link><space/>region as far east as the<space/><link><target>Punjab region</target><part>Punjab</part></link><space/>as well as territories far north of the<space/><link><target>Amu Darya</target></link>. However, as occurred so often in this region, the demise in 1030 of this military genius who had expanded the empire to its farthest reaches was the death knell of the dynasty itself. The rulers of the<space/><link><target>Ghurid Dynasty</target><part>Ghurids</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ghor</target></link><space/>in modern-day Afghanistan, captured and burned Ghazni in 1149, just as the Ghaznavids had once conquered Ghor. Not until 1186, however, was the last representative of the Ghaznavids uprooted by the Ghorids from his holdout in<space/><link><target>Lahore</target></link>, in the Punjab.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>History of Afghanistan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Timeline of Afghanistan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>History of Arabs in Afghanistan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pre-Islamic Hindu and Buddhist heritage of Afghanistan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Muslim conquests</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Elliot, Sir H. M., Edited by Dowson, John.<space/><link><target>The History of India, as Told by Its Own Historians. The Muhammadan Period</target></link>; published by London Trubner Company 18671877. (Online Copy:<space/><link type='external' href='http://persian.packhum.org/persian/index.jsp?serv=pf&amp;amp;file=80201010&amp;amp;ct=0'>The History of India, as Told by Its Own Historians. The Muhammadan Period; by Sir H. M. Elliot; Edited by John Dowson; London Trubner Company 18671877</link><space/>- This online Copy has been posted by:<space/><link type='external' href='http://persian.packhum.org/persian/index.jsp'>The Packard Humanities Institute; Persian Texts in Translation; Also find other historical books: Author List and Title List</link>)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The Guardian</italics>: &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.guardian.co.uk/print/0,3858,5217828-103595,00.html'>Lost Tribe Struggles for Survival</link>&quot;</listitem><listitem>''Press Trust of India :&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.indianexpress.com/res/web/pIe/ie/daily/20010105/iin05014.html'>Inscription throws new light to Hindu rule in Afghanistan<space/></link>&quot;</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.apaa.info/'>Association for the protection of Afghan Archeology</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Islamic Conquest Of Afghanistan</target></template><link><target>Category:Muslim conquests</target></link><link><target>Category:Medieval Afghanistan</target><part>Afghanistan</part></link></paragraph></article>