<article title='Teochew_cuisine'><paragraph><template><target>refimprove</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Chinese</target><arg name="title">Chaozhou cuisine</arg><arg name="c">潮州菜</arg><arg name="p">Cháozhōu cài</arg><arg name="j">ciu4 zau1 coi3</arg><arg name="pj"></arg><arg name="altname">Chaoshan cuisine</arg><arg name="c2">潮汕菜</arg><arg name="p2">Cháoshàn cài</arg><arg name="j2">ciu4 saan3 coi3</arg></template><template><target>Cuisine of China</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Teochew cuisine</bold>, also known as<space/><bold>Chiuchow cuisine</bold>,<space/><bold>Chaozhou cuisine</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Chaoshan cuisine</bold>, originated from the<space/><link><target>Chaoshan</target></link><space/>region in the east of<space/><link><target>Guangdong</target></link><space/>province, which includes the cities of<space/><link><target>Chaozhou</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Shantou</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jieyang</target></link>. Teochew cuisine bears more similarities to that of<space/><link><target>Fujian cuisine</target></link>, with which it shares some dishes. This may be due to the similarity of Chaoshan's and<space/><link><target>Fujian</target></link>'s culture and language and to their geographic proximity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kcc"><template><target>citation</target><arg name="title">Food in Chinese culture : anthropological and historical perspectives<space/></arg><arg name="first">Kwang-chih<space/></arg><arg name="last">Chang<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press</arg><arg name="year">1977</arg></template></extension><space/>However, Teochew cuisine is also influenced by<space/><link><target>Cantonese cuisine</target></link><space/>in its style and technique.<extension extension_name='ref' name="kcc"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Background</heading><paragraph>Teochew cuisine is well known for its<space/><link><target>seafood</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>vegetarian</target></link><space/>dishes and is commonly regarded<space/><template><target>by whom</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><space/>as being healthy. Its use of flavouring is much less heavy-handed than most other Chinese cuisines and depends much on the freshness and quality of the ingredients for taste and flavour. As a delicate cuisine, oil is not often used in large quantities and there is a relatively heavy emphasis on poaching, steaming and<space/><link><target>braising</target></link>, as well as the common Chinese method of stir-frying. Chaozhou cuisine is also known for serving<space/><link><target>congee</target></link><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">潮州糜</arg><arg name="p">Cháozhōu mí</arg></template>; or<space/><italics>mue</italics>), in addition to<space/><link><target>steamed rice</target></link><space/>or noodles with meals. The Teochew<space/><italics>mue</italics><space/>is rather different from the Cantonese counterpart. The former being very watery with the rice sitting loosely at the bottom of the bowl, while the latter is more a thin gruel.</paragraph><paragraph>Authentic Teochew restaurants serve very strong<space/><link><target>oolong</target></link><space/>tea called<space/><link><target>Tieguanyin</target></link><space/>in very tiny cups before and after the meal. Presented as<space/><italics><link><target>Gongfu tea ceremony</target><part>Gongfu cha</part></link></italics>, the tea has a thickly bittersweet taste, colloquially known as<space/><italics>gam gam</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">甘甘</arg><arg name="p">gān gān</arg></template>).</paragraph><paragraph>A condiment that is popular in Fujian and<space/><link><target>Taiwanese cuisine</target></link><space/>and commonly associated with cuisine of certain Teochew groups is<space/><link><target>shacha sauce</target></link><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="s">沙茶酱</arg><arg name="t">沙茶醬</arg><arg name="p">shāchá jiàng</arg></template>). It is made from soybean oil, garlic, shallots, chilies, brill fish, and dried shrimp. The paste has a savoury and slightly spicy taste.</paragraph><paragraph>As an ingredient, it has multiple uses:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>as a base for soups</listitem><listitem>as a rub for<space/><link><target>barbecue</target><trail>d</trail></link><space/>meats</listitem><listitem>as a seasoning for<space/><link><target>stir fry</target></link><space/>dishes</listitem><listitem>as a component for dipping sauces, for example as used in<space/><link><target>hot pot</target></link><space/>meals</listitem></list><paragraph>In addition to<space/><link><target>soy sauce</target></link><space/>(widely used in all Chinese cuisines), diaspora Teochew cuisine, (mainly Teochews in Indochina) uses<space/><link><target>fish sauce</target></link>. It is used as a flavouring agent in soups and sometimes as a dipping sauce, as in Vietnamese spring rolls.</paragraph><paragraph>Teochew chefs often use a special stock called<space/><link><target>Asian soups#Traditional soup bases</target><part>superior broth</part></link><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="s">上汤</arg><arg name="t">上湯</arg><arg name="p">shàngtāng</arg></template>). This stock remains on the stove and is continuously replenished. Portrayed in popular media, some Hong Kong chefs allegedly use the same superior broth that is preserved for decades. This stock can as well be seen on Chaozhou TV's cooking programmes.</paragraph><paragraph>There is a notable feast in Teochew cuisine / banquet called<space/><italics>jiat dot</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">食桌</arg><arg name="p">shízhuō</arg><arg name="l">food table</arg></template>). A myriad of dishes are often served, which include<space/><link><target>shark fin soup</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Edible bird's nest</target><part>bird's nest soup</part></link>, lobster, steamed fish, roasted suckling pig and braised goose.</paragraph><paragraph>Teochew chefs take pride in their skills of vegetable carving, and carved vegetables are used as garnishes on cold dishes and on the banquet table.</paragraph><paragraph>Teochew cuisine is also known for a late night meal known as<space/><italics>meh siao</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">夜宵</arg><arg name="p">yèxiāo</arg></template>) or<space/><italics>da lang</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">打冷</arg><arg name="p">dǎléng</arg></template>) among the Cantonese. Teochew people enjoy eating out close to midnight in restaurants or at roadside food stalls. Some<space/><link><target>dai pai dong</target></link>-like restaurants stay open till dawn.</paragraph><paragraph>Unlike the typical menu selections of many other Chinese cuisines, Teochew restaurant menus often have a<space/><link><target>dessert</target></link><space/>section.</paragraph><paragraph>Many people of Chaoshan origin, also known as Teochiu or Teochew people, have settled in<space/><link><target>Southeast Asia</target></link>, especially<space/><link><target>Singapore</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Hong Kong</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Cambodia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Thailand</target></link>; influences they bring can be noted in the<space/><link><target>cuisine of Singapore</target></link><space/>and that of other settlements. A large number of Teochew people have also settled in Taiwan, evident in<space/><link><target>Taiwanese cuisine</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2011</arg></template><space/>Other notable Teochew diaspora communities are in Vietnam and France. There is also a large diaspora of Teochew people (most were from Southeast Asia) in the United States - particularly in the state of California. There is a Teochew Chinese Association in Paris called L'Amicale des Teochews en France.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Notable dishes</heading><table class="wikitable"><tablecaption>List of notable dishes in Teochew cuisine</tablecaption><tablerow><tablehead>English</tablehead><tablehead>Traditional Chinese</tablehead><tablehead>Simplified Chinese</tablehead><tablehead>Pinyin</tablehead><tablehead>Teochew transliteration</tablehead><tablehead>Description</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Braised varieties</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>lwi</tablecell><tablecell>lo bah</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew cuisine is noted for its variety of braised dishes, which includes geese, duck, pork, beancurd, and offal.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew-style steamed<space/><link><target>pomfret</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu zhng chngy</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew chue chioh her</tablecell><tablecell>Silver<space/><link><target>pomfret</target></link><space/>steamed with preserved salted vegetables,<space/><link><target>lard</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sour plum</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Pork jelly</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>zhjio dng</tablecell><tablecell>ter ka dang</tablecell><tablecell>Braised pig's leg made into jelly form, sliced and served cold.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Steamed goose</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>chu<space/></tablecell><tablecell>chue gho</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew chicken</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu j</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew koi</tablecell><tablecell>A dish of sliced chicken</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Oyster omelette</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>holo</tablecell><tablecell>or lua</tablecell><tablecell>A dish of omelette cooked with fresh raw oysters and tapioca starch.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Salted vegetable duck soup</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>xinci ytng</tablecell><tablecell>kiam cai ak terng</tablecell><tablecell>A soup boiled with duck, preserved salted vegetable, tomatoes and preserved<space/><link><target>sour plum</target></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Pig's organ soup</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>zhztng</tablecell><tablecell>ter zap terng</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Bak kut teh</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>rugch</tablecell><tablecell>bak kut teh</tablecell><tablecell>A hearty soup that, at its simplest, consists of meaty pork ribs in a complex broth of herbs and spices (including star anise, cinnamon, cloves,<space/><link><target>Angelica sinensis</target><part>dang gui</part></link>,<space/><link><target>fennel</target><part>fennel seeds</part></link><space/>and garlic), boiled together with pork bones for hours. Dark and light soy sauce may also be added to the soup during the cooking stages. Some Teochew families like to add extra Chinese herbs such as yu zhu (rhizome of Solomon's Seal) and ju zhi (buckthorn fruit) for a sweeter, slightly stronger flavoured soup. These herbs are known to improve health.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><space/>The dish is usually eaten with rice or noodles (sometimes as a noodle soup), and often served with<space/><link><target>youtiao</target></link>. Garnish includes chopped coriander or green onions and a sprinkling of fried shallots. A variation of &quot;bak kut teh&quot; uses chicken instead of pork, which then becomes &quot;chik kut teh&quot;. &quot;Bak kut teh&quot; is particularly popular in<space/><link><target>South East Asia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>countries such as<space/><link><target>Singapore</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Malaysia</target></link><space/>(famous in the town of<space/><link><target>Klang, Malaysia</target><part>Klang</part></link>) where it was brought over with the Chinese diaspora.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Popiah</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>bobngzi</tablecell><tablecell>po piah</tablecell><tablecell>A fresh (non-fried) spring roll usually eaten during the<space/><link><target>Qingming Festival</target></link>. The skin is a soft, thin paper-like crepe made from wheat flour. The filling is mainly finely grated and steamed or stir-fried turnip, yam bean (jicama), which has been cooked with a combination of other ingredients such as bean sprouts, French beans, and lettuce leaves, depending on the individual vendor, along with grated carrots, slices of Chinese sausage, thinly sliced fried tofu, chopped peanuts or peanut powder, fried shallots, and shredded omelette. Other common variations of popiah include pork (lightly seasoned and stir-fried), shrimp or crab meat. It is eaten in accompaniment with a sweet sauce (often a bean sauce, a blended soy sauce or<space/><link><target>hoisin sauce</target></link><space/>or a<space/><link><target>shrimp paste</target></link><space/>sauce).</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew<space/><link><target>hot pot</target></link><space/>/ Teochew steamboat</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu hugu</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew zuang lou</tablecell><tablecell>A dish where fresh, thinly sliced ingredients are placed into a simmering flavourful broth to cook and then dipped into various mixed sauces, usually with Shacha and soy sauce as its main components. Ingredients often include leafy vegetables, yam, tofu, pomfret and other seafood, beef balls, fish balls, pork balls, mushrooms and Chinese noodles, amongst others. Teochew hot pot, like other Chinese hot pots, is served in a large communal metal pot at the center of the dining table.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Spring rolls with prawn or minced meat fillings</tablecell><tablecell><space/>/ /<space/></tablecell><tablecell><space/>/ /<space/></tablecell><tablecell>xijun / shojun / wxing</tablecell><tablecell>heh gerng / sio gerng /<space/><link><target>ngo hiang</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Mixed pork and prawn paste (sometimes fish), seasoned with<space/><link><target>five-spice powder</target></link>, wrapped and rolled in a beancurd skin and deep-fried or pan-fried. It is sometimes referred to as Teochew-style spring roll in restaurant menus.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Yusheng</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>yshng</tablecell><tablecell>her sae</tablecell><tablecell>A raw fish salad where typical ingredients include: fresh salmon, white radish, carrot, red pepper (capsicum), ginger, kaffir lime leaves, Chinese parsley, chopped peanuts, toasted sesame seeds, Chinese shrimp crackers or fried dried shrimp and five spice powder, with the dressing primarily made from plum sauce. It is customarily served as an appetiser to raise 'good luck' for the new year and is usually eaten on the seventh day of the<space/><link><target>Chinese New Year</target></link>. This delicacy is known to exist as far back as the<space/><link><target>Southern Song Dynasty</target></link>,<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template><space/>the original version consisting of a simple salad of raw and julienned vegetables, dressed in condiments. The modern version which is widely known today was developed by a chef in Lai Wah Restaurant in Singapore during the 1960s.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2012</arg></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew cold crab</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu dngxi</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew ngang hoi</tablecell><tablecell>The whole crab is first steamed then served chilled. The species of crab most commonly used is<space/><italics><link><target>Charybdis (genus)</target><part>Charybdis cruciata</part></link></italics>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Fishballs / fishcakes / fish dumplings</tablecell><tablecell><space/>/ /<space/></tablecell><tablecell><space/>/ /<space/></tablecell><tablecell>ywn / ygu / yjio</tablecell><tablecell>her ee / her kueh / her kiaw</tablecell><tablecell>This fish paste made into balls, cakes and dumplings can be cooked in many ways but are often served in Teochew-style noodle and soups.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Fishball noodle soup</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>ywn min</tablecell><tablecell>her ee mee</tablecell><tablecell>Any of several kinds of egg and rice noodles may be served either in a light fish-flavoured broth or dry, along with fishballs, fishcakes, beansprouts and lettuce.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Mee pok</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>minbo</tablecell><tablecell>mee pok</tablecell><tablecell>A popular noodle dish served with minced pork, braised mushrooms, fishballs, dumplings, sauce and other garnish.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Bak chor mee</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>rusu min</tablecell><tablecell>bak chor mee</tablecell><tablecell>Boiled noodles, dried and mixed with variety sauce such as soy sauce, chilli sauce and lard topped with vegetables, chopped onion, minced pork and mushroom, and fishballs or fishcakes.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Kueh chap</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>guzh</tablecell><tablecell>kueh chap</tablecell><tablecell>A dish of flat, broad rice sheets in a soup made from dark soy sauce served with pig offal, braised duck meat, various kinds of beancurd, preserved salted vegetables and braised hard-boiled eggs.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew rice noodle soup</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu gutio</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew kuay teow</tablecell><tablecell>A quintessential Teochew-style noodle soup that is also particularly popular in Vietnam and Cambodia (known respectively as<space/><italics>hu tieu</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>kuy teav</italics>), through the influx of Teochew immigrants. It is a dish of yellow egg noodles and thin rice noodles served in a delicate, fragrant soup with meatballs, other various meats, seafood (such as shrimp), fried fish cake slices, quail eggs, blanched Chinese cabbage and sometimes offal. The soup base is typically made of pork or chicken bones and dried squid. Just before serving, the noodle soup is garnished with fried minced garlic, fried shallots, thinly sliced scallions and fresh cilantro (coriander) sprigs. For those who enjoy their noodle soup with added depth, the solid ingredients may be dipped into<space/><link><target>Shacha sauce</target></link><space/>or Teochew chili oil.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Teochew-style<space/><link><target>congee</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>Chozhu zhu</tablecell><tablecell>Teochew mue</tablecell><tablecell>A rice soup that has a more watery texture as compared to the Cantonese congee. It is commonly served with various salty accompaniments such as salted vegetables (<italics>kiam chai</italics>), preserved radish (<italics>chai por</italics>), boiled salted duck eggs, fried salted fish and fried peanuts.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Yam dessert</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>yn</tablecell><tablecell>orh ni</tablecell><tablecell>Yams are steamed, mashed and then sweetened to form the dessert which resembles yam dough. It is often served with gingko seeds. This dessert contains fried onion oil to give it a nice fragrance.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Chai tao kway</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>citu gu</tablecell><tablecell>chai tau kueh</tablecell><tablecell>A savoury fried cake, made of white radish and rice flour. It is commonly stir fried with soy sauce, eggs, garlic, spring onion and occasionally dried shrimp.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Fun guo</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>fngu</tablecell><tablecell>hung gue</tablecell><tablecell>A type of steamed dumplings. This is usually filled with dried radish, garlic chives, ground pork, dried shrimp, Shiitake mushrooms and peanuts. The dumpling wrapper is made from a mixture of flour or plant starches mixed together with water. In Cantonese, these are called<space/><italics>chiu chow fun guo</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">潮州粉果</arg><arg name="p">Cháozhōu fěnguǒ</arg></template>), in which the Chinese character is replaced by .</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Steamed chives dumplings</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>ji ci gu</tablecell><tablecell>gu chai gue</tablecell><tablecell>They are sometimes<space/><link><target>Sauting</target><part>sauted</part></link><space/>to give them a crispy texture.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Crystal balls</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>shujng bo</tablecell><tablecell>zhui jia bao</tablecell><tablecell>A steamed dessert with a variety of fillings such as yellow milk (<template><target>zh</target><arg name="s">奶黄</arg><arg name="t">奶黃</arg><arg name="p">nǎihuáng</arg></template>;<space/><link><target>Teochew dialect</target><part>Teochew</part></link>:<space/><italics>ni ng</italics>), yam paste (<template><target>zh</target><arg name="c">芋泥</arg><arg name="p">yùní</arg></template>;<space/><link><target>Teochew dialect</target><part>Teochew</part></link>:<space/><italics>ou ni</italics>) or bean paste made from<space/><link><target>mung bean</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>azuki bean</target><trail>s</trail></link>. They are similar to<space/><link><target>mochi</target></link>.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Chwee kueh</target></link></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>shugu</tablecell><tablecell>chwee kueh</tablecell><tablecell>Cup-shaped steamed rice cakes topped with chopped preserved / salted radish.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Oolong</target></link><space/>tea</tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell></tablecell><tablecell>wlng ch</tablecell><tablecell>Ou-leeng teh</tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tieguanyin</target></link><space/>is one of the most popular Teochew teas. However, the Teochew people prefer their own brand of Oolong tea, which is the<space/><italics>hong wang dan cong teh</italics><space/>(<template><target>zh</target><arg name="s">凤凰单丛茶</arg><arg name="t">鳳凰單丛茶</arg><arg name="p">fènghuáng dāncóng chá</arg></template>).</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Gallery</heading><paragraph><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Shui jing bao zz.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Crystal balls ()</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Teochew pomfret.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Steamed fish ()</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Oyster omelette.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br><link><target>Oyster omelette</target></link><space/>()</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>File:Khanom kuichai.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Steamed chives dumplings ()</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of Chinese dishes</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.sfgate.com/cgi-bin/article.cgi?f=/chronicle/archive/2007/09/19/FD2SRSDKH.DTL'>Yeo's Teochew Popiah Recipe</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.jenius.com.au/2011/02/teochew_peach-shaped_kueh.php'>Jenius' Teochew peach shaped kueh Recipe</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Cuisine</target></template><template><target>Chaozhou cuisine</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Teochew Cuisine</target></template><link><target>Category:Chaozhou</target></link><link><target>Category:Regional cuisines of China</target></link><link><target>Category:Teochew cuisine</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>