<article title='Diplomatic_immunity'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><bold>Diplomatic immunity</bold><space/>is a form of<space/><link><target>Immunity from prosecution</target><part>legal immunity</part></link><space/>that ensures<space/><link><target>diplomat</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are given safe passage and are considered not susceptible to<space/><link><target>lawsuit</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>prosecution</target></link><space/>under the host country's laws, although they can still be<space/><link><target>deportation</target><part>expelled</part></link>. It was agreed as<space/><link><target>international law</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</target></link><space/>(1961), though the concept and custom have a much longer history. Many principles of diplomatic immunity are now considered to be<space/><link><target>customary law</target></link>. Diplomatic immunity as an institution developed to allow for the maintenance of government relations, including during periods of difficulties and<space/><link><target>War</target><part>armed conflict</part></link>. When receiving diplomatswho formally represent the sovereignthe receiving head of state grants certain privileges and immunities to ensure they may effectively carry out their duties, on the understanding that these are provided on a reciprocal basis.</paragraph><paragraph>Originally, these privileges and immunities were granted on a<space/><link><target>bilateralism</target><part>bilateral</part></link>,<space/><link><target>ad hoc</target></link><space/>basis, which led to misunderstandings and conflict, pressure on weaker states, and an inability for other states to judge which party was at fault. An international agreement known as the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</target><part>Vienna Conventions</part></link><space/>codified the rules and agreements, providing standards and privileges to all states.</paragraph><paragraph>It is possible for the official's home country to waive immunity; this tends to happen only when the individual has committed a serious<space/><link><target>crime</target></link>, unconnected with their diplomatic role (as opposed to, say, allegations of<space/><link><target>espionage</target><part>spying</part></link>), or has witnessed such a crime. However, many countries refuse to waive immunity as a matter of course; individuals have no authority to waive their own immunity (except perhaps in cases of<space/><link><target>defection</target></link>). Alternatively, the home country may prosecute the individual. If immunity is waived by a government so that a diplomat (or their family members) can be prosecuted, it must be because there is a case to answer and it is in the public interest to prosecute them. For instance, in 2002, a Colombian diplomat in London was prosecuted for manslaughter, once diplomatic immunity was waived by the Colombian government.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2284320.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">An example where diplomatic immunity was waived in the public interest<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 September 2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2133055.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Representations on behalf of the victim's family led to the prosecution of a military attache for manslaughter<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 July 2002<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ancient times</heading><paragraph><template><target>unreferenced section</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template><link><target>File:Krishna Mediating between the Pandavas and Kauravas.jpeg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>x216px</part><part>text</part><part><link><target>Krishna</target></link>, an avatar of<space/><link><target>Vishnu</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Kurukshetra War#Krishna's peace mission</target><part>mediating for peace</part></link><space/>to avert the<space/><link><target>Kurukshetra War</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link></part></link>The concept of diplomatic immunity can be found in ancient Indian epics like<space/><italics><link><target>Ramayana</target></link></italics><space/>(between 3000 and 2000 BC) (traditional Hindu dating: over 100,000 years ago) and<space/><italics><link><target>Mahabharata</target></link></italics><space/>(around 4th century BC; traditional Hindu dating: 3000 BC), where messengers and diplomats were given immunity from capital punishment. In<space/><link><target>Ramayana</target></link>, when the demon king<space/><link><target>Ravana</target></link><space/>ordered the killing of<space/><link><target>Hanuman</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ravana</target></link>'s younger brother<space/><link><target>Vibhishana</target></link><space/>pointed out that messengers or diplomats should not be killed or arrested, as per ancient practices.</paragraph><paragraph>During the evolution of international justice, many wars were considered rebellions or unlawful by one or more combatant sides. In such cases, the servants of the &quot;criminal&quot; sovereign were often considered accomplices and their persons violated. In other circumstances, harbingers of inconsiderable demands were killed as a declaration of war.<space/><link><target>Herodotus</target></link><space/>records that when heralds of the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target><part>Persian king</part></link><space/><link><target>Xerxes I of Persia</target><part>Xerxes</part></link><space/>demanded &quot;earth and water&quot; (i.e., symbols of submission) of Greek cities, the<space/><link><target>Athens</target><part>Athenians</part></link><space/>threw them into a pit and the<space/><link><target>Sparta</target><trail>ns</trail></link><space/>threw them down a well for the purpose of suggesting they would find both earth and water at the bottom, these often being mentioned by the messenger as a threat of siege. However, even for Herodotus, this maltreatment of envoys is a crime, and he immediately recounts a story of divine vengeance befalling Sparta for this deed.<extension extension_name='ref'>Herodotos.<space/><italics>Histories</italics>. Book VII, Ch. 133-134. (pp. 558559 in the cited version.) Transl. Rawlinson, G. Wordsworth. Ware, Herefordshire. 1996. ISBN 1-85326-466-0.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>envoy was urinated on as he was leaving the city of<space/><link><target>Taranto</target><part>Tarentum</part></link>. The oath of the envoy, &quot;This stain will be washed away with blood!&quot;, was fulfilled during the<space/><link><target>Second Punic War</target></link>. The arrest and ill-treatment of the envoy of<space/><link><target>Raja Raja Chola</target></link><space/>by the king of<space/><link><target>Kulasekhara dynasty (Second Cheras)</target></link>, which is now part of<space/><link><target>modern India</target></link>, led to the naval<space/><link><target>Kandalur War</target></link><space/>in AD 994.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pope Gelasius I</target></link><space/>was the first pope recorded as enjoying diplomatic immunity, as it is noted in his letter<space/><italics>Duo sunt</italics><space/>to emperor<space/><link><target>Anastasius I (emperor)</target><part>Anastasius</part></link>.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As diplomats by definition enter the country under safe-conduct, violating them is normally viewed as a great breach of honour, although there have been numerous cases in which diplomats have been killed.<space/><link><target>Genghis Khan</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Mongols</target></link><space/>were well known for strongly insisting on the rights of diplomats, and they would often take terrifying vengeance against any state that violated these rights. The Mongols would often raze entire cities in retaliation for the execution of their ambassadors, and<space/><link><target>Mongol invasion of Khwarezmia</target><part>invaded and destroyed the Khwarezmid Empire</part></link><space/>after their ambassadors had been mistreated.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Prawdin"><link><target>Michael Prawdin</target><part>Prawdin, Michael</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Mongol Empire</italics>.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>The beginnings of modern immunity</heading><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Parliament of Great Britain</target><part>British Parliament</part></link><space/>first guaranteed diplomatic immunity to foreign ambassadors in 1709, after Count<space/><link><target>Andrey Matveyev</target></link>, a Russian resident in London, had been subjected to verbal and physical abuse by<space/><link><target>Bailiff#British Isles</target><part>British bailiffs</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern diplomatic immunity evolved parallel to the development of modern diplomacy. In the 17th century, European diplomats realized that protection from prosecution was essential to doing their jobs and a set of rules evolved guaranteeing the rights of diplomats. These were still confined to Western Europe and were closely tied to the prerogatives of nobility. Thus, an emissary to the Ottoman Empire could expect to be arrested and imprisoned upon the outbreak of hostilities between his state and the empire. The French Revolution also disrupted this system, as the revolutionary state and Napoleon imprisoned numerous diplomats who were accused of working against France. More recently, the<space/><link><target>Iran hostage crisis</target></link><space/>is universally considered a violation of diplomatic immunity. Although the hostage takers did not officially represent the state, host countries are obligated to protect diplomatic property and personnel. On the other hand, during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, diplomatic immunity was upheld and the embassies of the belligerents evacuated through neutral countries.</paragraph><paragraph>For the upper class of the 17th, 18th, and 19th centuries, diplomatic immunity was an easy concept to understand. The first embassies were not permanent establishments but actual visits by high-ranking representatives, often close relatives, of the<space/><link><target>Sovereignty</target><part>sovereign</part></link><space/>or the sovereign in person. As permanent representations evolved, usually on a treaty basis between two powers, they were frequently staffed by relatives of the sovereign or high-ranking nobles.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>War</target><trail>fare</trail></link><space/>was not between individuals but between their sovereigns, and the officers and officials of European governments and armies often changed employers. Truces and ceasefires were commonplace, along with fraternization between officers of enemy armies during them. When prisoners, the officers usually gave their<space/><link><target>wikt:parole</target><part>parole</part></link><space/>and were only restricted to a city away from the theatre of war. Almost always, they were given leave to carry their personal sidearms. Even during French revolutionary wars, British scientists visited the French Academy. In such an atmosphere, it was easy to accept that some persons were immune to the laws. After all, they were still bound by strict requirements of honour and customs.</paragraph><paragraph>In the 19th century, the<space/><link><target>Congress of Vienna</target></link><space/>reasserted the rights of diplomats; and they have been largely respected since then, as the European model has spread throughout the world. Currently, diplomatic relations, including diplomatic immunity, are governed internationally by the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</target></link>, which has been ratified by almost every country in the world.</paragraph><paragraph>In modern times, diplomatic immunity continues to provide a means, albeit imperfect, to safeguard diplomatic personnel from any animosity that might arise between nations. As one article put it: &quot;So why do we agree to a system in which we're dependent on a foreign country's whim before we can prosecute a criminal inside our own borders? The practical answer is: because we depend on other countries to honor our own diplomats' immunity just as scrupulously as we honor theirs.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.jinnah-institute.org/issues/252-raymond-davis-and-the-vienna-convention-<space/></arg><arg name="title">Raymond Davis and the Vienna Convention<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Jinnah-institute.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the United States, the Diplomatic Relations Act of 1978 (<template><target>UnitedStatesCode</target><arg>22</arg><arg>254a</arg></template><space/>et seq.) follows the principles introduced by the Vienna Conventions. The United States has had a tendency to be generous when granting diplomatic immunity to visiting diplomats, because a large number of U.S. diplomats work in host countries less protective of individual rights. If the United States were to punish a visiting diplomat without sufficient grounds, U.S. representatives in other countries could receive harsher treatment. If a person with immunity is alleged to have committed a crime or faces a civil lawsuit, the<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target><part>State Department</part></link><space/>asks the home country to waive immunity of the alleged offender so that the complaint can be moved to the courts. If immunity is not waived, prosecution cannot be undertaken. However, the State Department still has the discretion to ask the diplomat to withdraw from her or his duties. Often, the diplomat's visas are canceled; and the diplomat and her or his family may be barred from returning to the United States. Crimes committed by members of a diplomat's family can also result in dismissal.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.answers.com/topic/diplomatic-immunity<space/></arg><arg name="title">diplomatic immunity: West's Encyclopedia of American Law (Full Article) from<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Answers.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Exceptions to the Vienna Convention</heading><paragraph>Some countries have made reservations to the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations, but they are minor. A number of countries limit the diplomatic immunity of persons who are citizens of the receiving country. As nations keep faith to their treaties with differing zeal, other rules may also apply, though in most cases this summary is a reasonably accurate approximation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="title">List of Party States, Declarations and Reservations to Chapter III of the Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations of 18 April 1961<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://treaties.un.org/Pages/ViewDetails.aspx?src</arg><arg name="date">16 April 2011<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">UNITED NATIONS TREATY COLLECTION<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>The Convention does not cover the personnel of<space/><link><target>international organization</target><trail>s</trail></link>, whose privileges are decided upon on a case-by-case basis, usually in the<space/><link><target>Treaty</target><part>treaties</part></link><space/>founding such organizations. The United Nations system (including its agencies, which comprise the most recognizable international bodies such as the World Bank and many others) has a relatively standardized form of limited immunities for staff traveling on<space/><link><target>United Nations laissez-passer</target><part>U.N. laissez-passer</part></link>; diplomatic immunity is often granted to the highest-ranking officials of these agencies. Consular officials (that do not have concurrent diplomatic accreditation) formally have a more limited form of immunity, generally limited to their official duties. Diplomatic technical and administrative staff also have more limited immunity under the Vienna Convention; for this reason, some countries may accredit technical and administrative staff as<space/><link><target>attach</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Other categories of government officials that may travel frequently to other countries may not have diplomatic passports or diplomatic immunity, such as members of the military, high-ranking government officials, ministers, and others. Many countries provide non-diplomatic official passports to such personnel, and there may be different classes of such travel documents such as official passports, service passports, and others. De facto recognition of some form of immunity may be conveyed by states accepting officials traveling on such documents, or there may exist bilateral agreements to govern such cases (as in, for example, the case of military personnel conducting or observing exercises on the territory of the receiving country).</paragraph><paragraph>Formally, diplomatic immunity may be limited to officials accredited to a host country, or traveling to or from their host country. In practice, many countries may effectively recognize diplomatic immunity for those traveling on diplomatic passports, with admittance to the country constituting acceptance of the diplomatic status.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Abuse</heading><paragraph>In reality, most diplomats are representatives of nations with a tradition of professional<space/><link><target>civil service</target></link>, and are expected to obey regulations governing their behaviour and they suffer strict internal consequences (disciplinary action) if they flout local laws. In many nations, a professional diplomat's career may be compromised if they (or members of their family) disobey the local authorities or cause serious embarrassment, and such cases are, at any rate, a violation of the spirit of the Vienna Conventions.</paragraph><paragraph>The Vienna Convention is explicit that &quot;without prejudice to their privileges and immunities, it is the duty of all persons enjoying such privileges and immunities to respect the laws and regulations of the receiving State.&quot; Nevertheless, on some occasions, diplomatic immunity leads to some unfortunate results; protected diplomats have violated laws (including those that would be violations at home as well) of the host country and that country has been essentially limited to informing the diplomat's nation that the diplomat is no longer welcome (<italics><link><target>persona non grata</target></link></italics>). Diplomatic agents are not, however, exempt from the jurisdiction of their home state, and hence prosecution may be undertaken by the sending state; for minor violations of the law, the sending state may impose administrative procedures specific to the foreign service or diplomatic mission.</paragraph><paragraph>Violation of the law by diplomats has included<space/><link><target>espionage</target></link>, smuggling,<space/><link><target>child custody</target></link><space/>law violations, tax evasion, making terrorist threats,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.slate.com/articles/news_and_politics/explainer/2010/04/cant_touch_this.html</arg><arg name="title">Can't Touch This: How far does diplomatic immunity go?</arg><arg name="author">Christopher Beam</arg><arg name="date">Apr 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Slate.com</arg></template></extension><space/>slavery, preying on children over the Internet for sex,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reader's Digest"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.rd.com/advice/diplomatic-immunity-going-too-far/</arg><arg name="title">The Untouchables: Is Diplomatic Immunity Going Too Far?</arg><arg name="publisher">Reader's Digest</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>murder</target></link>: In<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>in 1984, policewoman<space/><link><target>Yvonne Fletcher</target></link><space/>was killed on the street by a person shooting from inside the<space/><link><target>Libyan Embassy in London</target><part>Libyan embassy</part></link>. The incident caused a breakdown in<space/><link><target>diplomatic relations</target></link><space/>until Libya admitted &quot;general responsibility&quot; in 1999.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/april/17/newsid_2488000/2488369.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">1984: Libyan embassy shots kill policewoman<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 April 1984<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2010</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Drug smuggling</heading><paragraph>Diplomats and officials involved in drug smuggling have benefited from diplomatic immunity. For example, a Venezuelan general wanted in the United States on drugs charges and arrested in Aruba was released after the Venezuelan government protested his diplomatic immunity and threatened sanctions if Aruba did not release him.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Netherlands Says Venezuelan Detained in Aruba Has Immunity<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.wsj.com/articles/netherlands-rules-venezuelan-detained-in-aruba-has-diplomatic-immunity-1406505987<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">14 December 2014<space/></arg><arg name="agency">WSJ<space/></arg><arg name="date">27 July 2014<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl">yes<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl">https://web.archive.org/20150710115148/http://www.wsj.com/articles/netherlands-rules-venezuelan-detained-in-aruba-has-diplomatic-immunity-1406505987<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate">10 July 2015<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-plans-sanctions-on-some-venezuelan-officials-1406697081</arg><arg name="title">U.S. Plans Sanctions on Some Venezuelan Officials</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 March 2015</arg><arg name="date">30 July 2014</arg><arg name="agency">WSJ</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Employer abuse and slavery</heading><paragraph>Diplomatic immunity from local employment and labor law when employing staff from the host country has precipitated abuse. Local staff are employed where local knowledge is needed (such as an administrative assistant, press/PR officer), or as menial staff like a cleaner, maid or mechanic. When the employer is a diplomat, the employees are in a legal limbo where the laws of neither the host country nor the diplomat's country are enforceable, so that an abusive diplomat employer can act with virtual impunity. Diplomats have ignored local laws concerning<space/><link><target>minimum wage</target><trail>s</trail></link>, maximum working hours, vacation and holidays. The worst abusers have imprisoned the employees in their homes, deprived them of their earned wages,<space/><link><target>passport</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and communication with the outside world, abused them physically and emotionally, deprived them of food and invaded their privacy.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.commondreams.org/cgi-bin/newsprint.cgi?file</arg><arg name="title">ACLU: Abused Domestic Workers of Diplomats Seek Justice From International Commission<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Commondreams.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">15 November 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aclu.org/womensrights/humanrights/28030prs20070117.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">American Civil Liberties Union: ACLU Charges Kuwait Government and Diplomats With Abusing Domestic Workers<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Aclu.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 January 2007<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>Reported incidents include the following:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1999, a Bangladeshi woman, Shamela Begum, claimed she had been enslaved by a senior Bahraini envoy to the UN and his wife. Begum charged that the couple took her passport, struck her, and paid her just $800 for ten months of service during which she was only twice allowed out of the couples New York apartment. The envoy and his wife claimed diplomatic immunity, and Begum later reached a civil settlement with her employers. By some estimates, &quot;hundreds of women have been exploited by their diplomat employers over the past 20 years.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reader's Digest"></extension></listitem><listitem>In 2003 in Finland, a Filipino maid escaped from an embassy of an unidentified Asian country, and reported being held in conditions approaching slavery: she was forced to work from 7 am. to 10 pm., 7 days a week, and the ambassador's children were permitted to hit her. On grounds of diplomatic immunity, no charges could be filed.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iltalehti.fi/uutiset/201312140065720_uu.shtml'>Skandaali Suomessa: Suurlhettils piti naista orjatiss | Kotimaan uutiset | Iltalehti.fi</link></extension></listitem><listitem>In 2009,<space/><link><target>South Africa</target></link><space/>was criticised for claiming immunity from labor laws relating to a<space/><link><target>Ukrainians</target><part>Ukrainian</part></link><space/><link><target>domestic worker</target></link><space/>at the residence of the South African ambassador to Ireland in<space/><link><target>Dublin</target><part>Ireland</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.irishtimes.com/newspaper/letters/2009/1130/1224259709379.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Use of diplomatic immunity<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Irishtimes.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">11 November 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In 2010, the<space/><link><target>American Civil Liberties Union</target></link><space/>filed an<space/><link><target>amicus brief</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics>Swarna v. Al-Awadi</italics><space/>to argue that<space/><link><target>human trafficking</target></link><space/>is a commercial activity engaged in for personal<space/><link><target>Profit (economics)</target><part>profit</part></link>, which falls outside the scope of a diplomats official functions, and therefore diplomatic immunity does not apply.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aclu.org/womens-rights/swarna-v-al-awadi-amicus-brief<space/></arg><arg name="title">American Civil Liberties Union: Swarna v. Al-Awadi – Amicus Brief<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Aclu.org<space/></arg><arg name="date">16 February 2010<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><space/>An appeals court ruled that Al-Awadi did not have diplomatic immunity in that situation.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">U.S. Appeals Court Affirms Kuwait Immunity, Rejects Ex-Diplomat Immunity, in Abuse of Domestic Worker Case</arg><arg name="url">http://diplomaticlaw.com/blog/2010/10/u-s-appeals-court-affirms-kuwait-immunity-rejects-ex-diplomat-immunity-in-abuse-of-domestic-worker-case/</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 July 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In December 2013, Indian consular official<space/><link><target>Devyani Khobragade incident</target><part>Devyani Khobragade</part></link><space/>was detained, hand-cuffed, strip searched, DNA swabbed and held in a federal holding cell in New York, relating to allegations of non-payment of U.S. minimum wage and for fraudulently lying about the wages to be paid on a visa application for her domestic worker. India registered a strong protest and initiated a review of privileges afforded to American consular officials in India as a result.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.cnn.com/2013/12/20/politics/india-us-diplomat/<space/></arg><arg name="work">CNN<space/></arg><arg name="title">India's foreign minister: Drop charges against diplomat - CNN.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">20 December 2013</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 8 September 2015, two Nepalese women were rescued from the fifth floor of Gurgaon residence of a<space/><link><target>Saudi Arabia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>diplomat in India. They were allegedly confined there and abused physically and sexually by the diplomat and his family and friends.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last1">NDTV</arg><arg name="first1">NDTV</arg><arg name="title">Focus on Saudi Diplomat After Women Allege Gang-Rape, Torture</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ndtv.com/india-news/2-women-allegedly-raped-rescued-from-saudi-diplomats-gurgaon-home-1215651?utm_source</arg><arg name="accessdate">9 September 2015</arg><arg name="agency">NDTV</arg><arg name="publisher">NDTV</arg></template></extension><space/>The women were rescued in a police raid planned after the police received a letter from the Nepal embassy regarding their plight. Several persons, the Saudi diplomat among them, were booked for wrongful confinement and gang rape. Saudi Ambassador Saud Mohammed Alsati commented, &quot;This is completely false. We would not like to comment any further since the case is under investigation by the Indian police.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://indianexpress.com/article/india/india-others/saudi-diplomat-booked-for-gangrape-police-free-woman-daughter-from-his-gurgaon-home/</arg><arg name="title">Saudi diplomat booked for gangrape, police free woman, daughter from his Gurgaon residence</arg><arg name="date">September 11, 2015</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Indian Express]]</arg></template></extension><space/>Ten days after the diplomat was accused, it was confirmed that he had left India.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://indianexpress.com/article/india/india-others/gurgaon-rape-case-saudi-arabian-diplomat-leaves-india/</arg><arg name="title">Gurgaon rape case: Accused of rape, Saudi diplomat gets away to Saudi Arabia</arg><arg name="date">September 17, 2015</arg><arg name="newspaper">[[Indian Express]]</arg></template></extension></listitem></list><heading level='3'>Vehicular</heading><heading level='4'>Parking violations</heading><paragraph>A particular problem is the difficulty in enforcing ordinary laws, such as prohibitions on<space/><link><target>double parking</target></link>. For example, the<space/><link><target>Autobahn 555</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Cologne</target></link>, Germany was nicknamed the &quot;Diplomatenrennbahn&quot; (Diplomatic Raceway), back when Bonn was the capital of<space/><link><target>West Germany</target></link>, because of the numerous diplomats that used to speed through the highway under diplomatic immunity. Certain cities, e.g.,<space/><link><target>The Hague</target></link>, have taken to impounding such cars rather than fining their owners. Diplomats' status does not guarantee the release of impounded cars.</paragraph><paragraph>Diplomatic missions have their own regulations, but many require their staff to pay any fines due for parking violations. A 2006 economic study found that there was a significant correlation between home-country<space/><link><target>Political corruption</target><part>corruption</part></link><space/>(as measured by<space/><link><target>Transparency International</target></link>) and unpaid parking fines: six countries had in excess of 100 violations per diplomat:<space/><link><target>Kuwait</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Egypt</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chad</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Sudan</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Bulgaria</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mozambique</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="first"><space/>Ray<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Fisman<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Edward<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Miguel<space/></arg><arg name="title">Cultures of Corruption: Evidence from Diplomatic Parking tickets<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.usc.edu/schools/business/FBE/seminars/papers/AE_4-28-06_FISMAN-parking.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="date">28 April 2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">USC FBE APPLIED ECONOMICS WORKSHOP<space/></arg><arg name="id"><space/></arg><arg name="postscript"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>In particular,<space/><link><target>New York City</target></link>, the home of the<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link><space/>Headquarters, regularly protests to the<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target></link><space/>about non-payment of parking tickets because of diplomatic status. As of 2001, the city had more than 200,000 outstanding parking tickets from diplomats, totaling more than $21.3 million, of which only $160,682 had been collected.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JOHN J. GOLDMAN"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/2001/jul/03/news/mn-18122</arg><arg name="title">NYC's Diplomatic Take on Tickets</arg><arg name="date">2001-07-03</arg><arg name="author">JOHN J. GOLDMAN</arg><arg name="publisher">Los Angeles Times</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1997, then-mayor<space/><link><target>Rudy Giuliani</target></link><space/>proposed to the<space/><link><target>Clinton administration</target></link><space/>that the U.S. State Department revoke the special DPL plates for diplomats who ignore parking summonses; the State Department denied Giuliani's request.<extension extension_name='ref' name="JOHN J. GOLDMAN"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In cities that impose a<space/><link><target>Congestion pricing</target><part>congestion charge</part></link>, the decision of some diplomatic missions not to furnish payment has proved controversial. In London, embassies have amassed approximately 58 million in unpaid charges as of 2012, with the American embassy comprising approximately 6 million and the Russian, German and Japanese missions around 2 million each.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-politics-18725937<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="work">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="title">Diplomats 'owe £58m in London congestion charges'<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 July 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.london.gov.uk/media/press_releases_mayoral/new-york-times-urges-us-embassy-pay-congestion-charge<space/></arg><arg name="title">New York Times urges US Embassy to pay congestion charge &#124; Greater London Authority<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">London.gov.uk<space/></arg><arg name="date">31 March 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Drunk driving and vehicular assault</heading><paragraph>In January 1997, Gueorgui Makharadze, a high-ranking<space/><link><target>Republic of Georgia</target></link><space/>diplomat, caused a five-car pileup on<space/><link><target>Dupont Circle</target></link><space/>near<space/><link><target>Embassy Row</target></link><space/>that killed a 16-year-old<space/><link><target>Maryland</target></link><space/>girl. Makharadze's claim of diplomatic immunity created a national outrage in the United States, particularly given Makharadze's previous record of driving offenses: in April 1996, Makharadze had been charged with speeding in Virginia, and four months later, he was detained by District of Columbia police on suspicion of drunk driving.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1997/10/09/us/georgian-diplomat-pleads-guilty-in-death-of-teen-age-girl.html</arg><arg name="title">Georgian Diplomat Pleads Guilty in Death of Teenage Girl</arg><arg name="author">MICHAEL JANOFSKY</arg><arg name="date">1997-10-09</arg><arg name="publisher">New York Times</arg></template></extension><space/>In both prior cases, charges were dismissed based on his immunity. On the basis of the media coverage, Georgia revoked Makharadze's immunity, and he was ultimately sentenced to seven years in prison after pleading guilty to one count of involuntary manslaughter and four counts of aggravated assault.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/1997/dec/20/news/mn-531</arg><arg name="title">Ex-Diplomat Gets 7 Years for Death of Teen in Crash</arg><arg name="author">Associated Press</arg><arg name="date">1997-12-20</arg><arg name="publisher">Los Angeles Times</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2001, a Russian diplomat, Andrei Knyazev, hit and killed a woman while driving drunk in Ottawa. Knyazev refused to take a breathalyzer at the scene of the crash, citing diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CBC News"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.cbc.ca/news/world/former-russian-diplomat-guilty-of-involuntary-manslaughter-1.313443</arg><arg name="title">Former Russian diplomat guilty of involuntary manslaughter</arg><arg name="date">2002-03-19</arg><arg name="publisher">CBC News</arg></template></extension><space/>Russia refused Canadian requests to waive his immunity, and Knyazev was expelled from Canada. Though the Russian Foreign Ministry fired him and charged him with involuntary manslaughter, and Russian and Canadian authorities cooperated in the investigation, the case caused a political storm in Canada. Many accused the Foreign Ministry of incompetence after it emerged that Knyazev had twice been previously investigated for drunk driving. The Canadian Foreign Minister had fought unsuccessfully to have Knyazev tried in Ottawa.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://articles.latimes.com/2001/feb/17/news/mn-26623</arg><arg name="title">Russia Says Diplomat Will Be Tried in Drunk-Driving Case</arg><arg name="author"></arg><arg name="date">2001-02-17</arg><arg name="publisher">Los Angeles Times</arg></template></extension><space/>In 2002, Knyazev was found guilty of involuntary manslaughter in Russia.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CBC News"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Financial abuse</heading><paragraph>Historically, the problem of large debts run up by diplomats has also caused many problems. Some financial institutions do not extend credit to diplomats because they have no legal means of ensuring the money be repaid. Local citizens and businesses are often at a disadvantage when filing civil claims against a diplomat, especially in cases of unpaid rent, alimony, and child support.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Rents</heading><paragraph>The bulk of diplomatic debt lies in the rental of office space and living quarters. Individual debts can range from a few thousand dollars to $1 million in back rent. A group of diplomats and the office space in which they work are referred to as a<space/><link><target>diplomatic mission</target></link>. Creditors cannot sue missions individually to collect money they owe. Landlords and creditors have found that the only thing they can do is contact a city agency to see if they can try to get some money back. They cannot enter the offices or apartments of diplomats to evict them because the<space/><link><target>Foreign Sovereign Immunities Act</target></link><space/>says that &quot;the property in the United States of a foreign state shall be immune from attachment, arrest and execution&quot; (<template><target>UnitedStatesCode</target><arg>28</arg><arg>1609</arg></template>). This has led creditors who are owed money by diplomats to become more cautious about their renters and to change their rental or payment policies.</paragraph><paragraph>In one case, for example, officials from Zaire stopped paying rent to their private landlord and ran up $400,000 in debt. When the landlord sued, the U.S. State Department defended the Zaireans on the basis of diplomatic immunity, and a circuit court agreed. When the landlord finally cut off the utilities, the officials fled without paying their back rent. The landlords reportedly later reached an &quot;amicable agreement&quot; with the Zaire government.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Reader's Digest"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Alimony and child support</heading><paragraph>The issue of abusing diplomatic immunity in family relations, especially<space/><link><target>alimony</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>child support</target></link>, has become so widespread that it prompted discussion at the 1995 U.N. Fourth World Conference on Women, in Beijing. Historically, the United Nations has not become involved with family disputes and has refused to garnish the wages of diplomats who owe money for child support, citing Sovereign Immunity. However, in September 1995, the incumbent head of Legal Affairs for the United Nations acknowledged there was a moral and legal obligation to take at least a partial responsibility in family disputes. Fathers working as diplomats who refused to fulfil their family-related financial duties were increasing in numbers in the United Nations: several men who had left their wives and children were still claiming U.N. dependency, travel, and education allowances for their families, though they are no longer supporting those families.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com/Diplomatic+Immunity<space/></arg><arg name="title">Diplomatic Immunity legal definition of Diplomatic Immunity. Diplomatic Immunity synonyms by the Free Online Law Dictionary<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Legal-dictionary.thefreedictionary.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">19 July 1988<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Taxes and fees</heading><paragraph>Diplomats are exempt from most taxes, but not from &quot;charges levied for specific services rendered&quot;. In certain cases, whether a payment is or is not considered a tax may be disputed, such as<space/><link><target>central London</target></link>'s<space/><link><target>congestion charge</target></link>. In August 2009, it was reported that the Government of the UK believed the United States owed 3,500,000<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/politics/2009/aug/17/obama-ambassador-london-congestion-charge<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Guardian<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="title">Obama's ambassador to London will not pay congestion charge backlog<space/></arg><arg name="first">Hélène<space/></arg><arg name="last">Mulholland<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 August 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>in unpaid congestion charge fees.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>The Information: Diplomats Who Skip The Congestion Charge<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.ft.com/cms/s/0/e933c746-70ad-11dd-b514-0000779fd18c.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Financial Times<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>23 August 2008<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>13 March 2009<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>It was reported in 2006 that the UAE embassy had agreed to pay their own accumulated charges of nearly 100,000.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Embassy to pay congestion charge<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/london/4881442.stm<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>6 April 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>28 March 2007<space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>There is an obligation for the receiving State not to &quot;discriminate as between states&quot;; in other words, any such fees should be payable by all accredited diplomats equally. This may allow the<space/><link><target>diplomatic corps</target></link><space/>to negotiate as a group with the authorities of the receiving country.</paragraph><paragraph>Diplomats are exempt from<space/><link><target>import duty</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>tariffs</target></link><space/>for items for their personal use. In some countries, this has led to charges that diplomatic agents are profiting personally from resale of &quot;tax free&quot; goods. The receiving state may choose to impose restrictions on what may reasonably constitute personal use (for example, only a certain quantity of<space/><link><target>cigarette</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>per day). When enacted, such restrictions are generally quite generous so as to avoid<space/><link><target>Tit for tat</target><part>tit-for-tat</part></link><space/>responses.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Other incidents concerning diplomatic immunity</heading><paragraph><template><target>indiscriminate list</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">September 2015</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>In 1967, the<space/><link><target>Burma</target><part>Burmese</part></link><space/>Ambassador to Sri Lanka shot his wife as she got out of the car after seeing a nightclub bandmember of whom she was enamoured. The next morning, neighbours saw the Ambassador building a<space/><link><target>pyre</target></link><space/>on the back lawn. When the police were called, the Ambassador opened the metal front gates just enough to say that there was no trouble and to remind them that his house was Burmese territory. He later emerged with the body of his wife, placed it on the pyre and set it alight. He was &quot;well connected at home but after an awkward interval he was recalled&quot; from his position.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Police probe death of Burma envoy's wife</arg><arg name="url">http://eresources.nlb.gov.sg/newspapers/Digitised/Article/straitstimes19671017-1.2.19.8.aspx</arg><arg name="work">Mrs.Shirley Boonwaat murder case</arg><arg name="agency">The Straits Times</arg><arg name="issue">The Straits Times, 17 December 1967, Page 3</arg><arg name="publisher">National Library Board Singapore</arg><arg name="date">17 October 1967</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>In his memoirs,<space/><link><target>Gerald Hensley</target></link>, a former<space/><link><target>New Zealand</target></link><space/><link><target>diplomacy</target><part>diplomat</part></link>, recalled a Sudanese delegate to the UN who &quot;had been sued for paternity by a night club singer in New York and had had to invoke diplomatic immunity where the reproductive kind had failed.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link type='external' href='http://books.google.co.uk/books?id=Q3N0AAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;q=pyre#search_anchor'>Final Approaches: A Memoir</link></italics><space/>by<space/><link><target>Gerald Hensley</target></link><space/>(2006, Auckland University Press, NZ) ISBN 1-86940-378-9, pages 220-221,64</extension></listitem><listitem>In 1984, Libyan dissidents protested outside the Libyan embassy in<space/><link><target>London</target></link>. British policewoman<space/><link><target>Murder of Yvonne Fletcher</target><part>Yvonne Fletcher</part></link><space/>was killed by gunshots originating from the embassy. To date, the identity of the gunman has never been confirmed and the Libyan authorities made no effort to identify the culprit nor reveal whether the culprit was ever punished. Two years later, the incident became a major factor in Prime Minister<space/><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target></link>'s decision to allow<space/><link><target>President of the United States</target><part>U.S. President</part></link><space/><link><target>Ronald Reagan</target></link><space/>to launch the<space/><link><target>Bombing of Libya (1986)</target><part>U.S. bombing of Libya in 1986</part></link><space/>from American bases in the United Kingdom.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>citation</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.margaretthatcher.org/speeches/displaydocument.asp?docid</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Margaret<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Thatcher<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Statement on US bombing of Libya</arg></template>.</extension></listitem><listitem>In 1987, in New York City, 9-year-old Terrence Karamba was placed by the Human Resources Administration in a foster home after his elementary school teachers noticed suspicious scars and injuries. He and his 7-year-old sister, who was also placed in City custody, told officials the wounds had been inflicted by their father, Floyd Karamba, an Administrative Attache at the Zimbabwean Mission to the U.N. No charges were filed, as Mr. Karamba had diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/1988/01/01/nyregion/court-won-t-bar-return-of-boy-in-abuse-case-to-zimbabwe.html?pagewanted</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="first">Mark A.<space/></arg><arg name="last">Uhlig<space/></arg><arg name="title">Court Won't Bar Return of Boy In Abuse Case to Zimbabwe<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 January 1988</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 27 October 1998, in<space/><link><target>Vladivostok</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>, Douglas Kent, the American<space/><link><target>Consul (representative)#Consul general</target><part>Consul General</part></link><space/>to Russia, was involved in a car accident that left a young man, Alexander Kashin, disabled. Kent was not prosecuted in a U.S. court. Under the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Consular Relations</target><part>Vienna Convention</part></link>, diplomatic immunity does not apply to civil actions relating to vehicular accidents, but in 2006, the<space/><link><target>United States courts of appeals</target><part>U.S. Court of Appeals</part></link><space/>ruled that, since he was using his vehicle for consular purposes, Kent could not be sued civilly.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Immunity shelters former US Consul from Russian invalid<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://vn.vladnews.ru/issue531/Crime_watch/Immunity_shelters_former_US_Consul_from_Russian_invalid<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Vladivostok News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 August 2006</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Russia student in diplomatic controversy<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://media.www.dailylobo.com/media/storage/paper344/news/2002/09/16/News/Russia.Student.In.Diplomatic.Controversy-274101.shtml<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>New Mexico daily Lobo, From AP<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>16 September 2002</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On February 1999 in<space/><link><target>Vancouver</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Canada</target></link>, Kazuko Shimokoji, wife of the Japanese Consul-General, showed up at the ER of a city hospital with two black eyes and a bruised neck. She told doctors that her husband had beaten her. When local police questioned her husband, Mr. Shimokoji said, &quot;Yes, I punched her out and she deserved it&quot;, and described the incident as &quot;a cultural thing and not a big deal.&quot; Although an arrest warrant was issued, Mr. Shimokoji could not be arrested due to his diplomatic immunity. However, his statement to the police found wide echo in both the local and Japanese press. The subsequent public uproar prompted the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs to waive Mr. Shimokoji's immunity. Though he pled guilty in Canadian court, he was given an absolute discharge. Nonetheless, he was recalled to Japan where he was reassigned to office duty and had his pay cut.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Wife-beating diplomat ordered home<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cbc.ca/news/canada/story/1999/03/04/japan990304.html<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>CBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>4 March 1999</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 3 December 2004, in<space/><link><target>Bucharest, Romania</target></link>, Christopher Van Goethem, an American<space/><link><target>Marine (military)</target><part>Marine</part></link><space/>serving his embassy, ran a red traffic signal, collided with a taxi, and killed popular Romanian musician<space/><link><target>Teo Peter</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>People in the News, May 2005<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.vivid.ro/vivid72/pages72/people_in_the_news72.htm<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Vivid — Romania through international eyes</arg></template></extension><space/>Van Goethem's blood alcohol content was estimated at 0.09% from a<space/><link><target>breathalyser</target></link><space/>test, but he refused to give a blood sample for further testing and left for<space/><link><target>Germany</target></link><space/>before charges could be filed in Romania.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>"Compact" band bass-player, killed in a car accident caused by a US Embassy employee<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.nineoclock.ro/archive_index.php?page</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Nine O'Clock</arg><arg name="date"><space/>6 December 2004<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>29 November 2007</arg></template><space/><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">September 2010</arg><arg name="bot">H3llBot</arg></template></extension><space/>The Romanian government requested the American government to lift his immunity, which it refused to do. In a<space/><link><target>court-martial</target></link>, he was acquitted of<space/><link><target>manslaughter</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>adultery</target></link><space/>(which is still a court martial offence) but was convicted of<space/><link><target>obstruction of justice</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>making false statements</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://useu.usmission.gov/Article.asp?ID</arg><arg name="title">USEU: U.S. Military Law Expert Explains Verdict in Romanian Death</arg><arg name="date">20090108081030</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 13 November 2006, in New York City, Fred Matwanga, Kenyan diplomat to the U.N., was taken into police custody by officers responding to reports that he had assaulted his son; he was released after asserting diplomat immunity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Location Settings<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.news24.com/Africa/News/Abusive-Kenyan-diplomat-probed-20061114<space/></arg><arg name="title">'Abusive' Kenyan diplomat probed<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">News24<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 November 2006<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/14/nyregion/14mbrfs-QUEENSCUSTOD_BRF.html?_r</arg><arg name="work">The New York Times<space/></arg><arg name="title">Queens: Custody Battle Over Diplomat's Children<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 November 2006</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 24 April 2008, in<space/><link><target>New Orleans</target></link>, Mexican<space/><link><target>press attach</target></link><space/>Rafael Quintero Curiel was seen stealing<space/><link><target>BlackBerry</target></link><space/><link><target>Personal digital assistant</target><part>PDA</part></link><space/>units from a<space/><link><target>White House</target></link><space/>press meeting room. Quintero made it all the way to the airport before members of the<space/><link><target>United States Secret Service</target></link><space/>caught up with him. He initially denied taking the devices, but after being confronted with security video, Quintero claimed it was purely accidental, gave the devices back, claimed diplomatic immunity and left New Orleans with the Mexican delegation. He was eventually fired for the incident.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Fox News Channel</target><part>FoxNews.com</part></link><space/><link type='external' href='http://www.foxnews.com/story/0,2933,352378,00.html'>Mexican Embassy: Official Fired After Getting Caught With White House BlackBerries</link></extension></listitem><listitem>On 9 December 2009, in<space/><link><target>Tanzania</target></link>, Canadian<space/><link><target>Envoy (title)</target><part>Junior Envoy</part></link><space/>Jean Touchette was arrested after it was reported that he spat at a traffic police officer on duty in the middle of a<space/><link><target>traffic jam</target></link><space/>in the Banana district on the outskirts of<space/><link><target>Dar es Salaam</target></link>. Canada's<space/><link><target>High Commissioner</target></link>, Robert Orr, was summoned by the Tanzanian<space/><link><target>Foreign Minister</target><part>Foreign Ministry</part></link><space/>over the incident, and the junior envoy was later recalled.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/8411431.stm<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[BBC News]]<space/></arg><arg name="title">Canada recalls spitting diplomat<space/></arg><arg name="date">14 December 2009<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">1 May 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.iol.co.za/index.php?from=rss_Africa&amp;amp;set_id=1&amp;amp;click_id=68&amp;amp;art_id=nw20091214222225370C993592'>Tanzania irked by spitting envoy</link><space/>15 December 2009</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.canadainternational.gc.ca/tanzania-tanzanie/highlights-faits/PressReleaseDec13-09.aspx?lang=en'>The Canadian High Commission Regrets The Incident Involving One Of Its Officials</link><space/><link><target>Government of Canada</target></link></extension></listitem><listitem>On 15 December 2009, in Singapore, the<space/><link><target>Romania</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/><link><target>charg d'affaires</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Silviu Ionescu</target></link>, was allegedly behind a<space/><link><target>2009 Singapore Romanian diplomat incident</target><part>drunk-driving hit-and-run accident</part></link><space/>that killed a 30-year-old man and seriously injured two others. He left Singapore for Romania three days after the accident.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.channelnewsasia.com/stories/singaporelocalnews/view/1042671/1/.html</arg><arg name="title">Former Romanian diplomat "could be criminally involved"</arg><arg name="last">Leong</arg><arg name="first">Wee Keat</arg><arg name="date">10 March 2010</arg><arg name="work">[[Channel NewsAsia]]</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.straitstimes.com/BreakingNews/Singapore/Story/STIStory_498208.html</arg><arg name="title">I was sent 'flying' : Traffic video shows car swerving and hitting him; teen landed 10m away<space/></arg><arg name="date">5 March 2010</arg><arg name="work">The Straits Times</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2010</arg><arg name="author">Teh Joo Lin & Elena Chong</arg></template></extension><space/>The Romanian foreign ministry suspended Ionescu from his post.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.straitstimes.com/BreakingNews/Singapore/Story/STIStory_494014.html</arg><arg name="title">Romanian Embassy responds to MFA<space/></arg><arg name="date">23 February 2010</arg><arg name="work">The Straits Times</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>A coroner's inquiry in Singapore, which included testimony by the Romanian embassy driver, concluded that Ionescu was solely responsible for the accident.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.straitstimes.com/BreakingNews/Singapore/Story/STIStory_509148.html</arg><arg name="title">Coroner blames envoy<space/></arg><arg name="author">Elena Chong & Teh Joo Lin<space/></arg><arg name="date">1 April 2010</arg><arg name="publisher">The Straits Times</arg><arg name="accessdate">1 April 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>An<space/><link><target>Interpol notice</target><part>Interpol Red Notice</part></link><space/>was subsequently issued for his arrest and possible extradition<space/><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.interpol.int/public/data/wanted/notices/data/2010/56/2010_15456.asp</extension><space/>notwithstanding the fact that Romania had not waived his diplomatic immunity and had commenced criminal proceedings against him in Romania.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.mediafax.ro/english/romania-keeps-singapore-updated-on-steps-taken-in-criminal-case-of-fmr-envoy-ionescu-fm-5849023/</arg><arg name="title">Romania Keeps Singapore Updated On Steps Taken In Criminal Case Of Fmr Envoy Ionescu – FM</arg><arg name="publisher">Mediafax</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 April 2010</arg></template></extension><space/>The Singapore government argued that by reason of Article 39(2) of the Vienna Convention, Ionescu was no longer protected by diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.asiaone.com/News/AsiaOne%2BNews/Singapore/Story/A1Story20100415-210575.html</arg><arg name="title">Ex-envoy not protected by immunity</arg><arg name="date">15 April 2010</arg><arg name="work">Asiaone</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 April 2010</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.singaporelawwatch.sg/remweb/legal/ln2/rss/legalnews/67143.html?utm_source</arg><arg name="title">No diplomatic immunity for Ionescu: MFA</arg><arg name="date">16 April 2010</arg><arg name="work">Singapore Law Watch</arg><arg name="accessdate">16 April 2010</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In April 2010, a<space/><link><target>Qatar</target><trail>i</trail></link><space/>diplomat was arrested for having smoked in the toilet on a US-bound flight and having joked (upon questioning) that he was trying to light his shoe, a reference to the shoe-bomber<space/><link><target>Richard Reid</target></link>. Two<space/><link><target>F-16</target></link><space/>fighter jets had been scrambled to follow the airplane as a result.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2010/apr/08/qatari-diplomat-smoking-plane-scare<space/></arg><arg name="location">London<space/></arg><arg name="work">The Guardian<space/></arg><arg name="first">James<space/></arg><arg name="last">Meikle<space/></arg><arg name="title">US national security defence defense, US news, Airline industry (business sector), Air transport (News) ,World news, Business<space/></arg><arg name="date">8 April 2010</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 27 January 2011, in<space/><link><target>Lahore</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link>, an American embassy employee,<space/><link><target>Raymond Allen Davis incident</target><part>Raymond Allen Davis</part></link>, shot and killed two Pakistani civilians, while a third man was struck and killed by a U.S. consulate car responding to the shooting. According to Davis, they were about to rob him and he acted in self-defense. When detained by police, Davis claimed to be a consultant at the U.S. consulate in Lahore. He was formally arrested and remanded into custody. Further investigations revealed that he was working with the CIA as a contractor in Pakistan. U.S. State Department declared him a diplomat and repeatedly requested immunity under the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</target></link>, to which Pakistan is a signatory.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://islamabad.usembassy.gov/pr-11012901.html'>U.S. Embassy Calls for Release of American Diplomat U.S. Embassy, Islamabad, Pakistan</link><space/><template><target>wayback</target><arg name="url">http://islamabad.usembassy.gov/pr-11012901.html<space/></arg><arg name="date">20110201133320<space/></arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://edition.cnn.com/2011/WORLD/meast/02/04/pakistan.us.shooting.index.html'></link><template><target>Dead link</target><arg name="date">April 2011</arg><arg name="bot">RjwilmsiBot</arg></template></extension><space/></listitem><listitem>On 10 April 2011, in<space/><link><target>Islamabad</target></link>, Pakistan, Patrick Kibuta, an electrical engineer in the<space/><link><target>United Nations Military Observer Group in India and Pakistan</target></link><space/>caused a vehicle collision with another vehicle, while under the influence of alcohol. Kibuta, who was driving in the opposing lane, injured a Canadian citizen residing in Islamabad, who suffered multiple fractures and required surgery. The Kohsar police impounded Mr. Kibuta's U.N. vehicle on the scene, and a blood test confirmed that he had an elevated blood alcohol level. Charges for reckless and drunken driving were filed against Kibuta, who enjoyed diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dawn.com/2011/04/13/un-official-booked-for-accident-3.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">UN official booked for accident &#124; Provinces<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Dawn.Com<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 April 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.dailytimes.com.pk/default.asp?page</arg><arg name="title">Leading News Resource of Pakistan<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Daily Times<space/></arg><arg name="date">13 April 2011<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2011</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>In April 2012, in<space/><link><target>Manila</target></link>, Panamanian diplomat Erick Bairnals Shcks was accused of raping a 19-year-old<space/><link><target>Filipino people</target><part>Filipino</part></link><space/>woman, but was later released from detention because Shcks &quot;enjoys protection under the 1961 Vienna Convention&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Panamanian diplomat in alleged rape case enjoys diplomatic immunity"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">singh</arg><arg name="first">amoulin</arg><arg name="title">Panama diplomat in alleged rape case has full immunity</arg><arg name="url">http://www.gmanetwork.com/news/story/257821/news/nation/dfa-panama-diplomat-in-alleged-rape-case-has-full-immunity</arg><arg name="publisher">[[GMA News]]</arg><arg name="date">11 May 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 16 August 2012, it was alleged by the Ecuadorian embassy that the<space/><link><target>Government of the United Kingdom</target></link><space/>threatened to revoke the diplomatic status of the<space/><link><target>embassy</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Ecuador</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>in order to arrest<space/><link><target>Julian Assange</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Julian Assange: UK 'threat' to arrest Wikileaks founder"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Julian Assange: UK 'threat' to arrest Wikileaks founder</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-19259623</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC]]</arg><arg name="date">16 August 2012</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On 14 February 2013, a vehicle bearing diplomatic plates registered to the US Embassy got into an accident in<space/><link><target>Islamabad</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pakistan</target></link><space/>involving two residents out of which one was killed and the other survived. Murder charges were laid under Section 320 of Pakistan Penal Code against the driver of the vehicle who is a diplomat according to Pakistani official.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.geo.tv/GeoDetail.aspx?ID=88111'>US diplomat faces murder charges for mowing down man | PAKISTAN - geo.tv</link></extension></listitem><listitem>On 18 March 2013, the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of India</target></link><space/>restricted Italian ambassador Daniele Mancini from leaving India for breaching an undertaking given to the apex court.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">India-Italy marines row: 'No legal immunity' for envoy Daniele Mancini</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-21826651</arg><arg name="work">BBC News: India</arg><arg name="publisher">BBC</arg><arg name="date">18 March 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Despite Italian and European Union protests regarding the restrictions as contrary to the<space/><link><target>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations</target></link>, the Supreme Court of India said it would be unacceptable to argue diplomatic immunity after voluntarily subjecting to court's jurisdiction. The Italian envoy had invoked Article 32 of the Constitution of India when filing an affidavit to the Supreme Court taking responsibility for the return of the two Italian marines to India after casting their votes in the March 2012 general elections in Italy. The Indian Supreme Court opined that the Italian ambassador had waived his diplomatic immunity and could be charged for contempt. The two marines are being tried in India for the murder of two Indian fishermen off the coast of Kerala (see the<space/><link><target>2012 Italian Navy Marines shooting incident in the Laccadive Sea</target></link>).</listitem><listitem>In July 2013, Joshua Walde, an American diplomat in Nairobi, Kenya, crashed into a mini-bus, killing one man and seriously injuring eight others, who were left with no financial assistance to pay for hospital bills.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCAug13"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://abcnews.go.com/International/wireStory/us-diplomat-kills-man-car-crash-leaves-kenya-19851449</arg><arg name="title">US Diplomat Kills Man in Car Crash, Leaves Kenya</arg><arg name="date">2 August 2013<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[ABC News]]</arg><arg name="author">Jason Straziuso</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 August 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>United States embassy officials took the diplomat and his family out of Kenya the following day.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCAug13"></extension><space/>The United States government was concerned about the impact the accident could have on bilateral relations with Kenya.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCAug13"></extension><space/>Walde gave a statement to police, but was not detained due to his diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCAug13"></extension><space/>Kenyan police say the case remains under investigation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ABCAug13"></extension></listitem><listitem>In October 2013, Russian diplomat Dmitri Borodin was arrested in The Hague, The Netherlands, after neighbours alerted the police. Borodin was alleged to have been drunk and violent towards his children, aged two and four. Police were in the area because Borodin's wife had lost control over her car while also under influence, and had rammed four parked cars near the diplomats' house.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NOS08102013"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://nos.nl/artikel/560093-borodin-was-gevaar-voor-kinderen.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Borodin was gevaar voor kinderen<space/></arg><arg name="date">8 October 2013</arg><arg name="work">[[Nederlandse Omroep Stichting|NOS]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 October 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Russia immediately demanded an apology from the Dutch government for violating Borodin's diplomatic immunity. The row came at a time of tension between Russia and the Netherlands, after the Russian security services captured a<space/><link><target>Greenpeace</target></link><space/>vessel sailing under the Dutch flag,<space/><link><target>MV Arctic Sunrise</target><part>Arctic Sunrise</part></link>, that was protesting against oil drilling in the<space/><link><target>Prirazlomnoye field</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC04102013"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/world-europe-24395769<space/></arg><arg name="title">Dutch take legal action over Greenpeace ship in Russia<space/></arg><arg name="date">4 October 2013<space/></arg><arg name="work">[[BBC News]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">8 October 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>On 16 October a Dutch diplomat was beaten up in his house in<space/><link><target>Russia</target></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem>In June 2014, the New Zealand government confirmed that<space/><link><target>Mohammed Rizalman Bin Ismail</target></link><space/>from Malaysia, aged in his 30s and employed at Malaysia's High Commission in Wellington, had invoked diplomatic immunity when faced with charges of burglary and assault with intent to rape after allegedly following a 21-year-old woman to her home.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NZHJun30"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.nzherald.co.nz/politics/news/article.cfm?c_id</arg><arg name="title">Govt wanted sex case diplomat to face charges - Key<space/></arg><arg name="date">30 June 2014</arg><arg name="work">[[New Zealand Herald]]<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">30 June 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>The diplomat returned to Malaysia in May 2014 with his family while the case was still in hearing. The New Zealand foreign ministry was criticized for allowing the defendant to leave the country, which was blamed on miscommunication between the foreign ministries of the two countries, as Prime Minister<space/><link><target>John Key</target></link><space/>expressed his view that &quot;the man should have faced the charges in New Zealand&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="NZHJun30"></extension><space/>Malaysia eventually agreed to send the diplomat back to assist in investigations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Malaysia to send diplomat back to New Zealand wanted on sex charges"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.independent.ie/world-news/asia-pacific/malaysia-to-send-diplomat-back-to-new-zealand-wanted-on-sex-charges-30401617.html</arg><arg name="title">Malaysia to send diplomat back to New Zealand wanted on sex charges</arg><arg name="publisher">The Independent</arg><arg name="date">3 July 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Malaysian official on sex charge uses diplomatic immunity to leave NZ"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.theguardian.com/world/2014/jul/01/malaysian-official-sexual-assault-charge-diplomatic-immunity-leave-new-zealand</arg><arg name="title">Malaysian official on sex charge uses diplomatic immunity to leave NZ</arg><arg name="publisher">The Guardian</arg><arg name="date">1 July 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On August 25, 2014, police were called to the Arlington, Virginia, home of an ambassador from Equatorial Guinea, where they transported a female victim (reportedly the ambassador's teenage daughter) who had been struck in the head. Police could not press assault charges because the suspect had diplomatic immunity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ARLNowAug26"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.arlnow.com/2014/08/26/report-diplomat-beat-daughter-with-chair-leg-but-wont-be-charged/<space/></arg><arg name="title">Report: Diplomat Beat Daughter With Chair Leg But Won’t Be Charged<space/></arg><arg name="date">26 August 2014</arg><arg name="work">ARL Now<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">26 August 2014</arg></template></extension></listitem><listitem>On September 12, 2015, Sheikh Khalid bin Hamad Al Thani tried to claim diplomatic immunity when his<space/><link><target>Ferrari LaFerrari</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>Porsche 911 GT3</target></link><space/>were caught on camera<space/><link><target>drag racing</target></link><space/>through a residential neighborhood in<space/><link><target>Beverly Hills</target></link>. He owns the cars and a drag racing team, and is a member of<space/><link><target>Qatar</target></link>'s ruling family. The Beverly Hills Police Department contacted the<space/><link><target>U.S. State Department</target></link><space/>to clarify if he had diplomatic immunity. They stated he did not. However, his face was not shown on camera, and no officer witnessed the crime, so the state of California has not yet pressed charges. He has since fled the country. The investigation is ongoing.<extension extension_name='ref'>https://www.yahoo.com/autos/owner-of-beverly-hills-laferrari-does-not-have-129289165617.html</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.cbsnews.com/news/does-driver-in-beverly-hills-high-speed-race-have-diplomatic-immunity/</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Diplomatic immunity in the world</heading><paragraph><template><target>Globalize</target><arg name="date"><space/>section
</arg><arg name="discuss"><space/>Country 
<space/></arg><arg name="1"><space/>section
</arg><arg name="2"><space/>Country 
<space/></arg><arg name="2name">United States
</arg></template>The following chart outlines the immunities afforded to foreign diplomatic personnel residing in the United States.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.state.gov/m/ds/immunities/c9127.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Legal Aspects of Diplomatic Immunity and Privileges<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>28 March 2007<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>[[United States Department of State]]<space/></arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20070315084126/http://www.state.gov/m/ds/immunities/c9127.htm<space/></arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>15 March 2007</arg></template></extension>In general, these rules follow the Vienna Convention (or the New York Convention for UN officials) and apply in other countries as well (with the exceptions of immunities for United Nations officials, which can vary widely across countries based on the 'Host Country Agreement' signed between the UN and the host country, whereby additional immunities beyond those granted by the New York Convention may be established).</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead colspan="2">Category</tablehead><tablehead>May be arrested or detained</tablehead><tablehead>Residence may be entered subject to ordinary procedures</tablehead><tablehead>May be issued traffic ticket</tablehead><tablehead>May be subpoenaed as witness</tablehead><tablehead>May be prosecuted</tablehead><tablehead>Official family member</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead rowspan="3">Diplomatic</tablehead><tablehead>Diplomatic agent</tablehead><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table1">Reasonable constraints, however, may be applied in emergency circumstances involving self-defense, public safety, or the prevention of serious criminal acts.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>Same as sponsor</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Member of administrative and technical staff</tablehead><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table1"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell><tablecell>Same as sponsor</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Service staff</tablehead><tablecell>Yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2">This table presents general rules. Particularly in the cases indicated,the employees of certain foreign countries may enjoy<space/><italics>higher</italics><space/>levels of privileges and immunities on the basis of special bilateral agreements.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead rowspan="3">Consular</tablehead><tablehead>Career consular officers</tablehead><tablecell>Yes, if for a felony and pursuant to a warrant.<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table4">Note that consular residences are sometimes located within the official consular premises. In such cases,<space/><italics>only</italics><space/>the official office space is protected from police entry.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Testimony may not be compelled in any case.</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table3">A small number of senior officers are entitled to be treated identically to &quot;diplomatic agents&quot;.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Honorary consular officers</tablehead><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Yes, in all other cases</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Consular employees</tablehead><tablecell>Yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Yes, in all other cases</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead rowspan="3">International organization</tablehead><tablehead>Diplomatic-level staff of missions to international organizations</tablehead><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table1"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table9"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table9">If the international organisation is located in the country of the staff member's nationality, exemption only extends to official acts.</extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table9"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table9"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>Same as sponsor</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>International organization staff<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table3"></extension></tablehead><tablecell>Yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table3"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table3"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Yes, in all other cases</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table3"></extension></tablecell><tablecell>No<extension extension_name='ref' group="lower-alpha" name="table2"></extension></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead>Support staff of missions to international organizations</tablehead><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>Yes</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Yes, in all other cases</tablecell><tablecell>No, for official acts. Otherwise, yes</tablecell><tablecell>No</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Notes and references</heading><heading level='3'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg name="group">lower-alpha</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>David B. Michaels,<space/><italics>International privileges and immunities: A case for a universal statute</italics>, Springer, July 1971, ISBN 978-9024751266</listitem><listitem>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.state.gov/documents/organization/150546.pdf'>Diplomatic and Consular Immunity: Guidance for Law Enforcement and Judicial Authorities</link>&quot; -<space/><link><target>United States Department of State</target></link><space/>Office of Foreign Missions.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.nyc.gov/html/unccp/html/home/home.shtml'>New York City Commission for the United Nations Consular Corp and Protocol</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.straightdope.com/mailbag/mdiploimmunity.html'>What's the story on diplomatic immunity?</link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Straight Dope</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://legal.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/english/conventions/9_1_1961.pdf'>Vienna Convention on Diplomatic Relations, 1961</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://legal.un.org/ilc/texts/instruments/english/conventions/9_2_1963.pdf'>Vienna Convention on Consular Relations (VCCR), 1963</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://timesofindia.indiatimes.com/india/Waive-off-immunity-for-wife-beater-diplomat-Anil-Verma-UK-tells-India-/articleshow/7305079.cms'>Misusage of Diplomatic Immunity</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Diplomacy</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>Portal bar</target><arg>International relations</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Diplomatic Immunity</target></template><link><target>Category:Rules of the road</target><part>traffic regulations</part></link><link><target>Category:Diplomatic immunity and protection</target><part></part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>de:Diplomatie#Diplomatische Immunitt</target></link></paragraph></article>