<article title='Auguste_Rodin'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg>the sculptor</arg><arg>other people named Rodin</arg><arg>Rodin (surname)</arg></template><space/><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>Good article</target></template><template><target>Infobox artist</target><arg name="name"><space/>Auguste Rodin
</arg><arg name="image"><space/>Rodin-cropped.png
</arg><arg name="caption"><space/>Photo of Rodin wearing a beret.
</arg><arg name="alt"><space/>
</arg><arg name="imagesize"><space/>250px
</arg><arg name="birth_name"><space/>François-Auguste-René Rodin
</arg><arg name="birth_date"><space/>{{birth date|df</arg><arg name="birth_place"><space/>[[Paris]], France
</arg><arg name="death_date"><space/>{{death date and age|df</arg><arg name="death_place"><space/>[[Meudon]], [[Île-de-France]]
</arg><arg name="nationality"><space/>French
</arg><arg name="parents"><space/>Marie Cheffer and Jean Baptiste Rodin
</arg><arg name="field"><space/>Sculpture, drawing
</arg><arg name="training">
</arg><arg name="influenced">
</arg><arg name="awards"><space/>[[Légion d'Honneur]]
</arg><arg name="works"><space/>{{unbulleted list
 |''[[The Age of Bronze]] (L'age d'airain), 1877''
 |''[[The Walking Man]] (L'homme qui marche)'', 1877–78
 |''[[The Burghers of Calais]] (Les Bourgeois de Calais)'', 1889
 |''[[The Kiss (Rodin sculpture)|The Kiss]]'', 1889
 |''[[The Thinker]] (Le Penseur)'', 1902}}
</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Franois Auguste Ren Rodin</bold><space/>(12 November 1840 17 November 1917), known as<space/><bold>Auguste Rodin</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>ɡ</arg><arg>uː</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>_</arg><arg>r</arg><arg>oʊ</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>d</arg><arg>æ</arg><arg>n</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>IPA-fr</target><arg>oɡyst ʁɔdɛ̃</arg><arg>lang</arg></template>), was a French<space/><link><target>Sculpture</target><part>sculptor</part></link>. Although Rodin is generally considered the progenitor of modern sculpture,<extension extension_name='ref'>Tucker, 16.</extension><space/>he did not set out to rebel against the past. He was schooled traditionally, took a craftsman-like approach to his work, and desired academic recognition,<extension extension_name='ref' name="H76">Hale, 76.</extension><space/>although he was never accepted into Paris's foremost school of art.</paragraph><paragraph>Sculpturally, Rodin possessed a unique ability to model a complex, turbulent, deeply pocketed surface in<space/><link><target>clay</target></link>. Many of his most notable sculptures were roundly criticized during his lifetime. They clashed with the predominant figure sculpture tradition, in which works were decorative, formulaic, or highly thematic. Rodin's most original work departed from traditional themes of<space/><link><target>mythology</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>allegory</target></link>, modeled the human body with realism, and celebrated individual character and physicality. Rodin was sensitive to the controversy surrounding his work, but refused to change his style. Successive works brought increasing favor from the government and the artistic community.</paragraph><paragraph>From the unexpected realism of his first major figure inspired by his 1875 trip to Italy to the unconventional memorials whose commissions he later sought, Rodin's reputation grew, such that he became the preeminent French sculptor of his time. By 1900, he was a world-renowned artist. Wealthy private clients sought Rodin's work after his<space/><link><target>Exposition Universelle (1900)</target><part>World's Fair</part></link><space/>exhibit, and he kept company with a variety of high-profile intellectuals and artists. He married his lifelong companion, Rose Beuret, in the last year of both their lives. His sculptures suffered a decline in popularity after his death in 1917, but within a few decades, his legacy solidified. Rodin remains one of the few sculptors widely known outside the visual arts community.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Biography</heading><heading level='3'>Formative years</heading><paragraph>Rodin was born in 1840 into a working-class family in Paris, the second child of Marie Cheffer and Jean-Baptiste Rodin, who was a police department clerk. He was largely self-educated,<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;(Franois) Auguste (Ren) Rodin.&quot;<space/><italics>International Dictionary of Art and Artists</italics>. St. James Press, 1990. Reproduced in Biography Resource Center. Farmington Hills, Mich.: Thomson Gale. 2006.</extension><space/>and began to draw at age ten. Between ages 14 and 17, Rodin attended the<space/><italics>Petite cole</italics>, a school specializing in art and mathematics, where he studied drawing and painting. His drawing teacher,<space/><link><target>Horace Lecoq de Boisbaudran</target></link>, believed in first developing the personality of his students so that they observed with their own eyes and drew from their recollections. Rodin still expressed appreciation for his teacher much later in life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jianou &amp; Goldscheider, 31.</extension><space/>It was at Petite cole that he first met<space/><link><target>Jules Dalou</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Alphonse Legros</target></link>.<link><target>File:Auguste Rodin, Paris, c1862 by Charles Hippolyte Aubry.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>Rodin circa 1862.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1857, Rodin submitted a clay model of a companion to the<space/><link><target>cole des Beaux-Arts</target></link><space/>in an attempt to win entrance; he did not succeed, and two further applications were also denied.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytobit"></extension><space/>Given that entrance requirements at the<space/><italics>Grande cole</italics><space/>were not particularly high,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 40.</extension><space/>the rejections were considerable setbacks. Rodin's inability to gain entrance may have been due to the judges'<space/><link><target>Neoclassicism</target><part>Neoclassical</part></link><space/>tastes, while Rodin had been schooled in light, 18th-century sculpture. Leaving the<space/><italics>Petite cole</italics><space/>in 1857, Rodin earned a living as a craftsman and ornamenter for most of the next two decades, producing decorative objects and architectural embellishments.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin's sister Maria, two years his senior, died of<space/><link><target>peritonitis</target></link><space/>in a convent in 1862. Her brother was anguished, and felt guilty because he had introduced Maria to an unfaithful suitor. Turning away from art, Rodin briefly joined a Catholic order, the<space/><link><target>Congregation of the Blessed Sacrament</target></link>. Saint<space/><link><target>Peter Julian Eymard</target></link>, founder and head of the congregation, recognized Rodin's talent and, sensing his lack of suitability for the order, encouraged Rodin to continue with his sculpture. He returned to work as a decorator, while taking classes with animal sculptor<space/><link><target>Antoine-Louis Barye</target></link>. The teacher's attention to detail&amp;nbsp; his finely rendered musculature of animals in motion&amp;nbsp; significantly influenced Rodin.<extension extension_name='ref' name="morey"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Morey</arg><arg name="first">C. R.</arg><arg name="title">The Art of Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">The Bulletin of the College Art Association of America</arg><arg name="volume">1</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="year">1918</arg><arg name="pages">145–154</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3046338</arg><arg name="jstor">3046338</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1864, Rodin began to live with a young seamstress named Rose Beuret, with whom he would stay&amp;nbsp; with ranging commitment&amp;nbsp; for the rest of his life. The couple had a son, Auguste-Eugne Beuret (18661934).<extension extension_name='ref'>Date of death from Elsen, 206.</extension><space/>That year, Rodin offered his first sculpture for exhibition, and entered the studio of<space/><link><target>Albert-Ernest Carrier-Belleuse</target></link>, a successful mass producer of<space/><italics><link><target>objets d'art</target></link></italics>. Rodin worked as Carrier-Belleuse' chief assistant until 1870, designing roof decorations and staircase and doorway embellishments. With the arrival of the<space/><link><target>Franco-Prussian War</target></link>, Rodin was called to serve in the<space/><link><target>National Guard (France)</target><part>National Guard</part></link>, but his service was brief due to his<space/><link><target>near-sightedness</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jianou &amp; Goldscheider, 34.</extension><space/>Decorators' work had dwindled because of the war, yet Rodin needed to support his family; poverty was a continual difficulty for Rodin until about the age of 30.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tabhhj">Jianou &amp; Goldscheider, 35.</extension><space/>Carrier-Belleuse soon asked Rodin to join him in<space/><link><target>Belgium</target></link>, where they would work on ornamentation for<space/><link><target>Brussels Stock Exchange</target><part>Brussels' bourse</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin planned to stay in Belgium a few months, but he spent the next six years out of France. It was a pivotal time in his life.<extension extension_name='ref' name="tabhhj"></extension><space/>He had acquired skill and experience as a craftsman, but no one had yet seen his art, which sat in his workshop, since he could not afford castings. Though his relationship with Carrier-Belleuse deteriorated, Rodin found other employment in Brussels, displaying some works at salons, and his companion Rose soon joined him there. Having saved enough money to travel, Rodin visited Italy for two months in 1875, where he was drawn to the work of<space/><link><target>Donatello</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link>. Their work had a profound effect on his artistic direction.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 4950.</extension><space/>Rodin said, &quot;It is<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link><space/>who has freed me from academic sculpture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Taillandier, 91.</extension><space/>Returning to Belgium, he began work on<space/><italics><link><target>The Age of Bronze</target></link></italics>, a life-size male figure whose realism brought Rodin attention but led to accusations of sculptural cheating.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Artistic independence</heading><paragraph>Rose Beuret and Rodin returned to Paris in 1877, moving into a small flat on the<space/><link><target>Rive Gauche</target><part>Left Bank</part></link>. Misfortune surrounded Rodin: his mother, who had wanted to see her son marry, was dead, and his father was blind and senile, cared for by Rodin's sister-in-law, Aunt Thrse. Rodin's eleven-year-old son Auguste, possibly developmentally delayed, was also in the ever-helpful Thrse's care. Rodin had essentially abandoned his son for six years,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 65.</extension><space/>and would have a very limited relationship with him throughout his life. Father and son now joined the couple in their flat, with Rose as caretaker. The charges of fakery surrounding<space/><italics>The Age of Bronze</italics><space/>continued. Rodin increasingly sought more soothing female companionship in Paris, and Rose stayed in the background.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin earned his living collaborating with more established sculptors on public commissions, primarily memorials and<space/><link><target>neo-baroque</target></link><space/>architectural pieces in the style of Carpeaux.<extension extension_name='ref' name="j638">Janson, 638.</extension><space/>In competitions for commissions he submitted models of<space/><link><target>Denis Diderot</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Lazare Carnot</target></link>, all to no avail. On his own time, he worked on studies leading to the creation of his next important work,<space/><italics>St. John the Baptist Preaching</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Camille Claudel.jpg</target><part>alt=Head and shoulders of a young, dark haired woman looking downward.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>180px</part><part><link><target>Camille Claudel</target></link><space/>(18641943)</part></link><link><target>File:August rodin dornac 1898.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>250px</part><part>Rodin in his studio.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1880, Carrier-Belleuse&amp;nbsp; now art director of the<space/><link><target>Svres</target></link><space/>national<space/><link><target>porcelain</target></link><space/>factory&amp;nbsp; offered Rodin a part-time position as a designer. The offer was in part a gesture of reconciliation, and Rodin accepted. That part of Rodin which appreciated 18th-century tastes was aroused, and he immersed himself in designs for vases and table ornaments that brought the factory renown across Europe.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 70.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:The Thinker, Rodin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>160px</part><part>Rodin's ''<link><target>The Thinker</target></link>'' (18791889) is among the most recognized works in all of sculpture.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The artistic community appreciated his work in this vein, and Rodin was invited to<space/><link><target>Paris Salon</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>by such friends as writer<space/><link><target>Lon Cladel</target></link>. During his early appearances at these social events, Rodin seemed shy;<extension extension_name='ref' name="H71">Hale, 71.</extension><space/>in his later years, as his fame grew, he displayed the loquaciousness and temperament for which he is better known. French statesman<space/><link><target>Leon Gambetta</target></link><space/>expressed a desire to meet Rodin, and the sculptor impressed him when they met at a salon. Gambetta spoke of Rodin in turn to several government ministers, likely including Edmund Turquet, the Undersecretary of the Ministry of Fine Arts, whom Rodin eventually met.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H71"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Rodin's relationship with Turquet was rewarding: through him, he won the 1880 commission to create a<space/><link><target>Portal (architecture)</target><part>portal</part></link><space/>for a planned museum of decorative arts. Rodin dedicated much of the next four decades to his elaborate<space/><italics><link><target>Gates of Hell</target></link></italics>, an unfinished portal for a museum that was never built. Many of the portal's figures became sculptures in themselves, including Rodin's most famous,<space/><italics><link><target>The Thinker</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>The Kiss (Rodin sculpture)</target><part>The Kiss</part></link></italics>. With the museum commission came a free studio, granting Rodin a new level of artistic freedom. Soon, he stopped working at the porcelain factory; his income came from private commissions.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1883, Rodin agreed to supervise a course for sculptor<space/><link><target>Alfred Boucher</target></link><space/>in his absence, where he met the 18-year-old<space/><link><target>Camille Claudel</target></link>. The two formed a passionate but stormy relationship and influenced each other artistically. Claudel inspired Rodin as a model for many of his figures, and she was a talented sculptor, assisting him on commissions.</paragraph><paragraph>Although busy with<space/><italics>The Gates of Hell</italics>, Rodin won other commissions. He pursued an opportunity to create a historical monument for the town of<space/><link><target>Calais</target></link>. For a monument to French author<space/><link><target>Honor de Balzac</target></link>, Rodin was chosen in 1891. His execution of both sculptures clashed with traditional tastes, and met with varying degrees of disapproval from the organizations that sponsored the commissions. Still, Rodin was gaining support from diverse sources that propelled him toward fame.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1889, the Paris Salon invited Rodin to be a judge on its artistic jury. Though Rodin's career was on the rise, Claudel and Beuret were becoming increasingly impatient with Rodin's &quot;double life&quot;. Claudel and Rodin shared an<space/><link><target>wikt:atelier</target><part>atelier</part></link><space/>at a small old castle, but Rodin refused to relinquish his ties to Beuret, his loyal companion during the lean years, and mother of his son. During one absence, Rodin wrote to Beuret, &quot;I think of how much you must have loved me to put up with my caprices...I remain, in all tenderness, your Rodin.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 75.</extension><space/>Claudel and Rodin parted in 1898.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">(1) Camille Claudel</arg><arg name="publisher">Grove Art Online, Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="url">http://www.groveart.com/shared/views/article.html?section</arg><arg name="author">Ward-Jackson, Philip</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>Claudel suffered a nervous breakdown several years later and was confined to an institution by her family until her death.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Works</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rodin The bronze age.jpg</target><part>alt=Life-sized nude stature of a male on a pedestal on display in a museum.</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>150px</part><part>''<link><target>The Age of Bronze</target></link>'' (1877).</part></link><link><target>File:Brooklyn Museum - M. Auguste Rodin - Edward Steichen.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>150px</part><part>M. Auguste Rodin - photo by<space/><link><target>Edward Steichen</target></link>, ca. 1911</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In 1864, Rodin submitted his first sculpture for exhibition,<space/><italics>The Man with the Broken Nose</italics>, to the<space/><link><target>Paris Salon</target></link>. The subject was an elderly neighbourhood street porter. The unconventional<space/><link><target>bronze</target></link><space/>piece was not a traditional<space/><link><target>bust (sculpture)</target><part>bust</part></link>, but instead the head was &quot;broken off&quot; at the neck, the nose was flattened and crooked, and the back of the head was absent, having fallen off the clay model in an accident. The work emphasized texture and the emotional state of the subject; it illustrated the &quot;unfinishedness&quot; that would characterize many of Rodin's later sculptures.<extension extension_name='ref'>Janson, 637.</extension><space/>The Salon rejected the piece.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Early figures: the inspiration of Italy</heading><paragraph>In Brussels, Rodin created his first full-scale work,<space/><italics><link><target>The Age of Bronze</target></link></italics>, having returned from Italy. Modeled by a Belgian soldier, the figure drew inspiration from Michelangelo's<space/><italics><link><target>Dying Slave</target></link></italics>, which Rodin had observed at the<space/><link><target>Louvre</target></link>. Attempting to combine Michelangelo's mastery of the human form with his own sense of human nature, Rodin studied his model from all angles, at rest and in motion; he mounted a ladder for additional perspective, and made clay models, which he studied by candlelight. The result was a life-size, well-proportioned nude figure, posed unconventionally with his right hand atop his head, and his left arm held out at his side, forearm parallel to the body.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1877, the work debuted in Brussels and then was shown at the Paris Salon. The statue's apparent lack of a theme was troubling to critics&amp;nbsp; commemorating neither mythology nor a noble historical event&amp;nbsp; and it is not clear whether Rodin intended a theme.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 50.</extension><space/>He first titled the work<space/><italics>The Vanquished</italics>, in which form the left hand held a spear, but he removed the spear because it obstructed the torso from certain angles. After two more intermediary titles, Rodin settled on<space/><italics>The Age of Bronze</italics>, suggesting the<space/><link><target>Bronze Age</target></link>, and in Rodin's words, &quot;man arising from nature&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H51">Hale, 51.</extension><space/>Later, however, Rodin said that he had had in mind &quot;just a simple piece of sculpture without reference to subject&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H51"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Its mastery of form, light, and shadow made the work look so realistic that Rodin was accused of<space/><italics>surmoulage</italics>&amp;nbsp; having taken a cast from a living model. Rodin vigorously denied the charges, writing to newspapers and having photographs taken of the model to prove how the sculpture differed. He demanded an inquiry and was eventually exonerated by a committee of sculptors. Leaving aside the false charges, the piece polarized critics. It had barely won acceptance for display at the Paris Salon, and criticism likened it to &quot;a statue of a sleepwalker&quot; and called it &quot;an astonishingly accurate copy of a low type&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H51"></extension><space/>Others rallied to defend the piece and Rodin's integrity. The government minister Turquet admired the piece, and<space/><italics>The Age of Bronze</italics><space/>was purchased by the state for 2,200<space/><link><target>franc</target><trail>s</trail></link>&amp;nbsp; what it had cost Rodin to have it cast in bronze.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H51"></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:St-John-the-Baptist-Preaching.jpg</target><part>alt=Nude man holding is hand out, as if explaining a point.</part><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''St. John the Baptist Preaching'' (1878).</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A second male nude,<space/><italics><link><target>Saint John the Baptist (Rodin)</target><part>St. John the Baptist Preaching</part></link></italics>, was completed in 1878. Rodin sought to avoid another charge of<space/><italics>surmoulage</italics><space/>by making the statue larger than life:<space/><italics>St. John</italics><space/>stands almost 6' 7&quot;<extension extension_name='nowiki'>''</extension><space/>(2&amp;nbsp;m). While<space/><italics>The Age of Bronze</italics><space/>is statically posed,<space/><italics>St. John</italics><space/>gestures and seems to move toward the viewer. The effect of walking is achieved despite the figure having both feet firmly on the ground&amp;nbsp; a physical impossibility, and a technical achievement that was lost on most contemporary critics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 80.</extension><space/>Rodin chose this contradictory position to, in his words, &quot;display simultaneously...views of an object which in fact can be seen only successively&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H68">Hale, 68.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Despite the title,<space/><italics>St. John the Baptist Preaching</italics><space/>did not have an obviously religious theme. The model, an Italian peasant who presented himself at Rodin's studio, possessed an idiosyncratic sense of movement that Rodin felt compelled to capture. Rodin thought of<space/><link><target>John the Baptist</target></link>, and carried that association into the title of the work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H68"></extension><space/>In 1880, Rodin submitted the sculpture to the Paris Salon. Critics were still mostly dismissive of his work, but the piece finished third in the Salon's sculpture category.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H68"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Regardless of the immediate receptions of<space/><italics>St. John</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>The Age of Bronze</italics>, Rodin had achieved a new degree of fame. Students sought him at his studio, praising his work and scorning the charges of<space/><italics>surmoulage</italics>. The artistic community knew his name.</paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>The Gates of Hell</italics></heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Zrich - Kunsthaus - Rodin's Hllentor IMG 7384 ShiftN.jpg</target><part>alt=Ornate, bronze door panels and frame showing figures and scenes in relief.</part><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>''<link><target>The Gates of Hell</target></link>'' (unfinished),<space/><link><target>Kunsthaus Zrich</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A commission to create a<space/><link><target>Gate</target><part>portal</part></link><space/>for Paris' planned Museum of Decorative Arts was awarded to Rodin in 1880.<extension extension_name='ref' name="j638"></extension><space/>Although the museum was never built, Rodin worked throughout his life on<space/><italics><link><target>The Gates of Hell</target></link></italics>, a monumental sculptural group depicting scenes from<space/><link><target>Dante Alighieri</target><part>Dante's</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>The Divine Comedy</target><part>Inferno</part></link></italics><space/>in high relief. Often lacking a clear conception of his major works, Rodin compensated with hard work and a striving for perfection.<extension extension_name='ref' name="elsen35">Elsen, 35.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>He conceived<space/><italics>The Gates</italics><space/>with the<space/><italics>surmoulage</italics><space/>controversy still in mind: &quot;...I had made the<space/><italics>St. John</italics><space/>to refute [the charges of casting from a model], but it only partially succeeded. To prove completely that I could model from life as well as other sculptors, I determined...to make the sculpture on the door of figures smaller than life.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="elsen35"></extension><space/>Laws of composition gave way to the<space/><italics>Gates</italics>' disordered and untamed depiction of Hell. The figures and groups in this, Rodin's meditation on the condition of man, are physically and morally isolated in their torment.<extension extension_name='ref' name="qgzhpg">Jianou &amp; Goldscheider, 41.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><italics>The Gates of Hell</italics><space/>comprised 186 figures in its final form.<extension extension_name='ref' name="qgzhpg"></extension><space/>Many of Rodin's best-known sculptures started as designs of figures for this composition,<extension extension_name='ref' name="morey"></extension><space/>such as<space/><italics><link><target>The Thinker</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics>The Three Shades</italics>, and<space/><italics>The Kiss</italics>, and were only later presented as separate and independent works. Other well-known works derived from<space/><italics>The Gates</italics><space/>are<space/><italics><link><target>Ugolino della Gherardesca</target><part>Ugolino</part></link></italics>,<space/><italics>Fugit Amor</italics>,<space/><italics>The Falling Man</italics>, and<space/><italics>The Prodigal Son</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>The Thinker</italics><space/>(originally titled<space/><italics>The Poet</italics>, after Dante) was to become one of the most well-known sculptures in the world. The original was a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>27.5</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="sing">on</arg></template>-high bronze piece created between 1879 and 1889, designed for the<space/><italics>Gates</italics><extension extension_name='nowiki'>'</extension><space/><link><target>lintel</target></link>, from which the figure would gaze down upon Hell. While<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics><space/>most obviously characterizes Dante, aspects of the Biblical<space/><link><target>Adam</target></link>, the mythological<space/><link><target>Prometheus</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="j638"></extension><space/>and Rodin himself have been ascribed to him.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bell"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="alhadeff"></extension><space/>Other observers de-emphasize the apparent intellectual theme of<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics>, stressing the figure's rough physicality and the emotional tension emanating from it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taillandier, 42, 46, 48.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:The.burg.of.calais.london.arp.750pix.jpg</target><part>alt=See adjacent text.</part><part>thumb</part><part>''<link><target>The Burghers of Calais</target></link>'' (1884ca. 1889) in<space/><link><target>Victoria Tower Gardens</target></link>, London, England.</part></link></paragraph><heading level='3'><italics>The Burghers of Calais</italics></heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>The Burghers of Calais</arg></template>The town of Calais had contemplated a historical monument for decades when Rodin learned of the project. He pursued the commission, interested in the medieval motif and patriotic theme. The mayor of Calais was tempted to hire Rodin on the spot upon visiting his studio, and soon the memorial was approved, with Rodin as its architect. It would commemorate the six townspeople of Calais who offered their lives to save their fellow citizens.</paragraph><paragraph>During the<space/><link><target>Hundred Years' War</target></link>, the army of<space/><link><target>King Edward III</target></link><space/>besieged Calais, and Edward ordered that the town's population be killed<space/><italics>en masse</italics>. He agreed to spare them if six of the principal citizens would come to him prepared to die, bareheaded and barefooted and with ropes around their necks. When they came, he ordered that they be executed, but pardoned them when his queen,<space/><link><target>Philippa of Hainault</target></link>, begged him to spare their lives.<space/><italics><link><target>The Burghers of Calais</target></link></italics><space/>depicts the men as they are leaving for the king's camp, carrying keys to the town's gates and citadel.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin began the project in 1884, inspired by the chronicles of the siege by<space/><link><target>Jean Froissart</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="swedberg"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Swedberg</arg><arg name="first">Richard</arg><arg name="title">Auguste Rodin's ''The Burghers of Calais'': The Career of a Sculpture and its Appeal to Civic Heroism</arg><arg name="journal">Theory, Culture, & Society</arg><arg name="volume">22</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">45–67</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="doi">10.1177/0263276405051665</arg></template></extension><space/>Though the town envisioned an<space/><link><target>allegorical</target></link>, heroic piece centered on Eustache de Saint-Pierre, the eldest of the six men, Rodin conceived the sculpture as a study in the varied and complex emotions under which all six men were laboring. One year into the commission, the Calais committee was not impressed with Rodin's progress. Rodin indicated his willingness to end the project rather than change his design to meet the committee's conservative expectations, but Calais said to continue.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1889,<space/><italics>The Burghers of Calais</italics><space/>was first displayed to general acclaim. It is a bronze sculpture weighing two tons (1,814&amp;nbsp;kg), and its figures are 6.6&amp;nbsp;ft (2&amp;nbsp;m) tall.<extension extension_name='ref' name="swedberg"></extension><space/>The six men portrayed do not display a united, heroic front;<extension extension_name='ref' name="apollo"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Stocker, Mark</arg><arg name="title">A simple sculptor or an apostle of perversion?</arg><arg name="journal">Apollo</arg><arg name="pages">94–97</arg><arg name="volume">164</arg><arg name="issue">537</arg><arg name="date">November 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>rather, each is isolated from his brothers, individually deliberating and struggling with his expected fate. Rodin soon proposed that the monument's high pedestal be eliminated, wanting to move the sculpture to ground level so that viewers could &quot;penetrate to the heart of the subject&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 117.</extension><space/>At ground level, the figures' positions lead the viewer around the work, and subtly suggest their common movement forward.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 115</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The committee was incensed by the untraditional proposal, but Rodin would not yield. In 1895, Calais succeeded in having<space/><italics>Burghers</italics><space/>displayed in their preferred form: the work was placed in front of a public garden on a high platform, surrounded by a cast-iron railing. Rodin had wanted it located near the town hall, where it would engage the public. Only after damage during the First World War, subsequent storage, and Rodin's death was the sculpture displayed as he had intended. It is one of Rodin's best-known and most acclaimed works.<extension extension_name='ref' name="swedberg"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Commissions and controversy<space/><template><target>Anchor</target><arg>Balzac</arg></template></heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Monument to Balzac.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Cast of ''<link><target>Honor de Balzac</target><part>Balzac</part></link>'' (18911898) exposed in<space/><link><target>Muse Rodin</target><part>Jardin du Muse Rodin</part></link>. The same statue is used for the<space/><link><target>Monument to Balzac</target><part>monument</part></link><space/>in Paris</part></link><link><target>File:Auguste Rodin portrait middle aged.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>upright</part><part>Rodin in mid-career</part></link><link><target>File:Auguste Rodin - Monument to Victor Hugo.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Rodin observing work on the monument to<space/><link><target>Victor Hugo</target></link><space/>at the studio of his assistant Henri Leboss in 1896</part></link><link><target>File:Statue of BALZAC, made by RODIN, Paris.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Monument to Balzac</target></link><space/>in Paris</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Commissioned to create a monument to French writer<space/><link><target>Victor Hugo</target></link><space/>in 1889, Rodin dealt extensively with the subject of<space/><italics>artist and muse</italics>. Like many of Rodin's public commissions,<space/><italics>Monument to Victor Hugo</italics><space/>was met with resistance because it did not fit conventional expectations. Commenting on Rodin's monument to Victor Hugo,<space/><italics><link><target>The Times</target></link></italics><space/>in 1909 expressed that &quot;there is some show of reason in the complaint that [Rodin's] conceptions are sometimes unsuited to his medium, and that in such cases they overstrain his vast technical powers&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">M. Rodin and French Sculpture.</arg><arg name="publisher">The Times</arg><arg name="date">4 October 1909</arg><arg name="page">12</arg></template></extension><space/>The 1897 plaster model was not cast in bronze until 1964.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Socit des Gens des Lettres</italics>, a Parisian organization of writers, planned a monument to French novelist<space/><link><target>Honor de Balzac</target></link><space/>immediately after his death in 1850. The society commissioned Rodin to create the memorial in 1891, and Rodin spent years developing the concept for his sculpture. Challenged in finding an appropriate representation of Balzac given the author's rotund physique, Rodin produced many studies: portraits, full-length figures in the nude, wearing a<space/><link><target>frock coat</target></link>, or in a<space/><link><target>robe</target></link>&amp;nbsp; a replica of which Rodin had requested. The realized sculpture displays Balzac cloaked in the drapery, looking forcefully into the distance with deeply gouged features. Rodin's intent had been to show Balzac at the moment of conceiving a work<extension extension_name='ref' name="times1711"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Auguste Rodin. His Sculpture And Its Aims.</arg><arg name="publisher">The Times</arg><arg name="date">19 November 1917</arg><arg name="page">11</arg></template></extension>&amp;nbsp; to express courage, labor, and struggle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 136.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When<space/><italics>Balzac</italics><space/>was exhibited in 1898, the negative reaction was not surprising.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bell"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Bell</arg><arg name="first">Millicent</arg><arg name="title">Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">Raritan</arg><arg name="volume">14</arg><arg name="pages">1–31</arg><arg name="year">Spring 2005</arg></template></extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Socit</italics><space/>rejected the work, and the press ran<space/><link><target>parodies</target></link>. Criticizing the work, Morey (1918) reflected, &quot;there may come a time, and doubtless will come a time, when it will not seem<space/><italics>outre</italics><space/>to represent a great novelist as a huge comic mask crowning a bathrobe, but even at the present day this statue impresses one as slang.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="morey"></extension><space/>A modern critic, indeed, indicates that<space/><italics>Balzac</italics><space/>is one of Rodin's masterpieces.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Schor</arg><arg name="first">Naomi</arg><arg name="title">Pensive Texts and Thinking Statues: Balzac with Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">Critical Inquiry</arg><arg name="year">2001</arg><arg name="volume">27</arg><arg name="issue">2</arg><arg name="pages">239–264</arg><arg name="doi">10.1086/449007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The monument had its supporters in Rodin's day; a manifesto defending him was signed by<space/><link><target>Monet</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Debussy</target></link>, and future<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of France</target><part>Premier</part></link><space/><link><target>Georges Clemenceau</target></link>, among many others.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 122.</extension><space/>In the<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link><space/>series<space/><link><target>Civilisation (TV series)</target><part>Civilization</part></link>, art historian<space/><link><target>Kenneth Clark</target></link><space/>praised the monument as &quot;the greatest piece of sculpture of the 19th Century, perhaps, indeed, the greatest since<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Civilization (TV series)</target><part>Civilization</part></link>,<space/><link><target>BBC</target></link>, Episode 12</extension><space/>Rather than try to convince skeptics of the merit of the monument, Rodin repaid the<space/><italics>Socit</italics><space/>his commission and moved the figure to his garden. After this experience, Rodin did not complete another public commission. Only in 1939 was<space/><italics><link><target>Monument to Balzac</target></link></italics><space/>cast in bronze and placed on the<space/><link><target>Boulevard du Montparnasse</target></link><space/>at the intersection with<space/><link><target>Boulevard Raspail</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Other works</heading><paragraph>The popularity of Rodin's most famous sculptures tends to obscure his total creative output. A prolific artist, he created thousands of busts, figures, and sculptural fragments over more than five decades. He painted in<space/><link><target>Oil painting</target><part>oils</part></link><space/>(especially in his thirties) and in<space/><link><target>Watercolor painting</target><part>watercolors</part></link>. The Muse Rodin holds 7,000 of his drawings and prints, in<space/><link><target>chalk</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>charcoal</target></link>, and thirteen vigorous<space/><link><target>drypoint</target><trail>s</trail></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 12.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Early Drawings by Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="author">Varnedoe, Kirk</arg><arg name="journal">The Burlington Magazine</arg><arg name="volume">116</arg><arg name="issue">853</arg><arg name="date">April 1974</arg><arg name="pages">197–204</arg></template></extension><space/>He also produced a single<space/><link><target>lithograph</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Portraiture was an important component of Rodin's oeuvre, helping him to win acceptance and financial independence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 82.</extension><space/>His first sculpture was a bust of his father in 1860, and he produced at least 56 portraits between 1877 and his death in 1917.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Rodin and His English Sitters</arg><arg name="first">Marion J.</arg><arg name="last">Hare</arg><arg name="journal">The Burlington Magazine</arg><arg name="volume">129</arg><arg name="issue">1011</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="pages">372–381</arg></template></extension><space/>Early subjects included fellow sculptor<space/><link><target>Jules Dalou</target></link><space/>(1883) and companion Camille Claudel (1884).</paragraph><paragraph>Later, with his reputation established, Rodin made busts of prominent contemporaries such as English politician<space/><link><target>George Wyndham</target></link><space/>(1905), Irish playwright<space/><link><target>George Bernard Shaw</target></link><space/>(1906), Austrian composer<space/><link><target>Gustav Mahler</target></link><space/>(1909), former Argentinian president<space/><link><target>Domingo Faustino Sarmiento</target></link><space/>and French statesman<space/><link><target>Georges Clemenceau</target></link><space/>(1911).</paragraph><paragraph>His undated drawing<space/><italics>Study of a Woman Nude, Standing, Arms Raised, Hands Crossed Above Head</italics><space/>is one of the<space/><link><target>2012 Munich artworks discovery</target><part>works seized in 2012 from Cornelius Gurlitt</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="spiegel"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://www.spiegel.de/fotostrecke/photo-gallery-munich-nazi-art-stash-revealed-fotostrecke-103675-18.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Photo Gallery: Munich Nazi Art Stash Revealed<space/></arg><arg name="date">17 November 2013</arg><arg name="work">Spiegel</arg><arg name="accessdate">17 November 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetic</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rodin p1070095.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>A famous &quot;fragment&quot;: ''<link><target>The Walking Man</target></link>'' (1877-78)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Rodin was a naturalist, less concerned with monumental expression than with character and emotion.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="publisher">The Times</arg><arg name="date">14 July 1931</arg><arg name="page">12</arg><arg name="title">Art Exhibitions: Auguste Rodin</arg></template></extension><space/>Departing with centuries of tradition, he turned away from the idealism of the Greeks, and the decorative beauty of the<space/><link><target>Baroque</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Baroque Revival architecture</target><part>neo-Baroque</part></link><space/>movements. His sculpture emphasized the individual and the concreteness of flesh, and suggested emotion through detailed, textured surfaces, and the interplay of light and shadow. To a greater degree than his contemporaries, Rodin believed that an individual's character was revealed by his physical features.<extension extension_name='ref' name="H76"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Rodin's talent for surface modeling allowed him to let every part of the body speak for the whole. The male's passion in<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics><space/>is suggested by the grip of his toes on the rock, the rigidness of his back, and the differentiation of his hands.<extension extension_name='ref' name="morey"></extension><space/>Speaking of<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics>, Rodin illuminated his aesthetic: &quot;What makes my Thinker think is that he thinks not only with his brain, with his knitted brow, his distended nostrils and compressed lips, but with every muscle of his arms, back, and legs, with his clenched fist and gripping toes.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.nga.gov/collection/sculpture/flash/zone2-2.htm</arg><arg name="title">NGA Sculpture Galleries: Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="publisher">[[National Gallery of Art]], Washington, D.C.</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 December 2006</arg><arg name="format">[[Adobe Flash]]</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20061130113846/http://www.nga.gov/collection/sculpture/flash/zone2-2.htm</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>30 November 2006<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Sculptural fragments to Rodin were autonomous works, and he considered them the essence of his artistic statement. His fragments&amp;nbsp; perhaps lacking arms, legs, or a head&amp;nbsp; took sculpture further from its traditional role of portraying likenesses, and into a realm where forms existed for their own sake.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 69.</extension><space/>Notable examples are<space/><italics><link><target>The Walking Man</target></link></italics>,<space/><italics>Meditation without Arms</italics>, and<space/><italics>Iris, Messenger of the Gods</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin saw suffering and conflict as hallmarks of modern art. &quot;Nothing, really, is more moving than the maddened beast, dying from unfulfilled desire and asking in vain for grace to quell its passion.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="alhadeff"></extension><space/><link><target>Charles Baudelaire</target></link><space/>echoed those themes, and was among Rodin's favorite poets. Rodin enjoyed music, especially the opera composer<space/><link><target>Gluck</target></link>, and wrote a book about<space/><link><target>List of cathedrals in France</target><part>French cathedrals</part></link>. He owned a work by the as-yet-unrecognized<space/><link><target>Vincent van Gogh</target><part>Van Gogh</part></link>, and admired the forgotten<space/><link><target>El Greco</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="werner"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Method</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Rodin The Shade.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''The Shade'', (1880-81)<space/><link><target>High Museum of Art</target></link>, Atlanta</part></link><link><target>File:Age of bronze plaster.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>A<space/><link><target>plaster</target></link><space/>of ''<link><target>The Age of Bronze</target></link>''</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Instead of copying traditional academic postures, Rodin preferred his models to move naturally around his studio (despite their nakedness).<extension extension_name='ref' name="morey"></extension><space/>The sculptor often made quick sketches in clay that were later fine-tuned, cast in plaster, and forged into bronze or carved in marble. Rodin's focus was on the handling of clay.<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA">Quoted in Jianou &amp; Goldscheider, 62.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>George Bernard Shaw sat for a portrait and gave an idea of Rodin's technique: &quot;While he worked, he achieved a number of miracles. At the end of the first fifteen minutes, after having given a simple idea of the human form to the block of clay, he produced by the action of his thumb a bust so living that I would have taken it away with me to relieve the sculptor of any further work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>He described the evolution of his bust over a month, passing through &quot;all the stages of art's evolution&quot;: first, a &quot;<link><target>Byzantine art</target><part>Byzantine</part></link><space/>masterpiece&quot;, then &quot;<link><target>Bernini</target></link><space/>intermingled&quot;, then an elegant<space/><link><target>Houdon</target></link>. &quot;The hand of Rodin worked not as the hand of a sculptor works, but as the work of<space/><italics><link><target>Elan Vital (term)</target><part>Elan Vital</part></link></italics>. The<space/><italics>Hand of God</italics><space/>is his own hand.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After he completed his work in clay, he employed highly skilled assistants to re-sculpt his compositions at larger sizes (including any of his large-scale monuments such as<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics>), to cast the clay compositions into plaster or bronze, and to carve his marbles. Rodin's major innovation was to capitalize on such multi-staged processes of 19th century sculpture and their reliance on plaster casting.</paragraph><paragraph>Since clay deteriorates rapidly if not kept wet or fired into a terra-cotta, sculptors used plaster casts as a means of securing the composition they would make out of the fugitive material that is clay. This was common practice amongst Rodin's contemporaries, and sculptors would exhibit plaster casts with the hopes that they would be commissioned to have the works made in a more permanent material. Rodin, however, would have multiple plasters made and treat them as the raw material of sculpture, recombining their parts and figures into new compositions, and new names.</paragraph><paragraph>As Rodin's practice developed into the 1890s, he became more and more radical in his pursuit of fragmentation, the combination of figures at different scales, and the making of new compositions from his earlier work. A prime example of this is the bold<space/><italics>The Walking Man</italics><space/>(18991900), which was exhibited as his major one-person show in 1900. This is composed of two sculptures from the 1870s that Rodin found in his studio&amp;nbsp; a broken and damaged torso that had fallen into neglect and the lower extremities of a statuette version of his 1878<space/><italics>St. John the Baptist Preaching</italics><space/>he was having re-sculpted at a reduced scale.</paragraph><paragraph>Without finessing the join between upper and lower, between torso and legs, Rodin created a work that many sculptors at the time and subsequently have seen as one of his strongest and most singular works. This is despite the fact that the object conveys two different styles, exhibits two different attitudes toward finish, and lacks any attempt to hide the arbitrary fusion of these two components. It was the freedom and creativity with which Rodin used these practices&amp;nbsp; along with his activation surfaces of sculptures through traces of his own touch and with his more open attitude toward bodily pose, sensual subject matter, and non-realistic surface&amp;nbsp; that marked Rodin's re-making of traditional 19th century sculptural techniques into the prototype for modern sculpture.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later years (19001917)</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Legros -buste de Rodin (dessin).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>upright</part><part>A portrait of Rodin by his friend<space/><link><target>Alphonse Legros</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By 1900, Rodin's artistic reputation was entrenched. Gaining exposure from a pavilion of his artwork set up near the 1900<space/><link><target>World's Fair</target></link><space/>(<italics>Exposition Universelle</italics>) in Paris, he received requests to make busts of prominent people internationally,<extension extension_name='ref' name="bell"></extension><space/>while his assistants at the atelier produced duplicates of his works. His income from portrait commissions alone totalled probably 200,000 francs a year.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 147.</extension><space/>As Rodin's fame grew, he attracted many followers, including the German poet<space/><link><target>Rainer Maria Rilke</target></link>, and authors<space/><link><target>Octave Mirbeau</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Joris-Karl Huysmans</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Oscar Wilde</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="apollo"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Rilke stayed with Rodin in 1905 and 1906, and did administrative work for him; he would later write a laudatory<space/><link><target>monograph</target></link><space/>on the sculptor. Rodin and Beuret's modest country estate in<space/><link><target>Meudon</target></link>, purchased in 1897, was a host to such visitors as<space/><link><target>Edward VII of the United Kingdom</target><part>King Edward</part></link>, dancer<space/><link><target>Isadora Duncan</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>harpsichord</target><trail>ist</trail></link><space/><link><target>Wanda Landowska</target></link>. Rodin moved to the city in 1908, renting the main floor of the<space/><link><target>Htel Biron</target></link>, an 18th-century townhouse. He left Beuret in Meudon, and began an affair with the American-born Duchesse de Choiseul.<extension extension_name='ref' name="julius"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Julius, Muriel</arg><arg name="title">Human Emotion Made Tangible&nbsp;– The Work of Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">Contemporary Review</arg><arg name="volume">250</arg><arg name="issue">1452</arg><arg name="date">January 1987</arg><arg name="page">41</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>America</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Auguste Rodin, 1881-ca.1899, ve, bronze, Jardin des Tuilleries, Paris. DSC09221.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>''ve'', bronze, Auguste Rodin, 1881-ca.1899,<space/><link><target>Tuileries Garden</target><part>Jardin des Tuilleries</part></link>, Paris</part></link>While Rodin was beginning to be accepted in France by the time of<space/><italics>The Burghers of Calais</italics>, he had not yet conquered the American market and because of his technique and the frankness of some of his work, he did not have an easy time selling his work to American industrialists. Fortunately, he came to know<space/><link><target>Sarah Tyson Hallowell</target></link><space/>(18461924), a curator from Chicago who visited Paris to arrange exhibitions at the large Interstate Expositions of the 1870s and 1880s. Hallowell was not only a curator but an adviser and a facilitator who was trusted by a number of prominent American collectors to suggest works for their collections, the most prominent of these being the Chicago hotelier<space/><link><target>Potter Palmer</target></link><space/>and his wife,<space/><link><target>Bertha Palmer</target></link><space/>(18491918).</paragraph><paragraph>The next opportunity for Rodin in America was the 1893<space/><link><target>World's Columbian Exposition</target><part>Chicago World's Fair</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>The Indefatigable Miss Hallowell, Page 6</extension><space/>Hallowell wanted to help promote Rodin's work and he suggested a solo exhibition, which she wrote him was<space/><italics>beaucoup moins beau que l'original</italics><space/>but impossible, outside the rules. Instead, she suggested he send a number of works for her loan exhibition of French art from American collections and she told him she would list them as being part of an American collection.<extension extension_name='ref'>Rodin: The Shape of Genius, Page 399</extension><space/>Rodin sent Hallowell three works,<space/><italics>Cupid and Psyche</italics>,<space/><italics>Sphinx</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Andromeda</italics>. All nudes, these works provoked great controversy and were ultimately hidden behind a drape with special permission given for viewers to see them.<extension extension_name='ref' name="The Documented Image, Page 97">The Documented Image, Page 97</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Fortunately,<space/><italics>Bust of Dalou</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Burgher of Calais</italics><space/>were on display in the official French pavilion at the fair and so between the works that were on display and those that were not, he was noticed. However, the works he gave Hallowell to sell found no takers, but she soon brought the controversial Quaker-born financier<space/><link><target>Charles Yerkes</target></link><space/>(18371905) into the fold and he purchased two large marbles for his Chicago manse;<extension extension_name='ref' name="The Documented Image, Page 97"></extension><space/>Yerkes was likely the first American to own a Rodin sculpture.<extension extension_name='ref'>Franch, John (2006).<space/><italics>Robber Baron: The Life of Charles Tyson Yerkes.</italics><space/>Urbana: University of Illinois Press; p. 209.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Other collectors soon followed including the tastemaking Potter Palmers of Chicago and<space/><link><target>Isabella Stewart Gardner</target></link><space/>(18401924) of Boston, all arranged by Sarah Hallowell. In appreciation for her efforts at unlocking the American market, Rodin eventually presented Hallowell with a bronze, a marble and a terra cotta. When Hallowell moved to Paris in 1893, she and Rodin continued their warm friendship and correspondence, which lasted to the end of the sculptor's life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Extensive correspondence in Musee Rodin</extension><space/>After Hallowell's death, her niece, the painter<space/><link><target>Harriet Hallowell</target></link>, inherited the Rodins and after her death, the American heirs could not manage to match their value in order to export them, so they became the property of the French state.<extension extension_name='ref'>The indefatigable Miss Hallowell, page 8</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Great Britain</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Bundesarchiv Bild 183-R38535, Auguste Rodin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Rodin in 1914</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>After the start of the 20th century, Rodin was a regular visitor to Great Britain, where he developed a loyal following by the beginning of the First World War. He first visited England in 1881, where his friend, the artist<space/><link><target>Alphonse Legros</target></link>, had introduced him to the poet<space/><link><target>William Ernest Henley</target></link>. With his personal connections and enthusiasm for Rodin's art, Henley was most responsible for Rodin's reception in Britain.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Newton</arg><arg name="first">Joy</arg><arg name="title">'Rodin Is a British Institution'</arg><arg name="journal">The Burlington Magazine</arg><arg name="volume">136</arg><arg name="issue">1101</arg><arg name="year">1994</arg><arg name="pages">822–828</arg></template></extension><space/>(Rodin later returned the favor by sculpting a<space/><link><target>:File:HenleyRodin.JPG</target><part>bust of Henley</part></link><space/>that was used as the frontispiece to Henley's collected works and, after his death, on his monument in London.<extension extension_name='ref' name="b1"><template><target>cite DNB12</target><arg name="wstitle">Henley, William Ernest</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="pages">244, 246</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Through Henley, Rodin met<space/><link><target>Robert Louis Stevenson</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Robert Browning</target></link>, in whom he found further support.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 73.</extension><space/>Encouraged by the enthusiasm of British artists, students, and high society for his art, Rodin donated a significant selection of his works to the nation in 1914.</paragraph><paragraph>After the revitalization of the<space/><link><target>Socit Nationale des Beaux-Arts</target></link><space/>in 1890, Rodin served as the body's vice-president.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Biography</arg><arg name="publisher">Musée Rodin</arg><arg name="url">http://www.musee-rodin.fr/en/chronology-auguste-rodin</arg><arg name="accessdate">15 April 2007</arg></template></extension><space/>In 1903, Rodin was elected president of the<space/><link><target>International Society of Sculptors, Painters and Gravers</target><part>International Society of Painters, Sculptors, and Engravers</part></link>. He replaced its former president,<space/><link><target>James Abbott McNeill Whistler</target></link>, upon Whistler's death. His election to the prestigious position was largely due to the efforts of<space/><link><target>Albert Ludovici</target></link>, father of English philosopher<space/><link><target>Anthony Ludovici</target></link>, who was private secretary to Rodin for several months in 1906, but the two men parted company after Christmas, &quot;to their mutual relief.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ludovici, Anthony M. (1923). &quot;Personal Reminiscences of Auguste Rodin,&quot;<space/><italics>Cornhill Magazine</italics>, Vol. LV, Nos. 325-326, New Series.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>During his later creative years, Rodin's work turned increasingly toward the female form, and themes of more overt masculinity and femininity.<extension extension_name='ref' name="bell"></extension><space/>He concentrated on small dance studies, and produced numerous<space/><link><target>Erotic art</target><part>erotic drawings</part></link>, sketched in a loose way, without taking his pencil from the paper or his eyes from the model. Rodin met American dancer<space/><link><target>Isadora Duncan</target></link><space/>in 1900, attempted to seduce her,<extension extension_name='ref'>Hale, 10.</extension><space/>and the next year sketched studies of her and her students. In July 1906, Rodin was also enchanted by dancers from the Royal Ballet of Cambodia, and produced some of his most famous drawings from the experience.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Rodin Show Visits Home Of Artist's Muses</arg><arg name="author">Kinetz, Erica</arg><arg name="publisher">The New York Times</arg><arg name="date">27 December 2006</arg><arg name="page">E1</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Muse Rodin de Meudon 04.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Rodin's gravesite at the Muse Rodin de Meudon</part></link>Fifty-three years into their relationship, Rodin married Rose Beuret. The wedding was 29 January 1917, and Beuret died two weeks later, on 16 February.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nyt171117"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Auguste Rodin Gravely Ill
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>The New York Times
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>13
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>17 November 1917
</arg></template></extension><space/>Rodin was ill that year; in January, he suffered weakness from<space/><link><target>influenza</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Auguste Rodin Has Grip
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>The New York Times
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>3
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>30 January 1917
</arg></template></extension><space/>and on 16 November his physician announced that &quot;congestion of the lungs has caused great weakness. The patient's condition is grave.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="nyt171117"></extension><space/>Rodin died the next day, age 77, at his villa<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.musee-rodin.fr/'>Rodin's Villa des Brillants, now: Muse - Atelier Rodin 19 Avenue Auguste Rodin 92190 Meudon, Boulogne-Billancourt, Hauts-de-Seine, le-de-France, France</link></extension><space/>in<space/><link><target>Meudon</target></link>,<space/><link><target>le-de-France</target></link>, on the outskirts of Paris.<extension extension_name='ref' name="nytobit"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Rodin, Famous Sculptor, Dead
</arg><arg name="work"><space/>The New York Times
</arg><arg name="page"><space/>E3
</arg><arg name="date"><space/>18 November 1917
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>A cast of<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics><space/>was placed next to his tomb in Meudon; it was Rodin's wish that the figure serve as his<space/><link><target>headstone</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>epitaph</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Elsen, 52.</extension><space/>In 1923, Marcell Tirel, Rodin's secretary, published a book alleging that Rodin's death was largely due to cold, and the fact that he had no heat at Meudon. Rodin requested permission to stay in the<space/><link><target>Hotel Biron</target></link>, a museum of his works, but the director of the museum refused to let him stay there.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Art: Rodin's Death<space/></arg><arg name="work"><space/>Time<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>24 March 1923<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.time.com/time/magazine/article/0,9171,727018,00.html</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Duh!: The Stupid History of the Human Race<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Bob<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Fenster<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>99<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Andrews McMeel<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Kansas City<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>0-7407-1002-8<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2000</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Kiss Rodin.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>''The Kiss'', 1889</part></link><link><target>File:Auguste Rodin signature.jpg</target><part>alt=Artist's signature is raised above the surface of a sculpture.</part><part>thumb</part><part>Rodin's signature on ''<link><target>The Thinker</target></link>''</part></link><link><target>File:Musee Rodin.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The grounds of<space/><link><target>Muse Rodin</target></link></part></link><link><target>File:Philly042107-009-RodinMuseum.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Rodin Museum</target></link>, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Rodin willed to the French state his studio and the right to make casts from his plasters. Because he encouraged the edition of his sculpted work, Rodin's sculptures are represented in many public and private collections. The<space/><link><target>Muse Rodin</target></link><space/>was founded in 1916 and opened in 1919 at the<space/><link><target>Htel Biron</target></link>, where Rodin had lived, and it holds the largest Rodin collection, with more than 6,000 sculptures and 7,000 works on paper. The French order<space/><italics><link><target>Lgion d'honneur</target></link></italics><space/>made him a Commander,<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.culture.gouv.fr/public/mistral/leonore_fr?ACTION=CHERCHER&amp;amp;FIELD_1=COTE&amp;amp;VALUE_1=LH/2779/35'>Rodin, Lgion d'honneur, Ministre de la Culture et de la Communication, Lonore, Culture.gouv.fr</link></extension><space/>and he received an<space/><link><target>Honorary degree</target><part>honorary doctorate</part></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>University of Oxford</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>During his lifetime, Rodin was compared to<space/><link><target>Michelangelo</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="alhadeff"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="first">Albert</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Alhadeff</arg><arg name="title">Rodin: A Self-Portrait in the Gates of Hell</arg><arg name="journal">The Art Bulletin</arg><arg name="volume">48</arg><arg name="issue">3/4</arg><arg name="year">1966</arg><arg name="pages">393–395</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3048395</arg><arg name="jstor">3048395</arg></template></extension><space/>and was widely recognized as the greatest artist of the era.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hunisak"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Rodin Rediscovered</arg><arg name="first">John M.</arg><arg name="last">Hunisak</arg><arg name="journal">Art Journal</arg><arg name="volume">41</arg><arg name="year">1981</arg><arg name="pages">370–371</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/776450</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="jstor">776450</arg></template></extension><space/>In the three decades following his death, his popularity waned with changing aesthetic values.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hunisak"></extension><space/>Since the 1950s, Rodin's reputation has re-ascended;<extension extension_name='ref' name="werner"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Werner, Alfred</arg><arg name="title">The Return of Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">Criticism</arg><arg name="volume">2</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg><arg name="year">1960</arg><arg name="pages">48–54</arg></template></extension><space/>he is recognized as the most important sculptor of the modern era, and has been the subject of much scholarly work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="hunisak"></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="gardner"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The Hand of Rodin</arg><arg name="first">Albert Ten Eyck</arg><arg name="last">Gardner</arg><arg name="journal">The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, New Series</arg><arg name="volume">15</arg><arg name="issue">9</arg><arg name="year">1957</arg><arg name="pages">200–204</arg><arg name="doi">10.2307/3257752</arg><arg name="jstor">3257752</arg></template></extension><space/>The sense of incompletion offered by some of his sculpture, such as<space/><italics>The Walking Man</italics>, influenced the increasingly abstract sculptural forms of the 20th century.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taillandier, 23.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Rodin restored an ancient role of sculpture&amp;nbsp; to capture the physical and intellectual force of the human subject<extension extension_name='ref' name="gardner"></extension>&amp;nbsp; and he freed sculpture from the repetition of traditional patterns, providing the foundation for greater experimentation in the 20th century. His popularity is ascribed to his emotion-laden representations of ordinary men and women&amp;nbsp; to his ability to find the beauty and pathos in the human animal. His most popular works, such as<space/><italics>The Kiss</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics>, are widely used outside the fine arts as symbols of human emotion and character.<extension extension_name='ref' name="grove"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Rodin, (François-)Auguste(-René)</arg><arg name="publisher">Grove Art Online, Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="url">http://www.groveart.com/shared/views/article.html?section</arg><arg name="author">Lampert, Catherine</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 December 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>To honour Rodin's artistic legacy, the<space/><link><target>Google</target></link><space/>search engine homepage displayed a<space/><link><target>Google Doodle</target></link><space/>featuring<space/><italics>The Thinker</italics><space/>to celebrate his 172nd birthday on 12 November 2012.</paragraph><paragraph>Rodin had enormous artistic influence. A whole generation of sculptors studied in his workshop. These include<space/><link><target>Gutzon Borglum</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Antoine Bourdelle</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Constantin Brancusi</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Camille Claudel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Charles Despiau</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Malvina Hoffman</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Carl Milles</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Franois Pompon</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Clara Westhoff</target></link>, even though Brancusi later rejected his legacy. Rodin also promoted the work of other sculptors, including<space/><link><target>Aristide Maillol</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="author">Hans de Roos</arg><arg name="url">http://www.rodin-web.org/approach_art/cap18.htm</arg><arg name="date">2004</arg><arg name="title">Rodin's Approach to Art</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ivan Metrovi</target></link><space/>whom Rodin once called &quot;the greatest phenomenon amongst sculptors.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Syracuse University Archives</arg><arg name="title">Ivan Meštrović Papers</arg><arg name="url">http://archives.syr.edu/collections/fac_staff/sua_mestrovic_i.htm</arg><arg name="date">2011</arg><arg name="author">Ameena Mohammad and Meg Mason</arg></template></extension><space/>Other sculptors whose work has been described as owing to Rodin include<space/><link><target>Joseph Csaky</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Edith Balas, 1998"><link type='external' href='https://archive.org/details/bub_gb_0T8LAAAAIAAJ'>Edith Balas, 1998, ''Joseph Csaky: A Pioneer of Modern Sculpture''</link>, Philadelphia: American Philosophical Society</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Guggenheim"><link type='external' href='http://www.guggenheim.org/new-york/collections/collection-online/artists/bios/1069'>Solomon R. Guggenheim Museum, New York, ''Joseph Csky'', Collection Online</link></extension><space/><link><target>Alexander Archipenko</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Joseph Bernard</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Henri Gaudier-Brzeska</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Georg Kolbe</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Museum of Modern Art</arg><arg name="url">https://www.moma.org/collection_ge/artist.php?artist_id</arg><arg name="title">German Expressionism: Georg Kolbe</arg><arg name="author">Heather Hess</arg><arg name="date">2011</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Wilhelm Lehmbruck</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Jacques Lipchitz</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Pablo Picasso</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Adolfo Wildt</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Peggy Guggenheim Collection</arg><arg name="title">Adolfo Wildt</arg><arg name="url">http://www.guggenheim-venice.it/inglese/collections/artisti/biografia.php?id_art</arg></template></extension><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ossip Zadkine</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Musée d'Orsay</arg><arg name="url">http://www.musee-orsay.fr/en/events/exhibitions/in-the-musee-dorsay/exhibitions-in-the-musee-dorsay-more/article/oublier-rodin-20468.html?tx_ttnews%5BbackPid%5D</arg><arg name="title">Leaving Rodin behind? Sculpture in Paris, 1905-1914</arg><arg name="date">2006</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">Musée Rodin</arg><arg name="title">Rodin and Modernism</arg><arg name="url">http://www.musee-rodin.fr/en/rodin/educational-files/rodin-and-modernism</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Henry Moore</target></link><space/>acknowledged Rodin's seminal influence on his work.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="website">The Guardian</arg><arg name="url">http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2013/mar/23/henry-moore-auguste-rodin-exhibition</arg><arg name="date">23 March 2013</arg><arg name="title">Henry Moore talks about Rodin's irresistible influence – from the archive</arg></template></extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>In 2011 the world premiere of<space/><link><target>Boris Eifman</target></link>'s new ballet<space/><italics>Rodin</italics><space/>took place in Saint-Petersburg, Russia. The ballet is dedicated to the life and work of Auguste Rodin and Camille Claudel.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.eifmanballet.ru/en/repertoire/rodin</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Forgeries</heading><paragraph>The relative ease of making reproductions has also encouraged many forgeries: a survey of expert opinion placed Rodin in the top ten most-faked artists.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The 10 Most Faked Artists</arg><arg name="journal">ARTnews</arg><arg name="author">Esterow, Milton</arg><arg name="date">June 2005</arg><arg name="accessdate">5 February 2007</arg><arg name="url">http://www.artnews.com/2005/06/01/the-10-most-faked-artists/</arg></template></extension><space/>Rodin fought against forgeries of his works as early as 1901, and since his death, many cases of organized, large-scale forgeries have been revealed. A massive forgery was discovered by French authorities in the early 1990s and led to the conviction of art dealer<space/><link><target>Guy Hain</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.lejournaldesarts.fr/jda/archives/docs_article/49618/proces-guy-hain-une-decision-qui-fera-jurisprudence.php'>Procs Guy Hain, une dcision qui fera jurisprudence</link>. Le Journal des Arts. n 126. 27 April 2001. Artclair.com. Retrieved on 2011-11-02.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>To deal with the complexity of bronze reproduction, France has promulgated several laws since 1956 which limit reproduction to twelve casts&amp;nbsp; the maximum number that can be made from an artist's plasters and still be considered his work. As a result of this limit,<space/><italics><link><target>The Burghers of Calais</target></link></italics>, for example, is found in fourteen cities.<extension extension_name='ref' name="swedberg"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the market for sculpture, plagued by fakes, the value of a piece increases significantly when its provenance can be established. A Rodin work with a verified history sold for US$4.8 million in 1999,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Winship, Frederick M.</arg><arg name="title">Bogus bronzes flood market: an estimated 4,000 fake castings have put the market for 19th- and 20th-century bronze sculpture in jeopardy</arg><arg name="journal">Insight on the News</arg><arg name="date">16 September 2002</arg><arg name="volume">26</arg><arg name="issue">1</arg></template></extension><space/>and Rodin's bronze<space/><italics>Eve, grand modele&amp;nbsp; version sans rocher</italics><space/>sold for $18.9 million at a 2008<space/><link><target>Christie's</target></link><space/>auction in New York.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="publisher">AFP</arg><arg name="url">http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5jJ-nuOHmXSBq7_MFQrllsC6jrt4A</arg><arg name="title">Monet fetches record price at New York auction</arg><arg name="accessdate">8 May 2008</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20080512060740/http://afp.google.com/article/ALeqM5jJ-nuOHmXSBq7_MFQrllsC6jrt4A</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>12 May 2008<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension><space/>Art critics concerned about authenticity have argued that taking a cast does not equal reproducing a Rodin sculpture&amp;nbsp; especially given the importance of surface treatment in Rodin's work.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">The real Rodin</arg><arg name="journal">New Criterion</arg><arg name="author">Gibson, Eric</arg><arg name="year">2005</arg><arg name="issue">4</arg><arg name="volume">24</arg><arg name="pages">37–40</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Crone</arg><arg name="first">Rainer and Siegfried Salzmann, eds.</arg><arg name="title">Rodin: Eros and Creativity</arg><arg name="publisher">Prestel</arg><arg name="year">1992</arg><arg name="location">Munich</arg><arg name="isbn">3-7913-1809-8</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Elsen</arg><arg name="first">Albert E.</arg><arg name="title">Rodin</arg><arg name="publisher">The [[Museum of Modern Art]]</arg><arg name="year">1963</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="lccn">63014847</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Getsy</arg><arg name="first">David</arg><arg name="title">Rodin: Sex and the Making of Modern Sculpture</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Yale University Press</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="location">New Haven</arg><arg name="isbn">0-300-16725-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">World of Rodin, 1840-1917</arg><arg name="last">Hale</arg><arg name="first">William Harlan</arg><arg name="origyear">1969</arg><arg name="year">1973</arg><arg name="publisher">Time-Life Books</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="edition">Time-Life Library of Art</arg><arg name="lccn">70105511</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">History of Art</arg><arg name="last">Janson</arg><arg name="first">H. W.</arg><arg name="authorlink">H.W. Janson</arg><arg name="edition">3rd</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="publisher">Harry N. Abrams</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-8109-1094-2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Rodin</arg><arg name="author">Jianou, Ionel & Goldscheider, C.</arg><arg name="year">1967</arg><arg name="publisher">Arted, Editions d'Art</arg><arg name="location">Paris</arg><arg name="lccn">68084071</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Lampert</arg><arg name="first">Catherine</arg><arg name="title">Rodin: Sculpture and Drawings</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Yale University Press</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="location">New Haven</arg><arg name="isbn">0-7287-0504-4</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Le Normand-Romain</arg><arg name="first">Antoinette</arg><arg name="title">The Bronzes of Rodin</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Editions de la Réunion des Musées Nationaux</arg><arg name="year">2007</arg><arg name="location">Paris</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Ludovici</arg><arg name="first">Anthony</arg><arg name="title">Personal Reminiscences of Auguste Rodin</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>John Murray</arg><arg name="year">1926</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Morseburg</arg><arg name="first">Jeffrey</arg><arg name="title">The Indefatigable Miss Hallowell</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg></template><space/>(Online Essay)<template><target>full</target><arg name="date">November 2013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Rodin</arg><arg name="last">Taillandier</arg><arg name="first">Yvon</arg><arg name="year">1977</arg><arg name="publisher">Crown Trade Paperbacks</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-517-88378-3</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Tucker</arg><arg name="first">William</arg><arg name="title">Early Modern Sculpture</arg><arg name="year">1974</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Oxford University Press]]</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-19-519773-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Weisberg</arg><arg name="first">Gabriel</arg><arg name="title">The Documented Image, Visions in Art History</arg><arg name="year">1987</arg><arg name="publisher">[[Syracuse University Press]]</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0815624103</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Rodin</arg><arg name="first">Auguste</arg><arg name="title">Art: Conversations with Paul Gsell</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>University of California Press</arg><arg name="year">1984</arg><arg name="location">Berkeley</arg><arg name="isbn">0-520-05887-9</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Royal Academy of Arts</arg><arg name="title">Rodin</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Royal Academy of Arts</arg><arg name="year">2006</arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Chevillot</arg><arg name="first1">Catherine</arg><arg name="last2">Marraud</arg><arg name="first2">Hélène</arg><arg name="last3">Pinet</arg><arg name="first3">Hélène</arg><arg name="last4">[[John Adamson (publisher)|Adamson, John]] (transl.)</arg><arg name="first4"><space/></arg><arg name="title">Rodin: The Laboratory of Creation</arg><arg name="date">November 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Éditions Faton</arg><arg name="location">Dijon</arg><arg name="isbn">9782878442007</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Le Normand-Romain</arg><arg name="first1">Antoinette</arg><arg name="title">Rodin</arg><arg name="date">September 2014</arg><arg name="publisher">Abbeville</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">9780789212078</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Miller</arg><arg name="first">Joan Vita</arg><arg name="title">[http://libmma.contentdm.oclc.org/cdm/compoundobject/collection/p15324coll10/id/99556 Rodin: the B. Gerald Cantor Collection]</arg><arg name="year">1986</arg><arg name="publisher">Metropolitan Museum of Art</arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">9780870994432</arg></template></listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons</target><arg>Auguste Rodin</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.musee-rodin.fr/'>Muse Rodin, Paris</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rodinmuseum.org/'>Rodin Museum, Philadelphia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://museum.stanford.edu/view/rodin.html'>Rodin Collection, Stanford University</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/rodn/hd_rodn.htm'>Auguste Rodin: Timeline of Art History</link><space/>Metropolitan Museum of Art</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vam.ac.uk/content/articles/r/rodin-at-the-v-and-a/'>Rodin</link><space/>at the<space/><link><target>Victoria and Albert Museum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ils.salford.ac.uk/library/resources/special/butterworth.xml#Butterworth%20Family%20Papers'>Correspondence with Walter Butterworth</link><space/>held at the University of Salford</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.publicartfund.org/view/exhibitions/5856_rodin_at_rockefeller_center'>Public Art Fund: Rodin at Rockefeller Center</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.canal-educatif.fr/en/videos/art/2/rodin/gates-of-hell.html'>Video documentary about Rodin's work</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>Internet Archive author</target><arg name="sname">Auguste Rodin</arg></template></listitem></list><preblock><preline></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Auguste Rodin</target></template><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Persondata</target><arg name="NAME"><space/>Rodin, Auguste
</arg><arg name="ALTERNATIVE NAMES"><space/>Rodin, François-Auguste-René
</arg><arg name="SHORT DESCRIPTION"><space/>French sculptor of The Thinker and The Kiss
</arg><arg name="DATE OF BIRTH"><space/>12 November 1840
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF BIRTH"><space/>[[Paris]], France
</arg><arg name="DATE OF DEATH"><space/>1 November 1917
</arg><arg name="PLACE OF DEATH"><space/>[[Meudon]], France
</arg></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Rodin, Auguste</target></template><link><target>Category:Auguste Rodin</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:1840 births</target></link><link><target>Category:1917 deaths</target></link><link><target>Category:Artists from Paris</target></link><link><target>Category:French printmakers</target></link><link><target>Category:French sculptors</target></link><link><target>Category:Modern sculptors</target></link><link><target>Category:Grand Officiers of the Lgion d'honneur</target></link></paragraph></article>