<article title='Behistun_Inscription'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg><space/>translation of the Behistun text</arg><arg>Full translation of the Behistun Inscription</arg></template><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Bisitun</arg><arg>the city in Iran</arg><arg>Bisotun</arg></template><template><target>Coord</target><arg>34</arg><arg>23</arg><arg>26</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>47</arg><arg>26</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>E</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template><template><target>Infobox World Heritage Site</target><arg name="Name"><space/>Bisotun
</arg><arg name="Image"><space/>[[File:Bisotun Iran Relief Achamenid Period.JPG|230px|Modern day picture of the inscription]]
</arg><arg name="State Party"><space/>[[Iran]] (Islamic Republic of)
</arg><arg name="Type"><space/>Cultural
</arg><arg name="Criteria"><space/>ii, iii
</arg><arg name="ID"><space/>1222
</arg><arg name="Region"><space/>[[List of World Heritage Sites in Asia|Asia-Pacific]] ([[Iran]])
</arg><arg name="Year"><space/>2006
</arg><arg name="Session"><space/>30th
</arg><arg name="locmapin"><space/>Iran
</arg><arg name="latitude"><space/>34.388333
</arg><arg name="longitude"><space/>47.436667
</arg></template></paragraph><list type='def'><listitem><defkey></defkey></listitem></list><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Behistun Inscription</bold><space/>(also<space/><bold>Bisotun</bold>,<space/><bold>Bistun</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>Bisutun</bold>), (<template><target>lang-fa</target><arg>بیستون</arg></template>,<space/><link><target>Old Persian</target></link>:<space/><bold>Bagastana</bold>, meaning &quot;the place of god&quot;) is a multi-lingual inscription located on<space/><link><target>Mount Behistun</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>Kermanshah Province</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Iran</target></link>, near the city of<space/><link><target>Kermanshah</target></link><space/>in western<space/><link><target>Iran</target></link>. It was crucial to the decipherment of<space/><link><target>cuneiform</target></link><space/>script.</paragraph><paragraph>Authored by<space/><link><target>Darius the Great</target></link><space/>sometime between his coronation as king of the<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Empire</target><part>Persian Empire</part></link><space/>in the summer of 522 BC and his death in autumn of 486 BC, the inscription begins with a brief autobiography of Darius, including his ancestry and lineage. Later in the inscription, Darius provides a lengthy sequence of events following the deaths of<space/><link><target>Cyrus the Great</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Cambyses II</target></link><space/>in which he fought nineteen battles in a period of one year (ending in December 521 BC) to put down multiple rebellions throughout the Persian Empire. The inscription states in detail that the rebellions, which had resulted from the deaths of Cyrus the Great and his son Cambyses II, were orchestrated by several impostors and their co-conspirators in various cities throughout the empire, each of whom falsely proclaimed kinghood during the upheaval following Cyrus's death.</paragraph><paragraph>Darius the Great proclaimed himself victorious in all battles during the period of upheaval, attributing his success to the &quot;grace of<space/><link><target>Ahuramazda</target><part>Ahura Mazda</part></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The inscription includes three versions of the same text, written in three different<space/><link><target>cuneiform script</target></link><space/>languages: Old Persian,<space/><link><target>Elamite language</target><part>Elamite</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Babylonian language</target><part>Babylonian</part></link><space/>(a later form of<space/><link><target>Akkadian language</target><part>Akkadian</part></link>). In effect, then, the inscription is to<space/><link><target>cuneiform script</target><part>cuneiform</part></link><space/>what the<space/><link><target>Rosetta Stone</target></link><space/>is to<space/><link><target>Egyptian hieroglyph</target><trail>s</trail></link>: the document most crucial in the<space/><link><target>decipherment</target></link><space/>of a previously lost<space/><link><target>writing system</target><part>script</part></link>.</paragraph><preblock><preline>The inscription is approximately 15&amp;nbsp;metres high by 25&amp;nbsp;metres wide and 100&amp;nbsp;metres up a<space/><link><target>limestone</target></link><space/>cliff from an ancient road connecting the capitals of<space/><link><target>Babylonia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Medes</target><part>Media</part></link><space/>(<link><target>Babylon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Ecbatana</target></link>, respectively). The Old Persian text contains 414 lines in five columns; the Elamite text includes 593 lines in eight columns, and the Babylonian text is in 112 lines. The inscription was illustrated by a life-sized bas-relief of<space/><link><target>Darius the Great</target><part>Darius I, the Great</part></link>, holding a<space/><link><target>bow (weapon)</target><part>bow</part></link><space/>as a sign of kingship, with his left foot on the chest of a figure lying on his back before him. The supine figure is reputed to be the pretender<space/><link><target>Gaumata</target></link>. Darius is attended to the left by two servants, and nine one-meter figures stand to the right, with hands tied and rope around their necks, representing conquered peoples.<space/><link><target>Faravahar</target></link><space/>floats above, giving his blessing to the king. One figure appears to have been added after the others were completed, as was Darius's beard, which is a separate block of stone attached with<space/><link><target>iron</target></link><space/>pins and<space/><link><target>lead</target></link>.</preline></preblock><paragraph><link><target>File:BehistunRoute.jpg</target><part>225px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The route up to the inscription</part></link></paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>After the fall of the Persian Empire's<space/><link><target>Achaemenid Dynasty</target></link><space/>and its successors, and the lapse of Old Persian cuneiform writing into disuse, the nature of the inscription was forgotten, and fanciful explanations became the norm. For centuries, instead of being attributed to Darius I, the Great, it was believed to be from the reign of<space/><link><target>Khosrau II</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Persia</target></link><space/>one of the last<space/><link><target>Sassanid</target></link><space/>kings, who lived over 1000 years after the time of Darius I.</paragraph><paragraph>The inscription is mentioned by<space/><link><target>Ctesias</target><part>Ctesias of Cnidus</part></link>, who noted its existence some time around 400 BC and mentioned a well and a garden beneath the inscription. He incorrectly concluded that the inscription had been dedicated &quot;by Queen<space/><link><target>Semiramis of Babylon</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>Zeus</target></link>&quot;.<space/><link><target>Gaius Cornelius Tacitus</target><part>Tacitus</part></link><space/>also mentions it and includes a description of some of the long-lost ancillary monuments at the base of the cliff, including an altar to &quot;<link><target>Herakles</target></link>&quot;. What has been recovered of them, including a statue dedicated in 148 BC, is consistent with Tacitus's description.<space/><link><target>Diodorus Siculus</target><part>Diodorus</part></link><space/>also writes of &quot;Bagistanon&quot; and claims it was inscribed by Semiramis.</paragraph><paragraph>A legend began around<space/><link><target>Mount Behistun</target></link><space/>(Bisotun), as written about by the<space/><link><target>Persian literature</target><part>Persian poet and writer</part></link><space/><link><target>Ferdowsi</target></link><space/>in his<space/><italics><link><target>Shahnameh</target></link></italics><space/>(<italics>Book of Kings</italics>)<space/><template><target>c.</target><arg>1000</arg></template>, about a man named<space/><link><target>Farhad</target></link>, who was a lover of King Khosrow's wife,<space/><link><target>Shirin</target></link>. The legend states that, exiled for his transgression, Farhad was given the task of cutting away the mountain to find water; if he succeeded, he would be given permission to marry Shirin. After many years and the removal of half the mountain, he did find water, but was informed by Khosrow that Shirin had died. He went mad, threw his axe down the hill, kissed the ground and died. It is told in the book of<space/><link><target>Khosrow and Shirin</target></link><space/>that his axe was made out of a pomegranate tree, and, where he threw the axe, a pomegranate tree grew with fruit that would cure the ill. Shirin was not dead, according to the story, and mourned upon hearing the news.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1598, the<space/><link><target>England</target><part>Englishman</part></link><space/><link><target>Robert Sherley</target></link><space/>saw the inscription during a diplomatic mission to<space/><link><target>Iran</target><part>Persia</part></link><space/>on behalf of<space/><link><target>Austria</target></link>, and brought it to the attention of Western European scholars. His party incorrectly came to the conclusion that it was Christian in origin.<extension extension_name='ref'>E. Denison Ross, The Broadway Travellers: Sir Anthony Sherley and his Persian Adventure, Routledge, 2004, ISBN 0-415-34486-7</extension>French General Gardanne thought it showed &quot;Christ and his<space/><link><target>twelve apostles</target></link>&quot;, and<space/><link><target>Robert Ker Porter</target><part>Sir Robert Ker Porter</part></link><space/>thought it represented the<space/><link><target>Lost Tribes of Israel</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Shalmaneser I</target><part>Shalmaneser of Assyria</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/download/travelsingeorgia02port/travelsingeorgia02port.pdf'></link><space/>Robert Ker Porter, Travels in Georgia, Persia, Armenia, ancient Babylonia, &amp;c. &amp;c. : during the years 1817, 1818, 1819, and 1820, volume 2, Longman, 1821</extension>Italian explorer<space/><link><target>Pietro della Valle</target></link><space/>visited the inscription in the course of a pilgrimage in around 1621.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Translation</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Behistun DB1 1-15.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>330px</part><part>Column 1 (DB I 115), sketch by<space/><link><target>Friedrich von Spiegel</target></link><space/>(1881)</part></link><link><target>File:Aramaic translation of the behistun inscripton.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>270px</part><part><link><target>Papyrus</target></link><space/>with an<space/><link><target>Aramaic language</target><part>Aramaic</part></link><space/>translation of the Behistun inscription's text</part></link>German surveyor<space/><link><target>Carsten Niebuhr</target></link><space/>visited in around 1764 for<space/><link><target>Frederick V of Denmark</target></link>, publishing a copy of the inscription in the account of his journeys in 1778.<extension extension_name='ref'>Carsten Niebuhr, Reisebeschreibung von Arabien und anderen umliegenden Lndern, 2 volumes, 1774 and 1778</extension>Niebuhr's transcriptions were used by<space/><link><target>Georg Friedrich Grotefend</target></link><space/>and others in their efforts to decipher the<space/><link><target>Old Persian cuneiform</target></link><space/>script. Grotefend had deciphered ten of the 37 symbols of Old Persian by 1802, after realizing that unlike the Semitic cuneiform scripts, Old Persian text is alphabetic and each word is separated by a vertical slanted symbol.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.ancientscripts.com/oldpersian.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Old Persian<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Ancient Scripts<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-23</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20100418053701/http://www.ancientscripts.com/oldpersian.html</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>18 April 2010<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Old Persian text was copied and deciphered before the recovery and copying of the Elamite and Babylonian inscriptions had even been attempted, which proved to be a good deciphering strategy, since Old Persian script was easier to study due to its alphabetic nature and the fact that the language it represents had naturally evolved into<space/><link><target>Middle Persian</target></link>, and in turn, to the living modern<space/><link><target>Persian language</target></link><space/>dialects, and was also related to the<space/><link><target>Avestan</target></link><space/>language, used in the<space/><link><target>Zoroastrian</target></link><space/>book the<space/><italics><link><target>Avesta</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1835,<space/><link><target>Sir Henry Rawlinson, 1st Baronet</target><part>Sir Henry Rawlinson</part></link>, an officer of the<space/><link><target>East India Company</target><part>British East India Company</part></link><space/>army assigned to the forces of the<space/><link><target>Shah</target></link><space/>of Iran, began studying the inscription in earnest. As the town of Bisotun's name was anglicized as &quot;Behistun&quot; at this time, the monument became known as the &quot;Behistun Inscription&quot;. Despite its relative inaccessibility, Rawlinson was able to scale the cliff and copy the Old Persian inscription. The Elamite was across a chasm, and the Babylonian four meters above; both were beyond easy reach and were left for later.</paragraph><paragraph>With the Persian text, and with about a third of the<space/><link><target>syllabary</target></link><space/>made available to him by the work of<space/><link><target>Georg Friedrich Grotefend</target></link>, Rawlinson set to work on deciphering the text. Fortunately, the first section of this text contained a list of the same Persian kings found in<space/><link><target>Herodotus</target></link><space/>in their original Persian forms as opposed to Herodotus's Greek<space/><link><target>transliteration</target><trail>s</trail></link>; for example Darius is given as the original<space/><italics>Dryavu</italics><space/>instead of the Hellenized<space/><italics></italics>. By matching the names and the characters, Rawlinson was able to decipher the type of cuneiform used for Old Persian by 1838 and presented his results to the<space/><link><target>Royal Asiatic Society</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>London</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Socit Asiatique</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Paris</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the interim, Rawlinson spent a brief tour of duty in<space/><link><target>Afghanistan</target></link>, returning to the site in 1843. He first crossed a chasm between the Persian and Elamite scripts by bridging the gap with planks, subsequently copying the Elamite inscription. He was then able to find an enterprising local boy to climb up a crack in the cliff and suspend ropes across the Babylonian writing, so that<space/><link><target>papier-mch</target></link><space/>casts of the inscriptions could be taken. Rawlinson, along with several other scholars, most notably<space/><link><target>Edward Hincks</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Julius Oppert</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Henry Fox Talbot</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Edwin Norris</target></link>, either working separately or in collaboration, eventually deciphered these inscriptions, leading eventually to the ability to read them completely.</paragraph><paragraph>The translation of the Old Persian sections of the Behistun Inscription paved the way to the subsequent ability to decipher the Elamite and Babylonian parts of the text, which greatly promoted the development of modern<space/><link><target>Assyriology</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Later research and activity</heading><paragraph>The site was visited by<space/><link><target>A. V. Williams Jackson</target></link><space/>in 1903.<extension extension_name='ref'>A. V. Williams Jackson, The Great Behistun Rock and Some Results of a Re-Examination of the Old Persian Inscriptions on It, Journal of the American Oriental Society, vol. 24, pp. 7795, 1903</extension>Later expeditions, in 1904 sponsored by the<space/><link><target>British Museum</target></link><space/>and led by<space/><link><target>Leonard William King</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Reginald Campbell Thompson</target></link><space/>and in 1948 by George G. Cameron of the<space/><link><target>University of Michigan</target></link>, obtained photographs, casts and more accurate transcriptions of the texts, including passages that were not copied by Rawlinson.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.archive.org/download/sculpturesinscri00brituoft/sculpturesinscri00brituoft.pdf'></link><space/>W. King and R. C. Thompson, The sculptures and inscription of Darius the Great on the Rock of Behistn in Persia : a new collation of the Persian, Susian and Babylonian texts, Longmans, 1907</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>George G. Cameron, The Old Persian Text of the Bisitun Inscription, Journal of Cuneiform Studies, vol. 5, no. 2, pp. 4754, 1951</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>George G. Cameron, The Elamite Version of the Bisitun Inscriptions, Journal of Cuneiform Studies, vol. 14, no. 2, pp. 5968, 1960</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>W. C. Benedict and Elizabeth von Voigtlander, Darius' Bisitun Inscription, Babylonian Version, Lines 129, Journal of Cuneiform Studies, vol. 10, no. 1, pp. 110, 1956</extension>It also became apparent that rainwater had dissolved some areas of the limestone in which the text was inscribed, while leaving new deposits of limestone over other areas, covering the text.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1938, the inscription became of interest to the<space/><link><target>Nazi German</target></link><space/><link><target>think tank</target></link><space/><link><target>Ahnenerbe</target></link>, although research plans were cancelled due to the onset of World War II.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:BehistunInscriptiondetail.jpg</target><part>225px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Close-up of the inscription showing damage</part></link>The monument later suffered some damage from<space/><link><target>Allies of World War II</target><part>Allied</part></link><space/>soldiers using it for target practice in<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, during the<space/><link><target>Anglo-Soviet invasion of Iran</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://ancientstandard.com/2011/03/30/the-behistun-inscription-the-iranian-rosetta-stone/</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://atlantisonline.smfforfree2.com/index.php?topic=2799.5;wap2</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 1999, Iranian archeologists began the documentation and assessment of damages to the site incurred during the 20th century. Malieh Mehdiabadi, who was<space/><link><target>project manager</target></link><space/>for the effort, described a<space/><link><target>Photogrammetry</target><part>photogrammetric</part></link><space/>process by which two-dimensional photos were taken of the inscriptions using two cameras and later transmuted into 3-D images.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chnpress1"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.chnpress.com/news/?section</arg><arg name="title">Documentation of Behistun Inscription Nearly Complete<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Chnpress.com<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-23</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In recent years, Iranian archaeologists have been undertaking conservation works. The site became a<space/><link><target>UNESCO</target></link><space/><link><target>World Heritage Site</target></link><space/>in 2006.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.payvand.com/news/06/jul/1130.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Iran's Bisotoon Historical Site Registered in World Heritage List<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Payvand.com<space/></arg><arg name="date">2006-07-13<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-23</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2012, the Bisotun Cultural Heritage Center organized an international effort to re-examine the inscription.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.tehrantimes.com/arts-and-culture/98233-intl-experts-to-reread-bisotun-inscriptions'></link><space/>Intl. experts to reread Bisotun inscriptions, Tehran Times, May 27, 2012</extension><template><target>Clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Other historical monuments in the Behistun complex</heading><paragraph>The site covers an area of 116 hectares. Archeological evidence indicates that this region became a human shelter 40,000 years ago. There are 18 historical monuments other than the inscription of Darius the Great in the Behistun complex that have been registered in the Iranian national list of historical sites. Some of them are:</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>col-begin</target></template><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Hunters' cave</listitem><listitem><link><target>Farhad Tarash</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Medes</target><part>Median</part></link><space/>fortress</listitem><listitem><link><target>Parthia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>town</listitem><listitem><link><target>Seleucid</target></link><space/>statue of<space/><link><target>Herakles</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Parthia</target><trail>n</trail></link><space/>site of worship</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Behistun Palace</target></link><space/>(said to be Palace of<space/><link><target>Khosrau II</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ilkhanate</target><part>Ilkhanid</part></link><space/><link><target>caravanserai</target></link></listitem><listitem>Median temple</listitem><listitem>Bas relief of<space/><link><target>Mithridates II of Parthia</target></link></listitem><listitem>Bas relief of<space/><link><target>Gotarzes II of Parthia</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-3</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Sheikh Ali khan Zangeneh</target></link><space/>text endowment</listitem><listitem><link><target>Safavid</target></link><space/><link><target>caravanserai</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Vologases I of Parthia</target><part>Balash</part></link><space/>stone</listitem><listitem>Carved Sassanian stones</listitem><listitem><link><target>Royal Road</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>col-end</target></template><table style='border-collapse: collapse; border: 1px solid grey;'><tablerow><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Seleucid statue of Hercules 2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Statue of Herakles in Behistun complex</tablecell><tablecell valign="top" align="left"><link><target>Image:Godarz.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>center</part><part></part></link><xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Bas relief of<space/><link><target>Mithridates II of Parthia</target></link><space/>and bas relief of Gotarzes II of Parthia and Sheikh Ali khan Zangeneh text endowment</tablecell></tablerow></table></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Behistun palace</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Darius I of Persia</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Full translation of the Behistun Inscription</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Achaemenid dynasty</target><part>Achaemenid empire</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taq-e Bostan</target></link><space/>(Rock reliefs of various Sassanid kings)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Pasargadae</target></link><space/>(Tomb of Pasargadae<space/><link><target>Cyrus the Great</target></link>)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ka'ba-i Zartosht</target></link><space/>(The &quot;Cube of Zoroaster&quot;, a monument at Naqsh-e Rustam)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Naqsh-e Rajab</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Cities of the Ancient Near East</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gaumata (False Smerdis)</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Adkins, Lesley,<space/><italics>Empires of the Plain: Henry Rawlinson and the Lost Languages of Babylon</italics>, St. Martin's Press, New York, 2003.</listitem><listitem>Rawlinson, H.C.,<space/><italics>Archaeologia</italics>, 1853, vol. xxxiv, p.&amp;nbsp;74.</listitem><listitem>Thompson, R. Campbell. &quot;The Rock of Behistun&quot;.<space/><italics>Wonders of the Past</italics>. Edited by Sir J. A. Hammerton. Vol. II. New York: Wise and Co., 1937. (pp.&amp;nbsp;760767)<space/><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://members.ozemail.com.au/~ancientpersia/behistun.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Behistun<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Members.ozemail.com.au<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-23</arg></template><template><target>dead link</target><arg name="date">October 2014</arg></template></listitem><listitem>Cameron, George G. &quot;Darius Carved History on Ageless Rock&quot;.<space/><italics><link><target>National Geographic Magazine</target></link></italics>. Vol. XCVIII, Num. 6, December 1950. (pp.&amp;nbsp;825844)</listitem><listitem>Rubio, Gonzalo. &quot;Writing in another tongue: Alloglottography in the Ancient Near East&quot;. In<space/><italics>Margins of Writing, Origins of Cultures</italics><space/>(ed. Seth Sanders. 2nd printing with postscripts and corrections. Oriental Institute Seminars, 2. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 2007), pp.&amp;nbsp;3370.<template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://oi.uchicago.edu/research/pubs/catalog/ois/ois2.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Oriental Institute &#124; Oriental Institute Seminars (OIS)<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Oi.uchicago.edu<space/></arg><arg name="date">2009-06-18<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2010-04-23</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link><target>Louis Herbert Gray</target><part>Louis H. Gray</part></link>, Notes on the Old Persian Inscriptions of Behistun, Journal of the American Oriental Society, vol. 23, pp.&amp;nbsp;5664, 1902</listitem><listitem>A. T. Olmstead, Darius and His Behistun Inscription, The American Journal of Semitic Languages and Literatures, vol. 55, no. 4, pp.&amp;nbsp;392416, 1938</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Behistun Inscription</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The sculptures and inscription of Darius the Great on the Rock of Behistûn in Persia : a new collation of the Persian, Susian and Babylonian texts, with English translations, etc<space/></arg><arg name="first1">L. W.<space/></arg><arg name="last1">King<space/></arg><arg name="first2">R. Campbell<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Thompson<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[British Museum]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1907<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/details/sculpturesinscri00brituoft<space/></arg></template><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/be-bm/behistun/behistun01.html'>The Behistun Inscription</link>, livius.org article by Jona Lendering, including Persian text (in cuneiform and transliteration), King and Thompson's English translation, and additional materials</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="title">The Behistan inscription of King Darius: translation and critical notes to the Persian text with special reference to recent re-examinations of the rock<space/></arg><arg name="last">Tolman<space/></arg><arg name="first">Herbert Cushing<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">[[Vanderbilt University]]<space/></arg><arg name="year">1908<space/></arg><arg name="url">https://archive.org/details/behistaninscript00daririch<space/></arg></template><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://mcadams.posc.mu.edu/txt/ah/Persia/Behistun_txt.html'>Tolman's English translation of the inscription text</link></listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://whc.unesco.org/en/list/1222'>Brief description of Bisotun</link><space/>from<space/><link><target>UNESCO</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chnpress.com/news/?section=2&amp;amp;id=7430'>&quot;Bisotun receives its World Heritage certificate&quot;</link>,<space/><link><target>Cultural Heritage News Agency</target></link>, Tehran, July 3, 2008</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.livius.org/be-bm/behistun/behistun-rem.html'>Other monuments of Behistun</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>World Heritage Sites in Iran</target></template><template><target>Kermanshah Province</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Behistun Inscription</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Achaemenid Empire</target></link><link><target>Category:Buildings and structures in Kermanshah Province</target></link><link><target>Category:Multilingual texts</target></link><link><target>Category:Archaeological corpora documents</target></link><link><target>Category:Archaeological sites in Iran</target></link><link><target>Category:Sculpture of the Ancient Near East</target></link><link><target>Category:Cyrus the Great</target></link><link><target>Category:World Heritage Sites in Iran</target></link><link><target>Category:Visitor attractions in Kermanshah Province</target></link></paragraph></article>