<article title='Cruiser'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><link><target>Image:USS Port Royal CG-73.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>300px</part><part>right</part><part><template><target>USS</target><arg>Port Royal</arg><arg>CG-73</arg></template>, a<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Ticonderoga</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/><link><target>guided missile</target></link><space/>cruiser, launched in 1992</part></link><link><target>Image:Missile cruiser Varyag in Vladivostok, 2010.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Slava</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in Vladivostok</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>cruiser</bold><space/>is a type of<space/><link><target>warship</target></link>. The term has been in use for several hundred years, and has had different meanings throughout this period. During the<space/><link><target>Age of Sail</target></link>, the term<space/><italics>cruising</italics><space/>referred to certain kinds of missions &amp;ndash; independent scouting, raiding or commerce protection &amp;ndash; fulfilled by a<space/><link><target>frigate</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>sloop</target></link>, which were the<space/><italics>cruising warships</italics><space/>of a fleet.</paragraph><paragraph>In the middle of the 19th century,<space/><italics>cruiser</italics><space/>came to be a classification for the ships intended for this kind of role, though cruisers came in a wide variety of sizes, from the small<space/><link><target>protected cruiser</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>armored cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that were as large (although not as powerful) as a<space/><link><target>battleship</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>By the early 20th century, cruisers could be placed on a consistent scale of warship size, smaller than a battleship but larger than a<space/><link><target>destroyer</target></link>. In 1922, the<space/><link><target>Washington Naval Treaty</target></link><space/>placed a formal limit on cruisers, which were defined as warships of up to 10,000 tons displacement carrying guns no larger than 8&amp;nbsp;inches in calibre. These limits shaped cruisers until the end of World War II. The very large<space/><link><target>battlecruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the World War I era were now classified, along with battleships, as<space/><link><target>capital ship</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the later 20th century, the obsolescence of the battleship left the cruiser as the largest and most powerful surface combatant (excluding<space/><link><target>aircraft carrier</target><trail>s</trail></link>). The role of the cruiser varied according to ship and navy, often including air defense, commerce raiding, and shore bombardment. The U.S. Navy in the Cold War period built guided-missile cruisers primarily designed to provide air defense, while the navy of the USSR built battlecruisers with heavy<space/><link><target>anti-ship missile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>designed to sink NATO carrier task forces.</paragraph><paragraph>Currently only three nations operate cruisers: the<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target><part>United States</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Russian Navy</target><part>Russia</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Peruvian Navy</target><part>Peru</part></link>. (<template><target>ship</target><arg>BAP</arg><arg>Almirante Grau</arg><arg>CLM-81</arg></template><space/>is still in service with the Peruvian Navy, and is the last gun cruiser currently in service in any navy), though the line between cruisers and destroyers is once again blurred. New models of destroyers (for instance the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Zumwalt</arg><arg>destroyer</arg><arg>4</arg></template>) are often larger and more powerful than cruiser classes they replace.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Early history</heading><paragraph>The term &quot;cruiser&quot; or &quot;cruizer&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>The alternative spelling could be found at least as late as 1900:<space/><link><target>John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher</target><part>Jackie Fisher</part></link><space/>wrote &quot;We a require an increase.... in all classes of cruizer&quot; in a letter dated 20th Feb 1900. Mackay, R.<space/><italics>Fisher of Kilverstone</italics>, p. 242.</extension><space/>was first commonly used in the 17th century to refer to an independent warship. &quot;Cruiser&quot; meant the purpose or mission of a ship, rather than a category of vessel. However, the term was nonetheless used to mean a smaller, faster warship suitable for such a role. In the 17th century, the<space/><link><target>ship of the line</target></link><space/>was generally too large, inflexible, and expensive to be dispatched on long-range missions (for instance, to the Americas), and too strategically important to be put at risk of fouling and foundering by continual patrol duties.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Dutch navy</target></link><space/>was noted for its cruisers in the 17th century, while the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>and later French and Spanish naviessubsequently caught up in terms of their numbers and deployment. The British<space/><link><target>Cruiser and Convoy Act</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>were an attempt by mercantile interests in Parliament to focus the Navy on commerce defence and raiding with cruisers, rather than the more scarce and expensive ships of the line.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Rodger, N. A. M.</target></link>:<space/><italics>The Command of the Ocean, A Naval History of Britain 16491815</italics>. Allen Lane, London, 2004. ISBN 0-7139-9411-8</extension><space/>During the 18th century the<space/><link><target>frigate</target></link><space/>became the preeminent type of cruiser. A frigate was a small, fast, long range, lightly armed (single gun-deck) ship used for scouting, carrying dispatches, and disrupting enemy trade. The other principal type of cruiser was the<space/><link><target>sloop</target></link>, but many other miscellaneous types of ship were used as well.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Steam cruisers</heading><paragraph>During the 19th century, navies began to use steam power for their fleets. The 1840s saw the construction of experimental steam-powered frigates and sloops. By the middle of the 1850s, the British and U.S. Navies were both building steam frigates with very long hulls and a heavy gun armament, for instance<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Merrimack</arg><arg>1855</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>or<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Mersey</arg><arg>1858</arg><arg>2</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Parkes, p.8</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The 1860s saw the introduction of the<space/><link><target>ironclad</target></link>. The first ironclads were frigates, in the sense of having one gun deck; however, they were also clearly the most powerful ships in the navy, and were principally to serve in the line of battle. In spite of their great speed, they would have been wasted in a cruising role.<extension extension_name='ref'>Parkes, p.17</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The French constructed a number of smaller ironclads for overseas cruising duties, starting with the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French ironclad</arg><arg>Belliqueuse</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, commissioned 1865. These &quot;station ironclads&quot; were the beginning of the development of the<space/><link><target>armored cruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>, a type of ironclad specifically for the traditional cruiser missions of fast, independent raiding and patrol.</paragraph><paragraph>The first true armored cruiser was the Russian<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian cruiser</arg><arg>General-Admiral</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>, completed in 1874, and followed by the British<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shannon</arg><arg>1875</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>a few years later.</paragraph><paragraph>Until the 1890s armored cruisers were still built with masts for a full sailing rig, to enable them to operate far from friendly coaling stations.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hill, Richard:<space/><italics>War at Sea in the Ironclad Age</italics>. Cassell, London, 2000. ISBN 0-304-35273-X.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Unarmored cruising warships, built out of wood, iron, steel or a combination of those materials, remained popular until towards the end of the 19th century. The ironclad's armor often meant that they were limited to short range under steam, and many ironclads were unsuited to long-range missions or for work in distant colonies. The unarmored cruiser - often a<space/><link><target>screw sloop</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>screw frigate</target></link><space/>- could continue in this role. Even though mid- or late-19th century cruisers typically carried up-to-date guns firing explosive shells, they were unable to face ironclads in combat. This was evidenced by the clash between<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Shah</arg><arg>1873</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, a modern British cruiser, and the Peruvian<space/><link><target>Monitor (warship)</target><part>monitor</part></link><space/><link><target>Huscar (ironclad)</target><part>''Huscar''</part></link>. Even though the Peruvian vessel was obsolescent by the time of the encounter, it stood up well to roughly 50 hits from British shells.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Steel cruisers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Protected cruiser</arg></template><link><target>Image:Croiseur Aurore.png</target><part>thumb</part><part>The Russian protected cruiser<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian cruiser</arg><arg>Aurora</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1880s naval architects began to use<space/><link><target>steel</target></link><space/>as a material for construction and armament. A steel cruiser could be lighter and faster than one built of iron or wood. The<space/><italics><link><target>Jeune Ecole</target></link></italics><space/>school of naval doctrine suggested that a fleet of fast unprotected steel cruisers were ideal for<space/><link><target>commerce raiding</target></link>, while the<space/><link><target>torpedo boat</target></link><space/>would be able to destroy an enemy battleship fleet.</paragraph><paragraph>Steel also offered the cruiser a way of acquiring the protection needed to survive in combat. Steel armor was considerably stronger, for the same weight, than iron. By putting a relatively thin layer of steel armor above the vital parts of the ship, and by placing the coal bunkers where they might stop shellfire, a useful degree of protection could be achieved without slowing the ship too much.</paragraph><paragraph>The first protected cruiser was the Chilean ship<space/><link><target>Chilean cruiser Esmeralda (1883)</target><part>''Esmeralda''</part></link>. Produced by a shipyard at<space/><link><target>Elswick, Tyne and Wear</target><part>Elswick</part></link>, in Britain, owned by Armstrong, she inspired a group of protected cruisers produced in the same yard and known as the &quot;Elswick cruisers&quot;. Her<space/><link><target>forecastle</target></link>,<space/><link><target>poop deck</target></link><space/>and the wooden board deck had been removed, replaced with an armored deck.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Esmeralda</italics><template><target>'</target></template>s armament consisted of fore and aft 10-inch (25.4&amp;nbsp;cm) guns and 6-inch (15.2&amp;nbsp;cm) guns in the midships positions. It could reach a speed of<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>18</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>0</arg></template>, and was propelled by steam alone. It also had a displacement of less than 3,000 tons. During the two following decades, this cruiser type came to be the inspiration for combining heavy artillery, high speed and low displacement.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Torpedo cruisers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Torpedo cruiser</arg></template>The torpedo cruiser (known in the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/>as the<space/><link><target>torpedo gunboat</target></link>) was a smaller unarmored cruiser, which emerged in the 1880s-1890s. These ships could reach speeds up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>20</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg>km/h</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>and were armed with medium to small calibre guns as well as torpedoes. These ships were tasked with guard and reconnaissance duties, to repeat signals and all other fleet duties for which smaller vessels were suited. These ships could also function as flagships of torpedo boat flotillas. After the 1900s, these ships were usually traded for faster ships with better sea going qualities.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Pre-dreadnought armored cruisers</heading><paragraph>Steel also had an impact on the construction and role of armored cruisers. Steel meant that new designs of battleship, later known as<space/><link><target>pre-dreadnought battleship</target><trail>s</trail></link>, would be able to combine firepower and armor with better endurance and speed than ever before. The armored cruisers of the 1890s greatly resembled the battleships of the day; they tended to carry slightly smaller main armament (<template><target>convert</target><arg>9.2</arg><arg>in</arg><arg>mm</arg><arg name="adj">on</arg></template><space/>rather than 12-inch) and have somewhat thinner armor in exchange for a faster speed (perhaps<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>21</arg><arg>kn</arg><arg>km/h</arg></template><space/>rather than 18). Because of their similarity, the lines between battleships and armored cruisers became blurred.</paragraph><heading level='2'>In early 20th century</heading><paragraph>Shortly after the turn of the 20th century there were difficult questions about the design of future cruisers. Modern armored cruisers, almost as powerful as battleships, were also fast enough to outrun older protected and unarmored cruisers. In the Royal Navy,<space/><link><target>John Fisher, 1st Baron Fisher</target><part>Jackie Fisher</part></link><space/>cut back hugely on older vessels, including many cruisers of different sorts, calling them 'a miser's hoard of useless junk' that any modern cruiser would sweep from the seas.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Battlecruisers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Battlecruiser</arg></template><link><target>Image:LionSP 001672.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>HMS ''Lion'' (1910)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The growing size and power of the armored cruiser resulted in the<space/><link><target>battlecruiser</target></link>, with an armament and size similar to the revolutionary new<space/><link><target>dreadnought battleship</target></link>; the brainchild of British admiral Jackie Fisher. He believed that to ensure British naval dominance in its overseas colonial possessions, a fleet of large, fast, powerfully-armed vessels which would be able to hunt down and mop up enemy cruisers and armored cruisers with overwhelming fire superiority was needed. This type of vessel came to be known as the<space/><italics>battlecruiser</italics>, and the first were commissioned into the Royal Navy in 1907. Germany and eventually Japan followed suit to build these vessels, replacing armored cruisers in most frontline roles. Battlecruisers were in many cases larger and more expensive than contemporary battleships.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Light cruisers</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:HMS Caroline 1914.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Caroline</arg><arg>1914</arg><arg>6</arg></template>, a<space/><link><target>World War I</target></link><space/>era light cruiser, served as a headquarters and training vessel in<space/><link><target>Belfast</target></link><space/>until 2011.</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Light cruiser</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>At around the same time as the battlecruiser was developed, the distinction between the armored and the unarmored cruiser finally disappeared. By the British<space/><template><target>sclass2-</target><arg>Town</arg><arg>cruiser (1910)</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, it was possible for a small, fast cruiser to carry both belt and deck armor, particularly when turbine engines were adopted. These light armored cruisers' began to occupy the traditional cruiser role once it became clear that the battlecruiser squadrons were required to operate with the battle fleet.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Flotilla leaders</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Flotilla leader</arg></template>Some light cruisers were built specifically to act as the leaders of flotillas of<space/><link><target>destroyer</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Auxiliary cruisers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Auxiliary cruiser</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Armed merchantmen</target><part>auxiliary cruiser</part></link><space/>was a<space/><link><target>merchant marine</target><part>merchant ship</part></link><space/>hastily armed with small guns on the outbreak of war. Auxiliary cruisers were used to fill gaps in their long-range lines or provide escort for other cargo ships, although they generally proved to be useless in this role because of their low speed, feeble firepower and lack of armor. In both world wars the Germans also used small merchant ships armed with cruiser guns to surprise Allied merchant ships.</paragraph><paragraph>Some large liners were armed in the same way. In British service these were known as Armed Merchant Cruisers (AMC). The Germans and French used them in World War I as raiders because of their high speed (around 30&amp;nbsp;knots (56&amp;nbsp;km/h)), and they were used again as raiders in World War II by the Germans and Japanese. In both the First World War and in the early part of the Second, they were used as convoy escorts by the British.</paragraph><heading level='3'>World War I</heading><paragraph>Cruisers were one of the workhorse types of<space/><link><target>Naval warfare of World War I</target><part>warship during World War I</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>During mid-20th century</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Armando Diaz AllenGren3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Italian cruiser<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Italian cruiser</arg><arg>Armando Diaz</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Naval construction in the 1920s and 1930s was limited by international treaties designed to prevent the repetition of the<space/><link><target>Dreadnought</target></link><space/>arms race of the early 20th century. The<space/><link><target>Washington Naval Treaty</target></link><space/>of 1922 placed limits on the construction of ships with a displacement of 10,000<space/><link><target>ton</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>or more and an armament of greater than 8-inch (203&amp;nbsp;mm). A number of navies commissioned classes of cruisers at the top end of this limit.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>London Naval Treaty</target></link><space/>in 1930 then formalised the distinction between these 'heavy' cruisers and light cruisers: a 'heavy' cruiser was one with guns of 6.1-inch (155&amp;nbsp;mm) calibre or more. The<space/><link><target>Second London Naval Treaty</target></link><space/>attempted to reduce the tonnage of new cruisers to 8,000 or less, but this had little impact; Japan and Germany were not signatories, and navies had already begun to evade treaty limitations on warships.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Heavy cruisers</heading><paragraph><template><target>see also</target><arg>Heavy cruiser</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>heavy cruiser</italics><space/>was a type of cruiser, a naval warship designed for long range, high speed and an armament of naval guns roughly 8-inch (203&amp;nbsp;mm) in calibre. The first heavy cruisers were built in 1915, although it only became a widespread classification following the London Naval Treaty in 1930. The heavy cruiser's immediate precursors were the<space/><link><target>light cruiser</target></link><space/>designs of the 1910s and 1920s; the US 8-inch 'treaty cruisers' of the 1920s were originally classed as light cruisers until the London Treaty forced their redesignation. Heavy cruisers continued in use until after World War II.</paragraph><heading level='3'>German pocket battleships</heading><paragraph>The German<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Deutschland</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>was a series of three<space/><italics>Panzerschiffe</italics><space/>(&quot;armored ships&quot;), a form of heavily armed cruiser, built by the<space/><link><target>Reichsmarine</target><part>German Reichsmarine</part></link><space/>in nominal accordance with restrictions imposed by the<space/><link><target>Treaty of Versailles</target></link>. The class is named after the first ship of this class to be completed (the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>German cruiser</arg><arg>Deutschland</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template>). All three ships were launched between 1931 and 1934, and served with Germany's<space/><link><target>Kriegsmarine</target></link><space/>during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>. During the war, they were reclassified as heavy cruisers.</paragraph><paragraph>The British press began referring to the vessels as pocket battleships, in reference to the heavy firepower contained in the relatively small vessels; they were considerably smaller than contemporary<space/><link><target>battleship</target><trail>s</trail></link>, though at 28 knots, were slower than<space/><link><target>battlecruiser</target><trail>s</trail></link>. And although their displacement and scale of armor protection was that of a<space/><link><target>heavy cruiser</target></link>, they were armed with guns larger than the heavy cruisers of other nations.<space/><italics>Deutschland</italics>-class ships continue to be called<space/><italics>pocket battleships</italics><space/>in some circles.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Anti-aircraft cruisers</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:USS Atlanta (CL-51).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>USS Atlanta (CL-51)</target><part>USS ''Atlanta'' (CL-51)</part></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The development of the anti-aircraft cruiser began in 1935 when the<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link><space/>re-armed<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Coventry</arg><arg>D43</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Curlew</arg><arg>D42</arg><arg>6</arg></template>. Torpedo tubes and 6-inch (15&amp;nbsp;cm) low-angle guns were removed from these World War I light cruisers and replaced by ten 4-inch (10&amp;nbsp;cm) high-angle guns with appropriate fire-control equipment to provide larger warships with protection against high-altitude bombers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman, Norman &quot;Anti-Aircraft Cruisers: The Life of a Class&quot;<space/><italics>United States Naval Institute Proceedings</italics><space/>January 1965 p. 86</extension></paragraph><paragraph>A tactical shortcoming was recognized after completing six additional conversions of<space/><template><target>sclass2-</target><arg>C</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>1</arg></template>s. Having sacrificed anti-ship weapons for anti-aircraft armament, the converted anti-aircraft cruisers might need protection themselves against surface units. New construction was undertaken to create cruisers of similar speed and displacement with<space/><link><target>dual-purpose gun</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Dual-purpose guns offered good anti-aircraft protection with anti-surface capability for the traditional light cruiser role of defending capital ships from destroyers. The first purpose built anti-aircraft cruiser was the British<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Dido</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, completed shortly before the beginning of World War II. The US Navy<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Atlanta</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>anti-aircraft cruisers (CLAA) were designed to match capabilities of the Royal Navy. Both<space/><italics>Dido</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>Atlanta</italics><space/>carried torpedo tubes.</paragraph><paragraph>The quick-firing dual-purpose gun anti-aircraft cruiser concept was embraced in several designs completed too late to see combat including<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Worcester</arg><arg>CL-144</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Roanoke</arg><arg>CL-145</arg></template><space/>completed in 1948 and 1949, two<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>De Zeven Provinciën</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s completed in 1953,<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French cruiser</arg><arg>De Grasse</arg><arg>C610</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French cruiser</arg><arg>Colbert</arg><arg>C611</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>completed in 1955 and 1959, and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Tiger</arg><arg>C20</arg><arg>6</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Lion</arg><arg>C34</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Blake</arg><arg>C99</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>completed between 1959 and 1961.<extension extension_name='ref'>Friedman, Norman &quot;Anti-Aircraft Cruisers: The Life of a Class&quot;<space/><italics>United States Naval Institute Proceedings</italics><space/>January 1965 pp.96-97</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Most postWorld War II cruisers were tasked with air defense roles. In the early 1950s, advances in aviation technology forced the move from anti-aircraft artillery to anti-aircraft missiles. Therefore, most cruisers of today are equipped with surface-to-air missiles as their main armament. The modern equivalent of the anti-aircraft cruiser is the<space/><bold>guided missile cruiser</bold><space/>(CAG/CLG/CG/CGN).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Late 20th century</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Kirov-class battlecruiser.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Russian Navy battlecruiser of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kirov</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>4</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Soviet cruiser</arg><arg>Frunze</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The rise of air power during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>dramatically changed the nature of naval combat. Even the fastest cruisers could not maneuver quickly enough to evade aerial attack, and aircraft now had torpedoes, allowing moderate-range standoff capabilities. This change led to the end of independent operations by single ships or very small task groups, and for the second half of the 20th century naval operations were based on very large fleets able to fend off all but the largest air attacks.</paragraph><paragraph>This has led most navies to change to fleets designed around ships dedicated to a single role,<space/><link><target>anti-submarine</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>anti-aircraft</target></link><space/>typically, and the large &quot;generalist&quot; ship has disappeared from most forces. The<space/><link><target>United States Navy</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Russian Navy</target></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Peruvian Navy</target></link><space/>are the only remaining navies which operate cruisers. Italy used the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Italian cruiser</arg><arg>Vittorio Veneto</arg><arg>550</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>until 2003; France operated a single helicopter cruiser until May 2010,<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French cruiser</arg><arg>Jeanne d'Arc</arg><arg>R97</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, for training purposes only.</paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><link><target>Soviet Navy</target></link>, cruisers formed the basis of combat groups. In the immediate post-war era it built a fleet of large-gun ships, but replaced these fairly quickly with very large ships carrying huge numbers of<space/><link><target>guided missile</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and anti-aircraft missiles. The most recent ships of this type, the four<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kirov</arg><arg>battlecruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s, were built in the 1970s and 1980s. Two of the<space/><italics>Kirov</italics><space/>class are in refit until 2020, and one was scheduled to leave refit in 2018, with the<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian battlecruiser</arg><arg>Petr Velikiy</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in active service. Russia also operates three<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Slava</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s and one<space/><italics>Admiral Kuznetsov</italics>-class carrier which is officially designated as a cruiser.</paragraph><paragraph>Currently, the<space/><italics>Kirov</italics>-class heavy missile cruisers are used for command purposes, as the<space/><italics>Petr Velikiy</italics><space/>is the<space/><link><target>flagship</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Northern Fleet</target></link>. However, their air defense capabilities are still powerful, as shown by the array of<space/><link><target>Point defense</target></link><space/>missiles they carry, from 44<space/><link><target>9K33 Osa#Variants</target><part>OSA-MA</part></link><space/>missiles to 196<space/><link><target>Tor missile system#3K95 Kinzhal</target><part>9K311 Tor</part></link><space/>missiles. For longer range targets, the<space/><link><target>S-300 (missile)</target><part>S-300</part></link><space/>is used. For closer range targets,<space/><link><target>AK-630</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Kashtan</target></link><space/>CIWSs are used. Aside from that,<space/><italics>Kirov</italics>s have 20<space/><link><target>P-700 Granit</target></link><space/>missiles for anti-ship warfare. For target acquisition beyond the<space/><link><target>radar horizon</target></link>, three<space/><link><target>helicopter</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>can be used. Besides a vast array of armament,<space/><italics>Kirov</italics>-class cruisers are also outfitted with many sensors and communications equipment, allowing them to lead the fleet.</paragraph><paragraph>The United States Navy has centered on the aircraft carrier since World War II. The<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Ticonderoga</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>s, built in the 1980s, were originally designed and designated as a class of<space/><link><target>destroyer</target></link>, intended to provide a very powerful air-defense in these carrier-centered fleets.</paragraph><paragraph>In the years since the launch of<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Ticonderoga</arg><arg>CG-47</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>in 1981 the class has received a number of upgrades that have dramatically improved its members' capabilities for<space/><link><target>anti-submarine</target></link><space/>and land attack (using the<space/><link><target>Tomahawk (missile)</target><part>Tomahawk missile</part></link>). Like their Soviet counterparts, the modern<space/><italics>Ticonderoga</italics>s can also be used as the basis for an entire battle group. Their cruiser designation was almost certainly deserved when first built, as their sensors and combat management systems enable them to act as 'flagships' for a surface warship flotilla if no carrier is present, but newer ships rated as destroyers and also equipped with AEGIS approach them very closely in capability, and once more blur the line between the two classes.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Aircraft cruisers</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:VSTOL Guided Missile Cruiser CG VSTOL 1980.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>One cruiser alternative studied in the late 1980s by the United States was variously entitled a Mission Essential Unit (MEU) or CG V/STOL.</part></link><template><target>main</target><arg>Aircraft cruiser</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>From time to time, some navies have experimented with aircraft-carrying cruisers. One example is the Swedish<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>HSwMS</arg><arg>Gotland</arg><arg>1933</arg><arg>2</arg></template>. Another variant is the<space/><italics>helicopter cruiser</italics>. The last example in service was the Soviet Navy's<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Kiev</arg><arg>aircraft carrier</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, whose last unit<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Soviet aircraft carrier</arg><arg>Admiral Gorshkov</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>was converted to a pure aircraft carrier and sold to<space/><link><target>India</target></link><space/>as<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>INS</arg><arg>Vikramaditya</arg></template>. The Russian Navy's<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian aircraft carrier</arg><arg>Admiral Kuznetsov</arg><arg></arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>is nominally designated as an aviation cruiser but otherwise resembles a standard medium aircraft carrier, albeit with a<space/><link><target>surface-to-surface missile</target></link><space/>battery. The<space/><link><target>Royal Navy</target></link>'s aircraft-carrying<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Invincible</arg><arg>aircraft carrier</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Italian Navy</target></link>'s aircraft-carrying<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Italian aircraft carrier</arg><arg>Giuseppe Garibaldi</arg><arg>551</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>vessels were originally designated 'through-deck cruisers', but have since been designated as small aircraft carriers. Similarly, the<space/><link><target>Japan Maritime Self-Defense Force</target></link>'s<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Haruna</arg><arg>destroyer</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Shirane</arg><arg>destroyer</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>&quot;helicopter destroyers&quot; are really more along the lines of helicopter cruisers in function and aircraft complement, but due to the<space/><link><target>Treaty of San Francisco</target></link>, must be designated as destroyers.</paragraph><paragraph>One cruiser alternative studied in the late 1980s by the United States was variously entitled a Mission Essential Unit (MEU) or CG V/STOL. In a return to the thoughts of the independent operations cruiser-carriers of the 1930s and the Russian<space/><italics>Kiev</italics>-class, the ship was fitted with a hangar, elevators and a flight deck. The mission systems were Aegis, SQS-53 sonar, 12 SV-22 ASW aircraft and 200 VLS cells. The resulting ship had a waterline length of 700 feet, a waterline beam of 97 feet, and a displacement of about 25,000 tons. Other features included an integrated electric drive and advanced computer systems, both stand-alone and networked. It was part of the U.S. Navy's 'Revolution At Sea' effort. The project was curtailed by the sudden end of the Cold War and its aftermath, otherwise the first of class would have been likely ordered in the early 1990s.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>US Navy's &quot;cruiser gap&quot;</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>United States Navy 1975 ship reclassification</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Prior to the introduction of the<space/><italics>Ticonderoga</italics>s, the US Navy used odd naming conventions that left its fleet seemingly without many cruisers, although a number of their ships were cruisers in all but name. From the 1950s to the 1970s, US Navy cruisers were large vessels equipped with heavy offensive missiles (including the<space/><link><target>Regulus missile</target><part>Regulus</part></link><space/><link><target>nuclear weapon</target><part>nuclear</part></link><space/><link><target>cruise missile</target></link>) for wide-ranging combat against land-based and sea-based targets. All save one<template><target>USS</target><arg>Long Beach</arg><arg>CGN-9</arg></template>were converted from World War II cruisers of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Oregon City</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Baltimore</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Cleveland</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>classes.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Frigate</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>under this scheme were almost as large as the cruisers and optimized for<space/><link><target>anti-aircraft</target></link><space/>warfare, although they were capable anti-surface warfare combatants as well. In the late 1960s, the US government perceived a &quot;cruiser gap&quot;at the time, the US Navy possessed six ships designated as cruisers, compared to 19 for the Soviet Union, even though the USN had 21 ships designated as frigates with equal or superior capabilities to the Soviet cruisers at the time. Because of this, in 1975 the Navy performed a massive redesignation of its forces:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>CVA/CVAN (Attack Aircraft Carrier/Nuclear-powered Attack Aircraft Carrier) were redesignated CV/CVN (although<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Midway</arg><arg>CV-41</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>USS</target><arg>Coral Sea</arg><arg>CV-43</arg></template><space/>never embarked anti-submarine squadrons).</listitem><listitem>DLG/DLGN (Frigates/Nuclear-powered Frigates) of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Leahy</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Bainbridge</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Belknap</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template>,<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Truxtun</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>and<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>California</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>5</arg></template><space/>classes were redesignated CG/CGN (Guided Missile Cruiser/Nuclear-powered Guided Missile Cruiser).</listitem><listitem><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Farragut</arg><arg>destroyer (1958)</arg><arg>4</arg></template><space/>guided missile frigates (DLG), being smaller and less capable than the others, were redesignated to DDGs (<template><target>USS</target><arg>Coontz</arg><arg>DDG-40</arg><arg>6</arg></template><space/>was the first ship of this class to be re-numbered; because of this the class is sometimes called the<space/><italics>Coontz</italics><space/>class);</listitem><listitem>DE/DEG (Ocean Escort/Guided Missile Ocean Escort) were redesignated to FF/FFG (Guided Missile Frigates), bringing the US &quot;Frigate&quot; designation into line with the rest of the world.</listitem></list><paragraph>Also, a series of Patrol Frigates of the<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Oliver Hazard Perry</arg><arg>frigate</arg><arg>4</arg></template>, originally designated PFG, were redesignated into the FFG line. The cruiser-destroyer-frigate realignment and the deletion of the Ocean Escort type brought the US Navy's ship designations into line with the rest of the world's, eliminating confusion with foreign navies. In 1980, the Navy's then-building DDG-47-class destroyers were redesignated as cruisers (CG-47<space/><italics>Ticonderoga</italics><space/>guided missile cruisers) to emphasize the additional capability provided by the ships'<space/><link><target>Aegis combat system</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and their flag facilities suitable for an admiral and his staff.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Cruisers in service today</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Jeanne D Arc 4.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><template><target>ship</target><arg>French cruiser</arg><arg>Jeanne d'Arc</arg><arg>R97</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>of the<space/><link><target>French Navy</target></link>, launched in 1961, decommissioned in 2010</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Few cruisers remain operational in the world navies. Those that do are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>United States Navy</target></link>: 22<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nvr.navy.mil/nvrships/active/fleet.htm'>Naval Vessel Register</link></extension><space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Ticonderoga</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>guided missile cruisers.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Russian Navy</target></link>: 3<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Slava</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>0</arg></template><space/>missile cruisers. The 1900<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian cruiser</arg><arg>Aurora</arg></template><space/>was ceremonially recommissioned as the flagship of the Russian Navy due to its historical significance.<space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Peruvian Navy</target></link>: The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>BAP</arg><arg>Almirante Grau</arg><arg>CLM-81</arg><arg></arg></template>, a<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>De Zeven Provinciën</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template>, although modernized as a guided-missile cruiser in the late eighties, it is the world's last operational gun cruiser.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hellenic Navy</target></link>: The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Greek cruiser</arg><arg>Georgios Averof</arg></template><space/>remains ceremonially in commission as the flagship of the Hellenic Navy due to its historical significance.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ukrainian Navy</target></link>: The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Ukrainian cruiser</arg><arg>Ukrayina</arg></template>, a<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Slava</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>that was under construction prior to the breakup of the Soviet Union, was inherited to the Ukrainian Navy. She remains only 95% complete and has been docked in<space/><link><target>Mykolaiv</target></link>, awaiting completion. Cost of completion are estimated to be approximately, $30 million. Russia has expressed interest in buying the ship from Ukraine.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Museum Cruisers</heading><paragraph>As of 2015, several decommissioned cruisers have been saved from scrapping and exist worldwide as<space/><link><target>museum ship</target><trail>s</trail></link>. They are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>USS</target><arg>Olympia</arg><arg>C-6</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Philadelphia, Pennsylvania</target></link><space/>and is the world's oldest steel-hulled warship afloat.</listitem><listitem><template><target>USS</target><arg>Little Rock</arg><arg>CL-92</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Buffalo, New York</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>USS</target><arg>Salem</arg><arg>CA-139</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Quincy, Massachusetts</target></link><space/>and is the world's last heavy cruiser, she will be relocated to<space/><link><target>Boston</target></link><space/>at the end of 2015.<space/></listitem><listitem><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Belfast</arg><arg>C35</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>London, England</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>HMS</target><arg>Caroline</arg><arg>1914</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Belfast, Northern Ireland</target></link>, and is the last surviving ship from the<space/><link><target>Battle of Jutland</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>ship</target><arg>Russian cruiser</arg><arg>Aurora</arg></template><space/><link><target>St. Petersburg, Russia</target></link>, and is still active as the flagship of the<space/><link><target>Russian Navy</target></link></listitem><listitem><template><target>ship</target><arg>Soviet Cruiser</arg><arg>Mikhail Kutuzov</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Novorossiysk, Russia</target></link><space/>and is the last surviving<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Sverdlov</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>ship</target><arg>Greek cruiser</arg><arg>Georgios Averof</arg></template><space/>in<space/><link><target>Athens, Greece</target></link>, and is still active as the flagship of the<space/><link><target>Hellenic Navy</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Future Museums -</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Many interest groups favor preserving a<space/><template><target>sclass-</target><arg>Ticonderoga</arg><arg>cruiser</arg><arg>2</arg></template><space/>as the class retires from service</listitem><listitem>The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>Italian cruiser</arg><arg>Vittorio Veneto</arg></template><space/>is currently undergoing a restoration for preservation in<space/><link><target>Taranto</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Italy</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph>Former Museums -</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>The<space/><template><target>ship</target><arg>French cruiser</arg><arg>Colbert</arg><arg>C611</arg></template><space/>was on display in<space/><link><target>Bordeaux</target></link>,<space/><link><target>France</target></link><space/>until 2006, when she was forced to close due to financial difficulties. She currently sits in the<space/><link><target>French Navy</target></link>'s mothball fleet in<space/><link><target>Landevennec</target></link>. There is still a possibility that she can be saved.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of cruisers</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Parkes, Oscar<space/><italics>British Battleships</italics><space/>(2nd Edition). Leo Cooper, London, 1990. ISBN 0-85052-604-3.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.aandc.org/research/cruisers/cr_navsea.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Historical Review of Cruiser Characteristics, Roles and Missions<space/></arg><arg name="author">Philip Sims, Michael Bosworth, Chris Cable, Howard Fireman<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="work">SFAC Report Number 9030-04-C1<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Future Concepts and Surface Ship Design Group, Naval Sea Systems Command, United States Navy<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">March 25, 2011</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Warship types of the 19th &amp; 20th centuries</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Cruisers</target><part>*</part></link><link><target>Category:Ship types</target></link></paragraph></article>