<article title='Politics_of_Costa_Rica'><paragraph><template><target>Politics of Costa Rica</target></template>The politics of<space/><link><target>Costa Rica</target></link><space/>take place in a framework of a<space/><link><target>presidential system</target><part>presidential</part></link><space/><link><target>representative democracy</target><part>representative democratic</part></link><space/><link><target>republic</target></link>, with a<space/><link><target>multi-party system</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Executive power</target></link><space/>is exercised by the president and his cabinet, and the<space/><link><target>President of Costa Rica</target></link><space/>is both the<space/><link><target>head of state</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>head of government</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Legislative power</target></link><space/>is vested in the<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target><part>Legislative Assembly</part></link>. The president and 57<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target><part>Legislative Assembly</part></link><space/>deputies are elected for 4-year terms. The<space/><link><target>Judiciary</target></link><space/>operates independent of the executive and the legislature but remains involved in the political process.<space/><link><target>Costa Rica</target></link><space/>is a<space/><link><target>republic</target></link><space/>with a strong system of constitutional checks and balances.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://hup.sub.uni-hamburg.de/giga/jpla/article/view/40/40'>hup.sub.uni-hamburg.de</link></extension><space/>Voting is compulsory in Costa Rica but it is not enforced.</paragraph><paragraph>The position of governor in the seven<space/><link><target>province</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>was abolished in 1998.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nacion.com/ln_ee/2007/junio/29/pais1150113.html'>www.nacion.com</link></extension><space/>There are no provincial legislatures. In 2009, the state monopolies on insurance and telecommunications were opened to private-sector competition. Certain other state agencies enjoy considerable operational independence and autonomy; they include the<space/><link><target>Instituto Costarricense de Electricidad</target><part>electrical power company</part></link><space/>(Instituto Costarricense de Electricidad), the nationalized commercial banks (which are open to competition from private banks), and<space/><link><target>Caja Costarricense del Seguro Social</target><part>the social security agency</part></link><space/>(Caja Costarricense del Seguro Social).<space/><link><target>Military of Costa Rica</target><part>Costa Rica has no military</part></link><space/>but maintains a domestic police force and a Special Forces Unit as part of the Ministry of the President.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Recent history</heading><paragraph>The 1986 presidential election was won by<space/><link><target>scar Arias</target></link><space/>of the PLN. During his tenure he experienced some criticism from within his own party for abandoning its traditional social democratic teachings and promoting a<space/><link><target>neoliberal</target></link><space/>economic model. He received the<space/><link><target>Nobel Peace Prize</target></link><space/>in 1987 for his efforts to end civil wars then raging in several Central American countries.</paragraph><paragraph>In the February 1998 national election, PUSC candidate<space/><link><target>Miguel ngel Rodrguez</target></link><space/>won the presidency over PLN nominee<space/><link><target>Jos Miguel Corrales Bolaos</target></link>. President Rodriguez assumed office May 8, 1998. The PUSC also obtained 27 seats in the 57-member Legislative Assembly, for a plurality, while the PLN got 23 and five minor parties won seven. Social Christian in philosophy, the PUSC generally favors neoliberalism, conservative fiscal policies, and government reform. President Rodriguez pledged to reduce the country's large<space/><link><target>internal debt</target></link>, privatize state-owned utilities, attract additional foreign investment, eliminate social welfare programs, and promote the creation of jobs with decent salaries.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>The reforms he tried to promote found opposition from several parties, including his own, and he asserted several times the country was &quot;ungovernable&quot;. In particular, an attempt by the Legislative Assembly to approve a law that opened up the electricity and telecommunication markets (controlled by a monopoly of the Costa Rican Institute of Electricity - ICE) to market competition, known as the &quot;Combo&quot; law, was met with strong social opposition. The Combo law was supported by both major parties at the time (PLN and PUSC) as well as by President Rodriguez, but the first of three required legislative votes to approve it provoked the largest protest demonstrations the country had seen since 1970. The government quickly resolved to shelve the initiative. President Rodrguez's approval would reach an all-time low, and he was indicted by the Attorney General after leaving office on corruption charges.</paragraph><paragraph>In September 2000 the Constitutional Court rejected an argument by former president Arias that a 1969 constitutional amendment banning presidential reelection be rescinded. Arias thus remained barred from a second term as president; however, in April 2003by which time two of the four judges who had voted against the change in 2000 had been replacedthe Court reconsidered the issue and, with the only dissenters being the two anti-reelection judges remaining from 2000, declared the 1969 amendment null and thus opened the way to reelection for former presidentswhich in practice meant Arias.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://impreso.elnuevodiario.com.ni/2007/07/18/nacionales/54109'>&quot;Reeleccin seduce a los presidentes de America&quot;</link><space/>El Nueavo Diario, Managua, 18 July 2007, retrieved July 2009;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.nacion.com/ln_ee/2003/abril/05/pais1.html'>&quot;Reeleccin presidencial: Arias sin prohibicin para postularse&quot;</link>, La Nacion, Costa Rica, 5 April 2003; retrieved July 2009.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 2002 national election, a new party founded by former PLN Congressman and government Minister<space/><link><target>Ottn Sols</target></link><space/>captured 26% of the vote, forcing a runoff election for the first time in the country's history.<space/><link><target>Abel Pacheco</target></link><space/>was elected President, under a national unity platform, but continuing most of the neoliberal and conservative policies of<space/><link><target>Miguel ngel Rodrguez</target></link>. This election was also important because new parties won several seats in Congress, more than ever. The PUSC obtained 19 seats, PLN 17 seats, PAC 14 seats, PML 6 seats and PRC one seat.</paragraph><paragraph>During 2004, several high-profile corruption scandals shattered the foundations of PUSC. Two former presidents from the party, Miguel ngel Rodrguez and<space/><link><target>Rafael ngel Caldern Fournier</target><part>Rafael ngel Caldern</part></link>, were arrested on corruption charges and are currently waiting for the investigation to end and trial to begin. Also involved in scandals has been<space/><link><target>Jos Mara Figueres</target></link>, former President from PLN and former head of the<space/><link><target>World Economic Forum</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The 2006 national election was expected to be a landslide for former President (19861990) and PLN's candidate<space/><link><target>scar Arias</target></link>, but it turned out to be the closest in modern history. Although polls just a week before the election gave Arias a comfortable lead of at least 12% (and up to 20%), preliminary election results gave him only a .4% lead over rival<space/><link><target>Ottn Sols</target></link><space/>and prompted a manual recount of all ballots. After a month-long recount and several appeals from different parties, Arias was declared the official winner with 40.9% of the votes against 39.8% for Sols.</paragraph><paragraph>When scar Arias returned to office, the political debate shifted to the ratification of the<space/><link><target>Central American Free Trade Agreement</target></link><space/>(CAFTA). Main supporters of the approval included the President's PLN, which established a coalition with PUSC and ML in Congress to approve the implementation laws in Congress, as well as different business chambers. The main opposition to CAFTA came from PAC,<space/><link><target>Trade unions in Costa Rica</target><part>labor unions</part></link>, environmental organizations and public universities. In April 2007, former PLN Presidential candidate and CAFTA opponent<space/><link><target>Jos Miguel Corrales Bolaos</target></link><space/>won a legal battle at the Supreme Electoral Tribunal, which authorized him to gather over 100,000 signatures to send CAFTA to a referendum and let the people decide the fate of the controversial agreement. As the February 28, 2008 deadline to approve or reject CAFTA loomed, Arias decided to call for the referendum himself, and it took take place on October 7, 2007. CAFTA was approved with 51.5% of voters supporting it, although the election faced criticism due to international, including US, involvement.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">Lydersen</arg><arg name="first">Kari</arg><arg name="title">Costa Rica's CAFTA "Si" Vote Called into Question</arg><arg name="url">http://upsidedownworld.org/main/trade-archives-54/939-costa-ricas-cafta-si-vote-called-into-question</arg><arg name="accessdate">31 March 2014</arg><arg name="date">11 October 2007</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Costa Rican general election, 2010</target></link><space/>was won by<space/><link><target>Laura Chinchilla</target></link>, who had been Vice-President in the previous Arias administration.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2014,<space/><link><target>Luis Guillermo Sols</target></link>, PAC's presidential candidate campaigning on a platform of economic reform and anti-corruption, surprised political observers by winning 30.95% of votes in the first round, while PLN candidate<space/><link><target>Johnny Araya</target></link><space/>gained the second most votes with 29.95%.<space/><link><target>Broad Front (Costa Rica)</target><part>Broad Front</part></link>'s<space/><link><target>Jos Mara Villalta Florez-Estrada</target></link><space/>won 17% of the votes<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Mapa de Resultados Elecciones Costa Rica<space/></arg><arg name="trans_title">Costa Rican Map of Electoral Results<space/></arg><arg name="language">es<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.nacion.com/nacional/Mapa-Resultados-Elecciones-Costa-Rica_11_1378572130.html</arg><arg name="work">RESULTADOS ELECTORALES EN MAPA ELECTORAL<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">La Nación</arg><arg name="place">San José<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">20 February 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Soon thereafter, Araya announced that he would cease campaigning, making Sols the favorite.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC withdraw"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Costa Rica government's presidential candidate withdraws</arg><arg name="url">http://www.bbc.com/news/world-latin-america-26461528</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 March 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">BBC</arg><arg name="date">5 March 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Elections were still be held on April 6, 2014 as required by election law,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="title">Solís advierte que aún no es presidente a pesar de retirada de Araya</arg><arg name="trans_title">Solís warns that he is not yet president despite Araya's withdrawal</arg><arg name="language">es</arg><arg name="url">http://www.prensalibre.com/internacional/Costa_Rica-Solis-Araya-politica-elecciones_0_1096090681.html</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 March 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">Prensa Libre</arg><arg name="agency">AFP</arg><arg name="place">Guatemala City</arg><arg name="date">5 March 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>and Sols won with 77.81 of the votes. According to the BBC, the success of Sols and Villalta is another example of anti-neoliberal politics in Latin America.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BBC withdraw"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political involvement of government institutions</heading><heading level='3'>Executive branch</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Luis Guillermo Sols 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Luis Guillermo Sols will serve as President from 2014 to 2018. He is the first President in 66 years not to come from the<space/><link><target>Political parties in Costa Rica</target><part>two-party system</part></link>.</part></link>Executive responsibilities are vested in a<space/><link><target>List of Presidents of Costa Rica</target><part>president</part></link>, who is elected directly by the voters, not by the National Assembly as it would be in a parliamentary system. There also are two vice presidents and the president's cabinet composed of his ministers.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://whitepages.cr/gov'>List of Costa and Ministries with phonenumbers</link></extension><space/>A constitutional amendment approved in 1969 limits presidents and deputies to one term, although a deputy may run again for an Assembly seat after sitting out a term. The prohibition was officially recognized as unconstitutional in April 2004, allowing<space/><link><target>scar Arias</target></link><space/>to run for President a second time in the<space/><link><target>Costa Rica presidential elections, 2006</target><part>2006 Costa Rican presidential elections</part></link>, which he won with approximately a 1% margin.</paragraph><paragraph>The President of Costa Rica has limited powers, particularly in comparison to other Latin American Presidents. For example, he cannot veto the legislative budget, and thus Congress is sovereign over the year's single most important piece of legislation. On the other hand, he can appoint anyone to their cabinet without any approval from Congress. This provides the single most important power versus Congress that any Costa Rican President has.</paragraph><paragraph><template><target>office-table</target></template>|<link><target>President of Costa Rica</target><part>President</part></link>|<link><target>Luis Guillermo Sols</target></link>|<link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link>|8 May 1969|-|<space/><link><target>Vice President of Costa Rica</target><part>Vice President</part></link>|<space/><link><target>Helio Fallas Venegas</target></link>|<space/><link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link>| 8 May 1969|-|<space/><link><target>Vice President of Costa Rica</target><part>Vice Presidents</part></link>|<space/><link><target>Ana Helena Chacn Echeverra</target></link>|<space/><link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link>| 8 May 1969|}</paragraph><heading level='3'>Legislative branch</heading><paragraph>Legislative powers are held by the<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target><part>Legislative Assembly</part></link>. Legislators, called deputies, are elected to non-consecutive four year terms by popular,<space/><link><target>direct vote</target></link>, using<space/><link><target>proportional representation</target></link><space/>in each of the country's seven provinces. Elections were last held in February 2014 and will be held again in February 2018. As a result, there are nine separate political parties serving in the Legislative Assembly, with<space/><link><target>National Liberation Party (Costa Rica)</target><part>National Liberation Party</part></link><space/>holding 18 seats, the<space/><link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link><space/>holding 13, and<space/><link><target>Broad Front (Costa Rica)</target><part>Broad Front</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Social Christian Unity Party</target></link><space/>each holding 8. Other parties hold the remaining seats.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WFB"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The World Factbook: Costa Rica</arg><arg name="url">https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/cs.html</arg><arg name="work">The World Factbook (Central Intelligence Agency)</arg><arg name="publisher">Central Intelligence Agency</arg><arg name="accessdate">3 April 2014</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>office-table</target></template>|<link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target><part>Legislative Assembly President</part></link>|<link><target>Henry Mora Jimnez</target></link>|<link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link>|8 May 2014|}</paragraph><heading level='3'>Judicial branch</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Plaza justicia vista ES.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Supreme Court of Justice of Costa Rica</target></link>.</part></link>The main arm of the judiciary is the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Justice of Costa Rica</target><part>Supreme Court of Justice</part></link>. Twenty-two magistrates are selected for the CSJ for 8-year terms by the Legislative Assembly, and lower courts. Sala IV, also known as the Constitutional Chamber of the Supreme Court, reviews legislation, executive actions, and certain<space/><link><target>writ</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>for constitutionality. Courts below the Sala IV deal with issues involving legal and criminal disputes. Additionally, the Supreme Electoral Tribunal (TSE for its Spanish initials) is an independent branch of the CSJ, responsible for democratic elections. While the judiciary is independent of the politically-elected executive and legislative branches, it is often responsible for resolving political and legal conflicts.<extension extension_name='ref' name="WFB"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Institutional oversight</heading><paragraph>A<space/><link><target>Comptroller</target><part>Comptroller General</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Procurator General (disambiguation)</target><part>Procurator General</part></link>, and an<space/><link><target>Ombudsman</target></link><space/>oversee the government and operate autonomously. These institutions have the right to scrutinize, investigate and prosecute government contracts. In addition, they may impose procedural requirements on most political and governmental agencies. The actions of politicians and political parties are frequently researched by these institutions.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Elections in Costa Rica</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On the national level, the<space/><link><target>president</target></link>, two<space/><link><target>vice-presidents</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>legislature</target></link><space/>are elected every four years for a four-year term. The<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target><part>Legislative Assembly</part></link><space/>has 57 members, elected by<space/><link><target>proportional representation</target></link><space/>in each of the country's seven provinces.</paragraph><paragraph>The electoral process is supervised by an independent Supreme Electoral Tribunal (TSE for its Spanish initials). The TSE is a commission of three principal magistrates and six alternates selected by the<space/><link><target>Supreme Court of Justice of Costa Rica</target></link>. All elections are conducted by a secret ballot at local polling stations.</paragraph><paragraph>On election days, political parties often organize caravans and marches to get supporters to polling stations.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eltiempo.com">http://www.eltiempo.com/mundo/latinoamerica/ARTICULO-WEB-NEW_NOTA_INTERIOR-13432495.html</extension><space/>In many areas, voting takes on a festive atmosphere with supporters of each party wearing traditional colors and decorating their cars, houses, and livestock with colored ribbons.<extension extension_name='ref' name="eltiempo.com"></extension><space/>Because the day of elections is a national holiday, most people have the day off.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.tusalario.org/costarica/portada/derechos-laborales/vacaciones-anuales/trabajo-en-dia-de-elecciones</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political parties</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>List of political parties in Costa Rica</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Currently, there are nine active political parties with representation in the<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target></link>. An additional twelve parties ran, but did not receive enough votes to earn a seat in the assembly, making the total number of active parties in Costa Rica twenty-one. Starting in the 2000s, disagreement about many of the neo-liberal policies promoted by the dominant PLN caused the traditional party system of alliances among a few parties to fracture.<extension extension_name='ref' name="OSO"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Booth</arg><arg name="first">John A.</arg><arg name="title">Political Parties in Costa Rica: Democratic Stability and Party System Change in a Latin American Context</arg><arg name="date">January 2008</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford Scholarship Online</arg><arg name="location">Oxford</arg><arg name="isbn">9780199289653</arg><arg name="url">http://www.oxfordscholarship.com/view/10.1093/acprof:oso/9780199289653.001.0001/acprof-9780199289653-chapter-11</arg><arg name="edition">1</arg><arg name="author2">yes</arg><arg name="editor">Paul Webb and Stephen White</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 April 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Although still a stable country, the shift toward many political parties and away from PUSC and PLN is a recent development.<extension extension_name='ref' name="TT McPhaul"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="last">McPhaul</arg><arg name="first">John</arg><arg name="title">Costa Rica elections demonstrate country’s democratic stability</arg><arg name="url">http://www.ticotimes.net/2014/02/08/costa-rica-elections-demonstrate-countrys-democratic-stability</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 April 2014</arg><arg name="newspaper">The Tico Times</arg><arg name="date">8 February 2014</arg></template></extension><space/>Various elected positions within the country, such as mayors and city council members, are held by many different national and local political parties.</paragraph><table border="1" class="wikitable sortable collapsible "><tablerow><tablehead colspan="5"><bold>Political Parties in<space/><link><target>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</target></link>, 2014-2018</bold></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead scope="col">Party Name (English)</tablehead><tablehead scope="col">Party Name (Spanish)</tablehead><tablehead scope="col">Legislative Seats (2014)</tablehead><tablehead scope="col">Ideology</tablehead><tablehead scope="col">Historic Notes</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>National Liberation Party (Costa Rica)</target><part>National Liberation Party</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Liberacin Nacional (PLN)</tablecell><tablecell>18</tablecell><tablecell>Centrist, social democracy</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 1951. Controlled the legislative assembly since inception and presidency for all but four elections.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Citizens' Action Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Accin Ciudadana (PAC)</tablecell><tablecell>13</tablecell><tablecell>progressive, social democracy</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2002. Won presidential election of 2014.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Broad Front (Costa Rica)</target><part>Broad Front</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Frente Amplio (FA)</tablecell><tablecell>9</tablecell><tablecell>Green, progressivism, humanism</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2004. Never controlled presidency.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Social Christian Unity Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Unidad Social Cristiana, (PUSC)</tablecell><tablecell>8</tablecell><tablecell>Conservatism</tablecell><tablecell>Founded 1983 by four opposition parties. The main historical opposition to PLN. Three presidential victories in 1990, 1998, and 2002.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Libertarian Movement (Costa Rica)</target><part>Libertarian Movement</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Movimiento Libertario (PML)</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>Classical liberalism, conservatism</tablecell><tablecell>Founded 1994. Never controlled presidency.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Costa Rican Renovation Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Renovacin Costarricense (PRC)</tablecell><tablecell>2</tablecell><tablecell>Christian democracy, conservatism, right-wing</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 1995. Never controlled presidency.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>National Restoration Party (Costa Rica)</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Restauracin Nacional (PRN)</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>Social Christianity, conservatism, right-wing</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2005. Never controlled presidency.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Accessibility without Exclusion</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Accessibilidad sin Exclusin (PASE)</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>Single issue, rights for people with disabilities</tablecell><tablecell>Founded 2001. Never controlled presidency.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Christian Democratic Alliance (Costa Rica)</target><part>Christian Democratic Alliance</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Alianza Demcrata Cristiana (ADC)</tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>Conservative, provincial (<link><target>Cartago Province</target><part>Cartago</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2012.</tablecell></tablerow></table><table class="wikitable sortable collapsible "><tablerow><tablehead colspan="5"><bold>Recent Non-Represented and Defunct Political Parties</bold></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><bold>Party Name (English)</bold></tablehead><tablehead><bold>Party Name (Spanish)</bold></tablehead><tablehead><bold>Legislative Seats (2014)</bold></tablehead><tablehead><bold>Ideology</bold></tablehead><tablehead><bold>Historic Notes</bold></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>National Union Party (Costa Rica)</target><part>National Union Party</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Unin Nacional (PUN)</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Conservatism, Center-right</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 1901. Has existed in various forms and coalition parties until 2010. Won the presidency four times (1902, 1928, 1948, 1958, 1966). 1948 election was unrecognized. Defunct as of 2010.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>National Rescue Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Rescate Nacional (PRN)</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Center-left, Moderate socialist</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 1996. Held one legislative seat in 2006. Defunct as of 2010.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Union for Change Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Unin para el Cambio (PUC)</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Centrist, social democracy</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2005. Existed for one election cycle as protest from ex-PLN members. Defunct as of 2010.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Homeland First Party</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Patria Primero (PP)</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Conservative, social democracy, Catholic interest</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2006. Existed for one election cycle as a protest from ex-PAC members. Defunct as of 2010.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>National Democrat Alliance Party</tablecell><tablecell>Partido Alianza Democrtica Nacionalista</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Social democracy, nationalist</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 2004. Opposed<space/><link><target>Central American Free Trade Agreement</target><part>CAFTA</part></link>. Defunct as of 2010.</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>National Integration Party (Costa Rica)</target><part>National Integration Party</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>Partido Integracin Nacional (PIN)</tablecell><tablecell>0</tablecell><tablecell>Conservatism, center right</tablecell><tablecell>Founded in 1998. Active as of 2014 election.</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Foreign relations of Costa Rica</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.asamblea.go.cr'>Legislative Assembly of Costa Rica</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.poder-judicial.go.cr'>Supreme Court of Justice of Costa Rica</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Costa Rica topics</target></template><template><target>Americas topic</target><arg>Politics of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Costa Rica</target></template><link><target>Category:Politics of Costa Rica</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>