<article title='Democratic_Progressive_Party'><paragraph><template><target>Other uses</target></template><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="date">December 2010</arg></template><template><target>Infobox political party</target><arg name="colorcode"><space/>{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}
</arg><arg name="name_english"><space/>Democratic Progressive Party
</arg><arg name="native_name"><space/>{{nobold|民主進步黨}}<br />Mínzhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng
</arg><arg name="party_logo"><space/>[[File:DPP-Taiwan.svg|190px]]
</arg><arg name="leader1_title"><space/>Chairman
</arg><arg name="leader1_name"><space/>[[Tsai Ing-wen]], Ph.D.
</arg><arg name="foundation"><space/>{{Start date and age|1986|9|28}}
</arg><arg name="headquarters"><space/>[[Taipei]], [[Taiwan]]
</arg><arg name="think_tank"><space/>[http://www.dppnff.tw/ New Frontier Foundation]
</arg><arg name="membership_year"><space/>2014
</arg><arg name="membership"><space/>{{Increase}} 335,643
</arg><arg name="ideology"><space/>{{nowrap|[[Taiwan independence movement|Taiwanese independence]]<br>[[Taiwanese nationalism]]<br>[[Liberalism]]<br>[[Economic liberalism]]<br>[[Social liberalism]]<br>[[Progressivism]]}}
</arg><arg name="position"><space/>[[Centrism|Centre]] to [[Centre-left]]
</arg><arg name="national"><space/>[[Pan-Green Coalition]]
</arg><arg name="international"><space/>[[Liberal International]]
</arg><arg name="affiliation1_title"><space/>Regional affiliation
</arg><arg name="affiliation1"><space/>[[Council of Asian Liberals and Democrats]]
</arg><arg name="seats1_title"><space/>[[Legislative Yuan]]
</arg><arg name="seats1"><space/>{{Composition bar|40|113|hex</arg><arg name="seats2_title"><space/>Municipal Mayoralties
</arg><arg name="seats2"><space/>{{Composition bar|4|6|hex</arg><arg name="seats3_title"><space/>City Mayoralties and County Magistracies
</arg><arg name="seats3"><space/>{{Composition bar|9|16|hex</arg><arg name="seats4_title"><space/>Local Councillors
</arg><arg name="seats4"><space/>{{Composition bar|291|906|hex</arg><arg name="seats5_title"><space/>Township Chiefs
</arg><arg name="seats5"><space/>{{Composition bar|54|211|hex</arg><arg name="flag"><space/>[[File:Flag of Democratic Progressive Party.svg|250px]]
</arg><arg name="website"><space/>{{URL|http://www.dpp.org.tw/|www.dpp.org.tw}}
</arg><arg name="country"><space/>Taiwan
</arg></template><template><target>ChineseText</target></template><template><target>Chinese</target><arg name="title"><space/>Democratic Progressive Party
</arg><arg name="t"><space/>{{linktext|民主|進步|黨}}</arg><arg name="s">{{linktext|民主|进步|党}}
</arg><arg name="bpmf"><space/>ㄇㄧㄣˊ ㄓㄨˇ ㄐㄧㄣˋ ㄅㄨˋ ㄉㄤˇ</arg><arg name="w">Min²-chu³ Chin⁴-pu⁴ Tang³</arg><arg name="p">Mínzhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng</arg><arg name="tp">Mínjhǔ Jìnbù Dǎng</arg><arg name="mps">Mínjǔ Jìnbù Dǎng</arg><arg name="gr">Minjuu Jinnbuh Daang
</arg><arg name="poj"><space/>Bîn-chú Chìn-pō͘ Tóng</arg><arg name="tl">Bîn-tsú Tsìn-poō Tóng</arg><arg name="h">Mìn-chú Chin-phu Tóng
</arg><arg name="altname"><space/>Commonly abbreviated in Chinese as
</arg><arg name="t2"><space/>{{linktext|民進黨}}</arg><arg name="s2"><space/>{{linktext|民进党}}
</arg><arg name="bpmf2"><space/>ㄇㄧㄣˊ ㄐㄧㄣˋ ㄉㄤˇ</arg><arg name="w2">Min²-chin⁴ Tang³</arg><arg name="p2">Mínjìn Dǎng</arg><arg name="tp2">Mínjìn Dǎng</arg><arg name="mps2">Mínjìn Dǎng</arg><arg name="gr2">Minjinn Daang
</arg><arg name="poj2"><space/>Bîn-chìn Tóng</arg><arg name="tl2">Bîn-tsìn Tóng</arg><arg name="h2">Mìn-chin Tóng
</arg></template>The<space/><bold>Democratic Progressive Party</bold><space/>(<bold>DPP</bold>;<space/><template><target>zh</target><arg name="t">民主進步黨</arg><arg name="s">民主进步党</arg></template>) is a<space/><link><target>Progressivism</target><part>progressive</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Liberalism</target><part>liberal</part></link><space/><link><target>political party</target></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Taiwan</target></link>, and the dominant party in the<space/><link><target>Pan-Green Coalition</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Founded in 1986, DPP is the first meaningful<space/><link><target>opposition party</target></link><space/>in Taiwan. It has traditionally been associated with strong advocacy of<space/><link><target>human rights</target></link><space/>and a distinct<space/><link><target>Taiwanese identity</target></link>, including promotion of<space/><italics><link><target>de jure</target></link></italics><space/><link><target>Taiwan independence</target></link>. The current leader is<space/><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="chinapost.com.tw"><link type='external' href='http://www.chinapost.com.tw/taiwan/national/presidential-election/2012/01/14/329044/Tsai-steps.htm'>&quot;Tsai steps down as DPP chair after defeat in presidential poll&quot;</link><space/><italics>The China Post</italics>. 2012.01.14</extension><space/>The DPP is a long-term member of<space/><link><target>Liberal International</target></link><space/>and a founding member of the<space/><link><target>Council of Asian Liberals and Democrats</target></link>. It represented Taiwan in the<space/><link><target>Unrepresented Nations and Peoples Organisation</target></link>. The DPP and its affiliated parties are widely classified as socially liberal because of their strong human rights stance.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph>The DPP's roots were in opposition to<space/><link><target>Kuomintang</target></link><space/><link><target>Single-party state</target><part>one-party authoritarian rule</part></link>. It was founded as the<space/><link><target>Tangwai</target></link><space/>&amp;ndash; or &quot;outside-the-KMT&quot; &amp;ndash; movement. This movement culminated in the formation of the DPP as an alternative party on September 28, 1986. The new party contested the<space/><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 1986</target><part>1986 election</part></link><space/>even though competing parties remained illegal under national law until the next year. The first members of the party drew heavily from the ranks of family members and defense lawyers of political prisoners as well as intellectuals and artists who had spent time abroad. Such individuals were strongly committed to political change that would ensure constitutional support in Taiwan for freedoms of speech, press, assembly, and association. The party did not at the outset give open support to an independent Taiwanese national identitya move that could have invited a violent crackdown by the Taiwan's Kuomintang rulers. Its platform was pro-environment and pro-democracy. As more and more of its demands were met during the 1990ssuch as the direct popular election of Taiwan's<space/><link><target>president of the Republic of China</target><part>president</part></link><space/>and all representatives in its<space/><link><target>Legislative Yuan</target></link>, and open discussion of Taiwan's repressive past as represented in the<space/><link><target>February 28 Incident</target></link><space/>and its long<space/><link><target>martial law</target></link><space/>aftermatha greater variety of views could be advocated in the more liberal political atmosphere. Party members began openly promoting a national identity for Taiwan separate from that of China. The DPP supported reform of the Constitution that would make it official that Taiwan's national government represented only the people of Taiwan and made no claims to territory in<space/><link><target>mainland China</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Mongolia</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Once the DPP had representation in the<space/><link><target>Legislative Yuan</target></link><space/>(LY, Congress), the party used the legislature as a forum to challenge the government. However, it did not emerge as a formidable force until 1991, when the elderly LY members elected from the mainland provinces in 1948 retired. Fears that the DPP would one day take control of the legislature led then-President<space/><link><target>Lee Teng-hui</target></link><space/>to push through a series of amendments to strengthen presidential power (for example, Taiwan's<space/><link><target>premier of the Republic of China</target><part>premier</part></link><space/>would no longer have to be confirmed by the Legislative Yuan).</paragraph><heading level='3'>20002008: in minority government</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chen Shui-bian from VOA.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Former President Chen Shui-bian, the first DPP president (2000-2008)</part></link><link><target>File:DPP-Taiwan-old.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Old logo of DPP</part></link>The DPP won the presidency with the<space/><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2000</target><part>election</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link><space/>in March 2000 with a plurality, due to the split of KMT voters, ending more than half a century of KMT rule in Taiwan. Chen softened the party's stance on independence to appeal to moderate voters, appease the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and placate China. He also promised not to<space/><link><target>Four Noes and One Without</target><part>change the ROC state symbols or declare formal independence</part></link><space/>as long as the<space/><link><target>People's Republic of China</target></link><space/>did not attack Taiwan.</paragraph><paragraph>The DPP became the largest party having reached a plurality in the Legislative Yuan for the first time in 2002 following the<space/><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2001</target><part>2001 legislative election</part></link>. However, a majority coalition between the KMT,<space/><link><target>People First Party (Republic of China)</target><part>People's First Party</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>New Party (Republic of China)</target><part>New Party</part></link><space/>(collectively known as the<space/><link><target>Pan-Blue Coalition</target></link>) prevented it from taking control of the chamber.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2004,<space/><link><target>President of the Republic of China</target><part>President</part></link><space/>Chen Shui-bian was re-elected by a narrow margin following a controversial assassination attempt on him and the Vice President<space/><link><target>Annette Lu</target></link><space/>only hours before the<space/><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2004</target><part>election</part></link>. President Chen narrowly won the election over KMT candidate<space/><link><target>Lien Chan</target></link>. Lien Chan demanded a recount the following morning. A judicial recount under the jurisdiction of a special panel of the High Court began on 10 May 2004 and ended on May 18, 2004. It was conducted by about 460 teams situated in 21 courthouses across the Taiwan area. Each team had seven members one judge, two members each from the district court and the local government election authorities and two witnesses each representing the plaintiff (Pan-Blue Coalition) and the defendant (Pan-Green Coalition). Disputed votes were sent to High Court in Taipei for verification. After the recount, President Chen was confirmed the winner of the election by a smaller margin (25,563 as opposed to 29,518 originally). In the<space/><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2004</target><part>later legislative election</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Pan-Blue Coalition</target></link><space/>opposition remained control of the chamber.</paragraph><paragraph>The DPP suffered a significant election defeat in nationwide<space/><link><target>Republic of China local elections, 2005</target><part>local and county elections in December 2005</part></link>. The pan-blue coalition captured 16 of 23 county and city government offices under the leadership of popular<space/><link><target>Taipei City</target><part>Taipei</part></link><space/>mayor and KMT Party Chairman<space/><link><target>Ma Ying-jeou</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The results led to a shake up of the party leadership.<space/><link><target>Su Tseng-chang</target></link><space/>resigned as DPP chairman soon after election results were announced. Su had pledged to step down if the DPP lost either Taipei County or failed to win 10 of the 23 mayor/magistrate positions. Vice President<space/><link><target>Annette Lu</target></link><space/>was appointed acting DPP leader. Presidential Office Secretary-General<space/><link><target>Yu Shyi-kun</target></link><space/>was elected in a<space/><link><target>Democratic Progressive Party chairmanship election, 2006</target><part>three-way race</part></link><space/>against legislator<space/><link><target>Chai Trong-rong</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wong Chin-chu</target></link><space/>with 54.4% of the vote.</paragraph><paragraph>Premier<space/><link><target>Frank Hsieh</target></link>, DPP election organizer and former mayor of<space/><link><target>Kaohsiung</target></link><space/>twice tendered a verbal resignation immediately following the election, but his resignation was not accepted by President Chen until January 17, 2006 after the DPP chairmanship election had concluded. The former DPP Chairman Su Tseng-chang was appointed to replace Hsieh as premier. Hsieh and his cabinet resigned en masse on January 24 to make way for Su and his new cabinet. President Chen had offered the position of Presidential Office Secretary-General (vacated by Su) to the departing premier, but Hsieh declined and left office criticizing President Chen for his tough line on dealing with China.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Separate identity</heading><paragraph>On September 30, 2007, Taiwan's ruling Democratic Progressive Party approved a<space/><link><target>Resolution (law)</target><part>resolution</part></link><space/>asserting a separate identity from China and called for the enactment of a new constitution for a &quot;normal nation&quot;. It struck an accommodating tone by advocating general use of &quot;Taiwan&quot; as the country's name without calling for abandonment of the name<space/><link><target>Republic of China</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://usatoday30.usatoday.com/news/world/2007-09-30-taiwan_N.htm'>AP, Taiwan Party Asserts Separate Identity</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>2008present: in opposition</heading><paragraph>In the national elections held in early months of 2008 the DPP won less than 25% of the seats (38.2% vote share) in the new<space/><link><target>Legislative Yuan</target></link><space/>while its presidential candidate, former<space/><link><target>Kaohsiung</target></link><space/>mayor<space/><link><target>Frank Hsieh</target></link>, lost to KMT candidate<space/><link><target>Ma Ying-jeou</target></link><space/>by a wide margin (41.55% vs. 58.45%).</paragraph><paragraph>The first months after the election were dominated by press coverage of the travails of<space/><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link><space/>and his wife<space/><link><target>Wu Shu-jen</target></link>. On August 15, 2008 Chen resigned from the Democratic Progressive Party and apologized thus: &quot;Today I have to say sorry to all of the DPP members and supporters. I let everyone down, caused you humiliation and failed to meet your expectations. My acts have caused irreparable damage to the party. I love the DPP deeply and am proud of being a DPP member. To express my deepest regrets to all DPP members and supporters, I announce my withdrawal from the DPP immediately. My wife Wu Shu-jen is also withdrawing from the party.&quot; DPP Chairwoman<space/><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link><space/>followed with a public statement on behalf of the party: &quot;In regard to Chen and his wife's decision to withdraw from the party and his desire to shoulder responsibility for his actions as well as to undergo an investigation by the party's anti-corruption committee, we respect his decision and accept it.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.pacificmagazine.net/news/2008/08/17/former-taiwan-president-resigns-from-party-over-corruption-charges'>pacificmagazine.net, Former Taiwan President Resigns From Party Over Corruption Charges</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The DPP vowed to reflect on public misgivings towards the party. Chairwoman Tsai insisted on the need for the party to remember its history, defend Taiwan's sovereignty and national security, and maintain its confidence.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://tw.news.yahoo.com/article/url/d/a/080827/1/14w0t.html'><space/>via Yahoo! News, 11</link></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://tw.news.yahoo.com/article/url/d/a/080827/58/14wkq.html'><space/>via Yahoo! News, 11%<space/></link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The party re-emerged as a voice in Taiwan's political debate when Ma's administration reached the end of its first year in office. The DPP marked the anniversary with massive rallies in Taipei and Kaohsiung. Dr. Tsai's address to the crowd in Taipei on May 17 proclaimed a &quot;citizens' movement to protect Taiwan&quot; seeking to &quot;protect our democracy and protect Taiwan.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://dpptaiwan.wordpress.com/2009/05/17/tsai-ing-wens-opening-speech-at-the-517-rally/'></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Policies</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Tsai Ing-wen 2009.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Dr.<space/><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link>, current DPP Chairperson</part></link>Programs supported by the DPP include moderate<space/><link><target>social welfare</target></link><space/>policies involving the rights of women, senior citizens, children, young people, labour, minorities, indigenous peoples, farmers, and other disadvantaged sectors of the society. Furthermore, its platform includes a legal and political order based on human rights and democracy; balanced economic and financial administration; fair and open social welfare; educational and cultural reform; independent defence and peaceful foreign policy. For these reasons, it is often considered a party of the<space/><link><target>centre-left</target></link>, economically, and its base consists largely of the working class.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2012/jan/13/taiwan-election-china-us</arg><arg name="title">Taiwan election too close to call as China and US look on</arg><arg name="accessdate">13 January 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">''[[The Guardian]]''</arg><arg name="date">13 January 2012</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The primary political axis in Taiwan involves the issue of<space/><link><target>Taiwan independence</target></link><space/>versus eventual<space/><link><target>Cross-Strait Unification</target><part>unification with China</part></link>. Although the differences tend to be portrayed in polarized terms, both major coalitions have developed modified, nuanced and often complex positions. Though opposed in the philosophical origins, the practical differences between such positions can sometimes be subtle.</paragraph><paragraph>The current official position of the party is that the &quot;<link><target>Republic of China</target></link><space/>(Taiwan)&quot; is an independent and sovereign country whose territory consists of Taiwan and its surrounding smaller islands and whose sovereignty derives only from the ROC citizens living in Taiwan (similar philosophy of<space/><link><target>self-determination</target></link>), based on the &quot;<link><target>Resolution on Taiwan's Future</target></link>&quot; in 1999. It considers<space/><link><target>Taiwan independence</target></link><space/>to be a current fact making a formal declaration of independence unnecessary. The DPP rejects the so-called &quot;<link><target>One China principle</target></link>&quot; as the basis for official diplomatic relations with the<space/><link><target>People's Republic of China</target></link><space/>(PRC) and advocates a Taiwanese national identity which is separate from mainland China. The DPP argues that its efforts to promote a Taiwanese national identity are merely an effort to normalize a Taiwanese identity repressed during years of authoritarian Kuomintang rule. Democratic Progressive Party also differs from the KMT on foreign and defense policies in that the DPP considers relations with the United States, Japan, and European states, among other democratic countries, are crucial for Taiwan's security.</paragraph><paragraph>In contrast, the KMT or<space/><link><target>pan-blue coalition</target></link><space/>agrees that the Republic of China is an independent and sovereign country that is not part of the PRC, but argues that a<space/><link><target>one China principle</target></link><space/>(with different definitions across the strait) can be used as the basis for talks with China. The KMT also strongly opposes Taiwan independence and argues that efforts to establish a Taiwanese national identity separated from the Chinese national identity are unnecessary and needlessly provocative. Some KMT officials have called efforts from DPP &quot;<link><target>anti-China</target></link>&quot;, &quot;<link><target>fascist</target></link>&quot; (a charge for which they later apologised) and &quot;<link><target>racist</target></link>&quot;. At the other end of the political spectrum, the acceptance by the DPP of the symbols of the Republic of China is opposed by the<space/><link><target>Taiwan Solidarity Union</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The first years of the DPP as the ruling party drew accusations from the opposition that, as a self-styled Taiwanese<space/><link><target>nationalism</target><part>nationalist</part></link><space/>party, the DPP was itself inadequately sensitive to the ethnographic diversity of Taiwan's population. Where the KMT had been guilty of Chinese<space/><link><target>chauvinism</target></link>, the critics charged, the DPP might offer nothing more as a remedy than<space/><link><target>Hoklo people</target><part>Hoklo</part></link><space/>chauvinism.</paragraph><paragraph>The PRC has maintained a hostile position toward the DPP. It has made some efforts to moderate its tone since passing its<space/><link><target>Anti-Secession Law</target></link><space/>in 2005 to prevent a popular backlash from Taiwan's voters. In 2008 the PRC stated it was willing to negotiate with any party in Taiwan that &quot;accepts the so-called<space/><link><target>1992 consensus</target></link>&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>The deep-rooted hostility between<space/><link><target>Taiwanese aborigines</target></link><space/>and (Taiwanese) Hoklo, and the Aboriginal communities effective KMT networks contribute to Aboriginal skepticism against the DPP and the Aboriginals tendency to vote for the KMT.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Damm</arg><arg name="first1">Jens</arg><arg name="editor1-last">Damm</arg><arg name="editor1-first">Jens</arg><arg name="editor2-last">Lim</arg><arg name="editor2-first">Paul</arg><arg name="title">European perspectives on Taiwan</arg><arg name="date">2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Springer VS</arg><arg name="location">Wiesbaden</arg><arg name="isbn">9783531943039</arg><arg name="page">95</arg><arg name="chapter">Multiculturalism in Taiwan and the Influence of Europe</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Aboriginals have criticized politicians for abusing the &quot;indigenization&quot; movement for political gains, such as aboriginal opposition to the DPP's &quot;rectification&quot; by recognizing the Taroko for political reasons, with the majority of mountain townships voting for<space/><link><target>Ma Ying-jeou</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=ZOusAgAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA28#v=onepage&amp;amp;q&amp;amp;f=false'>Simon 2011</link>, p. 28.</extension><space/>The Atayal and Seediq slammed the Truku for their name rectification.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/books?id=0t_CU9gmi8cC&amp;amp;pg=PA220&amp;amp;dq=truku&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=P0QfVbq1MomWsAXRt4SADA&amp;amp;ved=0CD4Q6AEwBg#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=truku&amp;amp;f=false'>ed. Vinding 2004</link>, p. 220.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Huashan Business Building 20130118.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>DPP headquarter at Huashan Business Building Level 10 in<space/><link><target>Taipei</target></link>.</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>http://dpptaiwan.blogspot.com/p/contact.html</extension>The National Party Congress selects, for two year terms, the 30 members of the Central Executive Committee and the 11 members of the Central Review Committee. The Central Executive Committee, in turn, chooses the 10 members of the Central Standing Committee. The DPP since 2012 also has a &quot;China Affairs Committee&quot; to deal with<space/><link><target>Cross-Strait relations</target></link>; the name caused some controversy within the party and in the Taiwan media, with critics suggesting that &quot;Mainland Affairs Committee&quot; or &quot;Cross-Strait Affairs Committee&quot; would show less of a hostile &quot;<link><target>One Country on Each Side</target></link>&quot; attitude.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://english.peopledaily.com.cn/90785/8031251.html</arg><arg name="title">China Focus: "China Affairs Committee" negative to Taiwan opposition party: Taiwan media</arg><arg name="agency">Xinhua</arg><arg name="location">Taipei</arg><arg name="date">2012-11-22</arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-11-22</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>For many years the Democratic Progressive Party officially recognized several factions within its membership, such as the<space/><link><target>New Tide faction</target></link><space/>(), the<space/><link><target>Formosa faction</target></link><space/>(), the<space/><link><target>Justice Alliance faction</target></link><space/>() and<space/><link><target>Welfare State Alliance faction</target></link><space/>(). Each faction endorsed slightly different policies. The factions were often generationally identifiable, representing individuals who had entered the party at different times. In 2006 the party ended recognition of factions.<extension extension_name='ref' name="fractions"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="first"><space/>Jewel<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Huang<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.taipeitimes.com/News/front/archives/2006/07/24/2003320124<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Taipei Times<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>DPP votes to do away with factions<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>1<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/>July 24, 2006</arg></template></extension><space/>The factions have since stated that they will comply with the resolution.</paragraph><heading level='3'>List of Chairpersons</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>List of leaders of the Democratic Progressive Party</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Current Chairperson:<space/><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link><space/>(2008-2012, 2014present)</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Legislative Yuan leader (Caucus leader)</heading><preblock><preline>*<space/><link><target>Shih Ming-teh</target></link><space/>(1 February 1993 - 1 February 2002)</preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Ker Chien-ming</target></link><space/>(since 1 February 2002)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Election results</heading><heading level='3'>Presidential elections</heading><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Election</tablehead><tablehead>Candidate</tablehead><tablehead>Running mate</tablehead><tablehead>Total votes</tablehead><tablehead>Share of votes</tablehead><tablehead>Outcome</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 1996</target><part>1996</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><link><target>Peng Ming-min</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Frank Hsieh</target><part>Frank Hsieh Chang-ting</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>2,274,586</tablecell><tablecell>21.1%</tablecell><tablecell><bold>Lost</bold><space/><template><target>N</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2000</target><part>2000</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Annette Lu</target><part>Annette Lu Hsiu-lien</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>4,977,737</tablecell><tablecell>39.3%</tablecell><tablecell><bold>Elected</bold><space/><template><target>Y</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2004</target><part>2004</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Annette Lu</target><part>Annette Lu Hsiu-lien</part></link></tablecell><tablecell>6,446,900</tablecell><tablecell>50.1%</tablecell><tablecell><bold>Elected</bold><space/><template><target>Y</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2008</target><part>2008</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><link><target>Frank Hsieh</target><part>Frank Hsieh Chang-ting</part></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Su Tseng-chang</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>5,445,239</tablecell><tablecell>41.5%</tablecell><tablecell><bold>Lost</bold><space/><template><target>N</target></template></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China presidential election, 2012</target><part>2012</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Su Jia-chyuan</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>6,093,578</tablecell><tablecell>45.6%</tablecell><tablecell><bold>Lost</bold><space/><template><target>N</target></template></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Legislative elections</heading><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Election</tablehead><tablehead>Total seats won</tablehead><tablehead>Total votes</tablehead><tablehead>Share of votes</tablehead><tablehead>Outcome of election</tablehead><tablehead>Election leader</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 1992</target><part>1992</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>51</arg><arg>161</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>2,944,195</tablecell><tablecell>31.0%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>30 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition</bold></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Hsu Hsin-liang</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 1995</target><part>1995</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>54</arg><arg>164</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>3,132,156</tablecell><tablecell>33.2%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>3 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition</bold></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Shih Ming-teh</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 1998</target><part>1998</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>70</arg><arg>225</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>2,966,834</tablecell><tablecell>29.6%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>16 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition</bold></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Lin Yi-hsiung</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2001</target><part>2001</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>87</arg><arg>225</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>3,447,740</tablecell><tablecell>36.6%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>21 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition coalition</bold><space/><template><target>small</target><arg>([[Pan-Green Coalition|Pan-Green]])</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2004</target><part>2004</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>89</arg><arg>225</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>3,471,429</tablecell><tablecell>37.9%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>2 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition coalition</bold><space/><template><target>small</target><arg>([[Pan-Green Coalition|Pan-Green]])</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2008</target><part>2008</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>27</arg><arg>113</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>3,775,352</tablecell><tablecell>38.2%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>decrease</target></template>62 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition coalition</bold><space/><template><target>small</target><arg>([[Pan-Green Coalition|Pan-Green]])</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Chen Shui-bian</target></link></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Republic of China legislative election, 2012</target><part>2012</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>40</arg><arg>113</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell>4,556,526</tablecell><tablecell>34.6%</tablecell><tablecell><template><target>increase</target></template>13 seats;<space/><bold>Opposition coalition</bold><space/><template><target>small</target><arg>([[Pan-Green Coalition|Pan-Green]])</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='3'>Local elections</heading><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Election</tablehead><tablehead>Mayor &amp; Magistrates</tablehead><tablehead>Councils</tablehead><tablehead>Municipal heads</tablehead><tablehead>Municipal councils</tablehead><tablehead>Local heads</tablehead><tablehead>Election Leader</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead><link><target>Taiwan local elections, 2014</target><part>2014</part></link></tablehead><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>13</arg><arg>22</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>291</arg><arg>906</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>54</arg><arg>204</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>194</arg><arg>2137</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><template><target>Composition bar</target><arg>390</arg><arg>7836</arg><arg name="hex">{{Democratic Progressive Party/meta/color}}</arg></template></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Tsai Ing-wen</target></link></tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>List of liberal parties</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Politics of the Republic of China</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of political parties in Taiwan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Liberalism in Taiwan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Human rights in Taiwan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Culture of Taiwan</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taiwan independence movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taiwanese people</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Taiwanese identity</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Resolution on Taiwan's Future</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Free area of the Republic of China</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Formosa TV</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Democratic Progressive Party</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dpp.org.tw/'>DPP Official website</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bikhim.wordpress.com/'>DPP legislator Bi-khim Hsiao<space/></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.tibet.net/en/flash/2004/0504/images/chen.jpg'>Former President of Republic of China (Taiwan) Chen Shui-bian taking the oath of office</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://etd.lib.nsysu.edu.tw/ETD-db/ETD-search/getfile?URN=etd-1223103-143943&amp;amp;filename=etd-1223103-143943.pdf'>Academic thesis on the factions within DPP</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Democratic Progressive Party</target></template><template><target>Politics of Taiwan footer</target></template><template><target>Taiwanese political parties</target></template><template><target>interlib</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Democratic Progressive Party</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Liberal parties in Asia</target></link><link><target>Category:Political parties in Taiwan</target></link><link><target>Category:Taiwan independence movement</target></link><link><target>Category:Political parties established in 1986</target></link><link><target>Category:Political organizations in Taiwan</target></link><link><target>Category:Pro-independence parties</target></link><link><target>Category:1986 establishments in Taiwan</target></link></paragraph></article>