<article title='Aesthetics'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Aesthetic</arg><arg>the 19th century art movement</arg><arg>Aestheticism</arg><arg>the EP by From First to Last</arg><arg>Aesthetic (EP)</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2012</arg></template><template><target>Philosophy sidebar</target><arg>Branches</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold>Aesthetics</bold><space/>(<template><target>IPAc-en</target><arg>ɛ</arg><arg>s</arg><arg>ˈ</arg><arg>θ</arg><arg>ɛ</arg><arg>t</arg><arg>ɪ</arg><arg>k</arg><arg>s</arg><arg></arg></template>; also spelled<space/><bold>sthetics</bold><space/>and<space/><bold>esthetics</bold><space/>also known in Greek as , or<space/><italics>&quot;Aisthtik&quot;</italics>) is a branch of<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>dealing with the nature of<space/><link><target>art</target></link>,<space/><link><target>beauty</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>taste (sociology)</target><part>taste</part></link>, with the creation and appreciation of beauty.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Merriam-Webster.com</arg><arg name="url">http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/aesthetic</arg><arg name="accessdate">21 August 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.merriam-webster.com/dictionary/aesthetics'>Definition 1 of ''aesthetics''</link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Merriam-Webster Dictionary</target></link><space/>Online.</extension><space/>It is more scientifically defined as the study of<space/><link><target>senses</target><part>sensory</part></link><space/>or sensori-emotional values, sometimes called<space/><link><target>judgment</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Feeling</target><part>sentiment</part></link><space/>and taste.<extension extension_name='ref'>Zangwill, Nick. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/aesthetic-judgment/'>Aesthetic Judgment</link>&quot;,<space/><italics><link><target>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></italics>, 02-28-2003/10-22-2007. Retrieved 07-24-2008.</extension><space/>More broadly, scholars in the field define aesthetics as &quot;critical reflection on art, culture and<space/><link><target>nature</target></link>.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly (1998) p. ix</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.arlisna.org/artdoc/vol18/iss2/01.pdf'>Review</link><space/>by Tom Riedel (<link><target>Regis University</target></link>)</extension><space/>In modern English, the term aesthetic can also refer to a set of principles underlying the works of a particular art movement or theory: One speaks for example of the<space/><link><target>Cubism</target><part>Cubist</part></link><space/>aesthetic.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://oxforddictionaries.com/definition/english/aesthetic</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph>The word<space/><italics>aesthetic</italics><space/>is derived from the<space/><link><target>Ancient Greek</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>(<italics>aisthetikos</italics>, meaning &quot;esthetic, sensitive, sentient&quot;), which in turn was derived from (<italics>aisthanomai</italics>, meaning &quot;I perceive, feel, sense&quot;).<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.etymonline.com/index.php?term=aesthetic'>Definition of ''aesthetic''</link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Online Etymology Dictionary</target></link></extension><space/>The term &quot;aesthetics&quot; was appropriated and coined with new meaning in the German form<space/><italics>sthetik</italics><space/>(modern spelling<space/><italics>sthetik</italics>) by<space/><link><target>Alexander Baumgarten</target></link><space/>for the first time in his dissertation<space/><italics>Mediationes philosophicae de nonnullis ad poema pertinentibus</italics><space/>(&quot;Philosophical considerations of some matters pertaining the poem&quot;) in 1735,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Guyer 2005"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Guyer</arg><arg name="first1">Paul</arg><arg name="title">Values of Beauty - Historical Essays in Aesthetics</arg><arg name="date">13 June 2005</arg><arg name="publisher">Cambridge University Press</arg><arg name="isbn">0521606691</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.de/books?id</arg></template></extension>even though his later definition in the fragment<space/><italics>Aesthetica</italics><space/>(1753) is more often referred to as the first definition of modern aesthetics.<extension extension_name='ref'>N Wilson -<space/><link type='external' href='https://books.google.co.uk/books?id=8pXhAQAAQBAJ&amp;amp;pg=PA21&amp;amp;dq=Beauty+in+ancient+Greek+art&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ei=4XZSVeOoKuLd7Qbnk4CgAQ&amp;amp;ved=0CCAQ6AEwAA#v=onepage&amp;amp;q=Beauty%20in%20ancient%20Greek%20art&amp;amp;f=false'>Encyclopedia of Ancient Greece (p.20)</link><space/>Routledge, 31 Oct 2013 ISBN 113678800X [Retrieved 2015-05-12]</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetics and the philosophy of art</heading><paragraph><template><target>quotation</target><arg>Aesthetics is for the artist as [[Ornithology]] is for the birds.</arg><arg>[[Barnett Newman]]<ref>[http://www.barnettnewman.org/chronology.php Barnett Newman Foundation, Chronology, 1952] Retrieved 30 August 2010</ref><ref>''The Abuse of Beauty: Aesthetics and the Concept of Art'', By Arthur Coleman Danto, p.1, Published by Open Court Publishing, 2003, ISBN 0-8126-9540-2, ISBN 978-0-8126-9540-3</ref></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>For some, aesthetics is considered a synonym for the philosophy of art since<space/><link><target>Hegel</target></link>, while others insist that there is a significant distinction between these closely related fields. In practice, aesthetic judgement refers to the sensory contemplation or appreciation of an object (not necessarily an<space/><link><target>art object</target></link>), while artistic judgement refers to the recognition, appreciation or criticism of art or an<space/><link><target>work of art</target><part>art work</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Philosophical aesthetics has not only to speak about art and to produce judgments about art works, but has also to give a<space/><link><target>definition</target></link><space/>of what art is. Art is an<space/><link><target>autonomous</target></link><space/>entity for philosophy, because art deals with the<space/><link><target>senses</target></link><space/>(i. e. the etymology of aesthetics) and art is as such free of any moral or political purpose. Hence, there are two different conceptions of art in aesthetics: art as<space/><link><target>knowledge</target></link><space/>or art as action, but aesthetics is neither<space/><link><target>epistemology</target></link><space/>nor ethics.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Annemarie Gethmann-Siefert</target></link>,<space/><italics>Introduction to Aesthetics</italics><space/>(<italics>Einfhrung in die sthetik</italics>), Munich, Wilhelm Fink, 1995, p. 7.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>History of aesthetics before the 20th century</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>History of aesthetics before the 20th century</arg></template><italics>See also :<space/><link><target>Beauty (ancient thought)</target></link></italics><link><target>File:Poseidon.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Bronze sculpture</target></link>, thought to be either<space/><link><target>Poseidon</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Zeus</target></link>,<space/><link><target>National Archaeological Museum of Athens</target></link></part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Any aesthetic doctrines that guided the production and interpretation of<space/><link><target>prehistoric art</target></link><space/>are mostly unknown. An indirect concern with aesthetics can be inferred from<space/><link><target>ancient art</target></link><space/>in many early civilizations, including<space/><link><target>Ancient Egypt</target><part>Egypt</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Mesopotamia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Ancient Persia</target><part>Persia</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>Greece</part></link>,<space/><link><target>China</target></link>, the<space/><link><target>Etruscan civilization</target><part>Etruscans</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Ancient Rome</target><part>Rome</part></link>,<space/><link><target>History of India</target><part>India</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Celtic art</target><part>Celtic peoples</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Maya civilization</target><part>Maya</part></link>, as each of them developed a unique and characteristic style in its art.</paragraph><paragraph>Western aesthetics usually refers to<space/><link><target>Ancient Greece</target><part>Greek</part></link><space/>philosophers as the earliest source of formal aesthetic considerations.<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link><space/>believed in beauty as a<space/><italics>form</italics><space/>in which beautiful objects partake and which causes them to be beautiful. He felt that beautiful objects incorporated proportion,<space/><link><target>harmony</target></link>, and unity among their parts. Similarly, in the<space/><italics><link><target>Metaphysics (Aristotle)</target><part>Metaphysics</part></link></italics>,<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>found that the universal elements of beauty were order,<space/><link><target>symmetry</target></link>, and definiteness.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Violin and Candlestick.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part><link><target>Cubist</target></link><space/>painting by<space/><link><target>Georges Braque</target></link>, ''Violin and Candlestick'' (1910)</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>From the late 17th to the early 20th century Western aesthetics underwent a slow revolution into what is often called<space/><link><target>modernism</target></link>. German and British thinkers emphasised beauty as the key component of art and of the aesthetic experience, and saw art as necessarily aiming at absolute beauty.</paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>Alexander Gottlieb Baumgarten</target></link><space/>aesthetics is the science of the sense experiences, a younger sister of logic, and beauty is thus the most perfect kind of knowledge that sense experience can have. For<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link><space/>the aesthetic experience of beauty is a judgment of a subjective but similar human truth, since all people should agree that &quot;this<space/><link><target>rose</target></link><space/>is beautiful&quot; if it in fact is. However, beauty cannot be reduced to any more basic set of features. For<space/><link><target>Friedrich Schiller</target></link><space/>aesthetic appreciation of beauty is the most perfect reconciliation of the sensual and rational parts of human nature.</paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>Friedrich Wilhelm Joseph Schelling</target></link>, the philosophy of art is the &quot;organon&quot; of philosophy concerning the relation between man and nature. So aesthetics began now to be the name for the<space/><italics>philosophy of art</italics>.<space/><link><target>Friedrich von Schlegel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>August Wilhelm Schlegel</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Friedrich Schleiermacher</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target></link><space/>also gave lectures on aesthetics as<space/><italics>philosophy of art</italics><space/>after 1800.</paragraph><paragraph>For Hegel, all culture is a matter of &quot;absolute spirit&quot; coming to be manifest to itself, stage by stage, changing to a<space/><link><target>perfection</target></link><space/>that only philosophy can approach. Art is the first stage in which the absolute spirit is manifest immediately to sense-perception, and is thus an objective rather than subjective revelation of beauty.</paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>Arthur Schopenhauer</target></link><space/>aesthetic contemplation of beauty is the most free that the pure intellect can be from the dictates of will; here we contemplate perfection of form without any kind of worldly agenda, and thus any intrusion of utility or politics would ruin the point of the beauty. It is thus for Schopenhauer one way to fight the<space/><link><target>suffering</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The British were largely divided into intuitionist and analytic camps. The intuitionists believed that aesthetic experience was disclosed by a single mental faculty of some kind. For<space/><link><target>Anthony Ashley-Cooper, 3rd Earl of Shaftesbury</target></link><space/>this was identical to the moral sense, beauty just is the sensory version of moral goodness. For<space/><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target></link><space/>aesthetics consisted in the description of a whole culture which is a linguistic impossibility. Hence his viewpoint can be paraphrased as &quot;That which constitutes aesthetics lies outside the realm of the language game&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:The Painter and His Pug by William Hogarth.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>William Hogarth</target></link>, self-portrait, 1745</part></link>For<space/><link><target>Oscar Wilde</target></link>, the contemplation of beauty for beauty's sake (augmented by<space/><link><target>John Ruskin</target></link>'s search for moral grounding) was more than the foundation for much of his literary career; he once stated, &quot;Aestheticism is a search after the signs of the beautiful. It is the science of the beautiful through which men seek the correlation of the arts. It is, to speak more exactly, the search after the secret of life.&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>&quot;Oscar Wilde&quot; by<space/><link><target>Richard Ellman</target></link><space/>p 122, pub Alfred A Knopf, INC. 1988</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Wilde famously toured the United States in 1882. He travelled across the United States spreading the idea of Aesthetics in a speech called &quot;The English Renaissance.&quot; In his speech he proposed that Beauty and Aesthetics was &quot;not languid but energetic. By beautifying the outward aspects of life, one would beautify the inner ones.&quot; The English Renaissance was, he said, &quot;like the Italian Renaissance before it, a sort of rebirth of the spirit of man&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ellman, p164</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For<space/><link><target>Francis Hutcheson (philosopher)</target><part>Francis Hutcheson</part></link><space/>beauty is disclosed by an inner mental sense, but is a subjective fact rather than an objective one. Analytic theorists like<space/><link><target>Henry Home, Lord Kames</target></link>,<space/><link><target>William Hogarth</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link><space/>hoped to reduce beauty to some list of attributes. Hogarth, for example, thinks that beauty consists of (1) fitness of the parts to some design; (2) variety in as many ways as possible; (3) uniformity, regularity or symmetry, which is only beautiful when it helps to preserve the character of fitness; (4) simplicity or distinctness, which gives pleasure not in itself, but through its enabling the eye to enjoy variety with ease; (5) intricacy, which provides employment for our active energies, leading the eye on &quot;a wanton kind of chase&quot;; and (6) quantity or magnitude, which draws our attention and produces admiration and awe. Later analytic aestheticians strove to link beauty to some scientific theory of<space/><link><target>psychology</target></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>James Mill</target></link>) or<space/><link><target>biology</target></link><space/>(such as<space/><link><target>Herbert Spencer</target></link>).</paragraph><heading level='2'>New Criticism and<space/><italics>The Intentional Fallacy</italics></heading><paragraph>During the first half of the twentieth century, a significant shift to general aesthetic theory took place which attempted to apply aesthetic theory between various forms of art, including the literary arts and the visual arts, to each other. This resulted in the rise of the<space/><link><target>New Criticism</target></link><space/>school and debate concerning<space/><italics>the intentional fallacy</italics>. At issue was the question of whether the aesthetic intentions of the artist in creating the work of art, whatever its specific form, should be associated with the criticism and evaluation of the final product of the work of art, or, if the work of art should be evaluated on its own merits independent of the intentions of the artist.</paragraph><paragraph>In 1946,<space/><link><target>W. K. Wimsatt</target><part>William K. Wimsatt</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Monroe Beardsley</target></link><space/>published a classic and controversial New Critical essay entitled &quot;<link><target>Intentional Fallacy</target><part>The Intentional Fallacy</part></link>&quot;, in which they argued strongly against the relevance of an<space/><link><target>Authorial intentionality</target><part>author's intention</part></link>, or &quot;intended meaning&quot; in the analysis of a literary work. For Wimsatt and Beardsley, the words on the page were all that mattered; importation of meanings from outside the text was considered irrelevant, and potentially distracting.</paragraph><paragraph>In another essay, &quot;<link><target>Affective fallacy</target><part>The Affective Fallacy</part></link>,&quot; which served as a kind of sister essay to &quot;The Intentional Fallacy&quot; Wimsatt and Beardsley also discounted the reader's personal/emotional reaction to a literary work as a valid means of analyzing a text. This fallacy would later be repudiated by theorists from the<space/><link><target>reader-response</target></link><space/>school of literary theory. Ironically, one of the leading theorists from this school,<space/><link><target>Stanley Fish</target></link>, was himself trained by New Critics. Fish criticizes Wimsatt and Beardsley in his essay &quot;Literature in the Reader&quot; (1970).<extension extension_name='ref'>Leitch, Vincent B. , et al., eds.<space/><italics>The Norton Anthology of Theory and Criticism</italics>. New York: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 2001.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>As summarized by Gaut and Livingston in their essay &quot;The Creation of Art&quot;: &quot;Structuralist and post-structuralists theorists and critics were sharply critical of many aspects of New Criticism, beginning with the emphasis on aesthetic appreciation and the so-called autonomy of art, but they reiterated the attack on biographical criticisms' assumption that the artist's activities and experience were a privileged critical topic.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Gaut and Livingston, &quot;The Creation of Art&quot;, p.3.</extension><space/>These authors contend that: &quot;Anti-intentionalists, such as formalists, hold that the intentions involved in the making of art are irrelevant or peripheral to correctly interpreting art. So details of the act of creating a work, though possibly of interest in themselves, have no bearing on the correct interpretation of the work.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gaut and Livingston, p.6">Gaut and Livingston, p.6.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Gaut and Livingston define the intentionalists as distinct from formalists stating that: &quot;Intentionalists, unlike formalists, hold that reference to intentions is essential in fixing the correct interpretation of works.&quot; They quote<space/><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link><space/>as stating that, &quot;The task of criticism is the reconstruction of the creative process, where the creative process must in turn be thought of as something not stopping short of, but terminating on, the work of art itself.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gaut and Livingston, p.6"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Post-modern aesthetics and psychoanalysis</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Duchamp Fountaine.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Example of the<space/><link><target>Dada</target></link><space/>aesthetic,<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link>'s ''Fountain'' 1917</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Early-twentieth-century artists, poets and composers challenged existing notions of beauty, broadening the scope of art and aesthetics. In 1941,<space/><link><target>Eli Siegel</target></link>, American philosopher and poet, founded<space/><link><target>Aesthetic Realism</target></link>, the philosophy that reality itself is aesthetic, and that &quot;The world, art, and self explain each other: each is the aesthetic oneness of opposites.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Green<space/></arg><arg name="first">Edward<space/></arg><arg name="title">Donald Francis Tovey, Aesthetic Realism and the Need for a Philosophic Musicology<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">International Revue of the Aesthetics and Sociology of Music<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>227<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org/pss/30032170?searchUrl</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Siegel<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Eli<space/></arg><arg name="title">Is Beauty the Making One of Opposites?<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">''Journal of Aesthetics & Art Criticism<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1955<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.jstor.org/pss/425879?searchUrl</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Various attempts have been made to define<space/><link><target>Post-Modern</target></link><space/>Aesthetics. The challenge to the assumption that beauty was central to art and aesthetics, thought to be original, is actually continuous with older aesthetic theory; Aristotle was the first in the Western tradition to classify &quot;beauty&quot; into types as in his theory of drama, and Kant made a distinction between beauty and the sublime. What was new was a refusal to credit the higher status of certain types, where the taxonomy implied a preference for tragedy and the sublime to comedy and the<space/><link><target>Rococo</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Benedetto Croce</target><part>Croce</part></link><space/>suggested that &quot;expression&quot; is central in the way that beauty was once thought to be central.<space/><link><target>George Dickie (philosopher)</target><part>George Dickie</part></link><space/>suggested that the sociological institutions of the art world were the glue binding art and sensibility into unities.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">The Aesthetic Attitude</arg><arg name="url">http://www.iep.utm.edu/aesth-at/</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Marshall McLuhan</target></link><space/>suggested that art always functions as a &quot;counter-environment&quot; designed to make visible what is usually invisible about a society.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Grosswiler</arg><arg name="first1">Paul</arg><arg name="title">Transforming McLuhan: Cultural, Critical, and Postmodern Perspectives</arg><arg name="date">2010</arg><arg name="publisher">Peter Lang Publishing</arg><arg name="isbn">9781433110672</arg><arg name="page">13</arg><arg name="url">https://books.google.com.ph/books?id</arg><arg name="accessdate">10 March 2015</arg></template></extension><space/><link><target>Theodor Adorno</target></link><space/>felt that aesthetics could not proceed without confronting the role of the culture industry in the commodification of art and aesthetic experience.<space/><link><target>Hal Foster (art critic)</target><part>Hal Foster</part></link><space/>attempted to portray the reaction against beauty and Modernist art in<space/><italics>The Anti-Aesthetic: Essays on Postmodern Culture</italics>.<space/><link><target>Arthur Danto</target></link><space/>has described this reaction as &quot;kalliphobia&quot; (after the Greek word for beauty,<space/><italics>kallos</italics>).<extension extension_name='ref'>'Kalliphobia in Contemporary Art' in<space/><italics>Art Journal</italics><space/>v. 63 no. 2 (Summer 2004) p.&amp;nbsp;2435</extension><space/><link><target>Andr Malraux</target></link><space/>explains that the notion of beauty was connected to a particular conception of art that arose with the Renaissance and was still dominant in the eighteenth century (but was supplanted later). The discipline of aesthetics, which originated in the eighteenth century, mistook this transient state of affairs for a revelation of the permanent nature of art.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derek Allan,<space/><italics>Art and the Human Adventure, Andr Malraux's Theory of Art</italics><space/>(Amsterdam: Rodopi, 2009)</extension><space/><link><target>Brian Massumi</target></link><space/>suggests to reconsider beauty following the aesthetical thought in the philosophy of<space/><link><target>Deleuze</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Guattari</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Massumi, Brian, (ed.), A Shock to Thought. Expression after Deleuze and Guattari. London &amp; NY: Routeledge, 2002. ISBN 0-415-23804-8</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Jean-Franois Lyotard</target></link><space/>re-invokes the Kantian distinction between<space/><link><target>taste (sociology)</target><part>taste</part></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>sublime (philosophy)</target><part>sublime</part></link>. Sublime painting, unlike<space/><link><target>kitsch</target></link><space/><link><target>realism (visual arts)</target><part>realism</part></link>, &quot;...&amp;nbsp;will enable us to see only by making it impossible to see; it will please only by causing pain.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Lyotard, Jean-Franoise,<space/><italics>What is Postmodernism?</italics>, in<space/><italics>The Postmodern Condition</italics>, Minnesota and Manchester, 1984.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lyotard, Jean-Franoise,<space/><italics>Scriptures: Diffracted Traces</italics>, in Theory, Culture and Society, Volume 21, Number 1, 2004.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Sigmund Freud</target></link><space/>inaugurated aesthetical thinking in<space/><link><target>Psychoanalysis</target></link><space/>mainly via the &quot;Uncanny&quot; as aesthetical affect.<extension extension_name='ref'>Freud, Sigmund, &quot;The Uncanny&quot; (1919). Standard Edition of the Complete Psychological Work of Sigmund Freud, 17:234-36. London: The Hogarth Press</extension><space/>Following Freud and<space/><link><target>Merleau-Ponty</target></link>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Merleau-Ponty, Maurice (1964), &quot;The Visible and the Invisible&quot;. Northwestern University Press. ISBN 0-8101-0457-1</extension><space/><link><target>Jacques Lacan</target></link><space/>theorized aesthetics in terms of sublimation and the Thing.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lacan, Jacques, The Ethics of Psychoanalysis (The Seminar of Jacques Lacan Book VII), NY: W. W. Norton &amp; Company, 1992.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The relation of<space/><link><target>Marxist aesthetics</target></link><space/>to post-modern aesthetics is still a contentious area of debate.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Recent aesthetics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Guy Sircello</target></link><space/>has pioneered efforts in analytic philosophy to develop a rigorous theory of aesthetics, focusing on the concepts of beauty,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Guy Sircello</target></link>,<space/><italics>A New Theory of Beauty</italics>. Princeton Essays on the Arts, 1. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1975.</extension><space/>love<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Guy Sircello</target></link>,<space/><italics>Love and Beauty</italics>. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1989.</extension><space/>and sublimity.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Guy Sircello</target></link>, &quot;How Is a Theory of the Sublime Possible?&quot;<space/><italics>The Journal of Aesthetics and Art Criticism</italics>Vol. 51, No. 4 (Autumn, 1993), pp. 541550</extension><space/>In contrast to romantic theorists Sircello argued for the objectivity of beauty and formulated a theory of love on that basis.</paragraph><paragraph>British philosopher and theorist of<space/><link><target>conceptual art</target></link><space/>aesthetics,<space/><link><target>Peter Osborne (writer and academic)</target><part>Peter Osborne</part></link>, makes the point that &quot;'<link><target>post-conceptual art</target></link>' aesthetic does not concern a particular type of<space/><link><target>contemporary art</target></link><space/>so much as the historical-<link><target>ontological</target></link><space/>condition for the production of contemporary art in general...&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Peter Osborne,<space/><italics>Anywhere Or Not At All: Philosophy of Contemporary Art</italics>, Verso Books, London, 2013. pp. 3 &amp; 51</extension><space/>Osborne noted that<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.fondazioneratti.org/mat/mostre/Contemporary%20art%20is%20post-conceptual%20art%20/Leggi%20il%20testo%20della%20conferenza%20di%20Peter%20Osborne%20in%20PDF.pdf'>contemporary art is 'post-conceptual</link><space/>in a public lecture delivered in 2010.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gary Tedman</target></link><space/>has put forward a theory of a subjectless aesthetics derived from<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link>s concept of alienation, and<space/><link><target>Louis Althusser</target></link>s anti humanism, using elements of Freuds group psychology, defining a concept of the 'aesthetic level of practice'.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tedman, G. (2012)<space/><italics>Aesthetics &amp; Alienation</italics>, Zero Books</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gregory Loewen</target></link><space/>has suggested that the subject is key in the interaction with the aesthetic object. The work of art serves as a vehicle for the projection of the individuals identity into the world of objects, as well as being the irruptive source of much of what is uncanny in modern life. As well, art is used to memorialize individuated biographies in a manner that allows persons to imagine that they are part of something greater than themselves.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Gregory Loewen</target></link>, Aesthetic Subjectivity, 2011 pages 36-7, 157, 238)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetics and science</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Mandel zoom 00 mandelbrot set.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Initial image of a<space/><link><target>Mandelbrot set</target></link><space/>zoom sequence with continuously colored environment</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The field of<space/><link><target>experimental aesthetics</target></link><space/>was founded by<space/><link><target>Gustav Theodor Fechner</target></link><space/>in the 19th century. Experimental aesthetics is characterized by a<space/><link><target>Subject (philosophy)</target><part>subject</part></link>-based,<space/><link><target>inductive reasoning</target><part>inductive</part></link><space/>approach. The analysis of individual experience and behavior based on<space/><link><target>experiment</target><part>experimental methods</part></link><space/>is a central part of experimental aesthetics. In particular, the perception of works of art,<extension extension_name='ref'>Kobbert, M. (1986),<space/><italics>Kunstpsychologie</italics><space/>(&quot;Psychology of art&quot;), Wissenschaftliche Buchgesellschaft, Darmstadt</extension><space/>music, or modern items such as websites<extension extension_name='ref'>Thielsch, M. T. (2008),<space/><italics>sthetik von Websites. Wahrnehmung von sthetik und deren Beziehung zu Inhalt, Usability und Persnlichkeitsmerkmalen.</italics><space/>(&quot;The aesthetics of websites. Perception of aesthetics and its relation to content, usability, and personality traits.&quot;), MV Wissenschaft, Mnster</extension><space/>or other IT products<extension extension_name='ref'>Hassenzahl, M. (2008),<space/><italics>Aesthetics in interactive products: Correlates and consequences of beauty</italics>. In H. N. J. Schifferstein &amp; P. Hekkert (Eds.):<space/><italics>Product Experience.</italics><space/>(pp. 287-302). Elsevier, Amsterdam</extension><space/>is studied. Experimental aesthetics is strongly oriented towards the<space/><link><target>natural science</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Modern approaches mostly come from the fields of<space/><link><target>cognitive psychology</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>neuroscience</target></link><space/>(<link><target>neuroaesthetics</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Martindale, C. (2007),<space/><italics>Recent trends in the psychological study of aesthetics, creativity, and the arts</italics>. In<space/><italics>Empirical Studies of the Arts</italics>, 25(2), p. 121-141.</extension>).</paragraph><paragraph>In the 1970s,<space/><link><target>Abraham Moles</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Frieder Nake</target></link><space/>were among the first to analyze links between aesthetics,<space/><link><target>information processing</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>information theory</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>A. Moles:<space/><italics>Thorie de l'information et perception esthtique</italics>, Paris, Denol, 1973 (<link><target>Information Theory</target></link><space/>and aesthetical perception)</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>F Nake (1974). sthetik als Informationsverarbeitung. (Aesthetics as<space/><link><target>information processing</target></link>). Grundlagen und Anwendungen der Informatik im Bereich sthetischer Produktion und Kritik. Springer, 1974, ISBN 3-211-81216-4, ISBN 978-3-211-81216-7</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 1990s,<space/><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target></link><space/>described an<space/><link><target>algorithmic</target></link><space/>theory of beauty which takes the<space/><link><target>subjectivity</target></link><space/>of the observer into account and postulates: among several observations classified as comparable by a given subjective observer, the aesthetically most pleasing one is the one with the shortest description, given the observer's previous knowledge and his particular method for encoding the data.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.jstor.org/pss/1576418</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.idsia.ch/~juergen/beauty.html</extension><space/>This is closely related to the principles of<space/><link><target>algorithmic information theory</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>minimum description length</target></link>. One of his examples:<space/><link><target>mathematician</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>enjoy simple proofs with a short description in their<space/><link><target>formal language</target></link>. Another very concrete example describes an aesthetically pleasing human face whose proportions can be described by very few<space/><link><target>bit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of information,<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target><part>J. Schmidhuber</part></link>. Facial beauty and fractal geometry. Cogprint Archive: http://cogprints.soton.ac.uk, 1998</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target><part>J. Schmidhuber</part></link>. Simple Algorithmic Principles of Discovery, Subjective Beauty, Selective Attention, Curiosity &amp; Creativity. Proc. 10th Intl. Conf. on Discovery Science (DS 2007) p.&amp;nbsp;2638, LNAI 4755, Springer, 2007. Also in Proc. 18th Intl. Conf. on Algorithmic Learning Theory (ALT 2007) p. 32, LNAI 4754, Springer, 2007. Joint invited lecture for DS 2007 and ALT 2007, Sendai, Japan, 2007.<space/><template><target>arxiv</target><arg>0709.0674</arg></template></extension><space/>drawing inspiration from less detailed 15th century proportion studies by<space/><link><target>Leonardo da Vinci</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Albrecht Drer</target></link>. Schmidhuber's theory explicitly distinguishes between what's<space/><link><target>Beauty</target><part>beautiful</part></link><space/>and what's<space/><link><target>interesting</target></link>, stating that interestingness corresponds to the<space/><link><target>first derivative</target></link><space/>of subjectively perceived beauty. Here the premise is that any observer continually tries to improve the<space/><link><target>predictability</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>compressibility</target></link><space/>of the observations by discovering regularities such as repetitions and<space/><link><target>symmetries</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>fractal</target></link><space/><link><target>self-similarity</target></link>. Whenever the observer's learning process (which may be a predictive<space/><link><target>neural network</target></link>; see also<space/><link><target>Neuroesthetics</target></link>) leads to improved data compression such that the observation sequence can be described by fewer<space/><link><target>bit</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>than before, the temporary<space/><link><target>interestingness</target></link><space/>of the data corresponds to the number of saved bits. This compression progress is proportional to the observer's internal reward, also called curiosity reward. A<space/><link><target>reinforcement learning</target></link><space/>algorithm is used to maximize future expected reward by learning to execute action sequences that cause additional<space/><link><target>interesting</target></link><space/>input data with yet unknown but learnable predictability or regularity. The principles can be implemented on artificial agents which then exhibit a form of<space/><link><target>Artificial intelligence</target><part>artificial</part></link><space/><link><target>curiosity</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target><part>J. Schmidhuber</part></link>. Curious model-building control systems. International Joint Conference on Neural Networks, Singapore, vol 2, 14581463. IEEE press, 1991</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target><part>J. Schmidhuber</part></link>. Papers on artificial curiosity since 1990: http://www.idsia.ch/~juergen/interest.html</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Jrgen Schmidhuber</target><part>J. Schmidhuber</part></link>. Developmental robotics, optimal artificial curiosity, creativity, music, and the fine arts. Connection Science, 18(2):173187, 2006</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Schmidhuber's theory of beauty and curiosity in a German TV show<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.br-online.de/bayerisches-fernsehen/faszination-wissen/schoenheit--aesthetik-wahrnehmung-ID1212005092828.xml<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Br-online.de<space/></arg><arg name="language">German</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Truth as beauty, mathematics</heading><paragraph>Mathematical considerations, such as<space/><link><target>symmetry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>complexity</target></link>, are used for analysis in theoretical aesthetics. This is different from the aesthetic considerations of<space/><link><target>applied aesthetics</target></link><space/>used in the study of<space/><link><target>mathematical beauty</target></link>. Aesthetic considerations such as<space/><link><target>symmetry</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Occam's razor</target><part>simplicity</part></link><space/>are used in areas of philosophy, such as<space/><link><target>Categorical imperative</target><part>ethics</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>theoretical physics</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>cosmology</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>define</target></link><space/><link><target>truth</target></link>, outside of<space/><link><target>empirical</target></link><space/>considerations. Beauty and<space/><link><target>Truth</target></link><space/>have been argued to be nearly synonymous,<extension extension_name='ref'>Why Beauty Is Truth: The History of Symmetry,<space/><link><target>Ian Stewart (mathematician)</target><part>Ian Stewart</part></link>, 2008</extension><space/>as reflected in the statement &quot;Beauty is truth, truth beauty&quot; in the poem<space/><link><target>Ode on a Grecian Urn</target></link><space/>by<space/><link><target>John Keats</target></link>, or by the Hindu motto &quot;Satyam Shivam Sundaram&quot; (Satya (Truth) is Shiva (God), and Shiva is Sundaram (Beautiful)). The fact that judgments of beauty and judgments of truth both are influenced by<space/><link><target>processing fluency</target></link>, which is the ease with which information can be processed, has been presented as an explanation for why beauty is sometimes equated with truth.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reber, R,<space/><link><target>Norbert Schwarz</target><part>Schwarz, N</part></link>, Winkielman, P: &quot;Processing fluency and aesthetic pleasure: Is beauty in the perceiver's processing experience?&quot;,<space/><italics>Personality and Social Psychology Review</italics>, 8(4):364-382</extension><space/>Indeed, recent research found that people use beauty as an indication for truth in mathematical pattern tasks.<extension extension_name='ref'>Reber, R, Brun, M, Mitterndorfer, K: &quot;The use of heuristics in intuitive mathematical judgment&quot;,<space/><italics>Psychonomic Bulletin &amp; Review</italics>, 15(6):11741178</extension><space/>However, scientists including the mathematician<space/><link><target>David Orrell</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Orrell<space/></arg><arg name="first">David<space/></arg><arg name="title">Truth or Beauty: Science and the Quest for Order<space/></arg><arg name="location">New Haven</arg><arg name="publisher">Yale University Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2012<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0300186611<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>and physicist<space/><link><target>Marcelo Gleiser</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last">Gleiser</arg><arg name="first">Marcelo<space/></arg><arg name="title">A Tear at the Edge of Creation: A Radical New Vision for Life in an Imperfect Universe<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Free Press<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-1-4391-0832-1</arg></template></extension><space/>have argued that the emphasis on aesthetic criteria such as symmetry is equally capable of leading scientists astray.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Computational inference of aesthetics</heading><paragraph>Since about 2005, computer scientists have attempted to develop automated methods to infer aesthetic quality of images.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite conference</target><arg name="first1">R.<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Datta<space/></arg><arg name="first2">D.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Joshi<space/></arg><arg name="first3">J.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Li<space/></arg><arg name="first4">J.<space/></arg><arg name="last4">Wang<space/></arg><arg name="title">Studying aesthetics in photographic images using a computational approach<space/></arg><arg name="booktitle">Europ. Conf. on Computer Vision<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Springer<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.springerlink.com/content/j062q28222k34382/</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite conference</target><arg name="first1">L.-K.<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Wong<space/></arg><arg name="first2">K.-L.<space/></arg><arg name="last2">Low<space/></arg><arg name="title">Saliency-enhanced image aesthetic classification<space/></arg><arg name="booktitle">Int. Conf. on Image Processing<space/></arg><arg name="year">2009<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">IEEE<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/xpl/freeabs_all.jsp?arnumber</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite conference</target><arg name="first1">Y.<space/></arg><arg name="last1">Wu<space/></arg><arg name="first2">C.</arg><arg name="last2">Bauckhage<space/></arg><arg name="first3">C.<space/></arg><arg name="last3">Thurau<space/></arg><arg name="title">The good, the bad, and the ugly: predicting aesthetic image labels<space/></arg><arg name="booktitle">Int. Conf. on Pattern Recognition<space/></arg><arg name="year">2010<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">IEEE<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://ieeexplore.ieee.org/search/freesrchabstract.jsp?tp</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="faria13aesthetics"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Faria, J., Bagley, S., Rueger, S., Breckon, T.P.</arg><arg name="chapter">Challenges of Finding Aesthetically Pleasing Images</arg><arg name="title">Proc. International Workshop on Image and Audio Analysis for Multimedia Interactive Services</arg><arg name="year">2013</arg><arg name="publisher">IEEE</arg><arg name="url">http://www.durham.ac.uk/toby.breckon/publications/papers/faria13aesthetics.pdf</arg><arg name="accessdate">19 June 2013</arg></template></extension><space/>Typically, these approaches follow a<space/><link><target>machine learning</target></link><space/>approach, where large numbers of manually rated photographs are used to &quot;teach&quot; a computer about what visual properties are of relevance to aesthetic quality. The Acquine engine, developed at<space/><link><target>Penn State University</target></link>, rates natural photographs uploaded by users.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://acquine.alipr.com<space/></arg><arg name="title">Aesthetic Quality Inference Engine - Instant Impersonal Assessment of Photos<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Penn State University<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">21 June 2009</arg><arg name="archiveurl"><space/>http://web.archive.org/web/20090509101935/http://acquine.alipr.com/</arg><arg name="archivedate"><space/>9 May 2009<space/></arg><arg name="deadurl"><space/>no</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Notable in this area is Michael Leyton, professor of psychology at Rutgers University. Leyton is the president of the International Society for Mathematical and Computational Aesthetics and theInternational Society for<space/><link><target>Group Theory</target></link><space/>in Cognitive Science and has developed a generative theory of shape.</paragraph><paragraph>There have also been relatively successful attempts with regard to chess and music.<extension extension_name='ref'>Manaris, B., Roos, P., Penousal, M., Krehbiel, D., Pellicoro, L. and Romero, J.; A Corpus-Based Hybrid Approach to Music Analysis and Composition; Proceedings of 22nd Conference on Artificial Intelligence (AAAI-07); Vancouver, BC; 839-845 2007.</extension><space/>A relation between<space/><link><target>Max Bense</target></link>'s mathematical formulation of aesthetics in terms of &quot;redundancy&quot; and &quot;complexity&quot; and theories of musical anticipation was offered using the notion of Information Rate.<extension extension_name='ref'>Dubnov, S.; Musical Information Dynamics as Models of Auditory Anticipation; in Machine Audition: Principles, Algorithms and Systems, Ed. W. Weng, IGI Global publication, 2010.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Evolutionary aesthetics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Evolutionary aesthetics</arg></template>Evolutionary aesthetics refers to<space/><link><target>evolutionary psychology</target></link><space/>theories in which the basic aesthetic preferences of<space/><italics><link><target>Homo sapiens</target></link></italics><space/>are argued to have<space/><link><target>evolution</target><part>evolved</part></link><space/>in order to enhance survival and reproductive success.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last1">Shimura</arg><arg name="first1">Arthur P.</arg><arg name="last2">Palmer</arg><arg name="first2">Stephen E.</arg><arg name="title">Aesthetic Science: Connecting Minds, Brains, and Experience</arg><arg name="date">January 2012</arg><arg name="publisher">Oxford University Press</arg><arg name="page">279</arg></template></extension><space/>One example being that humans are argued to find beautiful and prefer<space/><link><target>landscape</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which were good<space/><link><target>habitat</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in the ancestral environment. Another example is that body symmetry is an important aspect of<space/><link><target>physical attractiveness</target></link><space/>which may be due to this indicating good health during body growth. Evolutionary explanations for aesthetical preferences are important parts of<space/><link><target>evolutionary musicology</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Darwinian literary studies</target></link>, and the study of the<space/><link><target>evolution of emotion</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Applied aesthetics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Applied aesthetics</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As well as being applied to art, aesthetics can also be applied to cultural objects such as crucifix or tools. Aesthetic coupling between art-objects and medical topics was made by speakers working for the US Information Agency<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Giannini AJ<space/></arg><arg name="title">Tangential symbols: using visual symbolization to teach pharmacological principles of drug addiction to international audiences<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Journal of clinical pharmacology<space/></arg><arg name="volume">33<space/></arg><arg name="issue">12<space/></arg><arg name="pages">1139–46<space/></arg><arg name="date">December 1993<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">7510314<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1002/j.1552-4604.1993.tb03913.x</arg></template></extension><space/>This coupling was made to reinforce the learning paradigm when English-language speakers used translators to address audiences in their own country. These audiences were generally not fluent in the English language. It can also be used in topics as diverse as<space/><link><target>Mathematical beauty</target><part>mathematics</part></link>,<space/><link><target>gastronomy</target></link>, fashion and website design.<extension extension_name='ref'>Moshagen, M. &amp; Thielsch, M. T. (2010). Facets of visual aesthetics. In:<space/><italics>International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</italics>, 68 (10), 689-709.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.interaction-design.org/encyclopedia/visual_aesthetics.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Visual Aesthetics<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Interaction-design.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">31 July 2012</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Lavie, T. &amp; Tractinsky, N. (2004). Assessing dimensions of perceived visual aesthetics of web sites. International Journal of Human-Computer Studies, 60, 269298.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetic ethics</heading><paragraph>Aesthetic ethics refers to the idea that human conduct and behaviour ought to be governed by that which is beautiful and attractive.<space/><link><target>John Dewey</target></link><extension extension_name='ref'>Dewey, John. (1932)'Ethics', with James Tufts. In:<space/><italics><space/>The Collected Works of John Dewey, 18821953<space/></italics><space/>Edited Jo-Ann Boydston: Carbonsdale: Southern Illinois University Press. p. 275.</extension><space/>has pointed out that the unity of aesthetics and ethics is in fact reflected in our understanding of behaviour being &quot;fair&quot; the word having a double meaning of attractive and morally acceptable. More recently,<space/><link><target>James Page (Australian educationist)</target><part>James Page</part></link><extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.infoagepub.com/products/content/p478d75b79b1ea.php</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>http://eprints.qut.edu.au/12263/</extension><space/>has suggested that aesthetic ethics might be taken to form a philosophical rationale for<space/><link><target>peace education</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetic judgment</heading><paragraph>Judgments of aesthetic value rely on our ability to discriminate at a sensory level. Aesthetics examines our affective domain response to an object or phenomenon.<link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>, writing in 1790, observes of a man &quot;If he says that canary wine is agreeable he is quite content if someone else corrects his terms and reminds him to say instead: It is agreeable to<space/><italics>me</italics>,&quot; because &quot;Everyone has his own (<link><target>sense</target></link><space/>of)<space/><link><target>taste</target></link>&quot;. The case of &quot;beauty&quot; is different from mere &quot;agreeableness&quot; because, &quot;If he proclaims something to be beautiful, then he requires the same liking from others; he then judges not just for himself but for everyone, and speaks of beauty as if it were a property of things.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>Aesthetic judgments usually go beyond sensory discrimination. For<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link>, delicacy of taste is not merely &quot;the ability to detect all the ingredients in a composition&quot;, but also our sensitivity &quot;to pains as well as pleasures, which escape the rest of mankind.&quot; (Essays Moral Political and Literary. Indianapolis, Literary Classics 5, 1987.) Thus, the sensory discrimination is linked to capacity for<space/><link><target>pleasure</target></link>. For<space/><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link><space/>&quot;enjoyment&quot; is the result when pleasure arises from sensation, but<space/><link><target>The Critique of Judgment</target><part>judging something</part></link><space/>to be &quot;beautiful&quot; has a third requirement: sensation must give rise to pleasure by engaging our capacities of reflective contemplation. Judgments of beauty are sensory, emotional and intellectual all at once.</paragraph><paragraph>Viewer interpretations of beauty possess two concepts of value: aesthetics and taste. Aesthetics is the philosophical notion of beauty. Taste is a result of an education process and awareness of elite cultural values learned through exposure to mass culture. Bourdieu examined how the elite in society define the aesthetic values like taste and how varying levels of exposure to these values can result in variations by class, cultural background, and education.<extension extension_name='ref'>Bourdieu, Pierre (1984). Distinction. Routledge. ISBN 0-674-21277-0</extension><space/>According to Kant, beauty is subjective and universal; thus certain things are beautiful to everyone.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/aesthetic-judgment/</arg><arg name="title">Aesthetic Judgment</arg><arg name="publisher"></arg><arg name="accessdate">23 September 2014</arg></template></extension><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template><space/>The contemporary view of beauty is not based on innate qualities, but rather on cultural specifics and individual interpretations.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2010</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Factors involved in aesthetic judgment</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Double-alaskan-rainbow.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part><link><target>Rainbow</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>often have aesthetic appeal.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Judgments of aesthetical values seem often to involve many other kinds of issues as well. Responses such as disgust show that sensory detection is linked in<space/><link><target>instinct</target><trail>ual</trail></link><space/>ways to<space/><link><target>facial expression</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and even behaviors like the<space/><link><target>gag reflex</target></link>. Yet disgust can often be a learned or cultural issue too; as Darwin pointed out, seeing a stripe of soup in a man's beard is disgusting even though neither<space/><link><target>soup</target></link><space/>nor<space/><link><target>beard</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are themselves disgusting. Aesthetic judgments may be linked to emotions or, like emotions, partially embodied in our physical reactions. Seeing a<space/><link><target>Sublime (philosophy)</target><part>sublime</part></link><space/>view of a landscape may give us a reaction of<space/><link><target>awe</target></link>, which might manifest physically as an increased heart rate or widened eyes. These unconscious reactions may even be partly constitutive of what makes our judgment a judgment that the landscape is sublime.</paragraph><paragraph>Likewise, aesthetic judgments may be culturally conditioned to some extent.<space/><link><target>Victorian Era</target><part>Victorians</part></link><space/>in Britain often saw<space/><link><target>African sculpture</target></link><space/>as ugly, but just a few decades later,<space/><link><target>Edwardian Era</target><part>Edwardian</part></link><space/>audiences saw the same sculptures as being beautiful. Evaluations of beauty may well be linked to desirability, perhaps even to<space/><link><target>Human sexuality</target><part>sexual</part></link><space/>desirability. Thus, judgments of<space/><link><target>Architectural design values</target><part>aesthetic value</part></link><space/>can become linked to judgments of economic, political, or<space/><link><target>morality</target><part>moral</part></link><space/>value.<extension extension_name='ref'>Holm, Ivar (2006).<space/><italics>Ideas and Beliefs in Architecture and<space/><link><target>Industrial design</target></link>: How attitudes, orientations, and underlying assumptions shape the built environment</italics>. Oslo School of Architecture and Design. ISBN 82-547-0174-1.</extension><space/>In a current context, one might judge a<space/><link><target>Lamborghini</target></link><space/>to be beautiful partly because it is desirable as a status symbol, or we might judge it to be repulsive partly because it signifies for us over-consumption and offends our political or moral values.<extension extension_name='ref'>Korsmeyer, Carolyn ed.<space/><italics>Aesthetics: The Big Questions</italics><space/>1998</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Aesthetic judgments can often be very fine-grained and internally contradictory. Likewise aesthetic judgments seem often to be at least partly intellectual and interpretative. It is what a thing means or symbolizes for us that is often what we are judging. Modern aestheticians have asserted that<space/><link><target>free will</target><part>will</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Desire (emotion)</target><part>desire</part></link><space/>were almost dormant in aesthetic experience, yet<space/><link><target>preference</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>choice</target></link><space/>have seemed important aesthetics to some 20th-century thinkers. The point is already made by<space/><link><target>David Hume</target><part>Hume</part></link>, but see Mary Mothersill, &quot;Beauty and the Critic's Judgment&quot;, in The Blackwell Guide to Aesthetics, 2004. Thus aesthetic judgments might be seen to be based on the senses, emotions, intellectual opinions, will, desires, culture, preferences, values, subconscious behavior, conscious decision, training, instinct, sociological institutions, or some complex combination of these, depending on exactly which theory one employs.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Are different art forms beautiful, disgusting, or boring in the same way?</heading><paragraph>A third major topic in the study of aesthetic judgments is how they are unified across art forms. We can call a person, a house, a symphony, a fragrance, and a<space/><link><target>mathematical proof</target></link><space/>beautiful. What characteristics do they share which give them that status? What possible feature could a proof and a fragrance both share in virtue of which they both count as beautiful? What makes a painting beautiful is quite different from what makes music beautiful, which suggests that each art form has its own language for the judgement of aesthetics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Consider Clement Greenberg's arguments in &quot;On Modernist Painting&quot; (1961), reprinted in Aesthetics: A Reader in Philosophy of Arts.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>At the same time, there is seemingly quite a lack of words to express oneself accurately when making an aesthetic judgment. An aesthetic judgment cannot be an empirical judgement. Therefore, due to impossibility for precision, there is confusion about what interpretations can be culturally negotiated. Due to imprecision in the standard English language, two completely different feelings experienced by two different people can be represented by an identical verbal expression. Wittgenstein stated this in his lectures on aesthetics and language games.</paragraph><paragraph>A collective identification of beauty, with willing participants in a given social spectrum, may be a socially negotiated phenomenon, discussed in a culture or context. Is there some underlying unity to aesthetic judgment and is there some way to articulate the similarities of a beautiful house, beautiful proof, and beautiful sunset?<extension extension_name='ref' name="kant"><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target></link>,<space/><link><target>The Critique of Judgment</target></link>.</extension><space/>Defining it requires a description of the entire phenomenon, as Wittgenstein argued in his lectures on aesthetics. Likewise there has been long debate on how perception of beauty in the natural world, especially perception of the human form as beautiful, is supposed to relate to perceiving beauty in art or<space/><link><target>Cultural artefact</target><part>artefacts</part></link>. This goes back at least to Kant, with some echoes even in St. Bonaventure.<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2008</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>What is &quot;art&quot;?</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Theory of art</arg></template><link><target>File:Siproeta epaphus Galawebdesign.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>Harmony of colors</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>How best to define the term &quot;art&quot; is a subject of constant contention; many books and journal articles have been published arguing over even the basics of what we mean by the term &quot;art&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="davies">Davies, 1991, Carroll, 2000, et al.</extension><space/><link><target>Theodor Adorno</target></link><space/>claimed in 1969 &quot;It is self-evident that nothing concerning art is self-evident.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danto2003">Danto, 2003</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Goodman">Goodman,</extension><space/>Artists, philosophers, anthropologists, psychologists and programmers all use the notion of art in their respective fields, and give it operational definitions that vary considerably. Furthermore, it is clear that even the basic meaning of the term &quot;art&quot; has changed several times over the centuries, and has continued to evolve during the 20th century as well.</paragraph><paragraph>The main recent sense of the word &quot;art&quot; is roughly as an abbreviation for<space/><bold><italics>creative art</italics></bold><space/>or &quot;<link><target>fine art</target></link>.&quot; Here we mean that skill is being used to express the artist's creativity, or to engage the audience's aesthetic sensibilities, or to draw the audience towards consideration of the &quot;finer&quot; things. Often, if the skill is being used in a functional object, people will consider it a<space/><link><target>craft</target></link><space/>instead of art, a suggestion which is highly disputed by many<space/><link><target>Studio Craft</target><part>Contemporary Craft</part></link><space/>thinkers. Likewise, if the skill is being used in a commercial or industrial way it may be considered design instead of art, or contrariwise these may be defended as art forms, perhaps called<space/><link><target>applied art</target></link>. Some thinkers, for instance, have argued that the difference between fine art and applied art has more to do with the actual function of the object than any clear definitional difference.<extension extension_name='ref'>Novitz, 1992</extension><space/>Art usually implies no function other than to convey or communicate an idea.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">February 2014</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Even as late as 1912 it was normal in the West to assume that all art aims at beauty, and thus that anything that wasn't trying to be beautiful couldn't count as art. The<space/><link><target>cubism</target><part>cubists</part></link>,<space/><link><target>dada</target><trail>ists</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>Igor Stravinsky</target><part>Stravinsky</part></link>, and many later art movements struggled against this conception that beauty was central to the definition of art, with such success that, according to<space/><link><target>Danto</target></link>, &quot;Beauty had disappeared not only from the advanced art of the 1960's but from the advanced philosophy of art of that decade as well.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Danto2003"></extension><space/>Perhaps some notion like &quot;expression&quot; (in<space/><link><target>Benedetto Croce</target><part>Croce's</part></link><space/>theories) or &quot;counter-environment&quot; (in<space/><link><target>Marshall McLuhan</target><part>McLuhan's</part></link><space/>theory) can replace the previous role of beauty.<space/><link><target>Brian Massumi</target></link><space/>brought back &quot;beauty&quot; into consideration together with &quot;expression&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brian Massumi,<space/><italics>Deleuze,<space/><link><target>Guattari</target></link><space/>and the Philosophy of Expression</italics>, CRCL, 24:3, 1997.</extension><space/>Another view, as important to the philosophy of art as &quot;beauty,&quot; is that of the &quot;sublime,&quot; elaborated upon in the twentieth century by the<space/><link><target>postmodern</target></link><space/>philosopher<space/><link><target>Jean-Franois Lyotard</target></link>. A further approach, elaborated by Andr Malraux in works such as<space/><italics>The Voices of Silence</italics>, is that art is fundamentally a response to a metaphysical question ('Art', he writes, 'is an 'anti-destiny'). Malraux argues that, while art has sometimes been oriented towards beauty and the sublime (principally in post-Renaissance European art) these qualities, as the wider history of art demonstrates, are by no means essential to it.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derek Allan.<space/><italics>Art and the Human Adventure. Andr Malraux's Theory of Art</italics>. (Amsterdam: Rodopi, 2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Perhaps (as in Kennick's theory) no definition of art is possible anymore. Perhaps art should be thought of as a cluster of related concepts in a<space/><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target><part>Wittgensteinian</part></link><space/>fashion (as in<space/><link><target>Morris Weitz</target><part>Weitz</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Joseph Beuys</target><part>Beuys</part></link>). Another approach is to say that &quot;art&quot; is basically a sociological category, that whatever art schools and museums and artists define as art is considered art regardless of formal definitions. This &quot;institutional definition of art&quot; (see also<space/><link><target>Institutional Critique</target></link>) has been championed by<space/><link><target>George Dickie (philosopher)</target><part>George Dickie</part></link>. Most people did not consider the depiction of a store-bought<space/><link><target>Urinal (restroom)</target><part>urinal</part></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Brillo</target><part>Brillo Box</part></link><space/>to be art until<space/><link><target>Marcel Duchamp</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Andy Warhol</target></link><space/>(respectively) placed them in the context of art (i.e., the<space/><link><target>art gallery</target></link>), which then provided the association of these objects with the associations that define art.</paragraph><paragraph>Proceduralists often suggest that it is the process by which a work of art is created or viewed that makes it art, not any inherent feature of an object, or how well received it is by the institutions of the art world after its introduction to society at large. If a poet writes down several lines, intending them as a poem, the very procedure by which it is written makes it a poem. Whereas if a journalist writes exactly the same set of words, intending them as shorthand notes to help him write a longer article later, these would not be a poem.<space/><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link>, on the other hand, claims in his<space/><italics>What is art?</italics><space/>(1897) that what decides whether or not something is art is how it is experienced by its audience, not by the intention of its creator. Functionalists like<space/><link><target>Monroe Beardsley</target></link><space/>argue that whether or not a piece counts as art depends on what function it plays in a particular context; the same Greek vase may play a non-artistic function in one context (carrying wine), and an artistic function in another context (helping us to appreciate the beauty of the human figure). '</paragraph><paragraph>Marxist attempts to define art focus on its place in the mode of production, such as in<space/><link><target>Walter Benjamin</target></link>'s essay<space/><italics>The Author as Producer</italics>,<extension extension_name='ref'>Benjamin, Walter,<space/><italics>Understanding Brecht</italics>, trans. Anna Bostock, Verso Books, 2003, ISBN 978-1859844182</extension><space/>and/or its political role in class struggle.<extension extension_name='ref'>Hadjinicolaou, Nicos,<space/><italics>Art History and Class Struggle</italics>, Pluto Press; 1978. ISBN 978-0904383270</extension><space/>Revising some concepts of the Marxist philosopher<space/><link><target>Louis Althusser</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gary Tedman</target></link><space/>defines art in terms of social reproduction of the relations of production on the aesthetic level.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tedman, Gary, Aesthetics &amp; Alienation, Zero Books; 2012.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Classificatory disputes about art</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>What should art be like?</heading><paragraph>Many goals have been argued for art, and aestheticians often argue that some goal or another is superior in some way.<space/><link><target>Clement Greenberg</target></link>, for instance, argued in 1960 that each artistic medium should seek that which makes it unique among the possible mediums and then purify itself of anything other than expression of its own uniqueness as a form.<extension extension_name='ref'>Clement Greenberg, &quot;On Modernist Painting&quot;.</extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>Dada</target><trail>ist</trail></link><space/><link><target>Tristan Tzara</target></link><space/>on the other hand saw the function of art in 1918 as the destruction of a mad social order. &quot;We must sweep and clean. Affirm the cleanliness of the individual after the state of madness, aggressive complete madness of a world abandoned to the hands of bandits.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Tristan Tzara, Sept Manifestes Dada.</extension><space/>Formal goals, creative goals, self-expression, political goals, spiritual goals, philosophical goals, and even more perceptual or aesthetic goals have all been popular pictures of what art should be like.</paragraph><heading level='3'>The value of art</heading><paragraph>Tolstoy defined art as the following: &quot;Art is a human activity consisting in this, that one man consciously, by means of certain external signs, hands on to others feelings he has lived through, and that other people are infected by these feelings and also experience them.&quot; However, this definition is merely a starting point for his theory of art's value. To some extent, the value of art, for Tolstoy, is one with the value of empathy. However, sometimes empathy is not of value. In chapter fifteen of<space/><italics>What Is Art?</italics>, Tolstoy says that some feelings are good, but others are bad, and so art is only valuable when it generates empathy or shared feeling for good feelings. For example, Tolstoy asserts that empathy for decadent members of the ruling class makes society worse, rather than better. In chapter sixteen, he asserts that the best art is &quot;universal art&quot; that expresses simple and accessible positive feeling.<extension extension_name='ref'>Theodore Gracyk, &quot;Outline of Tolstoy's What Is Art?&quot;,<space/><link type='external' href='http://web.mnstate.edu/gracyk/courses/phil%20of%20art/tolstoy.outline.htm'>course web page</link>.</extension><template><target>Original research</target><arg>section</arg><arg name="date">December 2012</arg></template>Other possible views are these: Art can act as a means to some special kind of knowledge. Art may give insight into the human condition. Art relates to science and religion. Art serves as a tool of education, or indoctrination, or enculturation. Art makes us more moral. It uplifts us spiritually. Art is politics by other means. Art has the value of allowing<space/><link><target>catharsis</target></link>. In any case, the value of art may determine the suitability of an art form. Do they differ significantly in their values, or (if not) in their ability to achieve the unitary value of art?</paragraph><paragraph>But to approach the question of the value of art systematically, one ought to ask: for whom? For the artist? For the audience? For society at large, and/or for individuals beyond the audience? Is the &quot;value&quot; of art different in each of these different contexts?</paragraph><paragraph>Working on the intended value of art tends to help define the relations between art and other acts. Art clearly does have spiritual goals in many contexts, but what exactly is the difference between religious art and religion<space/><italics>per se</italics>? The truth is complex; art is both useless in a functional sense, and also the most important human activity.<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">November 2012</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An argument for the value of art, used in the fictional work<space/><italics><link><target>The Hitchhikers Guide to the Galaxy</target></link></italics>, proceeds that, if some external force presenting imminent destruction of Earth asked humanity what its value waswhat should humanity's response be? The argument continues that the only justification humanity could give for its continued existence would be the past creation and continued creation of things like a Shakespeare play, a Rembrandt painting or a Bach concerto. The suggestion is that these are the things of value which define humanity.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The Hitchhiker's Guide to the Galaxy</italics>, by Douglas Adams</extension><space/>Whatever one might think of this claim and it does seem to undervalue the many other achievements of which human beings have shown themselves capable, both individually and collectively it is true that art appears to possess a special capacity to endure (&quot;live on&quot;) beyond the moment of its birth, in many cases for centuries or millennia. This capacity of art to endure over time what precisely it is and how it operates has been widely neglected in modern aesthetics.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derek Allan,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.c-s-p.org/flyers/Art-and-Time1-4438-4400-4.htm'>''Art and Time''</link>, Cambridge Scholars, 2013</extension><space/><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetic universals</heading><paragraph>The philosopher<space/><link><target>Denis Dutton</target></link><space/>identified six universal signatures in human aesthetics:<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dutton"><link><target>Denis Dutton</target></link>'s<space/><italics>Aesthetic Universals</italics><space/>summarized by<space/><link><target>Steven Pinker</target></link><space/>in<space/><italics><link><target>The Blank Slate</target></link></italics></extension></paragraph><list type='numbered'><listitem>Expertise or virtuosity. Humans cultivate, recognize, and admire technical artistic skills.</listitem><listitem>Nonutilitarian pleasure. People enjoy art for art's sake, and don't demand that it keep them warm or put food on the table.</listitem><listitem>Style. Artistic objects and performances satisfy rules of composition that place them in a recognizable style.</listitem><listitem>Criticism. People make a point of judging, appreciating, and interpreting works of art.</listitem><listitem>Imitation. With a few important exceptions like abstract painting, works of art simulate experiences of the world.</listitem><listitem>Special focus. Art is set aside from ordinary life and made a dramatic focus of experience.</listitem></list><paragraph>It might be objected<template><target>by whom</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template>, however, that there are too many exceptions to Dutton's categories. For example, the installations of the contemporary artist<space/><link><target>Thomas Hirschhorn</target></link><space/>deliberately eschew technical virtuosity. People can appreciate a Renaissance<space/><link><target>Madonna (art)</target><part>Madonna</part></link><space/>for aesthetic reasons, but such objects often had (and sometimes still have) specific devotional functions. &quot;Rules of composition&quot; that might be read into<space/><link><target>Duchamp</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Fountain (Duchamp)</target><part>Fountain</part></link></italics><space/>or<space/><link><target>John Cage</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>433</target></link></italics><space/>do not locate the works in a recognizable style (or certainly not a style recognizable at the time of the works' realisation). Moreover, some of Dutton's categories seem too broad: a physicist might entertain hypothetical worlds in his/her imagination in the course of formulating a theory. Another problem is that Dutton's categories seek to universalise traditional European notions of aesthetics and art forgetting that, as Andr Malraux and others have pointed out, there have been large numbers of cultures in which such ideas (including the idea &quot;art&quot; itself) were non-existent.<extension extension_name='ref'>Derek Allan,<space/><italics>Art and the Human Adventure: Andr Malraux's Theory of Art</italics>. (Amsterdam: Rodopi. 2009)</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Criticism</heading><paragraph>The philosophy of aesthetics as a practice has been criticized by some sociologists and writers of art and society.<space/><link><target>Raymond Williams</target></link><space/>argues that there is no unique and or individual aesthetic object which can be extrapolated from the art world, but that there is a continuum of cultural forms and experience of which ordinary speech and experiences may signal as art. By &quot;art&quot; we may frame several artistic &quot;works&quot; or &quot;creations&quot; as so though this reference remains within the institution or special event which creates it and this leaves some works or other possible &quot;art&quot; outside of the frame work, or other interpretations such as other phenomenon which may not be considered as &quot;art&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Pierre Bourdieu</target></link><space/>disagrees with Kant's idea of the &quot;aesthetic&quot;. He argues that Kant's &quot;aesthetic&quot; merely represents an experience that is the product of an elevated class habitus and scholarly leisure as opposed to other possible and equally valid &quot;aesthetic&quot; experiences which lay outside Kant's narrow definition.</paragraph><paragraph>Timothy Laurie argues that theories of musical aesthetics &quot;framed entirely in terms of appreciation, contemplation or reflection risk idealising an implausibly unmotivated listener defined solely through musical objects, rather than seeing them as a person for whom complex intentions and motivations produce variable attractions to cultural objects and practices&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite news</target><arg name="title"><space/>Music Genre As Method<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Timothy<space/></arg><arg name="last"><space/>Laurie<space/></arg><arg name="newspaper"><space/>Cultural Studies Review<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2014<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>https://www.academia.edu/9087511</arg></template><space/>20 (2), pp. 283-292.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Aesthetics in Non-Western cultures</heading><heading level='3'>Indian aesthetics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Indian art</target></link><space/>evolved with an emphasis on inducing special spiritual or philosophical states in the audience, or with representing them<space/><link><target>symbol</target><trail>ically</trail></link>. According to<space/><link><target>Kapila Vatsyayan</target></link>, &quot;Classical<space/><link><target>Indian architecture</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Indian sculpture</target><part>sculpture</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Indian painting</target><part>painting</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Indian literature</target><part>literature</part></link><space/>(<italics>kvya</italics>),<space/><link><target>Music of India</target><part>music</part></link>, and<space/><link><target>Indian dance</target><part>dancing</part></link><space/>evolved their own rules conditioned by their respective media, but they shared with one another not only the underlying spiritual beliefs of the Indian religio-philosophic mind, but also the procedures by which the relationships of the symbol and the spiritual states were worked out in detail.&quot;</paragraph><paragraph>In the Pan Indian philosophic thought the term 'Satyam Shivam Sundaram' is another name for the concept of the Supreme. 'Sat' is the truth value, 'Shiv' is the good value &amp; 'Sundaram' is the beauty value. Man through his 'Srabana' or education, 'Manana' or experience and conceptualization and 'Sadhana' or practice, through different stages of life (<link><target>Ashrama (stage)</target><part>Ashramas</part></link>) comes to form and realize the idea of these three values to develop a value system. This Value-system helps develop two basic ideas 1) that of 'Daksha' or the adept/expert and 2) of Mahana/Parama or the Absolute and thus to judge anything in this universe in the light of these two measures, known as 'Adarsha'. A person who has mastered great amounts of knowledge of the grammars, rules, &amp; language of an art-form are adepts (Daksha), whereas those who have worked through the whole system and journeyed ahead of these to become a law unto themselves is called a Mahana. Individuals idea of 'Daksha' and 'Mahana' is relative to the development of the concept of 'Satyam-Shivam-Sundaram.' For example, Tagore's idea of these two concepts should be above any common man's and many perceive Tagore as a 'Mahana' Artist in the realm of literature. This concept of Satyam-Shivam-Sundaram, a kind of Value Theory is the cornerstone of Indian Aesthetics.</paragraph><paragraph>Of particular concern to Indian drama and literature are the term 'Bhava' or the state of mind and<space/><italics><link><target>Rasa (aesthetics)</target><part>rasa</part></link></italics><space/>referring generally to the emotional flavors/essence crafted into the work by the writer and relished by a 'sensitive spectator' or<space/><italics>sahdaya</italics>. Poets like<space/><link><target>Klidsa</target></link><space/>were attentive to rasa, which blossomed into a fully developed aesthetic system. Even in contemporary India the term<space/><italics>rasa</italics><space/>denoting &quot;flavor&quot; or &quot;essence&quot; is used colloquially to describe the aesthetic experiences in films; &quot;msala mix&quot; describes popular Hindi cinema films which serve a so-called balanced emotional meal for the masses, savored as rasa by these spectators.</paragraph><paragraph>Rasa theory blossoms beginning with the<space/><link><target>Sanskrit</target></link><space/>text<space/><link><target>Ntyashstra</target></link><space/>(<italics>ntya</italics><space/>meaning &quot;drama&quot; and<space/><italics>shstra</italics><space/>meaning &quot;science of&quot;), a work attributed to<space/><link><target>Bharata Muni</target></link><space/>where the Gods declare that drama is the 'Fifth Veda' because it is suitable for the degenerate age as the best form of religious instruction. While the date of composition varies wildly among scholars, ranging from the era of<space/><link><target>Plato</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link><space/>to the seventh century CE. The Ntyashstra presents the aesthetic concepts of rasas and their associated bhvas in Chapters Six and Seven respectively, which appear to be independent of the work as a whole. Eight rasas and associated bhvas are named and their enjoyment is likened to savoring a meal: rasa is the enjoyment of flavors that arise from the proper preparation of ingredients and the quality of ingredients. What rasa actually is, in a theoretical sense, is not discussed and given the<space/><link><target>Ntyashstra</target></link>'s pithy wording it is unlikely the exact understanding of the original author(s) will be known.</paragraph><paragraph>The theory of the rasas develops significantly with the Kashmiri aesthetician ndandavardhana's classic on poetics, the Dhvanyloka which introduces the ninth rasa, shnta-rasa as a specifically religious feeling of peace (<italics>nta</italics>) which arises from its bhva, weariness of the pleasures of the world. The primary purpose of this text is to refine the literary concept<space/><italics>dhvani</italics><space/>or poetic suggestion, by arguing for the existence of the<space/><italics>rasa-dhvani</italics>, primarily in forms of Sanskrit including a word, sentence or whole work &quot;suggests&quot; a real-world emotional state or bhva, but thanks to<space/><link><target>aesthetic distance</target></link>, the sensitive spectator relishes the rasa, the aesthetic flavor of tragedy, heroism or romance.</paragraph><paragraph>The 9th10th century master of the religious system known as &quot;the nondual Shaivism of Kashmir&quot; (or &quot;Kashmir Shaivism&quot;) and aesthetician,<space/><link><target>Abhinavagupta</target></link><space/>brought rasa theory to its pinnacle in his separate commentaries on the Dhvanyloka, the Dhvanyloka-locana (translated by Ingalls, Masson and Patwardhan, 1992) and the Abhinavabharati, his commentary on the<space/><link><target>Ntyashstra</target></link>, portions of which are translated by Gnoli and Masson and Patwardhan. Abhinavagupta offers for the first time a technical definition of rasa which is the universal bliss of the Self or<space/><link><target>tman (Hinduism)</target><part>Atman</part></link><space/>colored by the emotional tone of a drama. Shnta-rasa functions as an equal member of the set of rasas but is simultaneously distinct being the most clear form of aesthetic bliss. Abhinavagupta likens it to the string of a jeweled necklace; while it may not be the most appealing for most people, it is the string that gives form to the necklace, allowing the jewels of the other eight rasas to be relished. Relishing the rasas and particularly shnta-rasa is hinted as being as-good-as but never-equal-to the bliss of Self-realization experienced by yogis.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Chinese aesthetics</heading><paragraph><link><target>Chinese art</target></link><space/>has a long history of varied styles and emphases.<space/><link><target>Confucius</target></link><space/>emphasized the role of the arts and humanities (especially music and poetry) in broadening human nature and aiding<space/><italics>li</italics><space/>(etiquette, the rites) in bringing us back to what is essential about humanity. His opponent<space/><link><target>Mozi</target></link>, however, argued that music and fine arts were classist and wasteful, benefiting the rich over the poor.</paragraph><paragraph>By the 4th century AD artists had started debating in writing over the proper goals of art as well.<space/><link><target>Gu Kaizhi</target></link><space/>has left three surviving books on the theory of painting. Several later artists or scholars both created art and wrote about the creation of it. Religious and philosophical influences on art were common (and diverse) but never universal.</paragraph><paragraph>Modern Chinese aesthetic theory took shape during the modernisation of China from Empire to republic in early 20th century. Thus thinkers like Kant, Hegel, Marx and Heidegger have all been incorporated into contemporary Chinese aesthetic theory, through philosophers like Li Zehou.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Li Zehou</target></link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>African aesthetics</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Great Mosque of Djenn 3.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>The<space/><link><target>Great Mosque of Djenn</target><part>Great Mosque</part></link>'s signature trio of<space/><link><target>minaret</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>overlooks the central market of<space/><link><target>Djenn</target></link>. Unique Malian aesthetic</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>African art</target></link><space/>has existed in many forms and styles, with relatively little influence from outside Africa. Most of it followed traditional forms; the aesthetic norms were handed down orally as well as textually. Sculpture and<space/><link><target>performance art</target></link><space/>are prominent, and abstract and partially abstracted forms are valued, and were valued long before influence from the Western tradition began in earnest. The<space/><link><target>Nok culture</target></link><space/>is testimony to this. The mosque of<space/><link><target>Timbuktu</target></link><space/>shows that specific areas of Africa developed unique aesthetics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Arab aesthetics</heading><paragraph>Arab art for the last 1400 years has taken place under the context of<space/><link><target>Islam</target></link><space/>and is sometimes referred to as<space/><link><target>Islamic art</target></link>, although many Arab artists throughout time have not been Muslim. The term &quot;Islamic&quot; refers not only to the religion, but to any form of art created by people in an<space/><link><target>Muslim culture</target><part>Islamic culture</part></link><space/>or in an Islamic context, whether the artist is Islamic or not. Not all Muslims are in agreement on the use of art in religious observance, the proper place of art in society, or the relation between secular art and the demands placed on the secular world to conform to religious precepts. Islamic art frequently adopts secular elements and elements that are frowned upon, if not forbidden, by some<space/><link><target>Kalam</target><part>Islamic theologians</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Davies, Penelope J.E. Denny, Walter B. Hofrichter, Frima Fox. Jacobs, Joseph. Roberts, Ann M. Simon, David L. Janson's History of Art, Prentice Hall; 2007, Upper Saddle River, New Jersey. Seventh Edition, ISBN 0-13-193455-4 pg. 277</extension><space/>Although the often cited opposition in Islam to the depiction of human and animal forms holds true for religious art and architecture, in the secular sphere, such representations have flourished in nearly all Islamic cultures.</paragraph><paragraph>The Islamic resistance to the representation of living beings ultimately stems from the belief that the creation of living forms is unique to God, and it is for this reason that the role of images and image makers has been controversial. The strongest statements on the subject of figural depiction are made in the Hadith (Traditions of the Prophet), where painters are challenged to &quot;breathe life&quot; into their creations and threatened with punishment on the<space/><link><target>Day of Judgment</target></link>. The Qur'an is less specific but condemns idolatry and uses the Arabic term musawwir (&quot;maker of forms,&quot; or artist) as an epithet for God. Partially as a result of this religious sentiment, figures in painting were often stylized and, in some cases, the destruction of figurative artworks occurred. Iconoclasm was previously known in the Byzantine period and aniconicism was a feature of the Judaic world, thus placing the Islamic objection to figurative representations within a larger context. As ornament, however, figures were largely devoid of any larger significance and perhaps therefore posed less challenge.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.metmuseum.org/toah/hd/figs/hd_figs.htm</extension></paragraph><paragraph>This tendency affected the narrowing field of artistic possibility to such forms of art as<space/><link><target>Arabesque (Islamic art)</target><part>Arabesque</part></link>,<space/><link><target>mosaic</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Islamic calligraphy</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Islamic architecture</target></link>, as well as any form of abstraction that can claim the status of non-representational art.</paragraph><paragraph>Limited possibilities have been explored by artists as an outlet to artistic expression, and has been cultivated to become a positive style and tradition, emphasizing the decorative function of art, or its religious functions via non-representational forms such as Geometric patterns, floral patterns, and<space/><link><target>arabesques</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Human portrayals can be found in early Islamic cultures with varying degrees of acceptance by religious authorities. Human representation for the purpose of worship is uniformly considered<space/><link><target>idolatry</target></link><space/>as forbidden in<space/><italics><link><target>Sharia</target></link></italics><space/>law.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://books.google.com/books?id=rpUuqLPPKK4C&amp;amp;dq=wijdan&amp;amp;printsec=frontcover&amp;amp;source=web&amp;amp;ots=QXySmKzsy6&amp;amp;sig=a9V6tTTfsrTT5Ex01QGnwrL7XYY'>''The Arab Contribution to Islamic Art: From the Seventh to the Fifteenth Centuries''</link>, [Wijdan Ali], American Univ in Cairo Press, 10 December 1999, ISBN 977-424-476-1</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www2.let.uu.nl/solis/anpt/EJOS/pdf4/07Ali.pdf'>''From the Literal to the Spiritual: The Development of the Prophet Muhammad's Portrayal from 13th century Ilkhanid Miniatures to 17th century Ottoman Art''</link>, [Steve Mwai],<space/><link type='external' href='http://www2.let.uu.nl/Solis/anpt/ejos/EJOS-1.html'>EJOS (Electronic Journal of Oriental Studies)</link>, volume IV, issue 7, p.&amp;nbsp;124, 2001</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The calligraphic arts grew out of an effort to devote oneself to the study of the<space/><link><target>Quran</target></link>. By patiently transcribing each word of the text, the writer was made to contemplate the meaning of it. As time passed, these calligraphic works began to be prized as works of art, growing increasingly elaborate in the illumination and stylizing of the text. These illuminations were applied to other works besides the Quran, and it became a respected art form in and of itself.</paragraph><paragraph>Arabic is written from right to left, like other<space/><link><target>Semitic</target></link><space/>scripts, and consists of 17 characters, which, with the addition of dots placed above or below certain of them, provide the 28 letters of the Arabic alphabet. Short vowels are not included in the alphabet, being indicated by signs placed above or below the consonant or long vowel that they follow. Certain characters may be joined to their neighbors, others to the preceding one only, and others to the succeeding one only. The written letters undergo a slight external change according to their position within a word. When they stand alone or occur at the end of a word, they ordinarily terminate in a bold stroke; when they appear in the middle of a word, they are ordinarily joined to the letter following by a small, upward curved stroke. With the exception of six letters, which can be joined only to the preceding ones, the initial and medial letters are much abbreviated, while the final form consists of the initial form with a triumphant flourish. The essential part of the characters, however, remains unchanged.<extension extension_name='ref'>http://www.calligraphyislamic.com/IntroIslamicCalligraphy.html</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Art movement</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Art periods</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Formal analysis</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mise en scne</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Style (visual arts)</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mario Perniola</target></link>,<space/><italics>20th Century Aesthetics. Towards A Theory of Feeling</italics>, translated by Massimo Verdicchio, London-New Delhi-New York-Sydney, Bloomsbury, 2013, ISBN 978-1-4411-1850-9.</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title">Creativity and Taoism, A Study of Chinese Philosophy, Art, and Poetry</arg><arg name="last">Chung-yuan<space/></arg><arg name="first">Chang<space/></arg><arg name="year">1963–1970<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Harper Torchbooks<space/></arg><arg name="location">New York</arg><arg name="isbn">0-06-131968-6</arg></template></listitem><listitem><italics>Handbook of Phenomenological Aesthetics</italics>. Edited by Hans Rainer Sepp and Lester Embree. (Series: Contributions To Phenomenology, Vol. 59) Springer, Dordrecht / Heidelberg / London / New York 2010. ISBN 978-90-481-2470-1</listitem><listitem><link><target>Theodor W. Adorno</target></link>,<space/><italics>Aesthetic Theory</italics>, Minneapolis, University of Minnesota Press, 1997.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ayn Rand</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Romantic Manifesto: A Philosophy of Literature</italics>, New York, NY, New American Library, 1971</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.home.netspeed.com.au/derek.allan/default.htm'>Derek Allan</link>,<space/><italics>Art and the Human Adventure, Andre Malraux's Theory of Art</italics>, Rodopi, 2009</listitem><listitem>Derek Allan.<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.c-s-p.org/flyers/Art-and-Time1-4438-4400-4.htm'>Art and Time</link>, Cambridge Scholars, 2013.</listitem><listitem>Augros, Robert M., Stanciu, George N.,<space/><italics>The New Story of Science: mind and the universe</italics>, Lake Bluff, Ill.: Regnery Gateway, c1984. ISBN 0-89526-833-7 (has significant material on Art, Science and their philosophies)</listitem><listitem>John Bender and Gene Blocker<space/><italics>Contemporary Philosophy of Art: Readings in Analytic Aesthetics</italics><space/>1993.</listitem><listitem>Ren Bergeron.<space/><italics>L'Art et sa spiritualit</italics>. Qubec, QC.: ditions du Pelican, 1961.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Christine Buci-Glucksmann</target></link><space/>(2003),<space/><italics>Esthtique de l'phmre</italics>, Galile. (French)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Nol Carroll</target></link><space/>(2000),<space/><italics>Theories of Art Today</italics>, University of Wisconsin Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Mario Costa (philosopher)</target><part>Mario Costa</part></link><space/>(1999) (in Italian), L'estetica dei media. Avanguardie e tecnologia, Milan: Castelvecchi, ISBN 88-8210-165-7.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Benedetto Croce</target></link><space/>(1922), ''Aesthetic as Science of Expression and General Linguistic.</listitem><listitem><link><target>E. S. Dallas</target></link><space/>(1866),<space/><italics>The Gay Science</italics>, 2 volumes, on the aesthetics of poetry.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Arthur Danto</target><part>Danto, Arthur</part></link><space/>(2003),<space/><italics>The Abuse of Beauty: Aesthetics and the Concept of Art</italics>, Open Court.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Stephen Davies (philosopher)</target><part>Stephen Davies</part></link><space/>(1991),<space/><italics>Definitions of Art.</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Terry Eagleton</target></link><space/>(1990),<space/><italics>The Ideology of the Aesthetic.</italics><space/>Blackwell. ISBN 0-631-16302-6</listitem><listitem>Susan Feagin and Patrick Maynard (1997), Aesthetics. Oxford Readers.</listitem><listitem>Penny Florence and Nicola Foster (eds.) (2000),<space/><italics>Differential Aesthetics</italics>. London: Ashgate. ISBN 0-7546-1493-X</listitem><listitem>Berys Gaut and Dominic McIver Lopes (eds.),<space/><italics>Routledge Companion to Aesthetics</italics>. 3rd edition. London and New York: Routledge, 2013.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Annemarie Gethmann-Siefert</target></link><space/>(1995),<space/><italics>Einfhrung in die sthetik</italics>, Munich, W. Fink.</listitem><listitem><link><target>David Goldblatt</target></link><space/>and Lee B. Brown, ed. (2010),<space/><italics>Aesthetics: A Reader in the Philosophy of the Arts.</italics><space/>3rd edition. Pearson Publishing.</listitem><listitem>Theodore Gracyk (2011),<space/><italics>The Philosophy of Art: An Introduction</italics>. Polity Press.</listitem><listitem>Greenberg, Clement (1960), &quot;Modernist Painting&quot;,<space/><italics>The Collected Essays and Criticism 19571969</italics>, The University of Chicago Press, 1993, 85-92.</listitem><listitem>Evelyn Hatcher (ed.),<space/><italics>Art as Culture: An Introduction to the Anthropology of Art.</italics><space/>1999</listitem><listitem><link><target>Georg Wilhelm Friedrich Hegel</target></link><space/>(1975),<space/><italics><link><target>Lectures on Aesthetics</target><part>Aesthetics. Lectures on Fine Art</part></link></italics>, trans. T.M. Knox, 2 vols. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Hans Hofmann</target></link><space/>and Sara T Weeks; Bartlett H Hayes;<space/><link><target>Addison Gallery of American Art</target></link>;<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.worldcatlibraries.org/oclc/1125858&amp;amp;referer=brief_results'>''Search for the real, and other essays''</link><space/>(Cambridge, Mass., M.I.T. Press, 1967)<space/><link><target>OCLC</target></link><space/>1125858</listitem><listitem>Michael Ann Holly and Keith Moxey (eds.),<space/><italics>Art History and Visual Studies</italics>. Yale University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-300-09789-1</listitem><listitem>Carol Armstrong and Catherine de Zegher (eds.),<space/><italics>Women Artists at the Millennium</italics>. Massachusetts: October Books/MIT Press, 2006. ISBN 0-262-01226-X</listitem><listitem><link><target>Immanuel Kant</target><part>Kant</part></link>, Immanuel (1790),<space/><link><target>Critique of Judgement</target></link>, Translated by Werner S. Pluhar, Hackett Publishing Co., 1987.</listitem><listitem>Kelly, Michael (Editor in Chief) (1998)<space/><italics>Encyclopedia of Aesthetics</italics>. New York, Oxford,<space/><link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>. 4 voll., pp.&amp;nbsp;XVII-521, pp.&amp;nbsp;555, pp.&amp;nbsp;536, pp.&amp;nbsp;572; 2224 total pages; 100 b/w photos; ISBN 978-0-19-511307-5. Covers philosophical, historical, sociological, and biographical aspects of Art and Aesthetics worldwide.</listitem><listitem>Alexander J. Kent, &quot;Aesthetics: A Lost Cause in Cartographic Theory?&quot; The Cartographic Journal, 42(2) 182-8, 2005.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Sren Kierkegaard</target></link><space/>(1843),<space/><italics><link><target>Either/Or</target></link></italics>, translated by Alastair Hannay, London, Penguin, 1992</listitem><listitem><link><target>Peter Kivy</target></link><space/>(ed.),<space/><italics>The Blackwell Guide to Aesthetics.</italics><space/>2004</listitem><listitem><link><target>Carolyn Korsmeyer</target></link><space/>(ed.),<space/><italics>Aesthetics: The Big Questions.</italics><space/>1998</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lyotard</target></link>, Jean-Franois (1979),<space/><italics>The Postmodern Condition</italics>, Manchester University Press, 1984.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Merleau-Ponty</target></link>, Maurice (1969),<space/><italics>The Visible and the Invisible</italics>, Northwestern University Press.</listitem><listitem>David Novitz (1992),<space/><italics>The Boundaries of Art.</italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mario Perniola</target></link>,<space/><italics>The Art and Its Shadow</italics>, foreword by Hugh J. Silverman, translated by Massimo Verdicchio, London-NewYork, Continuum, 2004.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert Pirsig</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Zen and the Art of Motorcycle Maintenance: An Inquiry into Values</target></link></italics>, 1974, paperpack, or hardback first edition ISBN 0-688-00230-7</listitem><listitem><link><target>Griselda Pollock</target></link>, &quot;Does Art Think?&quot; In: Dana Arnold and Margaret Iverson (eds.)<space/><italics>Art and Thought</italics>. Oxford: Basil Blackwell, 2003. 129-174. ISBN 0-631-22715-6.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Griselda Pollock</target></link>,<space/><italics>Encounters in the Virtual Feminist Museum: Time, Space and the Archive</italics>. Routledge, 2007. ISBN 0-415-41374-5.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Griselda Pollock</target></link>,<space/><italics>Generations and Geographies in the Visual Arts</italics>. Routledge, 1996. ISBN 0-415-14128-1.</listitem><listitem><link><target>George Santayana</target></link><space/>(1896),<space/><italics>The Sense of Beauty. Being the Outlines of Aesthetic Theory.</italics><space/>New York, Modern Library, 1955.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Elaine Scarry</target></link>,<space/><italics>On Beauty and Being Just.</italics><space/>Princeton, 2001. ISBN 978-0-691-08959-1</listitem><listitem><link><target>Friedrich Schiller</target></link>, (1795),<space/><italics>On the Aesthetic Education of Man</italics>. Dover Publications, 2004.</listitem><listitem>Alan Singer and Allen Dunn (eds.),<space/><italics>Literary Aesthetics: A Reader.</italics><space/>Blackwell Publishing Limited, 2000. ISBN 978-0-631-20869-3</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wadysaw Tatarkiewicz</target></link>,<space/><italics>A History of Six Ideas: an Essay in Aesthetics</italics>, The Hague, 1980. ISBN 978-90-247-2233-4</listitem><listitem><link><target>Wadysaw Tatarkiewicz</target></link>,<space/><italics>History of Aesthetics</italics>, 3 vols. (12, 1970; 3, 1974), The Hague, Mouton.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Markand Thakar</target></link><space/><italics>Looking for the 'Harp' Quartet: An Investigation into Musical Beauty</italics>. University of Rochester Press, 2011.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Leo Tolstoy</target></link>,<space/><italics><link><target>What Is Art?</target></link></italics>, Penguin Classics, 1995.</listitem><listitem>The<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/'>London Philosophy Study Guide</link><space/>offers many suggestions on what to read, depending on the student's familiarity with the subject:<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.ucl.ac.uk/philosophy/LPSG/Aesthetics.htm'>Aesthetics</link></listitem><listitem>John M. Valentine,<space/><italics>Beginning Aesthetics: An Introduction To The Philosophy of Art.</italics><space/>McGraw-Hill, 2006. ISBN 978-0-07-353754-2</listitem><listitem>von Vacano, Diego, &quot;The Art of Power: Machiavelli, Nietzsche and the Making of Aesthetic Political Theory,&quot; Lanham MD: Lexington: 2007.</listitem><listitem>Thomas Wartenberg,<space/><italics>The Nature of Art.</italics><space/>2006.</listitem><listitem><link><target>John W. Whitehead</target><part>John Whitehead</part></link>,<space/><italics>Grasping for the Wind.</italics><space/>2001.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Ludwig Wittgenstein</target></link>,<space/><italics>Lectures on aesthetics, psychology and religious belief</italics>, Oxford, Blackwell, 1966.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Richard Wollheim</target></link>,<space/><italics>Art and its objects</italics>, 2nd edn, 1980, Cambridge University Press, ISBN 0-521-29706-0</listitem><listitem>Sen, R. K.,<space/><italics>Aesthetic Enjoyment: Its Background in Philosophy and Medicine</italics>, Calcutta: University of Calcutta, 1966</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>wikiquote</target></template><template><target>Wikiversity</target><arg name="at">Topic:Philosophy of art</arg><arg>Aesthetics</arg></template><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Aesthetics</arg></template><template><target>Library resources box</target><arg name="by">no
</arg><arg name="onlinebooks">no
</arg><arg name="others">no
</arg><arg name="about">yes
</arg><arg name="label">Aesthetics<space/></arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Refbegin</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>InPho</target><arg>taxonomy</arg><arg>2247</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>category</arg><arg>aesthetics</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>IEP</target><arg>aestheti</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.iep.utm.edu/m-aesthe/'>Medieval Theories of Aesthetics</link><space/>article in the<space/><italics><link><target>Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://revues.mshparisnord.org/appareil/index.php?id=61'>Revue online ''Appareil''</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ditext.com/anka/beardsley/post.html'>Postscript 1980- Some Old Problems in New Perspectives</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ericdigests.org/pre-9219/art.htm'>Aesthetics in Art Education: A Look Toward Implementation</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.knowledgeworld.com.bd/what-is-art/'>More about Art, culture and Education</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.kunstbewegung.info/de/Revised_interpretation_of_founding%27s_and_concepts_through_an_history_of_aesthetics'>An history of aesthetics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://plato.stanford.edu/entries/aesthetic-concept'>The Concept of the Aesthetic</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.rep.routledge.com/article/M046'>Aesthetics</link><space/>entry in the Routledge Encyclopedia of Philosophy</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.philosophyarchive.com/index.php?title=Philosophy_of_Aesthetics'>Philosophy of Aesthetics</link><space/>entry in the Philosophy Archive</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.saylor.org/site/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/Module-1.pdf'>Washington State Board for Community &amp; Technical Colleges: Introduction to Aesthetics</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://cycleback.files.wordpress.com/2014/05/art_perception_cycleback1.pdf'>Art Perception</link><space/>Complete pdf version of art historian David Cycleback's book.</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Refend</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Aesthetics</target></template><template><target>Philosophy topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Aesthetics</target><part>Aesthetics</part></link></paragraph></article>