<article title='Chianti'><paragraph><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">July 2013</arg></template><link><target>File:HD.5A.036 (10555475386).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>Traditional straw basket ''<link><target>Fiasco (bottle)</target><part>fiasco</part></link>'' of Chianti wine.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>A<space/><bold>Chianti wine</bold><space/><template><target>IPA-it</target><arg>'kjanti</arg></template><space/>is any<space/><link><target>wine</target></link><space/>produced in the Chianti region, in central<space/><link><target>Tuscany (wine)</target><part>Tuscany</part></link>, Italy. It was historically associated with a squat<space/><link><target>bottle</target></link><space/>enclosed in a straw basket, called a<space/><italics><link><target>fiasco (bottle)</target><part>fiasco</part></link></italics><space/>(&quot;flask&quot;;<space/><italics>pl. fiaschi</italics>); however, the<space/><italics>fiasco</italics><space/>is only used by a few makers of the wine now; most Chianti is now bottled in more standard shaped wine bottles.<space/><link><target>Baron</target></link><space/><link><target>Bettino Ricasoli</target></link><space/>(later<space/><link><target>Prime Minister</target></link><space/>of the<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Italy (18611946)</target><part>Kingdom of Italy</part></link>) created the Chianti recipe of 70%<space/><link><target>Sangiovese</target></link>, 15%<space/><link><target>Canaiolo</target></link><space/>and 15%<space/><link><target>Malvasia bianca</target></link><space/>in the middle of the nineteenth century.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163">J. Robinson (ed)<space/><italics>&quot;The Oxford Companion to Wine&quot;</italics><space/>Third Edition pg 162-163 Oxford University Press 2006 ISBN 0-19-860990-6</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The first definition of a wine-area called<space/><italics>Chianti</italics><space/>was made in 1716. It described the area near the villages of<space/><link><target>Gaiole (Chianti)</target><part>Gaiole</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Castellina (Chianti)</target><part>Castellina</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Radda (Chianti)</target><part>Radda</part></link>; the so-called<space/><italics>Lega del Chianti</italics><space/>and later<space/><italics>Provincia del Chianti</italics><space/>(Chianti province). In 1932 the Chianti area was completely re-drawn and divided in seven sub-areas: Classico, Colli Aretini, Colli Fiorentini, Colline Pisane, Colli Senesi, Montalbano and Rfina. Most of the villages that in 1932 were suddenly included in the new Chianti Classico area added<space/><italics>in Chianti</italics><space/>to their name-such as<space/><link><target>Greve in Chianti</target></link><space/>which amended its name in 1972. Wines labelled &quot;Chianti Classico&quot; come from the biggest sub-area of Chianti, that includes the original Chianti heartland. Only Chianti from this sub-zone may boast the black rooster seal (known in Italian as a<space/><italics>gallo nero</italics>) on the neck of the bottle, which indicates that the producer of the wine is a member of the Chianti Classico Consortium, the local association of producers.<extension extension_name='ref'>Consorzio del Marchio Storico</extension><extension extension_name='ref'>Consorzio del vino Chianti Classico</extension><space/>Other variants, with the exception of Rufina from the north-east side of<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link><space/>and Montalbano in the south of<space/><link><target>Pistoia</target></link>, originate in the respective named provinces:<space/><link><target>Province of Siena</target><part>Siena</part></link><space/>for the Colli Senesi,<space/><link><target>Province of Florence</target><part>Florence</part></link><space/>for the Colli Fiorentini,<space/><link><target>Province of Arezzo</target><part>Arezzo</part></link><space/>for the Colli Aretini and<space/><link><target>Province of Pisa</target><part>Pisa</part></link><space/>for the Colline Pisane. In 1996 part of the Colli Fiorentini sub-area was renamed<space/><italics>Montespertoli</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>During the 1970s producers started to reduce the quantity of white grapes in Chianti. In 1995 it became legal to produce a Chianti with 100% Sangiovese. For a wine to retain the name of Chianti, it must be produced with at least 80% Sangiovese grapes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159">M. Ewing-Mulligan &amp; E. McCarthy<space/><italics>Italian Wines for Dummies</italics><space/>pg 147-159 Hungry Minds 2001 ISBN 0-7645-5355-0</extension><space/>Aged Chianti (38 months instead of 47), may be labelled as Riserva. Chianti that meets more stringent requirements (lower yield, higher alcohol content and dry extract) may be labelled as<space/><link><target>Chianti Superiore</target></link>, although Chianti from the &quot;Classico&quot; sub-area is not allowed in any event to be labelled as &quot;Superiore&quot;.</paragraph><heading level='2'>History</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>History of Chianti</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Grand Duke CosimoIII of Tuscany by van Douven.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>left</part><part>In 1716 Cosimo III de' Medici, the Grand Duke of Tuscany, legislated the first official boundaries of the Chianti region in what is today part of the Chianti Classico DOCG.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The earliest documentation of a &quot;Chianti wine&quot; dates back to the thirteenth century when viticulture was known to flourish in the<space/><italics>&quot;Chianti Mountains&quot;</italics><space/>around Florence. The merchants in the nearby townships of Castellina, Gaiole and Radda formed the<space/><italics>Lega del Chianti</italics><space/>(League of Chianti) to produce and promote the local wine. In 1398, records note that the earliest incarnation of Chianti was as a white wine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension><space/>In 1716<space/><link><target>Cosimo III de' Medici</target></link>, Grand Duke of Tuscany issued an edict legislating that the three villages of the<space/><italics>Lega del Chianti</italics><space/>(<link><target>Castellina in Chianti</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Gaiole in Chianti</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Radda in Chianti</target></link>) as well as the village of<space/><link><target>Greve (Chianti)</target><part>Greve</part></link><space/>and a<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2</arg><arg>mi</arg><arg>km</arg><arg name="adj">mid</arg><arg>-long stretch</arg><arg name="abbr">off</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>of hillside north of Greve near<space/><link><target>:it:Spedaluzzo</target><part>Spedaluzzo</part></link><space/>as the only officially recognized producers of Chianti. This delineation existed until July 1932, when the Italian government expanded the Chianti zone to include the outlying areas of<space/><link><target>Barberino Val d'Elsa</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Chiocchio</target></link>,<space/><link><target>:it:Robbiano</target><part>Robbiano</part></link>,<space/><link><target>San Casciano in Val di Pesa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>:it:Strada in Chianti</target><part>Strada</part></link>. Subsequent expansions in 1967 would eventually bring the Chianti zone to cover a very large area all over central Tuscany.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Bettino Ricasoli.jpg</target><part>150px</part><part>thumb</part><part>Baron<space/><link><target>Bettino Ricasoli</target></link><space/>developed the first &quot;modern&quot; Chianti recipe that was Sangiovese based.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>By the eighteenth century, Chianti was widely recognized as a red wine, but the exact composition and grape varieties used to make Chianti at this point is unknown.<space/><link><target>Ampelographer</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>find clues about which grape varieties were popular at the time in the writings of Italian writer<space/><link><target>Cosimo Villifranchi</target></link><space/>who noted that<space/><link><target>Canaiolo</target></link><space/>was widely planted variety in the area along with Sangiovese,<space/><link><target>Mammolo</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Marzemino</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension><space/>It was not until the work of the Italian statesman<space/><link><target>Bettino Ricasoli</target></link><space/>that the modern &quot;Chianti recipe&quot; as a Sangiovese-based wine would take shape.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson pg 414-420">H. Johnson<space/><italics>Vintage: The Story of Wine</italics><space/>pg 414-420 Simon and Schuster 1989 ISBN 0-671-68702-6</extension><space/>Prior to Ricasoli, Canaiolo was emerging as the dominant variety in the Chianti blend with Sangiovese and<space/><link><target>Malvasia</target></link><space/>playing supporting roles. In the mid-nineteenth century, Ricasoli developed a recipe for Chianti that was based primarily on Sangiovese. His recipe called for 70% Sangiovese, 15% Canaiolo, 10% Malvasia (later amended to include<space/><link><target>Trebbiano</target></link>) and 5% other local red varieties. In 1967, the Denominazione di origine controllata (DOC) regulation set by the Italian government firmly established the &quot;Ricasoli formula&quot; of a Sangiovese-based blend with 1030% Malvasia and Trebbiano.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The late nineteenth century saw a period of economic and political upheaval. First came<space/><link><target>oidium</target></link><space/>and then the<space/><link><target>phylloxera epidemic</target></link><space/>would take its toll on the vineyards of Chianti just as they had ravaged vineyards across the rest of Europe. The chaos and poverty following the<space/><italics><link><target>Risorgimento</target></link></italics><space/>heralded the beginning of the<space/><link><target>Italian diaspora</target></link><space/>that would take Italian vineyard workers and winemakers abroad as immigrants to new lands.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Johnson pg 414-420"></extension><space/>Those that stayed behind and replanted choose high-yielding varieties like<space/><link><target>Trebbiano</target></link><space/>and Sangiovese clones such as the<space/><italics>Sangiovese di Romagna</italics><space/>from the nearby<space/><link><target>Romagna</target></link><space/>region. Following<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link>, the general trend in the world wine market for cheap, easy-drinking wine saw a brief boom for the region. With over-cropping and an emphasis on quantity over quality, the reputation of Chianti among consumers eventually plummeted. By the 1950s, Trebbiano (which is known for its neutral flavours) made up to 30% of many mass-market Chiantis.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MacNeil pg 376-379">K. MacNeil<space/><italics>The Wine Bible</italics><space/>pg 376-379 Workman Publishing 2001 ISBN 1-56305-434-5</extension><space/>By the late twentieth century, Chianti was often associated with basic Chianti sold in a squat bottle enclosed in a straw basket, called a<space/><italics>fiasco</italics>. However, during the same period, a group of ambitious producers began working outside the boundaries of DOC regulations to make what they believed would be a higher quality style of Chianti. These wines eventually became known as the &quot;<link><target>Super Tuscans</target></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension><link><target>File:Italian DOCG Chianti label.jpg</target><part>left</part><part>thumb</part><part>The Italian DOCG Chianti label</part></link>Many of the producers behind the Super Tuscan movement were originally Chianti producers who were rebelling against what they felt were antiquated DOC regulations. Some of these producers wanted to make Chiantis that were 100%<space/><link><target>varietal</target></link><space/>Sangiovese. Others wanted the flexibility to experiment with blending<space/><link><target>French (wine)</target><part>French</part></link><space/>grape varieties such as<space/><link><target>Cabernet Sauvignon</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Merlot</target></link><space/>or to not be required to blend in any white grape varieties. The late twentieth century saw a flurry of creativity and innovation in the Chianti zones as producers experimented with new grape varieties and introduced modern wine-making techniques such as the use of new<space/><link><target>oak barrels (wine)</target><part>oak barrels</part></link>. The prices and<space/><link><target>wine ratings</target></link><space/>of some Super Tuscans would regularly eclipse those of DOC sanctioned Chiantis. The success of the Super Tuscans encouraged government officials to reconsider the DOC regulations in order to bring some of these wines back into the fold labelled as Chianti.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Chianti subregions</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:sottozone chianti.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>350px</part><part>Chianti wine area within Tuscany.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The Chianti region covers a vast area of Tuscany and includes within its boundaries several overlapping<space/><italics><link><target>Denominazione di origine controllata</target></link></italics><space/>(DOC) and<space/><italics><link><target>Denominazione di Origine Controllata e Garantita</target></link></italics><space/>(DOCG) regions. Other well known Sangiovese-based<space/><link><target>Tuscan wines</target></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>Brunello di Montalcino</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Vino Nobile di Montepulciano</target></link><space/>could be bottled and labeled under the most basic designation of &quot;Chianti&quot; if their producers chose to do so.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sotheby pg 282-286">T. Stevenson<space/><italics>&quot;The Sotheby's Wine Encyclopedia&quot;</italics><space/>pg 282-286 Dorling Kindersley 2005 ISBN 0-7566-1324-8</extension><space/>Within the collective Chianti region more than 8 million cases of wines classified as DOC level or above are produced each year. Today, most Chianti falls under two major designations of Chianti DOCG, which includes basic level Chianti, as well as that from seven designated sub-zones, and Chianti Classico DOCG.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension><space/>Together, these two Chianti zones produce the largest volume of DOC/G wines in Italy.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Chianti DOCG covers all the Chianti wine and includes a large stretch of land encompassing the western reaches of the<space/><link><target>province of Pisa</target></link><space/>near the coast of the<space/><link><target>Tyrrhenian Sea</target></link>, the Florentine hills in the province of Florence to the north, to the<space/><link><target>province of Arezzo</target></link><space/>in the east and the Siena hills to the south. Within this regions are vineyards that overlap the DOCG regions of Brunello di Montalcino, Vino Nobile di Montepulciano and<space/><link><target>Vernaccia di San Gimignano</target></link>. Any Sangiovese-based wine made according to the Chianti guidelines from these vineyards can be labelled and marked under the basic Chianti DOCG should the producer wish to use the designation.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Within the Chianti DOCG there are eight defined sub-zones that are permitted to affix their name to the<space/><link><target>wine label</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sotheby pg 282-286"></extension><space/>Wines that are labeled as simply Chianti are made either from a blend from these sub-zones or include grapes from peripheral areas not within the boundaries of a sub-zone. The sub-zones are (clockwise from the north): the Colli Fiorentini which is located south of the city of Florence; Chianti Rufina in the northeastern part of the zone located around the commune of<space/><link><target>Rufina</target></link>; Classico in the centre of Chianti, across the provinces of Florence and Siena; Colli Aretini in the Arezzo province to the east; Colli Senesi south of Chianti Classico in the Siena hills, which is the largest of the sub-zones and includes the Brunello di Montalcino and Vino Nobile di Montepulciano areas; Colline Pisane, the westernmost sub-zone in the province of Pisa; Montespertoli located within the Colli Fiorentini around the commune of<space/><link><target>Montespertoli</target></link>; Montalbano in the north-west part of the zone which includes the<space/><link><target>Carmignano (wine)</target><part>Carmignano</part></link><space/>DOCG.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension><space/>As of 2006, there were<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>786</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>under production in Montalbano,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2236</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in the Colli Fiorentini,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>140</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in Montespertoli,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1840</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in Rufina,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>8780</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in the Colli Senesi,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>380</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in Colline Pisane,<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>1603</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in the Colli Aretini, and an additional<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>25511</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>in the peripheral areas that do not fall within one of the sub-zone classifications. Wines produced from these vineyards are labelled simply &quot;Chianti&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chianti Classico</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Chianti 0002.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part></part><part>Chianti Classico premium wine.</part></link><link><target>Image:Chianti-colline2-2.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>Vineyards in<space/><link><target>Gaiole in Chianti</target></link><space/>in the Chianti Classico area.</part></link><link><target>File:Chianti Classico.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>150px</part><part>The iconic black rooster seal of the Consorzio Chianti Classico.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>The original area dictated by the edict of<space/><link><target>Cosimo III de' Medici</target></link><space/>would eventually be considered the heart of the modern &quot;Chianti Classico&quot; subregion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411">A. Domine (ed.)<space/><italics>Wine</italics>, pp. 402-411, Ullmann Publishing, 2008 ISBN 978-3-8331-4611-4</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension><space/>As of 2006, there were<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>17,640</arg><arg>acre</arg><arg>ha</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>of vineyards in the Chianti Classico subregion.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension><space/>The Chianti Classico subregion covers an area of approximate<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>100</arg><arg>sqmi</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template><space/>between the city of<space/><link><target>Florence</target></link><space/>to the north and<space/><link><target>Siena</target></link><space/>to the south. The four communes of Castellina in Chianti, Gaiole in Chianti, Greve in Chianti and Radda in Chianti are located entirely within the boundaries of the Classico area with parts of Barberino Val d'Elsa, San Casciano in Val di Pesa and<space/><link><target>Tavarnelle Val di Pesa</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>province of Florence</target></link><space/>as well as<space/><link><target>Castelnuovo Berardenga</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Poggibonsi</target></link><space/>in the<space/><link><target>province of Siena</target></link><space/>included within the permitted boundaries of Chianti Classico. The soil and geography of this subregion can be quite varied, with altitudes ranging from<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>820</arg><arg>to</arg><arg>2000</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template>, and rolling hills producing differing<space/><link><target>macroclimate</target><trail>s</trail></link>. There are two main soil types in the area: a weathered sandstone known as<space/><italics><link><target>alberese</target></link></italics><space/>and a bluish-gray<space/><link><target>chalk</target><trail>y</trail></link><space/><link><target>marlstone</target></link><space/>known as<space/><italics><link><target>galestro</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension><space/>The soil in the north is richer and more fertile with more<space/><italics>galestro</italics>, with the soil gradually becoming harder and stonier with more<space/><italics>albarese</italics><space/>in the south. In the north, the<space/><link><target>Arno river</target></link><space/>can have an influence on the climate, keeping the temperatures slightly cooler, an influence that diminishes further south in the warmer Classico territory towards Castelnuovo Berardenga.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Chianti Classico are premium Chianti wines that tend to be medium-bodied with firm<space/><link><target>tannins (wine)</target><part>tannin</part><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and medium-high to high<space/><link><target>acidity (wine)</target><part>acidity</part></link>. Floral, cherry and light nutty notes are characteristic<space/><link><target>aromas (wine)</target><part>aromas</part></link><space/>with the wines expressing more notes on the mid-<link><target>palate</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>finish (wine)</target><part>finish</part></link><space/>than at the front of the mouth. As with<space/><link><target>Bordeaux (wine)</target><part>Bordeaux</part></link>, the different zones of Chianti Classico have unique characteristics that can be exemplified and perceived in some wines from those areas. According to<space/><link><target>Master of Wine</target></link><space/><link><target>Mary Ewing-Mulligan</target></link>, Chianti Classico wines from the Castellina area tend to have a very delicate aroma and flavor, Castelnuovo Berardegna wines tend to be the<space/><link><target>most ripe (wine)</target><part>most ripe</part></link><space/>and richest tasting, wines from Gaiole tend to have been characterized by their structure and firm tannins while wines from the Greve area tend to have very concentrated flavours.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The production of Chianti Classico is realised under the supervision of<space/><link><target>:it:Consorzio del Vino Chianti Classico</target><part>Consorzio del Vino Chianti Classico</part></link>, a union of producers in the Chianti Classico subregion. The Consorzio was founded with the aim of promoting the wines of the subregion, improving quality and preventing<space/><link><target>wine fraud</target></link>. Since the 1980s, the foundation has sponsored extensive research into the viticultural and winemaking practice of the Chianti Classico area, particularly in the area of clonal research. In the last three decades, more than 50% of the vineyards in the Chianti Classico subregion have been replanted with improved Sangiovese clones and modern vineyard techniques as part of the Consorzio Chianti Classico's project &quot;Chianti 2000&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>In 2014 a new category of Chianti Classico was introduced: Chianti Classico Gran Selezione.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCGS"><template><target>Cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.chianticlassico.com/en/2014/02/chianti-classico-gran-selezione-carta-d%E2%80%99identita/</arg><arg name="title">Chianti Classico Gran Selezione: Identity Card</arg><arg name="work">chianticlassico.com</arg><arg name="publisher">Consorzio Vino Chianti Classico</arg><arg name="accessdate">January 22, 2015</arg></template></extension><space/>Gran Selezione is made exclusively from a winerys own grapes grown according to stricter regulations compared to regular Chianti Classico.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCGS"></extension><space/>Gran Selezione is granted to a Chianti Classico after it passes a suitability test conductedby authorized laboratories and after it is approved by a special tasting committee.<extension extension_name='ref' name="CCGS"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Greater Chianti region</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Chianti 0008.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>''Fiascos'' of basic Chianti that does not specify any sub-zone on the label. This wine may be a blend from several zones.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Outside of the Chianti Classico area, the wines of the Chianti sub-zone of Rufina are among the most widely recognized and exported from the Chianti region. Located in the<space/><link><target>Arno</target></link><space/>valley near the town of<space/><link><target>Pontassieve</target></link>, the Rufina region includes much area in the<space/><link><target>Pomino</target></link><space/>region, an area that has a long history of wine production. The area is noted for the cool climate of its elevated vineyards located up to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>2,950</arg><arg>ft</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg><arg name="disp">flip</arg></template>. The<space/><link><target>vineyard soil</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of the area are predominately<space/><link><target>marl</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>chalk</target></link>. The Florentine merchant families of the<space/><link><target>Antinori</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Frescobaldi</target></link><space/>own the majority of the vineyards in Rufina. Chianti from the Rufina area is characterized by its multi-layered<space/><link><target>complexity (wine)</target><part>complexity</part></link><space/>and elegance.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Colli Fiorentini subregion has seen an influx of activity and new vineyard development in recent years as wealthy Florentine business people move to the country to plant vineyards and open wineries. Many foreign &quot;<link><target>flying winemaker</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot; have had a hand in this development, bringing global<space/><link><target>viticulture</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>winemaking</target></link><space/>techniques to the Colli Fiorentini. Located in the hills between the Chianti Classico area and Arno valley, the wines of the Colli Fiorentini vary widely depending on producer, but tend to have a simple structure with strong character and fruit notes.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension><space/>The Montespertoli sub-zone was part of the Colli Fiorentini sub-zone until 2002 when it became its own tiny enclave.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The Montalbano subregion is located in the shadow of the Carmignano DOCG, with much of the best Sangiovese going to that wine. A similar situation exists in the Colli Senesi which includes the well known DOCG region of Vino Nobile di Montepulciano. Both regions rarely appear on wine labels that are exported out of Tuscany. The Colli Pisane area produces typical Chiantis with the lightest body and color. The Colli Aretini is a relatively new and emerging area that has seen an influx of investment and new winemaking in recent years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Grapes and classification</heading><paragraph>Since 1996 the blend for Chianti and Chianti Classico has been 75100% Sangiovese, up to 10% Canaiolo and up to 20% of any other approved red grape variety such as Cabernet Sauvignon, Merlot or Syrah. Since 2006, the use of white grape varieties such as Malvasia and Trebbiano have been prohibited in Chianti Classico.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson.com">Jancis Robinson<space/><italics>&quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.jancisrobinson.com/articles/20080701.html'>Chianti Classico - thoroughly red now</link>&quot;</italics><space/>5 July 2008</extension><space/>Chianti Classico must have a minimum<space/><link><target>alcohol level</target></link><space/>of at least 12% with a minimum of 7 months aging in oak, while Chianti Classico's labeled<space/><italics><link><target>riserva</target></link></italics><space/>must be aged at least 24 months at the winery, with a minimum alcohol level of at least 12.5%.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension><space/>The<space/><link><target>harvest (wine)</target><part>harvest</part></link><space/><link><target>yields (wine)</target><part>yields</part></link><space/>for Chianti Classico are restricted to no more than<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>7.5</arg><arg>tonne/ha</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg></template>. For basic Chianti, the minimum alcohol level is 11.5% with yields restricted to<space/><template><target>convert</target><arg>9</arg><arg>tonne/ha</arg><arg>0</arg><arg name="abbr">in</arg></template>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title"><space/>Disciplinari dei vini DOP e IGP italiani – Disciplinari DOCG</arg><arg name="url">http://www.politicheagricole.it/flex/cm/pages/ServeAttachment.php/L/IT/D/7%252Ff%252F7%252FD.17d17e8733bdd61a0792/P/BLOB%3AID%3D4625</arg><arg name="publisher">Ministero delle politiche agricole alimentari e forestali</arg><arg name="language">Italian</arg><arg name="accessdate">2 April 2014</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The aging for basic Chianti DOCG is much less stringent with most varieties allowed to be released to the market on 1 March following the<space/><link><target>vintage</target></link><space/>year. The sub-zones of Colli Fiorentini, Montespertoli and Rufina must be aged for a further three months and not released until 1 June. All Chianti Classicos must be held back until 1 October in the year following the vintage.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Oxford pg 162-163"></extension></paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead colspan="11" align="center">Comparative table of Chianti<space/><italics>laws of production</italics><extension extension_name='ref' name="Unione Italiana Vini"><link type='external' href='http://www.uiv.it'>Unione Italiana Vini</link></extension></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead></tablehead><tablecell><bold>normal</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Classico</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Colli Aretini</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Colli Fiorentini</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Colli Senesi</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Colline Pisane</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Montalbano</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Montespertoli</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Rfina</bold></tablecell><tablecell><bold>Superiore</bold></tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Max. grape prod. (<link><target>metric ton</target><part>t</part></link>/<link><target>hectare</target><part>ha</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>9.0</tablecell><tablecell>7.5</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>8.0</tablecell><tablecell>7.5</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Max. grape prod. (kg/vine)</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>3.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>4.0</tablecell><tablecell>2.2</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Min. vines/ha</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,350</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>3,300</tablecell><tablecell>4,000</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Min. age of vineyards (years)</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell><tablecell>4</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Min. wine dry extract (<link><target>gram</target><part>g</part></link>/<link><target>liter</target><part>l</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>19</tablecell><tablecell>23</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>21</tablecell><tablecell>22</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Min. alcohol cont. (<link><target>%</target></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>11.5</tablecell><tablecell>12.0</tablecell><tablecell>11.5</tablecell><tablecell>12.0</tablecell><tablecell>11.5</tablecell><tablecell>11.5</tablecell><tablecell>11.5</tablecell><tablecell>12.0</tablecell><tablecell>12.0</tablecell><tablecell>12.0</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Min. aging (months)</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>10</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>9</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>3</tablecell><tablecell>6</tablecell><tablecell>9</tablecell><tablecell>9</tablecell></tablerow></table><paragraph><link><target>Image:Sangiovese grapes for chianti.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Sangiovese</target></link><space/>grapes used to make Chianti wine</part></link><link><target>Jancis Robinson</target></link><space/>notes that Chianti is sometimes called the &quot;<link><target>Bordeaux (wine)</target><part>Bordeaux</part></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Italy (wine)</target><part>Italy</part></link>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Robinson.com"></extension><space/>The flexibility in the blending recipe for Chianti accounts for some of the variability in styles among Chiantis. Lighter<space/><link><target>body (wine)</target><part>bodied</part></link><space/>styles will generally have a higher proportion of white grape varieties blended in, while Chiantis that have only red grape varieties will be fuller and richer. While only 15% of Cabernet Sauvignon is permitted in the blend, the nature of the grape variety can have a dominant personality in the Chianti blend and be a strong influence in the wine.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Dummies pg 147-159"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Chianti Classico wines are characterized in their youth by their predominantly floral and<space/><link><target>cinnamon</target></link><space/>spicy bouquet. As the wine<space/><link><target>ages (wine)</target><part>ages</part></link>, aromas of<space/><link><target>tobacco</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>leather</target></link><space/>can emerge. Chiantis tend to have medium-high<space/><link><target>acidity (wine)</target><part>acidity</part></link><space/>and medium<space/><link><target>tannins (wine)</target><part>tannins</part></link>. The acidity in the wines make them very flexible with<space/><link><target>food and wine pairings</target></link>, particularly with<space/><link><target>Italian cuisine</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>that feature<space/><link><target>tomato sauce</target><part>red sauce</part></link>, as well as with<space/><link><target>beef</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lamb and mutton</target><part>lamb</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>wild game</target><part>game</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Wine pg 402-411"></extension><space/>Basic level Chianti is often characterized by its juicy fruit notes of<space/><link><target>cherry</target></link>,<space/><link><target>plum</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>raspberry</target></link><space/>and can range from simple<space/><link><target>quaffing</target></link><space/>wines to those approaching the level of Chianti Classico. Wine expert<space/><link><target>Tom Stevenson</target></link><space/>notes that these basic everyday-drinking Chiantis are at their peak drinking qualities often between three and five years after vintage with premium examples having the potential to age for four to eight years. Well-made examples of Chianti Classico often have the potential to age and improve in the bottle for six to twenty years.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Sotheby pg 282-286"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Chianti Superiore</heading><paragraph>Chianti Superiore is an Italian DOCG wine produced in the provinces of Arezzo, Florence, Pisa, Pistoia, Prato and Siena, in Tuscany. Superiore is a specification for wines produced with a stricter rule of production than other Chianti wines. Chianti Superiore has been authorized since 1996.<extension extension_name='ref'>D.M. 5.08.1996</extension><space/>Chianti Superiore wines can be produced only from grapes cultivated in the Chianti wine areas except from those vineyards that are registered in the Chianti Classico sub-zone. Vineyards registered in Chianti sub-zones other than Classico can produce Chianti Superiore wines but must omit the sub-zone name on the label. Aging is calculated from 1 January after the picking. Chianti Superiore cannot be sold to the consumer before nine months of aging, of which three must be in the bottle. Therefore it cannot be bottled before the June after picking or sold to consumers before the next September.</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead colspan="4" align="center">2004 production<extension extension_name='ref' name="Unione Italiana Vini"></extension></tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablehead></tablehead><tablecell>Chianti Superiore</tablecell><tablecell>Other Chianti</tablecell><tablecell>% Ch. Superiore</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Registered vineyards (<link><target>Hectare</target><part>ha</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>297.98</tablecell><tablecell>25,333.67</tablecell><tablecell>1.18%</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Grape production (<link><target>Tonne</target><part>t</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>1,808.51</tablecell><tablecell>184,023.10</tablecell><tablecell>0.98%</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell>Wine production (<link><target>liter</target><part>l</part></link>)</tablecell><tablecell>1,166,169</tablecell><tablecell>106,124,871</tablecell><tablecell>1.09%</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Special editions</heading><paragraph>Chianti Classico was promoted as the Official wine of the<space/><link><target>2013 UCI Road World Championships</target></link><space/>and sold bottles dedicated to the Championships with special labels.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="title">Profile of Ellen van Dijk at the 2012 Olympic Games site</arg><arg name="url">http://www.toscana2013.it/chianti-classico-gallo-nero-sponsor-dei-mondiali-di-ciclismo/?lang</arg><arg name="publisher">Toscana2013.it</arg><arg name="accessdate">12 September 2013</arg><arg name="accessdate">20 September 2013</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Chiantishire</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>Chianti (wine)</arg></template><template><target>Wikivoyage</target><arg>Chianti</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chianticlassico.com'>Chianti Classico Wine Producers Association</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.chiantisuperiore.it'>Chianti Superiore Wine Producers Association</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Wines</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Category:Tuscany</target></link><link><target>Category:Geographical, historical and cultural regions of Italy</target></link><link><target>Category:Wine regions of Italy</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian DOC</target></link><link><target>Category:Italian DOCG</target></link></paragraph></article>