<article title='London_Docklands'><paragraph><template><target>About</target><arg></arg><arg>the basketball team formerly known as London Docklands</arg><arg>London Towers</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">April 2013</arg></template><link><target>Image:08-14-05 Royal Victoria Dock.jpg</target><part>380px</part><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>The<space/><link><target>The O2 (London)</target><part>O2</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Canary Wharf</target></link><space/>from the<space/><link><target>Royal Victoria Dock</target></link>.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph><bold>London Docklands</bold><space/>is the name for an area in east and southeast London, England. It forms part of the boroughs of<space/><link><target>London Borough of Southwark</target><part>Southwark</part></link>,<space/><link><target>London Borough of Tower Hamlets</target><part>Tower Hamlets</part></link>,<space/><link><target>London Borough of Lewisham</target><part>Lewisham</part></link>,<space/><link><target>London Borough of Newham</target><part>Newham</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Royal Borough of Greenwich</target><part>Greenwich</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Dock (maritime)</target><part>docks</part></link><space/>were formerly part of the<space/><link><target>Port of London</target></link>, at one time the<space/><link><target>world's largest port</target></link>. They have now been redeveloped principally for commercial and residential use. The name<space/><bold>London Docklands</bold><space/>was used for the first time in a government report on redevelopment plans in 1971 but has since become virtually universally adopted. It also created conflict between the new and old communities of the London Docklands.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Establishment</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>Roman Britain</target><part>Roman</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>medieval</target></link><space/>times, ships tended to dock at small quays in the present-day<space/><link><target>city of London</target></link><space/>or<space/><link><target>Southwark</target></link>, an area known as the<space/><italics><link><target>Pool of London</target></link></italics>. However, this gave no protection against the elements, was vulnerable to thieves and suffered from a lack of space at the quayside. The<space/><link><target>Greenland Dock</target><part>Howland Great Dock</part></link><space/>in<space/><link><target>Rotherhithe</target></link><space/>(built 1696 and later forming the core of the<space/><link><target>Surrey Commercial Docks</target></link>) was designed to address these problems, providing a large, secure and sheltered anchorage with room for 120 large vessels. It was a major commercial success and provided for two phases of expansion during the<space/><link><target>Georgian era</target><part>Georgian</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Victorian era</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The first of the Georgian docks was the<space/><link><target>West India Docks</target><part>West India</part></link><space/>(opened 1802), followed by the<space/><link><target>London Docks</target><part>London</part></link><space/>(1805), the<space/><link><target>East India Docks</target><part>East India</part></link><space/>(also 1805), the Surrey (1807), the<space/><link><target>Regent's Canal Dock</target></link><space/>(1820),<space/><link><target>St Katharine Docks</target><part>St Katharine</part></link><space/>(1828) and the West India South (1829). The Victorian docks were mostly further east, comprising the<space/><link><target>Royal Victoria Dock</target><part>Royal Victoria</part></link><space/>(1855),<space/><link><target>Millwall Dock</target><part>Millwall</part></link><space/>(1868) and<space/><link><target>Royal Albert Dock</target><part>Royal Albert</part></link><space/>(1880). The<space/><link><target>King George V Dock, London</target><part>King George V Dock</part></link><space/>was a late addition in 1921.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Development</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Thames river 1882.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>600px</part><part>The London docks in 1882. The<space/><link><target>King George V Dock, London</target><part>King George V Dock</part></link><space/>had not yet been built.</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Three principal kinds of docks existed.<space/><bold>Wet docks</bold><space/>were where ships were laid up at anchor and loaded or unloaded.<space/><bold>Dry docks</bold>, which were far smaller, took individual ships for repairing. Ships were built at<space/><bold>dockyards</bold><space/>along the riverside. In addition, the river was lined with innumerable<space/><link><target>List of locations in the Port of London</target><part>warehouses, piers, jetties and dolphins</part></link><space/>(mooring points). The various docks tended to specialise in different forms of produce. The Surrey Docks<space/><link><target>British timber trade</target><part>concentrated on timber</part></link>, for instance; Millwall took grain; St Katharine took wool, sugar and rubber; and so on.</paragraph><paragraph>The docks required an army of workers, chiefly<space/><link><target>lightermen</target></link><space/>(who carried loads between ships and quays aboard small barges called<space/><link><target>Lighter (barge)</target><part>lighter</part><trail>s</trail></link>) and quayside workers, who dealt with the goods once they were ashore. Some of the workers were highly skilled - the lightermen had their own<space/><link><target>livery company</target></link><space/>or guild, while the<space/><link><target>deal porters</target></link><space/>(workers who carried timber) were famous for their acrobatic skills. Most were unskilled and worked as casual labourers. They assembled at certain points, such as pubs, each morning, where they were selected more or less at random by foremen. For these workers, it was effectively a lottery as to whether they would get work - and pay, and food - on any particular day. This arrangement continued until as late as 1965, although it was somewhat regularised after the creation of the<space/><link><target>National Dock Labour Scheme</target></link><space/>in 1947.</paragraph><paragraph>The main dockland areas were originally low-lying marshes, mostly unsuitable for agriculture and lightly populated. With the establishment of the docks, the dock workers formed a number of tight-knit local communities with their own distinctive cultures and slang. Poor communications meant that they were quite remote from other parts of London and so tended to develop in some isolation. The<space/><link><target>Isle of Dogs</target></link>, for instance, could only be accessed by road via two swing-bridges. Local sentiment there was so strong that Ted Johns, a local community campaigner, and his supporters, in protest at the lack of social provision from the state, proclaimed a unilateral declaration of independence for the area, setting up a so-called 'Island Council' with Johns himself as its elected leader, and blocked off the two roads coming in from the mainland.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/obituaries/1461749/Ted-Johns.html'>Ted Johns</link><space/>Telegraph 14 May 2004 accessed 14 May 2015 2007</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>20th century</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Museum in Docklands at night 2005-01-10.JPG</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part><link><target>Museum of London Docklands</target></link>, near<space/><link><target>Canary Wharf</target></link></part></link>The docks were originally built and managed by a number of competing private companies. From 1909, they were managed by the<space/><link><target>Port of London Authority</target></link>, or PLA, which amalgamated the companies in a bid to make the docks more efficient and improve<space/><link><target>labour relations</target></link>. The PLA constructed the last of the docks, the King George V, in 1921, as well as greatly expanding the<space/><link><target>Port of Tilbury</target><part>Tilbury docks</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>The Blitz</target><part>German bombing</part></link><space/>during<space/><link><target>World War II</target></link><space/>caused massive damage to the docks with 380,000 tons of<space/><link><target>timber</target></link><space/>destroyed in the Surrey Docks in a single night. Nonetheless, following post-war rebuilding they experienced a resurgence of prosperity in the 1950s. The end came suddenly, between approximately 1960 and 1970, when the shipping industry adopted the newly invented container system of cargo transportation. London's docks were unable to accommodate the much larger vessels needed by<space/><link><target>containerization</target></link><space/>and the shipping industry moved to deep-water ports such as<space/><link><target>Tilbury</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Port of Felixstowe</target><part>Felixstowe</part></link>. Between 1960 and 1980, all of London's docks were closed, leaving around eight square miles (21&amp;nbsp;km) of derelict land in East London. Unemployment was high, and poverty and other social problems were rife.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Redevelopment</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Canary Wharf at Sunset.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Canary Wharf at sunset</part></link></paragraph><paragraph>Efforts to redevelop the docks began almost as soon as they were closed, although it took a decade for most plans to move beyond the drawing board and another decade for redevelopment to take full effect. The situation was greatly complicated by the large number of landowners involved: the PLA, the<space/><link><target>Greater London Council</target></link><space/>(GLC), the<space/><link><target>British Gas plc</target><part>British Gas Corporation</part></link>, five borough councils,<space/><link><target>British Rail</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Central Electricity Generating Board</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>To address this problem, in 1981 the<space/><link><target>Secretary of State for the Environment</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Michael Heseltine</target></link>, formed the<space/><link><target>London Docklands Development Corporation</target></link><space/>(LDDC) to redevelop the area. This was a statutory body appointed and funded by central government (a<space/><link><target>quango</target></link>), with wide powers to acquire and dispose of land in the Docklands. It also served as the development planning authority for the area.</paragraph><paragraph>Another important government intervention was the designation in 1982 of an<space/><link><target>enterprise zone</target></link>, an area in which businesses were exempt from property taxes and had other incentives, including simplified planning and capital allowances. This made investing in the Docklands a significantly more attractive proposition and was instrumental in starting a property boom in the area.</paragraph><paragraph>LDDC was controversial - it was accused of favouring elitist luxury developments rather than affordable housing, and it was unpopular with the local communities, who felt that their needs were not being addressed. Nonetheless, the LDDC was central to a remarkable transformation in the area, although how far it was in control of events is debatable. It was wound up in 1998 when control of the Docklands area was handed back to the respective local authorities.</paragraph><paragraph>The massive development programme managed by the LDDC during the 1980s and 1990s saw a huge area of the Docklands converted into a mixture of residential, commercial and light industrial space. The clearest symbol of the whole effort was the ambitious<space/><link><target>Canary Wharf</target></link><space/>project that constructed Britain's tallest building and established a second major financial centre in London. However, there is no evidence that LDDC foresaw this scale of development and nearby<space/><link><target>Heron Quays</target></link><space/>had already been developed as low density offices when Canary Wharf was proposed, with similar development already underway on Canary Wharf itself,<space/><link><target>Limehouse Studios</target></link><space/>being the most famous occupant.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Canary Wharf</target></link><space/>was far from trouble free and the property slump of the early 1990s halted further development for several years. Developers found themselves saddled with property which they were unable to sell or let.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Transport</heading><preblock><preline>The Docklands historically had poor transport connections. This was addressed by the LDDC with the construction of the<space/><link><target>Docklands Light Railway</target></link><space/>(DLR), which connected the Docklands with the City. It was a remarkably inexpensive development, costing only 77&amp;nbsp;m in its first phase, as it relied on reusing disused railway infrastructure and derelict land for much of its length. (LDDC originally requested a full<space/><link><target>London Underground</target><part>Tube</part></link><space/>line, but the Government refused to fund it.)</preline></preblock><paragraph>LDDC also built<space/><link><target>Limehouse Link tunnel</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>cut and cover</target></link><space/>road tunnel linking the<space/><link><target>Isle of Dogs</target></link><space/>to<space/><link><target>The Highway</target></link><space/>(the A1203 road) at a cost of over 150&amp;nbsp;million per kilometre, one of the most expensive stretches of road ever built.</paragraph><paragraph>The LDDC also contributed to the development of<space/><link><target>London City Airport</target></link><space/>(<link><target>IATA airport code</target></link><space/>LCY), opened in October 1987 on the spine of the Royal Docks.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Future developments</heading><paragraph>The continued success of the Docklands redevelopment has prompted a number of further development schemes, including:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Extensions of the<space/><link><target>Docklands Light Railway</target></link><space/>possibly to<space/><link><target>Dagenham</target></link>.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Crossrail</target></link><space/>mainline link between Canary Wharf, central London and<space/><link><target>Heathrow Airport</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Further development of<space/><link><target>Canada Water</target></link>.</listitem><listitem>Redevelopment of<space/><link><target>Blackwall Basin</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Wood Wharf</target></link>, east of Canary Wharf</listitem><listitem>New skyscrapers to be built at Canary Wharf including the<space/><link><target>Riverside South (Canary Wharf)</target><part>Riverside South</part></link><space/>towers, the<space/><link><target>Heron Quays West</target></link><space/>double-skyscraper development and the<space/><link><target>North Quay, London</target><part>North Quay</part></link><space/>project, consisting of three towers.</listitem></list><paragraph>In the early 21st century redevelopment is spreading into the more suburban parts of East and Southeast London, and into the parts of the counties of<space/><link><target>Kent</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Essex</target></link><space/>which abut the<space/><link><target>Thames Estuary</target></link>. See<space/><link><target>Thames Gateway</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Lower Lea Valley</target></link><space/>for further information on this trend.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Today</heading><paragraph>Over the past 30 years, the population of the Docklands has more than doubled and the area has become both a major business centre and an increasingly desirable area to live. Transport links have improved significantly, with the Isle of Dogs gaining a<space/><link><target>London Underground</target><part>tube connection</part></link><space/>via the Jubilee Line Extension (opened 1999) and the DLR being extended to<space/><link><target>Beckton</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lewisham</target></link>,<space/><link><target>London City Airport</target></link>,<space/><link><target>North Woolwich</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Stratford, London</target><part>Stratford</part></link>. Canary Wharf has become one of Europe's biggest clusters of skyscrapers and a direct challenge to the financial dominance of the<space/><link><target>City of London</target><part>City</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Although most of the old Dockland wharfs and warehouses have been demolished, some have been restored and converted into flats. Most of the docks themselves have survived and are now used as marinas or watersports centres (the major exception being the<space/><link><target>Surrey Commercial Docks</target></link>, now largely filled in). Although large ships can - and occasionally still do - visit the old docks, all of the commercial traffic has moved down-river.</paragraph><paragraph>The revival of the Docklands has had major effects in run-down surrounding areas.<space/><link><target>Greenwich</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Deptford, London</target><part>Deptford</part></link><space/>are undergoing large-scale redevelopment, chiefly as a result of the improved transport links making them more attractive to commuters.</paragraph><paragraph>The Docklands' redevelopment has, however, had some less beneficial aspects. The massive property boom and consequent rise in house prices has led to friction between the new arrivals and the old Docklands communities, who have complained of being squeezed out. It has also made for some of the most striking disparities to be seen anywhere in Britain: luxury executive flats constructed alongside run-down public housing estates.</paragraph><paragraph>The Docklands' status as a symbol of<space/><link><target>Margaret Thatcher</target><part>Thatcher</part></link>'s Britain has also made it a target for terrorists. After a failed attempt to bomb Canary Wharf in 1992, a large IRA<space/><link><target>1996 Docklands bombing</target><part>bomb exploded</part></link><space/>at South Quay on 9 February 1996. Two people died in the explosion, forty people were injured and an estimated 150m of damage was caused.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>The parlous state of the Docklands property market at the time of the blast, combined with a lengthy delay in implementing redevelopment, means a true estimate of the financial cost is difficult to reach.</italics><space/><template><target>verifysource</target><arg name="date">December 2009</arg></template></extension><space/>This bombing ended an<space/><link><target>Provisional Irish Republican Army</target><part>IRA</part></link><space/>ceasefire.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/onthisday/hi/dates/stories/february/10/newsid_2539000/2539265.stm<space/></arg><arg name="title">BBC ON THIS DAY &#124; 10 &#124; 1996: Docklands bomb ends IRA ceasefire<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">BBC News<space/></arg><arg name="date">10 February 1996<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2012-06-23</arg></template></extension><space/>In a 1998 trial James McArdle was imprisoned for 25 years after a trial at<space/><link><target>Woolwich</target></link><space/><link><target>Crown Court</target></link><space/>that ended on 24 June. Under the terms of the<space/><link><target>Good Friday Agreement</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>royal prerogative of mercy</target></link><space/>officially signed by Queen<space/><link><target>Elizabeth II</target></link>, McArdle was released on 28 June 2000.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="last">Foster<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.telegraph.co.uk/news/uknews/1350556/Royal-release-for-IRA-bomber.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Royal release for IRA bomber<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Telegraph<space/></arg><arg name="date">2000-07-27<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-07-10</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>London Docklands also now boasts its own free newspaper,<space/><italics>The Docklands</italics>, launched in 2006 by Archant London, following the purchase of Docklands News, the ex LDDC newspaper which was then owned by Ivy Communications. The title is a mixture of news, sport and lifestyle, and comes out every Tuesday. It is delivered to properties in the area and available to pick up from various locations in Canary Wharf, Greenwich and the Royal Docks. It is the newspaper with the highest circulation in the area. A sister title,<space/><italics>The Peninsula</italics>, was launched in 2007, covering the<space/><link><target>Greenwich Peninsula</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In a further sign of regeneration in the area, the Docklands now has its own symphony orchestra -<space/><link><target>Docklands Sinfonia</target></link><space/>- which was formed in January 2009 and is based at<space/><link><target>St Anne's Limehouse</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.eastlondonadvertiser.co.uk/content/towerhamlets/advertiser/news/story.aspx?brand=elaonline&amp;amp;category=news&amp;amp;tBrand=northlondon24&amp;amp;tCategory=newsela&amp;amp;itemid=WeED16%20Sep%202008%2023%3A53%3A48%3A773'>'Docklands Sinfonia strikes chord to put East End on culture map</link>,<space/><italics>East London Advertiser</italics>, 16 September 2008</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Economy</heading><paragraph>At one time the offices of<space/><italics><link><target>The Independent</target></link></italics><space/>group of publications were situated in the Docklands. In 2008<space/><link><target>Independent News &amp; Media</target></link><space/>announced that<space/><italics>The Independent</italics><space/>would be moving its offices to the Northcliffe House in<space/><link><target>Kensington</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ponsford">Ponsford, Dominic. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.pressgazette.co.uk/story.asp?sectioncode=1&amp;amp;storycode=42559&amp;amp;c=1'>Sharing with Mail 'will safeguard future of Independent'</link>.&quot;<space/><italics><link><target>Press Gazette</target></link></italics>. 28 November 2008. Retrieved on 6 September 2011. &quot;Under a deal signed today, the Independent titles will share back office functions with the Daily Mail, Mail on Sunday, Metro and Evening Standard at Northcliffe House in Kensington.&quot;</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>In popular culture</heading><paragraph><link><target>Charles Dickens</target></link><space/>makes frequent use of the riverside and docklands in novels such as<space/><italics><link><target>Our Mutual Friend</target></link></italics><space/>and<space/><italics><link><target>Great Expectations</target></link></italics>, and there is a memorable description of the docks, their buildings and people, in<space/><link><target>Joseph Conrad</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>q:Joseph Conrad#On the River Thames</target><part>The Mirror of the Sea</part></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>The Docklands are the location of District 1, the most functional section of<space/><link><target>UK</target><part>Britain</part></link><space/>during the outbreak of Rage Virus and the headquarters for Army Officials in<space/><link><target>Juan Carlos Fresnadillo</target></link>'s 2007 movie<space/><italics><link><target>28 Weeks Later</target></link></italics>. The docklands also appear in<space/><italics><link><target>The Ruby in the Smoke</target></link></italics>, a novel by<space/><link><target>Philip Pullman</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>In the comedy<space/><italics><link><target>Not Going Out</target></link></italics>, the main characters live in a flat located in the Docklands.<space/><link><target>Mickey Mouse</target></link><space/>was involved as part of a fundraising idea to help make money for the Docklands along with the<space/><link><target>Gruffalo</target></link><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template>. . The TV series and book<space/><italics><link><target>Call the Midwife</target></link></italics><space/>is set in the 1950s in the Docklands as well.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Portal</target><arg>London</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Burrells Wharf</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Deal porters</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Destination Docklands</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gentrification</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of locations in the Port of London</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Pool of London</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Port of London Authority</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Rising East</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Safeguarded wharf</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Stepney Historical Trust</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>University of East London</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Kevin d'Arcy</target></link>.<space/><italics>London's 2nd City: Creating Canary Wharf.</italics><space/>Rajah Books ISBN 978-0-9556706-2-6.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Commons category</target><arg>London Docklands</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.docklands24.co.uk/content/docklands/default/default.aspx'>The Docklands newspaper</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.lddc-history.org.uk/beforelddc/index.html'>History of Docklands redevelopment</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.uel.ac.uk/londoneast'>London East Research Institute</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.royaldockstrust.org.uk/index.html'>Royal Docks Trust (London)</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.westsilvertownfoundation.org.uk/index.html'>West Silvertown Online</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.royaldocks.net'>Royal Docks Information</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>sub-regions of London</target></template><template><target>coord</target><arg>51</arg><arg>30</arg><arg>18</arg><arg>N</arg><arg>0</arg><arg>01</arg><arg>05</arg><arg>W</arg><arg>region:GB_type:landmark</arg><arg name="display">title</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:London docks</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:River Thames</target></link><link><target>Category:Geography of Tower Hamlets</target></link><link><target>Category:Geography of Newham</target></link><link><target>Category:Geography of Greenwich</target></link><link><target>Category:Redeveloped ports and waterfronts in London</target></link><link><target>Category:Port of London</target></link><link><target>Category:London sub regions</target></link></paragraph></article>