<article title='Epistle_to_the_Galatians'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the inhabitants of the historic region</arg><arg>Galatians (people)</arg></template><template><target>Books of the New Testament</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Epistle to the Galatians</bold>, often shortened to<space/><bold>Galatians</bold>, is the ninth book of the<space/><link><target>New Testament</target></link>. It is a letter from<space/><link><target>Paul the Apostle</target></link><space/>to a number of<space/><link><target>Early Christian</target></link><space/>communities in Galatia. Scholars have suggested that this is either the Roman province of<space/><link><target>Galatia</target></link><space/>in southern<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Asia Minor</target><part>Anatolia</part></link>, or a large region defined by an ethnic group of Celtic people in central Anatolia.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":0"><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Galatians, Epistle to the</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Betz</arg><arg name="first"><space/>H. D.</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1993</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Yale Anchor Bible Dictionary</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="access-date"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Paul is principally concerned with the controversy surrounding<space/><link><target>Gentile Christians</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Mosaic Law</target></link><space/>during the<space/><link><target>Apostolic Age</target></link>. Paul argues that the Gentile Galatians do not need to adhere to the tenets of the<space/><link><target>Mosaic Law</target></link>, particularly<space/><link><target>circumcision</target></link>, by contextualizing the role of the law in light of the revelation of Christ. Galatians has exerted enormous influence on the history of Christianity, the development of Christian theology, and the study of the<space/><link><target>apostle Paul</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Galatians Through the Centuries</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Riches</arg><arg name="first"><space/>John</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Wiley-Blackwell</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2008</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>West Sussex, UK</arg><arg name="pages"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Composition</heading><preblock><preline>No original of the letter is known to survive. The earliest reasonably complete version available to scholars today, named<space/><link><target>Papyrus 46</target><part>P<xhtml:sup>46</xhtml:sup></part></link>, dates to approximately the year 200 AD, approximately 150 years after the original was presumably drafted.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ehrman, Bart (2005) Misquoting Jesus: The Story Behind Who Changed the Bible and Why, Harper SanFrancisco. ISBN 0-06-073817-0. page 60.</extension><space/>This papyrus is fragmented in a few areas, causing some of the original text carefully preserved over the years to be missing, &quot;however, through careful research relating to paper construction, handwriting development, and the established principles of textual criticism, scholars can be rather certain about where these errors and changes appeared and what the original text probably said.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Metzger, Bruce M.,<space/><italics>A Textual Commentary on the New Testament</italics>, 2nd ed., United Bible Societies, 1994. 1*-16*. ISBN 3-438-06010-8</extension></preline></preblock><paragraph>Some scholars date the original composition to c. 5060 AD.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.earlychristianwritings.com/galatians.html<space/></arg><arg name="title">Early Christian Writings</arg></template></extension><space/>Other scholars agree that Galatians was written between the late 40s and early 50s.<extension extension_name='ref'>M. Coogan, ed.<space/><italics>The New Oxford Annotated Bible</italics><space/>(<link><target>Oxford University Press</target></link>: New York, 2001), 309 NT.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Authenticity</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Authorship of the Pauline Epistles</arg></template>Biblical scholars agree that Galatians is a true example of Paul's writing. The main arguments in favor of the authenticity of Galatians include its style and themes, which are common to the core letters of the Pauline corpus.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">March 2014</arg></template><space/>Moreover, Paul's possible description of the<space/><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>2:1–10</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Gal.2:1–10</arg></template>) gives a different point of view from the description in<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>15:2–29</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Acts 15:2–29</arg></template>, if it is, in fact, describing the Jerusalem Council.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":1"><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>A Critical Introduction to the New Testament</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Holladay</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Carl R.</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Abingdon Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Nashville, TN</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>463-466</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The central dispute about the letter concerns the question of how Gentiles could convert to Christianity, which shows that this letter was written at a very early stage in church history, when the vast majority of Christians were Jewish or Jewish<space/><link><target>proselytes</target></link>, which historians refer to as the<space/><link><target>Jewish Christians</target></link>. Another indicator that the letter is early is that there is no hint in the letter of a developed organization within the Christian community at large. This puts it during the lifetime of Paul himself.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":1"></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Galatia</heading><paragraph>Paul's letter is addressed &quot;to the churches of Galatia&quot; (<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>1:2</arg><arg>9</arg></template>), but the location of these churches is a matter of debate. A minority of scholars have argued that the &quot;Galatia&quot; is an ethnic reference to a<space/><link><target>Celt</target><trail>ic</trail></link><space/>people living in northern<space/><link><target>Asia Minor</target></link>, but most agree that it is a geographical reference to the Roman province in central Asia Minor, which had been settled by immigrant Celts in the 270s BC and retained Gaulish features of culture and language in Paul's day.<space/><link><target>Acts of the Apostles</target></link><space/>records Paul traveling to the &quot;region of Galatia and<space/><link><target>Phrygia</target></link>&quot;, which lies immediately west of Galatia.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Some<template><target>who?</target><arg name="date">October 2013</arg></template><space/>claim the New Testament says that the churches of Galatia (<link><target>Antioch of Pisidia</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Iconium</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Lystra</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Derbe</target></link>) were founded by Paul himself (<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>16:6</arg><arg>9</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians.1:8;4:13;4:19</arg><arg></arg><arg>9</arg></template>). They seem to have been composed mainly of converts from<space/><link><target>paganism</target></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>4:8</arg><arg>9</arg></template>). After Paul's departure, the churches were led astray from Paul's trust/faith-centered teachings by individuals proposing &quot;another gospel&quot; (which centered on salvation through the<space/><link><target>Mosaic law</target></link>, so-called<space/><link><target>Legalism (theology)</target><part>legalism</part></link>), whom Paul saw as preaching a &quot;different gospel&quot; from what Paul had taught (<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>1:6–9</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Galatians 1:1–9</arg></template>). The Galatians appear to have been receptive to the teaching of these newcomers, and the epistle is Paul's response to what he sees as their willingness to turn from his teaching.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The identity of these &quot;opponents&quot; is disputed. However, the majority of modern scholars view them as Jewish Christians, who taught that in order for converts to belong to the<space/><link><target>People of God</target></link>, they must be subject to some or all of the Jewish Law, (i.e.<space/><link><target>Judaizer</target><trail>s</trail></link>). The letter indicates controversy concerning<space/><link><target>Circumcision controversy in early Christianity</target><part>circumcision</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Biblical Sabbath</target><part>Sabbath observance</part></link>, and the<space/><link><target>Biblical law in Christianity</target><part>Mosaic Covenant</part></link>. It would appear, from Paul's response, that they cited the example of<space/><link><target>Abraham</target></link>, who was<space/><link><target>Religious male circumcision</target><part>circumcised</part></link><space/>as a mark of receiving the<space/><link><target>Covenant (biblical)#Abrahamic covenant</target><part>covenant blessings</part></link><space/>(<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Genesis</arg><arg>17</arg><arg>9</arg></template>). They certainly appear to have questioned Paul's authority as an<space/><link><target>Twelve apostles</target><part>apostle</part></link>, perhaps appealing to the greater authority of the<space/><link><target>Early centers of Christianity#Jerusalem</target><part>Jerusalem church</part></link><space/>governed by<space/><link><target>James the Just</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name=":0"></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>North Galatian view</heading><paragraph>The North Galatian view holds that the epistle was written very soon after Paul's second visit to Galatia (<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>18:23</arg><arg>9</arg></template>). In this view, the visit to<space/><link><target>Jerusalem</target></link>, mentioned in<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>2:1–10</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Galatians 2:1–10</arg></template>, is identical with that of Acts 15, which is spoken of as a thing of the past. Consequently, the epistle seems to have been written after the<space/><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target></link>. The similarity between this epistle and the epistle to the Romans has led to the conclusion that they were both written at roughly the same time, during Paul's stay in<space/><link><target>Macedonia (Roman province)</target><part>Macedonia</part></link><space/>in roughly 5657.<extension extension_name='ref'>Craig Evans, The Bible Knowledge Background Commentary (Colorado Springs, CO: Victor 2004), 2: 462. ,<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Acts</arg><arg>20:2–3</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>Acts 20:2–3</arg></template></extension><space/>This third date takes the word &quot;quickly&quot; in Gal. 1:6 literally.<extension extension_name='ref'>Craig Evans, The Bible Knowledge Background Commentary (Colorado Springs, CO: Victor 2004), 2: 462.</extension><space/><link><target>John P. Meier</target></link><space/>suggests that Galatians was &quot;written in the middle or late 50s, only a few years after the Antiochene incident he narrates&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Brown, Raymond E. and Meier, John P. Antioch &amp; Rome: New Testament Cradles of Catholic Christianity (Paulist Press: New York, 1983) 113.</extension><space/>Eminent Biblical scholar<space/><link><target>Helmut Koester</target></link><space/>also subscribes to the &quot;North Galatian Hypothesis&quot;. Koester points out that the cities of Galatia in the north consist of Ankyra, Pessinus, and Gordium (of the Gordian Knot fame of Alexander the Great).<extension extension_name='ref'>Koester, Helmut, Introduction to the New Testament, Volume 2 (Walter de Gruyter &amp; Co.: Berlin, 2000) 114. (</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>South Galatian view</heading><paragraph>The South Galatian view holds that Paul wrote Galatians before or shortly after the First Jerusalem Council, probably on his way to it, and that it was written to churches he had presumably planted during either his time in Tarsus (he would have traveled a short distance, since Tarsus is in Cilicia) after his first visit to Jerusalem as a Christian,<extension extension_name='ref'>Acts<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=Acts%209:30;&amp;amp;version=31;'>9:30</link></extension><space/>or during his first missionary journey, when he traveled throughout southern Galatia. If it was written to the believers in South Galatia, it would likely have been written in 49.<extension extension_name='ref'>Craig Evans,<space/><italics>The Bible Knowledge Background Commentary</italics><space/>(Colorado Springs, CO: Victor 2004), 2: 462.</extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Earliest epistle</heading><paragraph>A third theory<extension extension_name='ref'>Ronald Y.K. Fung,<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Galatians</italics><space/>(Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdman's Press, 1988), 1622. See also<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theologywebsite.com/nt/galatians.shtml'>New Testament Study Helps: Galatians</link><space/>Theology WebSite</extension><space/>is that Galatians 2:110 describes Paul and Barnabas' visit to Jerusalem described in Acts 11:30 and 12:25. This theory holds that the epistle was written before the Council was convened, possibly making it the earliest of Paul's epistles. According to this theory, the revelation mentioned (Gal 2:2) corresponds with the prophecy of Agabus (Acts 11:2728). This view holds that the private speaking about the gospel shared among the Gentiles precludes the Acts 15 visit, but fits perfectly with Acts 11. It further holds that continuing to remember the poor (Gal. 2: 10) fits with the purpose of the Acts 11 visit (but not Acts 15). In addition, the exclusion of any mention of the letter of Acts 15 is seen to indicate that such a letter did not yet exist, since Paul would have been likely to use it against the legalism confronted in Galatians. Finally, this view doubts Paul's confrontation of Peter (Gal. 2:11) would have been necessary after the events described in Acts 15. If this view is correct, the epistle should be dated somewhere around 47, depending on other difficult to date events, such as Paul's conversion.<extension extension_name='ref'>Ronald Y.K. Fung,<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Galatians</italics><space/>(Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdman's Press, 1988), 19.</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Kirsopp Lake</target></link><space/>found this view less likely and wondered why it would be necessary for the Jerusalem Council (Acts 15) to take place at all if the issue were settled in Acts 11:30/12:25, as this view holds.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kirsopp Lake,<space/><italics>The Beginnings of Christianity</italics>, vol 5. ed F. J. Foakes-Jackson and K. Lake (London: 192033), 201.</extension><space/>Defenders of the view do not think it unlikely an issue of such magnitude would need to be discussed more than once.<extension extension_name='ref'>I.H. Marshall,<space/><italics>The Acts of the Apostles</italics><space/>(Tyndale New Testament Commentaries; Grand Rapids, 1980), 205.</extension><space/>Renowned New Testament scholar<space/><link><target>Joseph Lightfoot</target><part>J.B. Lightfoot</part></link><space/>also objected to this view since it &quot;clearly implies that his [Paul's] Apostolic office and labours were well known and recognized before this conference.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fung">Ronald Y.K. Fung,<space/><italics>The Epistle to the Galatians</italics><space/>(Grand Rapids, MI: Eerdman's Press, 1988), 19</extension><space/>Defenders of this view, such as Ronald Fung, disagree with both parts of Lightfoot's statement, insisting a) Paul received his &quot;Apostolic Office&quot; at his conversion (Gal. 1:1517; Ac. 9). Fung holds, then, that Paul's apostolic mission began almost immediately in Damascus (Acts 9:20). While accepting that Paul's apostolic anointing was likely only recognized by the Apostles in Jerusalem during the events described in Gal. 2/Acts 11:30, Fung does not see this as a problem for this theory.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Fung"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Outline</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:PaulT.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>Artist depiction of &quot;Saint Paul Writing His Epistles&quot;, 16th century (Blaffer Foundation Collection,<space/><link><target>Houston</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Texas</target></link>).<space/><link><target>Joseph Barber Lightfoot</target><part>Lightfoot</part></link><space/>notes with respect to verse 6:11 that at this point &quot;the apostle takes the pen from his<space/><link><target>amanuensis</target></link>, and the concluding paragraph is written with his own hand&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Lightfoot continues, &quot;From the time when letters began to be forged in his name (<template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Thessalonians</arg><arg>2:2</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>bibleverse</target><arg>2</arg><arg>Thessalonians</arg><arg>3:17</arg></template>) it seems to have been his practice to close with a few words in his own handwriting, as a precaution against such forgeries... In the present case he writes a whole paragraph, summing up the main lessons of the epistle in terse, eager, disjointed sentences. He writes it, too, in large, bold characters (Gr.<space/><italics>pelikois grammasin</italics>), that his handwriting may reflect the energy and determination of his soul.&quot;<space/><link><target>Joseph Barber Lightfoot</target></link>,<space/><italics>Commentary on the Epistle to the Galatians</italics>.</extension></part><trail>The</trail></link><space/>citation here is based on the content of the gospel. Alternative outlines have been introduced based on the rhetorical form of the letter.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Galatians, Epistle to the</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Betz</arg><arg name="first"><space/>H. D.</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1993</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Yale Anchor Bible Dictionary</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="access-date"><space/></arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Salutation (1:15)</listitem><listitem>No other<space/><link><target>gospel</target></link>: Paul expresses displeasure that the community has turned from the gospel (1:610)</listitem><listitem>The past of Paul, including his life in Judaism (1:13-14), his &quot;apocalypse&quot; from God, often understood as the<space/><link><target>Conversion of Paul</target></link><space/>(1:15-16), and his early ministry (1:1724)</listitem><listitem>a<space/><link><target>Right hand of Christian fellowship</target><part>meeting</part></link><space/>with the &quot;pillar apostles&quot; in Jerusalem, possibly the<space/><link><target>Council of Jerusalem</target></link><space/>reported in Acts 15 (2:110)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Incident at Antioch</target><part>The Paul/Cephas Incident at Antioch</part></link>, where Cephas backed down from his previous table fellowship with Gentiles (2:1114)</listitem><listitem>Paul's speech expressing that Jews, like Gentiles, are<space/><link><target>Faith in Christianity</target><part>declared righteous by faith</part></link><space/>(2:1521)</listitem><listitem>A Consideration of Law or Faith (3:114)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Law and Gospel</target><part>Law and Promise</part></link><space/>(3:1520)</listitem><listitem>Slaves and Sons (3:214:7)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Sons of God</target></link><space/>(3:26)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>Concern for the Galatians (4:820)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Allegorical Interpretation</target></link><space/>of<space/><link><target>Hagar (Bible)</target><part>Hagar and Sarah</part></link><space/>(4:215:1)</listitem><listitem><link><target>Christian liberty</target><part>Christian Freedom</part></link><space/>(5:115)<list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Great Commandment#Love thy neighbour as thyself</target><part>Love thy neighbour</part></link><space/>(5:14)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fruit of the Spirit</target></link><space/>(5:1626)</listitem><listitem><link><target>The Law of Christ</target></link><space/>(6:110)</listitem><listitem>Final Warning and Benediction (6:1118)</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Contents</heading><paragraph><template><target>See also</target><arg>Biblical law in Christianity</arg></template>This epistle addresses the question of whether the Gentiles in Galatia were obligated to follow Mosaic Law to be part of the Christ community. After an introductory address (<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>1:1–10</arg><arg>9</arg></template>), the apostle discusses the subjects which had occasioned the epistle.</paragraph><paragraph>In the first two chapters, Paul discusses his life before Christ and his early ministry, including interactions with other apostles in Jerusalem. This is the most extended discussion of Paul's past that we find in the Pauline letters (cf.<space/><link><target>Epistle to the Philippians</target><part>Philippians</part></link><space/>3:1-7).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Paul</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Betz</arg><arg name="first"><space/>H. D.</arg><arg name="date"><space/>1993</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Yale Anchor Bible Dictionary</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg><arg name="pmid"><space/></arg><arg name="access-date"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Some have read this autobiographical narrative as Paul's defense of his apostolic authority (<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>1:11–19</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>1:11–19</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>2:1–14</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>2:1–14</arg></template>).<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>A Critical Introduction to the New Testament</arg><arg name="last"><space/>Holladay</arg><arg name="first"><space/>Carl R.</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Abingdon Press</arg><arg name="year"><space/>2005</arg><arg name="isbn"><space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Nashville, TN</arg><arg name="pages"><space/>466-467</arg></template></extension><space/>Others, however, see Paul's telling of the narrative as making an argument to the Galatians about the nature of the gospel and the Galatians' own situation.<extension extension_name='ref'>John M. G. Barclay, Pauls Story: Theology as Testimony, in<space/><italics>Narrative Dynamics in Paul</italics><space/>(Louisville London: Westminster John Knox, 2002), 13356.</extension><space/></paragraph><paragraph>Chapter 3 exhorts the Galatian believers to stand fast in the faith as it is in Jesus. Paul engages in an exegetical argument, drawing upon the figure of<space/><link><target>Abraham</target></link><space/>and the priority of his faith to the covenant of circumcision. Paul explains that the law was introduced as a temporary measure, one that is no longer efficacious now that the seed of Abraham, Christ, has come. Chapter 4 then concludes with a summary of the topics discussed and with the benediction, followed by<space/><template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>5:1–6:10</arg><arg>9</arg><arg>5:1–6:10</arg></template><space/>teaching about the right use of their Christian freedom.</paragraph><paragraph>In the conclusion of the epistle (<template><target>bibleref</target><arg>Galatians</arg><arg>6:11</arg><arg>9</arg></template>), Paul wrote, &quot;Ye see how large a letter I have written with mine own hand.&quot; Regarding this conclusion,<space/><link><target>Joseph Barber Lightfoot</target><part>Lightfoot</part></link>, in his Commentary on the epistle, says:</paragraph><paragraph><extension extension_name='blockquote'>&quot;At this point the apostle takes the pen from his<space/><link><target>amanuensis</target></link>, and the concluding paragraph is written with his own hand. From the time when letters began to be forged in his name (<template><target>bibleref2</target><arg>2Thessalonians</arg><arg>2:2</arg><arg>9</arg></template>;<space/><template><target>bibleref</target><arg>2Thessalonians</arg><arg>3:17</arg><arg>9</arg></template>) it seems to have been his practice to close with a few words in his own handwriting, as a precaution against such forgeries... In the present case he writes a whole paragraph, summing up the main lessons of the epistle in terse, eager, disjointed sentences. He writes it, too, in large, bold characters (Gr.<space/><italics>pelikois grammasin</italics>), that his hand-writing may reflect the energy and determination of his soul.&quot;</extension><template><target>Lightfoot, J.B. 1865. St. Paul's Epistle to the Galatians. Cambridge: Macmillan. pp. 211-212</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>Alternatively, some commentators have postulated that Paul's<space/><link><target>thorn in the flesh</target></link><space/>was poor eyesight, which caused him to write in characteristically large letters.<extension extension_name='ref'>Galatians,<space/><italics>Tyndale New Testament Commentary</italics>, revised edition, page 233.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Galatians also contains a catalogue of<space/><link><target>vice</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>virtue</target><trail>s</trail></link>, a popular formulation of ancient<space/><link><target>Christian ethics</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Probably the most famous single statement made in the Epistle, by Paul, is in chapter 3, verse 28: &quot;There is neither Jew nor Gentile, neither slave nor free, nor is there male and female, for you are all one in Christ Jesus.&quot; The debate surrounding that verse is legend and the two schools of thought are (1) this only applies to the spiritual standing of people in the eyes of God. it does not implicate social distinctions and gender roles on earth; and (2) this is not just about our spiritual standing but is also very much about how we relate to each other and treat each other in the here and now. Position (1) emphasises the immediate context of the verse and notes that it is embedded in a discussion about justification: our relationship with God. Position (2) reminds its critics that the &quot;whole letter context&quot; is very much about how people got on in the here and now together, and in fact the discussion about justification came out of an actual example of people treating other people differently (2:11ff).<extension extension_name='ref'>For an overview of the two theories see Jim Reiher, Galatians 3:28: liberating for women, or of limited application? Expository Times. (123.6) pp. 272-277. March 2012. Reiher comes down on the side of position (2).</extension><space/></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Paul the Apostle and Judaism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Prayer of St. John Gabriel Perboyre to Jesus</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Textual variants in the New Testament#Epistle to the Galatians</target><part>Textual variants in the Epistle to the Galatians</part></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>EBD</target><arg>Galatians, Epistle to the</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target><arg>Galatians (Bible)</arg><arg>Galatians</arg></template>Online translations of the Epistle to Galatians:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.biblegateway.com'>''Bible Gateway 35 languages/50 versions'' at GospelCom.net</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://unbound.biola.edu'>''Unbound Bible 100+ languages/versions'' at Biola University</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://bible.daresler.net/Galatians-1/'>Galatians King James Bible</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gospelhall.org/bible/bible.php?passage=Galatians+1'>''Online Bible'' at GospelHall.org</link></listitem></list><paragraph>Related articles:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.vts.edu/ftpimages/95/download/download_group10628_id314970.pdf'>A Brief Introduction to Galatians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.galatians-paul-the-torah-law-legalism.info'>Galatians, Paul, The Torah-Law &amp; Legalism</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourthcentury.com/index.php/john-chrysostom-on-galatians'>John Chrysostom's Commentary on Galatians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.eliyah.com/galatians.html'>An alternative commentary on Galatians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.galloturca.com/galatians.htm'>A Secular Site on Galatians</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://store.netivyah.org/samples/galatians.pdf'>Jewish messianic Commentary on Galatians (Jerusalem)</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>S-start</target></template><template><target>S-hou</target><arg>[[Pauline epistles|Pauline]] [[Epistles|Epistle]]</arg><arg></arg><arg></arg><arg></arg></template><template><target>S-bef</target><arg name="before">[[Second Epistle to the Corinthians|Second Corinthians]]</arg></template><template><target>S-ttl</target><arg name="title"><small>[[New Testament]]</small><br>[[Books of the Bible]]</arg></template><template><target>S-aft</target><arg name="after">[[Epistle to the Ephesians|Ephesians]]</arg></template><template><target>S-end</target></template><template><target>Epistle to the Galatians</target></template><template><target>Books of the Bible</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Epistle to the Galatians</target></template><link><target>Category:Canonical epistles</target><part>Galatians</part></link><link><target>Category:Galatia</target></link><link><target>Category:New Testament books</target><part>Galatians</part></link><link><target>Category:Pauline-related books</target></link><link><target>Category:Epistle to the Galatians</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>