<article title='Battle_of_%C5%9Awiecino'><paragraph><template><target>no footnotes</target><arg name="date">September 2011</arg></template><template><target>Infobox military conflict</target><arg name="conflict">Battle of Świecino
</arg><arg name="image">
</arg><arg name="caption">
</arg><arg name="partof">the [[Thirteen Years' War (1454–66)|Thirteen Years' War]]
</arg><arg name="date">September 17, 1462
</arg><arg name="place">Near [[Krokowa]], [[Poland]]
</arg><arg name="result">Decisive Polish Victory
</arg><arg name="combatant1">[[Image:Den tyske ordens skjold.svg|20px]] [[Teutonic Order]]
</arg><arg name="combatant2">[[Poland|Kingdom of Poland]]
</arg><arg name="commander1">[[Image:Den tyske ordens skjold.svg|20px]] [[Fritz Raweneck]]†<br>[[Image:Den tyske ordens skjold.svg|20px]] [[Kaspar Nostyc]]
</arg><arg name="commander2">[[Piotr Dunin]]
</arg><arg name="strength1">2,700
</arg><arg name="strength2">2,000
</arg><arg name="casualties1">Over 1,000 killed<space/><br><space/>50 captured
</arg><arg name="casualties2">~250
</arg></template><template><target>Campaignbox Thirteen Years' War</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>Battle of wiecino</bold><space/>(named for the village of<space/><link><target>wiecino</target></link>, near arnowiec Lake, northern Poland) also called the<space/><bold>Battle of<space/><link><target>arnowiec</target></link></bold><space/>or in German<space/><bold>Battle of Schwetz</bold>, took place on September 17, 1462 during the<space/><link><target>Thirteen Years' War (145466)</target><part>Thirteen Years' War</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Kingdom of Poland (13851569)</target><part>Poles</part></link><space/>commanded by<space/><link><target>Piotr Dunin</target></link>, consisting of some 2000 mercenares and Poles, decisively defeated the 2700 man army of the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Knights</target></link><space/>commanded by<space/><link><target>Fritz Raweneck</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kaspar Nostyc</target></link>. Auxiliary forces sent by duke<space/><link><target>Eric II of Pomerania</target></link>, an ally of the Polish king, did not enter the battle.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Polish forces</heading><paragraph>The Polish forces consisted mostly of the mercenaries hired by the Polish king,<space/><link><target>Casimir IV of Poland</target><part>Casimir IV the Jagiellon</part></link><space/>and the city of Danzig (<link><target>Gdask</target></link>). This army included 1000 cavalry, of which 112 were heavy cavalry, and another 1000 of infantry. 1000 cavalry and 400 infantry were mercenaries hired by Polish king, while the rest were units from Danzig.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Teutonic forces</heading><paragraph>Most of the<space/><link><target>Teutonic Knights</target><part>Teutonic army</part></link>, under the command of Fritz Raweneck and Kaspar Nostyc, were troops gathered from the nearby castles Mewe (<link><target>Gniew</target></link>), Stargard (<link><target>Starogard Gdaski</target></link>),<space/><link><target>Nowe</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Skarszewy</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Kiszewy</target></link>. This army totalled 1000 cavalry and 400 infantry. Raweneck also had the supply chain (<link><target>tabor (formation)</target><part>tabors</part></link>), cannons and up to 1300 auxiliary infantry of Pomeranian peasants, used mainly for fortification works.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Battle</heading><paragraph>The battle started in the evening. Adopting a relatively new tactic, Polish units built a fortified camp on the Hussite model consisting of wagons linked by a chain surrounded by a deep ditch (<link><target>Tabor (formation)</target><part>tabor</part></link>). The units of Raveneck and his subordinate, Kaspar Nostyc (commander from Conitz (<link><target>Chojnice</target></link>) also created a tabor. Piotr Dunin decided not to wait for the enemy and attacked first, setting infantry with crossbows on the left, defended by cavalry between the tabor and the coast of the nearby lake of Rogonica. Raveneck placed cavalry in front of his tabor, and infantry behind it, without any strategic plan. The first phase of the battle was started by a charge of Polish heavy cavalry under<space/><link><target>Pawe Jasieski</target></link>. Fierce fighting continued for three hours and ended without a clear winner. After a short pause at midday, Teutonic units were able to push the Poles back; however, they found themselves under very heavy fire from crossbows of the Polish infantry, which caused huge losses and a withdrawal. During this fight Raveneck was wounded. He stopped his soldiers and tried to attack again, but this charge ended with a total defeat - Raveneck died and the rest of the cavalry surrendered or escaped. The Teutonic infantry tried to defend themselves at the tabor but its resistance was broken by a quick attack of Polish cavalry.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Casualties</heading><paragraph>The Teutonic Order's army lost around 1000 soldiers, including some 300 cavalrymen. Fifty soldiers were captured. The Teutonic commander was also killed in battle and was buried in the arnowiec chapter church.</paragraph><paragraph>The Poles lost just 100 soldiers, although 150 later died from their wounds. Among the dead on the Polish side was<space/><link><target>Maciej Hagen</target></link><space/>from Gdask. Piotr Dunin was wounded twice.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Aftermath</heading><paragraph>The direct result of the battle of wiecino was that the city of Danzig and Pomerania were freed from the danger of an attack by the Teutonic Order. As a result the royal and municipal armed forces could be used elsewhere in the war, mainly to protect the Vistula waterway and to capture the Teutonic held strongholds. This way that Teutonic forces in Prussia on the right bank of Vistula were cut off from supplies from Western Europe.</paragraph><paragraph>The psychological significance of the battle was that this was the first open field battle won by the royal forces, so it increased the morale of the Polish forces and lowered the morale of the Teutonic Knights. Many military historians say that the battle of wiecino was the turning point of the<space/><link><target>Thirteen Years' War (145466)</target><part>Thirteen Years' War</part></link>, leading to the final Polish victory in 1466.</paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.pilot.pl/index.php3?Z_CITY_NAME=%B6wiecino'>wiecino near arnowiec Lake</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.zamek.malbork.com.pl/index.php?m=02&amp;amp;p=11'>Malbork Castle - Battle of wiecino</link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Janusz Sikorski,<space/><italics>Zarys historii wojskowoci powszechnej do koca wieku XIX. [Universal history of military operations till 1900]</italics>, Wojskowy Instytut Historyczny, Wydawnictwo Ministerstwa Obrony Narodowej, Warszawa 1972. - description of the battle of wiecino: pp.&amp;nbsp;287288, map of the battle of wiecino: p.&amp;nbsp;288</listitem><listitem>Janusz Sikorski (ed.), Wiesaw Majewski, Tadeusz Marian Nowak, Jerzy Teodorczyk,<space/><italics>Polskie tradycje wojskowe. Tradycje walk obronnych z najazdami Niemcw, Krzyakw, Szwedw, Turkw i Tatarw X-XVII w. [Polish military traditions. Tradition of defence struggles with the invasions of the Germans, Teutonic Knights, Swedes, Turks and Tartars in 10th-17th centuries]</italics>. Wojskowy Instytut Historyczny, Wydawnictwo Ministerstwa Obrony Narodowej, Warszawa 1990. - description of the battle of wiecino: p.&amp;nbsp;127, map of the battle of wiecino: p.&amp;nbsp;114</listitem><listitem>Stanisaw Herbst,<space/><italics>Wojna Trzynastoletnia - O bitwie pod wiecinem. [The Thirteen Years' War - About the Battle of wiecino]</italics>, Przegld Historyczno-Wojskowy, vol. 7: 1934/1935, issue 2, pp.&amp;nbsp;309311, reprinted in: Stanisaw Herbst,<space/><italics>Potrzeba historii czyli o polskim stylu ycia. Wybr pism.</italics><space/>Pastwowy Instytut Wydawniczy, Warszawa 1978</listitem><listitem>K. Grski,<space/><italics>Pomorze w dobie wojny trzynastoletniej. [Pomerania during the Thirteen Years' War]</italics>, Pozna 1932 - description and 3 maps of the battle of wiecino: p.&amp;nbsp;308</listitem><listitem>Marian Biskup,<space/><italics>Druga faza wojny trzynastoletniej (1462-1466). [Second phase of the Thirteen Years' War 1462-1466]</italics>, in: Gerard Labuda (ed.),<space/><italics>Historia Pomorza. [History of Pomerania]</italics>, Wydawnictwo Poznaskie, Pozna 1972, - description of the battle of wiecino: p.&amp;nbsp;738</listitem><listitem><italics>wiecino</italics>, in: Ra Ostrowska, Izabela Trojanowska,<space/><italics>Bedeker Kaszubski</italics>, Wydawcnictwo Morskie, Gdask 1974</listitem><listitem><italics>wiecino</italics>, in: Tadeusz Bolduan,<space/><italics>Nowy bedeker kaszubski</italics>, Gdask 1997</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>coord</target><arg>54.787222</arg><arg>18.087778</arg><arg name="format">dms</arg><arg name="display">title</arg><arg>type:event</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Battle Of Swiecino</target></template><link><target>Category:1462 in Europe</target></link><link><target>Category:Battles of the Thirteen Years' War (145466)</target><part>Swiecino</part></link><link><target>Category:Conflicts in 1462</target></link></paragraph></article>