<article title='Electromagnetic_field'><paragraph><template><target>for</target><arg>the British hacker convention</arg><arg>Electromagnetic Field (festival)</arg></template><template><target>Electromagnetism</target><arg name="cTopic">Electrodynamics</arg></template>An<space/><bold>electromagnetic field</bold><space/>(also<space/><bold>EMF</bold><space/>or<space/><bold>EM field</bold>) is a physical<space/><link><target>field (physics)</target><part>field</part></link><space/>produced by<space/><link><target>electric charge</target><part>electrically charged objects</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Richard Feynman<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Feynman Lectures on Physics Vol II<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Addison Wesley Longman<space/></arg><arg name="year">1970<space/></arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-201-02115-8<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.feynmanlectures.caltech.edu/II_01.html#Ch1-S2<space/></arg><arg name="quote">"A “field” is any physical quantity which takes on different values at different points in space."</arg></template></extension><space/>It affects the behavior of charged objects in the vicinity of the field. The electromagnetic field extends indefinitely throughout space and describes the<space/><link><target>electromagnetism</target><part>electromagnetic interaction</part></link>. It is one of the four<space/><link><target>fundamental force</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>of nature (the others are<space/><link><target>gravitation</target></link>,<space/><link><target>weak interaction</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>strong interaction</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>The field can be viewed as the combination of an<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>and a<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target></link>. The electric field is produced by stationary charges, and the magnetic field by moving charges (currents); these two are often described as the sources of the field. The way in which charges and currents interact with the electromagnetic field is described by<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lorentz force law</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>From a<space/><link><target>Classical physics</target><part>classical</part></link><space/>perspective in the<space/><link><target>history of electromagnetism</target></link>, the electromagnetic field can be regarded as a smooth, continuous field, propagated in a wavelike manner; whereas from the perspective of<space/><link><target>quantum field theory</target></link>, the field is seen as quantized, being composed of individual<space/><link><target>Subatomic particle</target><part>particle</part><trail>s</trail></link>.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Structure</heading><paragraph>The electromagnetic field may be viewed in two distinct ways: a continuous structure or a discrete structure.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Continuous structure</heading><paragraph>Classically, electric and magnetic fields are thought of as being produced by smooth motions of charged objects. For example, oscillating charges produce electric and magnetic fields that may be viewed in a 'smooth', continuous, wavelike fashion. In this case, energy is viewed as being transferred continuously through the electromagnetic field between any two locations. For instance, the metal atoms in a<space/><link><target>radio</target></link><space/><link><target>transmitter</target></link><space/>appear to transfer energy continuously. This view is useful to a certain extent (radiation of low frequency), but problems are found at high frequencies (see<space/><link><target>ultraviolet catastrophe</target></link>).<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Discrete structure</heading><paragraph>The electromagnetic field may be thought of in a more 'coarse' way. Experiments reveal that in some circumstances electromagnetic energy transfer is better described as being carried in the form of packets called<space/><link><target>quantum</target><part>quanta</part></link><space/>(in this case,<space/><link><target>photon</target><trail>s</trail></link>) with a fixed frequency. Planck's relation links the energy<space/><italics>E</italics><space/>of a photon to its frequency through the equation:<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Spencer, James N.</arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg><arg name="title">Chemistry: Structure and Dynamics</arg><arg name="publisher">John Wiley & Sons</arg><arg name="year">2010</arg><arg name="isbn">9780470587119</arg><arg name="page">78</arg><arg name="url">http://books.google.com/books?id</arg></template></extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>E= \, h \, \nu</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><italics>h</italics><space/>is<space/><link><target>Planck's constant</target></link>, and is the frequency of the photon . Although modern quantum optics tells us that there also is a semi-classical explanation of the<space/><link><target>photoelectric effect</target></link>the emission of electrons from metallic surfaces subjected to<space/><link><target>electromagnetic radiation</target></link>the photon was historically (although not strictly necessarily) used to explain certain observations. It is found that increasing the intensity of the incident radiation (so long as one remains in the linear regime) increases only the number of electrons ejected, and has almost no effect on the energy distribution of their ejection. Only the frequency of the radiation is relevant to the energy of the ejected electrons.</paragraph><paragraph>This<space/><link><target>quantum</target></link><space/>picture of the electromagnetic field (which treats it as analogous to<space/><link><target>harmonic oscillators</target></link>) has proved very successful, giving rise to<space/><link><target>quantum electrodynamics</target></link>, a<space/><link><target>quantum field theory</target></link><space/>describing the interaction of electromagnetic radiation with charged matter. It also gives rise to<space/><link><target>quantum optics</target></link>, which is different from quantum electrodynamics in that the matter itself is modelled using<space/><link><target>quantum mechanics</target></link><space/>rather than<space/><link><target>quantum field theory</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Dynamics</heading><paragraph>In the past, electrically charged objects were thought to produce two different, unrelated types of field associated with their charge property. An<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>is produced when the charge is stationary with respect to an observer measuring the properties of the charge, and a<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target></link><space/>as well as an electric field is produced when the charge moves, creating an electric current with respect to this observer. Over time, it was realized that the electric and magnetic fields are better thought of as two parts of a greater whole the electromagnetic field. Recall that until 1820 (when the Danish physicist H.C. rsted discovered the effect of electricity through a wire on a compass needle), electricity and magnetism had been viewed as unrelated phenomena<space/><template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="reason">This section was clearly written by someone with no historical knowledge and by this edit only a very basic fix has been performed</arg><arg name="date">October 2015</arg></template>. In 1831, Michael Faraday, one of the great thinkers of his time, made the seminal observation that time-varying magnetic fields could induce electric currents and then, in 1864, James Clerk Maxwell published his famous paper on a dynamical theory of the electromagnetic field.<extension extension_name='ref'>Maxwell 1864 5, page 499; also David J. Griffiths (1999), Introduction to electrodynamics, third Edition, ed. Prentice Hall, pp. 559-562&quot;(as quoted in Gabriela, 2009)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Once this electromagnetic field has been produced from a given charge distribution, other charged objects in this field will experience a force in a similar way that planets experience a force in the gravitational field of the sun. If these other charges and currents are comparable in size to the sources producing the above electromagnetic field, then a new net electromagnetic field will be produced. Thus, the electromagnetic field may be viewed as a dynamic entity that causes other charges and currents to move, and which is also affected by them. These interactions are described by<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Lorentz Force Law</target><part>Lorentz force law</part></link>. This discussion ignores the<space/><link><target>radiation reaction force</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Feedback loop</heading><paragraph>The behavior of the electromagnetic field can be divided into four different parts of a loop:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>the electric and magnetic fields are generated by electric charges,</listitem><listitem>the electric and magnetic fields interact with each other,</listitem><listitem>the electric and magnetic fields produce forces on electric charges,</listitem><listitem>the electric charges move in space.</listitem></list><paragraph>A common misunderstanding is that (a) the quanta of the fields act in the same manner as (b) the charged particles that generate the fields. In our everyday world, charged<space/><bold>particles</bold>, such as electrons, move slowly through matter with a<space/><link><target>drift velocity</target></link><space/>of a fraction of a centimeter (or inch) per second, but<space/><bold>fields</bold><space/>propagate at the<space/><link><target>speed of light</target></link><space/>- approximately 300 thousand kilometers (or 186 thousand miles) a second. The mundane speed difference between charged particles and field quanta is on the order of one to a million, more or less.<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link><space/>relate (a) the presence and movement of charged particles with (b) the generation of fields. Those fields can then affect the force on, and can then move other slowly moving charged particles. Charged particles can move at relativistic speeds nearing field propagation speeds, but, as<space/><link><target>Einstein</target></link><space/>showed<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">May 2011</arg></template>, this requires enormous field energies, which are not present in our everyday experiences with electricity, magnetism, matter, and time and space.</paragraph><paragraph>The feedback loop can be summarized in a list, including phenomena belonging to each part of the loop:<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">August 2015</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>charged particles generate electric and magnetic fields</listitem><listitem>the fields interact with each other<list type='bullet'><listitem>changing electric field acts like a current, generating 'vortex' of magnetic field</listitem><listitem><link><target>Faraday's law of induction</target><part>Faraday induction</part></link>: changing magnetic field induces (negative) vortex of electric field</listitem><listitem><link><target>Lenz's law</target></link>: negative feedback loop between electric and magnetic fields</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>fields act upon particles<list type='bullet'><listitem>Lorentz force: force due to electromagnetic field<list type='bullet'><listitem>electric force: same direction as electric field</listitem><listitem>magnetic force: perpendicular both to magnetic field and to velocity of charge</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem><listitem>particles move<list type='bullet'><listitem>current is movement of particles</listitem></list></listitem><listitem>particles generate more electric and magnetic fields; cycle repeats</listitem></list><heading level='2'>Mathematical description</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Mathematical descriptions of the electromagnetic field</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>There are different mathematical ways of representing the electromagnetic field. The first one views the electric and magnetic fields as three-dimensional<space/><link><target>vector field</target><trail>s</trail></link>. These vector fields each have a value defined at every point of space and time and are thus often regarded as functions of the space and time coordinates. As such, they are often written as<space/><bold>E</bold>(x, y, z, t) (<link><target>electric field</target></link>) and<space/><bold>B</bold>(x, y, z, t) (<link><target>magnetic field</target></link>).</paragraph><paragraph>If only the<space/><link><target>electric field</target></link><space/>(<bold>E</bold>) is non-zero, and is constant in time, the field is said to be an<space/><link><target>electrostatic field</target></link>. Similarly, if only the<space/><link><target>magnetic field</target></link><space/>(<bold>B</bold>) is non-zero and is constant in time, the field is said to be a<space/><link><target>magnetostatic field</target></link>. However, if either the electric or magnetic field has a time-dependence, then both fields must be considered together as a coupled electromagnetic field using<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Electromagnetic Fields (2nd Edition), Roald K. Wangsness, Wiley, 1986. ISBN 0-471-81186-6 (intermediate level textbook)</extension></paragraph><paragraph>With the advent of<space/><link><target>special relativity</target></link>, physical laws became susceptible to the formalism of<space/><link><target>tensor</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Maxwell's equations can be written in tensor form, generally viewed by physicists as a more elegant means of expressing physical laws.</paragraph><paragraph>The behaviour of electric and magnetic fields, whether in cases of electrostatics, magnetostatics, or<space/><link><target>electrodynamics</target></link><space/>(electromagnetic fields), is governed by Maxwell's equations. In the vector field formalism, these are:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \cdot \mathbf{E} = \frac{\rho}{\varepsilon_0}</extension><space/>(<link><target>Gauss's law</target></link>)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \cdot \mathbf{B} = 0</extension><space/>(<link><target>Gauss's law for magnetism</target></link>)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \mathbf{E} = -\frac {\partial \mathbf{B}}{\partial t}</extension><space/>(<link><target>Faraday's law of induction#The Maxwell-Faraday equation</target><part>Faraday's law</part></link>)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\nabla \times \mathbf{B} = \mu_0 \mathbf{J} + \mu_0\varepsilon_0 \frac{\partial \mathbf{E}}{\partial t}</extension><space/>(<link><target>Ampre's circuital law#Corrected Ampre's circuital law: the Ampre-Maxwell equation</target><part>Ampre-Maxwell law</part></link>)</listitem></list><paragraph>where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\rho</extension><space/>is the charge density, which can (and often does) depend on time and position,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\epsilon_0</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>permittivity</target></link><space/>of free space,<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\mu_0</extension><space/>is the<space/><link><target>Permeability (electromagnetism)</target><part>permeability</part></link><space/>of free space, and<space/><bold>J</bold><space/>is the current density vector, also a function of time and position. The units used above are the standard SI units. Inside a linear material, Maxwell's equations change by switching the permeability and permittivity of free space with the permeability and permittivity of the linear material in question. Inside other materials which possess more complex responses to electromagnetic fields, these terms are often represented by complex numbers, or tensors.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Lorentz force law</target></link><space/>governs the interaction of the electromagnetic field with charged matter.</paragraph><paragraph>When a field travels across to different media, the properties of the field change according to the various boundary conditions. These equations are derived from Maxwell's equations.The tangential components of the electric and magnetic fields as they relate on the boundary of two media are as follows:<extension extension_name='ref'>Schaum's outline of theory and problems of electromagnetics(2nd Edition), Joseph A. Edminister, McGraw-Hill, 1995. ISBN 0070212341(Examples and Problem Practice)</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{E}_{1} = \mathbf{E}_{2}<space/></extension></listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{H}_{1} = \mathbf{H}_{2}<space/></extension><space/>(current-free)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{D}_{1} = \mathbf{D}_{2}<space/></extension><space/>(charge-free)</listitem></list><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\mathbf{B}_{1} = \mathbf{B}_{2}<space/></extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The angle of refraction of an electric field between media is related to the permittivity<space/><extension extension_name='math'>(\varepsilon)</extension><space/>of each medium:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\frac{{\tan\theta_1}}{{\tan\theta_2}} = \frac{{\varepsilon_{r2}}}{{\varepsilon_{r1}}}</extension></listitem></list><paragraph>The angle of refraction of a magnetic field between media is related to the permeability<space/><extension extension_name='math'>(\mu)</extension><space/>of each medium:</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'>\frac{{\tan\theta_1}}{{\tan\theta_2}} = \frac{{\mu_{r2}}}{{\mu_{r1}}}</extension></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Properties of the field</heading><heading level='3'>Reciprocal behavior of electric and magnetic fields</heading><paragraph>The two Maxwell equations, Faraday's Law and the Ampre-Maxwell Law, illustrate a very practical feature of the electromagnetic field. Faraday's Law may be stated roughly as 'a changing magnetic field creates an electric field'. This is the principle behind the<space/><link><target>electric generator</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Ampere's Law roughly states that 'a changing electric field creates a magnetic field'. Thus, this law can be applied to generate a magnetic field and run an<space/><link><target>electric motor</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Light as an electromagnetic disturbance</heading><paragraph><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link><space/>take the form of an<space/><link><target>electromagnetic wave</target></link><space/>in a volume of space not containing charges or currents (<link><target>free space</target></link>) that is, where<space/><extension extension_name='math'>\rho</extension><space/>and<space/><bold>J</bold><space/>are zero. Under these conditions, the electric and magnetic fields satisfy the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic wave equation</target></link>:<extension extension_name='ref'>Field and Wave Electromagnetics (2nd Edition), David K. Cheng, Prentice Hall, 1989. ISBN 978-0-201-12819-2 (Intermediate level textbook)</extension></paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\left( \nabla^2 - { 1 \over {c}^2 } {\partial^2 \over \partial t^2} \right) \mathbf{E} \ \ = \ \ 0</extension></listitem><listitem><extension extension_name='math'><space/>\left( \nabla^2 - { 1 \over {c}^2 } {\partial^2 \over \partial t^2} \right) \mathbf{B} \ \ = \ \ 0</extension></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>James Clerk Maxwell</target></link><space/>was the first to obtain this relationship by his completion of<space/><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link><space/>with the addition of a<space/><link><target>displacement current</target></link><space/>term to<space/><link><target>Ampere's Circuital law</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Relation to and comparison with other physical fields</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Fundamental forces</arg></template><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">June 2008</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Being one of the four fundamental forces of nature, it is useful to compare the electromagnetic field with the<space/><link><target>gravitational</target></link>,<space/><link><target>strong interaction</target><part>strong</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>weak interaction</target><part>weak</part></link><space/>fields. The word 'force' is sometimes replaced by 'interaction' because modern<space/><link><target>particle physics</target></link><space/>models electromagnetism as an exchange of particles known as<space/><link><target>gauge boson</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Electromagnetic and gravitational fields</heading><paragraph>Sources of electromagnetic fields consist of two types of<space/><link><target>Charge (physics)</target><part>charge</part></link><space/>positive and negative. This contrasts with the sources of the gravitational field, which are masses. Masses are sometimes described as<space/><italics>gravitational charges</italics>, the important feature of them being that there are only positive masses and no<space/><link><target>negative mass</target><trail>es</trail></link>. Further, gravity differs from electromagnetism in that positive masses attract other positive masses whereas same charges in electromagnetism repel each other.</paragraph><paragraph>The relative<space/><link><target>field strength</target><part>strengths</part></link><space/>and ranges of the four interactions and other information are tabulated below:</paragraph><table class="wikitable"><tablerow><tablehead>Theory</tablehead><tablehead>Interaction</tablehead><tablehead>mediator</tablehead><tablehead>Relative Magnitude</tablehead><tablehead>Behavior</tablehead><tablehead>Range</tablehead></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Chromodynamics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Strong interaction</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>gluon</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>38</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>1</tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>15</xhtml:sup><space/>m</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Electrodynamics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Electromagnetic interaction</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>photon</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>36</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>1/<italics>r</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>infinite</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Flavordynamics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Weak interaction</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>W and Z bosons</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>25</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>1/<italics>r</italics><xhtml:sup>5</xhtml:sup><space/>to 1/<italics>r</italics><xhtml:sup>7</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>16</xhtml:sup><space/>m</tablecell></tablerow><tablerow><tablecell><link><target>Geometrodynamics</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>Gravitation</target></link></tablecell><tablecell><link><target>graviton</target></link></tablecell><tablecell>10<xhtml:sup>0</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>1/<italics>r</italics><xhtml:sup>2</xhtml:sup></tablecell><tablecell>infinite</tablecell></tablerow></table><heading level='2'>Applications</heading><paragraph><template><target>Expand section</target><arg name="date">February 2012</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Static E and M fields and static EM fields</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>electrostatics</arg><arg>magnetostatics</arg><arg>magnetism</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>When an EM field (see<space/><link><target>electromagnetic tensor</target></link>) is not varying in time, it may be seen as a purely electrical field or a purely magnetic field, or a mixture of both. However the general case of a static EM field with both electric and magnetic components present, is the case that appears to most observers. Observers who see only an electric or magnetic field component of a static EM field, have the other (electric or magnetic) component suppressed, due to the special case of the immobile state of the charges that produce the EM field in that case. In such cases the other component becomes manifest in other observer frames.</paragraph><paragraph>A consequence of this, is that any case that seems to consist of a &quot;pure&quot; static electric or magnetic field, can be converted to an EM field, with both E and M components present, by simply moving the observer into a<space/><link><target>frame of reference</target></link><space/>which is moving with regard to the frame in which only the pure electric or magnetic field appears. That is, a pure static electric field will show the familiar magnetic field associated with a current, in any<space/><link><target>frame of reference</target></link><space/>where the charge moves. Likewise, any new motion of a charge in a region that seemed previously to contain only a magnetic field, will show that that the space now contains an electric field as well, which will be found to produces an additional Lorentz force upon the moving charge.</paragraph><paragraph>Thus,<space/><link><target>electrostatics</target></link>, as well as<space/><link><target>magnetism</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>magnetostatics</target></link>, are now seen as studies of the static EM field when a particular frame has been selected to suppress the other type of field, and since an EM field with both electric and magnetic will appear in any other frame, these &quot;simpler&quot; effects are merely the observer's. The &quot;applications&quot; of all such non-time varying (static) fields are discussed in the main articles linked in this section.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Time-varying EM fields in Maxwells equations</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>near and far field</arg><arg>near field optics</arg><arg>virtual particle</arg><arg>dielectric heating</arg><arg>magnetic induction</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An EM field that varies in time has two causes in Maxwells equations. One is charges and currents (so-called sources), and the other cause for an E or M field is a change in the other type of field (this last cause also appears in free space very far from currents and charges).</paragraph><paragraph>An electromagnetic field very far from currents and charges (sources) is called<space/><link><target>electromagnetic radiation</target></link><space/>(EMR) since it radiates from the charges and currents in the source, and has no &quot;feedback&quot; effect on them, and is also not affected directly by them in the present time (rather, it is indirectly produced by a sequences of changes in fields radiating out from them in the past). EMR consists of the radiations in the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic spectrum</target></link>, including<space/><link><target>radio wave</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>microwave</target></link>,<space/><link><target>infrared</target></link>,<space/><link><target>visible light</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ultraviolet light</target></link>,<space/><link><target>X-rays</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>gamma ray</target><trail>s</trail></link>. The many commercial applications of these radiations are discussed in the named and linked articles.</paragraph><paragraph>A notable application of visible light is that this type of energy from the Sun powers all life on Earth that either makes or uses oxygen.</paragraph><paragraph>A changing electromagnetic field which is physically close to currents and charges (see<space/><link><target>near and far field</target></link><space/>for a definition of close) will have a<space/><link><target>dipole</target></link><space/>characteristic that is dominated by either a changing<space/><link><target>electric dipole</target></link>, or a changing<space/><link><target>magnetic dipole</target></link>. This type of dipole field near sources is called an electromagnetic<space/><italics>near-field</italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Changing<space/><italics>electric</italics><space/>dipole fields, as such, are used commercially as near-fields mainly as a source of<space/><link><target>dielectric heating</target></link>. Otherwise, they appear parasitically around conductors which absorb EMR, and around antennas which have the purpose of generating EMR at greater distances.</paragraph><paragraph>Changing<space/><italics>magnetic</italics><space/>dipole fields (i.e., magnetic near-fields) are used commercially for many types of<space/><link><target>Electromagnetic induction</target><part>magnetic induction</part></link><space/>devices. These include motors and electrical transformers at low frequencies, and devices such as<space/><link><target>metal detector</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>MRI</target></link><space/>scanner coils at higher frequencies. Sometimes these high-frequency magnetic fields change at radio frequencies without being far-field waves and thus radio waves; see<space/><link><target>RFID</target></link><space/>tags.See also<space/><link><target>near-field communication</target></link>.Further uses of near-field EM effects commercially, may be found in the article on<space/><link><target>virtual photon</target><trail>s</trail></link>, since at the quantum level, these fields are represented by these particles. Far-field effects (EMR) in the quantum picture of radiation, are represented by ordinary<space/><link><target>photon</target><trail>s</trail></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Health and safety</heading><paragraph>The potential health effects of the very low frequency EMFs surrounding power lines and electrical devices are the subject of on-going research and a significant amount of public debate. The US<space/><link><target>National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health</target></link><space/>(NIOSH) and other US government agencies do not consider EMFs a proven health hazard. NIOSH has issued some cautionary advisories but stresses that the data is currently too limited to draw good conclusions.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/docs/96-129/<space/></arg><arg name="title">NIOSH Fact Sheet: EMFs in the Workplace<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">31 August 2015</arg><arg name="publisher">United States National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health</arg><arg name="date">1996</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The potential effects of electromagnetic fields on human health vary widely depending on the frequency and intensity of the fields. For more information on the health effects due to specific parts of the<space/><link><target>electromagnetic spectrum</target></link>, see the following articles:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>Static electric fields: see<space/><link><target>Electric shock</target></link></listitem><listitem>Static magnetic fields: see<space/><link><target>MRI#Safety</target></link></listitem><listitem>Extremely low frequency (ELF): see<space/><link><target>Power lines#Health concerns</target></link></listitem><listitem>Radio frequency (RF): see<space/><link><target>Electromagnetic radiation and health</target></link></listitem><listitem>Light: see<space/><link><target>Laser safety</target></link></listitem><listitem>Ultraviolet (UV): see<space/><link><target>Sunburn</target></link></listitem><listitem>Gamma rays: see<space/><link><target>Gamma ray</target></link></listitem><listitem>Mobile telephony: see<space/><link><target>Mobile phone radiation and health</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>colbegin</target><arg></arg><arg>25em</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Afterglow plasma</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Antenna factor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Classification of electromagnetic fields</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electric field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetism</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic propagation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic tensor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electrotherapy</target><part>Electromagnetic therapy</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Free space</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Fundamental interaction</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic radiation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Electromagnetic spectrum</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>EMF measurements</target><part>Electromagnetic field measurements</part></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Gravitational field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>List of environment topics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Magnetic field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Maxwell's equations</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Photoelectric effect</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Photon</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quantization of the electromagnetic field</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quantum electrodynamics</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>RiemannSilberstein vector</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>SI units</target></link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>colend</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Further reading</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Maxwell, James Clerk (1865). &quot;A dynamical theory of the electromagnetic field&quot; (PDF). Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London 155: p.&amp;nbsp;499. doi:10.1098/rstl.1865.0008.(This article accompanied a December 8, 1864 presentation by Maxwell to the Royal Society.)</listitem><listitem>Griffiths, David J. (1999). Introduction to electrodynamics, Third Edition, ed. Prentice Hall, pp.&amp;nbsp;559562.</listitem><listitem>Gabriela, Davina (2009). Unpublished manuscript. Epistemology: Foundations for Clinical Theories, Endnote 5; p.&amp;nbsp;24.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourmilab.ch/etexts/einstein/specrel/www/'>On the Electrodynamics of Moving Bodies</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Albert Einstein</target></link>, June 30, 1905.<list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.fourmilab.ch/etexts/einstein/specrel/specrel.pdf'>On the Electrodynamics of Moving Bodies</link><space/>(pdf)</listitem></list></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://monographs.iarc.fr/ENG/Monographs/vol80/volume80.pdf'>Non-Ionizing Radiation, Part 1: Static and Extremely Low-Frequency (ELF) Electric and Magnetic Fields (2002)</link><space/>by the<space/><link><target>International Agency for Research on Cancer</target><part>IARC</part></link>.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="author">Zhang J, Clement D, Taunton J<space/></arg><arg name="title">The efficacy of Farabloc, an electromagnetic shield, in attenuating delayed-onset muscle soreness<space/></arg><arg name="journal">Clin J Sport Med<space/></arg><arg name="volume">10<space/></arg><arg name="issue">1<space/></arg><arg name="pages">15–21<space/></arg><arg name="date">January 2000<space/></arg><arg name="pmid">10695845<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://meta.wkhealth.com/pt/pt-core/template-journal/lwwgateway/media/landingpage.htm?issn</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.cdc.gov/niosh/topics/emf/'>National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health EMF Topic Page</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.princeton.edu/~ota/disk1/1989/8905/8905.PDF'>Biological Effects of Power Frequency Electric and Magnetic Fields (May 1989)</link><space/>(110 pages) prepared for US Congress Office of Technology Assessment by Indira Nair, M.Granger Morgan ,Keith Florig, Department of Engineering and Public Policy Carnegie Mellon University</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Electromagnetic Field</target></template><link><target>Category:Electromagnetism</target></link></paragraph></article>