<article title='Politics_of_Ethiopia'><paragraph><template><target>multiple issues</target><arg name="{{lead rewrite|date">January 2013}}
{{Refimprove|date</arg></template><template><target>Politics of Ethiopia</target></template></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><bold>politics of Ethiopia</bold><space/>arise from the way the government of<space/><link><target>Ethiopia</target></link><space/>is structured as well as socioeconomic factors.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Government of Ethiopia</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Government of Ethiopia</arg></template>The government of Ethiopia is structured in the form of a<space/><link><target>federation</target><part>federal</part></link><space/><link><target>parliamentary system</target><part>parliamentary</part></link><space/><link><target>republic</target></link>, whereby the<space/><link><target>Prime Minister of Ethiopia</target><part>Prime Minister</part></link><space/>is the<space/><link><target>head of government</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Executive power</target></link><space/>is exercised by the government while<space/><link><target>legislative power</target></link><space/>is vested in the<space/><link><target>Parliament of Ethiopia</target><part>Parliament</part></link>. The<space/><link><target>Judiciary</target></link><space/>is more or less independent of the executive and the legislature. There are 9 ethnically-based<space/><link><target>Regions of Ethiopia</target><part>administrative regions</part></link><space/>and two self-governing administrations; the capital city<space/><link><target>Addis Ababa</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Dire Dawa</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>president of Ethiopia</target></link><space/>is elected by the<space/><link><target>House of Peoples' Representatives</target></link><space/>for a six-year term. The prime minister is chosen by the parliament. The prime minister is designated by the party in power following legislative elections. The Council of Ministers, according to the<space/><link><target>1995 Constitution of Ethiopia</target><part>1995 constitution</part></link>, is comprised by the Prime Minister, the Deputy Prime Ministers, various Ministers and other members as determined and approved by the House of Peoples' Representatives. At the current time, this includes the 20 members of<space/><link><target>Council of Ministers of Ethiopia</target><part>Council of Ministers</part></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>Federal Parliamentary Assembly</target></link><space/>has two<space/><link><target>bicameralism</target><part>chambers</part></link>: the<space/><link><target>House of People's Representatives</target><part>Council of People's Representatives</part></link><space/>(<italics>Yehizbtewekayoch Mekir Bet</italics>) with 547 members, elected for five-year terms in single-seat<space/><link><target>constituency</target><part>constituencies</part></link>; and the<space/><link><target>House of Federation</target><part>Council of the Federation</part></link><space/>(<italics>Yefedereshn Mekir Bet</italics>) with 110 members, one for each<space/><link><target>Demographics of Ethiopia</target><part>nationality</part></link>, and one additional representative for each one million of its population, designated by the regional councils, which may elect them themselves or through popular elections.</paragraph><paragraph>The president and vice president of the<space/><link><target>Federal Supreme Court of Ethiopia</target><part>Federal Supreme Court</part></link><space/>are recommended by the prime minister and appointed by the House of People's Representatives; for other federal judges, the prime minister submits candidates selected by the Federal Judicial Administrative Council to the of People's Representatives for appointment.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Recent history</heading><paragraph><template><target>refimprove section</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template><template><target>main</target><arg>History of Ethiopia</arg></template>In May 1991, a coalition of rebel forces under the name<space/><link><target>Tigrayan People's Liberation Front</target></link><space/>(TPLF) defeated the government of Mengistu regime<space/><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template>. In July 1991, the TPLF, the<space/><link><target>Oromo Liberation Front</target></link><space/>(OLF), and others with the general exclusion of<space/><link><target>Amhara people</target><part>Amharas</part></link><template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">June 2010</arg></template><space/>established the Transitional Government of Ethiopia (TGE), which consisted of an 87-member Council of Representatives and guided by a national charter that functioned as a transitional constitution. Since 1991, Ethiopia has established warm relations with the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link><space/>and western<space/><link><target>Europe</target></link><space/>and has sought substantial economic aid from Western countries and<space/><link><target>World Bank</target></link>.<space/></paragraph><paragraph>In June 1992 the OLF withdrew from the government; in March 1993, members of the<space/><link><target>Southern Ethiopia Peoples' Democratic Coalition</target></link><space/>left the government. The<space/><link><target>Eritrean People's Liberation Front</target></link><space/>(EPLF), an ally in the fight against the Mengistu regime, assumed control of<space/><link><target>Eritrea</target></link><space/>and established a provisional government. Eritrea achieved full independence on May 24, 1993.</paragraph><paragraph>President<space/><link><target>Meles Zenawi</target></link><space/>and members of the TGE pledged to oversee the formation of a multi-party democracy. The first election for Ethiopia's 547-member constituent assembly was held in June 1994. This assembly adopted the constitution of the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia in December 1994. The elections for Ethiopia's first popularly-chosen national parliament and regional legislatures were held in May and June 1995. Most opposition parties chose to boycott these elections. There was a landslide victory for the<space/><link><target>Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front</target></link><space/>(EPRDF)<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">July 2015</arg></template>. International and non-governmental observers concluded that opposition parties would have been able to participate had they chosen to do so.</paragraph><paragraph>The Government of the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia was installed in August 1995. The first President was<space/><link><target>Negasso Gidada</target></link>. The EPRDF-led government of Prime Minister Meles has promoted a policy of ethnic federalism, seemingly devolving significant powers to regional, ethnically-based authorities. Ethiopia today has nine semi-autonomous<space/><link><target>Regions of Ethiopia</target></link><space/>that have the power to raise and spend their own revenues.</paragraph><paragraph>In 2004, the government began a<space/><link><target>Resettlement and villagization in Ethiopia</target><part>resettlement initiative</part></link><space/>to move more than two million people away from the arid highlands of the east, proposing that these resettlements would reduce food shortages.<extension extension_name='ref' name="resettlement"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/in_pictures/3640227.stm</arg><arg name="title">In Pictures: Ethiopia's great resettlement</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC News]]</arg><arg name="date">2004-04-22</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-26<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The incumbent President is<space/><link><target>Mulatu Teshome</target></link><space/>and has been at that position since October 2013. The ruling party, EPRDF was declared winner by the election board in 2000, and then again in 2005 amidst protests and riots that led to the death of many Ethiopians. Hundreds of political leaders&amp;ndash;some of whom were elected to parliamentary positions&amp;ndash; were arrested in connection with these protests.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>As of February 2006, hundreds political remained in custody, facing trial in March.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>About 119 people are currently facing trial, including journalists for defamation and opposition party leaders for treason.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>Human rights organisations have raised concerns over the well-being of some of these prisoners. However 8,000 prisoners have already been freed.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/africa/4440232.stm</arg><arg name="title">Mass release from Ethiopian jails</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC News]]</arg><arg name="date">2005-11-15</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-26<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension><space/>Concerns about the implications of these trials for the freedom of the press have also been raised.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>According to the US Department of State 2009 human rights report, there are hundreds of political prisoners in Ethiopia. Among them is the leader of the largest opposition party Birtukan Midekssa. Fundamental freedoms, including<space/><link><target>freedom of the press</target></link>, are, in practice, circumscribed.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">January 2013</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Political parties and elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>List of political parties in Ethiopia</arg><arg>Elections in Ethiopia</arg></template>In the<space/><link><target>Ethiopian general election, 2015</target><part>2015 general election</part></link>, Opposition parties lost the only seat which they still held in the<space/><link><target>House of Peoples' Representatives</target></link>. The<space/><link><target>Ethiopian Peoples Revolutionary Democratic Front</target></link><space/>and its allies won all 547 seats.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.theguardian.com/world/2015/jun/22/ethiopias-ruling-party-win-clean-sweep-general-election'>&quot;Ethiopia's ruling party wins by landslide in general election&quot;</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>The Guardian</target></link></italics>, 22 June 2015</extension></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>elect</target><arg>List of political parties in Ethiopia</arg><arg>Elections in Ethiopia</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>Political pressure groups include the Council of Alternative Forces for Peace and Democracy in Ethiopia (CAFPDE)<space/><link><target>Beyene Petros</target></link><space/>and the Southern Ethiopia People's Democratic Coalition (SEPDC) [Beyene Petros].</paragraph><paragraph>The coalition of<space/><link><target>List of political parties in Ethiopia</target><part>opposition parties</part></link><space/>and some individuals that was established in 2009 to oust at the general election in 2010 the regime of the<space/><link><target>TPLF</target></link>, Meles Zenawis party that has been in power since 1991, published a 65-page<space/><link><target>manifesto</target></link><space/>in Addis Ababa on October 10, 2009.</paragraph><paragraph>Some of the eight member parties of this Ethiopian<space/><link><target>Forum for Democratic Dialogue</target></link><space/>(FDD or<space/><link><target>Medrek</target></link><space/>in Amharic) include the<space/><link><target>Oromo Federalist Congress</target></link><space/>(organized by the<space/><link><target>Oromo Federalist Democratic Movement</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Oromo Peoples Congress</target></link>), the<space/><link><target>Arena Tigray</target></link><space/>(organized by former members of the ruling party TPLF), the<space/><link><target>Unity for Democracy and Justice</target></link><space/>(UDJ, whose leader was imprisoned), and the<space/><link><target>Coalition of Somali Democratic Forces</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>2005 Ethiopian general elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Ethiopian general elections, 2005</arg></template><link><target>Image:Ethiopian general elections 2005.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>400px</part><part>Ethiopian general election 2005. Only parties with more than 10 seats shown.<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Red: EPRDF<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Green: CUD<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Purple: UEDF<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Dark blue: SPDP<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Orange: OFDM<xhtml:br></xhtml:br>Light blue: Others</part></link>Ethiopia held its third<space/><link><target>Ethiopian general elections, 2005</target><part>general election in May 2005</part></link>, which drew a record number of voters, with 90% of the electorate turning out to cast their vote. While the election was deemed by the European Union election observer team to fall short of international standards for fair and free elections, other teams drew different conclusions. The African Union report on September 14 commended &quot;the Ethiopian people's display of genuine commitment to democratic ideals<space/><extension extension_name='ref' name="embassy"><link type='external' href='http://www.ethioembassy.org.uk/news/press%20releases/Facts%20about%20the%20Recent%20Ethiopian%20Parliamentary%20Elections.htm'>On 2005 Ethiopian elections</link></extension><space/>and on September 15 the US Carter Center concluded that &quot;the majority of the constituency results based on the May 15 polling and tabulation are credible and reflect competitive conditions&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="embassy"></extension><space/>The US Department of State said on September 16, &quot;these elections stand out as a milestone in creating a new, more competitive multi-party political system in one of Africa's largest and most important countries.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>http://2001-2009.state.gov/r/pa/prs/ps/2005/53355.htm</extension><space/>Even the EU preliminary statement of 2005 also said &quot;...the polling processes were generally positive. The overall assessment of the process has been rated as good in 64% of the cases, and very good in 24%&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="embassy"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The opposition complained that the ruling EPRDF engaged in widespread vote rigging and intimidation, alleging fraud in 299 constituencies.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>The ruling party complained that the main opposition party CUD's AEUP sub party had engaged in intimidation.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>All allegations were investigated by the National Electoral Board of Ethiopia in cooperation with election monitors, a process which delayed the release of the final results. In June 2005, with the results of the election still unclear, a group of university students protested these alleged discrepancies, encouraged by supporters of the Coalition for Unity opposition party, despite a ban on protests imposed by the government. On June 8, 26 people were killed in<space/><link><target>Addis Ababa</target></link><space/>as a result of rioting, which led to the arrest of hundreds of protesters.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>On September 5, 2005, the National Elections Board of Ethiopia released the final election results, which confirmed that the ruling Ethiopian People's Revolutionary Democratic Front retained its control of the government, but showed that opposition parties had increased their share of parliamentary seats, from 12 to 176. The Coalition for Unity and Democracy won all the seats in Addis Ababa, both for the Parliament and the City Council.</paragraph><paragraph>Street protests broke out again when the opposition called for a general strike and boycotted the new Parliament, refusing to accept the results of the election.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>The police forces once again attempted to contain the protests, and this time, 42 people were killed in Addis Ababa, including seven policemen, and another of whom later died because of fatal injuries caused by a hand grenade detonation. Thousands were arrested, and were taken to various detention centers across the country.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>As of February 2006, six hundred remained in custody, facing trial in March.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>On 14 November, the Ethiopian Parliament passed a resolution to establish a neutral commission to investigate the incidents of June 8 and November 1 and 2.<template><target>Citation needed</target><arg name="date">April 2007</arg></template><space/>In February 2006, UK Prime Minister Blair, acknowledging that the EPRDF has won the election, said he wanted to see Ethiopia resolve its internal problems and continue on a democratic path.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Blair"><template><target>cite news</target><arg name="url">http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/world/africa/4707232.stm</arg><arg name="title">UK PM targets Ethiopia at summit</arg><arg name="publisher">[[BBC News]]</arg><arg name="date">2006-02-12</arg><arg name="accessdate">2007-04-26<space/></arg><arg name="location">London</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>With Ethiopias national election in May 2010 approaching, some opposition groups begun to hint a boycott, accusing the government of stepping up harassment against them. Despite growing claims of &quot;harassment&quot; and &quot;undemocratic actions&quot; perpetrated by the ruling party, the Forum for Democratic Dialogue (FDD), Ethiopias biggest alliance of opposition political parties declared in October 2009 that it will contest in the scheduled election.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>Gebru Asrat</target></link>, a former ally of PM Meles Zenawi, said that his partys primary efforts were<space/><italics>&quot;to engage in negotiation with the government on key election issues&quot;</italics><space/>ahead of the election, but he added that the government was reluctant.</paragraph><paragraph>FDD insists to engage in a pre-election negotiation on 10 key subjects, among which the issues of access to the media for campaigning, the supremacy of law, the free access of international observers, the establishment of an independent electoral board and a stop to harassment and pressure on opposition members.</paragraph><heading level='3'>2010 Ethiopian general elections</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Ethiopian general election, 2010</arg></template>The EPRDF won the 2010 elections by a landslide, taking 499 seats, while allied parties took a further 35. Oppositions parties took just 2. Both opposition groups say their observers were blocked from entering polling stations during the election on Sunday, May 23, and in some cases the individuals beaten. The United States and the European Union have both criticized the election as falling short of international standards. Additionally, the EPRDF won all but one of 1,904 council seats in regional elections.</paragraph><heading level='2'>International organization participation</heading><paragraph><link><target>ACP (Lom Convention)</target><part>ACP</part></link>,<space/><link><target>AfDB</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Economic Commission for Africa</target><part>ECA</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Food and Agriculture Organization</target><part>FAO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Group of 24</target><part>G-24</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Group of 77</target><part>G-77</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IAEA</target></link>,<space/><link><target>IBRD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>ICAO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement</target><part>ICRM</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Development Association</target><part>IDA</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IFAD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Finance Corporation</target><part>IFC</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IFRCS</target></link>,<space/><link><target>IGAD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Labour Organization</target><part>ILO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IMF</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Maritime Organization</target><part>IMO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Intelsat</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Interpol (organization)</target><part>Interpol</part></link>,<space/><link><target>IOC</target></link>,<space/><link><target>International Organization for Migration</target><part>IOM</part></link><space/>(observer),<space/><link><target>International Organization for Standardization</target><part>ISO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>International Telecommunication Union</target><part>ITU</part></link>,<space/><link><target>Non-Aligned Movement</target><part>NAM</part></link>,<space/><link><target>OAU</target></link>,<space/><link><target>OPCW</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations</target></link>,<space/><link><target>UNCTAD</target></link>,<space/><link><target>UNESCO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>UNHCR</target></link>,<space/><link><target>United Nations Industrial Development Organization</target><part>UNIDO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>UNU</target></link>,<space/><link><target>UPU</target></link>,<space/><link><target>World Customs Organization</target><part>WCO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Federation of Trade Unions</target><part>WFTU</part></link>,<space/><link><target>World Health Organization</target><part>WHO</part></link>,<space/><link><target>WIPO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>WMO</target></link>,<space/><link><target>WToO</target></link></paragraph><paragraph>Scheye wrote in 2010 that significant donor resources are being invested in<space/><link><target>security sector reform</target></link><space/>in Ethiopia because of donor national interest, even though the country's ruling group is ideologically opposed to the core principles of SSR, and showed, at that time, little interest in justice and security sector development.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eric Scheye, Realism and Pragmatism in Security Sector Development, United States Institute of Peace, Special Report 257, October 2010, 7-8.</extension></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>The Guardian</target></link><space/>wrote just before the 2015 elections that '..the EPRDFs relations with donors are a crucial factor in maintaining its position. Ethiopia remains structurally dependent on aid, with the country receiving more than $3 billion a year from the<space/><link><target>Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development</target></link>. However, all indications are that external support will remain strong, regardless of electoral openness. Ethiopia is a key partner for countries concerned about security in the region, especially the US, UK and the European Union.'<extension extension_name='ref'>Jason Mosley,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.theguardian.com/global-development/2015/may/22/ethiopia-elections-controlled-political-participation'>Ethiopia's elections are just an exercise in controlled political participation</link>, 22 May 2015.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Royalists and government in exile</heading><paragraph>A group of<space/><link><target>Monarchies of Ethiopia</target><part>Ethiopian royalists</part></link><space/>continue to operate The<space/><link><target>Crown Council of Ethiopia</target></link><space/>as a<space/><link><target>government in exile</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>2</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.ethiopar.net'>The Parliament of Ethiopia</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.servat.unibe.ch/icl/et00000_.html'>Constitution of Ethiopia</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>dmoz</target><arg>Regional/Africa/Ethiopia/Government</arg><arg>Ethiopia Government</arg></template></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Ethiopia topics</target></template><template><target>Africa in topic</target><arg>Politics of</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Politics Of Ethiopia</target></template><link><target>Category:Politics of Ethiopia</target><part></part></link></paragraph></article>