<article title='Abstraction'><paragraph><template><target>about</target><arg></arg><arg>specific types of abstraction and other uses of the term</arg><arg></arg></template><bold>Abstraction</bold><space/>in its main sense is a<space/><link><target>conceptual process</target></link><space/>by which general<space/><link><target>rule of inference</target><part>rules</part></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>concept</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>are derived from the usage and classification of specific examples, literal (&quot;real&quot; or &quot;concrete&quot;) signifiers,<space/><link><target>first principle</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or other methods. &quot;An abstraction&quot; is the product of this processa concept that acts as a super-categorical noun for all subordinate concepts, and connects any related concepts as a<space/><italics>group, field,</italics><space/>or<space/><italics>category</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Langer"><link><target>Suzanne K. Langer</target></link><space/>(1953),<space/><italics>Feeling and Form: a theory of art developed from Philosophy in a New Key</italics><space/>p. 90: &quot;<link><target>Sculpture</target><part>Sculptural form</part></link><space/>is a powerful abstraction from actual objects and the three-dimensional space which we construe ... through<space/><link><target>sensory system</target><part>touch and sight</part></link>.&quot;</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Conceptual abstractions may be formed by filtering the<space/><link><target>information</target></link><space/>content of a<space/><link><target>concept</target></link><space/>or an observable<space/><link><target>phenomenon</target></link>, selecting only the aspects which are relevant for a particular purpose. For example, abstracting a leather soccer ball to the more general idea of a<space/><link><target>ball</target></link><space/>selects only the information on general ball attributes and behavior, eliminating the other characteristics of that particular ball.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Langer"></extension><space/>In a<space/><link><target>typetoken distinction</target></link>, a type (e.g., a 'ball') is more abstract than its tokens (e.g., 'that leather soccer ball').</paragraph><paragraph>Abstraction in its secondary use is a<space/><link><target>#Material process</target><part>material process</part></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA">Alfred Sohn-Rethel,<space/><italics>Intellectual and manual labour: A critique of epistemology</italics>, Humanities Press, 1977</extension><space/>discussed in the<space/><link><target>#Themes in abstraction</target><part>themes below</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>Origins</heading><paragraph>Thinking in abstractions is considered by<space/><link><target>anthropologist</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>archaeologist</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>sociologist</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>to be one of the key traits in<space/><link><target>modern human behaviour</target></link>, which is believed to have developed between 50 000 and 100 000 years ago. Its development is likely to have been closely connected with the development of human<space/><link><target>language</target></link>, which (whether spoken or written) appears to both involve and facilitate abstract thinking.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Abstraction</italics><space/>involves induction of ideas or the synthesis of particular facts into one general theory about something. It is the opposite of<space/><italics>specification</italics>, which is the analysis or breaking-down of a general idea or abstraction into concrete facts. Abstraction can be illustrated with<space/><link><target>Francis Bacon</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Novum Organum</target></link></italics><space/>(1620), a book of modern scientific philosophy written in the late<space/><link><target>Elizabethan era</target></link><extension extension_name='ref' name="Hesse">Hesse, M. B. (1964), &quot;Francis Bacon's Philosophy of Science&quot;, in A Critical History of Western Philosophy, ed. D. J. O'Connor, New York, pp. 14152.</extension><space/>of England to encourage modern thinkers to collect specific facts before making any generalizations. Bacon used and promoted induction as an abstraction tool, and it countered the ancient deductive-thinking approach that had dominated the intellectual world since the times of Greek philosophers like<space/><link><target>Thales</target></link>,<space/><link><target>Anaximander</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>Aristotle</target></link>. Thales (c. 624 BC c. 546 BCE) believed that everything in the universe comes from one main substance, water. He deduced or specified from a general idea, &quot;everything is water&quot;, to the specific forms of water such as ice, snow, fog, and rivers. Modern scientists can also use the opposite approach of abstraction, or going from particular facts collected into one general idea, such as the motion of the planets (<link><target>Isaac Newton</target><part>Newton</part></link><space/>(1642-1727)). When determining that the sun is the center of our solar system (<link><target>Copernicus</target></link><space/>(1473-1543)), scientists had to utilize thousands of measurements to finally conclude that Mars moves in an elliptical orbit about the sun (<link><target>Kepler</target></link><space/>(1571-1630)), or to assemble multiple specific facts into the law of falling bodies (<link><target>Galileo</target></link><space/>(1564-1642)).</paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><heading level='3'>Compression</heading><preblock><preline>An abstraction can be seen as a compression process,<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Citation</target><arg name="first">Gregory<space/></arg><arg name="last">Chaitin<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink">Gregory Chaitin<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.umcs.maine.edu/~chaitin/sciamer3.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Limits Of Reason<space/></arg><arg name="year">2006</arg></template></extension><space/>mapping multiple different pieces of<space/><link><target>wikt:constituent</target><part>constituent</part></link><space/>data to a single piece of abstract data;<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Murray Gell-Mann</target></link><space/>(1995) &quot;<link type='external' href='http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1002/cplx.6130010105/pdf'>What is complexity? Remarks on simplicity and complexity by the Nobel Prize-winning author of The Quark and the Jaguar</link>&quot;<space/><italics>Complexity</italics><space/>states the 'algorithmic information complexity' (AIC) of some string of bits is the shortest length computer program which can print out that string of bits.</extension><space/>based on similarities in the constituent data, for example, many different physical cats map to the abstraction &quot;CAT&quot;. This conceptual scheme emphasizes the inherent equality of both constituent and abstract data, thus avoiding problems arising from the distinction between &quot;abstract&quot; and &quot;<link><target>concrete (philosophy)</target><part>concrete</part></link>&quot;. In this sense the process of abstraction entails the identification of similarities between objects, and the process of associating these objects with an abstraction (which is<space/><link><target>#Physicality</target><part>itself an object</part></link>).</preline></preblock><list type='ident'><listitem>For example,<space/><italics><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>picture 1 below</part></link></italics><space/>illustrates the concrete relationship &quot;Cat sits on Mat&quot;.</listitem></list><paragraph>Chains of abstractions can be<space/><link><target>construe</target><trail>d</trail></link>,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Ross">Ross,L. (1987). The Problem of Construal in Social Inference and Social Psychology. In N. Grunberg, R.E. Nisbett, J. Singer (eds),<space/><italics>A Distinctive Approach to psychological research: the influence of Stanley Schacter</italics>. Hillsdale, NJ: Earlbaum.</extension><space/>moving from neural impulses arising from sensory<space/><link><target>perception</target></link><space/>to basic abstractions such as color or<space/><link><target>shape</target></link>, to experiential abstractions such as a specific cat, to<space/><link><target>semantic</target></link><space/>abstractions such as the &quot;idea&quot; of a CAT, to classes of objects such as &quot;mammals&quot; and even categories such as &quot;<link><target>#Physicality</target><part>object</part></link>&quot; as opposed to &quot;action&quot;.</paragraph><list type='ident'><listitem>For example,<space/><italics><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>graph 1 below</part></link></italics><space/>expresses the abstraction &quot;agent sits on location&quot;. This conceptual scheme entails no specific<space/><link><target>hierarchical</target></link><space/><link><target>Taxonomy (biology)</target><part>taxonomy</part></link><space/>(such as the one mentioned involving cats and mammals), only a progressive<space/><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>exclusion of detail</part></link>.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Instantiation</heading><paragraph>Things that do not exist at any particular place and time are often considered abstract. By contrast, instances, or members, of such an abstract thing might exist in many different places and times. Those abstract things are then said to be<space/><italics>multiply instantiated</italics>, in the sense of<space/><italics>picture 1</italics>,<space/><italics>picture 2</italics>, etc., shown<space/><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>below</part></link>. It is not sufficient, however, to define<space/><italics>abstract</italics><space/>ideas as those that can be instantiated and to define<space/><italics>abstraction</italics><space/>as the movement in the opposite direction to instantiation. Doing so would make the concepts &quot;cat&quot; and &quot;telephone&quot; abstract ideas since despite their varying appearances, a particular cat or a particular telephone is an instance of the concept &quot;cat&quot; or the concept &quot;telephone&quot;. Although the concepts &quot;cat&quot; and &quot;telephone&quot; are<space/><italics>abstractions</italics>, they are not<space/><italics>abstract</italics><space/>in the sense of the objects in<space/><italics>graph 1</italics><space/><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>below</part></link>. We might look at other graphs, in a progression from<space/><italics>cat</italics><space/>to<space/><italics>mammal</italics><space/>to<space/><italics>animal</italics>, and see that<space/><italics>animal</italics><space/>is more abstract than<space/><italics>mammal</italics>; but on the other hand<space/><italics>mammal</italics><space/>is a harder idea to express, certainly in relation to<space/><italics><link><target>marsupial</target></link></italics><space/>or<space/><italics><link><target>monotreme</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>Perhaps confusingly, some<space/><link><target>philosophy</target><part>philosophies</part></link><space/>refer to<space/><italics><link><target>trope (philosophy)</target><part>tropes</part></link></italics><space/>(instances of properties) as<space/><italics><link><target>abstract particular</target><trail>s</trail></link></italics>e.g., the particular<space/><link><target>red</target><trail>ness</trail></link><space/>of a particular<space/><link><target>apple</target></link><space/>is an<space/><italics>abstract particular</italics>. This is similar to<space/><link><target>qualia</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>sumbebekos</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Material process</heading><paragraph>Still retaining the primary meaning of 'abstrere' or 'to draw away from', the abstraction of money, for example, works by drawing away from the particular value of things allowing completely incommensurate objects to be compared (see the section on 'Physicality' below).<space/><link><target>Karl Marx</target></link>'s writing on the<space/><link><target>commodity</target></link><space/>abstraction recognizes a parallel process.</paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><link><target>state (polity)</target></link><space/>as both concept and material practice exemplifies the two sides of this process of abstraction. Conceptually, 'the current concept of the state is an abstraction from the much more concrete early-modern use as the standing or status of the prince, his visible estates'. At the same time, materially, the 'practice of statehood is now constitutively and materially more abstract than at the time when princes ruled as the embodiment of extended power'.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Paul James (academic)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Globalism, Nationalism, Tribalism: Bringing Theory Back In—Volume 2 of Towards a Theory of Abstract Community<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.academia.edu/1642214/Globalism_Nationalism_Tribalism_Bringing_Theory_Back_In_author_Sage_Publications_London_2006<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sage Publications<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg></template>, pages 318-19.</extension><space/><template><target>further</target><arg>Power projection</arg><arg>Display behavior</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Ontological status</heading><paragraph>The way that physical objects, like rocks and trees, have<space/><link><target>category of being</target><part>being</part></link><space/>differs from the way that properties of abstract concepts or relations have being, for example the way the<space/><link><target>concrete (philosophy)</target><part>concrete</part></link>,<space/><link><target>particular</target></link>,<space/><link><target>individual</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>pictured in<space/><italics><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>picture 1</part></link></italics><space/>exist differs from the way the concepts illustrated in<space/><italics><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>graph 1</part></link></italics><space/>exist. That difference accounts for the<space/><link><target>ontological</target></link><space/>usefulness of the word &quot;abstract&quot;. The word applies to properties and relations to mark the fact that, if they exist, they do not exist in space or time, but that instances of them can exist, potentially in many different places and times.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Physicality</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>History of accounting#Ancient history</arg></template>A physical object (a possible referent of a concept or word) is considered<space/><italics>concrete</italics><space/>(not abstract) if it is a<space/><italics>particular individual</italics><space/>that occupies a particular place and time. However, in the secondary sense of the term 'abstraction', this physical object can carry materially abstracting processes. For example, record-keeping aids throughout the<space/><link><target>Fertile Crescent</target></link><space/>included calculi (clay spheres, cones, etc.) which represented counts of items, probably livestock or grains, sealed in containers. According to<space/><template><target>harvnb</target><arg>Schmandt-Besserat</arg><arg>(1981)</arg></template>, these clay containers contained tokens, the total of which were the count of objects being transferred. The containers thus served as something of a<space/><link><target>bill of lading</target></link><space/>or an accounts book. In order to avoid breaking open the containers for the count, marks were placed on the outside of the containers. These physical marks, in other words, acted as material abstractions of a materially abstract process of accounting, using conceptual abstractions (numbers) to communicate its meaning.<extension extension_name='ref'>Eventually (<link type='external' href='http://www.laits.utexas.edu/ghazal/Chap1/dsb/chapter1.html'>Schmandt-Besserat estimates it took 4000 years</link>) the marks on the outside of the containers were all that were needed to convey the count, and the clay containers evolved into clay tablets with marks for the count.</extension><extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="first">Eleanor</arg><arg name="last">Robson</arg><arg name="author-link">Eleanor Robson</arg><arg name="year">2008</arg><arg name="title">Mathematics in Ancient Iraq</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-691-09182-2</arg></template>. p. 5: these calculi were in use in Iraq for primitive accounting systems as early as 32003000 BCE, with commodity-specific counting representation systems. Balanced accounting was in use by 30002350 BCE, and a<space/><link><target>sexagesimal number system</target></link><space/>was in use 23502000 BCE.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Abstract things are sometimes defined as those things that do not exist in<space/><link><target>reality</target></link><space/>or exist only as sensory experiences, like the color<space/><link><target>red</target></link>. That definition, however, suffers from the difficulty of deciding which things are real (i.e. which things exist in reality). For example, it is difficult to agree to whether concepts like<space/><italics>God</italics>,<space/><italics>the number three</italics>, and<space/><italics>goodness</italics><space/>are real, abstract, or both.</paragraph><paragraph>An approach to resolving such difficulty is to use<space/><italics><link><target>predicate (grammar)</target><part>predicates</part></link></italics><space/>as a general term for whether things are variously real, abstract, concrete, or of a particular property (e.g.,<space/><italics>good</italics>). Questions about the properties of things are then<space/><link><target>proposition</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>about predicates, which propositions remain to be evaluated by the investigator. In the<space/><italics>graph 1</italics><space/><link><target>#Simplification and ordering</target><part>below</part></link>, the graphical relationships like the arrows joining boxes and ellipses might denote predicates.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Referencing and referring</heading><paragraph>Abstractions sometimes have ambiguous<space/><link><target>referent</target><trail>s</trail></link>; for example, &quot;<link><target>happiness</target></link>&quot; (when used as an abstraction) can refer to as many things as there are people and events or<space/><link><target>being</target><part>states of being</part></link><space/>which make them happy. Likewise, &quot;<link><target>architecture</target></link>&quot; refers not only to the design of safe, functional buildings, but also to elements of creation and<space/><link><target>innovation</target></link><space/>which aim at elegant solutions to<space/><link><target>construction</target></link><space/>problems, to the use of space, and to the attempt to evoke an<space/><link><target>emotion</target><part>emotional response</part></link><space/>in the builders, owners, viewers and users of the building.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Simplification and ordering</heading><paragraph>Abstraction uses a<space/><link><target>strategy</target></link><space/>of simplification, wherein formerly concrete details are left ambiguous, vague, or undefined; thus effective<space/><link><target>communication</target></link><space/>about things in the abstract requires an<space/><link><target>intuition (knowledge)</target><part>intuitive</part></link><space/>or common experience between the communicator and the communication recipient. This is true for all verbal/abstract communication.</paragraph><paragraph><link><target>File:Cat-on-mat.svg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part><link><target>Conceptual graph</target></link><space/>for A Cat sitting on the Mat ''(graph 1)''</part></link><link><target>File:JerryFelix.JPG</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>125px</part><part>Cat on Mat ''(picture 1)''</part></link>For example, many different things can be<space/><link><target>red</target></link>. Likewise, many things sit on surfaces (as in<space/><italics>picture 1</italics>, to the right). The property of<space/><italics><link><target>red</target><trail>ness</trail></link></italics><space/>and the<space/><link><target>Relation of Ideas</target><part>relation</part></link><space/><italics><link><target>sitting</target><part>sitting-on</part></link></italics><space/>are therefore abstractions of those objects. Specifically, the conceptual diagram<space/><italics>graph 1</italics><space/>identifies only three boxes, two ellipses, and four arrows (and their five labels), whereas the<space/><italics>picture 1</italics><space/>shows much more pictorial detail, with the scores of implied relationships as implicit in the picture rather than with the nine explicit details in the graph.</paragraph><paragraph><italics>Graph 1</italics><space/>details some explicit relationships between the objects of the diagram. For example, the arrow between the<space/><italics>agent</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>CAT:Elsie</italics><space/>depicts an example of an<space/><italics><link><target>is-a</target></link></italics><space/>relationship, as does the arrow between the<space/><italics>location</italics><space/>and the<space/><italics>MAT</italics>. The arrows between the<space/><link><target>gerund</target></link>/<link><target>present participle</target></link><space/><italics>SITTING</italics><space/>and the<space/><link><target>noun</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/><italics>agent</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>location</italics><space/>express the<space/><link><target>diagram</target></link>'s basic relationship;<space/><italics>&quot;agent is SITTING on location&quot;</italics>;<space/><italics>Elsie</italics><space/>is an instance of<space/><italics>CAT</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>John F. Sowa</target><part>Sowa, John F.</part></link><space/>(1984).<space/><italics>Conceptual Structures: Information Processing in Mind and Machine</italics>. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley. ISBN 978-0-201-14472-7.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although the description<space/><italics>sitting-on</italics><space/>(graph 1) is more abstract than the graphic image of a cat sitting on a mat (picture 1), the delineation of abstract things from concrete things is somewhat ambiguous; this ambiguity or vagueness is characteristic of abstraction. Thus something as simple as a newspaper might be specified to six levels, as in<space/><link><target>Douglas Hofstadter</target></link>'s illustration of that ambiguity, with a progression from abstract to concrete in<space/><italics><link><target>Gdel, Escher, Bach</target></link></italics><space/>(1979):<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Douglas Hofstadter</target></link><space/>(1979)<space/><italics><link><target>Gdel, Escher, Bach</target></link></italics></extension><extension extension_name='blockquote'><list type='ident'><listitem>(1) a publication<list type='ident'><listitem>(2) a newspaper<list type='ident'><listitem>(3)<space/><italics>The San Francisco Chronicle</italics><list type='ident'><listitem>(4) the May 18 edition of the<space/><italics>The San Francisco Chronicle</italics><list type='ident'><listitem>(5) my copy of the May 18 edition of the<space/><italics>The San Francisco Chronicle</italics><list type='ident'><listitem>(6) my copy of the May 18 edition of the<space/><italics>The San Francisco Chronicle</italics><space/>as it was when I first picked it up (as contrasted with my copy as it was a few days later: in my fireplace, burning)</listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list></listitem></list></extension></paragraph><paragraph>An abstraction can thus encapsulate each of these levels of detail with no<space/><link><target>loss of generality</target></link>. But perhaps a detective or philosopher/scientist/engineer might seek to learn about something, at progressively deeper levels of detail, to solve a crime or a puzzle.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Thought processes</heading><paragraph>In<space/><link><target>philosophy</target><part>philosophical terminology</part></link>,<space/><italics>abstraction</italics><space/>is the<space/><link><target>thinking</target><part>thought process</part></link><space/>wherein<space/><link><target>idea</target><trail>s</trail></link><extension extension_name='ref'>But an idea can be<space/><link><target>symbol</target><trail>ized</trail></link>. &quot;A symbol is any device whereby we are enabled to make an abstraction.&quot; -- p.xi and chapter 20 of<space/><link><target>Suzanne K. Langer</target></link><space/>(1953),<space/><italics>Feeling and Form: a theory of art developed from<space/><bold>Philosophy in a New Key</bold></italics>: New York: Charles Scribner's Sons. 431 pages, index.</extension><space/>are distanced from<space/><link><target>object (philosophy)</target><part>objects</part></link>.</paragraph><heading level='2'>As used in different disciplines</heading><heading level='3'>In art</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Abstraction (art)</arg></template>Typically,<space/><italics>abstraction</italics><space/>is used in the arts as a<space/><link><target>synonym</target></link><space/>for<space/><link><target>abstract art</target></link><space/>in general. Strictly speaking, it refers to art unconcerned with the literal depiction of things from the visible worldit can, however, refer to an object or image which has been distilled from the real world, or indeed, another work of art.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.britannica.com/eb/article-9003405/abstract-art'>Encyclopdia Britannica</link></extension><space/>Artwork that reshapes the natural world for expressive purposes is called abstract; that which derives from, but does not imitate a recognizable subject is called nonobjective abstraction. In the 20th century the trend toward abstraction coincided with advances in science, technology, and changes in urban life, eventually reflecting an interest in psychoanalytic theory.<extension extension_name='ref'>Catherine de Zegher and Hendel Teicher (eds.),<space/><italics>3 X Abstraction</italics>. NY/New Haven: The Drawing Center/Yale University Press. 2005. ISBN 0-300-10826-5</extension><space/>Later still, abstraction was manifest in more purely formal terms, such as color, freedom from objective context, and a reduction of form to basic geometric designs.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.nga.gov/education/american/abstract.shtm'>National Gallery of Art: Abstraction.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In computer science</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Abstraction (computer science)</arg></template><link><target>Computer scientists</target></link><space/>use abstraction to make models that can be used and re-used without having to re-write all the program code for each new application on every different type of computer. They<space/><link><target>communication</target><part>communicate</part></link><space/>their solutions with the computer by writing<space/><link><target>source code</target></link><space/>in some particular<space/><link><target>computer language</target></link><space/>which can be translated into<space/><link><target>machine code</target></link><space/>for different types of computer to execute. Abstraction allows program designers to separate categories and concepts related to computing problems from specific instances of implementation. This means that the program code can be written so that it does not depend on the specific details of supporting applications,<space/><link><target>operating system</target></link><space/>software or hardware, but on an abstract concept of the solution to the problem that can then be integrated with the system with minimal additional work.</paragraph><heading level='3'>In linguistics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Abstraction (linguistics)</arg></template>Abstraction is frequently applied in<space/><link><target>linguistics</target></link><space/>so as to allow phenomena of language to be analyzed at the desired level of detail. A commonly considered abstraction is the<space/><italics><link><target>phoneme</target></link></italics>, which abstracts<space/><link><target>speech sound</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in such a way as to neglect details that cannot serve to differentiate meaning. Other analogous kinds of abstractions (sometimes called &quot;<link><target>emic unit</target><trail>s</trail></link>&quot;) considered by linguists include<space/><link><target>morpheme</target><trail>s</trail></link>,<space/><link><target>grapheme</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and<space/><link><target>lexeme</target><trail>s</trail></link>. Abstraction also arises in the relation between<space/><link><target>syntax</target></link>,<space/><link><target>semantics</target></link>, and<space/><link><target>pragmatics</target></link>. Pragmatics involves considerations that make reference to the user of the language; semantics considers expressions and what they denote (the<space/><link><target>designata</target></link>) abstracted from the language user; and syntax considers only the expressions themselves, abstracted from the designata.</paragraph><heading level='3'>In mathematics</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Abstraction (mathematics)</arg></template>Abstraction in<space/><link><target>mathematics</target></link><space/>is the process of extracting the underlying essence of a mathematical concept, removing any dependence on real world objects with which it might originally have been connected, and generalizing it so that it has wider applications or matching among other abstract descriptions of equivalent phenomena.</paragraph><paragraph>The advantages of abstraction in mathematics are:</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem>It reveals deep connections between different areas of mathematics</listitem><listitem>Known results in one area can suggest<space/><link><target>conjecture</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>in a related area</listitem><listitem>Techniques and methods from one area can be applied to prove results in a related area</listitem></list><paragraph>The main disadvantage of abstraction is that highly abstract concepts are more difficult to learn, and require a degree of<space/><link><target>mathematical maturity</target></link><space/>and experience before they can be assimilated.</paragraph><heading level='3'>In music</heading><paragraph>In music, the term<space/><italics>abstraction</italics><space/>can be used to describe improvisatory approaches to interpretation, and may sometimes indicate abandonment of<space/><link><target>tonality</target></link>.<space/><link><target>Atonal</target></link><space/>music has no key signature, and is characterized by the exploration of internal numeric relationships.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.wsu.edu/~dee/GLOSSARY/ABSTRACT.HTM'>Washington State University: Glossary of Abstraction.</link></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In neurology</heading><paragraph><template><target>Further</target><arg>Intelligence</arg><arg>Mental rotation</arg><arg>Mental operations</arg></template>A recent meta-analysis suggests that the verbal system has greater engagement for abstract concepts when the perceptual system is more engaged for processing of concrete concepts. This is because abstract concepts elicit greater brain activity in the inferior frontal gyrus and middle temporal gyrus compared to concrete concepts which elicit greater activity in the posterior cingulate, precuneus, fusiform gyrus, and parahippocampal gyrus.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last1"><space/>Wang<space/></arg><arg name="first1"><space/>Jing<space/></arg><arg name="last2"><space/>Conder<space/></arg><arg name="first2"><space/>Julie A.<space/></arg><arg name="last3"><space/>Blitzer<space/></arg><arg name="first3"><space/>David N.<space/></arg><arg name="last4"><space/>Shinkareva<space/></arg><arg name="first4"><space/>Svetlana V.<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2010<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Neural Representation of Abstract and Concrete Concepts: A Meta-Analysis of Neuroimaging Studies<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Human Brain Mapping<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>31</arg><arg name="issue"><space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>1459–1468</arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1002/hbm.20950<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>Other research into the<space/><link><target>human brain</target></link><space/>suggests that the left and right hemispheres differ in their handling of abstraction. For example, one meta-analysis reviewing human brain lesions has shown a left hemisphere bias during tool usage.<extension extension_name='ref'>James W. Lewis &quot;Cortical Networks Related to Human Use of Tools&quot;<space/><bold>12</bold><space/>(3): 211231<space/><italics>The Neuroscientist</italics><space/>(June 1, 2006).</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In philosophy</heading><paragraph>Abstraction in<space/><link><target>philosophy</target></link><space/>is the process (or, to some, the alleged process) in<space/><link><target>concept</target></link><space/>formation of recognizing some set of common features in<space/><link><target>individual</target><trail>s</trail></link>, and on that basis forming a concept of that feature. The notion of abstraction is important to understanding some philosophical controversies surrounding<space/><link><target>empiricism</target></link><space/>and the<space/><link><target>problem of universals</target></link>. It has also recently become popular in formal logic under<space/><link><target>predicate abstraction</target></link>. Another philosophical tool for discussion of abstraction is<space/><link><target>thought space</target></link>.</paragraph><heading level='3'>In psychology</heading><paragraph><link><target>Carl Jung</target></link>'s definition of abstraction broadened its scope beyond the thinking process to include exactly four mutually exclusive, different complementary psychological functions: sensation, intuition, feeling, and thinking. Together they form a structural totality of the differentiating abstraction process. Abstraction operates in one of these functions when it excludes the simultaneous influence of the other functions and other irrelevancies, such as emotion. Abstraction requires selective use of this structural split of abilities in the psyche. The opposite of abstraction is<space/><link><target>concretism (psychology)</target><part>concretism</part></link>.<space/><italics>Abstraction</italics><space/>is one of Jung's 57 definitions in Chapter XI of<space/><italics><link><target>Psychological Types</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='blockquote'>There is an abstract<space/><italics>thinking</italics>, just as there is abstract<space/><italics>feeling</italics>,<space/><italics>sensation</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>intuition</italics>. Abstract thinking singles out the rational, logical qualities ... Abstract feeling does the same with ... its feeling-values. ... I put abstract feelings on the same level as abstract thoughts. ... Abstract sensation would be aesthetic as opposed to sensuous<space/><italics>sensation</italics><space/>and abstract intuition would be symbolic as opposed to fantastic<space/><italics>intuition</italics>. (Jung, [1921] (1971):par. 678).</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>In social theory</heading><paragraph>In social theory, abstraction is used as both an ideational and material process.<space/><link><target>Alfred Sohn-Rethel</target></link>, asked &quot;Can there be abstraction other than by thought?&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="ReferenceA"></extension><space/>He used the example of commodity abstraction to show that abstraction occurs in practice as people create systems of abstract exchange that extend beyond the immediate physicality of the object and yet have real and immediate consequences. This work was extended through the 'Constitutive Abstraction' approach of writers associated with the Journal<space/><link><target>Arena (Australian publishing co-operative)</target><part>''Arena''</part></link>. Two books that have taken this theme of the abstraction of social relations as an organizing process in human history are<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Nation Formation: Towards a Theory of Abstract Community<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?isbn</arg></template>(1996) and the second volume of Towards a Theory of Abstract Community, published in 2006:<space/><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="title"><space/>Globalism, Nationalism, Tribalism: Bringing Theory Back In—Volume 2 of Towards a Theory of Abstract Community<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.academia.edu/1642214/Globalism_Nationalism_Tribalism_Bringing_Theory_Back_In_author_Sage_Publications_London_2006<space/></arg></template><space/>These books argue that the nation is an abstract community bringing together strangers who will never meet as such; thus constituting materially real and substantial, but abstracted and mediated relations. The books suggest that contemporary processes of globalization and mediatization have contributed to materially abstracting relations between people, with major consequences for how we live our lives.</paragraph><paragraph>It can be easily argued that abstraction is an elementary methodological tool in several disciplines of social science. These disciplines have definite and different man concepts that highlight those aspects of man and his behaviour by idealization that are relevant for the given human science. For example, homo sociologicus is the man as sociology abstracts and idealizes it, depicting man as a social being. Moreover, we could talk about homo cyber sapiens<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Steels<space/></arg><arg name="first">Luc<space/></arg><arg name="title">The Homo Cyber Sapiens, the Robot Homonidus Intelligens, and the ‘Artificial Life’ Approach to Artificial Intelligence<space/></arg><arg name="location">Brussel<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Vrije Universiteit, Artificial Intelligence Laboratory<space/></arg><arg name="year">1995<space/></arg></template></extension><space/>(the man who can extend his biologically determined intelligence thanks to new technologies), or homo creativus<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last"><space/>Inkinen<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Sam<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2009<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Homo Creativus – Creativity and Serendipity Management in Third Generation Science and Technology Parks<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Science and Public Policy<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>36</arg><arg name="issue"><space/>7<space/></arg><arg name="pages"><space/>537–548</arg><arg name="doi"><space/></arg></template></extension><space/>(who is simply creative).<space/></paragraph><paragraph>Abstraction (combined with Weberian<space/><link><target>idealization</target></link>) plays a crucial role in<space/><link><target>economics</target></link>. Breaking away from directly experienced reality was a common trend in 19th century sciences (especially<space/><link><target>physics</target></link>), and this was the effort which was fundamentally determined the way economics tried and still tries to approach the economic aspects of social life. It is abstraction we meet in the case of both Newtons physics and the neoclassical theory, since the goal was to grasp the unchangeable and timeless essence of phenomena. For example,<space/><link><target>Isaac Newton</target><part>Newton</part></link><space/>created the concept of the material point by following the abstraction method so that he abstracted from the dimension and shape of any perceptible object, preserving only inertial and translational motion. Material point is the ultimate and common feature of all bodies.<space/><link><target>Neoclassical economists</target></link><space/>created the indefinitely abstract notion of<space/><link><target>homo oeconomicus</target></link><space/>by following the same procedure. Economists abstract from all individual and personal qualities in order to get to those characteristics that embody the essence of economic activity. Eventually, it is the substance of the economic man that they try to grasp. Any characteristic beyond it only disturbs the functioning of this essential core.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="last">Galbács<space/></arg><arg name="first">Peter<space/></arg><arg name="chapter">Methodological Principles and an Epistemological Introduction</arg><arg name="pages">1–52</arg><arg name="title"><space/>The Theory of New Classical Macroeconomics. A Positive Critique<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>Heidelberg/New York/Dordrecht/London<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Springer<space/></arg><arg name="year">2015<space/></arg><arg name="isbn"><space/>978-3-319-17578-2</arg><arg name="url">http://link.springer.com/book/10.1007%2F978-3-319-17578-2</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikipedia books</target></template><template><target>portal</target><arg>Thinking</arg></template><template><target>Columns</target><arg name="colwidth">14.0em
</arg><arg name="col1">
* [[Abstract and concrete]]
* [[Abstract interpretation]]
* [[Abstract labour and concrete labour]]
* [[Abstract structure]]
* [[Charles Sanders Peirce]]
</arg><arg name="col2">
* [[Conceptual model]]
* [[Emergence]]
* [[Engaged theory]]
* [[Gottlob Frege]]
* [[Hypostatic abstraction]]
* [[Leaky abstraction]]
* [[Lyrical abstraction]]
</arg><arg name="col3">
* [[Nucleophilic abstraction]]
* [[Object of the mind]]
* [[Platonic realism]]
* [[Reification]]{{dn|date</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>References</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>The American Heritage Dictionary of the English Language, 3rd edition</italics>, Houghton Mifflin (1992), hardcover, 2140 pages, ISBN 0-395-44895-6</listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Paul James (academic)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Nation Formation: Towards a Theory of Abstract Community<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://books.google.com.au/books?isbn</arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sage Publications<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>1996</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>Cite book</target><arg name="last"><space/>James<space/></arg><arg name="first"><space/>Paul<space/></arg><arg name="authorlink"><space/>Paul James (academic)<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Globalism, Nationalism, Tribalism: Bringing Theory Back In - Volume 2 of Towards a Theory of Abstract Community<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.academia.edu/1642214/Globalism_Nationalism_Tribalism_Bringing_Theory_Back_In_author_Sage_Publications_London_2006<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2006<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Sage Publications<space/></arg><arg name="location"><space/>London<space/></arg></template></listitem><listitem>Jung, C.G. [1921] (1971).<space/><italics>Psychological Types</italics>, Collected Works, Volume 6, Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press. ISBN 0-691-01813-8.</listitem><listitem>Sohn-Rethel, Alfred (1977)<space/><italics>Intellectual and manual labour: A critique of epistemology</italics>, Humanities Press.</listitem><listitem><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="last">Schmandt-Besserat</arg><arg name="first">Denise</arg><arg name="author-link">Denise Schmandt-Besserat</arg><arg name="title">Decipherment of the Earliest Tablets</arg><arg name="journal">Science</arg><arg name="volume">211</arg><arg name="pages">283–285</arg><arg name="year">1981</arg><arg name="doi">10.1126/science.211.4479.283</arg><arg name="pmid">17748027</arg><arg name="issue">4479
</arg><arg name="bibcode">1981Sci...211..283S</arg></template>.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>abstraction</arg></template><template><target>Wikiquote</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><template><target>InPho</target><arg>idea</arg><arg>2013</arg></template></listitem><listitem><template><target>PhilPapers</target><arg>search</arg><arg>Abstraction</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.utm.edu/research/iep/f/frege.htm'>Internet Encyclopedia of Philosophy: Gottlob Frege</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://originresearch.com/sd/sd1.cfm'>Discussion at The Well concerning Abstraction hierarchy</link></listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>Human intelligence topics</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Authority control</target></template><link><target>Category:Abstraction</target><part></part></link><link><target>Category:Concepts in metaphysics</target></link><link><target>Category:Creativity</target></link><link><target>Category:Problem solving</target></link><link><target>Category:Thought</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>it:Astrazione (arte)</target></link></paragraph></article>