<article title='Bootstrapping'><paragraph><template><target>redirect</target><arg>Bootstrap</arg><arg>a UI web design tool called "Bootstrap"</arg><arg>Bootstrap (front-end framework)</arg></template><template><target>other uses</target></template>In general parlance,<space/><bold>bootstrapping</bold><space/>usually refers to a self-starting process that is supposed to proceed without external input. In<space/><link><target>computer technology</target></link><space/>the term (usually shortened to<space/><bold>booting</bold>) usually refers to the process of loading the basic software into the memory of a computer after power-on or general reset, especially the<space/><link><target>operating system</target></link><space/>which will then take care of loading other software as needed.</paragraph><paragraph>The term appears to have originated in the early 19th century United States (particularly in the phrase &quot;pull oneself over a fence by one's bootstraps&quot;), to mean an absurdly impossible action, an<space/><link><target>adynaton</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.worldwidewords.org/qa/qa-boo2.htm'>World Wide Words: Boot</link>, Michael Quinion</extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="linguist-listserv"><template><target>cite mailing list</target><arg name="url">http://listserv.linguistlist.org/cgi-bin/wa?A2</arg><arg name="title">bootstraps--speculation/questions<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005-08-28</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="examples"><template><target>cite mailing list</target><arg name="url">http://listserv.linguistlist.org/cgi-bin/wa?A2</arg><arg name="title">figurative 'bootstraps'<space/></arg><arg name="date">2005-08-11</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Etymology</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Dr Martens, black, old.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>200px</part><part>A pair of boots with one bootstrap visible</part></link>Tall<space/><link><target>boot</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>may have a tab, loop or handle at the top known as a bootstrap, allowing one to use fingers or a<space/><link><target>Boot jack</target><part>boot hook</part></link><space/>tool to help pulling the boots on. The<space/><link><target>saying</target></link><space/>&quot;to pull oneself up by one's bootstraps&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="examples"></extension><space/>was already in use during the 19th century as an example of an impossible task. The<space/><link><target>idiom</target></link><space/>dates at least to 1834, when it appeared in the<space/><italics>Workingman's Advocate</italics>: &quot;It is conjectured that Mr. Murphee will now be enabled to hand himself over the Cumberland river or a barn yard fence by the straps of his boots.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="Freeman1">Jan Freeman,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/ideas/theword/2009/01/bootstraps_and.html'>Bootstraps and Baron Munchausen</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Boston.com</target></link></italics>, January 27, 2009</extension><space/>In 1860 it appeared in a comment on<space/><link><target>metaphysical philosophy</target></link>: &quot;The attempt of the mind to analyze itself [is] an effort analogous to one who would lift himself by his own bootstraps.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Jan Freeman,<space/><link type='external' href='http://www.boston.com/bostonglobe/ideas/articles/2009/01/25/the_unkindliest_cut/'>The unkindliest cut</link>,<space/><italics><link><target>Boston.com</target></link></italics>, January 25, 2009</extension><space/>Bootstrap as a metaphor, meaning to better oneself by one's own unaided efforts, was in use in 1922.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics><link><target>Ulysses (novel)</target><part>Ulysses</part></link></italics><space/>cited in the Oxford English Dictionary</extension><space/>This metaphor spawned additional metaphors for a series of self-sustaining processes that proceed without external help.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://www.phrases.org.uk/meanings/290800.html'>Phrase Finder</link></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The term is sometimes attributed to a story in<space/><link><target>Rudolf Erich Raspe</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>wikisource:The Surprising Adventures of Baron Munchausen</target><part>The Surprising Adventures of Baron Munchausen</part></link></italics>, but in that story<space/><link><target>Baron Munchausen</target></link><space/>pulls himself (and his horse) out of a swamp by his hair (specifically, his pigtail), not by his bootstraps<template><target>snd</target></template><space/>and no explicit reference to bootstraps has been found elsewhere in the various versions of the Munchausen tales.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Freeman1"></extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Applications</heading><heading level='3'>Computing</heading><heading level='4'>Software loading and execution</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Booting</arg></template><bold>Booting</bold><space/>is the process of starting a computer, specifically with regard to starting its software. The process involves a chain of stages, in which at each stage a smaller simpler program loads and then executes the larger more complicated program of the next stage. It is in this sense that the computer &quot;pulls itself up by its bootstraps&quot;, i.e. it improves itself by its own efforts. Booting is a chain of events that starts with execution of hardware-based procedures and may then hand-off to<space/><link><target>firmware</target></link><space/>and software which is loaded into<space/><link><target>main memory</target></link>. Booting often involves processes such as performing<space/><link><target>power-on self-test</target><part>self-tests</part></link>, loading<space/><link><target>computer configuration</target><part>configuration</part></link><space/>settings, loading a<space/><link><target>BIOS</target></link>,<space/><link><target>resident monitor</target><trail>s</trail></link>, a<space/><link><target>hypervisor</target></link>, an<space/><link><target>operating system</target></link>, or<space/><link><target>utility software</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>The computer term bootstrap began as a metaphor in the 1950s. In computers, pressing a bootstrap button caused a<space/><link><target>hardwired control</target><part>hardwired program</part></link><space/>to read a bootstrap program from an input unit. The computer would then execute the bootstrap program, which caused it to read more program instructions. It became a self-sustaining process that proceeded without external help from manually entered instructions. As a computing term, bootstrap has been used since at least 1953.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="year"><space/>1953<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>The System Design of the IBM Type 701 Computer<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Buchholz, Werner<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Proceedings of the I.R.E.<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>41<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>10<space/></arg><arg name="page"><space/>1273<space/></arg><arg name="doi">10.1109/jrproc.1953.274300</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Software development</heading><paragraph>Bootstrapping can also refer to the development of successively more complex, faster programming environments. The simplest environment will be, perhaps, a very basic text editor (e.g.,<space/><link><target>ed (UNIX)</target><part>ed</part></link>) and an<space/><link><target>Assembly language#Assembler</target><part>assembler</part></link><space/>program. Using these tools, one can write a more complex text editor, and a simple compiler for a higher-level language and so on, until one can have a<space/><link><target>graphical user interface</target><part>graphical</part></link><space/><link><target>integrated development environment</target><part>IDE</part></link><space/>and an extremely<space/><link><target>high-level programming language</target></link>.</paragraph><paragraph>Historically, bootstrapping also refers to an early technique for computer program development on new hardware. The technique described in this paragraph has been replaced by the use of a<space/><link><target>cross compiler</target></link><space/>executed by a pre-existing computer. Bootstrapping in program development began during the 1950s when each program was constructed on paper in decimal code or in binary code, bit by bit (1s and 0s), because there was no high-level computer language, no<space/><link><target>compiler</target></link>, no assembler, and no<space/><link><target>Linker (computing)</target><part>linker</part></link>. A tiny assembler program was hand-coded for a new computer (for example the<space/><link><target>IBM 650</target></link>) which converted a few instructions into binary or decimal code: A1. This simple assembler program was then rewritten in its just-defined<space/><link><target>assembly language</target></link><space/>but with extensions that would enable the use of some additional mnemonics for more complex operation codes. The enhanced assembler's source program was then assembled by its predecessor's executable (A1) into binary or decimal code to give A2, and the cycle repeated (now with those enhancements available), until the entire instruction set was coded, branch addresses were automatically calculated, and other conveniences (such as conditional assembly, macros, optimisations, etc.) established. This was how the early assembly program SOAP (<link><target>Symbolic Optimal Assembly Program</target></link>) was developed. Compilers, linkers, loaders, and utilities were then coded in assembly language, further continuing the bootstrapping process of developing complex software systems by using simpler software.</paragraph><paragraph>The term was also championed by<space/><link><target>Doug Engelbart</target></link><space/>to refer to his belief that organizations could better evolve by improving the process they use for improvement (thus obtaining a compounding effect over time). His<space/><link><target>SRI International</target><part>SRI</part></link><space/>team that developed the<space/><link><target>NLS (computer system)</target><part>NLS</part></link><space/>hypertext system applied this strategy by using the tool they had developed to improve the tool.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Compilers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping (compilers)</arg></template>The development of compilers for new programming languages first developed in an existing language but then rewritten in the new language and compiled by itself, is another example of the bootstrapping notion. Using an existing language to bootstrap a new language is one way to solve the &quot;<link><target>chicken or the egg</target></link>&quot; causality dilemma.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Installers</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Installation (computer programs)</arg></template>During the installation of computer programs it is sometimes necessary to update the installer or package manager itself. The common pattern for this is to use a small executable bootstrapper file (e.g. setup.exe) which updates the installer and starts the real installation after the update. Sometimes the bootstrapper also installs other prerequisites for the software during the bootstrapping process.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Overlay networks</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg>Bootstrapping node</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>A bootstrapping node, also known as a rendezvous host,<extension extension_name='ref' name="Francis01"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Yoid: Extending the Internet Multicast Architecture<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">www.aciri.org<space/></arg><arg name="author">Francis, Paul<space/></arg><arg name="date">2000-04-02<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.cs.cornell.edu/people/francis/yoidArch.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-24</arg></template></extension><space/>is a<space/><link><target>Node (networking)</target><part>node</part></link><space/>in an<space/><link><target>overlay network</target></link><space/>that provides initial configuration information to newly joining nodes so that they may successfully join the overlay network.<extension extension_name='ref' name="sun01"><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.google.com/patents?id</arg><arg name="title">US Patent 7,065,579<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-23<space/></arg><arg name="author">Traversat<space/></arg><arg name="date">2006-06-20<space/></arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension><extension extension_name='ref' name="Saxena01"><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="title">Admission Control in Peer-to-Peer: Design and Performance Evaluation<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">In ACM Workshop on Security of Ad Hoc and Sensor Networks (SASN) 2003<space/></arg><arg name="author">Saxena<space/></arg><arg name="year">2003<space/></arg><arg name="url">http://www.ics.uci.edu/~gts/paps/sty03.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2008-12-24<space/></arg><arg name="display-authors">etal</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='4'>Discrete event simulation</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Discrete event simulation</arg></template>A type of<space/><link><target>computer simulation</target></link><space/>called<space/><link><target>discrete event simulation</target></link><space/>represents the operation of a system as a chronological sequence of events. A technique called<space/><italics>bootstrapping the simulation model</italics><space/>is used, which bootstraps initial data points using a<space/><link><target>pseudorandom number generator</target></link><space/>to schedule an initial set of pending events, which schedule additional events, and with time, the distribution of event times approaches its<space/><link><target>steady state</target></link>the bootstrapping behavior is overwhelmed by steady-state behavior.</paragraph><heading level='4'>Artificial intelligence and machine learning</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrap aggregating<space/></arg><arg><space/>Recursive self improvement</arg></template>Bootstrapping is a technique used to iteratively improve a<space/><link><target>classifier (machine learning)</target><part>classifier</part></link>'s performance. Seed AI is a hypothesized type of<space/><link><target>artificial intelligence</target></link><space/>capable of<space/><link><target>recursive self-improvement</target></link>. Having improved itself, it would become better at improving itself, potentially leading to an exponential increase in intelligence. No such AI is known to exist, but it remains an active field of research.</paragraph><paragraph>Seed AI is a significant part of some theories about the<space/><link><target>technological singularity</target></link>: proponents believe that the development of seed AI will rapidly yield ever-smarter intelligence (via bootstrapping) and thus a new era.<template><target>citation needed</target><arg name="date">September 2014</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='3'>Statistics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping (statistics)<space/></arg><arg><space/>Bootstrapping populations</arg></template>Bootstrapping is a<space/><link><target>resampling (statistics)</target><part>resampling</part></link><space/>technique used to obtain estimates of summary statistics.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Business</heading><paragraph><link><target>Bootstrapping (business)</target><part>Bootstrapping in business</part></link><space/>means starting a business without external help or capital. Such startups fund the development of their company through internal cash flow and are cautious with their expenses.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://venturebeat.com/2008/11/20/the-art-of-the-bootstrap/'>The Art of the Bootstrap, Venture Beat</link></extension><space/>Generally at the start of a venture, a small amount of money will be set aside for the bootstrap process.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Bootstrap"><link type='external' href='http://www.bootstrapbusiness.org/'>Bootstrap</link></extension><space/>Bootstrapping can also be a supplement for<space/><link><target>econometric</target></link><space/>models.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite journal</target><arg name="url"><space/>http://marketing.wharton.upenn.edu/documents/research/Bootstrapping%5b1%5d.pdf<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Judgmental Bootstrapping: Inferring Experts</arg><arg name="author"><space/>J. Scott Armstrong</arg><arg name="journal"><space/>Principles of Forecasting: A Handbook for Researchers and Practitioners<space/></arg><arg name="year"><space/>2001<space/></arg><arg name="publisher"><space/>Kluwer Academic Publishers</arg></template></extension><space/>Bootstrapping was also expanded upon in the book<space/><italics>Bootstrap Business</italics>, by<space/><link><target>Richard J. Christiansen</target><part>Richard Christiansen</part></link>.</paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Startup company</target><part>Startups</part></link><space/>can grow by reinvesting profits in its own growth if bootstrapping costs are low and return on investment is high. This financing approach allows owners to maintain control of their business, enables them to focus on customers instead of investors, and forces them to spend with discipline.<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://vimeo.com/86337488'>Bootstrapping in Entrepreneurship</link></extension><space/></listitem><listitem><link><target>Leveraged buyout</target><trail>s</trail></link>, or highly leveraged or &quot;bootstrap&quot; transactions, occur when an investor acquires a controlling interest in a company's equity and where a significant percentage of the purchase price is financed through leverage, i.e.,&amp;nbsp;borrowing.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Bootstrapping (finance)</target><part>Bootstrapping</part></link><space/>in finance refers to the method to create the<space/><link><target>Spot contract</target><part>spot rate</part></link><space/>curve.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Operation Bootstrap</target></link><space/>(<italics>Operacin Manos a la Obra</italics>) refers to the ambitious projects that industrialized<space/><link><target>Puerto Rico</target></link><space/>in the mid-20th century.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Biology</heading><paragraph><link><target>Richard Dawkins</target></link><space/>in his book<space/><italics>River Out of Eden</italics><extension extension_name='ref'>Richard Dawkins,<space/><italics>River Out of Eden</italics>, pages 23-25, 1995 (paper) ISBN 0-465-06990-8</extension><space/>used the computer bootstrapping concept to explain how biological cells differentiate: &quot;Different cells receive different combinations of chemicals, which switch on different combinations of genes, and some genes work to switch other genes on or off. And so the bootstrapping continues, until we have the full repertoire of different kinds of cells.&quot;</paragraph><heading level='4'>Phylogenetics</heading><paragraph>Bootstrapping analysis gives a way to judge the strength of support for clades on<space/><link><target>phylogenetic tree</target><trail>s</trail></link>. A number is written by a node, which reflects the percentage of bootstrap trees which also resolve the<space/><link><target>clade</target></link><space/>at the endpoints of that branch.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>Cite journal</target><arg name="year"><space/>1996
<space/></arg><arg name="title"><space/>Bootstrap confidence levels for phylogenetic  trees
<space/></arg><arg name="author"><space/>Bradley Efron, Elizabeth Halloran, and Susan Holmes
<space/></arg><arg name="journal"><space/>PNAS
<space/></arg><arg name="volume"><space/>93
<space/></arg><arg name="issue"><space/>23
<space/></arg><arg name="url"><space/>http://www.pnas.org/content/93/23/13429.full.pdf
<space/></arg><arg name="accessdate"><space/>11 June 2013
<space/></arg><arg name="doi"><space/>10.1073/pnas.93.23.13429
</arg></template></extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Law</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping (law)</arg></template>Bootstrapping is a rule preventing the admission of hearsay evidence in conspiracy cases.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Linguistics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping (linguistics)</arg></template>Bootstrapping is a theory of language acquisition.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Physics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrap model</arg></template>Bootstrapping is using very general consistency criteria to determine the form of a quantum theory from some assumptions on the spectrum of particles.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Electronics</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping (electronics)</arg></template>Bootstrapping is a form of positive feedback in analog circuit design.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Electric power grid</heading><paragraph><template><target>Main</target><arg>Black start</arg></template></paragraph><paragraph>An electric power grid is almost never brought down intentionally. Generators and power stations are started and shut down as necessary. A typical power station requires power for start up prior to being able to generate power. This power is obtained from the grid, so if the entire grid is down these stations cannot be started.</paragraph><paragraph>Therefore, to get a grid started, there must be at least a small number of power stations that can start entirely on their own. A<space/><link><target>black start</target></link><space/>is the process of restoring a power station to operation without relying on external power. In the absence of grid power, one or more black starts are used to bootstrap the grid.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Cellular networks</heading><paragraph><template><target>main</target><arg><space/>Bootstrapping Server Function<space/></arg><arg><space/>Generic Bootstrapping Architecture<space/></arg></template>A Bootstrapping Server Function (BSF) is an intermediary element in<space/><link><target>cellular network</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>which provides application independent functions for mutual<space/><link><target>authentication</target></link><space/>of user equipment and servers unknown to each other and for 'bootstrapping' the exchange of secret session keys afterwards. The term 'bootstrapping' is related to building a security relation with a previously unknown device first and to allow installing security elements (keys) in the device and the BSF afterwards.</paragraph><heading level='3'>Media</heading><paragraph>A media bootstrap is the process whereby a story or meme is deliberately (but artificially) produced by self and peer-referential journalism, originally within a tight circle of media content originators, often commencing with stories written within the same media organization. This story is then expanded into a general media &quot;accepted wisdom&quot; with the aim of having it accepted as self-evident &quot;common knowledge&quot; by the reading, listening and viewing publics. The key feature of a media bootstrap is that as little hard, verifiable, external evidence as possible is used to support the story, preference being given to the citation (often unattributed) of other media stories, i.e. &quot;journalists interviewing journalists&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>Because the campaign is usually originated and at least initially concocted internally by a media organization with a particular agenda in mind, within a closed loop of reportage and opinionation, the campaign is said to have &quot;pulled itself up by its own bootstraps&quot;.</paragraph><paragraph>A bootstrap campaign should be distinguished from a genuine news story of genuine interest, such as a natural disaster that kills thousands, or the death of a respected public figure. It is legitimate for these stories to be given coverage across all media platforms. What distinguishes a bootstrap from a real story is the contrived and organized manner in which the bootstrap appears to come out of nowhere. A bootstrap commonly claims to be tapping a hitherto unrecognized phenomenon within society.</paragraph><paragraph>As self-levitating by pulling on one's bootstraps is physically impossible, this is often used by the bootstrappers themselves to deny the possibility that the bootstrap campaign is indeed concocted and artificial. They assert that it has arisen via a groundswell of public opinion. Media campaigns that are openly admitted as concocted (e.g. a public service campaign titled &quot;Let's Clean Up Our City&quot;) are usually ignored by other media organizations for reasons related to competition. On the other hand, the true bootstrap welcomes the participation of other media organizations, indeed encourages it, as this participation gains the bootstrap notoriety and, most importantly, legitimacy.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Bootstrap paradox</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Conceptual metaphor</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Horatio Alger myth</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Mnchhausen trilemma</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Positive feedback</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Robert A. Heinlein</target></link>'s short sci-fi story<space/><italics><link><target>By His Bootstraps</target></link></italics></listitem><listitem><link><target>The Bootstrap Alliance</target></link>, an institute founded by Douglas Engelbart</listitem></list><heading level='2'>References</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg>30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wiktionary</target><arg>bootstrapping</arg><arg>bootstrap</arg><arg>pull oneself up by one's bootstraps</arg></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.allensboots.com/site/page/pg6068-pn_Boot_Glossary_2.html'>Pull straps for boots</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://dictionary.reference.com/browse/bootstrap'>Dictionary.com entries for Bootstrap</link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.thefreedictionary.com/bootstrap'>Freedictionary.com entries for Bootstrap</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>YouTube</target><arg name="id">xQx-tuW9A4Q</arg><arg name="title">A video talk by Douglas Engelbart on Bootstrapping</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.dougengelbart.org/about/bootstrapping-strategy.html'>Engelbart Institute on Bootstrapping Strategies</link></listitem></list><paragraph><link><target>Category:English-language idioms</target></link><link><target>Category:Metaphors</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><link><target>de:Bootstrap</target></link></paragraph></article>