<article title='A_Vindication_of_the_Rights_of_Woman'><paragraph><template><target>EngvarB</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>Use dmy dates</target><arg name="date">September 2013</arg></template><template><target>italic title</target></template><template><target>pp-move-indef</target></template></paragraph><preblock><preline><link><target>File:Vindication1b.jpg</target><part>200px</part><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Page reads &quot;A VINDICATION OF THE RIGHTS OF WOMAN: WITH STRICTURES ON POLITICAL AND MORAL SUBJECTS. BY MARY WOLLSTONECRAFT. PRINTED AT BOSTON, BY PETER EDES FOR THOMAS AND ANDREWS, Faust's Statue, No. 45, Newbury-Street, MDCCXCII.&quot;</part><part>Title page from the first American edition of ''Rights of Woman''</part></link></preline></preblock><paragraph><template><target>Feminist philosophy sidebar</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><bold><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: with Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects</italics></bold><space/>(1792), written by the 18th-century British<space/><link><target>feminist</target></link><space/><link><target>Mary Wollstonecraft</target></link>, is one of the earliest works of<space/><link><target>feminist philosophy</target></link>. In it, Wollstonecraft responds to those educational and political theorists of the 18th century who did not believe women should have an education. She argues that women ought to have an education commensurate with their position in society, claiming that women are essential to the nation because they educate its children and because they could be &quot;companions&quot; to their husbands, rather than mere wives. Instead of viewing women as ornaments to society or property to be traded in marriage, Wollstonecraft maintains that they are human beings deserving of the same fundamental rights as men.</paragraph><paragraph>Wollstonecraft was prompted to write the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>after reading<space/><link><target>Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Prigord</target></link>'s 1791 report to the French<space/><link><target>National Constituent Assembly</target><part>National Assembly</part></link>, which stated that women should only receive a domestic education; she used her commentary on this specific event to launch a broad attack against sexual double standards and to indict men for encouraging women to indulge in excessive emotion. Wollstonecraft wrote the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>hurriedly to respond directly to ongoing events; she intended to write a more thoughtful second volume but died before completing it.</paragraph><paragraph>While Wollstonecraft does call for equality between the sexes in particular areas of life, such as morality, she does not explicitly state that men and women are equal. Her ambiguous statements regarding the equality of the sexes have since made it difficult to classify Wollstonecraft as a modern feminist, particularly since the word and the concept were unavailable to her. Although it is commonly assumed now that the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>was unfavourably received, this is a modern misconception based on the belief that Wollstonecraft was as reviled during her lifetime as she became after the publication of<space/><link><target>William Godwin</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Memoirs of the Author of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</target></link></italics><space/>(1798). The<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>was actually well received when it was first published in 1792. One biographer has called it &quot;perhaps the most original book of [Wollstonecraft's] century&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sunstein, 3.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Historical context</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Talleyrand 01.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>alt=Portrait of a man, showing his head and shoulders. He is wearing a black jacket with a high-necked collar and a white shirt tied in a bow. His head is adorned by a curly blonde wig.</part><part><link><target>Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Prigord</target><part>Talleyrand</part></link>, by<space/><link><target>Pierre-Paul Prud'hon</target></link></part></link><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics><space/>was written against the tumultuous background of the<space/><link><target>French Revolution</target></link><space/>and the debates that it spawned in Britain. In a lively and sometimes vicious pamphlet war, now referred to as the<space/><italics><link><target>Revolution Controversy</target></link></italics>, British political commentators addressed topics ranging from representative government to human rights to the separation of church and state, many of these issues having been raised in France first. Wollstonecraft first entered this fray in 1790 with<space/><italics><link><target>A Vindication of the Rights of Men</target></link></italics>, a response to<space/><link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Reflections on the Revolution in France</target></link></italics><space/>(1790).<extension extension_name='ref' name="MS1112">Macdonald and Scherf, &quot;Introduction&quot;, 1112.</extension><space/>In his<space/><italics>Reflections</italics>, Burke criticised the view of many British thinkers and writers who had welcomed the early stages of the French revolution. While they saw the revolution as analogous to Britain's own<space/><link><target>Glorious Revolution</target></link><space/>in 1688, which had restricted the powers of the monarchy, Burke argued that the appropriate historical analogy was the<space/><link><target>English Civil War</target></link><space/>(16421651) in which<space/><link><target>Charles I of England</target><part>Charles I</part></link><space/>had been executed in 1649. He viewed the French revolution as the violent overthrow of a legitimate government. In<space/><italics>Reflections</italics><space/>he argues that citizens do not have the right to revolt against their government because civilisation is the result of social and political consensus; its traditions cannot be continually challengedthe result would be anarchy. One of the key arguments of Wollstonecraft's<space/><italics>Rights of Men</italics>, published just six weeks after Burke's<space/><italics>Reflections</italics>, is that rights cannot be based on tradition; rights, she argues, should be conferred because they are reasonable and just, regardless of their basis in tradition.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 4344.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>When<space/><link><target>Charles Maurice de Talleyrand-Prigord</target></link><space/>presented his<space/><italics>Rapport sur l'instruction publique</italics><space/>(1791) to the<space/><link><target>National Assembly (French Revolution)</target><part>National Assembly</part></link><space/>in France, Wollstonecraft was galvanised to respond.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 107; Sapiro, 2627.</extension><space/>In his recommendations for a national system of education, Talleyrand had written:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Let us bring up women, not to aspire to advantages which the Constitution denies them, but to know and appreciate those which it guarantees them&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. Men are destined to live on the stage of the world. A public education suits them: it early places before their eyes all the scenes of life: only the proportions are different. The paternal home is better for the education of women; they have less need to learn to deal with the interests of others, than to accustom themselves to a calm and secluded life.<extension extension_name='ref'>Talleyrand, &quot;Rapport sur l'instruction publique&quot;, reprinted in<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 39495.</extension></extension><link><target>File:Marie-Olympe-de-Gouges.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>right</part><part>alt=Portrait of a woman, showing her head, with a grey wig. Two large curls are sitting at the nape of her neck. Her shoulders are covered with a filmy, cream-coloured shawl.</part><part><link><target>Olympe de Gouges</target></link></part></link>Wollstonecraft dedicated the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>to Talleyrand: &quot;Having read with great pleasure a pamphlet which you have lately published, I dedicate this volume to you; to induce you to reconsider the subject, and maturely weigh what I have advanced respecting the rights of woman and national education.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 101.</extension><space/>At the end of 1791, French feminist<space/><link><target>Olympe de Gouges</target></link><space/>had published her<space/><italics><link><target>Declaration of the Rights of Woman and the Female Citizen</target></link></italics>, and the question of women's rights became central to political debates in both France and Britain.<extension extension_name='ref' name="MS1112"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is an extension of Wollstonecraft's arguments in the<space/><italics>Rights of Men</italics>. In the<space/><italics>Rights of Men</italics>, as the title suggests, she is concerned with the rights of particular men (18th-century British men) while in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, she is concerned with the rights afforded to &quot;woman&quot;, an abstract category. She does not isolate her argument to 18th-century women or British women. The first chapter of the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>addresses the issue of<space/><link><target>natural rights</target></link><space/>and asks who has those inalienable rights and on what grounds. She answers that since natural rights are given by God, for one segment of society to deny them to another segment is a sin.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor, 1056; Kelly, 107.</extension><space/><italics>The Rights of Woman</italics><space/>thus engages not only specific events in France and in Britain but also larger questions being raised by contemporary<space/><link><target>Political philosophy</target><part>political philosophers</part></link><space/>such as<space/><link><target>John Locke</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sapiro, 18284.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Themes</heading><paragraph>Wollstonecraft did not employ the formal argumentation or logical prose style common to 18th-century philosophical writing when composing her own works. The<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is a long essay that introduces all of its major topics in the opening chapters and then repeatedly returns to them, each time from a different point of view. It also adopts a hybrid tone that combines rational argument with the fervent rhetoric of<space/><link><target>sensibility</target></link>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="K110">Kelly, 110.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the 18th century,<space/><italics>sensibility</italics><space/>was a physical phenomenon that came to be attached to a specific set of moral beliefs. Physicians and anatomists believed that the more sensitive people's nerves, the more emotionally affected they would be by their surroundings. Since women were thought to have keener nerves than men, it was also believed that women were more emotional than men.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BB9">Barker-Benfield, 9.</extension><space/>The emotional excess associated with sensibility also theoretically produced an ethic of compassion: those with sensibility could easily sympathise with people in pain. Thus historians have credited the discourse of sensibility and those who promoted it with the increased humanitarian efforts, such as the<space/><link><target>abolitionism</target><part>movement to abolish the slave trade</part></link>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Barker-Benfield, 224.</extension><space/>But sensibility also paralysed those who had too much of it; as scholar G. J. Barker-Benfield explains, &quot;an innate refinement of nerves was also identifiable with greater suffering, with weakness, and a susceptibility to disorder&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="BB9"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>By the time Wollstonecraft was writing the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, sensibility had already been under sustained attack for a number of years.<extension extension_name='ref'>Todd,<space/><italics>Sensibility</italics>, 144.</extension><space/>Sensibility, which had initially promised to draw individuals together through sympathy, was now viewed as &quot;profoundly separatist&quot;; novels, plays, and poems that employed the language of sensibility asserted individual rights, sexual freedom, and unconventional familial relationships based only upon feeling.<extension extension_name='ref'>Todd,<space/><italics>Sensibility</italics>, 136.</extension><space/>Furthermore, as<space/><link><target>Janet Todd</target></link>, another scholar of sensibility, argues, &quot;to many in Britain the cult of sensibility seemed to have feminized the nation, given women undue prominence, and emasculated men.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Todd,<space/><italics>Sensibility</italics>, 133.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Rational education</heading><paragraph>One of Wollstonecraft's central arguments in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is that women should be educated rationally to give them the opportunity to contribute to society. In the 18th century, it was often assumed by both educational philosophers and<space/><link><target>conduct book</target></link><space/>writers, who wrote what one might think of as early self-help books,<extension extension_name='ref'>Batchelor, Jennie. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://www.litencyc.com/php/stopics.php?rec=true&amp;amp;UID=216'>Conduct Book</link>.&quot;<space/><italics>The Literary Encyclopedia</italics>. Retrieved on 14 May 2007.</extension><space/>that women were incapable of rational or abstract thought. Women, it was believed, were too susceptible to sensibility and too fragile to be able to think clearly. Wollstonecraft, along with other female reformers such as<space/><link><target>Catharine Macaulay</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Hester Chapone</target></link>, maintained that women were indeed capable of rational thought and deserved to be educated. She argued this point in her own conduct book,<space/><italics><link><target>Thoughts on the Education of Daughters</target></link></italics><space/>(1787), in her children's book,<space/><italics><link><target>Original Stories from Real Life</target></link></italics><space/>(1788), as well as in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 169ff; Kelly, 123; Taylor, 1415; Sapiro, 2728; 24344.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Stating in her preface that &quot;my main argument is built on this simple principle, that if [woman] be not prepared by education to become the companion of man, she will stop the progress of knowledge and virtue; for truth must be common to all&quot;, Wollstonecraft contends that society will degenerate without educated women, particularly because mothers are the primary educators of young children.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 102; Sapiro, 15455.</extension><space/>She attributes the problem of uneducated women to men and &quot;a false system of education, gathered from the books written on this subject by men who [consider] females rather as women than human creatures&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 109.</extension><space/>Women are capable of rationality; it only appears that they are not, because men have refused to educate them and encouraged them to be frivolous (Wollstonecraft describes silly women as &quot;spaniels&quot; and &quot;toys&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 144.</extension>).<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 12426; Taylor, 23437; Sapiro, 12930.</extension><space/>While stressing it is of the same kind, she entertains the notion that women might not be able to attain the same degree of knowledge that men do.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Tong"><template><target>cite book</target><arg name="author">Tong, Rosemarie</arg><arg name="title">Feminist Thought: A More Comprehensive Introduction</arg><arg name="year">2009</arg><arg name="edition">3</arg><arg name="publisher">Westview Press (Perseus Books)</arg><arg name="isbn">978-0-8133-4375-4</arg><arg name="page">20</arg></template></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Wollstonecraft attacks conduct book writers such as<space/><link><target>James Fordyce</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>John Gregory (moralist)</target><part>John Gregory</part></link><space/>as well as educational philosophers such as<space/><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target></link><space/>who argue that a woman does not need a rational education. (Rousseau famously argues in<space/><italics><link><target>Emile: Or, On Education</target><part>Emile</part></link></italics><space/>(1762) that women should be educated for the pleasure of men; Wollstonecraft, infuriated by this argument, attacks not only it but also Rousseau himself.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 126; Taylor, 1415; Sapiro, 13031.</extension>) Intent on illustrating the limitations that contemporary educational theory placed upon women, Wollstonecraft writes, &quot;taught from their infancy that beauty is woman's sceptre, the mind shapes itself to the body, and, roaming round its gilt cage, only seeks to adorn its prison&quot;,<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 157.</extension><space/>implying that without this damaging ideology, which encourages young women to focus their attention on beauty and outward accomplishments, they could achieve much more. Wives could be the rational &quot;companions&quot; of their husbands and even pursue careers should they so choose: &quot;women might certainly study the art of healing, and be physicians as well as nurses. And midwifery, decency seems to<space/><link><target>wikt:allot</target><part>allot</part></link><space/>to them&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. they might, also, study politics&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. Business of various kinds, they might likewise pursue.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 286; see also Kelly, 12524; Taylor, 1415.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>For Wollstonecraft, &quot;the most perfect education&quot; is &quot;an exercise of the understanding as is best calculated to strengthen the body and form the heart. Or, in other words, to enable the individual to attach such habits of virtue as will render it independent.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 129.</extension><space/>In addition to her broad philosophical arguments, Wollstonecraft lays out a specific plan for national education to counter<space/><link><target>Talleyrand</target></link>'s. In Chapter 12, &quot;On National Education&quot;, she proposes that children be sent to<space/><link><target>day school</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>as well as given some education at home &quot;to inspire a love of home and domestic pleasures&quot;, and that such schools be free for children &quot;five to nine years of age&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><template><target>cite web</target><arg name="url">http://www.infed.org/archives/e-texts/wollstonecraft_on_national_education.htm<space/></arg><arg name="title">Mary Wollstonecraft - on national education<space/></arg><arg name="publisher">Infed.org<space/></arg><arg name="date"><space/></arg><arg name="accessdate">2014-02-13</arg></template></extension><space/>She also maintains that schooling should be<space/><link><target>coeducation</target><part>co-educational</part></link>, contending that men and women, whose marriages are &quot;the cement of society&quot;, should be &quot;educated after the same model&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, Chapter 12; see also, Kelly, 12425; 13334; Sapiro, 237ff.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Feminism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Johann Heinrich Fssli 049.jpg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Three women sitting around a small table, one sewing, one sitting in front of a small cup. All three are drawn to look almost horrific. The third woman looks as if she has two heads, but it may be that there are four women. The women's heads do not look as if they are comfortable on their bodies. The palette of the picture is dark red, black, brown, and almond.</part><part>''The Debutante'' (1807) by<space/><link><target>Henry Fuseli</target></link>; &quot;Woman, the victim of male social conventions, is tied to the wall, made to sew and guarded by governesses. The picture reflects Mary Wollstonecraft's views in ''The Rights of Women''<space/><template><target>sic</target></template>&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Tomory, Peter.<space/><italics>The Life and Art of Henry Fuseli.</italics><space/>New York: Praeger Publishers, 1972; p. 217.<space/><template><target>LCCN</target><arg>72077546</arg></template>.</extension></part></link>It is debatable to what extent the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is a<space/><link><target>feminist</target></link><space/>text; because the definitions of<space/><italics>feminist</italics><space/>vary, different scholars have come to different conclusions. Wollstonecraft would never have referred to her text as feminist because the words<space/><italics>feminist</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>feminism</italics><space/>were not coined until the 1890s.<extension extension_name='ref'><italics>Feminist</italics><space/>and<space/><italics>feminism</italics>.<space/><italics>Oxford English Dictionary</italics>. Retrieved on 17 September 2007.</extension><space/>Moreover, there was no<space/><link><target>feminist movement</target></link><space/>to speak of during Wollstonecraft's lifetime. In the introduction to her seminal work on Wollstonecraft's thought,<space/><link><target>Barbara Taylor</target></link><space/>writes:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Describing [Wollstonecraft's philosophy] as feminist is problematic, and I do it only after much consideration. The label is of course anachronistic&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. Treating Wollstonecraft's thought as an anticipation of nineteenth and twentieth-century feminist argument has meant sacrificing or distorting some of its key elements. Leading examples of this&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. have been the widespread neglect of her religious beliefs, and the misrepresentation of her as a bourgeois liberal, which together have resulted in the displacement of a religiously inspired utopian radicalism by a secular, class-partisan reformism as alien to Wollstonecraft's political project as her dream of a divinely promised age of universal happiness is to our own. Even more important however has been the imposition on Wollstonecraft of a heroic-individualist brand of politics utterly at odds with her own ethically driven case for women's emancipation. Wollstonecraft's leading ambition for women was that they should attain virtue, and it was to this end that she sought their liberation.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor, 12; see also, 5557; see also Sapiro, 25759.</extension></extension>In the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, Wollstonecraft does not make the claim for gender equality using the same arguments or the same language that late 19th- and 20th century feminists later would. For instance, rather than unequivocally stating that men and women are equal, Wollstonecraft contends that men and women are equal in the eyes of God, which means that they are both subject to the same moral law.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 126, 146; Taylor, 105106; 11820.</extension><space/>For Wollstonecraft, men and women are equal in the most important areas of life. While such an idea may not seem revolutionary to 21st-century readers, its implications were revolutionary during the 18th century. For example, it implied that both men and womennot just womenshould be modest<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 102 and 252.</extension><space/>and respect the sanctity of marriage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 274.</extension><space/>Wollstonecraft's argument exposed the sexual double standard of the late 18th century and demanded that men adhere to the same virtues demanded of women.</paragraph><paragraph>However, Wollstonecraft's arguments for equality stand in contrast to her statements respecting the superiority of masculine strength and valour.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 110; Sapiro, 12021.</extension><space/>Wollstonecraft famously and ambiguously states:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>Let it not be concluded, that I wish to invert the order of things; I have already granted, that, from the constitution of their bodies, men seem to be designed by Providence to attain a greater degree of virtue. I speak collectively of the whole sex; but I see not the shadow of a reason to conclude that their virtues should differ in respect to their nature. In fact, how can they, if virtue has only one eternal standard? I must therefore, if I reason consequentially, as strenuously maintain that they have the same simple direction, as that there is a God.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 135.</extension></extension></paragraph><paragraph>Moreover, Wollstonecraft calls on men, rather than women, to initiate the social and political changes she outlines in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>. Because women are uneducated, they cannot alter their own situationmen must come to their aid.<extension extension_name='ref'>Poovey, 79; Kelly, 135.</extension><space/>Wollstonecraft writes at the end of her chapter &quot;Of the Pernicious Effects Which Arise from the Unnatural Distinctions Established in Society&quot;:<extension extension_name='blockquote'>I then would<space/><link><target>wikt:fain</target><part>fain</part></link><space/>convince reasonable men of the importance of some of my remarks; and prevail on them to weigh dispassionately the whole tenor of my observations.&amp;nbsp; I appeal to their understandings; and, as a fellow-creature, claim, in the name of my sex, some interest in their hearts. I entreat them to assist to emancipate their companion, to make her a help meet for them! Would men but generously snap our chains, and be content with rational fellowship instead of slavish obedience, they would find us more observant daughters, more affectionate sisters, more faithful wives, more reasonable mothers&amp;nbsp; in a word, better citizens.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 288.</extension></extension>It is Wollstonecraft's last novel,<space/><italics><link><target>Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman</target></link></italics><space/>(1798), the fictionalised sequel to the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, that is usually considered her most radical feminist work.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor, Chapter 9; Sapiro, 37; 149; 266.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Sensibility</heading><paragraph>One of Wollstonecraft's most scathing criticisms in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is against false and excessive<space/><link><target>sensibility</target></link>, particularly in women. She argues that women who succumb to sensibility are &quot;blown about by every momentary gust of feeling&quot;; because these women are &quot;the prey of their senses&quot;, they cannot think rationally.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 177.</extension><space/>In fact, not only do they do harm to themselves but they also do harm to all of civilisation: these are not women who can refine civilisation these are women who will destroy it. But reason and feeling are not independent for Wollstonecraft; rather, she believes that they should inform each other. For Wollstonecraft, as for the important 18th-century philosopher<space/><link><target>David Hume</target></link>, the passions underpin all reason.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jones, 46.</extension><space/>This was a theme that she would return to throughout her career, but particularly in her novels<space/><italics><link><target>Mary: A Fiction</target></link></italics><space/>(1788) and<space/><italics><link><target>Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman</target></link></italics>.</paragraph><paragraph>As part of her argument that women should not be overly influenced by their feelings, Wollstonecraft emphasises that they should not be constrained by or made slaves to their bodies or their sexual feelings.<extension extension_name='ref'>See, for example, Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 25960; Taylor, 11617.</extension><space/>This particular argument has led many modern feminists to suggest that Wollstonecraft intentionally avoids granting women any sexual desire. Cora Kaplan argues that the &quot;negative and prescriptive assault on female sexuality&quot; is a &quot;<italics><link><target>leitmotif</target></link></italics>&quot; of the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kaplan, &quot;Wild Nights&quot;, 35.</extension><space/>For example, Wollstonecraft advises her readers to &quot;calmly let passion subside into friendship&quot; in the ideal companionate marriage (that is, in the ideal of a love-based marriage that was developing at the time).<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 249.</extension><space/>It would be better, she writes, when &quot;two virtuous young people marry . . . if some circumstances checked their passion&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="W192">Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 192.</extension><space/>According to Wollstonecraft, &quot;love and friendship cannot subsist in the same bosom&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="W192"></extension><space/>As Mary Poovey explains, &quot;Wollstonecraft betrays her fear that female desire might in fact court man's lascivious and degrading attentions, that the subordinate position women have been given might even be deserved. Until women can transcend their fleshly desires and fleshly forms, they will be hostage to the body.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Poovey, 76.</extension><space/>If women are not interested in sexuality, they cannot be dominated by men. Wollstonecraft worries that women are consumed with &quot;romantic wavering&quot;, that is, they are interested only in satisfying their lusts.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 194.</extension><space/>Because the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>eliminates sexuality from a woman's life, Kaplan contends, it &quot;expresses a violent antagonism to the sexual&quot; while at the same time &quot;exaggerat[ing] the importance of the sensual in the everyday life of women&quot;. Wollstonecraft was so determined to wipe sexuality from her picture of the ideal woman that she ended up foregrounding it by insisting upon its absence.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kaplan, &quot;Wild Nights&quot;, 41.</extension><space/>But as Kaplan and others have remarked, Wollstonecraft may have been forced to make this sacrifice: &quot;it is important to remember that the notion of woman as politically enabled and independent [was] fatally linked [during the eighteenth century] to the unrestrained and vicious exercise of her sexuality.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kaplan, &quot;Wild Nights&quot;, 33; see also Taylor, 11819; Taylor, 138ff.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Republicanism</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:Eugne Delacroix - La libert guidant le peuple.jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>left</part><part>alt=Men with guns being led by a half-naked woman who is holding the French flag. She and they are walking over dead bodies. The painting is structured like a triangle, with the woman at the apex. The dead are lying at the base of the triangle.</part><part>''<link><target>Liberty Leading the People</target></link>'' by<space/><link><target>Eugne Delacroix</target></link><space/>(1833)</part></link><link><target>Claudia L. Johnson (scholar)</target><part>Claudia Johnson</part></link>, a prominent Wollstonecraft scholar, has called the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>&quot;a republican manifesto&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 24.</extension><space/>Johnson contends that Wollstonecraft is hearkening back to the<space/><link><target>Commonwealth men</target><part>Commonwealth</part></link><space/>tradition of the 17th century and attempting to reestablish a<space/><link><target>republicanism</target><part>republican</part></link><space/>ethos. In Wollstonecraft's version, there would be strong, but separate, masculine and feminine roles for citizens.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 29; see also Taylor, 21122; Sapiro, 8283.</extension><space/>According to Johnson, Wollstonecraft &quot;denounces the collapse of proper sexual distinction as the leading feature of her age, and as the grievous consequence of sentimentality itself. The problem undermining society in her view is feminized men&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 23.</extension><space/>If men feel free to adopt both the masculine position and the sentimental feminine position, she argues, women have no position open to them in society.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 45.</extension><space/>Johnson therefore sees Wollstonecraft as a critic, in both the<space/><italics><link><target>A Vindication of the Rights of Men</target><part>Rights of Men</part></link></italics><space/>and the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, of the &quot;masculinization of sensitivity&quot; in such works as<space/><link><target>Edmund Burke</target></link>'s<space/><italics><link><target>Reflections on the Revolution in France</target></link></italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Johnson, 30.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>Wollstonecraft adheres to a version of republicanism that includes a belief in the eventual overthrow of all titles, including the monarchy. She also briefly suggests that all men and women should be represented in government. But the bulk of her &quot;political criticism,&quot; as Chris Jones, a Wollstonecraft scholar, explains, &quot;is couched predominantly in terms of morality&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="J43">Jones, 43.</extension><space/>Her definition of virtue focuses on the individual's happiness rather than, for example, the good of the entire society.<extension extension_name='ref' name="J43"></extension><space/>This is reflected in her explanation of<space/><link><target>natural rights</target></link>. Because rights ultimately proceed from God, Wollstonecraft maintains that there are duties, tied to those rights, incumbent upon each and every person. For Wollstonecraft, the individual is taught republicanism and benevolence within the family; domestic relations and familial ties are crucial to her understanding of social cohesion and patriotism.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jones, 46; Taylor, 21122;<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 101102, for example.</extension></paragraph><heading level='3'>Class</heading><paragraph>In many ways the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is inflected by a<space/><link><target>bourgeoisie</target><part>bourgeois</part></link><space/>view of the world, as is its direct predecessor the<space/><italics><link><target>A Vindication of the Rights of Men</target><part>Rights of Men</part></link></italics>. Wollstonecraft addresses her text to the middle class, which she calls the &quot;most natural state&quot;. She also frequently praises modesty and industry, virtues which, at the time, were associated with the middle class.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 128ff; Taylor, 16768; Sapiro, 27.</extension><space/>From her position as a middle-class writer arguing for a middle-class ethos, Wollstonecraft also attacks the wealthy, criticising them using the same arguments she employs against women. She points out the &quot;false-refinement, immorality, and vanity&quot; of the rich, calling them &quot;weak, artificial beings, raised above the common wants and affections of their race, in a premature unnatural manner [who] undermine the very foundation of virtue, and spread corruption through the whole mass of society&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 111; see also Taylor, 15961; Sapiro, 9192.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>But Wollstonecraft's criticisms of the wealthy do not necessarily reflect a concomitant sympathy for the poor. For her, the poor are fortunate because they will never be trapped by the snares of wealth: &quot;Happy is it when people have the cares of life to struggle with; for these struggles prevent their becoming a prey to enervating vices, merely from idleness!&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 169.</extension><space/>Moreover, she contends that charity has only negative consequences because, as Jones puts it, she &quot;sees it as sustaining an unequal society while giving the appearance of virtue to the rich&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Jones, 45; see also Taylor, 21819; Sapiro, 9192.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>In her national plan for education, she retains class distinctions (with an exception for the intelligent), suggesting that: &quot;After the age of nine, girls and boys, intended for domestic employments, or mechanical trades, ought to be removed to other schools, and receive instruction, in some measure appropriated to the destination of each individual . . . The young people of superior abilities, or fortune, might now be taught, in another school, the dead and living languages, the elements of science, and continue the study of history and politics, on a more extensive scale, which would not exclude polite literature.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 311; Kelly, 13233.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Rhetoric and style</heading><paragraph><link><target>File:EmileTitle.jpeg</target><part>right</part><part>thumb</part><part>alt=Page reads &quot;mile, ou de L'Education. Par J. J. Rousseau, Citoyen de Genve....Tome Premier. A La Haye, Chez jean Neaulme, Libraire. M.DCC.LXII....&quot;</part><part><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target><part>Rousseau's</part></link><space/>''<link><target>Emile: Or, On Education</target><part>Emile</part></link>'' (1762)</part></link>In attempting to navigate the cultural expectations of female writers and the generic conventions of political and philosophical discourse, Wollstonecraft, as she does throughout her<space/><italics><link><target>wikt:oeuvre</target><part>oeuvre</part></link></italics>, constructs a unique blend of masculine and feminine styles in the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref' name="K109">Kelly, 109.</extension><space/>She utilises the language of philosophy, referring to her work as a &quot;treatise&quot; with &quot;arguments&quot; and &quot;principles&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref' name="K109"></extension><space/>However, Wollstonecraft also uses a personal tone, employing &quot;I&quot; and &quot;you&quot;, dashes and exclamation marks, and autobiographical references to create a distinctly feminine voice in the text.<extension extension_name='ref' name="K110"></extension><space/>The<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>further hybridizes its genre by weaving together elements of the conduct book, the short essay, and the novel, genres often associated with women, while at the same time claiming that these genres could be used to discuss philosophical topics such as rights.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 11314; Taylor, 5153.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Although Wollstonecraft argues against excessive<space/><link><target>sensibility</target></link>, the rhetoric of the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>is at times heated and attempts to provoke the reader. Many of the most emotional comments in the book are directed at<space/><link><target>Jean-Jacques Rousseau</target><part>Rousseau</part></link>. For example, after excerpting a long passage from<space/><italics><link><target>Emile: Or, On Education</target><part>Emile</part></link></italics><space/>(1762), Wollstonecraft pithily states, &quot;I shall make no other comments on this ingenious passage, than just to observe, that it is the philosophy of lasciviousness.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 162.</extension><space/>A mere page later, after indicting Rousseau's plan for female education, she writes &quot;I must relieve myself by drawing another picture.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 163.</extension><space/>These terse exclamations are meant to draw the reader to her side of the argument (it is assumed that the reader will agree with them). While she claims to write in a plain style so that her ideas will reach the broadest possible audience,<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 11112.</extension><space/>she actually combines the plain, rational language of the political treatise with the poetic, passionate language of sensibility to demonstrate that one can combine rationality and sensibility in the same self.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 109ff; Sapiro, 207208.</extension><space/>Wollstonecraft defends her positions not only with reasoned argument but also with ardent rhetoric.</paragraph><paragraph>In her efforts to vividly describe the condition of women within society, Wollstonecraft employs several different analogies.<extension extension_name='ref'>Kelly, 118ff; Sapiro, 222.</extension><space/>She often compares women to slaves, arguing that their ignorance and powerlessness places them in that position. But at the same time, she also compares them to &quot;capricious tyrants&quot; who use cunning and deceit to manipulate the men around them. At one point, she reasons that a woman can become either a slave or tyrant, which she describes as two sides of the same coin.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 158; Sapiro, 126.</extension><space/>Wollstonecraft also compares women to soldiers; like military men, they are valued only for their appearance. And like the rich, women's &quot;softness&quot; has &quot;debased mankind&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft,<space/><italics>Vindications</italics>, 165; Taylor, 15961; Sapiro, 12426.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Revision</heading><paragraph>Wollstonecraft was forced to write the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>hurriedly to respond to<space/><link><target>Talleyrand</target></link><space/>and ongoing events. Upon completing the work, she wrote to her friend<space/><link><target>William Roscoe</target></link>: &quot;I am dissatisfied with myself for not having done justice to the subject.&amp;nbsp; Do not suspect me of false modesty&amp;nbsp; I mean to say that had I allowed myself more time I could have written a better book, in every sense of the word&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;.&amp;nbsp;. I intend to finish the next volume before I begin to print, for it is not pleasant to have the Devil coming for the conclusion of a sheet fore it is written.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Wollstonecraft, Mary.<space/><italics>The Collected Letters of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Ed. Janet Todd. New York: Penguin Books (2003), 19394.</extension><space/>When Wollstonecraft revised the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>for the second edition, she took the opportunity not only to fix small spelling and grammar mistakes but also to bolster the feminist claims of her argument.<extension extension_name='ref'>Macdonald and Scherf, &quot;Introduction&quot;, 23 and Mellor, 14142.</extension><space/>She changed some of her statements regarding female and male difference to reflect a greater equality between the sexes.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 14142.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>Wollstonecraft never wrote the second part to the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman,</italics><space/>although<space/><link><target>William Godwin</target></link><space/>published her &quot;Hints&quot;, which were &quot;chiefly designed to have been incorporated in the second part of the<space/><italics>Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics>&quot;, in the posthumous collection of her works.<extension extension_name='ref'>Macdonald and Scherf, Appendix C.</extension><space/>However, she did begin writing the novel<space/><italics><link><target>Maria: or, The Wrongs of Woman</target></link></italics>, which most scholars consider a fictionalised sequel to the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>. It was unfinished at her death and also included in the<space/><italics>Posthumous Works</italics><space/>published by Godwin.<extension extension_name='ref'>Sapiro, 3031.</extension></paragraph><heading level='2'>Reception and legacy</heading><paragraph><link><target>Image:Mary Wollstonecraft by John Opie (c. 1797).jpg</target><part>thumb</part><part>250px</part><part>alt=Left-looking half-length portrait of a possibly pregnant woman in a white dress</part><part>''Mary Wollstonecraft'' by<space/><link><target>John Opie</target></link><space/>(c. 1797)</part></link>When it was first published in 1792, the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>was reviewed favourably by the<space/><italics><link><target>Analytical Review</target></link></italics>, the<space/><italics>General Magazine</italics>, the<space/><italics>Literary Magazine</italics>,<space/><italics>New York Magazine</italics>, and the<space/><italics>Monthly Review</italics>, although the assumption persists even today that<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>received hostile reviews.<extension extension_name='ref'>Janes, 293; Sapiro, 2829.</extension><space/>It was almost immediately released in a second edition in 1792, several American editions appeared, and it was translated into French. Taylor writes that &quot;it was an immediate success&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Taylor, 25; see also, Janes, 293302; Wardle, 15758; Kelly, 13536; Sapiro 2829.</extension><space/>Moreover, other writers such as<space/><link><target>Mary Hays</target></link><space/>and<space/><link><target>Mary Robinson (poet)</target><part>Mary Robinson</part></link><space/>specifically alluded to Wollstonecraft's text in their own works. Hays cited the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>in her novel<space/><italics><link><target>Memoirs of Emma Courtney</target></link></italics><space/>(1796) and modelled her female characters after Wollstonecraft's ideal woman.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 14344 and 146.</extension><space/>Although female conservatives such as<space/><link><target>Hannah More</target></link><space/>excoriated Wollstonecraft personally, they actually shared many of the same values. As the scholar Anne Mellor has shown, both More and Wollstonecraft wanted a society founded on &quot;Christian virtues of rational benevolence, honesty, personal virtue, the fulfillment of social duty, thrift, sobriety, and hard work&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 147.</extension><space/>During the early 1790s, many writers within British society were engaged in an intense debate regarding the position of women in society. For example, the respected poet and essayist<space/><link><target>Anna Laetitia Barbauld</target></link><space/>and Wollstonecraft sparred back and forth; Barbauld published several poems responding to Wollstonecraft's work and Wollstonecraft commented on them in footnotes to the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 153.</extension><space/>The work also provoked outright hostility. The<space/><link><target>bluestocking</target></link><space/><link><target>Elizabeth Carter</target></link><space/>was unimpressed with the work.<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gordon, 154">Gordon, 154</extension><space/><link><target>Thomas Taylor (neoplatonist)</target><part>Thomas Taylor</part></link>, the<space/><link><target>Neoplatonist</target></link><space/>translator who had been a landlord to the Wollstonecraft family in the late 1770s, swiftly wrote a satire called<space/><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Brutes</italics>: if women have rights, why not<space/><link><target>animal rights</target><part>animals too</part></link>?<extension extension_name='ref' name="Gordon, 154"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>After Wollstonecraft died in 1797, her husband<space/><link><target>William Godwin</target></link><space/>published his<space/><italics><link><target>Memoirs of the Author of A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</target></link></italics><space/>(1798). He revealed much about her private life that had previously not been known to the public: her illegitimate child, her love affairs, and her attempts at suicide. While Godwin believed he was portraying his wife with love, sincerity, and compassion, contemporary readers were shocked by Wollstonecraft's unorthodox lifestyle and she became a reviled figure.<space/><link><target>Richard Polwhele</target></link><space/>targeted her in particular in his anonymous long poem<space/><italics><link><target>The Unsex'd Females</target></link></italics><space/>(1798), a defensive reaction to women's literary self-assertion: Hannah More is Christ to Wollstonecraft's Satan. His poem was &quot;well known&quot; among the responses<space/><italics>A Vindication</italics>.<extension extension_name='ref'>Adriana Craciun,<space/><italics>Mary Wollstonecraft's a</italics><space/>Vindication of the Rights of Woman<italics>: A Sourcebook</italics><space/>(Routledge, 2002, 2).</extension><space/>One reviewer comments this &quot;ingenious poem&quot; with its &quot;playful sallies of sarcastic wit&quot; against &quot;our modern ladies,&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'>Ralph Griffiths,<space/><italics>The Monthly Review</italics><space/>30 (1799): 103.</extension><space/>though others found it &quot;a tedious, lifeless piece of writing.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref'><link type='external' href='http://etext.lib.virginia.edu/etcbin/toccer-new2?id=PolUnse.sgm&amp;amp;images=images/modeng&amp;amp;data=/texts/english/modeng/parsed&amp;amp;tag=public&amp;amp;part=front'>Introduction</link>,<space/><italics>The Unsex'd Females</italics>, Electronic Text Center, University of Virginia Library.</extension><space/>Critical responses largely fell along clear-cut political lines.</paragraph><paragraph>Wollstonecraft's ideas became associated with her life story and women writers felt that it was dangerous to mention her in their texts. Hays, who had previously been a close friend<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Elizabeth Robins Pennell</target><part>Pennell, Elizabeth Robins</part></link><space/>p351,<space/><italics>Life of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. (Boston: Roberts Brothers, 1884).</extension><space/>and an outspoken advocate for Wollstonecraft and her<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, for example, did not include her in the collection of<space/><italics>Illustrious and Celebrated Women</italics><space/>she published in 1803.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 145; Taylor, 2728.</extension><space/><link><target>Maria Edgeworth</target></link><space/>specifically distances herself from Wollstonecraft in her novel<space/><italics><link><target>Belinda (Edgeworth novel)</target><part>Belinda</part></link></italics><space/>(1802); she caricatures Wollstonecraft as a radical feminist in the character of Harriet Freke.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 155; Taylor, 3031.</extension><space/>But, like<space/><link><target>Jane Austen</target></link>, she does not reject Wollstonecraft's ideas. Both Edgeworth and Austen argue that women are crucial to the development of the nation; moreover, they portray women as rational beings who should choose companionate marriage.<extension extension_name='ref'>Mellor, 156.</extension></paragraph><paragraph>The negative views towards Wollstonecraft persisted for over a century. The<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>was not reprinted until the middle of the 19th century and it still retained an aura of ill-repute.<space/><link><target>George Eliot</target></link><space/>wrote &quot;there is in some quarters a vague prejudice against the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>as in some way or other a reprehensible book, but readers who go to it with this impression will be surprised to find it eminently serious, severely moral, and withal rather heavy&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'>Quoted in Sapiro, 30.</extension>The<space/><link><target>suffragist</target></link><space/>(i.e. moderate reformer, as opposed to<space/><link><target>suffragette</target></link>)<space/><link><target>Millicent Garrett Fawcett</target></link><space/>wrote the introduction to the centenary edition of the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics>, cleansing the memory of Wollstonecraft and claiming her as the foremother of the struggle for the vote.<extension extension_name='ref'>Gordon, 521</extension><space/>While the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>may have paved the way for feminist arguments, 20th century feminists have tended to use Wollstonecraft's life story, rather than her texts, for inspiration;<extension extension_name='ref'>Kaplan,&quot;Mary Wollstonecraft's reception and legacies&quot;.</extension><space/>her unorthodox lifestyle convinced them to try new &quot;experiments in living&quot;, as<space/><link><target>Virginia Woolf</target></link><space/>termed it in her famous essay on Wollstonecraft.<extension extension_name='ref'>Woolf, Virginia. &quot;<link type='external' href='http://etext.library.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91c2/chapter13.html'>The Four Figures</link>&quot;. Retrieved on 17 February 2007.</extension><space/>However, there is some evidence that the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>may be influencing current feminists.<space/><link><target>Ayaan Hirsi Ali</target></link>, a feminist who is critical of<space/><link><target>Women and Islam</target><part>Islam's dictates regarding women</part></link>, cites the<space/><italics>Rights of Woman</italics><space/>in her autobiography<space/><italics><link><target>Infidel (book)</target><part>Infidel</part></link></italics>, writing that she was &quot;inspired by Mary Wollstonecraft, the pioneering feminist thinker who told women they had the same ability to reason as men did and deserved the same rights&quot;.<extension extension_name='ref'><link><target>Ayaan Hirsi Ali</target><part>Hirsi Ali, Ayaan</part></link>.<space/><italics>Infidel</italics>. New York: Free Press (2007), 295.</extension><template><target>clear</target></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Timeline of Mary Wollstonecraft</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target><arg name="colwidth">30em</arg></template></paragraph><heading level='2'>Bibliography</heading><heading level='3'>Modern reprints</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Mary Wollstonecraft</target><part>Wollstonecraft, Mary</part></link>.<space/><italics>The Complete Works of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Ed. Janet Todd and Marilyn Butler. 7 vols. London: William Pickering, 1989. ISBN 0-8147-9225-1.</listitem><listitem>Wollstonecraft, Mary.<space/><italics>The Vindications: The Rights of Men and The Rights of Woman.</italics><space/>Eds. D.L. Macdonald and Kathleen Scherf. Toronto: Broadview Literary Texts, 1997. ISBN 1-55111-088-1</listitem><listitem>Wollstonecraft, Mary.<space/><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics>. Ed. Miriam Brody Kramnick. Rev. ed. Harmondsworth: Penguin, 2004. ISBN 0-14-144125-9.</listitem><listitem>Wollstonecraft, Mary.<space/><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics>. Ed. Deidre Shauna Lynch. 3rd ed. New York:<space/><link><target>W. W. Norton and Company</target></link>, 2009. ISBN 0-393-92974-4.</listitem><listitem>Wollstonecraft, Mary.<space/><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Men and A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics>. Ed. Sylvana Tomaselli. Cambridge:<space/><link><target>Cambridge University Press</target></link>, 1995. ISBN 0-521-43633-8.</listitem></list><heading level='4'>Contemporary reviews</heading><preblock><preline>*<space/><italics><link><target>Analytical Review</target></link></italics><space/>12 (1792): 241249; 13 (1792): 418489.</preline></preblock><list type='bullet'><listitem><italics>Christian Miscellany</italics><space/>1 (1792): 209212.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Critical Review</target><part>Critical Review</part></link></italics><space/>New Series 4 (1792): 389398; 5 (1792): 132141.</listitem><listitem><italics>General Magazine and Imperial Review</italics><space/>6.2 (1792): 187191.</listitem><listitem><italics>Literary Magazine and British Review</italics><space/>8 (1792); 133139.</listitem><listitem><italics>Monthly Review</italics><space/>New Series 8 (1792): 198209.</listitem><listitem><italics>New Annual Register</italics><space/>13 (1792): 298.</listitem><listitem><italics>New-York Magazine</italics><space/>4 (1793): 7781.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>The Scots Magazine</target><part>Scots Magazine</part></link></italics><space/>54 (1792): 284290.</listitem><listitem><italics>Sentimental and Masonic Magazine</italics><space/>1 (1792): 6372.</listitem><listitem><italics><link><target>Town &amp; Country (magazine)</target><part>Town and Country Magazine</part></link></italics><space/>24 (1792): 279.</listitem></list><heading level='3'>Secondary sources</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem>Barker-Benfield, G.J.<space/><italics>The Culture of Sensibility: Sex and Society in Eighteenth-Century Britain</italics>. Chicago:<space/><link><target>University of Chicago Press</target></link>, 1992. ISBN 0-226-03714-2.</listitem><listitem>Gordon, Lyndall.<space/><italics>Vindication: A Life of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Great Britain: Virago, 2005. ISBN 1-84408-141-9.</listitem><listitem>Janes, R.M. &quot;On the Reception of Mary Wollstonecraft's A Vindication of the Rights of Woman&quot;.<space/><italics>Journal of the History of Ideas</italics><space/>39 (1978): 293302.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Claudia L. Johnson (scholar)</target><part>Johnson, Claudia L.</part></link><space/><italics>Equivocal Beings: Politics, Gender, and Sentimentality in the 1790s</italics>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1995. ISBN 0-226-40184-7.</listitem><listitem>Jones, Chris. &quot;Mary Wollstonecraft's<space/><italics>Vindications</italics><space/>and their political tradition&quot;.<space/><italics>The Cambridge Companion to Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Ed. Claudia L. Johnson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-521-78952-4.</listitem><listitem>Kaplan, Cora. &quot;Mary Wollstonecraft's reception and legacies&quot;.<space/><italics>The Cambridge Companion to Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Ed. Claudia L. Johnson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-521-78952-4.</listitem><listitem>Kaplan, Cora. &quot;Pandora's Box: Subjectivity, Class and Sexuality in Socialist Feminist Criticism&quot;.<space/><italics>Sea Changes: Essays on Culture and Feminism</italics>. London: Verso, 1986. ISBN 0-86091-151-9.</listitem><listitem>Kaplan, Cora. &quot;Wild Nights: Pleasure/Sexuality/Feminism&quot;.<space/><italics>Sea Changes: Essays on Culture and Feminism</italics>. London: Verso, 1986. ISBN 0-86091-151-9.</listitem><listitem>Kelly, Gary.<space/><italics>Revolutionary Feminism: The Mind and Career of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. New York: St. Martin's, 1992. ISBN 0-312-12904-1.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Anne K. Mellor</target><part>Mellor, Anne K.</part></link><space/>&quot;Mary Wollstonecraft's<space/><italics>A Vindication of the Rights of Woman</italics><space/>and the women writers of her day&quot;.<space/><italics>The Cambridge Companion to Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Ed. Claudia L. Johnson. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2002. ISBN 0-521-78952-4.</listitem><listitem>Poovey, Mary.<space/><italics>The Proper Lady and the Woman Writer: Ideology as Style in the Works of Mary Wollstonecraft, Mary Shelley and Jane Austen</italics>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1984. ISBN 0-226-67528-9.</listitem><listitem>Sapiro, Virginia.<space/><italics>A Vindication of Political Virtue: The Political Theory of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1992. ISBN 0-226-73491-9.</listitem><listitem>Sunstein, Emily W.<space/><italics>A Different Face: The Life of Mary Wollstonecraft</italics>. New York: Harper and Row, 1975. ISBN 0-06-014201-4.</listitem><listitem>Taylor, Barbara.<space/><italics>Mary Wollstonecraft and the Feminist Imagination</italics>. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003. ISBN 0-521-66144-7.</listitem><listitem><link><target>Janet Todd</target><part>Todd, Janet</part></link>.<space/><italics>Sensibility: An introduction</italics>. London: Methuen, 1986. ISBN 0-416-37720-3.</listitem><listitem>Wardle, Ralph M.<space/><italics>Mary Wollstonecraft: A Critical Biography</italics>. Lincoln:<space/><link><target>University of Nebraska Press</target></link>, 1951.</listitem></list><heading level='2'>External links</heading><paragraph><template><target>Wikisource</target></template></paragraph><list type='bullet'><listitem><link type='external' href='https://books.google.com/?id=qhcFAAAAQAAJ'>1796 edition of ''Rights of Woman''</link><space/>from<space/><link><target>Google Books</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.gutenberg.org/ebooks/3420'>''Rights of Woman''</link><space/>at<space/><link><target>Project Gutenberg</target></link></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.earlymoderntexts.com'>A version of the ''Vindication'', slightly modified for easier reading</link></listitem><listitem><template><target>librivox book</target><arg name="title">A Vindication of the Rights of Woman<space/></arg><arg name="author">Mary Wollstonecraft</arg></template></listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/british/empire_seapower/wollstonecraft_01.shtml'>Mary Wollstonecraft: A 'Speculative and Dissenting Spirit'</link><space/>by<space/><link><target>Janet Todd</target></link><space/>at www.bbc.co.uk</listitem><listitem><link type='external' href='http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.rbc/anthony.11328.1'>''A Vindication of the Rights of Woman: with Strictures on Political and Moral Subjects''</link><space/>From the Collections at the Library of Congress</listitem></list><paragraph><template><target>featured article</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>Mary Wollstonecraft</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Vindication Of The Rights Of Woman, A</target></template><link><target>Category:1792 books</target></link><link><target>Category:Books by Mary Wollstonecraft</target></link><link><target>Category:Feminist books</target></link><link><target>Category:Women's rights</target></link><link><target>Category:History of education</target></link><link><target>Category:1792 in England</target></link><link><target>Category:First-wave feminism</target></link></paragraph></article>