<article title='Creature_of_statute'><paragraph><template><target>Refimprove</target><arg name="type">law</arg><arg name="date">June 2008</arg></template><bold>Creatures of statute</bold><space/>(also known as<space/><bold>creatures of the state</bold>) are legal entities, such as<space/><link><target>corporation</target><trail>s</trail></link>, created by<space/><link><target>statute</target></link>. Creatures of statute may include<space/><link><target>Municipality</target><part>municipalities</part></link><space/>and other artificial legal entities or relationships.<extension extension_name='ref' name="quaqua1"><link type='external' href='http://www.quaqua.org/creature.htm'>Creature of the State -- Quaqua Society</link></extension><space/>Thus, when a statute in some fashion requires the formation of a corporate bodyoften for governmental purposessuch bodies when formed are known as &quot;creatures of statute.&quot; The same concept is also expressed with the phrase &quot;creature of the state.&quot;<extension extension_name='ref' name="quaqua1"></extension></paragraph><paragraph>The term &quot;creature of statute&quot; is most common to the<space/><link><target>United States</target></link>. In the<space/><link><target>United Kingdom</target></link>, these bodies are simply called<space/><link><target>statutory corporation</target><trail>s</trail></link><space/>(or statutory bodies) and generally have some governmental function. The<space/><link><target>United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority</target></link><space/>is an example. In a wider sense, most companies in the UK are created under statute since the<space/><link><target>Companies Act 1985</target></link><space/>specifies how a company may be created by a member of the public, but these companies are not called 'statutory corporations'. Often, in American legal and business documents that speak of governing bodies (<italics>e.g.</italics>, a board that governs small businesses in China) these bodies are described as &quot;creatures of statute&quot; to inform readers of their origins and format although the national governments that created them may not term them as creatures of statute.<space/><link><target>Australia</target></link><space/>also uses the term &quot;creature of statute&quot; to describe some governmental bodies.</paragraph><paragraph>The importance of a corporate body, regardless of its exact function, when such a body is a creature of statute is that its active functions can only be within the scope detailed by the statute which created that corporation. Thereby, the creature of statute is the tangible manifestation of the functions or work described by a given statute. The jurisdiction of a body that is a creature of statute is also therefore limited to the functional scope written into the laws that created that body. Unlike most (private) corporate bodies, creatures of statute cannot expand their business interests into other diverse areas.</paragraph><heading level='2'>See also</heading><list type='bullet'><listitem><link><target>Competition regulator</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Statutory authority</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Regulatory agency</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Independent agencies of the United States government</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Public-benefit corporation</target></link></listitem><listitem><link><target>Quango</target></link></listitem></list><heading level='2'>Notes</heading><paragraph><template><target>Reflist</target></template></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>DEFAULTSORT:Creature Of Statute</target></template><link><target>Category:Administrative law</target></link><link><target>Category:Corporate law</target></link><link><target>Category:Statutory law</target></link><link><target>Category:Legal fictions</target></link></paragraph><paragraph><template><target>law-term-stub</target></template></paragraph></article>